<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00384001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Obituary for Jesse W. Lazear, by William Osler, Stewart Paton and William S. Thayer, [1900?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00384001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Osler, William</name>
<name type="person">Paton, Stewart</name>
<name type="person">Thayer, William S.</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore County (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia University, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-00-00">[1900?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00384001</idno>
<title>Obituary for Jesse W. Lazear, by William Osler, Stewart Paton and William S. Thayer, [1900?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This obituary encourages friends and admirers of the late Jesse Lazear to contribute to a fund for a Memorial in his name.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1900-00-00">
<head>Obituary for Jesse W. Lazear, by William Osler, Stewart Paton and William S. Thayer, [1900?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00384001"/>
<p>JESSE WILLIAM LAZEAR MEMORIAL.</p>
<p>On the 25th of September, 1900, Jesse William Lazear, at<lb/>
that time Acting-Assistant Surgeon in the United States<lb/>
Army and a member of the Government Commission for the<lb/>
investigation of yellow fever, lost his life from that disease<lb/>
at Quemados, Cuba.</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear was born in Baltimore County, Maryland, in<lb/>
1866, and graduated from the academic department of the<lb/>
Johns Hopkins University in 1889. In 1892 he received the<lb/>
degree of M. D. from Columbia University. From 1892-95<lb/>
he spent his time in study and investigation in Europe and<lb/>
as an interne at the Johns Hopkins Hospital in Baltimore.<lb/>
During the following three years and a half, while a member<lb/>
of the staff of the Out-Patient Department of the Johns<lb/>
Hopkins Hospital, he did much valuable work as a teacher<lb/>
and investigator in the laboratory of clinical pathology. In<lb/>
February, 1900, induced by the opportunity for research con-<lb/>
cerning malarial and yellow fevers, Lazear became an acting<lb/>
assistant surgeon in the United States Army and was assigned<lb/>
special laboratory duties at Columbia Barracks, near Havana.<lb/>
Later, he was appointed member of a special government<lb/>
commission for the investigation of yellow fever. The bril-<lb/>
liant discoveries of this commission concerning the &aelig;tiology<lb/>
and manner of infection of yellow fever have recently been<lb/>
referred to in public by a distinguished pathologist as the<lb/>
most important piece of work by American students since<lb/>
the discovery of an&aelig;sthesia. To these results Lazear, as a<lb/>
member of the commission, contributed largely. The final<lb/>
proof of their discovery that the disease is transferred by the<lb/>
bite of a certain mosquito, could only be obtained by direct<lb/>
experiment upon a human being. To this experiment Lazear,<lb/>
with another of the committee, courageously and heroically<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00384002"/>
subjected himself, and in the performance of this noble duty<lb/>
he lost his life.</p>
<p>The many friends and admirers of the talented and accom-<lb/>
plished student, of the brave, true, self-sacrificing man, desire<lb/>
to establish a lasting memorial to him and to his work. To<lb/>
this end a meeting was held on the evening of Wednesday,<lb/>
May 22d, which was presided over by Professor William Osler.<lb/>
At this meeting it was concluded that the nature of the<lb/>
memorial could better be decided upon when some idea<lb/>
could be obtained as to the amount of money available. It<lb/>
was, therefore, decided that a committee consisting of Dr.<lb/>
Stewart Paton and Dr. William S. Thayer be appointed to<lb/>
arrange for the distribution of a circular among the friends<lb/>
and admirers of Lazear, setting forth the object of the meet-<lb/>
ing. It is earnestly hoped that not only those who have<lb/>
known and admired Lazear and his work, but also others, who<lb/>
appreciate courage and manliness and self-sacrifice, may con-<lb/>
tribute to the fund for the Jesse William Lazear Memorial.</p>
<p>Subscriptions may be sent to Dr. Stewart Paton, Treasurer,<lb/>
213 West Monument Street, Baltimore, Md. It is to be<lb/>
hoped that the response to this circular may be made early,<lb/>
as it is hoped to be able to decide upon the nature of the<lb/>
memorial by the middle of June.</p>
<closer>
<signed>WILLIAM OSLER, Chairman.<lb/>
STEWART PATON,<lb/>
}Committee<lb/>
WILLIAM S. THAYER</signed>,
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
