<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00407001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: The Self-Sacrifice of Dr. Lazear, January 1902</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00407001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1902-01-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1902-01-00">January 1902</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00407001</idno>
<title>Report: The Self-Sacrifice of Dr. Lazear, January 1902</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This testimonial supports a petition to Congress for a pension for Mabel Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1902-01-00">
<head>Report: The Self-Sacrifice of Dr. Lazear, January 1902</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00407001"/>
<p>C1<lb/>
B17<lb/>
IN SUPPORT OF A PETITION TO BE PRESENTED TO CONGRESS<lb/>
ASKING FOR A PENSION FOR THE WIDOW AND CHIL-<lb/>
DREN OF DR. J. W. LAZEAR, WHO DIED IN THE ARMY<lb/>
SERVICE AS ACTING ASSISTANT SURGEON, AT QUEMA-<lb/>
DOS, CUBA, UNDER CIRCUMSTANCES OF EXTRAORDINARY<lb/>
SELF-SACRIFICE AND COURAGE.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00407002"/>
<p>THE SELF-SACRIFICE OF DR. LAZEAR.</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>On the 25th of September, 1900, Jesse William Lazear, Acting Assist-<lb/>
ant Surgeon in the United States Army and a member of the Government<lb/>
Commission for the investigation of yellow fever lost his life from that<lb/>
disease at Quemados, Cuba. The circumstances leading to this sad<lb/>
event were of a very unusual character. Lazear was a native of Balti-<lb/>
more County, Maryland, a graduate of the Johns Hopkins University,<lb/>
and of the Medical Department of Columbia University, New York. He<lb/>
had pursued important studies and investigations in Europe and in the<lb/>
laboratories of the Johns Hopkins University and hospital in Baltimore,<lb/>
and was a member of the staff of the hospital and an instructor in the<lb/>
University. In February, 1900, he was induced by the opportunity for<lb/>
research concerning malarial and yellow fevers to enter the United States<lb/>
Army as an Acting Assistant Surgeon and was assigned especial labora-<lb/>
tory duties at Columbia Barracks near Havana. Later he was appointed<lb/>
by Surgeon-General Sternberg a member of the Government Commission<lb/>
for the investigation of yellow fever of which Major Reed was chairman.</p>
<p>To the brilliant discoveries of this Commission, Lazear contributed<lb/>
largely. The investigations of the Commission led the members to the<lb/>
belief that a certain form of mosquito played an important part in the<lb/>
transmission of the poison of yellow fever. A time was reached, however,<lb/>
when the final proof of this hypothesis could only be determined by<lb/>
direct experiment upon human beings. To this experiment Lazear and<lb/>
another member of the Commission subjected themselves. His friend ac-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00407003"/>
quired the disease and recovered, Lazear escaped. Shortly afterwards,<lb/>
however, he repeated the experiment, allowing himself to be bitten by a<lb/>
mosquito in a yellow fever ward. In this manner he acquired the dis-<lb/>
ease which resulted fatally.</p>
<p>These two positive cases justified the Commission in making conclusions<lb/>
which have since then been entirely confirmed. This discovery has<lb/>
brought about results of incalculable public importance. By demon-<lb/>
strating, for the first time, the method by which yellow fever is acquired<lb/>
it has afforded positive and accurate means for protection of the public<lb/>
against the disease, with the result that, within one year, the city of<lb/>
Havana has been entirely freed from this malady.</p>
<p>No sacrifice could be more deliberate or courageous than that of Lazear,<lb/>
and the great results which have followed should insure to his memory<lb/>
the lasting gratitude of his fellow countrymen.</p>
<p>Dr. Lazear left a wife and two children in circumstances which oblige<lb/>
her to apply for a pension. Surely no soldier dead in battle could deserve<lb/>
more from his country than this man who by deliberately sacrificing his<lb/>
life has contributed to the saving of thousands of others.</p>
<p>T.</p>
<p>Johns Hopkins University,<lb/>
January, 1902</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00407004"/>
<p>From the Surgeon-General of the United States Army.<lb/>
SURGEON-GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
Washington, January 13, 1902.</p>
<p>I take pleasure in testifying to the value of the services rendered<lb/>
by Dr. Jesse William Lazear, who lost his life in Cuba, from yellow fever,<lb/>
while engaged in experimental researches relating to the cause and pre-<lb/>
vention of this disease, in compliance with Orders from the War Department<lb/>
assigning him to duty as a member of a board appointed for this purpose.<lb/>
The results attained by this board are of the utmost importance and will,<lb/>
without doubt, result in the saving of many valuable lives. I therefore feel<lb/>
justified in earnestly recommending legislation by the Congress of the United<lb/>
States providing a suitable pension for the widow of Dr. Lazear who is left<lb/>
with two children in destitute circumstances.</p>
<p>GEO. M. STERNBERG,<lb/>
Surgeon-General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>------</p>
<p>From the President of the Army Board of Medical Officers<lb/>
appointed to investigate the prevalence of Yellow Fever in Cuba.</p>
<p>As senior member of the Board of Medical Officers convened by Special<lb/>
Orders, No. 122, Adjutant-General's Office, Washington, May 24th, 1900, for<lb/>
the scientific investigation of yellow fever on the Island of Cuba, I cannot<lb/>
speak too highly of the services of the late Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, Acting<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<p>As a member of this Board he displayed at all times an enthusi-<lb/>
astic and fearless devotion to duty which was worthy of the highest com-<lb/>
mendation. He repeatedly risked his life by entering houses that were badly<lb/>
infected with yellow fever, in order that he might gain, if possible, some<lb/>
knowledge of the spread of this disease; and later when it became desirable<lb/>
to test the transmission of the disease by means of the bite of infected<lb/>
mosquitoes, Dr. Lazear unhesitatingly offered himself for the experiment.<lb/>
In thus voluntarily sacrificing his life he had no other object in view than<lb/>
the good that might thereby come to his fellow man. Although holding no<lb/>
commission in the Regular Army, Dr. Lazear, in my opinion, died as plainly<lb/>
in the line of duty as any officer or soldier who had ever fallen in battle.</p>
<p>WALTER REED,<lb/>
Major and Surgeon, U. S. A.,<lb/>
President of the Board.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
January 11, 1902.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
