<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00424001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from William S. Thayer to Mabel H. Lazear, June 29, 1904</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Thayer, William S.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00424001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1904-06-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lazear, Mabel H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Paton, Stewart</name>
<name type="person">Osler, William</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finley, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1904-06-29">June 29, 1904</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00424001</idno>
<title>Letter from William S. Thayer to Mabel H. Lazear, June 29, 1904</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Thayer believes that Lazear should receive credit for being the first to advocate the mosquito theory to the Yellow Fever Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1904-06-29">
<head>Letter from William S. Thayer to Mabel H. Lazear, June 29, 1904</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00424001"/>
<opener>
DR. W. S. THAYER,<lb/>
405 CATHEDRAL STREET.<lb/>
CONSULTATION HOURS,<lb/>
2.30-4.30 P. M.<lb/>
<dateline>
BALTIMORE,<lb/>
<date value="1904-06-29">June 29, 1904.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Mrs. Lazear:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>The brass plate, as Dr. Paton has I think written you, is done and is<lb/>
really fine. It will be unveiled probably at the time of the exercises of the opening<lb/>
of the new medical rooms at the hospital. I saw Dr. Osler day before yesterday and he<lb/>
quite agreed with me that we ought to have some special dedicatory exercises in connection<lb/>
with the plate. I shall want myself to say a few special words. I feel quite convinced<lb/>
that the world at large and more than that, those who really ought to know the facts<del>,</del><lb/>
are unaware of the full part which Lazear played in the work of the Yellow Fever Commission<lb/>
I know well enough that there is nothing more undignified and mistaken than strife with<lb/>
regard to questions of priority but unless I am very much mistaken there are some simple<lb/>
facts with regard to Lazear's work that I could state on this occasion in such a way<lb/>
as to offend no one and to do only good. While every one who know Reed was devoted to<lb/>
him and every one is enthusiastic about the plans for the Reed Memorial I feel that<lb/>
people ought to know-if it be true and I believe it is- that the first suggestion of<lb/>
the mosquito work - the original ideas and plans, came from Lazear. No one would have<lb/>
been quicker to acknowledge it than Reed had he been alive to-day. I remember very well<lb/>
a conversation that I had in my office in which you hinted at certain ideas that Lazear<lb/>
had worked out, and it occurred to me that you might care to tell me a few facts or to<lb/>
let me have a few extracts from his letters which might enable me to say something to<lb/>
the point. I should of course feel myself bound to say nothing which I had not pre-<lb/>
viously submitted to you. I do not know whether you ever saw a letter of Dr. Agramonte<lb/>
to the Journal of the American Medical Association which was published on the 13th of<lb/>
June of last year. It was in a controversy with regard to rather a stupid point I think -<lb/>
the amount of credit that should be given to Dr. Finley. In this letter he says: &ldquo;I<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00424002"/>
DR. W. S. THAYER,<lb/>
405 CATHEDRAL STREET.<lb/>
CONSULTATION HOURS,<lb/>
2.30-4.30 P. M.<lb/>
BALTIMORE.<lb/>
was present when the question of following out Dr. Finley's mosquito theory was brought<lb/>
up by the Army Yellow Fever Board ****At that time neither Drs. Reed, Carroll nor myself<lb/>
believed in said theory, the only one of us inclined to consider it favorably being<lb/>
my friend and classmate, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear. That the work in the lines of Finley's<lb/>
theory was undertaken as a matter of course from the fact that a thorough investigation<lb/>
into the aetiology of yellow fever was expected of our Board, and not because as a body<lb/>
the Board thought any too well of it. That of us all Dr. Lazear was the only one at<lb/>
the time prepared to initiate the work in this direction, he being thoroughly familiar<lb/>
with the anatomy and biology of the culex and conversant with the technique required;<lb/>
he had bred numerous varieties in his laboratory at Camp Columbia and had been sending<lb/>
specimens to Dr. Howard the entomologist, Department of Agriculture, Washington, for aid<lb/>
in identifying different species. That Dr. Lazear was the member of the Board, Dr. Reed<lb/>
being absent in Washington, who produced the first two cases by the bites of mosquitoes<lb/>
in the presence of Dr. Carroll, who, being an unbeliever, allowed him to apply one mosquito<lb/>
on August 27 and an American soldier who was bitten by the same mosquito, and three<lb/>
others August 31, 1900. That Dr. Lazear not content with this and not in ignorance, for<lb/>
he had suggested to me what the origin of Carroll's and the soldier's infection was, de-<lb/>
liberately allowed himself to be bitten by the mosquito, while in one of the wards of<lb/>

the Yellow Fever Hospital (Las Anamas) September 13, at a time when Carroll and the sol-<lb/>
dier were convalescing from their attacks. I am convinced that this mosquito produced<lb/>
the infection which caused his death September 25, 1900.</p>
<p>Major Reed was summoned from Washington and the investigation was then undertaken<lb/>
exclusively on the mosquito theory.</p>
<p>These are the facts which I deem necessary to make known for the present&rdquo;.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00424003"/>
<p>DR. W. S. THAYER,<lb/>
405 CATHEDRL STREET,</p>
<p>CONSULTATION HOURS,<lb/>
2.30-4.30 P. M.</p>
<p>BALTIMORE,</p>
<p>I fancy that this is true, and that you have always been aware of it. To bring such:<lb/>
facts out more forcibly and in such a way that it in no way detracts from the honour<lb/>
due to Dr. Reed, would it seems to me be easy on such an occasion as the unveiling of<lb/>
the plate. Should you not like to have me do this?</p>
<p>It seems a long time since I have heard from you. I sincerely hope that you and<lb/>
the children are well. With cordial good wishes, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>W.S. Thayer</signed>.
Mrs. Jesse W. Lazear,<lb/>
2012 N. Broadway,<lb/>
San Francisco, California.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
