<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00438001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Senate Report No. 431, March 27, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00438001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-03-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie M.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-03-27">March 27, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00438001</idno>
<title>Senate Report No. 431, March 27, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Committee on Pensions reports on a possible increase in the pensions of Jennie Carroll and Mabel Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-03-27">
<head>Senate Report No. 431, March 27, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00438001"/>
<opener>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
J. R. Kean<lb/>
Calendar No. 462.<lb/>
60TH CONGRESS,}<lb/>
1st Session.}<lb/>
SENATE.<lb/>
{REPORT<lb/>
{No. 431.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.<lb/>
-------------------------<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1908-03-27">MARCH 27, 1908.</date>
--Ordered to be printed.<lb/>
</dateline>
-------------------------<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Mr. McCUMBER, from the Committee on Pensions, submitted the<lb/>
following</p>
<p>REPORT.</p>
<p>[To accompany S. 6350.]</p>
<p>This bill proposes to <unclear>increase the</unclear> pension of Jennie M. Carroll,<lb/>
widow of James Carroll, late <unclear>major</unclear> and surgeon, U. S. Army, and<lb/>
also Mabel H. Lazear, widow of Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, late acting<lb/>
assistant surgeon, U. S. Army, to $125 per month each, in special<lb/>
recognition of the eminent services of the said Maj. James Carroll<lb/>
and Dr. Jesse W. Lazear in discovering and demonstrating upon<lb/>
their own persons the truth of the theory of the transmission and<lb/>
propagation of yellow-fever infection by mosquitoes, and therefore<lb/>
by reason of such discovery and demonstration it has been made pos-<lb/>
sible to practically eliminate the scourge of yellow fever that had<lb/>
heretofore ravaged the southeastern coast of the United States and<lb/>
the West Indies Archipelago, resulting in the saving of thousands of<lb/>
lives yearly that heretofore had been sacrificed to that dread disease.</p>
<p>The officers named in the bill were appointed to serve under Maj.<lb/>
Walter Reed on a commission to investigate the yellow-fever epi-<lb/>
demics in Cuba in 1900 and 1901. Major Reed was the head of the<lb/>
commission, but his duties required him to be in Washington the<lb/>
greater part of the time, and the actual work of making the experi-<lb/>
ments and demonstrating the truth of the theory was carried on in<lb/>
Cuba by Major Carroll and Doctor Lazear. The work of that com-<lb/>
mission, headed by Major Reed, is set out in detail in Senate Docu-<lb/>
ment No. 118, Fifty-seventh Congress, second session, and is in part<lb/>
as follows:</p>
<p>The first work by Major Reed bearing on the causation of yellow fever was in 1899-<lb/>
1900, when he overthrew the claim of the distinguished bacteriologist, Sanarelli, to<lb/>
have discovered the bacillus of yellow fever, by his demonstration that the Bacillus<lb/>
icteroides (Sanarelli) was an organism widely disseminated in this country and having<lb/>
no causative relation to that disease. He began the special work, with which his name<lb/>
will always be inseparably associated as one of the benefactors of mankind, in June,<lb/>
1900, when he went to Cuba as president of a commission to study the infectious dis-<lb/>
eases of Cuba, with special reference to yellow fever. The other members of this com-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00438002"/>
2<lb/>
JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.<lb/>
mission were Acting Asst. Surgs. James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear, and A. Agramonte.<lb/>
The time was most opportune for such investigation, as the disease was at that time<lb/>
prevalent both in Habana and in the little town of Quemados, near the camp of the<lb/>
American troops, and it was plainly evident that the energetic measures of the Ameri-<lb/>
can military government to clean up the towns, disinfect, and enforce other sanitary<lb/>
measures were without effect in preventing the spread of this particular disease. Major<lb/>
Reed became convinced that proper sanitation was not all that was needed, and that<lb/>
some other agent than unclean conditions was responsible for the spread of the disease.</p>
<p>The transmission of malaria by a certain species of mosquito had been recently<lb/>
demonstrated by the English military surgeon, Ronald Ross. The theory had also<lb/>
been advanced both by a Mobile physician and by Doctor Finlay, of Habana, that a<lb/>
mosquito was the agent for the transmission of yellow fever; but these theories, being<lb/>
unsupported by scientific demonstration, received no more attention than the vast<lb/>
number of others which had been at one time or another advanced with regard to<lb/>
this mysterious and deadly disease.</p>
<p>Doctor Reed's attention was attracted by a paper on the spread of yellow fever in<lb/>
Ormond, Miss., by Dr. H. R. Carter, of the Marine-Hospital Service, in which it was<lb/>
shown that although the period of incubation of the disease was five days fifteen or<lb/>
twenty elapsed before a house became infected after a patient sick with yellow fever<lb/>
was carried into it. He inferred that the difference between the time of incubation<lb/>
and the time required to infect a building was due to the fact that the infective agent<lb/>
passed through a stage of development in the body of some biting insect as an inter-<lb/>
mediate host, and he at once determined to conduct his experiments along that line.<lb/>
It was evident to his mind that the solution of this question, which meant so much<lb/>
for the human race, could never be satisfactorily determined without experiments<lb/>
on human beings, and he went to General Wood, the military governor of Cuba, to<lb/>
ask permission to conduct such experiments, and for a sum of money to liberally<lb/>
reward volunteers who should submit themselves for experiment. General Wood<lb/>
promptly granted both, with a ready appreciation of the importance of the matter<lb/>
and the force of Doctor Reed's arguments, which will entitle him to no small measure<lb/>
of the glory of this discovery.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, during a temporary <unclear>absence of</unclear> Doctor Reed in the United States his<lb/>
assistants, Dr. James Carroll and Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, who had offered themselves as<lb/>
the first volunteers for these experiments, had demonstrated that mosquitoes would<lb/>
convey yellow fever. Doctor Carroll, who was the first experimental case suffered a<lb/>
very severe attack, but recovered. Doctor Lazear was not infected at this time, due to<lb/>
the fact that the conditions necessary to the transmission of the disease by the mos-<lb/>
quito were not yet understood, but he was bitten while working in the yellow-fever<lb/>
ward somewhat later, and died a martyr of science, working in behalf of humanity.<lb/>
This was the only fatality which occurred in these experiments. The fourth member<lb/>
of the commission. Doctor Agramonte, did not participate in the mosquito work of the<lb/>
commission until a later date, nor did he share their dangers, as he was a Cuban and<lb/>
immune.</p>
<p>The efficient control of the spread of yellow fever is a matter of such vast practical<lb/>
importance, both from the hygienic and commercial point of view--not only for the<lb/>
countries where this disease prevails as an epidemic, but also for those in which, after<lb/>
importation, it may assume epidemic proportions--that it has seemed appropriate to<lb/>
bring together in this paper a summary of the work thus far accomplished by the U. S.<lb/>
Army commission on the island of Cuba during the years 1900 and 1901, in order that<lb/>
English and colonial readers who have not, perhaps, had access to the original contri-<lb/>
butions published in different American journals may be able to form an intelligent<lb/>
opinion concerning the permanent value of this work. It will also afford opportunity<lb/>
for recording the more recent confirmatory observations made by others concerning the<lb/>
mode of transmission of yellow fever discovered by the commission, and for calling<lb/>
attention to the results already obtained by the U. S. Army Medical Department in the<lb/>
suppression of this disease, especially in the city of Habana, through the enforcement<lb/>
of sanitary measures based on these later researches.</p>
<p>The American commission was organized in May, 1900, and began its investigations<lb/>
during the following month (June), being equipped with suitable laboratory facilities<lb/>
for practical work, both at the military garrison of Columbia Barracks, near Quemados,<lb/>
Cuba, and also in the city of Habana. As yellow fever was already prevailing at the<lb/>
time of our arrival in Cuba, suitable material for the scientific study of this disease was<lb/>
immediately available.</p>
<p>Before giving the results of our investigations, it may be well to recall the situation<lb/>
as regards the etiology of yellow fever at that time. Briefly, it may be said that the<lb/>
claims of all investigators for the discovery of the specific agent of yellow fever--since<lb/>
modern bacteriological methods had come into use--had been disproved by the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00438003"/>
JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR<lb/>
3<lb/>
exhaustive observations of Sternberg, published in 1890, except that made by Sanarelli<lb/>
for a small, motile bacillus isolated by him from the blood drawn during life in two<lb/>
of six cases of yellow fever, and from the blood and organs after death in seven of<lb/>
twelve cases of this disease (58 per cent), studied at Montevideo and Rio de Janeiro,<lb/>
Brazil. The results obtained, however, by those who had promptly undertaken to<lb/>
investigate Senarelli's claim for the specific character of Bacillus icteroides seemed to<lb/>
show a lack of agreement such as has never been reported, as far as the writer can<lb/>
recall, in connection with the supposed specific cause of any of the other acute<lb/>
infections.</p>
<p>Under these circumstances it seemed to the members of the commission of the first<lb/>
importance to give their entire attention to the bacteriological study of the blood of<lb/>
those sick with yellow fever and of the blood and organs of yellow-fever cadavers,<lb/>
having especially in view the isolation of B. icteroides. We were thus able during June,<lb/>
July, and August to take repeated cultures from the blood during life in 18 cases of<lb/>
yellow fever, adopting the usual method employed in withdrawing blood from a vein<lb/>
at the bend of the elbow, and transferring the blood at once in quantities of 0.5 c. c. to<lb/>
each of several tubes containing 10 c. c. of nutritive bouillon, which were afterwards<lb/>
incubated at 37&deg;C. for a period of one week. In seven cases, four of which were desig-<lb/>
nated as &ldquo;mild&rdquo; yellow fever and three as &ldquo;well-marked&rdquo; yellow fever, only one<lb/>
culture was made from the blood in each case, viz, in two cases on the first day, in one<lb/>
case on the second day, in three cases on the third day, and in one case on the fourth<lb/>
day. In the remaining 11 cases diagnosed as &ldquo;severe&rdquo; yellow fever, of whom four<lb/>
died, more frequent cultures were taken from the blood, these varying from two to<lb/>
six cultures on as many different days of the disease. In two of the fatal cases cultures<lb/>
were made each day from the commencement of the attack and including the day on<lb/>
which death occurred.</p>
<p>The negative result of these numerous cultures taken from the blood of cases of yel-<lb/>
low fever, as regards the presence of B. icteroides, was reported in a &ldquo;Preliminary note&rdquo;<lb/>
presented at the meeting of the American Public Health Association, held in Indian-<lb/>
apolis, Ind., October 22-26, 1900. To these 18 cases we can now add 6 other cases, or<lb/>
a total of 24, from which blood cultures have been made during life with negative<lb/>
results.</p>
<p>The importance of this negative finding as regards the growth of any specific bac-<lb/>
terium will be better appreciated when it is seen, as I shall soon have occasion to<lb/>
point out, that yellow fever may be produced in nonimmune human beings by the<lb/>
subcutaneous injection of a small quantity (0.5-2 c.c.) of blood withdrawn from the<lb/>
venous circulation of a patient suffering with this disease.</p>
<p>In addition to the results above recorded, the careful study of 11 autopsies was<lb/>
equally barren as to the presence of any particular microorganism, although the<lb/>
quantity of material with which our tubes were inoculated was greater than is usually<lb/>
made use of at autopsies.</p>
<p>In a word, then, the careful bacteriological study which the commission had made<lb/>
in cases of yellow fever had given no indications as to the presence of the specific<lb/>
agent of this disease. The same may be said concerning the result of numerous<lb/>
microscopic examinations of fresh and stained specimens of blood which he had in<lb/>
the meanwhile studied with the view of finding possibly some intracellular or extra-<lb/>
cellular body. Apparently no body, bacterial or protozoan, which could be brought<lb/>
into view with a one-twelfth Zeiss immersion objective was present in the blood of<lb/>
these cases.</p>
<p>Although displaced from the order in which the following observations were made,<lb/>
it will be best to present at this time the results of the experiments which were later<lb/>
carried out by the commission on nonimmune human beings by means of the sub-<lb/>
cutaneous injection of blood, withdrawn during the active stage of the disease, as<lb/>
these results bear so directly upon the subject which we are now considering, viz, the<lb/>
etiology of yellow fever.</p>
<p>The only reference that I can find in the literature relative to an attempt to convey<lb/>
yellow fever in this way is cited by Sternberg, who states that at Vera Cruz, Mexico, in<lb/>
1877, he saw Doctor Ruis inject into a nonimmune individual a hypodermic syringeful<lb/>
of blood drawn from a case of yellow fever on the eighth day of the disease. The<lb/>
result was negative, as was also the result of two other attempts related to him by Ruis.</p>
<p>Our own observations, undertaken for the purpose of ascertaining whether an attack<lb/>
of yellow fever could be induced in a second individual by the injection of a small<lb/>
quantity of blood, embrace experiments made on 12 American soldiers and Spanish<lb/>
immigrants, all nonimmune individuals.</p>
<p>These observations may be divided into the following classes:</p>
<p>(1) Injection of the fresh blood taken from a vein at the bend of the elbow: (2) injec-<lb/>
tion of partially defibrinated blood; (3) injection of partially defibrinated blood<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00438004"/>
4<lb/>
JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.<lb/>
heated for ten minutes at 55&deg;C.; (4) injection of blood-serum previously diluted with<lb/>
sterilized water and filtered slowly through a Berkefeld laboratory filter.</p>
<p>The following table gives the results of these several inoculations:</p>
<p>TABLE I.<lb/>
<table rows="14" cols="6">
<row>
<cell>No. of<lb/>
case.</cell><cell>Quantity and material used.</cell><cell>Day of<lb/>
disease.</cell><cell>Date of<lb/>
inoculation.</cell><cell>Result.</cell><cell>Date of<lb/>
attack.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>I</cell><cell>2 c. c. fresh blood.....................</cell><cell>Second......</cell><cell>Dec. 26, 1900</cell><cell>Negative....</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>II</cell><cell>.....do..................................</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>Jan. 4, 1901</cell><cell>Positive....</cell><cell>Jan. 8, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>III</cell><cell>1.5 c. c. fresh blood...................</cell><cell>First.......</cell><cell>Jan. 8, 1901</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>Jan. 11, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>IV</cell><cell>0.5 c. c. fresh blood....................</cell><cell>Second......</cell><cell>Jan. 22, 1901</cell><cell>.....do.....</cell><cell>Jan. 24, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>V</cell><cell>1 c. c. fresh blood.....................</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>Jan. 25, 1901</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>Jan. 28, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VI</cell><cell>0.75 c. c. partially defibrinated blood..</cell><cell>Third.......</cell><cell>Oct. 15, 1901</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>Oct. 20, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VII</cell><cell>1.5 c. c. partially defibrinated blood<lb/>
heated for ten minutes at 55&deg;C.</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>Negative....</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VIII</cell><cell>Same as No. VII......................</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>IX</cell><cell>.....do................................</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>X</cell><cell>1.5 c. c. of filtered blood serum........</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>Positive....</cell><cell>Oct. 19, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>XI</cell><cell>Same as No. X........................</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>Do.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell rows="13-14">XII</cell><cell>{....do.................................</cell><cell>.....do......</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>Negative....</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2 c. c. fresh blood.....................</cell><cell>Fourth.....</cell><cell>Oct. 22, 1901</cell><cell>Positive....</cell><cell>Oct. 23, 1901</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>By an examination of this table it will be seen that of the seven individuals who<lb/>
received subcutaneously the fresh or partially defibrinated blood in quantities of<lb/>
0.5-2 c. c., six (85.7 per cent) developed an attack of yellow fever within the usual<lb/>
period of incubation of the disease.</p>
<p>These results are of very great interest as demonstrating that the specific agent of<lb/>
yellow fever is present in the blood, at least during the first, second, and third days<lb/>
of the attack.</p>
<p>Another important point brought out by these experiments was that the blood<lb/>
which conveyed the disease did not contain any bacterium which would grow on<lb/>
our usual laboratory media.</p>
<p>In order to establish this fact, as soon as blood had been injected into the nonim-<lb/>
mune subject, additional blood was at once withdrawn in considerable quantity and<lb/>
transferred to tubes of nutritive bouillon. In one instance, where 2 c. c. of blood<lb/>
had been drawn into the syringe, 0.5 c. c. of this sufficed, when injected, to produce<lb/>
a severe attack of yellow fever, after seventy-three hours' incubation, while the remain-<lb/>
ing 1.5 c. c. transferred immediately to four tubes of bouillon gave no growth, except<lb/>
that from one tube we isolated on the fourth day Staphylococcus pyogenes citreus,<lb/>
found by us to be a common skin-contaminating organism in Cuba.</p>
<p>Table I further shows that the specific agent contained in the blood is destroyed or<lb/>
attenuated by heating the latter at 55&deg; C. for ten minutes, so that the injection of<lb/>
1.5 c. c. of this heated blood was harmless (Cases VII, VIII, and IX), while the<lb/>
injection of 0.75 c. c. of the same blood unheated sufficed to promptly induce an<lb/>
attack of yellow fever in a &ldquo;control&rdquo; individual (Case VI).</p>
<p>Of not less interest was the fact brought out by these observations that yellow fever<lb/>
can be produced by the injection of a small quantity of bacteria-free serum filtrate,<lb/>
obtained by passing the diluted serum through a Berkefeld laboratory filter (Cases X<lb/>
and XI), and further that the blood of a case of yellow fever, thus produced, when<lb/>
injected into a third nonimmune subject will promptly bring about an attack of this<lb/>
disease (Case XII), thus demonstrating that the specific agent of yellow fever can<lb/>
find its way through the pores of a filter which ordinarily serves to prevent the passage<lb/>
of all known bacteria.</p>
<p>I have elsewhere, in conjunction with one of my colleagues (Carroll), discussed the<lb/>
facts here presented more at length, and will limit myself, therefore, to the remark<lb/>
that these experiments appear to indicate that yellow fever, like the foot-and-mouth<lb/>
disease of cattle, is caused by a micro-organism so minute in size that it might be<lb/>
designated as ultra-microscopic.</p>
<p>THE PROPAGATION OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>Prior to the time at which the foregoing observations were made the commission<lb/>
had already turned its entire attention to the possible solution of the problem of<lb/>
the propagation of yellow fever, being induced thereto not only by the fruitlessness<lb/>
of the investigations made thus far along bacteriological lines, but also by reason<lb/>
of certain facts which seemed to call for a better interpretation than had hitherto<lb/>
been accorded them.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00438005"/>
<p>JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.</p>
<p>5</p>
<p>Without entering into details, I may say that, in the first place, the commission<lb/>
saw, with some surprise, what had so often been noted in the literature, that patients<lb/>
in all stages of yellow fever could be cared for by nonimmune nurses without danger<lb/>
of contracting the disease. The noncontagious character of yellow fever was there-<lb/>
fore hardly to be questioned.</p>
<p>In the second place, it had been observed that patients discharged from the wards<lb/>
during early convalesence could be brought into intimate association with non-<lb/>
immune individuals without thereby establishing fresh foci of the disease. This did<lb/>
not seem to indicate that any specific agent was present in the excreta of the sick.</p>
<p>Again, it has been noted that in certain cases of this disease no growth had been<lb/>
obtained on the ordinary laboratory media, either by frequent cultures from the<lb/>
blood during life or from the blood and organs after death.</p>
<p>Further, in the course of an investigation which the commission were able to make<lb/>
during the last week of July, 1900, concerning the origin and spread of a small epidemic<lb/>
of yellow fever that had appeared in a military garrison, numbering about 900 men,<lb/>
at Pinar del Rio, Cuba, they had seen that by reason of the false diagnosis of &ldquo;pernicious<lb/>
malarial fever&rdquo; which had been given to these cases no disinfection of bedding or<lb/>
clothing had been carried out, and yet there was no indication that this neglect had<lb/>
contributed in the least to the spread of the disease; nor had any harm come to those<lb/>
nonimmunes who had slept in the beds vacated by the sick or washed the supposedly<lb/>
infected garments of those who had recovered or died of this disease.</p>
<p>Putting these various data together, it seems probable that more progress might be<lb/>
made if attention should be turned to the mode of transmission of yellow fever, espe-<lb/>
cially as our own observations had caused us to seriously doubt the usually accepted<lb/>
belief of the conveyance of this disease by means of fomites.</p>
<p>Then, too, the endemic curve of yellow fever in the city of Habana, and its well-<lb/>
known epidemic curve in the United States, appeared to be more intimately asso-<lb/>
ciated with and more affected by the rise and fall of the annual temperature curve<lb/>
than was to be seen in any of the acute infections except malarial fever. The pecu-<lb/>
liar behavior of this disease (if I may use the expression) in rapidly spreading in cer-<lb/>
tain localities, when introduced, as contrasted with its failure to propagate itself in<lb/>
other places where the conditions for its increase were apparently just as favorable,<lb/>
seemed to point in the strongest manner to the necessity for some special agent or<lb/>
intermediate host in the dissemination of its specific cause. If malarial fever--a<lb/>
disease so much affected by temperature conditions--required the agency of a spe-<lb/>
cial genus of mosquito for its propagation, as had in recent years been so brilliantly<lb/>
worked out by Ross, Grassi, Bastianelli, Bignami, and others, it did not seem unrea-<lb/>
sonable to suppose that yellow fever--a disease so plainly controlled by seasonal con-<lb/>
ditions--might also depend on some such agent for its spread. Influenced by this<lb/>
line of reasoning the commission began, during the second week of August, 1900.<lb/>
its observations relative to the propagation of yellow fever by means of the bite of<lb/>
a certain species of mosquito, Stegomyia fasciata.</p>
<p>The work along this line was carried forward so rapidly that within thirty days 11<lb/>
individuals had been bitten by infected Stegomyia, of whom 2<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> developed well-marked<lb/>
attacks of yellow fever within the usual period of incubation, and under such circum-<lb/>
stances as to positively exclude in one case any other possible source of infection.</p>
<p>Appreciating fully the importance of this discovery, and in order to exclude all other<lb/>
possible sources of infection in our future observations, it was now determined to estab-<lb/>
lish a special experimental station where further observations could be made on non-<lb/>
immune human beings, both as to the propagation of yellow fever by means of the bite<lb/>
of the mosquito as well as by exposure to the most intimate contact with infected<lb/>
clothing and bedding, and this under the strictest enforcement of military quarantine.<lb/>
With the approval and assistance of the military governor of the island of Cuba, this<lb/>
experimental station was ready for occupancy on November 20, 1900, and was contin-<lb/>
uously occupied until March 1, 1901.</p>
<p>As the results obtained at this station have already been published in full elsewhere,<lb/>
I will here only present a brief account, first of the experiments with fomites and<lb/>
afterwards of those made with infected mosquitoes.</p>
<p>ATTEMPTS AT INFECTION BY FOMITES.</p>
<p>For this purpose there was erected at Camp Lazear a small frame house, consisting<lb/>
of one room, 14 by 20 feet, and known as &ldquo;Building No. 1,&rdquo; or the &ldquo;Infected clothing<lb/>
and bedding building.&rdquo; The cubic capacity of this house was 2,800 feet. It was<lb/>
_________________________________________________________<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> One of these cases was that of Dr. James Carroll, contract surgeon, U. S. Army, a<lb/>
member of the commission.<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00438006"/>
6<lb/>
JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.<lb/>
tightly sealed within with &ldquo;tongued and grooved boards,&rdquo; and was well battened<lb/>
on the outside. It faced the south and was provided with two small windows, each<lb/>
26 by 34 inches in size. These windows were both placed on the south side of the<lb/>
building, the purpose being to prevent, as much as possible, any thorough circulation<lb/>
of the air within the house. They were closed by permanent wire screens of 0.5<lb/>
mm. mesh. In addition, a sliding glass sash was provided within and heavy wooden<lb/>
shutters without; the latter intended to prevent the entrance of sunlight into the<lb/>
building, as it was not deemed desirable that the disinfecting qualities of sunlight,<lb/>
direct or diffused, should at any time be exerted on the articles of clothing contained<lb/>
within this room. Entrance was effected through a small vestibule, 3 by 5 feet,<lb/>
also placed on the southern side of the house. This vestibule was protected without<lb/>
by a solid door, and was divided in its middle by a wire-screen door swung on spring<lb/>
hinges. The inner entrance was also closed by a second wire-screen door. In this<lb/>
way the passage of mosquitoes into this room was effectually excluded. During the<lb/>
day, and until after sunset, the house was kept securely closed, while by means of<lb/>
a suitable heating apparatus the temperature was raised to 92&deg;-95&deg; F. Precaution<lb/>
was taken at the same time to maintain a sufficient humidity of the atmosphere.<lb/>
The average temperature of this house was thus kept up at 76.2&deg; F. for a period of<lb/>
sixty-three days.</p>
<p>November 30, 1900, the building now being ready for occupancy, three large boxes<lb/>
filled with sheets, pillowcases, blankets, etc., contaminated by contact with cases of<lb/>
yellow fever and their discharges, were received and placed therein. The majority<lb/>
of the articles had been taken from the beds of patients sick with yellow fever at<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital, Habana, or at Columbia Barracks. Many of them had been<lb/>
purposely soiled with a liberal quantity of black vomit, urine, and fecal matter. A<lb/>
dirty &ldquo;comfortable&rdquo; and a much-soiled pair of blankets, removed from the bed of a<lb/>
patient sick with yellow fever in the town of Quemados, were contained in one of<lb/>
these boxes. The same day, at 6 p. m., Dr. R. P. Cooke, acting assistant surgeon,<lb/>
U. S. Army, and two privates of the Hospital Corps, all nonimmune young Ameri-<lb/>
cans, entered this building and deliberately unpacked these boxes, which had been<lb/>
tightly closed and locked for a period of two weeks. They were careful at the same<lb/>
time to give each article a thorough handling and shaking, in order to disseminate<lb/>
through the air of the room the specific agent of yellow fever, if contained in these<lb/>
fomites. These soiled sheets, pillowcases, and blankets were used in preparing the<lb/>
beds in which the members of the Hospital Corps slept. Various soiled articles<lb/>
were hung around the room and placed about the bed occupied by Doctor Cooke.</p>
<p>From this date until December 19, 1900, a period of twenty days, this room was<lb/>
occupied each night by these three nonimmunes. Each morning the various soiled<lb/>
articles were carefully repacked in the aforesaid boxes and at night again unpacked<lb/>
and distributed about the room. During the day the residents of this house were<lb/>
permitted to occupy a tent pitched in the immediate vicinity, but were kept in strict<lb/>
quarantine.</p>
<p>* * * * * * *</p>
<p>December 19 these three nonimmunes were placed in quarantine for five days and<lb/>
then given the liberty of the camp. All had remained in perfect health, notwith-<lb/>
standing their stay of twenty nights amid such unwholesome surroundings.</p>
<p>During the week December 20-27 the following articles were also placed in this<lb/>
house, viz, pajamas suits, 1; undershirts, 2; nightshirts, 4; pillow slips, 4; sheets, 6;<lb/>
blankets, 5; pillows, 2; mattresses, 1. These articles had been removed from the<lb/>
persons and beds of four patients sick with yellow fever, and were very much soiled,<lb/>
as any change of clothing or bed linen during their attacks had been purposely avoided,<lb/>
the object being to obtain articles as thoroughly contaminated as possible.</p>
<p>From December 21, 1900, till January 10, 1901, this building was again occupied<lb/>
by two nonimmune young Americans, under the same conditions as the preceding<lb/>
occupants, except that these men slept every night in the very garments worn by<lb/>
yellow-fever patients throughout their entire attacks, besides making use exclusively<lb/>
of their much-soiled pillow slips, sheets, and blankets. At the end of twenty-one<lb/>
nights of such intimate contact with these fomites they also went into quarantine,<lb/>
from which they were released five days later in perfect health.</p>
<p>From January 11 till January 31, a period of twenty days, &ldquo;building No. 1&rdquo; con-<lb/>
tinued to be occupied by two other nonimmune Americans, who, like those who pre-<lb/>
ceded them, have slept every night in the beds formerly occupied by yellow-fever<lb/>
patients and in the nightshirts used by these patients throughout the attack without<lb/>
change. In addition, during the last fourteen nights of their occupancy of this<lb/>
house they had slept each night with their pillows covered with towels that had<lb/>
been thoroughly soiled with the blood drawn from both the general and capillary<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00438007"/>
JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.<lb/>
7<lb/>
circulation on the first day of the disease in the case of a well-marked attack of yellow<lb/>
fever. Notwithstanding this trying ordeal, these men have continued to remain in<lb/>
perfect health.</p>
<p>The attempt which we have therefore made to infect &ldquo;building No. 1&rdquo; and its<lb/>
seven nonimmune occupants during a period of sixty-three nights has proved an<lb/>
absolute failure.</p>
<p>INFECTION BY MOSQUITOES.</p>
<p>While the experiments with fomites were being carried out in building No. 1, cer-<lb/>
tain nonimmune individuals who were lodged in tents, in a separate part of the camp,<lb/>
were being subjected, with their full consent, to the bites of mosquitoes which had<lb/>
previously fed on the blood of cases of yellow fever occurring in the city of Habana.<lb/>
Thus, during the period from December 5, 1900, to February 7, 1901, we had subjected<lb/>
to this method of infection twelve nonimmune subjects who had previously passed<lb/>
their full record of quarantine in this camp. Of these 10, or 83.3 per cent, experienced<lb/>
attacks of yellow fever and always within the period of incubation of this disease.</p>
<p>The following table gives the necessary data concerning these observations:</p>
<p>TABLE II.<lb/>
<table rows="14" cols="9">
<row>
<cell>No. of<lb/>
case.</cell><cell>Days in<lb/>
quar-<lb/>
antine.</cell><cell cols="3-4">Inoculation.</cell><cell>Hour.</cell><cell>Date.</cell><cell>Method of<lb/>
inocula-<lb/>
tion.</cell><cell>Period<lb/>
of incu-<lb/>
bation,<lb/>
in<lb/>
hours.</cell><cell>Result.</cell><cell>Order<lb/>
of oc-<lb/>
cur-<lb/>
rence.</cell><cell>Date of<lb/>
occurrence.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>I.........</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>2 p. m......</cell><cell>Dec. 5, 1900</cell><cell>Mosquito.</cell><cell>81 1/2</cell><cell>Positive..</cell><cell>I.....</cell><cell>Dec. 8, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>II........</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4 p. m......</cell><cell>Dec. 8, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>137</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>III...</cell><cell>Dec. 13, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>III.......</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>10.30 a. m...</cell><cell>Dec. 9, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>83 1/2</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>II.....</cell><cell>Dec. 12, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>IV........</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>4.30 p. m....</cell><cell>Dec. 11, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>91 1/2</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>IV....</cell><cell>Dec. 15, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>V.........</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>12 noon.....</cell><cell>Dec. 21, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>95</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>V.....</cell><cell>Dec. 25, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VI........</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>10 a. m.....</cell><cell>Jan 8, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>Negative.</cell><cell>VI....</cell><cell>..............</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VII.......</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>11 a. m.....</cell><cell>Dec. 30, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>94 1/2</cell><cell>Positive..</cell><cell>VII...</cell><cell>Jan. 3, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VIII......</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>8.30 p. m....</cell><cell>Jan. 19, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>95 1/2</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>VIII..</cell><cell>Jan. 23, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>IX.......</cell><cell>74</cell><cell>10.30 a. m...</cell><cell>Jan. 25, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>Negative.</cell><cell>IX....</cell><cell>..............</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>X.........</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9.30 a. m....</cell><cell>Jan. 31, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>74 1/2</cell><cell>Positive..</cell><cell>X.....</cell><cell>Feb 3, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>XI.......</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>11 a. m......</cell><cell>Feb. 6, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>XI....</cell><cell>Feb. 9, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>XII.......</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>2 p. m......</cell><cell>Feb. 7, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>XII...</cell><cell>Feb. 10, 1901</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>The positive results obtained, therefore, by this mode of infection stand in striking<lb/>
contrast to the negative experiments made with fomites. Indeed, Cases VIII and XI<lb/>
of Table II had each slept twenty-one nights in the garments of yellow-fever patients<lb/>
while occupants of building No. 1. As they had remained in perfect health at Camp<lb/>
Lazear for yet thirty days longer, they were at the expiration of this time bitten by<lb/>
infected mosquitoes solely for the purpose of testing their immunity and with the<lb/>
result that an attack of yellow fever promptly followed in each case.</p>
<p>It should be borne in mind also that of the nonimmune residents at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
while all lived under the same hygienic conditions, only those individuals developed<lb/>
yellow fever who were purposely bitten by contaminated mosquitoes, or injected with<lb/>
the blood of those sick with this disease. Moreover, the precision with which the<lb/>
infection of the individual followed the bite of the mosquito left nothing to be desired<lb/>
in order to fulfill the requirements of a scientific experiment.</p>
<p>Case V of Table II is of especial interest, when taken in connection with the failure<lb/>
to induce the disease by contact with fomites.</p>
<p>This individual, having been quarantined for thirty-two days at Camp Lazear, vol-<lb/>
unteered to enter a newly erected building in which fifteen contaminated mosquitoes<lb/>
had just been freed. His first visit was at noon, December 21, 1901, and the length of<lb/>
his stay thirty minutes. At 4.30 p. m. the same day he again entered this building<lb/>
and remained twenty minutes. The following day at 4.30 p. m. he for the third time<lb/>
visited this room and remained twenty minutes. During each of these visits he was<lb/>
bitten by mosquitoes. He did not enter the building again, nor was he exposed to any<lb/>
other source of infection. Nevertheless, at the expiration of three days and twenty-<lb/>
three hours, or at 6 a. m., December 25, 1900, he was suddenly seized with an attack<lb/>
of yellow fever, which proved to be severe in character. That the infection was occa-<lb/>
sioned by the bites of contaminated mosquitoe was plainly shown by the immunity<lb/>
from the disease enjoyed by two nonimmune &ldquo;controls,&rdquo; who, protected only by a<lb/>
wire-screen partition, had been present at each of the subject's visits and who, under<lb/>
the same conditions of security against the bites of the infected mosquitoes, continued<lb/>
to sleep in and breathe the common atmosphere of this room for yet eighteen nights.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f00438008"/>
<p>8</p>
<p>JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.</p>
<p>To the positive cases contained in Table II, which were produced at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
we are now able to add four other cases of yellow fever occasioned by the bites of<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, thus making a total of 14 cases, in each of which happily recovery<lb/>
followed.</p>
<p>A very important point brought out by these observations is that an interval of about<lb/>
twelve days or more after contamination appears to be necessary before the infected<lb/>
Stegomyia is capable of conveying the disease to a susceptible individual. Repeated<lb/>
experiments made with insects which had bitten yellow-fever patients two to ten days<lb/>
previously were always negative, although these same insects were proven capable of<lb/>
conveying the disease after having been kept until seventeen to twenty-four days had<lb/>
elapsed. Our observations further demonstrate that mosquitoes that have been kept<lb/>
for periods varying from thirty-nine to fifty-seven days after contamination are still<lb/>
capable of conveying the disease, and, further, that infected Stegomyia may survive<lb/>
for a period of at least seventy-one days. This will explain how the contagion of yellow<lb/>
fever may cling to a building, although it has been vacated for a period of two or more<lb/>
months.</p>
<p>Bearing in mind that the observations made by means of blood injections (Table I)<lb/>
were only undertaken after we had succeeded in demonstrating that the disease could<lb/>
be conveyed by the bites of infected Stegomyia, it will be seen that our study of the<lb/>
method of propagation of yellow fever at Camp Lazear sufficed to prove very definitely,<lb/>
that, while the natural mode of transmission of this disease is through the bites of<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, yellow fever may also be conveyed, like malarial fever, by the<lb/>
injection of a small quantity of blood taken from the veins of an individual suffering<lb/>
with this disease.</p>
<p>Per contra, our observations show that notwithstanding the common belief in this<lb/>
mode of transmission, yellow fever can not be induced in the nonimmune individual<lb/>
even by the most intimate contact with contaminated articles of clothing and bedding.</p>
<p>Although the investigations made at Camp Lazear were only concluded one year<lb/>
ago, already confirmatory evidence of the strongest character has been furnished in a<lb/>
series of experiments carried out by Guit&eacute;ras at the inoculation station of the sanitary<lb/>
department at Habana.</p>
<p>I may be pardoned for quoting the paragraph with which Guit&eacute;ras begins his con-<lb/>
tribution. He says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The favorable results obtained by the U. S. Army commission in their experiments<lb/>
with yellow fever, the continued series of mild cases resulting from these experi-<lb/>
ments without a death, suggested very naturally the continuation of their work on a<lb/>
larger scale; not with a view to control or confirm the conclusions of the commission,<lb/>
for anyone who had followed their work with unprejudiced attention must have con-<lb/>
cluded that their solution of the problem of the etiology of yellow fever was final; but<lb/>
rather in the hope of propagating the disease in a controllable form, and securing<lb/>
among the recently arrived immigrants immunization with the minimum amount of<lb/>
danger to themselves and the community.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Of a total of 42 individuals inoculated by Guit&eacute;ras 25 were rejected by him by reason<lb/>
of having been bitten by insects that had been applied to cases of fever about which<lb/>
the diagnosis was in doubt. The following table, therefore, only includes 17 persons<lb/>
who were bitten by Stegomyia that had previously fed on unmistakable cases of yellow<lb/>
fever at intervals of fourteen to thirty-six days before being applied to the nonimmune<lb/>
subject.</p>
<p>TABLE III.<lb/>
<table rows="18" cols="5">
<row>
<cell>No. of case.</cell><cell>Date of inocu-<lb/>
lation.</cell><cell>Mode of inocu-<lb/>
lation.</cell><cell>Result.</cell><cell>Period of incuba-<lb/>
tion.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1.........................</cell><cell>Feb. 23, 1901</cell><cell>Mosquito.........</cell><cell>Positive............</cell><cell>3 days, 10 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 4, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative...........</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3.........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do..............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 7, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 8, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Positive............</cell><cell>4 days, 5 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6.........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do..............</cell><cell>3 days, 3 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>7.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 7, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>8.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 9, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Positive............</cell><cell>5 days, 3 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>9.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 10, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>10.........................</cell><cell>.....do...........</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>11.........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>12.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 13, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Positive............</cell><cell>3 days, 19 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>13.........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>14.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 14, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Positive............</cell><cell>3 days, 21 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>15.........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>5 days, 21 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>16.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 22, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>3 days.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>17.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 24, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative...........</cell><cell></cell></row>
</table></p>
<pb n="9" id="f00438009"/>
<p>JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.</p>
<p>9</p>
<p>A more complete confirmation of the results obtained by the American commission<lb/>
could not be furnished than the data contained in the foregoing table, since they<lb/>
show that of 17 individuals who were bitten by infected Stegomyia fasciata, 8 (47 per<lb/>
cent) developed the disease. Most unfortunately in three of these cases very grave<lb/>
symptoms ensued, such as black vomit and suppression of the urine, which eventuated<lb/>
in the death of the patients. I may add that in the hands of Guit&eacute;ras fomites failed to<lb/>
exert any effect on nonimmunes.</p>
<p>Whether other species of mosquitoes than Stegomyia are capable of conveying the<lb/>
parasite of yellow fever has not as yet been determined by the commission, nor have<lb/>
we been able to ascertain whether the parasite passes from the mother insect to daughter<lb/>
insects. The experiments which we have thus far been able to make for the purpose<lb/>
of determining these important points, although negative, have been too few in number<lb/>
to warrant any definite expression of opinion.</p>
<p>THE PREVENTION OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>The definite determination of the way in which yellow fever is transmitted from<lb/>
the sick to the well furnishes a solution at last of that much-vexed problem of how to<lb/>
prevent the spread of the disease. Even in the absence of more definite knowledge<lb/>
concerning its specific agent--knowledge greatly to be desired from the scientific<lb/>
standpoint--we are now able, as sanitarians, to direct our efforts along certain well-<lb/>
defined lines, with a feeling of security heretofore unknown.</p>
<p>From the point of view of prevention the situation may be briefly summed up in<lb/>
the following conclusion, which was presented by the American army commission to<lb/>
the Pan-American Congress of 1900, viz, &ldquo;The spread of yellow fever can be most<lb/>
effectually controlled by measures directed to the destruction of mosquitoes and the<lb/>
protection of the sick against the bites of these insects.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This conclusion was the logical outcome of the observations that had been made by<lb/>
the commission at its experimental station near Quemados, Cuba.</p>
<p>The importance of the discovery that yellow fever is transmitted by the bite of a<lb/>
certain species of mosquito did not fail to attract the prompt attention of the military<lb/>
governor of the island of Cuba, himself a physician and formerly a distinguished<lb/>
member of the Medical Department of the U. S. Army. By his direction the theory<lb/>
was at once subjected to a practical test in the city of Habana, in which city yellow<lb/>
fever had not failed to make its yearly appearance during the past one hundred and<lb/>
forty years.</p>
<p>Under the efficient management of the chief sanitary officer, Surg. Maj. William<lb/>
C. Gorgas, U. S. Army, the sanitary regulations were so far modified as to require that<lb/>
every patient having yellow fever should not only be quarantined, but that his room<lb/>
should be promptly protected with wire screens, so as to prevent the possibility of<lb/>
mosquitoes becoming infected by sucking the blood of the patient. As a second<lb/>
important measure, a systematic destruction of all mosquitoes in other rooms of the<lb/>
patient's house, as well as in adjoining houses, was at once begun, the fumes of pyr-<lb/>
ethrum being relied upon to stupefy the insects, after which they were carefully swept<lb/>
up and burned. In other words, Surgeon-Major Gorgas, relying upon the well-known<lb/>
slow progress of yellow fever, sought to destroy all mosquitoes, infected or noninfected,<lb/>
within a given radius of each case, while at the same time he effectually excluded<lb/>
all mosquitoes from access to the sick. If a secondary case occurred, the same hygienic<lb/>
measures were vigorously enforced along the lines indicated.</p>
<p>As an illustration of what has been accomplished by these newer sanitary regula-<lb/>
tions, I may state that counting from the date when they were put into force, viz,<lb/>
February 15, 1901--Habana was freed from yellow fever within ninety days; so that<lb/>
from May 7 to July 1--a period of fifty-four days--no cases occurred. Notwithstand-<lb/>
ing the fact that on the latter date and during the months of July, August, and Sep-<lb/>
tember the disease was repeatedly reintroduced into Habana from an inland town,<lb/>
no difficulty was encountered in promptly stamping it out by the same measures of<lb/>
sanitation intelligently applied both in the city of Habana as well as in the town of<lb/>
Santiago de las Vegas, whence the disease was being brought into Habana.</p>
<p>Maj. Walter Reed died in Washington November 23, 1902, from<lb/>
acute appendicitis, and his widow was given a pension of $125 per<lb/>
month by special act of Congress in recognition of the services of her<lb/>
husband in the yellow fever investigations. At the beginning of the<lb/>
present Congress a bill, S. 1157, was introduced by Senator Dick<lb/>
granting a pension of $125 per month to Mrs. Jennie Carroll, and a<lb/>
like bill, S. 1168, was introduced by Senator Knox for Mrs. Mabel<lb/>
Lazear. These bills were called to the attention of President Roose-<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f00438010"/>
10<lb/>
JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.<lb/>
velt, and the following letter to the chairman of the Senate Committee<lb/>
on Pensions shows his attitude toward the proposed legislation.</p>
<p>JANUARY 31, 1908.</p>
<p>The CHAIRMAN OF THE SENATE COMMITTEE ON PENSIONS:</p>
<p>I call your particular attention to the accompanying memorandum from the Surgeon-<lb/>
General of the Army in behalf of the widows and children of Dr. James Carroll and<lb/>
Dr. Jesse W. Lazear. I earnestly hope the pensions can be provided for in both cases.</p>
<p>THEODORE ROOSEVELT.</p>
<p>The following is the memorandum prepared by the Surgeon-General,<lb/>
Robert M. O'Reilly, and gives a comprehensive history of the services<lb/>
in these investigations of the officers named in the bill:</p>
<p>[Memorandum for the President.]</p>
<p>IN BEHALF OF THE WIDOWS AND CHILDREN OF DR. JAMES CARROLL AND DR. JESSE W.<lb/>
LAZEAR.</p>
<p>When the yellow-fever commission, composed of Walter Reed, James Carroll, Jesse<lb/>
W. Lazear, and A. Agramonte, assembled in Habana, they had no thought of investi-<lb/>
gating the connection of the mosquito with the spread of yellow fever. This idea<lb/>
came to Doctor Reed after the commission had demonstrated that the claim of San-<lb/>
arelli in favor of the bacillus icteroides was without foundation. The final deter-<lb/>
mination to investigate the mosquito theory was arrived at during an informal meeting<lb/>
of the commission at Columbia Barracks early in August, 1900. To Doctor Lazear,<lb/>
who was familiar with mosquito work, was assigned the duty of breeding and infecting<lb/>
the mosquitoes, while Doctor Carroll was to continue the bacteriological work in<lb/>
which the commission had been engaged.</p>
<p>Before the mosquitoes were ready for the experiment, Doctor Reed was called back<lb/>
to Washington to prepare for publication the abstract of the report of the board ap-<lb/>
pointed in 1898 to investigate the spread of typhoid fever in the volunteer camps in<lb/>
the United States, of which board he was president.</p>
<p>It was during his absence that the inoculations by means of infected mosquitoes<lb/>
were begun. The first experiment was made on August 11, but was unsuccessful, as<lb/>
sufficient time had not elapsed since the mosquito had bitten a yellow-fever patient<lb/>
to render it infectious. On August 27, Doctor Lazear applied to Doctor Carroll a<lb/>
mosquito which had been fed on four yellow-fever patients. The result was a very<lb/>
severe attack of yellow fever, in which, for a time, his life hung in the balance. This<lb/>
was the first successful experimental case. The fever developed on the 31st of Aug-<lb/>
ust, on which day Doctor Lazear applied the same mosquito which bit Doctor Carroll<lb/>
to another volunteer. This man came down with a mild but well-marked case.</p>
<p>On September 13, Doctor Lazear, while on a visit to Las Animas Hospital, allowed<lb/>
himself to be bitten by a mosquito of undetermined species. Five days thereafter he<lb/>
came down without further exposure with yellow fever, which progressed steadily<lb/>
to a fatal termination. These three cases established in the minds of Reed and Car-<lb/>
roll the proof of the mosquito theory, and formed the basis of their paper, &ldquo;The Etiology<lb/>
of Yellow Fever--A Preliminary Note,&rdquo; read before the American Public Health<lb/>
Association at Buffalo in October, 1900. Doctor Reed immediately returned to<lb/>

Cuba to conduct a second series of experiments, which began November 20, 1900, at<lb/>
an experimental camp near Quemados, called Camp Lazear, and embraced 14 cases,<lb/>
of which the last was taken sick February 10, 1901. All of these cases recovered.</p>
<p>The third series of six cases was produced by Doctor Carroll during the fall of 1901<lb/>
to settle certain undetermined facts as regards the etiology of the disease. The first<lb/>
of these cases came down with the fever September 19, 1901, and the last October 23,<lb/>
1901. None of them resulted fatally.</p>
<p>After this brief history of one of the most brilliant and far-reaching medical dis-<lb/>
coveries, attention is invited to a few facts concerning the three principal members<lb/>
of the commission, and to their untimely and lamented deaths.</p>
<p>Maj. Walter Reed, surgeon, U. S. Army, president of the commission, died in<lb/>
Washington from appendicitis, November 23, 1902, at the age of 51. At the time of his<lb/>
death the Secretary of War had said in his report, which was then in press but not yet<lb/>
given out:</p>
<p>"The brilliant character of this scientific achievement, its inestimable value to<lb/>
mankind, the saving of thousands of lives, and the deliverance of the Atlantic seacoast<lb/>
from constant apprehension, demand special recognition from the Government of<lb/>
the United States.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doctor Reed is the ranking major in the Medical Department, and within a few<lb/>
months will, by operation of law, become a lieutenant-colonel. I ask that the Presi-<lb/>
dent be authorized to appoint him assistant surgeon-general with the rank of colonel.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="11" id="f00438011"/>
<p>JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.</p>
<p>11</p>
<p>Gen. Leonard Wood said of him in an address delivered at a memorial meeting of<lb/>
scientific men in Washington, D. C., shortly after his death:</p>
<p>"I know of no other man on this side of the world who has done so much for humanity<lb/>
as Doctor Reed. His discovery results in the saving of more lives annually than were<lb/>
lost in the Cuban war, and saves the commercial interests of the world a greater finan-<lb/>
cial loss each year than the cost of the Cuban war. He came to Cuba at a time when<lb/>
one-third of the officers of my staff died of yellow fever, and we were discouraged at<lb/>
the failure of our efforts to control the disease.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the months when the disease was ordinarily worst, the disease was checked and<lb/>
driven from Habana. That was the first time in nearly two hundred years that the<lb/>
city had been rid of it. The value of his discovery can not be appreciated by persons<lb/>
who are not familiar with the conditions of tropical countries. Hereafter it will never<lb/>
be possible for yellow fever to gain such headway that quarantine will exist from the<lb/>
mouth of the Potomac to the mouth of the Rio Grande. Future generations will<lb/>
appreciate fully the value of Doctor Reed's services.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In a letter from Professor Welch to the Secretary of War he said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doctor Reed's researches in yellow fever are by far the most important contribu-<lb/>
tions to science which have ever come from any army surgeon. In my judgment they<lb/>
are the most valuable contributions to medicine and public hygiene which have ever<lb/>
been made in this country, with the exception of an&aelig;sthesia. They have led and will<lb/>
lead to the saving of thousands of lives.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A bill prepared in this office for a pension for his widow, equal in amount to his<lb/>
monthly pay, was passed, but the amount was so cut down that while it kept the wolf<lb/>
from the door it did not provide an adequate and comfortable income.</p>
<p>To supplement this pension a fund of $25,000 has been raised by the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association, the interest of which will be given to Mrs. Reed during her life-<lb/>
time, and the principal, after her death, will be devoted to some form of memorial.</p>
<p>The second member of the commission was Dr. James Carroll, at that time acting<lb/>
assistant surgeon, U. S. Army. Doctor Carroll was born at Woolwich, England, June<lb/>
5, 1854. He entered the military service June 9, 1874, and served as a private, corporal,<lb/>
sergeant, and hospital steward from that date to May 21, 1898, when he was appointed<lb/>
an acting assistant surgeon. He was appointed first lieutenant and assistant surgeon<lb/>
in the Medical Corps October 27, 1902, and was advanced to the grade of major by<lb/>
special act of Congress approved March 2, 1907, in recognition of his work in Cuba as a<lb/>
member of the yellow fever commission. He died in Washington, D. C., September 16,<lb/>
1907, after a protracted illness, which he always attributed to the severe attack of yellow<lb/>
fever he had in September, 1900.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll was Doctor Reed's colleague and efficient assistant in all the experi-<lb/>
ments which led to the scientific demonstration of the agency of the mosquito in the<lb/>
propagation of yellow fever. As expressed by Dr. Howard A. Kelly, Doctor Reed's<lb/>
biographer. &ldquo;While the experiments were planned by the master mind of the chief,<lb/>
the accuracy with which they were carried out and the care by which all possible<lb/>
precautions were taken to exclude every source of error are due to Doctor Carroll<lb/>
quite as much as to Doctor Reed.&rdquo; As stated above, the third series of experiments<lb/>
were performed by Doctor Carroll alone. Doctor Reed having been refused permis-<lb/>
sion to return to Cuba for the purpose. These experiments completed the demon-<lb/>
stration of the mosquito doctrine of yellow-fever infection. They proved, among<lb/>
other things, that the filtered blood serum of a yellow-fever patient is still capable<lb/>
of conveying the disease, and, therefore, that the specific agent was either a virulent<lb/>
toxin or an organism so tenuous as to elude the search of the microscope.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll left a wife and seven children without adequate means of support. It<lb/>
is presumed that his widow will receive the pension allowed by the Government for<lb/>
a major of the Army and $2 a month for each of the five minor children.</p>
<p>Dr. Jesse W. Lazear was the third member of the commission.</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear was a native of Baltimore and a graduate of Johns Hopkins Univer-<lb/>
sity, afterwards getting his professional degree at Columbia University and Bellevue.<lb/>
At the time he incurred the attack of yellow fever from which he died, in the course<lb/>
of these experiments, as above mentioned, he was 34 years old. He left a wife and<lb/>
two young children, the younger a little son born a few months before his death,<lb/>
whom he never saw. Mrs. Lazear receives from Congress a pension of $17 a month,<lb/>
with $2 additional for each of two minor children. A battery in Baltimore Harbor<lb/>
has also, by direction of the Secretary of War, been named in his honor. This is all<lb/>
the recognition that his work has so far received from the nation.</p>
<p>The services of Doctor Carroll and Doctor Lazear, under the leadership of Doctor<lb/>
Reed, in making possible the control and extirpation of yellow fever, thus bringing<lb/>
about the saving of thousands of lives and millions of treasure, have done so much for<lb/>
humanity and reflected so much honor and glory upon the American medical pro-<lb/>
fession that it is believed Congress will not hesitate to take action for the relief of<lb/>
their widows and children when all the facts are clearly brought before it.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f00438012"/>
<p>12</p>
<p>JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.</p>
<p>In contrast to the seeming indifference of this Government to reward distinguished<lb/>
achievements in medicine, let it be remembered that the English Government gave<lb/>
to Jenner, the discoverer of vaccination, grants amounting to &pound;30,000, and that he<lb/>
also received &pound;7,383 from a subscription in India.</p>
<p>Bills have been introduced into the present Congress to give a suitable pension to<lb/>
Mrs. Carroll and Mrs. Lazear, and it is believed they will receive favorable consider-<lb/>
ation if the President will exert his great personal influence in their behalf.</p>
<p>R. M. O'REILLY,<lb/>
Surgeon-General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>The following facts are ascertained by evidence filed with your<lb/>
committee concerning the beneficiaries named in the bill:</p>
<p>S. 1157. Jennie M. George Lucas Carroll is the widow of James<lb/>
Carroll, late major and surgeon, United States Army. Doctor Car-<lb/>
roll entered the Regular Army as a private in January, 1874. He was<lb/>
appointed hospital steward September 15, 1883, and served continu-<lb/>
ously in that capacity until May 21, 1898. During the war with<lb/>
Spain, and subsequently until October 29, 1900, he was acting assist-<lb/>
ant surgeon or contract surgeon in the Army and rendered conspicu-<lb/>
ous service in Cuba in locating the source and development of yellow-<lb/>
fever infection. In recognition of this great work he was appointed,<lb/>
October 27, 1902, assistant surgeon in the Army and served as first<lb/>
lieutenant until May 2, 1907, when Congress by special act created<lb/>
him a major. Doctor Carroll died in Washington October 7, 1907,<lb/>
of heart disease brought on, as stated by affidavit of physician filed<lb/>
with your committee, by attack of yellow fever incurred while mak-<lb/>
ing experiments and permitting himself to be bitten by an infected<lb/>
mosquito. He left a wife and seven minor children. His widow,<lb/>
claimant under this bill, was granted a general-law pension as widow<lb/>
of a lieutenant of $25 per month with $2 per month for each of six<lb/>
minor children, the youngest of whom was born in June, 1906, and<lb/>
the eldest of whom is now about to attain the age of 16 years. Mrs.<lb/>
Carroll is now about 37 years of age, and affidavits filed with your<lb/>
committee by responsible parties are to the effect that Mrs. Carroll<lb/>
has no property whatsoever or any income other than her pension,<lb/>
with the exception of a small equity in a house which was purchased<lb/>
the year before the death of Doctor Carroll, and which is encumbered<lb/>
by two deeds of trust aggregating over $7,500, and, as sworn to by the<lb/>
attorney for the deceased officer, in all probabilities it could not be<lb/>
sold for more than enough to pay the indebtedness against it. It is<lb/>
also shown that Mrs. Carroll is a woman in delicate health, unable to<lb/>
earn a livelihood for herself and seven children, and is in great need<lb/>
of financial assistance.</p>
<p>S. 1168. Mabel H. Lazear is the widow of Dr. Jesse W. Lazear.<lb/>
She was pensioned by special act of Congress at $17 per month during<lb/>
the first session of the Fifty-seventh Congress, with an additional<lb/>
allowance of $2 per month for each of her two minor children under<lb/>
the age of 16 years. Doctor Lazear was not a regularly commissioned<lb/>
officer of the Army. He served under contract in Cuba as acting<lb/>
assistant surgeon, United States Army, from February 5, 1900,<lb/>
until his death, September 25, 1900. His death is believed to be<lb/>
due to experiments made upon himself with infected mosquitoes to<lb/>
demonstrate the theory that the yellow fever infection was carried<lb/>
by the mosquito. The following letter from the Surgeon-General<lb/>
gives a complete history of his services.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f00438013"/>
<p>JENNIE M. CARROLL AND MABEL H. LAZEAR.</p>
<p>13</p>
<p>JANUARY 28, 1901.</p>
<p>SIR: Referring to your commission of the 26th instant, I have the honor to<lb/>
inform the Committee on Pensions, United States Senate, that Dr. Jesse W. Lazear,<lb/>
of Baltimore. Md., entered into contract February 5, 1900, at Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
with the Surgeon-General, United States Army, for service as an acting assistant<lb/>
surgeon, United States Army, compensation $150 per month. In obedience to orders,<lb/>
he proceeded at once to Columbia Barracks. Cuba, where he was stationed until his<lb/>
death September 25, 1900. May 24, 1900, he was appointed a member of a board<lb/>
to study infectious diseases prevalent in Cuba, and he was connected with this board<lb/>
during the remainder of his service. He was taken sick with yellow fever on Sep-<lb/>
tember 19 and died with this disease September 25. His death is believed to have<lb/>
been due to an experiment which he made upon himself with a view to obtaining<lb/>
positive evidence with reference to the manner in which this fatal infectious disease<lb/>
is communicated to man. Although his service was comparatively short his risking<lb/>
his life in the prosecution of the important duties with which he was charged should<lb/>
place him in the same category with those who fight their country's battles.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,</p>
<p>GEO. VON STERNBERG,<lb/>
Surgeon-General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>The CHAIRMAN COMMITTEE ON PENSIONS,<lb/>
U. S. Senate, Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>In view of the fact that Congress has established a precedent by<lb/>
granting a pension of $125 per month to the widow of Major Reed,<lb/>
the head of this commission, your committee believe that the other<lb/>
members of the commission are entitled to equal recognition, and<lb/>
with a view of rendering a fitting recognition of the great and bene-<lb/>
ficial discoveries of those men your committee are of the opinion<lb/>
that their widows should not be allowed to want for the necessities<lb/>
of life, and that a grateful Government can well afford to encourage<lb/>
future explorations by allowing these widows each a pension of $125<lb/>
per month, as stated in the bill.</p>
<p>The following individuals and organizations have filed petitions for<lb/>
the enactment of legislation giving adequate pension to Mrs. Carroll<lb/>
and Mrs. Lazear:</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<item>American Medical Association, Chicago, III.</item>
<item>Cleveland Chamber of Commerce, Cleveland, Ohio.</item>
<item>Milwaukee Chamber of Commerce, Milwaukee, Wis.</item>
<item>Portland Board of Trade, Portland, Oreg.</item>
<item>Jacksonville Board of Trade, Jacksonville, Fla.</item>
<item>New London Business Men's Association, New London, Conn.</item>
<item>Indianapolis Board of Trade, Indianapolis, Ind.</item>
<item>Pittsburgh Board of Trade, Pittsburg, Pa.</item>
<item>Atchison County Medical Association, Rockport, Mo.</item>
<item>Lieut. T. D. Neal Post, No. 124, Bethany, Mo.</item>
<item>Southwest Missouri Medical Society, Aurora, Mo.</item>
<item>Medical Men of Cass County, Mo. (signed by M. P. Overholser), Harrisonville,<lb/>
Mo.</item>
<item>Missouri State Medical Association, Salisbury, Mo.</item>
<item>Clinton County Medical Society, Clinton, Ia.</item>
<item>Wapello County Medical Society, Iowa.</item>
<item>Madison County Medical Association, Missouri.</item>
<item>Plymouth District Medical Society, Brockton, Mass.</item>
<item>Merchants' Association of New York City.</item>
<item>Belknap County Medical Society, Laconia, N. Y.</item>
<item>Merchants' Association of San Francisco, Cal.</item>
<item>Brooklyn League, Brooklyn, N. Y.</item>
<item>American Medical Association of Sumter County, Fla.</item>
<item>Spokane Chamber of Commerce, Spokane, Wash.</item>
<item>Gail D. Allee, secretary Missouri State Medical Association.</item>
<item>J. S. Triplett, M. D., Harrisonville, Mo.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Your committee recommend the passage of the bill.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
