<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00444043">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Circular on Jesse W. Lazear's actions in Cuba, [1908?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00444043</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-00-00">[1908?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00444043</idno>
<title>Circular on Jesse W. Lazear's actions in Cuba, [1908?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This circular relates Lazear's role in the yellow fever research.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-00-00">
<head>Circular on Jesse W. Lazear's actions in Cuba, [1908?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00444043"/>
<opener>
Circular to be endorsed by Reed, Sternberg,<lb/>
Trustees of university &amp; c<lb/>
and sent to Committee-<lb/>
<del>The Lazear Scholarship</del><lb/>
</opener>
<p>On the 25th of September Jesse William Lazear, assistant-surgeon in the United<lb/>
States army and a member of the government Commission for the investigation of yellow<lb/>
fever lost his life from that disease at Quemados, Cuba. The circumstances leading<lb/>
to this sad event were of a very unusual character. Lazear, a native of Baltimore<lb/>
County, Maryland, a graduate of the Johns Hopkins University and of the medical de-<lb/>
partment of Columbia University, New York, a highly educated physician, had pursued<lb/>
important studies and investigations in Europe and in the laboratories of the Johns<lb/>
Hopkins University in Baltimore. He was a member of the staff of the hospital and an<lb/>
instructor in the University. In February 1900 he was induced by the opportunity for<lb/>
research concerning malarial and yellow fevers to enter the United States army as<lb/>
acting assistant-surgeon and was assigned especial laboratory duties at Columbia Bar-<lb/>
racks near Havana. Later he was appointed by the Surgeon-general Sternberg a member<lb/>
of the especial government Commission for the investigation of yellow fever. To the<lb/>
brilliant discoveries of this Commission Lazear contributed largely, the investiga-<lb/>
tions of this Commission leading them to the belief that a certain form of mosquito<lb/>
played an important part in the transmission of the poison of yellow fever. A time<lb/>
was reached, however, when the final proof of this hypothesis could only be determined<lb/>
by direct experiment upon human beings. To this experiment Lazear and another member<lb/>
of the Commission courageously subjected themselves. The latter acquired the disease<lb/>
and recovered, Lazear escaped. Shortly afterwards, however, he repeated the experiment<lb/>
allowing himself to be bitten by a mosquito from a yellow fever ward. He acquired<lb/>
the disease which resulted fatally.</p>
<p>These two positive cases justified the Commission in making a preliminary report,<lb/>
the conclusions of which have since then been entirely confirmed. This discovery<lb/>
has brought about results of incalculable public importance. By demonstrating for the<lb/>
first time the method by which yellow fever is acquired it has afforded us positive<lb/>
(1)<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00444044"/>
and accurate means for protection of the public against the disease with the result<lb/>
that in one year the city of Havana has been for the first time in its history entirely<lb/>
free from this malady.</p>
<p>No sacrifice could be more deliberate or courageous than that of Lazear and the<lb/>
great results which have followed should insure to his memory the lasting gratitude<lb/>
of his fellow countrymen.</p>
<p>Dr. Lazear left a wife and two children in circumstances which oblige her to apply<lb/>
for a pension. Surely no soldier dead in battle could deserve more from his country<lb/>
than this man who by deliberately sacrificing his life has directly contributed to the<lb/>
saving of thousands of others.</p>
<p>(2)</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

