<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00455006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [S.C. Mead] to Daniel R. Anthony, June 20, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Mead, S.C.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00455006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-06-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Anthony Jr., Daniel R.,</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-06-20">June 20, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00455006</idno>
<title>Letter from [S.C. Mead] to Daniel R. Anthony, June 20, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Mead] writes to Congressman Anthony in support of the continuation of Mabel Lazear's annuity.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-06-20">
<head>Letter from [S.C. Mead] to Daniel R. Anthony, June 20, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00455006"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1922-06-20">June 20, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Honorable Daniel R. Anthony, Jr., Chairman,<lb/>
Subcommittee of Committee on Appropriations,<lb/>
House of Representatives,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>We have just learned that in the preparation of the War<lb/>
Department Appropriation Bill your Committee is very properly seeking<lb/>
information concerning the annuity which was granted by Congress in<lb/>
1908 to Mrs. Mabel H. Lazear at the same time that a similar annuity<lb/>
was granted to Mrs. Jennie H. Carroll.</p>
<p>It so happens that The Merchants' Association of New York<lb/>
took leadership in urging Congress at that time to grant these annu-<lb/>
ities, in which movement commercial organizations of <add>the</add> country generally,<lb/>
particularly those located on the Atlantic and Pacific seaboards and<lb/>
the Gulf of Mexico, and the American Medical Association actively co-<lb/>
operated.</p>
<p>The purpose of this letter is to give you and your Committee<lb/>
exact information as to the reasons which impelled the Association to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00455007"/>
Hon. Daniel R. Anthony, Jr., Chairman<lb/>
#2<lb/>
urge that action at that time, which reasons we feel are equally op-<lb/>
erative today as then.</p>
<p>Doctor Jesse W. Lazear, as well as Major James Carroll, was<lb/>
a member of the so-called Yellow Fever Commission, which undertook to<lb/>
determine the method of transmission and propagation of yellow fever<lb/>
germs to the end that determination of the cause and method of trans-<lb/>
mission might provide information upon which effective prevention of<lb/>
that scourge could be determined and applied. Many tests were made<lb/>
by the members of that Commission, including among others the volun-<lb/>
tary submission by Doctor Lazear and Major Carroll to the bite of the<lb/>
mosquito, which was suspected to be the germ carrier. As a result of<lb/>
such submission to inoculation by the mosquito these two men actually<lb/>
contracted yellow fever, which voluntary act in the service of humanity<lb/>
resulted finally in the death of these two men. The self-sacrifice,<lb/>
however, proved the case and provided the basis of knowledge upon which<lb/>
it has been possible to prevent any serious yellow fever scourge in<lb/>
this or other countries since that time.</p>
<p>Because of this sacrifice of service on the part of those two<lb/>
men, which resulted not merely in the elimination of suffering and death<lb/>
from yellow fever but also in service of incalculable value to the<lb/>
business of the United States engaged in trade and commerce, this Asso-<lb/>
ciation advocated that the widows of these two gentlemen should be ap-<lb/>
propriately recognized by an annuity granted by Congress.</p>
<p>The Association's investigation at that time proved that<lb/>
Doctor Lazear and Major Carroll, by their death, left their families<lb/>
without adequate means of support. That fact was emphasized by<lb/>
Brigadier-General Robert M. O'Reilly, then Surgeon-General of the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00455008"/>
Hon. Daniel R. Anthony, Jr., Chairman<lb/>
#3<lb/>
United States, in his Memorandum to Honorable Theodore Roosevelt,<lb/>
President of the United States, urging fitting recognition of the im-<lb/>
portant service of these two members of the Yellow Fever Commission.<lb/>
The facts presented by the Surgeon-General so appealed to President<lb/>
Roosevelt that the latter transmitted the Memorandum to Congress with<lb/>
his favorable endorsement.</p>
<p>Later, the propriety of such action was again emphasized, in<lb/>
the passage, by unanimous vote of the United States Senate and the<lb/>
House of Representatives, of the necessary legislation, in response to<lb/>
the desire for such recognition expressed by every section of the country,<lb/>
when the financial status of the families of Doctor Lazear and Major<lb/>
Carroll became known, especially as other members of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission were appropriately taken care of.</p>
<p>What change, if any, has taken place since 1908 in the fi-<lb/>
nancial resources of either of these two ladies we do not know. We<lb/>
understand, however, that in the case of Mrs. Lazear, at least, she is<lb/>
still entirely dependent upon the annuity granted by Congress in 1908.<lb/>
If this is the fact, we respectfully submit that the causes which not<lb/>
only justified but as a matter of justice required the granting of the<lb/>
annuity in 1908 still continue in full effect and we therefore urge<lb/>
upon your Committee that the annuities be continued in recognition of<lb/>
the enormous service to mankind as well as to business, in the rendering<lb/>
of which these two men sacrifice their lives.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very truly,</salute>
<signed>THE MERCHANTS' ASSOCIATION OF NEW YORK,<lb/>
By<lb/>
Secretary</signed>.
SB<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
