<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00459001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jedediah Tingle to Mabel H. Lazear, June 4, 1927</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Tingle, Jebediah</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00459001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-06-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lazear, Mabel H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-06-04">June 4, 1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00459001</idno>
<title>Letter from Jedediah Tingle to Mabel H. Lazear, June 4, 1927</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>"Tingle" decries the lack of recognition of Lazear's heroism and sends some money to Mabel Lazear. The stationery is imprinted with the story of Tingle, a pseudonym used by philanthropists who wish to remain anonymous.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1927-06-04">
<head>Letter from Jedediah Tingle to Mabel H. Lazear, June 4, 1927</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00459001"/>
<p>J.T+1750-1820<lb/>
<date value="1927-06-04">June 4, 1927.</date>
Mrs. Jesse Lazear,<lb/>
Care of Adjutant General,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
Dear Mrs. Lazear:</p>
<p>How emotional, mercurial, thoughtless<lb/>
is mankind. On Admiral Dewey's arrival from his<lb/>
Manilla victory, it drove itself half mad with<lb/>
enthusiasm, showering him with honors and gifts, and<lb/>
a week later buried him in vindictive anathema for<lb/>
giving to his wife one of the public offerings, a home,<lb/>
like the gallant gentleman he always was.</p>
<p>Today the world is hysteria driven<lb/>
over the truly marvelous sporting achievment of<lb/>
Charlie Lindbergh, but I fear me much that tomorrow<lb/>
or next day the wind of public favor will blow<lb/>
chill from another quarter due to some trivial error<lb/>
the young man may make - perhaps unconsciously.</p>
<p>I think the most or one of the most<lb/>
pathetic evidences of injustice in the distribution<lb/>
of honors for heroism at the hands of a democracy<lb/>
was in the case of your husband who laid down his<lb/>
life so willingly on the battlefield of science for<lb/>
life and health and through whose sacrifice thousands<lb/>
are in the world today and countries have been<lb/>
peopled and prospered that were heretofore a pest hole.<lb/>
No honor could have wiped out his loss but at least<lb/>
the nation might have indicated a recognition of its<lb/>
debt by crowning his loved ones with public<lb/>
favor and surrounding them with some of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00459002"/>
luxuries within its vast power. However, dear Mrs. Lazear,<lb/>
there are tenacious memories even in a democracy and a<lb/>
thousand years hence Jesse will be better known and<lb/>
more widely honored than today. As a token of my own<lb/>
belated recognition of the lowly and voiceless, I am<lb/>
enclosing my check for twenty dollars, drawn out perhaps<lb/>
not so much by your needs and Jesse's desserts as by<lb/>
a feeling of sadness that his grave is not heaped with<lb/>
flowers and watered with tears, and that you are not<lb/>
one of the publicly honored of the nation.</p>
<p>Yours sincerely,<lb/>
Jedediah Tingle<lb/>
In acknowledging, address in care of<lb/>
The American Trust Company<lb/>
209 Montague Street<lb/>
Brooklyn, N.Y.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00459003"/>
<p>Reprint from the Bowling Green Column of the New<lb/>
York Evening Post.</p>
<p>MR. JEDEDIAH TINGLE</p>
<p>Occasionally, in recent years, various people have<lb/>
been startled to receive a letter, most charmingly<lb/>
phrased, expressing gratitude for something they have<lb/>
done or painted or written or said, and signed Jedediah<lb/>
Tingle. These people have justly suspected that<lb/>
Jedediah Tingle is a pseudonym, but they have found<lb/>
that the check was perfectly valid and cashable or the<lb/>
book worth reading.</p>
<p>Now one of the most pleasing adventures we have<lb/>
had lately was a call from Mr. Tingle himself. He<lb/>
did not come, we must explain, to exert his benevo-<lb/>
lence upon ourself, but to consult us about a certain<lb/>
phase of his recreation of secretly rewarding, in a<lb/>
modest way, those whose works appealed to him.<lb/>
He did not tell us his real name, and we have no<lb/>
desire to know who he is, other than that he is a<lb/>
thoughtful business man who has found great delight<lb/>
in these mysterious gestures of helpfulness. To<lb/>
identify him would not only necessarily put an end<lb/>
to his cheerful avocation, but would also deprive the<lb/>
situation of its unique charm.</p>
<p>The secret circle of those who have received these<lb/>
letters from Jedediah Tingle is a curiously assorted<lb/>
one. We have had some of the letters shown us, in<lb/>
the past, by those who have received them. These<lb/>
letters have gone to Cabinet Ministers and to obscure,<lb/>
struggling poets, to great writers and to unknown<lb/>
heroes. But the point is this--while Mr. Tingle tells<lb/>
us he has greatly enjoyed the occasional acknowledg-<lb/>
ments that have come to him by being addressed to<lb/>
the banks on which his checks are drawn, certain<lb/>
individuals and newspapers have made determined<lb/>
attempts to unmask his innocent secret. We would<lb/>
like to ask all Managing Editors and others to be<lb/>
good sports and not spoil this admirable innocent<lb/>
generosity by trying to discover its source.</p>
<p>CHRISTOPHER MORLEY.</p>
<p>* * *</p>
<p>The undersigned feels mildly resentful at being<lb/>
called a &ldquo;pseudonym.&rdquo; He harbors a strong suspicion<lb/>
that he is the living incarnation of his own great<lb/>
grandfather whose name he has taken and who in<lb/>
turn came from generations of Abou Ben Adhems.</p>
<p>In 1820 they placed his bones in a country grave-<lb/>
yard in the Middle West, now an abandoned tangle<lb/>
of grasses, briars and broken<lb/>
trees, but that event was<lb/>
probably merely an episode<lb/>
in an eternal mission, which<lb/>
is to bring smiles and tender<lb/>
thoughts to the great in heart<lb/>
--in high and low places. To<lb/>
comfort and cheer those who<lb/>
do exceptional things, or<lb/>
suffer.</p>
<p>J.T+1750-1820</p>
<p>JEDEDIAH TINGLE</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
