<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00467001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Mabel H. Lazear, July 15, 1930</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Agramonte, Aristides</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00467001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1930-07-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lazear, Mabel H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1930-07-15">July 15, 1930</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00467001</idno>
<title>Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Mabel H. Lazear, July 15, 1930</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Agramonte reports that Columbia University plans an unveiling of a memorial plaque in honor of Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1930-07-15">
<head>Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Mabel H. Lazear, July 15, 1930</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00467001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
DR. ARISTIDES AGRAMONTE<lb/>
CALLE K. ENTRE 15 Y 17<lb/>
VEDADO, HABANA <date value="1930-07-15">July 15th, 1930</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. Mabel M. Lazear<lb/>
#6 Oakvale Ave<lb/>
Berkeley, Cal.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mrs. Lazear:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The Medical Faculty of Columbia University, some time in the<lb/>
Fall, will consider my suggestion to have a memorial placque, or tablet,<lb/>
or some such evident memento, erected in the halls of the Medical School,<lb/>
in honor to the immortal memory of Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, Clas of 1892.<lb/>
I am informed that it will be favorably acted upon.</p>
<p>I need not tell you that I shall leave nothing undone so as to have this<lb/>
tribute rendered to him, as I believe that, until the moment of his de-<lb/>
cease, he was the most important and the best trained member of the Army<lb/>
Board, in the service of which he met an untimely death.</p>
<p>In order to better carry out my purpose, I am very anxious to obtain<lb/>
certain data that I cannot get from any other <del>d</del> source than yourself, with<lb/>
regard to his family history and the early part of his life. His scientif-<lb/>
ic history we are well acquainted with; he was my classmate, as you may<lb/>
know, and every moment of our contact at Camp Columbia is still vivid in<lb/>
my mind, until the moment of his passing away at the hospital, which day<lb/>
I shall never forget, as long as I live.</p>
<p>Do you know that there is a bronze bust erected to his memory, in a<lb/>
little park facing our Sanitary Department, here? Reed and Carroll are<lb/>
also equally represented, but I unveiled Lazear's and made the correspond-<lb/>
ing address, at the time.</p>
<p>Will you let me know the following:<lb/>
What does the initial W stand for in the name Jesse W. Lazear?<lb/>
Date of his birth, and where.<lb/>
As much of his ancestors as you may know;<lb/>
Father's and Mother's names<lb/>
Father's profession or calling;<lb/>
Date of your wedding and where<lb/>
Your maiden name<lb/>
Your parents' names<lb/>
Your children's names and ages now.</p>
<p>Whatever you may think of interest regarding Lazear's early life,<lb/>
school training, surroundings in boyhood and adolescence that may have<lb/>
molded his character, and any other information that you may think per-<lb/>
tinent.</p>
<p>I am sending you herewith, two pamphlets, in which I had occasion to<lb/>
refer to his work and influence in the Board, that perhaps you will be<lb/>
pleased to know. At a recent, (June 22) meeting of the Medical Veterans of<lb/>
the World War, in Detroit, I made an address to an audience composed of the<lb/>
members, their wives and daughters; as I referred to the strenuous days<lb/>
of September 1900, the worry of Carroll's illness, your husband's sacri-<lb/>
fice and what his loss signified to us, there was not an eye but was moist<lb/>
with restrained tears and the silence and attention was almost reverential.<lb/>
My written copy was taken from me and will probably be published in the<lb/>
&ldquo;Military Surgeon&rdquo;. I have repeatedly rebelled against the disdain shown<lb/>
the &ldquo;<hi>working members</hi>&rdquo; of the Board; also against the appellations <del><unclear></unclear></del> &ldquo;Reed's<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00467002"/>
(2)<lb/>
Board&rdquo;, &ldquo;Reed's Discovery&rdquo;, &ldquo;Reed's Commission&rdquo;, &ldquo;Reed's Work&rdquo;, etc. Mainly<lb/>
for the reason that Maj. Reed <hi>was not on hand</hi> when the first series of <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
cases occurred, Carroll, Dean and Lazear, and he only came back to Cuba<lb/>
after the latter's death: then, with Gen. Wood's support and our experience,<lb/>
Carroll's and mine, the rest of the work of the Board was comparatively <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
easy and clear sailing.</p>
<p>I am writing rather extensively, (and tiresomely, perhaps,) because<lb/>
in my many visits to the United States I never had <add>opportunity</add> to see you and talk it<lb/>
over with you.</p>
<p>Thank you in advance for whatever information you may kindly give me,<lb/>
and with my best wishes for for your, and your children's, happiness and<lb/>
good health, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Aristides Agramonte</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
