<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00460001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter fragment to Mabel H. Lazear, January 10, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00460001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-01-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Mead, S. C.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-01-10">January 10, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00460001</idno>
<title>Letter fragment to Mabel H. Lazear, January 10, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The writer reports that an effort is underway to increase the annuities of the yellow fever investigators, volunteers, and their relatives.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1928-01-10">
<head>Letter fragment to Mabel H. Lazear, January 10, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00460001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1928-01-10">January 10, 1928.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Lazear:</salute>
</opener>
<p>This long delay in answering your good letter must seem to you in-<lb/>
excusable. You will pardon it, I am sure, when I tell you that I had a<lb/>
long four months of nervous exhaustion. I get so interested in this<lb/>
campaign to secure something like adequate recognition for those of you<lb/>
who have suffered such neglect all these years that I cannot seem to<lb/>
let go, until Nature steps in and calls a halt. It<del>s</del> was nothing serious,<lb/>
all I needed was a rest--and perhaps to give my friends a rest! I am<lb/>
all right now with the exception of a bad cold.</p>
<p>You will see by the enclosures that we have not been idle all these<lb/>
weeks. I had a very interesting talk with Mr. Mead last Saturday. He<lb/>
told me how the Merchants' Association became interested in securing the<lb/>
annuities for you, Mrs. Reed, Mrs. Carroll and the Kissingers, and he<lb/>
promises all the help his organization can give in this new endeavor of<lb/>
which he heartily approves. He suggested that I see the Secretary of<lb/>
the New York Academy of Medicine, for they gave their help in the dis-<lb/>
couraging, but finally successful, campaign at Washington. Dr. Fosdick<lb/>
and the other members of our wonderful Citizens' Committee are glad to<lb/>
continue until we get what we are working for.</p>
<p>We expect the bill for the increased annuities and for the Congress-<lb/>
ional medals will be introduced in the Senate by Senator Copeland of<lb/>
New York and by Congressman Merritt of Connecticut. Both are &ldquo;solD&rdquo; to<lb/>
the plan. The Bronx Home News will print and give to us 2000 copies of<lb/>
the enclosed story (I trust it contains nothing which you would disap-<lb/>
prove of). The OUTLOOK will let us have 2000 copies of their four strong<lb/>
editorials. I am hoping the American Museum of Natural History will<lb/>
print a similar number of copies of my lecture (a copy of which I sent<lb/>
you, I believe) together with illustrations. The White Plains Chamber of<lb/>
Commerce is sending a letter (much like the enclosed editorial which ap-<lb/>
peared in the White Plains Reporter) to every Chamber of Commerce in the<lb/>
United States. Something ought to result before Congress adjourns. Can<lb/>
we not get some organizations out there to do something to insure action<lb/>
among the western members of Congress?</p>
<p>Please give my regards to your son and daughter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially yours,</salute>
<seg>
P. S. It seems very probable that the American Museum will print 5000<lb/>
copies of the lecture I am to give in their large auditorium on February<lb/>
9th. 2000 of these copies will be used with the other material mentioned<lb/>
above for our campaign. The other copies will be used for study in the<lb/>
City High Schools. They plan to include the 35 illustrations from my<lb/>
lantern slides. President H. F. Osborn of the Museum, who has been re-<lb/>
cently elected President of the American Association for the Advancement<lb/>
of Science will do all he can to bring this matter to the attention of<lb/>
the scientists of the country.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
