<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00476001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Translation [from Spanish] of speech by Antonio D. Albertini, September 28, 1936</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00476001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1936-09-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William C.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Hume, Edgar E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="place">Quemados de Marianao</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1936-09-28">September 28, 1936</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00476001</idno>
<title>Translation [from Spanish] of speech by Antonio D. Albertini, September 28, 1936</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Albertini memorializes Lazear and Clara Maass.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1936-09-28">
<head>Translation [from Spanish] of speech by Antonio D. Albertini, September 28, 1936</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00476001"/>
<p>In Nat Acad Sciences Havana under <hi>Albertini</hi> as a list of<lb/>
Albertinis <add>&ldquo;published&rdquo;</add>papers - This paper is listed next to last but no ref given.<lb/>
never published<lb/>
Dr Nogueira will try to locate</p>
<p>ADDRESS BY DOCTOR ANTONIO DIAZ ALBERTINI, DIRECTOR OF &ldquo;LAS ANIMAS&rdquo;<lb/>
HOSPITAL AND PRESIDENT OF THE &ldquo;FINLAY&rdquo; INSTITUTE, TO HONOR THE MEMORIES OF<lb/>
DOCTOR JESSE W. LAZEAR AND MISS CLARA MAASS, SEPTEMBER 28, 1936.</p>
<p>The Finlay Institute, created to honor the memory of our glorious<lb/>
countryman, fulfills today a sacred duty and insofar as possible pays a debt<lb/>
of gratitude of long standing, honoring in this simple but transcendental<lb/>
ceremony the memories of those who, like Lazear and Miss Maass, contributed<lb/>
with their talent and heroism to confirm the discovery of the grand Cuban<lb/>
genius whose name is a glorious seal for our Institute.</p>
<p>Here in &ldquo;Las Animas&rdquo;, seat of immortal findings and experiments of<lb/>
great scientific value, will harbor from today those plaques which will remind<lb/>
future generations of the glory, heroism and martyrdom to science and duty of<lb/>
those two great ones, Lazear and Miss Clara Maass, so deserving of our reverent<lb/>
remembrance.</p>
<p>Dr. Lazear was one of the first victims of yellow fever during the<lb/>
experimental epoch of the American Commission of 1900, formed by Doctors Walter<lb/>
Reed, James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear and Aristides Agramonte. Reed was Pres-<lb/>
ident and Director of the Commission; Carroll had charge of bacteriological<lb/>
investigations; Lazear, all that referred to mosquitoes, Agramonte being the<lb/>
pathologist. The Commission selected for its experiments a pasture field in<lb/>
Quemados de Marianao to which was later given the name of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;, in<lb/>
memory of his name.</p>
<p>Lazear arrived in Cuba months before Reed and Carroll and devoted his<lb/>
time to the observation of yellow fever cases and to the performing of autopsies.<lb/>
<hi>I witnessed in Dr. Finlay's house, No. 110 Aguacate Street, the presentation of<lb/>
the Commission to the great Cuban sage, who delivered to Dr. Reed a small soap-<lb/>
dish with eggs of Stegomya which ten days before had bitten a case of yellow<lb/>
fever.</hi>. While Dr. Reed was absent in the United States, Lazear allowed an infected<lb/>
mosquito, which had rested on his hand, to bite him. This happened here in this<lb/>
historic yellow fever ward on September 13, 1900. On the night of the 17th,<lb/>
that is to say, on the fifth day, he had a chill, followed by others. The ill-<lb/>
ustrious patient was transferred to the Yellow Fever Isolation Camp. During the<lb/>
first three days he fought bravely but on the fourth day he succumbed to the<lb/>
terribly poisonous &ldquo;black vomit&rdquo;. Such was the end of Lazear; thus terminating,<lb/>
at the age of 34, a life of brilliant promise, great aptitude, nobility of<lb/>
character and an indefatigable worker.</p>
<p>find<lb/>
out who</p>
<p>get<lb/>
photo<lb/>
house<lb/>
of Finlay</p>
<p>Reed<lb/>
&amp; one other<lb/>
<del>possibly<lb/>
cannot<lb/>
not Agramonte?</del></p>
<p>Lazear " " " " as expert c mos<lb/>
Agramonte would be <unclear>hoped me</unclear> says Miss A (as interpreted)<lb/>
but Albertini thinks it was Carroll<lb/>
&amp; Miss A admits C was always trailing Reed like servant<lb/>
The fact that A doesn't specifically state he was there convinces<lb/>
me he wasn't</p>
<p>Lazear died before the Yellow Fever Commission terminated its work.<lb/>
For this reason his signature appears only on the Preliminary Note on the Eti-<lb/>
ology of Yellow Fever but as Dr. Barnet says in an article about the Commission,<lb/>
his premature demise deprived him of the great share which would have been his<lb/>
in the amazing results obtained by the Commission, but there is no room to<lb/>
doubt that his heroic and most useful act was a contributing factor in the<lb/>
final results. His remains were interred in the Military Cemetery at Camp Col-<lb/>
umbia and later on transferred to the London Park Cemetery, Baltimore.</p>
<p>We should remember certain facts in connection with experimental yellow<lb/>
fever contained in the memorandum published by Dr. Guiteras in &ldquo;American Medicine&rdquo;,<lb/>
where Dr. Guiteras explains that the favorable results obtained by the Commission<lb/>
in their yellow fever experiments, the continued series of mild cases resulting<lb/>
therefrom, suggested the idea of continuing this work, not with the object of<lb/>
proving or rectifying the conclusions of the Commission, in view of the fact that<lb/>
we considered them sufficiently proved, but with the purpose of spreading the<lb/>
disease in a controllable form and to obtain immunity in this way, with the least<lb/>
risk to the individual and to the community.</p>
<p>It was hoped that the results would be favorable, due to the series of<lb/>
mild cases produced by the Commission. Limitation of the number of bites would<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00476002"/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
be a factor, that is to say, the subject would be bitten once by infected<lb/>
mosquitoes while in the ordinary course, in an infected house for example,<lb/>
the individual would be exposed to successive bites. Also, the subject<lb/>
would be under observation during period of incubation and from the moment<lb/>
of attack he would be under treatment from the start, under mosquito-proof<lb/>
shelter, thus avoiding risk of spreading the disease.</p>
<p>Having these advantageous conditions in mind, the Chief Sanitary<lb/>
Officer of Havana, Major W. C. Gorgas, Medical Corps, U. S. Army, decided<lb/>
to establish an Inoculation Station in &ldquo;Las Animas&rdquo; Hospital. The approval<lb/>
and support of General Wood was obtained, greatly contributing to the<lb/>
success of the investigations. The Station, with its laboratory, was placed<lb/>
under the direction of Dr. Guiteras. A Commission, composed of Doctors<lb/>
Finlay, Gorgas, Diaz Albertini and Ross, the latter being Director of &ldquo;Las<lb/>
Animas&rdquo; Hospital, was formed to cooperate with Dr. Guiteras in the experi-<lb/>
mental work. The Inoculation Station was inaugurated in February, 1901.</p>
<p>In August of that year, Miss Clara Maass, a native of Orange,<lb/>
N. J., single, 25 years of age, a nurse employed at the Hospital (&ldquo;Las<lb/>
Animas&rdquo;) voluntarily submitted to be bitten by an infected mosquito. She why?<lb/>
had resided in Cuba for ten months and had been <hi>previously bitten</hi> by<lb/>
mosquitoes five times, without results. On August 14th, at 9:00 A. M., she<lb/>
was bitten by two of the Alvarez mosquitoes which had previously infected<lb/>
Represa, the latter having happily recovered. She developed yellow fever<lb/>
on August 18th, without any prior symptoms. Her temperature had commenced<lb/>
to rise, accompanied by headache and a slight chill. She had several hemo-<lb/>
rrages, succumbing to the disease on the seventh day, that is to say, Aug-<lb/>
ust 24, 1901.</p>
<p>Those are, ladies and gentlemen, expressed in a concise manner,<lb/>
the salient notes in the admirable lives of Miss Maass and Dr. Lazear who<lb/>
left us as a legacy the highest examples of abnegation, of sacrifice and<lb/>
love of science, in which they offered their useful existence for the good<lb/>
and progress of medicine. And in these moments in which we are honored<lb/>
with the visit of Dr. Edgar E. Hume, Lieutenant-Colonel of the U. S. Army<lb/>
Medical Corps, who represents his comrades of the Military Sanitation of<lb/>
North America, we consider as opportune and in which to render, in the name<lb/>
of the &ldquo;Finlay&rdquo; Institute, a tribute of remembrance and of gratitude to the<lb/>
memory of Lazear and Miss Maass; placing in this Hospital plaques which<lb/>
perpetuate the heroism of those cherished martyrs to science.</p>
<p>We desire to demonstrate by this act that we remember Lazear and<lb/>
Miss Maass and that we equally cherish a loving remembrance of the Doctors<lb/>
of the American Army who composed the Yellow Fever Commission presided over<lb/>
by Dr. Walter Reed and of which Doctors Carroll, Lazear and our own great<lb/>
Agramonte formed part. That there shall live in our hearts, with firmest<lb/>
sympathies, Gorgas, Kean, Havard, Ross and their companions who ably and<lb/>
disinterestedly had charge and direction of sanitary affairs in Cuba during<lb/>
the first American intervention.</p>
<p>To all, our affection and remembrances and we request Dr. Hume to<lb/>
accept and transmit to his companions of the Army our kindly sentiments and<lb/>
eternal recognition of the work they accomplished in the sanitation of our<lb/>
country, including the members of the Army Medical Corps who rendered<lb/>
valuable services in Cuba from 1899 to 1902, as well as during the days<lb/>
of the Provisional Government.</p>
<p><hi>Translated from Spanish by John J. Moran.</hi><lb/>
</p>
<closer>
<salute>TRANSLATION APPROVED:</salute>
<signed>Dr. Antonio Diaz Albertini</signed>.
Havana, May 2, 1940.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
