<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00709001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Rose Carter, Jr., October 25, 1888</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00709001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1888-10-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Jr., Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Eugenia Hook</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Jr., Henry Rose</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1888-10-25">October 25, 1888</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00709001</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Rose Carter, Jr., October 25, 1888</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter describes his work and comments on the quarantine.  He also provides family news.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1888-10-25">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Rose Carter, Jr., October 25, 1888</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00709001"/>
<opener>
MARINE HOSPITAL SERVICE<lb/>
1798 * U. S. * 1871<lb/>
<dateline>
U. S. Marine-Hospital Service,<lb/>
DISTRICT OF THE GULF,<lb/>
Port of Ship Island, Miss, Surgeon's Office,<lb/>
<date value="1888-10-25">Oct 25, 1888.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Ed:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I haven't answered y'r letter because<lb/>
I have been too busy to do so. You see my evenings<lb/>
are a dead loss. The musquitoes are so bad at night<lb/>
that unless one gets under a bar, life is aburden, &amp; even<lb/>
on the nights when one might work, the habit of going to bed<lb/>
early, formed during musquito nights, prevents.<lb/>
Laura is getting well now, fairly well but will perforce<lb/>
gain strength strongly. My diagnosis was I think correct,<lb/>
just here at the end of the season too I have been over<lb/>
run with vessels I have used 1255 lbs of sulphur <unclear>sin</unclear><lb/>
in the last 5 days: The worst of it is I do not exactly<lb/>
know <hi>when</hi> the Q. will end. I hope on the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> May; I<lb/>
want to get ashore, save one day, May 2, I have not been<lb/>
ashore since March, nor has any one of my employee's. The<lb/>
can be no complaint of &ldquo;communication with non-infected<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00709002"/>
districts from Quarantine&rdquo; as far as Ship Island is<lb/>
concerned. An &ldquo;inspection service&rdquo; will probably be kept<lb/>
up (as in the port) all winter &amp; vessels actually infected<lb/>
(either at port of departure, in a transiter, will be placed in<lb/>
Quarantine, This work is not strictly <hi>medical</hi>, at any rate<lb/>
not therapeutic or pathological, but to me <hi>now</hi> it is very inter-<lb/>
esting. I would be extremely glad to visit the different<lb/>
Quarantines of the U. S.: I almost <hi>know</hi>, that the disinfection<lb/>
(for vessels not infected), is extremely imperfect at most of<lb/>
them, La Quarantine included, although <add>the principle of</add> its <hi>system</hi> is by far<lb/>
the best. In these things it <add>is</add> the <hi>detail</hi> that counts &amp; the detail is<lb/>
left to employee's who have but little training &amp; not too much<lb/>
honesty. Now <hi>every</hi> process of every vessel (save 3) I have seen<lb/>
the <hi>whole</hi> of myself going in hold, cabin, forecastle, wherever<lb/>
the work was going on during the whole time of the disinfection.<lb/>
I think I have two men so trained to my methods that<lb/>
they can do very well with moderate supervision. I used<lb/>
to see charts at the Hospital at N. G. of sailors who had come<lb/>
through Quarantine with roaches &amp; bed-bugs. Very few pass<lb/>
through Ship Island, I don't feel as if the Jacksonville Quaran-<lb/>
tine was very well managed, but I really don't know. The law un<lb/>
der which Hamilton acted gives only power to <hi>enforce</hi><lb/>
the state law &amp; Fla. state law was almost <hi>nil</hi> on health mat-<lb/>
ters, &amp; he really could not establish an efficient cordon, as he did at<lb/>
Brownsville. Certainly a great many people left Jackson-<lb/>
ville who should have passed through Q. The criminal<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00709003"/>
2<lb/>
striving for theatrical effect of Atlanta &amp; &ldquo;opening their gates&rdquo;<lb/>
to the Jacksonville people was also a hard thing to fight. Un-<lb/>
doubtedly the Decatur fever came from Atlanta.<lb/>
The only perfect management of an epidemic I know, was that<lb/>
of the Plague at Vittianka in/78 &amp; is not possible in<lb/>
America. I wish I had had Camp Perry in lieu of Guiteras<lb/>
About my Fla. land, I have engaged to take it. At $3000, for<lb/>
100 acres, &amp; haven't seen it, I could get Fla. lands cheaper<lb/>
now I think, &amp; yet I still think it a good investment. No<lb/>
interest is to be paid save on payments, due one year<lb/>
from delivery of deed , I suppose about Nov 15 to 30.<lb/>
I have paid $950 &amp; have about $200 more ready. Can get<lb/>
$730 from Oregon next April &amp; will be able to pay<lb/>
about $75.00 per month (except the two months when<lb/>
I pay life insurance), except on months like last month<lb/>
when I had of course extraordinary expenses. I can average<lb/>
however $75, for 10 months so I can very nearly pay the<lb/>
amount by the end of the year.</p>
<p>I had two Tampa Refugees here of whom I inquired a<lb/>
bout the country, around Bloomingdale &amp; they said that land around<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00709004"/>
Bloomingdale was little for sale &amp; worth about $50<lb/>
to $75 00/100. I will go there as soon as I can get away<lb/>
from this place - i. e. when Quarantine is over. I<lb/>
These blots are caused by slapping at musquitoes.<lb/>
I have not been fishing since May or June, all of my spare<lb/>
time being with L., but I may be able to go soon. The fishing here<lb/>
is excellent, but unreliable, sometimes a great many &amp; again<lb/>
none. I have had some good sport with Alligators &amp; Devil-<lb/>
Fish. Catching the former with a noose &amp; the latter with a harpoon<lb/>
If you can find any thing about the latter you will find he is a very<lb/>
tough customer. One towed me about 6 or 8 miles &amp; then got off &amp; I<lb/>
caught a much smaller one which weighed <hi>2400</hi> lbs. The 1st<lb/>
must have been 3000 or 3,500 &amp; it was risky enough to be exciting.<lb/>
I have done no medical reading since I've been here, partly<lb/>
on account of my eyes; hurt by the glare, &amp; partly because my<lb/>
work required another class of thought &amp; reading.</p>
<p>I am hoping to get into a decent house in a month or 6 weeks,<lb/>
out at North Chandeleur &amp; hope to have a disinfection station<lb/>
fitted up so as really to do good sanitary work. I do believe<lb/>
that there is no really good work of these kind done in Ameri-<lb/>
ca in spite of the reports etc that the different state B's of Health<lb/>
make. Mine is not good &amp; yet I believe it to be all things considered<lb/>
the best I know; almost infinite pains taking the place of<lb/>
good apparatus. Do you know that we have <del>more</del> <add>as many</add> <hi>infected</hi><lb/>
ships here <del>these</del><add>as</add> La. has? owing of course to the class of ships that come<lb/>
I have had 4 this year &amp; La. so far only 2 &amp; only 4 for last year. She<lb/>
serves to Quarantine against <hi>Chagres Fever</hi>, why I don't know, we<lb/>
have had nearly a hundred cases of that, I'm at the end of my paper,</p>
<p>I find this letter is almost entirely on sanitary matters, well I was<lb/>
thinking of them. I have become a good boat sailor &amp; Laura &amp; Henry<lb/>
go with me a good deal.</p>
<p>The former can help a good deal &amp; both are intensely nauti-<lb/>
cal &amp; in no wise afraid of water, Laura, can steer, except &ldquo;by the wind,&rdquo; &amp; both<lb/>
of them row a little, but do not keep stroke well, are in <hi>good</hi> health<lb/>
I wish I were going to meet you at home in November<lb/>
If you think May would be improved by coming here, we will be glad to have her but<lb/>
the social advantages are nil: warm sea air is<lb/>
about the only attraction; only I hope to add oysters.</p>
<closer>
<signed>H. R. Carter</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
