<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00759001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Joseph Y. Porter to Henry Rose Carter, January 16, 1914</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Porter, Joseph Y.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00759001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1914-01-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1914-01-16">January 16, 1914</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00759001</idno>
<title>Letter from Joseph Y. Porter to Henry Rose Carter, January 16, 1914</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Porter thanks Carter for his educational malaria pamphlet for children.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1914-01-16">
<head>Letter from Joseph Y. Porter to Henry Rose Carter, January 16, 1914</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00759001"/>
<opener>
FORM 146<lb/>
IN GOD WE TRUST<lb/>
Joseph Y. Porter, M.D.<lb/>
P/B State Health Officer.<lb/>
<dateline>
Executive Office<lb/>
State Board of Health of Florida<lb/>
Jacksonville, Fla.,<lb/>
<date value="1914-01-16">January 16, 1914.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Surgeon, U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Carter:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of January 8th with attached printed copy of your ma-<lb/>
laria catechism has been received and my sincere thanks goes with this<lb/>
acknowledgement. I have read the little pamphlet with a good deal<lb/>
of interest and likewise with much instruction. It is an admirable<lb/>
compilation and the questions and answers are made so plain that the<lb/>

child cannot fail to understand exactly what is asked of him, and<lb/>
what he is taught. I have already sent a copy to the Superintendent<lb/>
of Public Instruction of the State who has acknowledged the same and<lb/>
commends it as a text book for the school. I enclose a copy of his<lb/>
letter so you will see what he has to say on the subject.</p>
<p>I enjoyed reading the typewritten portion of your letter, but not<lb/>
so much as that which you add in your own hand writing, and I am sorry<lb/>
you thought it necessary to interline &ldquo;Doctor&rdquo; before &ldquo;Porter&rdquo; because<lb/>
I never thought you would be so formal. We are both at an age where<lb/>
formality of that kind can be brushed aside and while we are not<lb/>
boys in age, yet, we can be in spirit and call each other by name<lb/>
without professional title.</p>
<p>If Professor Sheats, the Superintendent of Public Instruction<lb/>
of the State, does not acquire these catechisms I propose to either<lb/>
buy them from the public printer and distribute them myself from this<lb/>
office, or else, will take your copy with your permission, of course,<lb/>
and condense it somewhat, issuing it as one of the State Board of Health<lb/>
bulletins written by you. I don't see that there will be any plagiarism<lb/>
in doing this, and I certainly think you are entitled to a full need<lb/>
of credit for the good work which you have done in this line, and<lb/>
the plain way in which you have put the subject up to the children<lb/>
of the State. After all, the benefits of personal hygiene and rural<lb/>
sanitation must come from those who are now growing up into man-<lb/>
hood and womanhood, because the older generation I find are very<lb/>
hard to teach, and like old dogs learn new tricks very slowly.<lb/>
There will be no trouble whatever to get the children interested in<lb/>
this subject. In fact, the children here in Jacksonville have for<lb/>
sometime hatched mosquitoes in the schoolroom under screened ves-<lb/>
sels and the teachers have demonstrated the development of the mos-<lb/>
quitoes from the egg. However, a catechism such as you have com-<lb/>
piled will be wonderfully instructive and will simplify the work of<lb/>
those who already have done a little teaching in this line.</p>
<p>Personally, I am in pretty fair health. My boy whom you may<lb/>
remember as a little fellow is now practicing medicine in Key West<lb/>
and doing the laboratory work of that section of the State.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00759002"/>
#2.<lb/>
When I was home for the Christmas holidays he gave me a good over-<lb/>
hauling showing that my blood pressure is not too high and that<lb/>
my kidneys are in good normal condition, neither sugar nor albumin<lb/>
being found, not even a trace. The former you know is out of the<lb/>
ordinary in a man of 67 years of age.</p>
<p>I was right sick last summer in Atlantic City when attending the<lb/>
American Medical Association, but that was due more to personal neglect<lb/>
I think than any organic trouble, for you know what occurs when sewers<lb/>
are blocked and do not work properly.</p>
<p>I would be mighty glad to see you again down this way and hope<lb/>
that you will sometime get a detail that will bring you around Key<lb/>
West, and Jacksonville. Our old friends are getting remarkably<lb/>
few and the old guard is decreasing in numbers very rapidly. When<lb/>
I think of it it brings on a degree of sadness, but then there is<lb/>
one compensating thought that we have both accomplished something and<lb/>
perhaps mankind has been somewhat bettered that we have lived. Let<lb/>
us hope so any how, however little it may be, it has helped.</p>
<p>With best and kindest regards and good wishes for the new year<lb/>
both for health and professional success, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>- Porter</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
