<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00752001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Biographical notes on Henry Rose Carter, October 31, 1912</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00752001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1912-10-31</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Maryland, College Park (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Ship Island (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Chandeleur Island (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Brunswick (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Cape Charles (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Dry Tortugas (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">McHenry (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Key West (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="hospital">University Hospital, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1912-10-31">October 31, 1912</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00752001</idno>
<title>Biographical notes on Henry Rose Carter, October 31, 1912</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a detailed account of Carter's public health work and associated study of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1912-10-31">
<head>Biographical notes on Henry Rose Carter, October 31, 1912</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00752001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1912-10-31">October 31, 1912.</date>
</dateline>
Biographic (Carter)<lb/>
autobiographic sketch<lb/>
up to Oct. 1912<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
U. S. PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
Louisville, Ky.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>In Balt.(Med. student) Hayes &amp; Tilden election<lb/>
in yr 1876-</p>
<p>Henry R. Carter was born in Virginia in 1852 and lived on<lb/>
his father's plantation until he went to college. This was the University<lb/>
of Virginia, where he pursued a scientific course -- paying special atten-<lb/>
tion to mathematics -- and graduated in engineering in <del>'79</del><add>1873</add>.</p>
<p>Owing to a broken leg, the prognosis regarding which was<lb/>
permanent disability, he did not continue in this profession, but began<lb/>
the study of medicine -- teaching for three years, one as Assistant in<lb/>
Applied Mathematics in the University of Virginia, before going to medical<lb/>
school. He graduated in medicine at the University of Maryland and also<lb/>
served one year as <unclear>interne</unclear> in the University Hospital, Baltimore, leaving<lb/>
it in '79.</p>
<p>He entered the Marine Hospital Service, May 5, 1879.</p>
<p>The first detail was Boston. In July he was ordered to<lb/>
Cairo, Ill., and in the fall <unclear>saw</unclear> his first yellow fever. After Cairo<lb/>
he served in Memphis, New Orleans and San Francisco doing, except a little<lb/>
epidemic work while in Memphis, the ordinary work of an officer at hospital<lb/>
stations of the first and second class.</p>
<p>In January '88 he was order to Ship Island, the quarantine<lb/>
station of the Gulf, to relieve Surgeon Robt. Murray, with whom he had<lb/>
previously served in Memphis. This really was the beginning of his ser-<lb/>
vice.</p>
<p>cf. Carter's article in Hygenia for &amp; ,192-</p>
<p>Ship Island was the refuge station to which came all vessels<lb/>
infected, or probably infected, with yellow fever bound for any Gulf Port,<lb/>
except New Orleans which handled her own infected vessels. It handled<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00752002"/>
-2-<lb/>
many and a bad class of vessels -- sailing ships from Rio, Santos, Havana<lb/>
and Colon which, at that time, was especially dangerous.</p>
<p>The conditions of work at this station were especially dif-<lb/>
ficult. There was no certainty about it. There were no regulations for<lb/>
the conduct of the stations and when one began to formulate them he was<lb/>
confronted with the absence of reliable data on which to found them. It<lb/>
is true that there were quarantine procedures in operation at all tributary<lb/>
ports from Appalachaccla to Galveston, but they were all different. In<lb/>
disinfection, for instance -- New Orleans laid most stress on stem disin-<lb/>
fection of clothes and wetting the ballast with bi-chloride solution: Pen-<lb/>
sacola, with apparently very little faith in any disinfection, on the dis-<lb/>
charge of ballast and white washing the hold. Fortunately all used sulphur<lb/>
fumigation.</p>
<p>The periods of detention in quarantine were also different<lb/>
for each port of entry, and for New Orleans different for different ports<lb/>
of clearance. It varied in the Gulf Ports from 3 to 21 days or until<lb/>
after frost. Nor, although all required detention and certain processes<lb/>
called disinfection, was there any relation between the detention of the<lb/>
personnel aboard and the disinfection of the vessel. The detention<lb/>
dated -- days &ldquo;from date of leaving last infected port&rdquo; or &ldquo;from date of<lb/>
arrival in quarantine&rdquo; or &ldquo;from date of inspection by quarantine officer&rdquo;<lb/>
etc. In no case was any relation predicated between the date of disin-<lb/>
fection of the vessel and the detention of the personnel. It was a prob-<lb/>
lem then to determine what was efficient, justifiable quarantine.</p>
<p>Moreover, the work of this station was valueless unless its<lb/>
pratique was accepted at the port of entry of the vessel bearing it, and<lb/>
in the past that had been far from universal.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00752003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>It was necessary, then (1) to find out what was necessary<lb/>
to make an efficient and reasonable quarantine, especially what was the<lb/>
minimal period of safe detention, for detention is to a vessel the expen-<lb/>
sive part of quarantine.</p>
<p>2. To get the confidence of the Boards of Health of the Gulf ports<lb/>
in the work of the station so that its pratique might always be taken.<lb/>
For this last it was at times necessary -- especially at first -- to do<lb/>
things in treating a vessel judged unnecessary by the subject of this<lb/>
sketch.</p>
<p>3. To induce the Boards of Health to waive the plainly unnecessary<lb/>
requirements both of treatment and detention of vessels, in other words,<lb/>
as far as possible to render uniform the quarantine requirements of the<lb/>
Gulf Ports.</p>
<p>4. To conduct the station with minimal expense to vessels so that<lb/>
they would come to Ship Island by preference, when preference was allowed.<lb/>
This was to increase the usefulness of the station by increasing its cli-<lb/>
entele.</p>
<p>5. From such data as he had Carter tentatively deduced --<lb/>
wrongly indeed -- that five days fully covered the maximum period of incu-<lb/>
bation of yellow fever and made it his period of detention. He counted<lb/>
this period, however, from &ldquo;the completion of disinfection of a vessel;<lb/>
the last exposure of her personnel to infection.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He had also been convinced at the end of the third year<lb/>
that sulphur fumigation by pots was efficient by itself to destroy infec-<lb/>
tion of yellow fever aboard ships, although this method of treatment was<lb/>
locked upon as unreliable by the scientific sanitarians of the time.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00752004"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>He had, then, regulations consistent and founded on the best<lb/>
data obtainable, under which, although some unnecessary measures were taken,<lb/>
a safe quarantine was conducted.</p>
<p>Carter remained at this station four and a half years, by the<lb/>
end of which time the above desiderate (especially the 2nd, 3rd, and 4th)<lb/>
had been measurably carried out. Incidentally this was, I think, the be-<lb/>
ginning of the present maritime quarantine of the Service. The station<lb/>
had previously no principle of growth in it. White, at Sapalo, was doing<lb/>
much the same work for the South Atlantic ports. These stations -- Sapalo<lb/>
and Chandeleur -- were in constant correspondence.</p>
<p>Here Guoenvelt -- a most promising young officer -- died of<lb/>
yellow fever, sickening after a few days service. Why Carter did not con-<lb/>
tract it is hard to say. Only three others not immune to yellow fever were<lb/>
employed at the station during these four and a half years and they all con-<lb/>
tracted it.</p>
<p>The radical innovation in the Ship Island regulations of '88<lb/>
was not in prescribing any special method of disinfection or in fixing on a<lb/>
special period of detention for personnel, but in counting that period from<lb/>
the completion of disinfection of the vessel. At this time the regulations<lb/>
of all United States ports which quarantined against yellow fever -- I think<lb/>
of all United States ports -- dated this period of detention from &ldquo;the date<lb/>
of leaving the last infected port&rdquo; or &ldquo;the date of arrival in quarantine&rdquo;<lb/>
etc. In no case was any relation predicated between the date of disinfec-<lb/>
tion of the vessel and the time of detention. How so obvious a principle --<lb/>
the very pivot of a quarantine of disinfection and observation of personnel --<lb/>
could have been missed it is not easy to see, but missed it was. Not only<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00752005"/>
-5-<lb/>
the regulations of the United States ports were as quoted but the same was<lb/>
true of the regulations of such British ports in America as quarantined<lb/>
against yellow fever. Not until after the United States regulations became<lb/>
mandatory was this principle universally applied in this country.</p>
<p>In order to determine the period of detention of personnel<lb/>
it was necessary to know the period of incubation of yellow fever. For this<lb/>
there was no satisfactory data in existence -- he had access to a good spe-<lb/>
cial library. He set himself, then, to determine it; taking this, if neces-<lb/>
sary, as his life's work -- it being, at that time, a very important problem<lb/>
in maritime quarantine. This work was not completed until 1901 -- twelve<lb/>
years afterwards.</p>
<p>While working on this, another very puzzling phenomenon pre-<lb/>
sented itself. Just as there was a period of incubation in the man which<lb/>
must be passed before the infection became manifest, so there seemed to be<lb/>
a period of time through which the ship must pass before its infection be-<lb/>
came manifest -- in the only way it is ever manifest -- by being able to<lb/>
convey yellow fever to man. In other words, &ldquo;after a ship becomes infected<lb/>
a considerable period of time must elapse before it becomes infective&rdquo; --<lb/>
11 to 18 days was the first tentative determination.</p>
<p>We know well what this means now, but it introduced a very<lb/>
troublesome factor in his attempt to discover the period of incubation in<lb/>
man. Indeed, it was a long time before Carter was able to formulate the<lb/>
above as an explanation of his observations and then it was rather by intui-<lb/>
tion. It was an allowable, but not a necessary, deduction from his obser-<lb/>
vations. As the observations accumulated he became convinced absolutely,<lb/>
but others equally well able to judge were not convinced. Not until he had<lb/>
the data from the country-epidemics of Orwood and Taylor in '98 did he feel<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00752006"/>
-6-<lb/>
that he had convincing proof -- evidence convincing to other people. He<lb/>
used this principle, however, in the suppression of some epidemics, especial-<lb/>
ly at McHenry in '98 and elsewhere, and to a knowledge of it the suppression<lb/>
of that epidemic was due.</p>
<p>From the Gulf quarantine, after a short service at Cape Charles<lb/>
and Sapalo quarantines and at Cincinnati, Carter was ordered in the summer<lb/>
of '92 to Cape Charles Quarantine, which was to be prepared to provide<lb/>
against the cholera then prevalent in Hamburg. He fitted up the station<lb/>
and fitted up and moored the U. S. S. Jamestown, which, I believe, is still<lb/>
in commission there. He remained in charge of the station until cold wea-<lb/>
ther, handling a number of passenger steamers from cholera infected ports.</p>
<p>The next service to be noted was in the Brunswick epidemic<lb/>
in '93. Carter went down from Washington <add>June</add> 16th. to investigate, and remain-<lb/>
ed to clean up after a case of yellow fever that had been reported on the<lb/>
Satilla River, south of Brunswick. On his, Carter's, report of conditions<lb/>
at the Brunswick Quarantine Station and recommendations it was surrendered<lb/>
to the United States, under the Act of Feb. 15, 1893; the first station to<lb/>
be thus surrendered. The influence of this action was a decided factor in<lb/>
similar action in regard to the stations of Fernandina, Savannah, Charleston,<lb/>
and <unclear>Pascagoola</unclear>, and, I presume, for the Act of 1906.</p>
<p>In this epidemic Branham died of yellow fever -- a fine of-<lb/>
ficer of great force and high character. The sacrifice of his life was<lb/>
abundantly paid for by saving this section of the South from a much wider<lb/>
spread epidemic than occurred. He had been on the station about seven<lb/>
days when he contracted the fever.</p>
<p>Following the Brunswick epidemic the winter was spent at the<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00752007"/>
-7-<lb/>
Bureau and in installing the Brunswick Station. In the spring he was<lb/>
ordered to the Dry Tortugas -- the pleasantest quarantine station in the<lb/>
South, although somewhat isolated.</p>
<p>In consequence of the destruction of Chandeleur -- the quar-<lb/>
antine of the Gulf -- Oct. 2/93 -- Tortugas was to be used as the refuge<lb/>
station for Gulf ports until another station could be installed at Ship Is-<lb/>
land. There was, thus considerable work here and, on account of the prox-<lb/>
imity of Havana, which was then badly infected, a considerable number of<lb/>
vessels with yellow fever. Indeed, this station treated this year more<lb/>
than twice as many cases of yellow fever as all the other stations in the<lb/>
United States combined.</p>
<p>In 1890 Carter had proposed the disinfection of vessels from<lb/>
Cuban and Mexican ports at the port of departure or en route, so that the<lb/>
time en route to the port of entry after such disinfection could count as<lb/>
observation of personnel and by so much lessen the time of the detention of<lb/>
the ship in quarantine. He had especially advocated the use of Tortugas<lb/>
for vessels from Havana coming into the Gulf. He was now able -- much to<lb/>
his gratification -- to put this plan into practice. How this method has<lb/>
been developed there is no need to tell. It is the key to our maritime<lb/>
sanitation.</p>
<p>Waiving two summers spent inspecting the southern quarantines<lb/>
and looking after refugees from the North Coast of Cuba, the next two and<lb/>
a half years were spent ashore on hospital duty.</p>
<p>When, in the summer of '97 yellow fever was reported at Ocean<lb/>
Springs, Carter was ordered from Chicago to that point and, reporting to<lb/>
Surgeon Murray, was engaged in sanitary work in that neighborhood until fe-<lb/>
ver was declared in New Orleans. He was then put in charge of the Service<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00752008"/>
-8-<lb/>
work in Louisiana and Mississippi -- except the Mississippi Coast. This<lb/>
was to arrange for transportation from and through the fever infected dis-<lb/>
tricts and to assist the health authorities in preventing the further spread<lb/>
of the fever. The work was mainly pioneer work and the whole district and<lb/>
surrounding country was in a very unsettled and unsatisfactory state. Yet,<lb/>
on the whole, the work was smooth and successful. No counts it, however,<lb/>
the most <unclear>onerous</unclear> of all his details. In this epidemic Carter, himself, con-<lb/>
tracted yellow fever, but it was late -- November 18th; the epidemic was over;<lb/>
quarantine was raised, and no special inconvenience was caused by his illness.</p>
<p>When the post-epidemic work was over, there being reason from<lb/>
the mildness of the winter to fear a <unclear>recrudescence</unclear> of the fever. Carter was<lb/>
ordered to the New Orleans hospital so as to be on hand if needed. The win-<lb/>
ter and spring were consumed at various conferences trying to arrange for<lb/>
uniformity of method in handling epidemics, train inspection, passenger traf-<lb/>
fic, etc.</p>
<p>Early in June yellow fever was discovered at McHenry -- a<lb/>
small town in Southern Mississippi. Carter represented the Service in as-<lb/>
sisting the Mississippi Board in 1/ Confining it to McHenry, 2/ Eliminating<lb/>
it from that town. The measures taken were of the most vigorous character<lb/>
and he was given a very free hand both by the Department and his Mississippi<lb/>
coadjutors, for with yellow fever fairly epidemic in an inland town so early<lb/>
in the season the danger of a widespread epidemic was considered extreme.<lb/>
These measures were successful and the fever was eliminated from McHenry.</p>
<p>This was, I think, the first epidemic of yellow fever to be<lb/>
suppressed in the South in the summer time.</p>
<p>Later in the summer Carter was under orders for Santiago de<lb/>
Cuba when yellow fever was reported at Franklin, La., then in Taylor, Orwood,<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f00752009"/>
-9-<lb/>
and Jackson, Miss., and finally in New Orleans. His orders were cancelled,<lb/>
and he took charge of these outbreaks as they occurred and finally of the<lb/>
infected district as a whole, so far as United States work was concerned.</p>
<p>In this epidemic, although it was widespread, the work was<lb/>
far easier than in '97, because there was a feeling of confidence in Service<lb/>
measures and a reasonable uniformity of requirements of the Health Authorities.</p>
<p>In January '99 he went to Cuba as Chief Quarantine Officer of<lb/>
the island, in charge of all maritime sanitation of Cuban ports for both in-<lb/>
coming and outgoing vessels, except those of the Province of Santiago de Cuba.</p>
<p>At Havana he was able, with a good fumigating plant, to put in<lb/>
operation on a large scale, the plan of disinfection at the port of departure<lb/>
and counting the time in transit as observation of personnel so as to have<lb/>
short, or no, detention at the United States port of entry for her personnel.</p>
<p>He also served on the Board for the Diagnosis of Yellow Fever;<lb/>
Carlos Finley, Gorgas and, later, Juan Guiterras, being also members -- men<lb/>
with whom it was both a pleasure and an honor to be associated.</p>
<p>This position was held about eighteen months, although Carter<lb/>
spent the fall in the United States engaged with epidemics at Key West, New<lb/>
Orleans and Jackson, Miss. In the Key West epidemic died Assistant Surgeon<lb/>
McAdams -- a young man of the highest promise. He did most excellent work<lb/>
in the short time before he was taken ill.</p>
<p>During the winter Carter wrote, from his Taylor and Orwood<lb/>
notes, the brochure &ldquo;The Interval between Infecting and Secondary Cases of<lb/>
Yellow Fever,&rdquo; which Reed (and Lazear) said led him to believe that yellow<lb/>
fever was conveyed by a host and thus led to his experiments which proved<lb/>
it true. The brochure &ldquo;Extrinsic Incubation of Yellow Fever&rdquo; was written<lb/>
some months later.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f00752010"/>
<p>-10-</p>
<p>Leaving Cuba in 1900 on account of ill health -- Moniere's<lb/>
Disease -- the disability from which was considerable, Carter was in charge<lb/>
of hospitals in the United States until May '04 when he was assigned as<lb/>
Chief Quarantine Officer to the Isthmian Canal Commission.</p>
<p>He served in Panama, first in that capacity <unclear>organizing</unclear> the<lb/>
quarantine service and later, from Dec. 23/04, as Director of Hospitals --<lb/>
the second position in the Sanitary Department to that of Dr. Gorgas -- and<lb/>
in charge of all organizations for &ldquo;Public Assistance.&rdquo; He remained with<lb/>
the Commission for over five years and was concerned with much of the organ-<lb/>
ization and early work on the Isthmus.</p>
<p>While on this detail Major Ronald Ross -- himself a recipient<lb/>
of the Prize -- presented his name conjointly with that of Finlay for the<lb/>
Nobel Prize on the ground that the work done on the &ldquo;Extrinsic Incubation of<lb/>
Yellow Fever&rdquo; was the foundation on which Reed's rested and gave him the clue<lb/>
which led him to make the direct experiments which produced such brilliant<lb/>
results. Mr. Roosevelt <add>was the only American who</add> received <del>the</del><add>a</add> Nobel Prize that year, <add>the prize in medicine being divided between <unclear>Golgi</unclear> and Ramos y Cajal.</add> <del>for America.</del></p>
<p>Since returning to duty with his own Service Carter has had<lb/>
no detail worthy of note, except, possibly, an inspection of the Immigration<lb/>
work from Havre to Liban in connection with the regulations of Feb. 15/93.</p>
<p>In 1910 the University of Maryland conferred on him the de-<lb/>
gree of LL.D Last fall he was ordered to Honolulu for sanitary work, but<lb/>
before he could go, was taken sick with what was diagnosed as typhoid fever.<lb/>
This was really syphilitic fever from an infection contracted in '92 during<lb/>
a surgical operation. The diagnosis was not made until the fifty-sixth<lb/>
day of the fever and he has not yet recovered entirely from the effects of<lb/>
this long illness.</p>
<p>He has been a delicate man all his life and frequently sick,<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f00752011"/>
-11-<lb/>
yet his disabilities have come conveniently so as not to interfere with<lb/>
his work and this is the only time that one has prevented him from carrying<lb/>
out an order.</p>
<p>This sketch exemplifies how a man who was very fond of the<lb/>
practice of medicine and whose only ambition was to make himself a good in-<lb/>
ternist was led, by force of circumstances, to devote his life to sanitation.</p>
<p>Sanitary work at first was very distasteful to him and the<lb/>
life it involved especially onerous, yet he saw the importance of it and<lb/>
he clearly saw that only as a sanitary service could his Service expand --<lb/>
and that the possibilities of expansion as such were great. Although he<lb/>
did not, at first, look farther than its administration of a National Mari-<lb/>
time Quarantine system. Not only at his own station did he strive to de-<lb/>
velop this work, but he pressed the matter on the attention of others who<lb/>
might help -- commercial bodies, ship owners, certain boards of health, etc.,<lb/>
as well as on that of other officers of the Service and the Surgeon General --<lb/>
on the latter probably at times out of season. As the sanitary work of the<lb/>
Service increased, having had some experience, he was sent on a number of<lb/>
such details -- which were little sought after -- with the result that he<lb/>
gradually drifted into the sanitary division of the Service -- at that time<lb/>
almost exclusively maritime and tropical. This, of course, was proper as<lb/>
with increase of experience he became more suitable for such work.</p>
<p>His life has been less happy than if he had remained a hos-<lb/>
pital man, yet it has been a much more satisfactory life. He believes that<lb/>
he has been of more service to the world and to his Service than if he had<lb/>
continued as a practitioner of medicine. Looking back on his life these<lb/>
are some of the things which give him most satisfaction.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
