<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00756001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to [s.n.] Tillery, October 15, 1914</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00756001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1914-10-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Tillery, P.A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1914-10-15">October 15, 1914</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00756001</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to [s.n.] Tillery, October 15, 1914</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] reports on his observations of mosquito breeding conditions. He recommends mosquito control measures for a pond and inquires about when he will need to appear in court.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1914-10-15">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to [s.n.] Tillery, October 15, 1914</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00756001"/>
<p>U. S. Marine Hospital,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
<date value="1914-10-15">Oct. 15, 1914.</date>
Dear Mr. Tillery:</p>
<p>In addition to my field notes, of which Mr. Cordell took a<lb/>
copy, the following <hi>general</hi> observations on my recent trip should be<lb/>
submitted, I suppose to him.</p>
<p>(1) The lateness of the season--especially as we had a fair-<lb/>
ly cold September--would make against the breeding of Anopheles mos-<lb/>
quitoes and less of them would be found than if the survey had been<lb/>
made earlier. This effect--low temperature--would be more marked at<lb/>
shady breeding places than in those exposed to the sun and in fact in<lb/>
pools <del>or</del><add>and</add> marshes in good shade we did not find young larvae (&ldquo;wiggle-<lb/>
tails&rdquo;)--although some old ones and shells were found in such places<lb/>
shewing that Anopheles <hi>had</hi> been breeding in such places, but were not<lb/>
breeding then. I restrict this statement to &ldquo;pools and marshes&rdquo; be-<lb/>
cause where a stream ran from a breeding place exposed to the sun in-<lb/>
to the shade some young larvae would frequently be found in the shade<lb/>
--washed down from above where they were breeding.</p>
<p>Hence the breeding which was found was <hi>less</hi> than that which<lb/>
existed during the summer months, especially in shady places.</p>
<p>(2) My survey began Oct. 5th., just after a considerable rain<lb/>
on the 3th. and 4th. This washed out many of the small streams in<lb/>
the pools of which larvae were breeding. They were found in such<lb/>
streams only in places behind little hammocks etc. where they had<lb/>
lodged and in side pools and naturally in smaller number than would<lb/>
have been the case before the rain. In some places the stream was<lb/>
absolutely scoured out and if it had contained any larvae before the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00756002"/>
-2-<lb/>
rain none would have been left: My search thus was of necessity<lb/>
almost confined to pools and marshes about the <hi>heads of streams</hi><lb/>
which had not been washed out, or at least less washed out than the<lb/>
streams lower down.</p>
<p>This rain was repeated when the other physicians came down<lb/>
and was evidently quite hard the night of Monday, Oct. 12th. and<lb/>
the conditions for demonstrating larvae <hi>in streams</hi> were very un-<lb/>
favorable next morning.</p>
<p>(3) After the rise of the pond fish appeared in Smith's<lb/>
Creek, as high as Forest Road any way, and no larvae were then<lb/>
found in it below that road. Previously quite <unclear>annumber</unclear> of larvae<lb/>
had been found in it--Oct. 10th. with Rankin: and Oct 7th.: On<lb/>
the 7th. no fish were seen up in the creek: On the 10th. there<lb/>
were some and on the 12th. they were quite abundant and no larvae<lb/>
in creek below Forest Road, although they were in side pools.<lb/>
Up the creek further, from the crossing going to Mr. Meacham's up<lb/>
to well above the old mill site on Mr. Henry's land, they were abun-<lb/>
dant on Oct. 8th.: And at the former place--the only place in this<lb/>
section we tried--on Oct. 13th. in spite of a freshet in the creek.<lb/>
There were few or <unclear>no f<del>s</del>ish</unclear> seen in this creek during the September<lb/>
inspection and many larvae in both the creek and side pools as far<lb/>
up as a mile above Fork Road (left fork.)</p>
<p>(4) Much stress should be laid on the presence or absence of<lb/>
men or animals near a place physically suited for breeding. Since the<lb/>
female Anopheles requires a meal of blood to enable her to lay her<lb/>
eggs, obviously the presence or absence of a convenient blood supply<lb/>
will make much difference in the number of mosquitoes produced in<lb/>
places otherwise equally suited for breeding.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00756003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>Such places then, adjacent to houses: pastures etc. which<lb/>
have been abandoned, will now be breeding less, possibly much less,<lb/>
than they were when the premises were occupied.</p>
<p>As all of the above conditions militate against the breeding<lb/>
of Anopheles it is obvious that a decidedly larger number would<lb/>
have been found at the places examined had the examination been<lb/>
made in the hot summer and especially in the neighborhood of pre-<lb/>
mises now abandoned had the examination been made when they were<lb/>
occupied.</p>
<p>Very truly yours,</p>
<p>2 inclosures.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00756004"/>
<p>Memorandum. (1)</p>
<p>About the only thing I can suggest--which is feasible--to<lb/>
lessen the danger of the pond doing damage is to cut down the<lb/>
small sweet gums and willows--the former especially--which grow<lb/>
just in the water near the edge. These do not die on account of<lb/>
their roots being covered by water. This cannot be done until<lb/>
the low water next fall, because they must be cut as low as pos-<lb/>
sible so that the tops may be covered by water when they sprout.<lb/>
I do not think it would be a big job as few of them will require<lb/>
more than one stroke of an axe. They keep the drift from reach-<lb/>
ing the bank and the drift sometimes shelters mosquito larvae.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00756005"/>
<p>Memorandum. (2)</p>
<p>Dear Mr. Tillery:</p>
<p>I expect to have to go to the meeting of the Southern<lb/>
Medical Association at Richmond--Nov. 9th. to 12th.--and if I<lb/>
am wanted to apprar at court I hope it will not cover these days.<lb/>
Please advise me at what time it will be necessary for me to be<lb/>
at court--Waynesboro I presume.</p>
<p>Very truly,</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
