<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00758001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Editorial from The News Leader, Richmond, Virginia, by Douglas Freeman, November 10, 1914</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00758001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1914-11-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Richmond (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Hanover County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1914-11-10">November 10, 1914</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00758001</idno>
<title>Editorial from The News Leader, Richmond, Virginia, by Douglas Freeman, November 10, 1914</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Freeman celebrates Carter, Reed, and Gorgas as Virginians.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1914-11-10">
<head>Editorial from The News Leader, Richmond, Virginia, by Douglas Freeman, November 10, 1914</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00758001"/>
<p>Editorial<lb/>
from<lb/>
The News Leader, Richmond, Va. Nov. 10, 1914.<lb/>
By Douglas Freeman.<lb/>
Carter, Reed, Gorgas.</p>
<p>x Didn't come to Richmond with wood - its too far-<lb/>
Did sell cross ties to the <unclear>C. &amp; O.</unclear> at our R. R. station<lb/>
x</p>
<p>A strong-faced, gray-haired visitor to Richmond went yesterday<lb/>
afternoon to look for a cobble-stone on South Fifth Street.</p>
<p>He found it near the intersection of Cary and he told an old<lb/>
friend who accompanied him how he became acquainted with that particu-<lb/>
lar cobblestone. Forty-nine years ago, one April morning, he said,<lb/>
his father put on his gray uniform, kissed him and his mother and<lb/>
hurried away from their home near the old Confederate arsenal. The<lb/>
father left strict orders for the boy: the arsenal was to be fired.<lb/>
The flames might spread. If this happened and a certain nearby house<lb/>
caught fire, the 11-year-old boy was to remove the family Lares and<lb/>
was to go up Fifth street to an appointed place of refuge. In parti-<lb/>
cular, he was to lead the cow to safety; whatever might be lost, that<lb/>
cow must be saved.</p>
<p>It all befell as the Confederate brigadier had expected. The<lb/>
works at the arsenal were soon in flames, shells began to explode,<lb/>
houses were consumed, smoke issued from the dwelling the lad had been<lb/>
directed to watch; he went about his work of salvage. It was not<lb/>
easy--especially the removal of that cow. She had become alarmed at<lb/>
the crackle of the flames and the whistle of shells and refused to<lb/>
follow. But at length the boy had the rope about her horns and led<lb/>
her up Fifth Street. He reached Cary--a veritable wall of smoke be-<lb/>
hind him--and was starting up the hill to Main when many things hap-<lb/>
pened at once. A fragment of an exploding shell from the arsenal de-<lb/>
scended from the blue; it struck the cow; the cow bolted; the boy<lb/>
fell and, falling, bumped his head against the very cobblestone he<lb/>
identified yesterday.</p>
<p>We doubt if many in the panic-stricken city of Richmond had time<lb/>
that dismal day to minister to a little lad with a cracked crown. We<lb/>
doubt if many knew him except as the son of that great man, who, as<lb/>
Confederate Chief of Ordnance, was one of the most invaluable of<lb/>
Southern officers. But that boy became Surgeon-General William C.<lb/>
Gorgas, whose fame as a sanitarian, ripened by his brilliant work at<lb/>
Panama, is second to that of no living man.</p>
<p>The friend to whom Dr. Gorgas yesterday told the tragedy of the<lb/>
cow and the cobblestone was of the same age and the same traditions.<lb/>
He was not in Richmond on evacuation day, but in Hanover county,<lb/>
where his parents lived. He had heard the rumors of disaster and had<lb/>
seen the smoke of the flames which sent young Gorgas into the street<lb/>
with the cow. Besides, in the years of poverty after the war, this<lb/>
friend of the Surgeon-General had come to Richmond with a one-mule<lb/>
wagon and had passed that very corner, perhaps, selling cordwood and<lb/>
cedar posts to raise money for his medical education. That friend,<lb/>
it is scarcely necessary to say, is Senior Surgeon Henry R. Carter,<lb/>
whose early work on yellow fever made possible the experiments of<lb/>
Walter Reed and the remarkable sanitary conquests of General Gorgas.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00758002"/>
of General Gorgas.</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>The very mention of Reed completes the triumvirate. For while<lb/>
young Gorgas was leading his cow up Fifth Street and young Carter, in<lb/>
Hanover County, was wondering at war, the Gloucester County preacher's<lb/>
boy was 14 years old, all unconscious of his future fame, and scarcely<lb/>
thinking of medicine as a career.</p>
<p>We doubt if modern science records a like example of men of kin-<lb/>
dred sympathy and almost common birth whose labors in the same field<lb/>
of endeavor yielded such notable results. Carter and Reed were native<lb/>
Virginians, Gorgas, as the son of General Josiah Gorgas, passed the<lb/>
formative years of his life in this State and is knit to us by ties so<lb/>
close that we always think of him as a Virginian. They never knew one-<lb/>
another until manhood, but then they co-operated with splendid com-<lb/>
radeship in the study of yellow fever--that baffling scourge of the<lb/>
tropics. Dr. Carter worked out the period of extrinsic incubation, Dr.<lb/>
Reed, at Columbia Barracks, Quemados, proved the responsibility of<lb/>
the Stegomyia fasciata for the carriage of yellow fever; Dr. Gorgas,<lb/>
first at Havana and then at Panama, worked out measures for the preven-<lb/>
tion of the disease, without which, as all the world knows, the great-<lb/>
est engineering feat of the ages, the completion of the Panama Canal,<lb/>
could not have been accomplished.</p>
<p>The commonwealth that boasts great soldiers like Washington,<lb/>
Jackson and Lee, great jurists like Wythe, Marshall and Roane and<lb/>
great statesmen like Jefferson, Madison and Monroe rejoices that she<lb/>
has a claim on three of the greatest benefactors of our day--Carter,<lb/>
Reed and Gorgas.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
