<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00764017">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter to Henry Rose Carter, February 17, 1915</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00764017</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1915-02-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">Columbiana [s.l.]</name>
<name type="place">Montgomery [s.l.]</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1915-02-17">February 17, 1915</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00764017</idno>
<title>Letter to Henry Rose Carter, February 17, 1915</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The writer discusses fish stocks in local reservoirs.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1915-02-17">
<head>Letter to Henry Rose Carter, February 17, 1915</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00764017"/>
<opener>
FRANK S. WASHBURN,<lb/>
PRESIDENT<lb/>
J. W. WORTHINGTON, VICE-PRESIDENT<lb/>
F. H. CHAMBERLAIN, GEN'L. MGR.<lb/>
THOS. W. MARTIN, GEN. COUNSEL<lb/>
WILEY ALFORD, SEC'Y &amp; TREAS.<lb/>
<dateline>
ALABAMA POWER COMPANY<lb/>
BIRMINGHAM, ALABAMA.<lb/>
<date value="1915-02-17">February 17th, 1915.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H. R. Carter, Sr. Surgeon,<lb/>
U.S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I intended to reply to yours of the 30th sometime<lb/>
ago, but I have given practically all of my time recently to<lb/>
the Court proceedings at Columbiana. I am sure that you will<lb/>
be interested to know that we won our first suit. General<lb/>
Gorgas' testimony was of great assistance to us; in fact,<lb/>
I fully believe that it was his testimony which won the suit.<lb/>
The suit was one of L. D. Hand against the Company and was<lb/>
one of the worst suits which we had to contend with.</p>
<p>I spent three days with General Gorgas going over<lb/>
conditions around the Lock 12 reservoir and, as we have had<lb/>
several weeks of dry weather here, conditions were very sim-<lb/>
ilar, as far as breeding places for mosquitoes go, as we<lb/>
found them in the summer.</p>
<p>We covered all of the territory on both sides of<lb/>
the river where we have suits pending and investigated both<lb/>
the conditions around the houses and conditions in the reser-<lb/>
voir.</p>
<p>One thing which I was glad to note was that there<lb/>
are now a considerable number of minnows in the reservoir;<lb/>
just how numerous they are I am unable to say, but partic-<lb/>
ularly around Ida, which is a railroad station on the<lb/>
L. &amp; N., I noticed a good many. This was particularly inter-<lb/>
esting, after my experience at the Shrader's mill pond where<lb/>
I was unable to find a single one.</p>
<p>Mr. Van Dine, of the Bureau of Entomology, has been<lb/>
here and is also going to supply us with top minnows for<lb/>
stocking the reservoir and for breeding purposes. He went<lb/>
over the reservoir and is giving the matter study now and<lb/>
will advise us what he proposes to do sometime in the near<lb/>
future.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00764018"/>
<p>FRANK S. WASHBURN,<lb/>
PRESIDENT</p>
<p>J. W. WORTHINGTON, VICE-PRESIDENT<lb/>
F. H. CHAMBERLAIN, GEN'L. MGR.</p>
<p>THOS. W. MARTIN, GEN. COUNSEL<lb/>
WILEY ALFORD, SEC'Y &amp; TREAS.</p>
<p>ALABAMA POWER COMPANY<lb/>
BIRMINGHAM, ALABAMA.</p>
<p>#2 H.R.C. 2/17/1915/</p>
<p>Concerning your survey, I am somewhat uncertain as<lb/>
to the best place to conduct this, as I presume you are<lb/>
anxious to get prompt results. I think that possibly it<lb/>
might be worth while to consider a survey above Lock 5 on<lb/>
the Coosa River. This dam is now under construction and<lb/>
should be completed sometime this year. It was only 14 feet<lb/>
high and will not flood out a large amount of territory, and<lb/>
for this reason I presume that results will not be as satis-<lb/>
factory to you as if it was a higher dam and a larger reser-<lb/>
voir to survey.</p>
<p>If you do not think it worth while to consider<lb/>
this, possibly the area above Lock 18 on the Coosa River<lb/>
would be sorth considering. It is almost impossible to say<lb/>
when the Lock 18 will be constructed. This is the one which<lb/>
we wanted to start construction on in 1912 for the purpose<lb/>
of establishing a fertilizer plant at Montgomery, but we<lb/>
were not permitted to do this on account of the veto of<lb/>
President Taft.</p>
<p>Personally, I do not believe that this project<lb/>
will be started as soon as the Muscle Shoals project, but<lb/>
the Muscle Shoals project will take five years to construct,<lb/>
and possibly in that interval this dam may be started and<lb/>
completed.</p>
<p>If you consider going into any one of these sites<lb/>
with investigations and there is anything which we can do to<lb/>
assist you, we will be very glad to do it.</p>
<p>We have topographical plans of Muscle Shoals and<lb/>
of Lock 18, but we have no topography of Lock 5; however,<lb/>
you can get that from the War Department.</p>
<p>I notice from LePrince's report that there are<lb/>
quite a number of questions still open relating <add>to</add> breeding<lb/>
in the summer months.</p>
<p>Doubtless you are familiar with the fact that the<lb/>
Lock 17 dam on the Black Warrior River was recently completed<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00764019"/>
FRANK S. WASHBURN,<lb/>
PRESIDENT<lb/>
J. W. WORTHINGTON, VICE-PRESIDENT<lb/>
F. H. CHAMBERLAIN, GEN'L. MGR.<lb/>
THOS. W. MARTIN, GEN. COUNSEL<lb/>
WILEY ALFORD, SEC'Y &amp; TREAS.<lb/>
ALABAMA POWER COMPANY<lb/>
BIRMINGHAM, ALABAMA.<lb/>

#3 H.R.C. 2/17/1915/<lb/>
and the reservoir now covers over 10,000 acres. Possibly<lb/>
if you are anxious to get information on the breeding of<lb/>
the reservoir in the summer months of its first year, this<lb/>
may be a good place to go for this information. No clearing<lb/>
was done on this reservoir by the Federal Government.</p>
<p>I have a great deal of interest in this work which<lb/>
you are conducting and believe that results are already be-<lb/>
ginning to show from this agitation concerning the cause of<lb/>
malaria. The other day when we were driving through the<lb/>
country there were several instances where the better class<lb/>
of farmers had constructed ditches and drain<add>ed</add> pools close to<lb/>
their houses. Practically all the houses still remain<lb/>
unscreened, but possibly by the summer season there may be<lb/>
some progress along these lines.</p>
<p>After these several months experience in investi-<lb/>
gating conditions around our reservoir, and I presume these<lb/>
conditions are typical for a great part of the State, I<lb/>
believe that the lack of progress among our farmers can be<lb/>
attributed more to malaria than to anything else. In fact,<lb/>
these 700 people who have sued us have been having malaria<lb/>
for years, <add>or</add> they would not have sued us at all, as they would<lb/>
have had ambition enough to get out and hustle for a living<lb/>
by farming or some other means.</p>
<p>I certainly hope that you can see your way clear<lb/>
to conduct an active campaign against malaria in this State<lb/>
and that sufficient money will be apportioned to you for<lb/>
this purpose.</p>
<p>I notice from the papers that our Chamber of Com-<lb/>
merce and other civic organizations throughout the State<lb/>
are giving a great deal of time and attention to crop diver-<lb/>
sification and other matters of interest to the farmers; but<lb/>
it seems to me that matters like that are automatically<lb/>
looked after and, if you can direct the attention of these<lb/>
organizations to your work they can do a thousand times more<lb/>
good working on this subject than they can working along<lb/>
the lines on which they are now working.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00764020"/>
<p>FRANK S. WASHBURN,<lb/>
PRESIDENT</p>
<p>J. W. WORTHINGTON, VICE-PRESIDENT<lb/>
F. H. CHAMBERLAIN, GEN'L. MGR.</p>
<p>THOS. W. MARTIN, GEN. COUNSEL<lb/>
WILEY ALFORD, SEC'Y &amp; TREAS.</p>
<p>ALABAMA POWER COMPANY<lb/>
BIRMINGHAM, ALABAMA.</p>
<p>#4 H.R.C. 2/17/1915/</p>
<p>I could write all day on this subject with pleas-<lb/>
ure, but presume I have imposed on you by expressing opinions<lb/>
on a subject with which I have so little familiarity.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very truly,</salute>
<signed><unclear>BR Newton</unclear></signed>
OGT:LF<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
