<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00761001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter to James A. Haynes, February 20, 1915</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00761001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1915-02-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Haynes, James A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1915-02-20">February 20, 1915</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00761001</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter to James A. Haynes, February 20, 1915</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses his role in the prevention of yellow fever and malaria in South Carolina.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1915-02-20">
<head>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter to James A. Haynes, February 20, 1915</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00761001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
COLUMBIA RAILWAY, GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY<lb/>
COLUMBIA, S. C. <date value="1915-02-20">Feb. 20th, 1915.</date>
</dateline>
EDWIN W. ROBERTSON, PRESIDENT &amp; TREASURER.<lb/>
ALFRED WALLACE, GENERAL MANAGER.<lb/>
Dr. Jas. A. Haynes,<lb/>
City.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>MEMORANDUM.</p>
<p>The object of our visit to water imponded at Parr Shoals<lb/>
is primarily to advise what measures should be adopted to lessen the<lb/>
production of mosquitoes by said water as much as may be. This then<lb/>
will be set forth in this paper rather than a report of the condition<lb/>
of the pond. Obviously only a physical surevy of the pond was possible<lb/>
at this season of the year and such a survey must leave many ponts<lb/>
involving the breeding of mosquitoes undetermined. <unclear><del>T</del>Of</unclear> this a l<add>i</add>ogical<lb/>
survey would be necessary during the mosquitoe breeding season--pro-<lb/>
bably two of them.</p>
<p>We will, however, mention two peculiar features of this pond.</p>
<p>(1). Its nearly constant level.</p>
<p>The only rises are due to freshets and <add>the</add> only falls to a low<lb/>
stage of water in the river which fall<del>s</del> is minimized almost to the<lb/>
vanishing point by the obligation to keep the water up to the top of<lb/>
the dam.</p>
<p>(2). The large amount of flat land in the pond covered by the<lb/>
thick growth of saplings or underbrush.</p>
<p>The first condition, the high level maintained during the<lb/>
mosquitoe breeding season, prevents having bare banks at this season<lb/>
which are a valua<add><hi>ble</hi></add> factor in preventing mosquitoe production. The<lb/>
second <add>prevents</add> wa<del>i</del>ve action against the banks of the pond and may lead in<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00761002"/>
COLUMBIA RAILWAY, GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY<lb/>
COLUMBIA, S. C.<lb/>
EDWIN W. ROBERTSON, PRESIDENT &amp; TREASURER.<lb/>
ALFRED WALLACE, GENERAL MANAGER.<lb/>
#2.<lb/>
in places to breeding in the pond distant from the bank.</p>
<p>The general measures propsed are.</p>
<p>Primarily to increase fish control of the breeding and to<lb/>
a less degree increase wave action against the banks.</p>
<p>To Promote Fish Control.</p>
<p>(1). Clean the banks of brush and drift. (sticks, pine needles, etc)<lb/>
from the ordinary high level <hi>in the summer</hi> to as far out in the pond<lb/>
as one can reach in low water.</p>
<p>The brush should be cut as low as practicable so as not to<lb/>
project above the level of low water or sprout again. The drift or<lb/>
flotage should be dragged ashore with a rake. Trees and large saplings,<lb/>
except pine trees in this area need not be cut. Pine trees, however,<lb/>
in this area should be either cut or ringed, as should those <add>on the bank</add> close<lb/>
enough to drop needles in it. Laps of trees even a little distance<lb/>
outside of this area should be dragged ashore. The object of this work<lb/>
is to remove the brush, etc., against which floatage lodges and shelters<lb/>
mosquitoe larvae. This <add><hi>is</hi></add> most efficiently done when the water is lowest<lb/>
for then the brush can be cut down <add>lowest - hence</add> in the Fall<del>s</del>. In the present<lb/>
condition of the pond it should be done before the hatching season--<lb/>
<del>beginning</del><add>finishing it</add> about May 1st. The ra<del>c</del>king of the banks should be repeated<lb/>
from time to time during the summer <add><hi>after</hi></add> the brush and drift collect<lb/>
again. After the first cleaning the subsequent ra<del>c</del>king will be easily<lb/>
and rapidly done.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00761003"/>
<p>COLUMBIA RAILWAY, GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY<lb/>
COLUMBIA, S. C.</p>
<p>EDWIN W. ROBERTSON, PRESIDENT &amp; TREASURER.<lb/>
ALFRED WALLACE, GENERAL MANAGER.</p>
<p>#3.</p>
<p>(2). As the pond receeds watch should be kept for the pools left<lb/>
behind it. Such of those as will last over 15 days should be connected<lb/>
with the pond by ditches either draining them or letting in fish.<lb/>
The removal of clumps of blurushes in such places on the edge of the<lb/>
pond is advised where it is practicable.</p>
<p>(3). The hammocks of floatage in the edges of the <del>drift</del><add>drowned</add> wood<lb/>
should be <del>kept</del><add>set</add> adrift. These hammocks are on both banks of the old<lb/>
river bed, most on the East and were visited after coming out of<lb/>
Cannon's Creek with LePrince. We do not know that these hammocks will<lb/>
produce mosquitoes, but it seems not unlikely. Beginning up the river<lb/>
and working down it can be quickly done.</p>
<p>From the work contemplated in (1)such banks may be excepted<lb/>
as (a) are exposed to wave action (b) are clean and bare, or (c) are<lb/>
at a considerable distance-say three quarters of a mile-from a res-<lb/>
idence. This will enable one to concentrate for thorough work where<lb/>
it is most needed.</p>
<p>On the other hand in the fl<del>at</del><add>ooded</add> parts of the valleys, creeks,<lb/>
branches, sloughs and in the neighborhood of residences special pains<lb/>
should be taken to make the cleaning thorough.</p>
<p>Three quarters of a mile is <add><hi>farther</hi></add> by 50% <del>more</del> than is <add>usually</add> allowed<lb/>
for mosquitoes carrying malaria, but the allowance for this <hi>distance<lb/>
of safety</hi> should be greater if measured from a place breeding <del>very</del><lb/>
profusely than from one breeding less, especially if there be no blood<lb/>
supply for the insect closer.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00761004"/>
<p>COLUMBIA RAILWAY, GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY<lb/>
COLUMBIA, S. C.</p>
<p>EDWIN W. ROBERTSON, PRESIDENT &amp; TREASURER.<lb/>
ALFRED WALLACE, GENERAL MANAGER.</p>
<p>#4.</p>
<p>By banks we mean not only the banks of the main pond,<lb/>
but the banks of Islands &amp; mud flats and those of the sloughs making<lb/>
off from the river.</p>
<p>To Promote Wave Action.</p>
<p>This work of clearing the banks will generally be unneces-<lb/>
sary where the river is running in its natural banks. This begins for<lb/>
the West side about a mile and a quarter below Dawkins Ferry. For the<lb/>
lower part of this district, however, where the river although within<lb/>
banks is over the so called false banks, it will be necessary to ex-<lb/>
amine and when the brush on the false banks, willows <del>name</del><add>main</add>ly, is thick<lb/>
enough to protect the banks from wave action this must be cut down<lb/>
although it may be some yards out in the stream. Willow unless cut<lb/>
so as to have its stump covered by water most of the time will sprout<lb/>
again. Hence cut as low as possible and at extreme low water.</p>
<p>When the water is within the false banks <hi>nothing</hi> need be done<lb/>
in the way of bank clearing, but the creeks, branches and sloughs<lb/>
which come <add><hi>in</hi></add> up to slack water must be examined and these banks treated<lb/>
under the principles given before. It may be noted that the deep-<lb/>
ening of the mouths of these streams as they are backed up let in fish<lb/>
and are more apt to do good than do harm. This is especially true<lb/>
in sloughs containing marshes.</p>
<p>All of this work looks to increase fish control and wave action<lb/>
at the bank. In general in large ponds mosquitoe production has been<lb/>
found to be confined to the banks <del><unclear>but this</unclear></del>, and these measures well<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00761005"/>
COLUMBIA RAILWAY, GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY<lb/>
COLUMBIA, S. C.<lb/>
EDWIN W. ROBERTSON, PRESIDENT &amp; TREASURER.<lb/>
ALFRED WALLACE, GENERAL MANAGER.<lb/>
#5.<lb/>
carried out will lessen, we believe greatly lessen, this production.<lb/>
It is not, however, pretended that in ponds with <add>the</add> physical character-<lb/>
istics of some parts of this one production of anopheles mosquitoes<lb/>
may not occur away from the banks. Against this the measures outlined<lb/>
above would be futile. <add>Nor</add> obviously will they furnish pro<del>duc</del><add>tec</add>tion<lb/>
against anopheles mosquitoes bred <add>above</add> <del>in</del> back water <add>of the pond</add> in breeding places<lb/>
in running streams, seepage - out crops etc., not caused by the pond.<lb/>
A number of which were seen during this trip. It may be noted that<lb/>
anopheles mosquitoes breed by preference in small pools of clear water<lb/>
in grass, and in <add>pools &amp; in the</add> grassy edges of small running streams. They do not<lb/>
breed in foul water or in water which from standing is covered with<lb/>
a dirty scum.</p>
<p>ALGAE.</p>
<p>If algae, &ldquo;green frog moss&rdquo;, becomes prevalent later in the<lb/>
<del>year</del> summer and is found to be sheltering larvae from the fish.<lb/>
Dragging a crocus sack of &ldquo;Blue vitriol&rdquo; (<del>Sulphurate</del><add><hi>Sulphate</hi> of</add> Copper), behind<lb/>
a boat over the infected area will kill it <del>all</del>. This should be re-<lb/>
peated when it is necessary. Algae are most apt to show in the<lb/>
very still shallow water, in creeks and inlets.</p>
<p>Fish Propagation.</p>
<p>It would be well to see if <add>the</add> Carolina top minnow can be<lb/>
propagated economically in the pond. There are very efficient<lb/>
minnows in the pond at Hartsville, and this pond may be al<del>ready</del><add>readily</add> sto<del>pped</del><add><unclear>cked</unclear></add>.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f00761006"/>
<p>COLUMBIA RAILWAY, GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY</p>
<p>EDWIN W. ROBERTSON, PRESIDENT &amp; TREASURER.<lb/>
ALFRED WALLACE, GENERAL MANAGER.</p>
<p>#6.</p>
<p>COLUMBIA, S. C.</p>
<p>A Few Special Places.</p>
<p>(1) Dawkins: For the bad section of marsh North West of the<lb/>
station which has always been a place suitable for breeding mos-<lb/>
quitoes, cut a ditch parallel to a contouraround the base of the hill<lb/>
so as to cut off the hill seepage. This will run to the North East<lb/>
and East of the old marsh. Cut it deep enough for the fish from the<lb/>
pond to enter it. W<del><unclear></unclear></del> Clean the brush out of the old ditches<lb/>
up to back water so that fish can get in them. This is about all that<lb/>
can be done for this place, which we have said evidently was a breeding<lb/>
place before the pond was formed.</p>
<p>Next to the ferry cut a <del>short</del> <del><add><hi>straight</hi></add></del> <del>ditch</del> short ditch straight<lb/>
out from the sloughs to the river. <add>Also run a ditch down the length of this slough to the River</add> For both of these places at<lb/>
Dawkins burning the weeds and long grass should precede the ditching.</p>
<p>(2). Hiller's Creek: On the bank from the embankment to around<lb/>
the bight to the right (standing with ones back to the road) needs<lb/>
careful cleaning, especially an old fence <add>on the bank of the field</add> <del><unclear></unclear></del> and a lot of<lb/>
pine needles in the bight. Hereto a lot of brush <add>&amp; trees</add> have been cut from<lb/>
the bank so as to fall in the creek. <add>Move it out,</add> Higher up this creek, well above<lb/>
back water, and <add>the</add> influence of the pond, are a number of sloughs, which<lb/>
<del>are</del> are physically suited to breeding anopheles mosquitoes.</p>
<p>(3). Coles Creek: Up at the head of back water needs attention<lb/>
. Above back water and beyond the influence of the pond it too has<lb/>
places which are physically suited for breeding.</p>
<p>(4). Trestle near Mr. Cole's House: Clean banks of the bight<lb/>
very carefully and for some distance above and below for this house<lb/>
is <add>very</add> near the river.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f00761007"/>
<p>COLUMBIA RAILWAY, GAS AND ELECTRIC COMPANY<lb/>
COLUMBIA, S. C.</p>
<p>EDWIN W. ROBERTSON, PRESIDENT &amp; TREASURER.<lb/>
ALFRED WALLACE, GENERAL MANAGER.</p>
<p>#7.</p>
<p>(5) Sloughs above Dawkins where we ate dinner. Burn off<lb/>
the grass, cut brush with an axe and open ditch to let fish in.</p>
<p>This was <del><unclear></unclear></del> evidently a marsh breeding before the pond<lb/>
was made and will need be made better when this ditch was cut than it<lb/>
was before the pond was made</p>
<p>CLEANING OF BANKS ALREADY DONE.</p>
<p>The cleaning of the banks on the North side of Cannon Creek<lb/>
from the bridge to near its mouth is well done and although it has<lb/>
been done about five weeks, in only a very few places had any float-<lb/>
age collected on the bank. It could probably go at this rate nearly<lb/>
a month longer without being foul enough to require re-raking. Of<lb/>
course it is unnecessary to do this, however, until near the first<lb/>
flight of Anopheles, <del>About May 1st</del><add>say the early part of May</add>. It may require raking, however,<lb/>
oftener than this when the pine-needles fall from the trees in this<lb/>
part of the pond, and much less often when all such needles are<lb/>
down. Nearly all of this work of banks cleaning, especially after<lb/>
the first cutting out of brush would be unnecessary if the pond could<lb/>
raised and lowered during the summer season. It would be exceedingly<lb/>
advantageous, from a sanitary standpoint, if the level could be kept<lb/>
as high as possible--say to June, and as low as possible in August<lb/>
and September.- With such weekly and daily rises as are practicable<lb/>
during this - the breeding season. This would give us clean banks<lb/>
during this season.</p>
<closer>
<signed>H. R. Carter<lb/>
Sr. Surgeon, U. S. P. H. Service</signed>
<unclear>J A LePrince</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Sun.</unclear>Engr. U S P H Service<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
