<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00764106">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report on the control of malarial mosquitoes, by [Henry Rose Carter], [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00764106</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<idno rend="suppress">00764106</idno>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<title>Report on the control of malarial mosquitoes, by [Henry Rose Carter], [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] proposes that the International Health Commission carry out an experiment involving the control of malarial mosquitoes. He includes a detailed procedure for such an experiment.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report on the control of malarial mosquitoes, by [Henry Rose Carter], [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00764106"/>
<p><hi>Proposed demonstration</hi></p>
<p>In view of the foregoing exhibit of facts, it<lb/>
is proposed that the International Health Commission<lb/>
undertake to carry out an experiment which it is<lb/>
hoped may become a demonstration in the control of<lb/>
malaria. The purpose of the undertaking will be to<lb/>
try out on a small scale selected combinations of<lb/>
control measures in order to determine what degree<lb/>
of malaria control may be accomplished under the con-<lb/>
ditions of the average rural community in the<lb/>
Southern states; to determine the most effective<lb/>
methods of operation; and to standardize the working<lb/>
unit of organization and the cost. For this demon-<lb/>
stration the following tentative plan of procedure<lb/>
is proposed:</p>
<p>1. Select a small rural community in area about<lb/>
36 square miles; one in which malaria is very prevalent<lb/>
and has been prevalent for a long time; a community<lb/>
free from hookworm disease to avoid this complicating<lb/>
factor; a community as much isolated as possible to<lb/>
prevent the introduction of infection from the outside;<lb/>
a community which offers hearty cooperation on the part<lb/>
of the people and of the local physicians.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00764107"/>
<p>50 1/2</p>
<p>4</p>
<p>2.</p>
<p>2. Make a map of the community showing location<lb/>
of streams, roads and farm homes.</p>
<p>3. Take a census of the population, recording<lb/>
by families name, age, sex, color, address.</p>
<p>4. Make a survey to determine prevalence of<lb/>
malaria and its effects; the findings to include:<lb/>
(1) The parasite rate based on blood examination.)<lb/>
(2) The spleen rate based on spleen examination.)<lb/>
3) Average haemoglobin index of the community<lb/>
based on blood examination.<lb/>
4) Days lost from work and from school, based<lb/>
on individual history.<lb/>
5) History as to chills, fever and malaria.<lb/>
Report of local physicians to be used<lb/>
in connection with history of cases.</p>
<p>5. Exhibit results of survey on map.</p>
<p>6. Instruct the people of the community by<lb/>
illustrated lectures; by leaflets; by exhibits; by<lb/>
course in the schools; by house to house canvass. This<lb/>
instruction to be definite; to be simple; to be directed<lb/>
to the measure or measures to be carried out; to cover<lb/>
what is expected of each individual, of each family,<lb/>
of the community as a whole; to be driven home by such<lb/>
insistent repetition and energy as may be required to<lb/>
secure the desired action.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00764108"/>
<p>3.</p>
<p>7. Carry out the selected control measures:</p>
<p>1) In at least one such test community all<lb/>
effort will be centered on the single measure of<lb/>
treating all malaria carriers with quinine. The<lb/>
purpose here will be to determine to what degree malaria<lb/>
may be controlled in our temperate climate by destroy-<lb/>
ing the parasites in the blood of the human host. This<lb/>
treatment to be carried out on the basis of from 20 to<lb/>
30 grains of quinine a day for two or three days a<lb/>
week for six weeks; results to be tested by repeated<lb/>
blood examinations; to be continued till cure is<lb/>
effected.</p>
<p>2) In at least one other community the<lb/>
treatment of carriers will be supplemented:</p>
<p>a. By mosquito reduction: killing mature<lb/>
mosquitoes in the house; destroying breeding places<lb/>
by removing, emptying or screening artificial con-<lb/>
tainers about the house; filling or draining puddles,<lb/>
pools, ponds, urging only such measures as are<lb/>
feasible for the family or community in question.</p>
<p>b. By protecting the individual from the<lb/>
bites of the mosquito by means of <hi>screening</hi>; clearing<lb/>
weeds and brush from about the house; using mosquito<lb/>
<hi>bars</hi> and avoiding needless exposure from sunset to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00764109"/>
4.<lb/>
sunrise. In all cases placing the emphasis on those<lb/>
measures which are feasible under the conditions of<lb/>
the given case.</p>
<p>8. On completion of the work make a re-survey<lb/>
to get the measure of results. Formulate the work<lb/>
and its results in most impressive form and publish<lb/>
to the community.</p>
<p><hi>Extending the work</hi></p>
<p>If the undertaking should be successful and<lb/>
the experiment should thus become a demonstration,<lb/>
the work could be extended at will in the Southern<lb/>
states and in foreign countries. Its extension<lb/>
would be primarily a matter of education and could<lb/>
be carried out:</p>
<p>1. By making a series of demonstrations in<lb/>
selected communities throughout infected regions.</p>
<p>2. By publishing and distributing the story<lb/>
of these demonstrations, enlisting the press.</p>
<p>3. By teaching the people living in infected<lb/>
regions by means of illustrated lectures and exhibits.</p>
<p>4. By teaching physicians the importance of<lb/>
curing carriers and teaching them how to do it.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00764110"/>
<p>5.</p>
<p>5. By supplying leaflets and charts for definite<lb/>
instruction in the public schools and enlisting the<lb/>
school children in the active work of mosquito<lb/>
reduction.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
