<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00764069">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from John W. Kerr, September 20, 1915</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00764069</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1915-09-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Ezdorf, R.H. von</name>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1915-09-20">September 20, 1915</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00764069</idno>
<title>Memorandum from John W. Kerr, September 20, 1915</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kerr reports on cooperation with the International Health Commission and discusses steps to be taken in eradication of malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1915-09-20">
<head>Memorandum from John W. Kerr, September 20, 1915</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00764069"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1915-09-20">September 20, 1915.</date>
</dateline>
MEMORANDUM relative to Investigations of Malaria in Co-<lb/>
operation with the International Health Commission.<lb/>
-----------------<lb/>
</opener>
<p>In response to an invitation received from Mr. Wick-<lb/>
liffe Rose, Director of the International Health Commission,<lb/>
and in accordance with instructions from the Surgeon General,<lb/>
a conference was had with the former today at the University<lb/>
Club relative to the desirability and feasibility of anti-<lb/>
malarial demonstrations being conducted by the Service in<lb/>
cooperation with the International Health Commission.</p>
<p>In effect, Mr. Rose stated that during his travels<lb/>
in this country and abroad on business relating to the<lb/>
eradication of hookworm disease, it had been repeatedly<lb/>
pointed out to him that there was as much, if not greater,<lb/>
need of antimalarial measures as antihookworm measures.</p>
<p>In consequence, he had inquired into the work of<lb/>
Rose, Celli, Koch, and particularly Watson, and had re-<lb/>
viewed the literature relating to antimalarial work, and<lb/>
was now of the opinion that the International Health Com-<lb/>
mission might with advantage undertake some definite co-<lb/>
operative work with the following specific objects in<lb/>
view:</p>
<p>1. The treatment of malaria carriers after the method<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00764070"/>
-2-<lb/>
advocated by Bass, in a selected area.</p>
<p>2. Demonstration work for the eradication of malaria<lb/>
in a strictly rural section to be selected, using all prac-<lb/>
tical means that it would be economical for like communi-<lb/>
ties to adopt.</p>
<p>He proposed that the two lines of work should be car-<lb/>
ried on simultaneously, the former in Mississippi under the<lb/>
scientific supervision of Dr. Bass and the practical direc-<lb/>
tion of Dr. Leathers; the latter to be conducted under the<lb/>
supervision and direction of officers of the Public Health<lb/>
Service aided by officers of the International Health Com-<lb/>
mission. (It was not made clear whether these last mentioned<lb/>
officers were to be appointed or selected from among those<lb/>
now engaged in hookworm eradication work. It is believed,<lb/>
however, that it was his intention that a portion or all<lb/>
of the hookworm force should be utilized so as to eventual-<lb/>
ly carry on both lines of work together.) Special empha-<lb/>
sis was laid by Mr. Rose on the value of training officers<lb/>
in antimalarial work, whose services would then be available<lb/>
to the International Health Commission to carry on its anti-<lb/>
malarial work in foreign countries should it seem desirable<lb/>
to inaugurate such work on a large scale.</p>
<p>No mention was made by Mr. Rose of the amount of funds<lb/>
that could be made available for cooperative work with the<lb/>
Public Health Service. In fact, he stated that the matter<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00764071"/>
-3-<lb/>
had not been formally considered by his Commission, and<lb/>
that he would like to have a conference regarding details<lb/>
before taking it up for formal action. It is understood he<lb/>
had been informed that it was important to take up the mat-<lb/>
ter with the Bureau before a conference with Dr. von Ezdorf<lb/>
and other field officers was arranged for.</p>
<p>During our conference I informed Mr. Rose that it was<lb/>
the policy of the Bureau to encourage State, municipal and<lb/>
private initiative in public health work, and in so far as<lb/>
possible, cooperate with these agencies to the end that<lb/>
sanitation might be improved. I stated further that the<lb/>
field for antimalarial activities is large, so large in<lb/>
fact, that no single agency nor the federal government<lb/>
could fully occupy it. At the same time emphasis was<lb/>
laid on the importance of careful and unadvertised ex-<lb/>
perimental work in order that demonstration work, par-<lb/>
ticularly on the part of the federal government, would<lb/>
not be retarded. The danger of the exp<add>l</add>oitation of<lb/>
measurably success<add>ful</add> results on a small scale was pointed<lb/>
out. In other words, I informed him that a panacea for<lb/>
the prevention of malaria, if generally accepted as ade-<lb/>
quate, would prevent appropriation of funds and retard<lb/>
antimalarial work.</p>
<p>Mr. Rose was informed that it was the desire of the<lb/>
Surgeon General to arrange for cooperative work, and it was<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00764072"/>
-4-<lb/>
tentatively suggested that this cooperation might consist<lb/>
on the part of the Commission in the detail of its offi-<lb/>
cers to work under the direction of experienced officers<lb/>
of the Public Health Service and in the furnishing of funds<lb/>
for expenses in local communities selected, which expenses<lb/>
the Public Health Service was not in position to defray.<lb/>
This seemed agreeable to Mr. Rose, who expressed a desire<lb/>
that a conference be arranged which would be attended by<lb/>
our field officers and by the Surgeon General or a repre-<lb/>
sentative of his office, and a representative of the Inter-<lb/>
national Health Commission. He stated that he could attend<lb/>
such a conference in Washington or in the South any time be-<lb/>
tween the 20th and 30th of September.</p>
<p>It is evident that Mr. Rose is being urged to commit<lb/>
the International Health Commission to antimalarial demon-<lb/>
stration work. He has apparently made up his mind to fi-<lb/>
nance a demonstration under the supervision of Dr. Bass,<lb/>
and would willingly recommend to the Commission the financ-<lb/>
ing of cooperative work with the Public Health Service.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) John W. Kerr</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
