<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00765001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Draft of a lecture on yellow fever, by [Henry Rose Carter], 1915</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00765001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1915-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>14 pp.</extent>
<date value="1915-00-00">1915</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00765001</idno>
<title>Draft of a lecture on yellow fever, by [Henry Rose Carter], 1915</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] lectures on immunity to yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1915-00-00">
<head>Draft of a lecture on yellow fever, by [Henry Rose Carter], 1915</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00765001"/>
<p>Immunity to Yellow Fever</p>
<p><del>(From a Lecture for the Laboratory Class, U. S. Public Health Service.)</del><lb/>
<del>1915.</del></p>
<p>- - - - - - - - -</p>
<p><del>(Here is another debatable question.)</del> Is the immunity produced<lb/>
by an attack of yellow fever permanent or temporary? Naturally a<lb/>
disease caused by micro-organisms and which recovers spontaneously<lb/>
must produce immunity local or general, temporal or permanent, else<lb/>
one would not recover. That it is permanent has been, and is now,<lb/>
the opinion of American epidemiologists and of the older genera-<lb/>
tion of the French and English writers, who added so much to our<lb/>
knowledge of this disease by their observations in the West Indies<lb/>
and in Africa.</p>
<p>There was, however, a very common belief among the laity of<lb/>
localities in which yellow fever was endemic that leaving such fo-<lb/>
cus of endemicity for a sufficient time would restore the suscep-<lb/>
tibility to the disease. This belief is alluded to by many writers.<lb/>
It was, I think, universally regarded as erroneous by those <hi>not</hi><lb/>
living in endemic areas, but given more consideration, <del>although</del><add>and</add><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00765002"/>
-2-<lb/>
<del>not, I think, generally</del><add>sometimes - I think not generally</add> - affirmed by writers who lived in such en-<lb/>
demic areas. It is fair to say that epidemiological investigations<lb/>
of disease are far more apt to lead to correct conclusions when<lb/>
made in countries in which the disease is not endemic. The reason<lb/>
for this is too obvious to require explanation.</p>
<p>On the other hand the Commission of the Pasteur Institute<lb/>
(Marchoux, Simond and Salembeni) state categorically that the im-<lb/>
munity produced by an attack of yellow fever gives temporary immu-<lb/>
nity only and that the infection is kept up in endemic centers by<lb/>
recurrent attacks among the indigenes. This view is accepted by<lb/>
Seidelin and Rubbert Boyce and some other recent British writers.</p>
<p>I have seen no evidence advanced, except by Seidelin, in<lb/>
support of this view. I am inclined to think that the Pasteur Com-<lb/>
mission may have been influenced by the opinion which I have stated<lb/>
is common in localities of yellow fever endimicity. I will not say<lb/>
that no evidence--except as stated--has been advanced for this view--<lb/>
but I certainly have seen none.</p>
<p>I have said that I have seen no evidence for this last view.<lb/>
Looking in<del><unclear>s</unclear></del><add>to</add> that for the first, that one attack produced permanent<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00765003"/>
-3-<lb/>
immunity--which I hold--I am surprised to see that we have almost<lb/>
as little, which would be accepted by those holding the contrary,<lb/>
for our own. We have simply accepted previous opinion and not find-<lb/>
ing it contradicted by obvious facts have not examined the matter<lb/>
critically. We assume that one attack gives permanent protection.<lb/>
Obviously then, we would not be apt to consider an attack of illness<lb/>
occurring in one who had previously had yellow fever as yellow fever<lb/>
unless it were (1) well marked: or (2) <del>clearly</del> gave rise to yellow<lb/>
fever in others. The first might not be the case with light, cer-<lb/>
tainly not with ephemoral, attacks--the kind which would naturally<lb/>
occur as secondary attacks: The second we will consider presently.</p>
<p>Even if a secondary attack were clearly yellow fever one with<lb/>
our belief would, in the absence of good evidence to the contrary,<lb/>
question the diagnosis of the previously reported attack. This it<lb/>
is natural to do because we know how many cases of other diseases are<lb/>
diagnosticated as yellow fever during an epidemic. I did this in<lb/>
the case of <del>Assistant Surgeon Groenveldt</del><add>an officer of this service</add>, who died of yellow fever<lb/>
under my care at Chandeleur in 1890. He was reported to have had yellow<lb/>
fever in /78. For the acceptance of a secondary attack it would<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00765004"/>
-4-<lb/>
require then that a <hi>well marked</hi> case of yellow fever occur twice in<lb/>
the same person. Now even under the doctrine of temporary immunity<lb/>
this would be rare, as those who hold it also hold that there would<lb/>
be a <del>greatly</del> lowered susceptibility and that if the attacks were not<lb/>
very far apart that the second one would be mild, or very mild <add><del>which is <unclear>new trouble</unclear></del> and that is <unclear>remarkable</unclear></add>. You<lb/>
can see then that we have not been in a proper state of mind to ex-<lb/>
amine this part of the question critically, and indeed I, at least,<lb/>
have not done so. Even allowing for this the number of second at-<lb/>
tacks reported in places in which yellow fever occurs only in epi-<lb/>
demics--the only places in which we would expect them--are exceed-<lb/>
ingly rare. They <hi>are</hi> reported, however, and the recognition of<lb/>
such cases is proof that our eyes are not so blinded by our belief<lb/>
that we cannot recognise second attacks of yellow fever if they be<lb/>
plain enough. I have seen three cases of yellow fever in people who<lb/>
x were <del>supposed</del><add>said</add> to have had a previous attack. In two of them the<lb/>
evidence for the first attack seemed to me to be slight; the third<lb/>
I could not inquire into <add>P</add> When I come to individual cases--men who<lb/>
had yellow fever at one epidemic and were exposed to it a second<lb/>
time after a considerable interval, and I have seen many such--the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00765005"/>
-5-<lb/>
most I can say is that I have not known a second attack <hi>to be re-<lb/>
ported</hi>. Drs. P<del>(urnell)</del> and W<del>aldauer</del> had yellow fever in Memphis in<lb/>
/79 and /78 respectively and were not exposed again until /97 <add>at Edwards <unclear>house</unclear></add> after<lb/>
intervals of 18 and 19 years. Purnell was not reported to have yel-<lb/>
low fever at Edwards, but he was sick there with the diagnosis of<lb/>
malarial fever which was also prevalent, and to which he was subject.<lb/>
Waldauer was not sick at all. Major <del>Gorgas</del><add>Gorgas had</add> yellow fever in Brownsville, Texas /82. No expos-<lb/>
ure until /98 at Siboney, Cuba, 16 years later. He was sick at Si-<lb/>
boney, diagnosis malarial fever, which was extremely prevalent. He<lb/>
did have malaria; plasmodia demonstrated and recurrent attacks for a-<lb/>
bout a year, but that by no means excludes the possibility of yellow<lb/>
fever. Dr. P<del>ierce</del> of this Service, yellow fever at Chatanooga, Tenn.<lb/>
1878, next exposure Panama 1903--26 years interval. He was, after<lb/>
nearly a year's residence in good health in Panama City, <add>sick</add> at Ancon<lb/>
Hospital in Oct./04 with what I myself thought was going to develope<lb/>
into a severe attack of yellow fever until a typical eruption appear-<lb/>
ed and dengue was diagnosticated. I feel sure that the last case<lb/>
<hi>was</hi> dengue--although it was before we knew the diagnostic value of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00765006"/>
-6-<lb/>
the blood picture, for it was a severe case and such are well mark-<lb/>
ed. <add><del>The exception was well marked, &amp; <unclear>others you</unclear></del></add>, Yet you see that one believing that secondary cases are common<lb/>
might find fault with the diagnosis of all of them. I could add of<lb/>
my own knowledge I think from 25 to 50 cases to the above, but they<lb/>
would be more or less similar. Some did not get sick on the second<lb/>
or subsequent exposures, yet that is not convincing. Some people--<lb/>
who have never had yellow fever--go through an epidemic unscathed.<lb/>
Also light attacks might well escaped any notice.</p>
<p>The difficulty is that we recognize no sign pathognomonic for<lb/>
all cases of yellow fever, the mild and ephemeral as well as the<lb/>
severe. It is true that Seidelin claims to have such a sign in his<lb/>
Paraplasma flavigenum and also to have demonstrated it in a secon-<lb/>
dary (ephemoral) case of yellow fever in himself and in others--some<lb/>
of whom <unclear>shewed</unclear> no symptoms of illness--i. e. were &ldquo;carriers.&rdquo; With-<lb/>
out in any way pronouncing on the validity of his claims, yet un-<lb/>
til his primary contention is confirmed we cannot accept the exist-<lb/>
ence of his bodies as pathognomic of yellow fever and hence proving<lb/>
a second attack.</p>
<p>The second test, that yellow fever was communicated to others<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00765007"/>
-7-<lb/>
from cases of sickness of undeterminate nature of men who had pre-<lb/>
viously had yellow fever is again hard for us to apply.</p>
<p>When you consider how freely men &ldquo;protected by a previous at-<lb/>
tack of yellow fever&rdquo; have been allowed to move from places viru-<lb/>
lently infected with that disease into susceptible communities in<lb/>
the U. S. and how many hundreds of times this has occurred <add>during epedemics</add> you would<lb/>
think we should have satisfactory data on this subject, positive or<lb/>
negative. If not immune to yellow fever <hi>some</hi> of these men should<lb/>
have contracted it and developed it, and even if not diagnosticated,<lb/>
it should have infected mosquitoes and spread to others in whom the<lb/>
diagnosis would be easy. An epidemic cannot be hidden.</p>
<p>I know of no evidence that this has occurred, yet the evidence<lb/>
to the contrary has not been scrutinized critically. Since we did<lb/>
not believe that secondary cases of yellow fever occurred --or oc-<lb/>
curred very rarely--<add>if an outbreak <unclear>occurred</unclear></add> we would be little apt to impute conveyance of<lb/>
yellow fever from any sickness <del>as</del> occurr<del>ed</del><add>ing</add> among people who were<lb/>
&ldquo;protected by a previous attack of yellow fever&rdquo;--<del>if an outbreak of<lb/>
yellow fever occurred</del>. Almost any other hypothesis would be accept-<lb/>
ed to explain it. Indeed, in times of epidemics there are so many<lb/>
ways in which infection can be introduced that an outbreak without<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00765008"/>
-8-<lb/>
our being able to explain its introduction is not to be wondered at.</p>
<p>To use this test then, we must depend on the scrutiny of the<lb/>
exposures of susceptible communities to cases of sickness of such<lb/>
&ldquo;protected&rdquo; men, who had themselves been exposed to yellow fever,<lb/>
under such conditions<del>,</del> <hi>that other sources of exposure of the com-<lb/>
munity are exluded</hi>. Opportunity for this would rarely occur during<lb/>
an epidemic. Obviously in such a scrutiny <hi>one</hi> positive observation<lb/>
--i. e. the developement of yellow fever in the susceptible commu-<lb/>
nity if we <hi>know</hi> that there is no<del>t</del> other source of infection, would<lb/>
be conclusive. On the other hand, it would require many negative<lb/>
observations, many failures of of susceptible communities thus to<lb/>
receive infection, to be at all convincing. This would be negative<lb/>
testimony and is convincing only in proportion to its mass. I know of no positive observations on this subject. It<lb/>
seems useless to relate the 25 or 30--maybe 50--negative observa-<lb/>
tions I could give you. They are not enough to be convincing.</p>
<p>Possibly, however, we <hi>have</hi> in the passenger traffic of the Plant<lb/>
S. S. Line data of sufficient mass to be worth considering. From 1889 to 1897 inclusive--9 years--there was no bar to the<lb/>
transit on these vessels from Havana to Key West and Tampa of pas-<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f00765009"/>
-9-<lb/>
sengers &ldquo;protected against yellow fever by previous attack or ten<lb/>
years residence in an endemic focus&rdquo; and a great many of them came:<lb/>
Cubans on their 10 years residence and Americans on certificate of<lb/>
previous attack. How many I can<add><del>for an attempt to</del></add> only approximately estimate. There<lb/>
were cigar factories in Key West: Tampa and Jacksonville, all manned<lb/>
by Cuban employees. There was generally one vessel per week, but<lb/>
Havana was about 6 hours from Key West &amp; 24 from Tampa<lb/>
part of the  time two vessels. From my own observations I would es-<lb/>
timate the weekly passenger list at from 20 to 50. During the hot<lb/>
season, from April 15th. to Nov. 1st.--28 weeks--this would give at<lb/>
the lowest estimate <del>700</del><add>560</add> such passengers per annum--<del>6300</del><add>5040</add> during the<lb/>
9 years. Now remember that this very considerable number of people,<lb/>
and I have given you minimal numbers, came from a city where yellow<lb/>
fever was endemic: that they came in hot weather: to towns where<lb/>
Stegomyia were abundant and where people susceptible to yellow fever<lb/>
were also abundant. If then, any considerable proportion of them<lb/>
had been infective to Stegomyia I cannot but think that there would<lb/>
have been at least <hi>one</hi> outbreak of yellow fever in Florida during<lb/>
these nine years. There was none.</p>
<p><unclear>x x x x</unclear><lb/>
Take in x x x v</p>
<p>That <add><del>others</del></add> those susceptible to yellow fever were liable to contract<lb/>
that disease from exposure in Havana at this time was evidenced by<lb/>
the history of vessels from that part whose personnel had <hi>not</hi> had<lb/>
yellow fever. They frequently brought cases of yellow fever to our<lb/>
quarantine station. <del>Why</del> In 1895 at the Dry Tortugas I had 13 cases<lb/>
of yellow fever on Havana vessels out of a crew list of less than<lb/>
450 men. Indeed the crew list of men exposed to infection at Havana<lb/>
was not over half of 450, as the steamers lay in a safe part of the<lb/>
harbor--Trisconia--and allowed only a very few men ashore and were<lb/>
practically free from fever. It occurred (with one exception) only<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f00765010"/>
-10-<lb/>
on vessels which had laid on the Havana side of the harbor. Un-<lb/>
questionably then those susceptible to yellow fever could contract<lb/>
it in Havana during this time.</p>
<p>Compare these observations:</p>
<p>450 people who had not had yellow fever, from Havana,<lb/>
gave 13 cases of yellow fever, every one <add><unclear>of</unclear> which should have been</add> infective<lb/>
to Stegomyia.</p>
<p>Over <del>6</del><add>5</add>000 people from the same place, <add>during a period</add> covering the same time,<lb/>
give no evidence of infecting Stegomyia: certainly<lb/>
give rise to no outbreak in the susceptible communi-<lb/>
<unclear>ties into rhic</unclear> into which they move.</p>
<p>You may not consider this <hi>proof</hi>. There may not be enough of<lb/>
it to satisfy you; but the mass of this evidence, negative as it is,<lb/>
is sufficient, until the contrary is proven, to confirm me in the<lb/>
belief that one attack of yellow fever confers permanent immunity<lb/>
against becoming again infective to Stegomyia mosquitoes and that<lb/>
we are justified in basing sanitary measures thereon. This obser-<lb/>
vation is also inconsistent with the existence of &ldquo;carriers&rdquo; <add>as a common phenomenon</add> capa-<lb/>
ble of infecting Stegomyia with yellow fever<del>.</del> against which indeed<lb/>
a <unclear>strongest</unclear> argument <del>is stronger</del> can be made. <del>stronger</del>.</p>
<p>I said &ldquo;Until the contrary is proven&rdquo;, because if it is <unclear>shown</unclear><lb/>
that the organism causative of yellow fever occurs in men who have<lb/>
had previous attacks of this disease and is conveyable from them<lb/>
by Stegomyia mosquitoes to other men, producing yellow fever in them<lb/>
I will count the contrary proven. I well know how much more deter-<lb/>
minative are the results of experimental than epidemiological ob-<lb/>
servations. Yet in this disease it was, I believe, the latter that<lb/>
gave the key to the problem, which determined the direction of the<lb/>
experimental investigation which demonstrated the method of convey-<lb/>
ance.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f00765011"/>
<p>11 <unclear>nura for Secline</unclear></p>
<p>X</p>
<p>There are other epidemiological observations which are at least<lb/>
consistent with the doctrine of permanent immunity, <add>such</add> as the spontane-<lb/>
ous disappearance of yellow fever from small and moderate sized<lb/>
towns in the tropics which receive few susceptible immigrants. I<lb/>
do not mean that this always occurs, but it is by no means rare in<lb/>
America <del>and will be discussed later</del>. The great decrease of infec-<lb/>
tion in Havana in 1899, due to falling off of immigration in the<lb/>
previous years, is also consistent with it. This was shown in the<lb/>
small number of cases of yellow fever in the spring and summer of<lb/>
that year, <del>as compared with normal years</del><add>as compared with normal years</add> although the town was full of Americans who went every-<lb/>
where,</p>
<pb n="12" id="f00765012"/>
<p>There are other epidemiological observations which are at least<lb/>
consistent with the doctrine of permanent immunity as the spontane-<lb/>
ous disappearance of yellow fever from small and moderate sized<lb/>
towns in the tropics which receive few susceptible immigrants. I<lb/>
do not mean that this always occurs, but it is by no means rare in<lb/>
America and will be discussed later. The great decrease of infec-<lb/>
tion in Havana in 1899, due to falling off of immigration in the<lb/>
previous years, is also consistent with it. This was <unclear>shown</unclear> in the<lb/>
small number of cases of yellow fever in the spring and summer of<lb/>
that year, although the town was full of Americans who went every-<lb/>
where, as compared with normal years.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f00765013"/>
<p>There are other epidemiological observations which are at least<lb/>
consistent with the doctrine of permanent immunity as the spontane-<lb/>
ous disappearance of yellow fever from small and moderate sized<lb/>
towns in the tropics which receive few susceptible immigrants. I<lb/>
do not mean that this always occurs, but it is by no means rare in<lb/>
America and will be discussed later. The great decrease of infec-<lb/>
tion in Havana in 1899, due to falling off of immigration in the<lb/>
previous years, is also consistent with it. This was <unclear>shown</unclear> in the<lb/>
small number of cases of yellow fever in the spring and summer of<lb/>
that year, although the town was full of Americans who went every-<lb/>
where, as compared with normal years.</p>
<pb n="14" id="f00765014"/>
<p><del>x x x <unclear>I</unclear></del></p>
<p><del>The only question arises were those<lb/>
people as so exposed (to y. f.) in Havana<lb/>
that they a considerable portion of them<lb/>
would have <unclear>contacted</unclear> <add>y. f.</add>it if they were<lb/>
susceptible of it?</del></p>
<p>Were those people so exposed<lb/>
in Havana that any consid-<lb/>
erable <del>portion</del><add>member</add> of them would<lb/>
have contracted yellow fever<lb/>
if they <add>were</add> susceptible? I think so.</p>
<p>X X x x</p>
<p>Take in page. 9</p>
<p>Dear <del>van Ezdorf</del><lb/>
I.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
