<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00764049">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Harold Leidelin to Henry Rose Carter, May 18, 1915</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Leidelin, Harold</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00764049</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1915-05-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Macfie, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Connal, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Johnston, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1915-05-18">May 18, 1915</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00764049</idno>
<title>Letter from Harold Leidelin to Henry Rose Carter, May 18, 1915</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Leidelin thanks Carter for a reprint on impounded waters and malaria.  He expresses disappointment about the lack of support by others for his work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1915-05-18">
<head>Letter from Harold Leidelin to Henry Rose Carter, May 18, 1915</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00764049"/>
<opener>
THE INCORPORATED<lb/>
LIVERPOOL SCHOOL OF TROPICAL MEDICINE.<lb/>
____________<lb/>
Telephone 2402 Royal,<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER BUREAU,<lb/>
UNIVERSITY OF LIVERPOOL.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1915-05-18">May 18th 1915</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter,</salute>
</opener>
<p>Immediately on receipt of your letter of April 1st,<lb/>
for which I thank you heartily, I sent you all the reprints that I<lb/>
could lay hand on. I trust you have received them. Yesterday I received<lb/>
a reprint from your father of his paper on impounded water and malaria;<lb/>
I have read it with great interest, and I beg you to thank your father<lb/>
for it and to give him my sincere regards. I hope he is now quite well.</p>
<p>You are quite right in saying that no one has undertaken to <del><unclear>xxxxx</unclear></del><lb/>
repeat my work with an open mind. Even those who have confirmed my<lb/>
work started in the belief that I was wrong. Macfie, Connal, and Johnston<lb/>
who, working in West Africa, have confirmed my results, have all told<lb/>
me that they had been filled with so much talking against me that they<lb/>
were convinced of the non-existence of the <hi>Paraplasma</hi>, until they found<lb/>
it themselves. Personally, I have not the slightest doubt that my<lb/>
results will come to stand, but it may take a long time, and it appears<lb/>
that I shall have no opportunity of continuing my work on this problem.<lb/>
My work here is soon coming to an end, and I have been unable to<lb/>
obtain any other appointment which put me in a position to take up<lb/>
similar investigations. Considering the state of affairs in Mexico,<lb/>
you will understand that it is<del>n</del> out of the question to return to my<lb/>
previous or to a similar position there. I was therefore particularly<lb/>
glad to see that you take an interest in the matter, and I hope that<lb/>
you and your Colleagues in the Service will be successful in following<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00764050"/>
2<lb/>
up the life cycle of the parasite, especially the evolution in the<lb/>
mosquito - where I failed. Connal, who is a very good man indeed, has<lb/>
told me that he is not going to rest until he has done all in his<lb/>
power to <del><unclear>xxxxxx</unclear></del> settle the question one way or the other, but the<lb/>
problem is, of course, public property, and I daresay that you have both<lb/>
the men and the means.</p>
<p>If I live long enough I shall perhaps have the satisfaction<lb/>
of seeing the diagnosis of yellow fever on a firm basis by the routine<lb/>
demonstration of the <hi>P.flavigenum</hi>, and possibly a vaccine prophylaxis<lb/>
in full swing. I shall always be glad to discuss details with you, if<lb/>
you care to write to me, but what suggestions I might have to make<lb/>
are, I believe, embodied in my papers, of which those dealing with<lb/>
work in West Africa have been delayed, but will soon appear. I may<lb/>
not have a copy to send you, as the Colonial Office Commission are<lb/>
<del><unclear>xxxxxxxx</unclear></del> issuing these volumes, though in connection with our Bureau,<lb/>
but several of your libraries will, of course, receive copies.</p>
<p>In the meantime I am a bit sick at the way that my work has been<lb/>
attacked. You know Agramonte's way, and you have no doubt seen others<lb/>
using about the same style of &ldquo;criticism&rdquo;. What can one do when two<lb/>
authors assert that the scientific world is against me whilst the truth<lb/>
is that those two have been working up an opinion, doing all the writing<lb/>
themselves, signed or anonymously, the same two men in four Journals.</p>
<p>I shall probably go back to Denmark when my time is up here, but<lb/>
I do not know for certain yet. Before that I am getting ready the last<lb/>
number of the Bulletin which we have been preparing for some time, but<lb/>
the West African Reports have taken a lot of time and must be out first.</p>
<p>Be sure to send me all that you write.</p>
<p>Kindest regards also to Dr. James and others whom I had the pleasure of meeting<lb/>
at the Canal Zone.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very sincerely</salute>
<signed>Harold Leidelin</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
