<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00805001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on mosquito control, by [Henry Rose Carter?], [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00805001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00805001</idno>
<title>Notes on mosquito control, by [Henry Rose Carter?], [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter?] details ways to prevent the proliferation of mosquitoes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Notes on mosquito control, by [Henry Rose Carter?], [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00805001"/>
<p>(1</p>
<p>General Suggestions <add>in Precautionary Measures</add> for Preventing Prolific Anopheles<lb/>
Production in Proposed Impounded Water Bodies-</p>
<p>{Preliminary Work to be<lb/>
{Accomplished before<lb/>
{Water Elevation is Raised</p>
<p>(1) Make map to scale of area to be covered &amp; including<lb/>
all houses within one mile of the contour line<lb/>
of lake at time of maximum high water</p>
<p>(2) <del>Include on</del> Show on map in correct location all houses <add>with names tenants</add><lb/>
Rivers, creeks, <add>ravines</add> streams big &amp; small &amp; their branches, swamps,<lb/>
seepage outcrops, ponds, pools, ditches that stay wet<lb/>
soft bag lands; springs, wells &amp; other wet places in which<lb/>
mosquitoes might propagate, within the area to be flooded<lb/>
and for one mile distant and parallel to the maximum<lb/>
flood line contour- This is important-.</p>
<p>(3) Plot on map the contour line or lines of proposed<lb/>
high, average &amp; low flow lines allowed-.</p>
<p>(4) In places where land is flat or of gradual slope, show<lb/>
such land on map by <del>one foot</del> contours-spaced <del>one</del><lb/>
so as to show slope; 1 ft or 2 ft contours-.</p>
<p>(5)</p>
<p>Denote on map by appropriate symbols for Spring, Summer,<lb/>
and late Autumn the places &amp; species of <add>&amp; date.</add> Anopheles larvae occurrence<lb/>
in all wet areas mentioned in paragraph # 2-.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00805002"/>
<p>(2</p>
<p><hi>6</hi></p>
<p>Record several catches of Anopheles made at houses &amp; outhouses<lb/>
(particularly in barns &amp; pigpens &amp; under houses) at the height of<lb/>
the anopheles production season- If such work is done for<lb/>
two seasons, at various points both close to the main river<lb/>
and a mile from the pond edge, the data might prove<lb/>
of immense value at a future date-.</p>
<p>(7) Employ all physicians practicing in the neighborhood<lb/>
within from one to several miles of the proposed<lb/>
pond edge, to search their records &amp; give names and<lb/>
dates of malaria cases among their patients so far as<lb/>
they have record or can remember with such note or<lb/>
comment as they care to add-.</p>
<p>If possible take index of existing malaria rate, <add>for 1 mile <del>from river</del> flow line</add> supply<lb/>
all tenants <del>with</del> &amp; local physicians with printed matter<lb/>
pertaining to malaria prevention,-</p>
<p>(8) Settle <add>as far as possible</add> all damage and land claims fairly before water<lb/>
is turned on. Pay additional and just price for quiet<lb/>
residence claims on residences in areas near inlets<lb/>
that will be flooded &amp; apparently become <add>of</add> sanitary<lb/>
importance, or make written agreement for fixed sum<lb/>
to be paid if they should turn out to be so-.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00805003"/>
<p>(3</p>
<p>(9)</p>
<p>If at some future date flash boards might become<lb/>
desirable for financial reasons, it is well to<lb/>
purchase sufficient land above the heavy flood<lb/>
line flow of the proposed lake, so as to allow for<lb/>
the change and this will give room for raking out<lb/>
debris &amp; deposit of floatage.</p>
<p>(10) Purchase flat lands where the water table will<lb/>
be raised so close to the ground surface as to damage<lb/>
crops during wet seasons. It may become necessary<lb/>
as a sanitary measure to keep stock off some fields<lb/>
with ground water close to the surface as hoof<lb/>
marks increase anopheles production- Land values<lb/>
for purchasers <add>often</add> increase after water is impounded.</p>
<p>(11) At the mouths of small streams &amp; ravines<lb/>
toward the upper end of the pond, silt, sand &amp;<lb/>
gravel &amp; debris often pile up &amp; interfere with agricul-<lb/>
tural operations or grazing value of lands &amp; may<lb/>
become anopheles production areas - it simplifies matters<lb/>
for such lands to be transferred to the party using the<lb/>
water power.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00805004"/>
<p>(4</p>
<p><hi>12</hi></p>
<p>Proper fish control is most important tho not perfect.<lb/>
Some ponds of impounded water have become so<lb/>
thoroughly stocked with certain <del>practically</del> efficient top<lb/>
feeding minnows as to make those ponds <add>practically</add> non-productive<lb/>
of the species of Anopheles that convey malaria even where<lb/>
bass, peckerel, &amp; other game fish were present in fair numbers.<lb/>
In one instance, this occurred in a pond over (a mile) <add>? Hartsville</add> long<lb/>
where the <del>plant</del><add>aquatic</add> growth (water shield) extended almost<lb/>
from shore to shore. During two years of inspection<lb/>
of <add>various</add> lakes impounded by corporations for power purposes,<lb/>
it has been noted that in those portions lakes where<lb/>
the proper species of top feeding minnows were very<lb/>
numerous in most instances anopheles larvae were<lb/>
<add>either</add> relatively scarce (or of no sanitary importance), or were<lb/>
absent- It is therefore evident that advantage should<lb/>
be taken of these facts as early as possible after a<lb/>
company get a franchise to impound water and<lb/>
<add>proper</add> minnow propagation should <del>lie</del> in all cases be<lb/>
started early, so as to have <del>millions</del><add>thousands</add> of them ready<lb/>
to be liberated into the lake as soon as the impound<lb/>
ing of water starts- In case large fish such as prey<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00805005"/>
<hi>5</hi><lb/>
on the top feeders are numerous, it might be well to<lb/>
destroy those in the area to be covered by the lake<lb/>
provided the consent of the proper authorities is<lb/>
obtained with a written agreement that at a fixed<lb/>
future date, <del>say three years</del>, the proper authorities<lb/>
will restock the lake with game fish at the expense<lb/>
of the owners of the water power plant. Such an<lb/>
arrangement would enable the small top feeders to multiply<lb/>
much more rapidly than under normal conditions. &amp;<lb/>
later increase the supply - of game fish-.</p>
<p>Small ponds might be made at the sides of streams<lb/>
suitable topographically, and within the area to be flooded<lb/>
and above it-. They should be so located as not to have<lb/>
the fish washed out at time of freshets &amp; arranged so that<lb/>
minnows will thrive, multiply, &amp; can not escape-.</p>
<p>Much harm <del>would</del><add>might</add> be done by stocking the lake<lb/>
with the wrong kind of fish (ie) those that grow large<lb/>
and eat top minnows-. Carp</p>
<p><hi>12A</hi> Take proper preventive measures to keep the labor force at the<lb/>
dam, power house, etc fairly free from malaria during period of<lb/>
construction- Use mosquito control by drainage &amp; oiling, efficient<lb/>
<add>protected</add> screening <del>with</del> of 16 mesh, quinine control &amp; <unclear>bloold</unclear> examination<lb/>
Do not allow sale of harmful patent <add>so called</add> chill tonic at commissaries<lb/>
It does not reduce malaria but <add>often</add> increases it-</p>
<pb n="6" id="f00805006"/>
<p><hi>6</hi></p>
<p>Measures <add>or Precautions</add> to <del>Prevent Ano</del> <add>Control</add> prolific Anopheles Production<lb/>
in Impounded water-</p>
<p><hi>13</hi> Clear all brush <add>&amp; brambles</add> from inlets &amp; ravines &amp; hights that<lb/>
would otherwise be left standing in the water<lb/>
except that which will be completely &amp; continuously<lb/>
submerged at time of lowest water -- do the same<lb/>
along the flow line of the lake -- <del>where</del> pile the<lb/>
brush &amp; burn it completely as soon as dry-. This work<lb/>
can often be done most advantageously by contract<lb/>
by the previous land owners &amp; native labor -. Near the<lb/>
water line all brush &amp; saplings must be cut close to<lb/>
the ground- It will be advantage out to make this<lb/>
clearing for three <add>to 5</add> feet above the <add>high</add> water <add>mark</add> line also - so as<lb/>
to allow floatage to become stranded- On gentle slopes<lb/>
more than five feet back-. All growth that might<lb/>
reach over into the water should be removed-</p>
<p>Willow trees &amp; others, <del>whose tops are clustered &amp;</del><add>which we close together in narrow</add><lb/>
<del>will</del> bodies of water &amp; whose tops will pierce the<lb/>
water line should be removed, especially when<lb/>
near the shore line, or <del>that part</del> their tops removed<lb/>
so the place where cut is made will remain<lb/>
submerged-.</p>
<p><hi>14</hi> Cut down or ring all pine trees as early as possible<lb/>
which are within or not far from the proposed<lb/>
shore line to prevent pine tags collecting on the<lb/>
water surface- Do not leave cut trees or piled<lb/>
brush so it will be partially submerged at low<lb/>
water. Burn up all loose trash that would other<lb/>
wise become floatage-.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f00805007"/>
<p><hi>7</hi></p>
<p><hi>15</hi> the clearing of growth on, <add>below,</add> or near the flow line<lb/>
at upper end of all inlets should be thoroughly<lb/>
performed and the work mentioned in paragraphs<lb/>
13, 14, 15, should be inspected by a person having<lb/>
a thorough knowledge of anopheles habits &amp; production<lb/>
in impounded waters before the water is turned on-<lb/>
so that any additional necessary work can be finished<lb/>
up at reasonable cost before the water rises &amp; before<lb/>
it is too late to do so economically-. Precautionary<lb/>
measures for anopheles control undertaken after impounding<lb/>
of water are less satisfactory &amp; very expensive-.</p>
<p><hi>16</hi></p>
<p>Narrow strips of water between shorelines, with vegetation<lb/>
at edges frequently harbour anopheles larvae &amp; are more<lb/>
protected from wind &amp; wave action than <add>are</add> broad expanses<lb/>
between shores- It may be necessary to give such areas<lb/>
special treatment and is best to consider such places as<lb/>
needing inspection until proved to be negative-.</p>
<p><hi>17</hi></p>
<p>Where depressions occur close to the pond, &amp; will hold<lb/>
water after the pond is formed, or where such places<lb/>
hold water at time of low lake level, when practical<lb/>
they should be connected to the pond by ditches <add>facing down stream</add> to<lb/>
allow fish access to them-</p>
<p><hi>18</hi></p>
<p>Remove from ponds &amp; swamps near the lake &amp; in the<lb/>
drainage valley where practical all bull rushes, ( ),<lb/>
( ), ( ), and such other acquatic growth as may become<lb/>
an expensive nuisance if transported into the lake-</p>
<pb n="8" id="f00805008"/>
<p><hi>8</hi></p>
<p><hi>19</hi></p>
<p>It would be <del>adva</del> a marked advantage to<lb/>
Build dam as high as essential &amp; obtain<lb/>
previous consent of the authorities to use flash<lb/>
boards for mosquito control exclusively-.<lb/>
Also so far as practical to obtain <add>written</add> permit for<lb/>
allowing of <add>marked</add> fuctuations <add>when necessary</add> for purposes of malaria<lb/>
control-</p>
<p><hi>20</hi> After such of the precautions above mentioned<lb/>
as are practical have been carried out and<lb/>
the water in the lake brought to its final level-<lb/>
there may yet be some additional work to<lb/>
do which if neglected may cause the power<lb/>
plant owners <unclear>considerable</unclear> unnecessary<lb/>
expenditure-.</p>
<p><hi>21</hi> Certain classes of acquatic vegetation such<lb/>
as ( ) may appear in the pond &amp; a sharp<lb/>
lookout should be kept so as to remove such<lb/>
plants that protect mosquito larvae from wind<lb/>
drifting, from fish &amp; other natural enemies and<lb/>
they should all be removed at once while their<lb/>
eradication is a question of a few dollars expendi-<lb/>
ture rather than hundreds of dollars or thousands<lb/>
later on-. They may originate up stream or be<lb/>
introduced by other means-</p>
<pb n="9" id="f00805009"/>
<p><hi>22</hi></p>
<p><hi>9</hi></p>
<p>Hammocks of logs, collections of vegetable debris,<lb/>
&amp; fallen trees etc that will collect floating debris<lb/>
&amp; afford larvae protection should be removed in<lb/>
the early spring and at proper intervals during<lb/>
the anopheles breeding season-</p>
<p>Certain parts of some inlets within anopheles<lb/>
flight distance of habitations or inhabited areas<lb/>
may need to have the banks kept free of grasses<lb/>
that lean over into the water- Some steep banks<lb/>
against which vegetation lodges may need<lb/>
the removal of debris collecting at their base,<lb/>
from time to time when anopheles larvae<lb/>
are present- In some instances it is advisable<lb/>
to <del>have</del> use floating booms, similar to a log boom<lb/>
but made of saplings &amp; anchored close to shore in order<lb/>
to <del>keep</del><add>maintain</add> an oil film of about three feet in width<lb/>
parallel to the shore line between the boom &amp; shore line<lb/>
at the prolific production area-</p>
<p>In inlets and sections where there is a tendency<lb/>
for algae (spirogyra) to farm, inexpensive treatment<lb/>
with copper sulphate will generally prove<lb/>
satisfactory-.</p>
<p><del>Hence screens could be used to advantage on<lb/>
small ravines to prevent debris being washed into<lb/>
inlets</del></p>
<p><del>A .... - this A <unclear>decreasing</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>B &check;</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>C &check;</unclear></del></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
