<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00807001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter and Joseph A. LePrince, 1916</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00807001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Badin (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Whitney (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Palmerville (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-00-00">1916</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00807001</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter and Joseph A. LePrince, 1916</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter and LePrince discuss their survey of a planned mosquito-control pond in North Carolina and the local incidence of malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1916-00-00">
<head>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter and Joseph A. LePrince, 1916</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00807001"/>
<p><hi>MEMORANDUM</hi></p>
<p>PHYSICAL SURVEY FOR MOSQUITO CONTROL<lb/>
OF<lb/>
PROPOSED POND<lb/>
AT<lb/>
WHITNEY, NORTH CAROLINA.</p>
<p>__________________________</p>
<p>BY<lb/>
H. R. CARTER<lb/>
ASSISTANT SURGEON-GENERAL<lb/>
AND<lb/>
J. A. LE PRINCE<lb/>
SANITARY ENGINEER<lb/>
OF THE<lb/>
UNITED STATES PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
1916</p>
<p>__________________________</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00807002"/>
<p>MEMORANDUM</p>
<p>1</p>
<p>PHYSICAL SURVEY FOR MOSQUITO CONTROL<lb/>
<hi>OF PROPOSED POND AT WHITNEY, N.C.</hi><lb/>
By H. R. CARTER,<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon-General,<lb/>
and<lb/>
J. A. Le PRINCE,<lb/>
Sanitary Engineer,<lb/>
<hi>United States Public Health Service</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Present Condition</hi>:</p>
<p>From conversation with Mr. Hardaway and the Assistant Warden<lb/>
at the convict camp we learned that there had evidently been much<lb/>
malaria in this immediate vicinity of recent years. We heard also<lb/>
of this disease on the upper part of Beaver Dam Creek. Even without<lb/>
this information we came across -we were not looking for them- so<lb/>
considerable a number of places physically well suited for breeding<lb/>
anopheles that we would have come to the same conclusion. As these<lb/>
will generally be destroyed by filling the pond they will not be<lb/>
especially enumerated, but there is no question that where people<lb/>
are thick enough there should be considerable malaria in this country.</p>
<p><hi>General Measures</hi>:</p>
<p>We aim to prevent or lessen the breeding of mosquitoes and<lb/>
to do this by exposing their larvae (wiggle-tails) to wave action<lb/>
and fish, the main agents in their destruction.</p>
<p>We can do little to influence wave action as it depends main-<lb/>
ly on the shape of the shore. The removal of heavy drift wood,<lb/>
however, will help this to some extent. To increase the action<lb/>
of fish we can do <del>this</del> much, and at this place fish will be, in<lb/>
many portions of the pond, our sole dependence against mosquitoes.</p>
<p>The larvae are protected against fish by small flotage next<lb/>
to ar against the bank and our object is <add> 1 </add> to <del>(1st)</del> prevent its form-<lb/>
ation, and (2)<del>nd</del> to strand it up on the bank above water. The<lb/>
latter method is by far the most efficacious. Naturally all float-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00807003"/>
Memo-2<lb/>
ing material that stays in the pond for any length of time will<lb/>
reach the bank unless prevented by some obstruction from doing so.<lb/>
If this reaches the bank when the pond is high it will be left<lb/>
stranded upon the bank when the pond falls. We must then not<lb/>
allow obstructions to exist which will prevent this flotage reaching<lb/>
the bank.</p>
<p>I will take then two datum lines,- one the 540 contour,<lb/>
your ordinary maximum level, and a lower contour &ldquo;X,&rdquo; not left<lb/>
bar<del>e</del> more than ten consecutive days.</p>
<p>(1) Trees and brush completely submerged at all times are<lb/>
of no importance and can be left. The same is true of such in<lb/>
the pond (away from the bank) that do not reach above contour &ldquo;X.&rdquo;<lb/>
Hardwood trees anywhere in the pond are a matter of small importance,<lb/>
and need not be cut for sanitary reasons though I understand it<lb/>
is proposed to do so to prevent interference with the operation<lb/>
of the plant. Pine trees whose tops come above &ldquo;X&rdquo; should be<lb/>
&ldquo;ringed&rdquo; (belted) or <hi>cut down this spring</hi> so that they may not cast<lb/>
pine needles in the pond in the summer of 1917, and laps of trees<lb/>
any where in the pond that will float up to the surface had better<lb/>
be removed or destroyed.</p>
<p>(2) Clear the edges of the pond of brush. Taking the 540<lb/>
contour go up--say--three feet above it on very steep banks and 10<lb/>
or 15 ft. above it on sloping banks--<hi>measured</hi> on the surface. Cut<lb/>
out all brush that will stop floatage down to the contour &ldquo;X&rdquo; and<lb/>
below it--say--three feet on steep slopes and 10 feet on gentle<lb/>
slopes. This stuff that is cut must be removed from the pond eith-<lb/>
er by dragging above the clear space or by a complete burning. All<lb/>
laps down in this clear space must, of course, be removed.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00807004"/>
<p>Memo-3</p>
<p>(3) When there are thick groves of hard wood sap-<lb/>
lings growing at any point adjacent to the clear edge, whose<lb/>
tops project above the contour &ldquo;X&rdquo; and are so thick as to<lb/>
stop a considerable amount of drift they should be cut down<lb/>
and removed. The same for the brushy tops of trees in the<lb/>
same situation.</p>
<p>In our judgment this is all of the cutting that will<lb/>
do any good as a sanitary measure, but I cannot lay too much<lb/>
stress upon the necessity of removing the things out from<lb/>
the pond. The stumps on the upper contours of this edge<lb/>
should be cut as low as possible, because if the water covers<lb/>
the stump most of the time the stump will not throw up sprouts.<lb/>
If it does not, it will. It will be necessary, I think, once<lb/>
or possibly twice a year for the first few years, to go over<lb/>
this edge above your ordinary highwater line to cut off<lb/>
the sprouts that come up.</p>
<p>It will not be necessary to do any of this work in<lb/>
such parts of the pond as are -say- one and a quarter miles<lb/>
from a residence (an<del>n</del>occupied house). This distance is excess<lb/>
of what is deemed generally necessary, but is specified as<lb/>
giving <del>quite</del> a factor of safety.</p>
<p>(4) If it be practicable, weather conditions may<lb/>
prevent it, it would be a very great advantage to burn over<lb/>
the pond site, the whole of it, just before it is filled &amp;<lb/>
as close to the filling as possible. This will get rid of<lb/>
leaves, pine needles and small brush generally which would<lb/>
otherwise rise up and float on the pond. It will also tend<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00807005"/>
Memo-4<lb/>
to kill the stumps that are above high water level.</p>
<p>(6) With a pond in which there will be as large fluct-<lb/>
uations of level as this one it will be advisable to look over<lb/>
the upper contours and see if it will leave pools or <add>small</add> ponds as it fall<lb/>
and if so to drain them by suitable ditches. Likely enough it<lb/>
will be impracticable to judge of this until all parts of the pond<lb/>
are filled and you see whether it does leave such pools. A pool<lb/>
drained within fourteen or sixteen days of its formation does no<lb/>
harm, and a pool that does not last that time, by drying up or<lb/>
otherwise does no harm.</p>
<p>(7) Since you are depending mainly on fish for the control<lb/>
of mosquito breeding in this pond we would advise you to make<lb/>
arrangements for getting such fish, either this fall or at least<lb/>
very early next spring, the former being prefereable.</p>
<p>(8) The U.S. Fish Commission has a Hatchery of mosquito<lb/>
eating fish at Elizabeth City, N. C. Note that the fish that<lb/>
you want are TOP MINNOWS. Game fish would be a disadvantage to<lb/>
you as they would eat the minnows instead of the mosquito larvae.<lb/>
The minnows are needed in large quantities.</p>
<p>(9) <hi>SPECIAL LOCALITIES</hi></p>
<p>(Referring to property map.)</p>
<p>1. I do not think any of the willows here except those next to<lb/>
the bank, and next to the old Whitney Dam are high enough to re-<lb/>
quire attention. Those next to the bank on both sides of the<lb/>
river are to be cut or removed.</p>
<p>2. There is a lot of debris here, old tressels etc, which<lb/>
should be removed, as they will float up when the pond is low.</p>
<p>Can't be under-<lb/>
stood without map.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f00807006"/>
<p>Memo-5</p>
<p>3 &amp; 4. The measures to be taken, clearing of the brush etc.,<lb/>
are provided for in the general measures, but they should be taken<lb/>
with extreme pains on account of their proximity to Whitney,<lb/>
which doubtless will have considerable population. (5) The old canal<lb/>
and the bights that go off from beyond the Winston-Salem railroad<lb/>
will likely be a very troublesome proposition. Indeed a good part<lb/>
of the bottom of this canal, especially toward the lower part,<lb/>
was probably breeding profusely the last few summers. It is in<lb/>
every way well fitted physically for breeding mosquitoes now.<lb/>
It too will have to be cleaned with more than ordinary care,<lb/>
and the edges of the bank kept clean more than is necessary for<lb/>
the rest of the pond.</p>
<p>This place is dangerous for three reasons:-</p>
<p>(1) It is close to considerable villages, Palmerville and Whitney.</p>
<p>(2) It is so narrow that wave action will have no effect and we<lb/>
will have to depend entirely upon fish.</p>
<p>(3) The sides are so steep-vertical -in many places- that the<lb/>
fluctuations of the pond will not rid us of flotage.</p>
<p>The measures devised for the rest of the pond must be accen-<lb/>
tuated for this canal and <add>the</add> bights. It must be very carefully<lb/>
cleared. The bank must be kept clear of floating material -by<lb/>
hand I expect,- and <add>it</add> must be especially stocked with fish. I believe<lb/>
however, that these places in their natural condition are now<lb/>
producing many anopheles.</p>
<p>6. Is simply marked because all along the edge of this cliff<lb/>
there is a very large amount of tree laps in the woods, some<lb/>
of which would float up and hence should be removed.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f00807007"/>
<p>Memo-6</p>
<p>7. In the lower reaches of Bever Dam most of the stuff<lb/>
will be completely submerged and needs no attention, The edges<lb/>
will require cutting.</p>
<p>8. The upper reaches of Beaver Dam Creek and Reynolds Fork are<lb/>
in quite flat country and there are a number of farm houses empty<lb/>
around them. These places will probably be dangerous as they<lb/>
are too narrow for wave action to do much good.</p>
<p>They are far less dangerous, however, than the canal.</p>
<p>(1) Because there are not nearly so many people.</p>
<p>(2) In shoal water the fish have a great deal more control of the<lb/>
mosquitoes.</p>
<p>(3) The gentle slope of the banks allows flotage to strand, hence<lb/>
we should have clean edges. An extra planting of minnows<lb/>
in this locality is very advisable. Also lookout for pools<lb/>
left by the falling pond.</p>
<p>For the convenience of anyone making a biological survey<lb/>
of this place during the summer, which should be done as it would<lb/>
throw much light upon its present condition in the production<lb/>
of malaria breeding mosquitoes, I would enumerate <del>such</del><add>such</add><add>some</add> of those<lb/>
places as seem to us physically well suited for breeding anopheles<lb/>
as we have noticed. (See Numbers on Map)</p>
<p>1. Back of the old Whitney Office site there are a number<lb/>
of pools physically well suited for breeding.</p>
<p>2. Behind railway fill just below Whitney, -two places<lb/>
in upper part, one in lower.</p>
<p>3. Second bight below Whitney beyond the Winston-Salem<lb/>
South-bound, a large area physically well suited for breeding.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f00807008"/>
<p>Memo-7</p>
<p>4. In the valley of Beaver Dam Creek where the road<lb/>
crosses it not far from the river at No. 7. A rather large area.</p>
<p>5. At No. 8 from the Mouth of Buffalo Creek down to<lb/>
Beaver Dam and between them is a large area well suited for<lb/>
production.</p>
<p>6. At Glady<del>s</del> Fork where it joins Beaver Dam the creek<lb/>
spreads out into a number of pools extremely well suited<lb/>
physically for breeding.</p>
<p>7. A small place, spring head and marshy stream, to the<lb/>
rear of Elliott's house, about 200 yards off. This may dry up<lb/>
in summer time.</p>
<p>8. At saw mill beyond Elliott's house, a large breeding<lb/>
place.</p>
<p>9. Beyond abandoned house of J.C. Russell, a series of<lb/>
pools in the woods.</p>
<p>10. At the crossing of Reynold's Fork beyond a saw mill,<lb/>
and at the crossing of the last fork of Beaver Dam Creek where<lb/>
the land is very flat are several large areas (2 places).</p>
<p>11. At two crossings of Reynold's Fork going back towards<lb/>
the Yadkin, several pools on the side of the road in the woods, on<lb/>
the uplands, going towards the Yadkin; one place, in cat tails,<lb/>
in the race of the power plant, (several places)</p>
<p>It is not pretended that these are all, or even any con-<lb/>
siderable portion of the breeding places in the area to be cover-<lb/>
ed by the pond; they are simply some that we noted as we passed<lb/>
along a part of its periphery.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f00807009"/>
<p>Memo-8</p>
<p><hi>CARE OF THE POND AFTER IT IS FILLED</hi>.</p>
<p>1. Keep the winter level of the pond from October first<lb/>
to June 15th or 30th as high as possible, so <del>as to strand</del><add>that</add> all<lb/>
of the flotage that comes to the banks at this time of the year<lb/>
<add><hi>maybe stranded</hi></add> when the pond falls to<del>wards</del> the summer level.</p>
<p>2. Save the summer floods, July 1st to October 1st, as<lb/>
much as you can so as to have the pond level fluctuate during<lb/>
this season. It is understood that the summer level is less,<lb/>
by some feet, than the normal winter level. The pond should not<lb/>
be kept up during the summer time into the line of already stranded<lb/>
drift for as long a time as three weeks, preferably not over two<lb/>
weeks. It will generally be impossible to do this, even if you<lb/>
wish it.</p>
<p>3. For the first few years we judge it will ne necessary<lb/>
to cut down the sprouts that will come up above your 540 contour.<lb/>
Below that contour it should be kept clean of living growth by<lb/>
the pond itself.</p>
<p>4. The edge of the pond should be examined between July<lb/>
1st and October 1st so that collections of logs and heavy drift<lb/>
that may possibly land against the bank, and yet be floating,<lb/>
can be dragged out. This will <del>possibly</del><add>probably</add> not be necessary after<lb/>
the first year or two.</p>
<p>If collections of small flotage are seen resting against the<lb/>
bank they should be dragged out. The banks of the canal and <del>its</del><add>the</add><lb/>
bights from Whitney down should be given very special attention<lb/>
in this respect and will, we fear, require much attention.<lb/>
It all depends upon how efficacious the fish will prove here.</p>
<p>________________________________</p>
<pb n="10" id="f00807010"/>
<p>Memo-9</p>
<p>Nothing is advised to prevent the growth of aquatic plants which<lb/>
in the future <hi>may</hi> be a problem. This condition will have to be<lb/>
met when it arises, if it does arise. We do not know enough of<lb/>
this as yet to advise general manoeuvres in advance.</p>
<p>The measures we have indicated above are about all that are<lb/>
applicable for the control of mosquito<del>ee</del> (Anopheles) production<lb/>
by this pond within allowable economic limits. They are in excess<lb/>
of what we would feel justified in requiring, but are as specified<lb/>
for the following reasons:-</p>
<p>(1) The very considerable number of people who will be ad-<lb/>
jacent to the pond at Whitney, Palmersville and Badin.</p>
<p>(2) The unusual risk of mosquito production entailed by<lb/>
the canal and the bights behind the Winston Salem R. R. track.</p>
<p>(3) The statement that you were prepared to carry out all<lb/>
measures which would do good at any reasonable expense.</p>
<p>Even with these measures carried out it is not pretended<lb/>
that there will be no anopheles production from the pond. There<lb/>
will be. The total production of the pond site will likely be<lb/>
no greater, or less, than at present, but the location of breeding<lb/>
will be changed, and malaria may be increased in some places.<lb/>
The measures advised should, however, minimize mosquito production<lb/>
and this with proper screening, and possibly the use of quinine<lb/>
should minimize the malaria in the community.</p>
<p>It must be noted that the increase in population adjacent<lb/>
to the canal would increase the number of malaria cases among them,<lb/>
even with no change in the condition of breeding places. This<lb/>
increase will be out of proportion to the increase of population,<lb/>
rather as a function of the square, or possibly of the third power<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f00807011"/>
Memo-10<lb/>
of that increase, and this must be discounted in estimating the<lb/>
malaria due <hi>directly</hi> to mosquitoes produced by the pond. It<lb/>
will be the more noticeable as people come in from non-malarious<lb/>
communities.</p>
<p>_________________________</p>
<p>H. R. Carter<lb/>
Asst. Surgeon-General<lb/>
U. S. P. H. S.</p>
<p>J. A. Le Prince<lb/>
Sanitary engineer<lb/>
U. S. P. H. S.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
