<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00807028">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to William Crawford Gorgas, August 26, 1916</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00807028</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-08-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Gorgas, William Crawford</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">Barranquilla (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Cartagena (Columbia)</name>
<name type="place">Santa Marta (Columbia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-08-26">August 26, 1916</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00807028</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to William Crawford Gorgas, August 26, 1916</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter reports on yellow fever in Colombia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1916-08-26">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to William Crawford Gorgas, August 26, 1916</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00807028"/>
<opener>
C<lb/>
<dateline>
Barranquilla, Colombia,<lb/>
<date value="1916-08-26">August 26, 1916.</date>
</dateline>
General William C. Gorgas,<lb/>
Chairman,<lb/>
Yellow Fever Commission.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to submit the following report on<lb/>
some sanitary aspects of the city of Barranquilla, Colombia, and<lb/>
their relations with the sanitary conditions of the other towns<lb/>
on the north coast of Colombia. This report is to be considered<lb/>
in connection with the one submitted by Dr. Guiteras, and is<lb/>
complementary thereto.</p>
<p><hi>Barranquilla the<lb/>
only town examined.</hi></p>
<p>Our direct examination was confined to<lb/>
Barranquilla. On account of the schedule of<lb/>
the transportation lines fourteen days more would have been ex-<lb/>
pended had we done the same for Cartagena, or Santa Marta. We<lb/>
judged this delay inadvisable as, on account of the inter-communi-<lb/>
cation between them, a careful examination of the sanitary condi-<lb/>
tions of Barranquilla would in our opinion be sufficient to show<lb/>
the sanitary condition of the other two towns.</p>
<p><hi>Inter-relation of<lb/>
the three towns.</hi></p>
<p>With Cartagena it is in communication once a<lb/>
week by a vessel of the United Fruit Company<lb/>
from Cartagena, and three times a week, both ways, via Calamar.<lb/>
By this last route the bulk of the passengerstraffic comes. With<lb/>
Santa Marta there is communication nine times a week by a line of<lb/>
steam launches. There is considerable passenger traffic from<lb/>
both places - Cartagena and Santa Marta - so much that it is not<lb/>
conceivable that there should be yellow fever in either town for<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00807029"/>
2<lb/>
any considerable time, in years, without conveyance of the<lb/>
infection to Barranquilla.</p>
<p><hi>Susceptible people<lb/>
in Barranquilla</hi>.</p>
<p>Also, if yellow fever existed in Barranquilla<lb/>
its existence should be shown there more<lb/>
readily than in either Cartagena or Santa Marta. It is a much<lb/>
larger town than either of the others and it has proportionately<lb/>
a much larger foreign resident population, a number of whom are<lb/>
susceptible to yellow fever. Dr. Oscar Noguera, the Departmental<lb/>
Health Officer, estimates this population at 3,000, but a large<lb/>
number of them are old residents and immune to yellow fever. It<lb/>
is the gateway through which passes the great bulk of the passenger<lb/>
traffic between the plateau and the sea. This is considerable in<lb/>
amount and is practically all susceptible to yellow fever. Barran-<lb/>
quilla is the place of stopping to await the steamers going both ways.</p>
<p>There is thus, we think, a sufficient number of people in<lb/>
Barranquilla susceptible to yellow fever to give an index of its<lb/>
existence if it does exist there, certainly many more than in<lb/>
Cartagena or Santa Marta.</p>
<p><hi>Why the other two<lb/>
towns were not<lb/>
examined</hi>.</p>
<p>On both counts then; that if yellow fever existed<lb/>
in Santa Marta or Cartagena for any considerable<lb/>
time it would certainly have infected Barranquilla<lb/>
also and that it would be more readily found in Barranquilla if it<lb/>
existed there than in either of the other two towns, we decided to<lb/>
confine our investigations to Barranquilla, as this shows the sanitary<lb/>
condition of the other two towns also. We were thus enabled to<lb/>
make this examination thoroughly, which had not been possible if we<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00807030"/>
3<lb/>
had attempted to examine all three towns in the time at our<lb/>
disposal, and to spend fourteen days longer in doing this seemed<lb/>
not justified.</p>
<p><hi>Deductions from<lb/>
examination</hi>.</p>
<p>From the findings of our examination as shown<lb/>
by the report of Dr. Guiteras, we believe that<lb/>
yellow fever has not existed in Barranquilla since 1911, and the<lb/>
same statement should apply to Santa Marta and Cartagena. This<lb/>
may well be due to the removal of the Panama focus. It is stated<lb/>
that there has been none since 1905.</p>
<p><hi>Communication with<lb/>
ports to eastward</hi>.</p>
<p>In this connection it is to be noted that these<lb/>
ports receive very few vessels from the ports<lb/>
of Venezuela and other ports to the eastward, nearly all vessels<lb/>
going from west to east, and would be little apt to receive in-<lb/>
fection from the<del>m</del><add>se parts</add> if the<del>y</del> were infected. At present the quar-<lb/>
antine at Puerto Colombia is an added protection against those<lb/>
ports, which are listed by the quarantine officer as infected with<lb/>
yellow fever. We inspected this station and find it sufficiently<lb/>
equipped and working under good regulations.</p>
<p>One case of yellow fever is reported as entering Barranquilla<lb/>
from the A<del>l</del>trato Valley in 1910, sick on arrival, from which there<lb/>
was no spread.</p>
<p><hi>Stegomyia.</hi></p>
<p>I would also invite your attention to the scarcity of<lb/>
stegomyia (A&euml;des calopus), in Barranquilla during our<lb/>
visit of eight days. Why this should be so is not at first apparent.<lb/>
There is an intermittent water-supply, although an abundant one when<lb/>
running. The water is turned off each day from 2 p.m. to 2 a.m.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00807031"/>
4<lb/>
This naturally leads to stowage of water. Yet stegomyia<lb/>
were certainly scarce. We saw <hi>none</hi> in flight, but developed<lb/>
two from a collection of larvae from the American Consulate.<lb/>
There were about 60 larvae in the collection and only 3 of<lb/>
them - 2 of which developed - were stegomyia Culex fatigans<lb/>
(quinquefasciatus) were more common, but not abundant.</p>
<p>Possibly this condition is temporary, as breeding may be<lb/>
greater during the dry season than at present, and indeed it<lb/>
may not be general over the town, as I could examine but a few<lb/>
places. In them there were not 3% of what would have been<lb/>
found in Panama in 1904. I think, however, that stegomyia are<lb/>
normally not abundant, the breeding conditions being really<lb/>
less favorable than seemed to be the case at first sight.</p>
<p>(1) The water tanks in many of the houses of the better<lb/>
class are closed iron tanks with affluent and effluent pipes.<lb/>
I am informed that this is generally the case.</p>
<p>(2) Stowage being only from day to day the containers are<lb/>
fewer and much more often emptied than when water is scarce and<lb/>
rain water is depended on. In only a small section of the town<lb/>
is rain water stowed. Indeed, I saw no arrangement for stowing<lb/>
any. It is worth noting that the only stegomyiae found were<lb/>
from larvae in <hi>rain water</hi> in an old bowl set in the earth in the<lb/>
yard of the Consulate, hence not subject to emptying.</p>
<p>The general concensus of statement of residents was that<lb/>
stegomyiae were rare, as were any other day feeding mosquitoes<lb/>
at any time of the year.</p>
<p>Since the finding is that yellow fever does not exist in<lb/>
the Atlantic ports of Colombia it is scarcely necessary to say<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00807032"/>
5<lb/>
that it is not recommended that the Foundation undertake any<lb/>
work for the elimination of that disease from said ports. It<lb/>
is, however, advisable for the local authorities to take all<lb/>
such measures as are necessary and practicable to lessen the<lb/>
production of stegomyia so as to obviate the danger of a spread<lb/>
of yellow fever if it be introduced. The susceptible population<lb/>
in Barranquilla is increasing yearly and will ultimately reach<lb/>
a point, if this has not already been attained, at which even<lb/>
with the present small number of stegomyia, the disease will<lb/>
spread if introduced.</p>
<p>It is to obviate this danger that Dr. Vengoechea proposes<lb/>
to undertake an anti-stegomyia campaign.</p>
<p>I would add that we received every possible aid in our in-<lb/>
vestigations from Dr. Vengoechea, the sanitary officer of the<lb/>
Atlantic coast of Colombia, through whose courtesy we also visited<lb/>
the quarantine station of Puerto Colombia. We were very favor-<lb/>
ably impressed with the sincerity, ability and force of this officer.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>H. R. Carter<lb/>
Member, Yellow Fever Commission</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
