<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00803018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to R.H. von Ezdorf, February 16, 1916</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00803018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-02-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">von Ezdorf, Rudoph H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Hayne, Theodore</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi Alabama</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Maryland</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">North Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Georgia</name>
<name type="place">Whitney Pond (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-02-16">February 16, 1916</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00803018</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to R.H. von Ezdorf, February 16, 1916</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses anti-mosquito work and mentions the Rockefeller Foundation.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1916-02-16">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to R.H. von Ezdorf, February 16, 1916</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00803018"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1916-02-16">February 16, 1916.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear von Ezdorf:</salute>
</opener>
<p>This is a letter of details.</p>
<p>1st: So far as your Chatanooga affair is concerned I told Le-<lb/>
Prince to tell you I would be very glad for you to take the job1<lb/>
that it was in no sense any interference with my work, and if it<lb/>
were I would not care.</p>
<p>2nd: And far more important a thing: I have been think-<lb/>
ing how valuable--or rather how necessary--LePrince is for plan-<lb/>
ning and supervising the anti-mosquito work which various places<lb/>
undertake. Lanette: Crystal City: Emporia and some place near<lb/>
Vicksburg of which he spoke to me, whose name I forget, are all<lb/>
doing such work this year and not unlikely he may be needed as<lb/>
a consultant at Lake and Chicot. If it be practicable to put<lb/>
someone else with Griffitts would it not be better to simply<lb/>
give LePrince all the investigations--mainly entomological--this<lb/>
year of the impounded waters, letting him visit this party as<lb/>
necessary, and do this other anti-mosquito work, which I think<lb/>
no one else can do so well as himself. The same, indeed, is true<lb/>
of the work he would be leaving on the impounded waters.</p>
<p>I do not know that we can get any satisfactory man to go with<lb/>
Griffitts. I spoke to Kerr about it tentatively. It is a &ldquo;tri-<lb/>
lemma:&rdquo; a/ If money is available he says he could get King.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00803019"/>
-2-<lb/>
who, as the problems are entomological, would be very satisfac-<lb/>
tory for the work. b/ If it be possible to spare him--Fox--<lb/>
who wishes to make himself an all-round medical entomologist.<lb/>
I don't know what he knows about mosquitoes, but he is probably<lb/>
our highest American on fleas and, if he will take up this work<lb/>
he can do very much better in it than I would. I think he will<lb/>
not be available. It was Kerr's suggestion. c/ Nobody. Give<lb/>
Griffitts authority to employ some bright earnest fellow--like<lb/>
young Hayne was last year--and two such men--and <unclear>Lucrinceitce</unclear> to<lb/>
visiting and staying with them as much as he could with the oth-<lb/>
er duties. Possibly he could get some student of entomology--<lb/>
or local entomologist--who would do quite well. Conradi, Prof<del>f</del><lb/>
essor of Entomology at the University of South Carolina, could,<lb/>
I judge, be gotten for $150.00 a month and expenses.</p>
<p>What do you think of the need of LePrince and how much time<lb/>
would it take at the places that are doing and <unclear>ingoing</unclear> to do, work<lb/>
against mosquitoes? By the way, you might add Georgetown, S. C.<lb/>
which Hayne is anxious for you to visit and where he says they<lb/>
are prepared to pay any reasonable amount for anti-malarial work.<lb/>
The Mayor is a physician.</p>
<p>3rd: I certainly hope you will have good luck--I know you<lb/>
will take pains--in selecting the most suitable place for your<lb/>
Rockefeller work. Be sure that you don't take a place where the<lb/>
difficulties are too great. To explain a less success than Bass'--<lb/>
no matter if the reasons are good--would not be satisfactory.<lb/>
I am awfully sorry for the floods in Arkansas and hope they have<lb/>
not affected the places you have picked out injuriously. Had, it<lb/>
been possible to have done this work in Mississippi in a place<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00803020"/>
-3-<lb/>
where the conditions were as nearly as maybe the same as Bass's,<lb/>
the comparison would have been more accurate. I know too, that<lb/>
Leathers is an excellent administrative officer and would have<lb/>
handled that end--the most difficult one of the problem--well.<lb/>
Garrison may be the same, but I don't know him so well.</p>
<p>I am sending back your glossary with the names defined by<lb/>
the Standard Dictionary. I am unquestionably wrong in my &ldquo;ham-<lb/>
mock.&rdquo; I judge that it should more properly be called &ldquo;raft&rdquo; or<lb/>
&ldquo;mat&rdquo; although it is called &ldquo;hammock&rdquo; in Maryland: Virginia:<lb/>
North and South Carolina. I think I covered it properly, however,<lb/>
in my report by the devise I told you. I will add that &ldquo;marsh&rdquo;<lb/>
on the South Atlantic--South Carolina and Georgia--refers only<lb/>
to salt marsh, which, of course, is a mistack, but a fact. &ldquo;Pool&rdquo;<lb/>
is a technical name (U. S. Engineers) for the water impounded for<lb/>
navigation above a lock--although it is very large. It rightly<lb/>
means &ldquo;a small pond.&rdquo; &ldquo;Branch&rdquo; and &ldquo;brook&rdquo; are identical: &ldquo;A run-<lb/>
ning stream smaller than a creek.&rdquo; &ldquo;Creek&rdquo; in the United States<lb/>
needs no definition. It is spread on all our maps. Abroad it<lb/>
refers exclusively I think to salt water creeks.</p>
<p>About myself: I judge that I will be absent this summer and<lb/>
have not quite made up my mind on the matter as I could not see<lb/>
Dr. Gorgas Saturday. He is in Alabama, I think a witness in the<lb/>
suit for the Alabama Power Co. That is why, in my arrangements<lb/>
for this year, I have not taken account of my own work. I may<lb/>
not go, however. Will let you know as soon as it is definitely<lb/>
settled.</p>
<p>What about our getting the Service to supply certain stations<lb/>
with LePrince's book? It is very interesting to me because I know<lb/>
the Isthmus and it has a very large amount of new matter.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00803021"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>I am enclosing also, in accordance with our custom, our re-<lb/>
port on the Whitney work--the first attempt to utilize the observa-<lb/>
tions we have made on Impounded waters in the sanitation of a<lb/>
pond before it is made. It is an extremely difficult proposition.<lb/>
Please return it to me.</p>
<p>About when will you start the field work--especially the<lb/>
Rockefeller work?</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly your friend,</salute>
2 enclosures.<lb/>
HRC/LC<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
