<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00807016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report Extract: Rural Sanitation in the Tropics, by Malcolm Watson, with an introduction by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00807016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Watson, Malcolm</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Hearn, Lafcadio</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Manson, Patrick</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Asia</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">Tokyo (Japan)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Singapore</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">India</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00807016</idno>
<title>Report Extract: Rural Sanitation in the Tropics, by Malcolm Watson, with an introduction by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Watson discusses the possibility and ramifications of yellow fever spreading into Asia and the Indian sub-continent.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report Extract: Rural Sanitation in the Tropics, by Malcolm Watson, with an introduction by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00807016"/>
<p><unclear>carton</unclear></p>
<p>H.R. Carter</p>
<p>Extract from Dr. Malcolm Watson's book<lb/>
&ldquo;Rural Sanitation in the Tropics&rdquo;, showing danger from<lb/>
spread of yellow fever to Asia.</p>
<p>The following excerpt from Malcolm Watson's book &ldquo;Rural<lb/>
Sanitation in the Tropics&rdquo; is submitted as showing the opinion<lb/>
of a British sanitarian on the danger of the introduction of<lb/>
yellow fever to the Far East and the results which would follow.<lb/>
He thus concurs with Manson, whose belief that this danger was<lb/>
a real one and increased by the change of trade relations inci-<lb/>
dnet to the opening of the Panama Canal is too well known to<lb/>
require mention.</p>
<p>While not regarding this danger as increased by the con-<lb/>
struction of the Canal yet it is increasing because of the great-<lb/>
er ease and rapidity of communication between the ports of the<lb/>
world, and which will continally grow greater.</p>
<p>The risk of the introduction of yellow fever into Asia from<lb/>
an American focus seems small (that from Africa, as first pointed<lb/>
out by Guiteras, should be greater), but the result of its intro-<lb/>
duction into the dense, imperfectly educated and very conserva-<lb/>
tive populations of Asia, where A&euml;des calopus is abundant, would<lb/>
be so stupendous a calamity that one can scarcely conceive of a<lb/>
risk of such a thing small enough to be allowable. To remove all<lb/>
risks then the work contemplated by the Foundation, i.e., the<lb/>
elimination of yellow fever from the world, seems abundantly justi-<lb/>
fied and indeed a sanitary necessity.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Extract from Chapter XII, &ldquo;<hi>RURAL SANITATION IN THE TROPICS</hi>&rdquo; , by Dr. Malcolm Watson</head>
<pb n="2" id="f00807017"/>
<p>Extract from Chapter XII, &ldquo;<hi>RURAL SANITATION<lb/>
IN THE TROPICS</hi>&rdquo; , by Dr. Malcolm Watson.</p>
<p>---------o---------</p>
<p>Asia's Danger. - At the end of <hi>Kwaidan</hi>, in which Lafcadio<lb/>
Hearn has so exquisitely retold some of the weird tales from the<lb/>
old Japanese books, he has added three insect studies - butter-<lb/>
flies, mosquitos, ants. That on mosquitos I cannot help re-<lb/>
producing almost in full, for reasons which will be apparent.</p>
<p>"With a view to self-protection I have been reading Dr.<lb/>
Howard's book, <hi>Mosquitos</hi>. I am persecuted by mosquitoes. There<lb/>
are several species in my neighbourhood; but only one of them is<lb/>
a serious torment - a tiny needly thing, all silver-speckled and<lb/>
silver-streaked. The puncture of it is sharp as an electric burn,<lb/>
and the mere hum of it has a lancinating quality of tone which for-<lb/>
tels the quality of the pain about to come - much in the same way<lb/>
that a particular smell suggests a particular taste. I find that<lb/>
this mosquito much resembles the creature which Dr. Howard calls<lb/>
Stegomyia fasciata, or Culex fasciatus, and that its habits are the<lb/>
same as those of the Stegomyia. For example, it is diurnal rather<lb/>
than nocturnal, and becomes most troublesome during the afternoon.<lb/>
And I have discovered that it comes from the Buddhist cemetery - a<lb/>
very old cemetery - in the rear of my garden.</p>
<p>"Dr. Howard's book declares that in order to rid a neighbour-<lb/>
hood of mosquitoes, it is only necessary to pour a little petroleum<lb/>
or kerosene oil into the stagnant water where they breed. Once a<lb/>
week the oil should be used, 'at the rate of one ounce for every<lb/>
fifteen square feet of water surface, and a proportionate quantity<lb/>
for any less surface' ......But please to consider the conditions<lb/>
in my neighbourhood!</p>
<p>"I have said that my tormentors come from the Buddhist cemetery.<lb/>
Before nearly every tomb in that old cemetery there is a water<lb/>
receptacle, or cistern, called <hi>mizutam&eacute;</hi>'. In the majority of cases<lb/>
this <hi>mizutam&eacute;</hi> is simply an oblong cavity chiselled in the broad<lb/>
pedestal supporting the monument; but before tombs of a costly kind,<lb/>
having no pedestal-tank, a larger separate tank is placed, cut out<lb/>
of a single block of stone, and decorated with a family crest, or<lb/>
with symbolic carvings. In front of a tomb of the humblest class,<lb/>
having no <hi>mizutam&eacute;</hi>, water is placed in cups or other vessels - for<lb/>
the dead must have water. Flowers also must be offered to them;<lb/>
and before every tomb you will find a pair of bamboo cups, or other<lb/>
flower-vessels; and these, of course, contain water. There is a<lb/>
well in the cemetery to supply water for the graves. Whenever the<lb/>
tombs are visited by relatives and friends of the dead, fresh water<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00807018"/>
2<lb/>
(Extract from &ldquo;Rural Sanitation,&rdquo; etc.)<lb/>
is poured into the tanks and cups. But as an old cemetery<lb/>
of this kind contains thousands of <hi>mizutam&eacute;</hi>, and tens of thousands<lb/>
of flower-vessels, the water in all of these cannot be renewed<lb/>
every day. It becomes stagnant and populous. The deeper tanks<lb/>
seldom get dry - the rainfall at Tokyo being heavy enough to keep<lb/>
them partly filled during nine months out of the twelve.</p>
<p>"Well, it is in these tanks and flower-vessels that mine<lb/>
enemies are born; they rise by millions from the water of the<lb/>
dead; and, according to Buddhist doctrine, some of them may be<lb/>
reincarnations of those very dead, condemned by the error of<lb/>
former lives to the conditions of <hi>Jiki-ketsu-gaki</hi>, or blood-drinking<lb/>
pretas..... Anyhow, the malevolence of the Culex fasciatus would<lb/>
justify the suspicion that some wicked human soul had been com-<lb/>
pressed into that wailing speck of a body...</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wonder what would be said if the city government of Tokyo-<lb/>
which is aggressively scientific and progressive - were suddenly<lb/>
to command that all water surfaces in the Buddhist cemeteries should<lb/>
be covered, at regular intervals, with a film of kerosene oil! How<lb/>
could the religion which prohibits the taking of any life - even<lb/>
of invisible life - yield to such a mandate? Would filial piety<lb/>
even dream of consenting to obey such an order? And then to think<lb/>
of the cost, in labour and time, of putting kerosene oil, every<lb/>
seven days, into the millions of <hi>mizutam&eacute;</hi>, and the tens of millions<lb/>
of bamboo flower-cups in the Tokyo graveyards!...Impossible! To<lb/>
free the city from mosquitoes it would be necessary to demolish the<lb/>
ancient graveyards - and that would signify the ruin of the Buddhist<lb/>
temples attached to them - and that would mean the dispartition of<lb/>
so many charming gardens with their lotus-ponds and Sanscrit-lettered<lb/>
monuments and humpy bridges and holy groves and weirdly-smiling<lb/>
Buddhas! So the extermination of the Culex fasciatus would involve<lb/>
the destruction of the poetry of the ancestral cult - surely too<lb/>
great a price to pay!...&rdquo;</p>
<p>The boom of the big beell with its billowing peal, with its<lb/>
quaint tone, stirs a chord of sympathy with the lover of that Budd-<lb/>
hist graveyard in the heart of the sanitarian. And if those charm-<lb/>
ing gardens, and lotus-ponds, and holy groves, and all the poetry of<lb/>
the ancestral cult, pleading to be spared, hold for a moment his<lb/>
profaning hand, and make him realize the mighty forces at times ar-<lb/>
rayed against him, surely it will not be recorded that he was false<lb/>
to his charge. And yet this Buddhist graveyard with its tens of<lb/>
millions of little bamboo flower-cups, each and all a token of love<lb/>
and emblem of eternal life, might have bred death to the hundreds of<lb/>
millions who live in Asia; and had yellow fever not been stamped<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00807019"/>
3<lb/>
out on the Canal, can we doubt that the religion which prohibits<lb/>
the taking of life would have turned Asia into a shambles?</p>
<p>With the myriad mosquito breeding-places in Japan, and the<lb/>
countless myriads in All Asia, the disease would have flashed<lb/>
from east to west leaving millions of human beings rotting, un-<lb/>
buried, in heaps. Nothing the world has known, hardly anything<lb/>
we can imagine, all Asia crammed into a Black Hole of Calcutta,<lb/>
sketches even an outline of the disaster it would have been to<lb/>
the human race.</p>
<p>Time and again improved communications have led to the intro-<lb/>
duction and spread of disease; and all should rejoice that the<lb/>
American sanitarians, by their work in Havana and in Panama, have<lb/>
made it practically certain that yellow fever will never be allowed<lb/>
to reach Asia directly from America. Surely there was a Controlling<lb/>
Power who delayed the construction of the Canal until men had learned<lb/>
how to control yellow fever! But although the danger of yellow<lb/>
fever reaching Asia has been averted for a while, it would be folly<lb/>
to assume the comfortable attitude that all is well. Every Asiatic<lb/>
port is full of <hi>Aedes calopus</hi>, although all perhaps cannot rival<lb/>
Tokyo. Singapore is no exception; and if I refer to it now, it is<lb/>
because the subject is receiving attention. Anti-malaria work was<lb/>
specially urgent in 1911, so general anti-mosquito work was put<lb/>
aside for the time. The arguments in favour of anti-yellow fever<lb/>
work are, however, strong; and the following is an extract from my<lb/>
report to the Government of the Straits Settlements:-</p>
<p>"Were yellow fever to reach Asia, Singapore would, from its<lb/>
position on the great highway, become infected at a very early date;<lb/>
and through its great distributing trade it would, if once infected,<lb/>
act as the great distributor of the disease, despite all the quar-<lb/>
antine restrictions that would be put on Singapore ships by neighbor-<lb/>
ing countries. Perhaps it may be thought that there is no possibility<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00807020"/>
4<lb/>
(Extract from &ldquo;Rural Sanitation&rdquo;, etc)<lb/>
of yellow fever reaching Asia. Of that I am by no means sure.<lb/>
Certainly, with the eradication of the disease from the Panama<lb/>
Canal zone, the risk of the disease being brought to Asia by<lb/>
ships passing straight through the Canal has been reduced prac-<lb/>
tically to zero; but as the Canal will attract steamers and<lb/>
create a new sea-highway, there is always the chance that some<lb/>
tramp steamer using the Canal to reach one of the many infected<lb/>
Central or South American ports, may carry infection to one of<lb/>
the Pacific Islands; and that infection may reach Asia via the<lb/>
equatorial islands; nor need this involve any long period of<lb/>
time, certainly not enough to allow Singapore to put its house<lb/>
in order, if nothing has previously been done. Were the disease<lb/>
to come in this way, Singapore would probably be the first Asiatic<lb/>
port to become infected.</p>
<p>"But there is another source of danger to Asia, to which,<lb/>
until now, the British have not given attention; The American<lb/>
mote has been more apparent than the British beam. I refer, of<lb/>
course, to the yellow fever which exists in West Africa. When we<lb/>
remember that yellow fever has no repeated occasions spread from<lb/>
West Africa to Spain, and even farther north, we can only conslude<lb/>
it has not reached Asia via the Mediterranean because there is no<lb/>
direct and practically no indirect trade between these points. But<lb/>
are we quite safe in assuming that this immunity will last? The<lb/>
development of Africa makes great strides, and it does not seem<lb/>
to me that it is a danger to be disregarded. Finally there is<lb/>
another route by which yellow fever may reach Asia from West Africa.<lb/>
Up till now the disease has been confined to the equatorial por-<lb/>
tions of West Africa; it has been unable to spread much along the<lb/>
coast either north or south, because the trade routes do not lie<lb/>
in these directions; nor has it been able to spread far inland or<lb/>
across the continent, because on the high plateaus which occupies<lb/>
the whole of the centre of the contient the temperature is below<lb/>
that necessary for the parasite's development in the mosquito. At<lb/>
the present time, were a freshly infected man to leave the west<lb/>
coast for the east coast, his progress would be so slow that at the<lb/>
very most he could only reach the cold plateau before the disease<lb/>
showed itself; and as he is infectious for only three days, there<lb/>
would be no chance of his ever infecting mosquitoes on the east<lb/>
coast. But were a trans-contiental line constructed - and pro-<lb/>
posals have, I believe, already been made to connect the existing<lb/>
lines that now run inland from the east and west coasts-it would<lb/>
easily be possible for a man infected on the west coast to travel<lb/>
to the east coast during his incubating period, and so start the<lb/>
disease there. To India, then, would be but a short step. Indeed,<lb/>
given the trans-African railway, nothing will stop yellow fever<lb/>
travelling by it, except the eradication of the disease from the<lb/>
west coast previous to its construction.</p>
<p>&ldquo;That railway may not come today or tomorrow, but come it will<lb/>
some time; and anxiously we may peer into the future, to find what<lb/>
it will bring to Asia and to Singapore. I do not propose to assume<lb/>
the prophet's robe, yet I make bold to say that Singapore's danger<lb/>
may be measured by the extent of her neglect in the near future to<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00807021"/>
5<lb/>
(Extract from &ldquo;Rural Sanitation, etc&rdquo;)<lb/>
exterminate the yellow fever mosquito within her gates. For<lb/>
if Singapore fails to realize how great a stake in wealth as<lb/>
well as health, in trade no less than in happiness, depends on<lb/>
her decision now, and neglects to take the precautions to<lb/>
preserve her freedom from the disease, we may be quite sure that<lb/>
Africa is no less likely to fail to take such steps as will<lb/>
prevent the disease spreading to Asia&rdquo;.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
