<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00807012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Yellow Fever in Venezuela, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00807012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">Venezuela</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
<name type="place">Columbia</name>
<name type="place">Caracas (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Maracaibo</name>
<name type="place">Martinique</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00807012</idno>
<title>Report: Yellow Fever in Venezuela, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter reports on yellow fever in Venezuela and Colombia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report: Yellow Fever in Venezuela, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00807012"/>
<p><hi>Dr. Carter.</hi></p>
<p>REPORT<lb/>
of<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
in<lb/>
VENEZUELA.<lb/>
--------------------------------------<lb/>
by<lb/>
DR. HENRY R. CARTER.<lb/>
-------------</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00807013"/>
<p>Findings as definite as those made for Ecuador and Columbia<lb/>
cannot be made for Venezuela. We found no Yellow Fever in either<lb/>
Caracas or Maracaibo, in which cities it would probably be most<lb/>
apt to occur. I think that there is probably none in Venezuela,<lb/>
but its absence cannot be asserted with the same positiveness as<lb/>
in Columbia, simply that its presence was not apparent to us.</p>
<p>There was a sharp epidemic centering in Caracas in 1911,<lb/>
beginning in 1910 and running on into 1912, and with some deaths -<lb/>
7 - reported in Caracas in 1914. Deaths were reported in other<lb/>
towns in communication with Caracas during this time, and in<lb/>
Maracaibo prior to this time.</p>
<p>An examination of the mortuary records of Caracas from the<lb/>
latter part of 1910 to date does not show any Yellow Fever in<lb/>
1915 or 1916. It does however show a small number of deaths<lb/>
from the diagnoses quite frequently used for Yellow Fever when<lb/>
that disease is not recognized.</p>
<p>Practically all of those cases were examined into and in<lb/>
no case did Guiteras or myself think they were Yellow Fever.<lb/>
In one case, however, the diagnosis &ldquo;Bil<del>l</del>ious Remittent Fever&rdquo;<lb/>
was used to conceal the diagnosis of Yellow Fever, which the<lb/>
physician believed was the cause of death - we think on<lb/>
insufficient grounds.</p>
<p>A few cases, no deaths, were heard of in Caracas, Villa<lb/>
Cura, and Maracaibo during this year. In two of those which<lb/>
were described to us, one in Caracas and one in Villa Cura,<lb/>
the clinical history was that of Yellow Fever. In neither<lb/>
case, on account of certain features of association or en-<lb/>
vironment, did we concur in the diagnosis of these cases.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00807014"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>Only one of these cases, out of four, had been reported to<lb/>
the Health Authorities. There was not the slightest intention<lb/>
to conceal the existence of the disease - no secret was made of<lb/>
it, and one case was recorded as Yellow Fever on the Hospital<lb/>
Records. It was simply carelessness - neglect to report. The<lb/>
tendency is rather to make a positive diagnosis of Yellow Fever<lb/>
in doubtful cases than the contrary.</p>
<p>I have said that I think there is probably no Yellow<lb/>
Fever in Venezuela, yet in view, <hi>First</hi>, of its recent presence<lb/>
there in considerable amount in 1912, if not 1914; <hi>Second</hi>, the<lb/>
small amount of the population susceptible to Yellow Fever in<lb/>
many of the towns liable to it, making it difficult to discover<lb/>
the disease; <hi>Third</hi>, the existence of reports of Yellow Fever in<lb/>
some places; <hi>Fourth</hi>, the fact that all cases believed to be Yellow<lb/>
Fever by their Medical Attendants are not reported to the Health<lb/>
Authorities, it is not improbable that there may be infection<lb/>
from the epidemic of 1911 &amp; 1912 yet lingering in some communi-<lb/>
ties. It must <del>also</del> be noted however, that the second factor<lb/>
named above also tends to increase the chance of the prompt<lb/>
spontaneous elimination of Yellow Fever by the failure of the<lb/>
human host.</p>
<p>It would be entirely reasonable that Yellow Fever from<lb/>
Caracas introduced into, other towns near the end of the Caracas<lb/>
epidemic should persist in some of them after it had disappeared<lb/>
from, Caracas itself; indeed, by a similar process, (i.e.<del><unclear>l</unclear></del> the in-<lb/>
vasion of new territory), be kept up some years. This seems to<lb/>
be the most plausible explanation of the method by which the<lb/>
infection in the towns and large ranches of Yucatan and Campeche<lb/>
has<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00807015"/>
3<lb/>
has been kept up.</p>
<p>It is on this account that a further examination is<lb/>
advised of Venezuela in 1917 or 1918 - the first preferably.<lb/>
If the condition above outlined exists it should, unless it<lb/>
be disappearing, be then apparent.</p>
<p>It seems also extreemly advisable to investigate the<lb/>
so-called &ldquo;Acclimatization Fever&rdquo; at Maracaibo, which is be-<lb/>
lieved locally to be a mild kind of Yellow Fever. Not less<lb/>
advisable is it to make an investigation of the fevers that<lb/>
prevail in Martinique, as the teachings of some French investi<lb/>
gators, members of <add><hi>a</hi> Commission of</add> the Pasteur Institute, are that in this<lb/>
island Yellow Fever exists as a permanent infection, gener-<lb/>
ally in a form so mild as to be negligible, but developing<lb/>
greater virulence from time to time<del>,</del> in epidemics. This view,<lb/>
solely I believe on account of the standing of the men who<lb/>
advance it, is quite generally accepted, explicitly or implic-<lb/>
itly, in South America, and is applied to many other localities<lb/>
from which Yellow Fever has apparently disappeared for many<lb/> years.</p>
<p>------------------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
