<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00807022">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Yellow Fever in Guayaquil, by Henry Rose Carter, July 20, 1916</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00807022</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-07-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
<name type="place">Guyaquil (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Quito (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Huigra (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Esmeraldas (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Tumaco (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Buenaventura (Colombia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-07-20">July 20, 1916</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00807022</idno>
<title>Report: Yellow Fever in Guayaquil, by Henry Rose Carter, July 20, 1916</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses needed mosquito-control work in Guayaquil and the endemic focus of yellow fever. He believes that the local population will cooperate, and so work should proceed. The city should be provided with a proper water supply to ensure continued success of the work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1916-07-20">
<head>Report: Yellow Fever in Guayaquil, by Henry Rose Carter, July 20, 1916</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00807022"/>
<opener>
Report<lb/>
on<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
in<lb/>
Guayaquil.<lb/>
-----------o------------<lb/>
Submitted by Dr. H.R. Carter.<lb/>
----o----<lb/>
July 20, 1916.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00807023"/>
<dateline>
Aboard Steamship &ldquo;Ucayali&rdquo;,<lb/>
<date value="1916-07-20">July 20, 1916.</date>
</dateline>
General Wm. C. Gorgas.<lb/>
Chairman, Yellow Fever Commission,<lb/>
Rockefeller Foundation.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to submit the following report on the<lb/>
yellow fever situation in Guayaquil:</p>
<p>Status of<lb/>
Guayaquil.</p>
<p>Yellow fever prevails in Guayaquil endemically. This<lb/>
condition has existed, in all probability for, say - from<lb/>
thirty-five to forty-five years, during which time it has been<lb/>
always present in Guayaquil. This place is, then, and has been<lb/>
for many years an endemic focus of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Infection of<lb/>
other towns<lb/>
from Guaya-<lb/>
quil.</p>
<p>Yellow fever has, from time to time, been introduced<lb/>
from Guayaquil into a number of small towns in communi-<lb/>
cation with it and, where local conditions in such towns<lb/>
were suitable, they have become infected with that disease. This<lb/>
is especially true of those on the line of the Guayaquil &amp; Quito<lb/>
Railroad up to and including Bucay. At Huigra, at four thousand<lb/>
feet elevation, yellow fever has not spread, although it has been<lb/>
introduced quite frequently. The same infection has almost cer-<lb/>
tainly occurred in the coast towns of Ecuador. The communication<lb/>
between Guayaquil and these towns has been such that it is entirely<lb/>
credi<del>a</del>ble that Guayaquil should have been a source of infection to<lb/>
all of these towns and to Tumaco and Buenaventura in Colombia, as<lb/>
well. The latter of these towns was infected in 1915, as was<lb/>
Esmeraldas, in Ecuador. Epidemics of yellow fever in the coast<lb/>
towns of Peru and Chile have, in times past, also been attributed<lb/>
to Guayaquil and a recent sharp epidemic in the latter country seems<lb/>
clearly from this source.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00807024"/>
<p>(Yellow Fever situation in Guayaquil,- Carter)</p>
<p>2</p>
<p>Status of<lb/>
these towns.</p>
<p>The towns on the railroad and on the coast of Ecuador<lb/>
are, it is believed, small enough to clear themselves<lb/>
of yellow fever spontaneously if not re-infected from Guayaquil.<lb/>
Indeed, they seem to have done so at times in the past. Even if<lb/>
this be not true a very small amount of work should be sufficient<lb/>
to free them of yellow fever if further introduction from Guayaquil<lb/>
be stopped.</p>
<p>Whether Buenaventura (Keane gives it 6,000 inhabitants in 1909),<lb/>
would free itself of yellow fever without sanitary work, may be a<lb/>
question. I am inclined to think that it would. If not, only a<lb/>
small amount of work for mosquito-control should be required to so<lb/>
free it.</p>
<p>It is to be noted that the towns on the railroad and the ad-<lb/>
jacent haciendas, which are really small towns, are growing rapidly,<lb/>
and if Guayaquil remains infected some years longer they may, in the<lb/>
aggregate, be large enough to require sanitary work to free them of<lb/>
yellow fever. I say in the aggregate as the inter-communication<lb/>
between them is close enough for one to be a source of infection to<lb/>
the others.</p>
<p>Continued in-<lb/>
fection de-<lb/>
pendent on<lb/>
Guayaquil.</p>
<p>It is believed, then, that if Guayaquil is freed from<lb/>
the infection of yellow fever the remaining towns on the<lb/>
Pacific coast of South America will either spontaneously<lb/>
free themselves by a failure of the human host or, at most, only a<lb/>
small amount of work would be required and at a very few places to<lb/>
accomplish this result.</p>
<p>Advisability<lb/>
of sanitation<lb/>
of Guayaquil.</p>
<p>I regard Guayaquil then, as the key of the yellow fever<lb/>
situation o<del>f</del><add>n</add> the Pacific coast of South America.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00807025"/>
<p>3.</p>
<p>(Yellow Fever situation in Guayaquil; Carter)</p>
<p>The trade relations of this part of the coast are such that,<lb/>
once free of yellow fever there is a minimum chance of its re-<lb/>
infection from other existing foci. I consider then, the elimina-<lb/>
tion of yellow fever from Guayaquil as extremely advisable and need<lb/>
only consider its feasibility.</p>
<p>Feasi-<lb/>
bility.</p>
<p>For this the two main factors to consider are (1), the atti-<lb/>
tude of the authorities and the people of the place at which<lb/>
sanitary work is proposed toward such work, and (2), the natural diffi-<lb/>
culties to be overcome.</p>
<p>Support of<lb/>
authorities.</p>
<p>The proposition to eliminate yellow fever from Guayaquil<lb/>
meets with the cordial approval of the authorities of both<lb/>
that city and of the Republic, and of all such business men and<lb/>
physicians as we have seen. The attempt to do so along the lines<lb/>
outlined to them will receive their support and, if sufficient care<lb/>
and tact be used can, I believe, be carried out with little opposi-<lb/>
tion from any source.</p>
<p>Natural diffi-<lb/>
culties; water<lb/>
supply.</p>
<p>It seems then, that we need only consider the natural<lb/>
difficulties of the work to be overcome. Of these the<lb/>
only one worth mentioning is the insufficient water supply. Since<lb/>
the method mainly relied upon is the control of mosquitos (A&euml;des<lb/>
calopus), by the destruction of their breeding places and since the<lb/>
insufficiency of the present water supply necessitates the purchase<lb/>
and storage of water for domestic purposes in artificial containers<lb/>
in which water such mosquitos breed, it is obvious that if a suffi-<lb/>
cient supply of water were procurable and <hi>was properly distributed</hi> so<lb/>
as to do away with the necessity of water-storage, the work would be<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00807026"/>
4.<lb/>
(Yellow Fever situation in Guayaquil; Carter)<lb/>
much simplified. If this can be done the task becomes easy and<lb/>
success certain. This matter will be presented to the Foundation<lb/>
in a special communication by the Chairman of this Commission; but<lb/>
I cannot too strongly present the advisability of providing a suffi-<lb/>
cient and properly distributed water supply as an adjuvant, possibly<lb/>
a prerequisite, to the work proposed.</p>
<p>This can be done within eighteen months if funds be available,<lb/>
but under the arrangements which obtain at present will take decidedly<lb/>
longer.</p>
<p>Advisable to<lb/>
begin work as<lb/>
soon as prac-<lb/>
ticable.</p>
<p>It is deemed advisable, however, not to postpone the<lb/>
work for the elimination of yellow fever on this account<lb/>
but to begin it as soon as practicable. By the method<lb/>
purposed to be adopted the work will probably take considerable time<lb/>
as it is deemed advisable to proceed carefully so as to arouse no<lb/>
opposition to our sanitary measures. A disadvantage in waiting any<lb/>
considerable time would be that we would not then find (unless indeed<lb/>
the Foundation should undertake the introduction of water) the same<lb/>
willingness of the authorities and people to cooperate with us as at<lb/>
present exists.</p>
<p>It is believed that the work of mosquito control can be success-<lb/>
fully carried out now with the present water supply. It will be more<lb/>
difficult than if the supply were sufficient and properly distributed.<lb/>
It will take longer and require much care and tact to bring it to a<lb/>
successful issue. Given the care and tact, however, I believe it can<lb/>
be done.</p>
<p>Conditions<lb/>
favoring work<lb/>
at present.</p>
<p>Indeed, Guayaquil is, just now, better suited for work<lb/>
of this kind to be successful than is normally the case<lb/>
with that city. The existence of the present epidemic will make the<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00807027"/>
(Yellow Fever situation in Guayaquil; Carter)<lb/>
5<lb/>
civic authorities more anxious to have the work done and increase<lb/>
the cooperation of all classes with us. The considerable number<lb/>
of susceptible people it will immunize before it stops will raise<lb/>
the level of the &ldquo;critical number&rdquo; of mosquitos (A&euml;des calopus) al-<lb/>
lowable with the elimination of yellow fever. The temporary les-<lb/>
sening of the Serrano immigration due to the knowledge of this epi-<lb/>
demic, a fairly fatal one, will have the same effect.</p>
<p>There is one other point favorable for this work in Guayaquil,<lb/>
namely, the long, dry, cool, season, lasting about eight months.<lb/>
A&euml;des calopus were certainly not breeding at all freely during our<lb/>
stay. The temperature was about 65 to 70 degrees, F., and there<lb/>
is probably normally no very free production of this mosquito during<lb/>
the dry season. During this part of the year, then, the climatic<lb/>
conditions are favorable for success.</p>
<p>If the attempt to eliminate yellow fever should fail to do so<lb/>
prior to the introduction of a sufficient and properly distributed<lb/>
water supply it would at least control the disease during this time,<lb/>
and after a proper water supply is introduced a continuation of the<lb/>
attempt would of course have a better chance of success.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very Respectfully</salute>
<signed><hi>H. R. Carter</hi></signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
