<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00811015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Juan Guiteras] to William Crawford Gorgas, December 22, 1916</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Guiteras, Juan</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00811015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-12-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Gorgas, William Crawford</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-12-22">December 22, 1916</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00811015</idno>
<title>Letter from [Juan Guiteras] to William Crawford Gorgas, December 22, 1916</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Guiteras] reports to Gorgas on a Barbados epidemic, which he suspects may be yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1916-12-22">
<head>Letter from [Juan Guiteras] to William Crawford Gorgas, December 22, 1916</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00811015"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Port of Spain. <date value="1916-12-22">December 22, 1916.</date>
</dateline>
Gral. W. C. Gorgas, Chairman<lb/>
Rockefeller Yellow Fever Commission.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>My experience in Barbados has been rather trying, be-<lb/>
cause of the difficulties inherent to the problem itself, and<lb/>
the responsibilities attached. A form of febrile jaundice with<lb/>
albuminuria affecting a large number of people in one of the<lb/>
West India islands is very suspicious of yellow fever. I was<lb/>
never before confronted with such a situation<unclear>;</unclear> but I may say<lb/>
that I have been helped by all concerned.</p>
<p>I am sending you a number of temperature charts, co-<lb/>
pies of which I am keeping in my note book. If I have time here<lb/>
I shall transfer them first to uniform charts, I think these charts<lb/>
should be published with such notes as I have of each case.</p>
<p>I am sending you also copy of a newspaper report of a<lb/>
lecture I deleivered here and of my letter to the Barbados autho-<lb/>
rities.</p>
<p>As we had expressed it in our conversations, the fact<lb/>
that all the persons attacked were negroes was a strong point<lb/>
against yellow fever. Even the case you saw autopsied was not<lb/>
a pure white, as I found out later. Excepting him and one mild<lb/>
case, also nearly white, the few who were not blacks were dark<lb/>
mulattos.</p>
<p>It was a disease of the blacks and of the poorer class<lb/>
of blacks.</p>
<p>There were 10 deaths, and they were all blacks with the<lb/>
exception of the one you saw.</p>
<p>The findings in the autopsies was the first bases they<lb/>
had for the diagnosis of yellow fever, and, if we consider only<lb/>
the naked eye appearances, such findings were perhaps the most<lb/>
suspicious feature of all.</p>
<p>I saw one other autopsy, the features being the same<lb/>
that you observed, a very dark liver and extremely congested,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00811016"/>
2.<lb/>
the blood welling up profusely on cutting into the organ. Four<lb/>
of the 10 livers were found in this condition, and one doubtful<lb/>
as it was desenbed &ldquo;pale but not bowwood&rdquo; the other five were <del>de-</del><add>de-</add><lb/>
<del>senbed</del><add>scribed</add> as boxwood.</p>
<p>The stomach contained four times black vomit, once a dark<lb/>
gray fluid containing blood, and no black vomit in the other five.</p>
<p>In the case with the dark gray fluid, which I saw, the<lb/>
mucosa of the stomach was pale. It appears to have presented <unclear>pete-<lb/>
chi&oelig;</unclear> in other cases.</p>
<p>The causes with black vomit in the stomach had dark li-<lb/>
vers, the others had pale livers only one case presented at the same<lb/>
time black fluid in the stomach with boxwood liver.</p>
<p>The spleen was enlarged in one case.</p>
<p>Some nephritis is <del>desenbed</del><add>described</add> in all.</p>
<p>The bodies were all of a very deep yellow color, show-<lb/>
ing under the black and very intense in the selerotics.</p>
<p>The histelo<del>grical</del><add>gical</add> findings are strongly against yellow<lb/>
fever, the liver cells are rarely f<del>o</del><add>a</add>tty even in the livers that<lb/>
were <del>desenbed</del><add>described</add> as boxwood in some of the autopsies. The necrotic<lb/>
areas of liver cells are generally absent. In one case occasionally<lb/>
such are seen, quite irregularly distributed. The blood capillaries<lb/>
are <del>distributed</del><add>distended</add>, and some times very decidedly so.</p>
<p>The short fatal case of 5 days durations deserves special<lb/>
consideration, Joseph Miller, black, aged 23 years, had been work-<lb/>
ing in a water trench, and is admitted on December 7th with a his-<lb/>
tory of onset of the disease on the 4th with a chill, vomiting and<lb/>
pain in the loins. He is the only one of the cases I have seen<lb/>
who points distinctly to such pain. The patients thinks that on<lb/>
the third day he vomited once a fluid that contained blood. He<lb/>
staggers on admission and is quite weak, but his mind perfectly<lb/>
clear. He has jaundice and albumin that begins to precipitate soon<lb/>
after the examination. At 4 pm. the Temp. is <unclear>99-5&deg;</unclear> and Pulse 76. On<lb/>
the 8th in the morning Temp. <unclear>98-4&deg;</unclear> and Pulse 88. In the evening Temp.<lb/>
<unclear>101&deg;</unclear> and Pulse 100. He died the following morning early<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00811017"/>
3.<lb/>
<unclear>dyspri&oelig;a</unclear><lb/>
after a sudden attack of <unclear>dypri&oelig;a</unclear>. No convulsions. He had been<lb/>
pasing urina freely and there had been but a slight increase of<lb/>
the albumin on the 8th. jaundice quite intense.</p>
<p>The autposy shows a dark and greatly congested liver<lb/>
Upon section the blood wells up rapidly <del>filly</del><add>filling</add> the gap. The sto-<lb/>
mach contains about a pint of dark gray fluid which contains some<lb/>
blood. The mucous membrane is swollen and pale without echymotic<lb/>
spots. The spleen is much congested. The left lung is very much<lb/>
engorged and semisplenified. The upper right lobe is less so,<lb/>
but the lower right lobe is blanched and completely collapsed.<lb/>
Probably some sudden obstruction of the bronchus (which was not<lb/>
looked for) was the cause of the death, and may explain the short<lb/>
duration of the disease which appeared to be tending towards re-<lb/>
covery.</p>
<p>Chemical features:</p>
<p>The duration of the cases was too long. My record of cases<lb/>
in the past shows that the majority of deaths in yellow fever<lb/>
occur on the 6th. day of the disease.</p>
<p>The duration in these 10 fatal cases was:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>1 died on the 5th day.</item>
<item>1 " " " 6th "</item>
<item>3 " " " 7th "</item>
<item>1 " " " 8th "</item>
<item>1 " " " 10th "</item>
<item>1 " " " 12th "</item>
<item>1 " " " 16th "</item>
<item>1 " unknown</item>
</list></p>
<p>Which gives us an average duration of 8.6 days. The ave-<lb/>
rage duration of the Guayaquil, Panam&aacute;, (Buena Ventura) and<lb/>
Trinidad fatal cases, the only histories at my desposal here was<lb/>
6.4 days.</p>
<p>The duration of the cases <unclear>terminatinf</unclear> in recovery was<lb/>
likewise too long. In the majority of cases in Havana the dura-<lb/>
tion was of 7 days. Comparing the Barbados cases with those of<lb/>
Guayaquil, Buena Ventura and Trinidad we find the following ave-<lb/>
rages of duration.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00811018"/>
<p>4.</p>
<p>For the Barbadas cases 13.6 days.</p>
<p>For the Guayaquil, Buena Ventura and Trinidad 7.4 days.</p>
<p>Studing the charts we observe a tendency to a typhoid type<lb/>
with the occasional occurrence of a secondary rise disenbed in<lb/>
Weyl's disease, and as I have observed in the sporadice cases<lb/>
in Havana.</p>
<p>will</p>
<p>The temperature charts, you weel observe are generally<lb/>
quite distinct from yellow fever.</p>
<p>Please note the one of Constance Coppin which was the<lb/>
last case reported positively soon after my arrival. There are<lb/>
7 days in succession in which the temperature rises to 104 or<lb/>
over. Now no case of yellow fever ever got that far under such<lb/>
circumstances, nor recovered. This one recovers, the temperature<lb/>
having reached the normal 4 or 5 days after the last recorded<lb/>
in the chart I am sending you.</p>
<p>With the regard to the pulse though we notice often<lb/>
a slow pulse, is is found generally rather late, as a consequence<lb/>
of the jaundice; so that we do not see the <del>time</del><add>true</add> Faget sign of the<lb/>
diverging lines of the temperature and pulse. It is <del>time</del><add>true</add> that<lb/>
the cases generally came in too late under observation, but this<lb/>
in itself is an indication against yellow fever.</p>
<p>The jaundice in these cases has been more intense than<lb/>
that of yellow fever; has appeared later, and when it has appear-<lb/>
ed it has devolped very rapidly. Even in light cases the jaun-<lb/>
dice has been very well marked and the urine has contained lar-<lb/>
ge amounts of bile pigment. In others words, we have had, I think<lb/>
very distinctly the evidences of an obstruct<del>ure</del><add>ive</add> jaundice. To<lb/>
my knowledge the stools have been white in four of the cases.</p>
<p><del>It</del><add>As</add> is a matter of fact, until the two deaths occurred<lb/>
on the 22nd of September, it was generally believed by our con-<lb/>
freres that they had been having an epidemic of jaundice all over<lb/>
the island without anything extraordinary about the cases, except<lb/>
their frequency and the tendency of some of them to be prolongued<lb/>
and &ldquo;to turn into typhoid&rdquo; as one of the physicians expressed it.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00811019"/>
<p>5.</p>
<p>Vo<add>mi</add>ting was absent in a considerable number of cases,<lb/>
perhaps about one half. In some it was quite persistent. But<lb/>
I believe there was no one with characteristic black vomit. One<lb/>
vomit, or perhaps more than once, containing blood, is now and<lb/>
then mentioned, but never the persistent and proyectile vomiting<lb/>
of black liquid that is met with in the fatal and grave cases<lb/>
of yellow fever.</p>
<p>The liver and spleen were somewhat enlarged in some<lb/>
cases, and the former organ was quite tender, more often than<lb/>
the epigastrium in the cases that I saw. We should not forget<lb/>
in this connexion that there is no malaria in <unclear>Barbadas</unclear>.</p>
<p>Albumin. There are no exact data in most cases, as<lb/>
to the date of commencement of the albuminuria. As I have said<lb/>
with reference to the jaundice, the cases came rather late under<lb/>
observation, and even so the albumin appeared sometimes after<lb/>
admission. I beleive that this symptom appeared generally la-<lb/>
ter than in yellow fever. It certainly cannot be shown that it<lb/>
appeared on the third day in the majority of instances. In the<lb/>
cases in which I tested for albumin the amount was less than<lb/>
what is found in yellow fever in corresponding conditions of gra-<lb/>
vity. I gather that this was also true in examinations made by<lb/>
others, though some of my friends, I beleive, will not agree<lb/>
with me. The <del>s</del><add>r</add>ing test was frequently employed and I was told<lb/>
that albumin was shown by it and at times not by the heat and<lb/>
acid test. I beleive that the layer test may give <del>me</del><add>rise</add> to confu-<lb/>
sion in concentrated muddy and bilious urine, if the latter is<lb/>
not cleared by filtration.</p>
<p>The absence of restlessness and of complaint of spon-<lb/>
taneous pains in the back, the head and limbs was a feature of<lb/>
the cases that I saw. You would have to ask direct questions<lb/>
to get any history of spontaneous pains and they were generally<lb/>
of the head. On the other hand I did not find the tenderness<lb/>
of the muscles that I have observed in sporadic Weyl's disease.</p>
<p>The mental condition of the patients was not such as<lb/>
we meet in yellow fever. The patients were quiet dull, somewhat<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00811020"/>
6.<lb/>
depressed, I saw no one with excitement, or reasioning and talk-<lb/>
ative delirium.</p>
<p>In the short time at my desposal it was not possible<lb/>
to record and present the cases in a systematic form. I simply<lb/>
observed symptoms and facts from day to day, and weighed them<lb/>
with a view to arriving at a diagnosis of the epidemic.</p>
<p>I have recorded 46 cases concerning some of which I<lb/>
have but few data, at times only the temperature, and occasionally<lb/>
only the name given as of an individual belonging to this group<lb/>
of cases.</p>
<p>Out of 46 cases, 10 died. This gives a case mortality<lb/>
of 21.7%. I am sure, however that a very large number of light<lb/>
cases, and even those of a severer type that occurred early in<lb/>
the epidemic, are left out of this calculation. I amd inclined<lb/>
to think that the case-mortality did not exceed 4 or 6%.</p>
<p>Of the 46 cases that were reported or were the subject<lb/>
of some study from the view point of yellow fever, less than one<lb/>
third, I beleive, were officially reported as suffering from<lb/>
that disease. Of the 46 cases I saw certainly 22, and perhaps<lb/>
a few others that were convadescing. I saw also two post mortoms<lb/>
and examined the organs microspically in five of the fatal cases<lb/>
from preparations made by the Patho<del>gut</del><add>logist</add> of the Central Board of<lb/>
Health, Dr. Johnson, who kindly assisted me in all my investi-<lb/>
gations.</p>
<p>The cases were distributed rather irregularly over<lb/>
many of the parrishes. The port town, Bridgetown, was singularly<lb/>
exempt at the beginning of the outbreak.</p>
<p>The first case reported as yellow fever occurred in<lb/>
St. Andrews, the least accessible of all the parrishes, the second<lb/>
case in St. Georges, the third also in St. George, without any<lb/>
connexion between the two, the fourth in St. Michaels, the fifth<lb/>
in St. James, and likewise the sixth. Some of the cases of jaun-<lb/>
dice, however, did procede from the same neighborhood, but very<lb/>
rarely from the same house. Of the 10 deaths, seven proceded<lb/>
each one from a distinct parrish. Three parrishes, St. Andrews,<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00811021"/>
7.<lb/>
St. James and St. Mchaels had each 2 deaths.</p>
<p>The cases reported as yellow fever in what is called<lb/>
the first outbreak in September are the following:<lb/>
<table rows="6" cols="5">
<row>
<cell>1 --</cell><cell>Thomas Foster ------</cell><cell>Black--</cell><cell>Barbadian --</cell><cell>Aged 60 years.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2 --</cell><cell>Joseph Smith -------</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" 41 "</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3 --</cell><cell>Arnold Clarke ------</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" 12 "</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4 --</cell><cell>Gertrude Inniss ----</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" 31 "</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5 --</cell><cell>Joseph Small -------</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" 50 "</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6 --</cell><cell>James Walcott ------</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" --</cell><cell>" 50 "</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>Of these six cases, four were living at the time of<lb/>
the great epidemic of 1881, and all were living at the time of<lb/>
the epidemic of 1908.</p>
<p>Such individuals generally escape in and epidemic of<lb/>
yellow fever, having been immunized by a previous attack. It<lb/>
certainly is highly unprobable that such individuals, all of them<lb/>
blacks, and all residents of the country dis<del>tincts</del><add>tricts</add> in the interior,<lb/>
could be singled out to constitute the first cases of a new out-<lb/>
break.</p>
<p>Complete records of previous epidemics of yellow fever<lb/>
in Barbadas are not available. We should bear in mind that the<lb/>
colored population is greatly in excess over the white in that<lb/>
Island, and that cases of yellow fever among the former should<lb/>
be comparatively frequent. But I have seen epidemics of the di-<lb/>
sease in communities where there was a very large colored popu-<lb/>
lation, and though many of them may have had yellow fever, we<lb/>
never became cogrisant of the fact, because the disease was very<lb/>
mild among them, and the deaths were extremely rare, especially<lb/>
among the pure blacks. Witness the epidemics of Jacksonville<lb/>
(1888) and Brunswick (1893) where many years had ellapsed since<lb/>
the last previous epidemic, and where there was therefore, a very<lb/>
large non-immune population of white and colored.</p>
<p>Let us look into such records as we have of the two<lb/>
last epidemics of Barbadas.</p>
<p>There is no registation of deaths in that Island, so we<lb/>
know nothing of the intervening years, and very little of the<lb/>
epidemic years.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f00811022"/>
<p>8.</p>
<p>We know that the garrison was seriously affected in<lb/>
1881 and that the troops had to be removed.</p>
<p>There is a very interesting tabulated presentation of<lb/>
the cases treated that year <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>in</add> one yellow fever hospital by Dr.<lb/>
St. Claire Browne. He had under his care 36 patients in which<lb/>
the diagnosis of the disease was confirmed. Of these, 11 were<lb/>
whites, 7 colored and 18 blacks. The fatal cases were 4, and<lb/>
they were all whites. There was besides, one fatal case of<lb/>
pneumonia, who is supposed, on <add>in</add> sufficient grounds, I beleive,<lb/>
to have had also yellow fever. He was a black man who had a per-<lb/>
sistent high temperatre, with slight albuminuria. Jaundice appear-<lb/>
ed on the 10th day of the disease, and he died of gan<add>g</add>rene of the<lb/>
lungs.</p>
<p>Of the fatal cases, one died on the 6th. day, one on<lb/>
the 7th, one on the 9th and one on the 22nd day. The latter is<lb/>
a very doubtful case. The post mortom findings are Liver &ldquo;much<lb/>
enlarged, pale and hard, but congested&rdquo;, spleen much enlarged,<lb/>
stomach &ldquo;healthy and empty&rdquo;.</p>
<p>We <del>must</del><add>next</add> hear <add>of</add> yellow fever in an epidemic form in Decem-<lb/>
ber of 1908. The official records as far as they go, give a re-<lb/>
sum&eacute; of 86 cases with 20 deaths, but it is generally understood<lb/>
that the disease was much more widely prevalent than these figu-<lb/>
res would indicate.</p>
<p>Race distribution of the cases<lb/>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Blacks, -------</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>--or--</cell><cell>45.35%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Whites, -------</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>-- " --</cell><cell>37.21%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Colored, ------</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>-- "<unclear><del>"</del></unclear>--</cell><cell>17.44%</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>Distribution of the case<del>s</del> mortality according to race.<lb/>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Whites, -------</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>-- or --</cell><cell>34.37%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Blacks, -------</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>-- " --</cell><cell>17.94%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Colored, ------</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>-- " --</cell><cell>13.30%</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>If we consider now the race distribution of the population<lb/>
in Barbadas we find that in the year 1908 there were 20,000 whites<lb/>
in a total population of 194,000.</p>
<p>We should. for purposes of accurate estimation, calculate<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f00811023"/>
9.<lb/>
the proportion of cases and deaths in each group of the popula-<lb/>
tion, and this is shown in the following:</p>
<p>Table:-</p>
<p>Proportion of cases and deaths of Yellow fever in Bar-<lb/>
badas to 100,000 population of each race group.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="6">
<row>
<cell>Race</cell><cell>Population</cell><cell>Number<lb/>
of cases<lb/>
of Yellow<lb/>
fever</cell><cell>Proportion per<lb/>
100000 inhabitants<lb/>
of each race group</cell><cell>Number of<lb/>
deaths from<lb/>
Yellow<lb/>
fever</cell><cell>Proportion per<lb/>
100000 inhabitants<lb/>
of each group</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Whites</cell><cell>20,000</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>160.00</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>55.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Blacks &amp; col'd</cell><cell>174,000</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>31.03</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>5.17</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>The incidence of yellow fever was decidedly greater in<lb/>
the white race, and the death rate was greater still.</p>
<p>The difference may be expressed in the following formula:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>The relation of colored to whites, in reference to the<lb/>
number of cases, is as 1:5.15.</item>
<item>The relation of colored to whites in reference to the<lb/>
number of deaths, is as 1:10.62.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Epidemic jaundice, febrile jaundice, infectious jaun-<lb/>
dice appears to have been more prevalent in recent years than<lb/>
formerly. Grissinger's bilious typhoid is <del>disenbed</del><add>described</add> in recent mo-<lb/>
nographs on the diseases of Egypt. There has been an extensive<lb/>
epidemic in the Italian army of accupation in Tripoli; another<lb/>
epidemic in the army fighting in the Gallipoli peninsula. It<lb/>
appears to have been demonstrated that this outbreak was due to<lb/>
a paratyphoid infection. More recently an epidemic in Japan has<lb/>
been shown to be a form of spirochetosis, and this appears to<lb/>
have been confirmed in connexion with a very recent outbreak<lb/>
among the troops in Flanders.</p>
<p>Conditions somewhat similar to these prevailing in the<lb/>
armies mentioned may be said to exist, to some extent, at the<lb/>
present time in Barbadas. This island is one of the most densely<lb/>
populated countries in the world, the late season has been cha-<lb/>
racterised by the heaviest and most persistent rains in many<lb/>
years, the rise in the price of food stuffs renders it probable<lb/>
that the articles of this kind for the consumption of the poor,<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f00811024"/>
10.<lb/>
have been of bad quality.</p>
<p>In mentioning these three conditions I am touching upon<lb/>
factors that may, with some show of reason, be suggested as possi-<lb/>
ble causes of the disease. Forms of food poisoning or food infec-<lb/>
tion have been frequently suggested, and our own experience in<lb/>
Havana with sporadic cases of grave febrile jaundice, point to<lb/>
the probability of infection through the skin by prolonged im-<lb/>
mersion of the feet in more or less poluted water.</p>
<p>The last heavy rain of the season occurred in Barbadas<lb/>
during the first days of December. I remained there only eleven<lb/>
days which were very dry, and my impression was that the epi-<lb/>
demic was declining rapidly. This however requires confirmation.<lb/>
The epidemic of yellow fever of 190<del>1</del><add>8</add>-09, on the other hand began<lb/>
on the 12 of December and terminated in the following June.</p>
<p>I regret very much that the absence of all records of<lb/>
deaths in Barbadas has made it impossible for me to apply, for<lb/>
the epidemiologic disgnosis, the test obtained by study of the<lb/>
death rate of children and of certain diseases, as I have done<lb/>
in other places visited by the Commission.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very truly</salute>
<signed>Member of the Rockefeller<lb/>
Yellow Fever Commission</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
