<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00818099">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Edwin C. Shaw to Henry Rose Carter, August 1, 1919</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Shaw, Edwin C.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00818099</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1919-08-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1919-08-01">August 1, 1919</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00818099</idno>
<title>Letter from Edwin C. Shaw to Henry Rose Carter, August 1, 1919</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Shaw requests Carter's advice in establishing a city public health clinic in Akron, Ohio.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1919-08-01">
<head>Letter from Edwin C. Shaw to Henry Rose Carter, August 1, 1919</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00818100"/>
<p>EDWIN C. SHAW<lb/>
533 SECOND NATIONAL BUILDING<lb/>
Akron, Ohio<lb/>
<date value="1919-08-01">August 1st,<lb/>
1 9 1 9.</date>
Dr. H. C. Carter,<lb/>
U. S. Deputy Public Health Officer,<lb/>
Bureau of Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
Dear Doctor:</p>
<p>Following the custom generally observed, I believe,<lb/>
about the country, the Mayor of Akron has appointed a Committee<lb/>
to suggest the best type of memorial for Akron's contribution<lb/>
to the ending of the war. This Committee includes some who<lb/>
have long felt that Akron needed a Polyclinic, a building de-<lb/>
signed, equipped and manned to coordinate all the social acti-<lb/>
vities of the town and county as well as the curative and corr-<lb/>
ectional facilities to round out a better health control. It<lb/>
has been our idea that if all the social activities of the<lb/>
community as well as the health activities as met by the different<lb/>
kinds of medical clinics such as eye, ear, nose, throat, dental,<lb/>
baby welfare, and psychiatric, were in the same building under<lb/>
competent central direction, the result would be of inestimable<lb/>
value to the community.</p>
<p>I have discussed the different phases of the proposed<lb/>
plans with Dr. Phillip King Brown, Dr. Richard Cabot and Dr.<lb/>
Lewellys F. Barker. The splendid way in which these gentlemen<lb/>
have responded to my inquiry prompts me to write you in the hope<lb/>
that you also may find it convenient to give me the benefit of<lb/>
your ideas and knowledge as a result of your studies in welfare<lb/>
and health work. Perhaps you may be willing to make such<lb/>
recommendations as would be of aid to avoid making the Polyclinic<lb/>
a purely diagnostic one.</p>
<p>I have had some notion that it might be possible to<lb/>
effect a very good service without involving a pecuniary sacrifice<lb/>
on the part of physicians by paying them for a certain fixed time<lb/>
at the Clinic in proportion to their yearly earnings, and so<lb/>
arranging their contact with the patient that the demand on their<lb/>
time might be reduced to the minimum; first, by so arranging the<lb/>
appointments that the Polyclinic would have an even load each<lb/>
day; and second, by employment of a proper kind of clerk and over-<lb/>
seer to relieve the physician of so much of detail as would be<lb/>
involved in taking histories, answering questions, etc., as are<lb/>
preliminary to diagnosis, which when systematized, can be asked<lb/>
by the non-professional as well as by the doctor himself.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00818099"/>
<p>EDWIN C. SHAW<lb/>
533 SECOND NATIONAL BUILDING<lb/>
Akron, Ohio<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
<date value="1919-08-01">8-1-19.</date>
Dr. H. C. Carter---------</p>
<p>With this plan and with the thought that the Clinic would not<lb/>
be limited to diagnostic work only, but that it would deliver<lb/>
general outpatient aid, a very great service could be rendered<lb/>
to the community.</p>
<p>May I trouble you for an expression of opinion as<lb/>
to the desirability and the practicability of the plan suggested!</p>
<p>The desirability of having the benefit of your<lb/>
judgment at the earliest convenient date, together with the un-<lb/>
certainty of the mails, prompts me to send this inquiry by<lb/>
registered mail.</p>
<p>Please accept in advance my grateful appreciation<lb/>
for any assistance you may find it convenient to give us.</p>
<p>Yours very truly,<lb/>
E C Shaw.<lb/>
ECS-DMS</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
