<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00811003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Rupert Blue, January 20, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00811003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-01-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Blue, Rupert</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Colleton County (S.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-01-20">January 20, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00811003</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Rupert Blue, January 20, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter reports that malarial conditions in South Carolina have worsened.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1917-01-20">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Rupert Blue, January 20, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00811003"/>
<opener>
Relative to report of<lb/>
Asst. Surgeon General,<lb/>
H. R. Carter<lb/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
<dateline>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
Baltimore, Maryland.<lb/>
<date value="1917-01-20">January 20, 1917.</date>
</dateline>
The Surgeon General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<unclear>f3</unclear><lb/>
<salute>Sir:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to submit the following report of<lb/>
my recent visit to S. C. made under Bureau orders of Jan.<lb/>
&amp; 12, 1917,.</p>
<p>The State Health Officer <del>S</del><add>s</add>tates that there is complaint<lb/>
of a large amount of Malaria in Bloxton Township-Colleton Co.<lb/>
S.C., He states that of 67 deaths from Malaria in this county<lb/>
23 of them were in this township. I submit herewith a rough map<lb/>
of this township. It lays between the two Salkahatchie Swamps<lb/>
the Big and the Little and is crossed by <unclear>Villow</unclear> swamp &amp; by<lb/>
several &ldquo;branches&rdquo; which are small swamps.</p>
<p>It is claimed that the Malaria complained of is caused<lb/>
by the cutting of the lumber <del>-</del>of these two swamps by two lumber<lb/>
Companies. The State Health Officer has planned to have an in-<lb/>
vestigation of the whole subject made by a commission to consist<lb/>
of a representative of the State Board: A Civilian Physician:<lb/>
and A Man from the U. S. Public Health Service. A bill to that<lb/>
effect has either been introduced into or passed by the S. C.<lb/>
Legislature.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00811004"/>
<p>-----2------</p>
<p>This investigation is planned to begin about March 1, 1917, as<lb/>
the appropriation to pay the Civilian Physician will become<lb/>
available on that date.</p>
<p>It being of course impossible for me to make an investiga-<lb/>
tion of the conditions producing Malaria at this season of the<lb/>
year, or even <add>of</add> the amount of Malaria existing with the time at<lb/>
my disposal, it seemed better that I should simply visit this<lb/>
section and see the <hi>general</hi> condition so as to assist the Health<lb/>
Officer in planning the proper way of making a Satisfactory in-<lb/>
vestigation, when he was ready and, if it meets with the views<lb/>
of the Department, assisting him in it. Time and expense would<lb/>
thus be saved.</p>
<p>I went therefore to Varnville S.C. -see Map,- and conferred<lb/>
with Mr. W. C. Rentz who lives there thence was taken by Dr.<lb/>
Campbell of Varnville across the Big Salkahatchie Swamp-to<lb/>
confer with H. H. Rentz, in Bloxton just above Toad Bluff Crossing<lb/>
After talking with him I went at his instance to see a Mr. Freeman<lb/>
and Mr. J. W. Murdock, lower down the swamp on the Bloxton side<lb/>
Went into the swamp, Big Salkahatchie, at an abondoned skidway<lb/>
to within 1000 feet of the other side then down the swamp for 2 1/2<lb/>
miles-and then out on the Bloxton side again, on the skidway now<lb/>
being used. I was accompanied by three Mr. Murdock's. All of the<lb/>
part of the swamp which I saw had been cut over, I was in the<lb/>
swamp all of one afternoon.</p>
<p>After spending the night with Mr. Murdock I went to Island-<lb/>
town to see Mr. Varn. He was absent and I talked with several<lb/>
people there getting their views, and then saw Dr. R. A. Hudson of<lb/>
Islandtown who has most of the practice in the lower end of Bloxton<lb/>
where.<lb/>
Thence to Waterboro and thence to Colleton <add>Where I met Dr Carter. the physician of the</add> <add><unclear>Colletone</unclear></add> Cypress Co. which is<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00811005"/>
-----3------<lb/>
cutting the Little Salkahatchie and some in his own neighbor-<lb/>
hood-Smoke-about 7 miles distant from the swamp. I accompanied him<lb/>
to Smoke where I saw Dr. Thompson and talked with some other<lb/>
people there as I did at Waterboro and Colleton.</p>
<p>Very obviously this inquir<del>ing</del><add>y</add>ng of four days does not pretend to<lb/>
be <add>a</add> sufficient investigation but<del>,</del> it is such a survey of the gener-<lb/>
al problem as will throw some light on how a inquiry should be<lb/>
conducted and I gave the State Health Officer such data as I<lb/>
had secured and conferred with him as to how to conduct an inves-<lb/>
tigation.</p>
<p>There is no question but that this section -Bloxton Township-<lb/>
suffered severely from Malaria in 1916, much more than formerly<lb/>
both in number of cases and severity of the disease. Whether this<lb/>
is due in whole or in part to the cutting in the two swamps may<lb/>
be a question. The cutting in the Big Salkahatchie began July or<lb/>
August 1914. That of the Little Salkahatchie<del>-</del> has been going on<lb/>
for eleven years. The people with whom I talked <del>and</del> <add>--</add> farmers all --<lb/>
believe in good faith that the clearing of the swamps is the cause<lb/>
of the increase of Malaria- a number of them have moved away on<lb/>
this account and others contemplate moving. Their accounts of the<lb/>
coincidence of cutting timber and the increase of Malaria, <hi>if true</hi>,<lb/>
is evidence of a causal relation between the two. The statements<lb/>
of the three physicians I saw does not seem to bear out the above<lb/>
account and implies no relation between the two. It is a matter<lb/>
to be determined by investigation.</p>
<p>I think it is true however from what I heard outside of<lb/>
Bloxton Township that there was a marked increase of Malaria<lb/>
everywhere in the general section of S. C., to which a certain<lb/>
portion of the increase in Bloxton Township is due.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00811006"/>
<p>------4-------</p>
<p>I will add that I found that the water channels in the Big<lb/>
Salkahatchie Swamp were being obstructed by the method of con-<lb/>
structing the skidway tracks and, to a less extent, by the branches<lb/>
of the falling trees. I advised Dr. Hayne of this and suggested<lb/>
that he bring it to the attention of the Company. I do not<lb/>
know that the amount of obstruction thus caused will measureably<lb/>
influence Anophelus production, but it seems better, in view of <unclear>t</unclear><lb/>
the complaint of the cutting, not to obstruct them.</p>
<p>The only recommendation I have to make is that if it be<lb/>
practitable a representative <add>or <unclear>representations</unclear></add> of this Service be detailed to<lb/>
assist in the investigation of this section-when it is made about<lb/>
March 1, 1917, and that subsequent action of the Service be de-<lb/>
termined by the result of that investigation.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Assistant Surgeon General</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
