<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00813043">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Rupert Blue, November 20, 1918</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00813043</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1918-11-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Blue, Rupert</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Sabine (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">Port Arthur (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">Galveston (tex.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Tela (Honduras)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1918-11-20">November 20, 1918</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00813043</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Rupert Blue, November 20, 1918</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter reports on his investigation of a foreign sailor's illness and death, in Sabine, Texas.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1918-11-20">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Rupert Blue, November 20, 1918</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00813043"/>
<opener>
Investigation of alleged<lb/>
case of Yellow Fever at<lb/>
Sabine, Texas.<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General H.R. Carter<lb/>
<unclear>copy for</unclear> file<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1918-11-20">November 20, 1918.</date>
</dateline>
The Surgeon General,<lb/>
U.S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to submit this report of my investigation of a<lb/>
case alleged to be Yellow Fever aboard the S/S Belaire at Sabine, Texas.</p>
<p>I first saw Acting Assistant Winter at Port Arthur, Texas, and<lb/>
obtained his statement, then visited the State Quarantine Station at Sabine<lb/>
and got the statement of Dr. Chilton, Quarantine Officer, who had the records<lb/>
of his office with him. The Belaire returned to Sabine from Galveston while<lb/>
I was at the Quarantine Station and, after the vessel was passed, in I saw the<lb/>
Master and got such data from him as seemed needed. I then returned to Port<lb/>
Arthur and again talked to Dr. <unclear>Winter</unclear>, on some points that after my visit to<lb/>
Sabine seemed to need elucidation. On account of the return of the Belaire<lb/>
to Sabine it was unnecessary to visit Galveston, so asking for information<lb/>
on one point from Wilson, by wire, I came to New Orleans to look up the mat-<lb/>
ter of the Fruit vessel on which this case had been previously. Dr. Corput<lb/>
had the data needed here. On account of some discrepancies between Dr. Corput's<lb/>
record and my own it was necessary to get additional information by wire from<lb/>
Dr. Wilson and Dr. Chilton - this has been done.</p>
<p>I am sending (1) what I believe to be the facts in the case and<lb/>
(2) the statement of Dr. Winter, Dr. Chilton and the Master of the Belaire<lb/>
as made to me, on which some of my findings are based.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00813044"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>(I) <del>One</del><add>Juan</add> Llanez, 24 years, Spanish, left S/S Quinistan, a fruit vessel, at New<lb/>
Orleans, La., October 27, 1918, 4 days out from Tela, Honduras, (Immigration<lb/>
record New Orleans, La., by Dr. Corput) shipped aboard S/S Bellaire on Novem-<lb/>
ber 2, evening. Bellaire left New Orleans on November 3, arrived at Sabine<lb/>
Quarantine November 4, with &ldquo;all well aboard and no sickness enroute&rdquo; (affidavit<lb/>
of Master and Inspection of State Quarantine Officer at Sabine)</p>
<p>Vessel was cleared at Quarantine <del>and</del><add>but</add>, another vessel being in the berth<lb/>
she should take, the Bellaire laid <add>at</add> anchor at the Quarantine Boarding place. At<lb/>
the request of the Master, Dr. <unclear>Chilt<add>er</add>on</unclear> went aboard again on November 6, and<lb/>
found this man, Llanez, sick. He considered the case Yellow Fever and so re-<lb/>
ported. He visited the vessel again on the morning of November 7, about 10<lb/>
or 11 A.M. During this visit Dr. Winter came aboard and saw the sick man also.<lb/>
Dr. Chilton visited the vessel again on the 8<add>th</add>, about 10 A.M., and found the man<lb/>
dead, the Master stating that he died at 6 A.M. of that day. He was buried that<lb/>
afternoon on the beach and the vessel left for Galveston that evening or night.<lb/>
One other man was sick when, or shortly before, she left Sabine, but all reported<lb/>
well (on Wilson's inspection<del>s</del>) on arrival at Galveston Quarantine on November<lb/>
9, at 4:30 P.M. The Master states Llanez became sick on the evening of Novem-<lb/>
ber 5; he worked that day. The above dates and statement are verified as far<lb/>
as possible by the records.</p>
<p>(2) <hi>Statement of Dr. Winter November 16, 1918</hi>.</p>
<p>His information is as given him by the Captain of the Bellaire, except<lb/>
the clinical history:</p>
<p>Seaman arrived New Orleans, November 2, via fruit steamer, from South<lb/>
American port, and immediately, November 2, joined the Bellaire. First day<lb/>
after, this, man got sick; arrived Sabine November 4, and found ill by State<lb/>
Quarantine Officer, who made diagnosis of Yellow Fever. Was seen by Dr. Winter<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00813045"/>
3<lb/>
on November 6, early in the morning, who concurred in the diagnosis - died<lb/>
November 7, at night.</p>
<p><hi>Clinical History</hi>-</p>
<p>Man could not speak English and when seen was very sick. Skin <hi>very</hi><lb/>
yellow and man much depressed. Had been nauseated. Do not know that he vomited<lb/>
but <unclear>thinks</unclear> he did before his <add>(Winter's)</add> visit - ascribed to calomel taken. Had a large<lb/>
and very offensive stool. Liver but slightly, if at all, enlarged; <hi>very</hi> tender<lb/>
as was all of the abdomen. Some <unclear>tympanites</unclear> but not marked - no petechiae. Gums<lb/>
not bleeding but swollen. Tongue like sand paper, never saw a tongue like it<lb/>
before, <hi>not</hi> a malarial tongue. Am very familiar with malaria fever and am posi-<lb/>
tive this can be excluded. Pulse below normal, temperature about 102&deg;. Urine<lb/>
dark, Albuminous - no great deal of albumen, but distinctly albuminous. On<lb/>
questioning further - Said about 5% by volume of wet albumen. Suggested to Dr.<lb/>
Corput to disintor and make autopsy but he <unclear>said</unclear> it was too late.</p>
<p>(<hi>NOTE - Dr. Carter</hi>.</p>
<p>I did not ask what test for Albumen was used. Naturally from the per-<lb/>
centage given I judged he used heat and <unclear>nitric acid</unclear>. Dr. Corput states that<lb/>
(in answer to a question) Dr. Winter <unclear>said</unclear> he used cold nitric acid - the &ldquo;ring<lb/>
test&rdquo; and obtained a slight <del>or</del><add>but</add> definite ring.)</p>
<p>The above statement is made from memory, Dr. Winter having no notes<lb/>
of the case, except the dates as given in his telegrams and letter to the<lb/>
Bureau.</p>
<p><hi><unclear>Statement</unclear> Dr. <del>Chilton</del><add><unclear>Chiltern</unclear></add>, State Quarantine Officer, Sabine, Texas, and verified<lb/>
as to names, dates, etc., by Quarantine Records at his office November 16, 1918</hi>.</p>
<p>No <hi>clinical</hi> record kept; the clinical history is from memory.</p>
<p>The subject of this history could speak <unclear>no English</unclear> and the interpretor<lb/>
very little, so such history as came from the sick man is necessarily imper-<lb/>
fect. <del><unclear>One Ylanez</unclear></del><add>Juan Yanez</add>, Mexican, 23 years, arrived New Orleans, November 2, 1918,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00813046"/>
4<lb/>
on fruit vessel 4 days out from a port in Honduras, shipped aboard Bellaire<lb/>
as pump man on November 3. Bellaire arrived Saturday, November 4 - all<lb/>
aboard &ldquo;well enroute and on arrival&rdquo; (affidavit of Master and Dr. <unclear>Chiltern's</unclear>)<lb/>
examination of crew). Vessel cleared and could have <unclear>docked</unclear> but another vessel<lb/>
was at the dock ahead of her and she laid <add>at</add> anchor to the morning of November 6,<lb/>
when Dr. C. visited her again at the request of the Captain and found this man<lb/>
sick, temperature 102.5&deg;, in a well screened Hospital. Visited him again on<lb/>
November 7, about 10 or 11 A.M. Dr. Winter came aboard during this visit and<lb/>
saw him also. Dr. Winter came down on a tug; sent by the agents. Went aboard<lb/>
again about 10 A.M., November 8, found man dead; Captain said he died at 6 A.M.<lb/>
<unclear>He</unclear> was buried that afternoon and the vessel sailed for Galveston Quarantine<lb/>
that evening.</p>
<p><hi>Clinical History</hi>:</p>
<p>First visit on <add>Nov.</add> 6 - Injected eyes, red conjunctiva and from his motions<lb/>
much frontal headache. Pain in stomach - not vomiting but apparently trying<lb/>
to vomit, bending over bed; could not find out from any one whether he had<lb/>
vomited or not. Skin yellow. History taken that day and influenced diagno-<lb/>
sis, i.e. just off fruit steamer and from a Yellow Fever country. Made diag-<lb/>
nosis of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>Second visit Nov. 7 -Skin a deeper yellow, temperature about the same,<lb/>
Eyes <hi>blazing</hi>, not so much complaint, otherwise about the same. Pulse softer<lb/>
and more thready; about 120 the first day, not quite so frequent the second day<lb/>
<del>(NOTE discrepancy with Dr. Winter's account taken at this same time <add><unclear></unclear></add>)</del> Still nau-<lb/>
seated; tongue very dry, <unclear>sharpppointed</unclear>, coated in the middle - as dry as a chip-<lb/>
same both days.</p>
<p>Urine not examined; could not get any. The man watching him said<lb/>
he made none. One bowel movement seen - dark, watery diarrhoeal action. Dont<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00813047"/>
-5-<lb/>
know that he had taken any medicine for his bowels. He gave him none. Could not<lb/>
find if he vomited at any time <hi>but</hi> did not see him do so, or see any vomit. Urine<lb/>
was not taken by Dr. Winter or any one else. Dr. Winter stayed about 15 minutes<lb/>
aboard ship.</p>
<p>Buried 10 or 12 hours after death. Saw corps at 10 or 11 A.M. Body<lb/>
showed dark spots of the calves of legs. Whole body yellow: Saw no froth<lb/>
or dark material about mouth at any time.</p>
<p>(<hi>Note by Carter</hi></p>
<p>I was impressed by the straight forward honesty of Dr. Chiltern,<lb/>
telling just what he had observed. He was more interesting in determining<lb/>
the proper measures to take as a Quarantine Officer than about the patholog-<lb/>
ical accuracy of the diagnosis. It is needless to say that his action in<lb/>
holding the vessel in Quarantine as soon as this case was discovered and fi-<lb/>
nally remanding her to Galveston Quarantine was correct. A case of sickness<lb/>
occurring under such uncertain circumstances, unless <hi>known</hi> not to be Yellow<lb/>
Fever, should be treated as if it were Yellow Fever. This is what Dr. <unclear>Chilton</unclear><lb/>
did.)</p>
<p><hi>Statement Master of Bellaire</hi>.</p>
<p>Dates as given by Dr. Chilton concerning his vessel correct. Man's<lb/>
name is &ldquo;Llanez&rdquo; not &ldquo;Yanez&rdquo;. Became sick evening November 5. Sent for Doctor<lb/>
next morning; Worked all day of the 5<add>th</add>, so far as he knows. One other man sick<lb/>
when vessel left but was well before he reached Galveston. He gave his card<lb/>
to Dr. Wilson at Galveston; Thinks it was his passport as it had his photograph<lb/>
on it. It gives the name of the vessel he was last on before the Bellaire.</p>
<p><hi>Statement Dr. Winter November 17, 1918</hi>.</p>
<p>Got a small specimen of urine, but enough to <unclear>examine, Passed</unclear> while he<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00813048"/>
-6-<lb/>
was with the sick man, in a vessel which he had had emptied of the <unclear>stool..It</unclear> was<lb/>
high colored, rather than dark, not smoky, like <unclear>febrile. urine</unclear></p>
<p>Is very familiar with malarial fever <del>-</del> as it occurs in this vicinity. Not<lb/>
familiar with Malarial Hemoglobinuria (Black Water Fever) Dont know that it oc-<lb/>
curs in this vicinity. Is positive that he saw the sick man on the 6th, not on the<lb/>
7th, as Dr. Chilton says, and that the Captain told him that the man had been sick<lb/>
almost as soon as he came aboard and had not worked except an hour or so.</p>
<p><hi>Findings</hi></p>
<p>The history of this case is too meagre to certainly determine its nature.<lb/>
The diagnosis of Yellow Fever by Dr. Winter is based on (1) Yellowness of skin;<lb/>
(2) Extreme prostration; and (3) exclusion of other diseases - malaria and gall<lb/>
duct obstructions, especially <unclear>liable to</unclear> cause jaundice with which he was familiar.</p>
<p>That of Dr. Chilton was based on (1) Jaundice; (2) extreme sickness; (3)<lb/>
the infected face and headache, and (4) to some extent, from the place of origin<lb/>
of the patient - <unclear>A</unclear> Central American port via a fruit vessel which he thought<lb/>
the patient left on November 2; <unclear></unclear> judgement the diagnosis could be (a) Yellow<lb/>
Fever; <unclear>(b)</unclear> <del><unclear>Malarial Hemoglobinuria</unclear></del><add><unclear>Black Water Fever</unclear></add>; (c) any fulminating <unclear>infection <add>-</add> as</unclear> influenza<lb/>
or even such a peritoneal infection from any cause.</p>
<p>As sustaining the diagnosis of Yellow Fever we have (1) the appearance<lb/>
of the face as described by Dr. Chilton; (2) Jaundice; and (3) death. These<lb/>
appearances would occur in the fatal case of Yellow Fever. As against this di-<lb/>
agnosis we have (1) the early onset and rapid <del><unclear>jau</unclear></del> development of jaundice. The<lb/>
skin was found by Dr. Chilton &ldquo;Yellow&rdquo; on the first day of sickness and &ldquo;<hi>very</hi><lb/>
yellow&rdquo; on the <unclear>second</unclear> by both Dr. Chilton and Dr. Winter; (2) The early death.<lb/>
It is extremely rare for a case of Yellow Fever to die as quickly as this man<lb/>
died. Nevertheless there is always a possibliity of the man having been sick,<lb/>
altho working several, days before he was so reported, or of the case being one<lb/>
of fulminating severity. (3) Black vomit would be very apt, though not certain<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00813049"/>
7<lb/>
to show in a dying case of Yellow Fever and this sign is so marked that it would<lb/>
scarcely escape <unclear>notice</unclear> by any <unclear>at tendant</unclear> however stupid and traces of it should<lb/>
show to the Doctor on the patient's face and bedding - none was observed. (4)<lb/>
The absence of haemorragic symptoms - Gums and tongue, etc., is noted by Dr. Winter<lb/>
and their presence not observed by Dr. Chiltern. I do not recall that I have found<lb/>
such signs missing in cases that die and it must be extremely rare.</p>
<p>(5) With regard to the urine. Attention is called to the apparent discrepancy<lb/>
of Dr. Winter's statement to me and those of Dr. Chiltern and of Dr. Winter's to<lb/>
Dr. Corput. It is to be noted that the urine of a case of Yellow Fever, heavily<lb/>
jaundiced, very much depressed and 18 hours before death should be more than dis-<lb/>
tinctly albuminous. It should be loaded with albumen.</p>
<p>It is a question whether the &ldquo;previous environment&rdquo; of the patient should be<lb/>
seriously considered as a factor, certainly I have never done so where the clinical ev-<lb/>
idence was at all positive, yet possibly we should note the length of time from his<lb/>
leaving the Quimistan considered the last possible place of infection, to the re-<lb/>
ported date of the development of fever - October 27 to November 5, 9 days. This<lb/>
is well beyond the recognized period on incubation of Yellow Fever, which has not<lb/>
been noted to extend beyond 6 days and 2 hours. This of course if of weight only<lb/>
as applying to infection from this source.</p>
<p>The evidence for Black Water Fever is (1) the early advent of marked yellow-<lb/>
ness; (2) the rapid collapse and death, and (3) the suppression or partial suppres-<lb/>
sion of urine. If we accept the statement of Dr. Winter as to the color of urine,<lb/>
this is absolutely negatived by it, otherwise it would be a very probable diagno-<lb/>
sis.</p>
<p>The evidence for a full fulminating infection say- influenza is (1) the<lb/>
facies and headache observed by Dr. Chiltern; (2) marked prostration and jaundice<lb/>
and (3) the quick death. This syndrome has been noted a <unclear>rumor</unclear> of times in<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00813050"/>
8<lb/>
this epidemic.</p>
<p>With the data on hand a certain diagnosis is not possible to me. The<lb/>
balance of evidence seems to me to be dicidedly against Yellow Fever. Consider-<lb/>
ing the presence of the epidemic, I am inclined to the diagnosis of a fulminant<lb/>
case of Influenza as the most probable one, altho I have seen exactly those symp-<lb/>
toms in a case of appendicitis.</p>
<p>It is greatly to be regretted that an autopsy was not held.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Assistant Surgeon General</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
