<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00818074">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to the Surgeon General, May 13, 1919</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00818074</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1919-05-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Griffitts, T.H.D.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1919-05-13">May 13, 1919</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00818074</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to the Surgeon General, May 13, 1919</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter suggests changes in the administrative policy of the US Public Health Service. He discusses regulations, examining boards, education of newly accepted candidates, examinations, specialization, rank, and compulsory waiting orders.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1919-05-13">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to the Surgeon General, May 13, 1919</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00818074"/>
<opener>
Suggestions in re changes<lb/>
in the Regulations.<lb/>
ASSISTANT SURGEON GENERAL H.R. CARTER<lb/>
<unclear>Regulations</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1919-05-13">May 13, 1919.</date>
</dateline>
The Surgeon General,<lb/>
U.S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I doubt if I should say anything in regard to the<lb/>
changes in the Regulations to be shortly revised as requested<lb/>
in Bureau letter of ______, because I have been ill and have<lb/>
not been able to go over the present ones to give them de-<lb/>
tailed consideration. I will however make one or two sugges-<lb/>
tions.</p>
<p>(1) I think the Regulations should not go too much<lb/>
in detail. In my judgement both of the last two revisions have<lb/>
been open<del>ed</del> to this objection. Let them be as clear as possi-<lb/>
ble but Regulations that specify everything are not elastic<lb/>
and <add>are</add> apt to hamper both the Bureau and officers who possess in-<lb/>
itiative.</p>
<p>(2) Try to so arrange the Regulations so as to get<lb/>
the best personnel and to get rid of the poor personnel. This<lb/>
naturally is quite as much an affair of legislation in making<lb/>
the Service attractive and of administration as of regulations.<lb/>
For this:</p>
<p>(a) allow in the Regulations as much latitude as is<lb/>
reasonably possible to the Examining Boards so that they will<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00818075"/>
2<lb/>
have as free hand as possible, both in making the examination<lb/>
and determining the values to be attached to the different<lb/>
subjects. We, of course, should choose the best Boards pos-<lb/>
sible and <del>to</del> change them as seldom as pozsible. I doubt how-<lb/>
ever the wisdom of using the Bureau chiefs on such boards.<lb/>
The choice of boards is, however, a matter of administration<lb/>
not of regulations;</p>
<p>(b) If it be possible to arrange a school somewhat<lb/>
on the Army plan for the newly accepted candidates, I think<lb/>
it would be a very great advantage. They <add>the accepted candidates</add> would be appointed<lb/>
Acting Assistant Surgeons until they had finished the course<lb/>
and only those who proved satisfactory would be commissioned.<lb/>
The Army is <unclear>this</unclear> able to require less of its candidates at<lb/>
the first examination, thus saving some desirable men, because<lb/>
it can judge of them <unclear>again.in</unclear> this school. Naturally the men<lb/>
should also gain enormously from the school;</p>
<p>(c) The examination for P.A. should be used so<lb/>
as to eliminate undesirable men more than it has been in the<lb/>
past. Many a man has passed it who should not have done so<lb/>
and whom it was not desirable to keep in the Service. In this<lb/>
examination, I think the Board should be left free to allow<lb/>
<hi>much</hi> weight to the officers record in the Service, so that if<lb/>
it be good or very good it could make up for some professional<lb/>
deficiency. This seems especially advisable if his service has<lb/>
been in some non-professional branch, sanitary or otherwise.<lb/>
If it be bad or very bad, it would require an extremely high<lb/>
professional mark to pass. The present Regulations do not<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00818076"/>
3<lb/>
allow as much latitude to the Boards in this as I would give<lb/>
them and their past policy has been always to favor the offi-<lb/>
cer at the expense of the Service, <add><unclear>Although</unclear></add> <del>the &ldquo;the ship is worth more<lb/>
than the crew&rdquo;,</del> certainly than any member of it. The same policy<lb/>
<del>is</del><add>has</add> obtained in the investigation and trial of officers.</p>
<p>(3) The present Regulations provides for certain<lb/>
routine service of men on admission. It has not been carried<lb/>
out but it is Regulations. The object, I was told, is to train<lb/>
each man into every branch of the Service, to make him an &ldquo;all<lb/>
around man&rdquo;. This to me is impossible and inadvisable. We<lb/>
should rather specialize our men in the different lines of<lb/>
work we do. They should be assigned to their special work<lb/>
when it can be determined for what kind each one is most suit-<lb/>
able and as soon as he has received the training needed and a-<lb/>
vailable therefor. A Service school would help to determine<lb/>
the first and provide the second. It would probably be ideal<lb/>
for each man to spend- say- 2 or even 3 years in clinical work<lb/>
which is good training for nearly everything. Is it possible? I doubt it.</p>
<p>All this, of course, is more administration than<lb/>
Regulations, but I think the paragraph on assignment had best<lb/>
be admitted. The Bureau can determine assignments better with-<lb/>
out it. In any case I want to lay stress on my belief that<lb/>
the specializing of officers in the different classes of Ser-<lb/>
vice activities is essential for Service efficiency.</p>
<p>(4) I am inclined to think it advisable to make<lb/>
the same difference between the Reserve <unclear>Corps</unclear> and Commissioned</p>
<p>copy</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00818077"/>
<p>Copy.</p>
<p>Suggestions in re changes in<lb/>
the Regulations.</p>
<p>H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General.</p>
<p>New Orleans, La.,<lb/>
May 13, 1919.</p>
<p>****</p>
<p>(4) I am inclined to think it advisable to made the same<lb/>
difference between the Reserve Corps and Commissioned Officers that<lb/>
exists between Staff and Line in the other Service, i. e. that the<lb/>
C. O of the station be the Commissioned Officer. I am not <hi>certain</hi><lb/>
that this is always best, but generally I think it is. If the Re-<lb/>
gulations be made unless &ldquo;otherwise directed by the Bureau&rdquo; it would<lb/>
seem to meet this difficulty. Our men are usually more familiar<lb/>
with administration than the Reserve Corps men, who are rather ex-<lb/>
perts in their different lines--consultants whose advice in their<lb/>
own lines, any reasonable man would ask and follow. Sometimes the<lb/>
Reserve Corps men should be in charge, hence the proviso.</p>
<p>(5) If in accordance with the law--and I think it is--would<lb/>
it not be well to give, in some cases, brevet rank, so to speak, by<lb/>
the Reserve Corps Commission even to Commissioned Officers? I have<lb/>
seen cases--Griffitts was, and Acker is, each a case in point.<lb/>
Griffitts received sufficient salary, but a grade as Surgeon without<lb/>
increase in salary had been an advantage to his work last year.<lb/>
Acker if filling a Surgeon's place and his efficiency in dealing with<lb/>
other men would be increased by another bar. I have seen a number of<lb/>
similar cases. Here, it even makes a difference with the War <unclear>Risk</unclear><lb/>
Insurance patients. They have expressed themselves as lacking confi-<lb/>
dence in &ldquo;Lieutenant Doctors.&rdquo; Of course, the importance of grade will<lb/>
lessen, and I hope rapidly, with the end of the war. Still it is im-<lb/>
portant now, decidedly so.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00818078"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>(6) If it be legal, I think waiting orders should be com-<lb/>
pulsory at 64 years of age. The Bureau is the best judge of the<lb/>
advisability of bringing this subject up.</p>
<closer>
<signed>H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
