<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00814001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report fragment on malaria in England, in 1917 and 1918, by [Henry Rose Carter?], [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00814001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">England</name>
<name type="place">Gallipoli (Turkey)</name>
<name type="place">Palestine</name>
<name type="place">Egypt</name>
<name type="place">Sheppey, Kent (England)</name>
<name type="place">Isle of Grain, Kent (England)</name>
<name type="place">Sandwich, Kent (England)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00814001</idno>
<title>Report fragment on malaria in England, in 1917 and 1918, by [Henry Rose Carter?], [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter?] discusses the history of malaria in England.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report fragment on malaria in England, in 1917 and 1918, by [Henry Rose Carter?], [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00814001"/>
<opener>
Mal.<lb/>
England<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Reports and Papers on Malaria<lb/>
Contracted in England in 1917 and 1918.</p>
<p>Issued by<lb/>
the Local Government Board</p>
<p>These papers give the &ldquo;reaction&rdquo; of England to the importation<lb/>
of a large number of men infected with malaria in 1916: /17 and /18<lb/>
so far as had been determined to June /19--the date of the last paper.<lb/>
They are of interest to us in America, especially to those in regions in<lb/>
which malaria was, but is no longer, prevalent. The reports on the<lb/>
current year and the two or three following ones will be more so.</p>
<p>In the past malaria was prevalent in many parts of England so<lb/>
as to be of &ldquo;serious sanitary importance.&rdquo; Shakespeare is full of<lb/>
allusions to agues: James 1 and Charles 11 <unclear>both.suffered</unclear> from it and<lb/>
Cromwell died of a tertian fever. The Lincolnshire fens and parts<lb/>
of Kent especially enjoyed (?) a bad reputation and I presume a cer-<lb/>
tain immunity among the natives as a <unclear>Fen man</unclear> is exhorted not to<lb/>
take a wife &ldquo;out-foreign&rdquo; as she &ldquo;was sure to die of ague:&rdquo; the<lb/>
speaker, a Fen man (and a fictitious character) having had this ill<lb/>
luck three times. In some sections--as in Kent, south of the lower<lb/>
Thames--it was prevalent up to 1869 and /70 and maybe longer.- <unclear>in one to 1911</unclear><lb/>
England was generally believed to be free from it at the time<lb/>
of the beginning of the war.</p>
<p>Nuttall and Strangeways Pigg--1903 to 1904--found Anopheles<lb/>
of three species quite commonly distributed in the low lying parts<lb/>
of England, one species of which--A. maculipennis--the old world ana-<lb/>
logue of our quadrimaculatus--is known to be elsewhere an efficient<lb/>
vector of malaria. Unfortunately, attention was concentrated rather<lb/>
on the <hi>fact</hi> of <hi>finding Anopheles</hi> than on the <hi>number</hi> found--i. e.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00814002"/>
2<lb/>
whether they were numerous enough to be &ldquo;of sanitary <unclear>importance<del>,</del>&rdquo;:</unclear> so<lb/>
the surprise of these gentlemen at the absence of malaria in Eng-<lb/>
land, in spite of its frequent introduction from abroad, is, I think,<lb/>
not justified by their findings as published. (Foot note)<lb/>
_________________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The survey implies, however, a considerable--or even<lb/>
large amount-of breeding at some places. (End of foot note)<lb/>
_________________________________________________________<lb/>
The unknown &ldquo;third factor&rdquo; (in addition to Anopheles and infected<lb/>
men) predicated as necessary for the conveyance of malaria <add>and absent in England</add> may have<lb/>
been in many cases a temperature for much of the time so low that<lb/>
the full developement of the parasite in the mosquito took place<lb/>
either not at all or so slowly as to materially reduce the efficiency<lb/>
of the insect as a vector. Anopheles, of course, may be active at a<lb/>
temperature well below the optimum of that for the developement of<lb/>
the parasite in them.</p>
<p>The factors necessary for the conveyance of malaria are <unclear>obviously:</unclear></p>
<p>(1) Men infective to Anopheles mosquitoes:</p>
<p>(2) Active Anopheles of sufficient numbers to serve as vectors:</p>
<p>(3) Temperature suitable for the full developement of the para-<lb/>
site in the mosquito, and</p>
<p>(4) Men accessible to the infective mosquitoes.</p>
<p>In 1916:/17 &amp; /18 a large number of men suffering from malaria<lb/>
were brought to England from the Balkans: Gallipoli and, I presume,<lb/>
from Palestine and Egypt. How many one can only guess. In the re-<lb/>
port made in March /18 by Ross 2,460 cases are reported in 1917 as<lb/>
undergoing in hospital specially devised therapy to prevent relapses.<lb/>
The total number under treatment should be several times more than this.<lb/>
Angus McDonald reported 2,417 &ldquo;proven carriers&rdquo; (by blood examination?)<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00814003"/>
3<lb/>
at three places only at which malaria had been contracted in 1917.<lb/>
He says the &ldquo;actual number was obviously much greater.&rdquo; A conser-<lb/>
vative estimate would be that from 10,000 to 20,000 men infected with<lb/>
malaria were introduced into England in 1916 and 1917--a less num-<lb/>
ber in 1918--probably 15,000 to <unclear>20,000</unclear> in all. And they were pretty<lb/>
well scattered in England too, in Camps: villages and small towns.</p>
<p>Very obviously there was abundant material to infect Anophe-<lb/>
les if other conditions were suitable and they were so infected.<lb/>
During 1917 there are reported to have been contracted in England<lb/>
<table rows="3" cols="5">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>231 Cases of Malaria:</cell><cell>163 in the Army:</cell><cell>25 Navy:</cell><cell>43 Civilian</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>" 1918/</cell><cell>95 " " "</cell><cell>61 " " "</cell><cell>9 "</cell><cell>25 "</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>In all:--</cell><cell>326 " " "</cell><cell>224 " " "</cell><cell>34 "</cell><cell>68 "</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Twenty-nine foci of infection were established: All cases were<lb/>
tertian--the &ldquo;benign tertian&rdquo; of British writers<unclear>,-</unclear>although from 26% to<lb/>
32% of the infections at the places of origen were Aestivo-Autumnal--<lb/>
&ldquo;malignant tertian.&rdquo; We may note here (1) that this form seems to be<lb/>
less apt to relapse and (2) certainly requires a higher temperature<lb/>
for sporogony than the simple tertian. 270 of the cases occurred<lb/>
in Kent: 234 in three districts: Sheppey (an island south of the<lb/>
mouth of the Thames): the Isle of Grain and Sandwich.</p>
<p>At first the infection was, naturally, ascribed entirely to<lb/>
that derived from the imported infection, but a closer examination<lb/>
showed <del>its</del><add>its</add> existence, and in some amount, in Queensborough (in the<lb/>
Sheppey District) and in Isle of Grain prior to the advent of the<lb/>
soldiers. (Foot note)<lb/>
_____________________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) It existed also in the Romney Marsh area as late<lb/>
as 1911. (End of Foot note)<lb/>
_____________________________________________________________<lb/>
This is not asserted of Sandwich, although in the same general sec-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00814004"/>
4<lb/>
tion. The later conclusion was then that a certain number of these<lb/>
cases are true indigenous <unclear>infections:</unclear> the remainder being contract-<lb/>
ed, through English Anopheles, from the soldiers infected overseas.</p>
<p>S. P. James is very positive in claiming a marked clinical<lb/>
difference between the indigenous infections and the imported ones.<lb/>
The first being far milder and little subject to symptomatic re-<lb/>
lapses the second being extremely severe and relapses frequent. <unclear>No</unclear><lb/>
difference in the morphology of the parasites was made out. The<lb/>
Sandwich cases were in general mild, as much so as those from Queens-<lb/>
borough. By this test a number of them would then count as indi-<lb/>
genous infections. It seems then that malaria was not <hi>entirely</hi> ab-<lb/>
sent from England at any time, but lingered in very mild form in a<lb/>
few places and was discovered owing to the careful investigation<lb/>
caused by the cases of malaria contracted in England showing among<lb/>
the troops and among civilians in contact with troops.</p>
<p>The report shows that no measures likely to be sufficient to<lb/>
prevent the spread of malaria were taken in 1917. In 1918 measures<lb/>
of control were much better applied. In the Sheppey district: Sand-<lb/>
wich and Romney Marsh, where the great bulk of the cases occurred,<lb/>
measures for the control of mosquito production were undertaken.<lb/>
Generally, however, they were the prompt report of cases and their<lb/>
sterilization by quinine--Colonel James formulating the treatment.</p>
<p>To my mind the point in this paper which stands out as of<lb/>
prime importance is that, <hi>with the importation of not less than<lb/>
15,000 men infected with malaria during three years</hi>, <hi>the total num-<lb/>
ber of cases reported as contracted in England in two years <add>was</add> only<lb/>
326</hi><del><add><unclear>326--</unclear></add></del>--some of which were contracted from pre-existing (indigenous)<lb/>
infection. Very obviously malaria shows little tendency to spread<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00814005"/>
5<lb/>
in England.</p>
<p>This will be better seen if we look at the statistics for<lb/>
1917 by themselves, as the measures for control of that year may--<lb/>
I think--be almost disregarded. From 10,000 to 15,000 infected men<lb/>
imported and only 231 cases contracted in England (<hi>43</hi> among civilians)<lb/>
If these conditions of conveyance continue, the malaria introduced<lb/>
in 1917 will be &ldquo;of no sanitary importance&rdquo; within a year or two.</p>
<p>I think we may take it as a rule <hi>that if the biological condi-<lb/>
tions of the insect host are such that malaria once prevalent spon-<lb/>
taneously disappears</hi> <add>- or undergoes <unclear>great diminution -</unclear></add>, <hi>the introduction of carriers</hi>--<hi>no matter in<lb/>
what number</hi>--<hi>while they may cause an outbreak of malaria</hi>, <hi>yet this<lb/>
will be temporary only and malaria will spontaneously decrease and<lb/>
disappear</hi> <add>or undergo the same <unclear>diminution</unclear></add> <hi>if these conditions of the insect host remain the same</hi>. <unclear>XQueens</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>For Page 5 aXX</unclear></p>
<p>(Foot note) The same will hold if the malaria has been reduced in the<lb/>
community <hi>by a change of biologic conditions of its Anopheles</hi> to a cer-<lb/>
tain <hi>stationary</hi> amount. It will, after the flare up from the introduc-<lb/>
tion of carriers, spontaneously return to the same degree of infection.<lb/>
(End of foot note)<lb/>

what the number of infections we start with, we would have a de-<lb/>
creasing series, which would ultimately reach a number &ldquo;of no sanitary<lb/>
importance.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It would be inaccurate to say that the rate of decrease in<lb/>
England is 15,000 to 326 per annum. On the one hand, a number of re-<lb/>
lapses will occur in 1919 and /20 among the cases <del>already</del><add><unclear>previously</unclear></add> imported,<lb/>
which will infect others in addition to the 326, and, on the other,<lb/>
when the soldiers are demobilized they will live less commonly in<lb/>
camps in the country, where Anopheles most abound, and even there their<lb/>
house contact with other people would be less intimate than in <unclear>barracks</unclear></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
