<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00818112">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to J.E.S. Thorpe, October 14, 1919</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00818112</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1919-10-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Thorpe, J.E.S.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1919-10-14">October 14, 1919</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00818112</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to J.E.S. Thorpe, October 14, 1919</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter writes about the relationship between impounded water and malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1919-10-14">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to J.E.S. Thorpe, October 14, 1919</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00818112"/>
<opener>
Impounded Waters<lb/>
Tallassee Power Co.<lb/>
Badin, N. C.<lb/>
<hi>Confidential</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Baltimore, Md.,<lb/>
<date value="1919-10-14">October 14, 1919.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. J. H. S. Thorpe,<lb/>
General Superintendant,<lb/>
Tallassee Power Company,<lb/>
Badin, N. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mr. Thorpe:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wish to acknowledge your check for $123.11 in full for my<lb/>
expenses as witness in the Jane Elliott case.</p>
<p>We, the Public Health Service, purpose to continue the investiga-<lb/>
tions of impounded waters for certainly <hi>two</hi> years more--probably for<lb/>
<hi>two</hi> intensively and three more for special features. Whether the<lb/>
one purposed at High Rock is suitable for our purpose, I cannot now<lb/>
tell, but will know--or some one of us will know--by next spring.</p>
<p>One thing about such waters--no matter <hi>what</hi> is done, the impound-<lb/>
ing of water on a large scale (and to a less degree on a small one) will<lb/>
<hi>affect the incidence of malaria in its environment</hi>, lessening it in<lb/>
some places and increasing it in others. The same is true of any. at<lb/>
random, disturbance of the earth's surface: Railroads: county roads etc.<lb/>
Of course these statements only apply in sections warm enough for Ano-<lb/>
pheles to breed and become infective to men--i. e. in <hi>potential</hi> malarial<lb/>
areas.</p>
<p>Now the general effect of pondage is to <hi>make more malaria than it<lb/>
removes</hi>: (1) by changing the location of breeding places of Anopheles<lb/>
so that they will be nearer residences than they were before (see .<lb/>
marked passage in pamphlet enclosed: (2) by changing the proportion of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00818113"/>
-2-<lb/>
the <hi>species</hi> of Anopheles prevalent in the community. This latter<lb/>
is more important than the first. The breeding places destroyed by<lb/>
the pond may be those of Anopheles quadrimaculatus or of A. puncti-<lb/>
pennis. Those made by it are mainly--almost exclusively--A. quadri-<lb/>
maculatus. Now A. quadrimaculatus is unquestionably a more dangerous<lb/>
insect from a malarial point of view than A. punctipennis--far more<lb/>
so, and they fly further. An increase, and it is usually a large in-<lb/>
crease, in A. quadrimaculatus closer to residences will do more harm<lb/>
than the diminution of a larger number of A. punctipennis at a great-<lb/>
er distance, or even at the same distance, will do good. In  <hi>general</hi><lb/>
then, the impounding of water in a malarial region <hi>increases</hi> the a-<lb/>
mount of malaria.</p>
<p>I am telling you all this so that <hi>you</hi> may know the <hi>general</hi> effect<lb/>
of impounding water on its environment--especially for future ponds.<lb/>
I think there is no question that in the community close to such parts<lb/>
of the Tallassee Lake as are covered by floatage there will be a de-<lb/>
cided increase of malaria from Anopheles quadrimaculatus bred in the<lb/>
lake. I judge that from the number of A. quadrimaculatus found in<lb/>
the houses last fall.</p>
<p>This condition of breeding can be controlled by oiling such col-<lb/>
lections of floatage, or by fluctuation of the pond level. The former<lb/>
is quite expensive and naturally would have to be kept up every sum-<lb/>
mer: the latter is. I judge, impracticable--at least to lower the<lb/>
level enough to lodge all floatage.</p>
<p>In planning a new pond then, it seems to me that the most feasible<lb/>
method of meeting these conditions, which will certainly arise, would<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00818114"/>
-3-<lb/>
be (a) to allow for the damage to health in the purchase of the<lb/>
flowage rights or (b) to purchase all the land that will be af-<lb/>
fected. Note two things in (a)--(1) that the health damage to<lb/>
the land only affects <hi>residence</hi> on it, not its value in agriculture<lb/>
otherwise: (2) that lands will be damaged which are <hi>not</hi> flooded at<lb/>
all if the residences on them are close enough to the breeding places<lb/>
made by the pond. This would be equity anyway.</p>
<p>For the present ponds I think equity would justify damages to<lb/>
the adjacent community, but not based on the total destruction of<lb/>
the value of the land at $75.00 per acre. The verdict seems to have<lb/>
been at the rate of $20.00 per acre. I presume the land is worth<lb/>
$15.00 and part of that is lost by inability to reside on it during<lb/>
the malaria season.</p>
<p>- The preparation of the area (edges) to be covered by a pond can<lb/>
<hi>minimixe</hi> the amount of malaria which it will produce, as can stocking<lb/>
with fish etc. but I know no way by which it can be entirely prevented--<lb/>
that is, within economical limits. The most satisfactory way is, I<lb/>
think, to move people off from it.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Assistant Surgeon General</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
