<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00823017">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Henry Rose Carter to J. Gil Cardenas, July 23, 1920</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00823017</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1920-07-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Cardenas, J. Gil</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="place">Piura (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Payta (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Chulucanos (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Guyaquil (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1920-07-23">July 23, 1920</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00823017</idno>
<title>English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Henry Rose Carter to J. Gil Cardenas, July 23, 1920</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter informs Cardenas about the sanitary conditions in the department of Piura, Peru. </p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1920-07-23">
<head>English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Henry Rose Carter to J. Gil Cardenas, July 23, 1920 (See <xref id="f00823013">Spanish original</xref>.)</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00823017"/>
<opener>
<hi>Survey made from June 28 to July 19</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Lima, Per&uacute;,<lb/>
<date value="1920-07-23">July 23th., 1920.</date>
</dateline>
Peru<lb/>
Report<lb/>
Dr. Joseph Gil C&aacute;rdenas,<lb/>
Director of Public Health.<lb/>
Lima.<lb/>
<salute>Dear sir;</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to submit the following report on the<lb/>
sanitary condition of the department of Piura as regard yellow fe-<lb/>
ver.</p>
<p>"Let me begin by saying that the probability of yellow fe-<lb/>
ver spreading in any community in which it exists and into which<lb/>
it is introduced depends on (1) the numbers of active stegomyia<lb/>
present and (2) on the proportion of people susceptible to yellow<lb/>
fever; i.e. on the amount of fever which has previously occurred in<lb/>
the community.</p>
<p>Hence the fever is most apt to occur and spread next summer in<lb/>
towns in which there have been few cases last summer naturally if<lb/>
introduced into towns in which <hi>no</hi> cases have occurred it would find<lb/>
virgin soil. A town in which only few cases occurred and reporting fever in June<lb/>
or later needs watching.</p>
<p>The problem naturally divids itself geographycally into:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) The district on the line of Rail Road from Payta to Piura<lb/>
and Catacaos.</item>
<item>(2) The valley of the Piura-below Catacaos.</item>
<item>(3) The valley of the Piura-above Piura; the Valley of <unclear>Morrop&oacute;n.</unclear></item>
</list></p>
<p>The division is not sharp as Sullana: Piura and Catacaos are rather<lb/>
closely connected in their travel-relations with <add>the</add> Morrop&oacute;n Valley and,<lb/>
to a less extent, the last two with the valley of the lower Piura.<lb/>
Those three towns, Piura and Catacaos especially, are the key to the<lb/>
situation in this department.</p>
<p>(1).- Not only has no yellow fever <unclear>beeb</unclear> reported in Payta for three<lb/>
months but I am sure none exists here and I have made rather a care<lb/>
ful inspection. Drs. Reinoso and Z&uacute;&ntilde;iga state that thay see no sickness<lb/>
except a small amount of Grippe.</p>
<p>The inspection for larvae is well carried out. Not only do the records<lb/>
show a very small percentage of houses as breeding stegomyia, but the<lb/>
work done corresponds with the records. I went around with the Visita-<lb/>
dors and can assert this. The water supply too has been greatly im-<lb/>
proved making this work easier.</p>
<p>The records show that from July 1st. to 8th. inclusive 780 houses exa<lb/>
mined, yielded 18 depositos with larvae-nearly all of which were small<lb/>
and in only 2 cases were ninfas found. From July 9th. to 16th. of 645<lb/>
houses only 5 showed larvae; in only one case large and no ninfas.</p>
<p>The first gives index of 2.3% and the second of less 4/5 of 1%<lb/>
<hi>The &ldquo;Index of Production&rdquo;-larvae and ninfas-</hi> is much smaller in both<lb/>
cases than the above. Payta at present and as long as the production<lb/>
of stegomyia in kept at this level, is not infectable with yellow fe-<lb/>
ver and as long as these conditions hold it seems to me unnecessary<lb/>
to continue the quarantine against it for yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00823018"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>These has been no yellow fever reported since March or early April<lb/>
on the Lime of the Rail Road between Payta and Piura and considering<lb/>
the rather sharp epidemics in La Huaca and Tamarindo-both small pla-<lb/>
ces-last summer and the anti-stegomyia work done in these places,<lb/>
they at least would not be expected to show any at this time. Sullana<lb/>
is a larger place and had no great deal of fever last summer. Yet my<lb/>
examination showed the number of stegomyia produced to be small. The<lb/>
anti-stegomyia work was quite good and the facility with which water<lb/>
is obtain here makes the work easy and efficient.</p>
<p>No cases of yellow fever have been reported as contracted in Piura or<lb/>
Catacaos since April; although two cases developed in the Carcel in<lb/>
Piura in May. Dr. Vega is of the opinion that these were contracted in<lb/>
Chulucanas, which is probable but not entirely certain. The stegomyia<lb/>
index in Piura was low in April last-the water supply renders the<lb/>
work fairly easy-and with the cool weather is naturally lower now. It<lb/>
is an important place and, with Catacaos and Sullana, I consider it<lb/>
the key to the yellow fever situation in this department. The anti-ste-<lb/>
gomyia work should be continued and pressed to the limit at this place<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> <unclear>ao</unclear> that if fever be still present (I feel quite sure it is not)<lb/>
or reintroduced in the early summer it will not spread.</p>
<p>Catacaos is probably free from yellow fever but it is a place with<lb/>
much Malaria, which confuses diagnosis, and, as many of the sick, recover<lb/>
or die<del>d</del> without being seen by a physician, it is not easy to judge<lb/>
what sickness may, or may not, be there.</p>
<p>The records of the stegomyia work are favorable although far less so<lb/>
than at Payta. Such an inspection as I was able to make, with three Vi-<lb/>
sitadors only, was less encouraging. The actual work was less good than<lb/>
the records would indicate. Capt. Mitchel was given my findings and direc-<lb/>
ted to pay particular attention to this place as soon as he could vi-<lb/>
sit it and to remedy the defects found. A first class Chief of Visi-<lb/>
tadores is needed here; the one who <add>was here</add> has been moved to Tumbes.</p>
<p>I believe the main difficulty to efficient stegomyia control here is<lb/>
the problem of &ldquo;Casas cerradas&rdquo;. This is trouble-some enough every<lb/>
where, even in Payta, but owing to the multitude of fiestas and the ha-<lb/>
bits of the population is especially difficult in Catacaos.</p>
<p>(2).-In the lower Piura valley yellow fever was reported in June (1st.<lb/>
and 8th.) by Dr. Caballero and Saona. None has been reported since<lb/>
that date and as the place is small. There is <del>the</del> reason to <hi>hope that<lb/>
there has been none since</hi>. My advice was of the July 9th..There is<lb/>
however much Paludismo here which naturally confuses diagnosis.</p>
<p>None has been reported from Sechura or Vice for a much longer a time<lb/>
and Dr. Caballero-who visited Sechura July 10th-reported no sickness<lb/>
of any kind at that place. This too is an important place as the tra-<lb/>
vel south into Lambayeque-with fish and for grain-would infect that<lb/>
country if Sechura be infected.</p>
<p>The anti-stegomyia work in this district below Catacaos is directed<lb/>
by <unclear>Sabns</unclear>, selected as being an unuusually efficient man. I have not<lb/>
seen it. Mitchel was directed to visit this district ans pay attention<lb/>
to it, especially to Mu&ntilde;uela.</p>
<p>There is no graduate<del>d</del> physician living in this district-below Catacaos<lb/>
ans it is advisable that such a man he stationed here for diagnostic<lb/>
purposes-say-at Sechura. The Practicante Saona at Mu&ntilde;uela is I belie-<lb/>
ve an unusually well-informed man. Dr. Chipoco was <unclear>advised</unclear> to return<lb/>
to Sechura and assume medical (diagnostic) supervision of this district.</p>
<p>(3).- I did not visit the Morrop&oacute;n Valley. Had made arrangments to do<lb/>
so, but owing to delays this was not possible without unduly postpo-<lb/>
ning my visit to Lima. I saw however the physicians Valcarcel, Mendoza<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00823019"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
and Chipoco, who has been stationed there and Capt. Mitchel, who, with Dr.<lb/>
Chipoco came into Piura the Sunday before I left. No fever reported at<lb/>
Tambogrande (Valcarcel) since June 16th.-20 cases seen there with 5<lb/>
deaths. None in Chulucanas (mendoza) since June 28th. He left Chulucanas<lb/>
July 3th. None reported at Morrop&oacute;n for a long time; in April or early<lb/>
part of May I think-I have lost the record-and, considering the rather<lb/>
sharp epidemic earlier in the season and the vigorous anti-stegomyia<lb/>
campaign begin in April, there should be none now. Mitchel was returning<lb/>
from the inspection of a numbers of a small places between Piura, Tambo<lb/>
grande, Chulucanas, Morrop&oacute;n and Salitral and reported the stegomyia<lb/>
work good at Chulucanas. It is under Reyes and Velasco who are considered<lb/>
good men. That at Tambogrande was not so good and the Chief of Visitadors<lb/>
there was changed<unclear>.</unclear></p>
<p>Of this valley the key is Chulucanas. It is (1) a large town- 10000 popu-<lb/>
lation; (2) a commercail centre, from and to which there is a considera-<lb/>
ble travel; (3) no such considerable amount of fever has been reported<lb/>
here as at either Morrop&oacute;n or Tambogrande; although doubtless more occu-<lb/>
rred than has been reported and (4) fever has been reported quite recently.<lb/>
Intensive and continued stegomyia work is advisable here and naturally<lb/>
the same should be continued at Tambogrande and Morrop&oacute;n.</p>
<p>There is no graduated physician living in this district-the emp&iacute;rico<lb/>
Cruz rendering it medical assistance-and it seems advisable that a<lb/>
physician be stationed at Chulucanas-which lies between Morrop&oacute;n and<lb/>
Tambogrande-who could perform the diagnostic work needed in both of<lb/>
these towns as well as in Chulucanas. There is much Paludismo in this<lb/>
valley-especially about Morrop&oacute;n-tending to obscure diagnosis. It was<lb/>
<unclear>advised</unclear> that Dr. Mendoza return to Chulucanas.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS.</hi></head>
<item>(1).-That yellow fever has disappeared from most of the department of<lb/>
Piura, quite certainly from Payta and probably from the other places<lb/>
on the line of the Rail Road.</item>
<item>(2).-That the infection of this disease probably still lingers in same<lb/>
places in this department:Chulucanas, Mu&ntilde;uela and Tambogrande being <unclear><del>,</del></unclear> es-<lb/>
pecially to the suspected.</item>
<item>(3).-That pressing the campaign against the stegomyia during the pre-<lb/>
sent winter should result in the elimination of this infection and is<lb/>
therefore <hi>extremely</hi> advisable.</item>
<item>(4).-This work (stegomyia) should be continued at Payta and the group of<lb/>
towns, Piura; Catacaos and Sullana, and pressed to the limit in Chuluca-<lb/>
nas, Mu&ntilde;uela and Tambogrande.</item>
<item>(5).This work requires constant supervision by a highly <unclear>traied</unclear> Inspector.<lb/>
Indeed I do not believe one man can give the supervision required. Very<lb/>
obviously our success in this campaign depends primarily on the stego-<lb/>
myia work and hence on the Inspectors.</item>
<item>(6).-There should be organized a service in excess of ordinary needs-of<lb/>
two or more Visitadores and their gangs-to be quickly moved to any pla-<lb/>
ce in which especially quick<del>y</del> and intensive stegomyia work is needed.<lb/>
This is the so called &ldquo;Brigada Volante&rdquo; we have used in other countries (<lb/>
(Brazil ans <unclear>Central</unclear> Am&eacute;rica). Its perso<add>n</add>nel can be drawn from the other<lb/>
towns in which work is being done. It is especially disireable that<lb/>
this Brigada be avaible as the summer comes on: although I hope it may<lb/>
not needed.</item>
</list></p>
<p><unclear>Three</unclear> things I would invite your attention.</p>
<p>(1-) There is believed to be no yellow fever in any place on the Pacific<lb/>
Coast of South Am&eacute;rica, except in Piura and Guayaquil. When this is eli-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00823020"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
minated the whole of this coast will be free. Panam&aacute; and Guayaquil,<lb/>
the sources od so many Paruvian epidemics, being no longer able to con<lb/>
taminated us should remain free.</p>
<p>(2) The trade relations<del><unclear></unclear></del> of this coast are such that vessels do not<lb/>
pass directly from ports north of Panam&aacute; to those South of <unclear>its</unclear> passing<lb/>
into Balboa instead and the <del><unclear>Isthmus</unclear></del> <add>Isthmus</add>, instead of the menace is has been<lb/>
to us in past, is now a protection.</p>
<p>(3) The Coast south of the Canal then is not exposed to infection from<lb/>
such Mexican and Central American foci of infection as still exist;<lb/>
but if once freed from this infection completely, <hi>should remain perma -<lb/>
nently free</hi>.</p>
<p>I confidently expect the complete elimination of yellow fever from the<lb/>
Americas before it could reach our Pacific Coast by any indirect means.<lb/>
On the other hand if the fever recrudesces and spreads next season, <unclear>these</unclear><lb/>
<del>re</del> is chance of the recontaminatiom of Guayaquil which would again beco-<lb/>
me a menace to Per&uacute; and also of extension into the populous districts<lb/>
around Chiclayo in Lamabayeque; against which extension measures were,<lb/>
very wisely, taken last summer.</p>
<p>If <unclear>introduced</unclear> into this district and spread, its elimination would be<lb/>
costly and difficult with a possibility of forming a focus more or less<lb/>
lasting- for which the conditions are not unprovable. At any rate the<lb/>
some-what costly stegomyia work done last summer in this district would<lb/>
have be repeated.</p>
<p>These <unclear>considerations</unclear> to my mind render it advisable to press the work<lb/>
to render the complete elimination of yellow fever from Piura certain.<lb/>
This should be done now while the temperature is less favorable for ste-<lb/>
gomyia production. It is fair say in Piura the temperature is by no means<lb/>
so low as it is in Lima and yet the great epidemic in Lima, if I remem-<lb/>
ber aright lasted over the Winter and recrudesced the next Summer dying<lb/>
out I judge from exhaustion of the human material.</p>
<p>ooooooo0ooooooo</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
