<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00822007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Ralph N. Cresne, January 23, 1920</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00822007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1920-01-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Cresne, Ralph N.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Tampa (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Miami (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Key West (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Pensacola (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Fernandina (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Jacksonville (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Boca Grande (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">St. Andrews (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Apalachicola (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Campeche (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Progresso (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Merida (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Cape Gracias (Nicaragua)</name>
<name type="place">Belize</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1920-01-23">January 23, 1920</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00822007</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Ralph N. Cresne, January 23, 1920</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses the control of mosquitoes in southern U.S. ports.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1920-01-23">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Ralph N. Cresne, January 23, 1920</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00822007"/>
<opener>
Memorandum on the control of Yellow-Fever-Conveying Mosquitos<lb/>
in Florida Ports.<lb/>
Copy sent <unclear>liut</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1920-01-23">January <del>21</del><add>23</add>, 1920.</date>
</dateline>
File miss<lb/>
<hi>Y. F.</hi> Files<lb/>
Dr. Ralph N. Cresne,<lb/>
State Health Officer,<lb/>
State Board of Health,<lb/>
Jacksonville, Fla.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I examined at Tampa, Florida, during the past three days<lb/>
the records of the entries of all the ports of Florida for the <unclear>calendar</unclear><lb/>
year of 1919. Except for <hi>Tampa</hi>, <hi>Miami</hi>, and <hi>Key West</hi>, no records were<lb/>
available prior to June 1st. I think, however, that this makes little<lb/>
difference as entries in January and February (and in Pensacola in<lb/>
March) are of no importance from a yellow fever standpoint, being<lb/>
outside the Quarantine seasonal limits.</p>
<p>No vessels from any ports infected or suspected of infection<lb/>
from Yellow Fever enter at any of the following ports: Fernandina,<lb/>
Jacksonville, Miami, Boca Grande, St. Andrews or Apalachicola. Vessels<lb/>
from the last two cleared for ports in Mexico, but none entered direct<lb/>
from such ports.</p>
<p>For Pensacola, Tampa, and Key West, the case is different.<lb/>
The only places on the Gulf; Atlantic or Caribbean Seaports at which<lb/>
yellow fever is believed to exist at present is in Yucatan and <unclear>Campeche.</unclear><lb/>
There is a permanent focus in Yucatan of which Merida is the probable<lb/>
center and of which Progresso is the preferable port of exit. The<lb/>
portion of Mexico soutwest of Yucatan on the Isthmus of <unclear>Tehuantepec</unclear> is,<lb/>
I believe, not above suspicion, yet I do not know that it is infected.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00822008"/>
-2-<lb/>
Of the ports in this section, Progresso is easily the most dangerous<lb/>
having direct communication with Merida and being the port of exit<lb/>
for Merida passengers.</p>
<p>The Laguna de Carmen in <unclear>Campeche</unclear> and Frontera should be<lb/>
counted as suspicious. There was a regular line from Pensacola, the<lb/>
<unclear>Stesmare Hornot</unclear> and Oregon, to these ports and to Bluefields and Cape<lb/>
Gracias (Nicaragua) in logs--mahogany, cedar, etc. Farther south<lb/>
are the Bay Islands opposite the Mosquito Coast and <unclear>Belize</unclear>. <add>They are Honduran <hi>territory</hi> I think.</add> Both<lb/>
these islands and the coast mentioned are believed to be free from<lb/>
fever and have been so for a long time. We are able to have quite<lb/>
a close supervision of the Honduran Coast near to these Islands through<lb/>
the United Fruit Company's stations at Tela and Ceiba. Further east<lb/>
still is Cape Gracias A Dios, another log port; as is Bluefields<lb/>
south of it in Nicaragua. Both have long been very healthful ports<lb/>
and I believe are so still.</p>
<p>In the summer of 1918 and last spring and early <unclear>sooner</unclear><lb/>
there was yellow fever in Guatemala and Salvador on the <hi>Pacific</hi><lb/>
coast. This was taken in charge by the Health Authorities, the In-<lb/>
ternational Health Board furnishing most of the funds and the work<lb/>
being first under the supervision of Senior Surgeon White of this<lb/>
Service and afterwards of General Gorgas. This work is reported as<lb/>
having been completely successful. At any <unclear>rate</unclear> there is extremely<lb/>
little direct passenger travel across the mountain from the Pacific<lb/>
to the Caribbean Coast and we have heard of no infection on the<lb/>
Caribbean coast of Central America, nor do I believe that there is<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00822009"/>
-3-<lb/>
any. Even if there were, it would be little apt to show up at any of<lb/>
the ports I have mentioned in Central America, Bluefields, Cape<lb/>
Gracias, the Bay Islands, Belize or the Mosquito coast.</p>
<p>The largest Mexican trade to the Florida ports is from the<lb/>
oil fields of <unclear>Tampico, Tuxpam</unclear>, etc. These ports are certainly free<lb/>
from Yellow Fever, and if they become infected we ought, and I believe<lb/>
would, know it at once because they have a large number of people<lb/>
susceptible to yellow fever; Americans, English, Scotch and Germans<lb/>
living there. It is not at all probable then that they would become<lb/>
infected without our knowing it almost immediately.</p>
<p><hi>PENSACOLA</hi></p>
<p>Pensacola from June to December, inclusive, had one schooner<lb/>
(July), light, from <hi><unclear>Program</unclear></hi>: four steamers, in cargo (logs), from<lb/>
<hi>Frontera</hi>. Two of these, however, were not during quarantine season<lb/>
(in November and December). She has, however, a regular line of two<lb/>
small steamers bringing logs from Frontera, Bluefields and Cape<lb/>
Gracias; two trips are recorded from Cape Gracias and three from<lb/>
Bluefields. The Frontera and Progreso trade is not free from risk<lb/>
of infection. Progresso is the outlet for Merida and Yucatan pass-<lb/>
engers, and that country is infected in the Yellow Fever (Merida and<lb/>
some other parts of Yucatan).</p>
<p><hi>TAMPA</hi></p>
<p>Tampa had twenty-three steamers from the oil fields: Fif-<lb/>
teen during the quarantine season (March to November, inclusive).<lb/>
This trade is at present safe. A large trade, forty-seven schooners,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00822010"/>
-4-<lb/>
from the Bay Islands (<unclear>Rnatan and Benacca</unclear>) and Belize bring cocoanuts.<lb/>
This trade is also, I think, at present safe. If, however, yellow<lb/>
fever developed on the Caribbean coast of Guatemala, or  Honduras<lb/>
(Port Barrios, Livingston or Tela) this safety <hi>might</hi> not continue.<lb/>
Of suspicious trade it had four schooners bringing logs from the<lb/>
<hi>Laguna</hi>. I will add that the Bay Islands and Belize are probably the<lb/>
safest ports in the Central American litoral. Cape Gracias is also<lb/>
a <hi>very</hi> safe port. Progresso, Laguna and Frontera should count, the<lb/>
first as infected, the other two as suspicious.</p>
<p><hi>KEY WEST</hi></p>
<p>Key West shows twenty vessels from the oil ports, seventeen<lb/>
in quarantine season (March to November, inclusive), seventeen schooners<lb/>
from the Bay Islands, Belize and Bluefields, fourteen of which were<lb/>
in quarantine season and seven from Cape Gracias. All of the above<lb/>
count as safe enough traders. The only entries from infected or<lb/>
suspected ports are two steamers from Progresso and one from Front-<lb/>
era; the first two call<add>ed</add> for supplies.</p>
<p>It is fair to say then that the trade from ports infected<lb/>
with or suspected of yellow fever of last year was small in amount<lb/>
to any Florida port, , <unclear>and</unclear> that to most Florida ports there was<lb/>
none. The statistician at Tampa is quite positive that there will<lb/>
be a considerable increase in cocoanut imports into Tampa, which<lb/>
are large already, and although less positive of the log trade from<lb/>
Frontera and Laguna to Pensacola and Tampa, he looks for a consid-<lb/>
erable increase of this also. He does not think there will be any<lb/>
increase in trade to Key West from suspicious ports.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00822011"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>It would seem than that the only ports by which the intro-<lb/>
duction of yellow fever into Florida was at all threatened last<lb/>
year were Pensacola, Tampa and Key West, and in this order. If the<lb/>
opinion of Mr. <unclear>Ski<del>nner</del></unclear><add>ron</add>, above quoted, be correct, the difference<lb/>
in proportionate risk by the above three ports will be increased<lb/>
in 1920 and in the same order.</p>
<p>From some knowledge of the local conditions at the three<lb/>
ports mentioned, I believe measures to control the <unclear>Aedes</unclear> Calopus<lb/>
Mosquito (Yellow Fever Mosquito) would be very much more difficult<lb/>
and <unclear>expensive</unclear> in Key West than in either of the other places--it<lb/>
not, I think, having a piped water supply--and taking this into<lb/>
consideration together with the <unclear>lessened</unclear> risk at this place, I<lb/>
would recommend that in this work preference be given first to<lb/>
Pensacola and second to Tampa and Key West only in third place.<lb/>
This is for the purpose of getting a <hi>maximum amount of sanitary<lb/>
benefit per unit</hi> of <hi>expenditure</hi>. I would like to add that the con-<lb/>
trol of this mosquito, involving as it does the control of the<lb/>
other domestic species (Culex fatigans), in addition to the pro-<lb/>
tection given against yellow fever and dengue, will <hi>in any town<lb/>
with a piped water supply,</hi> pay in addition well over a hundred per-<lb/>
cent of the expenditure in increased comfort.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours respectfully,</salute>
<signed>H. R. Carter, M.D.<lb/>
United States Public Health Service</signed>.
HRC/B<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
