<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00822013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Louis L. Williams, Jr., to Henry Rose Carter, January 29, 1920</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Williams, Jr., Louis L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00822013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1920-01-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Charlottesville, Virginia</name>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1920-01-29">January 29, 1920</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00822013</idno>
<title>Letter from Louis L. Williams, Jr., to Henry Rose Carter, January 29, 1920</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Williams discusses the value of money in relation to the work in the Public Health Service.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1920-01-29">
<head>Letter from Louis L. Williams, Jr., to Henry Rose Carter, January 29, 1920</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00822013"/>
<opener>
L L Williams, Jr.<lb/>
P. A. Surg U.S. Public Health Service<lb/>
Miscl<lb/>
<del>Salaries</del><lb/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
ROOM 211<lb/>
289 MAIN ST.<lb/>
SPRINGFIELD, MASS.<lb/>
<dateline>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
<date value="1920-01-29">Jan. 29, 1920.</date>
</dateline>
<unclear>Regulation</unclear><lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter.</salute>
</opener>
<p>Altho my reply to your letter of Dec. 31, last, is<lb/>
somewhat delayed. I am none the less appreciative of the same. Your<lb/>
position is entirely clear; and, as usual, follow your ideals. I have<lb/>
always been glad of all oportunities to observe your method of<lb/>
thought and reasoning, and am not unmindful of the honor you do me<lb/>
in sending me your letter to Dr. Noland with comments. In the main<lb/>
I am compelled to agree with you, and to at least admit that on the<lb/>
bassis that you take that your reasoning is unassailable. You have<lb/>
ever held that, &ldquo;The work is the thing&rdquo;, and that all else should be<lb/>
subordinated to that end. True, and on that line of reasoning, it is<lb/>
unnecessary to pay large salaries to higher officers; they should do<lb/>
their work to their highest ability and not necessasarily expect to<lb/>
receive enormous salaries, a living wage only.</p>
<p>In my day in Charlottsville there was a shoe maker<lb/>
who did all the cobbling for the University students, whose name was<lb/>
Apple. He held a degree of B.A. from Yale, had fallen on hard times,<lb/>
become a shoe maker and somewhat of a philosepher----doubtless<lb/>
to fill up the tedium of his mechanical work, thought not being an<lb/>
essential in the fitting of a new sole. He was a very entertaining<lb/>
talker and we often listened to him discourse at length. Some of<lb/>
his sayings had a way of &ldquo;sticking&rdquo;. I can remember taking to him<lb/>
a shoe that needed one tack to hold a shoe plate that <del>aws</del> was falling<lb/>
off. Shoe makers do not usually charge for such small things. He<lb/>
charged me one cent, remarking with a smile. &ldquo;The laborer is worthy<lb/>
of his hire&rdquo;. He gravely handed me four cents from the nickle I handed<lb/>
him and resumed his work. The little quotation stuck. And this is,<lb/>
I think, a premise that you do not take into consideration at all.<lb/>
For the laborer <hi>is</hi> worthy of his hire and should be payed somewhat<lb/>
in accordance thereoff.</p>
<p>Of course the younger men of the Service need more<lb/>
pay---they are almost in want; I'm not so shure that many of the older<lb/>
men are not nearly as bad off. Consider my Dad for instance---he is<lb/>
in no sence a spendthrift; he sent his boys to college commencing in<lb/>
1907---to allow them to finish he had to borrow extensively--with<lb/>
the purchase of his last Liberty Bond in 1918 his assets (as represen-<lb/>
ted by these bonds) exceeded what he yet owed on his debts from our<lb/>
college days by only three hundred dollars---eleven years later!<lb/>
Should not a man who has attained the age sufficient to have grown<lb/>
children receive enough to enable him to educate them without having<lb/>
to go so extensively into debt. Have you any doubt that you could have<lb/>
gone with some large corporation and now be drawing in excess of<lb/>
twenty five thousand dollars a year---I have no doubt of it. The work<lb/>
you have done for this country in quarantine, in yellow fever, in malaria<lb/>
have been as valuable to the nation as an equal amount would have<lb/>
been to some private enterprise <add>&amp; more</add>, and they would have paid you many<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00822014"/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
times as much. Why should you maintain that you should not receive<lb/>
over five thousand because you can live on that sum instead of fifty<lb/>
thousand because you earn it? Is not the laborer worthy of his hire?"<lb/>
Suppose you had not been blessed with such a child as Laura is?<lb/>
Could you have afforded to hire (on your pay) a secretary? Without<lb/>
a secretary how much of your last ten years of writings could have<lb/>
been done? Even your modesty will not permitt you to think that<lb/>
these have not been of the greatest value. Had you been a lesser man<lb/>
cuold you have mantained the high rate of working production with all<lb/>
the family trouble that has been yours? Had your pay been double would<lb/>
it not have eased the path---cuold you not have attended to Edward<lb/>
without such a strain---would your mind not be easier in regard to<lb/>
what you could leave your daughter? If a man's mind is easy on his<lb/>
financial side his work is better (perhaps it ought not be affected,<lb/>
but it is). And so I most respectfully but firmly submit that I do<lb/>
truly believe that the laborer is indeed worthy of his hire and should<lb/>
receive a good proportion of it.</p>
<p>It also seems to me that one reason that we are loosing<lb/>
so many of our good men is that they see no very great monetary reward<lb/>
in the Service and cast their eye toward the industrial world. I do<lb/>
not mean by this that I think that the Service should offer twenty<lb/>
thousand dollar salaries, (some would earn them, many more would not),<lb/>
for a good man takes much of his remunaration not in money but in<lb/>
an increased oportunity to do his work in an ever widening field, and<lb/>
much of it in the realization of good work well done--and not a little<lb/>
of it in the doing of his work----never-the-less, he should not be<lb/>
expected to take too much of his reward in an internall feeling. Even<lb/>
the higher grades should receive much more than at present.</p>
<p>I do not believe that I have bored you for my statement<lb/>
has been frank and earnest. If you believe me to be too mercenary<lb/>
or otherwise missguided I know you will honor me by saying so and<lb/>
in taking the trouble to point out to me wherin and why you dissagree.</p>
<p>With affectionate regards to you and all the family from<lb/>
both Gertrude and myself I remain as ever</p>
<closer>
<salute>Your affectionate friend,</salute>
<signed>Louis L. Williams, Jr.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
