<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00907035">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, May 24, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00907035</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-05-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="person">Pareja, Wenceslao</name>
<name type="person">Spinden, Herbert Joseph</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Gorgas Memorial Institute (Panama)</name>
<name type="hospital">Santa Tomas Hospital (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-05-24">May 24, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00907035</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, May 24, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor comments on Hanson's and Pareja's work in Peru.  He also discusses issues related to yellow fever work in Mexico.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-05-24">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, May 24, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00907035"/>
<opener>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXACANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA DE MEXICO.<lb/>
____<lb/>
JEFATURA DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde; CONTRA<lb/>
LA FIEBRE AMARILLA EN YUCATAN.<lb/>
____<lb/>
MERIDA, YUC., MEX.<lb/>
R<lb/>
Connor<lb/>
<dateline>
Merida Yucatan Mexico.<lb/>
<date value="1921-05-24">May 24, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your welcome letter of May 3rd. to hand.<lb/>
I am indeed glad to know that Dr. Hanson will be able to give all<lb/>
his time to the problem. It was on this point that I had some<lb/>
fears when the outbreak was first announced and that you were coming<lb/>
home. Until your letter arrived I had been encouraging Dr. Rose to send<lb/>
some <add>one</add> down to work with Hanson. But now he will be able to train local<lb/>
men and to supervise their work with a frequency that will allow<lb/>
progress to be made.</p>
<p>On the last mail I received a letter from<lb/>
Dr. Pareja regarding his Bubonic problem. It seems to be upper-<lb/>
most in his mind. In reply I took advantage of the opportunity to<lb/>
encourage him once more to keep up his anti-larvae measures and I<lb/>
am hoping that he will do so. On the same mail there was a letter<lb/>
from Dr. Goding telling of your visit to him and he also mention-<lb/>
ed that Pareja was working hard and is making a good impression.</p>
<p>Enclosed you will find a copy of Dr.<lb/>
Villamil's artcile on yellow fever in which is mentioned the<lb/>
probable presence of yellow fever amongst the-older Mayan peoples.<lb/>
These references have been taken from the same source as those used<lb/>
by the Bishop Anco<unclear><add>a</add></unclear>-Carrillo and they are said to be authentic.</p>
<p>In Yucatan at the present moment there is a<lb/>
representative of the American Museum of Natural History, Dr. Spinden,<lb/>
and he is studying the ancient mayan civilization. I have discussed the<lb/>
matter of translation of the passages of the Codices Tizimin and he<lb/>
in turn submitted the question to Mr. Martinez, here in Merida, and<lb/>
an authority on Mayan History. Mr. Martinez says that the translation is<lb/>
in the main correct. He went on to state that the word translated from<lb/>
Mayan and used in English a BLACK should really read BLOOD in other words<lb/>
the Mayans did not used the equivilent of Black Vomit but BLOOD VOMIT.</p>
<p>To support your thought that yellow fever is of middle central american<lb/>
origin Dr. Spinden tells me that in his opinion there must have been<lb/>
a population of not less than 10,000,000 persons in the Peninsula and<lb/>
part of Guatamala. He has just returned from Quintana Roo and found<lb/>
there ruins larger than anything heretofore discovered in the Americas<lb/>
and he goes on to tell how these people secured their water from<lb/>
underground rivers which opened onto the surface at places and are<lb/>
called zenotes. This practice indicates quite clearly that the people<lb/>
were forced to conserve their home supply in conatiners which would<lb/>
make possible a large stegomyia population.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00907036"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA DE MEXICO.<lb/>
____<lb/>
JEFATURA DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde; CONTRA<lb/>
LA FIEBRE AMARILLA EN YUCATAN.<lb/>
____<lb/>
MERIDA, YUC., MEX.</p>
<p>Dr. Spinden is interested in the subject which we<lb/>
have been discussing for the reason that it may throw<lb/>
some light on the riddle of the disappearnce of the<lb/>
old Mayan civilization, and I have taken the liberty to<lb/>
suggest to him that on his return to Washington to con-<lb/>
sult you and he has made a note of your address.</p>
<p>Chalmers and Castellani mention the fact that the<lb/>
first yellow fever to be reported from Mexico was in<lb/>
1509 and occured at Vera Cruz. They do not give their<lb/>
references for this statement. Do you regard this<lb/>
as true?</p>
<p>A recent cable note states that Santa Tomas Hospital in Panama<lb/>
is to form the nucleus of the Gorgas Memorial Institute in which<lb/>
Tropical diseases will be studied and that the Rockefell Foundation<lb/>
would give encouragement. I am glad that there is to be this<lb/>
memorial to the General and wish for it every measure of success,<lb/>
but the thought keeps coming up as to whether Panama is the<lb/>
place to study tropical diseases. Would it not be wise to in-<lb/>
clude in the program the taking over of the sanitation of the<lb/>
cities of Panama and Colon and there to put in practice the<lb/>
<unclear>prinicipals</unclear> of co-operation in the prevention of diseases?</p>
<p>During your time in Panama we were formulating a plan with this<lb/>
in view, but somehow it was lost in the strife that followed.<lb/>
On my recent<del>s</del> visits to the Isthmus I could not help but be im-<lb/>
pressed with the wonderful opportunity that presents itself and<lb/>
how the present administration is letting it slip by. Their<lb/>
thought seems to be that by placing a large enough fine on the<lb/>
ignorant people that the principals of hygiene can be driven<lb/>
home and made effective.</p>
<p><unclear>Under</unclear> an organization that understands co-operation and has had<lb/>
experience in placing the principals before the people in<lb/>
such a manner that they can grasp the import, there can be built<lb/>
up a workable plan that all Latin America will be glad to<lb/>
adopt. The Government of Panama undoubtedly would be pleased to<lb/>
enter into such an arrangement.</p>
<p>There could be started in the schools, from the first grade on,<lb/>
a course in hygiene, elementary biology etc., that would be models<lb/>
for all other schools.</p>
<p>You will be glad to know that our road here is opening up<lb/>
with increasing clearness and that the public are responding to<lb/>
the work with a spirit of goodwill which at first I did not ex-<lb/>
pect to find as judged from the stories we heard before coming<lb/>
here. They like the fish and really the fish helps to make<lb/>
their stored cistern water more palatable and for this alone<lb/>
they are pleased.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With sincere good wishes, I am,</salute>
<signed>M E Connor</signed>-
<unclear>Labi</unclear> - Mr. Martinez has promised to look further into<lb/>
the Books of <unclear>Chumayel</unclear> and Lezinin and will advise-<lb/>
<unclear>over</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00907037"/>
<unclear>B22</unclear><lb/>
when you have the time will you out-<lb/>
line for me a plan that I could give Mr.<lb/>
Martinez so that he will not get off the trail<lb/>
two far - some essential points. that I<lb/>
should encourage him to hunt for.<lb/>
<unclear>yr.</unclear><lb/>
M E Connor<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
