<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00907029">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Wickliffe Rose, May 14, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00907029</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-05-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Noble, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-05-14">May 14, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00907029</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Wickliffe Rose, May 14, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter believes that yellow fever is still present in Africa.  Carter would be willing to go to Africa as an adviser if he is physically able.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-05-14">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Wickliffe Rose, May 14, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00907029"/>
<opener>
/LC<lb/>
R<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1921-05-14">May 14, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Africa<lb/>
Dr. Wickliffe Rose, General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway,<lb/>
New York, N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have been thinking about the African situation:</p>
<p>1/ In spite of no cases having been reported since 1919, it<lb/>
is very improbable that yellow fever has ceased to exist in Africa.</p>
<p>2/ Because of the fact that no cases have been reported since<lb/>
1919 it is equally improbable that it has not undergone considera-<lb/>
ble diminution from what existed during the years covered by the<lb/>
reports of the British West African Yellow Fever Commission--doubt-<lb/>
less due to the causes enumerated by Noble and Guiteras.</p>
<p>3/ These postulates taken together indicate the present as a<lb/>
time of election for a campaign for the elimination of yellow fever<lb/>
because (a) the work would now be most efficacious and (b) if not<lb/>
eliminated, or at least controlled<del>,</del> now, the accumulation of unac-<lb/>
climated people now going on, on the Coast especially (Noble) should<lb/>
lead to a decidedly wider spread of the fever than now exists.</p>
<p>You stated that personnel was lacking to initiate the African<lb/>
work, all available being needed for that going on in Mexico: Cen-<lb/>
tral America and Peru and for the protection of Guayaquil.</p>
<p>Admitting the impossibility of sending another Commission to<lb/>
Africa, could not the British local authorities be induced to take<lb/>
the one measure at once feasible and necessary for the elimination<lb/>
of yellow fever? It is this: To press a Stegomyia campaign in <hi>all<lb/>
large towns</hi> and in such smaller ones as (a) from their position or<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00907030"/>
2<lb/>
position or<lb/>
travel routes are especially liable to be sources of infection and<lb/>
(b) those in which susceptible people are apt to gather.</p>
<p>This should be done without regard to the existence of yellow<lb/>
fever at such places. If the Stegomyia in them can be so decreased<lb/>
that yellow fever will not propagate in them when introduced, I<lb/>
think we may safely trust it to eliminate itself spontaneously from<lb/>
the smaller places, or--at the worst--to smoulder along in such<lb/>
places until one has time to go after it.</p>
<p>Of course, the report of an outbreak in any small place should<lb/>
be the occasion for immediate Stegomyia control there and inspection<lb/>
of places in close communication therewith, but even without this<lb/>
(which is not really necessary) the method outlined will surely<lb/>
control--i. e. prevent, serious spread of-the fever and <add><unclear>not</unclear></add> probably eli-<lb/>
minate it.</p>
<p>The British local authorities can, I am sure, do this as well<lb/>
as anyone else; only it maybe that they have not thought of it. As<lb/>
I have outlined it, it is an entomological and administrative problem<lb/>
only and requires no experience with yellow fever. Should the local<lb/>
authorities then undertake this work I see no reason why they should<lb/>
not succeed in it without outside assistance.</p>
<p>If any be needed it would be minimal and I would be willing,<lb/>
and I believe able, to go and advise on such points as might be<lb/>
necessary, and I must confess that there are some few points--and<lb/>
important ones--in the control of breeding not yet in any book I<lb/>
have seen. I would not have to do any field work, but simply ad-<lb/>
vise as to the work to be done and especially as to <hi>how</hi> it should<lb/>
be done. Also, I would be available as a clinician for the diagno-<lb/>
sis of doubtful cases--some of which are impossible of diagnosis.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00907031"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Whether if this suggestion were made to them the local author-<lb/>
ities would undertaken this work, I do not know. If you think they<lb/>
would, it might be advisable to suggest it to them.</p>
<p>The above is primarily a suggestion as to how this work may<lb/>
possibly be done without interfering with the American work, which<lb/>
unquestionably should have precedence.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Assistant Surgeon General</signed>.
May 15, 1921.<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. Whether I would be physically capable of undertaking the<lb/>
work above outlined for myself--which is not hard work--may be a<lb/>
question, and whether, if I am, I could not be better utilized in<lb/>
Peru is another question.<lb/>
For the first, I am going into hospital within a few days<lb/>
for physical examination to get an opinion on my condition--which,<lb/>
frankly, does not seem as good as on arrival. Am not quite used<lb/>
to civilization again, I think.<lb/>
For the second, <hi>you</hi> must judge.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
