<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00907034">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, May 20, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00907034</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-05-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Wrightson, William D.</name>
<name type="person">Corrigan, John P.</name>
<name type="person">Pickett, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Mendoza, Ricardo</name>
<name type="person">Machado, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Ramirez, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Cardenas, Raul de</name>
<name type="person">Seeley, Morris Monroe</name>
<name type="person">Reyes, Jorge</name>
<name type="person">Richardson, George O.</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Libertad (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Pacasmayo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Callao (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-05-20">May 20, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00907034</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, May 20, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson reports on yellow fever work in Peru and comments on his employees, interpersonal issues, funding, and problems with steamship companies.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-05-20">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, May 20, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00907034"/>
<opener>
Ministerio de Fomento<lb/>
---------<lb/>
DIRECCION DE SALUBRIDAD <unclear>P&Uacute;BLICA</unclear><lb/>
---------<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru. <date value="1921-05-20">May 20, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Some time ago I wrote you about the organization here<lb/>
etc. Now in order to give you an idea of how things are going I am going to send<lb/>
you copies of my last letters to the Salubridad and to The International Health<lb/>
Board. As you will see the fever has presented itself in Trujillp, and other<lb/>
points in the Department of Libertad. This has not been on account of lack of<lb/>
efficiency in the work of Dr. Mendoza in the Province of Pacasmayo, but due to<lb/>
the inefficiency of the cordon and the lack of efficient work in Trujillo. As is<lb/>
always the case when you intrust a thing of this kind to people who have had no<lb/>
previous experience they simply do not know how to do, or how important it is.</p>
<p>Mr. Rose notified me that Corrigan and Pickett were coming, which sure<lb/>
is a good thing. They will furnish just the extra supervision needed for Libertad.<lb/>
Seeley is working hard here and I think he will make good. I am surprised though<lb/>
to nitice that he has a great deal more difficulty with the language than I ex-<lb/>
pected that he would have.</p>
<p>In regard to Seeley I wish you would let me know just what the agreement<lb/>
was which you made with him, in regard to salary. He seems to have the impression<lb/>
that he is to have the same rate that Corrigan and Pickett had last year. While I<lb/>
think he will make good I do not think that he is in the same class as the other<lb/>
two. He seems to be thoroughly impressed with the size of the job which we have<lb/>
before us.</p>
<p>In Libertad I have both Machado and Ramirez, Richardson was left in<lb/>
Callao to help Wrightson there. By the way I suppose you have heard that Wright-<lb/>
son has been named in place of Cardenas, and I am glad of it. Old Cardenas was<lb/>
trying to queer my game right up to <unclear>h</unclear> the last, but it seems the Minister of<lb/>
Fomento and Wrightson kept him from doing it, according to what Ramirez said.<lb/>
It seems the President has given pretty strict orders for them to attend to my<lb/>
requests. Still there a few matters which I may not be able to settle without<lb/>
personally going to Lima. If I can get a boat so as not to be gone to long I<lb/>
shall go to Lima after I have gone over the work with Corrigan and Pickett in<lb/>
Libertad and have otulined where and what they are to do.</p>
<p>When I <unclear>wnent</unclear> to Trujillo I took Reyes with me. He has developed wonder-<lb/>
fully, and I am not so sure but what he is the best of the whole bunch at the<lb/>
present time. I have used him as general supervising inspector before Seeley<lb/>
came, and with very good results.</p>
<p>I am still having difficulties with the steamship companies, they<lb/>
have adopted a ridiculous <unclear>proceedure</unclear>, refusing even to stop to either take or<lb/>
discharge mail or freight. There is no logical basis for that kind of a pro-<lb/>
<unclear>ceedure</unclear>, and is the means of causing a lot of <unclear>predjudice</unclear> against the campaign.</p>
<p>From Mr. Rose's letter I notice that you have had a conference with<lb/>
him. So far I have only received Lp 1000.0.00 from the Government for the work<lb/>
in this Department, and have paid all the expenses of the Pacasmayo campaign<lb/>
with the Rockefeller funds.</p>
<p>Wit all kinds of good wishes (and kindly <unclear>introduce</unclear> me to Laura)</p>
<closer>
<salute>Your <unclear>sincere</unclear> friend and admirer,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
<seg>
Ps.<lb/>
Martha complains that Daddy does not come home. She tells the people in the<lb/>
Hotel she is going to take a big boat and go see Daddy.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
