<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00903014">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, March 17, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00903014</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-03-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Quiroz, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Cayalti (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Sana (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Chongoyape (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Libertad (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Gudelupe (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Chepen (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Pacasmayo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Paita (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-03-17">March 17, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00903014</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, March 17, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson reports on a yellow fever epidemic in Peru. The local newspaper is publishing articles denouncing his sanitary campaign.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-03-17">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, March 17, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00903014"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION<lb/>
DE LA<lb/>
CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
____<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
Report<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo <date value="1921-05-17">March 17, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Asst Surgeon General, U.S.P.H.S.,<lb/>
Wahington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am addressing you at Washington as I forget<lb/>
to ask you where your addres would be but am sure that you will get<lb/>
your maik in this manner.</p>
<p>I am very busy rearranging the office and getting a lineup<lb/>
on the distribution of the forces. I hope by the end of this week that<lb/>
I will have things running on a more efficient basis. There has been<lb/>
considerable lack of judgement in the distribution of the forces.<lb/>
The work itself has been fairly well done as the stegomyia index is<lb/>
very considerably reduced. In Chiclayo it seems to be down to about<lb/>
5% at the present time, and there are very few cases which can be<lb/>
charged up to Chiclayo itself. However we have several cases on hand<lb/>
now. I have done two autopsies since arriving. One a case which died<lb/>
in the forth day of illness and the other after six days, both of<lb/>
which gave sufficient post mortem evidence.</p>
<p>The epidemic is spreading east and south, and I am rather<lb/>
worried, especially because I listened to Quiroz when we left, and<lb/>
did not take Mendoza with us at the time. I have practically certain<lb/>
evidence that the epidemic is in <unclear>Cayalt&iacute;</unclear> and Sa&ntilde;a. I have sent<lb/>
Quiroz there to investigate. The old Doctor there has made several<lb/>
diagnoses of &ldquo;fiebre biliosa hemoglobinurica&rdquo; which to me means noth-<lb/>
ing less than yellow fever. More he has treated several of these<lb/>
cases with hypos of quinine with the result that those so treated<lb/>
have promptly turned over and died. Yellow fever has also appeared<lb/>
in Chongoyape, which is due east from here, but of very little im-<lb/>
portance as far as Libertad is concerned.</p>
<p>Mendoza and Sainz are still waiting in the port of Pimentel<lb/>
for steamer to go south. It is most fortunate that I did not go on<lb/>
to Paita, because I probably should not have been back yet.</p>
<p>Valdevieso reports that he has commenced work in Guadelupe<lb/>
and Chep&eacute;n. Dr. Cavassa of Guadelupe also reports activity, and I<lb/>
hope they make it very active. Benites has been ordered to Pacasmayo<lb/>
and Reyes to Cayalt&iacute; for the time being. I think I will transfer <unclear>himo</unclear><lb/>
Pacasmayo as soon as the other two inspectors arrive from Piura. I<lb/>
Have also called Juan E. Adrienzen and Joaquin Castillo. I think it<lb/>
would be a very good thing to have one or possibly two of the Canal<lb/>
Inspectors, or men with equal aptitude for learning this line of work</p>
<p>The daily, &ldquo;El Pais&rdquo; is carrying on a most vicious propaganda<lb/>
against the sanitary campaign. For sensible people it should be with-<lb/>
out effect. Unfortunately here there are a lot of people who follow<lb/>
these ridiculous articles like a dog in a leash, and make things<lb/>
decidedly difficult for the Doctors and the Inspectors and Visitadors</p>
<p>I have been very well impressed with some of the local men who<lb/>
are working here. With proper supervision I think we have the material<lb/>
for developing several very good men here and hope in the final peri-<lb/>
od of the campaign to have several dependable men with which to clean<lb/>
up.</p>
<p>I think I will request the Prefecto to put a stop to the nonsene<lb/>
in the newspapers.</p>
<p>Hoping that you are having a pleasant trip and that you are<lb/>
better in health.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely and cordially</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
