<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00910001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from L.M. Fisher to Henry Rose Carter, June 20, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Fisher, L.M.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00910001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-06-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Griffitts, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Wateree River, Fairfield County (S.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-06-20">June 20, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00910001</idno>
<title>Letter from L.M. Fisher to Henry Rose Carter, June 20, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fisher reports on the malaria situation in South Carolina.  He discusses his malaria control work funded by the Rockefeller Foundation.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-06-20">
<head>Letter from L.M. Fisher to Henry Rose Carter, June 20, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00910001"/>
<opener>
L. M. FISHER<lb/>
ASSOCIATE SANITARY ENGINEER<lb/>
U. S. P. H. S.<lb/>
DIRECTOR<lb/>
State Board of Health<lb/>
of South Carolina<lb/>
DIVISION OF MALARIA CONTROL<lb/>
Executive Committee<lb/>
ROBERT WILSON, JR., M. D., CHM., CHARLESTON<lb/>
R. A. MARSH, M. D. " " " EDGEFIELD<lb/>
C. C. CAMPBELL, M. D. " " ASHEVILLE<lb/>
E. A. HINES, M. D. " " " " SENECA<lb/>
W. J. SURDELL, M. D. " " " LUGOFF<lb/>
WM. EGLESTON, M. D. " " HARTSVILLE<lb/>
W. W. <unclear>DODSON</unclear>, PH. D. " " GREENVILLE<lb/>
W. M. LESTER, M. D. " " " COLUMBIA<lb/>
S. M. WOLFE, ATTY GEN. " " COLUMBIA<lb/>
W. V. SUTHERLAND, COMP. GEN. " COLUMBIA<lb/>
---------<lb/>
JAMES A. HAYNE, M. D.<lb/>
SECRETARY AND STATE HEALTH OFFICER<lb/>
<dateline>
COLUMBIA <date value="1921-06-20">June 20, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H. R. Carter, Asst. Surgeon General<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service<lb/>
2121 California Avenue, N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Complying with your letter of a few days<lb/>
ago, I am sending you a copy of my letter of June 2nd<lb/>
which contains figures with reference to malaria pre-<lb/>
valence along Wateree river, in Fairfield County.<lb/>
Since writing you, we took a census of some fifty houses<lb/>
further away from the river toward Ridgeway, and find<lb/>
the following results:</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="3">
<row>
<cell>YEAR</cell><cell>POPULATION</cell><cell>NO. CASES</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1919</cell><cell>254</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1920</cell><cell>263</cell><cell>3</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1921</cell><cell>276</cell><cell>5</cell></row></table></p>
<p>We took this second census in a section<lb/>
of the country where we believe the river could not have<lb/>
effected the malaria rate. This gives us a control, and<lb/>
when the two groups are compared it leads one to infer<lb/>
that the pond may have effected the occurence of malaria<lb/>
to a greater distance than has been considered likely<lb/>
heretofore. Both censuses were taken by the same person<lb/>
in the same way.</p>
<p>At the request of the Power Company, I<lb/>
recently made a trip to the pond and found practically<lb/>
no breeding at the present time. The pond is about<lb/>
seven feet below the crest of the dam. The water is all<lb/>
drawn out of the shallows and the edges are clean. I<lb/>
could see very few top minnows. I imagine that many of them<lb/>
have been eaten by game fish, since there does not appear to<lb/>
be much protection for them. The timber has been cut out<lb/>
of the pond, with the exception a small strip in<lb/>
Dutchman creek, up to the high water mark. The pond no<lb/>
doubt looks entirely different when it is full, and the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00910002"/>
-2-<lb/>
gage readings at the Power houses show that from about<lb/>
July 20th on, the pond was full until about the twelth of<lb/>
October. At times, from two to four feet of water passed<lb/>
over the crest of the dam for days at a time.</p>
<p>I have not made any recommendations to the<lb/>
Company as to what should be done. This Power project is<lb/>
a particular favorite with Mr. Duke who owns the Southern<lb/>
Power Company. Men from all over the world come to visit<lb/>
the plant. The Company is proud of it and the way it is<lb/>
operated, and wants to feel just as proud of the way they<lb/>
handle the malaria problem as they are of the other<lb/>
features. They want to employ a man to do this work. I<lb/>
had in mind suggesting to them that a number of fish<lb/>
hatcheries be established just a little below high water<lb/>
mark; so that when the pond rises, these little hatcheries<lb/>
will be flooded out and the top minnows can scatter all<lb/>
through the shallow portion of the pond. When the pond<lb/>
goes down, the hatcheries should be cleaned of game<lb/>
fish and restocked with minnows. Possibly by employing a<lb/>
small force of men the fish could be given enough assist-<lb/>
ance to effect a pretty high degree of control. Mr. Duke<lb/>
has built a fine road from Great Falls to Wateree, thirty<lb/>
six miles along the pond. The Great Falls Farm Company<lb/>
a subsidiary of the Southern Power Company, is planning to<lb/>
build about fifty houses for a Farming colony this year,<lb/>
the contract already having been le<del>f</del>t. The plan is to<lb/>
develope the agricultural possibilities along the pond.<lb/>
The land is owned by the Company for a distance of approxi-<lb/>
mately one mile from the high water mark.</p>
<p>With reference to the situation at Chester,<lb/>
the pond Griffith referred to is a swimming pond about six<lb/>
miles from the town. The owner permits no fishing at all.<lb/>
He lives at the pond which is only about one-half mile<lb/>
in diameter and is well stocked with fish. We examined<lb/>
it on several occasions during the summer, and found very<lb/>
few larvae, and I think there was very little if any pro-<lb/>
duction. He also operates a small grist mill which gives<lb/>
a beneficial fluctuation in the water level. We carefully<lb/>
went over our records and eliminated all the cases which<lb/>
might have been typhoid.</p>
<p>Replying to your inquiry as to what I am doing<lb/>
in this state, I am directing the cooperative malaria<lb/>
control demonstration work, and am trying to build up a<lb/>
division of malaria control in the State Board of Health,<lb/>
for which purposes the Rockefeller people gave us $5,000<lb/>
in addition to the money appropriated for demonstration<lb/>
work. It was in connection with the latter feature of<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00910003"/>
-3-<lb/>
the work, that I became involved in the Wateree pond<lb/>
project, since a large number of complaints were received<lb/>
by the State Board of Health with reference to the amount<lb/>
of malaria prevailing along the river.</p>
<p>I am training two young men who graduated last<lb/>
year, and expect to add another one to our force before<lb/>
long. We are looking after the maintenance work at Bam-<lb/>
berg, Chester and Hartsville, and are working at the<lb/>
towns of Fairfax and Beaufort. I think we will be able<lb/>
to induce one or two other towns to take up the work<lb/>
sometime during the summer.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours</salute>
<signed>L.M. Fisher<lb/>
Associate Sanitary Engineer</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
