<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00915030">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Florence M. Read, September 17, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00915030</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-09-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Read, Florence M.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Chiclayo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-09-17">September 17, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00915030</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Florence M. Read, September 17, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson thanks Read for mail and the ruling regarding pay for campaign employees.  He describes the difficulties doing field work during a workers' strike. He discusses reassignment of investigators to Panama.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-09-17">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Florence M. Read, September 17, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00915030"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION<lb/>
DE LA<lb/>
CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EL LOS DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
---<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----<lb/>
<dateline>
Trujillo,<lb/>
<date value="1921-09-17">September, 17, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Miss Florence M. Read,<lb/>
Assistant Secretary,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York City,<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Miss Read:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I thank for Your letter in regard to my cable from Panama<lb/>
and the ruling in regard to the pay of the employees of the<lb/>
campaign, Before leaving Chiclayo I replied to several letters<lb/>
which had arrived during my absence, several of which were very<lb/>
much delayed, written in May and June etc., For instance<lb/>
since my arrival in Trujillo on the 15th of Sept. I have re-<lb/>
ceived a letter from Dr. Carter written on the 16th of May. No<lb/>
doubt Dr. Carter has wondered why I have not replied to this.</p>
<p>At present we are confronted with a rather annoying situ-<lb/>
ation here. There is a general strike on in the entire Province<lb/>
of Trujillo, as a results of which everything is tied up. There<lb/>
are no trains running, none of the dock laborers are working,<lb/>
the jitney drivers have gone out in sympathy with the rest and<lb/>
we are practicably unable to move. The object of our coming<lb/>
down on this trip was to make certain of our conditions in this<lb/>
Province and the Department. I wanted Mr. Pickett and Mr. Dunn<lb/>
to go over all the places where we had been working to give a<lb/>
general report checking on the actual conditions of the day, but<lb/>
with this bolshiviki condition existing we are going to be very<lb/>
much handicapped in this frinal revision of Mr. Pickett's.</p>
<p>I had planned for Mr. Pickett to make a revision of all the<lb/>
work down as far as the territory where Mr. Corrigan has been<lb/>
working, but it appears doubt<del>e</del>ful that we shall be able to do<lb/>
much under the existing conditions. Fortunately we had this<lb/>
Department in such condition that we are not yet in any danger<lb/>
and if conditions can be partially normalized within the next<lb/>
week we shall still be safe. None of my forces have joined the<lb/>
sympathetic strike, but our restricted movements handicapps us.</p>
<p>My plans have been for Mr. Pickett and Mr. Corrigan to re-<lb/>
turn to their positions on the Canal Zone in the first part of<lb/>
October. By that time I think we will have things in very good<lb/>
conditions all along the coast. From that time on it will be a<lb/>
case of &ldquo;watchful waiting&rdquo;, and it seems from the general atti-<lb/>
tude of the people that it will be better not to attempt to con-<lb/>
tinue the campaign any longer than is ansolutely necessary to<lb/>
be certain of the results. By January we can speak more definitely<lb/>
in regard to this matter.</p>
<p>In this letter I am enclosing a lest of Physicians and others<lb/>
who I think may be interested in receiving a copy of the trans-<lb/>
lation of Dr. Carter's lectures on Yellow Fever. From Chiclayo<lb/>
I sent you a copy of the translation made by our Interpretor in<lb/>
Chiclayo. In the <unclear>list</unclear> to which I refer above, The address is<lb/>
given above and the names of the men to receive a reprint is g<lb/>
indicated below.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
