<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00916018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George Parker to Henry Rose Carter, October 29, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Parker, George</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00916018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-10-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Texas</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-10-29">October 29, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00916018</idno>
<title>Letter from George Parker to Henry Rose Carter, October 29, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Parker reports on a malaria survey in Texas.  He describes campaign details.  All towns show good results.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-10-29">
<head>Letter from George Parker to Henry Rose Carter, October 29, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00916018"/>
<opener>
Malaria<lb/>
Texas<lb/>
THE STATE OF TEXAS<lb/>
MANTON M. CARRICK, M. D., PRESIDENT<lb/>
AND STATE HEALTH OFFICER<lb/>
<dateline>
TEXAS<lb/>
STATE BOARD OF HEALTH<lb/>
AUSTIN. TEXAS<lb/>
Jacksonville, Texas,<lb/>
<date value="1921-10-29">October 29, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Asst. Surgeon General, U.S.P.H.S.,<lb/>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I know you will be interested to learn of a malaria<lb/>
survey that is now being made in Cherokee County, Texas. I am enclosing<lb/>
my campaign map that you might see the progress to date, etc. The cam-<lb/>
paign was started on Sept. 15th., right after school opened. It is ex-<lb/>
pected to visit each of the 71 school districts where a lecture is de-<lb/>
livered, in the language of those present, on how malaria is contracted,<lb/>
what it is, and what everyone can do to prevent it or keep well of it.<lb/>
Literature of various kinds is distributed among the school children,<lb/>
pertaining to malaria fever. A thick blood smear is taken of about 33<lb/>
per cent of all scholastics, and examined in the laboratory, provided for<lb/>
this purpose, for the malaria parasite. The County Red Cross Chapter<lb/>
appropriated $1,000.00 to conduct this survey, which goes toward paying<lb/>
the salary of a medical officer and supplies.</p>
<p>The results so far obtained are as follows:<lb/>
<table rows="3" cols="6">
<row>
<cell>Number<lb/>
Examined</cell><cell>Total giving<lb/>
malaria history<lb/>
last 2 years.</cell><cell>Per cent<lb/>
History</cell><cell>Total<lb/>
Positive<lb/>
Malaria</cell><cell>Per cent<lb/>
Positive<lb/>
Malaria</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1150</cell><cell>517</cell><cell>45%</cell><cell>414</cell><cell>36%</cell><cell>Represents areas in<lb/>
which no control work<lb/>
has been done.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>305</cell><cell>41</cell><cell>13%</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>Jacksonville, Texas.<lb/>
Two years control work.</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>All records are being kept by age, sex, color, number lectured, number of<lb/>
pieces of literature distributed, the topographical features of each district<lb/>
and its percentages, etc. Any information desired can be compiled from the<lb/>
records.</p>
<p>The Cotton Belt Ry. passes through the entire length of this<lb/>
county and Mr. Van Hovenberg is rendering assistance in ever way possible to<lb/>
help to success.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00916019"/>
<p>In the percentages given the histories may seem to be a little out of<lb/>
proportion in relation to the positive findings, but I feel that that<lb/>
can readily be accounted for. To be sure that we <unclear>get</unclear> only a malarial<lb/>
history nothing is accepted but a typical chill history. Amongst the<lb/>
smaller children this is likely to be given inaccurate but care is taken<lb/>
that it is in every way a malaria history. Then with the older people<lb/>
we have the chill <unclear>tonic</unclear> users, who at this time of year are using plenty<lb/>
of the tonic and do during the malaria season of each year; some also<lb/>
use quinine in a measure and do not chill. However, in every <unclear>case</unclear> but<lb/>
two so far, the young ring form of Schizont has been found in the<lb/>
positive cases that gave no history. Some few that have been followed<lb/>
up have even chilled for the first time after our findings, so we get<lb/>
some new cases with negative histories.</p>
<p>What all this work will lead to I do not know. Prospects<lb/>
for going on with cooperative malaria work seem small for this State<lb/>
just now. The Legislature made no appropriation to enable the State<lb/>
Board to expand or carry the entire burden. All of this, and other<lb/>
things too, make my continuing here very uncertain. However, my plan<lb/>
for this county's work is to provide all funds locally. I have in mind<lb/>
a $250,000.00 program, and so far it has been well received but could<lb/>
not be put over without a great deal of additional work. A yearly tax<lb/>
does not appeal to me as the logical way to start and continue a program<lb/>
of this nature, and as taxes are already considered high, and business<lb/>
depressed, such a measure could hardly be put across. Any way if it was<lb/>
there would always be the possibility <unclear>of its</unclear> being discontinued. So the<lb/>
$250,000.00 would be in a form of a bond issue, 30 or 40 years, and to<lb/>
conduct a five to ten years program. This would result in an easy tax<lb/>
and in advance could be shown how it would pay itself off long before the<lb/>
bonds had to be redeemed.</p>
<p>It is hoped that after the initial examination survey is<lb/>
made to revisit the districts and hold conferences with the parents who,<lb/>
by that time, will have disposed of their crops and have the time to devote<lb/>
to the issue. On this survey we will have the result of malaria infection<lb/>
in each district and be able to put forth convincing arguments. The rural<lb/>
cooperation has been excellent, and every school superintendent and civic<lb/>
organization in the county <unclear>are</unclear> ready to help get rid of malaria.</p>
<p>We are trying to induce each school to establish and<lb/>
maintain a Gambusia hatchery for their district, and while there are a<lb/>
number of ponds being prepared I can not say how successful it will be.</p>
<p>The unit work has moved along very well this year, all towns<lb/>
showing good results and bound to continue the work through years to follow.</p>
<p>I hope you will be at the Hot Springs conference next month.</p>
<p>With all good wishes,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>George Parker</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
