<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00916001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, October 6, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Caldwell, Bert W.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00916001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-10-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lyster, Theodore C.</name>
<name type="person">Connor, Michael E.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughn, Emmett I.</name>
<name type="place">Vera Cruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-10-06">October 6, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00916001</idno>
<title>Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, October 6, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Caldwell thanks Carter for his informative and invaluable lecture.  He reports on field work, problems with local customs, and migrant workers' susceptibility to yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-10-06">
<head>Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, October 6, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00916001"/>
<opener>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA.<lb/>
----<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
----<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
Teodoro C. Lyster.<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Angel Brioso Vasconcelos<lb/>
VOCALES:<lb/>
Dr. Enrique Osornio.<lb/>
Dr. Emmel I. Vaughn,<lb/>
Dr. Bert W. Caldwell,<lb/>
Dr. M. E. Connor.<lb/>
Dr. F. Castillo Najera.<lb/>
<hi>Caldwell</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Vera Cruz Mexico<lb/>
<date value="1921-10-06">October 6th, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter<lb/>
U.S.P.H. Service.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I want you to know how much benefit<lb/>
you have conferred upon the campaign for the control of<lb/>
Yellow Fever in Vera Cruz with you Lecture on "Yellow<lb/>
Fever: Sanitary Measures for it Prophylaxis and Control.<lb/>
I have read and re-read it with increasing interest and<lb/>
I have distributed it among my force as widely as pos-<lb/>
sible and have read it aloud to them on two occasions.</p>
<p>We have worked during the past year, with far<lb/>
more success than we had hoped for. Nature has favored<lb/>
us continually. The wet season held off a month longer<lb/>
than usual and the &ldquo;Northers&rdquo; arrived on time and with<lb/>
unuasual velocity. In the mid<del><unclear></unclear></del>st of the dangerous seas-<lb/>
on the water system of the city became crippled and<lb/>
tanks and other containers were emptied frequently.<lb/>
While the number of water containers were increased<lb/>
greatly, still the fact that they were emptied frequently helped us rather than<lb/>
impeded our work.</p>
<p>We find in our work here, that on a scale of 100, the value of<lb/>
emptying and cleaning the containers at each &ldquo;vuelta&rdquo; scores 55, the use of<lb/>
fish scores 35 and oiling and other measures including permanently sealing<lb/>
the container scores the other 10. Our sheet anchor is emptying and clean-<lb/>
ing the container.</p>
<p>Our breeding in Barrils covers 52 percent of our breeding<lb/>
places. Smaller containers <del>the other</del> 48; 1 1/2 per cent occurs in well and<lb/>
cisterns which are fortunately few in number<del>s</del> as compared with our total<lb/>
containers, and the breeding in tanks, usually placed <unclear>upon</unclear> the house tops, is<lb/>
negliglibe, and has never been greater than .59%.</p>
<p>One of our greatest troubles is the intensive breeding in<lb/>
the &ldquo;cineza&rdquo; water, water in which the housewife has deposited <del><unclear></unclear></del> ashes<lb/>
to &ldquo;break&rdquo; the water for laundry purposes. This seems to conflict with your<lb/>
statement that the stegomyia must have clean water to breed in. This water<lb/>
is frequently dirty, and at times very strong with the wood ash lye. It is<lb/>
usually contained in an &ldquo;ola&rdquo; of about five gallons capacity and in oil<lb/>
tins of the same capacity. The container is rarely emptied and cleansed. Al-<lb/>
ways a sufficient quantity of water remains to permit breeding. The house<lb/>
wife cannot easily cover the container, refuses to have the water emptied and<lb/>
will not go to the trouble of straining it and destroying the breeding focus.<lb/>
The intensity of the larval and pupal infestation is maximum. Mosquito larvae<lb/>
<unclear>thrive</unclear> in it. Fish placed in the container die <unclear>promptly</unclear> and so far I have<lb/>
found no satisfactory method of handling this class of container. I would be<lb/>
grateful for your suggestions.</p>
<p>One thing that enters largely into the distribution<lb/>
of the aedes calopus and the increased number of foci is the mechanical<lb/>
distribution of the larvae through carrying in containers from <unclear>insted</unclear> wells<lb/>
and cisterns. <add><unclear>or bani</unclear></add> In Tampico last week, I located a large open well in the<lb/>
centre of a patio which evidently supplied the people not only of that patio<lb/>
but of others remote, with potable water. This well was litterally alive with<lb/>
larvae, and while I was in the patio, nine water carriers came to the well<lb/>
and drew <del><unclear></unclear></del> water. In every container<del>s</del> were large numbers of pupa and<lb/>
larvae and these were being transported all over the neighborhood. Of course<lb/>
this particular well was cared for, but I am convinced that this method of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00916002"/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA.<lb/>
----<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
----<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
Teodoro C. Lyster.<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Angel Brioso Vasconcelos<lb/>
VOCALES:<lb/>
Dr. Enrique Osornio.<lb/>
Dr. Emmel I. Vaughn,<lb/>
Dr. Bert W. Caldwell,<lb/>
Dr. M. E. Connor.<lb/>
Dr. F. Castillo Najera.<lb/>
spreading foci of infestation is by no means negligible</p>
<p>So far we have been able to keep Vera Cruz free<lb/>
of yellow fever except those cases which have been sent<lb/>
from the outside, to the Spanish Beneficencia and to<lb/>
the Military Hospitals here. The troop movements have<lb/>
been frequent and have carried the infection with them.<lb/>
I believe that the final elimination of yellow fever<lb/>
in Mexico is in sight, but hardly within the time limit<lb/>
suggested in former years.</p>
<p>One of areas near Vera Cruz which seems to<lb/>
have carried the disease over from year to year, is<lb/>
responsible for the infection we have had since March<lb/>
1st. This are is along the Papolopam River. The<lb/>
area is fairly well populated. Several important <unclear>towns</unclear><lb/>
containing from ten to twelve thousand inhabitants lie<lb/>
along its course of some 90 miles, extending from Al-<lb/>
varado to the borders of Oaxaca. It is <unclear>also</unclear> ng this<lb/>
river that the best sugar &ldquo;ingenios&rdquo; are located, and each<lb/>
of them imports the bulk of its labor from the mountain<lb/>
-ous states, during the cane cutting season. As many as<lb/>
five thousand laborers come down yearly, with their<lb/>
families, to work in the sugar fields. The laborers are all non-immune and<lb/>
seem<del>s</del> very susceptible to the disease. I am told that in former years, 40%<lb/>
of this labor never returned to their homes but were stricken and died in<lb/>
this area. Lyceaga, probably the most efficient of the Mexican sanitarians,<lb/>
while he controlled Vera Cruz and the ports for several years, never seemed<lb/>
to be satisfied with conditions in this area.</p>
<p>Lyster has been over recently and is now engaged on<lb/>
the West Coast. He will be in New York before November first. Conner is down<lb/>
at Merida, which has been free from yellow fever for the entire year. Vaughn<lb/>
is in Guatemala. All of them are enjoying good health.</p>
<p>Mrs. Caldwell and my boy Henry have been with me for<lb/>
the past three months. Mrs. Caldwell particularly desires to be remembered to<lb/>
you and to Miss Carter.</p>
<p>I hope that you will be able to come down and look<lb/>
this work over. You advice and counsel would be invaluable. While I think we<lb/>
have made great progress during the past year, I am sure that there are many<lb/>
little holes in the work, which you could, &ldquo;chuck up,&rdquo; and hasten the success of<lb/>
the campaign greatly.</p>
<p>With every good wish, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Bert W. Caldwell</signed>.
Calle Constitucion No.13<lb/>
vera Cruz Mexico.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
