<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00915016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter, September 8, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00915016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-09-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hanson, Mrs.</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-09-08">September 8, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00915016</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter, September 8, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter recommends continuation of work. He requests to stay since he is the most qualified. He fears a yellow fever outbreak in Lima.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-09-08">
<head>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter, September 8, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00915016"/>
<opener>
Sept 8/21<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
Memorandum.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Referring to the last paragraph of Page 3 of your letter of Septem-<lb/>
ber 8th., and what follows, I would say</p>
<p>1/ There is no question but that the work should be continued<lb/>
until completed.</p>
<p>I think, I would feel reasonable sure, that if no fever shows<lb/>
by Jan. 1st. that it is over--provided, of course, that a fairly good<lb/>
medical inspection is kept up to that time in both the territory in<lb/>
which the fever existed and in that which was exposed to infection<lb/>
from that territory.</p>
<p>Still, I think both the Stegomyia control and medical inspection<lb/>
had best--ought to--be<del>--</del>kept up until the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>this</hi> hot season. Frank-<lb/>
ly, I would not feel safe unless this were done. You have had fever in<lb/>
many places and in many of them not enough to immunize the population.<lb/>
Likely enough it <hi>is</hi> now already eliminated and the risk after Dec. 31st.--<lb/>
none showing--will be small, yet in my judgement too great to take. I<lb/>
would strongly recommend then to continue Stegomyia control and medical<lb/>
inspection to the beginning of the next cold season. It is possibly un-<lb/>
necessary, but I don't think beyond the limits of reasonable insurance.</p>
<p>2/ You are clearly the agent best qualified to complete this work.<lb/>
No man as suitable as yourself is available. You have handled the situa-<lb/>
tion well: You know the whole of it, personal and local, but this doesn't<lb/>
admit of argument.</p>
<p>I know how you desire to get back to the States, but having stayed<lb/>
so long I judge you could stay to finish the job; and<unclear>,</unclear> maybe a smaller<lb/>
thing and yet worth consideration, it will add to your reputation to<lb/>
have completed the elimination--we trust the permanent elimination--of<lb/>
yellow fever from the Pacific Coast of South America--no small thing to<lb/>
claim, I should say.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00915017"/>
<p>should say<lb/>
-2-</p>
<p>3/ Either Trujillo or Lima would do for headquarters. I am in-<lb/>
clined to favor the former as more central, but there are some advant-<lb/>
ages in Lima. You could thus have Mrs. Hanson and the two youngest--<lb/>
Carl going to school in the U. S., as you suggested. You would not be<lb/>
much with them, but would see them, as Mrs. Carter used to say of me:<lb/>
&ldquo;Semi-occasionally.&rdquo;</p>
<p>You can't reasonably expect fever to develope in any part of Lam-<lb/>
bayeque north or east of Chiclayo and Lambayeque town--too well immu-<lb/>
nized. You would have to watch from, and including, Chiclayo to Lima.</p>
<p>Lima is almost the only place I fear after Dec. 31st.--the summer<lb/>
comes late in Lima. I don't think our Japanese from <unclear>Ferranape</unclear> infected<lb/>
Lima. If so, it should have showed by last April. Also, I <hi>think</hi> that<lb/>
a small amount of fever in Lima at the advent of the cold season would<lb/>
most likely die out. The last epidemic lasted through <hi>2</hi> cold seasons,<lb/>
but it was quite large before the cold season began. If it be in Lima<lb/>
now, as everyone has yellow fever in mind, should it not show up by<lb/>
Jan. 1st? I take it for granted that Lima could not reasonably expect<lb/>
to get any from the North after--say--Sept. 15th.</p>
<p>H. R. Carter</p>
<p>one reason for making its headquarters</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
