<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00914002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report on mosquito control work in South Carolina, by [F.M. Boldridge], August 25, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00914002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-08-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Fisher, L.M.</name>
<name type="place">Wateree River, Fairfield County (S.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>22 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-08-25">August 25, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00914002</idno>
<title>Report on mosquito control work in South Carolina, by [F.M. Boldridge], August 25, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Boldridge's] report on a mosquito survey in South Carolina includes interviews with locals regarding mosquitoes, and information on the incidence of malaria and mosquito control measures.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-08-25">
<head>Report on mosquito control work in South Carolina, by [F.M. Boldridge], August 25, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00914002"/>
<p>AUGUST 25th 1921.</p>
<p>In compliance with telephonic instructions of August 24th-21 from<lb/>
Mr J. V. Sutton, Chief Claim Agent, Southern Power Company, I pro-<lb/>
ceeded on the morning of August 25th-21 to Roch Hill, S.C., where<lb/>
I joined him and proceeded by automobile to Wateree, S.C., The entire<lb/>
trip was spent in a general conversation concerning the situation<lb/>
now in question.</p>
<p>When within two miles of the Wateree Power Plant we met Dr. H.R. Carter<lb/>
and Captain L.M. Fisher, U.S.P.H.S., and after a short conference we<lb/>
decided to examine the streams crossing the main highway between Wateree<lb/>
Dam and Colonels Creek.</p>
<p><hi>FINDINGS ON STREAM # 1.</hi></p>
<p>Careful examination of this stream revealed the fact that there was<lb/>
more or less breeding of ANOPHELES on both sides of the highway. This<lb/>
stream seems deep-seated in places and rather shallow in others. Does<lb/>
not flow freely, but stands in pools. Banks of stream, grassy, and an<lb/>
abundance of trash, leaves etc, found in each of these pools. Several<lb/>
pools seemed well stocked with gambusia or top feeding minnows, while<lb/>
others showed none. <hi>BREEDING FREELY.</hi></p>
<p><hi>FINDINGS ON STREAM # 2.</hi></p>
<p>This stream is narrow and deep seated, containing but little water at<lb/>
time of examination. Water standing in pools, no running water. Banks<lb/>
of pools grassy and plenty of leaves, debris <unclear>etc</unclear> along banks. Breeding<lb/>
in this stream was not as large as No. 1, but still breeding freely.<lb/>
<hi>BREEDING FREELY.</hi></p>
<p><hi>FINDINGS ON STREAM # 3.</hi></p>
<p>This stream was found to be in much better condition than either No. 1,<lb/>
or No. 2. Water seemed to be flowing freely and stream well stocked<lb/>
with gambusia or top feeding minnows. We found breeding in a few small<lb/>
side pools and around some logs in stream. We examined this stream from<lb/>
the public highway down to the backwaters of the pond. Found some few<lb/>
breeding the entire distance. <hi>BREEDING FREELY.</hi></p>
<p><hi>FINDINGS ON STREAM # 4.</hi></p>
<p>This stream was not flowing, but standing in pit holes all along the<lb/>
channel of stream. No gambusia found in any of these pools. Each pool<lb/>
well filled with leaves and other debris. Each pool examined showed<lb/>
profuse breeding.</p>
<p><hi>PROFUSE BREEDING.</hi></p>
<p>BINDINGS ON STREAM # 5.</p>
<p>This stream seemed to have a good supply of free running water, although<lb/>
it was pooled on both sides of the culbert which crosses the public<lb/>
highway. We found a great many gambusia in this stream, and the banks<lb/>
were fairly clean, however we found some breeding in places.</p>
<p><unclear>BREEDING FREELY</unclear></p>
<pb n="2" id="f00914003"/>
<p>2.</p>
<p>AUGUST 25th, cont'd.</p>
<p>FINDINGS ON STREAM # 6.</p>
<p>This stream while flowing freely, contained a great amount of leaves<lb/>
and other debris. We found stream breeding freely all along banks, and<lb/>
around debris in center of same. Found a great many gambusia or top<lb/>
feeding minnows in this stream, which probably accounts for same not<lb/>
breeding profusly, as this is an ideal breeding place.</p>
<p><hi>BREEDING FREELY.</hi></p>
<p>We secured several specimens from each of the above streams, which<lb/>
upon hatching prooved to be <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS.</hi></p>
<p>We also examined the house of Ira J. Bush, located on Company property<lb/>
about 150 yds from backwater of Colonels creek. Caught 9 adult <hi>ANOPHELES<lb/>
QUADRIMACULATUS</hi> in this house. The indications are that these mosquitoes<lb/>
came from the pond, although an examination of the pond at this point<lb/>
at a later date did not reveal breeding.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00914004"/>
<p><hi>WATEREE POND.</hi></p>
<p>AUGUST 30th-21.</p>
<p>This inspection of the Wateree pond was made August 30th-21. The pond<lb/>
was examined from the Wateree Power Plant up to and including Colonels<lb/>
Creek. At time of inspection no ANOPHELES were found to be breeding<lb/>
in the main body of water. We found that the main body of pond was<lb/>
fairly clear of logs and other debris. Crews of laborers were at work<lb/>
clearing up and burning logs and debris along banks.</p>
<p>We examined several inlets along main body and found no breeding. The<lb/>
wave action was found to be good all over the entire pond and extended<lb/>
well up in each bite or cove. The pond was low at time of inspection,<lb/>
and the elevations constantly changing.</p>
<p>It was reported that the weather has been unusually dry this season,<lb/>
and just how that would affect the production of ANOPHELES in the<lb/>
locality under consideration has not yet been determined, however I<lb/>
believe it would tend to lessen breeding.</p>
<p>The people living near the pond all report that mosquitoes were much<lb/>
more numerous during 1919 than <unclear>than</unclear> 1920, and a great many state that<lb/>
there were only a few mosquitoes until the pond was closed.</p>
<p>It should be mentioned, as I believe it is important, that each bite<lb/>
or cove seemed to be alive with gambusia or top feeding minnows, which<lb/>
probably played a great part in the destruction of ANOPHELES if there<lb/>
were any.</p>
<p>To what extent the pond produced ANOPHELES in the early summer and spring<lb/>
I am unable to say, but I can say that the pond was not producing<lb/>
ANOPHELES at time this inspection was made.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00914005"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
GLENN W RAGSDALE.</p>
<p>AUGUST 26th-21.</p>
<p>On Friday, Aug 26th 1921 we examined the property of Glenn W Ragsdale,<lb/>
which is about four (4) miles from the backwaters of Dutchmans creek.<lb/>
Caleb Jackson (col) is the tenant living on premises. This property<lb/>
has two streams on it, one about 400 yards from house and other about<lb/>
1/4 mile from house.</p>
<p>The stream about 1/4 mile from house was found to have a good supply<lb/>
of free running water in places, while it was pooled in others. We<lb/>
found several pools about twenty feet from this stream. These pools<lb/>
were all breeding profusly. The main stream was found to be breed-<lb/>
ing profusly in places and freely in others. This stream is filled<lb/>
with sand beds, and contains a large amount of leaves and other debris.<lb/>
Stream flows through a large heavily wooded bottom. Stream shows no<lb/>
signs of ever being affected by the backwaters from the main pond.<lb/>
Found large cottonwood trees, <unclear>blauk</unclear> gum trees, some oak trees and<lb/>
a great many large willow trees all along area of stream. Found<lb/>
few gambusia or top feeding minnows in main body of stream. Caught<lb/>
several adult <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS</hi> mosquitoes under the banks of<lb/>
stream and in old dead log.</p>
<p><hi>AREA BREEDING PROFUSLY.</hi></p>
<p>Examination of the stream 400 yards from house of Caleb Jackson,<lb/>
showed free breeding of <hi>ANOPHELES</hi>. This seems to be a wet weather<lb/>
stream, and was dried up except in a few pools. A great many half<lb/>
grown larvae were found in each of these pools, which were ideal<lb/>
breeding places.</p>
<p><hi>AREA BREEDING FREELY.</hi></p>
<p>We secured several specimens from each of the above places, which<lb/>
when hatched out prooved to be <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS.</hi></p>
<p>As far as I am able to judge these two streams are at present in<lb/>
their natural condition, and show no evidence of ever being affected<lb/>
by backwater from the main pond.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00914006"/>
<p><hi>2nd VISIT.</hi></p>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
GLENN W RAGSDALE.</p>
<p>AUGUST 30th-21.</p>
<p>On August 30th I again visited the Ragsdale place in company with<lb/>
Captain L.M. Fisher, U.S.P.H.S., and Drs. Hamilton, Dobson and Sanders.<lb/>
The conditions as shown in my report of August 26th were found to<lb/>
be exactly the same. Each member of the party was supplied with a<lb/>
dipper and allowed to dip where they pleased. All were convinced<lb/>
that this stream was breeding profusly, (that is the stream 1/4 mile<lb/>
from house) and that the stream about 400 yards from house was<lb/>
breeding freely.</p>
<p>The party caught about twenty adult <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS</hi> under the<lb/>
banks of the first stream examined.</p>
<p>None of this party seemed to think that the conditions showed any<lb/>
signs of backwaters of main pond, and in conversation with Dr. Sanders,<lb/>
who seemed to be familiar with <unclear>this in locality</unclear>, he stated that it had<lb/>
not been cultivated to his knowledge in recent years. (Of course this<lb/>
refers to the bottom land on stream).</p>
<p>The meadows around this property were allowed to grow up in grass, trees,<lb/>
and weeds, thus indicating periodically overflow.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f00914007"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
JOHN R. AND J.C. WHITAKER.</p>
<p><hi>1st VISIT.</hi></p>
<p>AUGUST 27th-21.</p>
<p>On Saturday August 27th-21, Dr. Carter and myself examined the property<lb/>
of John R. and J.C. Whitaker, which is located about 150 ft. N.E. of<lb/>
companies public road between Wateree and Great Falls, just above<lb/>
Miley's creek. The spring is about 250 yards from house. We found<lb/>
<hi>ANOPHELES</hi> breeding in the spring and in the spring branch. We also<lb/>
found <hi>ANOPHELES</hi> breeding freely in a branch which runs within about<lb/>
150 yards of house. Both of these branches are somewhat pooled in<lb/>
places and contain a great many leaves and other debris. John Whitaker<lb/>
was with us on this examination, and was shown the larvae as we caught<lb/>
them.</p>
<p>We also examined a barrow pit on the road just above Whitaker's house<lb/>
but did not find breeding. We recommended at the time to Mr Sutton<lb/>
that this pit be drained.</p>
<p>We followed the stream from Whitaker's place down to the pond. The<lb/>
main stream seemed to be fairly swift, and as it neared pond we found<lb/>
a great many gambusia or top feeding minnows. We examined the pond<lb/>
at this point but did not find breeding. The wave action was good at<lb/>
this point of pond. The pond in this area has a great many standing<lb/>
trees and a great many logs in main body.</p>
<p>At time of examination we found a crew of laborers at work cutting<lb/>
down and cleaning up this area of pond. The logs and debris collected<lb/>
by this crew was being burned.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f00914008"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
JOHN R. AND J.C. WHITAKER.</p>
<p><hi>2nd VISIT.</hi></p>
<p>AUGUST 30th-21.</p>
<p>On Tuesday August 30th-21 in company with Captain L.M. Fisher, U.S.P.H.S.,<lb/>
and Drs. Hamilton, Dobson and Sanders, we went over the entire area of<lb/>
the Whitaker place. We found the spring and both streams breeding as<lb/>
stated in report of visit on Aug 27th-21.</p>
<p>We examined the house and found 2 <hi>Quadrimaculatus</hi> in bedroom. We also<lb/>
found 2 <hi>Quadrimaculatus</hi> in stable near house.</p>
<p>We secured a number of larvae from <unclear>each</unclear> of these branches and the<lb/>
spring, which when hatched out proved to be <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS.</hi></p>
<p>We also caught eight adult <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS</hi> under the banks of<lb/>
the branch above spring.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f00914009"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
WILLIAM BELTON.</p>
<p>VISIT # 1.</p>
<p>AUGUST 29th-21.</p>
<p>On August 29th I examined the property of William Belton. The spring<lb/>
and spring branch is about 100 yards from the house occupied by Wm.<lb/>
Belton and family. William Belton accompanied us on this trip. He<lb/>
stated that he had never had mosquitoes until October 1919, and that<lb/>
<unclear>there</unclear> had been plenty of them ever since. He stated that he and his<lb/>
family had had malaria since June 1920.</p>
<p>Examination of the spring showed that it was breeding <hi>ANOPHELES</hi> freely,<lb/>
and that the spring branch was breeding profusly in places and freely<lb/>
in others. This branch seemed to have a good flow of water, but con-<lb/>
tained a good deal of rubbish, leaves, etc. There were small pools of<lb/>
water all along the main spring branch, all of which were breeding<lb/>
profusly.</p>
<p>We showed the living larvae to Belton, and I talked with him for some<lb/>
time concerning same. I told him that if he properly cleaned out this<lb/>
spring and spring branch that he would have no mosquitoes, and I showed<lb/>
him beyond a <unclear>shawer of</unclear> doubt that he was responsible for his family<lb/>
having malaria. He told me he was going to do as I had directed him.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f00914010"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
WILLIAM BELTON.</p>
<p>VISIT # <unclear>2.</unclear></p>
<p>AUGUST 30th-21.</p>
<p>On the afternoon of August 30th in company with Captain Fisher and Drs<lb/>
Hamilton, Dobson and Sanders, we visited the property of William Belton.<lb/>
We examined the house and out buildings for mosquitoes, but found none.<lb/>
We next examined the spring branch about 100 yards from house. Here we<lb/>
found Belton and a farm hand cleaning out spring and spring branch. We<lb/>
found some full grown larvae in places that they had not reached. The<lb/>
spring had been well cleaned out and we were not able to find any larvae<lb/>
in same. Found a good many full grown larvae in some hoof prints below<lb/>
spring.</p>
<p>This property is about 1 1/8 mile from the backwaters of Colonels creek.<lb/>
I had previously examined the pond or backwaters below Belton's property.<lb/>
I found no breeding in pond. Found some few half grown larvae in floatage<lb/>
of Dead water, these had probably been washed down from above. In the<lb/>
running water <unclear>form</unclear> the branch I found free breeding, and the higher up<lb/>
I went the more breeding I found.</p>
<p>The dead water contained many gambusia as did the main pond below. The<lb/>
branch contained much trash and rubish and seemed to be an ideal breed-<lb/>
ing place for <hi>ANOPHELES.</hi></p>
<p>At the point of entrance of this branch to the pond we found a crew of<lb/>
laborers clearing up and burning all trash, logs and other accumilated debris.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f00914011"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
GEORGE BELTON.</p>
<p>AUGUST 29th-21.</p>
<p>VISIT # 1.</p>
<p>On August 29th I examined the property of George Belton, which is<lb/>
said to be about 9/10 of a mile from the backwaters of Colonels<lb/>
Creek. Belton secures his water from a spring about 150 yards from<lb/>
house. Examination of this spring and spring branch showed both to<lb/>
be breeding <hi>ANOPHELES.</hi> The spring and spring branch is on the opposite<lb/>
side of house from pond. The branch does not flow freely, but stands<lb/>
in pools, each of which was found to be breeding freely at time of<lb/>
examination. No gambusia or top feeding minnows were found in this<lb/>
stream. I would term this area as a whole BREEDING PROFUSLY.</p>
<p>In a conversation with George Belton, whom we found working in a<lb/>
small blacksmith shop just in front of his house, he told me that<lb/>
he and his family all had malaria. That malaria had never been in<lb/>
his family until in October of 1919. That they had always had some<lb/>
few mosquitoes, but not so many as in the fall of 1919. That the<lb/>
mosquitoes were not so bad in 1920. That the first case of malaria<lb/>
in his family developed in November 1919, and whole family has been<lb/>
down with it at intervals ever since.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f00914012"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
GEORGE BELTON.</p>
<p>VISIT # 2.</p>
<p>AUGUST 30th-21.</p>
<p>On August 30th-21, in company with Captain L.M. Fisher, U.S.P.H.S.,<lb/>
and Drs. Hamilton, Dobson and Sanders we visited the property of<lb/>
George Belton.</p>
<p>We examined the spring and spring branch, which is about 150 yards from house on opposite side from pond.</p>
<p>This examination revealed the same facts as shown in report of<lb/>
visit on the day before.</p>
<p>Several specimens were secured, which when hatched out proved to<lb/>
be <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS.</hi></p>
<p>Several adult <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS</hi> were caught under banks of<lb/>
stream near spring.</p>
<p>Every member of this inspection party declared that this area<lb/>
was BREEDING PROFUSLY.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f00914013"/>
<p>EXAMINATION OF POND NEAR PROPERTY OF GEORGE BELTON.</p>
<p>COLONELS CREEK.</p>
<p>AUGUST 27th-21.</p>
<p>On the afternoon of August 27th-21 I examined the pond at the nearest<lb/>
point to the property of George Belton. Examined pond for about 1/2 mile?<lb/>
but found no breeding. Wave action good. Found schools of gambusia or<lb/>
top feeding minnows in pond and in branches flowing into pond. Examined<lb/>
the branch which flows from the Belton property. Found no breeding in<lb/>
same at this point. Current of branch swift, and banks fairly clear<lb/>
of vegetation.</p>
<p>At time of this examination I found a large crew of laborers cutting<lb/>
down dead trees in edges of pond and burning same.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f00914014"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
JOE BELL.</p>
<p>VISIT # 1.</p>
<p>AUGUST 29th-21.</p>
<p>On August 29th I examined the property of Joe Bell. The spring and<lb/>
spring branch is about 100 yards from house. The area of the spring<lb/>
is very swampy and at time of examination found many small pools of<lb/>
water along the spring branch, all of which were breeding ANOPHELES<lb/>
more or less freely. The spring branch was not flowing freely, but<lb/>
stood in pools, all of which were breeding <hi>ANOPHELES</hi> freely. This<lb/>
branch contained a great many leaves and other rubbish and was an<lb/>
ideal breeding place.</p>
<p>We secured several specimens of larvae, which when hatched out<lb/>
proved to be <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS.</hi></p>
<p>Caught several adult <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS</hi> under the banks around<lb/>
spring.</p>
<p>I examined this area thoroughly, and followed the spring branch down<lb/>
stream for about <unclear>1/2</unclear> mile and found free breeding all along same.</p>
<p>Area <hi>BREEDING PROFUSLY.</hi></p>
<pb n="14" id="f00914015"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
JOE BELL.</p>
<p>VISIT # 2.</p>
<p>AUGUST 30th-21.</p>
<p>On August 30th in company with Capt Fisher and Drs Dobson, Hamilton,<lb/>
and Sanders we visited the property of Joe Bell. We examined the house<lb/>
and outbuildings for mosquitoes but found none. We found one <hi>QUAD-<lb/>
RIMACULATUS</hi> and six <hi>PUNCTIPENNIS</hi> in buggy top in shed.</p>
<p>Examination of the spring and spring branch showed exactly the condition<lb/>
stated in Report 1 of Aug 29th-21.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f00914016"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
DAVIDSON ROBERTSON.</p>
<p>On August 29th I visited the property of Davidson Robertson. The house<lb/>
on this property is located about 200 yards from Penny Fork Branch<lb/>
and about 200 yards from Cotton House branch. Examination of both of<lb/>
these branches revealed the fact that they were both breeding ANOPHELES<lb/>
freely. The Penny Fork branch was breeding profusly in places. It stood<lb/>
in pools and at time of examination was not flowing freely. A great<lb/>
deal of trash and leaves was found in nearly all pools. Banks of stream<lb/>
were grassy, and the area of stream more or less swampy. The Cotton<lb/>
House branch was flowing freely at time of examination, and did not<lb/>
seem to be breeding as freely as the Penny Fork branch.</p>
<p>In conversation with Robertson, he told me that there were a great<lb/>
many mosquitoes in the fall of 1919, but had not had many this year.<lb/>
He stated that there were a great many mosquitoes in 1908. He stated<lb/>
that there had always been some malaria in that part of the country,<lb/>
but that his family had never had it until late in the fall of <unclear>1920</unclear>.</p>
<p>The branches named in Par 1 were examined for a distance of about<lb/>
1/4 mile from house. later on, and the same conditions found to exist.</p>
<pb n="16" id="f00914017"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
DAVIDSON ROBERTSON.</p>
<p>VISIT # 2.</p>
<p>AUGUST 30th-21.</p>
<p>On August 30th in company with Capt Fisher and Drs. Hamilton, Dobson<lb/>
and Sanders we visited the property of Davidson Robertson. We found<lb/>
the exact conditions existing as was reported on my first visit. We<lb/>
examined an outhouse for mosquitoes, but were unable to catch any, all<lb/>
though there were several in the house.</p>
<p>We found a small pool of water standing near the well in yard which<lb/>
contained a great many CULEX. Also found a rain barrel in rear of<lb/>
house <unclear>full</unclear> of culex.</p>
<p>Robertson stated that he had taken no precautions against mosquitoes,<lb/>
and did not even think it necessary to have his house screened.</p>
<pb n="17" id="f00914018"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
DAN MALONEY.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 14th-21.</p>
<p>On Wednesday September 14th-21, Dr. Carter and myself examined the<lb/>
property of Dan Maloney. This property is located about 1/2 mile from<lb/>
the backwaters of Dutchmans creek. We examined a <unclear>creak</unclear> or small branch<lb/>
about 1/4 mile from the old Maloney house and found free breeding of<lb/>
ANOPHELES. This stream seemed to have a good flow <unclear>od</unclear> water in places,<lb/>
and pooled in others. Stream bontained a large amount of trash and<lb/>
debris. Examined several pools near stream and found most of them<lb/>
breeding profusly.</p>
<p>We examined several pools between the above mentioned stream and the<lb/>
tenant houses and found all of them to be breeding profusly. These<lb/>
pools were in a large willow bottom which showed indications of being<lb/>
constantly wet. Most of these pools contained very little water at<lb/>
time of examination, but were ideal breeding places for ANOPHELES.</p>
<p>We termed this area as <hi>BREEDING PROFUSLY.</hi></p>
<pb n="18" id="f00914019"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
MAJOR BUSH.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 14th-21.</p>
<p>On Wednesday September 14th-21, Dr. Carter and myself examined the<lb/>
Major Bush property. We examined the spring and spring branch which<lb/>
is about 200 yards from the house occupied by Major Bush. We found<lb/>
no breeding in spring, but found spring branch breeding freely. The<lb/>
branch was grown up in weeds and grass and was an ideal breeding<lb/>
place for ANOPHELES.</p>
<p>We next examined the creek which flowed about tewnty feet from spring<lb/>
and into which the spring branch flowed. This stream was standing in<lb/>
pools, held by rockey ledges and contained an abundance of ANOPHELES.<lb/>
No gambusia were found in any of these pools.</p>
<p>Samples secured from several of the pools, and the <unclear>soring</unclear> branch hatched<lb/>
out <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS.</hi></p>
<p>As far as I am able to tell, I cannot see where the backwaters of the<lb/>
main pond can possibly affect this stream at this point. Stream shows<lb/>
no indications of being affected by backwaters.</p>
<pb n="19" id="f00914020"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
DAN JONES.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 12th-21.</p>
<p>On September 12th 1921, Drs Carter, McKaskill and myself examined<lb/>
the property of Dan Jones. We examined the spring and spring<lb/>
branch about 200 yards from house on main road near the sawmill.<lb/>
We found frofuse breeding of ANOPHELES in the spring and the<lb/>
spring branch. There were several pools of water along edges of<lb/>
spring branch that were breeding profusly.</p>
<p>We next examined the saw mill branch which is a part of the spring<lb/>
branch. This branch was breeding profusly. Several pools along<lb/>
edges of this branch were also breeding profusly.</p>
<p>We secured several specimens from the above areas, all of which<lb/>
hatched out <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS.</hi></p>
<p>I have never seen so small an area breeding more profusly than the<lb/>
above.</p>
<pb n="20" id="f00914021"/>
<p>PROPERTY<lb/>
OF<lb/>
DAN JONES.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 13th-21.</p>
<p>On September 13th-21, Drs. Carter, McKaskill and myself examined the<lb/>
property of Dan Jones near Beaver Creek. We examined an unoccupied<lb/>
house on a small knoll surrounded by water. We found no mosquitoes<lb/>
in house or barn. This house evidently has been unoccupied for some<lb/>
time. We examined the pond or backwaters and found no breeding. There<lb/>
was no water supply on this property, the spring evidently having<lb/>
been covered bu the backwater from the pond. The banks of pond<lb/>
were fairly clean. Pond had good wave action on all sides of this<lb/>
property. Pond contained a great many gambusia or top feeding <unclear>minnows</unclear>.</p>
<pb n="21" id="f00914022"/>
<p>HILTON PROPERTY.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 13th-21.</p>
<p>On September 13th-21, Drs. Carter, McKaskill and myself examined the<lb/>
property of Mr. Hilton. We examined Beaver Creek at a point about<lb/>
1/2 mile from the Hilton house. We found free breeding in the creek<lb/>
and profuse breeding in several pools standing near creek. The area<lb/>
of creek at this point is grown up in trees and bushes and shows no<lb/>
signs of cultivation. The bottoms along this creek are very marshy,<lb/>
and seem to be ideal breeding places for <hi>ANOPHELES.</hi></p>
<p>We took several specimens from different parts of creek, and several<lb/>
pools which hatched out <hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS.</hi></p>
<p>We examined the spring and spring branch about 150 yards from the<lb/>
Hilton house. We found free breeding in the spring branch, but no<lb/>
breeding in spring. The spring branch had been recently cleaned out<lb/>
and was probably breeding profusly prior to that time. The area of<lb/>
the spring and spring branch is extremely marshy and an ideal breeding<lb/>
place for ANOPHELES.</p>
<p>We took several specimens from spring branch which hatched out<lb/>
<hi>ANOPHELES PUNCTIPENNIS</hi>.</p>
<pb n="22" id="f00914023"/>
<p>BEAVER CREEK.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 13th-21.</p>
<p>On September 13th-21, Drs Carter, McKaskill and myself examined the<lb/>
area around and above the mouth of Beaver Creek, just below the<lb/>
Hilton Place. We found no breeding at the mouth. We found a few<lb/>
half grown larvae in the deadwater of creek. We examined the creek<lb/>
for about 3/4 mile from the mouth, and in several places found<lb/>
free breeding.</p>
<p>We found profuse breeding in several side pools of water. This area<lb/>
seems to be very marshy, and is grown up in swamp grass. It is an<lb/>
ideal breeding place for ANOPHELES.</p>
<p>The specimens secured from above places hatched out ANOPHELES<lb/>
PUNCTIPENNIS.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
