<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00917012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Lunsford D. Fricks, December 24, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00917012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-12-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Fricks, Lunsford D.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-12-24">December 24, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00917012</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Lunsford D. Fricks, December 24, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] does not see the need to write another systematic treatise on malaria control.  He suggests two different alternatives.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-12-24">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Lunsford D. Fricks, December 24, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00917012"/>
<opener>
N. M. C.<lb/>
<hi>Fricks</hi><lb/>
(Proposed publication.<lb/>
on Malaria)<lb/>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1921-12-24">December 24, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Fricks:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have looked over &ldquo;Milk.&rdquo; I have not seen Sherry. I do not<lb/>
think it advisable for the Malaria Division to attempt to write a<lb/>
book on Malaria of the <hi>same scope</hi> as &ldquo;Milk.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(1) The status of malaria at present is quite different from<lb/>
that of milk when the book in question was written (1908-09).</p>
<p>At that time, as far as I can judge by reading &ldquo;Milk,&rdquo; there<lb/>
was no fairly complete, systematic publication treating of milk.<lb/>
There was, indeed, a great mass of information, much of it valuable,<lb/>
in monographs-each on some phase, or phases, of the question.<lb/>
Bringing this data together--coordinating and digesting it and mak-<lb/>
ing it available in one publication was very desireable.</p>
<p>This is not true of malaria. First consider its medical as-<lb/>
pect: I do not know if there has been enough added--on the <hi>purely<lb/>
medical aspect</hi>--since the treatises of Craig and Deaderick to re-<lb/>
quire a new book. Even if these are a little out of date, there are<lb/>
recent articles in several systems of medicine: In Woods (von Ez-<lb/>
dorf) about 1916: Tyce's (Bass I think) and the Nelson &ldquo;Loose-Leaf,&rdquo;<lb/>
both published since the war and the latter claiming to be kept up<lb/>
to date. James' &ldquo;Malaria at Home and Abroad&rdquo; is just out and &ldquo;The<lb/>
Practice of Medicine in the Tropics&rdquo; (Oxford Press) is now coming<lb/>
out with articles on malaria by Christophers: James: Parsons and<lb/>
John Thomson, <hi>each</hi> writing separately. Why they didn't get Stephens<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00917013"/>
2<lb/>
Stephens<lb/>
too and make a complete job of it, I don't know.</p>
<p>There seems then to be no lack of literature in <hi>book form</hi> on<lb/>
on malaria in its medical aspect. Absolutely up to date and a fair<lb/>
part of it American.</p>
<p>(2) I doubt if any of our men could write a better or more au-<lb/>
thoritative book on malaria than some of those available.</p>
<p>Frankly the, I think that for the Medical Aspect of Malaria,<lb/>
(1) there is no need for a better book than is now available and (2) if<lb/>
there is, we can't undertake to furnish it. We had best let that as-<lb/>
pect of malaria alone.</p>
<p>For the sanitary aspect conditions are somewhat different. There<lb/>
is really no book to be considered here but Ross' &ldquo;Prevention of Mal-<lb/>
aria.&rdquo; Unquestionably we can add to this--it dates from 1910 or '11--<lb/>
otherwise I doubt if we can improve on it. Certainly any systematic,<lb/>
basic treatise on this subject must duplicate much of Ross' material<lb/>
and the bulk of it is admirably presented.</p>
<p>I think then that there is little need of another systematic<lb/>
treatise on Malaria Control, basic and complete, as Milk was when<lb/>
written.</p>
<p>The following might be undertaken as an alternative, although I<lb/>
am not so sure that you are fixed just now to do it to the best ad-<lb/>
vantage:</p>
<p>We have, as have other men, added something to the knowledge of<lb/>
malaria control, since the publication of Ross' book, and this knowl-<lb/>
edge is not in convenient form.</p>
<p>1.</p>
<p>You might make up a small book composed of</p>
<p>(A) excerpts from published American work (1) from such Service: re-<lb/>
prints: bulletins etc. as show things of value for the U. S.:</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00917014"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>3</p>
<p>U. S.:</p>
<p>(2) similar excerpts from other U. S. workers (this is almost con-<lb/>
fined to Bass, but Van Dine: King and Freeborn also come in and possi-<lb/>
bly Thibault and Krauss. I don't think Dock has added anything re-<lb/>
cently, but am not sure.)</p>
<p>(B) Similar excerpts from foreign sources of such things as seem<lb/>
both valuable and <hi>applicable to American conditions.</hi></p>
<p>11.</p>
<p>Assuming all necessary knowledge of malaria for the purpose, get<lb/>
out a small book--like a hand-book--on Malaria <unclear>Control</unclear> for U. S. use.<lb/>
This could, I think, be made useful. It could give (a) an exposition<lb/>
of the cost of malaria in the U. S.: (b) the principles of control,<lb/>
with the <hi>general</hi> methods of applying it: (c) application of these dif-<lb/>
ferent methods with examples giving results: costs: gains etc. with<lb/>
such discussion as to the indications for the use of the different ones<lb/>
as may be advisable. (d) Details of the applications of each general<lb/>
method--as under &ldquo;Drainage&rdquo; the use of dynamite: ditching machines: ver-<lb/>
tical drainage etc.: similarly for Oiling: Larvecide: Fish etc. These<lb/>
last three, indeed, really come under one general method--fish are as<lb/>
much a larvecide as arsenic.</p>
<p>This would be preferably by papers by different field men and<lb/>
would be the bulk of the book.</p>
<p>111.</p>
<p>Get out 1. as soon as convenient--it involves the less work of<lb/>
the two. Then 11. as we can. Have both bound on the &ldquo;loose-leaf&rdquo; sys-<lb/>
tem so that an addition to each can, and will <hi>be</hi>, made every year (or<lb/>
6 months?). Thus the pamphlet would <hi>stay</hi> more or less up to date.</p>
<p>What do you think of it?</p>
<p>Unless something be provided for <hi>progress</hi> I would be in favor of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00917015"/>
favor of<lb/>
4<lb/>
postponing the work a few years. We haven't completed the study of<lb/>
impounded waters: of rice-fields: malaria: of the efficacy of A. punc-<lb/>
tipennis as a vector in nature: of the the differential breeding habits<lb/>
of this species as compared with quads. and crucians: of the effect of<lb/>
shade on breeding and a number of others. On all we have data--picked<lb/>
up in surveys made for other purposes--but none are really complete.<lb/>
Indeed, one would like to have a full year--or longer--trial of Paris<lb/>
green, which promises to be the most important addition to our arma-<lb/>
mentarium since the introduction of oil. The same is true of fish--as<lb/>
you are now using them--probably more valuable than either oil or ar-<lb/>
senic--and a longer observation seems advisable.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Assistant Surgeon General</signed>
(On Waiting Orders).<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
