<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00917005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 6, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00917005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-12-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Arces, Julian</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Miraflores (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-12-06">December 6, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00917005</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 6, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson refutes Dr. Arces' theory that yellow fever does not exist in Peru.  He expresses confidence in the work being done.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-12-06">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 6, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00917005"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
____<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
____<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
(see Rose<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.<lb/>
<date value="1921-12-06">December 6, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>We have completed the translation and the copying of<lb/>
your article on the Spontaneous Elimination of Yellow Fever from Endemic<lb/>
Centers. Enclosed you will find a copy and presume that you will revise<lb/>
and notify either me or Dr. Rose about any errors which may be found. I<lb/>
have sent one copy to White and one to Rose. I am also sending a copy to<lb/>
the Sambridad. I have previously sent them copy of the translation made<lb/>
by <unclear>Rivers</unclear> of the two lectures which you delivered before the U.S.P.H.S.<lb/>
and Dr. Eyzaguire, the Statistician, told me that they were going to have<lb/>
these lectures reproduced.</p>
<p>I was under the impression that I had sent you a copy of the<lb/>
reply I made to Dr. Julian Arces, harangue on the <del><unclear></unclear></del> error(?) of considering<lb/>
the recent epidemics as yellow fever. I find no record of having done so<lb/>
and am therefore inflicting this on you. I hope you will critizise where<lb/>
I am in error in this letter.</p>
<p>We are now in the midst of arranging all our records and files<lb/>
preparatory to taking them to Lima wjere we will establish the principal<lb/>
office from now on to the end of the campaign. As you know we have extended the<lb/>
work to the south and will have the bulk of it to do there. I feel very con-<lb/>
fident of the northern sections, and with Mr. Seeley continuously on the<lb/>
job up here and with Dr. Canseco as the local medical director I see no dan-<lb/>
ger from this section from now on. I shall visit up here as frequently as<lb/>
the campaign of the south will permit, so as not to get out of touch with<lb/>
the progress of events. Our percentage is actually down to and below <hi>one</hi>,<lb/>
and under such conditions there can be no danger.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00917006"/>
<p>2. Dr. H.R. Carter, December 6, 1921.</p>
<p>We have distributed fish in everything, and are still keeping it<lb/>
up. We have practically reach the half-million mark with our fish distribution.<lb/>
The actual numbers of fish bought is about 480 000, and how many more we will<lb/>
use I can not yet day. It all depends on how things will appear in our work in<lb/>
the south. We have set out to make sure of the thing this year and we dont<lb/>
want to have the disappointment which you had last year. I have wondered abo<lb/>
about this,- whether there was not some ultimate good in the fact that the<lb/>
epidemic showed up here. I am inclined to be sceptical about the supposed<lb/>
absence of the fever in these Departments last year. Their appearance this<lb/>
year has taught us a lesson which is eventually worth something, in as much<lb/>
as we are now talking about the completelimination of the disease from this<lb/>
coast, it is better to be scared into the necessity of making a general<lb/>
clean up of everything which might later serve to defeat our purpose. That<lb/>
is what we are doing now.</p>
<p>The letter from Dr. Rose, dated November 2, is a sort of unlimited<lb/>
blanket authority. I am very conceited over receiving a letter of that kind,<lb/>
and I had it translated that I might use it with some of the local people.<lb/>
I hope that we shall soon be able to show the results which are expected.</p>
<p>I have arranged for the family to come back and am expecting thm<lb/>
in Pimented tomorrow. They will come ashore and remain until D go to Lima,<lb/>
we have obtained a furnished house in Miraflores, so th y will stay there<lb/>
until I get through. I fully expect that by May there will be no object<lb/>
in having us continue longer.</p>
<p>Dr. Rose says that when the work is finished, I will prepare a<lb/>
report, does he mean that I am to do this before leaving here or after I<lb/>
get back to the states. A proper report on this campaign is a thing which ca<lb/>
can not be done in a hurry. We will have about two or three thousand pages<lb/>
of files and records to review for this report. We are doing what we can<lb/>
now to get things in shape, but to get this up as it should be will re-<lb/>
quire time and hard work.</p>
<p>My Address from now on will be Lima, either in care of the<lb/>
American Consul or just Lima will reach me O.K.</p>
<p>With best wishes,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
