<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00919001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report of the Yellow Fever Epidemic in the Department of Lambayeque, by Henry Rose Carter, February 25, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00919001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-02-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="place">Chiclayo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Ferranafe (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Salaverry (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-02-25"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">00919001</idno>
<title>Report of the Yellow Fever Epidemic in the Department of Lambayeque, by Henry Rose Carter, February 25, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter reports on the yellow fever epidemic in the department of Lambayeque, including nature of epidemic and campaign.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-02-25">
<head>"Report of the Yellow Fever Epidemic in the Department of Lambayeque," by Henry Rose Carter, February 25, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00919001"/>
<opener>
R<lb/>
Peru<lb/>
<del>Report</del><lb/>
<unclear>(<hi>Ferrinafe</hi>)</unclear><lb/>
Carter<lb/>
</opener>
<p><hi>REPORT OF THE YELLOW FEVER EPIDEMIC IN THE<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF LAMBAYEQUE</hi><lb/>
By<lb/>
Henry R. Carter, M.D.</p>
<p>At the instance of the Salubridad I went to Ferrenafe on<lb/>
January 20, 1921 to assist in determining the nature of the epidemic<lb/>
there existing and to aid in planning the campaign against it in case<lb/>
it proved to be yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>A. Nature of the Epidemic</hi></p>
<p>It is yellow fever. It is of about the same severity as<lb/>
that I saw in Paita and elsewhere in the Department of Piura last<lb/>
year. There is probably a somewhat larger proportion of deaths in<lb/>
the same class of patients on account of less care being taken with<lb/>
the sick. I saw no case in a native-born adult and I was in the<lb/>
district eleven days. I saw seven dead children in two days. This<lb/>
points to a general epidemic about twenty years ago.</p>
<p><hi>Duration</hi> -- There is a history (Mr. Bonzi, Chiclayo) of an epi-<lb/>
demic with some deaths and of unknown nature at Jayanca a month or<lb/>
two before such reports from Ferrenafe; also of the death of a man<lb/>
(Father Pita, Pacasmayo) from Catacaos, at a haciendo near Ferranafe<lb/>
in June or July believed to be from yellow fever, and several cases<lb/>
about a month later at the hacienda to which he first came.</p>
<p>From the stage of the epidemic the infection must have been<lb/>
introduced into Ferrenafe not later than early October.</p>
<p><hi>Extent</hi> -- Ferrenafe is thoroughly infected, probably past the acme<lb/>
of the epidemic. From the duration of the epidemic and the prevalence of<lb/>
the disease in Ferrenafe it is well nigh certain that it exists in a<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00919002"/>
-2-<lb/>
number of places outside of this town. I saw a case in Chiclayo<lb/>
and two cases, one dead, in Lambayeque. There is some reason to be-<lb/>
lieve that some of the smaller places to the north and east have<lb/>
passed through the epidemic and are now in a measure immunized. Ste-<lb/>
gomyia were found everywhere we looked for them.</p>
<p><hi>B. Campaign</hi>.</p>
<p>This is two fold: (1) To limit the epidemic, i.e. to<lb/>
prevent its extension to parts not<lb/>
yet infected.</p>
<p>(2) To eliminate it from the infected<lb/>
district</p>
<p>Of the two the first is by far the most important. The fever<lb/>
is quite certainly in many of the towns and villages of the Chiclayo<lb/>
district, but if it can be confined to it its elimination should not<lb/>
be difficult and it would be <hi>certain</hi>, as the district, while thickly<lb/>
settled, is not a large one. Should its extension not be opposed it<lb/>
will go into the populous regions of the Department of Libertad and<lb/>
continue south as far as climatic conditions allow. To the south we<lb/>
found stegomyia abundant in all towns, and all haciendas save one ex-<lb/>
amined.</p>
<p>There is of course danger of the reinfection of the Depart-<lb/>
ment of Piura to the north if the stegomyia index therein is allowed<lb/>
to rise sufficiently. There is, however, a certain amount <unclear>-</unclear> in some<lb/>
places a high degree - of immunization in this Department and at pre-<lb/>
sent the stegomyia index is - or rather on January 1 the stegomyia in-<lb/>
dex was - very low: too low for the propagation of yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00919003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><hi>The Method of Limiting the Epidemic</hi> relied on is to so control the<lb/>
production of stegomyia that their number is reduced below that neces-<lb/>
sary for the propogation of yellow fever even if it be introduced, i e<lb/>
to render the place &ldquo;non-infectable&rdquo; by yellow fever. Naturally the<lb/>
same method would eliminate yellow fever were it, unknown to us, already<lb/>
existant.</p>
<p>This was urgently advised and to an extent attempted for the<lb/>
Chiclayo and Ferranafe district last year to protect it against the<lb/>
Piura epidemic. Had this been done there would have been no yellow fever<lb/>
in Peru this year and unless it be done, and done effectively, the ex-<lb/>
perience of Lambayeque will be repeated in Libertad and further south.</p>
<p>There is no question as to the danger and no question as to<lb/>
the method of avoiding it. It is much cheaper both in money and lives<lb/>
to prevent the spread of fever to new places than to eliminate it when<lb/>
established. Many lives and some thousands of pounds had been saved had<lb/>
the anti-stegomyia campaign advised for the Chiclayo district last year<lb/>
been carried out. The whole department of Libertad should be thus<lb/>
treated - the province of Pacasmayo especially.</p>
<p><hi>Method of Controlling the Production of Stegomyia</hi>. Doctor Hanson<lb/>
and myself have agreed on a method of controlling stegomyia breeding in<lb/>
depositos of water which was think is generally - not universally - appli-<lb/>
cable in these districts. If so it will be a marked improvement on<lb/>
those used last year: as efficient and cheaper (requiring less personnel)<lb/>
and simpler (requiring less skill and experience). It would take sometime<lb/>
to describe it and as Doctor Hanson will do <unclear>so</unclear> by circular and otherwise<lb/>
it seems unnecessary. It involves no new principle, simply emptying com-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00919004"/>
-4-<lb/>
pletely and drying every container once in seven days instead of ex-<lb/>
amining them for larvae, which we found in 90% of the depositos.</p>
<p><hi>Administration</hi>. It goes without saying that the officer directly<lb/>
in charge of this work should make his headquarters in the infected<lb/>
district, probably at Chiclayo and should have full control of it.<lb/>
He should have sufficient funds ready at all times and with a suf-<lb/>
ficient personnel absolutely at his order; the central office giving<lb/>
him all the support possible. It is desirable that he be immune to<lb/>
yellow fever so that he can move freely from infected to non-infected<lb/>
places - if not so by previous attack he should be vaccinated. There<lb/>
is good reason to believe that this confers a temporary immunity.</p>
<p><hi>The Sanitary Outlook</hi>. This is to be considered both in regard<lb/>
to the elimination of the present epidemic in Lambayeque and its<lb/>
limitation to that area.</p>
<p>For the first and compared with the condition last year in<lb/>
Piura the area involved is much more densely populated than that in<lb/>
Piura and the breeding conditions of stegomyia could scarcely be<lb/>
worse. The large botijas are in well-nigh universal use and these<lb/>
are the worst of all possible depositos for stegomyia -- meaning the<lb/>
most difficult to control. On the other hand nowhere is there the<lb/>
scarcity of water which was such a handicap in Paita and much of<lb/>
the laundry is done in the streams, lessening the amount of water needed<lb/>
in the houses. Also we have a certain number of trained men for in-<lb/>
spectors and we begin in the majority of the towns coincident with or<lb/>
before the epidemic, thus preventing as well as controlling it. The sanitation of practically the whole district is to be undertaken at<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00919005"/>
-5-<lb/>
once from the beginning of the work.</p>
<p>For the second preventing the spread of fever to new territory<lb/>
the outlook is unquestionably better than last year. Then, owing I am<lb/>
told to the opposition of the authorities in the district to be pro-<lb/>
tected (that of Chiclayo and Ferranfe) practically nothing was accom-<lb/>
plished.</p>
<p>The feeling of both authorities and people in the zone south<lb/>
of Lambayeque is very different. Doctor Hanson, I accompanying him,<lb/>
made a hurried trip from Chiclayo to Salaverry by land visiting a number<lb/>
of towns and haciendas. The disposition of the people in this section<lb/>
left nothing to be desired. They will cooperate fully in carrying out<lb/>
the protective measures outlined to them. The haciendados generally<lb/>
promise to themselves undertake the sanitation of their establishments,<lb/>
some of which are towns.</p>
<p>Pressed and handled wisely this campaign to limit the epidemic<lb/>
will succeed.</p>
<p><hi>Vaccine</hi>. I have not time to discuss the use of Noguch's vaccine.<lb/>
Admitting that its use for men is in the experimental stage yet the<lb/>
animal experiments are such that I would recommend its use freely; as<lb/>
freely as it can be pressed in infected places to immunize the population<lb/>
and thus raise the allowable critical number of stegomyia for the place.<lb/>
Could it be used universally as vaccine for smallpox is and give the same<lb/>
immunity, we could render towns immune to yellow fever from absence of the<lb/>
human host temporarily at any rate. It cannot, I think, at present take<lb/>
the place of control of stegomyia production.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) Henry R. Carter</signed>
25 February 1921<lb/>
LIMA<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
