<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00915022">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to the Director of Health (Direccion de Salubridad), September 9, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00915022</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-09-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Chiclayo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Tumbes (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Buena Ventura (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Paita (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-09-09">September 9, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00915022</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to the Director of Health (Direccion de Salubridad), September 9, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson gives an account of his trip to Panama. He mentions a modification of quarantine process. He describes sanitary inspections to various regions of Peru [lists names of personnel].  He expresses concern about the government's funding of workers.  The yellow fever campaign is going well, but vigilance is required.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-09-09">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to the Director of Health (Direccion de Salubridad), September 9, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00915022"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
---<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.<lb/>
<date value="1921-09-09">September 9,1921</date>
</dateline>
Direccion de Salubridad,<lb/>
Lima, Peru.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I beg to report that I returned from Panama to my Chiclayo Office on the<lb/>
second of September. On this trip I left Callao on the evening of the 9th of<lb/>
August and arrived in Panama on the morning of the 14th of the same month.</p>
<p>While in Panama I had several interviews with the Health Authorities<lb/>
of the Panama Canal Zone, who were very much interested in the progress of the<lb/>
yellow fever campaign, as well as in other important sanitary problems on the<lb/>
Pacific Coast of South America and particularly in Peru. After a few conferences<lb/>
with the Chief Quarantine Officer of the Canal Zone, he issued orders lifting,<lb/>
or probably more correctly speaking, moderating the quarantine against Peruvian<lb/>
ports. I presume that you will have received copies of this modification before<lb/>
this letter will reach you. The effect of the modification was that passengers<lb/>
from Peruvian ports will not be taken to the quarantine station as the practice<lb/>
had been before, but that the would be put under a six day observation at their<lb/>
residence, and would be allowed to travel freely in Panama Colon of the Canal<lb/>
Zone. Indications are that even this restriction will be removed if the work<lb/>
continues satisfactory in the prophylactic campaign, if not the old restrictions<unclear>.</unclear><lb/>
will be reestablished.</p>
<p>On the return trip my ship called at Port of Pizarro, and since the<lb/>
port authorities had not made proper preparation to receive the ship, we were<lb/>
delyed an extra day in this port. I took advantage of this delay to visit and<lb/>
inspect Tumbes. I was agreably disappointed in Tumbes. It is a place of better<lb/>
than the average construction on the northern coast of Peru, and is cleaner than<lb/>
most town which I have seen with the exception of Trujillo. It has an abundant<lb/>
supply of water in the river (Rio Tumbes) and the land bordering the rives has<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00915023"/>
2. Salubridad, September 9, 1921.<lb/>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
---<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----<lb/>
the appearance of fertile productive land. It is rather<lb/>
surprising that so little effort is made to cultivate this land, where there is<lb/>
so much available water in the river.</p>
<p>Investigation for cases of suspicious illness resulted negatively.<lb/>
In my brief investigation it was apparent that the stegomya breeding was low,<lb/>
and I do not think that this Province constitutes any menace to the outcome of<lb/>
the campaign on the coast. While there I gave a few simple instructions to the<lb/>
man who said he was in charge of the anti-stegomya work - I advised him to be-<lb/>
gin the liberal distribution of fish in all doubtful palces and containers. He<lb/>
promised to do this, and if he does the stegomya problem will soon be solved.</p>
<p>The Port of Pizarro is a very small place and of no importance as a focus of infection.</p>
<p>On account of the rumor which Dr. <unclear>Laverbaia</unclear> reported to me, of a case<lb/>
of yellow fever in Buena Ventura last year, I went ashore while we were in this<lb/>
port and made a few inquiries and such inspections as was possible. I walked over<lb/>
practically the entire town making mental notes of sanitary conditions. It is a<lb/>
place which undoubtedly is heavily infected with malaria, on account of the many<lb/>
small swampy areas among the <unclear>low</unclear> hills on which the town is built. I saw no<lb/>
evidence of any profuse stegomya breeding. Inquiries faild to indicate that there<lb/>
had been any cases of yellow fever for several years. The case which gave rise<lb/>
to last years rumor was that of the death of the British Consul, where some of the<lb/>
local physicians made a diagnosis of yellow fever. This man had been subject to<lb/>
heart and liver trouble and had had repeated attacks of the same kind of illness<lb/>
as that in which he died. His last illness had a duration of about a month, and<lb/>
that in itself would exclude yellow fever. Dr. Smith, who has a hospital at La<lb/>
Cumbre said that he had previously attended him in an accack like that in which<lb/>
he died and said that he thought the diagnosis of yellow fever and error. No other<lb/>
cases were reported.</p>
<p>At paita I went ashore and had a conference with Dr. Reinese, who seems to<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00915024"/>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
---<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----<lb/>
3. Salubridad, September 9, 1921.<lb/>
be of the opinion that the work in Paita has been somewhat<lb/>
neglected, but states that he has neither seen nor heard of any suspicious cases<lb/>
of yellow fever this year. Dr. Caballero is at present in the Department of Piura<lb/>
and will investigate all important points in the Department before returning to<lb/>
his post in Ancash and the northern section of the Department of Lima. On account<lb/>
of the short stay of the ship I was unable to make any further personal investi-<lb/>
gations.</p>
<p>Here in the Department of Lambayeque I am glad to say that the work is<lb/>
continuing to progress as well as one could wish. Our mosquito index is now down<lb/>
to and even below 1% in all the principal places. Recently we have distributed<lb/>
a great many fish, up to the present writing we have distributed about one hundred<lb/>
fifty thousand fish as larvae consumers. It is the surest and the most effective<lb/>
method, but even with that we meet considerable resistance <unclear>on</unclear> the part of some<lb/>
people. All the data has not yet been collected on the fish distribution, but<lb/>
indications are that we have distributed more than three hundred thousand fish<lb/>
as larvae consumers in the campaign. We are pushing this system of control in<lb/>
Ancash and the norther towns in Lima. Mr. Corrigan reports finding 90% of breeding<lb/>
in Barranca, and 50% in Huache.</p>
<p>I expect to leave for the Department of Libertad to inspect and arrange<lb/>
matters in the Trujillo office, and from there I shall continue south, probably<lb/>
arriving in Lima about the end of the month, or early in October. While in Lima<lb/>
I shall expect to get the question of my unpaid salary satisfactorily arranged.<lb/>
Yesterday I forwarded you <del>of</del> a copy of the telegram received from the National<lb/>
City Bank, showing that the draft which the local treasurer gave me on the Treasury<lb/>
in Lima (a ten day sight draft) was still unpaid after thirty days, which means<lb/>
that I have not been paid for, May, June, July or August, besides the difference on<lb/>
the exchange for the balance of the year. Why is this? How is my family expected<lb/>
live unless I can get my pay and send them something to live on? I believe this<lb/>
matter should deserve a little more prompt attention from now on.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00915025"/>
<p>DIRRECION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
---<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----</p>
<p>4. Salubridad, September 9, 1921.</p>
<p>As a whole the campaign is going well but the people<lb/>
must not make the mistake of believing that all is over. Fortunately it seems<lb/>
that we have no more cases, but the work against the larvae must continue until<lb/>
we can be sure and until the percentage has been kept down a sufficiently long time<lb/>
after the last case so as not to have a repetition of what happened last year, and<lb/>
this year.</p>
<p>In my opinion the most serious possibility remaining is as to whether<lb/>
or not there may be some focus in Lima or Callao, as a result of the Japanese<lb/>

who died in Lima in the early <del>dys</del> days of the Ferronafe epidemic. If so this<lb/>
may show up with the coming of the hot weather there, and the stegomya index<lb/>
of Lima ought to be determined. The northern Departments are safe and will<lb/>
remain so with the work which we are doing, providing we get the support which<lb/>
is necessary.</p>
<p>Mr. Larry Dunn arrived today and will take up a part of the work of<lb/>
Mr. Pickett and Mr. Corrigan, who will soon return to the Canal Zone. In addition<lb/>
Mr. Dunn will help us work out some <unclear>entomological</unclear> problems on which we have<lb/>
been working during the campaign.</p>
<p>I am sorry that I can not send you a translation of this, as my in-<lb/>
terpreter is sick in bed with the grippe.</p>
<p>I sent you a brief letter on the reports which I have on Sr. Cantuarias.<lb/>
All who came down from up that way complained of his drinking and gambling and<lb/>
stated that he did no real work as a sanitary inspector. In Tumbes I was told that<lb/>
he was assuming the role of pharmacist and visiting and treating the sick, and<lb/>
that he was earning a great deal of money in this way. I have no objection to his<lb/>
earning money, but if he represents the Health Department he should conduct him-<lb/>
self accordingly.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully submitted,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson, M.D.,<lb/>
Director of Sanitary Campaign for the<lb/>
Eradication of Yellow Fever</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
