<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00912005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Commandante A. Herrera, June 25, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00912005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-06-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Herrera, H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lambayeque (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Libertad (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-06-25">June 25, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00912005</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Commandante A. Herrera, June 25, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson criticizes Peruvian officials for undermining yellow fever work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-06-25">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Commandante A. Herrera, June 25, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00912005"/>
<opener>
Dear Dr. Carter:<lb/>
Unfortunately the Prefecto<lb/>
of Libertad was changed with results as<lb/>
you will notice by the enclosed.<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
DIRECCION<lb/>
DE LA<lb/>
CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EL LOS DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
----<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
----<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.<lb/>
<date value="1921-06-25">June 25,1921.</date>
</dateline>
Comandante H. Herrera H,<lb/>
Prefecto of Libertad,<lb/>
Trujillo:<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Yesterday I received a telegram from Trujillo of which I enclose copy. This<lb/>
telegram expresses a sentiment which is so contrary to all the personal manifes-<lb/>
tations which you have repeatedly made to me that it seems incredible that you<lb/>
could have been the author of such a message. It is quite evident that there is<lb/>
a very serious misunderstanding of the importance of the work which is being<lb/>
carried on by the Sanitary Campaign for the Eradication of Yellow Fever from<lb/>
Peru. Many persons are talking profusely about a subject on which they have in-<lb/>
sufficient knowledge, and in the execution of which they have no experience.</p>
<p>I am compelled to conclude that you have been very improperly advised in<lb/>
the matter, because it had always been my opinion that you desired to do the<lb/>
right thing for your people and your country, and once the matter were explained<lb/>
in its true light you would take the right steps to bring this about regardless<lb/>
of the pressure of private interests. This situation of the insidious advance of<lb/>
the yellow fever towards the south constitutes a very serious menace to the en-<lb/>
tire Republic of Peru, as well to the adjacent Countries. This should be care-<lb/>
fully considered by those who are making the great outcry for the removal of the<lb/>
restrictions on travel,- they should find out what these restrictions are, and by<lb/>
whom made before they submit demands which can not be complied with. Neither the<lb/>
Government nor the Management of the Sanitary Campaign have any desire to impose<lb/>
useless restrictions either on passenger travel or Commerce. In regard to restric-<lb/>
tions on maratime commerce none has been recommended by the Director of the Cam-<lb/>
paign, as will be seen by the following extract of letter which I have written to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00912006"/>
#2. Prefecto of Libertad, June 25, 1921.<lb/>
Sanitary Authorities in Guayaquil, Ecuador. (See copy of extract enclosed)</p>
<p>In regard to passenger travel however the most rigid restrictions have been<lb/>
requested from the very beginning of the Campaigns, and if these regulations had<lb/>
been taken seriously by the authorities concerned there neither would have been<lb/>
yellow fever in the Department of Lambayeque or that of Libertad this year, and<lb/>
your people would not at the present time be smarting under the sting of refringe-<lb/>
ment on their personal liberties. The unfortunate restrictions on commerce also<lb/>
would have been avoided, which have resulted on account of overdue precautions<lb/>
adopted by some of the neighboring countries. These neighboring countries have<lb/>
learned from long and bitter experience what it means to have both endemic and<lb/>
epidemic yellow fever, and very naturally do not intend to take any chances of<lb/>
permitting it to re-enter after it once has been completely eliminated.</p>
<p>The attitude which you assume by virtue of your telegram to the President<lb/>
and to the Minister of Fomento, <del><unclear></unclear></del> has the effect of declaring that we<lb/>
do not know what we are talking about, or that we are all dishonest and that we<lb/>
are carying on the campaign for some ulterior motive. It will therefore be necessary<lb/>
for you to produce your proofs to sustain either the one or the other or both,<lb/>
and secure a complete reorganization of the campaign. It will also be necessary<lb/>
for you to convince the neighboring countries that neither the present nor the<lb/>
other epidemics of the last two years, in Peru, have been of yellow fever. If<lb/>
you can do this, you will be entitled to send such messages as the one enclosed,<lb/>
but under no other condition.</p>
<p>To what &ldquo;aservaci&oacute;n uniforme Cuerpo M&eacute;dico reunido mi Despacho dia 8 del<lb/>
presente&rdquo; do you refer? There was no such uniform agrement at the metting which<lb/>
I attended.</p>
<p>disconnected <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/></p>
<p>Why do you think that the five isolated cases to which you refer lessens<lb/>
the menace to the rest of the country? Has it not occured to you that instead<lb/>
of having one single concentrated focus this would indicate a lamentable pro-<lb/>
pagation with an equally increased risk of <del><unclear>propagation</unclear></del><add>spread</add> to new territory? Upon<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00912007"/>
#3. Prefecto of Libertad, June 25, 1921.<lb/>
what grounds do you base your assertions in regard to the neglect of the work<lb/>
in Paijan? What competent authority have you consulted in order to justify you<lb/>
in making public statements of this kind in a matter which a question of <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
life and death both to individuals and to commerce?</p>
<p>Among the patients seen by me in the Department of Libertad, in the Pro-<lb/>
vince of Trujillo, there have been the following findings:</p>
<p>These <unclear>patients</unclear> have gone<lb/>
to bed with a sudden attack of headache, pain in the back in the kidney re-<lb/>
gion, discomfort and pain in the stomach which has rapidly been followed by<lb/>
nausae and vomiting, great prostration from the beginning which has con-<lb/>
tinued through all the period of the illness. The eyes have been red and<lb/>
injected, tongue heavily coated dorsally with red margins and tip, gums<lb/>
injected some bleeding spontaneously others on slight pressure, this has<lb/>
been most marked in the portion of the gum immediately incontact with the<lb/>
teeth. The severest cases have had great discomfort all over the body<lb/>
but most pronounced in kidney region and stomach. The temperature has<lb/>
varied from 38 C to 41 C, and the pulse has been relatively low for the<lb/>
temperature, with a fall in the pulse rate characteristic of yellow<lb/>
fever. The urine has shown an abundance of albumen in the third and<lb/>
fourth day of the disease, in some of the severe, fatal cases, albumen<lb/>
has presented itself in the first and second day of the illness. Some<lb/>
of these patients have had black vomit, samples of which were kept for<lb/>
exhibition to any one who wished to assure himself in the matter. None<lb/>
of the attacked gave any history of ever having had a similar disease<lb/>
previously. In these cases as the disease progressed the <del><unclear></unclear></del> <hi>conjuncti-<lb/>
vae</hi> has gradually tured from the red injected appearance to a reddish<lb/>
yellow and later to a yellow brassy color, throughout there has been a<lb/>
partial edematous condition of the conjunctivae which is distinct from<lb/>
the condition seen in the icterus due to chronic malaria or other hepatic<lb/>
disturbances. After the fourth day the skin has commenced to show <unclear>icterico</unclear><lb/>
changes, in proportion to the severity of the disease and its duration.<lb/>
In those who have recovered the albuminuria has disappeared.</p>
<p>The autopsies practiced on those dying have shown marked cutaneous<lb/>
and subcutaneous yell discoloration, yellowness and fatty degeneration of<lb/>
the liver, <unclear><hi>potechial</hi></unclear> hemmorhages in the pleura, yellow discoloration of<lb/>
the serous surfaces, parenchymatous nephritis diffuse. Stomach with con-<lb/>
gestion, hyperaemia and catarrhal swelling of the mucosa, and contents<lb/>
black coffe color in nearly all cases.</p>
<p>The above has served as the basis for our diagnosis, <unclear>togather</unclear> with<lb/>
our experience and observation of the cases in the Departments of Piura and<lb/>
Lambayeque. We have found that these cases have a direct relationship with<lb/>
the number of stegomya in the locality, and that the elimination of the stego-<lb/>
mya is followed by a disappearance of the disease. Efforts to isolate cases has<lb/>
proven of practically no value in that when the people know that they are to be<lb/>
taken to place of isolation they hide the cases until the period of infectivity<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00912008"/>
#4. Prefecto of Libertad, June 25, 1921.<lb/>
has passed. In the first epidemics of the Department of Piura we established<lb/>
isolation hospitals, with the idea <del><unclear>orf</unclear></del> of immediately removing every suspi-<lb/>
cious case of sickness from the general population, and in that manner lessen<lb/>
the opportunities for propagation. In theory this seems to be a good measure<lb/>
but in practice it has not given the results expected for the reason mentioned<lb/>
above. This measure<del>s</del> gives rise to much resistance on the part of the people,<lb/>
and the political authorities have not seen fit to assure its enforcement.</p>
<p>The experience of the greatest authorities of modern times, in the matter<lb/>
of the control and eradication of yellow fever, such as the late General Gorgas<lb/>
with whom I personally discussed this problem in connection with the Piura<lb/>
Campaign, and Dr. Henry R. Carter, Assistant Surgeon General of the United<lb/>
States Public Health Service, and special advisor of the International Health<lb/>
Board, (one of the greatest authorities in the world on yellow fever) have<lb/>
abandoned both the practice of isolation of the sick, except by the use of<lb/>
mosquito bars, and the <hi>general fumigation of houses</hi>. They recommend an in-<lb/>
tensive campaign against the stegomya larva as the surest and most effective<lb/>
sanitary measure. The campaign in the Departments of Lambayeque and Libertad<lb/>
are conducted on this basis.</p>
<p>The recent publications in the Trujillo daily papers show a very evident<lb/>
lack of knowledge of the epidemiology of yellow fever, as well as a total lack<lb/>
of comprehension of what is, or what is not, effective practical sanitary work.</p>
<p>Trusting that you will give this matter the careful consideration which<lb/>
it deserves for the best interests of the country, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson, M.D.,<lb/>
Director of Sanitary Campaign<lb/>
against Yellow Fever, in the<lb/>
Departments of the North</signed>.
Copy to,<lb/>
Direccion de Salubridad,<lb/>
Lima, Peru.<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
New York, N.Y., U.S.A.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
