<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00915031">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 17, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00915031</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-09-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Read, Florence M.</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Pacasmayo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lambayeque (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-09-17">September 17, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00915031</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 17, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses a yellow fever outbreak in Trujillo.  He mentions the difficulty of doing prophylactic work in Lima.  He offers his opinions regarding a member of the Panama Canal Health Department and the Peruvian government.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-09-17">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 17, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00915031"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION<lb/>
DE LA<lb/>
CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
Contra la Fiebre Amarilla<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
Departamentos del Norte<lb/>
----<lb/>
TRUJILLO<lb/>
Hanson
Sept. 17/21<lb/>
<dateline>
Trujillo, <date value="1921-09-17">September 17, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of May 16, has just been re-<lb/>
ceived after my arrival in Trujillo on this trip. In this letter<lb/>
I notice that you had just received the news of the confirma-<lb/>
tion of the fever in the Province of Trujillo. I thin you will<lb/>
recall that we had prohesi<del>z</del>ed to these people when we were here<lb/>
that the fever would reach this Department about April. One of<lb/>
the Commissarios reminded me of this in June.</p>
<p>The criminal part of this thing was Quiro's obstructiveness<lb/>
when we wanted to take Mendoza south with us at the time of our<lb/>
leaving Lambayeque. I think the fever probably would have entered<lb/>
anyway, but there would have been more of a chance of catching<lb/>
the first cases in the province of Pacasmayo. I have sent up<lb/>
the statistical chart on the officially recognized cases in<lb/>
that Province which shows that the first cases there must have<lb/>
occured early in March. I am of the opinion that the disease<lb/>
was introduced after our visit to Pacasmayo and Trujillo. Still<lb/>
one can not be entirely certain of this. A great many things<lb/>
have been showing up which I have not yet been able to thoro-<lb/>
ugly analyze. At times I am very much in doubt about this<lb/>
pet diagnosis of &ldquo;fiebre biliosa hemoglobinurica&rdquo; and have<lb/>
wondered if it may not be possible that there have been some<lb/>
endemic foci of yellow fever in this northern section, and the<lb/>
cases so diagnosed have been cases of yellow fever. Also many<lb/>
of the diagnoses of &ldquo;paludismo perniciosa&rdquo; most likely have<lb/>
been cases of yellow fever. Why is it that in the zones which<lb/>
we have cleaned up you never hear of these diagnoses any more<lb/>
while formerly they were relatively frequent? I have just been<lb/>
talking to Mendoza about this, and he also is loosing his faith<lb/>
in the diagnoses of &ldquo;biliosa hemoglobinurica&rdquo; and &ldquo;paludizmo<lb/>
perniciosa&rdquo;. This man Don Juliano Arce is still making diagnoses<lb/>
of this type in Lima, and I have wondered what they are.</p>
<p>In regard to Dr. Tapias work here we corrected that fairly<lb/>
promptly and eventually got good work started here. Dr. Tapia<lb/>
has been a very valuable aquisition, seems to have good judge-<lb/>
ment and is very much interested. He has worked very conscien-<lb/>
tiously, and kepps his records quite well.</p>
<p>There is not a great deal of need for other physicians, with<lb/>
Cabellero and Mendoza, I have about all that is needed. The super-<lb/>
vising Inspectors was the most important addition needed. In so<lb/>
far as the final outcome is concerned it all depends on the<lb/>
larvae work, and the extension of the outside zones sufficiently<lb/>
to prevent anything jumping across. This I believe we are doing<lb/>
now. Our work in Ancash and the northern section of the Departm-<lb/>
ent of Lima ought to do this. The employment of Corrigan and<lb/>
Pickett, even at the high price, was justifiable. They have meant<lb/>
a great deal to the final outcome of the campaign. I have worked<lb/>
them and they have worked like very few men ever did work in a<lb/>
campaign of this kind.</p>
<p>If you think that this work should be continued for any<lb/>
great length of time, it might be well to send a couple of the<lb/>
Inspectors to which you refer, to help in the supervision of the<lb/>
final clean up. I have been thinking about two dates for the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00915032"/>
2. H.R.C., September 17, 1921.<lb/>
final termination of the campaign, January or April. By April<lb/>
one should know quite definitely what the conditions may be. I<lb/>
think that if anything is going to show up it should do so before<lb/>
January, and we ought to find it because it is my plan to keep<lb/>
up a continuous revision of the entire coast, and cases should<lb/>
not easily escape us, with such men as Caballero, Mendoza, Tapia<lb/>
and others continually on the lookout for suspicious cases.<lb/>
The most uncertain place will be Lima itself, and to do real<lb/>
prophylactic work there will be very difficult on account of<lb/>
the interference of the politicians and, Wrightson and Lavoreria.<lb/>
The last two were very pigheaded about our recommendations in<lb/>
regard to the quarantine during the Centennial. Dr. White no doubt<lb/>
will tell you about this. It appears that Lavoreria is running<lb/>
Wrightson considerably on this point. I shall very probably<lb/>
have somewhat of an argument with them when I get to Lima. I dont<lb/>
like their impudence.</p>
<p>In regard to Goldthwaites men, I know very little about them.<lb/>
I sympathize with them for having been obliged to work with a<lb/>
man of Goldthwaites type. As far as he is concerned I cant under-<lb/>
stand what keeps him in the Panama Canal Health Department. I<lb/>
think he is about the poorest and the most bigoted material I<lb/>
have ever seen in an important position of that kind. All bluff<lb/>
and foreflushing.</p>
<p>I know Beverly and Wolcott personally, both good men but I<lb/>
do not think that either are available. Converse is the man of<lb/>
the Iquitos fame.</p>
<p>You already know from my other letters and copies what the<lb/>
Peruvian Government is doing about funds, -which is practically<lb/>
nothing. I have grown tired of prodding them- it has been so<lb/>
useless to do so. However I shall make one more attempt when I<lb/>
get to Lima this time, and then try to leave some definite agre-<lb/>
ment, by which they fully recognize the International Health<lb/>
Board as the actual managers of the campaign.</p>
<p>The exchange seems to be improving, and I believe that if<lb/>
you leave your money for a while you will come out much better,</p>
<p>Our difficulty in the campaign <unclear>atb</unclear> present is a general<lb/>
strike effecting practically the entire Department of Libertad<lb/>
We are <unclear>unable</unclear> to get any transportation, of any kind and are very<lb/>
much handicapped in our inspections of this Department. In my<lb/>
letter to Miss Read, copy of which I enclose for your information<lb/>
you will note what I have written the board about the matter.</p>
<p>I hope the thing will be settled by next week. We need the<lb/>
railroad facilities to make sure of our conditions.</p>
<p>With the very best wishes, and with many thanks for your<lb/>
letters and your helpful advise,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>,
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
