<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00916014">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to H.C. Woodfall, October 26, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00916014</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-10-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Woodfall, H.C.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">Georgia</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-10-26">October 26, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00916014</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to H.C. Woodfall, October 26, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter gives Woodfall advice on proposed legislation to control spread of malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-10-26">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to H.C. Woodfall, October 26, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00916014"/>
<opener>
Impounded Waters<lb/>
Please Return<lb/>
H. R. Carter<lb/>
Georgia<lb/>
COPY<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1921-10-26">Oct. 26, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Mr. Woodfall,-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of Oct. 22, 1921 received with<lb/>
enclosure.</p>
<p>1. It seems to me that it might be well to divide your<lb/>
Sec. 5 into two: One for the requirements before the pond is<lb/>
filled and the other for the after care of the pond. This last<lb/>
is as important as the first; it may be more so. This is how-<lb/>
ever probably of no great importance.</p>
<p>2. Your provision for clean edges and fish control for<lb/>
small and moderate sized ponds is practical and advisable -<lb/>
indeed <hi>necessary</hi>. They are generally close to a considerable<lb/>
population <unclear>&amp;</unclear> their edges large in proportion to area; hence more breeding &amp; less<lb/>
wave action proportionally, than in large ponds.</p>
<p>3. You know however that to keep the edges of large<lb/>
ponds - that of Lock #17 Black Warrior, Ala. had a shore line of<lb/>
about <hi>225 miles</hi> - is economically impossible. Whether there are<lb/>
liable to be such ponds in Anopheles (<unclear>A.quad.</unclear>) producing parts<lb/>
of Georgia I do not know, and if so whether this should be re-<lb/>
quired of them by law is a question for Georgia to determine.<lb/>
It would probably be as cheap to buy the land within the distance<lb/>
of flight from the pond. This, however, would not free the pond<lb/>
owners from the penalties of this act, even if - the country be-<lb/>
ing vacated - no malaria is caused.</p>
<p>4. To what extent the <hi>methods</hi> or the <hi>details</hi> of the<lb/>
methods to accomplish the purpose of a law should be <hi>expressed</hi><lb/>
in the <hi>law itself</hi> is always a question.</p>
<p>My own feeling is that this should be done as little as<lb/>
may be: That in the law itself <hi>only</hi> such methods should be pre-<lb/>
scribed of the expediency of enforcing which there is not any<lb/>
doubt and concerning which we are quite sure that increased know-<lb/>
ledge will not lead to a change of view. Such of course may and,<lb/>
I think, should be expressed.</p>
<p>In addition the Act should express its <hi>purpose</hi> and<lb/>
authorize the H. O. to carry it out by such regulations and orders<lb/>
as may be necessary to do so, I think the Act of Congress of<lb/>
February 1893 - the organic Act for the Maritime system of the<lb/>
U. S. was established - is as near a model of this kind of law as<lb/>
I know.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00916015"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>If I can find it I will send you the memorandum, fixed<lb/>
up for Virginia by the H.O., Engineer and myself. Also one for<lb/>
the Badin pond and one drawn up for Gen'l Beach, Chief of Engi-<lb/>
neers U. S. Army, at his request for the general use for pools<lb/>
formed in the improvement of navigation. Lock #8 of the Coosa<lb/>
is the one he had immediately in view but the mem. is general.<lb/>
These are by no means for incorporation in any law - too much<lb/>
detail of method - but may be of use to you in making subsequent<lb/>
regulations.</p>
<p>5. In my experience large bodies of impounded water in<lb/>
the malaria section have <hi>always</hi> made some malaria. True they<lb/>
also destroy same<unclear>.</unclear> Some, as at Baldin, destroy more by flooding<lb/>
breeding places than they make elsewhere. Generally the contrary<lb/>
is the case.</p>
<p>6. Anopheles production from a pond, large pond, has<lb/>
also always been worse the first few (two?) years.</p>
<p>1. There is more floatage the first year or so and<lb/>
thus more protection of Larvae from fish.</p>
<p>2. It takes about 3 years to kill the land vegetation<lb/>
which standing on the edges acts the same way.</p>
<p>3. The banks are out sharp by wave action within a<lb/>
few years, which acts both by dr<del>ai</del><add><unclear>ow</unclear></add>ning the larvae and by removing<lb/>
this protection against fish.</p>
<p>4. And finally the <unclear>numuers, if</unclear> minnows, small at first,<lb/>
increase until the pond is stocked to its biologic equilibrium.</p>
<p>Everyone will admit that the <hi>complaint</hi> of malaria from a<lb/>
pond lessens after the first few years. I think the malaria it-<lb/>
self does. I have to draw a distinction between the two because<lb/>
the hope of getting damages for malaria caused by the pond is un-<lb/>
questionably a factor - the effect of which it is difficult to<lb/>
estimate - in the complaint of pond-made malaria.</p>
<p>Pardon so long a letter. I have possibly not helped you<lb/>
much in formulating your Act. I do not know your local conditions,<lb/>
sociological, legal, or even topographical, but I think if you<lb/>
read the enclosed memoranda you may find some points you can util-<lb/>
ize.</p>
<p>Please return the enclosures marked &ldquo;Return&rdquo; as I have<lb/>
no other copies of them.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) H. R. Carter</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
