<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00915018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 8, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00915018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-09-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-09-08">September 8, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00915018</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 8, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson includes the names of medical personnel and the places he has inspected.  He mentions the lack of cooperation from locals.  He is considering a return to the U.S.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-09-08">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 8, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00915018"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
____<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
____<lb/>
Havana<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.<lb/>
<date value="1921-09-08">September 8, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have several letters from you which I will endeavor to<lb/>
answer as best I can. It is always a pleasure and a help to hear from you, You<lb/>
appreciate and understand this situation better than any other man, and will be<lb/>
able to judge best of what we are doing and of what we have done.</p>
<p>Your letter of June 29th was forwarded to me in Panama, where I was<lb/>
for about eleven days, and it seemed a mighty short time at that. I noticed the<lb/>
hot weather considerably there, and did not get about as much as I had intended<lb/>
for that reason.</p>
<p>In regard to Seeley I finally decided that I better pay him $400.00<lb/>
as he wished. Frankly a man earns it in a campaign of this kind, and he has<lb/>
spared no effort to earn his. He has scarcely had a Sunday since he has been on the<lb/>
job, and has done a lot of work at night. I sent up a quarterly report which he pre-<lb/>
pared for me of the first three months after his arrival. If you have not already<lb/>
seen this you better ask Dr. Rose to let you have it too look it over. It has a great<lb/>
deal of information which I can not give you in a <unclear>latter</unclear>.</p>
<p>I fully appreciate your spirit in wishing to be down here on the job, but<lb/>
I have been glad for your sake that you have not been here. This campaign has been<lb/>
so much severer than any of the others that I am quite certain that you would have<lb/>
had trouble. You know you do not take care of yourself when you are out on a thing of<lb/>
this kind, and with the hardships we have had I feel quite certain that it would<lb/>
have done you up for good. I have never before worked like this, and what is more<lb/>
I wont do it again!! I wanted to show these people that we could get rid of the<lb/>
fever in spite of their dmanable opposition, and we have succeeded. Contrary to<lb/>
last year we have protected ourselves on all sides, and are still continuing to do<lb/>
so. On my way down from Panama I had an opportunity to find out what kind of a<lb/>
place Port of Pizarro and Tumbes were like, which is a great adavantage to me in<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00915019"/>
2. H.R.C., September 8, 1921.<lb/>
planning for the future.</p>
<p>Dr. Caballero had asked for permission to go to Catacaos (to see his<lb/>
sweetheart I think) so I requested him to look all the important points in the<lb/>
Department of Piura over before he goes back south. This he is doing at the present<lb/>
time. I expect him back in the south sometime next week. In regard to the south<lb/>
you will get a fairly good idea from the copies of the letters (reports of Corrigan)<lb/>
which I enclosed with other copies which I have sent you in the last few days.</p>
<p>I am glad to note what you say of White's work in New Orleans, he im-<lb/>
pressed me as a very capable and aggressive man. It seems that Wyman rather<lb/>
queered Whites report on the N.O. epidemic - did he not?</p>
<p>White stayed a while in Guayaquil and then was on his way to Lima, and<lb/>
would have arrived about the time of the fiestas or just before, which would have been<lb/>
time all <unclear>wasted</unclear>, so I went aboard and advised him to come ashore at Salaverry to see<lb/>
what we were doing before he went to Lima. I went with him to Lima, but had very<lb/>
little time with him in Lima. They were still having their <unclear>despedidos</unclear> for the foreign<lb/>
embassies, so I would not have been able to do any real business, and took my boat<lb/>
for Panama. I have not heard from Dr. White since. He went up by way of Guayaquil<lb/>
-how soon he will get to the states I do not know.</p>
<p>You speak of Peru <unclear>puttin</unclear> up Lp2050, &ldquo;each month&rdquo; - if she had we would not<lb/>
have needed to ask the I.H.B. for very much. Peru has scarcely put up more than<lb/>
that sum all told up to date. We will need from the I.H.B. about  $10,000, per month<lb/>
as available working capital in order to be able to make sure of this thing once<lb/>
and for all. I do not intend to spend that unless it is quite necessary, but I do<lb/>
not want to be handicapped for what is really needed to insure what it seems that we<lb/>
now have. I cabled them somewhat to this effect the other day but so far have not<lb/>
received any answer, they may think that this is a good deal, but they better do it to<lb/>
insure what they have already spent. The Government <unclear>is</unclear> not even paying my salary.<lb/>
This makes me tired because if they were not paying &ldquo;Willie&rdquo; such a fancy salary<lb/>
they might be able to pay me. Ten thousand will cover everything, and leave a balance,<lb/>
even the salaries of the American Inspectors.</p>
<p>I am palnning to go to Lima as soon as I can get things properly lined<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00915020"/>
3. H.R.C., September 8, 1921.<lb/>
up in the northerns sections, Lambayeque and Libertad. Dr. Canseco is working pretty<lb/>
well now and takes charge of the office here during my absence, and Tapia in Trujillo.<lb/>
I have made Mendoza the General Supervisor for the entire Department of <unclear>Libertad</unclear><lb/>
and have put Cavassa in charge of the Province of Pacasmayo, Dr. Caballero has all<lb/>
the coast from Libertad to Lima and Callao, so I thin<add>k</add> we have the entire coast pretty<lb/>
well taken care of, and all reports are encouraging. My ideas on the Lima proposition<lb/>
you will get from the copies of the other letters which I have sent up.</p>
<p>It is possible that the epidemic might reach Lima, but I dont think it<lb/>
will on account of the condition <add>in</add> which we have all this northern section, and what<lb/>
we have done in the Department of Ancash. This is putting a mighty wide barrier be-<lb/>
tween Lima and the infected zones, and what is more we are watching everything our-<lb/>
selves, and taking nobody's word for anything. If anything should happen it would have<lb/>
to attract the attention of the <unclear>men</unclear> we have in these parts, and we would know about<lb/>
it before it could get a start.</p>
<p>Machado picked up again under a little supervision and was doing very well<lb/>
when I was in Trujillo last. Quiros resigned when he thought that he was not going to<lb/>
be the whole cheese in the campaign, and I think that I have been just as well off<lb/>
without him. He is largely responsible for the spread of the fever to the Depart-<lb/>
ment of Libertad, on account of his obstinacy when we were here together. Sains is<lb/>
doing fine, so is <hi>Reyes</hi>, and I have several others now who are quite good.</p>
<p>I dont know what to say about Wrightson, or what he is doing. He was about<lb/>
as pigheaded about our recommendations of the quarantine as Cardenas was, and he got<lb/>
a real mess stirred up at the quarantine station as a consequence. I think he is too<lb/>
much impressed with his own importance to be able to see things staright.</p>
<p>In so far as my continuing with the stegomya control here is concerned I<lb/>
presume that I would be better qualified for this job than anyone else except your-<lb/>
self. I have been thinking about this - of finishing this job but am not ready to<lb/>
give a final answer now. Conditions have changed much and it is hard to say before-<lb/>
hand what one ought to do. If I could get a decent place for the family to live I<lb/>
would bring them to Trujillo, which would be quite a central location for the balance<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00915021"/>
4. H.R.C., September 8, 1921.<lb/>
of the campaign. I will investigate this <unclear>on my</unclear> next trip down there. The difficulty<lb/>
about this is Karl. I do not want to bring him back. If I could place him in some<lb/>
good school in the states where I could be sure that he would be well taken care of<lb/>
I would send him up and bring the rest of them back down here. What do you think of<lb/>
that? In that case I would not be away from them more than half of the time.</p>
<p>Sorry you had such an uncomfortable summer. Our weather here has been quite<lb/>
ideal. Never too hot and never too cold. This is a much better climate than Piura.</p>
<p>To return to the subject of the continuation of the stegomya work, I<lb/>
note what you say in the copy of your letter to Rose, about the difficulty of con-<lb/>
tinuing the stegomya work for a year in Peru. It will be difficult to continue this<lb/>
and I have wondered whether it will be practicable to attempt to continue it for a<lb/>
year after the last case. I at first figured on continuing it to the end of the<lb/>
year and later of a possibility of continuing to April. I think that one can be<lb/>
sufficiently certain by that time. If we have no more cases before that time and<lb/>
our stegomya index continues as it is, where is the new case coming from? This is<lb/>
different from last year in that we have spread <del><unclear>to</unclear></del> out a very great deal and now<lb/>
have things in such shape that there can be no epidemic in any of the Departments to<lb/>
the north. If there is special watching to do it seems to me that it should be done<lb/>
in Lima more than in the north, and in that case would it not be best for me to<lb/>
transfer my headquarters to Lima, leaving the local offices in charge of these men<lb/>
who are now looking after them? We are now starting work in Huacho which is a town<lb/>
of about 10,000, and as Corrigan says has about 50% of containers breeding. With our<lb/>
present system of fish control we can reduce the index very much faster than before.</p>
<p>Our last know case in Libertad was on the 11th of July, and I think that<lb/>
is going to remain the last, but we take no chances.</p>
<p>With all good wishes for you and yours,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Vey cordially and sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
