<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00916006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, October 21, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00916006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-10-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-10-21">October 21, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00916006</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, October 21, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson offers his opinions on the Peruvian government in regards to funding.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-10-21">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, October 21, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00916006"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
---<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
----<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.<lb/>
<date value="1921-10-21">October 21, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Wicliffe Rose, General Director,<lb/>
The International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway New York City,<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am inclosing herewith copies of letter to the &ldquo;Salubridad&rdquo;<lb/>
giving them a status of my salary up to the middle of this month. My object in<lb/>
presenting this statement is to try to get a liquidation up to the end of June<lb/>
at least, as it does not seem to me fair that The International Health Board<lb/>
should be expected to pay all these back accounts. My procedure in some of these<lb/>
points is probably a bit arbitrary, but I do not see what else I can do under the<lb/>
circumstances. In accepting the terms of the memorandum which I presented to the<lb/>
President the <unclear>Government</unclear> recognizes as legal debt 50% of the expenses of the<lb/>
Campaign, which improves the moral tone - if not the financial contribution.</p>
<p>Together with this you will find the draft on the National Treasury<lb/>
for Lp 682.5.34, endorsed to the Rockefeller Foundation, and await your further<lb/>
instructions in regard to this <unclear>ratter</unclear>.</p>
<p>You will also find a resume of the checks drawn on the Equitable Trust<lb/>
Co. Practically all the checks to the banks have been drawn in duplicate, except<lb/>
the last two to the National City Bank of New York, Lima <unclear>Branch</unclear>, and the last one<lb/>
to the Banco Mercantil Americano del Peru in Chiclayo. In addition there is a<lb/>
resume of the funds, in Peruvian currency, used in the Department of Lambayeque,<lb/>
this was made for my personal convenience as a reference, I enclose it since it<lb/>
may also be of use to the Comptroller.</p>
<p>In regard to Mr. <unclear>Seeley's</unclear> salary I have been in error in reporting that<lb/>
as running from the 4th to the 4th of each month. His last month ended October 16,<lb/>
and will be paid this month in Peruvian currency from the general campaign funds<lb/>
and in the future will probably figure in the general statement presented to the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00916007"/>
2. Dr. Wicliffe Rose, October 21, 1921.<lb/>
International Health Board and to the Government.</p>
<p>In regard to his service I have talked the matter over with him and<lb/>
made an arrangement by which he is to bring his family to the Port of Eten and<lb/>
continue with the campaign until its finish. I do not feel that he can be spared,<lb/>
it would be unsafe, not to have some one in whom I can have full confidence for<lb/>
the balance of the time of the campaign. Everything looks rosy at present, but<lb/>
the warm weather is <unclear>coming</unclear> on, and we do not want to let the breeding increase<lb/>
until we are ready to bid the country our final farewell. He did not feel that<lb/>
he could afford the expense of bringing the family and paying the rent in addition<lb/>
so I proposed that we furnish him quarters for the balance of the campaign, and<lb/>
that he bring the family which he has agreed to do. This will cost us about ten<lb/>
pounds per month. We will save half of that on his hotel bill since he will have<lb/>
maintenance only when away on the outside inspections.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson,<lb/>
Director of Campaign</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
