<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00918005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Special Measures Against Yellow Fever at Ports of Arrival (Domestic and Insular), [1921?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00918005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">United States</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-00-00">1921?</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00918005</idno>
<title>Report: Special Measures Against Yellow Fever at Ports of Arrival (Domestic and Insular), [1921/]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The report outlines special measures to screen passengers, including quarantine procedures and possible hospitalization.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-00-00">
<head>Report: Special Measures Against Yellow Fever at Ports of Arrival (Domestic and Insular),[1921?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00918005"/>
<p>R<lb/>
Q</p>
<p>SPECIAL MEASURES AGAINST YELLOW FEVER AT PORTS OF<lb/>
ARRIVAL (DOMESTIC AND INSULAR).</p>
<p>&check; 83. A vessel aboard which a case of yellow fever has occured<lb/>
at any time during the voyage shall be treated as follows:</p>
<p>(a) Careful visual and thermometric inspection of all persons.</p>
<p>(b) The sick are to be immediately disembarked, protected by<lb/>
netting against the access of stegomyia mosquitoes, and transferred to a<lb/>
place of isolation.</p>
<p>(c) Other persons should be disembarked, if possible, and de-<lb/>
tained under observation for six days, dating from the day of last possible<lb/>
exposure.</p>
<p>&check; (d) Persons under observation presenting an elevation of tem-<lb/>
perature above 37.6&deg; C. shall be isolated in a screened apartment.</p>
<p>&check; (e) The ship shall be moored if possible at least 200 meters<lb/>
from the inhabited shore.</p>
<p>(f) The ship shall be fumigated for the destruction of mosquit-<lb/>
oes before the discharge of cargo, if possible. If a fumigation be not<lb/>
possible before the discharge of the cargo, the discharge of cargo shall<lb/>
be under the supervision of the quarantine officer, and may be permitted<lb/>
as follows: By (1) the employment of immune persons for discharging the<lb/>
cargo; or (2) if nonimmunes be employed, they shall be kept under obser-<lb/>
vation during the discharging of cargo and for six days, to date from the<lb/>
last day of exposure on board.</p>
<p>&check; 84. A vessel which has lain in such proximity to the shore of a<lb/>
port known to be infected as to render it liable to the access of stegomyia<lb/>
mosquitoes shall be fumigated and the personnel held in detention under<lb/>
observation for six days.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00918006"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>85. A vessel arriving at a southern port (either direct or by<lb/>
&check; way of a northern port of the United States) which, although coming from<lb/>
an infected port or suspected port, has had neither death nor case of yellow<lb/>
fever on board, either before departure, during the voyage, or at the time<lb/>
of arrival, and which the quarantine officer is satisfied has not lain in<lb/>
such proximity to the shore as to render it liable to the access of steg-<lb/>
omyia mosquitoes, or which has been fumigated under the supervision of an<lb/>
accredited medical officer of the United States immediately before sailing,<lb/>
may, upon arrival at a port of destination in the United States with good<lb/>
sanitary history and in good condition (including the absence of any ex-<lb/>
posed collection of water in which A. calopus might breed) be subjected<lb/>
to the following treatment:</p>
<p>&check; (a) If arriving in six days or less, she may be admitted to<lb/>
pratique, with or without fumigation, in the discretion of the quarantine<lb/>
officer, and without further detention than is necessary to complete the<lb/>
six days.</p>
<p>&check; (b) If arriving after six days she shall be immediately fumi-<lb/>
gated (unless previously fumigated at a northern port) and may be admitted<lb/>
without detention.</p>
<p>86. Vessels from ports infected or suspected of infection with<lb/>
X<lb/>
yellow fever, calling at southern ports for bunker coal or supplies during<lb/>
&check; the active quarantine season may be allowed to take on such cargo after<lb/>
fumigation, provided the vessel be anchored in a place inaccessible to<lb/>
stegomyia and the crew or passengers be detained on board.</p>
<p>&check; 87. Traffic without detention may be allowed during the active<lb/>
quarantine season, from ports infected or suspected of infection with<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00918007"/>
-3-<lb/>
yellow fever, to ports in the United States south of the southern boundary<lb/>
of Maryland under the following conditions:</p>
<p>&check; (a) The vessel must lie at approved moorings in the open harbor;<lb/>
the crew must not be allowed ashore at the port of departure. Every poss-<lb/>
ible precaution must be taken to prevent the ingress of stegomyia mosquit-<lb/>
oes and their access to the crew.</p>
<p>&check; (b) The officer who must go ashore to enter his vessel must be<lb/>
immune to yellow fever. Passengers, unless immune to yellow fever, must<lb/>
have been free from possible exposure to yellow fever for six days immed-<lb/>
iately prior to embarking.</p>
<p>&check; (c) All the above conditions to be certified to specifically<lb/>
by an accredited medical officer of the United States.</p>
<p>88. All persons who can prove their immunity to yellow fever<lb/>
or who have not been exposed to possible infection of yellow fever, may<lb/>
&check; be permitted to land at once.</p>
<p>89. For the destruction of mosquitoes there shall be a complete<lb/>
and simultaneous fumigation of all parts of the vessel by sulphur dioxide<lb/>
<unclear>&check;</unclear> gas, 2 per cent volume gas, two hours' exposure, or by cyanide gas in<lb/>
strength of 1/2 ounce of cyanide per 1,000 cubic feet of space, one-half<lb/>
hour exposure.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
