<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00915008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, September 6, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00915008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-09-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph W.</name>
<name type="person">Pickett, I. W.</name>
<name type="person">Corrigan, John P.</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, Lawrence H.</name>
<name type="person">Guildstrand, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Read, Florence M.</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Pacasmayo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lambayeque (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Libertad (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-09-06">September 6, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00915008</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, September 6, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In a report on the yellow fever work in Peru, Hanson discusses financial matters, correspondence received, the help extended by White and Carter, and manpower needs. Hanson declares the campaign is going well.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-09-06">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, September 6, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00915008"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.<lb/>
<date value="1921-09-06">September 6, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Wicliffe Rose, General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York City.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am <unclear>surpirsed</unclear> to note by your letter of May <unclear>26</unclear>, that the<lb/>
Peruvian Consul in New York had charged you to the amount of $80.00 on the<lb/>
shipment of serum and vaccine for Peru. I will take this matter up at the<lb/>
earliest possible opportunity, and feel quite certain that instructions will<lb/>
be given without delay that these charges be remitted, and that there be no<lb/>
further charges on materials of this kind. I will write the Salubridad about<lb/>
the matter and follow the thing up when I get to Lima on my next trip.</p>
<p>In your letter of May 21, you speak of an advance of $30,000, in<lb/>
addition to previous appropriations. According to my records I have had $35,000,<lb/>
received here in addition to the $5,000, which I cashed in the National City<lb/>
Bank in Lima, before coming up to take complete charge of the Campaign. In<lb/>
addition to this there is the $500, which you gave to Corrigan and Pickett.<lb/>
Up to date we have not been able to turn in a detailed statement of the funds<lb/>
used in the Province of Trujillo, because at first I was hoping that the Govern-<lb/>
ment would advance sufficient funds to keep that section going, and in order not<lb/>
to have any interruption in the work there I advanced certain sums there from time<lb/>
to time, which we entered in the local books, as money advanced (<unclear>dinero</unclear> adelantado<lb/>
<unclear>en</unclear> calidad de prestamo) thinking that we would be able to reimburse these funds<lb/>
from money received from the Government. This we have never been able to do. For<lb/>
this reason as soon as Mr. Guldstarnd has the accounts for this section checked<lb/>
we will send them on and he will go on to check up on the Province of Pacasmayo,<lb/>
and to examine the accounts for the Province of Trujillo and the balance of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00915009"/>
2. W.R., I.H.B., September 6, 1921.<lb/>
campaign to the south. We will then send you a complete resume of expenditures<lb/>
up to the end of the month of August.</p>
<p>I think that it will be necessary to have an available working capital<lb/>
of about $10,000, a month. I cabled you to this effect yesterday, copy of cable<lb/>
enclosed. Were it not for the fact that we may be obliged to take all of the<lb/>
employees on your payroll, we might get along with less. With the exchange as it<lb/>
is now it works very much to our adavantage so far as all native employees, and<lb/>
local expenses are concerned. In regard to the exchange however, the local banks<lb/>
do not give me the same rate as the Lima Banks do. This matter was discussed with<lb/>
Mr. Calvin of the National City Bank in Lima, who suggested that I convert all my<lb/>
money there in order to get the best rate. The trouble with this is the rates<lb/>
which these local banks charge on taking Lima checks,- I will investigate this<lb/>
further. Some time ago <unclear>.August</unclear> 4th, I cashed $4500, here and got a rate of <unclear>$3.0</unclear>,<lb/>
while about the same time the pound was selling in Lima for about $3.20, repre-<lb/>
senting a difference of about Lp 82.7.20.</p>
<p>I believe that it will be possible to reduce the expenses considerably<lb/>
from now on. It certainly would if we could get the Government to come across with<lb/>
pay for the Medical Officers. I received a wireless from the Salubridad <unclear>the</unclear> day<lb/>
after I returned asking how much they owed me, which I presume they think should<lb/>
should encourage me to think that they are thinking about paying <unclear>me</unclear>. I replied<lb/>
indicating the months which were due but have heard nothing further. I do not like<lb/>
the idea of being obliged to take my salary out of your funds if it can be avoided.<lb/>
However I was compelled to send Mrs. Hanson some more funds, and sent her a check<lb/>
on the Equitable Trust Co., Check # 19, for $500. (five hundred) which I marked<lb/>
chargable to salary of Director Yellow Fever Campaign Peru. If the Government pays<lb/>
I will return this amount to the working capital of the campaign. I took the<lb/>
liberty of doing this on the strength of your cable to me in Panama, as follows:</p>
<p>HANSON CARE CHIEF HEALTH OFFICER BALBOA<lb/>
SALARY YOURSELF AND EMPLOYEES FROM ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION FUNDS<lb/>
APPROVED IN ACCORDANCE WITH KIRKS LETTER JUNE THIRD<lb/>
EMPLOY DUNN IF YOU NEED HIM PERU<lb/>
INTERCOM.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00915010"/>
<p>#3. W.R., I.H.B., September 6, 1921.</p>
<p>I am glad to note what you say about the progress in Mexico. Are they<lb/>
using fish freely? Fish distributed freely and properly controlled is the surest<lb/>
and quickest method of control that I know of, and I think that we have tried every-<lb/>
thing else that seems practical. I enclose two reports from Mr. Corrigan of his<lb/>
work in the south which I believe you will find interesting. In this you will note<lb/>
that we have also used tadpoles and shrimps.</p>
<p>Re your letter of May 23 introducing Dr. Hoffman, I am sorry not to have<lb/>
had the opportunity of meeting him. I received a letter from him addressed to me<lb/>
at Lima, but this letter also reached me a long time after the date which he had<lb/>
set for his visit to Lima. I wrote him at the <unclear>home</unclear> office as I did not have any<lb/>
other way of being certain of eventually reaching him.</p>
<p>Re your letter of May 27, advising me of Dr. Whites coming, I wish to re-<lb/>
<unclear>iterate</unclear> what I have already said that I was very glad indeed to meet him and to<lb/>
have him see what and how we were doing our work. I am always ready to profit by<lb/>
the experience of men who know more about the work than I do, and it is a real<lb/>
pleasure to be associated with men like Dr. White and Dr. Carter, they know a<lb/>
thing when they see it. Dr. Carter's presence here last year and the first part<lb/>
of this was vital to the final outcome of the campaign, it can not be overestimated.<lb/>
I discussed my plans freely with Dr. White and believe that we are quite <unclear>agreed</unclear> as<lb/>
to the <unclear>procedure</unclear> for the future.</p>
<p>Miss Read speaks in her letter of June 21, of the circulars number <unclear>122</unclear><lb/>
and 122-A which I sent up, and says that they have been referred to the Comptrollers<lb/>
Office. In a campaign of this kind with as many changes as we have had a circular<lb/>
soon becomes <unclear>obsolete</unclear>. Both of these have been considerably modified since that date.</p>
<p>Miss read in her letter of June 29, speaks hopefully of the resulst of my<lb/>
interview with the President in regard to funds. I also hoped, and now <unclear>am</unclear> doing the<lb/>
&ldquo;watchful waiting&rdquo;. I have Mr. Kirk's letters of May 13 and June 3 to which she<lb/>
refers.</p>
<p>In regard to the cable referred in the letter of July 12, i received one<lb/>
copy in ample time and suffered no inconvenience due to the slight delay.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00915011"/>
<p>4. W.R., I.H.B., September 6, 1921.</p>
<p>In Miss Read's letter of July 14, she speaks of the translation of Dr.<lb/>
Carter's lecture on yellow fever. We also have made a translation of the same<lb/>
article, and in addition also the first lecture. I will send you a copy of this<lb/>
translation. Our <unclear>Interpretor</unclear> is a Columbian and I think an unusually good <unclear>translator</unclear>.<lb/>
He has read the <unclear>translation</unclear> made by you and pronounces it very good. He has a few<lb/>
minor differences but nothing of importance. We are preparing a list of persons<lb/>
whom we think may be interested in this article.</p>
<p>I have your copy of letter to Dr. White under date of July 16, which I<lb/>
doubt that he received before leaving. I also <unclear>found</unclear> three other letters form him<lb/>
from the International Health Board on my return. I have forwarded all these to<lb/>
him in Washington.</p>
<p>In this letter you speak of sporadic cases in eastern Mexico. If we<lb/>
should have any more cases here they will be sporadic cases among the small places<lb/>
which you will note on the map of Lambayeque up near or in the foothills of the<lb/>
mountains. Even if this does occur it is very doubtful that we will ever hear of<lb/>
them because there is no medical assistance in that section. I do not think it is<lb/>
<unclear>worthwhile</unclear> to spend any money in that section for the present at least. We have the<lb/>
entire coast down to less than one percent of breeding with very few exceptions, and<lb/>
in no place that I know of either in Lambayeque of Libertad do we have over <unclear>2%</unclear> of<lb/>
the containers <unclear>breading</unclear>. From Corrigans reports it seems that the Department of<lb/>
Ancash is already controlled. Before the end of the month we will tackle the north-<lb/>
ern part of the Department of Lima. If you think that we are spreading out too much<lb/>
I trust you <unclear>will</unclear> criticise freely.</p>
<p>In your letter of July <unclear>20</unclear>, you <unclear>motion</unclear> statistical reports. We have sent<lb/>
you what we had of the officially confirmed cases from the Department of Libertad.<lb/>
These are more nearly complete that those we have from the Department of Lambayeque<lb/>
but at that they also are incomplete. Our officially confirmed cases here in this<lb/>
department are only a few hundred, which is a small fraction of what the total<lb/>
actually was. We are checking up as much as possible on these and will send you<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00915012"/>
5. W.R., I.H.B., September 6, 1921.<lb/>
copies. We are working up certain maps and records which we think important, of<lb/>
which I presume Dr. White will <unclear>have</unclear> told you before you receive this.</p>
<p>The blanks to which you refer (vaccination blanks) I have never received.<lb/>
We have taken certain records and will forward copies as I presume you wish these<lb/>
for your files.</p>
<p>In regard to Corrigan and Pickett, I discussed this matter with Dr. White<lb/>
and we dicided that it was justifiable to keep them on for a little longer until<lb/>
we should have the coast particularly well surveyed. The have done most excellent<lb/>
work, and have been <unclear>worth almost</unclear> twice what ordinary less trained men would have<lb/>
<unclear>been</unclear> worth. They have the big advantage of their last years campaign, both in know-<lb/>
ing the people and the peculiarities of the local breeding conditions. It is also a<lb/>
big advantage to me in having some men that I know with certainty that I can de-<lb/>
pend on in any detail that I assign them. However as I stated in my cable I shall<lb/>
terminate their <unclear>services</unclear> as soon as possible after the arrival of Mr. Dunn who I<lb/>
will use in the south, with his headquarters in <unclear>Huacho</unclear>.</p>
<p>In regard to your letter of the 29th of July quoting cables, I beg to say<lb/>
that I have taken note of your attitude in regard to furnishing funds, and I hope<lb/>
the Government will appreciate it. When I get to Lima I will see what can be<lb/>
gotten there. In so far as the epidemic is concerned it seems to be over. However<lb/>
we are still carrying on our work as though it were not yet over.</p>
<p>Your letter of August 8th has also been received. I am glad to say that<lb/>
that incident has been happily closed. I am told that this letter at first occasioned<lb/>
the threat of a challenge to a <unclear>duel</unclear>.</p>
<p>Trusting that I may be able to continue giving as good a report, and with<lb/>
a <unclear>reiteration</unclear> of my gratitude for your help and advice,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson,<lb/>
Director of Campaign</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
