<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00918001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Clinical Blood Findings in Yellow Fever, by J. Birney Guthrie, M.D. and R.T. Perkins, M.D., [1921?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00918001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-00-00">[1921?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00918001</idno>
<title>Report: Clinical Blood Findings in Yellow Fever, by J. Birney Guthrie, M.D. and R.T. Perkins, M.D., [1921?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a detailed report on clinical findings regarding yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-00-00">
<head>Report: Clinical Blood Findings in Yellow Fever, by J. Birney Guthrie, M.D. and R.T. Perkins, M.D., [1921?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00918001"/>
<opener>
CLINICAL BLOOD FINDINGS IN YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
Miss<lb/>
Y. F<lb/>
<unclear>Y.</unclear><lb/>
J. Birney Guthrie M. D. and R. T. Perkins, M. D.<lb/>
<dateline>
Tulane University, New Orleans, La.<lb/>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>______________________________________________</p>
<p>The object of this work was to determine, if possible, whether any<lb/>
characteristic picture existed which would furnish aid in the diagnosis of<lb/>
this disease. To this end, we made a determination of haemoglobin, a count<lb/>
of the red blood corpuscles, a calculation of the color-index, <add>an actual <unclear>husvey</unclear> to count</add> an examina-<lb/>
tion of stained smears, and a differential leucocyte countbased on at<lb/>
least 400 counted cells. This entire examination was made usually on the<lb/>
first day of admission. In five selected cases which clinically were typ-<lb/>
ical, a daily count was made until death or convalescence occurred, on or-<lb/>
der to note the changes in the course of the disease, from day to day.<lb/>
These serial counts are embodied in the paper.</p>
<p>The Thoma-Zeiss counter was used for the count of red and white cor-<lb/>
puscles. The haemoglobin was determined with the instruments of Dare, Gow-<lb/>
er, and occasionally with the Talquist Scale. We found that the Gower in-<lb/>
strument was most useful owing to convenience, and comparison with the<lb/>
Dare instrument showed uniform results. The Talquist Scale was unsuitable<lb/>
fort the very high haemoglobin findings which we encountered. The von Flei-<lb/>
schl instrument was used only in a few cases, because it was obtained only<lb/>
near the end of the epidemic. The smears were stained with Wright's modi-<lb/>
fication of the Romanowsky stain, or with the original Giemsa<del>mixture</del><add>mixture,</add><lb/>
after fixation in Merch's methyl alcohol. Sahli's polychrome methylene blue<lb/>
and also haematoxylon, counterstained with 1-1000 aqueous water-soluble<lb/>
<unclear>cosin</unclear> were also employed from time to time. These last two were used as<lb/>
a comtrol and had no special value.</p>
<p>The <del>stains</del><add>smears</add> stained by the Wright method were most easily prepared,<lb/>
and formed the basis for practically all of this clinical work. The Giem-<lb/>
sa stain was the cleanest of all and this factor made it especially de-<lb/>
sirable in the fascinating search for the parasite of the disease, which<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00918002"/>
at that time had not been found.</p>
<p>The cells which in our tables are classed as large and small mono-<lb/>
nuclears, we counted and recorded as large and small lymphocytes- a class-<lb/>
ification which was usual at that time(1905).</p>
<p>INSERT TABLE # 1.</p>
<p>Table 1 was was tabulated from the results of the clinical blood<lb/>
findings in forty-one cases of undisputed yellow fever. All doubtful cases<lb/>
were excluded and all cases in which plasmodia malariae were found, even<lb/>
though we agreed in several of these, that there was a double infection of<lb/>
yellow fever in a patient who at the same time was the host of malarial<lb/>
parasites.</p>
<p>As nearly as possible the same technic of the count was adhered to<lb/>
by each of us, and frequent checking showed that there was a uniformity of<lb/>
results. Variations from the personal equation of the one counting were,<lb/>
therefore, we believe, small. The 41 counts recorded in <unclear><del>the</del></unclear> Table 1 were<lb/>
made from the 1st to the 8th day of the illness.</p>
<p>All of the clinical findings we had collected were grouped and<lb/>
put together into Tables 2 and 3. In these tables the findings were put to-<lb/>
gether, classified, according to the day of the disease, and the averages<lb/>
on these days calculated. Co-ordinates were thereby obtained which repre-<lb/>
sented the average picture presented by our available data in fatal and<lb/>
non-fatal cases, and the observations were made to as late a period as<lb/>
they remained in the hospital. After the 5th day in the in the fatal cases<lb/>
and after the 9th day in the non-fatal cases, the number of observations<lb/>
are regrettably few. The average duration of the case in these series of<lb/>
fatal cases was 8 days.</p>
<p>Our conclusions, based on a study of the pictures thus obtained,<lb/>
are the following:</p>
<p>Haemoglobin in uniformly increased, averaging 11 in our series of<lb/>
41 fatal and non-fatal cases. The highest recorded reading was 138%, in<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00918003"/>
<unclear>casde</unclear><lb/>
case 87, a fatal case. The lowest was in two cases, both of which recov-<lb/>
ered- 80%.</p>
<p>There is nothing in our records which shows any marked difference<lb/>
in percent haemoglobin between the recovered and the fatal cases. Nothing<lb/>
indicates a diminution of <unclear>haemoglobin</unclear> of any marked degree in convalescence<lb/>
or ever below normal. However, there seems to be an approach to normal as<lb/>
convalescence progresses. This one would expect to see. The count of ery-<lb/>
throcytes varies also with the haemoglobin; but the increase in even more<lb/>
pronounced. The color-index for the entire series is.909. <unclear>The</unclear> maximum red<lb/>
blood count was 6,808,000; this was in case 82, a fatal case, which also<lb/>
showed the largest percentage of haemoglobin. <unclear>The</unclear>lowest erythrocyte<lb/>
count was 4,152,000 inc case 152 which recovered. This case gave a haemo-<lb/>
globin of 117% at this time. The average red blood count in the 41 cases<lb/>
was 5,892,000.</p>
<p>The actual leucocyte count was usually low and distinctly lower<lb/>
than normal. Our series averaged 5,002 although there stand out in the<lb/>
columns two counts, one, case 162, fatal, of 15,175 and case 124 fatal of<lb/>
11,300. In neither of these cases were we able to determine the cause of<lb/>
the relatively high leucocyte count.</p>
<p>The lowest count was 2,175 occurring in case 157, which died. There<lb/>
can be no doubt that yellow fever is characterized by a diminution in the<lb/>
actual leucocyte count<unclear>,</unclear>occuring in both fatal and more favorable cases.<lb/>
No data of prognostic importance is indicated bty the tables, except it<lb/>
be a confirmation of an impression we receive after a summer's work that<lb/>
a high leucocyte count occurring early was a grave indication. All uncom<lb/>
plicated cases with a leucocyte count of over eight thousand died. The<lb/>
differential count of leucocytes shows some diminution in the large mon<lb/>
onuclears, a slight increase in polymorhonuclears and small mononuclears.<lb/>
The eosinphiles are markedly diminished. This is noticable even where the<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00918004"/>
<del>existing</del> existence of intestinal parasites had been demonstrated.<lb/>
Basophiles are almost lacking. A very frequently encountered cell<lb/>
in examination of the smear were &ldquo;Ghosts&rdquo; of leucocytes. These showed<lb/>
no exoplasm as a rule and consisted of the rements of a reticulated<lb/>
nucleus usually of the transitional approaching the polymorhular<lb/>
nuclar type. Scattered about this nucleus were <del>the</del> granules stained <unclear>pu</unclear><lb/>
purple (Wright-Romanoskwy) which lay around the nucleus in groups as<lb/>
if a rupture of the cell had occurred. These degenerated form were not<lb/>
the result of technic in making the smears, for the reaction to the<lb/>
stain was distinctly different. This type of cell does not find a place<lb/>
in the columns of, our tables; but perhaps should have been included. It<lb/>
is much more frequently encountered than in normal blood.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
