<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00916036">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, November 22, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00916036</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-11-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Caballero, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Corrigan, John P.</name>
<name type="person">Sainz, Arturo</name>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Read, Florence M.</name>
<name type="person">Seeley, Morris Monroe</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, Lawrence H.</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Callao (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Casma (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Chorillos (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-11-22">November 22, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00916036</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, November 22, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson reports on the investigation of a possible yellow fever case.  He describes his field work and discusses personnel matters.  He hopes to bring the campaign to an end by the spring of 1922.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-11-22">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, November 22, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00916036"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION<lb/>
DE LA<lb/>
CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
Contra la Fiebre Amarilla<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
Departamentos del Norte<lb/>
____<lb/>
TRUJILLO<lb/>
__<lb/>
<dateline>
Trujillo, Per&uacute;<lb/>
<date value="1921-11-22">November 22, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Asst Surgeon General, U.S.P.H.S.,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I last wrote you aboard the S.S. Peru<lb/>
on my way to Lima to investigate the rumor of a case of yellow<lb/>
fever reported from Callao. When we arrived the case was dead<lb/>
and buried and we could get no other information than history<lb/>
and the autopsy findings. These were pretty evident that the<lb/>
case was one of pernicious malaria, but there were also other<lb/>
symptoms and findings which makes it a bit difficult to be<lb/>
certain that there was not something more in addition to the<lb/>
malaria. The man had a very marked astenia and turned very<lb/>
yellow before death. <unclear>H</unclear>e had vomiting, and bleeding gums, nose<lb/>
bleed and other symptoms quite typical of yellow fever accor-<lb/>
ding to Quiroz who saw him twice. In the autopsy they found<lb/>
a very marked congestion of the mucous membranes all the way<lb/>
down, kidneys showed an acute nephritis. Echymoses in the lungs<lb/>
etc, but the liver was not of the typical mustard yellow color<lb/>
which one finds in cases of several days duration. The liver<lb/>
was rather of a darker color and with more bleeding than one<lb/>
usually encounters in autopsies on yellow fever bodies.</p>
<p>Another point the case came from Casma, in the Depart-<lb/>
ment of Ancash but did not fall sick until about ten or twelve<lb/>
days after his arrival in Callao. They made quite a point of<lb/>
his having come down from up the coast, but this to me had no<lb/>
importance as I have practically no uneasiness about that sec-<lb/>
tion of the coast. There have been no cases reported from there<lb/>
and besides we have done fairly good work in all the coast towns<lb/>
of that Department. Dr. Caballero has been over it several times<lb/>
in addition to the work done by Corrigan and Sainz. Caballero<lb/>
has recently returned to go over the coast again. If it could<lb/>
have been a case it would mean that there has been a lurking<lb/>
focus somewhere about Lima or Callao and that he contracted his<lb/>
infection there. On this kind of a hypothesis I have decided<lb/>
that the best thing to do is to remove any doubts and go ahead<lb/>
with the clean up of all the coast at least as far south as<lb/>
Chorillos which will insure the outcome of the campaign and en-<lb/>
able us to accomplish our object of eliminating the fever this<lb/>
year, unless there is something further south, in Ica for example.</p>
<p>For your information I am enclosing copy of letter to<lb/>
Dr. Rose, and as I am writing Miss Read today I will send her a<lb/>
copy of the last letter I wrote you on this matter, also of<lb/>
this as it may serve as information to the board and save me a<lb/>
bit of time explaining things.</p>
<p>On account of the extent of the territory which we are<lb/>
watching I have arranged for Seeley to bring his family down<lb/>
and stay with me until we finish. He has done very good work and<lb/>
is very reliable and I will be able to depend on him for the<lb/>
northern section, i.e., the Department of Lambayeque and probably<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00916037"/>
2. Dr. H.R. Carter, November 22, 1921.<lb/>
also an occasional supervision of the Province of Pacasmayo.</p>
<p>I was surprised the other day while in Lima to get a cable<lb/>
from Corrigan that Fisher would allow him to come back, and in<lb/>
the cable he stated that he would leave it to me to fix his<lb/>
salary. I cabled back that I could not offer him over $450.00<lb/>
and if he wanted to come at that to come on with Seeley. I also<lb/>
cabled Rose at the same time and he evidently agreed as he said<lb/>
nothing to the contrary in the cable replying to some other<lb/>
matters in my message. I had told Seeley to get Bumiller and I<lb/>
had authorized him to offer Bumiller $350.00, but when Seeley<lb/>
arrived in Panama Bumiller had gone to the states, I had pre-<lb/>
viously sent a message for him to wait a few days but this<lb/>
miserable telegraph we have had so balled my message up that<lb/>
it had an entirely different meaning when Fisher received it.</p>
<p>On account of the high stegomya index which we continue to<lb/>
find as we advance to the south I have decided that the only<lb/>
safe thing to do is to continue with the cleaning up process.<lb/>
It will cost the I.H.B., a little more money, but the thing they<lb/>
are after is to make sure and in such a case it is poor policy<lb/>
to economize too much. I did not expect to be obliged to continue<lb/>
with the high priced supervision until we concluded to clean up<lb/>
everything from the Rimac valley north. The condition in the<lb/>
Rimac valley and in the valley of the Chillon could be a danger-<lb/>
ous one and remain as a residual if left as it is now.</p>
<p>When Corrigan comes I shall have him take up the work on the<lb/>
coast where Dunn has been working. Corrigan and Caballero can<lb/>
control everything from the Chancay valley in the Department of<lb/>
Lima to the Southern boundry of the Department of Libertad and<lb/>
Tapia is taking good care of the Province of Trujillo with<lb/>
Machado and Ramirez as supervising inspectors. Valdivieso who has<lb/>
been acting as general supervising inspector in this province will<lb/>
now be transferred to the southern sector to work with Mendoza in<lb/>
the south. I have also transferred Benites from Guadelupe to<lb/>
Callao and Adrienzen has the supervision of the whole province of<lb/>
Pacasmayo. He has several young fellows there who have turned out<lb/>
to be good reliable visitadores.</p>
<p>Before we conclude the campaign I shall probably make a tour<lb/>
of inspection farther south, with the object of ascertaining what<lb/>
has happened if anything in Ica where they have a great deal of<lb/>
hot weather and stegomya breeding.</p>
<p>In the cable from Rose received today he states that he ex-<lb/>
pects me to continue until April or May. This is the time which<lb/>
I now think it necessary to continue the campaign. Now that we<lb/>
have established an office in Lima I shall bring my family back<lb/>
I have secured a completely furnished house in Miraflores in<lb/>
which we can manage to get along until the closing of the cam-<lb/>
paign. Martha objects very strenuously to being away from her<lb/>
Daddy, also her Daddy objects to being away from her all the time.</p>
<p>I dont know what arrangements Mrs. Hanson has made about Karl.<lb/>
If she brings him back I shall put him to work with Dunn in the<lb/>
stegomya research, this will keep him both interested an occupied<lb/>
and may be of some help to Dunn.</p>
<p>Trusting that you will let me know what you think about this<lb/>
program, I am with best wishes,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>,
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
