<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00916038">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Estanislao Pardo Figueroa, November 26, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00916038</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-11-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Figueroa, Estanislao Pardo</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Arce, Julian</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Quiroz, M.J.</name>
<name type="person">Mendoza, Ricardo</name>
<name type="person">Caballero, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lambayeque (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-11-26">November 26, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00916038</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Estanislao Pardo Figueroa, November 26, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson refers to the Academy of Medicine meeting to study epidemics of yellow fever.  He rebuts the contention of a Peruvian physician to the absence of yellow fever in the area, noting that the goal of the campaign is to insure against recurrence.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-11-26">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Estanislao Pardo Figueroa, November 26, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00916038"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION<lb/>
DE LA<lb/>

CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
Contra la Fiebre Amarilla<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
Departamentos del Norte<lb/>
----<lb/>
TRUJILLO<lb/>
--<lb/>
<hi>Hanson</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Trujillo,<lb/>
<date value="1921-11-26">November 26, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Estanislao Pardo Figueroa,<lb/>
President of the Academy of Medicine,<lb/>
Lima, Per&uacute;.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wish to express to you my appreciation of the<lb/>
courtesy which you extended in inviting me to attend the sessions<lb/>
of the Academy of Medicine for the purpose of studying the epi-<lb/>
demics of yellow fever in <unclear>Peru</unclear>.</p>
<p>It is very gratifying to me and to the other Physicians<lb/>
who have labored in <unclear>these</unclear> campaigns to note the interest taken<lb/>
by the Academy for the purpose of arriving at the true nature of<lb/>
the epidemics in the Departments of the North during the last<lb/>
two years and a half. I was very much interested in <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
hearing the view point of Dr. Julian Arce in regard to the matter.<lb/>
I had heard from many different sources that he did not believe<lb/>
that we were dealing with yellow fever, and it had aroused a<lb/>
great deal of curiosity in my mind to know on what grounds he<lb/>
based his arguments. While I think I obtained his viewpoint in<lb/>
the three session which I attended, I still regret that I could<lb/>
not attend them all. His review of the history of yellow fever<lb/>
and his discussion of the recent epidemics was very interesting<lb/>
indeed, and I wish to further express my grateful appreciation<lb/>
to Dr. Arce for his courtesy in concluding his discussions before<lb/>
I sailed for the north.</p>
<p>The object of this letter is to, if possible, explain<lb/>
certain points which he referred to, on which it appears that he<lb/>
has <del><unclear></unclear></del> received incorrect information; also to add certain<lb/>
data for the convenience of the Academy of Medicine in case this<lb/>
honourable body desires to further consider the matter.</p>
<p>It is interesting to note that Dr. Arce considers the<lb/>
existence to two distinct types of black water fever (fiebre<lb/>
biliosa hemoglobinurica) due to different etiological agents,<lb/>
and that one of these <unclear>apperrs</unclear> in epidemics and confers immunity<lb/>
to subsequent attacks, <add>while</add> the other it seems he accepts as the black<lb/>
water fever of malarious sections and as due to the untoward<lb/>
effects of chronic malaria especially in tropical countries where<lb/>
there is a relatively large amount of <del>pernicious malaria</del>. the <unclear>pernicious</unclear><lb/>
type of this <unclear>diseases</unclear></p>
<p>In regard to black water fever I wish to say that we<lb/>
have seen no cases of this <del>type</del> among the patients observed by<lb/>
the Medical Staff of the Sanitary campaigns against yellow fever<lb/>
during the last two years and a half. In none of the cases ob-<lb/>
served and included in our statistics has there been any <del>case</del><lb/>
with either intermitent or continuous &ldquo;black water&rdquo; <del>urine</del> or <del>of</del> with<lb/>
urine of the color of port wine. Such a striking clinical mani-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00916039"/>
2. Dr. Estanislao Pardo Figueroa, November 26, 1921.<lb/>
festation would have received the careful attention of all the<lb/>
medical officers of the campaign, and would have been received<lb/>
with welcome as an evidence that it were unnecessary to continue<lb/>
our campaign. The urines of all <del>the cases</del> which figure in the<lb/>
statistics of the oficially confirmed cases were carefully<lb/>
observed for any such evidences of hemoglobinuria, and as I<lb/>
have stated in none were they found.</p>
<p>Furthermore if <del>the cases</del><add><unclear>there</unclear></add> observed by us in this epidemic<lb/>
or better said in these epidemics, were cases of biliosa hemoglo-<lb/>
binuria, why have they disappeared with the disappearance of the<lb/>
stegomya mosquito (Aedes Calopus, more recently designated as the<lb/>
Aedes Argentis)?</p>
<p>As you know there were a great many cases of black water<lb/>
fever in Panama in the district of the Canal Zone during the early<lb/>
days both before and after the yellow fever was eradicated from<lb/>
that territory. The yellow fever made its last appearance in<lb/>
Panama (i.e., with in the territory designated as the Canal Zone<lb/>
and the cities of Panama and Colon) in the year 1905, but cases<lb/>
of black water fever continued presenting themselves until recent<lb/>
years or until the malaria index was very markedly reduced,  show-<lb/>
ing for Panama a very evident relationship between the malaria<lb/>
index and black water fever, but none between yellow fever and<lb/>
black water fever. Hence in Panama <del>and</del> there was no relationship<lb/>
between the stegomya index and and cases of &ldquo;biliosa hemoglobin-<lb/>
urica&rdquo; while there distinctly was between the anopheles index<lb/>
and black water fever.</p>
<p>In consulting our statistics for the epidemics in Per&uacute;<lb/>
from July 1919 to the last cases seen by us in July 1921, it<lb/>
will be seen that the epidemics have attacked with preference<lb/>
young people and foreigners. Almost without exception all cases<lb/>
over 25 years of age have been foreigners or people recently<lb/>
arrived from the mountain districts. Such facts are in full<lb/>
harmony with the epidemiology of yellow fever. Furthermore<lb/>
among the foreigners who have arrived and who have previously<lb/>
had yellow fever no one has been attacked even though they have<lb/>
been quite extensively exposed while on the other hand all the<lb/>
foreigners none-immune to yellow fever who have been extensively<lb/>
exposed have been attacked by the fever. Of all persons attacked<lb/>
by the fever in the recent epidemics none have had a second<lb/>
attack.</p>
<p>In consulting the blue-print of the graphic chart of<lb/>
the campaign in the Department of Lambayeque you will see the<lb/>
definite relationship between the number of sick and the per-<lb/>
centage of stegomya breeding. In this chart there are no cases of yellow<lb/>
fever shown of fever after the Stegomya index has remaind low for a<lb/>
sufficient time to have eliminated the adult infected mosquito.<lb/>
In such a case in order to say that this <unclear>epdemic</unclear> has been one<lb/>
of black water fever, or &ldquo;fiebre biliosa homoglobinurica&rdquo; one<lb/>
would have to prove that the Stegomya is also the vector of the<lb/>
infection of the matter disease which is still <del>unproven.</del> to be proven.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00916040"/>
<p>3. Dr. Estanislao Pardo Figueroa, November 26, 1921.</p>
<p>In justice to Dr. Henry R. Carter, Assistant Surgeon<lb/>
General of the United States Public Health Service, and member<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Committee of the International Health<lb/>
Board of the Rockefeller Foundation, I can say that he did not<lb/>
consider the yellow fever to have been endemic in the coast<lb/>
of Per&uacute;, but even if he had he is a person of sufficient ex-<lb/>
perience and training in both yellow fever and malaria to be<lb/>
quite competent to distinguish between the two. It is possible<lb/>
that Dr. Arce may have been mislead in his reference to Dr.<lb/>
Carter on account of the unfounded statements of Dr. Mariano<lb/>
Pagador, who made very disparaging remarks in connection with<lb/>
Dr. Carter's proceedure in the examination of cases in Ferre&ntilde;afe.<lb/>
Dr. Pagador never saw Dr. Carter or myself examine a single case<lb/>
and never discussed or conversed with Dr. Carter about the matter<lb/>
of yellow fever in any form whatsoever.</p>
<p>In reference to the requirement of Dr. Arce that the<lb/>
route of introduction of the yellow fever into Peru be proven<lb/>
I wish to say that in so far as I and the other physicians who<lb/>
have studied the recent epidemics are concerned, this has been<lb/>
satisfactorily demonstrated. Still I consider this an unnecessary<lb/>
essential in establishing the diagnosis of yellow fever. <unclear>Suchx</unclear><lb/>
It has been common knowledge that yellow fever existed in<lb/>
Guayaquil continuously up to the time of the announcement of the<lb/>
epidemic in Piura in June 1919, and the person who has investiga-<lb/>
ted the travel and means of communication between Ecuador and<lb/>
the northern province of Per&uacute; can only explain the absence of the<lb/>
fever from Per&uacute; on the grounds that the former epidemics, in<lb/>
1894-95-96 and 97, left the population in the northern provinces<lb/>
immune, and a new outbreak could not occur until the increase in<lb/>
a sufficient non-immune population to allow a new general out-<lb/>
break. However the studies made by Dr. M.J. Quiroz in the Province<lb/>
of Tumbes are quite clear and convincing of the presence of<lb/>
yellow fever in that section before the epidemic in the Depart-<lb/>
ment of Piura in 1919. Dr. Quiroz has presented this so fully and<lb/>
so well that it is useless for me to discuss it.</p>
<p>Finally Dr. Julian Arce states in summing up his very<lb/>
interesting and instructive discourse, that he considers it<lb/>
essential to take the word of the Physicians in regard to the<lb/>
diagnosis inpreference to that of &ldquo;curanderos <unclear>e</unclear> empiricos&rdquo; and<lb/>
on this basis attempts to refute the facts presented by Dr.<lb/>
Quiroz. In this connection he cites DR. Reinoso, Dr. Zuniga, Dr.<lb/>
Angosto and Dr. Valcarcel. In so far as Dr. Zuniga is concerned<lb/>
he at first denied the presence of yellow fever and then later<lb/>
during the height of the epidemic in Paita saw and diagnosed<lb/>
about half of the cases in Paita. Dr. Reinoso declared himself<lb/>
in the Prefectura in Piura as convinced that the cases we were<lb/>
discussing were undoubted cases of yellow fever. Dr. Angosto<lb/>
I know nothing about- it may be possible that the cases seen<lb/>
by him may have been cases of malaria or &ldquo;fiebre biliosa hemo-<lb/>
globinurica&rdquo;. But in so far as Dr. Valcarcel&ldquo; M&eacute;dico Sanitario<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00916041"/>
4. Dr. Estanislao Pardo Figueroa, November 26, 1921.<lb/>
Departamental&rdquo; for the Department of Piura in 1919 and 1920,<lb/>
is concerned I wish to say that Dr. Valcarcel in our first con-<lb/>
ference in the Prefectura in Piura accepted the diagnosis of<lb/>
yellow fever, then in the street he denied it, later he reitera-<lb/>
ted to me and to Dr. Quiroz in the presence of Mr. Hope of the<lb/>
Duncan Fox Co., that it was and later again denied it and<lb/>
finally while he was in Sechura in February and March of 1920<lb/>
he was the first Physician to announce the presence of yellow<lb/>
fever in that place. Hence it seems to me that it is difficult<lb/>
for a scientific body like the Academy of Medicine of Lima, to<lb/>
place any reliance on these men who have contradicted themselves<lb/>
in this manner. The other Physician in Piura who denied the<lb/>
diagnosis was Dr. Cueva and he was consistent in his denial, but<lb/>
I was informed that as soon as the diagnosis was established he<lb/>
took all possible precautions to protect himself and family <unclear>against</unclear><lb/>
infection. Also another point before closing this portion of the<lb/>
discussion. Dr. Valcarcel never took any active part in the Cam-<lb/>
paign in Morropon, this epidemic was under the control of Dr. Ri-<lb/>
cardo Mendoza M., and Dr. Enrique Caballero, two very sincere and<lb/>
competent professionals.</p>
<p>In Piura the diagnosis was confirmed by Dr. Prieta, Dr.<lb/>
Gonzales, Dr. Guzman, Dr. Lituma, Dr. Marcos Vega, Dr. M.J. Quiroz and<lb/>
in addition by a Sr. Saona who had worked a long time in the<lb/>
yellow fever hospitals in Guayaquil. In addition the diagnosis<lb/>
was confirmed by Dr. Reinoso to whom Dr. Arce refers. Later the<lb/>
diagnosis was confirmed for other sections of the Department by<lb/>
Dr. Enrique Caballero, Ricardo Mendoza M., Benjamin Zapata, Chiri,<lb/>
Meldonada, Cruz, Victor Dies Canseco, Dr. Corsiglio (who later died<lb/>
with yellow fever in Paita), General Gorgas, Dr. H.R. Carter and<lb/>
the writer.</p>
<p>In the Department of Lambayeque the only Physician who<lb/>
has denied the diagnosis is Dr. Mariano Pagador, and in so far as<lb/>
I can ascertain this young man had never before seen a case of<lb/>
yellow fever. The diagnosis in this department was confirmed by<lb/>
Dr. M.J. Quiroz, and the following physicians, Victor Dies Canseco,<lb/>
A. Alva Diaz, Julio Benavides, Mayor Carrera, Capitan Seminario,<lb/>
Ugaz, Rezetto, Agillar, Ponce, Muro Pacheco, Torres of Patapo,<lb/>
Novoa of Tuman and many others whose names I can not for the<lb/>
moment recall in addition to Dr. H.R. Carter and the writer.</p>
<p>In the Department of Libertad the only denial was that<lb/>
of a certain M. Helio Uceda, also a person who never before had<lb/>
seen a case of yellow fever, but his denial was principally a<lb/>
denial of the cases in Trujillo. The diagnosis in this Department<lb/>
was confirmed by all Physicians who saw and treated the cases.<lb/>
Among these were DR. L.G. Tapia, Dr. Blondet, Velez, Fernandez,<lb/>
Ortis Silva, Taboada, Arce Davila, Buzzi, Casteneda of Casa Grande,<lb/>
and others. In the Province of Pacasmayo the disease was denied<lb/>
by no one, but was confirmed by all who saw the cases such as<lb/>
Drs. Ricardo Mendoza, Nicolas Cavassa and <unclear>two. Physicians</unclear> in San<lb/>
Pedor whoses names I do not at this moment recall.</p>
<p>In addition to the above we had the pleasure of the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00916042"/>
5. Dr. Estanislao Pardo Figueroa, November 26, 1921.<lb/>
association and cooperation of the distinguished French Mili-<lb/>
tary Surgeon, Colonel Eduardo Vergne who is a scholar and a<lb/>
perfect gentleman. Colonel Vergne studied especially the cases<lb/>
among the troops and has made a publication in the Cronica<lb/>
Medica of Lima. In this publication the Academy has acces to<lb/>
the opinions of the Colonel in the matter.</p>
<p>In view of the foregoing it seems that upon the very<lb/>
grounds which your distinguished <unclear>colaborator</unclear> Dr. Julian Arce has<lb/>
required, namely that one who has not personally studied the<lb/>
cases in the field is obliged to accept that of the profession<lb/>
which has made sincere efforts to arrive at the truth in the<lb/>
matter. In fact one can say that the opinion among the Medical<lb/>
men both Peruvian and foreign is unanimous among those who have<lb/>
observed the cases. It does not seem reasonable that the opinion<lb/>
of those who have not studied any of the cases, or those who have<lb/>
made denials due to pressure from certain commercial and politi-<lb/>
cal influences, should be accepted contradicting the opinions of<lb/>
virtually all the professionals of the the coast to the north of<lb/>
Lima.</p>
<p>In conclusion I beg to repeat that I am very grateful<lb/>
for the opportunity of hearing Dr. Julian Arce's views in the<lb/>
matter and that I respect his opinions, but believe that he has<lb/>
been incorrectly informed in the matter. I feel quite certain<lb/>
that if Dr. Arce had come <unclear>up</unclear> to Lambayeque and studied the cases<lb/>
while the epidemic was at its height that he would have gone<lb/>
back to Lima quite satisfied that it was yellow fever and nothing<lb/>
else that we were contending with, and that we were actually<lb/>
rendering a valuable service to the country in the fight which<lb/>
we carried on so unrelentingly.</p>
<p>Assuring you of my very high esteem and appreciation<lb/>
for the opportunity of presenting to you this brief statement<lb/>
of facts about the recent epidemics. As you know the object of<lb/>
this years campaign is to assure Peru and the Pacific Coast of<lb/>
South America for all time against the recurrence of this<lb/>
scourge which has existed from- no one knows what time. It is<lb/>
for the sake of insuring the successful attainment of this object<lb/>
that the International Health Board has furnished funds <unclear>liberally</unclear><lb/>
paying nine tenths of the expenses of the campaign. Naturally if<lb/>
this well known <unclear>Institution</unclear> had not fully convinced themselves<lb/>
that these epidemics were yellow fever and nothing else they<lb/>
would not have continued to furnish all funds necessary for the<lb/>
work.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully submitted,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson, M.D.,<lb/>
Director of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Campaign in Per&uacute;</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
