<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00913001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report; Prophylaxis and Serum Therapy of Yellow Fever, by Hideyo Noguchi, July 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00913001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-07-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="person">Pareja, Wenceslao</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-07-00">July 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00913001</idno>
<title>Report: Prophylaxis and Serum Therapy of Yellow Fever, by Hideyo Noguchi, July 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Noguchi's paper on prophylaxis and serum therapy of yellow fever.  Discusses isolation of Leptospira icteroides, as well as experiments, efficacy of serum therapy of yellow fever and vaccination against yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-07-00">
<head>Report:Prophylaxis and Serum Therapy of Yellow Fever," by Hideyo Noguchi, July 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00913001"/>
<p>Prophylaxis and Serum Therapy<lb/>
of<lb/>
Yellow Fever.<lb/>
Hideyo Noguchi.<lb/>
Journal A. M. A., July 1921.</p>
<p>This is easily the most important paper in yellow fever<lb/>
literature that has appeared this year.</p>
<p>The writer begins by stating that Leptospira icteroides<lb/>
has been isolated from yellow fever patients by Peres-Grovas<lb/>
and by LeBlanc at Vera Cruz--he (Noguchi) recognizing the cul-<lb/>
tures as identical with the other strains of the same organ-<lb/>
ism: that Gastiabur&uacute; of Lima states that he has transmitted<lb/>
the same infection to guinea pigs from cases occurring during<lb/>
the epidemic in Piura and, finally, that the spirochete de-<lb/>
monstrated in 1907 by Stimson of the U. S. Public Health Ser-<lb/>
vice in a preperation stained by the Levaditi Method in the<lb/>
kidney of a yellow fever patient dying in the New Orleans<lb/>
epidemic of 1905 is identified by himself as Leptospira ic-<lb/>
teroides.</p>
<p>He states that "the symptoms and lesions produced in ani-<lb/>
mals by the inoculation of Leptospira icteroides &ldquo;closely par-<lb/>
allel those of human yellow fever and comprise mainly jaundice:<lb/>
hemorrhages and intense acute nephritis.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He admits that the guinea pig thus infected differ from<lb/>
the man with yellow fever in <hi>the degree</hi> in which these general<lb/>
lesions occur in the different tissues. In them hemorrhages<lb/>
are much more marked in the lungs and serous surfaces of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00913002"/>
of the<lb/>
2<lb/>
stomach and intestines than in man. In puppies, however, hem-<lb/>
orrhage into the lung substance is slight and that into the<lb/>
gastro-intestinal tract (from its mucous membrane) gives the<lb/>
&ldquo;black vomit&rdquo; and melena so characteristic of of yellow fever<lb/>
in man.</p>
<p>That the reactions of guinea pigs and man differ even to<lb/>
a considerable extent does not negative the <del>possibility</del><add><unclear>claim</unclear></add> that<lb/>
the toxins producing these reaction are from the same or-<lb/>
ganism. Evidently the reactions of dogs and guinea pigs to<lb/>
the same infection were quite different.</p>
<p>He further instances the specific immunity reactions for<lb/>
Leptospira icteroides with serum of yellow fever convales-<lb/>
cents in Guayaquil: Merida and Peru as contributing further<lb/>
proof of the etiological relation of the organism. With this<lb/>
the editor agrees.</p>
<p><hi>Serum Therapy of Yellow Fever.</hi></p>
<p>He then discusses the therapeutic effect of an immune<lb/>
(horse) serum (to Leptospira icteroides) on human yellow fev-<lb/>
er patients. Animal experiment had shown that this serum was<lb/>
efficacious in proportion to its early use, preventing the de-<lb/>
velopement of the disease if given during the period of incu-<lb/>
bation and favorably modifying it if given soon after its de-<lb/>
velopement, but at a later stage it showed no beneficial ef-<lb/>
fect.</p>
<p>He presents 170 patients treated by serum, 95 on or before<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00913003"/>
before<lb/>
before<lb/>
the 3rd. day<lb/>
3<lb/>
3<lb/>
the 3rd. day and 75 after that time. Of the first, the mor-<lb/>
tality was 13.6%: of the second, 52%, while the average mor-<lb/>
tality of the epidemics in which these cases occurred was<lb/>
56%.</p>
<p>Spite of this showing--and in spite also of the editor's<lb/>
belief (from his observations in Peru) in the efficacy of the<lb/>
serum used early--the data as assembled are not convincing.<lb/>
The most that can be said of them is that they are very sug-<lb/>
gestive and invite further trial. It may be that some data<lb/>
on this subject will be added in Hanson's report of the epi-<lb/>
demic in Peru of this year.</p>
<p><hi>Vaccination against Yellow Fever</hi>.</p>
<p>Vaccination is by killed <unclear>Cultures</unclear> of Leptospira icteroides<lb/>
given in two doses of 2 cc each subcutaneously. That furnished<lb/>
us in Peru was given with an interval of from 5 to 8 days.<lb/>
The culture medium contains a small amount of agar, difficult-<lb/>
ly absorbable, and the seat of infection must be <hi>well</hi> massaged<lb/>
for several minutes, else there may be severe reaction or even<lb/>
a sterile abcess. Intro-muscular injection is not advised,<lb/>
because the massage is apt to be less perfect.</p>
<p>A total of over 10,000 people had been vaccinated when<lb/>
this article was written--and more since that time. It is<lb/>
obviously innocuous, or at least fairly well borne. Now as<lb/>
to its efficacy! What of the proportionate incidence of<lb/>
yellow fever among the vaccinated and the unvaccinated, other<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00913004"/>
4<lb/>
other<lb/>
conditions being the same?</p>
<p>In the first place, <add>he</add> considers this incidence in two groups:<lb/>
(a) Those in which the fever developes within 10 days from<lb/>
the time of last inoculation and (b) Those in whom it takes<lb/>
place &ldquo;one month or longer&rdquo; after vaccination.</p>
<p>He has a perfect right to make this division and to claim<lb/>
that the vaccination is not protective until after ten days<lb/>
have passed from the 2nd. dose--which his figures bear out--<lb/>
but to base this claim on an incubation period for yellow fever<lb/>
of 12 days, &ldquo;experimentally established by the French Commis-<lb/>
sion in Brazil,&rdquo; is not only unnecessary, but is to use a<lb/>
most insecure foundation. His claim is that such cases as de-<lb/>
velope within 10 days, and they seem to have been fairly nu-<lb/>
merous, were contracted and were in the incubative stage prior<lb/>
to the vaccination. Yet of 43 cases of yellow fever, some ex-<lb/>
perimental and some with a single short exposure of a few hours,<lb/>
of which the period of incubation was carefully observed, the<lb/>
longest was 6 days and 2 hours. <add>And</add> I think that these are the<lb/>
only cases, naturally acquired, the incubation periods of which<lb/>
are accepted by sanitarians.</p>
<p>Not considering the (a) class of cases the author seems to<lb/>
make a very good showing for the protective value of vaccina-<lb/>
tion. His data, however, need, and will repay, examination.<lb/>
The difficulty under the present conditions of yellow fever work<lb/>
of obtaining data both reliable and determinative has been ex-<lb/>
treme, and if that here presented does not completely fill both<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00913005"/>
5<lb/>
both<lb/>
conditions, it is not to be wondered at.</p>
<p>Some of it strongly evidences the protective value of the<lb/>
vaccination. Thus: <del>Tuxpan--2,000 vaccinated--</del></p>
<p>Tuxpan--2,000 vaccinated;--- 17 cases, class (a)-- 0-class (b)<lb/>
4,000 unvaccinated:---------- 85 cases.</p>
<p>Los Amates, 660 population: 12 cases June 6th.--Aug. 12th.<lb/>
600 vaccinated, Aug. 20-30---2 cases class (a)--0 class (b)<lb/>
39 unvaccinated--------------- 1 case Sept. 31.</p>
<p>The remainder 38 vaccinated Sept. 31st. gave no further<lb/>
cases.</p>
<p>Nothing is said as to whether other measures of control of the<lb/>
fever were adopted at this <add>last</add> place or no. I presume that if they<lb/>
had been it had been mentioned. This would <add>not</add> seem to have been<lb/>
even a possible factor in the result at Tuxpan as 85 cases oc-<lb/>
curred among the unvaccinated as compared with 34--the number<lb/>
which would have occurred in the same number of vaccinated. For<lb/>
a comparison, however, we must assume that such conditions of<lb/>
life as involve liability to control yellow fever other than<lb/>
the vaccination were approximately the same in the two groups.<lb/>
A greater difference than this existed in different sections of<lb/>
New Orleans in 1897.</p>
<p>Unless <del><add>then</add></del> there was a considerable difference in the above<lb/>
mentioned conditions of life protective to the vaccinated<lb/>
group, the difference in the rate of incidence is too great to<lb/>
allow other interpretation from these statistics than that a<lb/>
marked protection was given by the vaccination. We wish more<lb/>
detail had been given of this epidemic in Tuxpan.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f00913006"/>
<p>Tuxpan.</p>
<p>6</p>
<p>The data from Quirigua: Puerto Barrios: Virginia and Tambo<lb/>
Grande are not illuminating: Nor is that from Salvador.</p>
<p>For Guayaquil we have much fuller data--thanks to a pre-<lb/>
vious paper of Noguchi and Pareja:</p>
<p>In October 1918, the batallion of Vincedores--327 men--coming<lb/>
from Quito to Guayaquil, were vaccinated--149 with Vaccine A,<lb/>
and 178 with Vaccine B--very much weaker. The reason for us-<lb/>
ing Vaccine B was because there was not enough of Vaccine A to<lb/>
go around <del>than</del> so less had to be used for the last part of the<lb/>
batallion. This vaccine was not nearly as potent as that now<lb/>
used, the proportion being as 1 to 1,000.</p>
<p>These men, presumably all susceptible to yellow fever,<lb/>
were stationed in barracks in Guayaquil in which there had<lb/>
occurred 58 cases: 29 deaths, among 300 soldiers in the six<lb/>
months to June 1918. &ldquo;Owing to sanitary measures at and a-<lb/>
round the barracks,&rdquo; only one death--nothing is said of cases--<lb/>
occurred from July to October. So much from the paper mention-<lb/>
ed.</p>
<p>In the paper under review, Noguchi states that from this<lb/>
group of 427 vaccinated, there were 6 cases of yellow fever--<lb/>
1, class (a)----and-----5. class (b)---none of these were a-<lb/>
mong the 149 vaccinated with Vaccine A.</p>
<p>Among the civil population <add>susceptible to Yellow Fever</add>, estimated by him at 3,573, be-<lb/>
tween October 1918 and March 1919: <hi>386</hi> cases of fever occurred--<lb/>
Counting, as I think we must, the case in class (a), the pro-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00913007"/>
<del>pro</del><lb/>
pro-<lb/>
7<lb/>
portion is <hi>1</hi> to <hi>8</hi>.</p>
<p>Admitting that these men were confined to barracks as<lb/>
much as possible, by order and by counsel: that, in the begin-<lb/>
ning at least, they would be afraid to go into the infected<lb/>
city: that the barracks themselves were safe--as is shown by<lb/>
their being practically free from fever for the previous four<lb/>
months: yet this disproportion of infection testifies very<lb/>
strongly to a decided protection from vaccination. It seems<lb/>
too great to be explained away. Accepting these figures, no<lb/>
other interpretation seems reasonable. If only the Vince-<lb/>
dores had been vaccinated with the full dose, A, as far as it<lb/>
would have gone and left a portion of them--<hi>140</hi><unclear>--</unclear>as a Control<lb/>
we might have had absolutely definite, reliable data deter-<lb/>
mining the value of this vaccine for men as it is determined<lb/>
for animals!</p>
<p>The editor, while in Peru in 1920 and the early part of<lb/>
this year, pressed the use of vaccine-- of which he received<lb/>
from Dr. Noguchi at first a small, and afterwards a much larger,<lb/>
lot. He used it at first for sanitary workers and physicians<lb/>
going into the epidemic and later as we use the similar method<lb/>
in the control of small-pox. He, at this time, based his ad-<lb/>
vocacy of the vaccine <hi>solely</hi> on the result of animal experi-<lb/>
mentation. Had he known of the results of the Guayaquil vac-<lb/>
cination--that at Tuxpan had not yet been done--he had been<lb/>
even more zealous than he was. He used the vaccination and ad-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00913008"/>
ad-<lb/>
8<lb/>
vised its use in the sanitary campaign <hi>solely as an adjuvant</hi>,<lb/>
the method depended on being the control of Stegomyia<lb/>
breeding. That it can become a valuable adjuvant he fully<lb/>
believes, especially in small places. It is clearly of es-<lb/>
pecial value in places which can free themselves from yellow<lb/>
fever by &ldquo;failure of the human host,&rdquo; it hastening that process<lb/>
in proportion to the extent used. For such places <del>we should be able<lb/>
fever can</del> - <del><unclear>render</unclear></del> the <del>above</del> fever can be immediately elim-<lb/>
inated by an effective vaccination. For large places it<lb/>
<unclear>is</unclear> less applicable.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
