<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00912023">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, August 4, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00912023</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-08-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hanson, Henry</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Wrightson, William D.</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Ferranafe (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Olmos (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Casa Grande (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-08-04">August 4, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00912023</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, August 4, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter, preparing a paper, asks Hanson about his experience in Peru.  He believes that Hanson and his team have saved Peru. Carter wishes he could have returned to Peru.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-08-04">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, August 4, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00912023"/>
<opener>
<unclear>I H. B.</unclear><lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
Adj. to <unclear>chashal</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
New Glasgow P. O.,<lb/>
Amherst County, Va.<lb/>
<date value="1921-08-04">August 4, 1921</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Hanson:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am asked for a paper before the American Society of Tropical<lb/>
Medicine on the Yellow Fever Epidemic in Northern Peru.</p>
<p>Naturally, it would be better written next year and by you and<lb/>
myself jointly. However, I am purposing to <unclear>twll</unclear> what I can of the epidem-<lb/>
iology and control of this fever for 1920 and want to add a very<lb/>
brief sketch of the same for /21. I earnestly hope that there will be<lb/>
none in /22 of which to write.</p>
<p>Will you then kindly give me a few points:</p>
<p>1/ <hi>Fish.</hi></p>
<p>Did you use fish for the wells (in the houses) at Casa Grande?</p>
<p>If not, what did you use for these wells? In what other places and<lb/>
for what class of containers did you use fish? What were your results?<lb/>
What kind of fish and how obtained? Were they viviparous or oviparous?</p>
<p>How did you find the fever spread at the haciendas? You told me<lb/>
that the medico at Casa Grande would not admit its diagnos. Did he do so<lb/>
later? How did it do in haciendas like Roma where there was little<lb/>
breeding: At Cayati--with inefficient medico--and at Saman?</p>
<p>2/ <hi>Limit of Number of <unclear>Containers</unclear></hi>.</p>
<p>Were you able <hi>generally</hi> to limit the number of containers to a<lb/>
family? We had planned to allow only <hi>2</hi> botijas to each residence <add>- one full &amp; one empty &amp; drying</add>. I<lb/>
know that Dr. Tapia (your last letter) had ordered, and I presume your<lb/>
men carried this out, that no large containers be allowed in the sepa-<lb/>
rate apartments of the large lodging houses.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00912024"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>3/ <hi>Emptying Containers without Examination</hi>.</p>
<p>Were you able to use the control we had planned--emptying the con-<lb/>
tainers--preferably alternate containers--every week (or 10<del>)</del> days) without<lb/>
inspecting it, to see if it had larvae or no?</p>
<p>4/ <hi>Where Used</hi>.</p>
<p>Where were the above used and by what Inspectors and what were the<lb/>
results?</p>
<p>5/ <hi>Methods</hi>.</p>
<p>Anything else you can tell me of your <hi>methods</hi> of control of ste-<lb/>
gomyia production is desired--especially as they were the same as, or<lb/>
differed from, those in use last year.</p>
<p>6/ <hi>Origen.</hi></p>
<p>I judge from the outbreak in Olmos and other places in that valley<lb/>
above Ferrenafe that the fever probably did not enter by way of Morropon:<lb/>
Salitral and Olmos? Yet it might have done so and died out in the cool<lb/>
weather to spread in epidemic form when reintroduced in hot weather --<lb/>
as <hi>apparently</hi> was the case with Paita in the fall of /19 and summer of<lb/>
/20. Still this is unlikely as Paita is much colder in the winter than is<lb/>
the interior. It may not have <del><unclear>didn't</unclear></del> died out in P. in the cool weather - simply<lb/>
lessened very much &amp; the <unclear><del>s</del></unclear> cases occurring at long intervals failed<lb/>
of <unclear>report.</unclear></p>
<p>7/ <hi>Origen.</hi></p>
<p>Did you hear anything more of the <unclear>tle</unclear> Father Pita told us of the in-<lb/>
troduction into the hacienda near Ferranafe by a man from Catacaos?</p>
<p>8/ <hi>Mortality.</hi></p>
<p>You spoke of there &ldquo;having been about 1,000 deaths&rdquo; in the district<lb/>
north-east of Ferranafe: Can you form any estimate of the number of<lb/>
deaths in this 1921 epidemic?</p>
<p>You need be in no hurry to answer this. I judge that if you write<lb/>
by Sept. 15th, I should get it in time. Also, you need not confine<lb/>
yourself to the questions asked. Any information you have time to<lb/>
give will be gratefully received by the Tropical Society. Also, if you<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00912025"/>
3<lb/>
haven't time to write at all, don't do it. I don't want to impose<lb/>
on you. You have enough to do. I have enough for a paper.</p>
<p>I suspect that you and the International Health Board have saved<lb/>
Peru. One can't be sure until innext January. I think, however, that if<lb/>
it, the infection, has not established itself in some place south of<lb/>
Trujillo that you will have it eliminated by the end of the year--or<lb/>
even by Oct. or Nov. 1st.: Although I won't feel entirely sure until the<lb/>
end of the next hot season--June /22.</p>
<p>I did right to return to the U. S. I have been of more service to<lb/>
you here--especially in the beginning--than if I had stayed. Yet I do<lb/>
wish I could have gone back with, or in place of, White and stayed<lb/>
with you as long as was necessary or until the end. However, there is<lb/>
no decision involved and therefore I will not worry.</p>
<p>What of Wrightson?</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly your friend,</salute>
Address<lb/>
Dr/ H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St. N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
