<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00916004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, October 21, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00916004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-10-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="place">Canal Zone (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Chiclayo (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-10-21">October 21, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00916004</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, October 21, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson sends Carter a Spanish translation of a lecture.  Some inspectors are returning to the Canal Zone.  He hopes to bring his family to Peru. There has been an outbreak of bubonic plague. He offers his opinions on the Peruvian government.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-10-21">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, October 21, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00916004"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
----<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
Oct 21/21<lb/>
H. R. C<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.<lb/>
<date value="1921-10-21">October 21,1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Henry R. Carter, Asst Surgeon General,<lb/>
United States Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sending you the spanish translation of the talk which<lb/>
I gave before the Medical Society of the Canal Zone. I hope you will <unclear>critizese</unclear><lb/>
what you think is incorrect in the thing. It was purely an impromptu talk, but they<lb/>
had a stenographer there to take it and sent me a copy of the same. I gave the<lb/>
English copy to my interpretor and asked him if he thought it was worht trans-<lb/>
lating, with the result that you have the enclosed. I shall send Dr. White a copy<lb/>
also, and if you think it is worth it you can forward it to the I.H.B. I like the<lb/>
spanish version better than I do the English, besides I only have one English copy<lb/>
and no time to make any more.</p>
<p>Corrigan and Pickett have left for the Canal Zone, and I am now depending<lb/>
on Dunn and Seeley. Seeley thought he was going to have to leave, as his wife rather<lb/>
insisted on his coming back or bringing the family down here. I think he should stay<lb/>
to the finish, it is going to be very important to have enough reliable men to de-<lb/>
pend on for the finish, and I have made the arrangement which you will note in the<lb/>
copy of this letter. Seeley has done very good work and an enormous amount of it.</p>
<p>Under the circumstances Corrigan and Pickett were worth what they got in<lb/>
this years campaign. They had the experience of last year, both in knowing the<lb/>
people and the conditions, and besides they worked like very few men ever have<lb/>
worked except in time an engagement in actual warfare. The practically had no rest<lb/>
on any day from the time they landed until the sailed for the <del>states</del><add>Canal</add>. Their effect<lb/>
on the native inspectors was good, kept them on the qui vive for fear they were<lb/>
going to be caught with their districts in bad shape.</p>
<p>If I can get a decent place for the folks I think I will bring my family<lb/>
to Trujillo, as the warm weather seems to be too much for Mrs. Hanson in Panama and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00916005"/>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
----<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----<lb/>
" 2. H.R.C., October 21, 1921<lb/>
besides I want her and the kiddies where I can see them occasionally. If they dont<lb/>
come down I would go up to be with them for Christmas, but I believe it is better<lb/>
for them to come down here. This climate is about the best one can get, and they<lb/>
have had a pretty long pull with the heat. They only bad feature is the bubonic<lb/>
plague which is serious. Here in Chiclayo we have had plague in one of the best<lb/>
families, and the Salubridad seem to be doing nothing about it as usual. They do<lb/>
not even have good vaccine or serum. I wonder if you could get me some relaible<lb/>
serum and vaccine sent down from New York, or somewhere, probably the U.S.P.H.S.<lb/>
has some it could send.</p>
<p>Wrightson is getting up a reorganization sheet for the Health Depat<lb/>
ment which in my opinion is entirely impractical, and does not suit the condit-<lb/>
ions of the country at the present time. However that is his funeral, not mine.</p>
<p>Up to the present we have used neary four hundred thousand fish in the<lb/>
campaign, and with good results. The use of fish is the ticket, and the<del>y</del> only<lb/>
one where the conditions lend them selves freely to it. If I ever can get time<lb/>
to get up a proper general report on this thing, I shall give details and re-<lb/>
sults on this method of campaigning.</p>
<p>I hope you have received the information which I sent up for you<lb/>
on my return from Panama.</p>
<p>I havent time to write more today,</p>
<closer>
<salute>With best wishes, Very sincerely your friend,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
