<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00924019">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Regulations Governing the Impounding of Waters, by the Alabama State Board of Health, [1921?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00924019</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="place">Alabama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>19 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-00-00">[1921?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00924019</idno>
<title>Report: Regulations Governing the Impounding of Waters, by the Alabama State Board of Health, [1921?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report discusses control of debris and vegetation, fish stocking, and ditching. Pertinent state health laws are listed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-00-00">
<head>Report: Regulations Governing the Impounding of Waters, by the Alabama State Board of Health, [1921?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00924019"/>
<p>REGULATIONS GOVERNING THE IMPOUNDING OF WATERS.</p>
<p>Alabama State Board of Health,<lb/>
519 Dexter Avenue,<lb/>
Montgomery, Alabama.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00924020"/>
<p><hi>H E A L T H  L A W S</hi>.</p>
<p>Code of Alabama 1907, Volume 1,<lb/>
As Amended by Act of Legislature, No. 658,<lb/>
Approved September 29, 1919.</p>
<p>SECTION 702. The State Board of Health shall<lb/>
have authority and jurisdiction -</p>
<p>(6) to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations<lb/>
providing proper methods and details for adminis-<lb/>
tering the health and sanitary laws of the State,<lb/>
which rules and regulations shall have the force<lb/>
and effect of law and shall be executed and en-<lb/>
forced by the same courts, bodies, officials, agents<lb/>
and employees as in the case of health laws; and<lb/>
any person knowingly, violating or failing or re-<lb/>
fusing to obey or comply with, any such rule or<lb/>
regulation shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and<lb/>
shall be punished in accordance with the provisions<lb/>
of section 7073 of this Code; and if the violation<lb/>
or failure is a continuing one each day's viola-<lb/>
tion or failure shall constitute a separate offence<lb/>
and be punishable accordingly.</p>
<p><hi>SPECIAL PENAL STATUTE</hi>.</p>
<p>Code of Alabama 1907.</p>
<p>Volume 3.</p>
<p>7073. Any person violating any of the provisions<lb/>
of Article 1, of Chapter 22 of this Code, relating<lb/>
to the health laws, shall be guilty of a misdemean-<lb/>
or, and, upon conviction, shall be fined not less<lb/>
than five nor more than one hundred dollars, unless<lb/>
otherwise expressly provided for.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00924021"/>
<p>REGULATIONS GOVERNING THE IMPOUNDING OF WATERS.</p>
<p>In order to prevent an increase in the prevalence of<lb/>
malaria and to avoid the formation of foci of endemic<lb/>
malaria by the impounding of waters, under and by vir-<lb/>
tue of authority vested in it by the Legislature of<lb/>
Alabama (Amended Acts, 1919), the State Board of Health<lb/>
does hereby promulgate and publish the following rules<lb/>
and regulations governing the impounding of waters or<lb/>
damming of water courses in the State of Alabama.</p>
<p>SECTION 1. Any person, firm, corporation, county, or<lb/>
municipality desiring to impound water for any purpose<lb/>
whatever, such person or collection of persons who,<lb/>
propose to raise the level of a previously existing<lb/>
pond by the elevation of the top of the dam, other than<lb/>
for supplying water to domestic animals, shall, prior<lb/>
to the iniation of any construction activities, make<lb/>
application to the State Board of Health for, and ob-<lb/>
tain from it, a preliminary permit for the impounding of<lb/>
such water.</p>
<p>SECTION 2. Such application for a preliminary per-<lb/>
mit shall be made in writing in the name of the person,<lb/>
firm, corporation, county, or municipality making appli-<lb/>
cation, and shall be accompanied by a description of<lb/>
the proposed project, its purpose, and its exact loca-<lb/>
tion; also by an accurate plat of the area to be affect-<lb/>
ed, showing particularly the maximum and minimum water<lb/>
levels.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00924022"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>SECTION 3. Such a temporary permit for the inaugura-<lb/>
tion of initial construction shall be issued by the<lb/>
State Board of Health when the following rules and regula-<lb/>
tions, or modifications thereof, have been made to apply<lb/>
to the said project.</p>
<p>3-a. In the area to be occupied by the Reser-<lb/>
voir, its branches, bights, and indentations, all brush,<lb/>
trees, undergrowth, logs, stumps, and similar objects,<lb/>
which, if not removed, would float or collect flotage<lb/>
on the surface of the impounded water, and all of the above<lb/>
material that is lying on the ground or remaining in origi-<lb/>
nal or new position, which would probably cause collection<lb/>
of flotage to gather, and this constitute conditions favor-<lb/>
able to the protection of larvae of mosquitoes capable of<lb/>
conveying malaria, shall be removed, burned, or otherwise<lb/>
satisfactorily disposed of, prior to the impounding of the<lb/>
water.</p>
<p><hi>NOTE</hi>: The above does not include grass, vegetation, brush,<lb/>
trees, stumps, etc., which will be premanently and com-<lb/>
pletely submerged at time of low water and which are, there-<lb/>
fore, not of sanitary importance.</p>
<p>3-b. In the area to be occupied by the Reser-<lb/>
voir, its branches, bights, and indentations, all brush,<lb/>
trees, and undergrowth which would pierce the surface<lb/>
at low water level shall be cut off at least one foot<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00924023"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
below such low water level, to prevent the collec-<lb/>
tion and anchorage of any possible flotage, rafts,<lb/>
etc.</p>
<p>3-c. The shore line of the reservoir, its<lb/>
branches, bights, and indentations, from minimum low<lb/>
water level to a line 25 feet horizontally beyond<lb/>
maximum high water level, shall be cleared of all<lb/>
brush, trees, undergrowth, and the like, so as to<lb/>
prevent the collection of drift and flotage along<lb/>
the shore.</p>
<p>3-d. All pine trees within an area circum-<lb/>
scribed by a line 50 feet inland from the maximum<lb/>
high water level of the reservoir, its branches,<lb/>
bights, and indentations, shall be ringed and deaden-<lb/>
ed at the time of initial construction on the pro-<lb/>
ject, so as to prevent the falling into the water<lb/>
of pine tags, collections of which provide a favor-<lb/>
able breeding place for Anopheline larvae.</p>
<p>3-e. Hatcheries for the propagation of Gam-<lb/>
busia Affinis (top minnows) in sufficient numbers<lb/>
to stock the reservoir, its branches, bights, and<lb/>
indentations for effective mosquito control, shall<lb/>
be provided at the time of initial construction on<lb/>
the project, in accordance with definite written in-<lb/>
structions from the State Board of Health.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f00924024"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>3-f. All depressions which will be filled<lb/>
with water from the reservoir, its branches, bights,<lb/>
or indentations at time of maximum water level, in<lb/>
which water will be retained at lower stages of the<lb/>
water level, thus forming separate pools, shall be<lb/>
connected with the normal body of the reservoir, or<lb/>
any of its branches, bights, or indentations, with<lb/>
a ditch or culvert which will permit complete drain-<lb/>
age and the entrance of top-feeding minnows.</p>
<p><hi>NOTE</hi>: Such places are generally few in number, but<lb/>
are of importance in mosquito production.</p>
<p>3-g. All persons making application for em-<lb/>
ployment on the construction of the project shall<lb/>
be subjected to clinical or microscopic diagnostic<lb/>
examination (or both) for malaria, and no person<lb/>
giving a positive diagnosis, clinical or microscopic,<lb/>
shall be employed anywhere on the project.</p>
<p>Such other measures to prevent the intro-<lb/>
duction of malaria or other communicable diseases<lb/>
into the project area, and the territory adjacent<lb/>
thereto, as shall be directed by the State Board of<lb/>
Health from time to time, shall be adopted and put<lb/>
into effect.</p>
<p>SECTION 4. A preliminary permit for the impounding<lb/>
of water having been granted by the State Board of<lb/>
Health, and construction work on the project begun,<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00924025"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
a representative of the State Board of Health<lb/>
shall make inspections of the project from time<lb/>
to time, and as requested by the permit holder,<lb/>
and the State Board of Health shall approve in<lb/>
writing of that portion of the work as is out-<lb/>
lined in Section 3 of the Regulations which has<lb/>
been satisfactorily completed.</p>
<p>As the said representative of the State<lb/>
Board of Health determines that the preliminary<lb/>
permit holder is complying with the provisions of<lb/>
Section 3-a of these Regulations, and as it shall<lb/>
appear that the preliminary permit holder has com-<lb/>
plied with the provisions of Section 3-b of these<lb/>
Regulations, the permit holder may thereupon pro-<lb/>
ceed gradually, as authorized by written approval<lb/>
from the State Board of Health, with the impound-<lb/>
ing of water to a level specified by said represen-<lb/>
tative of the Board of Health, and, when it shall<lb/>
appear that the permit holder has complied with the<lb/>
Regulations to the satisfaction of the Board, said<lb/>
Board of Health shall certify such fact to the<lb/>
permit holder in writing, and the permit holder may<lb/>
thereupon proceed with the impounding of water to<lb/>
a maximum high water level.</p>
<p>SECTION 5. The State Board of Health shall there-<lb/>
upon issue a <unclear>final<del>p</del>permit</unclear> for the maintenance of an<lb/>
impounding project by said applicant, the validity<lb/>
of said permit being contingent upon the observance<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00924026"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
of the following regulations:</p>
<p>5-a During the mosquito breeding season the<lb/>
permit holder shall regularly and frequently<lb/>
remove all flotage and floating debris in the<lb/>
reservoir, its branches, bights, and indenta-<lb/>
tions, which are likely to harbor mosquito<lb/>
larvae.</p>
<p>5-b Prompt and proper measures shall be taken<lb/>
to prevent the growth of cat-tails, bulrushes,<lb/>
and other aquatic or semi-aquatic vegetation<lb/>
which offers protection of mosquito larvae from<lb/>
their fish enemies.</p>
<p>5-c Newly created impounded waters shall not<lb/>
be stocked with game fish without written permis-<lb/>
sion from the State Board of Health.</p>
<p>No fishing in the impounded water, between<lb/>
April 1st and November 1st, shall be permitted<lb/>
for a period of three years after impounding, un-<lb/>
less a permit is granted in writing from the State<lb/>
Board of Health.</p>
<p>5-d After the water has been impounded, the<lb/>
State Board of Health shall from time to time<lb/>
make such inspections of the impounded waters<lb/>
and adjacent areas as are deemed essential; and any<lb/>
conditions found on the impounded water project that<lb/>
are, or may<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f00924027"/>
- 7 -<lb/>
be, detrimental to public health, or are likely<lb/>
to cause an increase of malaria, shall be modi-<lb/>
fied by the permit holder so as to be satisfac-<lb/>
tory to the State Board of Health.</p>
<p>5-e. These regulations shall govern any<lb/>
change in water level and as soon as any pro-<lb/>
posed changes affecting the maximum water eleva-<lb/>
tion are contemplated, the State Board of Health<lb/>
shall be notified in writing.</p>
<p>SECTION 6. Failure to comply with the provision<lb/>
of any section of sub-section of these Regulations<lb/>
shall constitute a violation thereof, and shall con-<lb/>
stitute, according to Section 7073 of the Code of<lb/>
Alabama, a misdemeanor, punishable as provided in<lb/>
that Section.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f00924028"/>
<p>DETAILED EXPLANATION AND INTERPRETATION.</p>
<p>Section-by-Section.</p>
<p>SECTION 1. --Self-explanatory.</p>
<p>SECTION 2. Irrespective of its extent, an impound-<lb/>
ing project should be predicated on accurate data, and<lb/>
such of this data as is of value in determining any<lb/>
of the factors affecting mosquito-breeding should be<lb/>
furnished to the State Board of Health, for informa-<lb/>
tion and for purposes of record.</p>
<p>SECTION 3-a --Self-explanatory.</p>
<p>SECTION 3-b --Self-explanatory.</p>
<p>SECTION 3-c. The absence of permanent obstructions<lb/>
near the water line permits of wave action on the<lb/>
shore which is unfavorable to mosquito breeding. The<lb/>
dam should be designed so that flash-boards will not<lb/>
be needed nor used for any other purpose than the<lb/>
stranding of floating logs, etc., on the shore during<lb/>
winter months. During the mosquito-breeding season,<lb/>
pronounced fluctuations of the water level may be,<lb/>
or may be made to be, a controlling factor in breed-<lb/>
ing. When the water level is varied at ten-day<lb/>
intervals, a 24-inch fluctuation on steep slopes and<lb/>
a 48-inch fluctuation on flat slopes, will make pro-<lb/>
lific breeding improbable. Changes in water level<lb/>
tend to prevent rank growth of aquatic plants and<lb/>
aid fish enemies (Gambusia Affinis) in reaching the<lb/>
mosquito larvae or flush the larvae within reach of<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f00924029"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
the fish. It is usually necessary to clear only<lb/>
stranding places of low slope. Even here trees<lb/>
25 feet or more apart are not objectionable.</p>
<p>SECTION 3-d --Self-explanatory.</p>
<p>SECTION 3-e. The size of the hatchery ponds should<lb/>
be not less than 20 by 30 feet. These ponds should<lb/>
contain a large area of shallow water, but in order<lb/>
to prevent them from drying up in a brief space of<lb/>
time, it appears advisable to provide a pit near the<lb/>
center, of a depth of 3 or 4 feet, or more except<lb/>
where the sub-stratum is porous. It is advisable to<lb/>
maintain the water at a fairly constant level, but<lb/>
the deep pit would serve to carry some of the fish<lb/>
through a period of emergency; i.e., drought, or ex-<lb/>
tremely cold weather.</p>
<p>The hatcheries should be constructed either in<lb/>
areas already cleared or the woods should be cut back,<lb/>
permitting a maximum of sunshine. This will stimulate<lb/>
the growth of green plants (algae, etc.) and is es-<lb/>
pecially agreeable to Gambusia.</p>
<p>Flowing water is not necessary or desirable, but,<lb/>
if possible means for maintaining a fairly constant<lb/>
water level should be provided. This can often be<lb/>
done by making a connection between the pond and a<lb/>
nearby creek with a water pipe equipped with a valve,<lb/>
or perhaps by means of a connecting ditch provided with<lb/>
a <unclear>gate</unclear>.</p>
<p>As soon as the ponds are completed and filled<lb/>
with water, whether stocked with fish or not, a quan-<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f00924030"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
tity of green filamentous algae or pond scum<lb/>
should be placed in the ponds. The lot of algae<lb/>
transferred may die, but the spores from it will<lb/>
probably start new plants. The scums should be<lb/>
transferred in buckets or other waterproof con-<lb/>
tainers without permitting the water in which they<lb/>
are found to drain from them. In this way some of<lb/>
the small animal life among the scums, too, will<lb/>
be transferred and may establish themselves in the<lb/>
new ponds. (<hi>Gambusia</hi> is primarily carnivorous, but<lb/>
it also at times eats algae). A good growth of<lb/>
algae in a pond attracts small animal life, and<lb/>
such ponds are usually good <hi>Gambusia</hi> &ldquo;hatcheries&rdquo;.</p>
<p>A quantity of loose brush should also be placed<lb/>
in the hatcheries, to provide small patches of shade,<lb/>
attachment for the algae, and resting places for<lb/>
small animal life.</p>
<p>The fish are taken most conveniently by the<lb/>
use off a small drag net made of a good grade of mos-<lb/>
quito netting, or still better, of bobbinet. Where<lb/>
negetation is dense such a net cannot be operated,<lb/>
and then a dip net, made of the same material, can<lb/>
be used. The fish should be handled gently when<lb/>
caught, allowing them to be exposed to the air the<lb/>
shortest time necessary to make the transfer. It is<lb/>
preferable never to handle the fish with the hands.<lb/>
When a &ldquo;clean catch&rdquo; cannot be made and the fish can-<lb/>
not be transferred to the container with the net in<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f00924031"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
which they were taken, it is advisable to leave<lb/>
the net with fish in the edge of the water, sort-<lb/>
ing and transferring the catch with a small hand<lb/>
net.</p>
<p>If artificial feeding is found necessary (and<lb/>
it probably will be for a few months at least), corn<lb/>
bread, and fresh minced meat or fish may be provided.<lb/>
It must be remembered, however, that a minnow is<lb/>
small and cannot consume a large amount of food, and<lb/>
it is not advantageous to provide more food than is<lb/>
consumed before it decomposes. About two or three<lb/>
feedings a week are sufficient.</p>
<p>The number, location, and degree of stocking, and<lb/>
other directions concerning hatcheries will be speci-<lb/>
fied or furnished, after inspection of the project, by<lb/>
the State Board of Health.</p>
<p>SECTION 3-f. --Self-explanatory.</p>
<p>SECTION 3-g. It has frequently been determined that<lb/>
serious outbreaks of malaria following the impound-<lb/>
ing of waters have resulted from the introduction of<lb/>
malaria from other sources into the ranks of construc-<lb/>
tion organizations, leading to subsequent infection<lb/>
of the mosquitoes and later the infection of the resi-<lb/>
dents in the surrounding territory. This may be avoided<lb/>
by medical examination of all applicants for employ-<lb/>
ment, and the proper quinine treatment of the construc-<lb/>
tion forces during their presence in the project area.</p>
<pb n="14" id="f00924032"/>
<p>- 5 -</p>
<p>SECTION 4. --Self-explanatory.</p>
<p>SECTION 5-a. Fish cannot feed in flotage, and<lb/>
their effectiveness in larvae destruction is reduced<lb/>
in direct proportion to the flotage and debris pres-<lb/>
ent.</p>
<p>SECTION 5-b. Game fish are particularly destructive<lb/>
of Gambusia. Other types of fish, such as sun perch,<lb/>
white perch, goggle-eyed perch, bream, calico bass, or<lb/>
crappies, may be introduced without objection.</p>
<p>It has been found that well-stocked newly-formed<lb/>
lakes become popular fishing grounds. The prevention<lb/>
of fishing avoid the introduction of malaria by fisher-<lb/>
men, who may hale from widely separated localities.</p>
<p>SECTION 5-d. -- Self-explanatory.</p>
<p>SECTION 6. -- Self-explanatory.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f00924033"/>
<p>EXPLANATION AND INTERPRETATION OF STATE BOARD OF HEALTH</p>
<p>REGULATIONS GOVERNING THE IMPOUNDING OF WATERS.</p>
<p>***********</p>
<p>Malaria fever is transmitted from person to per-<lb/>
son by infected Anopheline mosquitoes. The suppression<lb/>
of Anopheline breeding and the control of malaria carriers<lb/>
are both essential measures in the prevention of malaria.</p>
<p>Past experience with impounded water projects<lb/>
has given many well-known illustrations of rapid and pro-<lb/>
nounced increases in the prevalence of malaria fever in<lb/>
the territories adjacent thereto, because of more favor-<lb/>
able conditions for the breeding of Anopheline mosquitoes<lb/>
in great numbers.</p>
<p>The impounding of waters in river valleys is an<lb/>
essential part of the proper development of the natural<lb/>
resources of the State, and may be of marked benefit to<lb/>
its present and future citizens. It is believed such in-<lb/>
dustrial progress can be made, however, without rendering<lb/>
considerable areas adjacent to such projects malarial and<lb/>
unhealthful, at relatively slight additional expense.</p>
<p>Water power developments of the past, with the<lb/>
resultant increases of malaria, in some instances of a<lb/>
more pernicious type than previously obtained, have led<lb/>
the State Board of Health to investigate such outbreaks<lb/>
and to make scientific studies of the relation of newly<lb/>
impounded waters to the increase and prevalence of malaria<lb/>
in contiguous territory.</p>
<pb n="16" id="f00924034"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Among other facts that developed were the fol-<lb/>
lowing, which have also been found to hold true in general<lb/>
in other southern states where malaria prevails:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) When large bodies of water are impounded,<lb/>
several years are required for nature to bring the<lb/>
newly formed pond under such biological control con-<lb/>
ditions as are found in old lakes or ponds, whether<lb/>
natural or artificial.</item>
<item>(2) The production of conditions favorable or<lb/>
unfavorable to the marked increase of malaria-bear-<lb/>
ing mosquitoes is dependent upon the following fac-<lb/>
tors:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>(a) The topography of the basin affected.</item>
<item>(b) The shape of the contour of the shore<lb/>
line.</item>
<item>(c) The species and number of trees, and<lb/>
the character of brush and vegetation, es-<lb/>
pecially that near or adjacent to and above<lb/>
and below the high and low water flow lines.</item>
<item>(d) The exposure of the lake surface to<lb/>
wind action.</item>
<item>(e) The frequency of strong wind in all in-<lb/>
lets of the lake, in summer and in autumn<lb/>
seasons.</item>
<item>(f) The frequency of heavy storms.</item>
<item>(g) The character of aquatic and semi-<lb/>
aquatic growth in the lake and on its<lb/>
rain-shed.</item>
<item>(h) The amounts of flotage and debris<lb/>
carried by the streams feeding the lake.</item>
<item>(i) The natural fluctuations of water level-<lb/>
seasonal, weekly or daily.</item>
<item>(j) The number and distribution of natural<lb/>
enemies of mosquito larvae.</item>
<pb n="17" id="f00924035"/>
<item>- 3 -</item>
<item>(k) Other variable factors.</item>
</list></item>
<item>(3) Under normal conditions in natura many<lb/>
aquatic insects have aquatic enemies that prey on them<lb/>
to the extent of materially decreasing their numbers.<lb/>
The mosquito, in its early stage of development, is ex-<lb/>
clusively aquatic and is preyed upon by various insects<lb/>
and certain species of fish. Some species of fish not<lb/>
only destroy very few larvae, but they sometimes almost<lb/>
eliminate the mosquito-destroying kind of fish. They<lb/>
also may limit the scope of action of those minnows which<lb/>
prefer mosquito-larvae to other food and insects. When<lb/>
water is freshly impounded, the ratio of fish that pre-<lb/>
fer Anopheles-larvae as a food to the mosquito-larvae<lb/>
supply is often very low, or below what will probably<lb/>
be true several years or more later. This has been ob-<lb/>
served to be the general rule in the upper portions of<lb/>
arms and indentations, or long bights, of impounded<lb/>
lakes. Also, if no precautionary measures (or unsatis-<lb/>
factory precautionary measures) are undertaken, there<lb/>
will generally be very much more protection afforded to<lb/>
the mosquito-larvae during the early years of the life<lb/>
of the artificial pond than is commonly found in older<lb/>
ponds or lakes, whether natural or man-made, and, con-<lb/>
sequently, their natural enemies will have difficulty<lb/>
in reaching them.</item>
<item>(4) The particular places in newly formed lakes<lb/>
or ponds where Anopheles-larvae frequently are to be<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f00924036"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
found in relatively large numbers are:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>(a) In flotage and collections of flotage.<lb/>
This if often composed of leaved, pine need-<lb/>
les, small sticks, branches of trees, logs,<lb/>
pieces of bark, etc., and some of it is some-<lb/>
times covered with green algae. Anopheles-<lb/>
larvae are also often found in numbers among<lb/>
collections of aquatic of semi-aquatic plants,<lb/>
especially so if certain algae are present.</item>
<item>(b) Clinging to isolated pieces of bark or<lb/>
other drift when against or close to abrupt<lb/>
banks in deep water, when wind and wave ac-<lb/>
tion are or have been absent or light.</item>
<item>(c) At the upper ends (say the upper third)<lb/>
of inlets of the pond or lake and their<lb/>
branches, more so when relatively wind-shaded,<lb/>
or in the absence of sufficiently severe wave<lb/>
action.</item>
<item>(d) In shallow waters not affected by marked<lb/>
fluctuation of water level or strong wave<lb/>
action, in the absence of small mosquito de-<lb/>
stroying fish; more frequently when certain<lb/>
algae are present.</item>
</list></item>
<item>(5) When the production of <hi>Anopheles quadri-<lb/>
maculatus</hi> is prolific over a considerable sized breed-<lb/>
ing area, such as in an impounded water project con-<lb/>
taining much flotage, overgrown banks with vegetation<lb/>
hanging over into the water, collections of aquatic<lb/>
plants, and absence of mosquito-destroying minnows,<lb/>
etc., then the adult mosquitoes of this kind emerging<lb/>
from the production area may be found at residences<lb/>
and stables a mile distant from such a breeding area.<lb/>
Under conditions similar to that outlined they have<lb/>
not yet been found to travel to buildings 1 1/4 or 1 1/2<lb/>
miles or more distant from their source. In the in-<lb/>
vestigation of this subject it was generally found that<lb/>
where the production of adult <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi><lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f00924037"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
was less prolific, the adults were absent from<lb/>
houses about a mile or more distant from the<lb/>
production area.</item>
</list></p>
<p>In view of the vast undeveloped water<lb/>
power in Alabama and because of the certainty of<lb/>
the development of a number of impounding pro-<lb/>
jects in the near future, these Regulations Govern-<lb/>
ing the Impounding of Waters have been adopted in<lb/>
order to conserve the public health and to serve<lb/>
as a guide to those who plan the impounding of<lb/>
water.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
