<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00928003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Report: Some Observations Bearing on the Control of Malaria, by P.M. Ashburn, [1914]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00928003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1914-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1914-00-00">[1914]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00928003</idno>
<title>Report: Some Observations Bearing on the Control of Malaria, by P.M. Ashburn, [1914]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ashburn reports on methods of curbing malaria through the control of mosquito populations.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1914-00-00">
<head>Report: Some Observations Bearing on the Control of Malaria, by P.M. Ashburn, [1914]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00928003"/>
<p>Probably written<lb/>
about the end<lb/>
of 1914.<lb/>
<unclear>P. M. A.</unclear></p>
<p><hi>SOME OBSERVATIONS BEARING ON THE CONTROL OF MALARIA</hi></p>
<p>By<lb/>
<hi>P. M. ASHBURN</hi>,<lb/>
Major, Medical Corps, U. S. A.,<lb/>
General Inspector, Health Department,<lb/>
Panama Canal.</p>
<p>When I came to the Isthmus I was familiar with the excel-<lb/>
lent work done by Mr. Le Prince and his assistants in determining the<lb/>
origin of the great flights of <hi>Anopheles</hi> at Gatun in 1912 and 1913, at<lb/>
which time it was clearly and definitely shown that the flight of<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles albimanus</hi> and <hi>Anopheles tarsimaculata</hi> might be as long as<lb/>
a mile and a quarter, and that across a fairly stiff breeze.</p>
<p>At the same time I knew that great good had been accom-<lb/>
plished in diminishing malaria here and in many parts of the world<lb/>
without making allowances for flights nearly so long as that demon-<lb/>
strated at Gatun, most workers having accomplished their results<lb/>
without going more than a few hundred yards from houses.</p>
<p>It was not long until I began to learn from conversations<lb/>
with Sanitary Inspectors that places which a few years ago, when<lb/>
populated, were great hot beds of malaria and great breeding places<lb/>
for <hi>Anopheles albimanus</hi>, now, since their depopulation, have very<lb/>
few or no <hi>Anopheles</hi>. Among places of this character Mr. Chidester<lb/>
told me of an area back of the new waterworks at Miraflores, and<lb/>
of another at <unclear>Cocoli</unclear>, and Mr. Trask told me of Ancon village in<lb/>
Culebra district. Then too, in one or two instances where we were<lb/>
finding a good many anopheles which were supposed to have come from<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00928004"/>
2<lb/>
considerable distances, the situations were found controllable by in-<lb/>
tensive effort expended close at hand. At Pedro Miguel, for instance,<lb/>
a considerable mosquito catch in two particular buildings was attri-<lb/>
buted by experienced inspectors to breeding places a thousand yards<lb/>
distant; where larvae were found. Yet by decreasing, instead of in-<lb/>
creasing, the extent of our work<del>,</del> the situation was controlled.</p>
<p>After a time hydraulic fills at Mindi Island (Cristobal),<lb/>
and near Ancon and the San Miguel district of Panama were found to be<lb/>
giving rise to great <hi>Anopheles</hi> breeding, probably similar to, though,<lb/>
less extensive than, that at Gatun in 1912-13. But, unlike that<lb/>
Gatun fill, these, while producing great numbers of mosquitoes, did<lb/>
not give rise to flights of any such length. In fact Ancon, though<lb/>
much less than a mile from the San Miguel fill, was practically un-<lb/>
affected by it. The reason for this appeared plain. There was<lb/>
food nearer at hand.</p>
<p>This led to the thought of interposing an animal barrier<lb/>
between extensive anopheles breeding places and human habitations,<lb/>
but little consideration was necessary to recall places where the<lb/>
<unclear>animals</unclear> were present but did not serve as barriers, among such places<lb/>
being the San Miguel fill, near which two dairies are located. On<lb/>
the other hand, it was known that extensive <hi>Anopheles</hi> breeding oc-<lb/>
curred in places frequented by cattle and almost unvisited by persons.</p>
<p>At about the same time I saw a report of Strickland's inter-<lb/>
esting observation that the rat flea of England (<hi>C. fasciata</hi>) will<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00928005"/>
3<lb/>
bite man as readily as it will bite a rat, but that it will not co-<lb/>
pulate until after a feed of rat-blood.</p>
<p>From the above facts the following hypothesis was evolved.<lb/>
I state it in three parts.</p>
<p>A. <hi>Parasitism</hi> - Yellow fever is transmitted by <hi>Aedes calopus</hi><lb/>
(Stegomyia fasciata) and malaria by certain anophelines because<lb/>
through the ages those particular mosquitoes have been so closely<lb/>
associated with man that an adaptation of mosquito, disease germ and<lb/>
man has occurred. It has occurred because those particular mosqui-<lb/>
toes want human blood to the exclusion of other varieties, and it is<lb/>
possible that they cannot perpetuate their species except when they<lb/>
get human blood.</p>
<p>(Dr. Darling has undertaken work that should tend to prove or<lb/>
disprove this, but it has thus far been defeated by the difficulty<lb/>
of rearing <hi>Anopheles</hi> on any diet. Work will be done with <hi>Stegomyia</hi>,<lb/>
though that will not directly prove anything in regard to malaria.)<lb/>
Stegomyia will bite<lb/>
<unclear>genuine pigs</unclear> &amp; breed<lb/>
thereafter - <unclear>P.M.A.</unclear></p>
<p>B. <hi>Long flights</hi> - In consequence of this yearning for a par-<lb/>
ticular kind of blood, <hi>Anopheles albimanus</hi> and <hi>Anopheles tarsimaculata</hi>,<lb/>
and probably other malaria-bearing <hi>Anopheles</hi> and possibly <hi>Stegomyia</hi>,<lb/>
will make great flights to obtain it, as did <hi>Anopheles Albimanus</hi> and<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles tarsimaculata</hi> at Gatun, provided that it cannot be obtained<lb/>
nearer at hand. If it be at hand they will take it and not make the<lb/>
long flights. Having made a very long flight and obtained a full<lb/>
feed of blood, the female would stand a relatively poor chance of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00928006"/>
4<lb/>
getting back to the <unclear>place</unclear> where she was bred, because of difficulty<lb/>
of her flight and her consequent greater exposure to natural enemies.<lb/>
The tendency therefore would be for such long flights to be self<lb/>
limited, unless a few persons living near the breeding place fur-<lb/>
nished enough blood to keep up the breeding but not enough to sup-<lb/>
ply all of the mosquitoes bred. Under special conditions a few<lb/>
breeding mosquitoes might produce a great progeny because, owing to<lb/>
the breeding places being newly made and artificial, the natural<lb/>
enemies of the mosquitoes have not yet come into action in them and,<lb/>
for a time, practically all eggs laid result in full grown mosqui-<lb/>
toes. This was true, I think, at Gatun, and it may be an important<lb/>
factor in all of those severe outbreaks of malaria that arise on new<lb/>
railway work and other extensive work in the tropics.</p>
<p>C. <hi>Anopheles breeding far from man not Malaria Carriers</hi> - If<lb/>
malaria carrying <hi><unclear>Anopheles</unclear></hi> normally breed only close to man, those<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles</hi> found breeding far from habitations and from places of com-<lb/>
mon human resort should not be malaria carriers.</p>
<p>This was a matter that appeared capable of proof or disproof and<lb/>
the observations necessary are now being made. As yet they are few<lb/>
in number, but, so far as they go, significant. Thus -<lb/>
Ancon village, a former hotbed of malaria, produces only <hi>A. apicimaculata</hi>;<lb/>
Pedro Miguel River, 800 yards from houses, produces only <hi>A. apicimaculata</hi>;<lb/>
S<add>w</add>amp 7, Cristobal, 800 yards from houses, produces only <hi>A. apicimaculata</hi>;<lb/>
Swamp 4, Cristobal, 800 yards from houses, frequented only by cattle,<lb/>
produces only <hi>A. apicimaculata</hi>.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00928007"/>
<p>5</p>
<p>I have the excellent authority of Dr. Darling for stating that<lb/>
<hi>A. apicimaculata</hi> is not a carrier of malaria.</p>
<p>The following places that formerly produced large numbers<lb/>
of <hi>A. albimanus</hi> have recently been carefully searched by the inspectors<lb/>
named and are reported to be producing none, the change being attribu-<lb/>
ted to the fact that the places are uninhabited and that no work is<lb/>
going on in the neighborhood, the conditions, in other respects, being<lb/>
most favorable to breeding:</p>
<p>Bas Obispo - examined by Capt. Ford and San. Inspr. Hull;<lb/>
The Mandingo River - examined by Capt. Ford and San. Inspr. Hull;<lb/>
Territory between Las Cascadas<lb/>
and Empire - examined by Capt. Ford and San. Inspr. Hull;<lb/>
Fill #3, Gatun - examined by San. Inspr. J. A. Corrigan;<lb/>
N. streams &amp; B stream, Reservoir<lb/>
system, Gatun - examined by San. Inspr. J. A. Corrigan;</p>
<p>An interesting bit of evidence was afforded by the Cardenas River.<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles</hi> breeding was reported from there in September and I had lar-<lb/>
vae sent in for identification about October 1st. Dr. Darling found<lb/>
them to be <hi>A. Albimanus</hi>. There were no habitations within a half mile<lb/>
of the place but a large gang of negroes had been working near there,<lb/>
laying the new water main. They finished there at about the time the<lb/>
larvae were identified and I instructed the Sanitary Inspectors to leave<lb/>
the place untreated and gather more larvae after November 1st. Mr.<lb/>
Chidester reports that he has carefully searched the neighborhood several<lb/>
times since that date and has been unable to find any larvae whatever.</p>
<p>I have tried to get the record of <add>a</add> newly established town in<lb/>
order to note in it the rise of <hi>Anopheles</hi> and <del>M</del><add>m</add>alaria. The only new<lb/>
town made for which the data are available is the present La Boca,<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00928008"/>
6<lb/>
where both mosquitoes and malaria have been kept at negligible figures.<lb/>
partly because of the town's good natural features and the good planning<lb/>
and construction of it, partly by work.</p>
<p>The nearest approach to what I sought was the contractor's camp<lb/>
at Cano Saddle. That camp was established November 26, 1913, at an un-<lb/>
inhabited place. The nearest and only house about was a quarter of a<lb/>
mile away. Hand catching of mosquitoes was begun early and the Anopheles<lb/>
catch was as follows:</p>
<p><table rows="24" cols="2">
<row><cell><hi>Week ending</hi></cell><cell><hi>Anopheles</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Dec. 6, 1913</cell><cell>6</cell></row>
<row><cell>Dec. 13, 1913</cell><cell>34</cell></row>
<row><cell>Dec. 20, 1913</cell><cell>165</cell></row>
<row><cell>Dec. 27, 1913</cell><cell>115</cell></row>
<row><cell>Jan. 3, 1914</cell><cell>378</cell></row>
<row><cell>Jan. 10, 1914</cell><cell>652</cell></row>
<row><cell>Jan. 17, 1914</cell><cell>346</cell></row>
<row><cell>Jan. 24, 1914</cell><cell>593</cell></row>
<row><cell>Jan. 31, 1914</cell><cell>1211</cell></row>
<row><cell>Feb. 7, 1914</cell><cell>673</cell></row>
<row><cell>Feb. 14, 1914</cell><cell>646</cell></row>
<row><cell>Feb. 21, 1914</cell><cell>755</cell></row>
<row><cell>Feb. 28, 1914</cell><cell>764</cell></row>
<row><cell>Mar. 7, 1914</cell><cell>3277</cell></row>
<row><cell>Mar. 14, 1914</cell><cell>975</cell></row>
<row><cell>Mar. 21, 1914</cell><cell>1018</cell></row>
<row><cell>Mar. 28, 1914</cell><cell>467</cell></row>
<row><cell>Apr. 4, 1914</cell><cell>813</cell></row>
<row><cell>Apr. 11, 1914</cell><cell>120</cell></row>
<row><cell>Apr. 18, 1914</cell><cell>452</cell></row>
<row><cell>Apr. 25, 1914</cell><cell>256</cell></row>
<row><cell>May 2, 1914</cell><cell>265</cell></row>
<row><cell>May 9, 1914</cell><cell>87</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>It will be noted that the catch was lowest at the beginning, a time<lb/>
when seasonal conditions favored breeding, that after the first two<lb/>
or three weeks the mosquitoes increased rapidly up to the 21st of<lb/>
March, after which a decline in numbers began. This decline may<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00928009"/>
7<lb/>
have been due in part to the advance of the dry season, in part<lb/>
to the establishment of a balance between mosquitoes and their<lb/>
natural enemies. No anti-mosquito work was done, except the<lb/>
catching of adults. Now as to malaria there: the figures are<lb/>
unduly favorable and are possibly misleading because the per-<lb/>
sonnel changed frequently and there is no doubt that men con-<lb/>
tracted malaria there whose cases do not show on the reports.<lb/>
Only those sent away to hospital do show. That malaria carriers<lb/>
were present from the beginning I have no doubt, as I think it<lb/>
would be almost impossible to pick at random 100 or more laborers<lb/>
without finding some. However, I have no examinations of the men<lb/>
there at that time to support my belief.</p>
<p>The first case of malaria sent to hospital was sent in<lb/>
the week ending February 7th, four cases were sent in March, five<lb/>
in April, and one in the first week of May, after which the camp<lb/>
closed.</p>
<p>On December 19, 1913, Dr. M. E. Connor inspected the place<lb/>
and predicted malaria, but did not report its presence. On<lb/>
February 9, 1914, Dr. Farmer inspected the camp and reported the<lb/>
presence of two cases of fever. Dr. H. C. Clark examined blood<lb/>
specimens taken from 62 men of the camp on March 16th and found<lb/>
malaria in 6, a rate of 9.7 percent. He examined blood drawn from<lb/>
30 other individuals on March 31st and found malaria in 6, - 20 per-<lb/>
cent. He examined 2 other bloods on April 4th and found malaria<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00928010"/>
8<lb/>
in both. We are justified in stating that at Ca&ntilde;o Saddle, a<lb/>
place characterized by Dr. Connor as highly favorable to malaria,<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles</hi> did not greatly abound until after the laborers had<lb/>
been there for three weeks or more, and malaria made no headway<lb/>
until after two months. It is probable that that uninhabited<lb/>
place was also uninhabited by mosquitoes capable of bearing<lb/>
malaria until the workmen took them there and created conditions<lb/>
particularly favorable for their breeding.</p>
<p>Let us, in view of what has been said, turn back to a<lb/>
further consideration of the big Gatun flight, and see if the<lb/>
facts available explain them. Mr. J. A. Corrigan, who has been<lb/>
Sanitary Inspector at Gatun for years, informs me that when Fill<lb/>
No. 1, just north of the lighthouse, and Fill No. 2, on the Colon-<lb/>
Gatun road, were made, they gave rise to no great and extended<lb/>
flights, but did cause a local increase of mosquitoes, the former<lb/>
causing the increase in the barracks nearest it and the latter in<lb/>
the houses in Stillson's addition. On the other hand, Fill No. 3,<lb/>
across the canal and over a mile away, caused great flights to<lb/>
Gatun, which flights continued for months. I would call atten-<lb/>
tion to the fact that both 1 and 2 were close and convenient to<lb/>
large negro populations and long flights were unnecessary. With<lb/>
Fill No. 3 the case was different. There a large area, one mile<lb/>
by one-half mile, mostly fresh water swamp, was being filled.<lb/>
The fill was of mud and salt water. The mixture of fresh and<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f00928011"/>
9<lb/>
salt water is most favorable to <hi>A. albimanus</hi> and <hi>A. tarsimaculata</hi>,<lb/>
while it is probably unfavorable or fatal to the natural enemies of<lb/>
the mosquitoes that normally dwell in fresh water, as it certainly<lb/>
is to the ordinary vegetation of the swamp. In the vicinity of<lb/>
this fill and serving as food supply for a moderate number of mos-<lb/>
quitoes were: (1) Certain dredge pipe workers, probably a few dozen,<lb/>
(2) the inhabitants of <del>Forme</del><add>Torna</add> <unclear>Sabalo</unclear>, probably 100, and (3) the in-<lb/>
habitants of Boracho, probably 20. Soon the whole fill area was<lb/>
breeding mosquitoes in enormous numbers. Few of them could get<lb/>
food at hand and so, like people, animals, birds and fishes, they<lb/>
migrated, going to the largest and nearest available food supply,<lb/>
that at Gatun. This migration was not the only departure from<lb/>
their ordinary routine that was forced upon them, as Mr. Le Prince<lb/>
noted that they bit very freely in bright sunshine.</p>
<p>That the migrating mosquitoes were non-infected ones is<lb/>
indicated by the fact that, notwithstanding the great numbers of them<lb/>
entering houses, the malaria rate at Gatun for the eighteen weeks of<lb/>
November, December, January and February<del>,</del> was actually lower than in<lb/>
the corresponding weeks of the preceding year, the average weekly<lb/>
admission rate being .30 and .32 percent, respectively.</p>
<p>I believe that what I have chosen to call the hypothesis<lb/>
outlined above is in its entire form, new, yet the essential facts<lb/>
that support it have been observed and reported by numerous workers,<lb/>
and it is possible that these facts have even been grouped much as<lb/>
I have grouped them, and the same general deductions drawn.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f00928012"/>
<p>10</p>
<p>Mr. Le Prince in writing of the Gatun flights (Report<lb/>
of the Department of Sanitation, Isthmian Canal Commission, January,<lb/>
1913) said: &ldquo;It was assumed that such a large number of adults as<lb/>
would be produced every twenty-four hours at the production area<lb/>
must of necessity spread out or travel a considerable distance in<lb/>
order to get blood sufficient to satisfy them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Facts and deductions have been both interesting and<lb/>
helpful to me and the hypothesis has in several instances served<lb/>
as a working basis, enabling us to accomplish results with a<lb/>
saving of money and to anticipate and prevent trouble.</p>
<p>-- o --</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
