<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00927021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Florence M. Read to Henry Rose Carter, March 30, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00927021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-03-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Read, Florence M.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Caballero, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, Lawrence H.</name>
<name type="person">Olivari, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Madre de Dios (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Chanchamayo valley (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lambayeque (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Libertad (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Piura (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-03-30">March 30, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00927021</idno>
<title>Letter from Florence M. Read to Henry Rose Carter, March 30, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Read sends Carter extracts from two letters by Hanson. In the first letter Hanson discusses a possible yellow fever outbreak in southern Peru.  His second letter deals with rumors of a yellow fever outbreak in the mountains.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-03-30">
<head>Letter from Florence M. Read to Henry Rose Carter, March 30, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00927021"/>
<opener>
ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF<lb/>
----<lb/>
WICKLIFFE ROSE<lb/>
GENERAL DIRECTOR<lb/>
JOHN A. FERRELL, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE UNITED STATES<lb/>
VICTOR G. HEISEN, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE EAST<lb/>
H. H. HOWARD, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE WEST INDIES<lb/>
F. F. RUSSELL, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR OF<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH LABORATORIES<lb/>
I. H. B.<lb/>
<del>Book</del><lb/>
Rose<lb/>
MEMBERS<lb/>
----<lb/>
GEORGE E. VINCENT<lb/>
CHAIRMAN<lb/>
HERMANN M. BIGGS<lb/>
WALLACE BUTTRICK<lb/>
SIMON FLEXNER<lb/>
RAYMOND B. FOSDICK<lb/>
FREDERICK T. GATES<lb/>
EDWIN O. JORDAN<lb/>
T. MITCHELL PRUDDEN<lb/>
JOHN D. ROCKEFELLER, JR.<lb/>
WICKLIFFE ROSE<lb/>
FREDERICK STRAUSS<lb/>
VICTOR C. VAUGHAN<lb/>
WILLIAM H. WELCH<lb/>
EDWIN N. <unclear>EMBREE</unclear><lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
FLORENCE M. READ<lb/>
ASSISTANT SECRETARY<lb/>
<dateline>
THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION<lb/>
INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD<lb/>
61 BROADWAY, NEW YORK<lb/>
<date value="1922-03-30">March 30, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You will find enclosed paragraphs from<lb/>
two letters received this week from Doctor Hanson.<lb/>
In view of your intimate knowledge of conditions in<lb/>
Peru, I am sending this information to you, to in-<lb/>
quire if you have any comments or suggestions to<lb/>
offer in connection with the closing up of the work.</p>
<p>Mr. Rose has written Doctor Hanson that<lb/>
the extent to which he should investigate conditions<lb/>
outside the departments which have been infected,<lb/>
will be left entirely to his judgment, and has told<lb/>
him that the work is to stop when he says it is<lb/>
safe to stop.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Florence M. Read</signed>
Dr. Henry R. Carter<lb/>
2121 California Street, N.W.<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
FMR:EP E1<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="2" id="f00927022"/>
<opener>
Extracts from Letters from Doctor Henry Hanson<lb/>
</opener>
<p><unclear>dated march</unclear></p>
<p>March 1, 1922</p>
<p>Dear Doctor Rose:</p>
<p>In regard to your letter of January 23 in which you<lb/>
speak of the extent of the investigations outside of the infected<lb/>
territory, I am taking a position which is quite different from what<lb/>
I would take in the case where one only has to consider the control<lb/>
of an epidemic. I am placing myself in what I judge to be your posi-<lb/>
tion in regard to the world program for the eradication of yellow<lb/>
fever. In such a case and with the circumstance that it seems that<lb/>
for the first time in history we propose to declare the west coast<lb/>
of South America free from yellow fever, it is of considerable impor-<lb/>
tance to know all the terrain which is infectable to this disease and<lb/>
to know whether there is anything suspicious or whether there has been<lb/>
recently or when. This was the object with which I directed the<lb/>
recent tour of investigation by Dr. Caballero, Mr. Dunn and Sr.<lb/>
Olivari.</p>
<p>We have lately been getting some reports to the effect<lb/>
that there is a sickness which they designate as black vomit in the<lb/>
extreme southeastern portion of the country, in the Department Madre<lb/>
de Dios, this is on the other side of the mountains in the Bolivian-<lb/>
Brazilian region to the east of the Department of Cuzco. Even if this<lb/>
is true I think there is very small danger of the reinfection of the<lb/>
coast, on account of the length of time to get across and the very low<lb/>
temperature in the mountains. The question is what importance it would<lb/>
have in the program of the Board in the eradication of the fever. If<lb/>
the means of communication should be very much improved it might be important<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00927023"/>
-2-<lb/>
unless one could depend on a spontaneous elimination. It would be<lb/>
interesting to hear what Dr. Carter has to say; while he was here in<lb/>
Peru he seemed to be of the opinion that there would be practically no<lb/>
danger to the coast from the presence of the disease in Brazil or the<lb/>
Peruvian territory to the east of the Andes.</p>
<p>There is one other section which we may investigate,<lb/>
namely the Chanchamayo valley. This is in quite easy communication<lb/>
by Lima by means of the Central Railway and if there should remain<lb/>
some focus in that section there would be a possibility of the reintro-<lb/>
duction of the disease on the coast. I think it better that we should<lb/>
know what the sanitary conditions of the remotely dangerous places are<lb/>
in so far as yellow fever possibilities are concerned. Certain individ-<lb/>
uals who have come down this way have spoken of a &ldquo;black vomit&rdquo; in<lb/>
this (the Chanchamayo) region. This is also on the east of the high<lb/>
range of the Andes, and the danger from that section is very small,<lb/>
probably nil.</p>
<p>The Departments of Lambayeque and Libertad seem to be<lb/>
completely free from infection, and I feel no uneasiness from those<lb/>
sections. I have sent an inspector to go over the conditions in the<lb/>
Department of Piura and Dr. Caballero will go up for another inspection<lb/>
soon. On the coast there has been nothing reported of a suspicious nature.</p>
<p>March 2, 1922</p>
<p>My dear Miss Read:</p>
<p>In my letter to Dr. Rose I spoke of the rumors which we<lb/>
had received about the presence of yellow fever on the other side of<lb/>
the mountains, but I have since had an opportunity of talking with a<lb/>
very intelligent man from the eastern part of the Department of Cuzco<lb/>
and find that there has been no known cases in that section since 1907,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00927024"/>
-3-<lb/>
which puts an entirely different light on the situation. I was<lb/>
thinking for a while that it might be necessary to make an inves-<lb/>
tigation in that region but with this added information unless<lb/>
something new comes in I do not think it will be necessary. The<lb/>
Chanchamayo territory is more accessible and I may make an investi-<lb/>
gation there before we close up all work. It is becoming somewhat<lb/>
of a problem now to keep up a proper line of investigations, because<lb/>
as I have indicated we do not want to have the disappointment of<lb/>
making a premature announcement.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
