<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00929010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from R.C. Derivaux to Henry Rose Carter, April 12, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Derivaux, R.C.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00929010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-04-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-04-12">April 12, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00929010</idno>
<title>Letter from R.C. Derivaux to Henry Rose Carter, April 12, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Derivaux tells Carter of his activities over the past three years.  He is now in private practice and teaching at Vanderbilt Medical School.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-04-12">
<head>Letter from R.C. Derivaux to Henry Rose Carter, April 12, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00929010"/>
<opener>
Miscellaneous<lb/>
Derivaux<lb/>
<dateline>
DR. R. C. DERIVAUX<lb/>
DOCTORS' BUILDING<lb/>
NASHVILLE, TENNESSEE<lb/>
<date value="1922-04-12">April 12, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It would put me to considerable embarassment to<lb/>
try to remember anything that has given me more genuine<lb/>
pleasure than that of your letter of a few days ago. I too,<lb/>
while shamefully remiss in my writing, have thought of you<lb/>
very often and we speak often of you at home, but my own<lb/>
failure to write to you has been due largely to lack of<lb/>
any but approximate knowledge as to where you were. I have<lb/>
been hearing of you at intervals; Dr. West has been able to<lb/>
bring back little fragments of gossip from Washington and<lb/>
elsewhere and has told me at various times that you were in<lb/>
South America, that you had suffered a very serious accident,<lb/>
that you were again travelling, etc., but at no time have I<lb/>
had any other than very vague idea as to where you were or<lb/>
what or how you were doing.</p>
<p>From your letter, however, it is plain that the<lb/>
term &ldquo;waiting orders&rdquo; has a number of meanings. You seem to<lb/>
have been into things which have long gone begging for the<lb/>
doing and should be most helpful. As to the malaria abstracts,<lb/>
it is high time that the chaff and the <unclear>grain</unclear> be sifted apart,<lb/>
and as for the Yellow Fever history, the thing seems almost<lb/>
Providential. To go in for that is a particularly graceful<lb/>
activity for the International Health Board to foster, and to<lb/>
get you do do it is simply fine; it is superfluous for me to<lb/>
add that you are probably the only man who is familiar with<lb/>
the major part of the western hemisphere zone at first hand<lb/>
and has participated in the solution of the epidemiology of<lb/>
the condition; I know that you will enjoy the accomplishment<lb/>
of the task, and I am am equally sure that when it will have<lb/>
been completed it is certain to be a source of real pride<lb/>
to you. I think it is just splendid.</p>
<p>As to my own work, I hardly know where or how to<lb/>
begin. I entered private practice here in July, 1919, at the<lb/>
close of my Service detail, taking up the class of work in which<lb/>
I was best qualified, ie., the laboratory side. I have worked<lb/>
very hard, and I have made a certain amount of progress; if<lb/>
success is to be measured in terms of bank balances or real<lb/>
estate holdings, I am still at my beginnings, but if on the<lb/>
other hand, friendships, confidence, etc., count for anything,<lb/>
my time has not been wasted. I have made more money since I<lb/>
have been at work here than I have ever made before, though it<lb/>
has cost much more to &ldquo;carry on&rdquo;. Each year has shown definite<lb/>
gains and I have much to be very grateful for as there are<lb/>
many other and older men here who have not fared so well.<lb/>
I am still doing laboratory work almost exclusively, &ldquo;almost&rdquo;<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00929011"/>
in that I have taken charge of a few medical cases; I am<lb/>
getting more and more interested in the field of Internal<lb/>
Medicine, particularly in the side of metabolism (diabetes,<lb/>
hypertension, etc), and the cases that I have taken so far<lb/>
have belonged almost exclusively to that class. Whether at<lb/>
some time in the future I will go into medicine is as yet<lb/>
not determined, though I find it very attractive.</p>
<p>I am teaching two courses at Vanderbilt Medical School,<lb/>
ie., Preventive Medicine and Clinical Pathology; the first<lb/>
is a lecture course to the Senior class, some thirty lectures<lb/>
in all, covering (?) the entire subject; I am probably open<lb/>
to the criticism in this that malaria and typhoid get by far<lb/>
the best of it, and Vital Statistics (shades of Trask!) some<lb/>
rather shabby treatment. The Clinical Pathology course is<lb/>
a laboratory course to the Sophomores and it is too heavy,<lb/>
-there is no &ldquo;probably&rdquo; about it this time, in parasitology.<lb/>
While one course, the Prev. Med., is a Fall course and the other<lb/>
comes in the Spring, I dont think I can carry the two any<lb/>
longer; the laboratory course calls for four hours a day for<lb/>
five days a week, six weeks, and, while I am being paid for the<lb/>
time, it is far too burdensome. I hope to get relieved next<lb/>
year and will gladly accept an unpaid assistantship instead of<lb/>
heading the course. The job, besides, ought to be the <unclear>official</unclear><lb/>
attachment of a full-time man by whom collateral research might<lb/>
be carried on. Lord knows, there is plenty of room for it in<lb/>
connection with some of our southern problems.</p>
<p>Speaking of research, however, I am almost ashamed to<lb/>
admit that malaria and its literature has gotten precious<lb/>
little of my time in the past few years. I have been studying<lb/>
chemistry and physiology almost to the exclusion of everything<lb/>
else, and besides, I have seen so little malaria that it seems<lb/>
almost a curiosity.</p>
<p>I would be doing neither you nor the truth justice, if<lb/>
I left you with the impression that Nashville and my work have<lb/>
been so completely absorbing that everything else has been<lb/>
subordinated. I have been homesick just lots of times and I<lb/>
have missed the Service and its associations, even the asinini-<lb/>
ties of the inspired Bureau and others whom I might but wont<lb/>
mention by name, seem, -in retrospect, to be sort of glossed<lb/>
over with a few lovable attributes. I have certainly missed<lb/>
our field trips, the &ldquo;talk&rdquo; part that is, for I detested the<lb/>
rest of it, as I have told you, probably only too often. I have<lb/>
though, found here a lot of things that I have wanted; I live in<lb/>
one place, I know a lot of people, I have accumulated a few<lb/>
books, and, in short, I like it, but there are days when I miss<lb/>
many things of the Service life. I cant say that I have ever<lb/>
had cause to regret my change though some of my best friends<lb/>
seem mighty inaccessible and faraway.</p>
<p>Your letter reached me on the day of one of the farewell<lb/>
dinners given to Dr. Olin West and when I told him that night<lb/>
of your letter and of its message to him, he was immensely<lb/>
pleased to have been remembered by you. He asked me to convey<lb/>
his good regards to you and to thank you for your message. I<lb/>
am deeply sorry at his going; he has been one of my closest<lb/>
friends here and often my advisor, but the loss to Dr. Wests<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00929012"/>
personal friends, who are legion, does not compare with the<lb/>
loss to the State of Tennessee. To me he has stood out as one<lb/>
of the best, if not the best State Health Officer in the South,<lb/>
and I know that he has done almost single-handed, work that<lb/>
compares very favorably with wealthier or more liberal States.<lb/>
He is being succeeded by his old predecessor, Dr. Lillard, an<lb/>
out-and-out political doctor of the most typical variety. It<lb/>
is a great pity and much of the most valuable rural work that<lb/>
has just been begun and is still in its infancy is certain to<lb/>
be utterly lost. Dr. West goes into his new work with all of the<lb/>
good wishes of a lot of fine people, but also with the deepest<lb/>
of regrets on the part of those who are familiar with what he has<lb/>
accomplished.</p>
<p>Good old friend, I find that in starting to write you a<lb/>
<unclear>latter</unclear>, I have come dangerously near undertaking a book. There<lb/>
is still much I should like to write of, but it is growing late<lb/>
and there will be other letters. My Mother and Sister, -both of<lb/>
whom are in excellent health, ask me to convey to you their<lb/>
good regards. Thanks again for your letter. Remember me warmly<lb/>
to Miss Laura and to Henry.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Derivaux</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
