<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00925005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Lunsford D. Fricks, January 8, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00925005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-01-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Fricks, Lunsford D.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">Badin (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Charlotte (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Bridgewater (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-01-08">January 8, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00925005</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Lunsford D. Fricks, January 8, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] asks that the Public Health Service supervise mosquito study and control of ponds at Badin and other places in North Carolina.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-01-08">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Lunsford D. Fricks, January 8, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00925005"/>
<opener>
/LC<lb/>
<unclear>N. M. C</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Imp'd</unclear> water<lb/>
<hi>Fricks</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1922-01-08">January 8, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Surgeon L. D. Fricks,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Room 17, Court House Building,<lb/>
Memphis, <unclear>Tonn</unclear>.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Fricks:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I Mr. Thorpe, the General Manager of the plant of the American<lb/>
Aluminum Co. at Badin, N. C., was in to see me a few days ago.<lb/>
He is desireous of carrying out such measures as are necessary<lb/>
and <hi>possible</hi> for the control of malaria caused by the Badin Pond.</p>
<p>He asked if I would be willing to undertake the general super-<lb/>
vision of this and to recommend someone who could give it the ne-<lb/>
cessary attention on the ground. It seemed to me better for him,<lb/>
however, if someone from the Malaria Division of the Service could<lb/>
be detailed for both the general and local supervision--not taking<lb/>
up all of their time upon this job, but visiting it from time to<lb/>
time, so as to see that their plans are carried out, and--naturally--<lb/>
varying these plans as conditions of weather etc. may require.<lb/>
The actual expense of carrying out these measures would, of course,<lb/>
be borne by the Power Company.</p>
<p>Should you find it advisable to undertake this work for the<lb/>
Malaria Division, and should <add>you</add> so wish. I will be very willing to<lb/>
visit the place two, three or four times the next summer for the<lb/>
sake of consulting with your representative. Mr. Thorpe would pay<lb/>
travelling expenses for so doing &amp; there would <add>of course,</add> be no charges for services.</p>
<p>This would be--if it be feasible--a good opportunity<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00925006"/>
opportunity</p>
<p>2.</p>
<p>1/ For research on a pond filled in 1916, part of which was per-<lb/>
fectly cleared: part of which partly, and part not cleared at all.<lb/>
The biological and epidemiological examination then, could be made to<lb/>
cover three conditions of pond preparation with less expenditure of<lb/>
time and effort than one would be apt to have elsewhere.</p>
<p>2/ One would have an opportunity to observe the effect of sani-<lb/>
tary measures in preventing mosquito breeding under, I think, unusually<lb/>
favorable conditions--I don't mean for success especially, but for de-<lb/>
termination. The Manager of the Company is a man of unusual abili-<lb/>
ty: force and good feeling and I think <del>orders</del><add>advice</add> will be carried out and<lb/>
co-operation given in a way that one would not find in many places.</p>
<p>This place is convenient to Charlotte--about two hours run by au-<lb/>
to--has machines: a good steam launch and small boats for towing: one<lb/>
man at least, who has had some training in malaria control and in rais-<lb/>
ing <hi>Gambusia</hi>: and a successful <hi>Gambusia</hi> nursery.</p>
<p>There would, of course, be no difficulty in getting Dr. Rankin to<lb/>
make the request on you should you be willing to grant it.</p>
<p>As I said, I think it would be better for Mr. Thorpe for this work<lb/>
to be under the supervision of the Service, yet, if you do not think it<lb/>
possible to undertake it, I can--I am quite certain--get Boldridge, of<lb/>
Chester, S. C., who has done some pond work with me, to take charge of <unclear>it</unclear>.</p>
<p>II) I wrote you a letter--in early October, I think, relative to the<lb/>
chances of taking up this problem of impounded waters in some of the pro-<lb/>
jects of the Southern Power Company. I do not know whether they applied<lb/>
to you or not. Before you could agree, this too, of course, would have<lb/>
to come from Dr. Rankin. I have no copy of the letter I wrote you, as<lb/>
it was in script, but my recollection is that it went into the question<lb/>
in some detail and suggested that if you stationed your representative at<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00925007"/>
at<lb/>
3.<lb/>
Charlotte, he could begin with the survey of the Mountain Island Pond,<lb/>
close to Charlotte, which will be filled next fall and on which I, my-<lb/>
self, outlined in some detail the preliminary work necessary, and had<lb/>
made a survey of one of its principal valleys<unclear>.</unclear></p>
<p>That I thought he would have time enough next year to make such<lb/>
other biological surveys as were needed to establish the status of the<lb/>
great Bridgewater Pond as to the production of Anopheles--a thing that<lb/>
is in question. Whether he could do this and also do the research and<lb/>
supervision necessary at Badin may be a question. I think I could have<lb/>
done so a few years ago. If it be advisable to conduct research in<lb/>
these three places and one man be unable to do it, all, I presume another<lb/>
man could be temporarily assigned in the Bridgewater matter--provided<lb/>
that you considered it more advantageous to make the research at Badin<lb/>
than at Bridgewater.</p>
<p>In case you cannot do the examination needed at Bridgewater, I, at<lb/>
present, purpose to complete it as far as may be necessary myself. I<lb/>
have been on the Pond three times already and I think two more trips of<lb/>
--say--14 days each--or may be better, three of 10 days each--next sum-<lb/>
mer should be sufficient.</p>
<p>Griffitts would seem to me the man best suited and available for<lb/>
this work. LePrince is absolutely suited, but I don't consider it con-<lb/>
ceivable that you could spare him for it and <add>xx</add> Griffitts is the only other<lb/>
man who has had any experience in this class of research. Also from one<lb/>
aspect of it at least, a physician and a bench man is <del>needed.</del> advisable<unclear>.</unclear> <del>alth</del><lb/>
Although an engineer <del>had</del> would be valuable also<lb/>
xx<lb/>
Griffitts is familiar with the Badin<lb/>
Pond: Made surveys there 1916:1919<lb/>
&amp; 1920</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Assistant Surgeon General</signed>
(On Waiting Orders)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
