<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00925033">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, January 19, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00925033</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-01-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Corrigan, John P.</name>
<name type="person">Pickett, I. W.</name>
<name type="person">Mendoza, Ricardo</name>
<name type="person">Caballero, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, Lawrence H.</name>
<name type="person">Seeley, Morris Monroe</name>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Chilca (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Lambayeque (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Libertad (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Callao (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-01-19">January 19, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00925033</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, January 19, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson details his yellow fever work in Peru, commenting on his workers, areas of the country where mosquito work is being done, the suspension of Dunn's stegomyia work, and fever cases.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-01-19">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, January 19, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00925033"/>
<opener>
DIRECTOR GENERAL<lb/>
HENRY HANSON<lb/>
M. D.<lb/>
BAJO LOS AUSPICIOS DEL<lb/>
GOBIERNO PERUANO Y LA<lb/>
JUNTA INTERNACIONAL DE<lb/>
SANIDAD DE ROCKEFELLER<lb/>
FOUNDATION<lb/>
NUMERO<lb/>
______<lb/>
<dateline>
Campa&ntilde;a Sanitaria contra la Fiebre Amarilla en el Per&uacute;<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
AVENIDA PIEROLA 545 -- TELEFONO ???<lb/>
LIMA -- PERU<lb/>
<date value="1922-01-19">Jan. 19, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your letters of Nov. 22nd and Dec. 21st before me; also the memorandum<lb/>
of Oct. 10th, which latter I do not remember having received before. These letters<lb/>
were even longer in reaching me than mine was in reaching you, and as you say,<lb/>
I think I could make the trip in much shorter time than the letters. I have<lb/>
recently received somewhere near a dozen letters from the International Health<lb/>
Board which should have reached me two or three weeks earlier than they did.<lb/>
I presume if they have not learned what the vagaries of this mail service<lb/>
are in this country they will think I am very lax and erratic in my correspondence.</p>
<p>You mention Corrigan and Pickett. From my other letters to you you doubtless<lb/>
know that I have brought Corrigan back again. The territory which we are watching<lb/>
now is so immensely big that it seems to me an absolute necessity to have a<lb/>
sufficient number of the reliable men for the supervising work so that I may be<lb/>
as nearly certain as possible as to what is going on.</p>
<p>In regard to what you say about Mendoza and Caballero, I now only have Caballero.<lb/>
Mendoza became over sensitive about the rules and regulations here and resigned.<lb/>
He had put on more men than I had authorized him to use in this section and<lb/>
when I called his attention to the matter, that and some recommendations of<lb/>
Corrigan's, hurt his dignity and he decided that his small contribution was no<lb/>
longer essential to the campaign. I had gradually been thinking somewhat in the<lb/>
same line so was not greatly disappointed when he resigned. Caballero, however,<lb/>
seems to hold his former steady pace, and seems to be always ready and willing<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00925034"/>
Dr. H.R. Carter, Jan. 19, 1922.<lb/>
2.<lb/>
to do whatever seems to be for the best interest of the final outcome of our<lb/>
work. I am using him both in the medical supervising capacity and as controller<lb/>
of the stegomya work in such places as Corrigan and Dunn are unable to reach.<lb/>
In so far as the work is concerned, we are aiming in so far as possible in our<lb/>
feeble judgment to make certain that there is no yellow fever in the country,<lb/>
and therefore we are extending our explorations sufficiently far so that we<lb/>
may be able to say, with certainty, that such is the case. You may be surprised<lb/>
to know how far we are going in the matter, but there are conditions which make<lb/>
me think it justifiable. We are extending our investigations even to the south<lb/>
of Lima; at the present time we have investigated as far south as Chilca, and<lb/>
I am planning for Dr. Caballero and either Dunn or Corrigan to leave for Canete<lb/>
next week. They are reporting a severe <unclear>paludismo</unclear> there and both Dr. Caballero<lb/>
and I think it important that we know with certainty what kind of paludismo<lb/>
this is. The entire territory between Lima and Piura has been very <unclear>throoughly</unclear><lb/>
worked and I think we have it in such condition that it is not possible for<lb/>
yellow fever to show up in this portion. In so far as the final extirpation is<lb/>
<unclear>cocerned</unclear>, as I see it at the present time, it depends entirely upon whether or<lb/>
not anything has gotten by us to the south, and for that reason we are making<lb/>
the investigations as far as Ica. Benites, who has just gone to Chilca, reports<lb/>
24% of the houses with stegomya breeding. However, unless we find something to<lb/>
arouse our suspicions, we shall not attempt to do as complete stegomya cam-<lb/>
paign work there as we did in the north. The departments of Lambayeque and<lb/>
Libertad are well organized and are under good supervision, and I think can be<lb/>
considered perfectly safe. Canseco and Seeley should be quite sufficient for<lb/>
Lambayeque. I have assumed what I considered the safest method of assuring the<lb/>
situation, namely, that of having no place within 200 miles of the infected portion<lb/>
with sufficient stegomya breeding to permit the disease of yellow fever; this<lb/>
because I have so little confidence in the reports from the local practicing<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00925035"/>
Dr. H.R. Carter, Jan. 19, 1922.<lb/>
3.<lb/>
physicians. In this manner I can be perfectly sure of results. It costs a<lb/>
little more money but is more certain. Keeping this up until April will mean<lb/>
that there will not be sufficient stegomya breeding to permit the spread of<lb/>
yellow fever until the following summer season, which will not be before<lb/>
October or November of this year. At the present time, then, we have about<lb/>
700 miles of the coast line, from the Ecuadorian border towards the south<lb/>
under our close supervision. With this extensive territory Lima becomes my<lb/>
most logical place for the central office, which has some advantages in that<lb/>
I am nearer to the center of Government for many affairs which I need to take<lb/>
up with them. It has the disadvantage in that I cannot be so much in the old<lb/>
infected territory, but as that is at the present time and with the supervision<lb/>
which we have there, it does not seem to me that it is of major importance that<lb/>
I spend a great deal of time there.</p>
<p>We very much appreciate the interest you have taken in regard to Karl's<lb/>
schooling. Unfortunately we have been obliged to postpone this matter and are<lb/>
doing what we can to keep him occupied and entertained here. I had fully<lb/>
expected to put him to work with Dunn on the stegomya research until I received<lb/>
a letter from Dr. Rose in which he states he does not think it would be worth while<lb/>
to carry out this investigation. Both Mr. Dunn and myself are very much dis-<lb/>
appointed at this decision. Personally, I think it a decided mistake. From<lb/>
my point of view, it would have been very much worth while to have made this<lb/>
investigation, at least to have put in all of Mr. Dunn's time from now until<lb/>
the time we finish the campaign. He could have given us some very valuable<lb/>
information on certain points and characteristics of the stegomya which are not<lb/>
known- points which would have a practical importance and certainly considerable<lb/>
historical importance and could have very well deserved their place in a campaign<lb/>
such as we think this Peruvian campaign is and will be considered in the history<lb/>
of yellow fever, namely, the last on the Pacific coast of South America. This<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00925036"/>
Dr. H.R. Carter, Jan. 19, 1922.<lb/>
4.<lb/>
work is not a work which can be done by a man who is obliged to spend a greater<lb/>
part of his time in the field. Mr. Dunn had done a great deal of work from<lb/>
the purely laboratory side in Panama, and what I had in mind would have been<lb/>
in the nature of completing his work and would have brought out the precise<lb/>
points which are lacking to us and on which I wanted information.</p>
<p>Yes, it seems that our work is beginning to draw to a close. I have absolutely<lb/>
no kick or complaint to make about what I have done or any effort which I have<lb/>
put into the work, but I doubt very much that any one except yourself and Dr.<lb/>
White will ever appreciate what this Peruvian campaign has been. I do not<lb/>
think the I.H.B. <unclear>reallize</unclear> it, principally for the reason that I have not had<lb/>
time to write them as extensively as I probably should have done.</p>
<p>In regard to your memorandum, I think I have practically answered your points<lb/>
in that. It seems to me that we have done just about what you suggested,<lb/>
except that maybe I have not laid as great stress on the medical inspection<lb/>
as you do in your memorandum. I feel that our rigorous stegomya control, in<lb/>
territory within 200 miles of the infected area, to the percentage which has<lb/>
eliminated the fever in the infected area is sufficient. Under the circumstances<lb/>
now existing Lima is really more central in that it puts me more in the center<lb/>
of the territory which has most recently been controlled, and where there are<lb/>
many problems to be decided. Everything in the north, as I stated, is completely<lb/>
organized and goes by definite rules which provide adequately for the situation.<lb/>
Lima, itself, is not a menace for the reason that the water system practically<lb/>
eliminates containers with breeding. We have had but one section, the Victoria<lb/>
section, which has had breeding enough for yellow fever, and also certain <unclear>scetions</unclear><lb/>
of Callao; but it is the territory both north and south of Lima which gives me<lb/>
uneasiness, if one should feel any such thing.</p>
<p>In regard to the case in Callao, that has practically been answered in what<lb/>
I have told you about Lima and Callao. What breeding there was we have reduced<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00925037"/>
Dr. H.R. Carter, Jan. 19, 1922.<lb/>
5.<lb/>
to below where any propagation could take place. It regard to the case itself,<lb/>
the man did not have a true black vomit, but considerable bleeding from the gums;<lb/>
the urine did not have as heavy an albumen content as a severe case of yellow<lb/>
fever should have had, and on the other hand the urine was not the urine of<lb/>
a typical Blackwater fever. In this connection, it has been interesting to note<lb/>
that there has been a number of cases of stomatitis in this section where we<lb/>
have been absolutely certain there has been no suggestion of yellow fever.<lb/>
These cases had bleeding gums on very slight pressure, but that was the only thing<lb/>
similar to the mouth conditions in yellow fever. I have not had time to go into<lb/>
this case any further since I came <unclear>nack</unclear>, principally because I have not thought<lb/>
it sufficiently important to do so at the present time. I appreciate very much<lb/>
getting this clinical discussion from you on the relation <unclear>netween</unclear> malaria,<lb/>
yellow fever, and Weil's disease.</p>
<p>In regard to what you say about Karl's illness, I am inclined to think the<lb/>
same as you do, and did at the time, which was one of my big reasons for<lb/>
sending him up to Panama. As to Col. Case's little girl, they have taken her to<lb/>
the states, and are reporting some improvement, but I do not expect complete<lb/>
recovery by any means.</p>
<p>At the present time, we are hoping to arrive in New York in the first part<lb/>
of June, but I will let you know later on. I should very much appreciate<lb/>
it if you could meet us in New York as I should like to make my call on<lb/>
Dr. Rose with you that we might talk the situation over together with him.<lb/>
We are trying to get up some data on the preliminary report but I fear I<lb/>
shall have to give them simply general statements and estimates since our<lb/>
files are so extensive; we have had such a tremendously big campaign this year<lb/>
that it will take us weeks to properly review what records we have on it.<lb/>
We have made considerably more than 500,000 house visits and more than<lb/>
1,000,000 individual container inspections. It appears that we have used more<lb/>
than 700,000 fish. Taking all this in addition to our other work, you can<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00925038"/>
Dr. H.R. Carter, Jan. 19, 1922.<lb/>
6.<lb/>
fully reallize what the magnitude of our task has been. I have no doubt that,<lb/>
as you say, it would have been a good thing to have taken Carter and Hayne in<lb/>
May. My Scandinavian you speak of, <unclear>Guldstand</unclear>, has acted as auditor for the<lb/>
campaign and has been kept quite busy.</p>
<p>In regard to your inquiry about Col. and Mrs. Wrightson, I might say that<lb/>
they are apparently getting on well and seem to be in good health. The<lb/>
&ldquo;Colonel&rdquo; has not been able to do much for the lack of funds.</p>
<p>With the best of good wishes, and with the hope that I shall not have<lb/>
occasion to send you any unfavorable news, I beg to remain</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson, M.D.</signed>
<seg>
P.S. <unclear>I enclose</unclear> Col. Vergne's report on<lb/>
his study of Yellow Fever among<lb/>
the troops in the north,<lb/>
Also a few copies of our last<lb/>
leaflet of propaganda.<lb/>
H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
