<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00928001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to P.M. Ashburn, April 15, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00928001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-04-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ashburn, P.M.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-04-15">April 15, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00928001</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to P.M. Ashburn, April 15, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] thanks Ashburn for sending him his manuscript. He discusses issues concerning mosquitos, specifically the Anopheles.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-04-15">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to P.M. Ashburn, April 15, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00928001"/>
<opener>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1922-04-15">April 15, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Colonel P. M. Ashburn, M. C. U. S. A.,<lb/>
Medical Field Service School,<lb/>
Carlisle Barracks, Pa.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Ashburn:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am very much obliged to you for your MSS, which I read with a great<lb/>
deal of interest. In two of the main points I have long been interested:<lb/>
1/ The breeding of Anopheles in the U. S. at a distance from the blood<lb/>
supply furnished by man and the domestic animals dependent on man:<lb/>
2/ Whether there is a difference in distance between the flight for<lb/>
first blood for oviposition and the flights thereafter, which only could<lb/>

be infecting flights.</p>
<p>To take the last matter first, I am inclined to think that there is--<lb/>
that Anopheles will go farther in the first flight than subsequent ones.<lb/>
The experiments that we have made with stained insects--not enough, of<lb/>
course, to be determinative--have been greater in distance when made<lb/>
with insects newly hatched than with those caught in houses the great<lb/>
majority of which had fed.</p>
<p>I am going to ask that an old publication from my Service be sent you<lb/>
touching upon this subject. If you get it, not Pages 33 and 34. Recent<lb/>
observations by von Bremen in Batavia give a distance of flight of 2 1/2<lb/>
kilometres whereas he states malaria is conveyed in that section to a-<lb/>
bout 1 6/10 kilometres from the breeding places of the vectors. His ex-<lb/>
perimental insects were newly developed--had never <unclear>fed--</unclear>but he does not<lb/>
<unclear></unclear> attention to this factor.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00928002"/>
<p>factor.<lb/>
2.</p>
<p>With regard to the first point, I had planned a survey of the prac-<lb/>
tically uninhabited cypress swamps of eastern South Carolina and Georgia,<lb/>
but have not been able to carry this out to any extent. Such little as<lb/>
was done (on the Salkahatchie in S. C.) showed no Anopheles--that is, I<lb/>
could find none, except within a reasonable distance of either men or<lb/>
stock.</p>
<p>We have noted this symbiosis of the three Anopheles common east of the<lb/>
Mississippi both with domestic animals and men. With the former it seems<lb/>
closest, which is natural, as animals are always both more numerous and<lb/>
more accessible to mosquitoes than the men at farm houses.</p>
<p>I have not found any special predeliction either for men or for ani-<lb/>
mals with our Anopheles: It is rather a question, I think, of ready<lb/>
access. Practically we do not find punctipennis in residences, except<lb/>
in the cool weather of early spring and late fall: quadrimaculatus are es-<lb/>
sentially a house mosquito so far as feeding is concerned: crucians ap-<lb/>
parently somewhat between the two, if anything nearer punctipennis in<lb/>
this habit.</p>
<p>I am inclosing an abstract of some work of Roubaud--not very recent<unclear>--</unclear><lb/>
but if you have not seen it, of interest to you. You will note that he--<lb/>
and the same is true of both Sella and Grassi--considers that the blood<lb/>
supply is an insignifigant factor in the production of Anopheles. This<lb/>
may be true in Europe where there is doubtless always sufficient blood<lb/>
supply within the distance of flight from any breeding place, but I am<lb/>
quite sure is not so here.</p>
<p>I got your Military Hygiene from the Surgeon General's Library and read<lb/>
the part referred to with much interest.</p>
<p>With best wished, I remain</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
Enclosure.<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
