<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00927002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Henry Hanson , March 11, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00927002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-03-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Dunn, Lawrence H.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Lyster, Theodore C.</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-03-11">March 11, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00927002</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Henry Hanson , March 11, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] informs Hanson that he has been lecturing on malaria and yellow fever at Johns Hopkins.  Currently he is working on a brief history of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-03-11">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Henry Hanson, March 11, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00927002"/>
<opener>
I. H. B.<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1922-03-11">March 11, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hanson:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am dictating this to my daughter because I am on my back again.<lb/>
I will tell you the cause of it presently.</p>
<p>I have received tow letters from you--indeed three--Jan. 19th.:<lb/>
Jan. 20th. and Feb. 20th.--since I wrote you. The reason of my not do-<lb/>
ing so earlier is (1) I have not been entirely well--my &ldquo;kink&rdquo; has given<lb/>
me a good deal of trouble.</p>
<p>More efficient as a cause of silence, however, has been the fact<lb/>
that I have been giving a few lectures on the sanitary management of<lb/>
malaria and yellow fever at the Hopkins School of <unclear>Hygiene</unclear> and have, in-<lb/>
deed, two more to give: Only one--the lastoone--will be on yellow fever.<lb/>
This is rather a cavalier way to treat a somewhat extensive subject.<lb/>
Naturally, I won't be able to go into details, but will exploit your<lb/>
fish campaign as being not only le dernier cri in Stegomyia control, but<lb/>
the most efficient method therefor.</p>
<p>There are quite a number of Latin Americans in the class and I at<lb/>
least wish to remove the erroneous ideas they have imbibed from the Pas-<lb/>
teur Commissions at Rio and Martinique. It is strange how uncritical a<lb/>
Latin American is in accepting as authoritative a statement from another<lb/>
Latin. Even Colonel Verne, who is not a Latin American, claims that Beau-<lb/>
perthuy picked out the Stegomyia as a vector of yellow fever. The &ldquo;Culex<lb/>
bobo&rdquo; of Beauperthuy, I feel quite sure, included Culex sollicitans, al-<lb/>
though he may have confounded Stegomyia with it. He makes it a distinctly<lb/>
marine species of &ldquo;brackish marshes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The cause of my present collapse is quite certainly from having rid-<lb/>
den back from Baltimore, from one of those lectures, in a jolting trolley.<lb/>
The &ldquo;kink&rdquo; cannot stand steady continued vibration.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00927003"/>
<p>vibration.</p>
<p>2.</p>
<p>In addition, I have finally agreed to write a brief history of yellow<lb/>
fever for the I. H. B., and have, indeed, been at work on it--getting data<lb/>
and taking notes--since about January 10th. Hence my knowledge of Beau-<lb/>
perthuy!</p>
<p>I declined at first to write it, but offered to work on it for six<lb/>
weeks or two months until I could determine:1/. Whether I could do the work<lb/>
to my own satisfaction--I lay more stress on my own criticism than on<lb/>
that of the I. H. B.--2/ Whether it would be right to stop my abstracts<lb/>
and reviews of the malaria articles in journals (all except Italian, which<lb/>
I can't read). These, since October, I have been getting out mimeographed<lb/>
and sending to the men in the field, and, indeed to a considerable num-<lb/>
ber of other people interested in malaria. 3/ How much of an onus the<lb/>
work would be.</p>
<p>I have finally decided--as I said--to take it up. I will have to<lb/>
drop the malaria work--for which I am really sorry. Sent off the last<lb/>
little article (a review of some work done in Batavia by the Dutch) last<lb/>
evening. It is quite an onus, but I believe I can do it, and I presume<lb/>
it ought to be done; though it is not really construtive work, like that<lb/>
I have been doing in malaria--more in the nature of an <unclear>ornament</unclear>, I think.<lb/>
However, I have decided.</p>
<p>I was exceedingly glad to get the pictures of the &ldquo;kids.&rdquo; Martha<lb/>
is a charming little thing. Virgil I would not have known. He is a fine<lb/>
looking, great big boy--as ernest as he was when a baby! I thought he<lb/>
was going to develope a considerable streak of <unclear>self-will:</unclear> would want what<lb/>
he wanted and want it now! Has he ever admitted the fact of gravitation?<lb/>
or will he still undertake to jump from one person's arms to another's<lb/>
clear across the room? A baby reminds me much of Einstein in his reject-<lb/>
ion of Isaac Newton's laws.</p>
<p>I am inclined to think that with your small force it was probably<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00927004"/>
probably<lb/>
3.<lb/>
wise not to take Dunn off the actual inspection and put him on the scien-<lb/>
tific side of Stegomyia work. Most--not all--of the problems you enumer-<lb/>
ate have been either settled or quite well studied.</p>
<p>One addition you have made to our knowledge of their breeding places.<lb/>
Francis states that larvae have not been found in puddles with earth bot-<lb/>
toms: Yours is with earth <hi>sides</hi> and this last, from our Peruvian exper-<lb/>
ience, is correct and naturally would be so from a consideration of the<lb/>
way she deposits her eggs at the very edge of the water--or even on the<lb/>
side itself. She has no knowledge of the bottom in--say-- a 4 ft. <hi>botija</hi>,<lb/>
while the side is a matter of importance to her in laying.</p>
<p>The recent work of Gordon and Young has settled beyond any cavil<lb/>
the fact that Stegomyia over 14 days old, and having received at least<lb/>
two previous blood meals, feed more often in the day (double as often)<lb/>
than in the night. Their work was scarcely necessary, as that of Seidelin<lb/>
in Merida and Goeldi in Para, as well, I think, as my own observations on<lb/>
conveyance in Panama, was sufficient.</p>
<p>This is the 11th. of March--the day you left us at Salaverry last<lb/>
year. I judge you feel very differently from what you did then. We knew<lb/>
your work was cut out out for you and was going to be a long, hard job--<lb/>
and our prognosis was about right! We both considered <add>it</add> more than probable<lb/>
that yellow fever was in Libertad at that time. I judge that we were<lb/>
right in that too. If it had not come in of itself it was practically<lb/>
compelled to do so by the maritime quarantine imposed--January 12th. or<lb/>
14th., I believe--by the Salubridad.</p>
<p>About Mexico and Central America--I don't think the work has been<lb/>
handled quite as well as it might have been--although no one knows better<lb/>
than we do the impossibility of judging from a distance of the difficul-<lb/>
ties that the man actually in charge of the work may have. I think they<lb/>
have done too much following up of small local o<del>p</del><add>u</add>tbreaks. My advice to<lb/>
Lyster when I saw him, and since then to White, was to concentrate and<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00927005"/>
<unclear>nd</unclear><lb/>
4.<lb/>
practically confine their work (Stegomyia work) to &ldquo;key-points&rdquo;--large<lb/>
towns or places which, from their travel-relations, would spread infection<lb/>
to large towns. To take such places, whether they were infected now or<lb/>
not, and render them uninfectable and not to worry about little out-<lb/>
breaks--at least not for their own sakes: That small places would free<lb/>
their own selves if you gave them a little time.</p>
<p>I am not ill pleased to see that the fever has--or rather has had--<lb/>
a wide distribution in Mexico. It means that many small places have burn-<lb/>
ed out and I cannot but hope that a campaign pressed will finish it by<lb/>
next winter. It would be a good thing, however, if White had two or three<lb/>
more good American Sub-Directors. I think he took two down with him: One<lb/>
(Scannell) should be a good man.</p>
<p>Whether the Guatamala revolution will make a back-fire or not I do<lb/>
not know. I think not.</p>
<p>I believe your work is done. It is right--it was necessary as an<lb/>
insurance--to keep on to, or into, June. <del>but</del> One would think that if any<lb/>
yellow fever were kept over it would have shown up by this time, although<lb/>
it is fairly hot--in the north at any rate--up to May 1st. With Peru goes<lb/>
the West Coast of South America and the freeing of that unit from yellow<lb/>
fever is a very great thing--important not only on account of the large<lb/>
area freed, but (unless the Cosmos Line starts up again) on account of<lb/>
this freedom being permanent --an important stepping stone to the perma-<lb/>
nent elimination of yellow fever.</p>
<p>With very best remembrances to you all, in which Laura asks to be<lb/>
included,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely your friend,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
