<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00926024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, February 27, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00926024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-02-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Wrightson, William D.</name>
<name type="person">Caballero, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, Lawrence H.</name>
<name type="person">Olivari, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-02-27">February 27, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00926024</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, February 27, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson reports on mosquito larvae studies in Peru.  He also discusses, at length, administrative and political issues related to his work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-02-27">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, February 27, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00926024"/>
<opener>
I. H. B.<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
<hi><unclear>Sleg</unclear></hi><lb/>
DIRECTOR GENERAL<lb/>
HENRY HANSON<lb/>
M. D.<lb/>
BAJO LOS AUSPICIOS DEL<lb/>
GOBIERNO PERUANO Y LA<lb/>
JUNTA INTERNACIONAL DE<lb/>
SANIDAD DE ROCKEFELLER<lb/>
FOUNDATION<lb/>
<dateline>
Campa&ntilde;a Sanitaria contra la Fiebre Amarilla en el Per&uacute;<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
AVENIDA PIEROLA 545 - TELEFONO 3428<lb/>
LIMA -- PERU <date value="1922-02-27">February 27, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
NUMERO<lb/>
----<lb/>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My daer Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just received your letter of February 6th and<lb/>
am sorry that due to the decision of Dr. Rose we are unable to giev you any-<lb/>
thing except general observations, and few of those. This line of information<lb/>
which you have asked for is a part of what we hoped to get by the work which<lb/>
Dunn and I had in mind. I presume that by this time you have the letter which<lb/>
I wrote you telling you that Dr. Rose had decided that he did not think it would<lb/>
be worth while for Dunn to devote more than part time to the investigations which<lb/>
we had mapped out. I presume that I had not given him sufficient details about<lb/>
our work, as we had been pretty busy and I had only written in a very general<lb/>
way about what I hoped to have Dunn do for us. As I told you before I think the<lb/>
decision was a decided mistake and eliminates a very important piece of information<lb/>
which we were in better position to get here than anywhere we have been before.<lb/>
We have as you know an arid climate which introduces certain features of interest<lb/>
in a study of this kind.</p>
<p>From the few observation which we have been able to make I think there is<lb/>
no doubt about that the Pasteur Commission have set their temperatures too high.<lb/>
We found the stegomya active and had them bite in the evenings at temperatures<lb/>
of 17 C, and we noted in Trujillo where the temperatures fell pretty low at<lb/>
night that we had practically a continuous new crop of young larvae. The men<lb/>
kept finding new young larvae throughout the last winter season. In order to<lb/>
make any authoritative statement it would be necessary to attempt to repeat<lb/>
these observations in some sort of a Laboratory where one would have accurate<lb/>
control so as to be able to judge about the conditions; whether all these young<lb/>
larvae came from botijas in kitchens where the temperature was higher than the<lb/>
official temperatures or whether it actually is a fact that they breed at these<lb/>
(by us) observed lower temperatures. Dr. Cavassa has had more time and patience<lb/>
in making observations of this kind than any of the rest of them. He recently<lb/>
sent me a glass in which he had been conducting some experimental observations<lb/>
on breeding and in this glass I found quite a number of the eggs attached to<lb/>
the sides even though it had been shipped<del>d</del> from Guadelupe to Lima. In regard to<lb/>
this feature <unclear>Duhn</unclear> claims that the eggs float to the sides and become attached<lb/>
by means of a number of cup-like depressions (a sort of a suctions or cohesion<lb/>
process) and that it is not the case that the Aedes (Stegomya) Aegyptus (Linnaeus)<lb/>
a tually smears her eggs on the side of the container as we at one time thought<lb/>
here.</p>
<p>In as much as this is Carnival Days, and as you know a species of fiesta<lb/>
which prevents us from doing any work I am writing this at home, but will show<lb/>
you letter to Dunn to-morrow or as soon as I see him and ask him to write you<lb/>
what he knows about the points which you have brought up.</p>
<p>Well so far as Wrightson is concerned things seem to have come to a crisis<lb/>
and the Minister of Fomento is insisting on his resignation, and W. has pre-<lb/>
sented it, although up to date it has not been accepted by the President I think<lb/>
it will be. There seems to be a sort of an impression here that it might cause<lb/>
offense to the U.S.A. to discharge him. Some of us citizens of the U.S.A. have<lb/>
intimated that we could not see that such could be the case when a discharge<lb/>
could be made for cause. Unfortunately I have been drawn into this muddle as<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00926025"/>
2.<lb/>
February 27, 1922.<lb/>
Dr. H.R. Carter.<lb/>
there has been quite a considerable demand that I take over the Salubridad<lb/>
even if it only temporarily. His tennure of office has been even a bigger<lb/>
mess than I previously thought it would be and certainly has not raised the<lb/>
prestige of American Sanitarians in the country. I can not see <del><unclear></unclear></del> where he<lb/>
has done anything of any value to the country aside from getting Cardenas out of<lb/>
the Office. It seems to me that all accomplishments are of a negative nature.</p>
<p>Saturday evening I cabled the International Health Board about the matter<lb/>
asking their advise. I can hardly afford to take it and I dont want it; not<lb/>
any more than Martha or Virgil like to take Castor oil. However there seems to<lb/>
be some matters in connection with the financial arrangements and details of the<lb/>
campaign which I could only hope for a proper adjustment of by taking the title<lb/>
of &ldquo;Direccion de Salubridad&rdquo; for the few remaining months of the campaign. On<lb/>
account of our practically Nation wide investigations I am almost forcibly con-<lb/>
fined to Lima, and it might be possible to steer that almost rudderless ship<lb/>
in addition to the part of our work which is still lacking. The thing which I<lb/>
wanted to do in connection with work on the final general report would have to<lb/>
be postponed if I did such a rash thing. In such a case I should make quite<lb/>
extensive use of Dr. Lavoreria. I think I know more about the actual sanitary<lb/>
conditions of the country than any other man they have got, and I also am be-<lb/>
comming quite well informed about the trickery of their politics etc, and they<lb/>
would not be able to put as many things over on me as they might have done<lb/>
formerly. If I dont take it and they let W. out there are a string of political<lb/>
aspirants for the job who have no qualifications whatever, and several of the<lb/>
better class want me to take it if it is only temporarily to avoid a calamity<lb/>
of that kind. Dr. Lavoreria and Dr. Ezayguirre (the statistician) are especially<lb/>
anxious that I do that, I believe that they are sincere in wanting some ability<lb/>
and dignity in the office. If I were a single man without family (I presume the<lb/>
latter part of this remark would be taken for granted in the U.S.A.) I would<lb/>
enjoy the fight for a year or two - there is no question about it being a fight f<lb/>
for the man who stays with it - because there is literally everything to do.</p>
<p>I am hoping <unclear>howev r</unclear> that things will so adjust themselves that it will not<lb/>
be necessary for me to have to mis up in this matter, I am like the soldier across<lb/>
the sea - &ldquo;I want to go home, I dont want to die&rdquo;, and have been planning on<lb/>
getting to the <unclear>State</unclear> in June or July at the latest.</p>
<p>I am glad to hear that you have considered writing the History of Yellow<lb/>
Fever. It appears that you are the logical man to do it as you have played one<lb/>
of the if not the biggest part in its control and elimination, and it seems<lb/>
quite appropriate that you should write its history. I can well imagine that<lb/>
it will be a big task, as the subject is quite big when one begins to go into<lb/>
it in some detail.</p>
<p>I had had an idea of wanting to include a brief historical sketch, a<lb/>
paragraph or two in what you might call the introductory part of our general<lb/>
report on the recent Peruvian epidemics, but I have no literature from which<lb/>
I might get a sort of bird's eye view of its history. Dr. Ezayguirre has written<lb/>
a sort of a resume of the history of yellow fever in Peru up to the year 1906<lb/>
which I have been reading a bit at times. It seems to me though that he draws<lb/>
some erroneous conclusions at times (probably due to influences such as Dr.<lb/>
<unclear>Arce</unclear> who did not want the <unclear>worl</unclear> to think that Peru has had quite as much yellow fe<lb/>
fever as actually is the case). Dr. Ezayguirre is a pretty good fellow and<lb/>
probably with the soundest judgement of all the men with whom I have had any-<lb/>
thing to do in the Salubridad. Recently he came out openly in the Lima Academy<lb/>
of Medicine and stated that he thought that probably all the cases which Dr.<lb/>
Julian Arce had reported as biliosa hemoglobinurica, were cases of yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00926026"/>
<p>3.<lb/>
February 27, 1922.<lb/>
Dr. H.R. Carter.</p>
<p>I noticed when I stopped in the office this afternoon that Nelsons<lb/>
had sent me the leaves of your article in NELSON'S LOOSE LEAF MEDICINE. I<lb/>
have not had time to read them yet but have no doubt that we will find them<lb/>
of great value. If I was not in doubts about securing the approval of<lb/>
Nelsons I would also translate this and use extracts of it in some of our<lb/>
publicity. I believe that I now have most of your articles, but there are still<lb/>
some lacking. If you have copies of others which you could spare me temporarily<lb/>
I should like to get them and put them all into spanish. For the near future it<lb/>
will be more important to have these available in the spanish speaking countries<lb/>
than anywhere else. When I think of this I feel as they say here sort of<lb/>
&ldquo;quejoso&rdquo; that we were not able to get this work of Dunns to include with our<lb/>
report and propaganda stuff, it would have so completely rounded out our cam-<lb/>
paign and certainly would have shown up as one more big thing done through the<lb/>
medium of the International Health Board and the Rockefeller Foundation. However<lb/>
&ldquo;no use to cry over spilled milk&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Dr. Caballero, Mr. Dunn and Sr. Olivari have returned from their tour of<lb/>
inspection in the south, and Caballero reports that there was nothing there in<lb/>
the line of suspicious illness, but they found a high stegomya index all the<lb/>
way to Moquegua. We shall make an inspection og Canete, and its port which is<lb/>
Cerro Azul, and then we will have completed a survey of the entire coast of Peru.<lb/>
We now know pretty well what the conditions are on the entire coast. We are still<lb/>
having a little trouble with the breeding in such places as Barranca, Pativilca,<lb/>
Supe and the port of Supe and also in Huarmey where on account of the very poor<lb/>
steamship schedules we have been unable to do any work until recently. Still<lb/>
taken as a whole I think we have the coast in very good shape and with a suffi-<lb/>
ciently low index to prevent <del><unclear>knowing</unclear></del> the spread of yellow fever in all parts.</p>
<p>I want to arrange to start on a tour of inspection soon, and will endeavor<lb/>
to<del>o</del> look over as much of the old infected territory as possible. If we do not<lb/>
find anything within the next month I think the job can be considered finished.</p>
<p>I will write you again as soon as I know what all our areas are<lb/>
showing. It has been a pretty big proposition to try to keep in touch with all<lb/>
parts of so extensive a territory as that which we now have.</p>
<p>With best wishes from all the family, and I might add here in<lb/>
reply to your remarks about Virgil and Martha, that Virgil does not see any<lb/>
reason why he should allow Martha or anyone else to interfere with any plan<lb/>
or project which he may have under way. His psychology of just dealing is<lb/>
that it is all just when it comes out his way, but not otherwise.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>,
17x9/5=3.4x9<lb/>
30.6+32<lb/>
=62.&deg;6F.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
