<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00924010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Impounded Waters, by Joseph Augustine LePrince, [1921?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00924010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">United States</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-00-00">[1921?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00924010</idno>
<title>Report: Impounded Waters, by Joseph Augustine LePrince, [1921?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>LePrince describes mosquito breeding in impounded waters, suggesting necessary regulations to be implemented by State Boards of Health.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-00-00">
<head>Report: Impounded Waters, by Joseph Augustine LePrince, [1921?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00924010"/>
<opener>
Imp'd water<lb/>
Alaban<lb/>
<hi>1921</hi><lb/>
</opener>
<p>I M P O U N D E D  W A T E R S<lb/>
_________<lb/>
by JA LePrince</p>
<p>The impounding of waters in river valleys is an essential<lb/>
part of the proper development of the natural resources of<lb/>
the state and is of marked benefit to its present and future<lb/>
citizens. It is believed such improvements can be accomplish-<lb/>
ed at a reasonable cost without rendering unhealthful consider-<lb/>
able areas adjacent to such projects.</p>
<p>As previous development of water power in states in the<lb/>
malaria belt has given many well-known illustrations where<lb/>
such procedure (in this state as well as others) resulted in<lb/>
a rapid and pronounced increase of malaria fever, in some in-<lb/>
stances of a more pernicious type than formerly obtained, it<lb/>
became necessary for the State Board of Health to investigate<lb/>
such outbreaks and make scientific investigations of the re-<lb/>
lation of newly impounded water to the increase and prevalence<lb/>
of malaria in territory adjacent.</p>
<p>Among other facts that developed were the following, which<lb/>
have also been found to hold true in general in other southern<lb/>
states where malaria prevails:</p>
<p>(1). When large bodies of water are impounded it takes<lb/>
several years or more for nature to bring the newly formed pond<lb/>
under such control conditions as are biologically found in old<lb/>
lakes or ponds whether natural or artificial (man made).</p>
<p>(2). Whether the conditions brought about by the impound-<lb/>
ing of waters produce a situation favoring marked increase of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00924011"/>
(2)<lb/>
malaria conveying mosquitoes or not depends on:</p>
<p>(a) The details of topography affected.</p>
<p>(b) Shape of contour of the lakes boundary line.</p>
<p>(c) The character and presence of trees, brush, and<lb/>
vegetation, especially that near or adjacent to and above<lb/>
and below its high and low water flow lines.</p>
<p>(d) Exposure of the lake surface to wind action.</p>
<p>(e) Frequency of strong wind in all inlets of the lake<lb/>
in summer and in autumn seasons.</p>
<p>(f) Prevalence of heavy storms.</p>
<p>(g) Character of aquatic and semi-acquatic growth in<lb/>
the rain shed of the lake.</p>
<p>(h) Amounts of floatage and debris carried by the river<lb/>
feeding the lake.</p>
<p>(i) Pronounced fluctuation of water level, may be (or by<lb/>
proper control can frequently be made to be) a controlling fac-<lb/>
tor. - Say two to four feet at ten day intervals or less in the<lb/>
mosquito season - the 24 inch for more abrupt and the 48 inch<lb/>
for affecting flat slopes.</p>
<p>(j) Natural fluctuations of water level, seasonal, summer,<lb/>
weekly or daily.</p>
<p>(k) Quantity and distribution of natural enemies of mos-<lb/>
quito larvae.</p>
<p>(l) Other important factors.</p>
<p>(3) Under normal conditions in nature many aquatic<lb/>
insects have aquatic enemies that prey on them to the extent of<lb/>
seriously decreasing their numbers. The mosquito, in its early<lb/>
stage of development is exclusively aquatic and is preyed upon<lb/>
by various insects and certain species of fish. Some species<lb/>
of fish not only destroy very few larvae, but they sometimes<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00924012"/>
(3)<lb/>
almost eliminate the mosquito destroying kind of fish. They<lb/>
also may limit the scope of action of those minnows which pre-<lb/>
fer mosquito larvae to other food and insects. When water is<lb/>
freshly impounded, the ratio of (fish that prefer Anopheles<lb/>
mosquito larvae to other food) to the mosquito larvae supply<lb/>
is often very low or below what will probably be true several<lb/>
years or more later. This has been observed to be the general<lb/>
rule in the upper portions of arms and indentations or long<lb/>
bights of lakes. Also if no precautionary measures (or un-<lb/>
satisfactory precautionary measures) are undertaken, there<lb/>
will generally be very much more protection afforded to the<lb/>
mosquito larvae during the early years of the life of the<lb/>
artificial pond than is commonly found in older ponds or lakes<lb/>
whether natural or man made, and consequently their natural<lb/>
enemies will have difficulty in reaching them.</p>
<p>(4) The particular places in newly formed lakes or ponds<lb/>
where Anopheles larvae frequently are to be found in relatively<lb/>
large numbers are:</p>
<p>(a) In floatage and collections of floatage. This<lb/>
is often composed of leaves, pine needles, small sticks,<lb/>
branches of trees, logs, pieces of bark, etc., and some of it<lb/>
is sometimes covered with green algae. Anopheles larvae are<lb/>
also often found in quantity among collections of aquatic or<lb/>
semi-aquatic plants, especially so if certain algae are present.</p>
<p>(b) Larvae are often found clinging to isolated<lb/>
pieces of bark or other drift when against or close to abrupt<lb/>
banks in deep water when wind and wave action are or have been<lb/>
absent or light.</p>
<p>(c) At the upper ends (say the upper third) of in-<lb/>
lets of the pond or lake and their branches, more so when rela-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00924013"/>
(4)<lb/>
tively wind shaded or in the absence of sufficiently severe wave<lb/>
action.</p>
<p>(d) Frequently in shallow waters not affected by<lb/>
marked fluctuation of water or wave <add>strong</add> action, in the absence of<lb/>
small mosquito destorying fish - often more so when certain<lb/>
algae are present.</p>
<p>(5) When the production of <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi> is<lb/>
prolific over a considerable sized breeding area, such as in<lb/>
an impounded water project containing such floatage, overgrown<lb/>
banks with vegetation, hanging over into the water, collections<lb/>
of aquatic plants, an absence of mosquito destroying minnows, etc.<lb/>
then the adult mosquitoes of this kind emerging therefrom may be<lb/>
found at residences and stables a mile distant from such a breed-<lb/>
ing area. Under conditions similar to that outlined they have<lb/>
not yet been found to travel to building 1 <unclear>1/4</unclear> or 1 <unclear>1/2</unclear> miles or more<lb/>
distant from their source. In the investigation of this subject<lb/>
it was generally found that where the production of adult<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi> was less prolific the adults were ab-<lb/>
sent from houses about half a mile <add>or more</add> distant from the production<lb/>
area.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00924014"/>
<p>(5)</p>
<p>PROPOSED REGULATIONS</p>
<p>_________________</p>
<p>In order that the impound ing of waters in the State of<lb/>
________________ shall not render unhealthful a strip of land<lb/>
about a mile wide adjacent to the maximum water elevation con-<lb/>
tour line of the lake, and be instrumental in increasing the<lb/>
prevalence of malaria in a considerable territory adjacent<lb/>
thereto - - - - -</p>
<p>The following Rules and Regulations relating to measures<lb/>
required to prevent the production of disease bearing mosquitoes<lb/>
and malaria transmission for the Protection of Public Health<lb/>
of the State of ______________________ etc. _______________.</p>
<p><hi>1a</hi> In the State of ______________, whenever any pond<lb/>
or lake or impounding of water or similar project is to be or<lb/>
has been, located, (under the provisions of this act?), in any<lb/>
county or part of the state where malaria exists or where there<lb/>
is reasonable cause in the opinion of the State Board of Health<lb/>
for fearing its introduction and dissemination, <add>all or</add> such parts of<lb/>
the following general measures as the State Board of Health<lb/>
deems essential are required to be accomplished and enforced<lb/>
by the licensee, whenever so directed by the State Board of<lb/>
Health for the protection of the public health.</p>
<p><hi>2a</hi> In the area to be occupied by the reservoir, its<lb/>
branches, bights and indentations, all brush, trees, undergrowth,<lb/>
logs, stumps and similar objects, which if not removed would<lb/>
float on the surface of the impounded water soon after the im-<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00924015"/>
(6)<lb/>
pounding of water, and all of the above that if lying on the<lb/>
ground or remaining in original or new position would probably<lb/>
cause collections of floatage to gather, and thus constitute<lb/>
conditions favorable to the protection of larvae of mosquitoes<lb/>
capable of conveying malaria, shall be removed, burned or other-<lb/>
wise satisfactorily disposed of, prior to the impounding of water.<lb/>
The above does not include grass, vegetation, brush, trees,<lb/>
stumps, <add>etc</add> <del>and things that will not float or</del> which will be perman-<lb/>
ently and completely submerged at time of low water and which<lb/>
<del>is</del><add>are</add> therefore not of sanitary importance. In cutting brush and<lb/>
trees, it is adviable to cut so that the remaining part will<lb/>
be submerged, at least so far as practical one foot below minimum<lb/>
water level to prevent future cost of removing floatage rafts,<lb/>
etc. that might otherwise collect and become anchored.</p>
<p><hi>3a</hi> The shore line of the reservoir, its branches, bights,<lb/>
and indentations shall be cleared of brush, trees, undergrowth,<lb/>
and the like, so as to prevent so far as practical, within<lb/>
reasonable economic limits, the collection of drift and float-<lb/>
age along shore. Also on gently sloping banks brush and saplings<lb/>
shall be removed back from the high water line for about 25<lb/>
feet horizontally, where its presence would prevent the strand-<lb/>
ing of heavy or accumulated floatage during storms and at time<lb/>
of high wind and water.</p>
<p>Pine trees shall be ringed where sufficiently close to<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00924016"/>
(7)<lb/>
the water to cause the falling pine tags to collect in the<lb/>
water of branches, bights, and indentations. Collections of<lb/>
pine tag floatage frequently become prolific sources of Anopheles<lb/>
larvae -- This deadening of pine trees shall be accomplished at<lb/>
the time the projected construction of the dam is started.</p>
<p><hi>4a</hi> Where advisable and practical the lake should be stock-<lb/>
ed with (Gambusia affinis) sufficiently for affective mosquito<lb/>
control, in accordance with definite written directions of the<lb/>
State Board of Health.</p>
<p>Newly created lakes and ponds shall not be artificially<lb/>
stocked with game fish without a written permit from the State<lb/>
Board of Health.</p>
<p><hi>5a</hi> During the first four years of the life of the new lake<lb/>
the State Board of Health shall make such inspections of the<lb/>
lake as are deemed essential, and any conditions found on the<lb/>
impounded water project that are or may be detrimental to public<lb/>
health or apt to cause an increase of malaria shall be modified<lb/>
by the licensee so as to become satisfactory to the State Board<lb/>
of Health. Prompt and proper care shall be taken to prevent<lb/>
the growth of cattails, bullrushes and other aquatic or semi-<lb/>
aquatic vegetation that offers protection for mosquito larvae<lb/>
from their fish enemies.</p>
<p>It is understood that during the mosquito breeding season<lb/>
that the licensee shall be held responsible for the prompt re-<lb/>
moval of all dangerous floatage and floating debris in<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00924017"/>
(8)<lb/>
bights, indentations and branch arms of the lake, which are<lb/>
found to harbour mosquito larvae, and the licensee is required<lb/>
to take all reasonable precautions to remove promptly, before<lb/>
they become extensive, aquatic growths that multiply rapidly<lb/>
and which are later expensive and difficult to remove.</p>
<p><hi>6a</hi> Where practical and not unreasonably expensive to<lb/>
accomplish, it is advisable to hold the water at higher level<lb/>
from (November to June first) than during the mosquito season -<lb/>
at least for the first three or four years. A greater portion<lb/>
of the floatage will then be left stranded on the shore during<lb/>
heavy winter storms and high flood and windy periods.</p>
<p>In case the water level is kept at a generally lower level<lb/>
(say 2 to 3 feet) from June first to about October thirtieth,<lb/>
it will cause the water edge to be against a clean bank, mostly<lb/>
free of vegetation, and mosquito production will be markedly<lb/>
reduced if not eliminated. Also the amount of maintenance<lb/>
work necessary under such conditions to prevent mosquito pro-<lb/>
duction would probably be small or negligible.</p>
<p><hi>7a</hi> So far as practical all depressions that will be cover-<lb/>
ed by water at flood stages and retain it at lower river stages<lb/>
thus forming separate pools, shall be connected by ditch with<lb/>
the lake so as to enable fish to enter at all times. Such<lb/>
places are few in number but important in mosquito production.</p>
<p><hi>8a</hi> The licensee shall be required to use every reason-<lb/>
able precaution (in accordance with these regulations?) to<lb/>
prevent the introduction or dissemination of malaria or other<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f00924018"/>
(9)<lb/>
communicable disease into the project areas and the territory<lb/>
contiguous thereto and to carry out all written instructions<lb/>
pertaining thereto from the State Board of Health.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
