<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00924001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Control of Malaria by Control of the Human Host, by [Henry Rose Carter], [1921]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00924001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Celli, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Koch, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Bass, C.C.</name>
<name type="person">Watson, Malcolm</name>
<name type="place">Lonoke (Ark.)</name>
<name type="place">Italy</name>
<name type="place">Algeria</name>
<name type="place">Greece</name>
<name type="place">East Africa</name>
<name type="place">Formosa</name>
<name type="place">Stephansort (New Guinea)</name>
<name type="place">Brione</name>
<name type="place">Bolivar County (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Sunflower County (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Mitchell County (Ga.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-00-00">[1921]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00924001</idno>
<title>Report: Control of Malaria by Control of the Human Host, by [Henry Rose Carter],[1921]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] details various methods of controlling malaria. He discusses segregation, screening, mosquito bars, and the use of quinine. [Carter] favors mosquito control because it does not require modification of human behavior.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-00-00">
<head>Report: Control of Malaria by Control of the Human Host, by [Henry Rose Carter], [1921]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00924001"/>
<p>Control of Malaria<lb/>
by<lb/>
Control of the Human Host.</p>
<p>As we agreed yesterday etc. if we can keep all infective men from<lb/>
access to Anopheles the life-cycle of the malaria organism will be broken:<lb/>
the organism will die and malaria disappear. <del>and</del> In proportion as we do<lb/>
this, malaria will diminish--i. e. be controlled.</p>
<p>1/ One method is to move the men infective to Anopheles away from<lb/>
the mosquitoes we wish to keep free from infection or what--from the stand-<lb/>
point of Relativity--is the same thing, select the mosquitoes we would<lb/>
keep free from infection at a distance from our infected men.</p>
<p>This is the &ldquo;Segregation&rdquo; on which so much importance is placed by<lb/>
the British--and possibly too little by the rest of us<unclear>:</unclear></p>
<p>House the men you would protect from mosquitoes so far from the<lb/>
residences of infected men that A. feeding on the latter will not visit<lb/>
the former. Simple, isn't it? Very rarely practicable in its entirety.</p>
<p>In its purpose it is comparable with screening; protecting the one<lb/>
a class; the other a family--neither the whole community. Still, it is<lb/>
well to protect individual families and classes--white Europeans the latter<lb/>
are--when we can do no better. In neither case is this done to the <hi>de-<lb/>
triment</hi> of the remainder of the co<del>untry</del><add>mmunity</add>. The principle then is a good one<lb/>
and should be observed as much as is conveniently practicable.</p>
<p>2/ Screens and mosquito bars which prevent access of infected Ano-<lb/>
pheles to uninfected men, also prevent access of uninfected Anopheles to<lb/>
infected men and <add>so</add> act to prevent malaria by both methods. I think this <add>latter</add> ef-<lb/>
fect of screening has been little noted and yet it is a very real one.<lb/>
It was thus used intentionally to prevent the infection of mosquitoes at<lb/>
Lonoke, Arkansas in 1918. The result aimed at--the protection of an avia-<lb/>
tion camp from Anopheles infected in the village--was extremely good; but<lb/>
other methods being also used, one cannot evaluate this factor in its pro-<lb/>
duction.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00924002"/>
<p>production.</p>
<p>2.</p>
<p>Segregation and screening, however, are of very minor importance in<lb/>
the control of the human host. The methods <hi>depended</hi> on involve the use of<lb/>
quinine.</p>
<p>There are 2 methods based on the use of quinine--both called the<lb/>
&ldquo;Method of Quinine Prophylaxis&rdquo; yet absolutely distinct in method and dis-<lb/>
tinct in immediate purpose. The one aims to so administer quinine to <hi>all</hi><lb/>
men <hi>infected with malaria</hi> that they will be freed from this infection and<lb/>
thus be <hi>unable to infect Anopheles</hi>. The other--to so administer quinine to<lb/>
<hi>uninfected</hi> men that they will not develope malaria <hi>even when bitten by in-<lb/>
fected Anopheles</hi>. The one is primarily to prevent the infection of Ano-<lb/>
pheles and thus of men: the other pays no attention to Anopheles, but aims<lb/>
to immunize men against infection from them.</p>
<p>These methods then are not only different, but contrasting. One is,<lb/>
and should be called, &ldquo;Quinine Sterilization of Carriers:&rdquo; the other &ldquo;Qui-<lb/>
nine Immunization.&rdquo; Both are, indeed, Quinine Prophylaxis against Malaria,<lb/>
but this term is definitive of <hi>purpose</hi> rather than of <hi>method</hi> and should be<lb/>
discarded. There have been, and are, much confusion and many statements<lb/>
at cross purpose in the Journals on account of not differentiating these<lb/>
methods--calling them indiscriminately "uinine Prophylaxis.</p>
<p>3/ Method. Let us take up the method by quinine immunization<lb/>
first. This is the Method of Celli: the Italian Method. Its object is<lb/>
explained by its designation. Quinine is given daily--as Celli gave it--<lb/>
or intermittently--as Koch and the Germans advise--to the <hi>uninfected</hi> men<lb/>
of a community during the whole duration of the malaria season.</p>
<p>This method was used in Italy--by Celli--from 1902 to --at any rate--<lb/>
1914. I presume it is still used: 40 gm., about 6 1/4 gr., per day was his<lb/>
basic adult dose: 50 gm. in bad malarial districts. It was used on a large<lb/>
scale and for a considerable time and the results <add>-in Italy</add> were distinctly good-.<lb/>
Good results, but less good, were claimed by the Sergeants in Algeria<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00924003"/>
Algeria<lb/>
3.<lb/>
and in Greece by others. This method has been generally favored by the<lb/>
Mediterranean people--less so by the French than the others.</p>
<p>Discuss-. <hi>Increasing</hi> Control<unclear>:</unclear> no <unclear>better</unclear> in 1913<lb/>
{<unclear>1873</unclear>-1902 - 14,000+<lb/>
{1903-1911 5,440<lb/>
{<hi>1906-" 3,859</hi></p>
<p>The Germans in East Africa, for the same purpose, gave 1 gm. of<lb/>
quinine on two successive days with an interval of from 6 to 8 days--<lb/>
varying with the prevalence of malaria. There were various modifications<lb/>
of dosage and of interval. Both the Germans and the Japanese, the latter<lb/>
in Formosa, reported good, indeed excellent, results from this intermittent<lb/>
dosage. This will be noticed later.</p>
<p>This method, quinine immunization, has never been favored, nor much<lb/>
used by the British, who certainly have a very large field available for<lb/>
both the exercise and the investigation of malaria control. It, quinine<lb/>
immunization, is generally considered to have been entirely discredited by<lb/>
its failure with the British troops in the Macedonian Campaign. This method<lb/>
is by no means a favorite of my own, and yet I am not so sure that it fail-<lb/>
ed as completely as asserted. Wenyon, who pronounces against it, gives<lb/>
the general morbidity from malaria where quinine was used as somewhat un-<lb/>
der 50% and that of the only unit to which he states no quinine was given<lb/>
as 100% in 3 weeks' service. It may, then, have had more effect than it<lb/>
was credited with. Castellani too, compares two units under, he thinks,<lb/>
the same conditions, except that one took quinine and the other did not.<lb/>
The first shewed a malaria rate of 45%, the other--in the same period--<lb/>
one of 100%. Wenyon believes, as do Watson: Ian McDonald and Ozzard, that<lb/>
it is far more efficacious in preventing malarial <hi>attacks</hi> than malarial<lb/>
<hi>infections</hi>. This, too, is my own observation.</p>
<p><hi>Balkans and Quinine</hi>.</p>
<p>4/ -- and last<unclear>.</unclear> Method: Quinine Sterilization of Carriers. This<lb/>
is the so-called &ldquo;Method of Koch&rdquo;--the &ldquo;Method of Stephansort.&rdquo; It was<lb/>
first used by <unclear>Cosio</unclear> at <unclear>Grosseto</unclear> in Northern Italy, at the instance of Koch,<lb/>
in 1900: then by Koch himself at Stephansort, in German New Guinea<del>--</del> the last<lb/>
part of the same year and in 1901 by Frosch (assisted by Dr. Rivas, now of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00924004"/>
now of<lb/>
4<lb/>
Philadelphia) at Brione--a small island in the Adriatic. Combined with<lb/>
quinine immunization, by intermittent dosage, it was the method generally<lb/>
used in German East Africa up to the time it ceased to be G. E. A.</p>
<p>Excellent results were reported at Stephansort and at Brione and,<lb/>
except by Dempwolf, universally from German East Africa. Orenstein, how-<lb/>
ever, who went to German East Africa after leaving the Canal Zone in 1914,<lb/>
considered the result at Dar-es-Salaam--his station--a failure. The same<lb/>
is asserted by Pearson, in charge there since the war, who has changed to<lb/>
Control of Anopheles Production, I will add Pearson is an entomologist.<lb/>
(Orenstein had a basis of comparison--a too perfect model--and Pearson<lb/>
came after an interval during which the work had been stopped)</p>
<p>The work <hi>exclusively</hi> by the sterilization of the human host, prior<lb/>
to 1916, was on a very small scale. Stephansort boasted of only 437 peo-<lb/>
ple <add>-157<unclear>Carnius</unclear></add> and Brione 131 <add>people</add>. That in German East Africa was combined with quinine<lb/>
immunization. The only work on a comparatively large scale by this meth-<lb/>
od is that done by Bass for the I. H. B. in this country in 1916-1920;</p>
<p>An area 10 miles square--100 sq. miles--was taken in a rural com-<lb/>
munity in Bolivar County, Miss. and worked in 1916 and 1917. Good results<lb/>
were reported by Bass--my recollection is over 70% reduction of malaria. I<lb/>
do not think that he considered this work entirely satisfactory--part of it<lb/>
being experimental. In 1918 then, basing his work on the experience ac-<lb/>
quired the past two years--a similar area of 10 miles square--containing<lb/>
10,000 souls--was taken in Sunflower County, Miss. For this year Bass re-<lb/>
ported a reduction of 89%--at a cost of $1.16 per head, exclusive of super-<lb/>
vision. This work was continued during 1919 and (probably imperfectly) in<lb/>
1920. The Report of the Rockefeller Foundation gives the end reduction for<lb/>
the 3 years at 55%.</p>
<p>I told you that the training of <unclear>streams:</unclear> the removal of water, was essentially an engineering problem</p>
<p>This is <unclear>a as</unclear> clearly a medical problem--the laboratory to determine which<lb/>
are the carriers: the therapist to determine the method of freeing them<lb/>
from infection and, again, the laboratory to determine when they are freed<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00924005"/>
freed<lb/>
5.<lb/>
from infection.</p>
<p>It may be noted here that this method has been favored <hi>only</hi> by phy-<lb/>
sicians, and especially such as are bench-men: Koch and his followers:<lb/>
Celli: Bass: James. On the contrary that it is damned by entomologists.<lb/>
(&ldquo;There is nothing like leather!&rdquo; says the Cobler.)</p>
<p><add>Insert <unclear>Alo</unclear> &amp; A(2)</add></p>
<p>Koch determined his carriers by a blood examination of all persons<lb/>
in the Co<del>unty</del><add>mmunity</add>--it was a small one. To all found positive--and only to<lb/>
these--quinine was administered:--1 gm. daily until parasites disappeared<lb/>
and thereafter the same dose was continued on two consecutive days with<lb/>
an interval of 7-8 days for 2 to 2 1/2 months. The same method was used<lb/>
in East Africa with some modifications, the interval being shortened to 6<lb/>
or even 5 days in badly malarious districts and quinine being continued in<lb/>
this way indefinitely <add>to all, whether they had been <unclear>Carriers</unclear> or not</add><unclear>:</unclear> <add>a combination of Koch's method <hi>with Q. immunization</hi></add></p>
<p>Very obviously, when this sterilization of carriers <add>at <unclear>Stephansort-say-</unclear></add> took place (even<lb/>
supposing that all carriers were sterilized) infected Anopheles were in<lb/>
flight and quinine sufficient to prevent re-infection--i. e. in immunizing<lb/>
doses--had to be continued until the death or freedom from infection of<lb/>
such Anopheles. This, I think, is the reason (although not so stated in<lb/>
Koch's report) for the long continuance of quinine after the disappearance<lb/>
of the parasites--and in smaller doses. He evidently regarded not finding<lb/>
parasites as equivalent to freedom from infection--an opinion with which<lb/>
few would now agree.</p>
<p>If that <hi>was</hi> the reason <unclear>for the cont'nce</unclear> of<lb/>
<unclear>the Aim.</unclear> Why he gave no Q. to those whose blood he did not find <unclear>&amp;</unclear>?<lb/>
Immune to <unclear>Inf. biolog. otherwise.</unclear>.</p>
<p>Bass, in 1918, administered 10 gr. of quinine per day--in a single<lb/>
dose at bed-time--for two months. He gave this to all (1) whose blood was<lb/>
found to be positive and (2) who gave a history of malaria the previous<lb/>
siason. <del>Obviously</del><add>I presume</add>, the long continuance of this treatment was sufficient<lb/>
to protect--immunize--against the infected Anopheles in flight, when the<lb/>
sterilization of carriers was completed. It continued until they were dead<lb/>
or free from infection. I do not think, however, that it was continued<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00924006"/>
continued<lb/>
6.<lb/>
with that intention--simply to <hi>cure</hi> the infection. Bass knew well enough<lb/>
that mere failure to find parasites (<del>on a single examination</del> did not neces-<lb/>
sarily negative infection--and relapse. Hence his long continued dosage</p>
<p>Very obviously, it would be quite an advantage, in any case, to avoid<lb/>
this chance of reinfection--i. e. sterilize our carriers when infected Ano-<lb/>
pheles were not in flight. This, generally speaking, is impracticable in<lb/>
the Tropics--where Koch tried this method. On my return from Panama--where<lb/>
the same conditions held--I thought that we might avoid this trouble in<lb/>
the U. S. and have better results if our quinine sterilization could be<lb/>
done during the season when Anopheles, at any rate infected Anopheles,<lb/>
were not in flight--i. e. in the early spring--Jan. to March.</p>
<p>The question at once arose--did the parasite hibernate in the mos-<lb/>
quito--which, as of course you know, does hibernate. If so, freeing our<lb/>
men of infection would do little good as they would be later reinfected<lb/>
by these hibernated parasites. There was no data on the subject for the<lb/>
U. S. Such as we had--Maritano's findings in the Maremna--implied that<lb/>
the parasites did so hibernate.</p>
<p>An examination was made by Mitzmain (Mayne) of a large number of<lb/>
<hi>hibernated</hi> Anopheles imagoes, at Scott, Miss. in 1914 and later at Talla-<lb/>
dega Springs, Ala. and at Monroe, La.--1,211 at Scott. I do not recall<lb/>
the number at the other two places. None of these imagos, taken up to lat-<lb/>
ter April or early May were infected with plasmodia. These results were<lb/>
corrobotated--incidentally--by the observations of King on mosquitoes from<lb/>
Mound. La.</p>
<p>From this it is an allowable deduction that in the U. S., except<lb/>
maybe in the extreme South, the plasmodium does not hibernate in its in-<lb/>
sect host. Man is clearly--in this section--the only winter carrier of<lb/>
malaria.</p>
<p>It seems advisable then to take advantage of this finding and begin<lb/>
our Quinine sterilization in --say--March or April.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f00924007"/>
<p>April.</p>
<p>7.</p>
<p>Discussion and Comparison of Methods.</p>
<p>1/ Under both of the Principal Methods of Malaria Control some de-<lb/>
tail methods are individualistic and some are community measures--e. g.<lb/>
the use of screening and of hand-catching in Control of the Insect Host<lb/>
are primarily individualistic measures and as such comparable with segre-<lb/>
gation: screening and quinine immunization--also individualistic--in the<lb/>
Control of the Human Host.</p>
<p>On the other hand--Control of Anopheles Production and Steriliza-<lb/>
tion of Carriers are both distinctively community measures and to be ef-<lb/>
fective, must be carried out on a community scale.</p>
<p>Advantages of Community measures over Individualistic.</p>
<p><hi>Resort to latter when 1st.</hi> fail. <unclear>-Canipare</unclear></p>
<p>Of the general methods I have given you, which is the best? It de-<lb/>
pends on the conditions--local and temporal--at this place, at this time.<lb/>
You do not ask what is the best stimulant or the best analgesic? It de-<lb/>
pends on the conditions for its us. We have considered the general ad-<lb/>
vantages of community measures over individualones and, as a further guide,<lb/>
I would say <hi>that method is the best which gives sufficient malaria control<lb/>
at the least cost</hi> or <hi>which gives greatest</hi> (<hi>and sufficient</hi>) <hi>control at the<lb/>
same cost</hi>. This is &ldquo;the Law and the Prophets!&rdquo; It is a question of ecomon-<lb/>
ics: each problem to be decided on its own merits-<hi>there</hi> and <hi>then</hi> existing.</p>
<p>Where economically practicable, however, the Control of Anopheles<lb/>
Production is, to my mind, clearly the Method of election, and yet I am a<lb/>
physician with, at least an appreciation of laboratory values, and not an<lb/>
Entomologist. But I have seen both tried.</p>
<p>My reasons:</p>
<p>1/ Work done once for all. Afterward the</p>
<p>2/ Upkeep is usually comparatively small and decreasing from year<lb/>
to year.</p>
<p>3/ Experience has shewn that this kind of work has always been<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00924008"/>
been<lb/>
8.<lb/>
kept up--i. e. is permanent.</p>
<p>4/ Work is with material, <add>water: clay: sand: stone</add> not people<add><unclear></unclear></add>--and every Health Officer etc.<lb/>
will tell you that no material etc. is so refractory as people can be.</p>
<p>5/ Both installation and upkeep are directly carried out by the<lb/>
H. O.--or Malaria Engineer--and in no wise dependent on the cooperation of<lb/>
the individuals--of all the individuals--in the community.</p>
<p>6/ The <hi>locality</hi> stays free from malaria independent of the movement<lb/>
of population.</p>
<p>7/ Getting rid of Anopheles--usually of all mosquitoes--as a pest.</p>
<p>On this Method--Control of Anopheles Production--the great bulk--<lb/>
practically all of our Malaria work now going on in the U. S. is based.</p>
<p>The objections to this method--Control of Anopheles Production--<lb/>
are (1) the cost and (2) the time necessary to get results. The first has<lb/>
always to be considered: The last sometimes makes it advisable to choose--<lb/>
temporarily at least--a quicker, if less permanent method. I will give you<lb/>
an instance later.</p>
<p>The results of Quinine Sterilization of Carriers are, I fear, little<lb/>
apt to be permanent in the U. S. Their permanence depends on the permanence<lb/>
of a population in a locality and our people move about too much. At Ste-<lb/>
phansort and Brione this was not so.</p>
<p>Not only is there a more or less constant passing of people from the<lb/>
territory in which Anopheles are infected into our territory, where they<lb/>
are not infected--our people returning from visits and strangers visiting<lb/>
us--but in the rural districts of the South--for which this method has been<lb/>
especially recommended--there is at the end of the cotton year<del>--</del>a whole-<lb/>
sale movement of tenant-farmers. This, I suspect was the cause of the re-<lb/>
duction of the result in Sunflower Co. from 89% in /18 to 55% in 1920, al-<lb/>
though work was continued. The results in places handled by Control of<lb/>
Anopheles Production have improved year by year. Roanoke Rapids, for in-<lb/>
stance, begun in 1914, gave a reduction of 99% in 1916--the last data I have.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f00924009"/>
<p>I have.</p>
<p>9.</p>
<p>The fundamental objection to both of the Quinine Methods of Con-<lb/>
trol is their non-permanence. Quinine Immunization, from its very nature,<lb/>
must go on from year to <unclear>year--in</unclear> perpetuity, so to speak. If its total<lb/>
annual cost--in trouble: inconvenience and money is greater than <add>the upkeep and</add> the in-<lb/>
terest on <del>and upkeep</del><add>the <unclear>first</unclear> cost</add> of<del>,</del> Control of Anopheles production and an equal Con-<lb/>
trol of Malaria is given, it is permanently economically good. If its to-<lb/>
tal cost be greater than this interest and up-keep it is permanently econo-<lb/>
mically bad. The chances for the permanence of the results of Sterilization<lb/>
of Carriers is better than the above and in places <add><unclear>this</unclear></add> will, I believe, <del>give</del> be<lb/>
permanent. <del>results.</del> But in the parts of the U. S. where Malaria Control is<lb/>
most needed--they are not good.</p>
<p>Yet there are conditions where Quinine Control is to be chosen.</p>
<p>Mitchell County, Ga.</p>
<p>Good that year, and so good, that we were practically compelled to con-<lb/>
tinue them the next 2 years<del>--</del>while the County was taking the permanent meas-<lb/>
ures--Screening Houses and Draining--of Mosquito Control</p>
<p>Continued good results--many white people--working their own lands.</p>
<p>There are other cases too, in which Quinine Control by lessening the<lb/>
malaria in a community, enabled it to do more permanent work of <add>Anopheles</add> Control--<lb/>
which they had never attempted until this incubus was lifted: Sunflower, Co.<lb/>
etc. Unless it thus leads to Mosquito Control it will, I fear, be of no<lb/>
great permanent benefit to the more malarious districts in the U. S.</p>
<p>Results--Read from Reprint.</p>
<p>Combination of Methods--James.</p>
<p>My own idea--<hi>Wilson</hi> and <hi>Ruleville</hi>.</p>
<p><unclear>Malcolm</unclear> Watson--the most ardent, and probably the ablest British ad-<lb/>
vocate of Control of Anopheles Production--uses Quinine to enable men to live<lb/>
in the country until they can control Anopheles Production.</p>
<p>Measure of the Reduction of <unclear>Mal,</unclear></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
