<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00929015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Bert W. Caldwell, April 24, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00929015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-04-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Caldwell, Bert W.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-04-24">April 24, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00929015</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Bert W. Caldwell, April 24, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] believes that human &ldquo;carriers&rdquo; of yellow fever, without symptoms, do not exist.  He feels that Caldwell's case must involve either a human with undiagnosed yellow fever or an erroneous diagnosis of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-04-24">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Bert W. Caldwell, April 24, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00929015"/>
<opener>
Connor<lb/>
I. H. B.<lb/>
Caldwell<lb/>
Copy sent Connor<lb/>
Please return to<lb/>
H. R. Carter<lb/>
2121 California street N. W<lb/>
Washington D. C.<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1922-04-24">April 24, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Caldwell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I will answer your questions categorically.</p>
<p>First I take your definition of carriers: &ldquo;One infective to<lb/>
Stegomyia mosquitoes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The existence of carriers without symptoms--or continuing as<lb/>
such after the attack of yellow fever has recovered--I count exceed-<lb/>
ingly improbable. There is no evidence therefor whatever; except analogy</p>
<p>If, however, one simply means a man with an infection so slight<lb/>
or so ill defined as to make diagnosis very difficult--or indeed in<lb/>
individual cases impossible--such carriers are of common occurrence.<lb/>
I have never seen an epidemic in which there were not cases recognized<lb/>
as such by the conditions under which they occurred, which had other-<lb/>
wise been impossible of diagnosis. I would not consider these carriers,<lb/>
however, in the ordinary <del><unclear>impl</unclear></del><add>sign</add>ication of the <unclear>word</unclear>--merely light cases<lb/>
of yellow fever.</p>
<p>I know of no latent infection of yellow fever incapable of in-<lb/>
fecting mosquitoes--or indeed of any latent infection of yellow fever<lb/>
at all: Nor is there any evidence for it.</p>
<p>1/ To your 1st. question: In my opinion there is substantial<lb/>
reason for believing that yellow fever carriers do not exist and none<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00929016"/>
none<lb/>
2.<lb/>
whatever for believing that they do.</p>
<p>2/ My experience has not at any time suggested that carriers<lb/>
have been a factor in the epidemiology of yellow <unclear>fever</unclear>, on the contrary<lb/>
<del>the</del><add>a</add> large number of people from places infected with yellow fever have been<lb/>
introduced <unclear>into</unclear> the infectable part of the U. S. without any known in-<lb/>
fection therefrom. See the enclosed article.</p>
<p>3/ I have known of patients having had yellow fever a second time--<lb/>
not oftener, however, than the same has been true of smallpox--the second<lb/>
attack coming after an interval of some years and during an epidemic was<lb/>
quite certainly a new infection.</p>
<p>I took up this matter (&ldquo;The Immunity of Yellow Fever&rdquo;) some years ago.<lb/>
I am sending you a Spanish translation of the paper I wrote at that time,<lb/>
published in the Liverpool Journal, Annals of Tropical Medicine and Para-<lb/>
sitology. I have not read it over--I mean the translation--but if there<lb/>
are errors in it I judge there are not enough of them to vitiate the ar-<lb/>
gument. Of necessity, since the proposition is a negative one: that<lb/>
secondary attacks do <hi>not</hi> occur (or no more <add>often</add> than with other immunizing<lb/>
infections) the argument therefor must necessarily be negative and, as<lb/>
negative evidence is convincing in proportion to its mass, it may be there<lb/>
is not a sufficient mass of it presented. The fact presented is that<lb/>
<del>with</del> over 30,000--probably 50,000 or 60,000-people &ldquo;immune to yellow fever<lb/>
by previous attack or ten years residence in an infected focus&rdquo; came from<lb/>
Havana into the infectable part of the U. S. (Tampa and Key West) without<lb/>
communicating any infection to the Stegomyiae of these last two places,<lb/>
while among 450 people not so immune, 13 cases of yellow fever developed<lb/>
at the Quarantine Station.</p>
<p>It would seem to me that this shows that a previous attack gives a<lb/>
fairly sufficient protection against subsequent ones.</p>
<p>For carriers, in addition to the above 30,000 to 60,000--who <del>might</del><add>should</add> also<lb/>
have had some carriers among them <add>if there be any such things</add>--sharply over 100,000 people who had been<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00929017"/>
been<lb/>
3.<lb/>
exposed to yellow fever entered the U. S. at Southern ports <add>during the summer season</add> without con-<lb/>
veying any infection to Stegomyiae.</p>
<p>The Commission of the Pasteur Institute--Marchoux and others--have<lb/>
<unclear>promulgated the idea that yellow fever practically never disappears from<lb/>
there are so many erroneous statements in the Report of<lb/>
from a focus one infected if the Stegomyiae continue in sufficient num-<lb/>
this Commission that one is surprised at seeing how absolutely it is ac-<lb/>
ber and active &ldquo;being kept up by recurrent attacks among the indigene&rdquo;<lb/>
cepted as authoritative in Latin America. They are wrong in their statement<lb/>
They believe that the immunity given by an attack of yellow fever is not<lb/>
that infected stegomyiae do not in nature feed in the day time. They are</unclear><lb/>
only not permanent, but <hi>ephemeral</hi> and that recurrent attacks are common and<lb/>
recur many times in the same man. They present no evidence therefor--simply<lb/>
make this assertion. It was to meet this--that I consider <unclear>mistaken view--</unclear><lb/>
that the article I send you was written. I think it <add>(<unclear>my view</unclear>)</add> is generally accepted<lb/>
by tropical sanitarians.</p>
<p>For the second part: I wrote in 1917 an article on the Spontaneous<lb/>
Elimination of Yellow Fever by Failure of the Human Host. I judge you<lb/>
have seen that.</p>
<p>Your own experience--certainly the experience of many of the physi-<lb/>
cians in Mexico--will show that yellow fever does not continue indefinitely<lb/>
in small or moderate sized places, even if no Stegomyia work is done. It<lb/>
does not become <unclear>latent--it</unclear> dies <unclear>out--as</unclear> completely as measles or whooping-<lb/>
cough does.</p>
<p>In effect there are so many erroneous statements in the Report of<lb/>
this Commission that one is surprised at seeing how absolutely it is ac-<lb/>
cepted as authoritative in Latin America. They are wrong in their statement<lb/>
that infected Stegomyiae do not in nature feed in the day time. They are<lb/>
wrong in the lower limit of temperature they set for Stegomyia feeding and<lb/>
flight. <add>Fernando</add> Lopez of Mexico City has shown that, as well as recent obser-<lb/>
vations in Peru. It is <del>quite probable</del><add>quite certain</add> that they are wrong in claiming con-<lb/>
veyance by the progeny of the infected mosquito, though I cannot say this<lb/>
is <hi>absolutely</hi> <unclear>proven against</unclear> them. The trouble was that they assumed a <hi>theory</hi><lb/>
theory<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00929018"/>
theory<lb/>
4.<lb/>
and almost <unclear><hi>compelled</hi></unclear> their observations to sustain it.</p>
<p>There are four conceivable explanations of the occurrence of your case<lb/>
of March 20th.</p>
<p>1/ That a mosquito may have retained its infection from the previous<lb/>
September. I count this extremely improbable--so much so that I would re-<lb/>
ject it altogether.</p>
<p>2/ That the infection was from a mosquito infected on account of be-<lb/>
ing the progeny of one infected in September. It is so highly improbable--<lb/>
though not maybe <unclear>impossible-</unclear> that this method of conveyance takes place<lb/>
that I feel also like throwing it into the discard.</p>
<p>3/ That other cases occurred on the plantation subsequent, and well<lb/>
subsequent, to September. <hi>No one</hi> can always recognize light cases of yel-<lb/>
low fever, especially in children, and <unclear>there</unclear> might have been several such,<lb/>
between September and March. This is not at all improbable.</p>
<p>4/ The case of March 20th. may not have been yellow fever. There<lb/>
are a number of the so-called <unclear>infectuous</unclear> jaundices caused by spirochetes,<lb/>
which it is very difficult to differentiate from yellow fever. I saw five<lb/>
such cases under conditions which excluded yellow fever and I confess had<lb/>
it been during an epidemic of that disease I would unquestionably have<lb/>
listed them with yellow fever. Weil's Disease (Leptospira ictero-haemmo-<lb/>
rhagica) is one of these, and the five I saw were this disease. Such<lb/>
diseases occur from time to time in various places not confined to the<lb/>
Tropics: Quebec: Dundee, Scotland: two of mine were at Mound City, Illinois<lb/>
in March; and it is no discredit to anyone to mistake such cases for yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>If your case was yellow fever, the presumption is you should e'er this<lb/>
have had other cases as the diagnosis was probably not made before he had a<lb/>
chance to feed a certain number of Stegomyiae and I would like much to hear<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00929019"/>
hear<lb/>
the further <unclear>outcome, of</unclear> the matter.</p>
<p>Give my best respects to Mrs. Caldwell and young Henry, whom I have<lb/>
never had the pleasure of seeing.</p>
<p>With best wishes to yourself,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly your friend,</salute>
<seg>
P. S. You can keep the Spanish translation as long as you want--say a month<lb/>
or two months, but I would be glad to have it again, as I have no reprints<lb/>
of it.<lb/>
Enclosures. <hi>2</hi><lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
