<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00925056">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to William H. Ballou, January 25, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Barber, M.A.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00925056</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-01-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Kudo, R.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-01-25">January 25, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00925056</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to William H. Ballou, January 25, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter requests a reference to an article, by Kudo, on a microorganism that kills mosquito larvae.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-01-25">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to William H. Ballou, January 25, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00925056"/>
<p>2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
<hi><unclear>Bacteria?</unclear></hi><lb/>
, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1922-01-25">January 25, 1922.</date>
/LC<lb/>
Dr. William H. Ballou,<lb/>
37 West 68th. Street, N. W.<lb/>
New York, N. Y.<lb/>
Dear Sir:</p>
<p>I have seen a page of the Sunday Edition of the Washington Times<lb/>
containing part of a story by Dr. Ballou of the discovery by a Jap-<lb/>
anese scientist--Dr. R. Koudo of the University of Illinois--of a<lb/>
microorganism--Thelamia--species?--which he found efficient in destroy-<lb/>
ing the larvae of mosquitoes--Culex pipiens and Anopheles punctipennis.</p>
<p>It is stated that Dr. Kudo's findings are published in the Jour-<lb/>
nal of Morphology. I have been unable to find them in such numbers as<lb/>
are on file in the libraries here, but all of them are not on file.</p>
<p>If you are the Dr. Ballou who wrote the above account, will you<lb/>
kindly advise me of the number and date of the above Journal contain-<lb/>
ing Dr. Kudo's article?</p>
<p>Very truly yours,</p>
<p>Address<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St, N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00925057"/>
<p>2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
, D. C.<lb/>
<date value ="1922-01-25">January 25, 1922.</date>
/LC<lb/>
Dr. R. Kudo,<lb/>
University of Illinois,<lb/>
Dear Sir:</p>
<p>I have seen a page of the Sunday Edition of the Washington Times<lb/>
containing part of a story by Dr. Ballou of the discovery by a Japan-<lb/>
ese scientist--Dr. R. Koudo of the University of Illinois--of a micro-<lb/>
organism-- Thelamia (species?), which he found efficient in destroy-<lb/>
ing the larvae of mosquitoes--Culex pipiens and Anopheles punctipennis.</p>
<p>It is stated that Dr. Kudo's findings are published in the Jour-<lb/>
nal of Morphology. I have been unable to find them in such numbers<lb/>
as are on file in the libraries here, but all of them are not on file.</p>
<p>Will you kindly advise me of the number and date of the above<lb/>
Journal containing the article to which Dr. Ballou alludes as I<lb/>
should like very much to read it?</p>
<p>Very truly yours,</p>
<p>Address<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00925058"/>
<p>OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
Brewton, ALA. <date value = "1922-01-26">Jan. 26, 1922.</date>
Dear Doctor Carter:</p>
<p>Your letter Jan. 23, e<add>n</add>closing that excellent account<lb/>
of Murderers in Paris obversed by the Mosquito Murderers, received this <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
morning. I think I have the explanation of <del><unclear></unclear></del> where those newspaper<lb/>
articles got their inspiration. Received a letter from Professor Kudo<lb/>
in which he makes no remark on the baterial article, but, in response to my<lb/>
request, sends reprints on some recent work on Microsporidia. I had the<lb/>
reference to the Microsporidia articles in Washington, but the numbers<lb/>
of the Jl. of Morphology containing them were out. I think that the<lb/>
newspapers got their information from the microsporidian, Thelohania magna<lb/>
article, and glorified this very modest protozoan into the mosquito <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
bacterium. I send you the whole evidence enclosed. Please return when<lb/>
convenient, since we have been interested in this same protozoan. Odd,<lb/>
but while I was trying to find out about the bacterium of Kudo we were<lb/>
taking notes on this same protozoan. We began to find it last Jan. near<lb/>
Camilla, and collected it from time to time all during the season. In-<lb/>
fected larvae would not pupate in the laboratory, so we tried to<lb/>
propagate the thing to see if it could be made of any value in diminishing<lb/>
breeding. It would not spread readily to other larvae. Besides, a small<lb/>
pond near Camilla was well seeded with this parasite, as well as one<lb/>
could hope to seed it artificially, yet this pond continued to be our<lb/>
best collecting place during the whole season. Being without fish it<lb/>
swarmed with Anopheles. We had <del>the</del> not at that time seen the article of<lb/>
Kudo, but sent some specimens to Hegner at Baltimore, who thought them<lb/>
Microsporidia. Mr. Komp found this or a very similar parasite this week<lb/>
on Culex territans. We had previously found it only on Anopheles, crucians<lb/>
and quads. I have written Prof. Kudo asking if he does not think the<lb/>
newspaper articles came from his Thelohania.</p>
<p>Mr. Hayne, Theodore, is with me now, arrived two days ago. We have<lb/>
a good field laboratory and have made a good start in the work. Mr. Komp<lb/>
and I have been here since about the first of the month. This is a very<lb/>
good region for studying the winter activities of mosquitoes, such a<lb/>
great variety of woods and water. The job this month, after getting<lb/>
laboratory established, has been to see what species are breeding in<lb/>
winter-a continuation of the work of last winter in Camilla. We have<lb/>
bred out here during the past three weeks about a thousand Anoph.<lb/>
Only one quad, some scores of punct. but the great mass are crucians,<lb/>
as was the case in Camilla last year. We shall repeat experiments of last<lb/>
year in which we demonstrated eggs laying, hatching of eggs, a d roughly<lb/>
the rate of development of larvae and pupae during winter conditions. We<lb/>
will study the hibernation of adults, of course, as we did last winter,<lb/>
and the prevalence of winter malaria for this region. One point, of course,<lb/>
is to try to get ev<del>e</del>idence on the question as to whether there is much<lb/>
malaria transmission before the quad season. Quads occurred in ponds in<lb/>
March last year, but breeding was not very marked <unclear>until</unclear> May.<lb/>
We infected many cages artificially, crucians mostly, and kept them at<lb/>
room temperature last spring. No sporozoites developed, or very few,<lb/>
until warm weather. The whole thing, as you see, of course, is to get<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00925059"/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
2.<lb/>
all possible information as to the seasonal incidence of malaria <del><unclear>transmission</unclear></del><lb/>
transmission, especially as regards the spring and early summer trans-<lb/>
mission. Could one postpone the attack on Anopheles until midsummer, in<lb/>
case funds were lacking for the whole season campaign, as they probably<lb/>
would be for a rural community<unclear>!</unclear> Also, is there any hope of a successful<lb/>
winter attack on Anopheles in this region, as has been often proposed for<lb/>
Anopheles in northern Europe? I doubt if there is much hope for a region<lb/>
like this, since there is so much winter breeding and hibernating (if there<lb/>
is any real hibernating) adults are so widely scattered.</p>
<p>We have some material, observations and experiments, on the domestic<unclear>,</unclear><lb/>
animal and malaria problem <del><unclear>for</unclear></del> as conditions are in the South. The gist<lb/>
of the <unclear>results</unclear> so far is that Anopheles here would about as soon bite<lb/>
man as an animal-they may prefer animals if very convenient to bite<lb/>
them, but they have lost little of their taste for human blood. We have<lb/>
done two series of comparing human and animal baits. Also, if animals<lb/>
must be housed in o<add>r</add>der to properly attract mosquitoes, they are not<lb/>
going to be very attractive in this region. I think I have the most of the<lb/>
literature on this subject, going back to the Italian observations of<lb/>
nearly 20 years ago. I presume you have seen the last Roubaud article-<lb/>
Bull. Soc. Path. Exot. XIV, 1921, 577. I am afraid we could not guage<lb/>
the amount of malaria in any region of this country by counting the<lb/>
quad's teeth!</p>
<p>Then, later in the summer, we may try the arsenic on a fairly large<lb/>
scale in some region like S.E. Missouri, where the most of the breeding<lb/>
is found in the large drainage ditches. We have also some unfinished<lb/>
work on mosquito dispersal, which may have to be done in the rice region,<lb/>
unless enough Anopheles can be found here.</p>
<p>We have been keeping several irons in the fire so as to fit the work<lb/>
into varying conditions of drouth, cold, and the like. I think Mayne<lb/>
will take up the punctipennis problem. I can think of no better way of<lb/>
getting at this than to get out into the field in some region where<lb/>
punct. is the only species and to follow observations on indigenous<lb/>
malaria over several seasons.</p>
<p>I have troubled you with a rather long letter, since I should much<lb/>
appreciate your counsel on any of our problems. Especially, do you think<lb/>
a careful study of the seasonal incidence of the different species of<lb/>
Anopheles and of malaria worth while? Winter activities is about all one<lb/>
can study now, anyway, unless one should move further south where condi-<lb/>
tions would not be typical for the South.</p>
<p>Respectfully yours,</p>
<p>M A Barber</p>
<p>My Univ. of <unclear>Kans.correspondent</unclear> could find no reference to<lb/>
bacterial disease of mosquito larvae in <unclear>J. Morph.</unclear> back to 1917.<lb/>
<unclear>nor could</unclear> I in Washington back 2 or 3 years.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
