<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00925013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to John A. Ferrell, January 9, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00925013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-01-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ferrell, John A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-01-09">January 9, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00925013</idno>
<title>Letter to Dear Doctor Ferrell</title>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to John A. Ferrell, January 9, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] comments extensively on a public health film on malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-01-09">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to John A. Ferrell, January 9, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00925013"/>
<opener>
/LC<lb/>
N. M. C.<lb/>
<hi>Ferrell</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1922-01-09">January 9, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. John A Ferrell,<lb/>
Director for the United States,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway,<lb/>
New York, N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Ferrell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am afraid you have sent your Scenario to the wrong man. Very<lb/>
little do I know of the methods for advertising of any kind--even mal-<lb/>
arial sanitation, and so little about moving pictures that I am doubt-<lb/>
ful of not a few of the meanings of the titles of your pictures.</p>
<p>However, since you have asked what I think, here is my judgment of<lb/>
it in some detail:</p>
<p><hi>Scene 1</hi>: If the dark stipple is meant--as I judge it is--to simply<lb/>
show the malarial regions, should not the great central plateau of Amer-<lb/>
ica, west of the Missouri, be shown white? And the same, though a<lb/>
smaller affair, for the Appalachians?</p>
<p><hi>Scene 3</hi>: <hi>title 6</hi>: Are there 1,000,000 deaths per annum from malaria<lb/>
in India?</p>
<p><hi>Title 7</hi>: Does not the malaria chill in fact show as often &ldquo;every<lb/>
day&rdquo; as &ldquo;every other?&rdquo; Also are not pains in the muscles--there are none<lb/>
in either bones or joints--more marked during the chill than in the hot<lb/>
stage of malaria? Of course you know that the fever--as shown by the <unclear>ther</unclear><lb/>
<del>former</del><add><unclear>mother com</unclear></add>--<unclear>goes</unclear> on with the chill.</p>
<p><hi>Title 9</hi>: I don't know whether you <del>want</del><add>count</add> spontaneous recovery <add>as</add> &ldquo;cured&rdquo;<lb/>
or not? but many cases, especially among negroes, do undergo spontaneous<lb/>
recovery: Among whites I think the majority become chronic.</p>
<p><hi>Scene 10:</hi> I don't think your farmer should pull out a watch. In<lb/>
the first place, he wouldn't be apt to have one and in the next &ldquo;sun-<lb/>
time&rdquo; is what he goes by. I also have plowed corn!</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00925014"/>
<p>2.</p>
<p>corn!</p>
<p><hi>Scene 11:</hi> I am glad you make the doctor young. He would be far<lb/>
more apt to make a blood examination than some of the old ones.</p>
<p><hi>Title 15</hi>: I think I would leave <add>this</add> out, as you have suggested. If<lb/>
you insist upon the extreme smallness of the plasmodium, the country-<lb/>
man will regard it as imaginary and of no importance.</p>
<p><hi>Title 21</hi>: Isn't the last <hi>e</hi> in &ldquo;Anopheles&rdquo; long? An-of-el-<hi>eez</hi>?</p>
<p><hi>Scene 16</hi>: Is exceedingly good, as is 15 and all about the doctor.</p>
<p><hi>Title 22</hi>: Shouldn't you insert after the word &ldquo;female&rdquo; &ldquo;bites and<lb/>
so carries&rdquo; etc. Otherwise our countryman will console himself with<lb/>
thinking that half of the mosquitoes that bite him are males any way and<lb/>
won't be as afraid of them as he should be.</p>
<p><hi>Title 23 to title 41</hi>: I don't know enough about making films to judge<lb/>
of this. In so far as it can be done it would--to me--be extremely in-<lb/>
teresting. I don't see how (Diagram 8) you can show the <unclear>ookinete</unclear> form-<lb/>
ing or entering the mid-gut wall, (Scene 19), the stomach with oocysts<lb/>
on the outside is easily shown, but not by section.</p>
<p>The sporozoites (<hi>Scene 20</hi>) can be shown.</p>
<p><hi>Title 28</hi>: Shouldn't &ldquo;about&rdquo; be inserted between &ldquo;After&rdquo; and &ldquo;twelve,&rdquo;<lb/>
for in cold weather the &ldquo;extrinsic incubation of malaria&rdquo; may take from 20<lb/>
to 28 days. The bursted <unclear>oo<del>a</del>cyst</unclear> scattering the sporozoites would be a<lb/>
good thing to show just after <hi>Scene 20</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Title 31</hi>: Here you make the mosquito infected from the sick man fly<lb/>
<hi>directly</hi> to the healthy man and, presumably, infect him. Yet you have<lb/>
just stated that &ldquo;it takes about twelve days&rdquo; from biting before the mos-<lb/>
quito becomes <hi>infective</hi>." What she <hi>really</hi> does after biting the sick<lb/>
man is to go out and lay her eggs and then come back when a sufficient time<lb/>
has elapsed for her to become infective and bite the well man. How to<lb/>
show this, save by title, I do not know.</p>
<p><hi>Title 36</hi>: Fortunately for our sick man, <hi>each new</hi> parasite does <hi>not</hi><lb/>
enter <hi>another</hi> blood cell. <add>Few would recover if this happened suffered far many cycles</add> A number of them fail to do this. Might in-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00925015"/>
3.<lb/>
in-<lb/>
sert &ldquo;tries to&rdquo; after &ldquo;parasite.&rdquo; I like your Tallquist test.</p>
<p>From <hi>Title 41</hi> to <hi>Title 47</hi> inclusive seems to be all right.</p>
<p><hi>title 53</hi>: I have no fault to find with the &ldquo;will&rdquo; in this, but<lb/>
Heiser: Christophers and some others won't stand for it. I think the<lb/>
most that is claimed for it, without controversy, a pretty strong &ldquo;may&rdquo;<lb/>
or &ldquo;generally will.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Good down to <hi>61</hi>: This is doubtless good too, but be sure to make<lb/>
your model door shut against battens all around, especially <hi>at the bot-<lb/>
tom</hi>--edge-fitting will not do. Would it be worth while to show a mos-<lb/>
quito riding into the house on a door when it opens inwards? I have seen<lb/>
it happen many times. <add><unclear>Once at Darlings house at Ancon/Refered #183 U.S.P.H. Report xx</unclear></add></p>
<p>I suppose you have the whole window opening screened: the screen-<lb/>
ing either tacked in or in a frame removable with difficulty, so that<lb/>
the servant girl cannot possibly open it. Good screening is <hi>safe</hi> in<lb/>
the hands of careful people, but both factors must be present.</p>
<p><hi>Scene 46</hi>: Why not give the sanitarian a dipper upon a cane han-<lb/>
dle 4 ft. long and make him really up to date? An enamel<add>ed</add> dipper, if you<lb/>
like it.</p>
<p><hi>Title 68</hi>: I object to the word &ldquo;stagnant&rdquo; if by this is meant what<lb/>
generally is--water which has acquired a scum and become offensive from<lb/>
standing. Anopheles never breed in this kind of water and one of the<lb/>
greatest bars to mosquito control has been the belief in the innocu-<lb/>
ousness of clear, potable water in freely running streams, but with<lb/>
pools and eddies in them <add>&amp; into which grass hangs.</add></p>
<p>If you change &ldquo;stagnant&rdquo; to &ldquo;standing&rdquo; or &ldquo;slightly moving&rdquo; water<lb/>
it will express the truth. And, of course, you know that some species<lb/>
of Anopheles--as the <hi>maculatus</hi>--breeds only in swift streams, and in<lb/>
the swift portions of such streams: &ldquo;like trout,&rdquo; Malcolm Watson says.</p>
<p>Mayne has <del>a</del><add>the</add> most perfect moving picture--evidently taken <del>in</del><add>from</add> na-<lb/>
ture--that I have ever seen--of the emergence of an Anopheles larva<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00925016"/>
4<lb/>
larva<lb/>
from the egg and of the imago from the pupa.</p>
<p><hi>Title 70</hi>: I think &ldquo;aquatic&rdquo; is nigher truth than &ldquo;larval.&rdquo;<lb/>
Oil destroys the eggs and pupae as well as the larvae. On the<lb/>
other hand, poisons that kill by ingestion--as Paris green--are ef-<lb/>
fective <hi>only</hi> against larvae.</p>
<p><hi>Title 71</hi>: Do not quite agree with the process here given, when<lb/>
the lighter coal oils are used, but it makes no difference.</p>
<p><hi>Title 73</hi>: Do you mean those that act by contact--cresols? Or<lb/>
do you mean to include those ingested--as Paris green and <unclear>para<del></del>form?</unclear><lb/>
Both would apply to <hi>Title 75</hi> also. <add>They can be used when oil is ineffective.</add></p>
<p><hi>Title 75</hi>: I would add here: &ldquo;where the minnows have access to<lb/>
the larvae.&rdquo; This is the truth and gets rid of the criticism of <add><unclear>Nigrego</unclear> &amp;</add><lb/>
the British entomologists.</p>
<p><hi>Title 83</hi>: If there is any way of <del>expressing</del><add>stressing</add> this--<hi>do so.</hi> Tile<lb/>
drainage is, to my mind, the key to drainage for malaria.</p>
<p>This is rather a long criticism from a man who confessed that he<lb/>
did not know much about the subject. Take this last proviso in in<lb/>
considering it.</p>
<p>In general I am inclined to think that the Scenario gives<lb/>
rather too much on the developement of the plasmodium in both the mos-<lb/>
quito and the man for a popular film. That practically is from<lb/>
Page 4 to Page 9 inclusive--six pages out of twenty. The essential<lb/>
seems to me to be rather that the plasmodium <hi>is</hi> conveyed from the<lb/>
sick man to the well by an Anopheles mosquito<del>--a question of an<lb/>
Anopheles mosquito</del> rather than the detailed mechanism of this con-<lb/>
veyance, but this is the only criticism I have to make, and I make<lb/>
this with some reserve. I honestly think that the opinion of <unclear>Smilist<lb/>
Maxif</unclear> and Coogle <add>&amp; Griffitts</add> would be far more valuable on this than mine. I am<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00925017"/>
5.<lb/>
am<lb/>
anything but an expert on publicity methods.</p>
<p>Of course, the idea of a scenario for malaria is an excellent<lb/>
one and this certainly shows all the facts in the case.</p>
<p>With kindest regards,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
