<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00931015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Michael E. Connor, May 22, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00931015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-05-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Connor, Michael E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lyster, Theodore C.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Pasteur, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Caribbean</name>
<name type="place">Lesser Antilles</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Rico</name>
<name type="place">French Antilles</name>
<name type="place">Coro (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-05-22">May 22, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00931015</idno>
<title>Letter to Dear Doctor Connor</title>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Michael E. Connor, May 22, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] critiques Connor's draft on yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-05-22">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Michael E. Connor, May 22, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00931015"/>
<opener>
Dictated at The Johns Hopkins Hospital, but address:<lb/>
2121 California <unclear>Washington</unclear>, D. C.<lb/>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
<date value="1922-05-22">May 22, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Connor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am going over your piece seriatum and criticise what strikes<lb/>
me: Remember, please, that to criticise is to <hi>judge</hi>--not to judge un-<lb/>
favorably.</p>
<p>(1/) Your division of the infectable area into &ldquo;endemic&rdquo; and &ldquo;epi-<lb/>
demic&rdquo; zones is in accordance with the nomenclature in Lyster's arti-<lb/>
cle, signed by Gorgas and myself (1920). As I revised it, naturally<lb/>
I have <unclear>&ldquo;no kick coming.&rdquo;</unclear> yet I cannot help thinking that the division<lb/>
of the infectable territory into <hi>3</hi>: &ldquo;epidemic&rdquo;: &ldquo;endemic&rdquo;: <del>and</del> &ldquo;perma-<lb/>
nently endemic&rdquo; were a better one--the divisions being based on ter-<lb/>
ritory alone.</p>
<p>1/ For places like New Orleans, infectable at the proper, <add><unclear>seven</unclear></add> but with<lb/>
the infection limited absolutely by the season: Stegomyia activity<lb/>
ceasing in cold weather.</p>
<p>2/ Places like--say--Colon and Tampico in which fever on intro-<lb/>
duction might last one: two or three years--<hi>Stegomyia active the whole<lb/>
year 'round</hi> and its duration dependent upon the amount of susceptible<lb/>
human material furnished.</p>
<p>3/ Permanently endemic--places like Habana and Rio, in which Ste-<lb/>
gomyia were active at all seasons and sufficient susceptible material<lb/>
steadily furnished to keep up the infection permanently. It is this<lb/>
division that I am going to adopt in the piece I am now writing--if I<lb/>
ever finish it! However, there is no special reason why you should<lb/>
change. What you mean is perfectly clear.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00931016"/>
<p>2/<lb/>
clear.</p>
<p>(2) I do not know that it has been generally accepted that babies<lb/>
play a greater part in the continuance of yellow fever than do immi-<lb/>
grants. I discussed this matter--briefly as one must in a short arti-<lb/>
cle--in my piece on the Elimination of Yellow Fever. You may be allud-<lb/>
ing, however, to the findings of that so-often-mistaken Pasteur Commis-<lb/>
sion: &ldquo;Fever is kept up in endemic centers&rdquo; (they mean permanently en-<lb/>
demic centers) &ldquo;by recurrent attacks among the indigenes.&rdquo; I suppose it<lb/>
is because they are Latins that this Commission is so blindly and abso-<lb/>
lutely followed in Latin America.</p>
<p>I have never attempted to evaluate numerically the <hi>comparative</hi> total<lb/>
effect of immigration and birth. Usually it is the large cities with--<lb/>
naturally--many births that have a large immigration <add>&amp; so the factors increase &amp; diminish together</add>. I am sure that im-<lb/>
migration is much the more important factor in a focus small in <hi>area</hi>--as<lb/>
are all cities: while in a large <hi>regional focus</hi>, such--say--as that of<lb/>
the south shore of the Caribbean and the Lesser Antilles, the children<lb/>
were the more important factor.</p>
<p>3/ Exception might be taken to your argument, or rather your state-<lb/>
ment, that there is no relation between the birth-rate and the number of<lb/>
yellow fever cases. If you had said &ldquo;yellow fever cases <hi>reported</hi>&rdquo; your<lb/>
statement had been correct. As you know, they are not reported among<lb/>
natives--certainly not among native children in places where yellow fever<lb/>
is permanently endemic, and yet I think you will agree that everyone liv-<lb/>
ing in such a focus for X years becomes immune to yellow fever: that he<lb/>
becomes immune only by attack. Obviously then, to your reported cases of<lb/>
yellow fever you must add for each year on the average a number approxi-<lb/>
mately equal to the annual number of births. I say &ldquo;approximately equal&rdquo;<lb/>
because, of course, a certain number of children die before they are im-<lb/>
munized, but all whol live X years have had yellow fever. This number of<lb/>
cases of yellow fever then <hi>has</hi> been occurring in households, the elder<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00931017"/>
elder<lb/>
3<lb/>
members of which are immune. The fact of their not being reported--none<lb/>
of them are--does not affect their infection of Stegomyia.</p>
<p>I will say here that during two years in Habana, during which the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board was supposed to see every case <hi>suspected</hi> of being yel-<lb/>
low fever (and <hi>did</hi> see every case reported as such, and many others) that<lb/>
only a single Cuban child was brought to our attention, and this one had<lb/>
measles. Yet there were 4,000 to 6,000 births per annum in Habana.</p>
<p>(4) I like your expression &ldquo;hacienda endemic center.&rdquo; Also I like<lb/>
your discussion of it. If, however, you consider a city as being <hi>not a<lb/>
unit</hi>, but a number of units in more or less close relation with each other<lb/>
and if you consider the regional foci, like--say--the south shore of the<lb/>
Caribbean and the Lesser Antilles, I think you can find rather close ana-<lb/>
logy in the laws governing continuance in all of them. We have never<lb/>
found all parts of a city--a permanently endemic focus--infected at the<lb/>
same time. It spreads from one house to another: from one barrio to another<lb/>
--not always to contiguous places, because people frequently do not de-<lb/>
velope a disease where it is contracted, or even close to that place.</p>
<p>(5) In some regions, even where the labor is not indentured, there is<lb/>
little travel (which is the essential) from place to place. In such cases<lb/>
elimination by failure of the human host is usually quite certain: Porto<lb/>
Rico is such an instance as, I think, were the French Antilles. Guiteras<lb/>
classes such places as with &ldquo;stagnating travel.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(6) You are right in saying there are not many true permanently en-<lb/>
demic hacienda infections reported. That of Yucatan and Campeche--the<lb/>
one I first used for illustration in 1914--is the best known. Possibly<lb/>
the same existed about Coro, Venezuela (sugar) and I certainly would not<lb/>
have trusted the sugar district around Trujillo to have cleared itself<lb/>
spontaneously--especially in conjunction on with the rice haciendas north of<lb/>
it.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00931018"/>
<p>north of it.<lb/>
4.</p>
<p>(7) Your discussion of the different Stegomyia indices is clear and<lb/>
good. I do not know that the index of containers is the most valuable.<lb/>
If it be to measure <hi>the carefulness of the work done by your inspectors</hi>,<lb/>
it is: If, however, it is for the purpose of measuring the number of<lb/>
Stegomyia breeding places to the population your house index is best.</p>
<p>(8) Page 9. Your point that during a Stegomyia campaign the in-<lb/>
dex of breeding is not the index of production (of imagos) is extremely<lb/>
well taken. For some time at least the first will depend upon the num-<lb/>
ber of Stegomyia in flight and their access to containers: the second<lb/>
upon the carefulness of your inspector. Where you use fish, however,<lb/>
the first part of this statement does not hold. You may have noticed<lb/>
that in Peru on the report we mentioned &ldquo;small larvae: large larvae:<lb/>
pupae.&rdquo; Obviously, the presence of small sized larvae means nothing in<lb/>
the way of production. It was on this subject that I had my big row<lb/>
with Professor Herms and other Army Surgeons about Anopheles. They in-<lb/>
sisted that I stop the <hi>breeding</hi>, whereas I only wanted to stop the <hi>pro-<lb/>
duction</hi>.</p>
<p>(9) Page 7. This distinction is particularly well taken. It means<lb/>
that a city epidemiologically is to be considered a number of units--<lb/>
not simply a single one. You must remember, however, that although all<lb/>
reported cases occur where strangers live yet if the <unclear>indigenes</unclear> are being<lb/>
immunized yellow fever <hi>must</hi> be occurring among them also, although un-<lb/>
reported.</p>
<p>I do not know that it is also true that there are more water con-<lb/>
tainers around hotels in proportion to the number of people than in pri-<lb/>
vate houses. I suspect, however, this is usually the case.</p>
<p>(10) Page 8. I think you intended to use the word &ldquo;lower&rdquo; where<lb/>
you have &ldquo;higher&rdquo; as the higher the index is the more Stegomyia breeding<lb/>
has occurred.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00931019"/>
<p>occurred.<lb/>
5.</p>
<p>(11) Pages 8 and 9 are very pertinent: very true and very good.</p>
<p>(12) Page 10. Have you ever used what Howlett calls &ldquo;trap breed-<lb/>
ing places?&rdquo; They were first used by Murphy and myself in Panama in 1904.<lb/>
It was when, the breeding places of election being destroyed, she was<lb/>
seeking others--usually more difficult to find: Put a couple of cala-<lb/>
bashes or a tinaja in a dark and shady place for her to lay in, which<lb/>
your inspector can turn over weekly.</p>
<p>(13) Stegomyia larvae will live quite a while under a film of pe-<lb/>
troleum--I mean 1-3 days. Pupae fortunately won't, but I count petro-<lb/>
leum as of <hi>very</hi> doubtful efficiency in a campaign against Stegomyia.</p>
<p>Finally, the paper is a good paper--a very good paper--and you have<lb/>
brought out a number of new points in it. Publish it by all means and<lb/>
send me a reprint.</p>
<p>It I were perfectly well I would write you a very much better, more<lb/>
logical--I hope not a longer!--criticism of it.</p>
<p>I still think, however, that the house index--having made proper<lb/>
allowance to determine the emergence of imagos in it--is most useful in<lb/>
determining <hi>the value of the work done</hi>--that is, how close we are coming<lb/>
to reducing Stegomyia below the limit at which the fever can be conveyed.<lb/>
This (as you very justly say) should be taken for the different sections<lb/>
of the town--the <add>critical</add> index <del>noted</del><add>in each section</add> varying inversely with the proportion of<lb/>
susceptible people in <del>each</del><add>such</add> section.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly your friend,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="6" id="f00931020"/>
<p>Memorandum.</p>
<p>1) <hi>Epidemic</hi>:--Stegomyia present and active part of the year only.<lb/>
Not active during the cold season--existing then (if at all) in the<lb/>
egg stage.</p>
<p>The duration of yellow fever limited by the season independently of<lb/>
the proportion of susceptible people--as Mobile: Memphis etc.</p>
<p>2) <hi>Endemic:</hi>--Stegomyia present and <hi>active</hi> the entire year.</p>
<p>The duration of yellow fever when introduced not limited by the<lb/>
season, but dependent on the proportion of susceptible people:--Colon:<lb/>
Tampico: Cartagena etc.</p>
<p>3) <hi>Permanently Endemic:</hi>--Stegomyia as with (2) and with a suffi-<lb/>
cient supply of susceptible people to continue yellow fever indefinitely:--<lb/>
Habana: Rio: Guayaquil etc.</p>
<p>The difference between (1) &amp; (2) depends on the biology<lb/>
of <unclear>stay</unclear>: between (2) &amp; (3) on the supply of susceptible<lb/>
<unclear>men</unclear>.</p>
<p><unclear>C</unclear></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
