<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00933020">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, June 26, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00933020</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-06-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hanson, Henry</term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Dept. of Piura (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Catacaos (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Paita (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-06-26">1922-06-26</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00933020</idno>
<title>Letter from <unclear></unclear></title>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, June 26, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses yellow fever cases in Peru.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-06-26">
<head>Letter to My dear Doctor Carter, June 26, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00933021"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN EL PERU<lb/>
----<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
----<lb/>
BOOK<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1922-06-26">June 26, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just received your letter of June 3,<lb/>
written after you got out of the Hospita, I am sorry that you are<lb/>
not much improved, however let us hope that the brace which Dr. Baer<lb/>
is fixing up for you will give you the relief expected.</p>
<p>Now in regard to the statistics which you ask for I judge<lb/>
the enclosed sheet will give you most of the things you want. It<lb/>
was <unclear>gooten</unclear> up by Burga to serve as a resume (statistical) of the<lb/>
campaign, and in as much as there were many asking for such data<lb/>
we had them printed in this form. Unfortunately some data was not<lb/>
included as it should have been and no reference was made to the<lb/>
campaign in Piura. He got this up as the work done under the auspices<lb/>
of the Rockefeller Foundation. The number of cases given are simply<lb/>
those of which there is a complete medical history, and does not<lb/>
represent the total seen and diagnoses as yellow fever by the differ-<lb/>
ent members of the Medical staff of the campaign. The total seen<lb/>
and diagnosed was 1063. Also you will note that under the heading<lb/>
of Pueblos infectadas, 53 of them we have not included those of<lb/>
the campaigns of the previous years. The work given for the Depart-<lb/>
ment of Piura simply refers to what we did this year as a fial check<lb/>
on the north. We went up there to check on the Stegomyia conditions<lb/>
in Catacaos and Paita, and also made a general fish distribution,<lb/>
both as propaganda and to hold down the breeding.</p>
<p>I<del>m</del> am very much surpirsed to hear that you had received no<lb/>
letters since the 21st of February. I shall look up my files and<lb/>
the copies of letters which I have sent you since that time. It is<lb/>
probable that I quit writing you during the month of March since at<lb/>
that time I did not expect to stay on as long as I have. At that<lb/>
time I had no intention of accepting the position of Director of<lb/>
Public Health, and it was not until after the 15th of March that I<lb/>
did so. However from some of the remarks which you have made commen-<lb/>
ting on my taking the position I gained the impression that you<lb/>
must have received letters of a later date than that of February 21.</p>
<p>We have closed all our yellow fever work. I am now only<lb/>
waiting for Guldstrand to present me the final statement of accounts.<lb/>
We closed the Lima Office on the 15th of this month. Most of our<lb/>
materials have been sold, and the only remaining thing is to write<lb/>
the report. This however is a big job and will take some time, and<lb/>
probably will have to be done after I leave Peru. I shall only en-<lb/>
deavor to get them a preliminary report, a sort of an official good-<lb/>
bye.</p>
<p>They say that they do not want me to leave, and that I am<lb/>
needed here etc., so to make my getaway a little easier I am sub-<lb/>
mitting a proposition to them to the effect that if they will pass<lb/>
the necessary legislation and procure the funds needed I will con-<lb/>
sider coming back for two or three years to organize the Health<lb/>
Department for them and to get them on a working basis. I am inclined<lb/>
to think that they will not do this.</p>
<p>Dunn writes me that the I.H.B. is planning an extensive mal-<lb/>
aria campaign in Italy, and that the I.H.B. is looking for a Medic<lb/>
to take charge of the medical end of this work. This sounds inter-</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00933022"/>
<p>Dr. H.R. Carter, #2.<date value="1922-06-26">June 26,1922</date></p>
<p>interesting to me, and I think I should like to be considered if<lb/>
there is nothing else in sight, however we can discuss this when I<lb/>
arrive in the U.S.A.</p>
<p>I shall leave here either at the end of July or a little<lb/>
before, probably a little before as I need to stop for a few days<lb/>
in Panama to gather up some articles which I have in storage, and<lb/>
some Liberty Bonds etc. In my last letter I think I told you<lb/>
that I expected to get one of the P.S.N.C. boats and go direct to<lb/>
New York, but at the present it appears that there will be no P.S.N.C<lb/>
boat in the month of <unclear>July</unclear> after the 21st, and I may arrange to go to<lb/>
Panama on it.</p>
<p>As this was written simply to be a letter of transmittal of<lb/>
the enclosed resume I shall close, but will write you again before<lb/>
sailing for the states.</p>
<p>I have your cable and also your former letter about the money<lb/>
you have on depsoit, and as it seems very highly possible that the<lb/>
exchange will soon pass beyond the point of 4.25 I am waiting a bit<lb/>
before converting. Today it is 4.10.</p>
<p>With all good wishes from the whole family, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
