<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00931009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from E. J. Scannell to Henry Rose Carter, May 20, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Scannell, E.J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00931009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-05-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Guatemala</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Tapachula (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tonola (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Jalisco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tabasco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tuxtla (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Chiapa de Corzo (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-05-20">May 20, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00931009</idno>
<title>Letter from E. J. Scannell to Henry Rose Carter, May 20, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Scannell reminisces about times he and Carter spent in Panama.  He reports on yellow fever field work in Mexico and claims to have created a &ldquo;no man's land&rdquo; between Mexico and Guatemala.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-05-20">
<head>Letter from E. J. Scannell to Henry Rose Carter, May 20, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00931009"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Tapachula,<lb/>
Chiapas,<lb/>
Mexico.<lb/>
<date value="1922-05-20">May 20, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
I. H. B<lb/>
Scannell<lb/>
Dr. H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon-General,<lb/>

United States Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter;</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wish to thank you so much for the reprint which came yesterday<lb/>
forwarded from New York - I had not seen the article before and no<lb/>
doubt would have missed it entirely since I have nothing in way<lb/>
of medical works except a few old fundamentals, in fact I have<lb/>
been out of the world as it were for about four months now.<lb/>
The work which you so well describe I can visualize and can well<lb/>
understand the many problems with which you were confronted. Am<lb/>
sorry I did not see some of the work first hand.</p>
<p>I do not like to think that your field service days are over<lb/>
although I do think you have done more than your share already<lb/>
toward the prevention of disease in the world, which in turn means<lb/>
or spells greater happiness and prosperity for the human family.<lb/>
We, of the old Panama days still think of Doctor Carter as our<lb/>
Chief and when we fore-gather, in spirit we are back at Panama<lb/>
wondering what Doctor Carter is going to do next - always fair<lb/>
and just is the verdict of all who ever served under him.</p>
<p>I have been here now some three months without seeing a case of<lb/>
yellow fever however have gone ahead and created a no mans land<lb/>
between Guatemala and Mexico - all travel to and from Guatemala<lb/>
passes through Tapachula, am enclosing a rough sketch to show the<lb/>
key points - Tapachula controls Central America overland, Tonala<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00931010"/>
2.<lb/>
and Jalisco control the interior of the state - all travel from the<lb/>
interior passes through Jalisco except a few pack trains now and<lb/>
then over very poor trails (three or four day trips) into Tabasco.<lb/>
The average house index along the coast here was about 20 during<lb/>
the dry weather but as soon as the rains began in April it increased<lb/>
considerably - Tapachula showed about 20 per cent index and a rather<lb/>
unusual feature here is the deep well breeding - I was told that<lb/>
the deep wells need not be considered in the anti-stegomyia work<lb/>
and that may hold true in many places but I find here that the wells<lb/>
which run 20 to 30 feet deep are prolific breeders - it is a problem<lb/>
also just how to care for them. I have been fishing all of them<lb/>
although many are bound to die and affect the water which hardly<lb/>
seems fair to the people involved however the people in Mexico<lb/>
as a whole have been very nice to me and allow me to go ahead<lb/>
<unclear>and</unclear> no questions asked.</p>
<p>Tapachula has a population of 10,000.<lb/>
Elevation about 75 feet.<lb/>
Temperature - no figures available but about the same as Panama<lb/>
very hot (I assume Maximum about 100 Mean 80) with high degree<lb/>
of humidity.</p>
<p>Water supply - from river through pipes but only a few houses<lb/>
supplied, for most part people are supplied from fountains which<lb/>
naturally calls for storage in the house, tinajas, ollas, <unclear>barr</unclear><lb/>
and the like being used.</p>
<p>Sewerage system- two streets only - a few have pit closets <unclear>bt</unclear><lb/>
but most consign their wastes to the calles or patios-<lb/>
All along the coast here there is a history of &ldquo;fiebre<lb/>
perniciosa&rdquo; it is described as a fiebre con hemorragias and<lb/>
causes death within four to six days - last year Tapachula<lb/>
had 110 deaths during month of May from above fiebre and that<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00931011"/>
3.<lb/>
in a population of only 10,000.</p>
<p>There is no laboratory here and no facilities for doing research<lb/>
work but clinically the chief diseases are malaria, hook-worm<lb/>
and dysentery.</p>
<p>We started organizing about April 1st. and a little sketch enclosed<lb/>
will show how the index has gradually dropped especially since I<lb/>
got my fish started - am fishing all wells, tanks, barrels etc.<lb/>
and find they as a rule they live readily although it is necessary to<lb/>
use extreme care in handling them. The people watch their fish and<lb/>
for the most part take good care of them.</p>
<p>We have 5 principal varieties of fish here - <unclear>Pupos</unclear>, Mojarritas and<lb/>
Sardinas make three, the other two are not classified - one of the<lb/>
unclassified being an especially good fish for our work feeding<lb/>
both top and bottom. Shall send samples to the Board in hopes<lb/>
the unknown may be definitely placed.</p>
<p>I have just recently returned from a trip into the interior to<lb/>
Tuxtla also Chiapa de Corzo - at Tuxtla which by the way is a<lb/>
very old town I found a house index of 67 per cent<unclear>.</unclear> the worst<lb/>
thing I have seen in Mexico - their history shows Yellow fever<lb/>
to have been present epidemic form in 1916 - nothing since has<lb/>
been recognized as such.</p>
<p>I am satisfied that yellow fever is constantly being overlooked<lb/>
in this section.</p>
<p>Let me again thank you for the reprint - it will help me in my<lb/>
work I feel sure. Please commend me to your family and believe<lb/>
me ever,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>E. J. Scannell</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
