<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00933013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, June 15, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00933013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-06-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Wrightson, William D.</name>
<name type="person">Arce, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Sainz, Arturo</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-06-15">June 15, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00933013</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, June 15, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson updates Carter on his search for material for Carter's yellow fever book.  The Peruvian health authorities have suggested he stay after the end of campaign, but he is uncertain what he will do.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-06-15">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, June 15, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00933013"/>
<opener>
DIRECTOR GENERAL<lb/>
HENRY HANSON<lb/>
M. D.<lb/>
I. H. B.<lb/>
<unclear>Hanson-</unclear><lb/>
BAJO LOS <unclear>AUSPICIOS</unclear> DEL<lb/>
GOBIERNO PERUANO Y LA<lb/>
JUNTA INTERNACIONAL DE<lb/>
SANIDAD DE ROCKEFELLER<lb/>
FOUNDATION <unclear>.. .. ..</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
Campa&ntilde;a Sanitaria contra la Fiebre Amarilla en el Per&uacute;<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
AVENIDA PIEROLA 545 - TELEFONO 3428<lb/>
LIMA -- PERU<lb/>
<date value="1922-06-15">JUne 15,1922.</date>
</dateline>
NUMERO<lb/>
-----<lb/>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St. N.W.,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Referring again to the records which you wanted of<lb/>
previous yellow fever in Peru, Dr. Ezayguirre the other day sent you his<lb/>
library copy of the monograph which he wrote on the subject in 1906. This<lb/>
was his last copy, (due to the fact that <unclear>wheh</unclear> Wrightson entered the Salubridad<lb/>
he ordered the porters to throw away a lot of old pamphlets and papers which<lb/>
he found on taking the office) but fortunately Ezayguirre had previously given<lb/>
me two copies which enabled me to return one to him. Had I not had this he<lb/>
probably would not have had a copy. I am sorry that you did not <unclear>come</unclear> to know<lb/>
him better as he is a man who is quite a student, very modest and unobtrusive,<lb/>
and usually tending to his own business. He is in charge of the <del><unclear>department</unclear></del>f<lb/>
section on statistics for the Health Department. He said that he <unclear>know</unclear> of no<lb/>
other complete publication on other yellow fever epidemics. Possibly Dr. Julian<lb/>
Arce (the man with whom I had my recent arguments) has other records as he<lb/>
was looking up quite fully the records on yellow fever, in connection with his<lb/>
discourse on the &ldquo;fiebre hemoglobinurica&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I have been thinking that it would be a good thing to make a collec-<lb/>
tion of the articles written by you which I have had translated, togather with<lb/>
the last one which you sent me and have them published in the spanish. I think<lb/>
I have most of them. In as much as I have the translations they could all be<lb/>
compiled and published in a small volume and be made available for the spanish<lb/>
medical literature. What do you say? I suggested the idea to the President and<lb/>
he took to it very readily, and took occasion to say that he was very impressed<lb/>
with Dr. Carter. Dr. Lavoreria could translate your &ldquo;Note on the Spread of<lb/>
Yellow Fever in Houses&rdquo;, which is very interesting, and <unclear>shows</unclear> your great powers<lb/>
of <unclear>observation</unclear>.</p>
<p>In my last &ldquo;acuerdo&rdquo; I told the President that I expected to leave soon,<lb/>
and that I thought that it proper that I should do so since the country had no<del>t</del><lb/>
funds to go ahead with their sanitary program, and I thought it unwise to have<lb/>
a foreigner in the position of Director. It appeared to me better to have foreign-<lb/>
ers as advisors or in charge of some special work than in that of Director, an<lb/>
administrative position. He did not like the idea of my leaving. The next day I<lb/>
also told the Minister of Fomento that I expected to leave, and he made very<lb/>
much more demonstartion in the matter than the President did. He and Dr. Lavorer-<lb/>
ia argued quite extensively that I should stay on, trying to convince me that<lb/>
I was a necessity to the country- that I could do things here which the Peruvians<lb/>
themselves could not do - that Congress would accept recommendations from me which<lb/>
they would not from Wrightson or from the Peruvians themselves, and that at the<lb/>
present time they had no one could fill the place. The American and British Colony<lb/>
are also quite anxious that I saty on. But is it worth while? If I did I would<lb/>
only want to do for sufficient time to see whether it were possible to improve<lb/>
the organization and the legislation. This could be done in a year, providing<lb/>
congress could be made to see the point. A congress is a congress in any country,<lb/>
and a Latin congress in a Latin country is also a congress which can not be counted<lb/>
on to do logical things always. However if I were a young man without a family I<lb/>
think I should enjoy the venture for a while,- and I think I could accomplish<lb/>
something.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00933014"/>
<p>#2.</p>
<p>June 15, 1922<del>1</del></p>
<p>Dr. H.R. Carter,</p>
<p>As things are at present I am out of touch with things in the states,<lb/>
and I have no previous standing with the International Health Board, so can not<lb/>
expect them to make any special provision. What they are <unclear>planning</unclear> I do not know.<lb/>
Dr. Rose once wrote me to let him know whether or not I had any definite plans<lb/>
after finishing the work of the campaign. To this I replied that I expected to<lb/>
go to the states and take a few months rest, and to arrange some work which I<lb/>
have not had time to do during my time in Peru. I have heard nothing further<lb/>
from them in the matter and have asked no questions.</p>
<p>I rather feel that I would like to report in person on the campaign<lb/>
and see if some arrangements can be made to work up a complete report on the<lb/>
Peruvian work. I have very extensive files now, a great deal of which is in<lb/>
such shape that one could work it over quite rapidly. However what value, except<lb/>
as an historic one would such a complete report have. You are writing the final<lb/>
history of yellow fever. I am beginning to believe that we shall soon reach the<lb/>
stage in the world which we have now reached in Peru, namely the extinction of<lb/>
Yellow fever. Hence much of what I might report on this last campaign will not<lb/>
have a practical value in that it could be adopted or adapted to future yellow<lb/>
fever campaigns. However if I had another similar proposition to this in Peru<lb/>
I think I could improve considerably on what we have done. In the first place<lb/>
I would organize properly right from the start, and I think I would pick several<lb/>
of the men I have had with me here. One of the first to <unclear>be</unclear> chosen would be Sr.<lb/>
Arturo Sainz, he certainly has made <unclear>good</unclear>!!! Corrigan and Pickett also are real<lb/>
material for this kind of campaigning. Seeley is good when you have him with you.<lb/>
He is almost a tireless worker, but does not have as good judgement as Pickett of<lb/>
Corrigan.</p>
<p>Well I presume that this will probably be <unclear>the</unclear> last letter until I leave.<lb/>
We are planning to sail on the <unclear>Eoro</unclear>, which leaves here some time between the 28th<lb/>
of July and the 1st of August. This should get us to New York on or before the<lb/>
15th of August.</p>
<p>Trusting that both your aciatica and your &ldquo;kink&rdquo; have mended, I am</p>
<p>As ever,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
