<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00931023">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, May 29, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00931023</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-05-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Caldwell, Bert W.</name>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-05-29">May 29, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00931023</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, May 29, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson writes that he has announced to the press and government that yellow fever has been eradicated along the coast.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-05-29">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, May 29, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00931023"/>
<opener>
DIRECTOR GENERAL<lb/>
HENRY HANSON<lb/>
M. D.<lb/>
BAJO LOS AUSPICIOS DEL<lb/>
GOBIERNO PERUANO Y LA<lb/>
JUNTA INTERNACIONAL DE<lb/>
SANIDAD DE ROCKEFELLER<lb/>
FOUNDATION<lb/>
<unclear>I. H. B</unclear><lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
<dateline>
Campa&ntilde;a Sanitaria contra la Fiebre Amarilla en el Per&uacute;<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
AVENIDA PIEROLA 545 - TELEFONO 3428<lb/>
LIMA -- PERU<lb/>
<date value="1922-05-29">May 29,1922.</date>
</dateline>
NUMERO<lb/>
___<lb/>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Asst Surgeon General, U.S.P.H.S.,<lb/>
2121 California Street, N.W.,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My daer Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In my last letter I failed to acknowledge <unclear>your</unclear><lb/>
reprint &ldquo;A NOTE ON THE SPREAD OF YELLOW FEVER IN HOUSES&rdquo;, for which I<lb/>
thank you very much. Had it not been for the sad fact that my interpretor,<lb/>
or perhaps it should be, translator, died recently, I should also have this<lb/>
translated so as to have quite a collection your writings in the spanish.<lb/>
As <unclear>I</unclear><del>I</del> notice this is an only copy so I will take good care not to lose it.<lb/>
I am trying to get Karl to copy it. It will give him good practice in<lb/>
using the typewriter and at the same time get me a copy of your article.</p>
<p>I have also received your paper on the epidemics of 1919 and<lb/>
1920 in Piura which I naturally find very interesting, and correct as<lb/>
your writings always are. In as much as I am hoping to embark for the<lb/>
states not later than two months from today I will wait to discuss your<lb/>
paper and the last epidemic until I see you. There are many points which<lb/>
will make interesting comparison.</p>
<p>I have announced to the press and to the different Legations<lb/>
that I think yellow fever is a thing of the past on this coast. We are<lb/>
now getting togather the last data on our work. In my last letter to you<lb/>
I believe that I estimated the total number of house visits at about<lb/>
1,500,000, and also made the same statement to Dr. Rose. I am afraid that<lb/>
this is a little too high. They were fully 800,000, up to the end of the<lb/>
year 1921, and we have worked quite intensively in some places for five<lb/>
months more, in many for two or three months, so I presume that 1,200,000<lb/>
will be closer to the correct figures. There was a lot of work which at<lb/>
first was not properly recorded so even though we thought we were well<lb/>
organized this year there is much data lacking for the full final report.</p>
<p>I notice that you are <unclear>keeping</unclear> quite busy, with lectures, and<lb/>
writing articles, and the history of Yellow Fever. I am trying to get<lb/>
things lined up so that I can soon begin to dedicate myself to getting<lb/>
my outline worked out at least.</p>
<p>I am somewhat surprised at Caldwells suggestion of carriers in<lb/>
yellow fever. I did not know that any men who had experience in the work<lb/>
took such suggestions seriously. Some of these people have asked about it<lb/>
but we have had absolutely no evidence that there could be such a thing.<lb/>
All the late cases have had a perfectly reasonable explanation, and the<lb/>
suspicious cases reported which have not proven to be genuine, have failed<lb/>
to present symptoms which would tend to puzzle the man who knows yellow fever.<lb/>
If Caldwell had a genuine case after six months I am willing to bet that he<lb/>
had others of a mild unrecognized type &ldquo;tambien&rdquo;. Furthermore you can not<lb/>
always be dead sure that even on the haciendas they tell you &ldquo;the truth, the<lb/>
whole truth and nothing but the truth, So help you God&rdquo;, this for more rea-<lb/>
sons than one.</p>
<p>What you say about Africa is mighty interesting, let us hope that<lb/>
you are right,- if so we can soon gather for the last rites of &ldquo;yellow Jack&rdquo;.</p>
<p>You say that up to May 1, you had received no letters since Feb.<lb/>
I have written several both in March and April, some long detailed ones.<lb/>
Well must close, with the warmest regards from us all,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours as ever,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
