<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00935001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report on the Epidemic of Yellow Fever at Grand-Bassam, by Bauvallet and Houillon, October 25, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00935001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-10-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="place">Dahomey (Togo)</name>
<name type="place">Accra (Gold Coast)</name>
<name type="place">Bassam (Ivory Coast)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>12 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-10-25">October 25, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00935001</idno>
<title>Report on the Epidemic of Yellow Fever at Grand-Bassam, by Bauvallet and Houillon, October 25, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report is a detailed account of the yellow fever epidemic 
in French West Africa, including information on control measures, vaccinotherapy, serotherapy, and experimental findings.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-10-25">
<head>Report on the Epidemic of Yellow Fever at Grand-Bassam, by Bauvallet and Houillon, October 25, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00935001"/>
<opener>
<unclear>Blanndt</unclear> Grand Bassam No 1 &amp; 2?<lb/>
<hi>REPORT ON THE EPIDEMIC OF YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
AT GRAND-BASSAM</hi><lb/>
(August 18 to September 8, 1922.)<lb/>
****<lb/>
<hi>French West Africa<lb/>
Colony of the Ivory Coast<lb/>
Health Service.</hi><lb/>
</opener>
<p>The information that brought to our attention a few cases<lb/>
of yellow fever in Dahomey, Togo and the Gold Coast in July did<lb/>
not find us unprepared.</p>
<p>1-</p>
<p>In fact, as early as June 28, and before any official notifica-<lb/>
tion, the Chief Physician, Head of the Health Service, came down to Bassam<lb/>
to examine a patient who had been reported by the physician at that post.<lb/>
This was the sailor A. of the S.S. &ldquo;New Georgia&rdquo;, coming from the south.<lb/>
This man was found to be suffering from malaria, and the ship was declared<lb/>
free from Stegomyia.</p>
<p>2-</p>
<p>On July 29 some patients on board the &ldquo;Barracoo&rdquo;, also from<lb/>
the south, engaged our attention. One of those patients, the ship-boy B.,<lb/>
died on the 31st. The development of the disease, the anamnesis, and the post-<lb/>
mortem findings all established the diagnosis of a pernicious attack of malaria.<lb/>
This diagnosis was confirmed by the absence of contagion and of Stegomyia.<lb/>
The ship remained anchored in the roads for 16 days and no one on board<lb/>
fell ill.</p>
<p>A very strict and constant supervision of the native morbidity<lb/>
and mortality gave only negative results.</p>
<p>The marine sanitary police supervision was carried out under<lb/>
conditions of complete security, since it was physically impossible to<lb/>
land except at the wharf. All arrivals by the sea from the south were<lb/>
examined on arrival, and all passengers were observed for 6 days without any<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00935002"/>
abnormal findings.</p>
<p>3-</p>
<p>However, danger did exist on the land side on account of<lb/>
the proximity of the Gold-Coast. Bassam is one day's journey on foot<lb/>
from Aferonou, the English frontier post. Continual and unsupervised<lb/>
communication took place by way of the shore. This explains how an<lb/>
Italian Mr. C., who left Accra by the road, was able to reach Bassam<lb/>
on June 29, brought in by his men in a state of complete coma, without<lb/>
having his passage of the frontier known to anyone. In this case it<lb/>
was nothing but sunstroke with resulting mental confusion, which was<lb/>
quickly cured.</p>
<p>The month of July passed with nothing of note.</p>
<p>4-</p>
<p>Mrs. D. of the Atlantic Hotel died on August 4. The records<lb/>
show that the symptoms were those of bilious hematuria. There was no<lb/>
one infected in the vicinity of the patient. This case was brought to<lb/>
the attention of the Chief of the Health Service on account of an epi-<lb/>
gastralgic symptom. This symptom alone was not sufficient to allow us to<lb/>
pronounce the word yellow fever, the diagnosis of which haunted us and<lb/>
became almost obsession.</p>
<p>5+</p>
<p>Seventeen days after the beginning of Mrs. D.'s fatal illness<lb/>
a resident of the Atlantic Hotel, Mr. E., was admitted in haste to the<lb/>
Ambulance Hospital at Bassam. He fell ill on August 16. On the 17th<lb/>
he had a pathognomonic attack of black vomit, and died at 6:45 P.M. The autopsy, which was made on the forenoon of the 18th, revealed a<lb/>
hemorrhagic stomach filled with &ldquo;coffee grounds&rdquo;, a chamois-colored<lb/>
liver, and a saffron-yellow skin. The Chief of the Health Service, to<lb/>
whom the case was reported by telegram under date of the 17th, came down<lb/>
to Bassam on the 18th and confirmed the diagnosis by examination of the pieces.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00935003"/>
<p>Mr. E., who had no means of any kind, had managed to live in<lb/>
Bassam for several months by various shifts, and led a mysterious kind of<lb/>
existence.</p>
<p>He belonged to a group of Italians who had made their head-<lb/>
quarters at the Atlantic Hotel. These Italians, who came from the Gold-<lb/>
Coast to recruit laborers, sometimes vanished for a week at a time, and<lb/>
E. did the same.</p>
<p>As these recruiting agents had found themselves refused permission<lb/>
to carry on their activities, it is perfectly logical to suppose that the<lb/>
high exchange value of the pound sterling made it possible for them to<lb/>
engage men just the same. Thus E. and F., another Italian of the same group,<lb/>
living under unsanitary conditions and especially without mosquito nets,<lb/>
got infected at Accra, where yellow fever was officially recognized, when<lb/>
they secretly took a group of laborers there.</p>
<p>1+<lb/>
5<lb/>
<unclear>a-t</unclear></p>
<p>The case of E. created an accidental center which developed<lb/>
chronologically in the following way among the guests, the neighbors, and<lb/>
the patrons of the Atlantic Hotel, a particularly ill-kept property the<lb/>
cleaning-up of which is a sanitary necessity.</p>
<p><del><unclear>Sick or 16 died out than 21 Toophal</unclear></del></p>
<p>1. August 16, <del>death</del><add>case</add> E. <unclear>error sick 16-died 17 6.45 P.M</unclear></p>
<p>2+<lb/>
6<lb/>
<unclear>r</unclear></p>
<p>2. August 18, case F. This Italian <unclear>foll</unclear> ill on the 18th,<lb/>
was at once isolated, and had a form of yellow fever that was cured. E.<lb/>
was F.'s roommate, sleeping in the same bed with him at the Atlantic Hotel.</p>
<p>3+<lb/>
7<lb/>
<unclear>or</unclear></p>
<p>August 18, case G. The disease appeared during the night<lb/>
of the 18th with coup de barre, facial congestion, epigastralgia, vomit.<lb/>
The development was favorable, and the patient recovered.</p>
<p>4+<lb/>
8<lb/>
<unclear>D+</unclear></p>
<p>4. August 20, case of Mrs. H. The patient fell ill about<lb/>
August 15, and was treated at home, Fever, epigastralgia, vomiting,<lb/>
then uterine hemorrhage, icterus, albuminuria followed by anuria. Died<lb/>
on August 20. There was no autopsy, as the patient was cared for by her<lb/>
family.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00935004"/>
<p>5+(9)<lb/>
<unclear>d f</unclear></p>
<p>August 21, case I. This Syrian fell ill about 10 A.M. on<lb/>
the 21st. Rachialgia, facial congestion, high fever, vomiting all<lb/>
came on at once. The disease developed very rapidly. Died at 2 P.M.<lb/>
on the 22d. There was no autopsy, partly for lack of time and partly<lb/>
on account of the clear clinical indications.</p>
<p>All sick persons with a fever were examined and their cases<lb/>
discussed by Physician-Major Bauvallet and Chief Physician Houillon, Head<lb/>
of the Health Service.</p>
<p>As soon as the first case was reported the Bassam territory<lb/>
was put under observation, and on the 20th of the month it was declared<lb/>
infected with <hi>yellow fever</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>CONTROL MEASURES PUT INTO EXECUTION</hi>.</p>
<p>A conference took place on August 18 about 9 A.M. between:</p>
<p>M. Houillon, Chief Physician of the 1st class of the T. C.,<lb/>
Head of the Health Service of the Ivory Coast.</p>
<p>M. Mondon, Administrator and Mayor of Bassam.</p>
<p>M. Bauvallet, Physician-Major of the 2nd class of the T. C.,<lb/>
physician of Bassam.</p>
<p>A plan of sanitary mobilization, the details and possibility<lb/>
of which had been discussed long before by the Health Service, was decided<lb/>
upon in its larger aspect. A meeting of the Committee on Hygiene, composed<lb/>
of members of the Municipal Commission, was hastily called and informed of<lb/>
the state of affairs.</p>
<p>The public was informed, in a circular that was composed at<lb/>
once, of the existence of a death by yellow fever, of the precautionary<lb/>
measures to be taken, and of the necessity of reporting every case of illness<lb/>
accompanied by fever. Besides, a sanitary bulletin was established and<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00935005"/>
published daily to the population of Bassam during the whole epidemic,<lb/>
according the the formally expressed wish of the Head of the Health Service<lb/>
and the resulting decision of the administrative authorities, who thought<lb/>
it absolutely necessary that the inhabitants be exactly informed and warned<lb/>
against false reports.</p>
<p>The following control measures, the rapid execution of which<lb/>
was one of the chief factors of success, considering that there was no<lb/>
European quarantine station in Bassam, were carried out.</p>
<p>1. Requisition of all mosquito netting, which was put at the<lb/>
disposal of the entire population on the indication of the medical author-<lb/>
ities, in order to protect everyone.</p>
<p>2. Installation of mosquito traps in every suspected or infected<lb/>
house.</p>
<p>(No point 3 in original)</p>
<p>4. Disinfection, by hot cresyl fumes, of every house that was<lb/>
infected or harbored Stegomyia.</p>
<p>5. Isolation of every one suspected of infection (persons<lb/>
in the vicinity of the sick) either in their homes or in hastily prepared<lb/>
buildings. The Richmond house was requisitioned, with 5 beds; two rooms in<lb/>
the European Ambulance Hospital, 10 beds; first floor of the Maternity<lb/>
Hospital, 10 beds.</p>
<p>6. Isolation of all fever patients before diagnosis, under<lb/>
mosquito nets, and with mosquito traps at the doors. Isolation and ob-<lb/>
servation, under (proper) conditions, of 9 Europeans, <hi>all of them uninfected</hi>.</p>
<p>7. Checking up, repairing and distributing mosquito nets to<lb/>
well persons.</p>
<p>8. Increase in the severity of Stegomyia control. This control<lb/>
had been begun in Bassam several years before, but had become much more<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00935006"/>
effective since June, particularly on account of the large increase<lb/>
in legal summons followed by judgments. The relative scarcity of<lb/>
Stegomyia in Bassam, due to the activity of the Health Service, and<lb/>
pointed out by Dr. Bauvallet and Dr. Blanchard, explains why the<lb/>
early cases, which were the only ones that appeared, were limited to<lb/>
5. The Health Service functioned as usual with the regular personnel<lb/>
during the epidemic, in addition to a few workmen loaned by the<lb/>
Administrator-Mayor. The search for the hiding places of Stegomyia<lb/>
larvae was carried on by the regular specialized brigades in the six<lb/>
control sectors established since August, 1920, 2 of these being European<lb/>
and the other 4 native. It must however be noted that the entire house<lb/>
to house visits were made under the direction either of a sworn European<lb/>
agent of the Health Service or of a physician. Valuable, efficient and<lb/>
disinterested assistance was spontaneously given by M. Landre, a planter<lb/>
of the Ivory Coast, who was passing through Bassam, and who came to offer<lb/>
his services to the physician in charge.</p>
<p>9. Visiting, disinfecting, clearing of mosquitoes and oiling<lb/>
of the coastal steamers and barges that were blocked at Bassam by the<lb/>
quarantine. This service was under the direction of Sergeant Javelas,<lb/>
of Batallion No. 3, who was placed at the service of the Bassam physician<lb/>
by the military authorities.</p>
<p>10. Order of service, guards composed of sharpshooters of<lb/>
Batallion No. 3, loaned by the Batallion Chief Steef, military commander,<lb/>
at the request of the physician of Bassam, and placed in every infected<lb/>
or suspected house. These soldiers were under the direct command of the<lb/>
Physician, who gave them a very simple order, which consisted of keeping<lb/>
absolutely everyone out of the houses under observation.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f00935007"/>
<p>11. Printed information, got out and distributed at the<lb/>
suggestion of the Head of the Health Service, gave the public excellent<lb/>
advice. Samples of Stegomyia in tubes were circulated by the physician<lb/>
of Bassam.</p>
<p>12. Talks were given by M. Mondon to the native chiefs<lb/>
of the Circle. Every case of illness, and all deaths, which were<lb/>
very few, were inspected by the physician, thanks to the reports of<lb/>
the village chiefs. <hi>No native, either before, during, or after the<lb/>
epidemic, presented any morbid symptoms that could lead one to suspect<lb/>
yellow fever</hi>.</p>
<p>13. Placing under observation, individual mosquito nets, in<lb/>
the quarantine station, of every native coming from the Gold Coast, either<lb/>
by land or water.</p>
<p>14. All Europeans who landed at Bassam during the course of<lb/>
the epidemic were given &ldquo;sanitary passports&rdquo;, and were sent away <hi>im-<lb/>
mediately</hi> by day in automobiles.</p>
<p>15. The organization of a sanitary cordon around the infected<lb/>
zone.</p>
<p>16. Sanitary observation of the population living on the<lb/>
frontier of the Gold Coast. Nothing suspicious found in the Aboisse<lb/>
section.</p>
<p>The successful conception, execution and control of all these<lb/>
measures, the practical application of which bristled with difficulties,<lb/>
were due to the close collaboration of the Head of the Health Service,<lb/>
the Administration, the Bassam Physician, and the Hygienic Commission.</p>
<p>As a whole the population of Bassam good-naturedly accepted<lb/>
all the required restrictions, even those that were very unpleasant,<lb/>
such as house inspections. It would have been fatal, and it did happen<lb/>
in a few cases, that ill-natured persons complained of despotism and<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00935008"/>
denied the presence of yellow fever. When necessary, regular <unclear>penal</unclear><lb/>
action was most successfully applied.</p>
<p><hi>VACCINOTHERAPY AND SEROTHERAPY</hi></p>
<p>The physician stationed in Bassam, which is a city particularly<lb/>
exposed to epidemics, had already entered into personal correspondence<lb/>
with Mr. Hideyo Noguchi of the Rockefeller Institute in 1921, and had<lb/>
received from him early in 1922 a certain amount of anti-yellow-fever<lb/>
serum and vaccine preserved in ice.</p>
<p>At the very beginning of the epidemic a circular letter was<lb/>
published informing the inhabitants that anyone who wished it would be<lb/>
vaccinated in accord with the results published by the eminent Japanese<lb/>
biologist.</p>
<p>From August 18 to 24, 140 Europeans out of a population of about<lb/>
200 were vaccinated with dead cultures of Leptospira icteroides from lot 15,<lb/>
prepared on December 9, 1921. One hundred and thirty-one received two<lb/>
injections of 2 cc. at an interval of 6 days, according to the author's<lb/>
technique; 9 did not appear for the second injection.</p>
<p>Practically all of the persons vaccinated presented the following<lb/>
reaction on the evening of the day on which they had received the injection<lb/>
between 8 and 10 A.M.; light fever with pain in the small of the back, more<lb/>
or less marked rachialgia, typical picture of the &ldquo;coup de barre&rdquo;, consisting<lb/>
of very severe pain in the lumbar region. The intensity of the rachialgia<lb/>
was what kept 8 of the 9 that had the first injection only from returning<lb/>
for the second. The ninth of these persons is mentioned in a special report<lb/>
at the end of this one.</p>
<p>Four of the persons vaccinated presented sterile abscesses, indicated<lb/>
by Noguchi as being due to the presence of agar-agar in the culture medium,<lb/>
after 15-20 days and appearing at the point of innoculation in spite of<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f00935009"/>
systematic massage immediately after the penetration of the skin by<lb/>
the vaccine. These abscesses were cured by simple cupping and left<lb/>
no scars.</p>
<p>At the same time serotherapy with Noguchi's serum, kept<lb/>
at a temperature of minus 4 degrees Centigrade, was applied to all<lb/>
the patients, in addition to the classical and purely symptomatic<lb/>
treatment.</p>
<p>The results of this serotherapy were as follows:</p>
<p>Case 1.- The diagnosis of yellow fever was not absolute<lb/>
until the appearance of the black vomit. The patient received immediately,<lb/>
at 4:30 P.M., an intravenous injection of 60 cc. of serum. Death occurred<lb/>
at 5:43 P.M. This injection was given in extromis, after the third day,<lb/>
when it is said by Noguchi to be no longer of any value.</p>
<p>Case 2.- The disease made its appearance in the evening<lb/>
of August 18, with a very high fever. The patient said that he had<lb/>
had a temperature of 39.9 degrees C. at the time. The case was not<lb/>
reported until the next morning, when the patient was isolated in the<lb/>
Ambulance hospital. Pain in the back, &ldquo;coup de barre&rdquo;, congestion of<lb/>
the face, epigastralgia, scant urine with no albumen. Temperature of<lb/>
39.4. Received 60 cc. of serum at 8:30 A.M. Decrease in temperature<lb/>
and diuresis in the afternoon; cure.</p>
<p>Case 3.- High fever during the night of the 17-18. Seen by the<lb/>
physician on the 18th at 9 A.M. Temperature of 39.2, extreme pain in the<lb/>
lumbar region, cramps in the legs, bilious vomit and internal epigastralgia,<lb/>
albuminuria. Received 60 cc. of serum intravenously. The temperature<lb/>
fell to 38.6 in the afternoon. Decrease in the vomiting, appearance of a<lb/>
subicteric condition that persisted until August 24. Disappearance of the<lb/>
albuminuria; defervescence; cure.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f00935010"/>
<p>Case 4.- Patient fell ill on August 15, but her husband did<lb/>
not call a physician, as he thought that it was merely a fever due to<lb/>
acclimatization. Isolated only in the evening of the 17th, actually later<lb/>
than case 1., although the symptoms suggested a malarial attack. On the<lb/>
19th the diagnosis became evident; slight uterine hemorrhages, epigastralgia,<lb/>
bilious vomit, congestion of the face, <unclear>prostration</unclear>, subicterus, scant<lb/>
urine with albumen. Was given as intravenous injection of 60 cc. of serum.<lb/>
On the 20th the icterus was general and the prostration still more marked;<lb/>
there were subcutaneous sanguineous effusions and the anuria was total.<lb/>
A second intravenous injection of 60 cc. of serum was administered; a few<lb/>
drops of very albuminous urine were expelled after the injection. Death<lb/>
at 7.10 P.M. The serotherapeutic treatment was late and useless.</p>
<p>Case 5.- The patient took to bed on the 21st about 10 A.M.<lb/>
Was seen at once and sent to the Ambulance hospital to be isolated.<lb/>
No pain in the lumbar region, but epigastralgia, bilious vomit, congestion<lb/>
of the face. The temperature remained at from 39.2 to 39.6 during the<lb/>
whole day of the 21st. The patient passed a restless night, with a tem-<lb/>
perature of 39.8 at 7 A.M. on the 22nd. Received 60 cc. of serum less than<lb/>
4 hours after the beginning of the disease. The vomiting continued and was<lb/>
tinged with blood. Death at 1:45 P.M. The treatment was not totally un-<lb/>
successful; autopsy was not performed on account of lack of time.</p>
<p>One case must receive special mention, that of the ninth person<lb/>
who had only one injection.</p>
<p>Mr. B..., living at the Atlantic Hotel, and a neighbor of Mr. X...,<lb/>
and Mr. Y..., received 2 cc. of vaccine on August 22, but did not appear for<lb/>
the second injection on the 23rd. The proprietor of the Atlantic Hotel,<lb/>
on being asked over the telephone as to why Mr. B... remained absent,<lb/>
replied guardedly that Mr. B... was not well. The patient was seen at<lb/>
10:30 A.M. He had had no reaction after the first injection, but on the<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f00935011"/>
night of the 27-28 he had a fever and a back-ache. He did not take his<lb/>
temperature at the time. When seen his temperature was 39.2. &ldquo;coup de barre&rdquo;,<lb/>
cramps in the legs, congestion of the face that was in marked contrast to<lb/>
his usual pallor, gums edged with white, a symptom that appeared only in<lb/>
this case, vomiting, albuminuria. Was isolated in the Ambulance hospital,<lb/>
and received an intravenous injection of 60 cc. of serum at 1 P.M.<lb/>
The patient immediately presented an intense seric reaction, pruritus,<lb/>
generalized erythrosis, very grave syncope. An intravenous injection<lb/>
of 1 mg. of adrenaline caused the disappearance of the anaphylactic<lb/>
phenomena. The fever and the disturbing symptoms disappeared during the<lb/>
night.</p>
<p><hi>EXPERIMENTAL FINDINGS</hi>.</p>
<p>It is perfectly clear that the great number and urgency of<lb/>
the activities to be carried on did not allow the physician of Bassam,<lb/>
who is alone at this post, to make any consecutive microbiological exam-<lb/>
inations, especially early in the epidemic, when everything had to be done<lb/>
at once.</p>
<p>It was however possible to obtain the following findings in the<lb/>
case of Mr.</p>
<p>Three cc. of blood was collected from the patient's vein with<lb/>
a citrated seringe before the injection of serum.</p>
<p>This citrated blood was immediately injected into the<lb/>
cellular tissue of the shaved and disinfected abdominal wall of guinea pig<lb/>
No. 1.</p>
<p>This guinea pig was isolated under a mosquito net and died during<lb/>
the night of September 4-5, 7 days after innoculation. The animal's temper-<lb/>
ature curve showed a distinct hypothermia, 39.4 degrees, in the evening of<lb/>
the 4th. The autopsy was made the next morning. The animal was very thin,<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f00935012"/>
with no icterus of the skin or conjunctiva; but there was subicterus of<lb/>
the muscles. Intense congestion of the lungs and kidneys, with small<lb/>
hemorrhagic foci. The bladder contained 1 cc. of very albuminous urine.<lb/>
The stomach contained food and revealed a mucous membrane with hemorrhagic<lb/>
spots in the vicinity of the pylorus. The intestinal mucous membrane had<lb/>
the same appearance at the level of the duodenum. The liver was very con-<lb/>
gested but showed no degeneration.</p>
<p>Sections of the liver and the kidney were aseptically removed<lb/>
and placed in the oven at 32 degrees in Ringers solution. Smears of the<lb/>
centrifuged cultures and fragments of the viscera preserved in formol<lb/>
have been sent to the Rockefeller Institute.</p>
<p>The examination made in Bassam under poor conditions, the<lb/>
ultra-microscope being badly lighted on account of the lack of a light<lb/>
condenser, did not reveal the presence of Leptospira icteroides.</p>
<p><hi>CONCLUSIONS.</hi></p>
<p>Since the end of this epidemic no cases of yellow fever, or<lb/>
resembling yellow fever, has been found in Bassam, either among the<lb/>
natives or the Europeans.</p>
<p>There is therefore no question of the revival of an endemicity<lb/>
the continuity of which would have been preserved by the natives.</p>
<p>It is at present possible to affirm that the importation<lb/>
of an original case of yellow fever, probably from the Gold Coast,<lb/>
created a small accidental epidemic focus that was quickly extinguished.</p>
<p>Grand-Bassam, October 25, 1923.</p>
<p>Physician-major</p>
<p>(Signed) Dr. Bauvallet, of the 2nd class, physician of the post of Bassam.<lb/>
Dr. Houillon, Chief Physician of the 1st class of the T.C.,<lb/>
Head of the Health Service of the Ivory Coast.</p>
<p>(True copy.)</p>
<p>good</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
