<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00936001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report on the Probable Origin of the Epidemic of Yellow Fever, by Bauvallet, August 25, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00936001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-08-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Dahomey (Togo)</name>
<name type="place">Ivory Coast</name>
<name type="place">Accra (Gold Coast)</name>
<name type="place">Bassam (Ivory Coast)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-08-25">August 25, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00936001</idno>
<title>Report on the Probable Origin of the Epidemic of Yellow Fever, by Bauvallet, August 25, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report discusses the probable origin of yellow fever in Africa.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-08-25">
<head>Report on the Probable Origin of the Epidemic of Yellow Fever, by Bauvallet, August 25, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00936001"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
<dateline>
Grand-Bassam, Ivory Coast.<lb/>
<date value="1922-08-25">August 25, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p><hi>REPORT ON THE PROBABLE ORIGIN OF THE EPIDEMIC<lb/>
OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>*****</p>
<p>As early as June 26 we pointed out by T-o-v-p-33-H that there<lb/>
was at least one case of yellow fever in Dahomey. On June 27 we con-<lb/>
firm this by t-o-34-H, giving the information furnished us by the<lb/>
physician of Kouroussa.</p>
<p>On the 28th we sent out Circular 35-H, in which we warned<lb/>
the population that all infractions of our orders concerning stagnant<lb/>
water would be punished. The same day our service orders to the<lb/>
Adjutant, chief technical agent of the Sanitary Service, defined the<lb/>
measures to be taken.</p>
<p>On the same day, the Chief Physician, Head of the Health<lb/>
Service of the Ivory Coast, arrived at our request to examine a patient<lb/>
on the Steamship &ldquo;New Georgia&rdquo; which had arrived from the south. The<lb/>
patient V., was found to be suffering from malaria. The ship remained<lb/>
in port 18 days, had no more cases of illness, and was recognized to be<lb/>
free from Stegomyia.</p>
<p>We kept all arrivals from the south under careful surveillance.<lb/>
As a result we discovered on board the S.S. &ldquo;Barracoo&rdquo; on July 28 some<lb/>
sick persons whose illness we diagnosed as malaria, one of the cases<lb/>
being serious. On the 29th we received the t-o 92 S.S. pointing out<lb/>
a caso of yellow fever at Accra and ordering that all arrivals from the<lb/>
Gold Coast be kept under observation.</p>
<p>On the 31st occurred the death of the very sick patient on the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00936002"/>
&ldquo;Barracoo&rdquo;, a ship-boy of 14. Our diagnosis on August 1, after autopsy,<lb/>
was that the patient died of pernicious attack. The body showed no<lb/>
appreciable icterus, no sanguineous diffusion, and no trace of blood in<lb/>
the abdominal cavity. Besides, the ship had stayed from June 29 to<lb/>
July 23, at Lagos, where the work was very hard, and it had many patients.</p>
<p>In spite of the advice of the ship's officers, the sailors<lb/>
wore no helmets and took no quinine. The ship-boy imitated the rest<lb/>
and owned no helmet. From July 23 to 26, the date of reaching Bassam,<lb/>
the &ldquo;Barracoo&rdquo; touched at Secondi and Axim, but <hi>not at Accra</hi>, cast anchor<lb/>
at sea, and <add>sent</add> no one but the purser ashore (according to the statement of<lb/>
Captain G. Owen.) to make arrangements for the very small amount of freight<lb/>
that was to be taken on.</p>
<p>After the examination of the body, the &ldquo;Barracoo&rdquo; was thoroughly<lb/>
inspected and was declared free from Stegomyia. A single Culex Pipiens was<lb/>
found after a three hours' search. The cargo consisted of wood, cotton,<lb/>
and palmetto. The ship was regularly disinfected every Monday with creoline.</p>
<p>If the ship had at anytime harbored infected Stegomia, supposing<lb/>
that the ship-boy's case had been yellow fever, the latter's neighbors would<lb/>
have been infected, as he passed his entire illness in the sleeping quarters<lb/>
of the ship, with 10 bunks grouped one above the other, and no mosquito<lb/>
netting. The ship remained 16 days in Bassam and no other case of fever<lb/>
occurred.</p>
<p>Sixteen crew-boys <add><unclear>Knot</unclear></add> from the wharf, who spent the night of July 31-<lb/>
August 1 transferring the passengers of the &ldquo;Eleina&rdquo;, which reached Bassam<lb/>
about 10 p.m., were kept under observation at the quarantine station for<lb/>
6 days as a special precautionary measure and were observed for 6 days more.<lb/>
The agent of the Elder Co., and two passengers of the &ldquo;Elmina&rdquo;, who came<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00936003"/>
from the north and spent the night on board the &ldquo;Barracoo&rdquo;, were placed<lb/>
in &ldquo;sanitary passports&rdquo;, None of them revealed any traces of fever.<lb/>
The death of the ship-boy occurred on the 31st after the closing of the<lb/>
wharf.</p>
<p>Early in July we turned our attention to the strict super-<lb/>
vision of the native morbidity and mortality. The Administrator of<lb/>
Bassam, without whose aid we would not have been able to accomplish<lb/>
anything, and to whom we wish to express at this point our sincere<lb/>
thanks, called the native chiefs together and explained to them the<lb/>
necessity of informing us of the cases of sickness so that we could<lb/>
take precautionary measures from the first.</p>
<p>The native mortality was 7 in June and 6 in July. There is<lb/>
absolutely nothing unusual in these figures for a population of over 3000.<lb/>
The cases were sought out by the sanitary agents in the sections. Secret<lb/>
agents at France Imperial and Moossou informed us of the very rare cases<lb/>
that were not reported.</p>
<p>No case could be considered suspicious.</p>
<p>However, we were aware that the danger lay in the direction of<lb/>
the Gold Coast, and we asked the Chief of the Health Service to watch<lb/>
the frontier.</p>
<p>Although the sanitary clearance papers were all absolutely<lb/>
<hi>clean</hi> even after the telegram from the Governor of the Gold Coast<lb/>
announcing a case of yellow fever at Accra, we considered the maritime<lb/>
inspection at Bassam sufficient and efficient. All the native passengers<lb/>
had since several months been examined on landing and their baggage<lb/>
<hi>disinfected</hi>. This measure was applied to ships from every locality<lb/>
after the past-laden breath from Dakar in August, 1921.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00936004"/>
<p>From the land side the situation was uncertain. There was<lb/>
incessant communication by way of the shore between Bassam, Assinie and<lb/>
the Gold Coast (one day's journey on foot).</p>
<p>On June 29, Mr. X., who left Afornou on the 28th at 2 A.M.,<lb/>
by the Accra road, arrives in Bassam, sent there by the chief epidemic<lb/>
officer in Assinie. He was brought back half dead to Assinie by his men,<lb/>
and immediately sent on to us in a hammock. Without this accident, his<lb/>
crossing the frontier would have remained unknown.</p>
<p>He was isolated at once, in coma, at the quarantine station,<lb/>
or rather in one of the sheds that go by that name. He was found to<lb/>
be suffering from sunstroke with resulting mental &ldquo;afusion&rdquo;, and was<lb/>
discharged completely cured on July 11.</p>
<p>In July the European morbidity and mortality was normal. There<lb/>
were two deaths, that of Mr. Y., who was accidentally killed on July 14,<lb/>
and that of Mr. Z., a naturalized Dahomeyan and a salesman for tree nurseries.<lb/>
He had received judicial summons, and was found dead on the morning of the<lb/>
17th. The autopsy, which was performed at the request of the prosecuting<lb/>
attorney, who suspected suicide, showed lesions of apoplectic icterus. The<lb/>
stomach, which was kept for the purpose of a possible expert opinion, was<lb/>
perfectly normal and completely empty. The Court held that the cause of<lb/>
death was definitely discovered by the autopsy, and did not ask for a<lb/>
toxicological analysis.</p>
<p>We now come to August 4, the date of the death of Mrs. R., who<lb/>
was treated at home.</p>
<p>This case is worth discussing. We have already described it<lb/>
in our 144-S.</p>
<p>The patient took to her bed on July 31, and we saw her in the<lb/>
course of the forenoon. The anamnesis and the early symptoms were those<lb/>
of bilious hemoglobinuria. On the third day the urine was decidedly &ldquo;bitter&rdquo;.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00936005"/>
<p>We noted:</p>
<p>August 3 - anuria, no icterus, epigastralgia, bilious vomit<lb/>
with no trace of blood.</p>
<p>August 4 - forenoon (7 A.M.) - the patient got up to urinate<lb/>
and had a fatal syncope.</p>
<p>There was no icterus at the time of placing the body in the<lb/>
load coffin for transportation to France. Diagnosis: bilious hemo-<lb/>
globinuria, but with a suspicious epigastralgic symptom. It was im-<lb/>
possible to make a diagnosis of yellow fever on this epigastralgia; there<lb/>
was no autopsy.</p>
<p>If this case can be considered suspicious, and we readily admit<lb/>
it, it must be noted that the persons who surrounded the patient, and her<lb/>
husband, who slept in the same bed with her until she died, none of them<lb/>
were infected.</p>
<p>On August 5 our circular 51-H announced the increased severity<lb/>
of the Sanitary Service. On August 7 we made out 7 summons for Europeans.<lb/>
The entire week from the 7th to the 12th was marked by an increase in the<lb/>
number of summons to Europeans and of disciplinary measures for the natives.<lb/>
The average for the past months is about 40.</p>
<p>Seventeen days after the beginning of the illness of Mrs. R.,<lb/>
we admitted to the ambulance hospital as an urgent case Mr. E., a resident<lb/>
at the Hotel Botteleau. He fell ill on the 16th, had an attack of path-<lb/>
ognomonic black vomit on the 17th at about 5 P.M., and died at 6:45 P.M.<lb/>
The autopsy, which was made in the forenoon of the 18th, revealed a stomach<lb/>
full of &ldquo;coffee grounds&rdquo;, a chamois-colored liver, and a saffron-yellow skin.<lb/>
The Chief Physician, to whom we reported the case by a telegram dated the<lb/>
17th in the evening, came down to Bassam and confirmed the diagnosis by<lb/>
examination of the pieces.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f00936006"/>
<p>Mr. E. was absolutely without resources and had arrived in<lb/>
Bassam some two or three months before, leading a mysterious existence.<lb/>
He belonged to a crowd composed of a few Italians who had made the<lb/>
Hotel Botteleau their headquarters. These Italians, who come down<lb/>
from the Gold Coast to recruit laborers for Secondi and Accra, sometimes<lb/>
vanish for a week at a time, and Mr. E. did the same.</p>
<p>On august 18, Mr. F., an Italian, fell ill, was isolated in<lb/>
the quarantine station, and passed through an attenuated but distinct attack<lb/>
of yellow fever. He was E.'s room-mate and slept in the same bed with him.</p>
<p>Two Italians of the same crowd, and who lived in another house,<lb/>
were questioned on the order of Mr. Mondon. One of them did not deny<lb/>
that he was aware of the escapades of E. and F., and said that they could<lb/>
very well have gone recently to the Gold Coast. The other one refused to<lb/>
talk.</p>
<p>It is reasonable to suppose that E. and F., when they found<lb/>
themselves forbidden to do any recruiting, had themselves secretly conducted<lb/>
men to the Gold Coast. According to all probability they were infected on<lb/>
the Gold Coast, and this the more easily since they lived in unsanitary<lb/>
conditions and had no mosquito nets.</p>
<p>We believe that that is where the source of the accidental<lb/>
center in Bassam is to be found.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) Bauvallet</signed>.
<unclear>July</unclear> 30/09<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. <unclear>This</unclear><lb/>
Report<lb/>
Y. F. from <unclear>An</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>into Togoland</unclear><lb/>
1896<lb/>
<unclear>Cont. to 1909 July 30</unclear><lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
