<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00933004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, June 8, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00933004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-06-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Wrightson, William D.</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins University Hospital, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-06-08">June 8, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00933004</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, June 8, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses the political situation in Peru and his difficulties in dealing with local authorities.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-06-08">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, June 8, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00933004"/>
<opener>
I. H. B<lb/>
DIRECTOR GENERAL<lb/>
HENRY HANSON<lb/>
M. D.<lb/>
BAJO LOS AUSPICIOS DEL<lb/>
GOBIERNO PERUANO Y LA<lb/>
JUNTA INTERNACIONAL DE<lb/>
SANIDAD DE ROCKEFELLER<lb/>
FOUNDATION<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
<dateline>
Campa&ntilde;a Sanitaria contra la Fiebre Amarilla en el Per&uacute;<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
AVENIDA PIEROLA 545 - TELEFONO 3428<lb/>
LIMA -- PERU<lb/>
<date value="1922-06-08">June 8, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
NUMERO<lb/>
____<lb/>
DR. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I received your letter written from the<lb/>
Johns Hopkins Hospital and am very sorry to hear of your sciatic<lb/>
trouble and that the old kink has been kicking up again. However<lb/>
we hope that with the good care and treatment which you have there<lb/>
you will soon be in good condition to continue with your big work<lb/>
on the history of yellow fever and other writings on malaria. I<lb/>
am ver anxiously looking forward to our chat on the Peruvian situ-<lb/>
ation and other sanitary problems when I arrive in August.</p>
<p>In regard to the cable I sent up about your money,- I<lb/>
sent this because I noticed that the exchange began rising and<lb/>
on noting this I went to see Mr. Oehmichen, the new manager of the<lb/>
Banco Mercantil Americano del Peru, <unclear>expalaining</unclear> to him the circum-<lb/>
stances of your deposit. He told me that we better arrange for au-<lb/>
thorization to convert this into dollars after the exchange had<lb/>
risen sufficiently to justify doing so. He saud that he expected<lb/>
the exchange to go up above four on account of the movement of<lb/>
cotton, sugar and some other factors which were decidedly influen-<lb/>
cing the exchange. The we in the cable was partly put in on account<lb/>
of <unclear>the</unclear> part which the <unclear>Manager</unclear> of the bank played and because in our<lb/>
code there was no code word correspoinding to the I. Yesterday the<lb/>
exchange reached 4.03 and I am quite sure that it is going still<lb/>
higher, however I will again consult my good banker friends before<lb/>
making the conversion into dollars. It is a bit difficult to do<lb/>
this because it is a sort of a gamble, and one can not tell when<lb/>
it is the safest time to make the transaction.</p>
<p>In regard to the Salubridad, I find that there is an<lb/>
enormous amount of work to be done here, some of it which can be<lb/>
done, but much of it which can not be done on account of the poli<unclear>t</unclear>ic-<lb/>
al situation and more on account of the lack of funds. What I am<lb/>
aiming to accomplish before I leave is to establish a more workable<lb/>
regulation covering the duties and relations of the M&eacute;dicos Sanitar-<lb/>
ios Departamentales, Titulares, and the Municipal Health Departments.<lb/>
Even if I do nothing else of note this will leave a very decided<lb/>
benefit for the future, because it will make possible much work which<lb/>
under existing conditions can not be done. In this I am simply using<lb/>
and coordinating what they already have, hence arousing no very great<lb/>
opposition by introducing a marked revolutionary change such as was<lb/>
the case with the proposals which Wrightson had in mind. The <unclear>Sanitaro</unclear><lb/>
with whom I have talked the matter over <unclear>are</unclear> quite thoroughly in favor<lb/>
of my plan and look upon it as opening up a possibility to them to<lb/>
do something practical. Among many other faults with the present sys-<lb/>
tem and organization, one of the most serious is that <unclear>the</unclear> men who we <unclear>o</unclear><lb/>
have have no workable regulations under which to operate.</p>
<p>Well this is just a note, it should only be about 7 or 8<lb/>
weeks until I sail, so will reserve other things for our chat in USA.</p>
<p>With the warmest regards from all the family. When Ernstina<lb/>
asks Virgil what Dr. Carter says, he (V) replies Ey, ey, ey,. I think they<lb/>
are all looking forward to seeing GrandPa Carter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>As ever yours,</salute>
<signed>Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
