<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00933007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, June 12, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Caldwell, Bert W.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00933007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-06-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Connor, M.E.</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico City (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Vera Cruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Merida (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-06-12">June 12, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00933007</idno>
<title>Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, June 12, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Caldwell agrees with Carter that there are no human carriers of yellow fever.  He discusses, in detail, his field work in Mexico.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-06-12">
<head>Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, June 12, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00933007"/>
<opener>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXICANOS<lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Teodoro C. Lyster<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Angel <unclear>Britte Vasconcelos</unclear>,<lb/>
VOCALES:<lb/>
Dr. Enrique <unclear>Osornio.</unclear><lb/>
Dr. Emmet I. Vaughn.<lb/>
Dr. Bert W. Caldwell.<lb/>
Dr. M. E. Connor.<lb/>
Dr. F. Castillo <unclear>Najera</unclear>.<lb/>
I. H. B,<lb/>
Caldwell.<lb/>
<dateline>
Vera Cruz Mexico.<lb/>
<date value="1922-06-12">June 12th, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of April twenty-fourth was read with<lb/>
the greatest interest. It cleared up several hazy points<lb/>
and the facts you present in your letter are most con-<lb/>
vincing. I could see no substantial reasons for believe-<lb/>
ing that a reservoir for yellow fever, was maintained by<lb/>
the existence of so-called &ldquo;carriers&rdquo;. The matter had<lb/>
been suggested and discussed chiefly by my Mexican col-<lb/>
leagues and your letter convinced them as it did me, of<lb/>
the distinct improbability of such a factor, as a human<lb/>
&ldquo;carrier&rdquo; of yellow fever, as we understand &ldquo;carriers&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The Medical profession in Mexico, more particularly<lb/>
those interested in Tropical Medicine, hold you in high<lb/>
esteem. That is rather a rare compliment, for the reason<lb/>
that they find their Medical dieties more among the French<lb/>
and German, and occasionally Spanish medical men.</p>
<p>Your theory of the elimination of yellow fever by<lb/>
failure of the human host has been distinctly supported by<lb/>
m<del>a</del>y experiences here in Mexico.</p>
<p>I am returning the Spanish translation on<lb/>
&ldquo;Immunity in Yellow Fever&rdquo;. I have had several typewritten<lb/>
copies made and handed to the Mexican physicians in this<lb/>
port. I did this without your permission, but felt that you<lb/>
would not object.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00933008"/>
<p>PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXICANOS<lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Teodoro C. Lyster<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Angel <unclear>Britte Vasconcelos</unclear>,<lb/>
VOCALES:<lb/>
Dr. Enrique <unclear>Osornio.</unclear><lb/>
Dr. Emmet I. Vaughn.<lb/>
Dr. Bert W. Caldwell.<lb/>
Dr. M. E. Connor.<lb/>
Dr. F. Castillo <unclear>Najera</unclear>.</p>
<p>The work in Mexico is rapidly growing to a close.<lb/>
I feel that intensive <unclear>ork</unclear> should be continued in my Zone,<lb/>
the area of most recent infection until after the present<lb/>
rainy season or until the first of January at least. There<lb/>
have been no other cases since the case at the Ingenio San<lb/>
Cristobal and I anticipate no further difficulties along<lb/>
the Papapolpoam River. I am, in addition to the regular<lb/>
brigades working there, sweeping the entire valley with a<lb/>
Brigada Volante. The second sweep will end about the last<lb/>
of this month or early in July.</p>
<p>Dr. White who has just left for Tampico with Con-<lb/>
nor, thinks that there will be no necessity for work after<lb/>
the rainy season. But I feel that aclose watch should be<lb/>
<unclear>maintined</unclear> until all danger is eliminated, so far as it is<lb/>
humanly possible to eliminate it.</p>
<p>The possibility of error in diagnosis of the San<lb/>
Ingenio case is admitted, but it is hardly probable. The<lb/>
symptoms were classical, both per se and in the sequence of<lb/>
their development and appearance. Again there were many<lb/>
others who were living in the Hacienda who exhibited no<lb/>
symptoms of the disease. The majority of these were immunes.<lb/>
The patient was a young man from Mexico City who had never<lb/>
been out of high altitudes except on one short visit to<lb/>
Tampico. He was in no possible sense immune. He came to<lb/>
an area of recent known infection by yellow fever and with<lb/>
-in less than two months was attacked by yellow fever. No<lb/>
<unclear>othr</unclear> cases were reported after his attack, for two reasons.<lb/>
Intensive anti-stegomyia work was instituted without delay,<lb/>
and the house in which he was taken ill and the adjoining<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00933009"/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXICANOS<lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Teodoro C. Lyster<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Angel <unclear>Britt Vasconcelos</unclear>,<lb/>
VOCALES:<lb/>
Dr. Enrique <unclear>Osornio.</unclear><lb/>
Dr. Emmet I. Vaughn.<lb/>
Dr. Bert W. Caldwell.<lb/>
Dr. M. E. Connor.<lb/>
Dr. F. Castillo <unclear>Najera</unclear>.<lb/>
houses were <del><unclear>s</unclear></del> fumigated. The patient him-<lb/>
self, was isolated under screen, in a two story house, which<lb/>
contained but a single room in the second story, within<lb/>
a few hours after he was attacked. I am very much<lb/>
of the opinion that had not the anti-stegomyia measures<lb/>
been promptly taken, the patient isolated, and his house<lb/>
and those adjoining, fumigated, there would have been sev-<add><unclear>eral</unclear></add><lb/>
<unclear><add><del>eral</del></add></unclear> addition<add>al</add> cases reported.</p>
<p>We know that we had the infection in San Crist-<lb/>
obal, and in the city of <unclear>Cosomolopoam</unclear> which is but 4 miles<lb/>
distant aslate as October of 1921, that Teirra Blanca<lb/>
was infected in November. Tierra Blanca is 30 miles dis-<lb/>
tant overland. That Ojitlan in Oaxaca was infected badly<lb/>
in October 1921, and is located on the Papolopoam river<lb/>
about 65 miles distant. That Cross <del><unclear>died</unclear></del><add>was infected</add> in Tuxtepec in<lb/>
Decmeber and Tuxtepec is on the Popolopoam river about<lb/>
50 miles overland, rather a longer distance by river.</p>
<p>The sugar plantations and sugar mills are<lb/>
practically continuous, with no great areas intervening<lb/>
throughout the valley of the Papolopoam, for a distance<lb/>
of 125 miles along its banks. The<del>y</del> Inge<add>n</add>ios are within<lb/>
easy walking distance from each other for the most part.<lb/>
Large numbers of laborers are imported each year from the<lb/>
States on the Mexican plateau and they bring with them<lb/>
their families, wives and children. They move from Ingen<lb/>
-io to Ingenio<del>a</del>. The movement is comparatively large, and<lb/>
in normal times has been much larger. In this manner a<lb/>
constant flow of non-immune material through out this<lb/>
valley, is maintained for several months of each year<lb/>
from the first week in January to late in June.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00933010"/>
<p>PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXICANOS<lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Teodoro C. Lyster<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
Dr. Angel <unclear>Britte Vasconcelos</unclear>,<lb/>
VOCALES:<lb/>
Dr. Enrique <unclear>Osornio.</unclear><lb/>
Dr. Emmet I. Vaughn.<lb/>
Dr. Bert W. Caldwell.<lb/>
Dr. M. E. Connor.<lb/>
Dr. F. Castillo <unclear>Najera</unclear>.</p>
<p>I have observed this area very closely for 18<lb/>
months past and I am convinced, that the City of Vera<lb/>
Cruz, has been infected from this area repeatedly and<lb/>
quite as often as from Merida. There are few phys-<lb/>
icians in the whole area, with a population of apprximat-<lb/>
ely 150 000 grouped along its banks, the Papolopoam<lb/>
has, only two graduate physicians.</p>
<p>No doubt many cases have gone unrecognised, and<lb/>
a mild epidemic could have occurred in any one of <unclear>thse</unclear><lb/>
places without being officially recognised, especially<lb/>
during the revolution, when this fertile valley was the<lb/>
rendezvous of several large outfits.</p>
<p>It is good of you to remember Mrs. Caldwell<lb/>
and our boy. You are very close to our affections..<lb/>
I had to accompany Mrs. Caldwell to the States early<lb/>
in May. She was in poor health, and she has just left<lb/>
the Hospital where her pgysicians advise me that <unclear>her</unclear><lb/>
condition is very satisfactory that there is no occasion<lb/>
for further anxiety.</p>
<p>I will join her <unclear>towards</unclear> the end of this year. I<lb/>
want very much to complete the present year in Mexico<lb/>
and at the end of that time return to the States and<lb/>
take up my work there. I have been kept rather close<lb/>
in the work here for 18 months and I am ready to <unclear>retire</unclear><lb/>
when our object is obtained.</p>
<p>I thank you for your kindness in going into<lb/>
such detailed explanation, and for your cordial expression<lb/>
for my family.</p>
<p>With every good wish, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Bert W. Caldwell</signed>
Calle Constitucion No.13<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
