<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00933019">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, June 24, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00933019</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-06-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hanson, Henry</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="place">Ylo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-06-24">June 24, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00933019</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, June 24, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter writes about the history of yellow fever in South America and his research on the subject.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-06-24">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, June 24, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00933019"/>
<opener>
Book<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1922-06-24">June 24, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hanson:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have received your long and very satisfactory letters of May 21st.<lb/>
and 29th. and will answer them Sunday when I get time. I am sending this<lb/>
because it may make a difference in catching a steamer.</p>
<p>In an old book, &ldquo;Relation du Voyage de la Mer du Sur&rdquo; by Frezier--a<lb/>
French Engineer, in 1717 (the voyage being 1712: '13 and '14) he states<lb/>
first that in 1713 there was a great drought at Ylo, Peru and they could<lb/>
only get water by burying barrels in the sand to &ldquo;receive the distalla-<lb/>
tion of the earth,&rdquo; that this water was bad and unhealthy and that to it<lb/>
was attributed the great sickness which this year destroyed more than<lb/>
half of the crews of the French vessels lying there, but--he goes on to<lb/>
say--&ldquo;this was really a species of peste which made itself felt about 18<lb/>
leagues therefrom at Moquequa and even at Arequipa--40 leagues distant.<lb/>
He does not state at what time of year this occurred, but from the drought<lb/>
it should have been the fall and winter--i. e. the hot, but not the hottest<lb/>
season (the Piura was dry from October 12th. to after Jan. 23rd. when I<lb/>
left there.</p>
<p>Occurring in the hot season would seem to eliminate dysentary: aboard<lb/>
ship as well as ashore makes us suspicious of yellow fever. I should think<lb/>
the vessels lay too far off shore for malaria. Small-pox they would have<lb/>
recognized.</p>
<p>Has Dr. Azayguirre any record of this peste--the name which, of course,<lb/>
applies to all epidemics of the time? The same man mentioned that the Dutch<lb/>
had to abandon Valdivia, which they had conquered in in 1643, on account of<lb/>
scarcity of provisions and sickness --especially the deaths of their gen-<lb/>
erals had so weakened them that they were compelled to retire, leaving bag-<lb/>
gage and connon, when they were informed of the expedition which the Vice-</p>
<pb n="2" id="f00933020"/>
<p>Vice-</p>
<p>2</p>
<p>roy was sending against them. Beranger Feraud considers this a yellow fever<lb/>
possibility. I don't. Too far South. The general tendency, however, of<lb/>
French writers is to consider every sharp epidemic in the Americas or Africa<lb/>
from Valdivia to Montreal as yellow fever.</p>
<p>The first definite absolutely reliable account that I can find of it on<lb/>
the West Coast is La Condimene's report of it at Guayaquil in 1740, which,<lb/>
he says, was &ldquo;its first visitation to this place.&rdquo; (They all say this of all<lb/>
epidemics everywhere!) &ldquo;Brought by a vessel from Panama.&rdquo; La Condimene--a<lb/>
great naturalist, as you know, had had the fever himself in 1735 in Marti-<lb/>
nique.</p>
<p>I have done a lot of digging up of old records--a lot of which are not<lb/>
medical. They date in America from Maya inscriptions to your article be-<lb/>
fore the C. Z. Medical Society and abroad from the translation of a Tamil<lb/>
MSS, alledged to be from 1500 to 3000 B. C. ascribing many diseases, in-<lb/>
cluding &ldquo;fevers and burnings&rdquo; to the &ldquo;bites of serpents and other venemous<lb/>
insects,&rdquo; among which, by name, are included scorpians and a number of mos-<lb/>
quitoes. This last, of course, does not bear on yellow fever--simply on<lb/>
the insect conveyance of disease. This has been very interesting and at<lb/>
times amusing. I have written, however, very little and this has been a<lb/>
hard and laborious grind. I do hate to write! but I judge that this will<lb/>
not be the only thing I have done that was really an onus.</p>
<p>You have done a very great work--a very great work indeed--not only in<lb/>
the number of lives saved in holding it back this year, but there was at<lb/>
least a 50% chance of it forming a permanent focus in Peru and even had<lb/>
it lasted for--say--three years the chance of reinfecting Guayaquil was<lb/>
great and preventing this should be estimated at certainly an average death<lb/>
rate of 100 per annum--and that for many years.</p>
<p>Laura, who is writing this, joins me in best remembrances to you all and<lb/>
in looking for ward to seeing you on your return.</p>
<closer>
<salute><unclear>Very Truly Yours</unclear></salute>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
