<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00930001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">South Carolina Supreme Court Decision: George D. Belton v. Wateree Power Company, April 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00930001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-04-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Wateree River, Fairfield Country (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Fairfield Country (S.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>15 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-04-00">April 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00930001</idno>
<title>South Carolina Supreme Court Decision: George D. Belton v. Wateree Power Company, April 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This opinion discusses a case in which a power company has been sued by a farmer for building a dam. This dam damaged his farm land and created stagnant pools where malarial mosquitoes breed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-04-00">
<head>South Carolina Supreme Court Decision: George D. Belton v. Wateree Power Company, April 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00930001"/>
<p><unclear>Inf'd watere<lb/>
Wateree</unclear></p>
<p>THE STATE OF SOUTH CAROLINA,<lb/>
IN THE SUPREME COURT<lb/>
FAIRFIELD COUNTY<lb/>
APRIL TERM 1922.<lb/>
NO. 131.</p>
<p>George D. Belton,</p>
<p>Respondent,</p>
<p>against</p>
<p>Wateree Power Co.</p>
<p>Appellant.</p>
<p>OPINION</p>
<p>Cothran, A. J.</p>
<p>Action for $2,000.00 damages on account of injury al-<lb/>
leged to have been sustained by the erection of a certain dam<lb/>
across the Wateree or Catawba River at Getty's Shoals. It is al-<lb/>
leged that the dam raised the water in the channel of the river<lb/>
and the streams, ditches, drains and hollows upon the plaintiffs<lb/>
land, throwing it back upon the bottom 1 and, obstructing the<lb/>
natural drainage and injuring it for agricultural purposes; and<lb/>
that the back water caused the formation of pools and stagnant<lb/>
water on or near plaintiff's land, providing a breeding place for<lb/>
mosquitoes of the malaria bearing species, which have caused the<lb/>
tenants upon the place to become sick, thereby creating health<lb/>
conditions which render the land unfit for residential purposes<lb/>
and greatly depreciating its value.</p>
<p>From a judgment in favor of the plaintiff the defendant<lb/>
has appealed.</p>
<p>There was no evidence at all, tending to sustain the<lb/>
allegation of injury to the plaintiff's land by back water upon<lb/>
his bottoms. He lived about a mile and a half from the pond and<lb/>
the nearest point on his land was half a mile from the pond. He<lb/>
testified: &ldquo;I have some bottom <unclear>land</unclear> on all the creeks. There has<lb/>
been no water on it, no more than where you come to these big rains<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00930002"/>
and the creek could overflow. <hi>It does not overflow now, not more<lb/>
than when the pond was not there.</hi>&rdquo; So that his case is to be con-<lb/>
sidered with reference only to the allegation that the pond caused<lb/>
stagnant pools which breed malarial mosquitoes, causing sickness,<lb/>
the removal of his tenants, and consequent depreciation of the<lb/>
value of his land.</p>
<p>One of the plaintiff's witnesses testified that he had<lb/>
made a careful investigation and search for the malaria bearing<lb/>
mosquitoes about plaintiff's premises, found practically none in<lb/>
the pond, but &ldquo;we went to the spring about 150 yards north of the<lb/>
house, and in this branch we found mosquitoes. The anopheles<lb/>
(malaria bearing) <hi>mosquitoes breeding in profusion.</hi>&rdquo; (Dr. Hamilton)<lb/>
Other witnesses gave testimony tending to show that the pond grea-<lb/>
ly increased the prevalence of mosquitoes in the immediate locality<lb/>
and in this discussion that fact may be assumed. That the preva-<lb/>
lence of the pest was not confined to the plaintiff's premises but<lb/>
extended generally to all within a radius of a mile and a half from<lb/>
the pond, is shown by the testimony of the witnesses for the plain-<lb/>
tiff: <hi>Dave Robertson:</hi> &ldquo;After the dam was closed and the pond put<lb/>
there, there was plenty of chills and fever. <hi>It was from house to<lb/>
House&rdquo;:</hi> that he lived one and one half miles from plaintiff and<lb/>
had malaria after the pond was created, tho' had had none before;<lb/>
That John Belton, a mile away, also had had sickness. Major Bush<lb/>
lived three quarters of a mile from plaintiff, and had had it under<lb/>
similar circumstances; had heard of several others in the neighbor-<lb/>
hood being taken sick. <hi>A. W. Mathewson:</hi> &ldquo;Knew of other cases of<lb/>
<hi>malaria all around down there everywhere&rdquo;:</hi> He lived a mile from the<lb/>
pond, and had chills and fever on his place; never heard of malaria<lb/>
there before the pond was there; that parties living on the highest<lb/>
hills in Fairfield County, were having chills on the longtown road<lb/>
two miles from his house; heard different ones say that they could<lb/>
hardly rest at night for mosquitoes. Dr. Douglass; Had been going<lb/>
down there since 1919 when dam<del><unclear>a</unclear></del> was closed treating malaria. The<lb/>
question put to Dr. Douglass by the attorneys for the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00930003"/>
-3-<lb/>
plaintiff indicate their conception of the situation. &ldquo;If you had<lb/>
found down on this river before the pond was put there that there<lb/>
was very little malaria, and that malaria was only occasional on<lb/>
the river, and after this immense pond was put there <hi>you found all<lb/>
the neighborhood had malaria</hi>, what <unclear>would</unclear> you say caused it.&rdquo; &ldquo;If<lb/>
you find a large area of water like they have out here on the Water<lb/>
ee River when that pond is up, malaria is prevalent, <hi>everybody in<lb/>
the neighborhood having</hi> it one year when the pond is up, the whole<lb/>
region around there is flooded, etc.&rdquo; <hi>Dr. Hamilton:</hi> <del><unclear>&ldquo;</unclear></del> A portion<lb/>
of that section lies along the pond. Its proximity <hi>extends as far<lb/>
back as eight miles</hi> of the pond on the branches and creeks running<lb/>
in and out of the pond. Malaria was prevalent there last year.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The testimony for the plaintiff thus showing that the<lb/>
activities and effects of the mosquitoes were not confined to the<lb/>
premises of the plaintiff, but were prevalent in that whole com-<lb/>
munity, it has been <unclear>emonstrated</unclear> that the damage suffered by the<lb/>
plaintiff was not peculiar to himself. It shows that the nuisance<lb/>
was a public nuisance and not a private nuisance, and the law is<lb/>
well settled that the plaintiff is not entitled to damages for an<lb/>
injury resulting from a public nuisance unless his injury is not<lb/>
only different in degree but different in kind from that suffered<lb/>
by the public generally, or that the nuisance has been caused by<lb/>
the negligent conduct of the defendant.</p>
<p>The following principles have been established beyond<lb/>
controversy:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. If the act claimed to have been noxious to the plaintiff<lb/>
was authorized by the Legislature, it cannot be considered a pub-<lb/>
lic nuisance, and the plaintiff can recover damages only upon the<lb/>
theory that the injury was caused by the negligent exercise of that<lb/>
legally authorized act. Wallace v. R. Co. 34 S. C. 62.</item>
<item>2. If the act claimed to have been noxious to the plain-<lb/>
tiff constituted a public nuisance, the plaintiff can recover<lb/>
damages only upon the theory that the injury sustained by him was<lb/>
different not only in degree but in kind, from that suffered<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00930004"/>
<unclear>-4-</unclear><lb/>
by the public generally.</item>
<item>3. If the act claimed to have been noxious to the plain-<lb/>
tiff resulted in an injury peculair to him, some special inconven-<lb/>
ience or discomfort not experienced by the public at large, the<lb/>
defendant cannot invoke the protection of any statute purporting<lb/>
to authorize the act, for it would be in violation of the Consti-<lb/>
tution which forbids the taking of private property for public use<lb/>
without just compensation.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The case of Richards v. Washington Terminal Co., 233<lb/>
U. S. 546, is an exceedingly interesting one, and particularly in-<lb/>
structive in the present emergency, for the reason that it contains<lb/>
a clear differentiation between items of damage common to the pub-<lb/>
lic generally, and those peculiar in kind suffered by the plaintiff<lb/>
the complaint claiming damages on account of such. The facts<lb/>
were as follows:</p>
<p>The Terminal Company owned the tunnel which extends<lb/>
from one side of Washington to the other, passing under the Capitol<lb/>
and the Library grounds<unclear>,</unclear> It also owned the double track therein,<lb/>
its ownership of it ceasing at the south portal or north of the<lb/>
tunnel. The tunnel and tracks were built upon property acquired<lb/>
by purchase or condemnation proceedings and were constructed under<lb/>
authority of the Acts of Congress and of permits issued by the<lb/>
municipal authorities. The plaintiff owned a house a little over<lb/>
100 feet from the south portal of the tunnel. His action was: (1)<lb/>
For the injury to his premises by the volumes of dense black or<lb/>
gray smoke, and also by dust and dirt, cinders and gases <hi>emitted<lb/>
from the trains while passing over the tracks</hi> in and out of the<lb/>
tunnel, or standing upon the tracks near the signal tower. (2)<lb/>
For the injury to his premises by the gases and smoke emitted from<lb/>
locomotive engines <hi>while in the tunnel and forced out of it by<lb/>
means of the fanning system</hi> through the portal located near to<lb/>
plaintiff's Property.</p>
<p>As to the first ground of alleged damage the Court held<lb/>
that the plaintiff <hi>was not</hi> entitled to recover, declaring:</p>
<pb n="5" id="f00930005"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Acts of Congress referred to, followed by the construc-<lb/>
tion of the tunnel and railroad tracks substantially in the mode<lb/>
prescribed, had the effect of legalizing the construction and opera-<lb/>
tion of the railroad, so that is operations <hi>while properly <unclear>conducted</unclear><lb/>
and regulated</hi> cannot be deemed to be a public nuisance. x x x x<lb/>
Railroads constructed and operated for the public use, altho' with<lb/>
private capitol and for private gain, are not subject to actions<lb/>
in behalf of neighboring property owners for the ordinary damages<lb/>
attributable to the <hi>operation of the railroad in the absence of ne-</hi><lb/>
gligence. Such roads are treated as public highways and the pro-<lb/>
prietors as public servants, with the exemption normally enjoyed<lb/>
by such servants from liability to private suit, as far as concerns<lb/>
<hi>the incidental damages accruing to owners of non-adjacent land thro-</hi><lb/>
gh the proper and skillful management and operation of the rail-<lb/>
roads. Any diminuition of the value of property not directly in-<lb/>
vaded nor peculiary affected, but sharing in the common burden of<lb/>
incidental damages arising from the legalized nuisance, is held not<lb/>
to be a &lsquo;taking&rsquo;, within the constitutional provision. The immu-<lb/>
nity is limited to much damages as naturally and unavoidably re-<lb/>
sult from the proper conduct of the <unclear>roadsand</unclear> are shared generally<lb/>
by property owners whose lands lie within range of the inconven--<lb/>
iences necessarily incident to proximity to a railroad. It includes<lb/>
the noises and vibrations incident to the running of trains, the<lb/>
necessary emission of smoke and sparks from the locomotives, and<lb/>
similar annoyances <unclear>inseparable</unclear> from the normal and non-negligent<lb/>
operation of a railroad. &ldquo;x x x&rdquo; That the constitutional inhibition<lb/>
against the taking of private property for public use without<lb/>
compensation does not confer a right to compensation upon a land-<lb/>
owner no part of whose property has been actually appropriated, and<lb/>
who has sustained only those consequential damages that are neces-<lb/>
sarily incident to proximity to the railroad.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As to the second ground of alleged damage the Court held<lb/>
that the plaintiff <hi>was</hi> entitled to recover, that is, for the dam-<lb/>
ages caused by the gases and smoke emitted from engines while in<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f00930006"/>
-6-<lb/>
the tunnel, and forced out of it by means of the fanning system<lb/>
through the portal located practically at the plaintiff's door.<lb/>
The basis of the liability was distinctly placed upon the fact<lb/>
that the plaintiff had suffered special inconvenience and dis-<lb/>
comfort, a burden direct, not experienced by the public at large<lb/>
and unnecessarily imposed. The Court cites and relies upon the<lb/>
case of B &amp; P R. R. Co. vs Baptist Churcy, 108 U. S. 317, and<lb/>
says, commenting on it: &ldquo;While recognizing that the legislative<lb/>
authority for operating a railway carried with it an immunity to<lb/>
private action based upon those incidental inconveniences that<lb/>
are unavoidably attendant upon the operation of a railroad, never-<lb/>
the <unclear>les</unclear> (the Court) sustained the right of action in a case where a<lb/>
building for hous<del>e</del>ing and repairing engines was unnecessarily es-<lb/>
tablished in close proximity to a place of public worship&rdquo;, so that<lb/>
the noise and other incidents of its operation created a constant<lb/>
disburbance of the religious services. The reasoning of the Court<lb/>
is not quite clear upon the element of necessity. They say that<lb/>
the doctrine of immunity <hi>being founded upon necessity</hi> is limited ac<lb/>
cordingly, and quote from the <hi>Baptist Church</hi> case in which the li-<lb/>
ability is apparently placed upon the fact that it was not neces-<lb/>
sary that the house be placed in that exact location; and at the<lb/>
same time declare that &ldquo;this circumstance, however, does not as we<lb/>
think afford sufficient ground for a distinction affecting the re-<lb/>
sult.&rdquo; The necessary effect of this ruling is to relegate both<lb/>
cases to the common ground of a direct, peculiar and substantial<lb/>
burden imposed upon the plaintiff, not experienced by the public at<lb/>
large.</p>
<p>The Court further declares:</p>
<p>&ldquo;If the damage (that is, I assume, the damage of a direct,<lb/>
peculiar and substantial burden) is not preventable by the em-<lb/>
ployment of reasonable expense of devices such as have been sug-<lb/>
gested (the installation of ventilating shafts or other devices<lb/>
&lsquo;for preventing the outpouring of gasses and smoke <hi>from the entire<lb/>
length of the tunnel at a single point</hi> upon the surface&rsquo; which con-<lb/>
stituted a direct, peculiar and substantial injury of the plain-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f00930007"/>
-7-<lb/>
tiff), then plaintiff's property is necessary for the purpose con-<lb/>
templated and may be acquired by purchase or condemnation, and <unclear>pend</unclear>-<lb/>
ind its acquisition defendant is responsible. If the damage is read<lb/>
ily preventible, the statute furnishes no excuse and the defendants'<lb/>
responsibility follows on general principles; a declaration entirely<lb/>
true if the injury to the plaintiff was the result of the nuisance,<lb/>
direct, peculiar and substantial, but not at all applicable if the<lb/>
injury was the result of a public nuisance legalized by the <unclear>et</unclear>, as<lb/>
the Court had already determined in <unclear>refeence</unclear> to the alleged ground<lb/>
of damage founded upon the &ldquo;volumes of dense black or gray smoke<lb/>
and the dust and dirt, cinders and gases emitted from the trains<lb/>
while passing over the tracks in and out of the tunnel, or standing<lb/>
upon the tracks near the signal tower.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This is in entire accord with the decisions of this Court</p>
<p>In Steemboat Co v. R. C 46 S. C. 327, the Court re-<lb/>
affirmed the following quotation from Steamboat Co. v. R. Co. 30 S.<lb/>
C. <unclear>539</unclear>:</p>
<p>&ldquo;What the injury must be particular, as several of the<lb/>
cases express it, special or peculiar --<hi>must result directly from<lb/>
the obstruction (nuisance) and not as a secondary consequence there<lb/>
of</hi>, and must differ in kind not merely in extent or degree, from<lb/>
that which the general public sustains&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In Cherry vs Hook Hill 488 S.C. <unclear>553</unclear>, which was an ac-<lb/>
tion by an individual for damages on account of an alleged nuisance,<lb/>
the Court said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;As there is no allegation in the complaint that the<lb/>
plaintiff by reason of the acts of the defendant, <hi>has sustained any<lb/>
or peculiar injury, differing in kind from that which the public<lb/>
generally has sustained</hi>, it is abvious that the complaint fails to<lb/>
state facts sufficient to constitute a cause of action either for<lb/>
an injunction or for damages.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In Baltze-ger v. R. Co. 54 S. C. 242, it is held that a<lb/>
complaint for nuisance alleging no damages special or peculiar to<lb/>
plaintiff as distinguised from those sustained by the general pub-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f00930008"/>
-8-<lb/>
lic does not state a cause of action. In a very clear opinion by<lb/>
the present Chief Justice, it is shown that the test of a public<lb/>
nuisance is not the number of persons annoyed, but the possibility<lb/>
of annoyance to the public by invasion of its rights, the fact<lb/>
that it is in a public place and annoying to all who come within<lb/>
its sphere. In that case the plaintiff claimed that the act of the<lb/>
defendant in obstruction the flow of surface water, and causing<lb/>
an accumulation thereof, rendered his dwelling unhealthy and dan-<lb/>
gerous to live in and caused sickness and suffering to his family;<lb/>
it was held not an allegation of injury peculiar to himself, dif-<lb/>
ferent in kind from that suffered by the public.</p>
<p>In Manson v R. Co 64 S. C120, which <unclear>as</unclear> an action to<lb/>
enjoin the Seaboard Airline from destroying Sidney Park in the<lb/>
City of Columbia and converting it into a railroad yard, it was held<lb/>
that as the plaintiff was not an abutting owner and could not show<lb/>
that he had sustained injury different in kind from that which<lb/>
might reasonably be expected to be suffered by those &ldquo;<hi>in the neigh-<lb/>
borhood&rdquo;</hi>, altho differing in degree, he had no <hi>locus standi</hi>. The<lb/>
present Chief Justice cited in support of the Court's conclusion the<lb/>
<hi>Cherry</hi> case. High on Inj. section 1298-1301, 10 A &amp; E Enc. Pl. &amp; Pr<lb/>
897-900. In the last named authority it is said, (quoted by the<lb/>
Court):</p>
<p>&ldquo;A private individual is a proper party plaintiff where<lb/>
the injuries which he will sustain are special and particular, dif-<lb/>
fering in kind and not merely in degree from those which the pub-<lb/>
lic at large will suffer&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In McMeekin v. Power Co. 80 S. C. 512 the Court says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The obstruction of a navigable stream is a public nuisance<lb/>
and the remedy is by indictment unless the person instituting pro-<lb/>
ceedings on the civil side of the Court can show special or pecu-<lb/>
liar damages differing in kind from those to which all others in com-<lb/>
mon with him are exposed&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In Gray v. R. Co. 81 S. C <unclear>380</unclear>, it is said:</p>
<p>&ldquo; The exception to the rule (that an indictment is the<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f00930009"/>
-9-<lb/>
remedy for a public nuisance) is that a private citizen may main-<lb/>
tain a civil action for damages or abatement with respect to a<lb/>
public nuisance upon allegations and proof of such construction<lb/>
and of direct and special damages resulting to him, different in<lb/>
kind from what the public may sustain.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In the <hi>Baptist Church</hi> case, supra, it is declared:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Legislative authorization exempts only from lia-<lb/>
bility to suite civil or criminal, at the instance of the state:<lb/>
it does not affect any claim of a private citizen for damages for<lb/>
any special inconvenience or discomfort not experienced by the<lb/>
public at large.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I do not agree with the declaration of the learned<lb/>
Chief Justice:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the first place, it will be observed that the pro-<lb/>
vision as to condemnation proceedings in <hi>mandatory</hi>.&rdquo; I do not<lb/>
find any <unclear>warrent</unclear> for this position in the act of Charter, nor<lb/>
do I see the pertinency of the observation. Unquestionably, the de-<lb/>
fendant could acquire all rights necessary for its purpose by <hi>pur-<lb/>
chase</hi> as well as <hi>condemnation.</hi> If the observation was intended sim-<lb/>
ply as limiting the power of acquisition either by purchase or con-<lb/>
demnation, to those rights necessary for the corporate purposes of<lb/>
the defendant, I thoroughly agree. The remainder of the paragraph<lb/>
is subject ot the explanation of a similar statement given above in<lb/>
the <hi>Richards</hi> case; it is entirely true, if the injury to the plain-<lb/>
tiff was the result of a private nuisance, or a public nuisance<lb/>
when the injury was direct, peculiar and substantial, but not at all<lb/>
applicable if the injury was the result of a public nuisance, legal-<lb/>
ized by the act, where the injury to the plaintiff was not direct,<lb/>
peculiar and substantial, differing in kind, etc.</p>
<p>To hold that the duty to condemn the right of the plain-<lb/>
tiff to be free from mosquitoes, appears to me to be an assumption<lb/>
of the very point in controversy, the character of the alleged nui-<lb/>
sance is private, or as public with special injury to the plain-<lb/>
tiff; and to annihilate the policy which prescribes an <unclear>indictment</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f00930010"/>
as the appropriate remedy in order to avoid a multiplicity of suits<lb/>
at the instance of individuals sustaining a common injury. If<lb/>
the duty was mandatory, so far as the plaintiff is concerned, why is<lb/>
it not so in reference to each individual residing within the mos-<lb/>
quito zone of from one and one half to eight miles in diameter, af-<lb/>
fected as the plaintiff was. The multitude of such individuals,<lb/>
as shown by the plaintiff's evidence, is conclusive proof of the<lb/>
fact that the injury to the plaintiff was not of that direct, pe-<lb/>
culiar and substantial character from which the public generally has<lb/>
not suffered.</p>
<p>In Haggard v. Stehlin (Ind) 22 L. R. A. 577, it is <unclear>held</unclear>,<lb/>
quoting from Wood and Nuisance, sections 645 and 646:</p>
<p>&ldquo;No person can maintain a private action for a mere pub-<lb/>
lic or common nuisance, for the reason that the exercise of such<lb/>
a right would lead to a multiplicity of suits and endless intermi-<lb/>
nable litigation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am not sufficiently informed as to the habits of the<lb/>
anopheles quadrimaculatus or punctipennis (the malaria bearing<lb/>
mosquitoes) to know whether or not their breeding is a necessary<lb/>
incident of the creation of such a pond of water, as in this case.<lb/>
There is testimony tending to show that there is less likelihood<lb/>
of such an event in such a pond than in small stagnant pools.<lb/>
But assuming that is is incidental, the incident has been authorized<lb/>
by the Act of the Legislature and cannot be considered a public<lb/>
nuisance subjecting the <unclear>doneee</unclear> of <add>the</add> power to indictment; and the<lb/>
plaintiff has no private cause of action without showing either<lb/>
that the authority conferred has been so negligently exercised as<lb/>
to produce the nuisance, or that his injury has been peculiar in<lb/>
kind to himself. The attorneys for the plaintiff appear to have<lb/>
recognized the obligation of alleging negligence, for the complaint<lb/>
abounds in virulent expressions of such a delict, with vituperative<lb/>
epithets. Their evidence is entirely lacking to support them, As<lb/>
Judge <unclear>Memminger</unclear> remarked upon occasion: &ldquo;The force and vigor of<lb/>
the war has fallen short of the fine phrases of the manifesto&rdquo;.<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f00930011"/>
-11-<lb/>
Not only this, but the testimony, so far from showing an injury<lb/>
peculiar to the plaintiff, was abundant that the whole neighborhood<lb/>
for miles around was similarly affected: &ldquo;a vaulting ambition that<lb/>
o'erleaps itself and falls on t'other side&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seems to me that the <hi>Wallace</hi> case 34 S. C. 62 is con-<lb/>
clusive of the one proposition and the Baltzeger case 54 S. C. 242<lb/>
of the other.</p>
<p>In the <hi>Wallace</hi> case it was held that in an action against<lb/>
a railroad company for damage done to plaintiff's land, through<lb/>
which the railroad company had acquired a right of way, by he ob-<lb/>
struction of a stream, the complaint failed to state sufficient<lb/>
facts, in not alleging negligent construction of the road <unclear>bed</unclear>.<lb/>
&ldquo;There must be some allegations of fact showing that the defendant<lb/>
in doing the act which it was authorized to do has either <unclear>want only</unclear><lb/>
or through negligence done the act in such a manner as unnecessarily<lb/>
impaired or injured the rights of the plaintiff&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The Baltzeger case has already been referred to.</p>
<p>In Lumpley v. R. Co 71 S. C. 156 it is held that a rail-<lb/>
road company having obtained a right of way had the right to ob-<lb/>
struct water courses and is not liable to a land owner for flooding<lb/>
his land in the absence of evidence showing a negligent construction;<lb/>
following the Wallace case.</p>
<p>&ldquo; When a railroad company under the statutes, has a right<lb/>
to construct its railroad, and has entered with the expressed or<lb/>
implied permission of the owner, it is not liable as a trespasser<lb/>
to adjacent owners, under the common law, for the act and result<lb/>
of construction with due care, since the law will not declare that<lb/>
to be a nuisance or trespass which it has authorized. Johnson vs.<lb/>
R. C. 71 S. C. 241.</p>
<p>In Lawton v. Ry. Co., 75 S. C. 82, the action was for<lb/>
the <hi>negligent</hi> construction of an embankment across a water course in<lb/>
consequence of which the plaintiff's Lands were injured. So were<lb/>
Jones v. R. C, 76 S. C. 181. Free v. Parr Shoals C. 111 S. C.<lb/>
192.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f00930012"/>
<p>-12-</p>
<p>-----------------------------</p>
<p>Another consideration is, I think, decisive of the ap-<lb/>
peal: Upon the facts of the case developed by the testimony for<lb/>
the plaintiff alone, he was entitled only to a recovery of compen-<lb/>
sation under condemnation proceedings and not to an action for dam-<lb/>
ages.</p>
<p>There was an allegation of negligent construction but no<lb/>
evidence of it. It would be assumed then that the cause of the<lb/>
plaintiff's injury was incidental to the exercise of the defendant's<lb/>
legal authority to construct the dam and impound the water, and with<lb/>
out negligence on its part. If so, the plaintiff's cause of action<lb/>
was for compensation under the statute, regardless of the fact that<lb/>
the injury may have been peculiar to him, in the sense above indicated.</p>
<p>Of course, if the injury resulted from a cause not <unclear>inci-<lb/>
dental</unclear> to the legally authorized construction, and constituted a<lb/>
public nuisance, the defendant could claim no protection for the<lb/>
Act of Charter, so far as relieving it from the charge of creating<lb/>
a nuisance is concerned; and in that event the plaintiff would be<lb/>
entitled to recover from an injury peculiar to himslef; or if the<lb/>
works were negligently constructed, he would be entitled to recover,<lb/>
regardless of whether or not the cause was a public nuisance or the<lb/>
injury peculiar to himself.</p>
<p>But when it appears, as I think it does, that the works<lb/>
were authorized by statute, and therefore not a public nuisance,<lb/>
and that the cause of injury was incidental to the construction, and<lb/>
therefore a necessary, in-evitable result of it, I think that the<lb/>
authorities in this state are conclusive of the proposition that the<lb/>
plaintiff's only remedy was under the condemnation statute.</p>
<p>The rule, <unclear>as</unclear> established by the decisions of this Court, is,<lb/>
that where the right of condemnation exists and the corporation takes<lb/>
possession of the property of another, without the consent of the<lb/>
owner, express or implied or by <unclear>condemnation,</unclear> it becomes a trespas-<lb/>
ser; and that while it may be made liable in damages for such un-<lb/>
authorized entry, it may not be ejected as are ordinary trespassers;<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f00930013"/>
-13-<lb/>
that having the right to take the property under condemnation, it<lb/>
may retain possession upon payment of due compensation to the<lb/>
owner for the taking. Cayce Land Co. v. R. C. 111 S. C. 115<lb/>
Ingleside C. v. Light &amp; Power Co., 76 S. C. 95</p>
<p>But where the entry has been <unclear>made</unclear> with the consent of the<lb/>
owner, express or implied, the owner's remdey is exclusively under<lb/>
the condemnation statute. In the former case the compensation is<lb/>
ascertained under the statute, if the right to compensation is ad-<lb/>
mitted; or by an action for damages, if it is denied. In the lat-<lb/>
ter case, the remedy under the statute is exclusive.</p>
<p>In the case at bar there has been no entry upon the pro-<lb/>
perty of the plaintiff; the damage, if any is shown to have been en-<lb/>
tirely consequential from a lawful entry upon other lands as to<lb/>
which the plaintiff was not required to be consulted.</p>
<p>If it should be held, nevertheless, that this presents a<lb/>
case of entry, where the plaintiff would be entitled to damages, if<lb/>
there has been an entry without his consent, the evidence shown as<lb/>
strongly as it does in the <hi>Leitzsey</hi> case, that the plaintiff was<lb/>
fully aware of the developement and made no objection; in fact he<lb/>
conveyed to the defendant a part of his land which was to be flood-<lb/>
ed by the dam; and that therefore his consent will be implied.</p>
<p>In the case of <unclear>Leitzey v.</unclear> Water Power Co., 47 S. C. 464,<lb/>
affirming and followed by other cases, the plaintiff owned land on<lb/>
the west side of and adjacent to Broad River; the defendant was<lb/>
authorized by its charter, or that of its predecessor, to erect a<lb/>
dam across the river for the purpose of developing the canal; the<lb/>
water was raised six feet in the channel, thereby obstructing<lb/>
the flow, preventing the usual drainage of the lands, causing fre-<lb/>
quent overflows and the destruction of his crops. The Power Com-<lb/>
pany was authorized to condemn rights of way necessary for its<lb/>
purpose. The plaintiff-brought an action for damages and the de-<lb/>
fendant demurred upon the ground that the remedy under condemnation<lb/>
proceedings was exclusive, there being no allegation that the dam<lb/>
was negligently constructed. The demurrer was sustained by the Cir-<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f00930014"/>
-14-<lb/>
cuit Judge and on appeal his order was affirmed by this Court.<lb/>
There it appeared that the nuisance was a private one, affecting the<lb/>
the plaintiff peculiarly; but the Court held that the remedy under<lb/>
under the statute was exclusive; a much stronger case for the plain-<lb/>
tiff than the case at bar, where the nuisance was a <hi>public one</hi> and<lb/>
the plaintiff <hi>not</hi> peculiarly effected. There can arise no question<lb/>
of the plaintiff being deprived of his property without compensation<lb/>
as the Court very clerely shows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of course the permission granted by plaintiff to the<lb/>
board of trustees to enter for the construction of the dam and ap-<lb/>
purtenances (a permission, I will add, which arose by implication<lb/>
only, as it does in the case at bar) did not deprive the plaintiff<lb/>
of his constitutional right of compensation, for which a <hi>remedy<lb/>
was provided</hi>: it simply relieved the board of trustees so entering<lb/>
from the charter (imputation) of trespassers. Tompkins v. R. Co.<lb/>
21 S. C. 431. Neither is the defendant granted a trespasser for con<lb/>
tinuing the use. &ldquo;<hi>The remedy provided by the statute is exclusive.</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
Citing McLaughlin v. R. Co., 5 Rich. 584; Fuller v. Eddings, 11 Ric<lb/>
239; Verdier v. R. Co., 15 S. C. 483; Sams v. R. Co., 15 <unclear>S. C.</unclear> 487;<lb/>
Ross v. R. C., 33 S. C. 477, See also Touchberry v. R. Co., 83<lb/>
S. C. 315.</p>
<p>In Garraux v. Greenville, 53 S. C. 575, it is held; citing<lb/>
the <hi>Leightsey</hi> case:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In reference to the remedy for compensation for right of<lb/>
way provided by statute, this Court has repeatedly held that such<lb/>
remedy is exclusive&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In Rankin v. R. Co., 58 S. C. 532, it is held:</p>
<p>A Railroad corporation, chartered under the laws of this<lb/>
State, and authorized to construct a railroad, is not a trespasser<lb/>
for entry upon lands for the purpose of such construction, unless<lb/>
such entry is made without the consent of the owner, and it is neces<lb/>
sary to the cause of action to allege the absence of such consent.<lb/>
Tompkins v. R. R., 37 S. C. 382. The complaint, then, is fatally de-<lb/>
fective for failure to make such allegation. So far as the com-<lb/>
plaint shows, the only objection ever made by plaintiff was as to<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f00930015"/>
-15-<lb/>
cutting down two oaks, and it appears that they were not cut down.<lb/>
As the route of the railroad was very near plaintiff's dwelling, she<lb/>
must have had knowledge of the first entry for construction, and<lb/>
having made no objection thereto in the manner required by statute,<lb/>
her consent would be <unclear>precumde</unclear>, and her only remedy would be for com-<lb/>
pensation under the condemnation statutes."</p>
<p>In Johnson v. R. Co., 71 S. C. 241, it is held:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In all cases, except where the right to compensation is<lb/>
disputed or where the owner has not actually or constructively per-<lb/>
mitted the entry for construction, the remedy afforded by the con-<lb/>
demnation statute is exclusive.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As a matter of supreme public concern the affirmance of<lb/>
this judgment, opening the floodgates of litigation, will not only<lb/>
bankrupt the useful instutions which mark the progress of this<lb/>
State, but will bar for ever the development of millions of horse-<lb/>
power in the streams that now &ldquo;run want on to the sea&rdquo;.</p>
<p>For these reasons I think that the judgment should be<lb/>
reversed. And it is so ordered.</p>
<p>We concur:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>J. H. Marion, A. J.</item>
<item>R. W. Meinminger, Circuit Judge.</item>
<item>J. W. DeVore, Circuit Judge.</item>
<item>S. W. G. Shipp, Circuit Judge.</item>
<item>T. S. Sease, Circuit Judge.</item>
<item>Jas. E. Peurifoy, Circuit Judge.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
