<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00934024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter to Wickliffe Rose, July 22, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00934024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-07-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="place">Curacao</name>
<name type="place">Trinidad</name>
<name type="place">Barbados</name>
<name type="place">French Antilles</name>
<name type="place">Amazon Valley</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Rico</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Venezuela</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Bogota (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Coro (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Manaos (Brazil)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-07-22">July 22, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00934024</idno>
<title>Letter to Wickliffe Rose, July 22, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The writer makes recommendations concerning how the International Health Board should handle inquiries concerning the status of yellow fever in various South American countries.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-07-22">
<head>Letter to Wickliffe Rose, July 22, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00934024"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Wateree, S. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1922-07-22">July 22/22.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Wickliffe Rose, General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway,<lb/>
New York, N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In answer to your letter of the 12th. inst., relative to the gen-<lb/>
eral yellow fever situation, I would say:</p>
<p>That I am inclined to think it advisable to send a letter of in-<lb/>
quiry in the early part of next year to the Health Authorities of the re-<lb/>
gions which we are not sure are free from yellow fever.</p>
<p>The only objection I can see to so doing would be if the Board were<lb/>
unwilling in any case to accept a negative reply to this question as<lb/>
final--i. e. if even with such a reply it should desire to make further<lb/>
investigation. In that case it might <add>be</add> embarrassing to ask permission to<lb/>
do this after a negative reply had been received. The regions in the<lb/>
Americas you mention as not certainly free from yellow fever are those<lb/>
immediately south of the Caribbean and the Amazon Valley--the latter<lb/>
doubtless including Para, its sea-port.</p>
<p>I think that with the first it would be well to write also to the<lb/>
islands in close travel relation with this coast--Curacao: Trinidad:<lb/>
Barbadoes and the French Antilles: (1) Because they naturally form a<lb/>
part of the same focus as the eastern Caribbean litoral; and (2), and<lb/>
more important, from them one should hear of yellow fever in the ports<lb/>
of the mainland if it exists there.</p>
<p>For the last reason, I would also suggest that the U. S. Quarantine<lb/>
Officers at Porto Rico and at Colon be asked for such information as they<lb/>
may have of <unclear>Venezuelan</unclear> and Colombian ports respectively. These letters<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00934025"/>
2.<lb/>
letters<lb/>
it would be well to send before the end of this year so as to have this<lb/>
information before writing the formal letters to the countries on the main-<lb/>
land.</p>
<p>To give the detail reasons for this opinion: (1) I would accept<lb/>
negative reports at their face value from the health authorities of Dutch:<lb/>
British or French colonies--island and mainland. Indeed, the French will<lb/>
be more apt to report a mild yellow fever where none exists than the con-<lb/>
trary.</p>
<p>(2) Similarly for a negative report from the Central Health Office<lb/>
of Colombia, unless contradicted by the Quarantine Office at Colon.</p>
<p>Colombia's communication with infected places has been almost nil.<lb/>
Her coast towns have been so long without any considerable amount of<lb/>
yellow fever that if it occurred in them there would be a number of cases--<lb/>
possibly a small epidemic--and hence recognized and known both to Bogota<lb/>
and to Colon.</p>
<p>(3) I am inclined to think the same credence should be given to a<lb/>
negative report from Venezuela. On this, however, I would be glad to<lb/>
have the opinion of Dr. Guiteras, as he was in Venezuela for much of 1917<lb/>
working at Coro and elsewhere, and his judgement on this matter should<lb/>
be worth more than mine.</p>
<p>I would say here that I do not question the good faith of the Central<lb/>
Health Officers of either Colombia or Venezuela, but I am doubtful of the<lb/>
results of their investigations of reports of yellow fever. In 1916 we<lb/>
found that the error of both had been on the side of reporting yellow<lb/>
fever where none existed: as at Puerto Berrios: the Mines of Muso: Car-<lb/>
tagena: Caracas and near Maracay, rather than the reverse. I do not know<lb/>
the official history of the yellow fever which Guiteras saw at Coro in 1917.</p>
<p>On the other hand, I do not think the <hi>Port</hi> Authorities of Colombia<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00934026"/>
3.<lb/>
Colombia<lb/>
would report yellow fever if they thought (1) that it would lead to quar-<lb/>
antine by Colon and (2) if it could be concealed. The same has been true<lb/>
habitually of cities in the U. S.</p>
<p>(4) In 1916 we accepted somewhat similar evidence for the non-exist-<lb/>
ence of yellow fever in the Amazon Valley. Not quite the same, however,<lb/>
as the official statement was supplemented by the inquiries of Guiteras<lb/>
at Para, to which, indeed I, and I believe Dr. Gorgas, gave much weight;<lb/>
Para being in close commercial and sanitary relation to that Valley.</p>
<p>This Valley--adjudged free in 1916--has been exposed to infection<lb/>
for some years from that which existed since 1917 on the coast between<lb/>
Victoria and Pernambuco. I do not know that it has been reported further<lb/>
north.</p>
<p>Hanson too has mentioned report of yellow fever on the Peruval Ama-<lb/>
zon. If these be true it would mean a previous infection in Iquitos and<lb/>
Manaos. The extremely depressed condition of the rubber trade--lessening<lb/>
immigration into this valley--however, has been a great safe-guard both<lb/>
against the introduction of infection and the persistence of infection<lb/>
if introduced--as, indeed, were the considerable epidemics in 1910 to<lb/>
/13 or /14.</p>
<p>All things considered, I would be willing to rely on the report of<lb/>
the Central Health Office at Rio in this matter. If yellow fever has re-<lb/>
turned to the Amazon Valley they should know it. Unless in Manaos it<lb/>
would soon die out and I doubt if under present, and recent, commercial<lb/>
conditions it would last indefinitely at Manaos. At any rate, it is of<lb/>
no greater--indeed of less--importance here than that alleged to be on<lb/>
the Coast of Brazil.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
Address: New Glasgow P. O.,<lb/>
Amherst County, Va.<lb/>
&ldquo;Geddes.&rdquo;<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
