<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00937013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to John A. Ferrell, August 25, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00937013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-08-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ferrell, John A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Barber, M. A.</name>
<name type="person">Fricks, Lunsford D.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-08-25">August 25, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00937013</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to John A. Ferrell, August 25, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter suggests several possible field studies on malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-08-25">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to John A. Ferrell, August 25, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00937013"/>
<opener>
The New Charlotte Sanatorium<lb/>
Charlotte, N. C.<lb/>
<dateline>
New Glasgow, P O<lb/>
Amherst County, Va<lb/>
&ldquo;Geddes&rdquo; <date value="1922-08-25">August 25,1922</date>
</dateline>
Dr. John A Ferrell,<lb/>
Director for the United States,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York, N Y<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Ferrell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of July 26/22 addressed to me at Marion, N C just to<lb/>
hand.</p>
<p>In answer to your request for suggestions of field studies or<lb/>
demonstrations of malaria which it seems advisable to make, I would name the<lb/>
following:</p>
<p>1. A study of the effect of impounding water on the incidence of malaria.</p>
<p>This study was begun in 1914 and carried on during 1915 and 1916 by La<lb/>
Prince, Griffitts and myself. Some surveys, minor, but not without value,<lb/>
have been made by Griffitts and myself since that time and the study/would <add>suggested</add><lb/>
be in continuation (completion?) of the work already done.</p>
<p>The problem is of much economic and sanitary importance and I think that<lb/>
a moderate amount of work for not less than two years and a much smaller<lb/>
amount, as inspection and observation only, continued for some years longer,<lb/>
(how many I cannot say) would be well repaid.</p>
<p>I have been purposing, when I have a little more data on this subject and<lb/>
some spare time, to write up the findings we have been able to arrive at so<lb/>
far and especially to formulate the measures advisable for preventing, or at<lb/>
least, minimising, malaria caused by making these large ponds. A good deal<lb/>
of data for this purpose is already available and I hope to get a little<lb/>
more this fall.</p>
<p>The general method of study for the first two years would be (a) select<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00937014"/>
Page - 2<lb/>
The New Charlotte Sanatorium<lb/>
Charlotte, N. C.<lb/>
a location in which a large body of water will be impounded within a year<lb/>
or two - a hydro-electric plant in the making is the best possible (b) make<lb/>
a survey: (1) of the incidence of malaria in this section: (2) of the<lb/>
Anopheles production, noting breeding places; species and prevalence in<lb/>
residences.</p>
<p>These surveys should not only cover the flowage area of the purposed<lb/>
pond, but should extend, roughly, a mile or mile and a half beyond the<lb/>
flowage contour - indeed, the survey, especially as to the species of<lb/>
Anapheles and the production in this area beyond the contour should be<lb/>
especially full.</p>
<p>There is no need of including the whole of the area indicated in the<lb/>
survey; this might involve a very large amount of work. It is sufficient<lb/>
that cross-sections be taken, a half-mile to a mile wide, at suitable<lb/>
places so as to sample the country we are investigating. This limitation<lb/>
is especially advised for the Anopheles survey. The malaria survey is so<lb/>
much easier made that this may, escept in very large ponds - that of Lock<lb/>
17, Black Warrior - was over 65 miles long - be made to include all<lb/>
people in the area indicated.</p>
<p>An examination of the same territory - after the <del><unclear>poind</unclear></del> pond is filled<lb/>
and for as many years thereafter as may be necessary - should give us<lb/>
data to determine the effect of the impounded water on the incidence of<lb/>
malaria: Naturally, there are a number of other factors to be noted, but<lb/>
this is the general plan.</p>
<p>Detail and modifications available of the above general plan should be<lb/>
given only if this study be undertaken as it would involve sometime to<lb/>
write them out.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f00937015"/>
<p>Page - 3</p>
<p>The New Charlotte Sanatorium<lb/>
Charlotte, N. C.</p>
<p>The above was what was planned and, more or less imperfectly, carried<lb/>
out in 1915 and 1916</p>
<p>A working party should consist of a chief (man of status of Barber or<lb/>
Griffitts) with two or three intelligent young men for helpers (students<lb/>
on vacation are about the type needed) and a Ford automobile. This is for<lb/>
the surveys of areas before the water is impounded. After the pond is<lb/>
filled, the use of a motor boat - usually cheaply obtainable from the<lb/>
Power Company - and one or two small skiffs or canoes are necessary in<lb/>
addition. The skiffs should be furnished with Evenrude motors.</p>
<p>One such party should be able to examine for two large ponds and<lb/>
transportation between them must be provided for several trips.</p>
<p>The work will last only during the season of contaminative Anopheles<lb/>
production - May 1st - October 31st as a maximum; mainly from June 1st -<lb/>
Oct 31st.</p>
<p>The cost I cannot estimate. A guess estimate would be about $12,500<lb/>
to $15,000 each year for the first two years and about 67% to 50% of<lb/>
that amount for - say five years thereafter - not necessarily consecutive<lb/>
years.</p>
<p>The estimate is for one party with three assistants, working - the<lb/>
chief twelve and the assistants 6 1/2 months.</p>
<p>It is possible enough that the intensive work outlined for the first<lb/>
2 years would need to be repeated - so as to cover, at least, <hi>four</hi> large<lb/>
ponds in which case the larger estimate should hold for four years.</p>
<p><hi>Study of Cypress Swamp Breeding of Anopheles</hi></p>
<p>This involves, and unquestionably includes, a study of such breeding<lb/>
at a distance from the blood-supply furnished by man and domestic<lb/>
animals.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00937016"/>
<p>Page - 4</p>
<p>The New Charlotte Sanatorium<lb/>
Charlotte, N. C.</p>
<p>I had purposed to take this up, in a small way, in 1917, but the war<lb/>
prevented. It is of some importance, both from a scientific and a practical<lb/>
standpoint, but especially from the former. Of much less importance than<lb/>
(1), but is an absolutely untouched problem</p>
<p>Estimate of cost - about $12,500 to $15,000 per annum - or less - for<lb/>
say - <hi>two</hi> years. Same field party as for Impounded Water, but no launch<lb/>
needed.</p>
<p>3. To determine the different valencies <hi>in nature</hi> of our three principal<lb/>
species of Anopheles as vectors of malaria.</p>
<p>Dr. Fricks is already working on this problem as regards the role of A.<lb/>
punctipennis compared with the other two, but I am sure he would be glad<lb/>
to be able to extend this work.</p>
<p>It is obviously most important. Indeed, I have considered it the most<lb/>
important of the field problems of malaria yet unsolved, and have done some<lb/>
epidemiological (field) work on it myself.</p>
<p>The methods and costs of carrying them out can be obtained from Dr.<lb/>
Fricks better than from myself. The expense will depend, <unclear>maturally</unclear>, on the<lb/>
extent to which the work is carried.</p>
<p>4. To study how best to combine control of malaria (control of Anopheles<lb/>
production) with the large scale drainage projects for agriculture.</p>
<p>I think this is not the class of studies to which your letter refers.<lb/>
It is, however, important and I am sure, feasible.</p>
<p>Obviously, both the efficacy of the Anopheles control and the economical<lb/>
adaptation of the measures therefor to the drainage work, must be considered<lb/>
It should begin by a preliminary study, <hi>in the field where drainage work is<lb/>
going on</hi>, by a thoroughly competent malarial engineer in consultation with<lb/>
a drainage engineer. During this, the measures tentatively agreed on by<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f00937017"/>
Page - 5<lb/>
The New Charlotte Sanatorium<lb/>
Charlotte, N. C.<lb/>
both as necessary to control Anopheles production and allowable from a<lb/>
drainage standpoint could be checked up.</p>
<p>Practically the only expense for this preliminary work would be the pay of<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> the malaria engineer and his traveling expenses - for he should visit more<lb/>
than one drainage project. It would need one of the very best of our engineers,<lb/>
however.</p>
<p>If this should result in the general adoption of measures for the control of<lb/>
Anopheles by drainage engineers, and it might well be an important step thereto,<lb/>
its value would be very great. We have been trying since 1917 to get these men<lb/>
interested in malaria control, so that the lands fitted for agriculture by<lb/>
drainage might be, by the same measure, freed from malaria. This has not, by<lb/>
any means, always been the case.</p>
<p>5. The repetition, in various places and times, of Mitzmain's work at Monroe,<lb/>
<unclear>La</unclear> in 1917 to determine the last date in the fall at which Anopheles are in-<lb/>
fective to men.</p>
<p>This is important, as giving us the date in the fall at which it is safe<lb/>
to suspend oiling and other measures for the control of Anopheles production.<lb/>
I think the saving to my Service in 1918, due to this knowledge, was not less<lb/>
than $150,000.</p>
<p>This is a purely scientific study - partly field and partly bench - and a<lb/>
working party should consist of one entomological microscopist and a helper.<lb/>
More than one party can be used - and for several years.</p>
<p>This work, however, as it can be done for only about 1 month per annum in<lb/>
any one district, had best be made a side issue to other work of the same kind -<lb/>
such as Barber and Mayne are doing now. I doubt, then, if this fails in the<lb/>
category of the class of studies you <del><unclear></unclear></del> mean. I think not.</p>
<closer>
<signed>H R Carter</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
