<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00934012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Herbert Joseph Spinden, July 6, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00934012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-07-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Spinden, Herbert Joseph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Antilles</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-07-06">July 6, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00934012</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Herbert Joseph Spinden, July 6, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses scientific theories concerning the origins of yellow fever in humans.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-07-06">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Herbert Joseph Spinden, July 6, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00934012"/>
<opener>
/LC<lb/>
Book<lb/>
<hi><unclear>Maya</unclear></hi><lb/>
(Spinden<lb/>
theory<lb/>
(resevoir <unclear>host<lb/>
for y. f. examine)</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1922-07-06">July 6, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H. J. Spinden,<lb/>
Peabody Museum of Harvard University,<lb/>
Cambridge, Mass.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Spinden:</salute>
</opener>
<p>About what you were speaking yesterday: Your idea is that man<lb/>
first received the infection of yellow fever from a Stegomyia mos-<lb/>
quito, infected by feeding on some animal other than man.</p>
<p>This may be assumed:</p>
<p>1/ It would be extremely improbable that an organism should<lb/>
undergo much of a developement in a host to which it is so extremely<lb/>
pathogenic (and in which its life is so short) as this one is to man.<lb/>
Its chance of conveyance to the alternative host, and hence of survival,<lb/>
would be <unclear>enormously</unclear> less than in a host to which it was not pathogenic.<lb/>
This simply needs statement.</p>
<p>2/ There is the analogy of other diseases: of sleeping sickness,<lb/>
conveyed to man--to whom it is pathogenic--by the tetse fly infected<lb/>
from the large game--to which it is not: of Rocky Mountain Fever, taken<lb/>
to man--to whom it is pathogenic--by ticks infected by game and <hi>rodents</hi>--<lb/>
to which it is not. So for Tulare Fever and for Chagas Disease--of<lb/>
which you will hear in Rio. The armadillo--to which it is not patho-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00934013"/>
patho<lb/>
2.<lb/>
genic--is a host of this organism--a tripanosome. I could instance<lb/>
others.</p>
<p>It seems highly--almost infinitely--probably then that the de-<lb/>
velopement of what is now the causative organism of yellow fever took<lb/>
place in some animal to which it was not pathogenic--or at least in<lb/>
which it had a fairly long life--and, having developed its metaxenic<lb/>
relation with the mosquito, was by it transferred to man. If we could<lb/>
predicate such a resevoir host for the yellow fever organism coming in<lb/>
contact with the Mayas--at or near Chicken Itza--there would have been<lb/>
an epidemic of yellow fever, and a severe one, as might well have led to<lb/>
the abandonment of that place. If this host stayed at, or returned to,<lb/>
Chicken Itza yellow fever would recur whenever there were any suscep-<lb/>
tible people--the &ldquo;failure of human hosts&rdquo; would not have &ldquo;eliminated&rdquo;<lb/>
it. In an article in the Liverpool Journal: &ldquo;Annals of Tropical Medi-<lb/>
cine and Parisitology,&rdquo; March 15/20, I wrote: &ldquo;It would be much easier<lb/>
to accept the American origen of yellow fever, for which the historical<lb/>
evidence is very strong, if we had evidence of such a host&rdquo; (animal re-<lb/>
sevoir host) &ldquo;in pre-Columbian times in the Antilles or on the Carib-<lb/>
bean litoral.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Note that in none of the diseases I have mentioned as transferred<lb/>
by insects from animals to man, was there any <hi>specialization</hi> of the<lb/>
causative organism, beyond that it had already acquired, needed for its<lb/>
life in man. Indeed, for it to utilize man as means of continuing its<lb/>
life to best advantage this specialization should have been on the<lb/>
lines of a <hi>loss</hi> of pathogenicity to him. Those bred in man retain their<lb/>
power to infect their animal hosts as well as man himself and the former<lb/>
continue as resevoir hosts. There is then no reason to believe that<lb/>
the animal from which man was--by the mosquito--infected with yellow<lb/>
fever, ceased to function as a resevoir host to the parisite pathogenic<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00934014"/>
pathogenic<lb/>
3.<lb/>
to man when the infection of man had taken place.</p>
<p>Such a host should have existed, or may still exist--although I<lb/>
hope not to an extent of any sanitary importance.</p>
<p>Accepting <hi>Leptospira icteroides</hi> as this organism--neither Welch:<lb/>
Guiteras nor Rosenau are satisfied that it is--naturally<unclear>,</unclear> one would<lb/>
expect this host to be--as you suggested--a rodent. Rats are resevoir<lb/>
hosts for <hi>Leptospira <unclear>icterohemorrhagica</unclear></hi> --a very closely allied organism.</p>
<p>With many thanks for the help you have given me, I remain</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
Assistant Surgeon General H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
