<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t00937027">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, August 29, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Caldwell, Bert W.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>00937027</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-08-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Scannell, E. J.</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Ojitlan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tierra Blanca (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Vera Cruz (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-08-29">August 29, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">00937027</idno>
<title>Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, August 29, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Caldwell replies to questions raised by Carter concerning yellow fever outbreaks in Mexico and Africa.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-08-29">
<head>Letter from Bert W. Caldwell to Henry Rose Carter, August 29, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f00937027"/>
<opener>
D. S. P. FORMA 28<lb/>
I H. B.<lb/>
Caldwell<lb/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS-UNIDOS-MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. JOSEPH H. WHITHE<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. ANGEL BRIOSO VASCONCELOS<lb/>
<unclear>VOCALES</unclear><lb/>
DR. BERT W. CALDWELL<lb/>
DR. FRANCISCO CASTILLO NAJERA<lb/>
DR. MICHAEL E. CONNOR<lb/>
GRAL. DR. ENRIQUE C. OSORNIO<lb/>
DR. EMMETT I. VAUGHN<lb/>
MIEMBROS <unclear>ASOCIADOR</unclear><lb/>
DR. ALFREDO CUARON<lb/>
DR. JUAN GRAHAM CASASUS<lb/>
DR. E. C. HOULE<lb/>
DR. EVERARDO LANDA<lb/>
DR. MAURO LOYO<lb/>
DR. PEDRO PEREZ GROVAS<lb/>
DR. TOMAS G. PERRIN<lb/>
ING. J. A. LE PRINCE<lb/>
DR. E. J. SCANNELL<lb/>
DR. A. R. STUBBS<lb/>
<dateline>
Vera Cruz Mexico.<lb/>
<date value="1922-08-29">August 29th,1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was greatly encouraged and very much pleased to<lb/>
receive your letter of August 17th. The fact is that<lb/>
the work I am doing down here has a greater personal int-<lb/>
erest than any work I <unclear>have</unclear> ever engaged in. I am so<lb/>
desirous that the work be done well, and that the work<lb/>
under my direction stand every test, that I have become<lb/>
a <unclear>material</unclear> part of it. It was that reason, and the<lb/>
additional one, that I knew you are interested in every<lb/>
phase of the work, that I burdened you with my report.</p>
<p>Now to answer your questions. <del>1</del></p>
<p>1. The work in Tampico was undertaken in December of<lb/>
1920, under the auspices of the Associated Oil Managers.<lb/>
This association is composed of the managers of each of<lb/>
the oil companies operating in the Tampico <unclear>field</unclear> and has<lb/>
has for its purpose <unclear>that</unclear> promotion of the oil companies'<lb/>
interests' of whatever character. It is purely egoistical<lb/>
in character and purpose, and is never prompted by altru-<lb/>
istic motives except when such motives redound to the<lb/>
advantage of the oil companies. This the <unclear>assocoiation</unclear> free-<lb/>
ly states.</p>
<p>In addition to other matters, sanitation and the care<lb/>
of sick employes interests their attention. They were hav-<lb/>
ing yellow fever, that was tying up their ships, and <unclear>they</unclear><lb/>
were seriously inconvenienced in the field by that incid-<lb/>
ence of malaria among their employes. They had as their<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f00937028"/>
D. S. P. FORMA 28<lb/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS-UNIDOS-MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. JOSEPH H. WHITHE<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. ANGEL BRIOSO VASCONCELOS<lb/>
<unclear>VOCALES</unclear><lb/>
DR. BERT W. CALDWELL<lb/>
DR. FRANCISCO CASTILLO NAJERA<lb/>
DR. MICHAEL E. CONNOR<lb/>
GRAL. DR. ENRIQUE C. OSORNIO<lb/>
DR. EMMETT I. VAUGHN<lb/>
MIEMBROS <unclear>ASOCIADOR</unclear><lb/>
DR. ALFREDO CUARON<lb/>
DR. JUAN GRAHAM CASASUS<lb/>
DR. E. C. HOULE<lb/>
DR. EVERARDO LANDA<lb/>
DR. MAURO LOYO<lb/>
DR. PEDRO PEREZ GROVAS<lb/>
DR. TOMAS G. PERRIN<lb/>
ING. J. A. LE PRINCE<lb/>
DR. E. J. SCANNELL<lb/>
DR. A. R. STUBBS<lb/>
Medical and Sanitary advisor, Dr. A.R. Stubbs, who when the<lb/>
situation <del><unclear>exit</unclear></del> got beyond control, advised them to ask<lb/>
your service for the loan of Le Prince. This was <unclear>accompl-</unclear><lb/>
-ished, and Le Prince came down on a four months tour of<lb/>
duty generously loaned to these people by the S<add>e</add>rvice.</p>
<p>Le Prince at once took charge, instituted the fish<lb/>
campaign, and soon had yellow fever under control in Tampico<lb/>
and had contributed a great deal towards the reduction of<lb/>
the malarial incidence. The Associated Oil Managers sup-<lb/>
plied all funds for the work, which aggregated $180.000.00<lb/>
Le Prince demonstrated the utility of fish in Mexico for<lb/>
the first time, from December 1920 to March 1921.</p>
<p>2nd. The Ojitlan epidemic would have burned out<lb/>
without our assitance - in Ojitlan. The town is isolated<lb/>
and is rather off the usual travel routes. It was introduc-<lb/>
ed into the little place by soldiers who had visited<lb/>
Tierra Blanca, at that time <unclear>Badly</unclear> infected. I am of course<lb/>
referring to yellow fever. Indeed it had burned out, to<lb/>
all practical purposes when we institued our campaign, but<lb/>
our campaign, undoubdtedly prevented further <unclear>spread</unclear> among<lb/>
the <unclear>India's</unclear> to the West and South.</p>
<p>3rd. The Egg to Imago period.</p>
<p>When I first <unclear>began</unclear> the work, I wanted to start<lb/>
the campaign on an intelligent basis, both as to the length<lb/>
of each of our &ldquo;vueltas&rdquo;, and from an economical standpoint<lb/>
as to the number of men I should employ. I made a survey<lb/>
of the number of houses in Vera Cruz with the number and<lb/>
character of containers. I placed a dozen men at work<lb/>
and personally checked their work back of them to ascertain<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f00937029"/>
D. S. P. FORMA 28<lb/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS-UNIDOS-MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. JOSEPH H. WHITHE<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. ANGEL BRIOSO VASCONCELOS<lb/>
<unclear>VOCALES</unclear><lb/>
DR. BERT W. CALDWELL<lb/>
DR. FRANCISCO CASTILLO NAJERA<lb/>
DR. MICHAEL E. CONNOR<lb/>
GRAL. DR. ENRIQUE C. OSORNIO<lb/>
DR. EMMETT I. VAUGHN<lb/>
MIEMBROS <unclear>ASOCIADOR</unclear><lb/>
DR. ALFREDO CUARON<lb/>
DR. JUAN GRAHAM CASASUS<lb/>
DR. E. C. HOULE<lb/>
DR. EVERARDO LANDA<lb/>
DR. MAURO LOYO<lb/>
DR. PEDRO PEREZ GROVAS<lb/>
DR. TOMAS G. PERRIN<lb/>
ING. J. A. LE PRINCE<lb/>
DR. E. J. SCANNELL<lb/>
DR. A. R. STUBBS<lb/>
the number of premises which an average inspector<lb/>
could carefully revise each day. From my observations I<lb/>
concluded that a good Inspector could cover from 80 to<lb/>
100 houses as the are located in Vera Cruz in each 8-<lb/>
hour day. Le Prince thinks that they could do more and<lb/>
in one of his reports states that in Tampico his Inspec<lb/>
-tors <unclear>revised</unclear> successfully and satisfactorily 260 houses<lb/>
per day. That is impossible from a standpoint of careful<lb/>
or satisfactory work.</p>
<p>After this was <unclear>determined</unclear>, I had to find out the<lb/>
<hi>Minimum</hi>, <hi>safe period</hi> for each &ldquo;vuelta&rdquo;. I did this by<lb/>
growing my own stegomyia. I found that under laboratory<lb/>
conditions, rather more favorable, I think than natural<lb/>
<unclear>conditions</unclear>, that I had from 36 to 48 hours after ovipos-<lb/>
it, before hatching commenced, this continued for another<lb/>
30 to 40 hours. I found 120 hours to be the average<lb/>
time between the appearance of larvae and the the<lb/>
appearance of the first pupa, and I found pupal life to<lb/>
continue from 30 to 40 hours sometimes longer. Under<lb/>
favorable conditions the cycle in Laboratory was of<lb/>
from 7 3/4 to 8 2/3 days. I therefor took the min-<lb/>
imum as the length of my vuelta. This for the sake of<lb/>
security, and to make due allowance for a reasonable<lb/>
per cent of failure to locate <hi>all</hi> breeding places<lb/>
on the part of my Inspectors. I expect each inspector<lb/>
to average 80 houses each day in the more central<lb/>
portions of a town and 100 in the buburbs where the<lb/>
water containers are more easily located, and the prem-<lb/>
ises less <unclear>difficulty</unclear> to inspect thoroughly.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f00937030"/>
<p>D. S. P. FORMA 28<lb/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS-UNIDOS-MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. JOSEPH H. WHITHE<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. ANGEL BRIOSO VASCONCELOS<lb/>
<unclear>VOCALES</unclear><lb/>
DR. BERT W. CALDWELL<lb/>
DR. FRANCISCO CASTILLO NAJERA<lb/>
DR. MICHAEL E. CONNOR<lb/>
GRAL. DR. ENRIQUE C. OSORNIO<lb/>
DR. EMMETT I. VAUGHN<lb/>
MIEMBROS <unclear>ASOCIADOR</unclear><lb/>
DR. ALFREDO CUARON<lb/>
DR. JUAN GRAHAM CASASUS<lb/>
DR. E. C. HOULE<lb/>
DR. EVERARDO LANDA<lb/>
DR. MAURO LOYO<lb/>
DR. PEDRO PEREZ GROVAS<lb/>
DR. TOMAS G. PERRIN<lb/>
ING. J. A. LE PRINCE<lb/>
DR. E. J. SCANNELL<lb/>
DR. A. R. STUBBS</p>
<p>I agree that in nature the egg to imago cycle is<lb/>
longer, but under favorable climatic conditions, and in<lb/>
containers in the laboratory, where the water was never<lb/>
agitated, and always protected from sun and shock, the<lb/>
cycle was between 8 and 9 <del><unclear>nones</unclear></del><add>days</add>, perhaps nearer 9 days,<lb/>
on the average, than 8.</p>
<p>The cycle varied with the climatic changes, varying<lb/>
from the minimum when the weather was warm and no winds<lb/>
to speak of during the July <add>to Sept.</add> months, to 13 and 14 days<lb/>
when the thermometer was around 65 and the Northers<lb/>
were blowing, during the Fall and Winter months. In such<lb/>
clmiatic conditions, there would be periods of 4 or more<lb/>
days when all creative proceedure upon the part of the<lb/>
adult as well as on the part of the pupa and larva was<lb/>
apparently suspended, or at best very reluctant.</p>
<p>4th.</p>
<p>We examine for larvae with an ordinary flash <unclear>light</unclear><lb/>
But I have trained my inspectors to take plenty of time<lb/>
and locate the one and two day old larvae, if they exist.<lb/>
In fact the Inspctor stud<del><unclear>d</unclear></del>ies the container, and waits<lb/>
quietly and patiently for a time sufficiently long to<lb/>
permit the larvae and pupae to recover from their fright<lb/>
of the approaching shadow and come up for air. I regard<lb/>
the finding of pupae in any container, <unclear>by</unclear> the revisador,<lb/>
as reflecting upon the care and efficiecieny of the<lb/>
Inspector and repeated findings results in the dismissal<lb/>
of the guilty man.</p>
<p>We have a variety of good fish around Vera Cruz<lb/>
but I cannot locate your &ldquo;Life&rdquo;. I am now convinced f<lb/>
from the results of my work here, that fish can be of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f00937031"/>
D. S. P. FORMA 28<lb/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS-UNIDOS-MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
____<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
____<lb/>
DIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. JOSEPH H. WHITHE<lb/>
SUBDIRECTOR:<lb/>
DR. ANGEL BRIOSO VASCONCELOS<lb/>
<unclear>VOCALES</unclear><lb/>
DR. BERT W. CALDWELL<lb/>
DR. FRANCISCO CASTILLO NAJERA<lb/>
DR. MICHAEL E. CONNOR<lb/>
GRAL. DR. ENRIQUE C. OSORNIO<lb/>
DR. EMMETT I. VAUGHN<lb/>
MIEMBROS <unclear>ASOCIADOR</unclear><lb/>
DR. ALFREDO CUARON<lb/>
DR. JUAN GRAHAM CASASUS<lb/>
DR. E. C. HOULE<lb/>
DR. EVERARDO LANDA<lb/>
DR. MAURO LOYO<lb/>
DR. PEDRO PEREZ GROVAS<lb/>
DR. TOMAS G. PERRIN<lb/>
ING. J. A. LE PRINCE<lb/>
DR. E. J. SCANNELL<lb/>
DR. A. R. STUBBS<lb/>
the greatest possible value in malarial control, in the<lb/>
States, if a variety can be located that will thrive and<lb/>
reproduce as some of our tropical varieties do, under<lb/>
tropical conditions. I believe that it will solve the<lb/>
problem for many small communities and if generally<lb/>
introduced will minimise the problem for our larger<lb/>
cities. I mean the growing of these varieties in the<lb/>
ponds, ditches, larger holes and other anopheles breeding<lb/>
places, which contain water in sufficient quantity to<lb/>
support fish life during several months of the year. It<lb/>
would be the most economical and most effective of <unclear>re</unclear> as-<lb/>
ures and would finally result in the eradication of<lb/>
malaria from certain communities now badly infected.<lb/>
I would like to see it tried intelligently and from a<lb/>
rational rather than from an empirical standpoint.</p>
<p>I was so glad to hear from you. Dr. White is in<lb/>
Tampico. They had a recurrence there, in one of the places<lb/>
which so aptly justifies your statement that it is"<lb/>
&ldquo;More important to work in places <hi>liable</hi> to be infected&rdquo;<lb/>
I am so firmly convinced of this that I am sure, the<lb/>
Mexican campaign can never be completed, until such places<lb/>
are covered with several vueltas of intensive work.</p>
<p>Conner is in Merida and Scannell is in Tam-<lb/>
Pico. My Zone stills remains free and I anticipate no<lb/>
trouble this year. I have done my work th<add>o</add>roughly in such<lb/>
places where brigades have been established, and my in-<lb/>
cidence is very low. I can maintain it indefinitely.</p>
<p>I was so glad to hear from you. If I can give<lb/>
you any information at any <unclear>time</unclear>, let me know. With<lb/>
my kindest regards to Miss Laura and yourself, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<signed>Respy, Caldwell</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
