<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01004005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Yellow Fever in Ceara, Brazil, by [Lewis W. Hackett], [December, 1922?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01004005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-12-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">Ceara (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Fortaleza, Ceara (Brazil)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-12-00">[December, 1922?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01004005</idno>
<title>Yellow Fever in Ceara, Brazil, by [Lewis W. Hackett], [December, 1922?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hackett's] report to the International Health Board traces the history of yellow fever in Ceara, Brazil. The report includes mortality records and clinical records of cases among Americans and Europeans.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-12-00">
<head>Yellow Fever in Ceara, Brazil, by [Lewis W. Hackett], [December, 1922?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01004005"/>
<p>COPY</p>
<p><hi>YELLOW FEVER IN CEARA, BRAZIL</hi></p>
<p>In the year 1851 yellow fever became rooted in Fortaleza, capital of<lb/>
Ceara. This was two years after the disease had first entered Brazil by the port<lb/>
of Bahia. An American brig sailing from New Orleans had carried the disease to<lb/>
this country where it has ever since been maintaining a foothold. In the first<lb/>
year of the disease in Fortaleza 8,000 of the 15,000 inhabitants were attacked.<lb/>
Since that time there has never been a serious epidemic of the disease in Forta-<lb/>
leza probably because the small port does not permit of much intercourse with<lb/>
the world at large. The mortality records of Fortaleza since 1914 up to the<lb/>
1st of November of this year are as follows:</p>
<p>
<table rows="10" cols="2">
<row>
<cell><hi>Year</hi></cell><cell><hi>No. of Deaths</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1914</cell><cell>8</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1915</cell><cell>4</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1916</cell><cell>11</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1917</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1918</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1919</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1920</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1921</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1922</cell><cell>3</cell></row></table></p>
<p>Clinical records of the last four fatalities as well as one suspected<lb/>
case which recovered are presented below. It should be borne in mind that much<lb/>
of the data was secured from the attending physicians who had kept no written<lb/>
records of the cases.</p>
<p><hi>Case I.</hi> Claude Ashmare - Age 50, American Engineer - Heavy Drinker.</p>
<p>In May 1921 he became sick suffering daily with chills, high fever and<lb/>
frontal headache. After three days there was a short interval with few symptoms<lb/>
followed by a recrudesence. When first seen by a doctor on the 4th day the pulse<lb/>
was above 100 and temperature 39.5&deg; C. Abdomen a little tympanitic with slight<lb/>
generalized tenderness. Liver one finger below costal border, hard to palpation.<lb/>
Spleen not palpable.</p>
<p>5th day. Temperature 38.5&deg; C. Patient felt better.</p>
<p>6th day. " 38&deg; C.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01004006"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>8th day. Temperature rose above 38&deg; C. A bloody extravesation found at the<lb/>
point where a serum was injected. Delirium set in during the night.<lb/>
10th day. Jaundice, great prostration. Temperature 37&deg; <unclear>+</unclear>. Pulse number not<lb/>
recorded but was weak. Lungs - bases congested.</p>
<p>11th day. Condition worse. Completely jaundiced. Slight cough with dark<lb/>
bloody sputum. Blood examination negative for malaria: Very weak agglutination<lb/>
for paratyphoid B. Urine bloody. Died in the afternoon. Consultation with 2<lb/>
colleagues. Diagnosis, clinical yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>Autopsy.</hi></p>
<p>Liver enlarged, yellow. Spleen appeared normal. Stomach wall showed<lb/>
dilated arterioles. Lungs - bases greatly congested. Attending physician in<lb/>
view of clinical history and autopsy reported death from yellow fever.</p>
<p>Material was taken for microscopic examination. Culture of spleen was<lb/>
positive to plague. Because of doubt, all the viscera were sent to the Oswaldo<lb/>
Cruz Institute in Rio and examined by Dr. Crowell who reported that <unclear>lesion<del>s</del></unclear><lb/>
characteristic of yellow fever were not found but those of chronic malaria were<lb/>
reported. This report caused a great surprise to the clinicians of Fortaleza.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01004007"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><hi>CASE 2</hi> - <hi>JAMES DAY</hi>, <hi>AMERICAN</hi></p>
<p>No clinical is extent. The following telegrams from<lb/>
the Secretary of the Recife Department of Health are pertinent<lb/>
however.</p>
<p>1) I advise you that yesterday James Day, age 37, died<lb/>
in this city. He came from Fortaleze and disembarked here on the<lb/>
18 February 1922; already sick - Dr. Bentes Carvalho.</p>
<p>2) In regard the previous telegram I sent you, I advise<lb/>
you that James Day died on February 22, 1922 of yellow fever -<lb/>
Dr. Bentes Carvalho.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01004008"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p><hi>CASE 3</hi> - <hi>MRS. CHAGNON</hi>, <hi>FRENCH</hi></p>
<p>July 24, 1922 called her physician who furnished this cli-<lb/>
nical record:</p>
<p>Temperature oscillating between 38&deg; &amp; 39&deg; C. Vomiting and<lb/>
epigastric pain. Symptoms improved and on fourth day judged patient<lb/>
to be convalescing; fifth day symptoms all returned and death follow-<lb/>
ed at once. Generalized jaundice became apparent immediately after<lb/>
death.</p>
<p>The attending physician diagnosed the case Yellow Fever<lb/>
which was substantiated by the gross pathological examination.<lb/>
Cultural and microscopic diagnosis was plague.</p>
<p>About the same time, the brother of Mrs. Chagnon also fell<lb/>
ill of an identical disease but much milder; microscopic examination<lb/>
of the sputum, urine, feces, etc. revealed the bacillus of Yersin.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01004009"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p><hi>CASE 4</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>MASTERSON - AMERICAN - RESIDENT IN BRAZIL 4 MONTHS.</hi></p>
<p>1st day. First day of illness, September 21, 1922, showed temperature<lb/>
39.5&deg;C. Conjunctiva congested, lumbar pains and headache.<lb/>
Liver not tender but enlarged. Tongue coated.</p>
<p>2nd day. Temperature 38.3&deg; C. symptoms more severe.</p>
<p>3rd day. Temperature 37.3&deg; C. Conjunctiva less congested. Lumbar pains<lb/>
more severe. Urine showed large quantity of albumin.</p>
<p>4th day. Temperature 37&deg; C. Slight conjunctival jaundice. General condition<lb/>
better.<lb/>
The jaundice gradually became more intense involving skin.</p>
<p>8th day. Temperature 36.5&deg; C. to 37&deg; C. Pulse 60 to 62.</p>
<p>9th day. Albumin began to disappear as well as the jaundice.<lb/>
By the twelfth day the patient was entirely free of symptoms.<lb/>
Diagnosis of attending physician was Suspected Yellow Fever.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f01004010"/>
<p>-6-<lb/>
No.</p>
<p><hi>CASE No. 5.</hi></p>
<p><hi>LEE GREENLEAF, Age 25, American.</hi> He arrived in Fortaleza October<lb/>
6, 1922. Visited the Masterson's house on several occasions before<lb/>
falling ill October 13th.</p>
<p><hi>2nd. day.:</hi> - Seen by a physician - Temp. 39 c. Pulse 102, Headache<lb/>
and generalized pains. Prostrated and indifferent to his surroundings.<lb/>
Liver normal. Conjuntiva congested; lachrymation; tongue coated.</p>
<p><hi>3rd. day:</hi> - Symptoms less severe, Temp. 39, Pulse 84.</p>
<p><hi>4th. day:</hi> - Generalized pains continue. Headache intense, epigastric<lb/>
tenderness, slight, conjunctive icterus. Urine diminished &amp; contained<lb/>
considerable albumin. Tep. 38 Pulse 62.</p>
<p><hi>5th. day</hi>: - Fetid breath. Complete anuria. Conjunctival-icterus more<lb/>
intense. Much pain on pressure over stomach and liver. Nasal hemorrhage.</p>
<p><hi>6th. day:</hi> - Delirium set in. Expelled blood from nose and mouth<lb/>
repeatedly. Removed by catheter, 30 cc. of urine.</p>
<p><hi>7th. day:</hi> - In the early morning patient had an abundant hemorrhage<lb/>
and expired immediately thereafter.</p>
<p><hi>AUTOPSY:</hi> - Skin - generalized icterus. Blood <unclear>oozing</unclear> from mouth and<lb/>
nose. Lividity of the dependant parts.</p>
<p>Conjunctiva intensely yellow.</p>
<p>Lungs - right - anthrocosis and small hemorrhagic infarcts.<lb/>
left - upper lobe anthracosis and hemorrhagic infarcts.</p>
<p>Pleural cavities - 80 to 100 cc. sero sanguinous liquid in<lb/>
each side.</p>
<p>Pericardium - 50 c.c. of a clear egg yellow liquid.</p>
<p>Heart - More or less normal.</p>
<p>Intestines - intensely yellow.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f01004011"/>
<p>- 7 -</p>
<p>Liver - slightly enlarged - straw yellow color with<lb/>
greenish anterior edge. <unclear>Cut</unclear> surface showed nutmeg appearance.</p>
<p>Stomach - Contained 350 c.c. of a black bloody<lb/>
liquid. Hemorrhagic areas visible internally or externally.</p>
<p>Kidney - Slightly yellow otherwise appeared normal.</p>
<p>Intestines - Hemorrhagic areas.</p>
<p>Spleen - Appeared normal.</p>
<p>Bladder - Contained about 80 c.c. urine. Walls appeared<lb/>
normal.</p>
<p>The report of the microscopic examination of viscera<lb/>
has not yet been received.</p>
<p><hi>DIAGNOSIS</hi>: From clinical and gross pathological findings;<lb/>
Yellow Fever. Case was considered to be typical.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
