<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01003028">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Wickliffe Rose, November 9, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01003028</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-11-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Mobile (Ala.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-11-09">November 9, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01003028</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Wickliffe Rose, November 9, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] discusses an alleged case of yellow fever. He believes that a quarantine should be instituted for safety's sake.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-11-09">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Wickliffe Rose, November 9, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01003028"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1922-11-09">November 9, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Wickliffe Rose,<lb/>
General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York, N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In reply to your letter, received this morning, I would say<lb/>
that I had already received from the Bureau Dr. Lombard's report<lb/>
of September 18th. on the alleged case of yellow fever aboard the<lb/>
American schooner Burnham at Mobile Quarantine.</p>
<p>There is no question that from a quarantine standpoint the<lb/>
case must be considered yellow fever. The rule there is to con-<lb/>
sider for quarantine purposes all cases as yellow fever unless we<lb/>
know they are not.</p>
<p>From a pathological standpoint, however, it is not so clear.<lb/>
Very evidently neither the clinical history nor the autopsy were<lb/>
made by one familiar with yellow fever. They are less definitive<lb/>
therefor than had the contrary been the case.</p>
<p>That the onset of the fever was 14 days after leaving Paramaibo<lb/>
does not in the least militate against the diagnosis of yellow fever--<lb/>
simply against yellow fever contracted ashore. Death on the 7th.<lb/>
day is a point in favor of positive diagnosis as is, possibly, the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01003029"/>
the<lb/>
apparent improvement on the 3rd. The malaise a few days prior to the<lb/>
onset of the fever is, to some extent, against it.</p>
<p>The autopsy is very doubtful. The appearance of the liver as<lb/>
described is in favor of a positive diagnosis, but the description is<lb/>
so incomplete that it is by no means determinative. Clear, highly al-<lb/>
buminous urine is the same, and probably of at least as much weight,<lb/>
probably of more weight than the liver.</p>
<p>If there were no black vomit in the stomach--unless he had vomited<lb/>
it just before death--and if punctate hemmorrhages were not seen, I<lb/>
think yellow fever would be negatived, in spite of the two points I<lb/>
have mentioned. The spleen is what one would expect to find in a death<lb/>
from malaria. There is little change from normal in this organ in<lb/>
yellow fever, certainly not on the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day</p>
<p>If I were sure that no lesions existed save those reported--i. e.<lb/>
that there were no discolored spots on the body: no stains of black<lb/>
vomit about the mouth: that the liver was not firm and bloodless on<lb/>
section: that the kidneys were not both congested and yellow: that<lb/>
there were no signs of hemorrhage into the stomach or duodenum I would<lb/>
be inclined to negative the diagnosis of yellow fever, spite of the<lb/>
highly albuminurious, clear urine. Taking into consideration, however,<lb/>
that what is not mentioned is not always absent and that possibly the<lb/>
reporter did not know quite what points to look for,<lb/>
I feel like saying that the probability of its being yellow fever<lb/>
is about 40%--that of its not bein, of course, 60%. If it was yellow<lb/>
fever, iwhether plasmodia were found or not, it was complicated with<lb/>
malarial infection. The spleen described could mean nothing else.</p>
<p>From a quarantine standpoint it was--as I have said--yellow fever<lb/>
and it was right to treat it as such.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
