<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01002001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to G.H. Hazlehurst, October 3, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01002001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-10-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hazlehurst, G.H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="place">Wison (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Greenville, (S. C.)</name>
<name type="place">Saginaw (Mich.)</name>
<name type="place">Hartsville (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Toshes (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Badin (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-10-03">October 3, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01002001</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to G.H. Hazlehurst, October 3, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter critiques the tentative requirements for impounding water to prevent the production of malaria which were sent to him by Hazlehurst. He discusses the costs of malaria prevention measures. He comments on the ideas of LePrince and Griffitts.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-10-03">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to G.H. Hazlehurst, October 3, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01002001"/>
<opener>
File<lb/>
Imp. Waters<lb/>
(Ala)<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1922-10-03">October 3, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. G. H. Hazlehurst,<lb/>
Chief Sanitary Engineer,<lb/>
Alabama State Board of Health,<lb/>
Montgomery, Ala.<lb/>
<unclear>Return</unclear> to H. R. Carter<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mr. Hazlehurst:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In judging what measures should be taken by one impounding water to<lb/>
prevent the production of malaria therefrom it seems to me we must be<lb/>
guided by this principle:--If the cost of the malaria averted be greater<lb/>
than that of the measures necessary to avert it, the measure should be<lb/>
taken. If the cost be less, it should not. Cost, of course, being used<lb/>
in its most comprehensive sense. In other words, that one should ex-<lb/>
pend $1.00 to get $1.20 worth of health and should not expend it to get<lb/>
$0.80. On this basis I will try to criticize the tentative requirements<lb/>
you sent me:</p>
<p><hi>Sec. 1: Sec. 2:</hi> leave nothing to be desired.</p>
<p>Sec. 3:a Right, with the understanding, which I am sure is<lb/>
implied, that it will enforced on a commonsense basis and<lb/>
that the removal of <hi>all</hi> grass, weeds, leaves, pine-needles etc.<lb/>
some of which will <hi>not</hi> be submerged, even temporarily, but float<lb/>
up when the pond fills, will not be required. To do other-<lb/>
wise is so obviously impracticable--in a pond, say, like Lake<lb/>
Bankhead--that it seems foolish for me to make this reserva-<lb/>
tion and I would not save for the general tone of some<lb/>
other sections.</p>
<p>Sec. 3-b I am willing to accept this, yet it would to my mind<lb/>
be better if the words &ldquo;and thus be liable to collect and<lb/>
anchor floatage: rafts etc. and <del>thus</del> produce mosquitoes,&rdquo;<lb/>
be inserted after &ldquo;low water level&rdquo; and, naturally, omit<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01002002"/>
omit<lb/>
2.<lb/>
the last line and a half of this section.</p>
<p>I say this because neither LePrince nor myself have found the pres-<lb/>
ence of hard wood trees--as distinguished from brush or groves of sap-<lb/>
ling-<del>-</del>as ordinarily spaced in a forest--well out in the pond, of any<lb/>
sanitary importance at all, no matter whether they pierced the level of<lb/>
the water or no. The change suggested makes this requirement depend on<lb/>
its effect on mosquito production and can be applied or not as the<lb/>
State Board of Health judges advisable.</p>
<p>In large ponds this requirement will involve sometimes considera-<lb/>
ble expenditure--well into five figures--and, if unnecessary, should<lb/>
not be required.</p>
<p><hi>3-C</hi> I would feel like carrying this clearing somewhat below the minimum<lb/>
low water (vid. ), although this is, I judge, provided for in 3-b.<lb/>
Nor would I carry it quite as far as 25 ft. beyond high water. This last<lb/>
is of no special importance, however.</p>
<p>3-d There is no special fault to find with this. It is specially based<lb/>
on LePrince's first survey of Lock #12, Coosa. The only question is<lb/>
the ratio of the cost to the ill averted. Pine needles proved bad float-<lb/>
age at Lock #12, and <add>if one is</add> to get rid of them one should ring all trees within<lb/>
a distance of more than 50 ft., not only of the pond, but of every stream<lb/>
that flows into it, including the river itself; as they float down such<lb/>
streams and collect in the bights at their entrance, where, on account of<lb/>
the absence of wave action, they give maximum protection to larvae. I<lb/>
presume, too, it is purposed to <hi>keep</hi> this strip free from pines in the fu-<lb/>
ture! This seems impracticable &amp; it is thus <hi>a</hi> question and I am inclined to prefer a clause inserted<lb/>
imposing these measures at the discretion of the Board of Health in each<lb/>
case.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01002003"/>
<p>case.</p>
<p>3.</p>
<p>It is to be noted that there were no <hi>Gambusia</hi> in the Coosa Pond in<lb/>
1914 when Le Prince found pine needles such a nuisance. We did not find<lb/>
them worse than other floatage at Parr Shoals or Stevens Creek or on the<lb/>
Coosa itself the next summer.</p>
<p><hi>3-e</hi> Nothing but approval for this. Might add <hi>Fundulus notatus</hi> in upper<lb/>
country.</p>
<p><hi>3-f</hi> Right. Might insert the words: &ldquo;long enough to produce Anopheles&rdquo;<lb/>
or &ldquo;for two weeks&rdquo; after &ldquo;separate pools.&rdquo; This, I judge, is implied<lb/>
anyway.</p>
<p>Also, failure to note all such pools is not so bad--<hi>provided</hi> the<lb/>
edges of the pond are gone over and this condition remedied when the pond<lb/>
first falls after filling. This is more certain than work done before<lb/>
filling.</p>
<p><hi>3-g</hi> I cannot agree with this. Unquestionably it would prevent some<lb/>
malaria--at times epidemics--both among the working force and in the com-<lb/>
munity. I feel quite sure that malaria was thus produced at Blewett's<lb/>
Falls and that it was increased at Wateree--and doubtless at other places.<lb/>
My objection, however, is two-fold: (1) The cost would be, I think, much<lb/>
in excess of the ill averted and (2) Isn't it inconsistent? I mean, is<lb/>
this required of gangs engaged in other work in the Anopheles-producing<lb/>
part of the State?</p>
<p>For the first I have an idea that it would probably double the labor<lb/>
cost of construction. You could take this up with some of the large con-<lb/>
tracting companies and get a better estimate than this, my guess.</p>
<p>It strikes me that the cost--taken in a comprehensive sense--would<lb/>
be more--in my judgement far more--than the malaria which it would avert.</p>
<p>For the second, there seems to me to be but little--there is some--more<lb/>
reason for requiring this of the men engaged in making the pond than of<lb/>
other gangs of equal size working in the same territory. If Alabama does<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01002004"/>
does<lb/>
4.<lb/>
require this of all it is not inconsistent. The epidemic of malaria (<lb/>
(E. A.) at Wilson, Va., was caused (absolutely) by a gang--double-<lb/>
tracking a railroad: Those at Brookline and at Norwich, by bridge-gangs:<lb/>
that at Greenville, S. C. in 1912 most probably by gangs engaged in con-<lb/>
structing a cotton mill and quarters and that at Saginaw, Mich. (1921-22)<lb/>
by a party of Marines--I presume a recruiting party: etc.</p>
<p>It seems to me then that unless this requirement is to apply to<lb/>
labor gangs generally on what is called &ldquo;public work&rdquo; to apply it ponds<lb/>
would be inconsistent and wrong.</p>
<p>The only reason I can see for making an exception of the pond men<lb/>
is that the pond is expected--or is at least liable--to increase mos-<lb/>
quito production and the two factors--increase of carriers, followed by<lb/>
increase of vectors--may act together. Yet I know of but few--if any--<lb/>
places in the potentially malarial sections of the South in which there<lb/>
are not enough carriers to infect the rest of the community--if Anopheles<lb/>
be markedly increased.</p>
<p>It may take a year longer--or even more--but that is about all the<lb/>
difference it would make. Ultimately the malaria incidence will reach a<lb/>
level, a function of Anopheles production and the sociological conditions,<lb/>
but <hi>independent</hi> of the number of carriers introduced. Nor does this take<lb/>
a great while.</p>
<p>How would this requirement apply to the construction of small ponds<lb/>
with strictly neighborhood labor?</p>
<p><hi>Sec. 4</hi> Good.</p>
<p>Sec. 5-a. I hardly know what to say. The Board of Health should have au-<lb/>
thority to order the removal of such floatage as is (indirectly) produc-<lb/>
ing, or will produce, malaria, but to require the removal regularly and<lb/>
frequently over the whole extent of the shore line of all floatage that<lb/>
is <hi>likely</hi> to harbor mosquito larvae is a large order. We estimated the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01002005"/>
the<lb/>
5.<lb/>
shore line of the pool of Lock 17, Black Warrior, as 225 miles. What<lb/>
it would cost to hand-clean it once a week during the mosquito season<lb/>
you can estimate. It would be cheaper to buy all the land within a<lb/>
mile of the river up to Cordova and depopulate it and clean only the<lb/>
creeks near Cordova <add>-<unclear>Cordova</unclear></add> and Frog Ague.</p>
<p>I would feel like re-writing this paragraph and, for the present<lb/>
until one could see how it would work out, make it apply to orders of<lb/>
the Board of Health <hi>in individual instances</hi> rather than to a general<lb/>
requirement such as we have here. What do you think?</p>
<p>The only way practicable to clean all the edges of a large pond--<lb/>
as Lock 17--is to lower the water level. This can be made absolutely<lb/>
efficacious. I have seen it applied in several <add>-5-</add> cases. The only way<lb/>
to keep them clean is to properly raise and lower the level. It is al-<lb/>
ways physically possible to lower the level--although it may involve<lb/>
much loss. It may not always be possible to raise it as desired.</p>
<p><hi>5-b</hi> Quite hard to do I should think. I have not, however, had enough<lb/>
experience with old ponds to justify an opinion on what should be done<lb/>
with them. One at Hartsville, S. C.--about 30 years old when examined--<lb/>
was adjudged by LePrince and myself not to be producing Anopheles of<lb/>
sanitary importance--controlled by fish: One at Wilson, Va.,--153<lb/>
years old--was producing and was cured--temporarily at least--by raising<lb/>
it--5 ft. as I recollect. Three others:--at Birmingham: at Natalie and<lb/>
at Toshes, Va.,-were all breeding freely or profusely in Burr-reed (<hi>Spar-<lb/>
ganum Americanum</hi>). Breeding in <add>other</add> vegetation, including cat-tails, was<lb/>
efficiently controlled by fish. I have examined only a few others.</p>
<p>Why have you confined your requirements for old ponds to aquatic<lb/>
plants? The shoaling of the upper end of the Pond--inevitable I judge--:<lb/>
the filling up of the lower reaches of creeks and their natural conse-<lb/>
quences<del>--</del>are also of importance from the stand point of mosquito production,<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01002006"/>
production.<lb/>
6.<lb/>
and I judge difficult to remedy save by raising or breaking the pond--<lb/>
at least that is the only way I have ever been able to do so.</p>
<p><hi>5-c</hi> Good--except I see no reason for the last paragraph prohibiting<lb/>
fishing. One does not catch <hi>Gambusia</hi> with a hook and they are too<lb/>
small to use as bait: <hi>Fundulus notatus</hi> may not be, but you haven't men-<lb/>
tioned them. Catching game fish is a good thing.</p>
<p><hi>5-d</hi> Good--and to my mind rendering unnecessary some that preceeds.</p>
<p><hi>5-e Good.</hi></p>
<p>This is a tremendously long paper: I am tired from my trip and not<lb/>
overly well, else I had been able to condense it. Accept then my apo-<lb/>
logies therefor.</p>
<p>You will note two things in my point of view (1) that I am mainly<lb/>
looking at the large hydro-electric pond and (2) that I believe it prac-<lb/>
tically--I do not say <hi>absolutely</hi>--impossible to construct such a pond,<lb/>
in a district in which A. quadrimaculatus will breed, without somewhere<lb/>
making malaria. True enough sometimes, as at Badin and probably the<lb/>
lower part of Wateree, one sees more malaria destroyed by a pond than<lb/>
made, yet in my experience some has always been produced. My aim then is<lb/>
simply to minimize this production--and by such measures as do not cost<lb/>
more than the malaria which they avert. It seems to me that LePrince<lb/>
and Griffitts are either more optimistic about the prevention of malaria<lb/>
than I am or under estimate the cost of some of the measures they advo-<lb/>
cate. I don't know why either should be the case as they know as much<lb/>
about this matter as I do. Still, we evidently have different views on<lb/>
some parts of this matter.</p>
<p>Sometime ago I thus formulated the effect of impounding water on<lb/>
the incidence of malaria:</p>
<p>1) That in all cases, known to me, the pond eliminated some breed-<lb/>
ing places of Anopheles and made other breeding places:</p>
<pb n="7" id="f01002007"/>
<p>breeding places:</p>
<p>7.</p>
<p>2) That the sum of its effects on the incidence of malaria depended<lb/>
on</p>
<p>(a) The locations of the breeding places eliminated and produced:</p>
<p>(b) The comparative production of such breeding places and</p>
<p>(c) The species of Anopheles prevented and produced.</p>
<p>The proximity to a sufficient blood supply in this country to men<lb/>
and domestic animals quite certainly, and to my mind decidedly, in-<lb/>
fluences Anopheles production. This is denied by French and Italian<lb/>
writers. It is, however, included in (b).</p>
<p>You will allow me to suggest--and please show all this to LePrince<lb/>
and Griffitts--it would seem better for you now to only impose such<lb/>
<hi>general</hi> requirements as you are absolutely sure of: retaining authority<lb/>
to the Board of Health to order in any individual instance such other<lb/>
things as are necessary: on the general lines of <hi>Section 5-d</hi>.</p>
<p>This for your immediate needs and when you see how things work out--<lb/>
i. e. both the effect on malaria and the cost of the measures instituted--<lb/>
you can better tell what other general requirements should be imposed.</p>
<p>I am not even certain that you may not find it advisable to make<lb/>
separate regulations for large and small ponds--or in some way to take<lb/>
cognizance (1) of the difference in proportion of area to edge in the<lb/>
two: the one increasing wave action: the other breeding: (2) of the<lb/>
difference in the density of population adjacent to the two kinds of<lb/>
ponds and (3) of the convenience of blood-supply in each case. All<lb/>
these things affect the incidence of malaria.</p>
<p>How would it do, when the time is ripe to formulate <hi>general</hi> rules,<lb/>
for you to meet LePrince: Griffitts and myself in <hi>personal</hi> conference?<lb/>
Some of the men impounding water--in large ponds and in mill ponds--<lb/>
should also be consulted by this Board before these rules are finally<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01002008"/>
finally<lb/>
8.<lb/>
formulated. Frankly, I do not think the problem a very simple one.</p>
<p>Alabama is a great State and will last a long time. We are working<lb/>
then for far in the future. We aim to give maximum protection against<lb/>
malaria with as little obstruction to developement of water-power and to<lb/>
internal navigation as may be and it seems to me better to do this thing<lb/>
right than quickly.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General</signed>.
Assistant Surgeon General H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
