<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01005001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Yellow Fever, October 31, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01005001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-10-31</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Nigeria</name>
<name type="place">Warri (Nigeria)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-10-31"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">01005001</idno>
<title>Report: Yellow Fever, October 31, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a detailed clinical report from Africa, which describes a case of yellow fever in which the patient died. Included is a detailed description of the treatment program and the autopsy record.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-10-31">
<head>Report: Yellow Fever, October 31, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01005001"/>
<opener>
CLINICAL REPORT - YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
_______________________________<lb/>
NAME - G.A. Bradenelli. DATE OF ADMISSION - 31,10.22<lb/>
SEX - Male - Age - 27 years. DATE OF DEATH - 9,11.22<lb/>
NATIONALITY - Italian. DIAGNOSIS - Yellow Fever<lb/>
OCCUPATION - Merchant. RESULT - D e a t h.<lb/>
__________________________________________________________<lb/>
</opener>
<p><hi>HISTORY</hi>-<lb/>
3/10/22.</p>
<p>Patient has been in Nigeria several years, principally in<lb/>
Northern Nigeria. The present is his first tour in the Southern<lb/>
Provinces at Warri. Health has been good, does not practise quinine<lb/>
prophylaxis. On Sunday the 29th October, patient felt ill, severe<lb/>
headache and general malaise all day with nausea.</p>
<p>Towards the evening he felt worse. Temperature taken by<lb/>
himself 104.6. Severe frontal headache, loin pains and pains in his<lb/>
eyes. Patient took 5 grs: quinine with 5 grs: Aspirin and an aperient<lb/>
just at bed time. He had a very restless night, epigastric pain appear-<lb/>
ed, accompanied by vomiting, at first contents of stomach, later bilious<lb/>
in character. Next day 30th October he felt considerably worse with<lb/>
severe frontal headache, backache, continuous vomiting. Temp: was<lb/>
raised, - 104.6. Bowels only moved slightly, urine was freely passed<lb/>
during this day. Very bad night, no sleep, severe headache, backache,<lb/>
and epigastric pain, vomiting was worse, dark green bile, could not<lb/>
retain anything. On the morning of the 31st as he felt very ill, I<lb/>
was sent for at 12 noon and found him very ill, temp: 104, Pulse 72.<lb/>
Face flushed, conjunctivae injected, vomiting present. From his appear-<lb/>
ance I suspected more than a mere attack of malaria fever and had him<lb/>
immediately removed to the Warri Hospital, although much against his<lb/>
will.</p>
<p><hi>ON ADMISSION</hi>. -</p>
<p>1:30 P.M. Patient perspiring freely, Temp: 102.4, P.90.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01005002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
Complains of frontal headache, and backache, with aching pains in<lb/>
limbs. Face flushed, eyes bright, conjunctivae injected. Lips and<lb/>
mouth dry, great thirst, <unclear>Sclerae</unclear> slightly jaundiced.</p>
<p>ALIMENTARY SYSTEM - Vomiting present, bilious character. Epigastrium<lb/>
very tender. Liver and spleen tender on palpation, both slightly en-<lb/>
larged. Stomach intensely irritable. Vomits anything taken, vomit<lb/>
consists of dark greenish bile.</p>
<p><hi>CIRCULATORY SYSTEM</hi> - Pulse slow, low tension 90 mt: Heart sounds normal.</p>
<p><hi>NERVOUS SYSTEM</hi> Severe frontal headache, aching pain in the loins and<lb/>
limbs, mind quite clear.</p>
<p><hi>URINARY SYSTEM</hi> - Urine had been freely passed the day before but none<lb/>
passed since 10 P.M., last night (30th Oct.) At 2 P.M. patient passed<lb/>
<unclear>zt</unclear> of bloody urine.</p>
<p><hi>EXAMINATION</hi> Acid reaction - Blood present, Albumen present in large<lb/>
amount. Casts present, hyaline as well as granular.</p>
<p><hi>BLOOD EXAMINATION</hi> - Few malaria parasites present - subtertian,<lb/>
Haemoglobin 85%. Polymorphonuclears numerous. No actual Leucocytosis.<lb/>
Patient sponged, cold application to head and mustard leaf to epigastrium.<lb/>
One pint normal saline solution given high up rectum and retained.<lb/>
Calomel grs: IV in 1 gr: doses given hourly. Intramuscular injection<lb/>
of quinine bihydrochlor grs; 6 given.</p>
<p>6. P.M. Patient more comfortable, no vomiting since application of mustard<lb/>
leaf. Saline retained, and repeated 6 P.M. Cold barley water given<lb/>
to allay thirst and retained. Temp: 101.8 P.80.</p>
<p>11. P.M. Patient vomited at 8:30 P.M., 4 ozs of dark green bile; mustard leaf<lb/>
repeated to epigastrium. Bowels opened once. Yellow watery stool.<lb/>
Temp: 101.4, P.80. at 10 P.M. Vomited again at 11, 2 ozs: green bile.<lb/>
Passed 2 ozs urine at 10 P.M. dark yellow in colour, clearer.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01005003"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p><hi>EXAMINATION</hi> - No blood or haemoglobin, acid reaction, 1018 sp: gr:<lb/>
Albumin present, Perspiring profusely.</p>
<p>1/11/22 Patient was quiet but did not sleep, retained his saline and all<lb/>
fluids from 11 P.M. to 6 A.M. when vomiting again occurred, greenish<lb/>
yellow bile. Bowels moved at 7.15 A.M.- large watery yellow offensive<lb/>
motion. Passed 2 ozs: urine at 7:15 yellow in colour, acid reaction,<lb/>
albumin present in large amount. Temp: (Rectal) 100. P. 72. Passed<lb/>
1/2 oz: urine at 11, similar to last specimen, albumin present. Vomited<lb/>
at 4:30 P.M. dark green bile. Retained his rectal salines, also<lb/>
iced Champagne and Barley Water. Temp: at 6 P.M. 99.4 (Rectal) P.62<lb/>
low tension. At 6 P.M. 1/2 oz of urine passed similar to last specimen.<lb/>
At 9:30 P.M. patient vomited 10 oz of dark brown fluid, black debris<lb/>
on standing. Very restless at 10:30 P.M. passed one <unclear>drachm</unclear> of urine -<lb/>
cloudy, acid reaction, albumin present, no haemoglobin. Temp: at 10 P.M.<lb/>
99.4. (Rectal) P.60.</p>
<p>2/11/22 Patient very restless, practically no sleep, had vomited at 1:15 A.M.<lb/>
6 ozs of dark brown fluid with black debris. Retained his rectal salines.<lb/>
Vomiting again occurred, similar to last specimen at 6 A.M. Thirst<lb/>
intense, will only take small pieces of ice to suck. No urine passed<lb/>
since 10:30 P.M. last night. Fermentations to loins continued. Mind<lb/>
quite clear. No effort in vomiting, simply gushes out. Intravenous<lb/>
saline 18 ozs; given at 10:15 A.M. Temp: at 9 A.M. 98.6 P.70.<lb/>
Vomiting continued, dark brown fluid with black debris. Tongue is<lb/>
clean and with red tip and edges. At 2 P.M. patient vomited 6 ozs<lb/>
of black fluid, very heavy black deposit on standing. Temp: at 12:30<lb/>
101 P.92 Sclerae show jaundice. Vomited again at 1:15, 8 ozs of<lb/>
black fluid with debris. No urine passed at all, restlessness marked,<lb/>
vomiting again occurred at 2,3, and 3:15 P.M., dark reddish fluid<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01005004"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
with black deposit on standing. At 6 P.M. Catheter passed and 1 oz. of<lb/>
urine obtained: Acid reaction, cloudy, albumin present - large amount:<lb/>
T. 99, P.60. Hiccough appeared and was very distressing. Vomiting con-<lb/>
tinued through the night, dark red fluid with black debris. Patient doz-<lb/>
ing in the intervals. Temp: at 10 P.M. 99.4 P. 58. Epigastrium very<lb/>
tender. Ice Pack to epigastrium retarded the hiccough for a time.</p>
<p>3/11/22 Patient very restless, hiccough and vomiting continued, sleep only pos-<lb/>
sible at intervals. Vomited fluid is dark reddish black with black<lb/>
debris on standing. No urine passed. Catheter passed at 12 noon and<lb/>
only 1 oz of yellow pale cloudy urine obtained.</p>
<p><hi>EXAMINATION</hi> - Acid, highly albuminous, No Bile. No haemoglobin or blood.<lb/>
Esbach's Estimation of Albumin for 24 hours gave a result of 16 grms<lb/>
albumen per oz :- 1% Hiccough very distressing, but vomiting causes no<lb/>
effort. Solerae are pale yellow. Retains rectal salines. Intravenous<lb/>
saline 16 ozs given at 3 P.M. stopped hiccough. Pulse improved 58 mt:<lb/>
low tension. Temp at 6 P.M. 100.2, P. 55 Dozes at intervals. Hiccough<lb/>
returned at 10:30.P.M. vomitting recommenced, dark reddish fluid 10 ozs.<lb/>
at a time. Temp: at 10 P.M. 99., P.50.</p>
<p>4/11/22 Patient had a bad night, little sleep, hiccough and vomiting very dis-<lb/>
tressing. Epigastric pain complained of. Tongue red and clean. Mind<lb/>
quite clear. Temp: at 6 A.M. (rectal) 99.2 P. 50 low tension. No urine<lb/>
since catheter passed yesterday. Catheter passed at 10. and <unclear>1"3/4</unclear> ozs<lb/>
drawn off - similar to last specimen - yellow and cloudy. Acid, highly<lb/>
albuminous. Retained the glucose and saline injections. Temp: at<lb/>
6 P.M. 100., P.60 Very distressed, hiccough and vomiting continuous;<lb/>
only ice to suck given to allay thirst. Sclerae yellow, complains of<lb/>
burning pain in epigastrium. Ice applied. Vomited matter throughout<lb/>
day varied from black to dark red with black debris on standing.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01005005"/>
<p>- 5 -</p>
<p>5/11/22 General condition same, no improvement, hiccough and vomiting continue.<lb/>
No urine passed for 24 hours, Catheter passed at 10 A.M. and 3 1/2 ozs:<lb/>
obtained, increased since last catheterisation due to Intravenous saline<lb/>
16 ozs: <hi>Examination</hi> - Acid, pale, yellow, cloudy, No bile, albumin pres-<lb/>
ent. Percentage for last 24 hours equals 3/4% equals 12 grs: albumin<lb/>
per oz. Retains the rectal glucose and saline. Temp: at 6 A.M. - 100.,<lb/>
P 58, at 2 P.M. 100.2., P. 60, and at 6 P.M., 99.8., P. 50. Temperature<lb/>
taken rectally owing to the fact that iced fluid and ice was taken by<lb/>
the mouth. Axillary temp: is 1<unclear>&deg;</unclear> lower than rectal. Vomited matter con-<lb/>
sisted of black slightly acid fluid varying from 8 to 10 ozs and occurring<lb/>
nearly every hour or oftener sometimes. Bowel washed out with large<lb/>
warm saline. Very distressed and restless. Mind quite clear.</p>
<p>6/11/22 General condition much the same, hiccough and vomiting still present de-<lb/>
spite all treatment attempted. At 2 A.M. and again at 3 bowels moved -<lb/>
dark red offensive fluid. Temp: at 6 A.M. 98.8 P.60. No urine passed<lb/>
all yesterday since catheter passed at 11 A.M. 4 1/2 ozs. of cloudy urine<lb/>
drawn off (an increase on last quantity).</p>
<p><hi>EXAMINATION</hi> - Faintly acid. Sp. Gr: 1008. No blood, albumin present.<lb/>
Estimation for last 24 hours 8 grs per oz - 1/2%. Pulse bad, injection<lb/>
of camphor in oil given at 11:45 A.M. Improved later. At 6 P.M., con-<lb/>
dition unchanged. Hiccough despite treatment, very distressing and pract-<lb/>
ically continuous. Vomiting every half hour. Calcium Chloride grs 15<lb/>
added to Rectal Saline, retained, Temp: at 2 P.M., 100., P. 60 low<lb/>
tension at 11 P.M. pulse irregular. Inject Strychnine P. 56., T. 100.</p>
<p>7/11/22 Condition very bad but mind quite clear, slept for only 1/2 hour during<lb/>
the night. Hiccough constant. Vomiting practically every hour 4 to 8 ozs:<lb/>
dark brown fluid. Petechial haemorrhage appeared on arms and scrotum and<lb/>
under finger nails - also seen on M.M. of mouth. Haemorrhages from gums.<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01005006"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
No urine passed. Intravenous Injection Saline at 9 A.M., 16 oz.<lb/>
Catheter passed at 9:30 and 5 3/4 ozs. of urine drawn off. Pale yellow,<lb/>
very cloudy, faintly acid. - Sp: Gr: 1010, highly albuminous. No bile.<lb/>
Estimation of Albumin for previous 24 hours - 6 grs: per oz: 10 A.M.<lb/>
patient quieter. Temp: 99., P.66. Hiccough not so distressing. At<lb/>
2:30 P.M. vomiting recommended - dark reddish brown fluid, Black Debris.<lb/>
Hypo-Injection Ernutin m: 10 repeated in 4 hours. Bowels began to move<lb/>
and by 10.10 P.M. three dark red offensive stools passed. No urine since<lb/>
last catheterisation. Temp: at 6 P.M. 99., 4., P. 70.</p>
<p>8/11/22 Patient had a restless night, dozed at intervals after Bromide and Chloral<lb/>
Injection given at 2 P.M. yesterday. Hiccough very distressing, vomiting<lb/>
still continues despite any treatment. Retains the rectal saline and<lb/>
glucose given 4 hourly. Temp: at 6 A.M. 99., P. 66 low tension. Catheter<lb/>
Passed at 10 A.M. 11 ozs: of urine drawn off - pale yellow, cloudy, faint-<lb/>
ly acid. No bile. Albumin present. Estimation of albumin for 24 hours<lb/>
4 grains per oz:, Vomited matter consists of dark red fluid. Bowels moved -<lb/>
large reddish brown offensive watery motion, General Condition bad, pulse<lb/>
low tension, Patient dozed from 3 to 3:30 P.M. Mind very clear. At 11 P.M.<lb/>
catheter again passed and 5 ozs: of urine drawn off similar in character<lb/>
to last specimen. Pulse 65. Very low tension. Injection of Stryohnine.<lb/>
.0002 grm given.</p>
<p>9/11/22 Patient dozed for a short period but hiccough and vomiting began again at<lb/>
1 <unclear>P.M.</unclear> Very restless and irritable. Subsultus Tendinum present. Temp:<lb/>
at 2 A.M. 97 (axillary) 98 (rectal) P. 72 irregular. Hiccough distress-<lb/>
ing. At 2:30 A.M. a petechial rash appeared. Haemorrhages from gums.<lb/>
Bowels moving - dark red offensive motions. At 6 A.M. Temp: 96 (axillary)<lb/>
rectal 97. Skin cold and clammy. <unclear>Sclerae</unclear> yellow. At 10 A.M. general<lb/>
condition the same. Mind perfectly clear. Vomiting continuous - dark<lb/>
red fluid. Catheter passed and 6 ozs: of cloudy yellow urine drawn off.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f01005007"/>
<p>- 7 -</p>
<p><hi>EXAMINATION</hi> - Faintly soid Sp: Gr: 1010 albumin present. Petechial<lb/>
haemorrhages on M.M. of mouth and in skin over thorax. Injection<lb/>
Digitalis. .0001 grm: Tongue clean and red. Quite conscious. Vomit-<lb/>
ing and hiccough continued, dark reddish brown fluid, faintly acid.<lb/>
At 12 noon general condition became very bad. Pulse irregular. Temp:<lb/>
96.4 very restless. At 3 P.M. convulsions came on, not violent, and<lb/>
death took place at 3:30 P.M.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Sgd) <unclear>Thoms</unclear>. M. Russell-Leonard.<lb/>
S.M.O.<lb/>
AG: Asst: Director of<lb/>
Medical Services., C. D.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-10-31">
<pb n="8" id="f01005008"/>
<p>TREATMENT - DIET.<lb/>
_____________</p>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="4">
	<row>
		<cell>DATE</cell>
		<cell>PRESCRIPTION AND ORDERS</cell>
		<cell>DIET</cell>
		<cell>EXTRAS</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>31/10/22</cell>
		<cell>R/. Aspirin grs 10, Sponge down<lb/> Mustard leaf to epigastrium 1 hr</cell>
		<cell>Barley Water<lb/>Soda "</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>R/. Calomel grs. 1 to be given<lb/>every hour for 4 doser.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>2:30 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>Rectal Saline - 1 pt.<lb/>Repeat at 5:30 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>6 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>Intramusc. Inject. Quin. Bihy-<lb/>drochlor grs 6</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>8 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>Repeat Rectal Saline - 1 pt:</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>1/11/22</cell>
		<cell>R/. Sodii Bicarb grs. 10<lb/>Liq. Hydrag. Perchlor Perchlor m. 30<lb/>
			Aqua ad 1 oz.<lb/>Ft tales 10 oz.<lb/>1 oz. in water every 4 hours<lb/>
			Fomentations to Loins<lb/>Repeat Rectal Saline 10 ozs.<lb/>4 hourly.</cell>
		<cell>Ice to suck</cell>
		<cell>Champagne<lb/>Iced 1/2 oz<lb/>in sips<lb/>frequently.</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>2/11/22<lb/>2:30 A.M.)</cell>
		<cell>Hypo Inject. Morphine grs 1/6</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>10 A.M.</cell>
		<cell>Intramusc. Inject. Quin. Bihydrochlor grs 6<lb/>Intravenous Saline Inject. 16 ozs.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>3 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>R/. Solution Sodii Sulphi drm.<lb/>in 1 oz or 2 oz in 1/2 pt. warm water<lb/>Rectal Inject. every 4 hours.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>9 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>Ice bag to epigastrium.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>3/11/22</cell>
		<cell>Intravenous Saline Inject: 16 ozs.<lb/>Stop mixture of 1/11/22</cell>
		<cell>Lime Water<lb/>with Barley</cell>
		<cell>Stop<lb/>Champagne</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>10 A.M.</cell>
		<cell>Amyl Nitris Capsule-Inhalation<lb/>when hiccough bad.</cell>
		<cell>water</cell>
		<cell>Brandy - X</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>3 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>Glucose Solution 1 drm to 8 ozs.<lb/>Saline sol: Rectally - 4 hourly.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>Iced sips of<lb/>2 drms every<lb/>2 hrs.</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>4/11/22</cell>
		<cell>Intravenous Saline - 16 ozs.<lb/>Hypo Inject: Strychine. .002 grms.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>5/11/22</cell>
		<cell>R/. ???: Chloride grs. 10<lb/>Aqua ad 1 oz. in 1 oz. as<lb/>directed.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
</table>
</p>
<pb n="9" id="f01005009"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>TREATMENT - DIET.</p>
<p>
<table rows="10" cols="4">
	<row>
		<cell>DATE</cell>
		<cell>PRESCRIPTION AND ORDERS</cell>
		<cell>DIET</cell>
		<cell>EXTRAS</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>11 A.M.</cell>
		<cell>Intravenous Saline - 16 ozs. Wash<lb/>out lower Bowel and rectum Warm<lb/>Saline.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>7/11/22</cell>
		<cell>R/. Pot. Bromide grs. 30 Chloral</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>2 A.M.</cell>
		<cell>Hydras grs 15 Aqua ad 2 ozs.<lb/>In - Rectal Injection.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>3:45 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>Hypo Inject. Emetin m. 10.<lb/>Repeat at 10 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>8/11/22</cell>
		<cell>Hypo Inject. Emetin m. 10.<lb/>Strychnine .002 grm.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>10 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>Repeat Bromide &amp; chloral Inject.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>9/11/22<lb/>9 A.M.</cell>
		<cell>Rectal Saline - 1 pt.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>10 A.M.</cell>
		<cell>Hypo Digitaline .0001 grm.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
	<row>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>Death at 3:30 P.M.</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
		<cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	</row>
</table>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-10-31">
<pb n="10" id="f01005010"/>
<p>POST MORTEM RECORD.</p>
<p>___________________</p>
<p>Death 3:30 P.M. - 9/11/22.</p>
<p>Post Mortem Examination performed 2 hours after death - 5:30 P.M.</p>
<p>
<table rows="19" cols="2">
     <row>
          <cell>Skin</cell>
          <cell>Very sallow. Hypostatic congestion very marked on all dependent<lb/>
               parts. Ecchymosis of scrotum marked. Petechial haemorrhages present<lb/>
               on arms and thighs. Sclerae pale yellow.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>General<lb/>nutrition and<lb/>development</cell>
          <cell>-</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Rigor mortis</cell>
          <cell>Had not begun. Subcutaneous tissue pale yellow.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Brain and<lb/>Membranes.</cell>
          <cell>Appeared normal.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Spinal cord</cell>
          <cell>-</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Membranes</cell>
          <cell>-</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Heart</cell>
          <cell>Weight 11 ozs. Ventricles contracted. Valves normal. Pericardium<lb/>
               contained 2 ozs. of clear fluid.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Large Vessels</cell>
          <cell>Normal</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Lungs: Right.</cell>
          <cell>Weight 24 ozs. Normal in appearance and section.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Left</cell>
          <cell>Weight 23 1/2 ozs. Normal in appearance and section.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Pleurae</cell>
          <cell>Normal. A little clear fluid present in each cavity.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Larynx, Trachea,<lb/>and Bronchi.</cell>
          <cell>Normal, Small petechial haemorrhages seen in m.m. of Trachea</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Peritoneum</cell>
          <cell>Normal. Abdominal cavity contained 6 ozs. clear fluid.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Stomach</cell>
          <cell><hi>Externally</hi> - showed congestion. <hi>Internally</hi> M. Membrane intensely con-<lb/>
               gested and thrown into folds. Haemorrhages present all over, particular-<lb/>
               ly at Oesophageal and Pyloric openings and along greater curvature. 4 ozs<lb/>
               of thick dark red gelatinous fluid present.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Small Intestine</cell>
          <cell>Duedenum intensely congested. M. Membrane shows intense congestion and<lb/>
               haemorrhagic areas. Ileum in the same condition. Contents - dark brown<lb/>
               offensive fluid.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Large Intestine</cell>
          <cell>Congested in patches externally. M. Membraneeappears normal. Contents -<lb/>
               dark brownish red offensive fluid.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Helminths</cell>
          <cell>None present.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Liver</cell>
          <cell>Enlarged. Weight 70 ozs. Mottled appearance externally. Small yellow<lb/>
               areas. On section pale yellowish in parts. Greasy on section.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Gall Bladder</cell>
          <cell>Distended. 2 ozs. of dark green bile present. No stones.</cell>
     </row>
</table>
<pb n="11" id="f01005011"/>
<table rows="10" cols="2">
     <row>
	     <cell>&nbsp;</cell>
	     <cell>- 2 -</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Pancreas</cell>
	     <cell>Weight 11 ozs. Normal in appearance.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Spleen</cell>
	     <cell>Enlarged. Weight 18 1/2 ozs. very dark in colour. Soft on section<lb/>
		     shows a distinct mottled appearance.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Kidneys: Right</cell>
	     <cell>Enlarged. Weight 9 1/4 ozs Capsule strips. On section, Cortex pale.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Left</cell>
	     <cell>Enlarged. Weight 9 ozs. Similar to Right Kidney.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Suprarenal capsules</cell>
	     <cell>Normal.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Lymphatic system</cell>
	     <cell>Normal.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Bladder</cell>
	     <cell>Contracted. M. M. congested. Contains 1 oz yellow cloudy urine.<lb/>
		     Faintly acid. Albumin present. Microscopic examination - Casts<lb/>
		     present.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Ovaries</cell>
	     <cell>&nbsp;</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
	     <cell>Uterus and<lb/>Fallopian Tubes.</cell>
	     <cell>&nbsp;</cell>
     </row>
</table></p>
<p>__________________________________________</p>
<p>N.B. Portions of all organs preserved in 8% formalin given<lb/>
to Dr. Young, Yaba Research - also blood slides and<lb/>
smears from kidney, Spleen, Liver, Lung.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
