<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01001019">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to the Western Carolina Power Company, September 18, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01001019</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-09-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="place">Bridgewater (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>14 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-09-18">September 18, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01001019</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to the Western Carolina Power Company, September 18, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter reports on his survey of mosquito breeding in certain portions of Bridgewater Lake and the surrounding area.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-09-18">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to the Western Carolina Power Company, September 18, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01001019"/>
<p>Bridgewater (Sept/22)<lb/>
CHARLOTTE, N. C.<lb/>
<date value="1922-09-18">Sept. 18, 1922.</date>
Western Carolina Power Company,<lb/>
Charlotte, N. C.<lb/>
Gentlemen:</p>
<p>I have the honor to submit this report of a survey<lb/>
to determine mosquito breeding in certain portions of Bridgewater<lb/>
Lake and in some of the breeding places, streams, marshes etc. in<lb/>
its neighborhood, made during the four days Sept. 12th to 15th in-<lb/>
clusive. This survey is a continuation of those made Aug. 16th<lb/>
to 22nd, 1921 and July 17th and 18th of this year, and this report<lb/>
is to be considered in connection with the other two.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>(A). LAND-BREEDING OF ANOPHELES MOSQUITOES</p>
<p>I must premise by saying, that the weather was exceed-<lb/>
ingly unfavorable for land breeding of Anopheles--meaning the<lb/>
breeding in streams, ponds, marshes etc. as distinguished from<lb/>
pond-breeding. It was exceedingly dry, I was informed by many<lb/>
farmers that there had been no rain for over four weeks and conse-<lb/>
quently many marshes and <unclear>small</unclear> streams were dry and only permanent<lb/>
collection of water were breeding Anopheles. Naturally the amount<lb/>
of breeding <add>on land</add> of this kind then, was less than would have been found<lb/>
under normal conditions, say two to three or four weeks earlier.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p><unclear>(1)</unclear> THE JAMISON PLACE</p>
<p>Mrs. Hemphill occupies the house which she states was<lb/>
occupied by Jamison last year. This is about 400 yards beyond<lb/>
Nebo Station., up the valley from the station<unclear>:</unclear> on the ridge between<lb/>
this valley and the next one.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) A pot-hole, not much larger than a wash tub, was<lb/>
in the woods about 120 yards from the house, and to the west of it,<lb/>
is breeding Anopheles profusely<unclear>.</unclear> Too small to be of <del>much</del> impor-<lb/>
tance. There were evidently a series of these <add>holes</add> in a ravine the<lb/>
others of which have dried up. All of them breeding would have<lb/>
been of sanitary importance.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f01001020"/>
<item>-2-</item>
<item>(b) West of the house, 200 to 250 yards in a good<lb/>
sized pool at the intersection of the ravine with the branch<lb/>
breeding Anopheles very profusely, all sizes; 100 larvae and<lb/>
pupae taken.</item>
<item>(c) Two small eddies in this branch breeding freely.<lb/>
Other eddies seen but not examined.</item>
<item><p>(d) Same branch as (b) and (c), at the junction with<lb/>
another branch from the right, Anopheles breeding freely in<lb/>
side pools and <unclear>eddies</unclear>, the same above this junction.</p>
<p>The larvae from these breeding places developed into<lb/>
Anopheles punctipennis Sept. 13th 14th and 15th.</p>
<p>Of the above places (b) is of the greatest sanitary<lb/>
importance on account of its position and the freedon of its<lb/>
breeding.</p></item>
</list></p></item>
<item>(2) THE BOST HOUSE.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Branch from the spring to the creek cleaned out.<lb/>
Work very well done except some caving near the spring and<lb/>
near the creek end. Not dipped but the latter place would pro-<lb/>
bably be breeding Anopheles as it was doing so profusely last<lb/>
year. It is only a very small area now, however. <unclear>No S. C.</unclear></item>
<item>(b) The marsh across the creek from his house at the<lb/>
bridge is also ditched and free from water, except a very<lb/>
samll pool which is breeding tremendously. (a concentration<lb/>
pool.) It is too small to be of <add>any</add> sanitary importance.</item>
<item>(c) The edges of the creek about the bridge below,<lb/>
under and above, are breeding freely where the water is flowing<lb/>
slowly and grass hangs down in it. This was not breeding last<lb/>
year when the creek was high. This is of sanitary importance.</item>
</list></item>
<item><p>(3) LEWIS HOUSE (MRS. EDITH LEWIS AND SON).</p>
<p>This house is higher up the creek than Mr. Bost's<lb/>
and on the other side of both the creek and railroad. It is,<lb/>
roughly, one-quarter to one-third mile distance from Bost's and<lb/>
probably 100 or 125 yards from Mrs. Weaver's house which is on<lb/>
the same side of the railroad with it and just above it. This<lb/>
place, Weaver's and Bost's are all close enough to be affected<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01001021"/>
-3-<lb/>
by the breeding in the area around the old Mill race.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) A small branch from back of the Lewis house, just<lb/>
below it, runs through the railroad. The lower portion of this<lb/>
from the crossing to the main creek is breeding Anopheles<lb/>
freely. (Dr. Boldridge examined this, I did not see it). A<lb/>
large pool at the railroad, say 150 yards from the house, is<lb/>
breeding Culex profusely, a few Anopheles, but not of sanitary<lb/>
importance. It is evidently badly contaminated.</item>
<item>(b) The pools in and about the old mill race which<lb/>
were breeding so profusely last year, are still breeding, but<lb/>
very much less so. Some are entirely dried up and some are<lb/>
scummed. Two only are breeding profusely. One good size and<lb/>
one small. Those that are dried up have done so recently as<lb/>
the ground is very boggy. Water rises in one's track as the<lb/>
foot comes out of the mud.</item>
<item><p>(c) The creek itself is breeding, <hi>and breeding freely</hi>,<lb/>
in every eddy and side pool around this place. On the grassy<lb/>
banks and behind little hammocks. It is producing more than<lb/>
the pools around the Mill race. This condition of breeding ex-<lb/>
tends both up and down as far as we examined, say 100 feet<lb/>
each way. The same condition was found above ((a): <unclear>(b)</unclear> &amp; <unclear>(c)</unclear> - pages 3 &amp; 4) &amp; below ((c)<lb/>
page 2): &amp; doubtless extends more or less, up the <unclear>each other</unclear>.</p>
<p>These last places (a), (b) and (c) are none of them<lb/>
more than 300 yards from the Lewis house and some of them less<lb/>
than 200. The pools in the upperpart of the old mill race and<lb/>
the breeding part of the creek are some 100 to 150 yards of the<lb/>
Weaver house. These places are also close enough to Mr. Bost's<lb/>
house to affect it, but less than they would the other two.</p></item>
</list></p></item>
<item>(C) MASON'S HOUSE, one-half mile more or less up<lb/>
the creek from Mrs. Weaver's house, between creek and railroad;<lb/>
about 50 yards from railroad.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) In the main creek just below the mouth of a small<lb/>
branch is long back-water 30 to 40 feet, breeding profusely<lb/>
about 300 yards from house and below the house.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f01001022"/>
<item>-4-</item>
<item>(b) Same condition occurs in some eddies in the<lb/>
creek a few yards, 30 to 40, above this place. All sizes and<lb/>
pupae.</item>
<item>(c) Meadow at the angle of the creek and this branch<lb/>
near the old sawdust pile, dry now, but evidenly marshy in or-<lb/>
dinary weather. A few cat-tails, many bulrushes and the hollows<lb/>
show bare; glazed; cracked surfaces. This place would be physi-<lb/>
cally well suited for Anopheles breeding in the ordinary wet<lb/>
weather of the summer.</item>
<item>(d) A creek, small, beyond Mr. Mason's house, say<lb/>
60 yards, a few Anopheles near the crossing, but of no sanitary<lb/>
importance and none further down. This creek higher up towards<lb/>
the railroad is breeding freely or profusely, all sizes, where-<lb/>
ever grass or other obstructions are down in the water or where<lb/>
there is any little indentation of the bank. The total of this<lb/>
breeding is large. It is from 100 to 200 yards from the house.</item>
<item><p>(e) The main creek above the house about the edge of<lb/>
the cornfield 300 yards from the house is breeding moderately<lb/>
or freely.</p>
<p>This creek would not breed <add><del><unclear>-a would not head nimb-</unclear></del></add> in wet weather. It runs too<lb/>
freely. At that time, however, the marshes and small streams<lb/>
now dry, would be physically suited for breeding and doubtless<lb/>
be breeding.</p></item>
</list></item>
<item>(5) MISS CORA BRITTAIN'S HOUSE: About one-quarter<lb/>
mile above Hendrix and probably one-third of a mile below Carswell's.<lb/>
North side of railroad.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Four Anopheles larvae taken in the spring. One<lb/>
winged insect, Anopheles punctipennis, caught in barn. Spring about<lb/>
40 or 50 yards from house, of no sanitary importance</item>
<item>(b) Branch runs down out of the pasture close by the<lb/>
spring and house to the big creek. Presents many places physi-<lb/>
cally well suited for breeding--pools, eddies etc., but has no<lb/>
breeding of sanitary importance. Is very full of Dixa larvae<lb/>
which is probably the reason for the absence of the Anopheles.</item>
<pb n="5" id="f01001023"/>
<item>-5-</item>
<item>(c) The main creek, probably 300 <add>or 350</add> yards from the house,<lb/>
is breeding in grass and behind hammocks, but less freely than<lb/>
it is above.</item>
<item>(d) In the angle between the creek and the branch, left<lb/>
side of both, about 250 yards from the house, is a meadow, dry now,<lb/>
but in which there has recently been pools. The ground is still<lb/>
wet; glazed and cracked, but there is no water standing. This<lb/>
place should have been physically well fit for breeding, say seven<lb/>
days ago.</item>
</list></item>
<item>(6) CARSWELL'S. Small pool, on Mr. Pyatts land, I<lb/>
think, close to box for minnows. Breeding freely. About one doxen<lb/>
and half Anopheles taken from it. 100 yards from the Carswell<lb/>
house.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(b) The branch going down from this place is not<lb/>
breeding sufficiently to be of sanitary importance. Many Dixa<lb/>
larvae.</item>
<item>(c) The main creek running between this place and Bost's<lb/>
breeding moderately opposite this house, probably one-quarter or<lb/>
one-third of a mile distant.</item>
<item>(d) This house is about one-third of a mile from the<lb/>
places that were breeding so freely on Mr. Bost's land last year.<lb/>
In his spring branch and the marsh between the hog pen and the bridge.<lb/>
(See report of Aug. 21st, Page 4.) These two and the creek are of<lb/>
greater importance in affecting this place than the pool within<lb/>
the 100 yards unless it was generally producing more freely than<lb/>
when we examined it--which I judge it is in wet weather.</item>
</list></item>
<item>(7) HOUSE OF RAYMOND LEWIS: About 200 yards or 250<lb/>
yards from Nebo higher up the valley. No one in the house when<lb/>
we called.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) A stream runs from behind the house and then across<lb/>
the road and railroad from 20 to 50 yards distant from the house,--<lb/>
breeding Anopheles freely or profusely; all sizes of larvae and<lb/>
pupae <add>&amp; in great number</add>. The only place that was not breeding in at is a piece of<lb/>
about 25 feet long where ducks evidently bathe. It was breeding<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01001024"/>
-6-<lb/>
most freely where just crossing the road. At a pool dammed up<lb/>
just below the railroad, we took 60 to 75 larvae and 15 pupae.</item>
</list></item>
<item><p>(8) MR. AND MRS. EDWARDS' HOUSE ON THE SOUTH SIDE<lb/>
OF THE RIVER.</p>
<p>This is the place (2) Culverson's Creek on Page 5 of<lb/>
the report of July 18, 1922.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Small marsh inside the pasture breeding in July<lb/>
is dry now, absolutely.</item>
<item>(b) The branch running from the spring, breeding<lb/>
slightly in July, is breeding freely now, all sizes; from<lb/>
just above the road crossing up to the fence at the spring, in-<lb/>
creasing as one goes. up.</item>
<item><p>(c) The small marshy places about the spring is<lb/>
breeding freely or profusely now, all sizes and pupae, as is<lb/>
the old abandoned spring. This place is about 100 yards dis-<lb/>
tance from the house of J. W. Edwards, deceased.</p>
<p>The <unclear>joint</unclear> production of (b) &amp; (c)<lb/>
is large &amp; is close to the house<lb/>
<unclear>mentioned</unclear></p></item>
</list></p></item>
<item>(8) GRANT EDWARDS. No one at home. No water found<lb/>
close enough to this house to affect it. Mr. George Whetstine<lb/>
states that Edwards has recently moved here.</item>
<item>(9) GEORGE WHETSTINE'S HOUSE: On the hill not far<lb/>
from Grant Edwards. The only water close by is not breeding and<lb/>
I think would not breed in wet weather. Young woman in house<lb/>
sick. The old woman says with malaria. Mr. Whetstine says had<lb/>
malaria and new baby.</item>
<item>(10) _________GLASS. (colored). Five families live<lb/>
in this settlement; all colored; on the ridge going down to-<lb/>
wards the creek that flows into the pond at Curtis' place. There<lb/>
is probably 300 yards distance from the one highest on the hill<lb/>
to the one closest to the spring.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) This is the place marked &ldquo; (3) Station X &rdquo; on<lb/>
page 5 of the report of July 18th. All this section was breed-<lb/>
ing in July. A few are found in the creek now, but the marshes<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01001025"/>
-7-<lb/>
are dried up, with cracked glazed bottoms of the old pools.<lb/>
This creek goes down and empties into the pond just above what<lb/>
I am told is the old Curtis place, roughly, a mile from the<lb/>
spring. All of this bottom is marshy. The lower part is one<lb/>
big marsh. We did not go into it.</item>
</list></item>
<item><p>(11) THE CURTIS PLACE.</p>
<p>The house has just been torn down; chimney still<lb/>
standing; said to be the place George Whetstine lived last<lb/>
year. Is about 50 yards from the edge of the pond and close<lb/>
to, say 300 yards from the lower part of the marsh on the last<lb/>
creek mentioned. The spring branch just below his house, 40<lb/>
yards distant, is marshy, but not breeding of no sanitary im-<lb/>
portance. Where there is no blood supply for the Anopheles<lb/>
they are rarely found breeding and as this house is abandoned<lb/>
and there is no stock in the immediate vacinity we would not<lb/>
have expected to find breeding here now, although it might<lb/>
have been present when the house was occupied.</p></item>
</list></p></item>
<pb n="8" id="f01001026"/>
<item><unclear>1 Page</unclear></item>
<item><p>(B) EXAMINATION OF POND.</p>
<p>The pond by my measure is 6 or 7 feet below the<lb/>
ordinary <add>(top of <unclear>spillway</unclear>)</add> grade.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item><unclear>(1)</unclear> The Club House is screened with #12 wire.<lb/>
Chimneys not screened and door loose. No Anopheles found inside.<lb/>
(No complaint made by guests.) Bath houses not screened; cool<lb/>
and moist. No Anopheles found. Two good size spider webs on<lb/>
the mens' side. No Anopheles found on them. Small house on<lb/>
the hill examined by Dr. Boldridge. (He reports none found.)<lb/>
Evidently no winged Anopheles in neighborhood of Club House;<lb/>
#12 wire would not exclude them.</item>
<item>(2) Bight at the left of the <unclear>mouth</unclear> of Mill Creek<lb/>
(Marked (2) on Page one of July report)<lb/>
<unclear></unclear><lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) A few <del><unclear>baby</unclear></del> larvae in stranded alga in seepage - <unclear>not developed Sept 1922</unclear><lb/>
from the hill about 6 feet above the present pond level. The<lb/>
water quite cool here; cooler than the surface of the pond,<lb/>
hence it is seepage. Nothing found in the bulrushes dead,<lb/>
or alive, on either bank of this bight. Many minnows seen<lb/>
along the bank in shore water.</item>
</list></item>
<item>(3) Mouth of stream about 1,000 feet below the Curtis<lb/>
house. No breeding in pond water. Some breeding in a branch<lb/>
from a spring about 20 yards above the pond flowing through<lb/>
grass in which the larvae <add>(a) above</add> are found.</item>
<item>(4) Mouth of creek that comes from Glass's spring<lb/>
emptying in above the Curtis house.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) No breeding found in bight of pond or in the<lb/>
backwater of creek. Many minnows seen in edges of pond in<lb/>
shallow water.</item>
<item>(b) A flat on the left bank of the creek has evidently<lb/>
been dry sometime, had young grass on it as long as one's finger.<lb/>
Many bulrushes in clumps are there and when the water was, say,<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01001027"/>
-2-<lb/>
four to five feet higher than at present, these bulrushes<lb/>
had formed a place physically suitable for Anopheles breeding.<lb/>
There is however, no evidence of alga having been among them.<lb/>
A few patches of dried alga, greenish spots on the ground are<lb/>
seen on the right side of the creek in the open.</item>
</list></item>
<item><p>(5) MOUTH OF TWO LOG CREEK.</p>
<p>This is a bight of Mill creek (Marked 1, Page one of<lb/>
the July report).<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) The pond here and the back-water are absolutely<lb/>
free from breeding. A fair number of minnows on the edge in<lb/>
shore water.</item>
<item>(b) Going up the creek on land about one-third of a mile<lb/>
from the pond, a good sized marshy place was found breeding<lb/>
fairly. This is the place marked (1) on Page 4 of the July report.<lb/>
It is breeding now, much more freely than it was in July. The<lb/>
creek above this forks and both forks, the right especially, have<lb/>
<del>a</del> wide marshy bottoms. The creek itself was not breeding at or<lb/>
near its mouth.</item>
</list></p></item>
<item>(6) Bight 250 below the last one (nearer the pond),<lb/>
Two streams going in, both small, <del>but</del> (the larger one is to the<lb/>
right), join before reaching the back-water. Neither stream is<lb/>
breeding. There are two pools in the valley of the larger<lb/>
stream both scummed, one with red water, the other might have<lb/>
bred two weeks ago. A fair amount of trash and some alga, of<lb/>
unknown species, about the head of the bight. This was dipped<lb/>
very carefully, over 100 dips made, but nothing found.</item>
<item>(7) Off the mouth of Culvertson's Creek, (see #3, Page<lb/>
1, July report). This is a long bight.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Banks on the right side is steep and cut by waves<lb/>
from its commencement to the old road--showing that there has<lb/>
been much wave action there and breeding impossible.</item>
<item>(b) The old road is sunken and should have made still<lb/>
water and <add>hence</add> given protection from the <unclear>wave.</unclear> Some stranded floatage<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f01001028"/>
-3-<lb/>
near the present water line in this old road which might have<lb/>
given protection from fish. There is then a <hi>possibility</hi><lb/>
of there having been breeding in the old road before the pond<lb/>
reached its present level. There is a school of minnows in<lb/>
the road and at present it is absolutely free from breeding.</item>
<item>(c) Beyond the road the ridge showed wave action by<lb/>
the floatage at some places.</item>
<item>(d) No breeding in back-water, breeding in the creek<lb/>
itself well above the pond, but not of sanitary importance,<lb/>
probably washed down from above. (This is the creek that runs<lb/>
from Mr. Edward's house, Page 6 <add>of the <unclear>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></unclear> part</add> of this report. Land Breeding of Anopheles <add>mosquitos</add></item>
<item>(e) On the left hand side of the bight the banks<lb/>
had been well cleared up to the flo<del>at</del><add>w</add>age line but sprouts had<lb/>
come up from many stumps and brushes. Now the sprouts are<lb/>
dead. Sprouts are also standing in the creek bed.</item>
<item>(f) On the left bank beyond the high water, <unclear>the</unclear> water here<lb/>
has been on the grass and up to, and possibly in, the broom-sage<lb/>
edge. If this was so, protection would have been given against<lb/>
the fish and as there is considerably flat ground, wave action<lb/>
would have been impeded, although, there is a long stretch of<lb/>
water from this place southeast and the waves would have<lb/>
bad a long sweep.</item>
</list></item>
<item>(8) Bight<del>s</del> to the east of 7 bears north by west looking<lb/>
up.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>(a) Bight going out to the west side--negative. Runs<lb/>
to main road and beyond the road is a large pond of clear water;<lb/>
<unclear>bank,</unclear><lb/>
not scummed; with grassy except that it has no<lb/>
alga (Frog broth) is apparently an ideal place for Anopheles<lb/>
quadrimaculatus. In it were many Culex and a few very small Ano-<lb/>
pheles. One only full grown and two or three half grown, were<lb/>
taken. Two of us dipped 15 minutes.</p>
<p>One larva developed <unclear>&amp; un Sept</unclear> 23- was A. <unclear>punctepennis</unclear>, like all others<lb/>
found in this section</p></item>
<pb n="11" id="f01001029"/>
<item>-4-</item>
<item><p>(b) Went up to the head of the bight one-half mile<lb/>
or more from the Edwards bight #7. The banks show wave-action<lb/>
nearly to the end. A full wave action too much for breeding<lb/>
to have been possible<del>,</del> except for about 200 feet<del>,</del> from the end<lb/>
where there is a slight bend which shelters the bank from wave-<lb/>
action. The bank is steep on the west side and precipitors on<lb/>
the east side. Evidently there has been much wave action in<lb/>
this bight and breeding, except at the very end <del>b</del><add>h</add>ad, I think,<lb/>
been impossible.</p></item>
</list></item></list></p></item></list></p>
<p><hi>Summary</hi></p>
<p>No Anopheles larvae then were found in the pond<lb/>
water, <del>or,</del> except possibly, those named in (a) of #2 Page 1 of<lb/>
this paper; none <add>other</add> found in any water in any way connected with<lb/>
the pond. These <del>are</del><add>were</add> absolutely of no sanitary importance</p>
<p>Nevertheless, with regard to the investigation of our<lb/>
pond breeding, a criticism somewhat similar to that of the land<lb/>
breeding might be made at least for this years survey, <unclear>i.e.</unclear> that<lb/>
it was not made at the best time.</p>
<p>To determine whether a pond produces Anopheles, very<lb/>
obviously, the examination of the pond should be made <hi>when the<lb/>
conditions are most favorable for such production.</hi> To examine<lb/>
a pond in January and find no Anopheles would be little evidence<lb/>
that it was not breeding in August.</p>
<p>The conditions which control<del>s</del> production in ponds are:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Temperature</item>
<item>(2) Protection against wave action,</item>
<item>(3) Protection against fish.</item>
</list></p>
<p>It is also true that access to a sufficient blood<lb/>
supply-- in this country to men and domestic animal-- tends to<lb/>
affect production.</p>
<p>About Bridgewater, the temperature conditions would gen-<lb/>
erally be best suited for breeding, from about August 15th to<lb/>
September 15th. Protection against wave-action depends on the<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f01001030"/>
-5-<lb/>
<add>configuration of the banks &amp; does not change. It</add> <del>locality and</del> is greatest in the ends of twisted bights of the<lb/>
pond; especially if they have rafts of logs lodged in them.<lb/>
Protection against fish is given by the fine stuff-floatage-<lb/>
washed down into the ends of such bights and by grass on the<lb/>
waters edge when the water is in such grass. Broomstraw and<lb/>
bulrushes would be especially good.</p>
<p>My first survey, Aug. 16th to 22nd inclusive<del><unclear>,</unclear></del> of 1921,<lb/>
was made at the proper time of year. It was made of<del>f</del> the south<lb/>
bank of Catawba pond only, from the dam to a point up the pond<lb/>
one and one-quarter miles from the Bost house. There <add>are</add> a number of<lb/>
twisted bights in this area, some of which have rafts of logs<lb/>
protecting the ends and banks against wave action. In most of<lb/>
these bights there was lots of fine floatage and in a few, grass<lb/>
on the waters edge, giving protection against fish.</p>
<p>All the conditions <del>then</del> of this survey then were favor-<lb/>
able for breeding Anopheles and the examination made at that<lb/>
time was sufficient. No anopheles were found and it is fair to say<lb/>
that none existed in the area examined and it is reasonable to<lb/>
claim the same of similar shores adjacent to those examined. I<lb/>
have given the probable alternative reasons for this in my re-<lb/>
port of Aug. 1921.</p>
<p>For the north side of the Catawba pond and of Paddy<lb/>
Creek as far as examined the water in the bights above the mouth<lb/>
of streams, is shallow. There is no shallow water on <add>the</add> part of<lb/>
the south bank examined. The water in the bights on the north side<lb/>
then should be warmer and indeed is warmer, than that examined in<lb/>
1921.</p>
<p>The survey of July of this year was negative. No breed-<lb/>
ing was found in the pond, although some of the water seemed quite<lb/>
warm, Yet as it would have been warmer later in the season, I could<lb/>
not say that the most favorable temperature for breeding in this<lb/>
section had been reached and hence it was proper to come back<lb/>
later in the summer. The other two conditions at this time-pro-<lb/>
tection against fish and against wave-action-were <unclear>ideal</unclear></p>
<pb n="13" id="f01001031"/>
<p>-6-</p>
<p>The surveys just finished were made the proper time<lb/>
of the year and there was of course the same protection against<lb/>
wave-action as always exists. The pond, however, had fallen from<lb/>
6 1/2 to 7 feet and there was an absolute absence of floatage on the w<lb/>
water edge and except in one place no protection against fish.<lb/>
That there was no breeding in the pond was true, but I wish much,<lb/>
I could have examined it before it was lowered at all, when there<lb/>
would have been, or might have been protection against fish, if<lb/>
there is ever such protection. Had this been the case all condi-<lb/>
tions for Anopheles production has been the best possible in this<lb/>
section of the lake as they were on the south side last year.</p>
<p>Frankly, <del>if</del><add>since</add> there was no breeding up to July 18th, and<lb/>
as all of August, after the 3rd was cold, I profoundly doubt if t<lb/>
there was any production of Anopheles even on the north side of<lb/>
the lake between that time and the date in the latter part of<lb/>
August (Aug 29th) when <add>the</add> pond was lowered. Still I have only my<lb/>
opinion of this, and if I could have made the survey in latter part<lb/>
of August, I feel quite sure I would have had this as an observed<lb/>
facts.</p>
<p>I have to add that the north side of the Catawba lake<lb/>
and Paddy Creek section where I had opportunity to examine them,<lb/>
were well cleared and banks remarkably free from logs and all<lb/>
heavy trash. Indeed this part of the lake showed the cleanest<lb/>
banks of any new pond that I have ever examined.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
H. R. Carter</p>
<pb n="14" id="f01001032"/>
<p>MEMO #1.</p>
<p>I think it will be necessary to determine the distance<lb/>
of the residents of the nearest plaintiff to the nearest part<lb/>
of the lake-- and if it is practical-- to plat them on the map.<lb/>
I note that every one of them to whom I spoke gave the distance<lb/>
as less than the facts.</p>
<p>Respectfully,</p>
<p>MEMO #2.</p>
<p>When all these Bridgewater suits are settled, I<lb/>
would like much to have a survey made without any expense to<lb/>
yourself<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Of the lake the survey<del>ing</del> <add>had</add> better start<del>ed</del> on <del>it<lb/>
from</del> Aug. 1st <add>&amp; last</add> to Sept. 30th and maybe for more than one year.</item>
<item>(2) At the same time a survey of the pools in the<lb/>
old bed of the Catawba and <add>of</add> the pools cut off by the company<lb/>
road.</item>
</list></p>
<p>This would determine whether the pond-breeding<lb/>
mosquito (A. Quad) is breeding in this section, and if not why<lb/>
not.</p>
<p>This investigation would be extremly valuable from a<lb/>
scientific standpoint and would go in with my general investi-<lb/>
gation begun in 1913 of the &ldquo;Effect of Impounding Water of the<lb/>
Incidents of Malaria.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Also, when all the suits are over, I would ask per-<lb/>
mission to use my reports to you as data in some investigation.<lb/>
This, by-the-way is pretty good evidence that I consider such<lb/>
reports as scientifically accurate.</p>
<p>Respectfully,<lb/>
H. R. Carter</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
