<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01001010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Selskar M. Gunn to Frederick F. Russell, August 29, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Gunn, Selskar M</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01001010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-08-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Russell, Frederick F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Antonetti, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Paris (France)</name>
<name type="place">Ivory Coast</name>
<name type="place">Grand Bassam, (Ivory Coast)</name>
<name type="place">Pasteur Institute, Paris (France)</name>
<name type="place">Anetchou (Togo)</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-08-29">August 29, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01001010</idno>
<title>Letter from Selskar M. Gunn to Frederick F. Russell, August 29, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gunn reports to Russell on yellow fever and public health conditions in the Ivory Coast, Africa.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-08-29">
<head>Letter from Selskar M. Gunn to Frederick F. Russell, August 29, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01001010"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD<lb/>
<dateline>
Paris<lb/>
<date value="1922-08-29">August 29, 1922</date>
</dateline>
Dr. F. F. Russell,<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation,<lb/>
61 Broadway<lb/>
New York City<lb/>
<salute>Dear Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am in receipt of a cablegram from you relative to yellow fever<lb/>
at Grand Bassam, Ivory Coast. I am sending you tonight cablegram, copy of<lb/>
which I append.</p>
<p>It so happens that Mr. Antonetti, Lieutenant-Governor of the Ivory<lb/>
Coast is in Paris and I have had an interview with him today. He states<lb/>
that the Medical Service in Grand Bassam is first class and that he does not<lb/>
believe there are any cases hidden. He has a physician on his staff trained<lb/>
at the Pasteur Institute in Paris. All cases are being immediately isolated<lb/>
and out of contact of mosquitoes. He would be very pleased to receive some<lb/>
of the Noguchi serum for treatment and vaccine for immunisation and promises<lb/>
to have his physician make a report on the use of this material if its need<lb/>
is still indicated when it arrives. I told him that I did not know if it<lb/>
would be possible to send these biological products at this time.</p>
<p>According to Mr. Antonetti yellow fever has not been present in<lb/>
the Ivory Coast for years; he did not specify how many. The population of<lb/>
Grand Bassam consists of 150 Europeans and 6,000 negroes. Mr. Antonetti<lb/>
states that mosquitoes are not found in other parts of this colony and that<lb/>
therefore the disease cannot spread within the territory. he states that he<lb/>
has under his direction a well trained sanitary squad of native men who<lb/>
inspect the city from the point of view of mosquito suppression.</p>
<p>He states further that the two big problems to be met in connection<lb/>
with mosquito control consist in the tens of thousands of crab holes which<lb/>
become full of water and excellent breeding places for mosquitoes. These<lb/>
are located very near the town and in the opinion of Mr. Antonetti breed<lb/>
yellow fever mosquitoes. His other problem is in connection with sandy soil<lb/>
near the town where heavy rain stands in pools up to two weeks and present<lb/>
a grave difficulty as far as draining is concerned.</p>
<p>Mr. Antonetti indicates that the physicians at his disposal are<lb/>
thoroughly conversant with yellow fever control. He is in conference with<lb/>
the Pasteur Institute in Paris. Mr. Antonetti further believes that yellow<lb/>
fever of a very mild form is probably endemic amongst the natives who<lb/>
constitute a reservoir of yellow fever virus and which for some obscure<lb/>
reason becomes virulent for Europeans from time to time.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01001011"/>
<p><hi>Dr. F. F. Russell</hi></p>
<p><hi>August 29th, 1922</hi></p>
<p>Mr. Antonetti would be pleased if you would send him directly to<lb/>
Grand Bassam, Cote d'Ivoire, reprints of yellow fever literature and reports<lb/>
of the International Health Board for his medical staff. I doubt if the<lb/>
French Colonial Office would be willing at this time to have a representative<lb/>
of the I.H.B. go to the Ivory Coast, but, of course, have not discussed the<lb/>
matter with anybody as I do not know whether such a thing might be possible<lb/>
for the I.H.B. I have a slight impression that the situation is actually<lb/>
worse than reported to me. The Colonial Office here has just received a<lb/>
cablegram announcing a death from yellow fever at Anetcheou, in Togo. Mr.<lb/>
Antonetti states that ships are constantly coming to Grand Bassam from various<lb/>
points on the west coast of Africa.</p>
<p>If I receive any other information I shall send it to you by mail,<lb/>
and by cable if it seems important.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Selskar M. Gunn</signed>
SMG/OM<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
