<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01002022">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from L.M. Fisher to Henry Rose Carter, October 28, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Fisher, L.M.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01002022</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-10-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="place">Marion (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Badin (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-10-28">October 28, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01002022</idno>
<title>Letter from L.M. Fisher to Henry Rose Carter, October 28, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fisher thanks Carter for his public health recommendations. He describes his anti-malaria work and tells of the prevalence of malaria at North and South Carolina sites.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-10-28">
<head>Letter from L.M. Fisher to Henry Rose Carter, October 28, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01002022"/>
<opener>
JAMES A. HAYNE, M. D.<lb/>
Secretary and State Health Officer<lb/>
L. M. FISHER<lb/>
Associate Sanitary Engineer<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service<lb/>
In Charge Malaria Co-operative Work<lb/>
<dateline>
State Board of Health<lb/>
of South Carolina<lb/>
DIVISION MALARIA CO-OPERATIVE WORK<lb/>
Columbia <date value="1922-10-28">Oct. 28, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H. R. Carter<lb/>
2121 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wish to thank you for a copy of the Recommendations<lb/>
prepared by LePrince and Griffiths for the governing of<lb/>
the Alabama Power Company on the Coosa River. I will<lb/>
examine this over Sunday and return it to you on Monday.</p>
<p>I also received your letters addressed to me at Raleigh<lb/>
and Marion, and appreciate your writing to me and your<lb/>
discussion of the conditions at both ponds.</p>
<p>At Marion I found full grown larvae and pupae in the pond<lb/>
near the head of Mill Creek on the Padey Creek section,<lb/>
and also in some other coves; one I recall, at the foot<lb/>
of a slope on which Lawyer Mull of Morganton built a<lb/>
fish lodge. This examination was made after a spell of<lb/>
rainy weather and very probably the larvae were washed<lb/>
in from the streams. On one of the coves on Mill Creek<lb/>
I found small larvae, not over one-third grown, which it<lb/>
seems to me must have developed in the pond because if<lb/>
they had been carried into the pond from streams I should<lb/>
think they would have drowned. I found these fairly<lb/>
numerous, picking up from 0 to 4 in each dip for 15 or<lb/>
20 dips, with about 75 percent of the dips containing<lb/>
larvae. I found them among flotage along the bank in<lb/>
places where there was very little wave action. Under-<lb/>
neath the flotage I observed small sun fish and a small<lb/>
black fish, about the size of a full grown Gambusia, but<lb/>
much quicker and very shy. Schools of perch in the deep-<lb/>
er water kept the small fish close to the shore and re-<lb/>
peatedly darted among them.</p>
<p>In one of the pools near Yancey's bridge, about three-<lb/>
quarters of a mile east of the bridge, I found a few full<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01002023"/>
-2-<lb/>
grown larvae that developed into punctipennis. This pool<lb/>
had neither in-flow or outflow of water. A little further<lb/>
east among some dead undergrowth standing in the waters<lb/>
edge and among small pieces of drift I found full-grown<lb/>
larvae and pupae which I think were washed in from the<lb/>
stream. I found no small larvae among them.</p>
<p>The weather was getting very cool; the temperature of the<lb/>
water had fallen to 65 degrees. We had had several frosts.</p>
<p>At Badin I found breeding in the pond at places where it<lb/>
could not reasonably be expected to have had its origin in<lb/>
streams and found small larvae and pupae. I found larvae<lb/>
in flotage at the bank and attached to floating pieces of<lb/>
bark and logs away from the shore. The pond was drawn<lb/>
down about 9 feet, but was rising, having come up about<lb/>
6 feet in the last two weeks. The Plant is running and is<lb/>
taking on new men. Four pot rooms were in operation and<lb/>
the fifth was to be placed in operation soon.</p>
<p>Mr. Nash, who is directly in charge of the control work<lb/>
was with me.</p>
<p>My principal criticism at Badin, I thin, is that the control<lb/>
measures recommended to the Company, which they are trying<lb/>
to carry out, have not been carried out sufficiently fully<lb/>
to be a hundred percent effective. Just how effective they<lb/>
are it is hard to state. All of the families I visited<lb/>
within flight distance of the area where control measures<lb/>
were employed, claim to have had malaria this year or last.<lb/>
The Company screened one of its houses on Glady Fork, but<lb/>
used fourteen mesh wire and did not screen the chimney.<lb/>
They oiled log jams at intervals of 16 to 25 days. This<lb/>
interval I think was too long. They introduced between<lb/>
15,000 and 18,000 top minnows this summer. This I think is<lb/>
a mere drop in the bucket compared with what is required for<lb/>
the pond. Undoubtedly it is a step along the right direction.</p>
<p>Dr. Moore was employed by the Company this summer to work<lb/>
among the people at the upper end of the pond in order to<lb/>
elliminate malaria. He visited them several times a week<lb/>
and gave intrevenes injections of quinine in 7 1/2 to 10 grain<lb/>
doses, at intervals of two or three days. He told me of<lb/>
one person who had not had any chills, but the doctor thot<lb/>
he looked as tho he had malaria and advised him to take the<lb/>
doctor's treatment. After taking two or three shots he de-<lb/>
veloped chills. The doctor made, therefore, the same<lb/>
degree of success of Mr. Nash with his fish hatchery. He<lb/>
had to move it to a new location because everybody in a<lb/>
house a few hundred feet from the hatchery came down with<lb/>
chills!</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01002024"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>Dr. Moore made blood examination of fifty-three people and<lb/>
got twenty-seven positive blood smears and twenty-six<lb/>
negative. The positive ones were invariably obtained from<lb/>
persons who had had chills recently; that is, within a<lb/>
month or two of the time the blood was taken.</p>
<p>The Company shows a willingness to do whatever is reasonable.<lb/>
Dr. Rankin wants the Service to formulate regulations which<lb/>
power companies can be asked to follow. Dr. Moore received<lb/>
very poor cooperation from some of the people among whom<lb/>
he was trying to work.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very truly,</salute>
<signed>L. M. Fisher<lb/>
Associate Sanitary Engineer<lb/>
In Charge Mal. Cont. Work in S. C.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
