<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01001002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 7, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01001002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-09-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Connor, Michael E.</name>
<name type="person">Wolcott, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Cumming, Hugh S.</name>
<name type="person">Cardenas, J. Gil</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">North Dakota</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-09-07">September 7, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01001002</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 7, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses financial matters and his feelings towards the International Health Board. He comments on Connor and Cumming.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-09-07">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, September 7, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01001002"/>
<opener>
DIRECTOR GENERAL<lb/>
HENRY HANSON<lb/>
M. D.<lb/>
BAJO LOS AUSPICIOS DEL<lb/>
GOBIERNO PERUANO Y LA<lb/>
JUNTA INTERNACIONAL DE<lb/>
SANIDAD DE ROCKEFELLER<lb/>
FOUNDATION<lb/>
Mis.<lb/>
<unclear>Many in Banco Mercantile</unclear><lb/>
Campa&ntilde;a Sanitaria contra la Fiebre Amarilla en el Per&uacute;<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
AVENIDA PIEROLA 545 - TELEFONO 342<unclear>8</unclear><lb/>
LIMA -- PERU<lb/>
<dateline>
Yankton, S. D.<lb/>
<date value="1922-09-07">September ???7,1922,</date>
</dateline>
NUMERO<lb/>
____<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of August the 17th was received<lb/>
while we were in Sioux City. Just before coming west to South Dakota<lb/>
I received two other letters from you which were forwarded to me fr<lb/>
Peru, and I was very much interested in them even though we had talk-<lb/>
ed to some extent about those matters in New York.</p>
<p>In regard to your money in Lima I wrote to the bank from <del><unclear>N w</unclear></del><lb/>
York confirming the instructions which I gave them before leaving<lb/>
to convert your Peruvian pounds in to Dollars at the rate of 4:15 or<lb/>
better. It will do no harm to write them and advise them to credit<lb/>
the bank in New York or any other bank you may see fit to designate.<lb/>
If you so prefer you can have them draw you a New York draft for the<lb/>
amount and send you the draft direct which will enable you to cash<lb/>
or deposit the money in any bank you like, and it will not be necessary<lb/>
to take it up officially through the New York Bank unless you so pre-<lb/>
fer/.</p>
<p>I am glad that the report on the fish proved of some value to<lb/>
you. I have not yet been able to get busy on the rport which I want<lb/>
to write as I have been travelling and will continue to travel until<lb/>
about the first part of October. I do not understand Dr. Rose's atti-<lb/>
tude in the matter. He impressed me as being rather indifferent about<lb/>
a report on the work. Had I been in his place I should have insisted<lb/>
on having a report, as I should have considered that an essential to<lb/>
pass judgement on what had been done finally.</p>
<p>I do not think that I shall do any more for the I.H.B., I<lb/>
shall feel quite content to have gotten through with this job in<lb/>
Peru without any difficulty. There is something about the attitude<lb/>
of the Office in New York which I do not understand and which has<lb/>
given me the impression that the less I have to do with it the<lb/>
better for my peace of mind. However as soon as I get to Baltimore<lb/>
I shall talk to Dr. Welch as you suggest, advice from Welch or your-<lb/>
self is about the best one can get.</p>
<p>About the African expedition Dr. Rose stated that they had de-<lb/>
cided on Connor for the African expedition, and Wolcott to go as an<lb/>
assistant or clinician. In that capacity Wolcott is away ahead of<lb/>
M.E.C. in ability. MEC as far as I know has seen very little Y.F.<lb/>
and I personally would not be any too ready to accept his clinical<lb/>
diagnosis.</p>
<p>I have received a letter from one of my Secretaries of the Cam-<lb/>
paign, and he speaks of my coming back as though they are still look-<lb/>
ing for it down there. I do not think that Cardenas has much chance<lb/>
if I really care to go back there. That however is a difficult prob-<lb/>
lem to decide. It has very many attractive features, which practically<lb/>
ofset the undesirable ones; however I will let that rest until later<lb/>
in the year.</p>
<p>I had a very pleasant visit with the Surgeon General Cummins at<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01001003"/>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN EL PERU<lb/>
____<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
____<lb/>
____<lb/>
Dr. H.R. Carter, September 7, 1922.<lb/>
Dr. Grubbs house on Staten Island. He seemed to ahev a very practical<lb/>
way of looking at things, and I was favourably impressed with<lb/>
him all the way thorugh.</p>
<p>You spoke of the length of the trip and the babies. They stood<lb/>
it very well, and I am not sure that they were not happier enrout w<lb/>
while they were living in the car than they have been after we have<lb/>
commenced stopping and sort of establishing ourselves (<unclear>temporarily</unclear><lb/>
at least with our relatives)/ We are fast becoming Gypsified, and I<lb/>
fear it would not take so very long to acquire a taste for this rov-<lb/>
ing life. We have a new seven passenger Buick which was sufficiently<lb/>
rooming to enable us to make improvised beds for the <unclear>boies</unclear> in the<lb/>
back and they would lie down and take a nap when they began to feel<lb/>
very tired. This was a special stunt on the part of Virgil. We had<lb/>
two large very soft and <unclear>cmfortable</unclear> pillows and a couple of blankets<lb/>
which he seemed to enjoy for his bed, and about two or three times<lb/>
a day he would take a little nap while we were driving. On the whole<lb/>
it was a very pleasant and comfortable trip.</p>
<p>Well this note is simply to acknowledge the receipt of you<lb/>
letters, and in as much as I am on the road again I will not go into<lb/>
any fuller discussion of plans or reports at the present time.</p>
<p>We lwave here tomorrow for Chamberlain South <unclear>Dakota, ,a</unclear> trip<lb/>
of about 150 miles to the Northwest. We will remain there for about<lb/>
two days when we will go from there to my sisters place in Hand<lb/>
County, S.D., to near a small place called Vayland. There we will<lb/>
only remain about two days when we will begin our return trip to<lb/>
Sioux City by way of Brookings and Sioux Fallas in the state.<lb/>
On the 17th or 18th we shall have to start our trip back to Wisc.<lb/>
to take Karl to the St. John's Military Academy at Belafield, Wisc.</p>
<p>From tere we shall return to Sioux City for a short visit<lb/>
and probably back here to Yankton again before I go on to Balti-<lb/>
more where I am planning to put in the year in doing post Graduate<lb/>
work and try for a Doctorate in Public Health.</p>
<p>With the very best wishes from us all to both Laura and<lb/>
yourself.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
Temporary address,<lb/>
2300 Summit Ave.,<lb/>
Sioux City, Iowa.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
