<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01004012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 5, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01004012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-12-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, L.H.</name>
<name type="person">Sainz, Arturo</name>
<name type="place">Sioux City (Iowa)</name>
<name type="place">Jacksonville (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Canal Zone (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-12-05">December 5, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01004012</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 5, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses his career options in Peru and Africa. He mentions the possibility of leaving public health.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-12-05">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 5, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01004012"/>
<opener>
<unclear>Kris</unclear>.<lb/>
Hanson<lb/>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN EL PERU<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
Answered<lb/>
Dec 10/22.<lb/>
<dateline>
3014 Winfield Ave., Forest Park,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md. <date value="1922-12-05">December 5, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I feel rather guilty in taking up so much of your<lb/>
valuable time by these letters of mine on purely personal matters, but I<lb/>
appreciate your opinions and advice above that of othermen and for that you<lb/>
have to suffer.</p>
<p>I have not yet been able to set my mind at rest on what I want to<lb/>
do, or rather on what I ought to do. In regard to what I want to do there is<lb/>
no question, but one can not always do what he wants to do and it becomes a<lb/>
problem of choosing the least undesirable substitute; that is my present dilemma.<lb/>
The Sioux City proposition has some very desirable features in that it would<lb/>
be virgin territory in which to carry out the diphtheria work which Park of<lb/>
New York has inaugurated with such apparently promising results. This feature<lb/>
of the work seems to be very well done here, and I am at present helping out<lb/>
to a certain extent on it.</p>
<p>Sioux City has for some time had a very much higher diphtheria rate t<lb/>
than it should and it has occurred to me that a person who knows how to carry<lb/>
of this work could (if the people would let him) go in and do a general immuni-<lb/>
zation, after testing the children out by the Shick method, and in about two<lb/>
years or less bring their diphtheria incidence down to practically nothing. The<lb/>
difficulty in my way there is that they have some state law that one can not<lb/>
be a Health Officer in Iowa or the Iowa cities unless he is licensed to prac-<lb/>
tice and has actually been in the practice of medicine there for a certain<lb/>
specified time. As far as I am concerned I am licenced in Wisconsin and Florida<lb/>
but not in Iowa. Whether there is a way to get around this I do not yet know.<lb/>
Going there however would mean the laying aside of all my tropical experience,<lb/>
even to a greater extent than going to Florida in the private capacity of which<lb/>
I have been thinking of late. The work there would be surgical pathology in<lb/>
which cancer and other malignant conditions would take the lead. In addition<lb/>
there would be a certain amount of blood work, bacteriology and vaccines etc.<lb/>
Beyond that it would be what one would choose to put in the energy to make it.<lb/>
The idea of leaving the public health career depresses me more than anything I<lb/>
have contemplated so far. I have labored under the delusion that I was fairly<lb/>
well established and that I had a training and experience which would be worth<lb/>
something where there still is work to be done. In this connection I believe that<lb/>
I would be of more value to Peru than to any other place that I know of. There<lb/>
I know the conditions, the people and to a workable extent the language. It also<lb/>
seems that the people there have more confidence in me than in any other place<lb/>
outside of the medical department of the Panama Canal. For some reason the pro-<lb/>
fession (doctors and inspectors) on the Zone seem to estimate my ability and<lb/>
work very highly.</p>
<p>The political situation in Peru seems to be very uncertain. The<lb/>
President and his cousin the &ldquo;Ministro de Gobierno&rdquo; have had a serious falling<lb/>
out, to the extent that if is reported that Leguia-Martinez attempted to start<lb/>
a revolution against Leguia, but the latter took him prisoner and what has<lb/>
happened after that I do not know. This situation would mean that the present<lb/>
executive will bee too busy trading and buying support to be able to fulfil<del>l</del><lb/>
an<del>d</del> promises to the health department. He has, however? put through an<del>d</del> act in<lb/>
this last congress which allows the president to run for reelection without<lb/>
waiting for an intervening term as formerly. This means that he will probab-<lb/>
ly succeed himself. The present finances however are said to be even more<lb/>
stringent than when I left. The Government employees are having great diffi-<lb/>
culty in collecting their wages which extends even to the peones. Under such<lb/>
conditions I do not see that it is worth while going back.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01004013"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
December 5, 1922.</p>
<p>As far as the I. H. B. is concerned I presume that the only chance<lb/>
I would have had with them would have been to have gone to Mexico. May be<lb/>
that I made a mistake in not taking the proposition which Dr. White made. It<lb/>
however was contingent upon his making certain modifications in their plans<lb/>
there which I am not certain that he could have put through. Even if he had<lb/>
it probably would have been unpleasant on account of the relation with the<lb/>
older men in the service. As for their African work it is difficult to know<lb/>
what Dr. Rose has in mind if he does not take your advice. If he did and I<lb/>
should be asked to go I quite agree that it would be better that it would be<lb/>
preferable to have someone conduct the preliminary negociations and let me<lb/>
take charge of the field work and the men. As you say one man could not do<lb/>
both, in the beginning at least, or even later it were better if he did not<lb/>
have much of the diplomatic work. That was not what I had in mind when I said<lb/>
that the I.H.B. did not have many men to whom I would care to be subordinate.<lb/>
I would want to have considerable to say about the makeup of the personnel,<lb/>
and would like to have a limited few of my old staff with me, such as Dunn,<lb/>
probably Guldstarnd, and Sainz would be worth taking.</p>
<p>At present I have an opportunity to do a bit of part time work<lb/>
here which would bring in enough to reduce my expenses by about $150.00<lb/>
per month, and still allow me to carry on some special studies in the special<lb/>
lines I may wish to take up. The work would be in the diphtheria control<lb/>
and immunixation, which in itself would be valuable experience. The only<lb/>
objection to this is that if I am to take up the Jacksonville work it is<lb/>
open now; the opportunity there probably will not again be what it is now<lb/>
and if I do not take that I will be obliged to continue seeking &ldquo;a living&rdquo;<lb/>
in public health work. A person should not think of a public health job as<lb/>
&ldquo;seeking a living&rdquo;, it ought to be a very dignified career, as it has been<lb/>
for many, and as it would be for many of us if we could work with men of<lb/>
your type. Unfortunately there seem to be very few H.R. Carters, only one<lb/>
at the present time.</p>
<p>You need not apologize for any of your letters. They are all full<lb/>
of helpful information and guidance. I am preserving them all in my permanent<lb/>
files. I know how busy you are and I do not want my personal affairs to<lb/>
interfere too much with your great work.</p>
<p>It seems the decision which I shall be obliged to make within the<lb/>
next few days will one which shall definitely determine what my future work<lb/>
is to be. If it be Jacksonville, it will be the end of the public life, if<lb/>
I stay on here through the year it will be a continuation of the public<lb/>
health work. If I go to Jacksonville, Africa and all other positions of that<lb/>
kind will be eliminated.</p>
<p>Martha and Virgil are asleep, otherwise they would join Mrs. Hanson<lb/>
and myself in sending love to you and Laura.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
