<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01007001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Anopheles and Sea Water. Observations on the Development of A. quadrimaculatus, A. crucians and a. punctipennis in Salt and Brackish Waters, by T.H.D. Griffitts, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01007001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T.H.D.</name>
<name type="place">Langley Field, Hampton (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Virginia Beach (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">West Point (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Newport News (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Eustis (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01007001</idno>
<title>Report: Anopheles and Sea Water. Observations on the Development of A. quadrimaculatus, A. crucians and a. punctipennis in Salt and Brackish Waters, by T.H.D. Griffitts, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Griffitts reports on the breeding of Anopheles in salt water, mainly in Virginia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report: Anopheles and Sea Water. Observations on the Development of A. quadrimaculatus, A. crucians and a. punctipennis in Salt and Brackish Waters, by T.H.D. Griffitts, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01007001"/>
<opener>
to Dr. Carter<lb/>
<hi><unclear>Preceeding</unclear> in</hi><lb/>
Sea water<lb/>
ANOPHELES AND SEA-WATER<lb/>
Observations on the Development of <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi>,<lb/>
<hi>A. crucians</hi> and <hi>A. punctipennis</hi> in Salt and Brackish Waters.<lb/>
By<lb/>
T.H.D. Griffitts, Epidemiologist,<lb/>
U.S. Public Health Service.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>In connection with the control of malaria in extra-canton-<lb/>
ment zones located in &ldquo;tidewater&rdquo; country and in the course<lb/>
of other malaria investigations, both extending over a period<lb/>
of four years, the writer has had occasion to note something<lb/>
of the relative breeding habits of <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi>, <hi>A.<lb/>
crucians</hi> and <hi>A. punctipennis</hi> in relation to sea-water and di<lb/>
lutions of sea-water.</p>
<p>As stated by Howard, Dyar and <unclear>Knab<hi rend="superscript">#</hi>,</unclear> &ldquo;Anopheles have been<lb/>
found breeding in salt or brackish water in many parts of the<lb/>
world; in every case the habit has been found restricted to<lb/>
certain species&rdquo;. Literature (that available, at least) is si-<lb/>
lent as to the amount of salinity withstood by the common<lb/>
North American species of Anopheles. Smith, in speaking of<lb/>
Anopheles in New Jersey, says of <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi>, &ldquo;this form<lb/>
also occurs in brackish water on the salt marshes, hence has<lb/>
a somewhat wider range [than <hi>punctipennis</hi>] and adds the pos-<lb/>
itive danger of disease to the disadvantages of an undrained<lb/>
marsh&rdquo;. That <hi>A. crucians</hi> breeds freely in the brackish marshes<lb/>
<unclear><hi rend="superscript">#</hi></unclear> &ldquo;The Mosquitoes of North and Central America and the West Indies,&rdquo; Vol. I, p. 224.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01007002"/>
2<lb/>
is well and generally known, but there appears to be no record<lb/>
as to the per cent. of sea<del><unclear></unclear></del>-water that even this species will<lb/>
withstand.</p>
<p>The observations herein noted were made in areas bordering<lb/>
upon either <unclear>Chesapeake</unclear> Bay, Hampson Roads (or tidal tributa-<lb/>
ries) or the Atlantic Ocean at Virginia Beach, Virginia.</p>
<p><hi>Anopheles Crucians.</hi></p>
<p>(1) Near Langley Field, Hampton, Virginia, in September, 1917,<lb/>
a heavy <hi>A. crucians</hi> infestation of barns was found. The pro-<lb/>
duction area was found to be a salt marsh three-fourths of a<lb/>
mile away. Subsequent and repeated examinations revealed <hi><unclear>A.-</unclear><lb/>
crucians</hi> breeding (producing) generally in the marsh in water<lb/>
showing a salinity of 10,086 (Hampton Roads at Newport News,<lb/>
salinity 10,146). <hi>Aedes sollicitans</hi> was also breeding pro-<lb/>
fusely in the same water. The <hi>A. crucians</hi> larvae were gener-<lb/>
ally found amongst the salt grass, <hi>distichlis spicata</hi>, the<lb/>
smaller and finer of the principal marsh grasses found in this<lb/>
locality. The larger salt marsh grass, <hi>spartina glabra</hi>, grows<lb/>
more abundantly where there is more tidal action, and <hi>A. cruc-<lb/>
ians</hi> breeding was found amongst this grass only where growth<lb/>
was much retarded or where it was dead. No other species of<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles</hi> bred in this marsh, although a fresh water pond was<lb/>
producing <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> and the fresh water streams near<lb/>
were producing <hi>A. punctipennis</hi>.</p>
<p>(2) At Virginia Beach, Virginia, Lake Rudes, originally a ti-<lb/>
dal stream and salt marsh, is intermittently formed by a de-<lb/>
posit of sand at the beach, blocking the outlet and impound-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01007003"/>
3<lb/>
ing salt water. With addition of fresh water from small<lb/>
streams and rainfall the water of the lake becomes propor-<lb/>
tionately less saline. The grassy borders of this lake were<lb/>
found at different times from August to October, 1919, to be<lb/>
breeding <hi>A. crucians</hi> very freely, larvae of all sizes, or pupae,<lb/>
were taken at every selective dip. This lake, the salinity of<lb/>
which had undergone no appreciable change during several weeks,<lb/>
conformed to Carter's classification of a &ldquo;complete&rdquo; breeding<lb/>
place, i.e., the eggs deposited here hatched and the succeed-<lb/>
ing stages of larvae and pupae through to the imagos were<lb/>
completed in the same water. The salinometer reading here was<lb/>
10,088 (the salinity of the Ocean here was 10,196). Express-<lb/>
ed, then, in percentage of sea-water at this point, the lake<lb/>
was 34.6. Here was a body of diluted sea-water covering approx-<lb/>
imately five acres producing <hi>A. crucians</hi>, a malaria vector, in<lb/>
sufficient numbers to be of decided health importance to the<lb/>
community. Extending to near Lake Rudee and separated there-<lb/>
from by a strip of elevated land only a few hundred feet wide<lb/>
was Lake Holly which, with very rare exceptions, was fresh water.<lb/>
(During the time of observations, the highest salinity was<lb/>
10,003) This lake was producing <hi>A. <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>quadrimaculatus</add></hi> in great<lb/>
numbers. Was not this a striking contrast in the selective<lb/>
breeding places of the two species? Lake Rudee, 34.6% sea-<lb/>
water, <hi>Anopheles</hi> production 100% <hi><del><unclear></unclear></del> <add><unclear></unclear></add></hi> Holly, prac-<lb/>
tically fresh (1.5% sea-water) Anopheles production 100%<lb/>
<hi>quadrimaculatus</hi>. The two breeding <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>areas</add> were separated by less<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01007004"/>
4<lb/>
600 feet, and in a stable on this strip of land on an early<lb/>
day in September there were collected 67 <hi>A. crucians</hi> and 85<lb/>
<hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi>.</p>
<p>(3) At West Point, York River showed a salinity of 10,110. A<lb/>
pond had been formed by dumpage of rubbish across a salt marsh<lb/>
for the purpose of extending a street, the fill being very loose<lb/>
and porous and no culvert was installed. The main tidal stream<lb/>
was blocked and at high tide additional salt water entered<lb/>
the pond through the fill. However, the level of the pond<lb/>
varied little between tides. The salinity at the lower por-<lb/>
tion of the pond was 10,077, or 70% York River water (This<lb/>
would be approximately 50% sea-water as generally occuring<lb/>
along this section of the Atlantic coast). <hi>A. crucians</hi> was breed-<lb/>
ing (producing) profusely in this water. Two hundred feet away,<lb/>
in a different portion of the same body of water, but where<lb/>
the salinity was only 10,003, due to large amount of seepage<lb/>
and the lack of mixing of the waters by wave action, <hi>A. quad-<lb/>
rimaculatus</hi> was producing freely.</p>
<p>(4) <hi>Experiment. A. crucians</hi> larvae of all sizes and pupae coll-<lb/>
ected from obstructed ditches in the marsh of Back River near<lb/>
Langley Field September 9, 1920 (salinity 10,088), placed in<lb/>
sea-water, salinity 10,100, on September 10, were not unfavor-<lb/>
ably affected by the transfer. All but three (these of first<lb/>
molt when placed in the sea-water) had developed into imagos<lb/>
within twelve days. Even the smallest of the larvae developed<lb/>
equally as well in the sea-water as those in the fresh water<lb/>
control.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01007005"/>
<p>5</p>
<p><hi>Anopheles Quadrimaculatus</hi>.</p>
<p>(1) Lake Holly, at Virginia Beach, as before stated, is prac-<lb/>
tically always fresh. Some years ago a flume was constructed<lb/>
connecting the lake with the ocean for the purpose of admit-<lb/>
ting sea-water at high tide, In its present condition, salt<lb/>
water come<add>s</add> into the lake only at times of very high storm<lb/>
tide; so no success is accomplished in keeping the salinity<lb/>
even high enough to preclude the breeding of <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi>.<lb/>
In many parts of the lake, prior to the successful malaria<lb/>
control operations in 1920, this species was foud breeding<lb/>
freely. The highest salinity found at any time was 10,003,<lb/>
or approximately 1,5% sea-water at this place. No other<lb/>
species of Anopheles was found breeding in this lake at any<lb/>
time. <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> was breeding profusely in another<lb/>
fresh water pond one half mile distant and <hi>A. crucians</hi> in the<lb/>
saline Lake Rudee a few hundred feet away.</p>
<p>(2) The small body of impounded water at West Point, previous-<lb/>
ly noted, covered an area approximately three acres in extent,<lb/>
in which there was a growth of raeds and salt grass (<hi>distich-<lb/>
lis apicata</hi>) still remaining. As noted, the lower saline<lb/>
portion of the pond was producing <hi>A. crucians</hi>. On the oppo-<lb/>
site <add>side</add> of the pond, 200 feet away, where seepage outcrop ren-<lb/>
dered the water fresh, only <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> was breeding.<lb/>
The salinometer reading here was 10,003. The land rises ab-<lb/>
ruptly from the narrow valley and this topographic condition,<lb/>
together with the amount of vegetation in the water, served<lb/>
to prevent wave action and mixing of the waters, and, conse-<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01007006"/>
6<lb/>
quently, the water on this side of the pond remained almost en-<lb/>
tirely fresh.</p>
<p>(3) A pond at the upper end of a salt marsh near Newport<lb/>
News produced <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> in great numbers in 1917.<lb/>
This pond was one of the notorius products of road construc-<lb/>
tion to be found in tide-water country, where roads are built<lb/>
across salt marshes: culverts are set at too <del>h</del> high elevation<lb/>
or are inadequate in capacity, resulting in the impoundment<lb/>
of fresh or more or less saline water above the fill. In this<lb/>
particular case, at times of storm tides salt water was ad-<lb/>
mitted to the fresh water of the pond. However, the salinity<lb/>
was never so strong or so continuous as to kill the luxurient<lb/>
growth of cat-tails that occupied practically all of the<lb/>
two acres of the pond, except a small portion near the efflu-<lb/>
ent culvert. On an occasion of high tide the lower portion of<lb/>
the pond showed a salinity of 10,076. At this time breeding<lb/>
was under control, but the question naturally arises as to<lb/>
whether or not the larvae and pupae <unclear>CIA</unclear> <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi><lb/>
may resist a relatively high degree of salinity intermittent-<lb/>
ly. The determination of this point has a practical bearing<lb/>
on malaria control and could be <unclear>trated</unclear> readily by ex-<lb/>
periments.</p>
<p>(4) Near Lee Hall and Camp Eustis, Virginia, in 1918, F.E.<lb/>
Chidester and T.B.Hayne, Jr., working with the writer, collected<lb/>
Anopheles larvae from the edge of a tidal marsh, the water<lb/>
showing a salinity of 10,048. Two specimans of <del><unclear>acquad-</unclear></del><add>A. quadrimac-</add><lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01007007"/>
7<lb/>
ulatus emerged from this collection. Chidester and Hayne<lb/>
are both careful observers and they expressed the opinion<lb/>
that this was a complete breeding place. However, in surveys<lb/>
extending over several seasons, under various conditions and<lb/>
in many salt marsh areas, the writer has been unable to sub-<lb/>
stantiate their findings.</p>
<p>(5) <hi>Experiment</hi>. Fourteen <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> larvae, all sizes,<lb/>
collected from a fresh water pond and put into sea-water, sa-<lb/>
linity 10,160, were all killed within twelve hours, the larger<lb/>
ones surviving the longest. No mortality in the pond water<lb/>
control.</p>
<p><hi>Anopheles Punctipennis</hi></p>
<p>The writer has never found breeding of this species, <hi>A.<lb/>
punctipennis</hi>, in salt or brackish water, nor is there report<lb/>
of such breeding. But there is much evidence that <hi>A. puncti-<lb/>
pennis</hi> has a wider range of breeding habits than either <hi>A</hi>.<lb/>
<hi>quadrimaculatus or A. crucians</hi>. It is found in the coldest<lb/>
mountain springs and branches and at times in streams and ditch-<lb/>
es foul with sewage. It is not <unclear>resistent</unclear>, however, to sea-water.<lb/>
<hi>Experiment</hi>. Twenty-five <hi>A. punctipennis</hi> larvae, all sizes, coll-<lb/>
ected from a ditch and a fresh water lake and transferred to<lb/>
sea-water, salinity, 10,100, all killed within seven hours. No<lb/>
mortality in fresh water control.</p>
<p><hi>Conclusions</hi></p>
<p>1. <hi>A. crucians</hi> was found to breed in sea-water diluted to a<lb/>
maximum salinity of 10,088, or slightly more than 50% aver-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01007008"/>
8<lb/>
age sea-water. Transferring <hi>A. crucians</hi> larvae which had<lb/>
<unclear>started</unclear> their development in saline water to sea-water<lb/>
did not unfavorably affect their subsequent development.</p>
<p>2. <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> was not found to breediin numbers<lb/>
to be of importance in a higher salinity than 10,003, or<lb/>
1.5% sea-water. In one case two larvae found in water with<lb/>
a salinity of 10,046 developed into <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> imagos,<lb/>
but this observation requires confirmation <add>as to whether</add>
this species may<lb/>
complete its entire water cycle in so high a per cent. of<lb/>
sea-water. The question is raised as to whether <hi>A. quadri-<lb/>
maculatus</hi> larvae may not withstand <add>much</add> higher salinity inter-<lb/>
mittantly then continuously. Specimens of <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi><lb/>
larvae transferred from non-saline pond-water to sea-water,<lb/>
salinity 10,160, were all killed within 12 hours.</p>
<p>3. <hi>A. punctipennis</hi> was not found breeding in salt or brack-<lb/>
ish waters. This species breeds under a wider range of con-<lb/>
ditions than either <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> or <hi>A. crucians</hi>, but<lb/>
apparently does not breed in salt or brackish waters. Lar-<lb/>
vae of <hi>A. punctipennis</hi> put into sea-water were all dead with-<lb/>
in seven hours.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
