<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01004026">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 14, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01004026</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-12-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-12-14">December 14, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01004026</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 14, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor reports on yellow fever in Mexico. He suspects a Caribbean epidemic spreading from Brazil.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-12-14">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 14, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01004026"/>
<opener>
I. H. B<lb/>
<hi>Connor</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
125 Dunning Avenue.<lb/>
San Antonio, Texas.<lb/>
<date value="1922-12-14">December 14th., 1922</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your welcome letter of December 5th., with enclosures<lb/>
reached me yesterday. I am planning on returning to Mexico soon after<lb/>
Xmas and will probably leave here for that country on the 27th., inst.,<lb/>
and therefore will not have the pleasure of seeing you this year.</p>
<p>You speak of the out-break in Panuco. The infection<lb/>
had undoubtedly been present in that city (10,000 inhabitants) for<lb/>
months before we recognized it, the diagnosis having been that of malaria<lb/>
with hemmorhages or pernicious malaria, and from here? it extended<lb/>
to Tampico and then along the line of the railroad to Ciudad<lb/>
Victoria and possibly other places. Tuxpam later reported a case and<lb/>
reports had it, that in the Huastecas there had been cases amongst<lb/>
the soldiers.</p>
<p>Lyster shaped our campaign on the plan of guarding<lb/>
the key centers and depending on the smaller places cleaing them-<lb/>
selves. I think Lyster must have have arrived at this conclusion without<lb/>
the benefits of a through preliminary <del><unclear></unclear></del> survey of the area<lb/>
and without a study of the vital statistics of the 'steg' infested<lb/>
zone. LePrince nor Caldwell considered Panuco as a place in which<lb/>
anti-larvae measures should be applied. Caldwell told me that he re-<lb/>
comended going into Panuco but that Lyster would not approve of<lb/>
same. When I took over that area in January (1922) there had been no<lb/>
case of yellow fever reported in Tampico for one year and on July<lb/>
1st of the present year <del><unclear></unclear></del> I thought the index had been low<lb/>
enough for a long enough period to warrant turning over the zone to<lb/>
the local authorities with a trained force of men to carry on, Dr.<lb/>
White reviewed the city of Tampico with Monroe and approved of the<lb/>
transfer to the local men.</p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del> Before we made this transfer a report of<lb/>
hemmorhagic malaria was announced in Panuco. Dr. White order Monroe to<lb/>
investigate (Dr. White was in Mexico City at the time, while I was in<lb/>
Vera Cruz) Monroe reported that he could no evidence of pernicous<lb/>
nor hemmorhagic malaria nor malaria and here the matter ended, the<lb/>
process of transfer to the local authorities was concluded by Monroe<lb/>
on June 30th. and he later came North.</p>
<p>Dr. White and I were at this time on the west<lb/>
coast inspecting Colima, Mazatlan and other places. On our return to<lb/>
Mexico City, late in July, came the announcement of a case of yellow<lb/>
fever originating in Panuco and <del><unclear></unclear></del> dying in the Tampico Hosp.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01004027"/>
<p>C1<lb/>
B22<lb/>
2.</p>
<p>We hesitated to accept the clinical diagnosis and held off until an<lb/>
examination of tissues could be made which was later done by<lb/>
Dr. Perrin and confirmed as yellow fever. As soon as the announce-<lb/>
ment was made, that is the clinical diagnosis, men were placed at<lb/>
work reducing the stegomyiae in Panuco and surrounding country.</p>
<p>In due time and according to schedule undoubted cases of y.f. began<lb/>
to appear in Panuco and about the same time in Tampico and the<lb/>
epidemic was on.</p>
<p>Later in conversation with Dr. White he stated that it appeared<lb/>
that the infection had been present in Tampico all the while and<lb/>
was endemic, being kept alive thru the children in a certain area<lb/>
of Tampico. I have been loath to accept this thought because if<lb/>
true there would have been some well marked cases in the course<lb/>
of eighteen months which is the period that no cases were reported,<lb/>
it seems to be <del>to be</del> quite unusuall to expect that the infection<lb/>
could have laid dormant for so long a period when there are<lb/>
large numbers of non-immunes in the city and a large number arrivng<lb/>
every day, many of whom lived in the distrcits in which Dr. Scannell<lb/>
later found cases, and had been living in the same district for<lb/>
many months.</p>
<p>The case aboard the Schooner William E. Burnham which arrived at<lb/>
Mobile September 14 1922 has caused Dr. White to think that perhaps<lb/>
the infection may have been introduced into Panuco from the<lb/>
Dutch Guiana as one of the oil companies had been receiving men from<lb/>
the oil fields of Dutch Guiana and the first cases found in Panuco<lb/>
were in one of these companies <add>camps.</add>. Dr. White is I believe foll<add>o</add>wing up<lb/>
this clue.</p>
<p>After having made the trip over Mexico in company with Dr. WHite<lb/>
I am convinced that we have in Mexico a problem the like of<lb/>
which we have not met with before. Cuba, Panama, Guayaquil and<lb/>
Peru, the first three places had for all intents and purposes only<lb/>
one endemic center of infection in each country, Peru was purely<lb/>
an<del>d</del> epidemic proposition and none of the foregoing countries had<lb/>
good, fast and easy system of intercommunicatios as ha<del><unclear></unclear></del><add>s</add> Mexico.<lb/>
In Mexico we ha<del><unclear></unclear></del><add><unclear></unclear></add> at three centers of endemicity and the highways<lb/>
of travel are <del>we</del> so well developed that it is possible to journey<lb/>
from Yucatan on the Gulf to Mazatlan on the Pacific within the period<lb/>
of incubation of the disease, this phase of the problem I don't<lb/>
think we <unclear>realized</unclear> at the begining of the campaign, again Mexico is<lb/>
still in throes of a revolution, that is, conditions are such <del>that</del><add>as to</add><lb/>
call for constant movement of troops and this troop movement has<lb/>
been responsible for spreading the infection at times. In brief,<lb/>
the entire area of Mexico below the 1000 meter above sea-level is<lb/>
i<add>n</add>fested with stegomyiae and the area sufficiently <del><unclear></unclear></del> popu-<lb/>
lated to allow the infection to travel around in a circle, if we<lb/>
pursue the plan of guarding only the key points. The point I wish<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01004028"/>
3.<lb/>
to bring out is that if we continue holding only the key centers<lb/>
and working in towns only when the disease has declared itself that<lb/>
the campaign will be a prolonged one wher<add>e</add>as if we would sweep the<lb/>
area the length of time <add>of elimination</add> ought to be considerably reduced.</p>
<p>The Mexican officials have given good co-operation and are sincere<lb/>
in their desires to rid the country of yellow fever, but their or-<lb/>
ganization is handicapped by not having a sufficient number of<lb/>
full time officers, this is true all thru the country, not withstanding<lb/>
this defect they do remarkably well.</p>
<p>I feel that we both, Mexicans and Americans, have gained by association<lb/>
and perhaps the greatest contribution from us has been the <del>practical</del><lb/>
demonstration that co-operation is the elimination of disease is a<lb/>
practical and economical measure.</p>
<p>Another need in our work is the laboratory to aid us in clearing<lb/>
up these cases that simulate <del><unclear></unclear></del> yellow fever yet respond readily to<lb/>
quinine, this condition is very confusing to the native and he being<lb/>
naturally sensitive to ridicule does not wish to announce a case<lb/>
as yellow fever until there could be no doubt as to the diag-<lb/>
nosis when of course it would be evident to everyone what the <del><unclear>a</unclear></del><lb/>
ailment <del>was</del><add>is</add>.</p>
<p>The Yucatan area is seemingly free of the infection as is Campeche,<lb/>
but the danger here is from re-infection and these<del>s</del> areas cannot<lb/>
be left for long in the hands of the local authorities. Merida<lb/>
will I think will hold a low 'steg' index longer than most places<lb/>
as the most important breeding places in that city are in the under<lb/>
ground cisterns (aljibes) and fish one placed therein will remain<lb/>
until the water is drained from the cistern, but this does not obtain<lb/>
in other places and further the rainfall is usually greater in the<lb/>
other cities of Mexico than in Merida therefore there is greater op-<lb/>
portunity for the re-filling of the water containers. Troop move-<lb/>
ment for the Peninsula is an <del><unclear>impotant</unclear></del> important item.</p>
<p>The interior of Tabasco during the present year reported an epi-<lb/>
demic of malaria with blood vomit and one or two cases <del>we</del> the same<lb/>
disease were reported from Frontera, one case died and one recovered<lb/>
under quinine, both cases had vomiting of blood, I am inclined to re-<lb/>
gard such cases sufficiently suspicious as to warrant a careful survey<lb/>
at least of the <add>entire</add> area. There is a belief amongst many physicans that<lb/>
Tabasco at San Juan <del><unclear></unclear></del> Bautista, now Villahermosa, was once an en-,lb/>
demic focus. It is these cases of benign yellow fever with an obvious<lb/>
malarial infection superimposed responding to quinine that confuse the<lb/>
local man and it is right here that the laboratory man can render<lb/>
great aid.</p>
<p>The African detail as you know has been definitely postponed until<lb/>
the Mexican situation has cleared up and this will probably mean<lb/>
a year or so.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01004029"/>
<p>4</p>
<p>The Brazil situation appears to be gathering strength and should it<lb/>
jump its limits and light up the Carribean litoral we certainly<lb/>
would a tremendous epidemic. I believe Dr. White has hopes of interest<lb/>
ing Dr. Chagas in a co-operative campaign for all Brazil and if suc-<lb/>
cessful it ought to be easy to extend same to the Guianas.</p>
<p>I am hopeful that in the near future a <add>detail</add> will be given me where I can<lb/>
take my family as Mrs. Connor is not too strong and finds it increas-<lb/>
ingly difficult to carry on alone. You know we have three youngsters<lb/>
Grace age 11 whom you saw at Panama, Ruth age 9 and Lucille age 6 all<lb/>
healthy and full of energy. We <del><unclear></unclear></del> came on to San Antonio as the<lb/>
winters are less <del><unclear></unclear></del>severe and it is near enough to Mexico so that<lb/>
in case of emergency I could reach them within a reasonable time, again<lb/>
the housing situation in the north has been so acute that we found it<lb/>
disagreeable and for a time were forced to live in with another<lb/>
family, while here we have a bungalow plainly furnished and convienent<lb/>
to some former Isthmian friends, the Osterhouts, whom you will probably<lb/>
re-call as one time health Officer at Bocas del Toro.</p>
<p>I am enclosing a picture of our youngsters which will give you an idea<lb/>
of them as they are to-day.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With sincere good wishes to you and yours,<lb/>
in which Mrs. Connor joins me, I am,<lb/>
as ever, your friend.</salute>
<signed>M E Connor</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
