<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01016002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Yellow Fever, Fifth Zone, North West Coast of Mexico (1919-1922), January 1, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01016002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-01-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Houle, E.C.</name>
<name type="person">Harris, H.A.</name>
<name type="person">Lyster, Theodore C.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Connor, M.E.</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Nayarit (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Sinaloa (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Sonora (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Mazatlan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Culiacan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Manzanillo (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>30 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-01-01">January 1, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01016002</idno>
<title>Report: Yellow Fever, Fifth Zone, North West Coast of Mexico (1919-1922), January 1, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a detailed report on yellow fever work in Mexico. Topics discussed include: the history of yellow fever in the area, recent epidemics and public health efforts at mosquito control and vaccination.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-01-01">
<head>Report: Yellow Fever, Fifth Zone, North West Coast of Mexico (1919-1922), January 1, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01016002"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
Mr. Wickliffe Rose<lb/>
61 Broadway<lb/>
New York, N. Y.<lb/>
With the Compliments of<lb/>
Dr. E.C. Houle<lb/>
Chief of the 5th Zone<lb/>
Chief Surgeon F.C.S.R. de M.<lb/>
Empalme, Sonora, Mexico<lb/>
Dr. H.A. Harris<lb/>
Assistant to Chief of Zone<lb/>
Division Surgeon F.C.Z.P. de M.<lb/>
Mazatlan, Sonora, Mexico<lb/>
<dateline>
Empalme, Sonora, Mexico<lb/>
<date value="1923-01-01">January 1, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
<pb n="2" id="f01016003"/>
COPY<lb/>
<hi>YELLOW FEVER</hi><lb/>
Fifth Zone<lb/>
North West Coast of Mexico<lb/>
1919-1922<lb/>
</opener>
<p>This paper, largely the story of an amateur and volunteer effort<lb/>
against a menacing disease, is written particularly for those interested in Public<lb/>
Health Work on the West Coast of Mexico. Names of local assistants in the<lb/>
campaign have been freely used, so that those who follow us in this or similar<lb/>
work, may avail themselves of wholly interested and at least partially trained<lb/>
men.</p>
<p><hi>PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION OF AREA</hi></p>
<p>The territory in question comprises the littoral of the States of<lb/>
Nayarit, Sinaloa and Sonora, from the Santiago River in the south to the Ari-<lb/>
zona border in the north, about fifteen hundred kilometers long and averaging<lb/>
one hundred kilometers in width. There is very restricted communication with<lb/>
the interior, the mountains to the west and south providing an almost impassa-<lb/>
ble barrier. All ordinary travel from the south is by steamer, usually stopp-<lb/>
ing last at Manzanillo (port for Guadalajara and the interior.)</p>
<p>There are only four ports connecting with railroads - Mazatlan, Al-<lb/>
tata, Topolobampo and Guaymas. Only two of these - Mazatlan and Guaymas - are<lb/>
ports for passenger steamers, and Guaymas is out of the line of ordinary travel.</p>
<p>The country is sparsely populated, with long distances of uninhabited<lb/>
country between communities. The towns are all small, the largest being Mazat-<lb/>
lan with about thirty thousand inhabitants.</p>
<p>The average winter temperature south of Mazatlan is probably high<lb/>
enough to support stegomyia breeding the year around, although March inspections<lb/>
in Mazatlan in 1921 and 1922 show house incidence of less than ten (10%) percent<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01016004"/>
2<lb/>
and probably less than five (5%) percent. Some few cuartels, with large<lb/>
numbers of permanent containers, show indices as high as thirty (30%) percent.<lb/>
North of Mazatlan, between December and May, there is probably a negligible<lb/>
amount of stegomyia breeding.</p>
<p>All of the above conditions insure that this area is epidemic and<lb/>
not endemic for yellow fever. The area is also safeguarded by the fact that<lb/>
infection can come from only one direction, the south, which to the forewarned,<lb/>
allows for proper watchfulness by means of public health reports.</p>
<p>Communication within the area is provided almost entirely by one<lb/>
railroad - The Southern Pacific of Mexico - which traverses it from end to end.<lb/>
The writers, being in the medical service of this railroad, have had unusual<lb/>
opportunities to keep informed on public health conditions.</p>
<p><hi>History</hi>.</p>
<p>According to Dr. Ruperto Paliza, Dr. A. M. Fernandez and others,<lb/>
and corroborated by port records at Mazatlan, yellow fever was a frequent visitor<lb/>
to the Northwest Coast, appearing at least once each decade since 1880. It is<lb/>
also suggested by a relative immunity of the adult natives of the coast, in<lb/>
comparison to foreigners and travelers from the interior.</p>
<p>The disease developed epidemic nature in 1883-1884, 1886, 1888, 1902<lb/>
and 1919-20-21.</p>
<p>The epidemic of 1883-84 was a terrible visitation. It is estimated<lb/>
that eight thousand deaths occurred on this sparsely populated coast. In<lb/>
Mazatlan the disease persisted all through the winter months (beginning in<lb/>
mid-summer 1883) and killed fifteen (15%) percent of the population. In Culiacan<lb/>
and vicinity the mortality was from five (5%) percent to ten (10%) percent. The<lb/>
infection also invaded the ports of Altata and Guaymas and extended to Hermosillo.<lb/>
It is said that the first infection was brought to Mazatlan by an opera company<lb/>
traveling from Colima, through Manzanillo. The Prima-donna, Peralta, died<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01016005"/>
3<lb/>
three days after arrival in Mazatlan, and the entire troupe was practically<lb/>
wiped out. The mortality was extremely high for strangers generally.</p>
<p>The later epidemics of 1885, 1888 and 1902, all started late in the<lb/>
fall of their respective years and were much milder and less extensive, undoubt-<lb/>
edly due to a very general immunity of the population.</p>
<p>Reappearance of yellow fever in 1919 was probably due to troop move-<lb/>
ments through Manzanillo. There was much delay in recognizing it. At that<lb/>
time, due to natural depletion of medical ranks by death, and unusual shifting<lb/>
of locations caused by the Revolutions, there were not more than a half dozen<lb/>
of Doctors living in the area who had had personal contact with the disease.<lb/>
Due to the scarcity of doctors who had practical experience with Yellow Fever,<lb/>
and to the general worthlessness of the average medical texts on the subject,<lb/>
there was great difficulty in establishing a diagnosis, the general tendency,<lb/>
either from misinterpretation or from unpraiseworthy motives, was to declare<lb/>
&ldquo;Hemorrhagic Malaria.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(Later, in June 1922, the Department of Public Health of Mexico,<lb/>
found it necessary to place Hemorrhagic Malaria in the list of reportable<lb/>
diseases and to issue a circular to the effect, admitting that certain isolated<lb/>
cases of malaria might present various hemorrhages as complications or attend-<lb/>
ant accidents of the disease, it was not admissible that Epidemics of Hemorrhagic<lb/>
Malaria could exist; that ignorance or malice had confused cases of Yellow Fever<lb/>
and so-called Hemorrhagic Malaria to the extent that the Department was much<lb/>
handicapped in its measures against yellow fever.)</p>
<p>Cases began to appear in Mazatlan in late August, in Culiacan in<lb/>
September and gradually extended north. One American and three other foreigners<lb/>
died in Mazatlan, beside various native deaths, under very suspicious symptoms<lb/>
in October and November. There was unusual mortality from &ldquo;Pernicious Malaria&rdquo;<lb/>
in Culiacan and Eldorado. In the military encampment of Torin on the Yaqui River,<lb/>
more than ninety deaths occurred in October and November in a garrison of<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01016006"/>
4<lb/>
three hundred men. Four officers of this organization, falling sick on duty<lb/>
and attempting to escape the general fate, left the camp to succumb, two in<lb/>
Guaymas and two in Hermosillo.</p>
<p>In all this period, only one doctor, Dr. Andres Vidales, of Culiacan,<lb/>
definitely diagnosed Yellow Fever. Despite the apathy or untruthfulness of the<lb/>
medical profession, the general populace were sufficiently alert, so that anti-<lb/>
mosquito campaigns in Guaymas and Empalme were enthusiastically supported in this<lb/>
year and in 1920.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemic of 1920</hi>.</p>
<p>The disease again appeared in Culiacan in August, the diagnosis again<lb/>
being clearly stated by Dr. Vidales, this time ably supported by Dr. Cliserio<lb/>
Garcia, J. By September 1st, seven cases had been diagnosed, four resulting<lb/>
fatally. About this time &ldquo;Hemorrhagic Malaria&rdquo; began to be reported with increas-<lb/>
ing frequency from the Santiago River, Acaponeta and Mazatlan.</p>
<p>By October 1st, there had been reported in Culiacan about twenty-nine<lb/>
cases, of which twenty-four had a fatal termination. There were probably an equal<lb/>
or greater number of cases not reported. About this time, there was a notable<lb/>
spread of the disease to the north, due to the annual pilgrimage to the shrine<lb/>
of San Francisco in Magdalena, Sonora. One case was diagnosed in Empalme,<lb/>
two in Guaymas, possibly four occurred in Hermosillo and one case as far north<lb/>
as Cananea, almost on the border.</p>
<p>Luckily, in both years, the infection arrived late in the summer into<lb/>
this area. Due to the necessary delays of the incubation periods, especially in<lb/>
<hi>the mosquito</hi> - dangerous momentum of the disease was not developed until<lb/>
October 1st, when the natural decline of stegomyia breeding begins.</p>
<p>The Department of Public Health of Mexico now began active measures<lb/>
for organization of the entire Republic against the disease, as there were active<lb/>
epidemics in three other areas. Unfortunately, an investigating committee, sent<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01016007"/>
5<lb/>
to this coast, arrived late in the year, when all active manifestation had<lb/>
disappeared.</p>
<p>In January, 1921, a Special Commission was appointed under control<lb/>
of the Department of Public Health, and Dr. Theodore C. Lyster, of the Interna-<lb/>
tional Health Board, was appointed Director.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemic of 1921</hi>.</p>
<p>In March of 1921, a preliminary survey was made on this coast.<lb/>
Little or no stegomyia breeding was found north of Mazatlan at this time.</p>
<p>By midsummer, definite outbreaks of Yellow Fever were in progress in<lb/>
Vera Cruz, Tampico, Quintana Roo and British Honduras, Suspicious reports<lb/>
were being received from the small port of Manzanillo, just south of our area.<lb/>
Due to the pressure of work in other and more active areas and the scarcity of<lb/>
trained personnel, it was impossible to organize this zone as early as had<lb/>
been hoped. The arrival, August 26th, of the Director of the Commission on<lb/>
his second visit to the zone, was almost coincidental with the long delayed offi-<lb/>
cial declaration of Yellow Fever in Manzanillo and the recognition of four cases<lb/>
from various ships, which had called at Manzanillo, in the maritime quarantine<lb/>
station in Mazatlan, where the Port Doctor was having considerable difficulty<lb/>
in enforcing quarantine measures.</p>
<p>Anti-mosquito work was hurriedly improvised in Mazatlan, beginning on<lb/>
September 3d. Due to absolute lack of trained personnel and to the exceptionally<lb/>
easy conditions for control in this city, the simplest possible measure was<lb/>
adopted, that of <unclear>emotying</unclear> all containers of standing water. The city has a good<lb/>
water supply and no particular hardship was imposed by dumping all containers as<lb/>
found. A squad of inspectors was organized with a view of making a thorough revi-<lb/>
sion.of the city every ten days and preferably every week. The first revision<lb/>
actually required more than two weeks. Then, due to further alarm from the<lb/>
direction of Culiacan, the squad was increased in size and speeded up to a revi-<lb/>
sion of the whole city each nine or ten days.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f01016008"/>
<p>6</p>
<p>About September 14th, Yellow Fever was reported in Culiacan, breaking<lb/>
out in the family of the Bishop, who himself was the first to succumb. The acti-<lb/>
vities of our organization were hurriedly extended to Culiacan, borrowing some<lb/>
of the more promising personnel of the Mazatlan inspecting squad and organizing<lb/>
a new group under the direction of Dr. Cliserio Garcia, special delegate of the<lb/>
Health Department. By September 21st, the anti-mosquito work was progressing<lb/>
here on the same plan as in Mazatlan, but under physical conditions not so favor-<lb/>
able.</p>
<p>The exact origin of the infection in Culiacan could not be traced, but<lb/>
the logical belief is that some passenger from Manzanillo slipped through the<lb/>
quarantine in Mazatlan in time to infect the household of the Bishop in which<lb/>
two deaths occurred and two other cases were diagnosed.</p>
<p>The next development, on September 28th, was a sharp but limited out-<lb/>
break in the village of Palmar de los Leales, just a day's journey overland<lb/>
north from Culiacan, seven deaths occurring in a group of nine sick, who presented<lb/>
typical symptoms. These persons all fell sick on or about September 18th, sugg-<lb/>
esting they were all infected on the same occasion, possibly in visiting some<lb/>
unrecognized case.</p>
<p>By this time the possibilities of the improvised zone organization<lb/>
were spreading very thinly over a large area but with some effort a new anti-<lb/>
stegomyia brigade was organized October 11th under instruction of one of the<lb/>
original group of inspectors in Mazatlan, and under the supervision of Dr.<lb/>
Carlos Salazar of Guamuchil, forty kilometers away, but the only doctor in a<lb/>
sixty kilometers radius. Fortunately, conditions were most unpropitious for<lb/>
spread of the disease, being in a sparsely populated agricultural district,<lb/>
huts flimsily constructed and unfavorable for stegomyia breeding, and with very<lb/>
little <hi>impounded</hi> water. There may have been some additional protection to one<lb/>
or two neighboring hamlets in the stringent shotgun quarantines they established<lb/>
on their own initiative and which were not interfered with.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f01016009"/>
<p>7</p>
<p>In this zone, some use was made of the Noguchi Vaccine, one hundred<lb/>
and ninety-three first vaccinations being made in the village of Palmar (about<lb/>
three hundred and fifty inhabitants) and forty second vaccinations of the more<lb/>
exposed. Vaccine was used to a lesser extent in Culiacan and Mazatlan, due<lb/>
mostly to scarcity of the material. No inference can be drawn on its use, due<lb/>
to lack of opportunity for close observation.</p>
<p>The campaign in this zone was made possible and timely only by the<lb/>
assistance of the International Health Board, in advancing funds which were<lb/>
later repaid by the Mexican Government.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f01016010"/>
<p>8</p>
<p>RESULTS OF DUMPING INSPECTIONS</p>
<p>MAZATLAN</p>
<p>September 3d - November 30th, 1921.</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="7">
     <row>
          <cell>Inspection</cell>
          <cell>Houses</cell>
          <cell>Con-<lb/>tainers</cell>
          <cell>Houses<lb/>Breed-<lb/>ing</cell>
          <cell>Cont'rs<lb/>Breed-<lb/>ing</cell>
          <cell>Index<lb/>House</cell>
          <cell>Notes</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>9/6-9/21</cell>
          <cell>5845</cell>
          <cell>34289</cell>
          <cell>3615</cell>
          <cell>6922</cell>
          <cell>.61</cell>
          <cell></cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>9/27-10/6</cell>
          <cell>6160</cell>
          <cell>28570</cell>
          <cell>1059</cell>
          <cell>1557</cell>
          <cell>.17</cell>
          <cell>House index reduction 70%</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>10/7-10/22</cell>
          <cell>6418</cell>
          <cell>33782</cell>
          <cell>478</cell>
          <cell>627</cell>
          <cell>.07</cell>
          <cell>Do. 60%</cell>
     </row>
<row>
<cell>10/23-10/29</cell><cell>490</cell><cell>3525</cell><cell>97</cell><cell>117</cell><cell>.05</cell><cell>Worst Areas</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>10/30-11/15</cell><cell>6090</cell><cell>33106</cell><cell>245</cell><cell>256</cell><cell>.04</cell><cell>House Index reduction 43%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>11/16-11/18</cell><cell><hi>167</hi></cell><cell><hi>1046</hi></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>.01</cell><cell>Worst Areas</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>25170</cell><cell>134318</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></p>
<p>CULIACAN</p>
<p>September 21st - December 31st, 1921.</p>
<p>
<table rows="10" cols="7">
<row>
<cell>Inspection</cell><cell>Houses</cell><cell>Con-<lb/>
tainers</cell><cell>Houses<lb/>
Breed-<lb/>
ing</cell><cell>Cont'rs<lb/>
Breed-<lb/>
ing</cell><cell>Index<lb/>
House</cell><cell>Notes</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>3015</cell><cell>17148</cell><cell>1803</cell><cell>3974</cell><cell>58</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>3173</cell><cell>15869</cell><cell>1181</cell><cell>1639</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>House index reduction 36%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>3091</cell><cell>13605</cell><cell>748</cell><cell>935</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>Do. 35%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4</cell><cell>3176</cell><cell>15006</cell><cell>412</cell><cell>522</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>Do. 50%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5</cell><cell>3379</cell><cell>14839</cell><cell>235</cell><cell>289</cell><cell>06</cell><cell>Do. 50%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6</cell><cell>3369</cell><cell>13927</cell><cell>140</cell><cell>156</cell><cell>04</cell><cell>Do. 33%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>7</cell><cell>3322</cell><cell>13117</cell><cell>92</cell><cell>101</cell><cell>027</cell><cell>Do. 33%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>8</cell><cell><hi>2476</hi></cell><cell><hi>9383</hi></cell><cell>32</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>0129</cell><cell>Do. 52%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>25001</cell><cell>112894</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></p>
<pb n="10" id="f01016011"/>
<p>RESULTS OF DUMPING INSPECTIONS</p>
<p>Mocorito District.</p>
<p>Guamuchil, Mocorito and Palmar de los Leales</p>
<p>October 11th - December 31st, 1921.</p>
<p>
<table rows="26" cols="7">
<row>
<cell>Inspection</cell><cell>Houses</cell><cell>Con-<lb/>
tainers</cell><cell>Houses<lb/>
Breed-<lb/>
ing</cell><cell>Cont'rs<lb/>
Breed-<lb/>
ing</cell><cell>Index<lb/>
House</cell><cell>Notes</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G</cell><cell>319</cell><cell>1263</cell><cell>172</cell><cell>250</cell><cell>53.9</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>M - Oct.12</cell><cell>428</cell><cell>1876</cell><cell>216</cell><cell>370</cell><cell>50.4</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>P - Oct.24</cell><cell>205</cell><cell>1125</cell><cell>104</cell><cell>245</cell><cell>50.7</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G - Oct.22</cell><cell>316</cell><cell>1080</cell><cell>154</cell><cell>181</cell><cell>48.7</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>M</cell><cell>422</cell><cell>1678</cell><cell>187</cell><cell>261</cell><cell>45.3</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>P - Nov. 1</cell><cell>252</cell><cell>1329</cell><cell>105</cell><cell>235</cell><cell>41.6</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G - Nov. 2</cell><cell>331</cell><cell>1249</cell><cell>121</cell><cell>125</cell><cell>35.5</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>M - " 13</cell><cell>424</cell><cell>1615</cell><cell>170</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>40.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>P - " "</cell><cell>263</cell><cell>1753</cell><cell>96</cell><cell>190</cell><cell>36.5</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G - Nov.14</cell><cell>350</cell><cell>1410</cell><cell>98</cell><cell>99</cell><cell>28.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>M - " 24</cell><cell>390</cell><cell>1490</cell><cell>142</cell><cell>201</cell><cell>36.4</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>P - " "</cell><cell>265</cell><cell>1507</cell><cell>90</cell><cell>154</cell><cell>33.9</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G - Nov.25</cell><cell>345</cell><cell>1300</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>85</cell><cell>20.3</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>M - Dec. 5</cell><cell>345</cell><cell>1501</cell><cell>112</cell><cell>181</cell><cell>28.2</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>P - Dec. 5</cell><cell>238</cell><cell>1197</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>80</cell><cell>29.4</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G - Dec. 6</cell><cell>330</cell><cell>1322</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>12.1</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>M - Dec.17</cell><cell>422</cell><cell><unclear>1680</unclear></cell><cell>96</cell><cell>160</cell><cell>22.7</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>P - " "</cell><cell>226</cell><cell>1140</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>26.1</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G - Dec.17</cell><cell><unclear>335</unclear></cell><cell>1305</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>10.4</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>M - " 27</cell><cell>426</cell><cell>1578</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>120</cell><cell>14.7</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>P - " "</cell><cell>230</cell><cell>1162</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>52</cell><cell>17.3</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G - Dec.28</cell><cell>125</cell><cell>431</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>10.4</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>M - " 31</cell><cell>142</cell><cell>581</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>12.6</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>P - " "</cell><cell><hi>78</hi></cell><cell><hi>364</hi></cell><cell>10</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>17.8</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>7207</cell><cell>30836</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></p>
<p>Note: This District shows the lack of supervision. The Delegado<lb/>
Especial in charge suffered a broken leg November 5th<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f01016012"/>
10<lb/>
and it was impossible to replace an experienced Doctor here. However<lb/>
the District was quiet - no case appearing after October 15th and very un-<lb/>
propitious for spread of disease.</p>
<p>The reducing of mosquito breeding here shown is probably only<lb/>
50% better than the natural decline due to temperature change at this<lb/>
time of the year.</p>
<p>SUMMARY OF CAMPAIGN</p>
<p>September 1st - December 31st, 1921</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="7">
<row>
<cell>Town</cell><cell>No. of In-<lb/>
spections</cell><cell>Total No.<lb/>
Housed</cell><cell>Total No.<lb/>
Containers</cell><cell>Initial<lb/>
House<lb/>
Index</cell><cell>Final<lb/>
House<lb/>
Index</cell><cell>Cost<lb/>
Peso's<lb/>
O. N.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mazatlan</cell><cell>3 comp.</cell><cell>25179</cell><cell>134318</cell><cell>Sept.3d</cell><cell>Nov.30</cell><cell>5185.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>2 spec.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>61%</cell><cell>4%</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Culiacan</cell><cell>7 comp.</cell><cell>25001</cell><cell>112894</cell><cell>Sept.21</cell><cell>Dec.31</cell><cell>5043.48</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>1 part 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>58%</cell><cell>2%</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mocorito</cell><cell>7 comp.</cell><cell>7248</cell><cell>30936</cell><cell>Oct.12</cell><cell>Dec.31</cell><cell>2955.82</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Dist.</cell><cell>1 part 1.</cell><cell>____</cell><cell>____</cell><cell>51.6%</cell><cell>13.6%</cell><cell>_______</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>57428</cell><cell>278148</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>13184.30</cell></row></table></p>
<p>General expense of organization and supervision<lb/>
of Zone, by Chief of Zone <hi>1576.80</hi><lb/></p>
<p>Total Local Cost 14761.10</p>
<p>Includes all local expense of campaign, including salaries<lb/>
and expenses of Delegados Especiales, etc., but does not include over-<lb/>
head expense of the Mexican Government or International Health Board.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f01016013"/>
<p>11</p>
<p>PROGRESS OF EPIDEMIC</p>
<p>1921</p>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="7">
<row>
<cell>Town</cell><cell>First<lb/>
Case</cell><cell>Last<lb/>
Case</cell><cell>Total<lb/>
Cases</cell><cell>Total<lb/>
Death</cell><cell>Anti<lb/>
Mosquito<lb/>
Campaign</cell><cell>Campaign<lb/>
Finished</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mazatlan</cell><cell>Aug.25</cell><cell>Sept.20</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>Sept. 3d</cell><cell>Nov.30th</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Four in maritime quarantine)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Culiacan</cell><cell>Sept.12</cell><cell>Oct. 18</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>Sept.21</cell><cell>Dec.31</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mocorito<lb/>
District</cell><cell>Sept.18</cell><cell>Oct. 15</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>Oct. 11</cell><cell>Dec. 31</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Guaymas</cell><cell>Aug. 30</cell><cell>---</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>---</cell><cell>---</cell></row></table></p>
<p>Ruiz &amp;<lb/>
San Blas Cases suspected but not proved</p>
<p>Rosa Morada Cases suspected but disproved</p>
<p>Total Cases 44 Total Deaths 27</p>
<p>Notes:</p>
<p>Mazatlan. Three cases from Manzanillo died in quarantine August<lb/>
25 to September 3. One case from Culiacan September, dying September 25.<lb/>
One case Dr. P. Lopez delegated Sanitary Officer of Port of Mazatlan while<lb/>
en route called on convalescent friend in Manzanillo on September 13 and 14,<lb/>
became sick September 17, arrived Mazatlan September 19 with mild case<lb/>
Yellow Fever. Had received one prophylactic injection of Perrin Vaccine year<lb/>
before. Long convalescence.</p>
<p>Culiacan. Infection probably from Manzanillo via Mazatlan. Late<lb/>
in October, Bernardo J. Gastellum reported finding leptospira icteroides in<lb/>
two cases, one of which died.</p>
<p>Guaymas. Juan Ruiz, Captain of Marines, after spending several<lb/>
days in Manzanillo, left that port August 27, arriving in Guaymas seriously ill,<lb/>
on that night of August 30, dying September 3. At time of arrival temperature<lb/>
39, pulse 90, vomiting but no hemorrhage, no icterus, no albuminuria. Director<lb/>
of Civil Hospital found plasmodia in blood and diagnosed Malaria. Up to time<lb/>
of death temperature remained high, pulse became slower. Never showed hemorrhages<lb/>
or albuminuria but developed moderate icterus, increasing somewhat after death.<lb/>
Temperature rose after death. Autopsy finding suggestive of Yellow Fever.<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f01016014"/>
12<lb/>
Year of 1922.</p>
<p>The entire Republic of Mexico was now thoroughly organized against<lb/>
Yellow Fever. Seven major zones had been created, of which the territory under<lb/>
discussion in this paper constituted the Fifth. Each zone was under the charge<lb/>
of a Chief, whose responsibility it was to prepare a budget in advance for the<lb/>
year of 1922. Dr. Joseph H. White now succeeded Dr. Theodore C. Lyster as Direc-<lb/>
tor, working under the Departamento de Salubridad Publica of Mexico.</p>
<p>This zone, the Fifth, was catalogued as epidemic only, but all other<lb/>
zones were classified as possibly, if not actually, endemic. Zone siz, Colima<lb/>
and Manzanillo, immediately to the south of us, was newly classified as endemic.<lb/>
However, in 1921, an intensive antimosquito campaign had been pursued in Zone<lb/>
six, with the result that the mosquito index was reduced below the danger point<lb/>
five (5%) percent, and was kept under control by the systematic use of fish.</p>
<p>With the zones to the south well supervised and controlled, practi-<lb/>
cally all danger to this area was removed. Consequently, it was believed<lb/>
there would be no Yellow Fever development in the zone this year. (At the time<lb/>
of this writing - December 1, 1922 - there has actually been no development of<lb/>
any kind.)</p>
<p>Therefore, early in the year, the Chief of the Zone proposed to re-<lb/>
duce expense by carrying out no active antimosquito work whatever. It was pro-<lb/>
posed to create and maintain a skeleton organization under training, to be ex-<lb/>
panded to meet requirements, if our forecast for the year proved wrong. We<lb/>
were convinced by the work of 1921 that, being prepared, we could in a month's<lb/>
time reduce mosquito breeding below the danger point in any community.</p>
<p>This plan being approved by the Comision Especial, the skeleton organ-<lb/>
ization was formed as a &ldquo;Flying Squad&rdquo; consisting of a Chief Inspector, and two<lb/>
Assistant Inspectors, who were to be trained as future Chiefs of Districts.<lb/>
This Brigade operated under the orders of the writers and Dr. A. M. Fernandez,<lb/>
Delegado Especial in Mazatlan. We were fortunate in securing a highly trained<lb/>
Chief Inspector, Mr. H. B. Richardson, who had had experience in the more active<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f01016015"/>
13<lb/>
Yellow Fever zones of Tampico and Vera Cruz. The duties of the Flying<lb/>
Squad while waiting possible service in active campaign, were the following:</p>
<p>Physical Survey of all important towns, particularly the Ports,<lb/>
in the states of Sinaloa and Nayarit, card-indexing the following information:</p>
<p>Geographical or topographical advantages or disadvantages</p>
<p>Estimate of population, number of houses and number of inspectors<lb/>
necessary to make a thorough revision in seven days</p>
<p>Obtain monthly index of mosquito incidence and noting type of<lb/>
mosquitoes</p>
<p>List and locate permanent water containers, such as wells,<lb/>
cisterns, tanks, etc.; noting control measures best adaptable,<lb/>
such as sealing, screening, oiling, fish implantation, etc.</p>
<p>Classification of local fish, turtles, water bugs, weeds (chara<lb/>
foetida) and other larva destroying factors. Fish to be<lb/>
identified as top or bottom feeder, source of supply, cost of<lb/>
collection and transportation, availability and viability<lb/>
for various classes of containers, etc.</p>
<p>Incidentally, the Brigade was to disseminate as much popular<lb/>
information as possible during the course of these investi-<lb/>
gations.</p>
<p>This work was carried on from April to the end of July, then,<lb/>
due to the generally favorable conditions in all zones, the work was super-<lb/>
seded in August and September by a program of distribution of selected<lb/>
local fish to permanent containers in Culiacan and Mazatlan, for experimental<lb/>
and educational purposes. The work has cost, from April 1st to date, exclu-<lb/>
sive of overhead and supervision, about Five thousand (5,000.00) pesos.</p>
<p>The results of some of the investigations of the Brigade are noted<lb/>
in the appendix to this paper. As a result of this work, <add>if</add> it should ever<lb/>
again become necessary to institute active measures against house mosquitoes,<lb/>
it will undoubtedly be done by the systematic use of fish and other larva<lb/>
destroying factors.</p>
<p>The Chief impressions gained:</p>
<p>1. The remarkable facility by which Yellow Fever may be controlled<lb/>
by organized and informed effort, striking at the most pampered and vulnerable<lb/>
of mosquitoes. (Note the reduction of Sixty (60%) percent of the breeding by<lb/>
each single, rapidly conducted emptying of all water containers.)</p>
<p>2. The relative difficulty of obtaining exact information on<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f01016016"/>
14<lb/>
Yellow Fever from sources available to the general profession. General<lb/>
medical texts are invariably vague and misleading on the subject, in direct<lb/>
opposition to the positive assurance radiated by those Sanitarians who <add>have</add> had<lb/>
large experience with it. A disease so exactly studies as this and so<lb/>
amenable to control should have better reporters.</p>
<p>3. The good fortune of this Coast and the region to the North,<lb/>
that communication from the South has been restricted and difficult in the<lb/>
past. In 1919, 1920 and 1921, the disease effected its jump, from the<lb/>
endemic area to the South to this zone, so late in the summer or fall<lb/>
that the reduction of mosquito breeding by cooler weather probably averted<lb/>
more rapid development.</p>
<pb n="16" id="f01016017"/>
<p><hi>APPENDIX</hi></p>
<p>Notes and Recommendations<lb/>
From Antimosquito Survey of<lb/>
Sinaloa and Nayarit during<lb/>
Campaign of 1922.</p>
<p>LOCAL LARVICIDE FACTORS</p>
<p>Constant supervision must be provided to keep mosquito breeding<lb/>
under control, unless an active factor, such as fish, is present, in the tank<lb/>
or container, to consume larvae continuously. Dumping campaigns, such as pur-<lb/>
sued in this area in 1921 are purely emergency measures, effective only during<lb/>
the active period of work. Two months of such dumping inspection in Mazatlan<lb/>
reduced the Mosquito index from 65% to 4%, but two months after stoppage of<lb/>
active work the index had again risen to 30%.</p>
<p>Connor and others have proven that certain small fish can be success-<lb/>
fully employed as larvicides in all reasonably large water containers.</p>
<p>To investigate the possibilities of local fish for this purpose, a<lb/>
special tank was established at the railroad emergency hospital in Mazatlan.<lb/>
The tank was constructed on plans indicated by Dr. M. E. Connor:</p>
<p>1. Of Sufficient size to support fish life conveniently (twelve<lb/>
feet long, four feet wide, two feet deep, divided by fine<lb/>
mesh screen into three compartments approximately four feet<lb/>
square)</p>
<p>2. Well shaded, yet allowing air currents from all sides</p>
<p>3. Bottom liberally provided with large rocks, broken pottery, etc.;<lb/>
to provide resting caves for fish</p>
<p>4. A corner of each compartment fitted with coarse mesh screen,<lb/>
allowing young fish to seek refuge from their elders.</p>
<p>Observations made in this tank have shown that this area has an<lb/>
ample supply of larvicide fish. In addition we have made considerable study<lb/>
of a certain water-bug (Notonecta) and a few experiments with turtle and Algae.</p>
<pb n="17" id="f01016018"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>Photograph of THE CHALACO<lb/>
DORMITATOR LATIFRONS</p>
<p>According to Dr. Eigenmann, Dean of Indiana University - occurr-<lb/>
ing within the tidal zone in rivers from Northern Peru to California.</p>
<p>Very widely distributed, bottom feeder, and a voracious feeder<lb/>
of larvae. This fish, used by Connor at Guayaquil, was found the most<lb/>
satisfactory for consuming mosquito larvae and mosquito eggs in small<lb/>
containers. Has best viability of all fish in this region to withstand<lb/>
change and handling.</p>
<p>Next to the Gambusia Affinis is the most widely distributed of<lb/>
all small larvicide fish in this area. Is found in all of the rivers and<lb/>
most of the arroyos from the Mocorito to the Santiago River.</p>
<p>Has been used most successfully and economically in Culiacan<lb/>
and Mazatlan.</p>
<p>(Photo by McKenna, Mazatlan.)</p>
<pb n="18" id="f01016019"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>Photograph of LISA (Jumping Fish)</p>
<p>Fairly well distributed, top feeder and good eater of<lb/>
larvae.</p>
<p>More delicate than Chalaco but hardier than Mojarra or<lb/>
Robalo. Used in aljibes, deep wells and narrow necked containers.</p>
<p>Has been located in the following rivers:</p>
<p>Presidio and Rosario.</p>
<p>(Photo by McKenna, Mazatlan.)</p>
<pb n="19" id="f01016020"/>
<p>4</p>
<p>Photograph of ROBALO PLATEADO</p>
<p>Widely distributed, top and bottom feeder and a voracious feeder of<lb/>
larvae. Used at Vera Cruz. Richardson claims to have had good results<lb/>
with it in Vera Cruz District. Has advantge of giving birth to young<lb/>
direct and not by hatching eggs. Propagation rapid. It will, when fright-<lb/>
ened, jump from containers - can be used in aljibes and wells and narrow<lb/>
necked containers. Does not attain its full growth until contact with salt<lb/>
water.</p>
<p>Used at first in Culiacan in September, 1922, but all died by end of<lb/>
third day. Experience here at Mazatlan demonstrates that it is very delicate<lb/>
and does not easily accustom itself to new surroundings.</p>
<p>Has been identified in the following rivers:</p>
<p>Mocorito, Humaya, Presidio, Rosario, Acaponeta,<lb/>
and Santiago.</p>
<p>(Photo by McKenna, Mazatlan.)</p>
<pb n="20" id="f01016021"/>
<p>5</p>
<p>Photograph of <hi>MOJARRA VERDI</hi></p>
<p>Fairly well distributed, top and bottom feeder. Voracious feeder<lb/>
of larvae and fighter. Is more delicate than chalaco, but may prove to<lb/>
be very servicable. Should be studied further.</p>
<p>Has been found in the Presidio and Rosario Rivers.</p>
<p>(Photo by McKenna, Mazatlan.)</p>
<p><hi>GAMBUSIA AFFINIS.</hi></p>
<p>Very plentiful but not considered because of its inability to with-<lb/>
stand rough handling.</p>
<p>It is better adapted to antimalarial work.</p>
<pb n="21" id="f01016022"/>
<p>6.</p>
<p>Photograph of - Notonecta glauca, resting. and<lb/>

Notonecta Glauca feeding.</p>
<p><hi>NOTONECTIDAE (Glauca</hi></p>
<p>CLASS HEXAPODA</p>
<p>ORDER HEMIPTERA (HALF WING)</p>
<p>SUBORDER HETEROPTERA</p>
<p>TRIBE CRYPTOCERATA</p>
<p>FAMILY NOTONECTIDAE.</p>
<p>(Photos by Dr. Cliserio Garcia<lb/>
J. Culiacan.)</p>
<pb n="22" id="f01016023"/>
<p>7.</p>
<p><hi>NOTONECTIDAE</hi></p>
<p>Notonecta Glauca.</p>
<p>Notonecta (Backswimmer)<lb/>
English - &ldquo;Waterboatman.&rdquo;<lb/>
Local - &ldquo;Zeppelina.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This waterbug has been our most interesting find.</p>
<p>Noted in Culiacan in 1921 by one of our Inspectors, Enrique<lb/>
Boyles, that there was an absence of larvae wherever these waterbugs<lb/>
were found. Transplanting the bugs into jars of water swarming with<lb/>
larvae he found the bugs destroyed the larvae at an astonishing rate,<lb/>
considering relative sizes.</p>
<p>He communicated these findings to Dr. Cliserio Garcia J., Delegado<lb/>
Especial in Culiacan, who experimented with them and developed many inter-<lb/>
esting facts, along with work by Richardson in Mazatlan and ourselves in<lb/>
the railroad service.</p>
<p>E. H. Ross mentions these insects in his work on &ldquo;Reduction of<lb/>
Domestic Mosquitos&rdquo; as being successfully used at Port Said. He condemns<lb/>
them as being inefficient in grassy ponds, but we have found them consider-<lb/>
ably better, on account of their diminutive size, then fish under the same<lb/>
conditions.</p>
<p>They are widely distributed all over this area, in fresh water pools<lb/>
and ponds, being brought down from the higher lands by the spring and<lb/>
summer floods. Richardson saw them in Tampico and in the Papantla district.</p>
<p>Garcia writes:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The name Notonecta&rdquo; has been given to the insect for its custom<lb/>
of swimming upside down. In order to propel itself through the water, it<lb/>
makes use of fast and powerful thrusts of its hind legs, which are thickly<lb/>
provided with hairs, much on the order of the feathering of an arrow.<lb/>
<pb n="23" id="f01016024"/>
8<lb/>
When the insect is at rest these legs are extended laterally, similar to<lb/>
the position of oars in a rowboat, for which reason it has been named &ldquo;boatman.&rdquo;</p>
<p>"The Boatman apparently receives its oxygen in the form of airbubbles<lb/>
that are caught and held in a heavy coating of hairs which cover its body.</p>
<p>"The Boatman deposits its eggs in the shelter of whatever Algae or<lb/>
other aquatic plant that may be present in its habitat. Its food consists of<lb/>
Larvae, Pupae, Bugs and other small insects. I have also noted that it will<lb/>
eat the eggs of fish and even the small fish themselves.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Observing them in their swimming position, (upside down) it will<lb/>
be noticed that they have in their <unclear>anterior</unclear> extremity a considerable number<lb/>
of small tentacles or claws with which they catch the prey that they are about<lb/>
to devour. The Larva of Pupa is invariably caught by the head and while its<lb/>
contents are being sucked, it is dragged through the water by the Boatman,<lb/>
giving the appearance of a tiny boat with an enormous flag flying. The suction<lb/>
(of the body juices) once finished, he frees himself of the hide or shell of<lb/>
his prey and starts in quest of another.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The following observations are mostly from Harris of Mazatlan:</p>
<p>The Notonecta is about the same length of the average larva (occasion-<lb/>
ally growing to twice that length) and four to six times the thickness of the<lb/>
larva at its greatest girth.</p>
<p>The inferior surface (swimming position) is shaped like the hull of<lb/>
a racing yacht, and has a metallic luster on movement. The body is encased<lb/>
in a hard shell which is covered with hair.</p>
<p>The superior surface is much hairier and reflects a brown color.<lb/>
From this surface on each side of the median line, just back of the center of<lb/>
the body are attached the hind legs (oars). Forward of the central point on<lb/>
this surface are four tentacles arranged in <unclear>enterior</unclear> and posterior pairs. Each<lb/>
tentacle end is armed with a quarter moon shaped claw, like the nails on the<lb/>
claws of a hawk. Harris believes the tips of these claws to be hollow, for<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f01016025"/>
9<lb/>
injecting and aspirating fluids. The two <unclear>enterior</unclear> tentacles, when placed to-<lb/>
gether, form a tube like canal to the head. These tentacles grasp the victim,<lb/>
draw it to the thorax and head, suck in liquid contents by tubes in the ten-<lb/>
tacles, then cast aside the solid portion.</p>
<p>The Head is encased in a helmet-like, many faceted, hard cartilagi-<lb/>
nous substance, brown in color. When excited the insect often repeatedly rams<lb/>
its head against the walls of the container, producing a very audible clicking<lb/>
sound.</p>
<p>Movements.</p>
<p>Dives and swims through the water with amazing rapidity, often escap-<lb/>
ing our speediest fish, dodging if pursued, and leaping over surface of water.</p>
<p>It will leap from surface of water upwards for a meter. When seeking<lb/>
a new water deposit it can progress over land by a series of flights of two or<lb/>
three meters, flying in reverse (upright) position and using legs as wings. (Garcia)<lb/>
Habits.</p>
<p>Top or bottom feeder, voracious for mosquito larvae. Its movements<lb/>
are so rapid that it rarely fails to catch its victim, striking from below or<lb/>
from side, grasping larva by the head, and small fish near the caudal end. It<lb/>
is necessarily a slower feeder than fish, holding on to larva from five to ten<lb/>
minutes before casting aside dead remains.</p>
<p>Propagation:</p>
<p>Rapid if fed and properly cared for. If starved no attempt at propa-<lb/>
gation.</p>
<p>Viability:</p>
<p>Exceedingly good. Known to live for month or more without food or<lb/>
change of water. Very resistant to handling.</p>
<p>Connor suggested to Richardson several experiments to ascertain via-<lb/>
bility of Notonecta in Lejia solution (lejia; woodlye solution much used for<lb/>
laundry purposes in hardwater regions, constitutes an important problem in certain<lb/>
parts of Mexico, for larvae thrive in the solution, while fish die almost immediately<lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f01016026"/>
10<lb/>
when placed therein.) Richardson's experiments seem to prove that the notanecta<lb/>
was equally viable as the larva in strong lejia as long as the ash residue was<lb/>
not stirred sufficiently to cloud the water and obstruct the air passages of<lb/>
the insect. Healthy gambusia placed in the same solution dies in two minutes<lb/>
while the notonecta were all living on the sixth day.</p>
<p><hi>NOTONECTIDAE AND FISH</hi></p>
<p>It is best not to mix the two in the same container.</p>
<p>Adults of both species soon learn to respect each other's fighting<lb/>
qualities but each preys upon the young of the other.</p>
<p>Usefulness:</p>
<p>In fish planting in Mazatlan in 1922, notonectae were used in the<lb/>
first cuartel and part of the second cuartel. The results were entirely<lb/>
satisfactory. It was observed that in small containers both in house and<lb/>
garden, these insects lived where fish died, also that in all containers ex-<lb/>
posed to much light and heat these insects were superior.</p>
<p>Since 1921, in the course of many hundreds of inspections of water<lb/>
tanks maintained by the railroad for various purposes, we have yet to encounter<lb/>
mosquito breeding in places where the Boatman are found. We are of the belief<lb/>
that these insects are very useful larvicides.</p>
<p><hi>TURTLES</hi></p>
<p>Our experiments with turtles were too few to be conclusive. Garcia<lb/>
reported absolute failure with several varieties in Culiacan, while Harris had<lb/>
considerable encouragement from one species in Mazatlan.</p>
<p><hi>ALGAE</hi></p>
<p>Chara Foetida. A. Br., recommended by Dr. Arturo Caballero of Spain.<lb/>
We have no experience with it as we have not yet identified it on this Coast.</p>
<p>Local Algae, when sufficiently thick to interfere with larva activity,<lb/>
also killed off the fish and other natural protectors.</p>
<pb n="26" id="f01016027"/>
<p>11</p>
<p><hi>ACTIVE CAMPAIGN OF FISH PLANTING<lb/>
IN PERMANENT DEPOSITS</hi></p>
<p>August, September, and October, 1922</p>
<p>Culiacan: August 25 to September 25, 1922, under direction of Dr. Andres Vidales.</p>
<p>Robalo and Chalaco used.</p>
<p>One hundred and sixty-two Robalo planted during the first week all<lb/>
died, in addition to heavy mortality in transplanting from breeding place.<lb/>
After first week no more Robalo were used but Chalaco only, of which 4749 were<lb/>
planted. At the end of the month it was found there had been no mortality<lb/>
among the Chalaco other than due to actual mishandling or carelessness of the<lb/>
householders. Mosquito breeding, which had been very active before, had ceased<lb/>
entirely in all containers holding fish.</p>
<p>The cost of this work in Culiacan, including cost, and transportation<lb/>
of fish, and salaries of two inspectors and four mozos, was $745.80 pesos. The<lb/>
same work could now be repeated in fifteen days instead of thirty-three and for<lb/>
$400,00 pesos instead of $750.00.</p>
<p>Mazatlan: October 1 to October 31, 1922, under direction of Dr. Arnulfo M.<lb/>
Fernandez.</p>
<p>Of fish only the Chalaco was used.</p>
<p>About fifteen hundred were planted in five cuartels with the same<lb/>
good results as noted in Culiacan.</p>
<p>Control experiments were made in two cuartels with the Notonectae of<lb/>
which 665 were used. In the last cuartel 420 Notonectae (no Chalaco) were<lb/>
used. In the second cuartel 265 Notonectae and 141 Chalaco were used. The<lb/>
same good results of freedom from mosquito breeding were observed with the<lb/>
Notonectae as with the Chalaco. The following notes were made:</p>
<p>Advantages of Notonectae:</p>
<p>More resistant than Chalaco in very small containers, very shallow<lb/>
containers and in containers exposed to sun and heat. (Garden and roof tanks.)</p>
<pb n="27" id="f01016028"/>
<p>12</p>
<p>Disadvantages of Notonectae:</p>
<p>Being so very small, little care is taken of them by the householders,<lb/>
allowing them to escape with drainage dipping them up with buckets, etc.</p>
<p>The cost of plantation of fish in Mazatlan, including cost of fish<lb/>
and salaries of two inspectors and four mozos was $497.20 pesos (twenty-two<lb/>
days.) It could have been repeated in about twelve to fifteen days for less<lb/>
than $300.00.</p>
<p><hi>PRESUPUESTO (Budget) FOR FUTURE WORK IF NECESSARY</hi></p>
<p>1. General Presupuesto.</p>
<p>Headquarters should be established in Mazatlan, as being the only<lb/>
important port, the metropolis, the geographical, transportation and distribut-<lb/>
ing center of this area.</p>
<p>General Staff.</p>
<p>Chief of the Zone (full time) in charge.</p>
<p>1 - Delegado Especial, who may be a local man on part time<lb/>
1 - Inspector General<lb/>
2 - Division Inspectors (north and south)<lb/>
1 - Clerk<lb/>
1 - Mozo</p>
<p>Central experimental tank and distributing pond or well<lb/>
to be maintained in Mazatlan.</p>
<p>Divisions.</p>
<p>Northern Division</p>
<p>(1st) Topolobampo District.</p>
<p>Rio Fuerte to Rio Mocorito.</p>
<p>This district as well as all others to have the<lb/>
following preliminary organization. One Delegado Especial<lb/>
in Charge. (Part time.) One or two mozos to maintain<lb/>
breeding and distributing pond.</p>
<p>(2nd) Culiacan District.<lb/>
Rio Mocorito to Rio Piaxtla.</p>
<p>Central Division</p>
<p>(3d) Mazatlan District.<lb/>
Rio Piaxtla to Rio Presidio.</p>
<p>Southern Division</p>
<p>(4th) Acaponeta District.<lb/>
Rio Presidio to Rio Santiago</p>
<p>Possibly also a Fifth District.<lb/>
Rio Santiago to Rio Tepic.</p>
<pb n="28" id="f01016029"/>
<p>13</p>
<p>II. DETAIL PRESUPUESTO (Budget)</p>
<p>of time and cost of fish implantation and each later revision<lb/>
in important towns.</p>
<p>Note:</p>
<p>Permanent containers (depositos) include wells, tanks, troughs and<lb/>
fountains. Temporary containers include unattached barrels and all smaller<lb/>
containers, capable of easy cleaning and dumping.</p>
<p>
 <table rows="8" cols="5">
     <row>
          <cell>Town and<lb/>Population</cell>
          <cell>Special Notes</cell>
          <cell>Personnel<lb/>Required</cell>
          <cell>Days</cell>
          <cell>Cost<lb/>Approx.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Guamuchil<lb/>Sin.<lb/>1445</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 125<lb/>Others 1424. No water or drainage<lb/>
               systems. Many norias on river bank.<lb/>
               Fish abundant in summer - few in<lb/>
               winter. Can be supplied from<lb/>Mocorito.</cell>
          <cell>1 Inspector<lb/>2 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>4</cell>
          <cell>$50.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Mocorito<lb/>Sin.<lb/>2153</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 92. Others<lb/>
               2009. Partial water system, defi-<lb/>
               cient at night. Drainage system.<lb/>
               Rich supply of suitable fish.<lb/>
               Notonectae abundant.</cell>
          <cell>1 Inspector<lb/>2 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>6</cell>
          <cell>75.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>El Jalon<lb/>Sin.<lb/>134</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 20. Others<lb/>
               135. No water or drainage systems.<lb/>
               Many norias near river and in<lb/>
               houses. Abundant supply of fish.</cell>
          <cell>1 Inspector<lb/>2 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>2</cell>
          <cell>25.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Palmar de<lb/>los Leales<lb/>Sin.<lb/>460</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 47. Others 292.<lb/>
               No water or drainage systems. Many<lb/>norias. Fish abundant.</cell>
          <cell>1 Inspector<lb/>2 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>2</cell>
          <cell>25.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Culiacan<lb/>Sin.<lb/>20000?</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 597. Others<lb/>
               13657. Fairly good water system.<lb/>
               Drainage system deficient. Many<lb/>
               houses have drainage norias. Abun-<lb/>
               dant fish and notonectae supply.</cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>15</cell>
          <cell>400.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Altata<lb/>Sin.<lb/>125</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 11. Others 93.<lb/>
               No water. Inhabitants conserve rain<lb/>
               water or import from Culiacan. Port<lb/>
               of entry for shipping with rail connec-<lb/>
               tion to Culiacan. No local fish.<lb/>
               Must be supplied from Culiacan -<lb/>
               30 Kilms.</cell>
          <cell>1 Inspector<lb/>2 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>1</cell>
          <cell>25.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Mazatlan<lb/>Sin.<lb/>32000</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 867. Others 19282.<lb/>
               Fairly good water and drainage systems.<lb/>
               Excess of permanent containers not nec-<lb/>
               essary under present conditions. No<lb/>
               local supply of fish. Must be imported<lb/>
               from Piaxtla or Presidio rivers, or<lb/>
               Esquinapa ponds.</cell>
          <cell>4 Inspectors<lb/>8 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>9</cell>
          <cell>500.00</cell>
     </row>
 </table>
 <pb n="29" id="f01016030"/>
 <table rows="10" cols="5">
     <row>
          <cell></cell>
          <cell></cell>
          <cell></cell>
          <cell></cell>
          <cell>14</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Town and<lb/>Population</cell>
          <cell>Special Notes</cell>
          <cell>Personnel<lb/>Required</cell>
          <cell>Days</cell>
          <cell>Cost<lb/>Approx.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Puerto de<lb/>
          las Canoas<lb/>
          Sin.<lb/>408</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 13. Others<lb/>
               436. No drinking water nearer than<lb/>
               Mazatlan 20-Kilms. 100% index of<lb/>
               stegomyia. <unclear>12.5 miles</unclear></cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>1</cell>
          <cell>$50.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Villa Union<lb/>including<lb/>Presidio<lb/>&amp; Pozole<lb/>2600</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 64. Others<lb/>2548. No water or drainage
               systems.<lb/>Many norias in houses and near<lb/>rivers. 
               Fish supply abundant and<lb/>varies. Also notonectae.</cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>3</cell>
          <cell>75.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Concordia<lb/>Sin.<lb/>1828</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 88. Others<lb/>1892. No water or drainage
               systems.<lb/>Fine situation and terrain. Fish<lb/>abundant and 
               varied.</cell>
          <cell>1 Inspector<lb/>2 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>4</cell>
          <cell>50.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>La Noria<lb/>Sin.<lb/>1067</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 106. Others<lb/>1346. No water or drainage 
               systems.<lb/>All water from an arroyo which is<lb/>
               dry for considerable periods. No<lb/>fish available here. Must be 
               car-<lb/>ried from Concordia or Villa Union</cell>
          <cell>1 Inspector<lb/>
          4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>4</cell>
          <cell>50.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Rosario<lb/>Sin.<lb/>4500</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 171. Others<lb/>2799. Partial water 
               system. Fish<lb/>available but must be secured up-<lb/>stream as 
               river here is contamina-<lb/>ted by cyanide.</cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>6</cell>
          <cell>150.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Chametla<lb/>Sin.<lb/>1203</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 52. Others<lb/>697. No water or drainage 
               service.<lb/>Water from river in barrels, etc.<lb/>
               Many norias requiring attention.<lb/>Fish available and abundant. Re-<lb/>
               gion very malarious.</cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>3</cell>
          <cell>75.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Escuinapa<lb/>Sin.<lb/>4178</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 611. Others<lb/>2594. Nearly every house has a<lb/>
               noria - little used and dangerous.<lb/>Many fish in arroyos. 
               Also a small<lb/>lake, property of Sra. Juana Gomez,<lb/>
               containing immense numbers of Chalaco.<lb/>
               Mazatlan was supplied from this lake.</cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>6</cell>
          <cell>150.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Acaponeta<lb/>Nay.<lb/>7273</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 602. Others<lb/>
               3712. No water or drainage systems.<lb/>
               Many wells and norias. Fish easily<lb/>available and abundant.</cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>7</cell>
          <cell>175.00</cell>
     </row>
 </table>
 <pb n="30" id="f01016031"/>
 <table rows="6" cols="5">
     <row>
          <cell></cell>
          <cell></cell>
          <cell></cell>
          <cell></cell>
          <cell>15</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Town and<lb/>Population</cell>
          <cell>Special Notes</cell>
          <cell>Personnel<lb/>Required</cell>
          <cell>Days</cell>
          <cell>Cost<lb/>Approx.</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Rosa Morada<lb/>Nay.<lb/>2892</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 60. Others<lb/>
               1200. No water or drainage systems.<lb/>
               Fish available and abundant locally.</cell>
          <cell>1 Inspector<lb/>2 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>6</cell>
          <cell>$75.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Santiago<lb/>Ixcuintla<lb/>Nay.<lb/>5000</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 598. Others<lb/>
               2700. No water or drainage sys-<lb/>
               tems. Many wells and norias, re-<lb/>
               sembling Escuinapa. Fish available<lb/>and abundant.</cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>6</cell>
          <cell>200.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>San Blas<lb/>Nay.<lb/>1246</cell>
          <cell>Permanent containers 382. Others<lb/>
               1398. Port of entry. No water or<lb/>
               drainage systems. Water carried<lb/>
               fifteen kilometers with result that<lb/>
               there are many permanent containers,<lb/>
               jealously guarded. Fish available<lb/>
               only in rainy season. Other times<lb/>
               must be supplied from Topic or Santi-<lb/>ago Ixcuintla.</cell>
          <cell>2 Inspectors<lb/>4 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>8</cell>
          <cell>250.00</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
          <cell>Tepic<lb/>Nay.<lb/>1500?</cell>
          <cell>Containers probably as numerous as<lb/>
               in Culiacan or more. Partial water<lb/>
               system. No drainage system but<lb/>
               many norias which constitute peril.<lb/>
               Fish available and abundant.</cell>
          <cell>4 Inspectors<lb/>8 Mozos</cell>
          <cell>15</cell>
          <cell>700.00</cell>
     </row>
 </table>
</p>
<p><unclear>62.5</unclear><lb/>
x<lb/>
, 937.5<lb/>
30&deg;</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
