<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01013001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Abstract: Diagnosis and Treatment of B.T. and M.T. Fevers, by H.W. Acton, Dagman F. Curjel and J.O. Dewey, 1920-1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01013001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-00-00">[1921]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01013001</idno>
<title>Abstracts from Diagnosis and Treatment of B.T. and M.T. Fevers, by H.W. Acton, Dagman F. Curjel and J.O. Dewey, 1920-1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The authors primarily discuss the treatment of malaria with quinine.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1921-00-00">
<head>Abstracts from Diagnosis and Treatment of B.T. and M.T. Fevers, by H.W. Acton, Dagman F. Curjel and J.O. Dewey, 1920-1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01013001"/>
<opener>
<unclear>C1</unclear><lb/>
B21<lb/>
Malaria<lb/>
Abstracts<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Abstracts<lb/>
from<lb/>
Diagnosis and Treatment of B. T. and M. T. Fevers,<lb/>
Indian Journal of Medical Research<lb/>
Vol 8, 1920-1921.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01013002"/>
<p>C1<lb/>
B21</p>
<p>-1-</p>
<p>(1)</p>
<p>Diagnosis and Treatment of H. T. and M. T. Fevers.</p>
<p>H. W. Acton, Dagman F. Curjel &amp; J. O. Dewey.</p>
<p>Indian Journal of<lb/>
Medical Research.<lb/>
Vol. 8, 1920-1921.</p>
<p><hi>Page 767:</hi></p>
<p>(1) Are they mutation forms of the malignant tertian parasite?</p>
<p>(2) Are they quinine-resistant forms of the malignant tertian para-<lb/>
site?</p>
<p>(3) Are they a separate species of parasite which are relatively<lb/>
quinine-resistant?</p>
<p><hi>Page 768.</hi></p>
<p>(1) These parasites are known to be of two different species.</p>
<p>(2) The short interval relapses after quinine treatment, according<lb/>
to this view, would be more likely to be due to benign tertian forms and<lb/>
the long interval relapses (8 to 14 weeks after treatment) would more<lb/>
likely be due to malignant tertian forms, but this is not so (see Sec-<lb/>
tion 11, Tables 11 and 111). These were all cases on tonic treatment<lb/>
and the quinine effect should have worn off after cessation of treatment.</p>
<p>(3) Benign tertian parasites are seen in persons who have never<lb/>
had quinine treatment.</p>
<p>Section IV--What Constitues A Cure.</p>
<p><hi>Page 784</hi>-<hi>786.</hi></p>
<p>---------- THE NATURE OF CURES IN MALARIA, by H. W. Acton.<lb/>
Major. I. M. S.</p>
<p>Conclusions.</p>
<p>(1) Cures in malaria occur in the following ways:--</p>
<p>(A) Natural cures by a gradual conversion of the whole of<lb/>
the asexual cycle into gametocytes. The gametocytes in turn dying as<lb/>
the result of senility or being destroyed by the splenic cells.</p>
<p>(B) Artificial cures by the rapid destruction of the asex-<lb/>
ual cycle by quinine or other alkaloids of cinchona bark.</p>
<p>(2) The production of cure may be considered to be brought about<lb/>
in three phases--</p>
<p>(A) Immediate or relative cure is the immediate effect pro-<lb/>
duced by destroying the greater part of the asexual cycle and is shown<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01013003"/>
C1<lb/>
B21<lb/>
shown<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
by the disappearance of fever and the asexual forms from the peripheral<lb/>
blood.</p>
<p>(B) Partial cure or relapse due to the incomplete destruction<lb/>
of the asexual cycle by quinine or by excessive gametocyte formation, the<lb/>
asexual parasites reappear and cause fever.</p>
<p>(C) Complete cure or sterilisation is the complete destruction<lb/>
of the asexual cycle by quinine or by gametocyte formation and leads to a<lb/>
permanent cure.</p>
<p>(3) Relative cures of particular types of treatment should always<lb/>
be tested experimentally as the rapid abatement of fever is important to<lb/>
the patient. The intravenous treatment gives the best relative cure.</p>
<p>(4) Partial cures or relapses--</p>
<p>(A) During treatment, are due to the maladministration of<lb/>
quinine (i. e., by intermittent dosage, and the patient avoiding treat-<lb/>
ment), or to non-absorption. These faults are all rectifiable.</p>
<p>(B) After treatment, relapses are due to the failure of the<lb/>
drug to destroy the whole of the asexual cycle and are probably caused<lb/>
by one of the following factors:--</p>
<p>Insufficiency of treatment, this is dependent on the number of<lb/>
parasites present and the rate of destruction by quinine. The destruct-<lb/>
ion may be considered to be a fractional process with each new cycle.</p>
<p>Inaccessibility of the drug to destroy the young forms, as schizo-<lb/>
gony may occur in areas where these alkaloids are not sufficiently con-<lb/>
centrated.</p>
<p>(5) Complete cure or sterilisation is brought about by the acces-<lb/>
sibility of the alkaloid for the parasite, i. e., quinine for the malig-<lb/>
nant tertian parasite. The concentration of the alkaloid must be suf-<lb/>
ficient to destroy young broods and the site of multiplication must be<lb/>
accessible to the action of the alkaloid. This destruction may be con-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01013004"/>
C1<lb/>
B21<lb/>
con-<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
sidered to be fractional in effect and so a continuous treatment over<lb/>
some days is necessary to obliterate the whole of the asexual cycle.</p>
<p>CONDITIONS REQUIRED FOR AN EXPERIMENTAL TEST OF A CURE IN MALARIA.</p>
<p>(1) The full curative value of quinine and other alkaloids can on-<lb/>
ly be properly estimated under conditions that preclude the possibiliti-<lb/>
ties of reinfection occurring during treatment and observation.</p>
<p>(2) The observation period necessary to establish a cure in be-<lb/>
nign tertian infections should not be under eight weeks so as to in-<lb/>
clude 90 per cent of the relapses. The number of cases not relapsing dur-<lb/>
ing this period are spoken of as &ldquo;cures.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(3) The relapses that occur after eight weeks can roughly be es-<lb/>
timated at 8% of the relapses that have occurred during the eight weeks'<lb/>
observation, the sum of these relapses we call &ldquo;the total relapse rate.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(4) 'The total estimated cures' will be the total population un-<lb/>
der treatment, minus the total relapse rate.</p>
<p>(5) Before a particular treatment can be recommended, the error<lb/>
of chance distribution should be excluded by repeating the test.</p>
<p>DIAGNOSIS AND TREATMENT OF B. T. AND M. T., FEVERS. (Section V)<lb/>
The Effect of Quinine on Benign Tertian Infection.<lb/>
by<lb/>
Major P. M. Rennie, I. M. S.<lb/>
Major H. W. Acton, I. M. S.<lb/>
Dagmar F. Curjel, M. D., W. M. S.,<lb/>
attached R. A. M. C.<lb/>
Asst. Surg. J. O. Dewey, I. M. D.</p>
<p><hi>Page 794</hi>-<hi>795</hi></p>
<p>Conclusion.</p>
<p>(1) The immediate cure of benign tertian <hi>fever</hi> by quinine is soon-<lb/>
est effected by the intravenous method, but by whatever method quinine<lb/>
is given, the parasites in benign tertian infection disappear from the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01013005"/>
C1<lb/>
B21<lb/>
from the<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
peripheral blood in one to four days.</p>
<p>(2) By whatever method quinine is given, approximately 25 to 30<lb/>
per cent of cases are cured by a single course.</p>
<p>(3) Of the various methods of quinine administration the oral is<lb/>
the most practical for routine use, and gives as good results as the<lb/>
others.</p>
<p>(4) The continuous oral administration is better than the inter-<lb/>
mittent.</p>
<p>(5) The percentage of cures resulting from a three weeks' course<lb/>
and from an eight weeks' course is about the same.</p>
<p>(6) The difference between a four months' course (Ross and Thomson) and<lb/>
the short continuous oral course is small, and probably two short courses<lb/>
would give a better cure percentage than one long course.</p>
<p>Section VI.</p>
<p>The Effect of Repeated Courses of Quinine on the Benign and Malignant<lb/>
Tertian Parasites.</p>
<p>H. W. Acton, Dagmar F. Curjel and J. O. Dewey.</p>
<p><hi>Page 859</hi>-<hi>860.</hi></p>
<p>Conclusions.</p>
<p>(1) In malignant tertian infections, with a month's course of qui-<lb/>
nine treatment, a cure rate of over 90 per cent is obtained when the pa-<lb/>
tient is removed from the chance of reinfection. Under these circum-<lb/>
stances, three courses of quinine would cure all cases of infection due<lb/>
to this parasite.</p>
<p>(2) In benign tertian infections, with every two months' course of<lb/>
quinine treatment, about 25 to 30 per cent of the cases are cured whether<lb/>
by a single or repeated courses. We have observed this effect with five<lb/>
consecutive courses. Under such conditions, 16 courses of quinine would<lb/>
be required to cure every case in a large series of men.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f01013006"/>
<p>C1<lb/>
<unclear>B21 men.</unclear></p>
<p>5</p>
<p>(3) Two short courses of three weeks' continuous treatment is as ef-<lb/>
fective as long four months' course, and gives as large a number of ef-<lb/>
fective men in a shorter space of time besides saving money in quinine.</p>
<p>(4) The high cure rate in malignant tertian infections, i. e., 90%,<lb/>
is dependent on the hign destructive rate of quinine on the young asex-<lb/>
ual parasite coupled with the easy accessibility of this drug to the<lb/>
parasitic breeding grounds, which are in the portal area. A cure is as-<lb/>
sured every time, provided the treatment is carried over eight to ten cy-<lb/>
cles (21 to 30 days).</p>
<p>(5) The low cure rate in benign tertian infections, i. e., 25 to<lb/>
30 per cent, is dependent not on the low destructive rate of quinine on<lb/>
the asexual parasites, but on the fact that schizogony occurs through-<lb/>
out the body and is not specially restricted to the portal area. Quinine,<lb/>
therefore, does not gain an easy access to these young forms, and the cure<lb/>
or complete destruction is dependent on pure chance.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
