<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01018016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, January 19, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01018016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-01-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Pareja, Wenceslao</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-01-19">January 19, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01018016</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, January 19, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson suspects that the reported case of Weil's disease, reported in Guayaquil, may be yellow fever. He believes that the International Health Board should investigate.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-01-19">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, January 19, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01018016"/>
<opener>
Book<lb/>
<hi><unclear>Clarac</unclear></hi><lb/>
<unclear>Intrinsic Incubator</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
3014 Winfield Ave.,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md. <date value="1923-01-19">January 19, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just received your letter of the 18th and very<lb/>
much appreciate the fact that you are always ready to reply in spite of your<lb/>
mucho ocupado tiempo. Yes the time is short for the outline I have made and<lb/>
as I stated in the card which I sent you today I find that I shall have to<lb/>
eliminate a lot of things which ought to be interesting and worth while pre-<lb/>
senting. I shall not follow Halstead's example, in fact I shall not take up more<lb/>
than about 40 minutes of their time in this talk. If they want to prolong it<lb/>
by asking questions, that is another question. I shall not even be able to cover<lb/>
what I indicated on my card in the time allowed. Between now and Monday I shall<lb/>
think over very carefully what I may be able to present in the time, most like-<lb/>
ly taking mainly the points which you have commented on.</p>
<p>My reference to Clarac is in &ldquo;GRALL et CLARAC, TRAIT&Eacute; de PATHOLOGIE<lb/>
EXOTIQUE&rdquo; -- DENGUE, FI&Egrave;VRE JAUNE?<lb/>
CHOL&Eacute;RA MALADIE DU SOMEIL,<lb/>
published in 1912.</p>
<p>Chapter on &ldquo;Fi&egrave;vre Jaune&rdquo;</p>
<p>I. - Historique et G&eacute;ographie M&eacute;dicala, Par A. Clarac. This<lb/>
<unclear>chapter</unclear> begins on page 21. What he says of your observation is, &ldquo;<unclear>Or, des</unclear><lb/>
observations faites en 1898 par le Dr. H.R. Carter semblaient indiquer<lb/>
que l'agent de la fi&egrave;vre jaune, comme celui du <unclear>paludismo, n'etait</unclear> pas<lb/>
capable de transmettre la maladie avant qu'un d&eacute;lai d&eacute;termin&oacute; se f&ucirc;t<lb/>
&eacute;coul&eacute; &agrave; partir du moment <unclear>e&ugrave;</unclear> cet agent avait eu l'occasion de s'infector<lb/>
sur un malade.&rdquo; page 38 beginning with fifth line. Again on page 51<lb/>
the last paragraph on page in speaking of the interval between the<lb/>
first and secondary cases he says; &ldquo;<unclear>Neus</unclear> avens signal&eacute; d&eacute;j&agrave; les re-<lb/>
marquables observations faites par Carter &agrave; <unclear>Orveed</unclear> et Taylor en 1898.<lb/>
Carter avait pu relever exactement l'intervalle <unclear>qui</unclear> s'&eacute;coule entre<lb/>
l'introduction d'un <unclear>malade</unclear> amaril dans un <del><unclear></unclear></del> hameau isol&eacute;, jusqu'<lb/>
alers indemne de fi&egrave;vre jaune, et le <unclear>primier</unclear> <unclear>cas</unclear> qui suit cette intro-<lb/>
duction. Cet intervalle est <unclear>r&eacute;guli&egrave;rement</unclear> de deux &agrave; treis semaines. A<lb/>
partir de ce moment, la manifestation de nouveaux cas n'ob&eacute;it plus<lb/>
&agrave; aucune r&egrave;gle de <unclear>tempa</unclear>.&rdquo;<lb/>
he quotes you again in <unclear>regard</unclear> to the length of the period of incubation in<lb/>
man on page 81, second paragraph. If I come over Sunday afternoon I will bring<lb/>
my book with me in case you care to read this article of Clarac's.</p>
<p>I am sorry for the subpoena because it would ahve lent me great moral<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01018017"/>
Dr. H.R. Carter<lb/>
2<lb/>
January 19, 1923<lb/>
support to have you present.</p>
<p>I do not know how safe it is to lay stress on 19 with all the Weil's<lb/>
disease which is reported from Guayaquil. Ever since you last wrote me about<lb/>
the reports of this disease from Ecuador I have been a bit uneasy. You remember<lb/>
that it was Weils disease which Dr. Zuniga was diagnosing in Paita before you<lb/>
came to Peru, (i.e. <unclear>Spirocetosis ictero hemorraghica</unclear>) and it seems to me very<lb/>
important that we should have some very reliable information as to the true<lb/>
nature of the disease in Guayaquil. In fact if I were running the yellow fever<lb/>
section for the I.H.B., I think I would either go in person, or I would send<lb/>
some one down the west coast to make a very careful systematic survey all the<lb/>
way down. This person should be one who really knows yellow fever when he sees<lb/>
it. These people down there are not going to make an error in diagnosis in<lb/>
favor of yellow fever, by that I mean they are going to continue making the<lb/>
diagnosis of <unclear>Weil's</unclear> disease until they are forced to make the other. I am not<lb/>
suggesting myself for the job, but I know of no one who could so well do this<lb/>
as I can, for the simple fact that I am still officially the Director of Public<lb/>
Health for Peru, and I could call in both Columbia and Ecuador on a friendly<lb/>
visit basis. I have a very cordial invitation from Dr. Pareja to visit Guayaquil,<lb/>
and Columbia and Peru are very friendly. The only importance of Columbia would<lb/>
be in case this were no Weil's disease there could be some temporary feeding<lb/>
foci from Columbia which would be annoying but not serious.</p>
<p>If you are to busy to talk Sunday do not hesitate to say so, I am going<lb/>
to Washington to see what information I can get about the roads to the south, as<lb/>
I may start for Florida by auto at the end of next week or the first part of<lb/>
the week following, all depending on the weather and reports on the roads.</p>
<p>Since I may have the opportunity to see you Sunday P.M. I shall not write<lb/>
more at present. With best wishes from all the Hanson family,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
