<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01018001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from H. McG. Robertson to [Hugh S. Cumming], January 3, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Robertson, H. McG.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01018001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-01-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Cumming, Hugh S.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Atlantic Coast (United States)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-01-03">January 3, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01018001</idno>
<title>Letter from H. McG. Robertson to [Hugh S. Cumming], January 3, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robertson inquires about the possibility of doing a flea survey and discusses threat of a plague.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-01-03">
<head>Letter from H. McG. Robertson to [Hugh S. Cumming], January 3, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01018001"/>
<opener>
Further relative to necessity<lb/>
for <hi>flea</hi> survey.<lb/>
H. McG. Robertson, Surgeon.<lb/>
<dateline>
1110 Capitol Street,<lb/>
Richmond, Virginia,<lb/>
<date value="1923-01-03">January 3, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
The Surgeon General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to invite the attention of the Bureau<lb/>
to my letter of May 9 last relative to making a flea survey of<lb/>
the cities of our Atlantic Coast, and requesting that I be assign-<lb/>
ed to that duty. In regard to this request I may say that I am<lb/>
very much interested in my present work and prefer to be con-<lb/>
tinued on duty with the Virginia State Board of Health, yet I<lb/>
cannot get rid of the idea that this flea survey should be made,<lb/>
- possibly not in so many places as suggested in my letter, yet<lb/>
at least in some City far enough north, say Washington or<lb/>
Baltimore, to give a definite idea of the seasonal prevalence of<lb/>
fleas at that point. The prevalence further north would of course<lb/>
be less.</p>
<p>My attention was drawn to this subject at this time by<lb/>
the attached clipping from a late copy of the Journal of the<lb/>
American Medical Association. From the point of view of one whose<lb/>
beliefs, are as expressed in my letter of May 9, 1922, it is as<lb/>
useless to search for plague infected rats in our North Atlantic<lb/>
Cities between December 15 and April 1 as it would be to search<lb/>
for yellow fever cases in the human population of New Orleans at<lb/>
the same time. Certainly until a flea survey is made any anti-<lb/>
plague work that is done is based on a knowledge that is in-<lb/>
complete insofar as one of the factors in the spread of Plague<lb/>
is concerned. In a general way it is known to all of us that<lb/>
fleas are scarce in the winter months, but to leave the matter<lb/>
at this point is unscientific and unnecessary.</p>
<p>In speaking to different persons of the advisability to<lb/>
making this flea survey I have been met with a good many sugges-<lb/>
tions as to the uselessness of the work. It has been said that<lb/>
the great plague of London continued through the cold months.<lb/>
It may be said that yellow fever in years past existed in<lb/>
Philadelphia, yet various causes have conspired to rid Philadel-<lb/>
phia of this disease and make it impossible for it to get an<lb/>
extensive foothold in that City.</p>
<p>It has been said that plague occurs the year around in<lb/>
Manchuria, yet, if I am correctly informed, this is the pneumonic<lb/>
form of plague.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01018002"/>
<p>SG</p>
<p>January 3, 1923.</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Someone advanced the idea that it would be necessary<lb/>
to search the nests of rats for fleas. It seems that it is<lb/>
immaterial where the fleas may be in the winter months if they<lb/>
are not on the rats.</p>
<p>It has also been said that some cases of plague would<lb/>
continue as chronic cases into the winter and spring. If this<lb/>
is so they would be entirely harmless during the winter, but<lb/>
would probably die or recover before the flea season began in<lb/>
the spring.</p>
<p><unclear>Scandinavia B. D.</unclear></p>
<p>It is not alone our North Atlantic Seaboard that is<lb/>
free from plague - Canadian ports both eastern and western have<lb/>
never been plague infected, nor have any of the Scandanavian<lb/>
ports, to the best of my knowledge, though no quarantine efforts<lb/>
have been made in any of the countries mentioned to exclude this<lb/>
disease. In Great Britain during the past 25 years there have<lb/>
occurred about fourteen outbreaks of plague, only one of which<lb/>
lasted for more than a week or two. This was an epidemic in<lb/>
Glasgow in the fall of 1900 in which 28 cases occurred with 4<lb/>
deaths. If Great Britain during these years, without any<lb/>
quarantine protection and in intimate daily shipping contact<lb/>
with India and other plague centres has suffered so little<lb/>
from this disease, it seems that the fumigation of the large<lb/>
passenger liners plying only between North European ports and<lb/>
the ports of our North Atlantic Coast might be omitted except<lb/>
as some particular occasion might arise. It is my idea that<lb/>
the quarantine procedure in case of bubonic plague might be<lb/>
modified along the line now in practice in case of yellow fever,<lb/>
if my theory of a seasonal distribution of fleas is correct.</p>
<p>If plague should break out in the late summer or fall<lb/>
in any of our cities north, say, of Savannah, an intensive cam-<lb/>
paign in the immediate vicinity of the outbreak would be sufficient<lb/>
and the inaugurating of city-wide rat-proofing with its attendant<lb/>
financial and legal difficulties would be avoided.</p>
<p>I am mentioning more in detail than in my former letter<lb/>
these two instances of the possible practical effects that might<lb/>
follow changed ideas based on an accurate knowledge of the flea<lb/>
prevalence in any given locality because it has been suggested<lb/>
that definite knowledge along this line would be of academic<lb/>
value only.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) H. McG. Robertson<lb/>
Surgeon</signed>.
HMR/MBD<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
