<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01015001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Yellow Fever in West Africa in 1922, by [s.n.] Gouzien, [1922]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01015001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">Dahomey</name>
<name type="place">Togoland</name>
<name type="place">Gold Coast</name>
<name type="place">Ivory Coast</name>
<name type="place">Gambia</name>
<name type="place">Senegal</name>
<name type="place">Sudan</name>
<name type="place">Grand Bassam (Ivory Coast)</name>
<name type="place">Sierra Leone</name>
<name type="place">Cameroon</name>
<name type="place">Nigeria</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-00-00">[1922]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01015001</idno>
<title>Report: Yellow Fever in West Africa in 1922, by [s.n.] Gouzien, [1922]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gouzien reports on yellow fever in West Africa and discusses epidemics and their control since 1900. He stresses the continued need for mosquito control.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-00-00">
<head>Report: Yellow Fever in West Africa in 1922, by [s.n.] Gouzien, [1922]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01015001"/>
<p><hi>YELLOW FEVER IN WEST AFRICA in 1922</hi></p>
<p>(Abstract of an article from the monthly bulletin of<lb/>
the Office International d'Hygi&egrave;ne Publique for December, 1922.<lb/>
The article is the report of an address given in French before<lb/>
the committee of the Office International d'Hygi&egrave;ne Publique<lb/>
at its meeting of October, 1922, by Dr. Gouzien, Medical Inspec-<lb/>
tor General, President of the Superior Council of Health for the<lb/>
Colonies, Delegate of French Indo-China to the committee.)</p>
<p>____________</p>
<p>Yellow fever has reappeared this year along the West African coast,<lb/>
the cases being sometimes isolated, sometimes in groups. It has traveled from<lb/>
east to west following the Gulf of Guinea.</p>
<p>The first case was at Grand Popo (Dahomey) June 12, 1922; then cases<lb/>
were reported at Anecho (Togoland) June 20; at Accra (Gold Coast) July 22; at<lb/>
Grand Bassam (Ivory Coast) August 16; and finally as reported in a cable of<lb/>
October 14, among the natives in Bathurst (English Gambia), thus directly<lb/>
menacing Senegal.</p>
<p>The West African coast, especially Senegal and the Soudan, is one of<lb/>
the oldest strongholds of yellow fever. The last serious epidemic in Senegal<lb/>
was in 1900.</p>
<p>The author observed the epidemic of 1906 in the Soudan involving<lb/>
forty cases with twenty-six deaths, when for the first time the prophylactic<lb/>
measures against yellow fever outlined by the American Commission in Cuba were<lb/>
used. The plague was stopped at Kayes, the port of embarkation for Senegal.</p>
<p>Since then only sporadic cases, or local epidemics quickly controlled,<lb/>
have been reported in West Africa. The mission which the International Health<lb/>
Board sent could not find a single case, although it was in the epidemic season.</p>
<p>Previous to the five cases which occurred in August, 1922, at Grand<lb/>
Bassam, the last two epidemics on the Ivory Coast had appeared in 1890 with<lb/>
twenty-one cases, and in 1903 with ten. After 1903 there had been only two<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01015002"/>
-2-<lb/>
cases, one in 1913 and one in 1914.</p>
<p>Dahomey had its first case in 1905, its last, in Porto Novo, in 1917,<lb/>
A slight outbreak occurred in Belgian Congo in 1917 also. Several scattered<lb/>
cases have been reported in Sierra Leone, the Gold Coast, and Kamerun.</p>
<p>Yellow Fever has been crossed off the list of diseases attaining<lb/>
epidemic proportions in the endemic African zone. It now only manifests itself<lb/>
sporadically and these cases are controlled and prevented from spreading by the<lb/>
anti-Stegomyia fight which is immediately undertaken.</p>
<p>* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
<p>To return to the slight epidemic of Grand Bassam, we have, up to the<lb/>
present, received only fragmentary reports. Here is a summary of the facts.</p>
<p>On August 4 the proprietress of a hotel in Grand Bassam, who had been<lb/>
sick for five days, succumbed to an attack of hemoglobinuric bilious fever,<lb/>
which happens fairly commonly in these countries. The history and symptoms of<lb/>
the disease were so clear - death coming in a syncope, the patient having gotten<lb/>
up too soon, which is, in fact, one of the rather frequent terminations of the<lb/>
malady - that this incident would not have attracted any special attention, if,<lb/>
on August 16, exactly eighteen days after the beginning of this case, a lodger<lb/>
in the same building had not shown symptoms, typical in this case of yellow<lb/>
fever, to which he succumbed the following day. His room-mate (and bed fellow)<lb/>
was confined to his bed two days later, August 18, but developed only an<lb/>
attenuated case of yellow fever. Three cases broke out later, the last on<lb/>
August 22; and September 9, eighteen days after the isolation of the latter,<lb/>
the local order which had been issued, declaring Grand Bassam infected and fix-<lb/>
ing the limits of the tainted area, lapsed by application of our new sanitary<lb/>
maritime police order of June 7, 1922, fixing the period of territorial observa-<lb/>
tion at eighteen days after the isolation or the death of the last patient.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01015003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>As I have already stated, this lapse of eighteen days, between the<lb/>
case of hemoglobinuric bilious fever, which resulted in death, and the first<lb/>
authentic case of yellow fever, could have made a poorly informed practitioner<lb/>
suspect that there was a relation between the two cases especially in view of<lb/>
the coincidence of place. But, besides the fact that the symptoms of bilious<lb/>
hemoglobinuria paroxysm could not lead to confusion (hemoglobinuria being, in<lb/>
fact, very rare in yellow fever, where hematuria, although exceptional, is<lb/>
more apt to be observed), the skin did not show any trace of icterus, even when<lb/>
it was put in the coffin, and it is known that icterus is late in yellow fever.<lb/>
An autopsy of the patient was not made, as it was judged purposeless.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the two Europeans who were the first smitten led<lb/>
a rather mysterious existence and, most important of all, the investigation<lb/>
proved that, violating the orders given following the discovery of yellow fever<lb/>
on the Gold Coast, they passed the frontier rather frequently. It was without<lb/>
doubt on one of these sprees that they must have become infected, as there is<lb/>
constant communication between Grand Bassam and Assinie (Ivory Coast) on the<lb/>
one hand, and Axim, Sekondi, and Accra (Gold Coast) on the other. And, although<lb/>
this last place only was declared infected, it is well known that in a time of<lb/>
epidemic many unrecognized and undiagnosed cases exist, especially among the<lb/>
native population and particularly among the children, who are said to contract<lb/>
a weak kind of yellow fever, which, however, would immunize them sufficiently<lb/>
to explain the rarity of infection among the adult native.</p>
<p>It should be noted that the Noguchi serum was tried at Bassam, but<lb/>
its effect seems to have been uncertain. It is of interest to recall in this<lb/>
connection the excellent results obtained by Dr. Deprez in 1917 at Matadi, by<lb/>
using neosalvarsan with his two last patients.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01015004"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>To sum up the situation there seems to have been a yellow fever wave<lb/>
extending from Grand Popo to the Ivory Coast forest, a wave of which only the<lb/>
crest was seen, that is, the authentic cases, while the chain of infection which<lb/>
leads to isolated cases 500 or 1,000 kilometers from the coast is concealed.<lb/>
Every effort must be made to break this chain and to find the permanent hiding<lb/>
place of the Stegomyia. Meanwhile in these countries where yellow fever is<lb/>
still endemic, the antilarval fight must not be stopped.</p>
<p>The author mentions certain of the prophylactic measures taken by<lb/>
the Chief of the Health Service. The circulation of vegetables, and of any<lb/>
other commodities susceptible of harboring mosquitoes was forbidden, travelers'<lb/>
baggage was disinfected by sulphur vapor and trains were fumigated.</p>
<p><hi>NOTE</hi>: Later information enabled the author to report five fatal cases in<lb/>
the Soudan between October 16 and 28, at Segu-Sekoro, on the Niger,<lb/>
more than 1,000 kilometers from the coast, and in November even<lb/>
English Nigeria was reported to be infected at Wari, and also at<lb/>
Lagos where a case appeared imported from Wari.</p>
<p>All this confirms the necessity of continuing the organization to<lb/>
prevent yellow fever in these countries which are in perpetual<lb/>
danger.</p>
<p>7638</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
