<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01017001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Impounded Waters, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01017001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">United States</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01017001</idno>
<title>Report: Impounded Waters, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is an unsigned manuscript on impounded waters, which details public health regulations, worker conditions, and the bodies of water themselves.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report: Impounded Waters, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01017001"/>
<p><hi>IMPOUNDED WATERS</hi></p>
<p>1. Wherever impounded water projects are to be located under the<lb/>
provisions of this act in those parts of the United States in which<lb/>
malarial fevers exist, or malaria bearing mosquitoes are known to<lb/>
propagate, the following general measures shall be enforced for the<lb/>
protection of the public health:</p>
<p>(a) All laborers employed in the construction of the<lb/>
dam and the impounding of the water, shall be<lb/>
housed in properly screened houses and such steps<lb/>
taken by quinine administration and control of<lb/>
mosquito production in the vicinity of the camps<lb/>
as may be necessary to prevent the infection of<lb/>
malaria mosquitoes and the introduction of<lb/>
malaria into this locality.</p>
<p>(b) In the area to be occupied by the reservoir, its<lb/>
branches and indentations, all brush, trees, under-<lb/>
growth, logs and similar objects, which if not<lb/>
removed would float on the surface of the impound-<lb/>
ed water and thus constitute conditions favorable<lb/>
to the production of malaria mosquitoes, shall be<lb/>
removed, burned or otherwise disposed of prior to<lb/>
the closing of the dam and impounding water. All<lb/>
stumps of trees or underbrush shall be cut suffi-<lb/>
ciently near to the surface of the ground to prevent<lb/>
their standing above the surface of the water at<lb/>
any and all stages of the water, and thus holding<lb/>
drift and floatage.</p>
<p>(c) The formation of the log <unclear>jams</unclear> and the collection<lb/>
of drift and floatage in narrow valleys or indent-<lb/>
ations and along the banks of the reservoir where<lb/>
wave action is absent or weak, shall be prevented<lb/>
during the mosquito season.</p>
<p>(d) In so far as practicable, the water level in the<lb/>
reservoir shall be fixed so as to reduce to a<lb/>
minimum shallow, submerged areas on which acquatic<lb/>
plants will grow and reach the surface of the<lb/>
water.</p>
<p>(e) When practicable the water level in the reservoir<lb/>
shall be held 3-feet above normal high water level<lb/>
from December 1 to June 1, but where this method<lb/>
of clearing the banks is impracticable, the entire<lb/>
<unclear>short</unclear> line of the reservoir for 15-feet back from<lb/>
normal high water level shall be cleared of all<lb/>
brush, trees, stumps, logs, and undergrowth before<lb/>
the water is impounded.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01017002"/>
<p><hi>IMPOUNDED WATERS</hi></p>
<p>Page - 2</p>
<p>(f) The reservoir shall be adequately stocked with<lb/>
top minnows which feed upon mosquito larvae<lb/>
and every effort shall be made to protect them<lb/>
against their enemies and secure their success-<lb/>
ful propagation.</p>
<p>(g) All separate pools and seepage places created<lb/>
during the construction of the dam or by the<lb/>
impounding of the water, whether adjacent to<lb/>
the reservoir or situated in the stream bed<lb/>
below the dam shall be filled, ditched, oiled,<lb/>
or stocked with top minnows (gambusia) in order<lb/>
to prevent mosquito production.</p>
<p>2. Wherever an impounded water project is to be located under the<lb/>
provisions of the Act aforesaid in any part of the United States,<lb/>
the locenses shall carry out such measures as an officer of the<lb/>
Public Health Service designated by the Commission may determine<lb/>
to be necessary in each case to prevent pollution of the drainage<lb/>
shed and the water of the reservoir with excreta or other refuse<lb/>
matter likely to casue or aggravate a nuisance or danger to the<lb/>
health of persons living near the reservoir or dependent in any<lb/>
way upon the water in or flowing from the reservoir.</p>
<p>3. The foregoing rules may be amended from time to time as<lb/>
necessary within the discretion of the Commission.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
