<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01025010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report [on fever cases] by Frederick A. Miller, March 19, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01025010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-03-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Medina, Garcia</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Santander (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Muzo (Colombia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-03-19">March 19, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01025010</idno>
<title>Report [on fever cases] by Frederick A. Miller, March 19, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Miller reports on a possible yellow fever outbreak in Colombia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-03-19">
<head>Report [on fever cases] by Frederick A. Miller, March 19, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01025010"/>
<p>COPY</p>
<p>On Wednesday, March 7, 1923, an article appeared in a local newspaper<lb/>
saying that there had appeared in Bucaramanga, the Capital of Santander, about<lb/>
twenty cases with eight deaths of a disease that manifested itself, by quick onset,<lb/>
high fever, vomiting of blood (black vomit) and albumin in the urine.</p>
<p>At this time I went to Dr. Garcia Medina, the Director of National Hygiene,<lb/>
and asked him whether I should cable the Board to send a commission to investigate<lb/>
this affair. In the absence of any data or official information, he replied<lb/>
that it was not necessary and that we should wait for further information. In<lb/>
the meantime Dr. Garcia had cabled and telegraphed to all possible places from<lb/>
which a case might originate and receiving a negative reply and as the distance<lb/>
from any infected area to Bucaramanga is more than twelve days, he ruled out<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<p>From data secured from Bucaramanga it seems that this disease first<lb/>
appeared as a single case in November 1922, and with two more cases in December.<lb/>
From January 1 to March 7 there appeared seventy more cases with twenty deaths,<lb/>
although sixty of these cases did not show any vomiting of blood.</p>
<p>Follows the manifestation of the disease from official reports to Dr.<lb/>
Garcia: Quick onset with chills and fever; the temperature rising rapidly to<lb/>
39 and 40C; intense frontal headaches and superorbital pain on pressure; move-<lb/>
ments of the abdominal muscles; skin very hot and dry; sudden rash; anorexia;<lb/>
constipation and abdominal pain; the temperature falls on the third day and comes<lb/>
to normal on the fifth or sixth day with much sweating; generally on the third day<lb/>
appear pains in the epigastric region and over the liver and a low grade jaundice;<lb/>
vomiting present in all cases. Some cases pursue a worse course, and black vomit<lb/>
presents itself on the third day with melenic evacuations. The patient is gener-<lb/>
ally very anxious: albumin is intense and rapid, increasing until death; pulse<lb/>
slow at first full and strong, later depressed and disappears; jaundice accentuated;<lb/>
urine without any biliary pigments, albumin abundant up to twelve per thousand,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01025011"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
oliguria and anuria in some cases; hemorrhages in all the mucous membranes and ecchy-<lb/>
moses; delirium terminating in coma.</p>
<p>There were approximately twenty cases of black vomit all of which were fatal.</p>
<p>Autopsies only show a slightly bloody fluid in the intestinal tract and<lb/>
a congestion of the gastric mucous membrane; the liver pallid.</p>
<p>On account of the lack of any definite autopsy findings, Dr. Garcia is<lb/>
of the opinion that this disease is the same that appeared in Muzo in 1916 when<lb/>
Drs. Gorgas and Carter came here to investigate and decided that it was not yellow<lb/>
fever but a form of malaria.</p>
<p>Bucaramanga is approximately three days on horseback from Puerto Wilches<lb/>
the river port on the Magdalena River. Puerto Wilches is five days from the coast<lb/>
town of Barranquilla and the nearest foreign port is Colon. Steamers coming from<lb/>
Colon take three days so that it would require at least eleven days to reach Buca-<lb/>
ramanga. From Buenaventura on the Pacific coast is at least twelve days, and there<lb/>
has been no yellow fever in Buenaventura for at least three years.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) Frederick A. Miller</signed>
March 19, 1923<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
