<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01025032">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from W.E. Safford to Henry Rose Carter, April 24, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01025032</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-04-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-04-24">April 24, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01025032</idno>
<title>Letter from W.E. Safford to Henry Rose Carter, April 24, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Safford describes his work and theories on the origins of cultivated plants. He believes that the banana is of Old World origin.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-04-24">
<head>Letter from W.E. Safford to Henry Rose Carter, April 24, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01025032"/>
<opener>
Book<lb/>
Stegomyia<lb/>
(Safford)<lb/>
ECONOMIC AND SYSTEMATIC BOTANY<lb/>
<dateline>
UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE<lb/>
BUREAU OF PLANT INDUSTRY<lb/>
WASHINGTON<lb/>
<date value="1923-04-24">April 24, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
Assistant Surgeon General H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California Street, N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In reply to your inquiry, which reached me this morning, I<lb/>
hasten to say that I must have been very misleading, if I gave you the<lb/>
impression that I believed the banana to be a native of America. It is<lb/>
undoubtedly of Old World origin. It was brought by the Polynesians with<lb/>
them and had become spread among the islands of the Pacific before the<lb/>
time of Magellan, but from the definite testimony of the most reliable<lb/>
early writers it was introduced into America after the discovery.</p>
<p>Mr. O. F. Cock, of the Department of Agriculture, is one of my<lb/>
best friends, yet I differ from him on several of his theories, especially<lb/>
with many things he said in his article &ldquo;The American Origin of Agriculture,&rdquo;<lb/>
first published in the <hi>Popular Science Monthly</hi>, October 1902. In that<lb/>
paper he included bananas among the food plants which existed in America<lb/>
before the arrival of the Spaniards (loc. cit. p. 495). In <hi>Contributions<lb/>
from the United States National Herbarium,</hi> vol. 7, 1901, he declared<lb/>
the coconut palm to be of American origin and added (p. 258) that &ldquo;the<lb/>
evidence of the existence of the banana in prehistoric America is equal, if<lb/>
not superior, to that here presented for the coconut.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01025033"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>In my work on the <hi>Useful Plants of the Island of Guam</hi>, published<lb/>
as vol. 9 of <hi>Contributions from the United States National Herbarium,</hi> p.<lb/>
328. 1905, I speak of the cultivation of the banana on the Island of Guam<lb/>
in prehistoric times, and give its vernacular names in various eastern<lb/>
localities. I remember talking with Mr. Cook about the origin of the banana<lb/>
and asking him what tangible evidence he could cite to show the pre-<lb/>
Columbian existence of the banana in America. He referred to some explorer<lb/>
in Peru, who had found a leaf believed to be a banana leaf in a prehistoric<lb/>
grave. I replied that I had assisted in the opening of about two hundred<lb/>
graves in Peru, all of which contained vestiges of edible plants and some<lb/>
of them representations of fruits, edible roots, etc., in terracotta<lb/>
funeral vases, and among all of my material and the material obtained by<lb/>
other explorers, there was not a vestige of a banana fruit, or leaf; al-<lb/>
though some one had mistaken the terracotta representation of a manioc stem<lb/>
with a cluster of roots hanging to it for a bunch of bananas.</p>
<p>Afterwards Mr. Cook, in <hi>Contributions from the United States National<lb/>
Herbarium</hi>, vol. 14, part 2, 1910, states definitely that the banana is a na-<lb/>
tive of the eastern continent (p.341): and in speaking of the introduction<lb/>
of Old World plants into America (p. 274) he says: &ldquo;The only tropical<lb/>
types introduced during the period of the early discoveries appear to have<lb/>
been the varieties of bananas and sugar-cane brought gver from the Canary<lb/>
Islands.</p>
<p>I am sending you herewith a paper which I read before the First Pan<lb/>
Pacific Scientific Conference, held at Honolulu in the summer of 1920, and<lb/>
published in part 1, p. 183, of the Proceedings. 1921. This will show<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01025034"/>
-3-<lb/>
the identity of the names of many of the food plants in various island<lb/>
groups, and also of the Malayan origin of the plants and their names,<lb/>
as well as of the Polynesians, which brought them from the cradle of<lb/>
their race, in the Malay Archipelago.</p>
<p>An earlier paper of mine, read before the Nineteenth International<lb/>
Congress of Americanists, was entitled <hi>Food-plants and Textiles of Ancient</hi><lb/>
America. This paper, based upon my material from prehistoric Peruvian<lb/>
graves, was published in the Proceedings of that Congress pp. 12 ff. 1917;<lb/>
also (with fewer illustrations) in the Proceedings of the Second Pan<lb/>
American Scientific Congress, vol. 1, p. 146, ff. 1917.</p>
<p>In a recent paper, read last Summer at Rio Janeiro, on <hi>The Isolation of<lb/>
Ancient America and the Antiquity of its Colonization Established by the<lb/>
Food Plants of its Inhabitants</hi>, I contrast the conditions on this continent<lb/>
with those of Polynesia. While the principal economic plants of the<lb/>
Primitive Polynesians were of Asiatic origin and had undoubtedly accompanied<lb/>
the Polynesians on their migrations from their cradle in the Malay Archipelago,<lb/>
every cultivated plant encountered by Columbus and those who followed him to<lb/>
the New World, in both North and South America, and in the islands where<lb/>
they first landed, was absolutely unknown to the inhabitants of the Old World.<lb/>
In other words, not a single cereal, vegetable, fruit, or edible root of Europe,<lb/>
Asia, or Africa, had found its way to the Western Hemisphere before the time<lb/>
of Columbus; nor had a grain of maize, common beans or Lima beans, potato or<lb/>
sweet potato, or any other plant indigenous to the New World reached the Old<lb/>
World. Thousands and thousands of years must have been necessary to produce<lb/>
maize in all its varieties and spread it over North and South America into<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01025035"/>
-4-<lb/>
localities characterized by widely different conditions of soil and climate.<lb/>
And the same is true of beans, squashes, and other food staples widely<lb/>
spread in prehistoric times; as well as of the various species of tobacco.<lb/>
Once discovered it is remarkable how rapidly many of these plants spread<lb/>
to the remotest corners of the earth.</p>
<p>But I will refrain. I expect some day to publish my paper, and<lb/>
will be glad to send you a reprint of it should you care for one.</p>
<p>I am very glad to know you are interested in the origin of culti-<lb/>
vated plants. I hope some day to do a great work bearing upon this subject.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Believe me, ever faithfully yours,</salute>
<signed><unclear>W. E. Safford</unclear><lb/>
Economic Botanist</signed>.
WES/EBH<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
