<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01025003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, April 4, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01025003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-04-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-04-04">April 4, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01025003</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, April 4, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson must decide whether to stay in private practice or resume yellow fever work with the International Health Board. Enclosing a telegram from Russell, he asks Carter if there is suspicion of yellow fever in Colombia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-04-04">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, April 4, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01025003"/>
<opener>
HENRY HANSON, M. D.<lb/>
<dateline>
LABORATORY<lb/>
460 ST. JAMES BLDG.<lb/>
JACKSONVILLE, FLORIDA<lb/>
<date value="1923-04-04">April, 4, 1923,</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am enclosing a copy of <xref id="f01025004">telegram</xref> received from<lb/>
Col. Russel, which will be self explanatory. This has rather upset all my<lb/>
plans and I am as much up in the air about what I am to do and about a<lb/>
home for the family as I was while in Baltimore. I replied stating that I<lb/>
would consider it if they would assure me permanent work, and a good salary.<lb/>
I did not state the amount, and dont know whether or not I ought to do so.<lb/>
They know what I was getting in Peru, but I know that they also think that<lb/>
is more than they can pay, or rather it is more than they have planned to pay.</p>
<p>The situation with me is, as you know, that I have gone to considerable<lb/>
expense in getting down here, getting my things to gather once more, the cost<lb/>
of setting up house keeping again, besides the expense which I have gone to<lb/>
on my preliminary laboratory equipment. This would all be practically a com-<lb/>
plete loss if I should go on this work. The work here is looking promising<lb/>
even at this early stage before I have made any announcement to the profession<lb/>
as a whole. What I have done so far has been simply local work for Jacksonville<lb/>
Surgeons and Physicians, and I have had as much as I could do up to date. It<lb/>
would be possible for me to do more if I were better equipped for it, but as<lb/>
it is I am employing an office helper now (not a highly skilled one, but one<lb/>
who does take care of a part of the routine) and we can not do very much more<lb/>
than the work which we are getting, unless we improve the equipment consider-<lb/>
ably. This of course I can not do until it is decided what I am to do for the<lb/>
I.H.B., and what they think they have in mind for me to do.</p>
<p>It seems to me that if I am to tear up and go out on another foreign<lb/>
detail that they will have to plan on continuous employment, since one can<lb/>
not go on a detail of this kind for a <unclear>sh rt</unclear> period and then be turned loose<lb/>
to start all over again. Even I am getting too old for that, and I have not<lb/>
got the pep I had before the work in Peru.</p>
<p>Last fall Dr. White offered $8000, per annum and expenses (travel expense)<lb/>
in a lump sum that looks like a pretty good salary, and I realize that in this<lb/>
country it would be a very good salary, but when one is out on these foreign<lb/>
details it is not so much as it looks, especially if it is only for a year or<lb/>
two. At present it has taken all my savings to get established again, and if<lb/>
I tear up now most of that will be lost, especially what I have spent on the<lb/>
laboratory. Still I am very much interested in the work and am willing to<lb/>
make a reasonable sacrifice to help out in this big yellow fever program.</p>
<p>The family will be the greatest sufferer in this thing. It is a<lb/>
question where one could satisfactorily locate them. Where to establish the<lb/>
home which must be established? If one were to work with them permanently<lb/>
it might be best to set up housekeeping in some place near New York, such<lb/>
as Long Island, near Headquarters.</p>
<p>I wired Russel that I would consider it and later wrote him but I<lb/>
can not very well make any final decision until he gives me some more definite<lb/>
program to consider. Simply to go on this survey of Columbia, could not be<lb/>
considered except for a salary of $1000, permonth and all incidental travel<lb/>
expense. I stated that I could start about May first if things could be satis-<lb/>
factorily arranged.</p>
<p>What is in the wind-is there some suspicion of yellow fever in Columbia?</p>
<p>Well here I am bothering you again, but I know of not better place to go<lb/>
for advice.</p>
<p>With the best regards from all the Hansons,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
Answered, April 6 (8)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
