<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01024001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: A Possible Explanation of the Absence of Bubonic Plague from Cold Countries, by H. McG. Robertson, April 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01024001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-04-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">India</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Great Britain</name>
<name type="place">Japan</name>
<name type="place">China</name>
<name type="place">Russia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>25 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-04-00">April 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01024001</idno>
<title>Report: A Possible Explanation of the Absence of Bubonic Plague from Cold Countries, by H. McG. Robertson, April 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robertson reports on plague distribution and speculates that its absence from cold climates is related to the absence of fleas in these areas.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-04-00">
<head>Report: A Possible Explanation of the Absence of Bubonic Plague from Cold Countries, by H. McG. Robertson, April 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01024001"/>
<opener>
Miscell<lb/>
<unclear>Robertson</unclear><lb/>
Plague<lb/>
A Possible Explanation of the Absence of<lb/>
Bubonic Plague from Cold Countries.<lb/>
by<lb/>
H. McG. Robertson, Surgeon, U. S. P. H. S.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>A study of statistical reports of plague as published<lb/>
in the Weekly Public Health Reports of the United States Public<lb/>


Health Service will show that in the past twenty-six years<lb/>
bubonic plague has spread in an east and west direction from<lb/>
India until at the present time it may be found encircling the<lb/>
globe in a rather broad band bounded, roughly, by the 35th degree<lb/>
parallel north and south of the equator. This plague circle of<lb/>
the globe was completed as far back as 1914 when this disease<lb/>
appeared for the first time in one of the cities of our Southern<lb/>
States. Bubonic plague has appeared north of the 35th parallel<lb/>
north latitude rather extensively in southern Europe; in fact it<lb/>
may be said that in this part of the world the 45th latitude north<lb/>
is more probably the boundary. It is also noted that in our own<lb/>
country this disease, appearing in San Francisco, is north of<lb/>
the 35th parallel. Reference to climatic conditions along the<lb/>
Mediterranean Coasts and in San Francisco will show that the<lb/>
temperatures are markedly modified as compared with the temper-<lb/>
atures in other countries of this same latitude. This of<lb/>
course is due in great part to ocean currents and the warm waters<lb/>
of the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>While during this 26 year period bubonic plague has<lb/>
spread around the globe there has been no such corresponding<lb/>
spread to the north and south of parallels 35 with one notable<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01024002"/>
-2-<lb/>
exception. This exception is in the case of the British Isles;<lb/>
yet here we see the climate modified to a great extent by the<lb/>
Gulf stream. Notwithstanding this modification of climate and<lb/>
in spite of the fact that bubonic plague has appeared in dif-<lb/>
ferent places in Great Britain as often as twenty times during<lb/>
the past twenty-six years there has been no general spread of<lb/>
the disease during this time; there has been no spread at any<lb/>
time from city to city, and during the past twelve months no<lb/>
cases or deaths have been reported. In twenty-six years there<lb/>
have been twenty-six deaths from the disease in question in all<lb/>
parts of Great Britain, and this in spite of daily maritime<lb/>
contact with the plague centers of the world and without until<lb/>
recently any efforts along the lines of quarantine restrictions<lb/>
or any extensive effort on the part of local authorities to<lb/>
suppress these outbreaks.</p>
<p>It is seen from this study of the Public Health Reports<lb/>
that bubonic plague during this term of years has spread alike<lb/>
to countries which endeavored to prevent its entrance and to<lb/>
those which made no such efforts; it is seen, too, that this<lb/>
disease has failed to spread alike to colder countries which<lb/>
made no effort to prevent its entrance as well as to those which<lb/>
like our own North Atlantic Seacoast have made strenous effort<lb/>
to prevent its ingress. In other words it appears that the<lb/>
efforts of man to control the spread of this disease have been<lb/>
of little or no avail. It would seem also that in this extended<lb/>
period of time bubonic plague would have spread to northern<lb/>
countries were it epidemiologically possible for it to have<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01024003"/>
-3-<lb/>
done so. The fact that it has not so spread is not due<lb/>
apparently to efforts on the part of man and it is equally<lb/>
hard to look upon this phenomenon as accidental. This<lb/>
brings up the question of the explanation of the failure<lb/>
of this disease to spread to countries where the climate<lb/>
is cold or relatively cold. This disease has never been<lb/>
reported north of the 60th degree of latitude north; in<lb/>
the western hemisphere it has never been reported north of<lb/>
the 40th degree of latitude, except in Seattle. The existence<lb/>
of this disease north of latitude 35 north has never in any<lb/>
part of the world constituted a serious sanitary problem,<lb/>
except in those warmer sections previously mentioned or in<lb/>
ages past under conditions with which we cannot now be entirely<lb/>
familiar.</p>
<p>It appears that little or no work, from an epidemio-<lb/>
logical point of view, has been done which would explain the<lb/>
absence, or practical absence, of bubonic plague from the<lb/>
colder sections of the world. This absence is not believed<lb/>
to be accidental, as before stated, nor is it believed in any<lb/>
great degree to be the result of man's efforts.</p>
<p>In considering bubonic plague in its relation to human<lb/>
beings, it is necessary, or usual, at this period of the world's<lb/>
history to consider this disease in the rat as antecedent, and<lb/>
necessary, to its spread to the human population. The time<lb/>
may have been, when man, dressing in skins and furs and living<lb/>
with lower animals in insanitary surroundings, contracted<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01024004"/>
-4-<lb/>
bubonic plague through fleas coming directly from a member<lb/>
of his own race. Such a transfer of this infection is not<lb/>
now of sanitary significance, and the three factors - man,<lb/>
the rat and the flea- are taken together in any epidemio-<lb/>
logical study.</p>
<p>We see in the tropical sections of the world, that<lb/>
human plague is or has been, reported in all months of the<lb/>
year, and for numbers of years in succession. The inference<lb/>
is, and this inference is supported by studies of the Indian<lb/>
Plague Commission, that all three factors are present through-<lb/>
out the entire year. The flea is the only factor which might<lb/>
be considered variable, but this insect is found at all seasons,<lb/>
though more plentiful during certain months. Man and the rat<lb/>
must be active at all seasons in order to live. They are<lb/>
relatively long-lived; they do not hibernate in any climate<lb/>
and their young do not pass through the winter in the immature<lb/>
state. Neither the human nor the rat population change<lb/>
extensively in any given area during short periods. The adult<lb/>
flea on the other hand lives usually not many months, and in<lb/>
cold or cool climate the adult rarely passes through the winter.<lb/>
The flea, as a species, is prevented from dying out in cold<lb/>
countries by the ability of the immature forms to exist for<lb/>
periods which may range to more than a year. These long<lb/>
pupal stages are seen only in cool or cold weather. These<lb/>
facts are borne out by the studies of the Indian Plague<lb/>
Commission and by work done by the Bureau of Entomology of<lb/>
the United States Department of Agriculture. In regard to<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01024005"/>
-5-<lb/>
the absence of fleas, the adult form, in the winter months,<lb/>
my observation of this phenomenon was confined to cats.<lb/>
During two recent winters I was unable to find fleas on this<lb/>
animal between December 15 and March 15, although the cats<lb/>
in question spent the entire winter months indoors in warm<lb/>
places and although the basements where they slept were,<lb/>
during the previous summers, heavily infested with fleas.</p>
<p>It was this observation that led me to speculate as<lb/>
to the probable absence of fleas from their rat hosts during<lb/>
the cold months of the year and that farther led me to suspect<lb/>
that in this absence of fleas was to be had an explanation<lb/>
of the freedom of certain countries from outbreaks of human<lb/>
cases of bubonic plague. During the past year I have advocated<lb/>
making a flea survey of the cities of our Atlantic Coast in<lb/>
order to determine definitely whether I was correct in thinking<lb/>
this probable explanation the right one.</p>
<p>Should this flea survey show that fleas are relatively<lb/>
abundant on rate at all seasons of the year, the absence of<lb/>
bubonic plague would of necessity be accidental, as all three<lb/>
factors needed in its spread would be present. If on the other<lb/>
hand it was shown that during certain cold months no fleas, or<lb/>
only an occasional flea, was found, an explanation of the<lb/>
absence of human plague would be at hand. Rat plague introduced<lb/>
into a locality where adult fleas were present would spread<lb/>
among the rats, the rapidity of this spread being dependent<lb/>
on the abundance of fleas and the larger or smaller number of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01024006"/>
-6-<lb/>
rats. If the fleas were present throughout the entire year, as<lb/>
in the tropics, the infection among the rats must become so<lb/>
extensive as eventually to result in human cases appearing. Rat<lb/>
plague, introduced into a community where fleas are absent for<lb/>
certain months, must of necessity die out when the flea disappears,<lb/>
as one factor in the spread of the disease will be absent with<lb/>
their disappearance.</p>
<p>The question as to whether human plague will appear in<lb/>
a locality where rat plague must disappear at the beginning of<lb/>
each winter can be answered only after consideration of several<lb/>
factors. Among these are the number of fleas per rat in the<lb/>
months when they are present; the number of months in which<lb/>
fleas are found present; and the relative number of rats in the<lb/>
locality under consideration. The character of the communication<lb/>
with active plague centers might also be taken into account.<lb/>
As regards the number of fleas per rat, this knowledge will be<lb/>
valuable only when compared with a like knowledge of similar<lb/>
conditions in localities where bubonic plague has prevailed<lb/>
throughout the entire year, as in New Orleans, or some city in<lb/>
India. The months in which fleas may be found on rats should be<lb/>
fewer the farther north the locality studies is situated. In<lb/>
regard to communication with plague centers, we have noted that<lb/>
Great Britain, though in intimate maritime association with<lb/>
India, has not suffered seriously.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f01024007"/>
<p>-7-</p>
<p>In order to have some definite data based on statistical<lb/>
reports, which might sustain my belief that the absence or<lb/>
relative absence of fleas during the cold months determined the<lb/>
absence of bubonic plague from such countries, a rather detailed<lb/>
study of the reports of cases of plague as given in the Public<lb/>
Health Reports for the past twenty-six years was undertaken.<lb/>
A table was prepared giving the names of cities and countries<lb/>
in which plague had been reported in the Public Health Reports<lb/>
for the years 1897 to 1922 inclusive. Each year was divided<lb/>
into two periods, corresponding to the semi-annual summaries<lb/>
given in the last issues of the Public Health Reports for June<lb/>
and December. Thus there were 52 semi-annual periods to theb<lb/>
table. Each of the 52 volumes of the Public Health Reports<lb/>
was consulted and the figures for the six months put in the<lb/>
appropriate column under cities and countries. The totals thus<lb/>
obtained have been used in preparing the tables which follow.<lb/>
Upon securing from the U. S. Weather Bureau, Department of<lb/>
Agriculture in Washington, a book entitled &ldquo;The Climates of<lb/>
the Continents&rdquo;, by W. G. Kendrew, M. A., Oxford, published in<lb/>
1922, it was possible to take the cities and countries of the<lb/>
world in which plague had occurred and combine them in four<lb/>
temperature groups, as shown later in tables 1, 2, 3, and 4.</p>
<p>It was in this way possible to show at a glance where<lb/>
plague had actually occurred, how extensively and what was its<lb/>
seeming relation to different temperatures. These temperature<lb/>
periods also explain the apparent exceptions to the spread of<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01024008"/>
-8-<lb/>
plague north of parallel 35 degrees north, mentioned in the<lb/>
beginning of this article.</p>
<p>Tables one to eight follow, and after them a brief<lb/>
explanation and discussion is given.</p>
<p>No question is raised in this statistical study of the<lb/>
accuracy and completeness of the reports. It is obvious that<lb/>
in some instances in certain countries they are far from<lb/>
complete, yet there is no reason to suspect that any reported<lb/>
cases are incorrect. It is more likely that fairly complete<lb/>
returns have been made for those cities and countries in tables<lb/>
one and two than for those in table three and four, as the<lb/>
former are those which have for years paid more attention<lb/>
to sanitary matters and from which correct reports of all<lb/>
kinds might be expected.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f01024009"/>
<p>-9-</p>
<p>Bubonic Plague:<lb/>
Cases Reported<lb/>
in<lb/>
Public Health Reports -<lb/>
January, 1897 to December 31, 1922.</p>
<p>Table I</p>
<p>Seaport cities (except two) with mean mid-winter temperatures<lb/>
35 degrees F. or below. (The principal cities of the world<lb/>
having such temperatures).</p>
<p>
<table rows="32" cols="3">
<row>
<cell><hi>Name</hi></cell><cell><hi>Number Cases</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Washington</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Baltimore</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Philadelphia</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>New York</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Boston</cell><cell>---------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Portland, Me,</cell><cell>---------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>St. Johns</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Halifax</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Montreal</cell><cell>-------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Bergen</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Christiania</cell><cell>-----------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Stockholm</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Gothenburg</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Danzig</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hamburg</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Bremen</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Copenhagen</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Amsterdam</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Rotterdam</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Antwerp</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Bahia Blanca</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Punta Arenas, Chile</cell><cell>---------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Otaru, Japan</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>None</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Peking</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>2 (Jan. 24, 1911)</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>St. Petersburg</cell><cell>--------------------------------</cell><cell>7 (May, July, Nov.)</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Moscow</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>14 (12 in winter<lb/>
(2 in August</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Odessa</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>140 July to Nov.<lb/>
1910<lb/>
8 June to Aug.<lb/>
1911.<lb/>
3 Dec. 29, 1911.<lb/>
<hi>49</hi> To Nov., 1901.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>223</cell></row></table></p>
<p>Note: It will be noted that 200 of the 223 cases occurred<lb/>
in the one port. Odessa.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f01024010"/>
<p>-10-</p>
<p>Bubonic Plague:<lb/>
Cases Reported<lb/>
in<lb/>
Public Health Reports -<lb/>
January 1, 1897 to December 31, 1922.</p>
<p>Table II</p>
<p>Seaport cities principally with mean mid-winter temperatures<lb/>
36 to 45 degrees F., showing only those cities in which plague<lb/>
has been reported.</p>
<p>
<table rows="27" cols="3">
<row>
<cell><hi>Name</hi></cell><cell><hi>Number Cases</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Trieste</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Fiume</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>4</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Cattaro</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>3</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Auckland</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>17</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Paris</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>54</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Saloniki</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>26</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Gleegow</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>35</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Bristol, Eng.</cell><cell>-------------------------------</cell><cell>3</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hull</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Dublin</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Liverpool</cell><cell>-----------------------------------</cell><cell>27</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Suffolk (Co.), Eng.</cell><cell>-------------------------</cell><cell>4</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>London</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>4</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Leith</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>4</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Cardiff</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Govan</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Shanghai</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>73</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Seattle</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>5</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Batoum</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>39</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Constantinople</cell><cell>------------------------------</cell><cell>10</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Nagasaki</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>36</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Yokohama</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>86</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Tokyo</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>58</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Kobe</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>310</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Osaka</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell><hi>604</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>-----------------------------------</cell><cell>1409</cell></row></table></p>
<p>Memo. - The cities of Norfolk, Virginia and Wilmington, North<lb/>
Carolina belong in this temperature division.</p>
<p>It will be noted that 914 of the 1409 cases in this<lb/>
group occurred in Kobe and Osaka, Japan.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f01024011"/>
<p>-11-</p>
<p>Bubonic Plague:<lb/>
Cases Reported<lb/>
in<lb/>
Public Health Reports -<lb/>
January 1, 1897 to December 31, 1922.</p>
<p>Table III</p>
<p>Seacoast countries and cities with mean mid-winter temperatures<lb/>
66 to 55 degrees F., showing only those in which bubonic plague<lb/>
has been reported.</p>
<p>
<table rows="21" cols="3">
<row>
<cell><hi>Name</hi></cell><cell><hi>Number Cases</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Algeria</cell><cell>--------------------------------------</cell><cell>325</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Tunis</cell><cell>--------------------------------------</cell><cell>19</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Morocco</cell><cell>--------------------------------------</cell><cell>48</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Tripoli</cell><cell>--------------------------------------</cell><cell>56</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Bagdad and vicinity</cell><cell>--------------------------</cell><cell>2691</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Lisbon</cell><cell>--------------------------------------</cell><cell>122</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Oporto</cell><cell>--------------------------------------</cell><cell>564</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Naples and Catania</cell><cell>---------------------------</cell><cell>79</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Barcelona</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>39</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Marseilles</cell><cell>-----------------------------------</cell><cell>92</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Piraeus and Islands nearby</cell><cell>------------------</cell><cell>137</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Australia</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>1361</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Rosario and Beunos Ayres (all of Argentina)</cell><cell>----</cell><cell>316</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>South Africa</cell><cell>---------------------------------</cell><cell>3359</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>San Francisco</cell><cell>---------------------------------</cell><cell>279</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Galveston</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>18</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>New Orleans</cell><cell>---------------------------------</cell><cell>49</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Pensacola</cell><cell>-----------------------------------</cell><cell>10</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Beaumont</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell><hi>14</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>---------------------------------------</cell><cell>9578</cell></row></table></p>
<p>It will be noted that nearly two thirds of these cases<lb/>
were reported from Bagdad and vicinity and from South Africa.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f01024012"/>
<p>-12-</p>
<p>Bubonic Plague:<lb/>
Cases Reported<lb/>
in<lb/>
Public Health Reports -<lb/>
January, 1897 to December 31, 1922.</p>
<p>Table IV</p>
<p>Countries with mean mid-winter temperatures of 56 degrees F.<lb/>
and over.</p>
<p>
<table rows="36" cols="3">
<row>
<cell><hi>Name</hi></cell><cell><hi>Number Cases</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Cuba</cell><cell>-------------------------------------</cell><cell>68</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Trinidad</cell><cell>-----------------------------------</cell><cell>62</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Granada</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Panama</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Venezuela</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>229</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Chile</cell><cell>-------------------------------------</cell><cell>2576</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Brazil</cell><cell>-------------------------------------</cell><cell>4770</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Paraguay</cell><cell>-----------------------------------</cell><cell>91</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Uraguay</cell><cell>------------------------------------</cell><cell>14</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>W. Africa</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>296</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>E. Africa</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>3968</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mauritius</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>7732</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Reunion Island</cell><cell>-----------------------------</cell><cell>12</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Madagascar</cell><cell>---------------------------------</cell><cell>627</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Persia</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>2044</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Arabia</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>2469</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Ceylon</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>1481</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Turkey</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>890</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Azores</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>583</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Cape Verde</cell><cell>---------------------------------</cell><cell>12</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hawaii</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>204</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Philippines</cell><cell>--------------------------------</cell><cell>1446</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mexico</cell><cell>---------------------------------</cell><cell>515</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Porto Rico</cell><cell>---------------------------------</cell><cell>71</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>China, South East</cell><cell>--------------------------</cell><cell>33207</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>New Caledonia</cell><cell>------------------------------</cell><cell>290</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Japan - Formosa</cell><cell>----------------------------</cell><cell>35540</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Equador</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>5807</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Peru</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>13247</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Egypt</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>15217</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Java</cell><cell>----------------------------------</cell><cell>69105</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>India (Indo China etc.)</cell><cell>------------------</cell><cell><hi>8864504</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>-----------------------------------</cell><cell>9067080</cell></row></table></p>
<p>Cases for this division exclusive of India- 202576</p>
<p>Cases for this division from India--------- 8864504</p>
<pb n="13" id="f01024013"/>
<p>-13-</p>
<p>Bubonic Plague:<lb/>
Cases Reported<lb/>
in<lb/>
Public Health Reports -<lb/>
January 1, 1897 to December 31, 1922.</p>
<p>Table V</p>
<p>Showing total cases reported according to the four temperature<lb/>
periods as given in tables 1, 2, 3 and 4; also showing percent-<lb/>
age of cases occurring in each division.</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="3">
<row>
<cell><hi>Mean mid-winter temperature</hi></cell><cell><hi>Total Cases</hi></cell><cell><hi>Per cent</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>35 degrees F. and below ---------</cell><cell>223 ------ </cell><cell>0.0025</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>36 degrees F. to 45 degrees F.---</cell><cell>1397 ------ </cell><cell>0.015</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>46 degrees F. to 55 degrees F.--- </cell><cell>9578 ------</cell><cell>0.15</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>56 degrees F. and over(India excluded<lb/>
202576)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>56 degrees F. and over(India alone<lb/>
8864504)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>(Total for 56 degrees and over)--</cell><cell><hi>9067080</hi></cell><cell>------- 99.8325</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total for all countries -------</cell><cell>9078278</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></p>
<p>Because of the fact that some of the cases reported from<lb/>
India were in the extreme northern part of the country where<lb/>
the mean mid-winter temperatures are below 56 degrees F. the<lb/>
percentage of cases occurring in each of the four temperature<lb/>
divisions is given below having been computed with the 8864504<lb/>
cases from India excluded.</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 1st temperature division---- 0.1</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 2nd temperature division---- 0.7</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 3rd temperature division---- 4.75</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 4th temperature division---- 94.45</p>
<pb n="14" id="f01024014"/>
<p>-14-</p>
<p>Bubonic Plague:<lb/>
Cases Reported<lb/>
in<lb/>
Public Health Reports -<lb/>
January, 1897 to December 31, 1922.</p>
<p>Table VI</p>
<p>Comparing the percentages as given in Table V with the percent-<lb/>
ages as calculated for the last 15 1/2 years of the 26 year period<lb/>
under consideration.</p>
<p>For 26 years from Jan. 1, 1897 to December 31, 1922 the<lb/>
figures are as follows:</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 1st division (35 degrees F. or below) 0.1</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 2nd division (36 to 45 degrees F.) 0.7</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 3rd division (46 to 55degrees F.) 4.75</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 4th division (56 degrees F. and over) 94.45</p>
<p>For 15 1/2 years from July 1, 1907 to December 31, 1922 the<lb/>
figures are as follows:</p>



<p>Per cent cases in 1st division (35 degrees F. or below) 0.17</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 2nd division (36 to 45 degrees F.) 1.3</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 3rd division (46 to 55 degrees F.) 4.6</p>
<p>Per cent cases in 4th division (56 degrees F. and over) 93.93</p>
<p>It will be seen that the percentages changed practically<lb/>
not at all upon taking into consideration the more than 5000000<lb/>
cases of bubonic plague reported in various countries between<lb/>
January 1, 1897 and June 30, 1907.</p>
<p>The cases reported in India are not included in computing<lb/>
the figures given above. If India is included the percentage<lb/>
of cases occurring in the highest temperature group is 99.8<lb/>
in both instances.</p>
<p>Note: The separation of the figures into two periods was for<lb/>
purposes of convenience in tabulation. The 15 1/2 years from<lb/>
July 1, 1907 to December 31, 1922 were first compiled. The<lb/>
10 1/2 years from January 1, 1897 to June 30, 1907 were compiled<lb/>
later and added to the figures of the former period. This made<lb/>
possible the obtaining of separate percentages for the whole<lb/>
period and for the last 15 1/2 years.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f01024015"/>
<p>-15-</p>
<p>Bubonic Plague<lb/>
Cases Reported<lb/>
in<lb/>
Public Health Reports -<lb/>
January 1, 1897 to December 31, 1922.</p>
<p>Table VII</p>
<p>Showing the decrease in number of cases reported in certain <unclear>Chi</unclear>-<lb/>
nese and Japanese cities where the mean mid-winter temperatures<lb/>
decline progressively from south to north.</p>
<p>China</p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="3">
<row>
<cell><hi>Name of City</hi></cell><cell><hi>Mean Mid-winter Temperature</hi></cell><cell><hi>No. Cases Reported</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hongkong</cell><cell>59 degrees F.</cell><cell>20000 plus</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Shanghai</cell><cell>37 degrees F.</cell><cell>73</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Peking</cell><cell>25 degrees F.</cell><cell>2 (probably)<lb/>
(pneumonic)<lb/>
(occurred in)<lb/>
(winter of 1911.)</cell></row></table></p>
<p>Japan</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="3">
<row>
<cell>Taiwan (Formosa)</cell><cell>60 degrees F.</cell><cell>20000 plus</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Toyko</cell><cell>37 degrees F.</cell><cell>55</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Otaru</cell><cell>23 degrees F.</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>Note:</p>
<p>It may be said that this same phenomenon is markedly<lb/>
noticeable in India. No accurate figures have been compiled look-<lb/>
ing towards separating the plague cases reported in India into<lb/>
groups corresponding to temperature changes. However, of the<lb/>
322560 cases reported between October, 1919 and October, 1922,<lb/>
none were given as occurring north of Delhi; at which point the<lb/>
mean mid-winter temperature is 59.5 degrees F. It has been noted<lb/>
in this study that cases of bubonic plague were reported in the<lb/>
north of India, but the number was relatively very small.</p>
<pb n="16" id="f01024016"/>
<p>-16-</p>
<p>Bubonic Plague:<lb/>
Cases Reported<lb/>
in<lb/>
Public Health Reports -<lb/>
July 1, 1907 to December 31, 1922.</p>
<p>Table VIII</p>
<p>Showing dates on which bubonic plague appeared and disappeared<lb/>
in cities with mean mid-winter temperatures 36 degrees F. to<lb/>
45 degrees F.</p>
<p>
<table rows="28" cols="3">
<row>
<cell><hi>Name</hi></cell><cell><hi>Dates</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Dublin</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>October 18</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Bristol, Eng.</cell><cell>-----------------</cell><cell>August 18-31</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hull</cell><cell>----------------------</cell><cell>August 18-31</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Liverpool</cell><cell>--------------------</cell><cell>September 22-October 6</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Liverpool</cell><cell>--------------------</cell><cell>August; June 20-26</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Suffolk County</cell><cell>---------------</cell><cell>Oct.; Sept.; June 19</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Glasgow</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>August to October</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>London</cell><cell>----------------------</cell><cell>August</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Leith</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>May 7-14</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Cardiff</cell><cell>----------------------</cell><cell>February (1 death)</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Govan</cell><cell>--------------------</cell><cell>September</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Saloniki</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>Oct.-Dec.; April and May</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Volo</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>September and October</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Paris</cell><cell>-----------------------</cell><cell>(June to Oct.; August;<lb/>
(Jan. 3 suspected</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Auckland, N. Z.</cell><cell>(<hi>South. Hemisphere</hi></cell><cell>(Mar.-May; March; June</cell><lb/>
<cell>((Sept.) (Nov) (Sept) (Dec.)</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Trieste</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>November 1-8</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Fiume</cell><cell>----------------------</cell><cell>September 21</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Cattaro</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>Feb. 23 (in French troops)</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Shanghai</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>August-December; June</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Nagasaki</cell><cell>--------------------</cell><cell>To November</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Tokyo</cell><cell>----------------------</cell><cell>June and August</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Batoum</cell><cell>---------------------</cell><cell>November 24 to December 3</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Kobe</cell><cell>----------------------</cell><cell>Sept. to Dec.; May to Nov.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Yokohama</cell><cell>--------------------</cell><cell>May 22 to November 12</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Osaka</cell><cell>----------------------</cell><cell>May to December; Nov. to May</cell></row></table></p>
<pb n="17" id="f01024017"/>
<p>-17-</p>
<p>Table I contains the principal seaports of the world in<lb/>
which the mean mid-winter temperature is 35 degrees fahrenheit<lb/>
or below. In only four of these cities has plague been report-<lb/>
ed, the others being given because of the rather prevalent<lb/>
belief that plague had already spread to the principal seaports<lb/>
of the world. Two inland cities are also included because they<lb/>
have reported plague.</p>
<p>Table II shows those cities of the world having a mean<lb/>
mid-winter temperature of 36 degrees to 45 degrees fahrenheit<lb/>
in which plague has been reported and the number of cases in<lb/>
each.</p>
<p>Table III shows those cities and countries in which plague<lb/>
has been reported in which the mean mid-winter temperature is<lb/>
between 46 degrees and 55 degrees fahrenheit.</p>
<p>Table IV shows those countries and states having a mean<lb/>
mid-winter temperature of 56 degrees fahrenheit and over in<lb/>
all of which bubonic plague has been reported during the twenty-<lb/>
six years under consideration.</p>
<p>Table V shows the total number of cases occurring in each<lb/>
of the four temperature periods mentioned and the percentage<lb/>
of cases reported for each one of these temperature divisions.<lb/>
The percentages are given with and without including the cases<lb/>
reported from India.</p>
<p>Table VI compares the percentages when computed for the<lb/>
entire period of twenty-six years with those obtained when only<lb/>
the last fifteen and one half years of that period are taken<lb/>
into consideration.</p>
<pb n="18" id="f01024018"/>
<p>-18-</p>
<p>Table VII shows the decrease in number of cases reported<lb/>
in certain Chinese and Japanese cities where the mean mid-winter<lb/>
temperatures decline progressively from south to north. It is<lb/>
interesting to note that Peking, China, in twenty-six years,<lb/>
has reported only two cases of plague though tens of thousands<lb/>
of cases of the bubonic type occurred during that period in<lb/>
South Eastern China, and two disastrous epidemics of pneumonic<lb/>
plague visited Manchuria to the north during that time.</p>
<p>Table VIII shows the dates of beginning and ending of<lb/>
those scattered outbreaks of plague which have occurred during<lb/>
the last twenty-six years in cities with a mean mid-winter<lb/>
temperature of 36 degrees to 45 degrees fahrenheit. It will<lb/>
be noted that with scarcely any exceptions these outbreaks have<lb/>
occurred in the late summer and fall. Being absent during the<lb/>
winter months, it seems that only after incubation in the rat<lb/>
population through the spring and early summer do these human<lb/>
outbreaks occur. The time of these outbreaks seems to coincide<lb/>
with the season in which fleas are known to be most plentiful.<lb/>
It is also noted that there is a disappearance of this disease<lb/>
not later than November or early December in nearly all cases<lb/>
reported. This coincides with the idea I have advanced that<lb/>
this disease would disappear with the disappearance of the fleas<lb/>
at the beginning of the cold season, - up to a certain temperature<lb/>
which remains to be determined.</p>
<p>In looking over tables I and II for facts that would tend<lb/>
to discredit the deductions made as to bubonic plague occurring<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f01024019"/>
-19-<lb/>
and disappearing in accordance with the seasonal prevalence<lb/>
of fleas, we are confronted with a few data that seem incon-<lb/>
sistent with this idea.</p>
<p>In table I only four cities out of 27 have ever report-<lb/>
ed plague. Of these four, Moscow reported 12 cases in two<lb/>
outbreaks between December and February. If this was bubonic<lb/>
plague it is incompatible with the belief that fleas disappear<lb/>
in climates such as Moscow in cold weather. No mention is<lb/>
made, however, in the Public Health Reports, as to whether<lb/>
these cases were bubonic or pneumonic. In any event no further<lb/>
cases were reported in Moscow in the summers following these<lb/>
two outbreaks.</p>
<p>The cases occurring in St. Petersburg in May, 1910 are<lb/>
also somewhat early in the year to be in accord with the belief<lb/>
that fleas have not become plentiful at this season. As in<lb/>
the case of the winter cases in Moscow no mention is made as<lb/>
to these cases being bubonic or pneumonic. It is shown, how-<lb/>
ever, in the Public Health Reports that in the years that these<lb/>
winter cases were reported in St. Petersburg and Moscow, pneu-<lb/>
monic plague was reported in Asiatic Russia and in the Astrakhan<lb/>
District.</p>
<p>Three cases of plague occurred in Odessa in January,<lb/>
1911 and can possibly be explained in the same manner as the<lb/>
cases in Moscow and St. Petersburg.</p>
<p>In Peking, China the only two cases reported in twenty-<lb/>
six years occurred in January. It is significant that these<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f01024020"/>
-20-<lb/>
two cases occurred in the winter in which 50000 deaths were<lb/>
reported in Manchuria from pneumonic plague, and it is more<lb/>
than possible that these two cases were pneumonic, though<lb/>
they were not so reported.</p>
<p>The only city in table I in which plague was reported<lb/>
as occurring in the summer and fall months is Odessa, Russia.<lb/>
This disease was reported as follows:</p>
<p>1901 - To November --------------------- 49 cases</p>
<p>1910 - July 18 to November 25 ---------- 140 cases</p>
<p>1911 - June 18 to August 8 ------------ 8 cases</p>
<p>In a grain shipping port such as Odessa, in a country where,<lb/>
possibly, little attention is paid to sanitation and where<lb/>
the human and rat populations may be both numerous and closely<lb/>
associated it is possible for an outbreak of bubonic plague<lb/>
to occur, and the last three reported for Odessa are probably<lb/>
such.</p>
<p>Mention may be made here of the fact that it is only<lb/>
in Russia and China that plague of any type has been reported<lb/>
in localities having a mean mid-winter temperature of 35<lb/>
degrees F. or below.</p>
<p>In table II there are mentioned twenty-five cities in<lb/>
which bubonic plague has occurred in the period 1897 to 1922.<lb/>
Of 1409 cases reported during this time 914 occurred in Kobe.<lb/>
and Osaka, Japan.</p>
<p>The only reported outbreaks in this list which seem to<lb/>
contravene the theory that the prevalence of fleas affects the<lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f01024021"/>
-21-<lb/>
spread of bubonic plague will be mentioned below. It should<lb/>
be noted, however, that we are dealing here with mean mid-<lb/>
winter temperatures considerably higher than in table I, and<lb/>
it is possible that while fleas may be definitely absent in<lb/>
the winter months where the temperature is 35 degrees fahren-<lb/>
heit or below, they may be sufficiently numerous in the next<lb/>
temperature division - 36 degrees fahrenheit to 45 degrees<lb/>
fahrenheit - to make possible the continuance of the disease<lb/>
through the winter. Yet, the exceptions are so few as to<lb/>
make it difficult to believe that some explanation of the<lb/>
discrepancy might not be found if the correct records of the<lb/>
cities involved were accessible.</p>
<p>Those outbreaks mentioned in this table which may cast<lb/>
some doubt on the correctness of the theory advanced are as<lb/>
follows:</p>
<p>Paris, January, 3 cases reported as suspected. They<lb/>
possibly were not plague.</p>
<p>Cattaro, port of Cettinje, February, 3 cases reported<lb/>
in French troops. These were possibly imported, but<lb/>
it is not so stated.</p>
<p>Japan, in the nineteen outbreaks reported in five cities<lb/>
in Japan all but two show the disease occurring between<lb/>
May and December. Both of these were in Osaka; one<lb/>
from January to April and the other from November to<lb/>
May. This last was an outbreak of 297 cases, reported<lb/>
in the June 30 summary of Public Health Reports as<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="f01024022"/>
-22-<lb/>
occurring between November and May. Reference to the<lb/>
weekly reports from January to June of that year show<lb/>
that 234 of these cases occurred between November 17<lb/>
and December 21; 31 cases between December 21 and<lb/>
January 11 and the remaining 32 cases between January<lb/>
12 and May 9, at the rate of about 2 cases a week.<lb/>
While there was a decided drop in the number of cases<lb/>
reported weekly - from 47 per week in November and<lb/>
December to 2 per week from January 11 to May 9 -<lb/>
during the cold months, the fact remains that in Osaka<lb/>
human cases of bubonic plague were reported throughout<lb/>
the winter. The mean January and February temperature<lb/>
of Osaka is about 39.5 degrees fahrenheit. The December<lb/>
and March temperatures are 41 degrees fahrenheit.<lb/>
Whether this was an exceptionally warm winter in Japan<lb/>
has not been determined.</p>
<p>It should be mentioned in considering the cities of<lb/>
table I that the principal seaports have all more or less<lb/>
intimate maritime relations with the plague centres of the<lb/>
tropics and with those occassionally infected areas which are<lb/>
found in the regions adjoining the tropics. In many of these<lb/>
cities vessels have been reported from time to time in the<lb/>
Public Health Reports as arriving with human cases of plague<lb/>
aboard and it must be that many plague infected rats have<lb/>
been introduced in the period of years under consideration.<lb/>
In studying the outbreaks listed in table II, it is seen that<lb/>
<pb n="23" id="f01024023"/>
-23-<lb/>
they are short-lived, apparently self-limited and practically<lb/>
never result in a recurrence the following season after dying<lb/>
out in the winter season. The only exception to this is the<lb/>
outbreak in the Kobe-Osaka vicinity in the year 1908. Ex-<lb/>
cluding the 914 cases reported in these two cities, only<lb/>
483 cases of bubonic plague have been reported in the remain-<lb/>
ing 23 cities in this group during a period of twenty-six<lb/>
years.</p>
<p>The outbreaks shown in table III show in a general<lb/>
way a rather definite seasonal prevalence for plague. This<lb/>
seems not always to coincide with the rise and fall in<lb/>
temperature and it is possible that at these temperatures<lb/>
the prevalence of fleas is influenced both by rainfall and<lb/>
temperature variations. Further study of the Public Health<lb/>
Reports and flea surveys of localities in this temperature<lb/>
division are necessary to make any accurate deductions as<lb/>
to what it is reasonably possible to predict for such localities.<lb/>
It is, however, obvious that some rather strong influence has<lb/>
been at work in localities even of these high temperatures<lb/>
to limit the spread of bubonic plague in 23 cities and countries<lb/>
over a period of twenty-six years to less than 10000 cases,<lb/>
nearly two thirds of which have been reported from two<lb/>
localities, Bagdad and vicinity and South Africa.</p>
<p>The periodic and infrequent occurrence of bubonic<lb/>
plague in cities and countries of this group is in rather<lb/>
striking contrast to the almost constant presence of this<lb/>
disease in the countries which are mentioned in the last group.<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f01024024"/>
-24-<lb/>
These last are the really tropical countries and it is in<lb/>
these that 94.5 per cent of cases reported in twenty-six<lb/>
years have occurred. Bubonic plague has been reported<lb/>
continuously for the past twenty-six years, or since first<lb/>
reported, in the following countries: India, Java, Ceylon,<lb/>
Egypt, South East China, Peru, Brazil and Equador. This is<lb/>
in rather marked contrast to its <unclear>irregulat</unclear> periodicity in<lb/>
those cities and countries in the third temperature division<lb/>
which have a lower mean mid-winter temperature. It is in<lb/>
much more marked contrast to those cities mentioned in<lb/>
tables one and two where bubonic plague occurs at rare<lb/>
intervals, and at definite seasons in most instances.</p>
<p>Mention must be made of the report of plague in two<lb/>
sections of the world where it has been often reported and<lb/>
where it has caused tens of thousands of deaths. These two<lb/>
areas are Manchuria and the districts surrounding the Caspian<lb/>
Sea. In this study it has not been possible to examine the<lb/>
weekly records of cases reported. The semi-annual summaries<lb/>
of cases given in the Public Health Reports sometimes refer<lb/>
to the outbreaks in these regions as &ldquo;pneumonic&rdquo;, but not<lb/>
always so. From the relatively short periods in which so<lb/>
many cases and deaths were reported, and the exceedingly<lb/>
high mortality rate mentioned the belief is strong that all<lb/>
or most of this plague was of the pneumonic variety. Further<lb/>
detailed study will be necessary, however, should more accurate<lb/>
data as to the reports from these areas be desired.</p>
<pb n="25" id="f01024025"/>
<p>-25-</p>
<p>All of the 35500 cases of plague reported in Japan with<lb/>
the exception of something over 1000 were reported from the<lb/>
Island of Formosa.</p>
<p>The more obvious conclusions to be drawn from this dis-<lb/>
cussion and these tables are:</p>
<p>1st. that bubonic plague is essentially a disease of hot<lb/>
climates, and that having been introduced into tropical<lb/>
countries it tends to persist indefinitely.</p>
<p>2nd that outside of the immediate tropics, this disease is<lb/>
rather definitely limited in the extent to which it will spread.</p>
<p>3rd that in countries with a mean mid-winter temperature of<lb/>
45 degrees fahrenheit or below bubonic plague is occasional,<lb/>
accidental and <unclear>distinctly</unclear> self-limited and that it seems<lb/>
possible for it to occur in the colder regions only for short<lb/>
periods under unusual conditions.</p>
<p>As to the bearing of this study on my deduction that<lb/>
the seasonal prevalence of fleas regulates the spread of<lb/>
bubonic plague, it appears to me to sustain the belief; other-<lb/>
wise it becomes necessary to find some equally reasonable<lb/>
explanation for the absence of bubonic plague from cold countries.</p>
<p>Any estimate of the practical results that would ensue<lb/>
from a determination of the correctness of the theory advanced<lb/>
in the article, and the conclusions drawn therefrom must await<lb/>
confirmation by an actual and comparative flea survey of any<lb/>
given locality.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
