<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01022001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to the Medical Officer in Charge, U.S. Public Health Service, Memphis, Tennessee, March 1, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01022001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-03-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Welch, S.W.</name>
<name type="person">Hazlehurst, G.H.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, J. C.</name>
<name type="place">Little Choctawhatchee River, Dale County (Ala.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-03-01">March 1, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01022001</idno>
<title>Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to the Medical Officer in Charge, U.S. Public Health Service, Memphis, Tennessee, March 1, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Griffitts writes that he has surveyed a power company pond and makes recommendations for malaria prevention measures.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-03-01">
<head>Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to the Medical Officer in Charge, U.S. Public Health Service, Memphis, Tennessee, March 1, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01022001"/>
<opener>
<hi>IMPOUNDED WATER.</hi>-- Griffitts.<lb/>
Pond of Houston Power Co., near Newton, Dale Co., Ala.<lb/>
Copy for<lb/>
Dr. Carter<lb/>
<unclear>IHDG</unclear><lb/>
F.I. MALARIA<lb/>
U.S. PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
MEMPHIS, TENN.<lb/>
MAR -2 1923<lb/>
RECEIVED<lb/>
<dateline>
519 Dexter Avenue,<lb/>
Montgomery, Alabama,<lb/>
<date value="1923-03-01">March 1, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
Medical Officer in Charge,<lb/>
Field Investigations of Malaria,<lb/>
U.S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Memphis, Tenn.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The dam of the Houston Power Company, located on the Little<lb/>
<unclear>Choctawhatchee</unclear> River, six miles below the town of Newton, Dale<lb/>
County, was closed in January, 1921, and the area to be flooded<lb/>
was not cleared. For the most part, it was wooded territory, there<lb/>
was such brush, tree-tops(felled) and old <unclear>logs</unclear>.</p>
<p>In August, 1920, citizens of that community, anticipating<lb/>
unhealthful conditions following the making if the pond, peti-<lb/>
tioned the Alabama State Board of Health to cause action that<lb/>
might protect them. Accordingly, the following recommendations<lb/>
were made by the State Board of Health, after a preliminary<lb/>
survey by Asistant Sanitary Engineer J.C. Carter.-</p>
<p>"1. A hatchery for the raising of top minnows (Gambusia aff-<lb/>
inis) to be established at once. Sufficient minnows can<lb/>
be collected in the various streams near the dam site to<lb/>
start this hatchery. The minnows raised in the hatchery<lb/>
are to be placed in the lake made by the dam, at inter-<lb/>
vals throughout the year and in sufficient quantities to<lb/>
control mosquito breeding. The hatchery should be con-<lb/>
structed near the lake, but at a height that will pre-<lb/>
vent an overflow from the main stream.</p>
<p>"2 All brush and vegetation under six inches in diame-<lb/>
ter to be removed between a line twenty foot out from<lb/>
the seventy-five feet contour line to a line sufficient-<lb/>
ly far toward the main stream that the brush at full<lb/>
growth will not protrude above the surface of the water.</p>
<p>"3. All trees or growth above six inches in diameter,<lb/>
extending from the seventy-five feet contour line to<lb/>
a line fifty feet outward to be ringed. The trees and<lb/>
other growth standing in the water will die after one<lb/>
or two years. It will be necessary to patrol this area<lb/>
at intervals to see that no flotage collects on the trees<lb/>
or other growth.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01022002"/>
<p>2-- Imp. Wat. Newton, Ala.</p>
<p>"4. At certain seasons when the water in the lake recedes<lb/>
some water may be left in depressions. Such places must be<lb/>
drained by ditches constructed as soon as practicable af-<lb/>
ter the water in the main body has receded.</p>
<p>" Special attention should be paid to the streams and ditch-<lb/>
es which enter the lake <unclear>fromtthe</unclear> hills. Still water which<lb/>
is very favorable to the breeding of mosquitoes is apt to<lb/>
be found in such places. These places must be kept clean<lb/>
of all growth and flotage to enable the mosquito-destroying<lb/>
fish to work freely.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Inspections should be made from time to time after the<lb/>
water is damned, and such recommendations as may be necessary,<lb/>
due to the change of conditions, be made.&rdquo;</p>
<p>None of the above recommendations was carried out, save the <unclear>stock-</unclear><lb/>
ing with top-minnows (<hi>gambusia</hi>). The Power Company <unclear>claims</unclear> they did not<lb/>
get the written recommendations.</p>
<p>During the Fall of the first year of this uncleared pond, there<lb/>
was a decided rise in the prevalence of malaria in the territory<lb/>
contiguous thereto. The following summer and Fall (1922), this prev-<lb/>
alence reached epidemic proportions. Several investigators for the<lb/>
State Board of Health visited the community, made rapid surveys of<lb/>
the shores of the pond, house-to-house canvass to determine the<lb/>
amount of malaria and supplied quinine to the people.</p>
<p>As to the prevalence of malaria, it was ascertained that of a<lb/>
population of 199, approximately 176 had malaria, with one death.</p>
<p>Toward the late season of 1922 there was a rather heavy infes-<lb/>
tation of <unclear>hedges</unclear> with <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi>, but of the rapid exam-<lb/>
inations of the shores of the pond, comparatively little breeding<lb/>
was found. No extra-pond breeding was found to explain the infestiv-<lb/>
ity. The body of the pond was not sufficiently examined to base<lb/>
an opinion on as to the part it played in production.</p>
<p>It being the desire of the State Health Officer, Dr. S.W. Welch,<lb/>
that there be applied such knowledge as we now have, and may be<lb/>
able to acquire, to the prevention of malaria within the influ-<lb/>
ence of this and other ponds, I have selected this pond as one on<lb/>
which to conduct studies, including those of control methods, dur-<lb/>
ing the coming season.</p>
<p>Preliminary surveys have been made and memoranda concerning<lb/>
conditions and measures to be inaugurated submitted to <del>the</del><lb/>
Mr. G.H. Haslehurst, Chief State Sanitary Engineer, State Board of<lb/>
Health. These memoranda are respectfully submitted as a part of<lb/>
this report-- appended hereto, (Exhibit &ldquo;A&rdquo;)</p>
<p>When further data are collected, report of this project will<lb/>
be submitted on the prescribed blanks--&ldquo;Original Survey of Im-<lb/>
pounded Water&rdquo;.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>T.H.D. Griffitts,<lb/>
Epidemiologist</signed>.
Incl.2cc, 5p Mem.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="3" id="f01022003"/>
<p>Exhibit &ldquo;A&rdquo; Houston P.Co.</p>
<p>Memorandum to Chief Sanitary Engineer, G. H. <unclear>Haslehurst</unclear>,<lb/>
in re malaria investigation and prevention on pond of Houston<lb/>
Power Company, Little Choctawhatchee River, six miles south of<lb/>
Newton. - 2/24/23</p>
<p>1. Surveys made on this pond on February 6th, 20th, 21st,<lb/>
and 22nd, 1923, showed that there is free Anopheline breeding<lb/>
in practically all favorable places along the shores of the main<lb/>
body, as well as banks of islands.</p>
<p>On February 6th, it was not difficult dipping from the<lb/>
shore and 8 or 10-feet away from the shore in collections of<lb/>
flotage-particularly pine bark, pine needles, and small stick<lb/>
flotage, to find Anopheline larvae, all sizes, particularly those<lb/>
under three-fourths developed. The bight designated on the map<lb/>
as B1R (meaning bight 1 right bank), was found on February 6th,<lb/>
to be breeding very freely from 1 to 10 larvae at a dip in<lb/>
selected flotage collections. This was a cold rainy day and<lb/>
the main body of the pond was not examined.</p>
<p>On February 20th, just two weeks following the previous<lb/>
examination, in this same bight, breeding was found to be very<lb/>
free - might say profuse - approximately 60 larvae of all sizes<lb/>
and about 8 pupae were collected within about an hours time.<lb/>
On the previous morning isolated side pools were completely frozen<lb/>
over and ice skirted the banks of the pond so that the water, at<lb/>
the time of examination, was icy cold.</p>
<p>Following the right shore line from this bight upward,<lb/>
very little breeding was found in the old field with grassy<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01022004"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
banks, but in the protected bights where drifts and flotage<lb/>
were collected, both along the shore and 8 or 10-feet away,<lb/>
larvae of all sizes were collected.</p>
<p>This shore was examined on this side up to McSwain's<lb/>
Bridge. Many Gambusia were observed, ranging from one-half to<lb/>
full grown, and they were particularly active in the shallow water<lb/>
in the old field between B1R and B2R. However, they were noticed<lb/>
in smaller numbers in the wooded section.</p>
<p>Three streams that discharge into upper ends of<lb/>
bights on the right side of the pond between McSwain's bridge<lb/>
and (B1R) carry a great deal of sand. By removing some of the<lb/>
log and brush obstructions, these bights will be obliterated<lb/>
in a relative<add>ly</add> short time. This should be done.</p>
<p>2. Examination on the left shore and bights gave some-<lb/>
what similar results, but the heaviest breeding noted along the<lb/>
shore was <add>in</add> <unclear>BIR</unclear>.</p>
<p>3. <hi>Examination of the Body of the Pond</hi>. <hi>Wherever flotage</hi><lb/>
of pine bark, pine needles, and small stick flotage was collected<lb/>
against logs, particularly old logs that are growing grasses and<lb/>
weeds - and these can be found over a good portion of the pond -<lb/>
Anopheline production is taking place. Many large larvae and<lb/>
pupae were collected from such places and in many instances on<lb/>
submerging large pieces of pine bark, larvae wiggled away and<lb/>
a regular summer time collection was made.</p>
<p>NOTE: <hi>No Gambusia were noted any distance away from the shore.</hi></p>
<pb n="5" id="f01022005"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>4. <hi>Prevention of Anopheline Production.</hi> To remove<lb/>
the flotage necessary for prevention of Anopheline production<lb/>
on this pond would be so expensive that it would not be reason-<lb/>
able to expect the Power Company to do it. I do not believe<lb/>
it reasonably possible to prevent the entire production of<lb/>
Anophelines on this pond during the coming summer. The best<lb/>
that we can hope to accomplish, is a decided reduction in the<lb/>
production, and to this end, I would recommend the following:</p>
<p>(a) That brush and flotage along the shore of<lb/>
B1R be dragged out sufficiently far that it would not wash<lb/>
back into the lake.</p>
<p>NOTE. Breeding in this bight perhaps affects more people<lb/>
than that of any other single place. Other bights on the right<lb/>
bank and along the shore in the wooded section, where logs and<lb/>
brush are collecting flotage, should also be taken care of in<lb/>
the same way as B1R.</p>
<p>In addition, small brush for a few feet out in the<lb/>
water and, say 5-feet on the land, should be removed where<lb/>
necessary so that one can get through for inspecting the shore.<lb/>
This latter should be done only where necessary to facilitate<lb/>
inspections and the removal of collections of flotage ashore.</p>
<p>(b) The left bank should be similarly taken care<lb/>
of and only in places where there are log-jams and much flotage.</p>
<p>(c) In order to make it more nearly possible<lb/>
to inspect the body of this pond, and to facilitate the use of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01022006"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
<hi>paris green</hi>, it will be necessary to clean out a way for<lb/>
getting through with a boat. It is therefore recommended<lb/>
that an opening be made from the old channel or open part<lb/>
of the pond to the shore line on each side, say about 8 to<lb/>
10-feet wide, and these places spaced about 1000 feet apart<lb/>
from above the dam to McSwain's bridge. Much of this brush<lb/>
can be beaten down with a pole or paddle, but in many places,<lb/>
logs will have to be chopped into and turned around so as to<lb/>
allow the boat to get through. Aside from the immediate<lb/>
cleaning of <unclear>BIR</unclear>, it is suggested that the lateral channels<lb/>
be provided as soon as possible. <hi>We will attempt to devise<lb/>
a method of applying paris green to this pond just as soon<lb/>
as these runs are opened up.</hi></p>
<p>(d) The area of the pond above McSwain's bridge<lb/>
is certainly an A. Punctipennis breeding area and may produce<lb/>
Quadrimaculatus. At the present time, however, there is<lb/>
perceptible current for a short distance below the bridge.<lb/>
This area should be taken care of after the work on the lower<lb/>
portion of the pond is progressing.</p>
<p>(e) It is suggested that the Houston Power<lb/>
Company be advised that within the next two weeks this work<lb/>
be started, and that they notify you when they are ready, so<lb/>
that we may advise them on the ground in order that only the<lb/>
necessary work be done. Their Mr. Spigner was with me on the<lb/>
investigation - he should now be familiar in a general way <del>of</del><add>with</add><lb/>
the places requiring clearing and the way to do it. It is<lb/>
*These will be spaced as <hi>close as necessary</hi><lb/>
later on.<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01022007"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
not feasible to clean extensive areas - only the worst<lb/>
places at reasonable expense.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully submitted,</salute>
<signed>T. H. D. Griffitts,<lb/>
Epidemiologist,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service</signed>.
<del>1955*</del><lb/>
<hi>NOTE</hi>: Of the collection of larvae and pupae made on 2/20-21/23, there<lb/>
were developed <del>16</del><add>18</add> A. <hi>punctipennis</hi>-- <del>7</del><add>8</add> females and <del>7</del><add>10</add> males.<lb/>
THDG:E<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
