<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01021061">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, February 24, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01021061</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-02-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Coello, Carlos</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-02-24">February 24, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01021061</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, February 24, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson informs Carter that he has settled in Jacksonville, Florida and has started his own practice. He discusses an alleged case of Weil's Disease in Guayaquil, Ecuador.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-02-24">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, February 24, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01021061"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
1144 Oak Street,<lb/>
Jacksonville, Fla.<lb/>
<date value="1923-02-24">February,24,1923.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have been thinking of writing you ever since we<lb/>
arrived but, with the business of getting settled, looking for and office<lb/>
and the effort to take care of some of thewrok which the local men want me<lb/>
to do it has not seemed that the day had hours enough for what was to be<lb/>
done. Now we are almost settled in our house, which promises to be both<lb/>
comfortable and with sufficient &ldquo;lujo&rdquo;, in fact we have a place where we<lb/>
can and would be delighted to entertain both Dr. Carter and his charming<lb/>
daughter Laura, at any time which they see fit to notify us that they<lb/>
are coming. The weather is fine, the evenings cool enough to make one<lb/>
revel in the burning of pitchy pine knots in the fireplace, the only<lb/>
drawback to the latter procedure is that it is so demoralizing to work,<lb/>
one simply wants to sit lazily by gazing and dreaming.</p>
<p>The present indications for the work are most too good to be<lb/>
true. If it keeps up I shall have more work than I can take care of. The<lb/>
Profession have been most courteous, and the daily paper<del>s</del> has come out<lb/>
with the usual squib of what a h--- of a fellow I am and the miracles (?)<lb/>
accomplished. Seriously I can not complain of the reception to my &ldquo;home<lb/>
coming&rdquo; It has been five years and eight months from the time I left for<lb/>
my army service until I returned to take up residence again, and it has<lb/>
actually seemed like coming home.</p>
<p>I believe the work here can be made a real success. The doctors<lb/>
claim that it will only be limited by the amount of work I want to do. They<lb/>
say they have had no one in whom they have had full confidence since I left<lb/>
in 1917.</p>
<p>Now to come to something important. I have just received a letter<lb/>
from Dr. Rose with enclosures of copies of report on the Weil's disease in<lb/>
Guayaquil. I do not like the looks of things. I enclose the copy of my letter<lb/>
to Dr. Rose. I di not make an extra copy so will ask that you return this, as<lb/>
I have sort of gotten a habit of keeping copies of letters to him. As I said<lb/>
to Dr. Rose I wish that you and I could make a survey of that coast together.<lb/>
It ought to be done as the situation can yet be saved, but the delay should<lb/>
not be too long. I believe that we have a more vital interest in that coast<lb/>
so far as the yellow fever situation is concerned than any one else, and it<lb/>
is certainly worth while to the I.H.B. to have this thing done; but who is to<lb/>
do it? In a case of this kind unless you be one of the party I shall not feel<lb/>
altogather satisfied with the final report. Four case out of seven dying on<lb/>
or before the sixth day is not very characteristic of Weil's Disease, but is<lb/>
quite paralell to what we saw in Peru, No doubt you have seen the report which<lb/>
Dr. Coello sent to the Surgeon General, U.S.PH.S.</p>
<p>I have nothing new to write, do not seem to be able to get my mind<lb/>
of this report.</p>
<p>Our trip down was pleasant all the way, and the children as usual<lb/>
seemed to improve in health as we toured. We had a bit of rough road in South<lb/>
Carolina, about two miles of bad road near Oxford, N.C. and some small stretches<lb/>
between<del><unclear>xxxxxxxx</unclear></del> Savannah and Jacksonville, but nothing which was really diffi-<lb/>
cult to pass. We stayed in Savannah from Sunday to Wednesday, while there I<lb/>
called on your friend Dr. &ldquo;Bill&rdquo; Brunner, who like the rest of us is a great<lb/>
admirer of yours.</p>
<p>With the best of good wishes for you and Laura,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
