<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01021008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Charles W. Comstock to George Schobinger, September 11, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Comstock, Charles W.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01021008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-09-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Schobinger, George</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hackett, Lewis W.</name>
<name type="place">Fortaleza, Ceara (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Para (Brazil)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-09-11">September 11, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01021008</idno>
<title>Letter from Charles W. Comstock to George Schobinger, September 11, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Comstock describes possible yellow fever cases to Schobinger. All involve foreigners in Brazil. Comstock criticizes the local physicians' attitude and treatment of the cases.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-09-11">
<head>Letter from Charles W. Comstock to George Schobinger, September 11, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01021008"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
No. 213<lb/>
<dateline>
Fortaleza, <date value="1922-09-11">September 11, 1922</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George Schobinger<lb/>
Dwight P. Robinson &amp; Co., Inc.<lb/>
Caixa Postal 69<lb/>
Rio de Janeiro.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Schobinger:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of August 14 explaining your telegraphic inquiry for<lb/>
information about deaths reported to be due to yellow fever, arrived just as<lb/>
I was about to leave for the interior and had to wait until my return for a<lb/>
reply.</p>
<p>You can readily understand that we have very little real information<lb/>
about any of these cases, being dependent on the statements of the physicians,<lb/>
who are frequently at variance, and in no position to judge among them.</p>
<p>The first case that came to my attention was that of C.D. Ashmore,<lb/>
representative of the American Locomotive Co., who arrived here on May 6, 1921,<lb/>
and died May 31. Ashmore was not more than fifty years old (perhaps not more<lb/>
than forty-five) appeared robust and active and spoke of being in excellent<lb/>
health. He did not touch any alcoholic drink and had never been a drinking<lb/>
man. He was a moderate smoker, did not keep late hours and was not given any<lb/>
sort of dissipation or excess.</p>
<p>He lived at the Pensao Bitu. About ten days before his death he<lb/>
complained of not feeling quite right, and kept to his room for a day. Then<lb/>
he was out for a day or two, saying he felt better. Then he remained in his<lb/>
room for a couple of days, and H. B. Fisher (of the Baldwin Locomotive Works),<lb/>
who was also at the Bitu, called a physician. The physician thought the<lb/>
ailment slight, prescribed some treatment and did not call again until sent<lb/>
for two days later. Then a second physician was called in consultation. The<lb/>
day before his death, the physicians diagnosed the case as yellow fever, and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01021009"/>
<hi>Mr. George Schobinger, RIO DE JANEIRO</hi>:<lb/>
2.<lb/>
the following morning he was taken to the hospital where he died that<lb/>
afternoon.</p>
<p>There was an autopsy at which, we were told, six or seven<lb/>
physicians were present, and after which the certificate of death from<lb/>
yellow fever was prepared.</p>
<p>The viscers were sent to Rio, and the newspapers subsequently<lb/>
announced that the Federal sanitary authorities had decided that the<lb/>
case was not yellow fever.</p>
<p>I saw Ashmore two or three times during his illness, but he did<lb/>
not talk very rationally and I could not determine in my own mind how serious<lb/>
his illness was. The last time I saw him was on the morning of the day he died.<lb/>
At that time he seemed to be in a stupor and was not conscious of anyone's<lb/>
presence. Everytime I saw him he had a bilious, almost jaundiced appearance.</p>
<p>Mr. H. B. Fisher may be able to tell you something more of this<lb/>
case, but I do not see how you can get anything which would be of value to<lb/>
the Rockefeller Institute except from the reports of the physicians.</p>
<p>The next death was that of an Englishman named Ritson, a salesman<lb/>
for Gold Medal Flour. I never saw this man, and heard little of his illness,<lb/>
but I think it was not called yellow fever by anyone. His death was assigned<lb/>
to some affection of the liver.</p>
<p>The third was Walsh. You know quite as much of his case as I do<lb/>
He complained of not feeling well on Friday, but stayed at his work through<lb/>
Saturday. No one thought it worth while to call a physician until Sunday.<lb/>
The physician said it was nothing. On Monday he still thought the illness<lb/>
slight. On Tuesday he said the patient must be taken to Fortaleza at once.<lb/>
Wednesday he was taken to Lavras and on Thursday morning he died on the train.<lb/>
The two physicians, one who accompanied Walsh from Sao Goncalo and one at<lb/>
Iguatu, gave the cause of death as &ldquo;grippe intestinal&rdquo;. They insisted upon<lb/>
burial within two hours because they said the disease was very infectious.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01021010"/>
<p><hi>Mr. George Schobinger, RIO DE JANEIRO:</hi></p>
<p>3.</p>
<p>The fourth case was McGuckin. He left here on January 22, 1922,<lb/>
in good health. He was, as you know, a robust, strong man. At Tutoya,<lb/>
about thirty hours from here, he complained of chills down his spine. The<lb/>
ship's doctor put him to bed and that night he was delirious. At Para<unclear>,</unclear> on<lb/>
the 27th, the doctor on the Polycarp and the one on the ship to which he was<lb/>
to transfer (the &ldquo;<unclear>Stephen</unclear>&rdquo;) diagnosed the case as yellow fever. He was<lb/>
taken to the isolation hospital at Para, where he died on the morning of<lb/>
February 7th. He was attended in Para by Dr. Carlos Ornstein and by the<lb/>
physicians of the public health department. The cause of death was assigned<lb/>
as &ldquo;peste <unclear>pneumonia</unclear>&rdquo;.</p>
<p>You may remember Day, who was employed for a time on our work<lb/>
here and afterward went to Piranhas. During my absence in Para in February,<lb/>
Day sailed from here for Recife. I later received a letter from the American<lb/>
Consul at Recife advising that Day died of yellow fever the day after leaving<lb/>
the steamer. I have no other information about this case.</p>
<p>At Sao Goncalo, G. W. <unclear>Kaill</unclear> was taken ill in the same way as Welsh<lb/>
a short time after the latter's death. There is no doubt in my mind that<lb/>
his life was saved by the prompt attendance of Dr. Jose Frota who went up<lb/>
from here. I do not know how Dr. Frota diagnosed the case. Dr. Frota attended<lb/>
both cases and diagnosed both as yellow fever.</p>
<p>W. D. Crider, Superintendent of operation of our cement mill,<lb/>
arrived here May 30th, 1922. He had been here only a short time when he was<lb/>
taken ill. The physician diagnosed his case as &ldquo;grippe intestinal&rdquo; and seemed<lb/>
to think that he had no further obligation, having given a name to the disease.<lb/>
In less than a week Crider was a more living skeleton, although a strong, robust<lb/>
man when he arrived. Only the most careful nursing by a man who stayed by him<lb/>
day and night saved his life. He was a month in recovering his strength.<lb/>
Crider never drinks, smokes very little and does not dissipate his energies in<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01021011"/>
4.<lb/>
<hi>Mr. George Schobinger, RIO DE JANEIRO</hi>:<lb/>
any way. He is probably in the late forties in age.</p>
<p>A few weeks ago a young Englishman named Walker, whom I did not<lb/>
know, complained one Saturday evening that he did not feel well. The<lb/>
following Wednesday evening at six o'clock he died. The physician called<lb/>
it yellow fever. The local head of the &ldquo;Prophylaxia Rural&rdquo;, after an<lb/>
autopsy and a bacteriological investigation, said it was not yellow fever<lb/>
but the &ldquo;peste&rdquo;, whatever that means.</p>
<p>The physicians here seem to be all alike in one respect. They<lb/>
think they have done their duty when they give a name to the patient's<lb/>
ailment. If another calls the disease by a different name they will argue for<lb/>
a month about the name. The treatment and whether the patient recovers are<lb/>
unimportant points.</p>
<p>We know only this: that there is some form of intestinal fever that<lb/>
attacks very suddenly, especially unacclimated foreigners, and that it proves<lb/>
fatal within a few days unless the patient is unusually fortunate. Whether they<lb/>
call it yellow fever or toothache seems to me unimportant. They do little to<lb/>
cure it and nothing to prevent it. If the physicians know why one patient re-<lb/>
covers and another dies, they seem to think it is a State secret. They never<lb/>
by any chance give the rest of us the benefit of the information so that we may<lb/>
profit by it in the next case.</p>
<p>I do not believe the contents of this letter will be of much use to<lb/>
Dr. Hackett, but this is all we really know, and it is worse than useless for<lb/>
a layman to speculate on such matters. If you or Dr. Hackett can think of<lb/>
anything further which would be useful and which we may be able to find out, I<lb/>
shall be glad to follow up any suggestions.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours truly,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) C.W.C.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
