<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01021027">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, February 4, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01021027</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-02-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Scannell, E.J.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Panuco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tuxpam (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Progreso (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-02-04">February 4, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01021027</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, February 4, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor reports extensively on the yellow fever campaign in Mexico.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-02-04">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, February 4, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01021027"/>
<opener>
<unclear>N. H. B</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Oficina</unclear> de <unclear>Sanided.</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Merida Lucatan</unclear> Mexico.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1923-02-04">February 4th. 1 9 2 3.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del> A copy of your letter to Mr. LePrince in answer<lb/>
to his without date, comes to me this morning. The article to which<lb/>
LePrince refers is my final report on yellow fever control in Merida<lb/>
and which was published in the Journal (American) of Tropical Medicine<lb/>
in November last.</p>
<p>I did not know that the Board had authorized the pub-<lb/>
lication of this report. When reprints are received I will send one om<lb/>
to you.</p>
<p>Doctor White passed through Progreso yesterday on his<lb/>
way to the States and no doubt you will soon see him and he will give<lb/>
at first hand the status of the campaign which seems to me to be going<lb/>
along very nicely.</p>
<p>Last month there was a case reported from the oil fields<lb/>
near Panuco. Dr. White considers it very doubtful but the case will I<lb/>
believe be officially announced as yellow fever. The entire area around<lb/>
Panuco and extending to Tuxpam is I understand to be gone over again by<lb/>
Dr. Scannell and this inspection should prove to be very interesting.</p>
<p>I have discussed with Dr. White, and I think he agrees<lb/>
with me, that we have <add>reached</add> a period in the campaign where a laboratory and a<lb/>
good laboratory man would be of inestimable aid, more especially a man<lb/>
that has been trained under Noguchi and cando the <unclear>Pffifier</unclear> reaction.<lb/>
Do you regard this test as postive indetermining whether <del>on</del><add>one</add> has had<lb/>
yellow fever? The Trager case <unclear>clinically</unclear> was considered as <unclear>a heavey</unclear> e.a.<lb/>
infection yet Noguchi reports a positive Pfiffer whereas the Coss case<lb/>
was finally diagnosed as Y.F. and Noguchi reports a negative Pfiffer.<lb/>
<unclear>If</unclear> this reaction is reasonably accurate it will be of great aid to us<lb/>
here especially when the malaria season begins again.</p>
<p>Progreso and some other towns have experienced an increase<lb/>
of malaria cases <add>in</add> the latter of 1922 and there were quite a few deaths in<lb/>
very young children and very old people. The type was tertian withall the<lb/>
classical symptoms, herpes, enlarged spleen, vomiting of greatquanitities of<lb/>
bile but no blood. There followed profound anemia in some cases and a<lb/>
jaundice which was more marked in the sclerae. The unfortunate part of<lb/>
this outbreak was that the poor people had no money to buy quinine and the<lb/>
municipalities would <unclear>not</unclear> furnish it.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01021028"/>
<p>C1<lb/>
B22</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>I have completed a second inspection trip of the interior towns and<lb/>
am unable to find or hear of any cases resembling yellow fever and aswe<lb/>
have had an increased movement of people from the highlands og Mexico and<lb/>
developments amongst them I am inclined to think that the situation here<lb/>
has been dominated. We are not however relaxing our work in the least and<lb/>
to keep going here at top speed so long as there is a case anywhere in Mexico.</p>
<p>The more I <del><unclear></unclear></del> study the stegomyia in relation to the aljibe the more<lb/>
convinced am I that the aljibe is beyond doubt the ideal breeding place<lb/>
for this specie of mosquito, and wherever the fish die in analjibe <del><unclear>and</unclear></del> the<lb/>
stegomyia seems to know it and at once pounces upon the aljibe and lay<lb/>
a batch of eggs, never have I found an aljibe breeding mosquitoes with a<lb/>
mojarra in it. Unfortunately many people take the fish out and before we<lb/>
know what has happened in that aljibe, <add><unclear>it is breeding</unclear></add> we now test out each aljibe on each<lb/>
cycle of inspection by dropping a small piece of tortilla or white bread into<lb/>
it and if the mojarra is living it will dart after the material, if not we<lb/>
order another fish to be placed therein, and thus make sure of that con-<lb/>
tainer.</p>
<p>Did I write you that the Stegomyia will not deposit eggs in Lejia when<lb/>
the lejia is in a copper container. It is a fact they will not. I asked<lb/>
Richardson, our Inspector at Tampico to paint the inside of <unclear>a</unclear> tin container<lb/>
with copper paint and note the results. He did and for a period of one<lb/>
month did not observe any mosquitos in that container. Before using<lb/>
copper paint I suggested the use of pieces of copper in the lejia and the<lb/>
results were very encouraging but the trouble appears to be the indifference<lb/>
of the people to place the copper when making new lejia. Richardson has<lb/>
noted that some houseswives were using using pieces of orange or lime skins<lb/>
for the purpose of keeping the 'moscas' out of the lejia and they claim that<lb/>
it can be done <add><unclear>with</unclear></add> this. In Merida we <add><unclear>are</unclear></add> recommending to the people that all containers<lb/>
other than copper receptacles, to place pieces of orange or lime skins there-<lb/>
in and to my surprise they are doing it as they claim that these fruit skins<lb/>
increase the life of the lejia, this maybe the solution to the lejia prob-<lb/>
lem. I hope so.</p>
<p>I will be <unclear>leaving</unclear> Merida this month to go to Colima to close that<lb/>
office as Dr. Cassasus has reported to Dr. White that the former endemic<lb/>
center is now eliminated and Dr. White sees no need of continuing the station,<lb/>
after this I will make <unclear>t</unclear> trip to Nueva Lareua, Matamoras, Ciudad Victoria<lb/>
and adjoining places for purpose of inspecting same.</p>
<p>I have a lot of data, epidemiological, which I will try to work up into <unclear>a</unclear><lb/>
readable paper later in the year and am wondering if you would do me the<lb/>
great favor of reading and critising it before I send it in. The Mexican<lb/>
situation has been vastly different, not in the fundamentals, but in <del><unclear>the</unclear></del> area<lb/>
infected and the rapidity and ease with which <del><unclear>in</unclear></del> the infection has travelled<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01021029"/>
-3-<lb/>
from place to place. The infection has gone around in a circle as it were,<lb/>
first as a mild type which at times was quite completely masked by the<lb/>
malaria infection and only coming to our notice when it reached the large<lb/>
centers. It appears to me that there have been many temporary endemic<lb/>
centers that we have no knowledge of whatever and in <unclear>in</unclear> collecting data of<lb/>
these sparsely setlled areas I am quite convinced that there operated the<lb/>
factor<del>s</del>, unnoticed by anyone, of a constant movement of a very small number of<lb/>
people to these temporary endemic centers such as I have <unclear>observee</unclear> in the<lb/>
oil fields where the geoligists go into new country establish temporary<lb/>
headquarters which becomes a sort of hotel for people passing thru that<lb/>
region. You know that geologist are watched and when they leave headquarters<lb/>
they are followed first by native spies, then <del><unclear>wait</unclear></del> by white men and in due<lb/>
time there is a constant stream of non-immunes, going into an area that was<lb/>
hardly spoken of before their event.</p>
<p>Somyime ago you sent me a copy of your <unclear>latest</unclear> writing, for Nelson's loose<lb/>
leaf medical library, on yellow fever in which you divide endemiicity<lb/>
as follows: Endemic and Permanently Endemic, Do you still hold to this<lb/>
division? Doesn't the word <add><unclear>endemic</unclear></add> as you are using <add>it</add> carry with it the idea, to the<lb/>
average person, of greater or longer <del>p</del>permanency than would the term Temporary<lb/>
Endemicity or temporarily endemic; and doesn't custon sanction the inference<lb/>
to mean permanency?</p>
<p>In your future writings will you <del><unclear>xxxx</unclear></del> refer to the 'stegomyia' as the Aedes<lb/>
Egyptus of Calopus? Would it be better to <unclear>drop</unclear> the name 'stegomyia' <unclear>alto-<lb/>
gether.</unclear> I do not like to do it for the reason that in Latin America the<lb/>
intelligent part of the public know the 'stegomyia' and its relation to<lb/>
yellow fever, and therefore it is easier for us in publicity to convey to<lb/>
the public what we are doing.</p>
<p>Refering to mosquito indices I am of the opinion that the Deposit index<lb/>
is of more value to the Director of a campaign in the early weeks of his<lb/>
work and once the situation has been controlled a <hi>pupaeindex</hi> should be<lb/>
started, as it is at that time the Director should know somthing definitely<lb/>
about the adult production and the larvae index really does not tell him<lb/>
much of anything because all the larvae noted will presumably be destroyed<lb/>
by the Inspector finding them whereas with a pupae index you really get some<lb/>
thing tangible but not <unclear>necssarily</unclear> correct data. The more accurate data on<lb/>
adult production will come from a recheck of a district by a special man<lb/>
and for this purpose I always try to nominate a Revisador and at intervals<lb/>
I recheck the Revisador myself.</p>
<p>On the development of an organization in yellow fever campaign<lb/>
In a phamphlet/which I have submitted to the Home and suggested publication<lb/>
I stress the point that the mosquito indices is not to be relied upon in<lb/>
<unclear>arriving</unclear> at a decision <del><unclear></unclear></del> as to the presence or absence of<lb/>
yellow fever in a community. Hereafter I am not using the <del><unclear></unclear></del> term safety-<lb/>
index, it is misleading, I may use the term 'relative safety-index' meaning<lb/>
thereby that a stage in the campaign has been reached indicating that the<lb/>
stegomyia has been reduced a favorable minimum as based on the indices of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01021030"/>
-4-<lb/>
of other countires hwere anti-larvae measures against the stegomyia have<lb/>
been practiced but will lay emphasis on the fact the index of one community is<lb/>
not accurate criteria for another community.</p>
<p>Lyster when in charge of the Mexican campaign was wont to stress the point<lb/>
that endemicity and I suppose he meant permanent <unclear>endemicity,</unclear> was only possible<lb/>
in large centers. I think I have seen evidence here in Mexico <unclear>where</unclear> endemicity<lb/>
lasting several years in relatively small communities kept up by the constant<lb/>
stream of non-immunes, never in large numbers at any one time, but at the<lb/>
right intervals to keep the infection alive. What I am trying to get at is that<lb/>
the general impression has been and is that endemicity can only be established<lb/>
in large communities whereas my idea is that endemicity is determined in a great<lb/>
measure by the movement of the people with-out regard as to numbers and in a small <unclear><add>community</add></unclear><lb/>
the interval of arrival <del>is the</del> of the non-immunes is <del>the</del><add>a</add> principal factor <unclear>in</unclear><lb/>
maintaining endemicity in that small community. The 'wall of immunity' mentioned<lb/>
by Giteras is protection to the new-comerin proportion to the number of people<lb/>
making up that 'wall' which are relatively few in the average small town in<lb/>
Mexico where the vast majority of homes are detached and <del><unclear></unclear></del> social inter<lb/>
course scant. All of which brings us to the point of whether, in Mexico, it<lb/>
would not have been the right thing to have started sweeping our areas from<lb/>
the begining of the campaign rather than to have depended upon the self-elimina<lb/>
tion of the infection in the small community while we were working in the so-<lb/>
called 'key-centers'. The fact has been that the infection <del><unclear></unclear></del> was flourish<lb/>
ing in small communities, in a mild form to begin with, near our key centers and<lb/>
we did not know it and these communities were closeenough or rather the <unclear>cummica</unclear><lb/>
tion was that easy that the infection went around in a circle and would <add>have</add> kept<lb/>
up indefinitely had it not <del><unclear></unclear></del> assumed the severe type of virulency and there was<lb/>
no mistaking the diagnosis.</p>
<p>I am returning LePrince's letter to you.</p>
<p>When you have the time I will be glad to receive your opinion on the points<lb/>
brought up here and as I am to do some travelling over the country this year<lb/>
your letter should be addressed to the Home Office.</p>
<p>With all good wishes and the kindliest personal regards,</p>
<closer>
<salute>I am, as ever, your friend</salute>
<signed>M.E. Connor</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
