<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01023001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Summary of Progress Yellow Fever From October 1, 1922 to April 1, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01023001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-04-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Connor, M.E.</name>
<name type="person">Scannell, E.J.</name>
<name type="person">Houle, E.C.</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Payta [Peru?]</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-04-01">April 1, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01023001</idno>
<title>Report: Summary of Progress Yellow Fever From October 1, 1922 to April 1, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The writer reports on progress in yellow fever work. Pathology, mortality, sanitation measures, epidemiology and the locations of recent outbreaks are all mentioned.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-04-01">
<head>Report: Summary of Progress Yellow Fever From October 1, 1922 to April 1, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01023001"/>
<p>Summary of Progress<lb/>
Yellow Fever<lb/>
From October 1, 1922 to April 1, 1923.</p>
<p>From neither pathological nor clinical standpoint has there been<lb/>
any marked progress in our knowledge of yellow fever during the above in-<lb/>
terval. For <del>S</del><add>s</add>anitation and <del>E</del><add>e</add>pidemiology the showing is better.</p>
<p><hi>Pathology</hi>: Hoffman of Havana (8) states, and shows, that the histo-<lb/>
pathological lesions in certain organs and tissues (especially the liver<lb/>
and blood) of guinea pigs infected with <hi>Leptospira icteroides</hi> (Merida<lb/>
strain, originally isolated by Noguchi in 1919) are not at all similar to<lb/>
those produced by yellow fever in man. Grovas-Ferrin of Mexico City (10),<lb/>
also showing micro-photographs, using a strain from Vera Cruz, finds such<lb/>
lesions very similar. He suggests that the culture used by Hoffman is con-<lb/>
taminated.</p>
<p>The writer of Sitjar's paper (12)--it is a translation of one by Borges<lb/>
Vieyra of S&atilde;o Paula, Brazil--was unable at Nazareth to verify Noguchi's<lb/>
findings, either bacteriological or immuniological. He frankly admits that<lb/>
the absence of ice, in a hot climate, and other difficulties incident to<lb/>
the environment, made a negative result of little significance.</p>
<p>To the writer, the most significant recent determination on this ques-<lb/>
tion, the etiological role of <hi>L. icteroides</hi>, is the frequent positive im-<lb/>
muniological reaction given by the blood of men recently recovered from<lb/>
yellow fever with <hi>L. icteroides.</hi> That with <hi>L. ictero</hi>-<hi>haemorrhagica</hi>has<lb/>
been negative. If this reaction is shown to be universal, or even ex-<lb/>
tremely general, it will be (a) evidence of value on this question and (b)<lb/>
a laboratory method of diagnosis of the disease recovered from fairly prac-<lb/>
ticable under field conditions--an inestimable boon to sanitarians.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01023002"/>
<p>sanitarians.</p>
<p><hi>Clinically.</hi> Nothing new has been added which we can accept.<lb/>
The figures given by Anigstein (1) on the case mortality of yellow fever,<lb/>
whites 94%: Blacks 64%, would, indeed, mark a new departure from the teach-<lb/>
ings of any modern clinician; but they are much too high, as the rate given<lb/>
by Carter (2)--7%--as occurring in Payta, 1920, is too low for the usual<lb/>
average. The case mortality in hospital among the &ldquo;Gold Roll&rdquo; employees,<lb/>
Americans, British, French etc. on the Canal Zone in 1905 was 26.3% and<lb/>
this was a decidedly severe type of fever: the patients were all newly ar-<lb/>
rived from colder countries and adults, among whom the mortality is decid-<lb/>
edly greater than among the general population with a reasonable number of<lb/>
children. That the fever was mainly among people under twenty--the older<lb/>
people being immune from a previous epidemic about 18 years before--was<lb/>
one of the factors in the low mortality at Payta. The normal mortality<lb/>
among blacks is extremely small.</p>
<p>(See page 3)</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01023003"/>
<p>small.</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><hi>Sanitation</hi>. Much detail valuable to the sanitarian engaged in a cam-<lb/>
paign against yellow fever in an endemic focus, is given by the field-work-<lb/>
ers in Mexico. Connor's papers (3): (4): &amp; (5) are well worth reading to this<lb/>
end. Rightly he stresses fish-control wherever practicable, as do Carter (2)<lb/>
and Hanson in his Peruvian Campaign of 1921-22 (report not published) to the<lb/>
success of which it was the key. After trying many kinds all give the pre-<lb/>
ference to bottom-feeding minnows: <del>in</del> in Mexico the <hi>Mojarra (Aequidens rivu-<lb/>
latus</hi> (G) of the Cichlidae)--a small perch: in Peru the <hi>Life</hi> (<hi>Phygidium punctu-<lb/>
latum</hi> <unclear>puiral</unclear> (Eigenmenn), looking like a little cat-fish. (Foot note)<lb/>
______________________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) These determinations are by Dr. C. H. Eigenmann, University<lb/>
of Indiana. (End of foot note).</p>
<p>___________________________________________________________</p>
<p>This latter, indeed, feeds at the surface at night. Both are  hardy--<hi>Life</hi><lb/>
extremely so--and neither are apt to jump out of the container. Naturally,<lb/>
bottom feeders are not liable (a) to be injured by sudden changes of tem-<lb/>
perature, as during Northers in Mexico, or (b) to be washed out when the<lb/>
cisterns overflow--to both of which accidents top-feeders, the fish first<lb/>
used, are subject. Scannell (personal communication) has found Mojarra to<lb/>
to do well in deep (30 ft. or more) wells and that it was the only fish<lb/>
that he could depend on in such places.</p>
<p>Houle, of Empalme, Sonora, Mexico (unpublished report) has used a<lb/>
predatory aquatic insect, &ldquo;water boatmen&rdquo; (<hi><unclear>Notanecta</unclear></hi>, spec.)--also a bot-<lb/>
tom feeder--to advantage (a) in collections of water too small for fish<lb/>
(the west coast of Mexico is dry and water scarce) and (b) in the ashes-<lb/>
water of the laundresses, in which no fish will live, but which produces<lb/>
<hi>aegypti</hi> in profusion. The editor, however, regards the use of this in-<lb/>
sect as very limited, though useful in those limits. The control of breed-<lb/>
ing in this <hi>agua ceniza</hi> has been an important and a difficult problem in<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01023004"/>
in<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
Mexico and Central America. This water is too valuable to be thrown away--<lb/>
to do so would lead to hiding it--it cannot be oiled and fish will not live<lb/>
in it. We controlled it satisfactorily in Peru by the addition of soap,<lb/>
which was not objected to, and this will be tried in Mexico.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemiology</hi>. With this the papers of Peterson (11) and Dunn (6):<lb/>
most of Carter's (2) and much of Connor's (3: 4: and 5) are concerned. The<lb/>
points specially brought out <add>are:</add> (11) the spontaneous elimination of yellow<lb/>
fever from the Virgin Islands (St. Thomas especially used to be virulently<lb/>
infected) by the "failure of the human host--aegypti being extremely abun-<lb/>
dant there. In this connection Connor, in a personal communication, ex-<lb/>
presses the, tentative, opinion that yellow fever had been eliminated from<lb/>
Merida--by failure of the human host--before sanitary (mosquito control)<lb/>
work was undertaken, the extensive epidemics just previous thereto having<lb/>
exhausted the susceptible himan material. One can see how a marked in-<lb/>
crease of infection in a community receiving few immigrants <hi>might</hi> have<lb/>
the effect of thus leading to its own extinction! Connor (E) also notes<lb/>
the concentration and permanence of infection in endemic canters about<lb/>
hotels and the boarding houses of strangers.</p>
<p>We may note here too the formulation by Carter (Unpublishec Lectures,<lb/>
Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene), as the result of many observations: in<lb/>
various countries: for a number of years; of the obligatory limits (nega-<lb/>
tive) for <hi>aegypti</hi> breeding. &ldquo;The eggs of this species have not been found<lb/>
<del>to have been</del> deposited by the imago in any collection of water the sides<lb/>
of which <hi>at the water line</hi> consist <add>entirely</add> of mud.&rdquo; The editor is of the opinion<lb/>
that this limitation is not only generally but universally true and that<lb/>
<del>a knowledge</del><add>the acceptance</add> of it will, to an extent, simplify sanitary measures.</p>
<p><hi>Historical and Geographical.</hi> The abstract of Gouzien's paper (7)<lb/>
is so full that no comment is needed. It is only necessary to say that<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01023005"/>
that<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
after a period of over two and a half years, Sept. 11/19 to June 12/22,<lb/>
during which no yellow fever was reported from Africa it has again appear-<lb/>
ed there, scattered from the Gambia to the mouth of the Niger and over<lb/>
600 miles inland (on the Niger). Recent advices show it increasing.</p>
<p>In March a report was received, which was later verified, of an epi-<lb/>
demic of yellow fever at Bucaramanga, Colombia, a town slightly over 3,000 ft.<lb/>
above sea-level. No infection had been reported from this regional focus--<lb/>
in the South Caribbean--since 1917 (at Coro, Venezuela, by  Guiteras) and<lb/>
there was reason to hope that, with the lessened travel due to the Great<lb/>
War, this section had been freed from infection spontaneously. It will<lb/>
probably, this region now being decidedly prosperous with much travel in<lb/>
it, require much sanitary work--control of <hi>aegypti</hi> production--to eliminate<lb/>
it. Without this it will likely last indefinitely and extend.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
