<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01022028">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter and memorandum from Wenceslao Pareja to Wickliffe Rose, March 27, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Pareja, Wenceslao</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01022028</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-03-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Noboa, Carlo</name>
<name type="person">Coello, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Connor, Michael E.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-03-27">March 27, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01022028</idno>
<title>Letter and memorandum from Wenceslao Pareja to Wickliffe Rose, March 27, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Pareja discusses fever cases in Guayaquil and emphatically denies that they are yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-03-27">
<head>Letter and memorandum from Wenceslao Pareja to Wickliffe Rose, March 27, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01022028"/>
<opener>
Translated from the Spanish, HRM<lb/>
3-27-23<lb/>
HRM<lb/>
REPUBLIC OF ECUADOR<lb/>
BUREAU OF PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
<dateline>
Guayaquil,<lb/>
<date value="1923-03-27">March 27, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Wickliffe Rose,<lb/>
Director of the International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York City.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In reply to your letter of February 15, 1923, and<lb/>
in reference to the subject on hemorrhagic icterus, I shall have to<lb/>
amplify my previous report as follows:</p>
<p>During the middle of last year Dr. Carlo Noboa reported<lb/>
to the Medical-Surgical Society of this city that he had verified a case of<lb/>
spirochetosis <unclear>icterohemorrhagica</unclear>. I investigated the matter and Dr. Carlo<lb/>
Noboa showed me some slides with abundant spirochetes in the renal tissue<lb/>
which, he said, came from a guinea-pig inoculated with the blood of this<lb/>
patient.</p>
<p>After a few months Dr. Coello asked me how many cases of<lb/>
this disease had occurred in the city and we searched the hospital records,<lb/>
because this disease was not yet reportable. We found, in six hospital cases on<lb/>
record, the diagnosis of spirochetosis icterohemorrhagica, but without any<lb/>
experimental proof. Our hospital organization is so imperfect that neither<lb/>
clinical histories nor records are kept, so that any physician can make a<lb/>
capricious or fantastic diagnosis, even without performing an autopsy.</p>
<p>In view of this situation, I have addressed a circular<lb/>
to all physicians asking them to report to the Health Department any case<lb/>
of spirochetosis icterohemorrhagica or any similar disease which they might<lb/>
have in their private or hospital practice in order that it may be studied.<lb/>
Furthermore, I have organized a commission composed of the Dean of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01022029"/>
-2-<lb/>
Faculty of Medicine, the professors of internal pathology, bacteriology,<lb/>
hygiene, the President of the Medical-Surgical Society, and one physician<lb/>
of the Health Department, to study and determine the nature of infectious<lb/>
and contagious diseases in general and especially those which might be found<lb/>
to be communicable for the first time or that might be subject to quarantine,<lb/>
such as, yellow fever, exanthematous typhus, cholera, etc. The object of this<lb/>
board is to remove any doubt or avoid any discussion which might arise in<lb/>
this matter.</p>
<p>The circular sent to the doctors concerning the notification<lb/>
of cases of icterus was mailed at the beginning of January and up to the present<lb/>
time no suspected case has been reported.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, those facts have caused a certain feeling of<lb/>
anxiety in the Sanitary Service of the United States, because it has called<lb/>
attention to the high mortality resulting from cases of spirochetosis ictero-<lb/>
<unclear>hemorrhagica</unclear>. This has given rise to the suspicion that we are confronted<lb/>
with the reappearance of yellow fever. Guayaquil is not much trusted because<lb/>
it has been an endemic center for many years.</p>
<p>From the epidemiological point of view, I will have to call<lb/>
your attention to the fact that since 1919, that is, during the last four years,<lb/>
many non-immune foreigners and persons from the interior have come to Guayaquil,<lb/>
so that the attention of doctors has been attracted to this disease since many<lb/>
still doubt that the sickness which was considered proper to our climate could<lb/>
be eradicated by such <hi>simple measures</hi>, as, covering tanks and placing fishes<lb/>
in barrels. Nevertheless, during all this time no case has ever been confirmed.</p>
<p>It has repeatedly occurred, that whenever soldiers from the<lb/>
interior of the country came to Guayaquil, yellow fever reappeared. During the<lb/>
month of November 1922, many serious strikes occurred in this region <unclear>and</unclear> on this<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01022030"/>
-3-<lb/>
account about 1500 non-immune soldiers came to the city from the interior.<lb/>
These battalions remained here throughout the entire rainy <unclear>season</unclear>; in fact,<lb/>
they are still here. <hi>Not one soldier</hi> has ever been suspected. This is a<lb/>
strict examination of the facts. If we accept the axiom that spontaneous<lb/>
generation is impossible and that yellow fever may remain concealed in <hi>regions</hi><lb/>
where it is neither investigated nor sought for, consisting of several groups<lb/>
of towns or cities with little immigration and that a small number of unobserved<lb/>
or unconfirmed patients are preserving the endemic <hi>chain</hi> until typical cases<lb/>
are revealed, then the same thing does not happen in the large cities having<lb/>
considerable immigration and active commerce, like Guayaquil, where, on the<lb/>
average, two ships enter daily and where there is a Health Department which<lb/>
functions regularly. Under these conditions it is impossible for the disease<lb/>
to remain concealed for any length of time. On the other hand, in regard to<lb/>
the Stegomyia factor, its control is kept under the same, or perhaps even under<lb/>
better conditions than three years ago, because not only does the public any<lb/>
longer distrust the supervision, but <del><unclear>it</unclear></del> being convinced of its usefulness<lb/>
helps it efficiently and I am sure that the most careful survey would give<lb/>
us such a low index that even if a case of yellow fever should enter from<lb/>
the exterior, it would not spread.</p>
<p>In spite of these arguments, we are continuing to watch<lb/>
very closely cases of icterus, and, if unfortunately, any case should be<lb/>
<hi>confirmed</hi> as yellow fever by the above mentioned board, it would immediately<lb/>
be reported without reserve.</p>
<p>If this should be made an opportunity to have a man like<lb/>
Dr. Connor come here with the manifest or <hi>ostensible</hi> object of making a malaria<lb/>
and <unclear>uncinariesis</unclear> <hi>survey</hi> and at the same time to inquire, reservedly, if desired,<lb/>
what we are doing in regards to yellow fever, I should not consider this depressing<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01022031"/>
-4-<lb/>
on the contrary, I would like to have the man who did the work come here<lb/>
to see if we have preserved it.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I will have to inform you that on February<lb/>
26, 1923, I received the following cable: &ldquo;Balboa Heights- Dr. Wenceslao<lb/>
Pareja, Guayaquil- Seven cases ictero hemorrhagic fever with four deaths<lb/>
reported in Guayaquil, please cable accurate diagnosis these cases and<lb/>
statement whether or not yellow fever and if disease spreading. Fisher<lb/>
Chief Health Officer.&rdquo; I replied as follows: &ldquo;Colonel Fisher Chief Health<lb/>
Officer- Balboa. During 1922 one single case confirmed of ictero hemorrhagic<lb/>
fever coming from the interior, six cases merely suspected without proof<lb/>
but no suspected yellow fever recently, numerous foreigners enter, various<lb/>
battalions of soldiers from the interior, no suspected cases. Stegomyia<lb/>
index absolutely low, I guarantee Guayaquil to be immune, any cases<lb/>
would be reported without reserve. W. Pareja- Health Director.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01022032"/>
<p>Dr. Coello himself stated to me that he went to Balboa for the<lb/>
purpose of personally obtaining information on the subject. I have not<lb/>
as yet received further notice from Balboa, but no restrictions have been<lb/>
placed on the coming and going of steamships.</p>
<p>In regard to the questions proposed by Dr. Carter, I beg to<lb/>
reply as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. This question has already been cleared up by the information which<lb/>
I have submitted previously. The only verified case of hemorrhagic icterus<lb/>
was that of a native of the coast who was possibly immune from yellow fever.<lb/>
Of the other six, five are born in the mountains and one on the coast.</item>
<item>2. It is interesting to note that the six cases of hemorrhagic<lb/>
icterus, which were reported, came from localities situated at a great<lb/>
distance from one another; two of Guayaquil, one Daule (a good many hours<lb/>
up stream by steamer) one in Milagro (a distance of 34 Kilometers by<lb/>
railroad on the east side of the town) one in Barraganetal (a distance of<lb/>
69 Kilometers by railroad), another one in Bucay (87 Kilometers on the<lb/>
same line). No other cases occurred in the same house.</item>
<item>3. We think it most probable that hemorrhagic icterus is prevalent<lb/>
among us; this was shown in the records of Dr. Noguchi. There must be<lb/>
some isolated cases which have not been reported. The fact that some<lb/>
cases came from the country gives one to believe that the disease exists;<lb/>
only at first the illness was not diagnosed and it is possible that at<lb/>
that time it was taken for malaria on account of the symptoms; this latter<lb/>
disease was very prevalent throughout the entire region.</item>
<item>4. As I have already stated, no records are kept in our hospitals<lb/>
of the patients with the exception of a very brief note giving the name,<lb/>
age, nationality, the place from where the patient comes, state and<lb/>
diagnosis, formulated by the physician without further explanations.</item>
</list></p>
<pb n="6" id="f01022033"/>
<p>As a last point, I wish to express my personal opinion on the<lb/>
subject. Dr. Carbo Noboa, who is a young doctor and desirous of attracting<lb/>
attention in order to show his talent and activity, wanted to give resonance<lb/>
to his discovery in such a way that other physicians saw hemorrhagic icterus<lb/>
in cases that did not even have <unclear>a</unclear> remote resemblance, and without experimental<lb/>
proof, and were able to say that they too had seen cases of this disease.<lb/>
This may not sound very serious, but it occurs very frequently in our country.<lb/>
It is sufficient here to announce that a case of strange illness has been<lb/>
found to cause others to say that they have also seen the same thing. I<lb/>
remember when Dr. Noguchi showed the leptospira for the discovery of the<lb/>
disease to the doctors who assisted him in his laboratory, this same Dr.<lb/>
Noboa told me that he had found the same germ. The procedure in this<lb/>
matter has therefore not been serious.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Dr. W. Pareja<lb/>
Sanitary Director</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
