<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01021016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">The Conduct of the Yellow Fever Campaign in Vera Cruz and the Second Yellow Fever Zone, 1921-1922, by Bert W. Caldwell, July 30, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01021016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-07-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Vaughn, Emmett I.</name>
<name type="person">Connor, Michael E.</name>
<name type="person">Cuaron, Tomas</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Stubbs, A. R.</name>
<name type="person">Cassasus, Juan Graham</name>
<name type="person">Cross, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="place">Vera Cruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Papantla (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tuxpam (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Mexico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tehuantepec (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tabasco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Chiapas (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tuxtepec (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tierra (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Cosamaloapam (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tierra Blanca (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Alvarado (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">El Hule (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Ojitlan (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-07-30">July 30, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01021016</idno>
<title>The Conduct of the Yellow Fever Campaign in Vera Cruz and the Second Yellow Fever Zone, 1921-1922, by Bert W. Caldwell, July 30, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Caldwell reports on the Mexican yellow fever and antimalarial campaign, describing the cooperative efforts of the Mexicans and the Rockefeller Commission workers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-07-30">
<head>The Conduct of the Yellow Fever Campaign in Vera Cruz and the Second Yellow Fever Zone, 1921-1922, by Bert W. Caldwell, July 30, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01021016"/>
<p>THE CONDUCT OF THE YELLOW FEVER CAMPAIGN IN VERA CRUZ<lb/>
AND THE SECOND YELLOW FEVER ZONE,- 1921 - 1922.</p>
<p>- - - - - - - O - - - - - - -</p>
<p>The campaign for the control of the epidemic of yellow fever that<lb/>
spread over the area comprised in the Second Yellow Fever Zone, of which<lb/>
the city of Vera Cruz is the center, began in June 1920. During this<lb/>
year a total of 505 cases of yellow fever were reported in the whole of<lb/>
Mexico of which number two-thirds were reported from the city of Vera<lb/>
Cruz and the territory within a radius of 200 kilometers of that city.<lb/>
During the year 1921 a total of 123 cases were reported for the whole of<lb/>
Mexico of which number 75 were reported from Vera Cruz and contiguous<lb/>
territory. During the present year- 1922- but five cases have been<lb/>
reported in the Republic of which one was reported from the territory<lb/>
comprised in the Second Zone.</p>
<p>The campaign for control, which the Departamento de Salubridad<lb/>
Publica had conducted from June to December 1920, had produced excellent<lb/>
results and when the Comision Especial began its work in the city of<lb/>
Vera Cruz in the month of January 1921, the epidemic was being rapidly<lb/>
placed under control, due to the efficient service performed by Doctor<lb/>
Juan Graham Cassasus and his associates.</p>
<p>Outside of Vera Cruz the whole area was badly infected. To the<lb/>
North Papantla and Tuxpam, which at that time were included in this Zone,<lb/>
were experiencing formidable epidemics, and a few cases had been previ-<lb/>
ously reported in the city of Tampico. To the West the small cities and<lb/>
towns along the lines of the Interoceanic and Mexican Railroads were<lb/>
reporting cases, while practically every town and hacienda along the<lb/>
Papaloapam Valley from the Oaxacan mountains to the Gulf Coast was badly<lb/>
infected. Puerto Mexico and the towns along the Tehuantepec Railroad<lb/>
were supposedly free from the disease although previously one or two<lb/>
cases had been reported from Puerto Mexico.</p>
<p>The entire area was carefully surveyed and the program for the<lb/>
campaign was decided upon. That program, with but few minor changes,<lb/>
has been consistently adhered to in this Second Zone. It was decided to<lb/>
throw a line of brigades across the Isthmus of Tehuantepec located in<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01021017"/>
located in<lb/>
each of the important centers except the city of Tehuantepec and at a<lb/>
distance of 75 kilometers south of any reported infection, not only to<lb/>
reduce the stegomyia incidence along this Railroad, but to prevent, if<lb/>
possible any infection invading the States of Tabasco and Chiapas from<lb/>
the infected area in Vera Cruz and in the &ldquo;tierra caliente&rdquo; portion of<lb/>
the State of Oaxaca, as well as to prevent any accidental infection from<lb/>
invading Vera Cruz from the south. These brigades were outposts to pre-<lb/>
vent further spread of the infection and have functioned continuously<lb/>
as such.</p>
<p>In the Papantla-Tuxpam-Gutierrez Zamora area to the north the<lb/>
problem was more difficult. Here an extensive and a commercially im-<lb/>
portant area was heavily infected and epidemics of sizable proportions<lb/>
were raging in Papantla and Tuxpam, and the towns and haciendas along<lb/>
the Tuxpam and Gutierrez Zamora Rivers were reporting cases. Alamo, San<lb/>
Isidro and San Rafael with other small settlements reported positive<lb/>
cases as late as November 1921.</p>
<p>In this area permanent brigades were established in Papantla,<lb/>
Tuxpam, Gutierrez Zamora and Alamo, while Brigadas Volantes swept through<lb/>
the smaller places and haciendas and the epidemic was brought under con-<lb/>
trol. By the end of May both Tuxpam and Papantla were free from the<lb/>
disease, but in the territory between these places cases occurred as<lb/>
late as November 1921.</p>
<p>In July Doctor Emmet I. Vaughn took charge of this area with head-<lb/>
quarters at Tuxpam, and until September 1st 1921, conducted an intensive<lb/>
campaign, leaving for Belize during the first week in September. By the<lb/>
first of December the entire area had been freed from the disease and<lb/>
since January 1st of the present year, when Doctor M. E. Connor took<lb/>
charge of the First Zone, to which this territory had been attached,<lb/>
the effective campaign which he has conducted has prevented any recur-<lb/>
rence of the disease.</p>
<p>In Tampico the Associated Oil Managers, under the able direction<lb/>
of Doctor Tomas Cuaron and Mr. Le Prince, the distinguished Sanitary En-<lb/>
gineer, had instituted a decidedly effective campaign. The work which<lb/>
these two sanitarians, in conjunction with Doctor A.R. Stubbs, accom-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01021018"/>
Stubbs, accom-<lb/>
plished in Tampico city and the adjacent territory was the outstanding<lb/>
feature of the yellow fever campaign in Mexico. It was in Tampico that<lb/>
the efficiency of fish was demonstrated for the first time in Mexico and<lb/>
the service they rendered freed Tampico from yellow fever and kept it<lb/>
free. This accomplishment was of the greatest possible importance to<lb/>
the remainder of the Gulf Coast.</p>
<p>In July 1921 the Associated Oil Managers retired from active par-<lb/>
ticipation in the campaign and the territory was attached to the Vera<lb/>
Cruz Division, with Dr. Cuaron in charge of Tampico and Dr. Monroe as<lb/>
his assistant in charge of work in the field. From January 1st this<lb/>
territory, north of the 20th degree of latitude, was comprised in the<lb/>
First Yellow Fever Zone and Dr. M. E. Connor assumed direction. The<lb/>
results of his work during the first half of the present year in the<lb/>
Tampico area justified him in turning the area over to the representa-<lb/>
tives of the Departamento de Salubridad Publica on July 1st 1922.</p>
<p><unclear>Protested</unclear> in this manner by a line of outpost brigades 75 kilome-<lb/>
ters south of any reported infection, and with an area free from the di-<lb/>
sease to the north of the 20th degree of latitude, the problem centered<lb/>
around the city of Vera Cruz. Intensive work was instituted in January<lb/>
1921 in the city and in the adjacent territory and no halt has been per-<lb/>
mitted since that time. Continuing the successful campaign which my<lb/>
efficient predecessor, Doctor Juan Graham Cassasus, had conducted, the<lb/>
mosquito incidence was rapidly reduced and further spread of the infec-<lb/>
tion in the city was inhibited. On March 16th 1921 the last case of yel-<lb/>
low fever originating in Vera Cruz was reported and since that time there<lb/>
never has been a stegomyia incidence sufficiently high to permit secon-<lb/>
dary infection in the city. The mosquito incidence has been maintained<lb/>
remarkedly low for the past twelve months, with the stegomyia incidence<lb/>
practically nil. Cases originating outside of the city have been brought<lb/>
to Vera Cruz during the year 1921 for hospital care and medical treat-<lb/>
ment, and some of these cases have been reported and charged to Vera<lb/>
Cruz. The last case of this kind was the Doctor Cross case reported<lb/>
December 23rd of last year.</p>
<p>With Vera Cruz free, our next problem and decidedly more import-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01021019"/>
more import-<lb/>
ant was to clean up an area which presents all of the characteristics<lb/>
and every requisite of an endemic area and from which the city of Vera<lb/>
Cruz and other cities in the State of Vera Cruz have undoubtedly been<lb/>
infected in years past.</p>
<p>This area is along the fertile valley of the Papaloapam River<lb/>
extending from the Oaxacan mountains to the Gulf, a distance of 220<lb/>
kilometers, and includes the contiguous territory from Tierra to Tuxte-<lb/>
pec, thence to Cosamaloapam. It is along this river that the large sugar<lb/>
haciendas of the State, the immense banana plantations and the important<lb/>
tobacco and cotton haciendas of the Valle Nacional and the adjacent val-<lb/>
leys are located. Commercially and agriculturally it is the most im-<lb/>
portant section of the State of Vera Cruz. These large industries<lb/>
annually import thousands of laborers from the States of Oaxaca, Puebla,<lb/>
Michoacan, San Luis Potosi and other States of the Central Plateau who<lb/>
sweep through the cities of Tuxtepec, Cosamaloapam, Tierra Blanca, Tla-<lb/>
cotalpam, Alvarado and other cities or come by rail through Vera Cruz,<lb/>
they and their women and children, every one of whom is non-immune to<lb/>
yellow fever. They roam from ingenio to ingenio, from hacienda to ha-<lb/>
cienda, and in prosperous times this movement of non-immune labor is<lb/>
sufficiently large to keep the area constantly infected and to establish<lb/>
and maintain its endemicity.</p>
<p>Along the course of this important valley for a distance of 250<lb/>
kilometers a population of 200,000 exists and important commercial and<lb/>
population centers are within easy communication. For a large part of<lb/>
the distance the homes of &ldquo;colonos&rdquo; line either side of the river bank<lb/>
and the villages are frequently continuous.</p>
<p>In July 1921 the first case from this area was reported at Cosa-<lb/>
maloapam, a city of some ten thousand people. The patient lived in a<lb/>
house adjacent to the &ldquo;cuartel&rdquo; and the soldiers became infected. From<lb/>
this focus the soldiers carried the disease from house to house and from<lb/>
Cosamaloapam to nearby cities and by the end of July Tierra Blanca, Chan-<lb/>
guiltanguis, Tlacotalpam, Otatitlan and Alvarado were reporting cases.<lb/>
From Tierra Blanca the infection spread north and cases were introduced<lb/>
into Cordoba, Orizaba, Nogales and Paso del Macho. Due to the measures<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01021020"/>
the measures<lb/>
that were instituted by Medico Delegados, Dr. Angeles in Cordoba and Dr.<lb/>
Hopper in Orizaba, no secondary cases occurred in either of these cities.</p>
<p>Our campaign at once took a very wide range. It became necessary<lb/>
to limit the disease within the already wide area which had been invaded.<lb/>
It was determined to clean up the Papaloapam Valley in a manner that<lb/>
would prevent a reappearance of the disease after we had once wiped it<lb/>
out. Brigades were established in each of the important population cen-<lb/>
ters and in addition Brigadas Volantes were sweeping both banks of the<lb/>
river, house by house, from Alvarado on the coast to El Hule, 200 kilo-<lb/>
meters inland.</p>
<p>It was at this period of the campaign that a serious error of<lb/>
omission was made, in that the valley of the Papaloapam River above El<lb/>
Hule and on through Tuxtepec was not covered in our campaign. The Vocal<lb/>
of the Commission in charge of the campaign in this area had made a sur-<lb/>
vey and had recommended that intensive work be done from Tuxtepec to the<lb/>
upper reaches of the river covering the haciendas and municipalities to<lb/>
the west of that city, and had included in his &ldquo;presupuesto&rdquo; the esti-<lb/>
mate for the brigades to be located for this purpose. But as no cases<lb/>
had been reported from this part of the Zone above El Hule it was final-<lb/>
ly determined not to institute work there until later.</p>
<p>Retribution for this error followed fast. In August the captain<lb/>
in command of the garrison at Ojitlan, a distance of 45 kilometers west<lb/>
of Tuxtepec was called to Tierra Blanca, which place had already been in-<lb/>
fected from Cosamaloapam. He returned to Ojitlan after a two days stay<lb/>
in Tierra Blanca, and on August 22nd came down with yellow fever and<lb/>
died on the 27th.</p>
<p>The municipality of Ojitlan is composed of some 8,000 people, of<lb/>
which 2,000 live in the village of Ojitlan. They are for the greater<lb/>
part Oaxacan Indians, who never leave their mountain homes except to go<lb/>
down to the haciendas to labor. With but very few exceptions they are<lb/>
non-immune to yellow fever and seemed to be particularly susceptible to<lb/>
attack. Among them, the disease once introduced, spread rapidly. In<lb/>
October the epidemic was reported through the Governor of the State of<lb/>
Oaxaca to the Departamento de Salubridad Publica and the Vocal in Charge<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01021021"/>
in Charge<lb/>
of the area was directed to investigate and take necessary action. The<lb/>
inspection was made on October 16th to October 20th 1921. Conditions<lb/>
were bad, the epidemic was at its peak and the morbidity rate was high.<lb/>
Intensive work was at once instituted. The disease burnt itself out and<lb/>
the work of our brigades prevented its recurrence. By the end of Decem-<lb/>
ber 1921 Ojitlan had ceased reporting cases and it has been free of the<lb/>
disease since that time.</p>
<p>From Ojitlan the disease spread down the valley through Laguna<lb/>
infecting the haciendas and finally reached Tuxtepec, where in December<lb/>
Dr. Cross contracted the disease, was brought to Vera Cruz for hospital<lb/>
care and died December 28th 1921.</p>
<p>Our work was now extended to cover the entire valley. The epi-<lb/>
demic was well under control. All known foci of infection were intensive<lb/>
ly worked and all potential foci were given careful attention by Brigadas<lb/>
Volantes. Permanent brigades continued their work in all of the more<lb/>
important places and in every city of consequence with the exception of<lb/>
two, San Andres de Tuxtla and Tehuantepec, our campaign was conducted<lb/>
vigorously.</p>
<p>Each of these places contain approximately 17,000 inhabitants.<lb/>
Work was not instituted in San Andres for the reason that the altitude<lb/>
protects the city from a high stegomyia incidence, nor in the city of<lb/>
Tehuantepec where in the opinion of the Director of the Commission no<lb/>
work was necessary at this time for the reason that the city had expe-<lb/>
rienced an epidemic of large proportions in 1917 and that the inhabitants<lb/>
were immune to the disease. In Salina Cruz the stegomyia incidence is<lb/>
at no time of the year sufficiently high to permit secondary infection.</p>
<p>The entire area was well under control by January 1st of the pre-<lb/>
sent year, but on March 20th a well-defined case of yellow fever develop-<lb/>
ed at the Ingenio San Cristobal, seven kilometers from Cosamaloapam, and<lb/>
the seat of the most intensive infection during August and September of<lb/>
last year. This case has been the only case reported on the Gulf Coast<lb/>
during 1922.</p>
<p>In addition to the anti-stegomyia work, our brigades have inci-<lb/>
dentally done anti-malarial work. All anti-larval measures are anti-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01021022"/>
are anti-<lb/>
malarial measures and the reduction of mosquito incidence is accompanied<lb/>
with a constant and emphatic fall in the malarial rate. It has been not-<lb/>
able to an unusual degree in the Second Zone. In all places in which our<lb/>
brigades have worked and under normal conditions malaria was highly pre-<lb/>
valent, the morbidity from malaria has decreased decidedly. In Vera<lb/>
Cruz, where malaria is distinctly &ldquo;urban&rdquo; in character, there is the<lb/>
lowest malaria incidence of recent years. For the reason that no pro-<lb/>
vision for malaria work had been made, the Commission did what it could<lb/>
do, without prejudice to the anti-stegomyia work, towards its control.<lb/>
Drainage ditches were opened up, ponds were drained, fish were abundantly<lb/>
planted in all parts of the city where the water collected during the<lb/>
rains; all such breeding places were regularly and generously oiled and<lb/>
with decidedly satisfactory results. The labor for this work was supplied<lb/>
by the generous action of General Guadalupe Sanchez in command of the<lb/>
military operations in the State of Vera Cruz; General Gabriel Carvallo,<lb/>
Comandante of the Naval School; and Hon. Rafael Garcia, the Alcalde of<lb/>
Vera Cruz, and without any cost to the Comision Especial. The co-opera-<lb/>
tion of these public spirited officials of Vera Cruz has contributed in<lb/>
a very large way to the success of this phase of our work and their as-<lb/>
sistance is acknowledged with the most grateful appreciation of the Co-<lb/>
mision Especial.</p>
<p>In Tierra Blanca, El Hule, Santa Lucrecia and other places the<lb/>
Comision secured the co-operation of Superintendent Vera of the Vera<lb/>
Cruz and Istmo Railroad, and Superintendent Enriquez of the Tehuantepec<lb/>
Railroad, who have in every possible way supported the work of the Co-<lb/>
mision Especial. In conjunction with these gentlemen and the municipal<lb/>
authorities of these places the Comision has covered the cost of con-<lb/>
struction of drainage ditches and other necessary work with decided be-<lb/>
nefit to the citizens of these cities and to the traveling public. In<lb/>
none of these places is the house index of mosquitos above five <unclear>percent</unclear><lb/>
and the malaria rate has been reduced materially.</p>
<p>In the methods of stegomyia breeding control the Vocal in Charge<lb/>
of the Second Zone has depended upon the following measures, listed in<lb/>
the order of their importance to the work.</p>
<p>First: The emptying and cleaning of all man made water deposits<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01021023"/>
water deposits<lb/>
wherever and as often as possible. The period of time between the ovi-<lb/>
posita and the adult mosquito life varies from eight days in the wet<lb/>
season to somewhat longer in the winter months. Our vueltas are estab-<lb/>
lished at eight days intervals and every house and every deposit con-<lb/>
taining water, however small, is carefully examined for larval and pupal<lb/>
life. If the containers are small, and the vast majority are, they are<lb/>
emptied and cleansed when breeding is discovered. For the reason that<lb/>
the greater number of breeding places in the Second Zone are encountered<lb/>
in deposits too small to support fish life, the regular inspection and<lb/>
cleansing of these small deposits is considered the most important<lb/>
measure.</p>
<p>Second: Next in importance and always to be insisted upon where<lb/>
the deposits contain sufficient water to support fish life, is the plant-<lb/>
ing of fish. No particular variety need be insisted upon; all varieties<lb/>
of minnows are the natural enemies of larval life and they devour both<lb/>
larva and pupa as well as the eggs rapaciously. The top feeder, the<lb/>
bottom feeder and the fish that range all through the water in search of<lb/>
food supply are used. Personally I prefer the free ranging fish to any<lb/>
of the other varieties. He protects himself better, eats the larvae as<lb/>
he finds them and will go to the top in search of eggs and other food.<lb/>
In addition he stays in his natural element, the water, and is not con-<lb/>
tinuously jumping out of the barrel or uncovered tank or trying to get<lb/>
out of the container when the rain fills it to overflowing. He is usual-<lb/>
ly hardier, lives longer and is more resistant to the rough usage occa-<lb/>
sioned by emptying and filling the deposit. Great loss always attends<lb/>
the use of &ldquo;jumping&rdquo; fish. The success of the use of fish depends upon<lb/>
the constancy with which they remain in the container and do the work<lb/>
assigned them. For this reason I prefer the fish that remains well with-<lb/>
in the container and ranges freely in search of his food supply.</p>
<p>Third: Next in importance, and it would be of first importance if<lb/>
the measure could be made one of universal <unclear>adoption</unclear>, is the permanent<lb/>
covering of each water container. This is the most efficient, most eco-<lb/>
nomical and by all means the most satisfactory measure, and if univer-<lb/>
sally adopted would do away with fish planting, oiling and other less<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01021024"/>
other less<lb/>
efficient measures. I am convinced that as a matter of economy, as well<lb/>
as of security, if campaigns are to be extended over a period of ten<lb/>
years or more, it would be best to cover containers with permanent co-<lb/>
vers at the expense of the Campaign, in all cases where the property<lb/>
owners would not or could not provide such covers. This measure is of<lb/>
value in proportion to the degree that it is adopted, and further to the<lb/>
care which the owners use in keeping the tops in repair and constantly<lb/>
on the container. In Vera Cruz we have succeeded in having practically<lb/>
all of the tanks and a great number of the barrels equipped with covers.</p>
<p>Fourth: The use of oil is next in importance. Oil can be used<lb/>
in the drains in the patios, in the cineza-water containers and in other<lb/>
containers which cannot be emptied and cleansed and which may be too<lb/>
small to support fish life. It is an expensive measure and its use is<lb/>
generally objected to on the part of the people of the community.</p>
<p>Fifth: Last and of minor importance, for the reason that its use<lb/>
is but seldom indicated, is fumigation. We have used it for the purpose<lb/>
of destroying adult mosquitos which we had reason to believe were infect-<lb/>
ed, and in those occasional cases where there was a heavy mosquito in-<lb/>
festation in schools, theaters, cuartels and other places of public<lb/>
congregation located in infected or suspicious areas.</p>
<p>A survey of the Second Zone recently completed shows a satisfactory<lb/>
condition existing in every city save one. That is the city of Tlacotal-<lb/>
pam. Here the incidence of mosquitos is high. The prevailing species<lb/>
are culicidae, with some anophelines and stegomyia. Throughout the Zone<lb/>
the results of our work have been satisfactory beyond our expectations.<lb/>
Yellow fever has been reduced to the vanishing point. Both the United<lb/>
States and Cuba have removed the yellow fever quarantine against Mexican<lb/>
Gulf ports. It seems that the campaign has secured definite control.<lb/>
The work that has been done should be continued until all danger is past<lb/>
and with as great an intensity as it has been previously conducted. I am<lb/>
referring to the area comprised in the Second Yellow Fever Zone. I am<lb/>
most reluctant to disagree with the distinguished Director of the Comi-<lb/>
sion Especial, Dr. Jos. H. White, or with my able and experienced col-<lb/>
league, Dr. M. E. Connor, as to the maintenance of the active work in<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f01021025"/>
work in<lb/>
the area of which I am in charge; but from my knowledge of, and expe-<lb/>
tience with, conditions in the Second Zone, I have no hesitancy in em-<lb/>
phasizing that the withdrawal of intensive active work in this area<lb/>
would be neither prudent nor wise and that such withdrawal would be<lb/>
attended with the gravest risks.</p>
<p>I am not unmindful that less than one year ago all of this area<lb/>
within 150 kilometers of Vera Cruz was reporting yellow fever cases.<lb/>
That in October of last year a violent epidemic was raging through the<lb/>
&ldquo;tierra caliente&rdquo; portion of Oaxaca and was extending down through<lb/>
Tuxtepec. That at the end of last December, a trifle over eight months<lb/>
ago, Dr. Cross became infected with yellow fever and died of the disease,<lb/>
and that on March 20th of this year, a little more than four months ago,<lb/>
a non-immune from Mexico City contracted the disease in San Cristobal,<lb/>
near <unclear>Cosamaloapam</unclear>, in an area of known yellow fever infection six<lb/>
months previous. In my best judgment the campaign should be continued<lb/>
through the present rainy season and beyond that period if there is<lb/>
the slightest element of doubt as to the future safety of the area from<lb/>
infection. To discontinue or to abridge the work at this time, when<lb/>
mosquito incidence under normal conditions is at its peak, and when any<lb/>
diminution of anti-stegomyia work would result in the usual high ste-<lb/>
gomyia incidence within a short time, would lay the foundation for the<lb/>
invasion of the port of Vera Cruz by yellow fever from any focus that<lb/>
may have been overlooked and would constitute an error potential with<lb/>
most unsatisfactory results.</p>
<p>The work of the Comision Especial and of the Consejo Superior<lb/>
before the Comision Especial was created, and for a time after, has<lb/>
been conducted at great expense. The results obtained have fully<lb/>
justified the expenditure incurred. To continue this work until its<lb/>
efficacy has been fully demonstrated will cost but little more, and<lb/>
that cost would be small in comparison with the cost that would be<lb/>
made necessary if a single case of yellow fever should originate in<lb/>
or near any Gulf port. The campaign would have to be reopened with<lb/>
all its vigor. Quarantine, which has so revently been withdrawn, would<lb/>
be immediately instituted, and more than all the lasting good which<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f01021026"/>
good which<lb/>
will result from the teachings we have been able to inculcate among<lb/>
the people, in matters of mosquito control, would be destroyed, in<lb/>
the event that our work fails to stand the test of time.</p>
<p>Whatever action that the Comision may take as to other Zones,<lb/>
I most urgently recommend that it continue the campaign in the Second<lb/>
Zone until the end of the present rainy season and longer if conditions<lb/>
at that time should make desirable.</p>
<closer>
<signed>BERT W. CALDWELL, M. D.<lb/>
Vocal in Charge of<lb/>
the Second Yellow Fever Zone</signed>.
Vera Cruz, Mexico,<lb/>
July 30th 1922.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
