<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01021005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Charles W. Comstock to R.B. Howland, March 30, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Comstock, Charles W.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01021005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-03-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Howland, R.B.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="place">Ceara (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Fortaleza, Ceara (Brazil)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-03-30">March 30, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01021005</idno>
<title>Letter from Charles W. Comstock to R.B. Howland, March 30, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Comstock describes possible yellow fever cases to Howland. All involve foreigners in Brazil.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-03-30">
<head>Letter from Charles W. Comstock to R.B. Howland, March 30, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01021005"/>
<opener>
Copy<lb/>
<dateline>
DWIGHT P. ROBINSON &amp; COMPANY<lb/>
125 East 46 Street<lb/>
New York<lb/>
Fortaleza, <date value="1922-03-30">March 30, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
Dwight P. Robinson &amp; Co., Inc.,<lb/>
125 East 46 Street,<lb/>
New York, N.Y.<lb/>
<hi>Attention Mr. Howland</hi><lb/>
<salute>Dear Mr. Howland:</salute>
</opener>
<p><hi>SUBJECT: YELLOW FEVER</hi></p>
<p>After some consideration of your letter of February 22 on this sub-<lb/>
ject, I turned over the yellow fever vaccine sent by you, together with the lit-<lb/>
erature on the subject and Dr. Noguchi's letter of instructions, to Dr. Jose<lb/>
Paracampos, the Chief Officer of the Inspectoria medical service. Dr. Philo-<lb/>
meno, to whom the letter was addressed is Dr. Paracampos' assistant.</p>
<p>I have not up to this time said anything about the matter to our<lb/>
men, partly because I am a little afraid of creating a panicky feeling, but<lb/>
chiefly because I'm not convinced that this vaccination is generally necessary.</p>
<p>The number of cases here has been few, all among the foreigners it<lb/>
is true, and all are traceable to two centers of infection, viz., the two prin-<lb/>
cipal hotels in Fortaleza.</p>
<p>The first case was that of C. D. Ashmore, a man sent here by the<lb/>
American Locomotive Co., who arrived May 6, 1921 and died May 31, 1921.</p>
<p>The second was that of E. T. Walsh, who died November 10, 1921, in<lb/>
the interior but a short time after he left Fortaleza. There is no doubt but<lb/>
that he was inoculated with the disease here.</p>
<p>The third was G. W. Naill, who had a narrow escape from death.<lb/>
He had lived in close association with Walsh during the latter's illness and<lb/>
no doubt contracted the disease from that association.</p>
<p>The fourth was Mr. Robotton's daughter, twelve years old, living at<lb/>
one of the suspected hotels. She escaped death by a narrow margin.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01021006"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>The fifth was McGuckin who undoubtedly was inoculated during the<lb/>
last few days of his stay here and became ill about two days after sailing.<lb/>
There seems to be no doubt that he had yellow fever, notwithstanding the<lb/>
death certificate gave another cause.</p>
<p>I am told by Brazilians of high standing that the Government medical<lb/>
authorities never allow yellow fever to be assigned as a cause of death if<lb/>
they can help it, so that they may say to the world at large &ldquo;there is no<lb/>
yellow fever in Brazil.&rdquo; This ostrich policy delays any preventive measures<lb/>
until they are forced by an epidemic.</p>
<p>The explanation of the fact that all the cases are among foreigners<lb/>
seems to be that all the natives have had the disease as children, a large<lb/>
proportion dying before they are two years of age, and the survivors having<lb/>
a certain immunity.</p>
<p>In the interior conditions are not favorable to the spread of the<lb/>
disease, as there are very few mosquitos. About Fortaleza there are many<lb/>
standing pools, many of which cannot be covered with oil, as for instance all<lb/>
the water supply is from shallow dug wells from which water is pumped by wind-<lb/>
mills to elevated tanks. Both wells and tanks are open and are excellent<lb/>
breeding places for mosquitoes. The reform of all the unsanitary conditions<lb/>
here would require a dictatorship such as existed in the Panama Canal Zone.</p>
<p>I do not mean to convey the idea that there is any great danger of<lb/>
yellow fever in Fortaleza and I think there is practically none at all in the<lb/>
interior.</p>
<p>There are only a few of us who make headquarters in Fortaleza. We<lb/>
have a house of our own which we make strenuous efforts to keep above the<lb/>
native standard of cleanliness. We sleep under mosquito nets and take the pre-<lb/>
caution to stay at home in the evening, at which time the mosquitoes are<lb/>
especially active.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01021007"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>Notwithstanding my feeling that there is little or no danger from<lb/>
this cause, it is a comfort to know that the preventive vaccine is available<lb/>
in the event that my views should change or in case some of the others may<lb/>
feel differently.</p>
<p>I assure you that your trouble and thoughtfulness in providing<lb/>
this facility is greatly appreciated by me, as I know it would be by the<lb/>
others if the fact were generally known.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours truly,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Charles W. Comstock</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
