<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01109013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, June 5, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01109013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-06-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hernandez, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Iglesias, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Pierce, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Walcott, Alan</name>
<name type="person">Scannell, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Perrin, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Merida (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Veracruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Villahermosa (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tabasco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-06-05">June 5, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01109013</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, June 5, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor comments on Carter's paper on the epidemiology of yellow fever. Connor discusses his work on malaria and yellow fever in Mexico.  He mentions the resignation of Guiteras.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-06-05">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, June 5, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01109013"/>
<opener>
PODERI EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA.<lb/>
----<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA.<lb/>
----<lb/>
JEFATURA EN COLIMA.<lb/>
SEXTA ZONA.<lb/>
----<lb/>
<dateline>
Colima, Col., <date value="1923-06-05">June 5-1923</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have twice read your Epidemiology<lb/>
section of your forthcoming work on yellow fever.<lb/>
If I may criticize it will be to point out that I could<lb/>
find no reference to the fact that yellow fever in<lb/>
endemic centres, such as cities and fair sized towns, is<lb/>
as a general rule circumscribed. It was in Guayaquil and<lb/>
I think it was in Merida and as I remember the situation<lb/>
the same is true for Panama. Of Havana I have no personal<lb/>
knowledge and have never seen a spot-map of cases record-<lb/>
ed in that city.</p>
<p>I am enclosing my section on epi-<lb/>
demiology which I have in mind to develope into an artic-<lb/>
le on yellow fever in Mexico to be read at the annual<lb/>
yellow fever convention during the latter part of this<lb/>
year.</p>
<p>I am wondering if it will take up<lb/>
too much of your time to read over the enclosed notes and<lb/>
to let me have your criticism of same. There is nothing<lb/>
new in these notes and my thought all through has been to<lb/>
emphasize certain points in the epidemiology of yellow fe-<lb/>
ver which I have learned from experience that the average<lb/>
Latin physician overlooks. I think you will agree with me<lb/>
that for the most part physicians in Latin America when<lb/>
occupying a position in the Health Department regards the<lb/>
work in coonection therewith as of minor importance and<lb/>
will rarely if ever take the time to read up on the subject<lb/>
and this is especially true regarding epidemiology.</p>
<p>The paper which I have in mind will<lb/>
briefly relate the history of yellow fever in Mexico foll-<lb/>
owed by the epidemiology of this infection then some facts<lb/>
concerning the aedes egypti concluding the article with a<lb/>
description of the anti-larvae measures as practised in the<lb/>
present campaign.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01109014"/>
<p>Dr. Carter</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>June 5-1923</p>
<p>Your suggestion to treat Lejias (aguas de ceniza) with<lb/>
a soap solution is a practical one and will be tried out in the<lb/>
Colima area and brought to the attention of our men in other Zones<lb/>
where Lejia is in general use.</p>
<p>I wonder if I wrote you that Doctor Hernandez of Merida,<lb/>
Yucatan, and Doctor Iglesias of Veracruz have been granted fellow-<lb/>
ship by our Board for technical training at the Institute under<lb/>
Noguchi. This training will consist for the most part in making<lb/>
practical demonstrations in Pfeiffer tests. Unfortunately, we<lb/>
have not been able as yet to find a physician for the Tampico<lb/>
area that would be accept&aacute;ble to Doctor Noguchi for training but<lb/>
we hope that Doctor Perrin of Mexico City will handle this detail<lb/>
for us and the plan is to forward to him serum from cases in which<lb/>
the Pfeiffer test is to be applied.</p>
<p>I agree with you that antimalarial work generally in con-<lb/>
nection with the yellow fever campaign over as large an area as we<lb/>
have here in Mexico is not practicable, notwithstanding that the<lb/>
antimalarial measures which our men in Veracruz and Tampico have<lb/>
carried out have on the whole been very successful.</p>
<p>I really believe that the Yellow Fever Council should re-<lb/>
view our present campaign and a programm<unclear><del>e</del></unclear> be developed for the future,<lb/>
more especially now that Colombia and possibly Venezuela are a real<lb/>
menace for reinfection of this country.</p>
<p>In the last year there seems to have developed in the mind<lb/>
of some of the Politicians in Mexico that the present campaign is be-<lb/>
ing continued for the benefit of the few. The trouble perhaps is due<lb/>
to their regarding Guayaquil and Peru as typical examples of yellow<lb/>
fever infected areas and reason that the rapidity with which the work<lb/>
advanced should be duplicated in Mexico. It may be that the Consejo<lb/>
have similar thoughts. Scannel writes me that Doctor Stubbs of Tampico<lb/>
a long time resident in this country, and Miembro Asociado of the Com-<lb/>
isi&oacute;n Especial, has stated that it will require twenty years to erad-<lb/>
icate yellow fever from Mexico. It is these little things coming up<lb/>
first in one section of the country and later in another section and<lb/>
finally concentrating in a definite programme amongst the Politicians<lb/>
to hold up appropriations for the work, this year the appropriation<lb/>
for the Departamento de Salubridad Publica was long held up in the<lb/>
Congress and it was only a few weeks ago that the budget for yellow<lb/>
fever and malaria work amounting to $800,000 pesos was approved.</p>
<p>Personally I am sorry that Doctor Guiteras has resigned from<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Council. He is a fearless man and would be a factor<lb/>
for good on any Council. No doubt he was influenced by <del>who</del> Labredo<lb/>
against Noguchi's Leptospira but the opposition serves as a stimulant<lb/>
to urge other workers in the same field of endeavour to prove or dis-<lb/>
prove the results of Noguchi's investigations.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01109015"/>
<p>Dr. Carter</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>June 5-1923</p>
<p>Regarding the legend of San Juan Bautista now Villaher-<lb/>
mosa it appears that the city itself was noninfectible territory be-<lb/>
cause of its complete water system serving an abundance of water to<lb/>
all habi<del>a</del>tations at all hours of the day or night and this system re-<lb/>
mained in good condition and served the public from 1865 down to 1915,<lb/>
this is according to the older residents of Villahermosa that I have<lb/>
talked with. The water system has now been abandoned due to bad man-<lb/>
agement of the Socialists. I have seen the plant and I was impressed<lb/>
by it. There are a number of other small places in Tabasco that could<lb/>
be classed as noninfectible areas from a campaign viewpoint but other-<lb/>
wise no.</p>
<p>I think you have done well to bring up the point that an<lb/>
animal may have been a reservoir host for the yellow fever infection.<lb/>
This has long been in the minds of some investigators and while the<lb/>
evidence for this belief is negative as yet, the suspicion shoudl be<lb/>
cleared up if it is possible to do so.</p>
<p>Since my first visit to Yucatan and meeting up with the<lb/>
archeologists there who are studying the monuments of the ancient<lb/>
peoples the thought has been cons<del>a</del>tantly with me that our Board might<lb/>
consider, if the matter was brought up to them, detailing a Paleopath-<lb/>
ologist to work with the Archeologists and attempt to discover what<lb/>
diseases afflicted the older races. The Archeologists tell me that<lb/>
this field of research has never been properly developed and it is<lb/>
their belief that rich knowledge awaits the concientous and patient<lb/>
worker in this branch of research medicine.</p>
<p>From now on the &lsquo;Jingo Press&rsquo; of Mexico will be carrying<lb/>
sensational articles relative to the presence of yellow fever in this<lb/>
and other parts of the Republic. Of course no attention should be giv-<lb/>
en to these rumors but the Depa<add>r</add>tamento believes, and I agree with them<lb/>
that all reports of yellow fever_should be investigated and an earnest<lb/>
effort is made to do this. The &lsquo;El Mundo&rsquo; to which you referred <del>to</del> in<lb/>
your letter is a sensational periodical and does lend itself, according<lb/>
to rumors, in aiding certain interests.</p>
<p>I think you have done a great service in advising the<lb/>
Surgeon General that the reports of the Comisi&oacute;n Especial will be un-<lb/>
biased. Unfortunately your service sometimes has representatives here<lb/>
who never make an inspection of the areas over which they are supposed<lb/>
to maintain at least a nominal supervision. Therefore it is difficult<lb/>
for us to actually show these men how the campaign is being carried on.<lb/>
Pierce noted this when he was here, and I have the impression that he<lb/>
will embody the observation in his report to the Surgeon General, in<lb/>
fact, I understand he proposes to recommend that our men here act as<lb/>
connecting links for the U. S. Public Health Service and the Departameno<lb/>
de Salubridad Publica. I recommended against this plan to Doctor Russ-<lb/>
ell for fear that it would involve our men in decisions on quarantine<lb/>
matters and as you know none of our men here at the present time have<lb/>
enough quarantine experience to permit them to act as advisors on these<lb/>
questions.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01109016"/>
<p>Dr. Carter</p>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>June 5-1923</p>
<p>Doctor Walcott for the present is supervising the Sanitary<lb/>
Inspectors in Merida and will remain there until the return of Doc-<lb/>
tor Hernandez when I have in mind transferring Walcott, if agreable to<lb/>
Doctor Scannell, to Tampico for the express purpose of making daily<lb/>
rounds ofnthe hospitals and sanitariums in that city.<lb/>
Doctor Walcott as you know is essentially a clinical man and the<lb/>
above detail will admit of his applying his diagnostic ability.</p>
<p>Doctor Scannel writes me thatvin the event no case of<lb/>
yellow fever developes in his area prior to August he will expect to be<lb/>
detailed away from Mexico on the grounds that his services will no<lb/>
longer be required. I wish I could agree with him and in a recent<lb/>
letter to him I expressed the hope that the work in the Tampico Zone<lb/>
would hold his interest until October at least at which time we will<lb/>
be in a position to know more definitely the real conditions existing<lb/>
in his area. I will bring to Tampico in August your Mss. on the his-<lb/>
tory of yellow fever, at that time requesting him, when he will have<lb/>
finished reading it to undertake getting it back to you.</p>
<p>Referring again to the chapter on epidemiology I wish that<lb/>
it were possible to convey to you the great service that you have<lb/>
rendered workers in the yellow fever field by writing on this phase<lb/>
of yellow fever infection and placing the same at our disposal for<lb/>
use.</p>
<p>It is the most complete work on the epidemiology of yellow fever I<lb/>
have ever read and if I may make a suggestion it will be that our<lb/>
Board would advise its men to study this chapter on epidemiology<lb/>
and not merely read it because to use a slang expression &ldquo;There is<lb/>
meat in every line of the article&rdquo;.</p>
<p>This letter brings to you the sincere thanks for all<lb/>
kindly consideration which you have always shown me and the hope<lb/>
that your prayer for the elimination (not controll<del>ed</del>) of yellow fever<lb/>
from Mexico and Central America this year be realized.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With continued good wishes, I am<lb/>
as always, very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>M E Connor</signed>
Dr. H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California Street, N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
