<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01109024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from W.H.W. Komp to Henry Rose Carter, June 11, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Komp, W.H.W.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01109024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-06-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Barber, M. A.</name>
<name type="person">Beyer, George</name>
<name type="place">Brewton (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Crowley (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Ship Island (Mississippi Sound)</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="hospital">Veteran's Hospital (Gulfport, Miss.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-06-11">June 11, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01109024</idno>
<title>Letter from W.H.W. Komp to Henry Rose Carter, June 11, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Komp writes about mosquito identification.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-06-11">
<head>Letter from W.H.W. Komp to Henry Rose Carter, June 11, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01109024"/>
<opener>
I. W.<lb/>
Komp.<lb/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
<dateline>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
Box 231, Crowley, La.<lb/>
<date value="1923-06-11">June 11, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your kind letter was forwarded to me from Memphis, and I<lb/>
want to thank you for your commendation of my paper on mosquito identification.<lb/>
I was not at all satisfied with it in the form in which it appeared, but<lb/>
I had to cut down the number of illustrations to a minimum on account of the<lb/>
expense involved, and also omitted several of the less important species which<lb/>
are sometimes encountered, in the interests of briefness.</p>
<p>I realize that I should have figured a wing of <hi>pseudopunctipennis</hi>,<lb/>
but omitted it because I had no authentic material before me, and also because<lb/>
it did not occur in those regions where malaria is most prevalent. I think<lb/>
that the white-ringed palpi, as noted in my paper, will be sufficient to<lb/>
distinguish it from <hi>punctipennis</hi>, as this character is less evanescent than<lb/>
wing-spots, which are easily rubbed off.</p>
<p>We have <hi>Aedes canadensis</hi> here in the South, as I have found it in<lb/>
Brewton, Alabama, last year, and also here at Crowley this spring. But it<lb/>
is very early in appearing (here in February), and does not last long, besides<lb/>
being a woodland species. If I had had more space this easily recognized species<lb/>
should have been included, along with that hard biter, <hi>Mansonia perturbans</hi>.<lb/>
We have had quite a flight of this last species here in May, and it usually<lb/>
attracts attention because it is such a vicious biter. Maybe when the bulletin<lb/>
is revised these two and perhaps some others may be included.</p>
<p>Regarding your questions: I have seen, much to my disturbance, <hi>A.<lb/>
quadrimaculatus</hi> breeding in a fair running stream, that also was not much<lb/>
better than an open sewer. I could not control them there (this was before the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01109025"/>
days of quick-acting Paris green) for the current would float the oil off<lb/>
downstream before it could act on the larvae. <hi>Gambusia</hi> helped some here,<lb/>
but they had too much else to eat to be greatly interested in wiggletails.<lb/>
(2) I have never seen <hi>punctipennis</hi> breeding in a large body of water, where<lb/>
where it could be said definitely that they were not washed down into it<lb/>
from some stream. I asked Dr. Barber what had been his experience in this<lb/>
matter, and he said he had never seen <hi>punctipennis</hi> in a large pond. We<lb/>
got them here in small numbers in Crowley this spring, in small woodland<lb/>
pools, some with pine needles on the bottom, but none more than ten feet<lb/>
or so in diameter.</p>
<p>We have turned up that rare Anopheles, <hi>A. walkeri</hi>, here in<lb/>
Crowley, that I rediscovered <del><unclear></unclear></del> fifteen years <add>after</add><del><unclear></unclear></del> it was <add>first</add> reported<lb/>
for Louisiana by Dr. George Beyer of New Orleans. My first specimens were<lb/>
taken on Ship Island in the Mississippi Sound, back in 1921. We are the<lb/>
first to find the larvae in nature, although Beyer bred them from eggs<lb/>
in the laboratory. We hope to get enough of them to try out their malaria<lb/>
carrying capacity, as this has never been determined. Last spring, as well<lb/>
as for a short time this year, they migrated from Ship and Cat Islands to<lb/>
the mainland in sufficient numbers to be quite noticeable at the U. S.<lb/>
Veterans' Hospital in Gulfport, Miss.</p>
<p>I feel very gratified to think that you took time enough from your<lb/>
pressing work to write me so fully concerning your data on quads and puncts,<lb/>
and I want to express my appreciation of your kind remarks anent my little<lb/>
mosquito identification paper.</p>
<p>Dr. Barber wishes me to convey his best regards to you.</p>
<p>With kind personal regards and best wishes, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>W. H W. Komp</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
