<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01102038">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Oliver L. Pothier to Joseph H. White, May 26, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Pothier, Oliver L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01102038</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-05-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">White, Joesph H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Bogata (Colombia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-05-26">May 26, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01102038</idno>
<title>Letter from Oliver L. Pothier to Joseph H. White, May 26, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Pothier reports on the reactions obtained from the sera of the cases of yellow fever seen in Bucaramanga.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-05-26">
<head>Letter from Oliver L. Pothier to Joseph H. White, May 26, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01102038"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
I. H. B.<lb/>
Columbia<lb/>
<dateline>
Baranquilla <date value="1923-05-26">May 26th, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. J. H. White<lb/>
Chief of the Commission<lb/>
sent to Colombia.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wish to report as follows on the reactions obtained from the sera<lb/>
of the cases of Yellow fever that we saw in Bucaramanga.</p>
<p>The first case was that of Esteban Figueroa, who had been sick for six<lb/>
days and who presented the cardinal symptoms of yellow fever, in the most typical<lb/>
and classical way. This case was seen by the Commission on May the first 1923<lb/>
and his blood taken the same morning. On account of the impossibility of obtain-<lb/>
ing guinea pigs that day a reaction was made in vitro, using equal parts of serum<lb/>
and a culture of Leptospira Icteroides, (Nugochi) (Arias Strain). The specimen<lb/>
was observed for a period of half an hour to an hour and gave what appeared to<lb/>
be a complete agglutination, Two days after May 3/23 having obtained guinea pigs<lb/>
Pfeiffer test was made and it gave a positive reaction with equal parts of serum<lb/>
and culture of Leptospira Icteroides, (Nugochi, Arias Strain)</p>
<p>On May 1st, 1923, we saw another case, Cristobal Rueda, a mild case<lb/>
who was then without fever, after being sick three days. His blood was taken on<lb/>
the same date and submitted also to a reaction in vitro, it being impossible on<lb/>
that date to obtain any guinea pigs. It gave also a positive reaction with a<lb/>
mixture of equal parts of serum and culture of Leptospira Icteroides (Nugochi,<lb/>
Arias Strain) On May 3/23 having obtained guinea pigs Pfeiffer test was made and<lb/>
it gave a positive reaction. The reaction of this serum were weaker and appeared<lb/>
after a longer period of time, not before forty-five minutes and were observed for<lb/>
one hour and a <unclear>half</unclear>.</p>
<p>The Arias Strain was used because these cultures were the best the others<lb/>
presenting contemminations. The difficulties of transportations that we had to<lb/>
reach Bucaramanga and the transportation on mule back of these cultures by one of<lb/>
us who had them continually with him did not prevent the action of excessive heat on<lb/>
them and also the more or less jarring in riding, may have accounted for the con-<lb/>
tamination of several of the cultures, the Arias Strain, were all free from con-<lb/>
taminations.</p>
<p>On may 4th, 1923, we went to the College San Pedro, where several cases<lb/>
had appeared in February. We saw two of these cases one a very severe case Father<lb/>
Hidalgo, and the other one a mild case, one of the brothers of the order, Jesuits.<lb/>
Their blood was taken and carried to Bogota, in sealed ampoules, that is the serum.<lb/>
These were subjected to Pfeiffer reaction in Bogota at the Laboratory of Drs<lb/>
Samper and Martinez. They gave positive reactions with equal parts of serum and<lb/>
cultures of Leptospira Icteroides. (Arias Strain.)</p>
<p>The cross reaction Leptospira Icterohaemorrhagica, were made with the<lb/>
serum obtained from Figueroa, and from Father Hidalgo, only. These Pfeiffer<lb/>
reactions with Leptospira Icterohaemorrhagica were negative, the reaction was<lb/>
made one part of serum to fifty parts of culture.</p>
<p>We would have made a series of reaction at different titers had it not<lb/>
been the difficulties that we had in obtaining the proper light and other ac-<lb/>
cessories. We deemed however that these reactions were sufficiently clear to es-<lb/>
tablish a positive diagnosis, they were seen by all of the commission and Drs<lb/>
Samper and Martini, in whose Laboratory we were working.</p>
<p>I wish to state that I owe many thanks to Dr. McCormick in Bucaramanga<lb/>
for the use of his laboratory and apparatus, and his kind assistance in my work<lb/>
and in procuring guinea pigs, in Bogota, to Drs Samper and Martiniez who put their<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01102039"/>
(Report of Dr. Pothier) Cont'd<lb/>
(2)<lb/>
exceptionally well equipped laboratory at my disposal and that of the commission,<lb/>
and furnished all the guinea pigs that I needed.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully Submitted</salute>
<signed>(Signed) O. L. Pothier</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
