<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01101001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Field Note No. 14: Pine Trees in Relation to Mosquito Production, May 23, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01101001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-05-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-05-23">May 23, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01101001</idno>
<title>Field Note No. 14: Pine Trees in Relation to Mosquito Production, May 23, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The writer discusses the influence of pine trees on mosquito production.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-05-23">
<head>Field Note No. 14: Pine Trees in Relation to Mosquito Production, May 23, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01101001"/>
<opener>
Imp'd water<lb/>
<hi>Pines</hi><lb/>
FB<lb/>
<dateline>
Hdq: Field Investigations of Malaria,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Room 17, Court House,<lb/>
Memphis, Tennessee.<lb/>
<date value="1923-05-23">May 23, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>--------</p>
<p>-------------Field Note No. 14---------------<lb/>
<hi>Pine Trees in Relation to Mosquito Production.</hi></p>
<p>It has frequently been observed that certain pine trees<lb/>
growing on the borders of impounded waters increased mosquito<lb/>
production in these waters by furnishing protection to the mos-<lb/>
quito larvae underneath and among the fallen pine leaves. There-<lb/>
fore, the practice of ringing pine trees within fifty feet of<lb/>
the water's edge has been recommended as the easiest way of<lb/>
getting rid of the leaves which would fall during the mosquito<lb/>
season. Recently an officer in the field reported that the<lb/>
ringing of pine trees did not always cause the death of the trees,<lb/>
and that unless properly and seasonably done the procedure might<lb/>
prove harmful rather than beneficial as a means of mosquito<lb/>
reduction.</p>
<p>In view of the fact that eleven different species of<lb/>
pines occur in the southeastern United States, any one of which<lb/>
might be encountered, and that there is considerable difference<lb/>
among them in growth and time at which they shed their leaves,<lb/>
it is hardly to be expected that all pine trees have the same<lb/>
influence upon mosquito production.</p>
<p>Because of the practical importance of this matter each<lb/>
officer in the field is requested to conduct a series of observa-<lb/>
tions throughout the summer on:</p>
<p>(1) The influence of pine trees on mosquito production.<lb/>
(2) The cheapest and quickest way of destroying pine<lb/>
trees which are increasing mosquito production.</p>
<p>In order that there may be no confusion of the species under ob-<lb/>
servation, you are being sent a list of the pines of this region<lb/>
with a brief discription taken from Sargent's Manual of the Trees<lb/>
of North America which may help in their identification. Each<lb/>
officer in the field will be expected to submit notes on his ob-<lb/>
servations at the end of the season, and it is hoped that every<lb/>
important aspect of this study will be touched upon.</p>
<p>- - - - - - - - - - - - - </p>
<pb n="2" id="f01101002"/>
<p><hi>Pinus Strobus. White Pine</hi>: A tree 100 or more feet high at<lb/>
maturity; bark thin on branches, 1 to 2 inches thick on old<lb/>
trunk; wood light; leaves in 5-leaved clusters, soft <unclear>bluish</unclear><lb/>
green, from 3 to 5 inches long, turning yellow and falling in<lb/>
autumn of their second season, or persisting until the follow-<lb/>
ing summer. Distribution: Found in the Alleghany Mountains<lb/>
and their foot hills.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus palustris. Long-leaved Pine. Southern Pine</hi>: A tree 100<lb/>
or more feet high at maturity; bark thin, 1/16 to 1/2 inch<lb/>
thick on trunk, light orange-brown; wood heavy; leaves in<lb/>
crowded 3-leaved clusters forming dense tufts at the ends of<lb/>
the branches, slender, flexible, dark green in color, 8 to<lb/>
18 inches long, deciduous at the end of their second year.<lb/>
Distribution: Found in belt up to <unclear>one</unclear>-hundred and twenty-<lb/>
five miles wide, stretching from southeast Virginia to<lb/>
Floroda, thence to the Mississippi River and through east-<lb/>
ern Louisiana and eastern Texas.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus Caribaea, Slash Pine. Swamp Pine</hi>: A tree often 100 feet<lb/>
high at maturity; bark thin, 1/2 to 3/4 inch thick on trunk,<lb/>
shallow fissures, dark red-brown scales; wood heavy, rich in<lb/>
pitch; leaves stout, in crowded 2 and 3-leaved clusters, 8 to<lb/>
12 inches long, deciduous at the end of their second season.<lb/>
Distribution: Coast region of South Carolina, southward to<lb/>
Southern Florida and along Gulf Coast to Louisiana.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus Taeda. Loblolly Pine. Old Field Pine</hi>: A tree generally<lb/>
80 to 100 feet high at maturity; bark 3/4 to 1 1/2 inches thick<lb/>
on trunk, bright red-brown; wood weak, brittle; leaves slen-<lb/>
der, stiff, color pale green in 3-leaved clusters, 6 to 9<lb/>
inches long, deciduous during their third year. Distribution:<lb/>
Widely distributed throughout Middle, South Atlantic and<lb/>
Gulf States.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus rigida. Pitch Pine:</hi> A tree 50 to 60 feet high at<lb/>
maturity, short trunk; bark thin, 3/4 to 1 1/2 inches thick<lb/>
on trunk and greatly roughened; wood light and soft; leaves<lb/>
dark yellow-green in 3-leaves clusters, 3 to 5 inches long,<lb/>
deciduous during their second year. Distribution: Middle,<lb/>
South Atlantic States and Alleghany region.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus serotina. Pond Pine. Marah Pine:</hi> A tree usually 40<lb/>
to 50 feet high at maturity; bark 1/2 to 3/4 inches thick,<lb/>
dark red-brown, shallow fissures; wood soft, rich in pitch;<lb/>
leaves in clusters of three or occasionally four, 6 to 8<lb/>
inches long, deciduous during their third and fourth years.<lb/>
Distribution: Wet, sandy flats or swamps along the Atlantic<lb/>
Coast from North Carolina to Florida.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01101003"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p><hi>Pinus glabra. Spruce Pine. Cedar Pine:</hi> A tree usually 80 tO<lb/>
100 feet high at maturity; bark 1/2 to 3/4 inches thick, red-<lb/>
dish-brown, shallow fissures; wood soft; leaves slender, dark<lb/>
greem 1 1/2 to 3 inches long, deciduous at the end of their sec-<lb/>
ond and in the spring of their third year. Distribution:<lb/>
South Carolina to central Florida and eastern Louisiana.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus echinata. Yellow Pine. Short-leaved Pine</hi>: A tree<lb/>
usually 80 to 100 feet high at maturity; bark 3/4 to 1-inch<lb/>
thick, light cinnamon-red scales; wood variable in quality;<lb/>
leaves in clusters of two or three, dark blue-green, 3 to 5<lb/>
inches long, deciduous at the end of their second season and<lb/>
dropping irregularly until their fifth year. Distribution:<lb/>
Widely distributed throughout the Middle, South Atlantic<lb/>
and Gulf States.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus Virginiana. Scrub Pine</hi>: A tree usually 30 to 40 feet<lb/>
high at maturity; bark 1/4 to 1/2 inches thick, shallow<lb/>
fissures, dark brown scales, wood soft; leaves in two-leaved<lb/>
remote clusters, gray green in color, 1 1/2 to 3 inches long,<lb/>
gradually and irregularly deciduous during their third and<lb/>
fourth years. Distribution: Middle and South Atlantic<lb/>
States.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus clausa. Sand Pine. Spruce Pine</hi>: A tree usually 15 to<lb/>
20 feet high at maturity; bark 1/3 to 1/2 inch thick, narrow<lb/>
deep fissures, bright red-brown scales; wood soft; leaves<lb/>
slender in 2-leaved clusters, dark green in color, 2 to 3 1/2<lb/>
inches long, deciduous during their third and fourth years.<lb/>
Distribution: Gulf States near coast and narrow strip on<lb/>
east coast of Florida.</p>
<p><hi>Pinus pungens. Hickory Pine</hi>: A tree occasionally 60 feet<lb/>
high at maturity; bark 3/4 to 1-inch thick, brown scales<lb/>
tinged with red; wood soft; leaves in 2-leaved crowded<lb/>
clusters, dark blue-green in color, 1 1/2 to 2 1/2 inches long,<lb/>
deciduous during their second and third year. Distribu-<lb/>
tion: Alleghany Mountains and foot hills.</p>
<p>---------------------------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
