<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01102030">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, April 9, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01102030</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-04-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Scannell, E. J.</name>
<name type="person">Spinden, Herbert Joseph</name>
<name type="place">Gulf Coast</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Spain</name>
<name type="place">Villahermosa (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tabasco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Zacamixtle (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-04-09">April 9, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01102030</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, April 9, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor discusses a test for the diagnosis of yellow fever and the possibility of combining an anti-malarial campaign with yellow fever work. He suggests that the Board employ someone to study paleo-pathology.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-04-09">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, April 9, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01102030"/>
<p>I H B<lb/>
Merida, Yucatan, Mexico.<lb/>
<date value="1923-04-09">April 9th., 1 9 2 3.</date>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
ESTADOS UNIDOS MEXICANOS<lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA DE MEXICO<lb/>
----<lb/>
JEFATURA DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A CONTRA<lb/>
LA FIEBRE AMARILLA EN YUCATAN<lb/>
----<lb/>
MERIDA, YUC., MEX.<lb/>
Connor<lb/>
Answered in detail May 20/23<lb/>
I. H. B<lb/>
My dear Doctor Carter;</p>
<p>Your very welcome letter of March <del><unclear>of</unclear></del> 11th., ult.<lb/>
was here in Merida on my arrival April 3rd., I do appreciate<lb/>
all the trouble that you have been put to in answering my<lb/>
last long letter.</p>
<p>I am hoping that the Pfiffier reaction will prove to be<lb/>
of value as border line cases will be constantly coming up<lb/>
for decision more especially in the Gulf Coast region and it<lb/>
means that in the absence of some definite or fairly definite test<lb/>
we will continue to have yellow fever diagnosed and our work never<lb/>
finished.</p>
<p>In my last talk with Doctor White I sugges<del>s</del>ted the advisa-<lb/>
bility or wisdom of doing anti-malaria work in connection with<lb/>
our yellow fever campaign. It has been done in some places and<lb/>
in these localities borderline cases have been eliminated. I wish<lb/>
that our Board were contemplating an anti-malaria campaign in Mexico<lb/>
in stead of a hookworm campaign.</p>
<p>Speaking about the Habana school, has Dr. Guiteras re-<lb/>
signed from the yellow fever council? On the last letter head recently<lb/>
received from Doctor White his name did not appear.</p>
<p>Further experiments with lejia (agua cenizas) show that our<lb/>
best hope with this class of containers is in the direction of de-<lb/>
veloping a copper container or else soldering or riveting a piece of<lb/>
copper plate to the ordinary container. It is difficult to change<lb/>
the <del><unclear></unclear></del> habits of long standing in a few months and this ex-<lb/>
plains why the pieces of copper plate suelto are not as sucessful as the<lb/>
might be. The orange or lime peel is being more generally used and<lb/>
in time there use will increase. Wherevever used they <del><unclear>are</unclear></del> appear to be<lb/>
successful. The copper paint, one coat, does not last long, the<lb/>
alkaline solution dissolves it off the tin. The action of the copper<lb/>
and orange or lime peel is purely that of a repellant. It will not<lb/>
kill larve already in the receptacle but will prevent the adult from de-<lb/>
positing eggs.</p>
<p>I will be glad and consider it a great honor to review<lb/>
the history which you have in preparation. My address until Doctor<lb/>
White returns to Mexico will be Calle Constitucion #13, Vera Cruz, Ver.<lb/>
The foregoing will be my headquarters while on this general in-<lb/>
specting detail.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01102031"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>It is Mr. Martinez, but we all call him Doctor, as far as I know he carries no<lb/>
titles but as you say he should. He appears to me to be <add>a</add> genuine scientist<lb/>
in his special line, Maya Antiguities and <add>is</add> imposed upon by nearly every archeolog-<lb/>
ist that comes here but he rarely says a word <del><unclear></unclear></del> against them but never for-<lb/>
gets to eulogize those that have been <unclear>kind</unclear> to him and this explains in part why he<lb/>
is ever anxious to aid you.</p>
<p>I have just come across an old work on yellow fever, perhaps you have it, the <unclear>t</unclear><lb/>
title page is next attached. Should you care to see it I feel quite that <del><unclear></unclear></del><add><unclear>same</unclear></add><lb/>
arrangements might be made to send it to you. Dr. Roman <unclear>Sebas</unclear> Flores has it, and<lb/>
his address is <del><unclear></unclear></del> Calle 58 #497 Merida, Yucatan, Mexico. The work is in the<lb/>
main historical and <add>an</add> attempt to establish a separate entity for yellow fever in<lb/>
Spain.</p>
<p>The two <add>big</add> mistakes that have been made in Mexico are; 1st. The Comision form of<lb/>
organization for supervison of the work with the Director in the early days of<lb/>
the campaign outside the country a large part of the time, and 2nd: our mis-<lb/>
conception of what constituted a key center or area in Mexico in the first year of<lb/>
the campaign. Through this misconception we were lured, as it were, into a false<lb/>
sense of <del><unclear></unclear></del> security and from which we were rudely shaken in time to<lb/>
apply the knowledge gained, what a calamity it would have been had we been out<lb/>
of the country when the &lsquo;bubble burst&rsquo;. I am going to try and reduce our ex-<lb/>
perience here to writing for the <del><unclear></unclear></del> convention this fall.</p>
<p>Regarding the legend as to the freedom of <del><unclear></unclear></del> San Juan Bautista noew Villa-<lb/>
hermosa from Yellow fever there does seem to be a story that that city was free<lb/>
and had been free from many years. It will have to be verified by going to the<lb/>
town which I propose to do in June and possibly before if it can be arranged.<lb/>
In the meantime am sending out in quiries to medicos who should have some know-<lb/>
ledge of the <del><unclear></unclear></del> history of yellow fever in Tabasco.</p>
<p>The only village that I know of being free of stegomyia mosquitos was Zacamixtle<lb/>
an <unclear>oil</unclear> town of about 2000 inhabitants. It was free during LePrinces time in Mexico<lb/>
but recently Scannell states that he found Aedes Egyptus there, unfortunately his<lb/>
findings were not submitted to experts which should have been done in the interest<lb/>
of history. No doubt Scannell did find the &lsquo;legitimos&rsquo; and they should have been<lb/>
Zacamixtle long before as there had been a constant stream of people moving into<lb/>
this area from &lsquo;steg&rsquo; infested regions and it would have been the easiest thing in<lb/>
the wo<add>r</add>ld to have carried larvae along with them, but I wish they had been identi-<lb/>
fied as by this time they have all been destroyed. I will make it a point to go to<lb/>
Zacamixtle to see what present conditions are.<del><unclear></unclear></del> Drop a line to Scannel <unclear>re This</unclear><lb/>
I saw Morely and Spinden. The former is in Mexico City trying to arrange for a<lb/>
concession to reconstruct Chichen Itza. Spinden is back in the states and at work I believe<lb/>
on an article showing the march of syphilis and other diseases that have taken a<lb/>
part in the &lsquo;rise and fall of civilizations&rsquo;.</p>
<p>It has occured to me of late that our Board should be interested in paleopatholo<lb/>
gy and <del><unclear>we might learn something of interest if</unclear></del> detail a man to work with the arch<lb/>
eologists in their researches. There undoubtedly would be some surprising findings<lb/>
that would help us in our present day worK.</p>
<p>Referring to the <del><unclear></unclear></del> term &lsquo;endemic&rsquo;, it seems to me that this word carries the<lb/>
same meaning to yellow fever as it does to other diseases and something more, be-<lb/>
cause yellow fever is not a carrying disease in the sense that other infections are,<lb/>
yellow fever is <del>in every</del> truly a self-limited infection and the sub-divisions &lsquo;tem-<lb/>
porarily&rsquo; and &lsquo;permanently&rsquo; endemic accurately describes the condition, a time element<lb/>
might be worked out to show when &lsquo;temporarily&rsquo; becomes &lsquo;permanently&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Am now collecting data with the thought of reducing to a formula the time necess<lb/>
ary for mosquito index (&lsquo;Aedes&rsquo;) to rise from five to ten percent, and if of practic<lb/>
able service it ought to effect a saving in adminstration.</p>
<p>with all good wishes</p>
<p>as ever your friend<lb/>
M E Connor</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
