<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01108001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Translation [from French] of a medical report from 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Class Chief Physician to the Lieutenant Governor at Dahomey, Porto-Novo, June 23, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01108001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-06-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Ouidah (Benin, West Africa)</name>
<name type="place">Cotonou (Benin, West Africa)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-06-23">June 23, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01108001</idno>
<title>Translation [from French] of a medical report from 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Class Chief Physician to the Lieutenant Governor at Dahomey, Porto-Novo, June 23, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a medical report on the outbreak of yellow fever in Benin, West Africa. It details the measures taken to prevent further cases.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-06-23">
<head>Translation [from French] of a medical report from 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Class Chief Physician to the Lieutenant Governor at Dahomey, Porto-Novo, June 23, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01108001"/>
<opener>
<unclear>? Onido (Why doh?)</unclear><lb/>
<hi>TRANSLATED FROM THE FRENCH</hi><lb/>
<hi>Ferris</hi><lb/>
good last Part<lb/>
<dateline>
Porto-Novo, <date value="1923-06-23">June 23, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
DAHOMEY COLONY<lb/>
HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
The 1st Class Chief Physician,<lb/>
To the Lieutenant-Governor<lb/>
at Dahomey, Porto-Nov.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>On the morning of June 6th, a telephone call from Dr. Valmorin, stationed<lb/>
at Ouidah, notified the head of the Health Service that Mr. Cabanes, agent of the<lb/>
F.A.O. at Ouidah, who had been sick since the first of June, had died on the night<lb/>
of the 5th day of his illness, and a short time before his death had presented<lb/>
the following suspicious symptoms:</p>
<p>&ldquo;At the moment of his death, the patient vomited a certain amount of<lb/>
black liquid containing dust-like substance similar to coffee grounds. A few<lb/>
hours after death he turned yellow and developed hemorrhagic effusions over the<lb/>
entire back of the body.&rdquo;</p>
<p>According to the medical report which confirmed these data, Mr. A.,<lb/>
on the 1st of June, came down with a severe attack of fever preceded by chills<lb/>
and accompanied by bilious vomiting. The fever went up to 39.6 degrees on the<lb/>
first day and persisted although gradually diminishing. Liver sensitive, cardiac<lb/>
insufficiency, large quantity of albumen in the urine, constipation. On the<lb/>
evening of June 5th, the patient became worse, subdelirious. The heart gave<lb/>
out, the extremities became cold, and death supervened towards 3 o'clock in the<lb/>
morning with the symptoms related above. At the same time two other Europeans<lb/>
were sick at Ouidah, Mr. B. a French Overseas Agent, and Mr. C., an officer<lb/>
in the Colonial Artillery. The first of these developed a fever with delayed<lb/>
icterus, the second was reported by the doctor of the Senegalese Regiment as<lb/>
having had a certain amount of fever and felt somewhat tired, but as already<lb/>
improving. Learning that these two patients were getting ready to go to Cotonou,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01108002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
the chief of the Health Service immediately forbade evacuation of all patients<lb/>
coming from Ouidah (telegrams 42 and 43 of the 6th of June). At the same time<lb/>
the following instructions were given to Dr. Valmorin:</p>
<p>In view of the grave emergency confronting us, I am asking you without<lb/>
awaiting the arrival of further instructions, to take the following measures:</p>
<p>(1) As soon as possible install isolation accommodations for Europeans<lb/>
and natives with rooms screened by a wire or strong mosquito notting.</p>
<p>(2) Prepare a screened stretcher for transporting patients.</p>
<p>(3) Undertake energetically the destruction of mosquitoes, getting in<lb/>
touch with the authorities for the purpose of organizing several working squads<lb/>
under guards who will take instructions from you.</p>
<p>(4) Evacuation of dwellings inhabited by suspects. Disinfection of these<lb/>
dwellings and a sanitary cordon around the houses.</p>
<p>(5) Observation of persons who have had contact with suspects.</p>
<p>(6) Methodical house inspections among Europeans and natives for locating<lb/>
the sick.</p>
<p>(7) Examination at the station by Assistant Physician Titus of all persons<lb/>
leaving Ouidah and observation of every suspect.</p>
<p>You may refer to the local decree of July 5, 1906, for supplementary<lb/>
sanitary measures which you may think necessary.</p>
<p>Without delay the local board of health was called together and at<lb/>
the suggestion of the chief of the Health Service it was decided that observation<lb/>
of the Ouidah settlement was necessary. A local decree of June 8th declared<lb/>
Ouidah under observation.</p>
<p>At 8 o'clock in the morning Mr. B. died with icterus that was very<lb/>
pronounced at the end, without black vomit, but with melena. These two deaths<lb/>
with symptoms sufficiently characteristic, established yellow fever beyond a<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01108003"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
doubt and by decree of June 9th, several hours after that of June 8th, the<lb/>
city and the settlements of Ouidah were declared infected with yellow fever.</p>
<p>Urgent measures were necessary because it was a question not only<lb/>
of combating this incipient epidemic at Ouidah, but also of avoiding at all<lb/>
price the further contamination of Cotonou only 60 kilometers away and in<lb/>
daily communication by rail with Ouidah. On the morning of the 9th of June<lb/>
the condition of Officer C. which up till then had not been considered serious,<lb/>
became worse and aroused suspicion. The head of the Health Service, who had<lb/>
set out for Ouida, arrived the morning of the 10th, only to learn that this<lb/>
officer had died during the night. The autopsy which he himself performed<lb/>
gave him a chance to confirm the yellow fever diagnosis. Another European,<lb/>
a commercial agent, was likewise attacked by the same disease, but he, Mr. D.<lb/>
is at present well again. Detail orders were given on the spot by the head<lb/>
of the Health Service in agreement with the Commander of the settlement, the<lb/>
Military Commander, and Dr. V., the Physician of the Assistance. They consisted<lb/>
of measures:</p>
<p>(1) To bring about, with the aid of the military authorities, the isolation<lb/>
of inhabitants by means of a sanitary cordon, in order to avoid all egress of<lb/>
patients to the exterior.</p>
<p>(2) To watch attentively any person the least bit ill, and if necessary<lb/>
to place him under observation in a screened room so as to avoid surprises and<lb/>
errors in diagnosis.</p>
<p>(3) To provide for the possible immediate dispersion to the interior of<lb/>
the European population of the settlement and have in readiness isolated<lb/>
dwellings.</p>
<p>(4) To have the military European element still in good health abandon<lb/>
the portion of the city where the yellow fever had occurred and for the present<lb/>
to group these Europeans in the non-contaminated Zoumai camp.</p>
<p>(5) To issue an order for the soldiers to retire at 6:15.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
