<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01102019">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jno [John] H. Smith to Henry Rose Carter, May 10, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Smith, Jno [John] H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01102019</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-05-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Rucker, William C.</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
<name type="place">Australia</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal</name>
<name type="place">North America</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">New Zealand</name>
<name type="place">Eastern Asia</name>
<name type="place">Valparaiso (Chile)</name>
<name type="place">Iquique (Chile)</name>
<name type="place">Antofagasta (Chile)</name>
<name type="place">Arica (Chile)</name>
<name type="place">Pisco (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Mollendo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Callao (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Balboa (Canal Zone)</name>
<name type="place">Manzanillo (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Salina Cruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Los Angeles (Calif.)</name>
<name type="place">San Francisco (Calif.)</name>
<name type="place">Honolulu (Oahu, Hawaii)</name>
<name type="place">Manila (Philippines)</name>
<name type="place">Moji (Japan)</name>
<name type="place">Kobe (Japan)</name>
<name type="place">Yokohama (Japan)</name>
<name type="place">Hong Kong</name>
<name type="place">Shanghai (China)</name>
<name type="place">China</name>
<name type="place">Asia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-05-10">May 10, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01102019</idno>
<title>Letter from Jno [John] H. Smith to Henry Rose Carter, May 10, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Smith provides detailed information on the steamer traffic between South America, Asia and Australia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-05-10">
<head>Letter from Jno [John] H. Smith to Henry Rose Carter, May 10, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01102019"/>
<opener>
<unclear>ZEAL OF THE CANAL ZONE ESTR OF PANAMA</unclear><lb/>
* * *<lb/>
<dateline>
THE PANAMA CANAL<lb/>
CANAL ZONE<lb/>
EXECUTIVE DEPARTMENT<lb/>
Balboa Heights, C. Z.<lb/>
<date value="1923-05-10">May 10, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
IN REPLY REFER TO FILE<lb/>
CABLE ADDRESS:<lb/>
&ldquo;PANCANAL, PANAMA&rdquo;<lb/>
Dr. Henry R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St., N.W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Referring to your letter of April 18, 1923, to Dr. W. C. Rucker,<lb/>
Chief Quarantine Officer, The Panama Canal, requesting data relative to<lb/>
steamer traffic between the west coast of Central and South America to<lb/>
Asia and Australia:</p>
<p>At the present time there are no lines direct from west Central<lb/>
and South American ports to Australia excepting those transiting the Canal<lb/>
en route from North American and European ports. A number of these stop<lb/>
at Canal ports for taking on or discharging passengers or freight, but as<lb/>
you are aware we have had no yellow fever on the Isthmus for a number of<lb/>
years and the chances of introduction from this source would be quite re-<lb/>
mote. These vessels go direct to either New Zealand or Australian ports<lb/>
and the voyage takes approximately three to four weeks after clearing from<lb/>
Canal ports.</p>
<p>The Toyo Kisen Kaisha Line has sailings approximately once every<lb/>
seven weeks between west Central and South American ports and eastern Asia.<lb/>
Ports of call include Valparaiso, Iquique, Antofagasta, and Arica, Chile;<lb/>
Pisco, Mollendo, and Callao, Peru; Balboa, Canal Zone; Manzanillo and<lb/>
Salina Cruz (optional), Mexico; Los Angeles and San Francisco, U.S.A.;<lb/>
Honolulu, Manila, Moji, Kobe, Yokohama, Hongkong, and Shanghai. The ves-<lb/>
sels of this line carry both passengers and freight, and the voyage con-<lb/>
sumes about five weeks after leaving Manzanillo, Mexico, before touching<lb/>
at Asiatic ports. First, second and third class passengers are handled,<lb/>
the latter predominating, and they frequently carry as high as 200 passeng-<lb/>
ers per trip. Four of the vessels that have been employed on this route<lb/>
are the &ldquo;<hi>Rakuyo Maru</hi>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<hi>Seiyo</hi> Maru&rdquo;, &ldquo;<hi>Anyo</hi> Maru&rdquo;, and &ldquo;<hi>Ginyo</hi> Maru&rdquo;, and<lb/>
their respective registered gross tonnages are, 9,419, 6,550, 9,257 and<lb/>
8,600 tons.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;Hwah Ping&rdquo;, a vessel of 4,254 tons registered gross, owned<lb/>
by the Chinese Government, has made two round trips within the past year<lb/>
between China and west South and Central American ports. This vessel also<lb/>
carries both freight and passengers and the itinerary is much the same as<lb/>
that of the Toyo Kisen Kaisha. Whether this will develop into a regular<lb/>
service or not is problematical.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01102020"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>As in the Australian traffic, there are a number of lines<lb/>
transiting the Canal for Asiatic ports, some of which load supplies or<lb/>
cargo at Canal ports, but none of these call at west Central or South<lb/>
American ports after transiting the Canal.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>JNO. H. SMITH<lb/>
Acting Executive Secretary</signed>
42<lb/>
42<lb/>
(164)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
