<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01107002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Place of Origin of Malaria: America?, by [Henry Rose Carter], [1923]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01107002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">Amazon River</name>
<name type="place">Tabasco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Honduras</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Port Royal (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-00-00">[1923]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01107002</idno>
<title>Report: Place of Origin of Malaria: America?, by [Henry Rose Carter], [1923]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter contends that America was free from malaria prior to its exploration and settlement by Europeans and Africans.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-00-00">
<head>Report: Place of Origin of Malaria: America?, [Henry Rose Carter], [1923]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01107002"/>
<p>Miscel.<lb/>
S. M. J.</p>
<p>Place of Origin of Malaria.<lb/>
America?</p>
<p>Did malaria exist in America prior to its discovery? The writer is<lb/>
inclined to doubt it. Anopheles mosquitoes did, however, the American spe-<lb/>
cies differing from those in the Old World, and when the parasites were<lb/>
introduced by European, and <hi>African</hi>, carriers it quickly spread both from<lb/>
them and from the Indians infected <add>from them-,</add> directly and indirectly.</p>
<p>The evidence for this is:</p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>(1) That in the early expeditions of Europeans coming from reason-<lb/>
ably healthful regions and simply <hi>passing through</hi> hitherto unvisited In-<lb/>
dian country extensive sickness is rarely recorded, except that due to<lb/>
hardship and starvation. This is true even when the region traversed by<lb/>
the expedition is now malarious and was at the time physically well suited<lb/>
for the production of Anopheles mosquitoes and doubtless was then produc-<lb/>
ing them. In a number of such cases the absence of sickness is implied and<lb/>
in some specifically mentioned.</p></item>
<item><p>(2) When, however, a fairly prolonged stay or a settlement was<lb/>
made by Europeans in places which are now malarious &ldquo;fevers and calen-<lb/>
turas&rdquo; very generally developed and in many cases were deadly. This was<lb/>
especially the case when the expeditions came <add>from</add>, or via, places (usually<lb/>
in America) where such fevers were prevalent. Even a somewhat prolonged<lb/>
stay at one place--as when Orellana remained &ldquo;over the whole of Lent&rdquo; at<lb/>
one place on the Amazon--did not lead to sickness when the Europeans had<lb/>
been long resident in regions free from malaria.</p></item></list>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>For example: (1) The implication is strong that there was no se-<lb/>
rious sickness--if there was any--in Oxenham's expedition of 1575 across<lb/>
the Isthmus of Darien and return until he had gone into fairly perma-<lb/>
nent camp on the north coast in the country of the &ldquo;Cimaroons&rdquo;--negro<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01107003"/>
negro<lb/>
2<lb/>
slaves who had run away from the Spaniards. Yet Isaac Strain, U. S. Navy,<lb/>
in 1854, with all the facilities of that much later period, lost a number of<lb/>
his men from fevers on crossing one way and could not have made the re-<lb/>
turn journey.</p></item>
<item><p>(2) Drake's Darien expedition of 1572 reported no sickness until<lb/>
they had been long in permanent camp on the north coast of the Isthmus<lb/>
and practically in communication with Spanish settlements. They had been<lb/>
in the country about six months before the outbreak of &ldquo;calenturas&rdquo; show-<lb/>
ed--which may, or may not, have been malaria.</p></item>
<item><p>(3) Raleigh's expedition of 1595 by boat and on foot up the Orino-<lb/>
co for 400 miles. To quote him: &ldquo;Moreover the country is healthful as<lb/>
100 persons and more which lay (without shift most sluttishly and were<lb/>
evry day almost melted with heat in rowing and marching and suddenly wet<lb/>
againe with greate showers and did eat all sorte of corrupt fruits and made<lb/>
meales of fresh fish without seasoning: of Tortugas: of Lagartos and of al<lb/>
sorte good and bad without either order or measure and besides did lodge<lb/>
in the open air evry night) we lost not any one, nor had one ill disposed<lb/>
to my knowledge, nor found anie Calentura or other of those pestilent dis-<lb/>
eases which dwell in all hote regions so near the Equinoctial line.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He entered the river the latter part of March or early in April--<lb/>
was there in the rainy season--and made it his business to stop at Indian<lb/>
villages. This result could not now be duplicated even with quinine.</p></item>
<item><p>(4) Orellana's long voyage down the Amazon in 1541 entailed lit-<lb/>
tle, apparently no, loss from sickness, although the men were broken by pri-<lb/>
vation and starving before they started--seven dying of hunger. They made<lb/>
at least two prolonged stops--one of not less than 47 days near the mouth<lb/>
of the Napo (building boats) and one of 18 days, repairing them some months<lb/>
later. They had much communication--hostile generally--with the Indians<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01107004"/>
Indians<lb/>
3<lb/>
and got their provisions from their villages.</p>
<p>At present from such a trip of over seven months, and without quinine,<lb/>
we should expect a loss of over 75% of the expedition.</p></item>
<item><p>(5) The first invasion of Tabasco by Cortez in 1519 was apparently<lb/>
not followed by sickness among his men, yet in 1529, when Montejo wished to<lb/>
use this province as a base for the invasion of Yucatan, it was so un-<lb/>
healthful that the Spaniards, occupying it since 1523, were on the point of<lb/>
abandoning it.</p></item>
<item><p>(6) There were deaths, probably a number of them, in the expedi-<lb/>
tion Cortez led across the wet lands of Tehuantepac and southern Campeche<lb/>
and Yucatan to Honduras in 1524-5, but they seem to have been due to priva-<lb/>
tion and hardships rather than disease--they even ate their guides (&ldquo;a stra-<lb/>
tegic error,&rdquo; records Capitan Don Bernal Diaz) and thus lost their way.<lb/>
Had that country been as malarious as it is now, these Spaniards and Mexi-<lb/>
cans from the highlands had probably never reached the Honduran Coast.</p></item>
<item><p>(7) The sanitary condition of the country adjacent to the port of<lb/>
Vera Cruz (Medillin) changed much for the worse both for Spanish and In-<lb/>
dians after its occupation as a permanent settlement from--say--1519, when<lb/>
it was first occupied and when we hear nothing of its unhealthfulness, to<lb/>
1537 when Bishop Marroquin complained so bitterly of it.</p></item></list>
<p>For the second part: settlements once established in places now re-<lb/>
cognized as malarious became unhealthful--sometimes extremely so--as Isabe-<lb/>
la: Nombre de Dios: Vera Cruz. Sta. Marta: Martinique: the Guianas: James-<lb/>
town: Biloxi: Port Royal, S. C.: New Orleans: Savannah etc. It is to be<lb/>
noted that almost as soon as these settlements in Spanish and French Ameri-<lb/>
ca were established, negroes direct from Africa were introduced.</p>
<p>Compare this with Africa. Europeans visiting the West Coast of Af-<lb/>
rica--even the first visitors--came away with fevers, although the visit<lb/>
may have been very brief. No stay on any West African river comparable to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01107005"/>
to<lb/>
4<lb/>
Raleigh's on the Orinoco or Orellana's on the Amazon was possible without<lb/>
an enormous loss of life--possibly of the whole expedition judging from<lb/>
the loss from staying a shorter time. When in the voyage to America ves-<lb/>
sels stopped at West African ports, whether mainland or on the adjacent<lb/>
islands, we find almost always, no <hi>expressed</hi> exceptions are recalled, that<lb/>
they suffered from fevers during the remainder of the voyage before reach-<lb/>
ing America. Such was the case with Hawkins in 1567: with Drake and Car-<lb/>
leisle in 1588 and with very many others.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
