<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01109017">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from <unclear>Willys</unclear> M. Monroe to Henry Rose Carter, [June 1923]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Monroe, Willys M.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01109017</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-06-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Connor, M. E.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Matanzas (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Neuvitas (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Heredia (Costa Rica)</name>
<name type="place">San Domingo (Costa Rica)</name>
<name type="place">La Mesa (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Veracruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Panuco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">El Higo (Mexico)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-06-00">[June 1923]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01109017</idno>
<title>Letter from <unclear>Willys</unclear> M. Monroe to Henry Rose Carter, [June 1923]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter responds to Monroe's letter that asks several questions about the epidemiology of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-06-00">
<head>Letter from <unclear>Willys</unclear> M. Monroe to Henry Rose Carter, [June 1923]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01109017"/>
<opener>
Book<lb/>
<del>I. H. B.</del><lb/>
<unclear>Monroe.</unclear><lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just read a mimeographed copy of the Section<lb/>
on Epidemiology of your History of Yellow fever, and as there are a few<lb/>
points that I have been wondering about for some time which I had hoped<lb/>
would be cleared up in your book, but which you probably thought too<lb/>
unimportant to mention, I am taking the liberty of writing to you for<lb/>
a word or two of explanation.</p>
<p>When I was working with Dr. Connor in Mexico in 1921<lb/>
and 1922, I heard a great deal of the condition which you designate re<lb/>
gional endemicity, and which Dr. Connor calls &ldquo;hacienda infection&rdquo;, At<lb/>
the time I gained the impression that such a condition could exist only<lb/>
where the combined populations of the various units of the area would be<lb/>
equal to that of a single large town, travel conditions being such that<lb/>
the area is a unit in reality. For example, I can readily see that the<lb/>
Papalo-apan Valley in the southern part of the State of Vera Cruz would<lb/>
be considered as an area of regional endemicity, for it has a larte popul<lb/>
ation with river communication, and the temperature is such that there are<lb/>
throughout the year, and I think uniformly, active A. aegypti mosquitoes.</p>
<p>But I have been wondering if certain regions with<lb/>
not<lb/>
a much smaller total population could also be considered areas of<lb/>
regional endemicity, if certain other factors were variable. According to<lb/>
your postulate B, three factors are necessary for the continued existence<lb/>
of Yellow fever in any place (1) The causative organism of the disease,<lb/>
(2) Active A. aegypti mosquitoes, and (3) Men susceptible to the disease.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01109018"/>
Granted the presence of the first factor, would not the continuance of<lb/>
the disease depend not so much on the number of non-immunes, as on the<lb/>
rate of exhaustion of non-immunes, which, it would seem to me, would dep<lb/>
end on how closely the number of active A. aegypti mosquitoes approached<lb/>
the critical number, a close approximation causing a low rate of exhausti<lb/>
ion, but, on the other hand, a large excess of A. aegypti in the active<lb/>
state causing a rapid exhaustion of the non-immune population.</p>
<p>In your discussion of the effects of temperature, Page 37, you<lb/>
show the relation of the increase and decrease of Yellow fever to the rise<lb/>
and fall of temperature as it applies to cities, and I assume that this<lb/>
is due to the lessened mosquito breeding during the cooler weather.<lb/>
Might not this lower rate of production of imagoes cause the disease to<lb/>
continue in rural areas with populations so small that they would not be<lb/>
considered endemic regions but rather epidemic, if the temperature were<lb/>
the optimum for mosquito production?</p>
<p>I was working in Tampico during parts of 1921 and 1922, shortly<lb/>
after there had been several epidemics in the country districts between<lb/>
Tampico and Vera Cruz, where the winters were hardly severe enough to in-<lb/>
terfere with mosquito production. These epidemics were controlled, perhaps<lb/>
with the aid of anti-mosquito measures, perhaps by spontaneous eliminat<lb/>
ion. After a year without any cases, control measures were discontinued<lb/>
in Tampico, but just at the end of my stay there were rumors of cases up<lb/>
the Panuco Valley, above Tampico. These, however, were disregarded after<lb/>
inspections of the city of Panuco by both Dr. Connor and myself. Above<lb/>
the city of Panuco there is a small but well populated district called<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01109019"/>
El Higo. In Tampico the production of adult A. aegypti is greatly reduced<lb/>
in the winter. This I know from personal observation. El Higo has practi<lb/>
cally the same latitude as Tampico, but it is at a slightly higher elevat<lb/>
ion, so that the winter is even cooler. Just above El Higo there is an<lb/>
other valley at Micos where I was unable to find A. aegypti breeding dur<lb/>
ing the winter. After I left Tampico in 1922, several cases of Yellow<lb/>
fever were imported from Panuco. Do you think that the <del>region</del><add>valley</add> above Panuco<lb/>
could have remained as a region of endemicity, the lessened mosquito pro<lb/>
duction, due to the cool weather, compensating for the relative paucity<lb/>
of non-immunes, by causing the rate of exhaustion to be very low?</p>
<p>I have recently returned from Colombia, S. A., where Dr. White<lb/>
is investigating a reported outbreak of Yellow fever in Bucaramanga. I<lb/>
have not seen Bucaramanga, but I have seen in Departments adjacent to and<lb/>
very much like Santander, valleys, where because of the altitude, condit<lb/>
ions analagous to winter conditions in El Higo exist throughout the year,<lb/>
and mosquito production must be greatly retarded. Could not endemic condit<lb/>
ions prevail for many years in such a valley where the high percentage of<lb/>
non-immunes would lead one to believe that the disease would be epidemic?</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,</salute>
<signed><unclear>Willys</unclear> M. Monroe.<lb/>
International Health Board</signed>
Dr. H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
