<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01109033">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to E.J. Scannell, June 17, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01109033</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-06-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Scannel, E.J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Connor, M. E.</name>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Perrin, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Darling, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Eugenia Hook</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Iquitos (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Petropolis (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico City</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-06-17">June 17, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01109033</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to E.J. Scannell, June 17, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] responds to Scannell's critique of his epidemiology paper.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-06-17">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to E.J. Scannell, June 17, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01109033"/>
<opener>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1923-06-17">June 17, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Scannell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was glad to get your letter of June 3rd, and I hope Connor's<lb/>
and Hanson's (and possibly White's) will be as constructive in their<lb/>
criticisms on my Epidemiology. How the thing appears from a different<lb/>
view-point is always desireable.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>1/ The only duration of life of <hi>aegypti</hi> of importance in epidem-<lb/>
iology necessarily is that duration <hi>in nature</hi>: (a) the maximum for any<lb/>
one insect: (b) the duration of life of such numbers as would suffice<lb/>
to continue infection. The first might well be occasional<add>ly</add> as <add>long as</add> occurs<lb/>
in a laboratory, and an insect thus preserved <hi>might</hi> once in a while<lb/>
lead to a very much belated case of yellow fever.</p>
<p>at that time &amp; place</p>
<p>(B) Naturally depends upon the critical number of <add>at that time and place</add> <hi>aegypti</hi>--i. e. on<lb/>
the number of susceptible and unsusceptible men in a community <add>their distribution</add></p>
<p>At Iquitos this seemed to be about six weeks--the same length of<lb/>
time is obtainable from an analysis of Connor's report of Guayaquil. I<lb/>
was able to fix the time more definitely than either at Paita, having<lb/>
the advantage of working under closer conditions. In a community where<lb/>
there was a large number of susceptible people the chance is that this<lb/>
time would be somewhat longer than either myself or Converse observed it.</p></item>
<item>2/ And here is where you helped me: In the script of the Epidemio-<lb/>
logy I wrote &ldquo;in no collection of water with &lsquo;exclusively earth&rsquo; (mud)<lb/>
&lsquo;sides&rsquo; at the surface of the water.&rdquo; I struck out &ldquo;mud&rdquo;, because I<lb/>
thought earth in contact with water would naturally be considered mud.<lb/>
I am going to return to my original statement. I am quite sure that it<lb/>
is the <hi>consistency</hi> of the container <hi>at the surface of the water</hi> rather<lb/>
than its material that affects ovaposition. A hardened hollow in wood</item>
</list></p>
<pb n="2" id="f01109034"/>
<p>wood<lb/>
2<lb/>
ashes would be perfectly suitable as would burnt earth.</p>
<p>3/ It is reasonable to believe that the limits of viability of the<lb/>
causative organism might well be different from, and less than, those of<lb/>
its insect host. For malaria this is certainly the case; (a) the parasite<lb/>
dies from an exposure much less than that which killes the Anopheles<lb/>
carrying it and (b) does not develope in the insect at some temperatures<lb/>
at which the insect is functionally active--although here the difference<lb/>
in temperature limits is slight.</p>
<p>For the first, however, one must note that Anopheles hibernates as<lb/>
imago and <hi>aegypti</hi> does not, or if so for only a very short time. This<lb/>
would prevent this part of the analogy from having much, if any, weight.</p>
<p>I considered saying something about this in the Epidemiology, but did<lb/>
not, because we have no sufficient data on this subject and I purposed to<lb/>
include in it only proven things. There are a number of instances in<lb/>
which the temperature (outside) has fallen well below 60&deg;F (some below<lb/>
50&deg;F) in which yellow fever has continued quite vigorously <hi>after</hi> it rose<lb/>
again. This happened at Memphis in /97 after moderate frost. Of course<lb/>
it would be impossible to say to what temperature the mosquitoes that<lb/>
carried on this infection were exposed, many of them being sheltered in<lb/>
houses, but I doubt if it was not well below 80&deg;F. Immediately after<lb/>
the cold weather there was practically a cessation of yellow fever,<lb/>
which recrudesced, and indeed increased, in a week or ten days. The<lb/>
picture (and inference) was as if the function of the agency infective<lb/>
to man was <hi>suspended</hi> by the cold, but not destroyed, or even much less-<lb/>
ened when the temperature rose again.</p>
<p>Admitting the causative relation of the <hi>L. icteroides</hi> and that 80 F.<lb/>
is the optimum temperature for their culture, we do not know in what form<lb/>
they exist in the insect and it may well be that in this stage they may<lb/>
be able to <hi>live</hi> at a temperature below that necessary for <hi>development</hi>.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01109035"/>
<p>development.</p>
<p>3</p>
<p>This is true of the <hi>plasmodium malariae</hi>, both tertian and falciparum.</p>
<p>The epidemiological evidence, as far as it goes, implies (I do<lb/>
not say <hi>proves</hi>) that the insects retain their infection --not necessar-<lb/>
ily their infectivity--under almost any conditions that enable them to<lb/>
live.</p>
<p>Experimentally the question could be readily settled by human exper-<lb/>
iments. Expose a few aegypti known to be infective to man to X&deg; Centi-<lb/>
grade (X&deg;C. being low enough to suspend functional activity of the in-<lb/>
sects, but not to kill them) and see if they are still infective when<lb/>
the temperature is raised again. Guinea pigs could be used, of course,<lb/>
but their infection by aegypti seems to be so uncertain that a very large<lb/>
number of observations would be needed to establish a <hi>negative</hi> result.</p>
<p>The only epidemiological evidence on this matter which I can think<lb/>
of as readily obtainable would be to see whether in nature the geographi-<lb/>
cal limits of the propagation of yellow fever (i. e. of &ldquo;infectable ter-<lb/>
ritory&rdquo;) corresponds to that of functionally active <hi>aegypti.</hi> If the in-<lb/>
sects are functionally active in a place known to be non-infectable there<lb/>
are three hypotheses:</p>
<p>(a) They <del>might</del><add>were</add> not be in sufficient numbers to convey yellow fever<lb/>
with the chances that they have had:</p>
<p>(b) The parasite does not at the temperature of that place undergo<lb/>
the development (Noguchi would say the <hi>increase</hi>) in the mosquito neces-<lb/>
sary to render her infective or</p>
<p>(c) The parasite dies in the mosquito.</p>
<p>Subjecting mosquitoes which had fed on a sick man at the place in<lb/>
question to a higher temperature after feeding and determining their in-<lb/>
fectivity would settle between (b) and (c).</p>
<p>Petropolis, Brazil; and the City of Mexico might give you data on<lb/>
this subject.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01109036"/>
<p>subject.</p>
<p>4</p>
<p>Fernando Lopez found that in their laboratory--apparently not heated--<lb/>
<hi>aegypti</hi> were functionally active--although slow in their life processes--<lb/>
in Mexico City, which I think we have a right to call non-infectable<lb/>
territory. <unclear>Are they</unclear> found there, <unclear>L'coaga</unclear> said not, <unclear>&amp;</unclear> if so to what extent,</p>
<p>I think, however, I will insert a foot note in the Epidemiology,<lb/>
when published, calling attention to this matter and, naturally, men-<lb/>
tioning you as suggesting it.</p>
<p>4/ I have from the beginning been inclined (possibly because very de-<lb/>
sireous) to accept the causarive role of <hi>L. icteroides</hi> and have done so<lb/>
since Feb./20, when Noguchi published his differentiation between this<lb/>
organism and <hi>Icteroides haemorrhagica</hi> (by cross Pfeiffer and immune re-<lb/>
actions). It is (See Page 5)<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01109037"/>
is<lb/>
5<lb/>
fair to say, however--as I did for the Nelson Loose-Leaf people--that<lb/>
this is &ldquo;generally, but not universally accepted.&rdquo; Neither Welch of<lb/>
Hopkins nor Rosenau of Harvard regard it as established and I confess<lb/>
I would myself be better satisfied were the mosquito conveyance experi-<lb/>
ments more satisfactory. I feel like discounting the opposition of<lb/>
Guiteras--for whose opinion I have in general the very highest regard--<lb/>
because I doubt the technique with which the experiments with this or-<lb/>
ganism have been made by the Havana school. I could wish much that he<lb/>
(Guiteras) and they could get in such personal touch with Noguchi as<lb/>
to have the matter settled, at least as between them.</p>
<p>By the way, a recent description by a Dr. Perrin of the histo-path-<lb/>
ology of the liver in yellow fever would. I think, not be accepted by<lb/>
Darling: Russell or da Rocha Lima as distinctive. This last, as you<lb/>
know, gave his name to the <del>inter</del><add>&ldquo;mid-</add> zonal necrosis&rdquo;; in general characteristic<lb/>
of yellow fever.</p>
<p>With very best remembrances, in which Laura, who is writing this<lb/>
joins</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly your friend,</salute>
<seg>
P. S.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
