<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01103002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Preliminary report of the special commission on yellow fever for Colombia by Joseph H. White, [1923]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01103002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Miller, Frederick A.</name>
<name type="person">Pareja, Wenceslao</name>
<name type="person">Pothier, Oliver L.</name>
<name type="person">Capina, Pedro Nel</name>
<name type="person">Medina, Pedro Garcia</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Barranquilla (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Bogota (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Cucuta (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Colombia (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Cartagena (Colombia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-00-00">[1923]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01103002</idno>
<title>Preliminary report of the special commission on yellow fever for Colombia by Joseph H. White, [1923]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>White's report states that the Colombian government accepts the existence of yellow fever in the country, and will pay half of the funding for the International Health Board's yellow fever campaign. It details the geographic locations of the disease.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-00-00">
<head>Preliminary report of the special commission on yellow fever for Colombia by Joseph H. White, [1923]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01103002"/>
<opener>
<hi>COPY</hi><lb/>
I. H. B<lb/>
Columbia<lb/>
</opener>
<p>PRELIMINARY REPORT OF THE SPECIAL COMMISSION<lb/>
ON YELLOW FEVER FOR COLOMBIA.</p>
<p>The three members of the commission met in Colon on April 18, and sailed<lb/>
on S. S. Carrillo on the 19th. for Puerto Colombia arriving there on the 21st.,<lb/>
and the same night at Barranquilla by rail, being met at that point by Dr. Miller.</p>
<p>We took the first steamer up the Rio Magdalena on the 23rd., and arrived<lb/>
at Puerto Wilches on the 26th. at 4 P. M., and then went by rail to Ceiba, 27<lb/>
kilometers the same night.</p>
<p>After three days mule back through swamps, deserts and mountains we arrived<lb/>
at Bucaramanga on the afternoon of April 30th. and were met just outside the<lb/>
city by the Governor, the Departmental Health Officer and a large delegation of<lb/>
citizens.</p>
<p>On the afternoon of our arrival a case of fever was reported in the city<lb/>
hospital and immediately seen by Dr. Pareja and the next morning by the whole<lb/>
commission. This case, Esteban Figueroa, a police officer showed all the<lb/>
classical signs of yellow fever in the sixth day and was in our opinion unques-<lb/>
tionably yellow fever, but Dr. Pothier took blood from this, and from another<lb/>
very mild case deemed suspicious and probably yellow fever. The case of the<lb/>
policeman gave a posite reaction with cultures &ldquo;Leptospira-Icteroides&rdquo; and the<lb/>
other a somewhat vague reaction.</p>
<p>Dr. Pothier was unable to secure sufficient number of guinea pigs to make<lb/>
the cross reaction with &ldquo;Leptospira Icteroides Haemorrhagica&rdquo; and therefore<lb/>
took blood from the above mentioned cases and from one severe and one mild case<lb/>
occuring in February for further test in Bogota where ample laboratory facilities<lb/>
are available.</p>
<p>We deemed it necessary to proceed to Bogota for the reasons above mentioned,<lb/>
because the difference in expense was unimportant, and for the more important<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01103003"/>
-2-<lb/>
reason that it was believed that it might need the testimony of the whole com-<lb/>
mission to satisfy the government, which had manifested strong disbelief in the<lb/>
diagnosis.</p>
<p>Leaving Bucaramanga mule back on May 6, we arrived after five days of<lb/>
arduous travel at Belen on the night of May 10, and on May 11, went into Bogota<lb/>
by automobile 150 miles, meeting the Honorable the Minister of Agriculture and<lb/>
the Director of Public Health at Tunja 100 miles from Bogota.</p>
<p>The commission was received Saturday afternoon May 12 by his Excellency,<lb/>
General Pedro Nel Capina the President of Colombia and after a conference of one<lb/>
and one half hours an agreement was reached by which the diagnosis was accepted<lb/>
and the Colombian Government obligated to pay one half the general expense of a<lb/>
campaign this year estimated by the head of the commission to be about 25,000.00<lb/>
U. S. Currency and the International Health Board to pay the other $25,000.00,<lb/>
and the expense of the direction.</p>
<p>The direction was conceded to the International Health Board whose director<lb/>
is to report his actions to Dr. Pablo Garcia Medina, Director of Public Health<lb/>
but be in fact in complete control.</p>
<p>It was explained to the President that at least a year of continuous work<lb/>
would be necessary and that the commission basing its opinion on casual but<lb/>
epidemiologicaly powerful evidence was convinced of the following:</p>
<p>1. That the coast towns are not (as yet) infected.</p>
<p>2. That the source of infection to Bucaramanga is almost certainly Cucuta.</p>
<p>3. That careful investigations of Barranquilla and Cucuta are essential.</p>
<p>4. That active campaigns must be initiated at once at all infected points.</p>
<p>(From conversation with a recently arrived resident of Cucuta the commission<lb/>
is disposed to agree with the chairman who feels certain that Cucuta is now<lb/>
and has been for many years an endemic focus of yellow fever.)</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01103004"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>The $50,000.00 agreed upon will be probably sufficient for the remaining<lb/>
months of the year 1923 for the whole country even though Cucuta with its<lb/>
nearby and easily accessible smaller neighbors numbering about 80,000 should be<lb/>
endemic.</p>
<p>Bucaramanga like Cucuta is in effect a town of nearer 80,000 than its nomi-<lb/>
nal 25,000 having several smaller cities closely tied up with it and all infected<lb/>
to some extent.</p>
<p>There is an incidence of 70% Stegomyia infestation in Bucaramanga.</p>
<p>Since the commission rode away twenty new cases are reported in Bucaramanga,<lb/>
and some in the small nearby towns.</p>
<p>From the information obtainable at our hands we believe that Bucaramanga has<lb/>
been infected from Cucuta several times during the last forty years and that it<lb/>
in turn has infected many small places on the trail to the Magdalena and to some<lb/>
degree up and down that river.</p>
<p>The commission is not prepared pending a more searching study, to acquit<lb/>
entirely the coast towns of infection but in as much as Americans and Europeans<lb/>
are in these towns in large numbers and constantly arriving and departing with-<lb/>
out the appearance of a single suspicious indication among them, we doubt the<lb/>
existence of yellow fever in either Barranquill, Puerto Colombia or Cartagena.</p>
<p>Further report will be submitted by Drs. Pothier and Pareja on completion<lb/>
of their work.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Sgd) J. H. White</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
