<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01109031">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Malaria News Item No. 14, Organization of County Mosquito Control Associations, by the State health Department, June 12, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01109031</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-06-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Americus (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Rusk (Tex.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-06-12">June 12, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01109031</idno>
<title>Report: Malaria News Item No. 14, Organization of County Mosquito Control Associations, by the State health Department, June 12, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This health department report uses three county associations as examples of what can be done to control malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-06-12">
<head>Report: Malaria News Item No. 14, Organization of County Mosquito Control Associations, by the State health Department, June 12, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01109031"/>
<p>Malaria News Item No. 14<lb/>
State Health Department.<lb/>
_____________<lb/>
<date value="1923-06-12">June 12, 1923.</date>
</p>
<p><hi>ORGANIZATION OF COUNTY MOSQUITO CONTROL ASSOCIATIONS.</hi></p>
<p>Recently three voluntary county malaria control associations<lb/>
have been formed in three southern states: The Sumter County Mal-<lb/>
aria Control Association at Americus, Ga, The Cherokee County<lb/>
Malaria Control Association at Rusk, Texas, and the Shelby County<lb/>
Malaria Control Association at Memphis, Tennessee.</p>
<p>The object of these county mosquito control associations is<lb/>
to endorse and support the efforts and activities of state, county<lb/>
and local health authorities in accomplishing malaria and mosquito<lb/>
elimination; to stimulate interest in the suppression of disease<lb/>
bearing mosquitoes that effect human comfort and health; to secure<lb/>
and spread information and to urge cooperative efforts in the county<lb/>
by individuals, associations, communities and their governments to<lb/>
the end that these insect nuisances may be done away with.</p>
<p>Mr. John W. Shiver of Americus, Ga., president of the Sumter<lb/>
County, Ga., Association, induced his association to start active<lb/>
drainage operations in the county the day of his election and has<lb/>
appointed active delegates in each county school district. The<lb/>
Chamber of Commerce of Americus, Ga., is greatly interested and<lb/>
feels the results of the work going on will increase the value of<lb/>
every acre of land in the county.</p>
<p>The members of the Shelby County, Tenn., Association sel-<lb/>
ected for their leader and president one of the most prominent bus-<lb/>
iness men of Memphis Mr. Wm. C. Johnson. As president of the Mem-<lb/>
phis Chamber of Commerce Mr. Johnson had much to do with its success-<lb/>
ful development, and is intensely interested in the elimination of<lb/>
malaria from Shelby County. He believes it will have a most im-<lb/>
portant bearing on the growth and development of Memphis.</p>
<p>There are many counties in our southern states where<lb/>
malaria control is every bit as important to their commercial and<lb/>
agricultural development as was the control of malaria and yellow<lb/>
fever to the construction of the Panama Canal. It is encouraging<lb/>
to see these leaders of the prominent business men of the South de-<lb/>
vote their time gratis and identify themselves with such voluntary<lb/>
organizations. The results that can be accomplished by these and<lb/>
similar organizations will lead to such progress and development<lb/>
of the South as she is justly entitled to.</p>
<p>If your county has a mosquito problem it would be well<lb/>
for you to ask yourselves this question &ldquo;WhaT help can we give to<lb/>
the state and local health authorities in handling this problem for<lb/>
us.&rdquo; Possibly a Mosquito Control Association in your county is all<lb/>
that is needed to put the thing across. Ask your State Health<lb/>
Officer about it.</p>
<p>---------------------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
