<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01119018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Case history of David Manrique by Roberto Serpa, translated by Frederick A. Miller, [1923]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01119018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Columbia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-00-00">[1923]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01119018</idno>
<title>Case history of David Manrique by Roberto Serpa, translated by Frederick A. Miller, [1923]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The case history describes Manrique's final illness and his autopsy.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-00-00">
<head>Case history of David Manrique by Roberto Serpa, translated by Frederick A. Miller, [1923]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01119018"/>
<p>COPY</p>
<p>History #2</p>
<p>David Manrique, 52 years of age, citizen of Onzaga and lived in<lb/>
Rionegro for more than eight years where he was employed as a farm laborer.</p>
<p>In past years had been a patient in the hospital in Bucaramanga<lb/>
on account of some nervous disease undetermined. He had suffered from fre-<lb/>
quent diarrheas. He took intoxicating liquors in excess and was accustomed<lb/>
to become drunk about every eight days. He lived on an hacienda named<lb/>
&ldquo;Las Quebradas&rdquo; distant from Rionegro four hours or twelve miles, this<lb/>
hacienda being the closest to the town.</p>
<p>On the 30th of July, he arrived from the hacienda and stayed in the<lb/>
house until 7.p.m. and then went to the street returning at 8 p.m. on account<lb/>
of having felt symptoms of diarrhea. On the 31st. he felt better and went<lb/>
again to the street occupied in normal occupation; during the day he was seen<lb/>
to take &ldquo;aguardiente&rdquo; (native brandy) and &ldquo;guarapo&rdquo;. He went to bed at 8 p.m.<lb/>
feeling a little indisposed. He awoke at 10 p.m. with great pain in the<lb/>
abdomen, nausea, vomiting, great pain in the hips and diarrhea. The vomiting<lb/>
and the diarrhea were normal in color and he thought it was one of the usual<lb/>
attacks of diarrhea. The vomiting and the diarrhea continued, the diarrhea<lb/>
becoming bloody and the vomiting at first yellow, then red and then black at<lb/>
the same time the abdominal pains increased as well as those of the hips. At<lb/>
this time patient could not urinate.</p>
<p>On the 2nd. of August this office was notified of the condition of<lb/>
the patient. He was sent to the hospital immediately and the physical examina-<lb/>
tion showed: Face anxious, respirations shallow, great pain in the abdomen,<lb/>
restlessness, and great pain in the epigastric region on palpation. Pulse<lb/>
thready, imperceptible, temperature 39 1/2 C.</p>
<p>From time to time the patient vomited material the color of<lb/>
&ldquo;cafecon leche&rdquo;. The stools were abundant and bloody. A sound was passed<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01119019"/>
2<lb/>
to secure urine and the bladder found completely empty. At that time was<lb/>
prescribed small doses of solution of Sodium Bicarbonate 3%.</p>
<p>At 8.30 p.m. of the 2nd of August the patient died vomiting black<lb/>
material. The death occurred 48 hours after the appearance of the first<lb/>
symptom;</p>
<p>On the 3rd. of August at 3.30 p.m. an autopsy was performed and<lb/>
showed the following: the tissues very slightly subicteric with post mortem<lb/>
ecchimomtic spots. The subcutaneous tissue showed a yellow tint a little<lb/>
more pronounced than normal. The mucosa of the lips and gums showed haemorrhagic<lb/>
spots. On opening the abdominal cavity the intestines were seen to be dilated<lb/>
and congested in their whole extent, with all the vessels visible and of a<lb/>
dark red color, bathed in a transudate haematic or peritoneal fluid.</p>
<p>The contents of the stomach were of a dark grey color and the<lb/>
mucosa showed many plaques ecchimotic in the cardiac region, haemorrhagic<lb/>
points along the greater and lesser curvatures and ecchimotic plaques in the<lb/>
pyloric region. Liver greatly congested of the color of red wine and with<lb/>
some spots a little darker. Some parts of the liver were harder than the<lb/>
normal liver and others softer so that one could press their finger into it.<lb/>
The liver bled on section. The gall bladder was one and one half times<lb/>
normal size and contained a great amount of normal bile; thirteen gall stones<lb/>
of the size of a grain of corn were found but none in the ducts. SPLEEN normal.<lb/>
KIDNEYS congested but of normal size with haemorrhagic points on the surface.<lb/>
The parenchyma more congested and blood flowed on section. The BLADDER re-<lb/>
tracted and doubled and the pubis was completely empty. The LUNGS normal,<lb/>
The HEART normal in size, congested and the ventricules contained liquid<lb/>
blood. It was noted that the blood was more fluid and less viscous than<lb/>
normal.</p>
<p>Translated from the report of Dr. Roberto Serpa</p>
<closer>
<signed>F.A.M.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
