<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01118001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Abstract: Yellow Fever, edited by Henry Rose Carter, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01118001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Connor, M. E.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Brazil</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">Ceara (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Bahia (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Amazon (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Manaos (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Iquitos (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Gold Coast (West Africa)</name>
<name type="place">Ivory Coast (Africa)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
<name type="place">North America</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-00-00">1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01118001</idno>
<title>Abstract: Yellow Fever, edited by Henry Rose Carter, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter comments on recent yellow fever articles and summarizes yellow fever work. He discusses the relation of Leptospira icteroides to yellow fever and the use of curative sera. He also mentions the recent yellow fever outbreaks in Brazil, Colombia, and West Africa.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-00-00">
<head>Abstract: Yellow Fever, edited by Henry Rose Carter, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01118001"/>
<opener>
Miscl-<lb/>
Nelson Loose-Leaf<lb/>
March 1/<hi>23</hi>-Oct. <hi>1/23</hi><lb/>
YELLOW FEVER.<lb/>
Edited by H. R. Carter.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Not many articles of value have been published within the six<lb/>
months ending Oct. 1/23 on the above subject. The most important, in the<lb/>
opinion of the writer, have been those involving the rather general accept-<lb/>
ance <hi>in practi<del>s</del><add>c</add>e</hi> of the Leptospira icteroides as without question its cau-<lb/>
sative organism. The reactions of the serum of patients sick or conval-<lb/>
escent of suspected yellow fever with cultures of this organism have been<lb/>
used in a number of places (Mexico: Colombia: Brazil) as determinative of<lb/>
the disease suffered from and the results seem to <add>have been</add> <del>be</del> consistent with the<lb/>
clinical and epidemiological data.</p>
<p>On the same basis, the use of the curative serum, when used early,<lb/>
is <add>shown by the protocols</add> reported as having given markedly good results in the epidemic in<lb/>
French West Africa.</p>
<p>The diagnostic value of the serological reactions spoken of above are<lb/>
far more valuable in determining what the patient has had, when convales-<lb/>
cent, than as a means of diagnosis during the acute sickness as they are<lb/>
not reported as showing early in the disease. Perez Grovas of Mexico, for<lb/>
instance, (<hi>vide infra</hi>) finds that the serum acquires agglutinative proper-<lb/>
ties &ldquo;by the beginning of the second week&rdquo;; at which time the attack is<lb/>
over, the aphorism still holding that &ldquo;if not past hope by the end of the<lb/>
5th. day, he recovers,&rdquo; and the 7th. being the day on which most deaths<lb/>
occur.</p>
<p>Still a certainty of diagnosis in recovered cases may be of very<lb/>
great value to the sanitarian.</p>
<p>The regions specially attacked during the six months above mentioned<lb/>
have been</p>
<p>1/ <hi>Brazil</hi>: roughly from Ceara (Fortaleza) to Bahia. Infection in<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01118002"/>
infection in<lb/>
2<lb/>
Ceara especially threatens the rubber country on the upper Amazon around<lb/>
Manaos and Iquitos--free from infection certainly since 1915.</p>
<p>2/ The town of <hi>Bucaramanga</hi> in the N. E. part of <hi>Colombia.</hi></p>
<p>3/ Portions of the Gulf of Guinea in West Africa (the Gold and<lb/>
Ivory Coast), <add>where none was found by the expedition (Noble C<lb/>
Guiteras) of the I. H. B. in 1920</add></p>
<p>There has been no report of yellow fever in Mexico or Central America<lb/>
during this time (or since) and there is good reason to believe that it<lb/>
has been eliminated from the North American continent as well as from the<lb/>
Pacific coast of both Americas. In Connor's article then, abstracted be-<lb/>
low, one may be justified in saying that his statement: &ldquo;there are at<lb/>
least three areas in Mexico where the disease in endemic&rdquo; should be<lb/>
changed to &ldquo;<hi>there were</hi>.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Africa</hi>: A number of the articles upon the African fever show lit-<lb/>
tle acquaintance with the epidemiological problems which have been work-<lb/>
ed out elsewhere. They are valuable for the data which they contain<lb/>
<del>and</del><add>but</add> in many cases their deductions from it are not justified, e. g. White<lb/>
(<hi>vide infra</hi>) states there is no evident endemic center in West Africa,<lb/>
meaning there is no one town or section always infected. He ignores en-<lb/>
tirely the doctrine of the regional <del>center</del><add>focus</add> in which, in a large region, some<lb/>
place (not the same place, of course) is always infected, the infection<lb/>
travelling from place to place and being always present somewhere in the<lb/>
region. In attempting to explain the outbreaks from time to time on the<lb/>
Gold Coast he states that the &ldquo;indigenous natives&rdquo; were &ldquo;incapable of main-<lb/>
taining the virus&rdquo; the fever; becoming milder and milder among them until<lb/>
it ceases to have power to infect anyone. He does not advance (and there<lb/>
is not) one iota of evidence for this and there is considerable against<lb/>
it. This deduction which he draws from Peterson's paper on the Spontaneous<lb/>
Disappearance of the disease in the Virgin Islands is absolutely repudiated<lb/>
by Peterson himself, as <del>it is</del> by the writer <add>is the claim</add>, that <add>it</add> <del>the deduction</del> is sustained<lb/>
by his doctrine of the Spontaneous Elimination of Yellow Fever by Failure<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01118003"/>
Failure<lb/>
3<lb/>
of the Human Host; and his <add><unclear>the;</unclear></add> further statement that change of residence<lb/>
causes loss of immunity to yellow fever is a partial revival of the old<lb/>
doctrine of Mithradatism, so prevalent about the middle of the last Cen-<lb/>
tury, but which the writer th<del>inks</del><add><unclear>ought</unclear></add> had been held by no student of yellow<lb/>
fever since it was laid to rest by the papers of Chaill&eacute; (1881) and Gui-<lb/>
teras (1888).</p>
<p>In point of fact, yellow fever is kept up in West Africa by attacks<lb/>
among the natives, which when confined to them (on account of their mild-<lb/>
ness) are not noted. The whites are not in sufficient number in this<lb/>
part of Africa to keep up the disease, but since they have it with severity<lb/>
it is readily recognized when it occurs among them and gives rise to the<lb/>
report of yellow fever.</p>
<p>In other words, the African <hi>preserves</hi> the infection from one re-<lb/>
ported outbreak to another while the whites serve as <hi>indicators</hi> of its<lb/>
existence.</p>
<p>The following articles have appeared in the period March 1, 1923 to<lb/>
October 1, 1923.</p>
<p>Grovas, P. P.: Serological Reactions in Yellow Fever, Am. J. Trop.<lb/>
Med. 3:325, 1923. In agglutination tests on the serum of 183 yellow fever<lb/>
cases, 17 cases of other diseases, and 23 normal persons, it was found<lb/>
that the serum acquires agglutinating properties in yellow fever patients<lb/>
by the beginning of the second week of the disease; the agglutination<lb/>
test was negative in diseases other than yellow fever and in normal per-<lb/>
sons, but positive in recently vaccinated individuals. Pfeiffer's re-<lb/>
action was positive in 17 patients convalescing from yellow fever, but<lb/>
was negative in one case on the eight day of the disease. The comple-<lb/>
ment fixation test in yellow fever did not prove satisfactory. The<lb/>
author concludes that the agglutination test is the most practical and<lb/>
satisfactory for diagnosis.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
