<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01114008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter fragment from [Henry Rose Carter] to Kenneth F. Maxcy, August 30, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01114008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-08-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Maxcy, Kenneth F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Ezdorf, R. H. von</name>
<name type="person">Mayne, Bruce</name>
<name type="person">Bass, C. C.</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
<name type="place">England</name>
<name type="place">Scott (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-08-30">August 30, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01114008</idno>
<title>Letter fragment from [Henry Rose Carter] to Kenneth F. Maxcy, August 30, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] discusses past experiments and problems with the use of the blood index in relation to malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-08-30">
<head>Letter fragment from [Henry Rose Carter] to Kenneth F. Maxcy, August 30, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01114008"/>
<opener>
Miscl<lb/>
Maxcy<lb/>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
Badin Hospital,<lb/>
Badin, N. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1923-08-30">August 30, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Kenneth Maxcy,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Care State Health Officer,<lb/>
Montgomery, Alabama.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Maxcy:</salute>
</opener>
<p>About the problem in relation to the blood index of malaria<lb/>
about which you asked, I had purposed to wait until I got back home,<lb/>
where I have access to notes etc., but as I am still in bed I will out-<lb/>
line it to you as well as I can without notes and send you a supple-<lb/>
mentary letter when I get to Washington, which I think will be shortly.</p>
<p>The problem was</p>
<p>1/ To determine what proportion of infections would be<lb/>
missed by a blood examination (thick film) by a carefully trained man on<lb/>
a single examination.</p>
<p>2/ What proportion of cases found positive by such examination<lb/>
in the late fall would be found negative (presumably, but not neces-<lb/>
sarily, cured spontaneously) in the spring or summer under the <del>original</del><add>ordinary</add><lb/>
conditions of life in the country on plantations in the South. The or-<lb/>
dinary conditions of life do not imply the exclusion of quinine or its<lb/>
efficient use--simply the people living as they habitually live during the<lb/>
fall: winter and spring.</p>
<p>Let me take the second problem first:</p>
<p>The desireability of its solution--or rather of the in-<lb/>
verse problem: the proportion of relapses (parasitic or symptomatic) is<lb/>
stressed by Ross in his</p>
<p>&ldquo;Prevention of Malaria.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01114009"/>
<p>Malaria.&rdquo;</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>A good deal of work on it has been done by the Italians--especially by<lb/>
Cacina and by Sella. Ross himself gives data on this problem and Bass has<lb/>
a note on it in his work on the Yazoo, where, however--judging partly by<lb/>
the statistics of Taylor in Arkansas and my can observations at Wilson--<lb/>
his proportion of relapses is too high. My recollection is that he found<lb/>
from a little over 50% to about 69% relapses among the people who had mal-<lb/>
aria in 1918: but you have access to his papers.</p>
<p>This problem was taken up in 1914, It was planned to take a care-<lb/>
ful blood index of a badly infected community <hi>after</hi> the date at which in-<lb/>
fection could be contracted, taking the names of all persons. To take<lb/>
the same index by the same man--or one equally careful and skillful--in<lb/>
the early spring before malaria could be contracted. A comparison of these<lb/>
would give us data upon the subject--for instance: if 20% of all those that<lb/>
were positive in the fall showed negative in the spring and continued to<lb/>
show negative until well into the malaria season, it would be evidence--<lb/>
although not quite proof--that that proportion, under the conditions that<lb/>
existed, had freed themselves from infection. I say not quite proof, be-<lb/>
cause for proof these people should be conveyed to some place where they<lb/>
were not exposed to infection at all and watched a long time. On the other<lb/>
hand, if 20% of those found negative in the fall were found positive in the<lb/>
early spring before it was reasonably possible to contract malaria it would<lb/>
be <hi>proof</hi> not merely evidence) that 20% at least of infections had been miss-<lb/>
ed on our supposedly careful examination. I say'at least'because it is ob-<lb/>
vious that if a careful examination in the late fall missed finding some<lb/>
infections a similar careful examination in the early spring might do the<lb/>
same and 20% would not represent all the infections that existed. This<lb/>
difficulty could be met, however, by keeping our men who were negative<lb/>
in the fall out of contact with infected Anopheles for a considerable time<lb/>
until we could be certain that no parasites could be found in their blood.</p>
<p>In the spring (reasonable chances of exposure to infected Anopheles)<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01114010"/>
Anopheles)<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
we must take into consideration the hibernated females which--in any district<lb/>
we have in the United States--are indeed uninfected, but which if they en-<lb/>
ter houses (as quads do) can readily become infected from carriers in whom,<lb/>
of course, the parasite does winter and, it being warm in the house, at the<lb/>
and of 20 or 30 days infect others.</p>
<p>This matter has never been worked out in America and frankly I am in-<lb/>
clined to think that a considerable number of the early spring cases are<lb/>
by infections by these hibernated females becoming thus infected in houses<lb/>
and staying in houses or maybe warm stables long enough to become <hi>infective</hi>.<lb/>
This, of course, could happen before the flight of the earliest spring brood<lb/>
who have no houses to warm up in.</p>
<p>Angus McDonald has laid some stress on this in the early spring post<lb/>
bellum malaria in England.</p>
<p>Dr. von Ezdorf took a blood index (thick film) at Scott, Miss. in<lb/>
the fall of 1914. At my instance, Mayne took a similar index there in Febru-<lb/>
ary 1915 in conjunction with his great work on the hibernation of the parasite<lb/>
in the mosquito. As I remember the figures------my memory is quite relia-<lb/>
ble, but I will send the exact data when I get home--von Ezdorf out of<lb/>
either 1640 or 1460 people found a positive blood index of 49 8/10%.<lb/>
Mayne on 1160 specimens found an index of 41.1 or 41.2. Both were careful<lb/>
men: both sused the same method in getting the specimens and in examining<lb/>
them: both took a sufficient number of specimens to eliminate accidental er-<lb/>
rors of observation: both found approximately the same number of positives.<lb/>
If then there was no chance of new infections in the interval between these<lb/>
indices one must take one horn or the other of this dilema:</p>
<p>(a) either the men that were positive in the fall were positive in<lb/>
the spring and those that were negative in the fall were negative in the<lb/>
spring or</p>
<p>(b) that equal number changed from negative to positive and from<lb/>
positive to negative.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01114011"/>
<p>negative.</p>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>In only a small number--103 is my recollection--were specimens taken<lb/>
from the same men whose names were recorded by von Ezdorf as positive and<lb/>
he kept no record of his negative cases. Of these 103 (?) 53, as I re-<lb/>
collect were now negative (nearly 52%). Now 103 is not enough to make a<lb/>
percentage on, but if this proportion held true of other positives turning<lb/>
to negatives we will have to accept (b) as our explanation as a result of<lb/>
these observations.</p>
<p>Mayne's observation was certainly made before the spring flight of<lb/>
Anopheles: his own dissections of wild Anopheles stisfy me that it was made<lb/>
before the hibernated ones became infective. I am not, however, so certain<lb/>
that von Ezdorf's index was taken after all reasonable probality of in-<lb/>
fection was passed.</p>
<p>I made several attempts with Mayne at the rural units of the peni-<lb/>
tentiaries of Louisiana and Mississippi to repeat this experiment record-<lb/>
ing the names, and had dates which would be beyond dispute, yet the posi-<lb/>
tive data was so small that while I have it it is not enough to draw con-<lb/>
clusions from</p>
<p>I did send to the Central Office, however--in 1917 as I recollect --<lb/>
a rather long-winded equation by which--admitting certain postulates, which<lb/>
I confess are only approximately correct--one can, from a few satisfactory<lb/>
observations of this kind, determine the <add>proportion</add> of infections that are miss-<lb/>
ed at a careful examination by the method used and therefor the faction by<lb/>
which this positive finding must be multiplied to get approximately a true<lb/>
infection from such a blood index. It is rather an intricate equation,<lb/>
but not especially so. Certainly not any more so than the one Ross gives<lb/>
for the increase and diminution of malaria with the increase and diminution<lb/>
of the number of Anopheles present, and, at any rate, it is not in the<lb/>
same class with Pearl's transcendental equation definition of Ross', which<lb/>
while I could follow I would never recommend to any friend as light reading.</p>
<p>Whether it is worth undertaking, even incidentally, any observv-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
