<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01119011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, October 22, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01119011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-10-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Veracruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Merida (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Maracaibo (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Cucuta (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Venezuela, Mexico City (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-10-22">October 22, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01119011</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, October 22, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor reports to Carter that the Mexican yellow fever campaign is going well, although he has had difficulties with local officials. He agrees that Maracaibo, rather than the larger Colombian towns, is the focal point for yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-10-22">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, October 22, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01119011"/>
<opener>
I. H- B-<lb/>
Mexico<lb/>
(Connor)<lb/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS-UNIDOS-MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
----<lb/>
COMISION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
----<lb/>
PRIMERA ZONA<lb/>
----<lb/>
TAMPICO, TAMAULIPAS<lb/>
<dateline>
Tampico Tamps. Mexico<lb/>
<date value="1923-10-22">Octuber 22nd. 1923</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter;</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have delayed answering your letter of September<lb/>
5th. until concluding a survey of the East Coast region. This has<lb/>
been completed and have reported to Doctor Russell that no evi-<lb/>
dence of yellow fever could be found, after December 1922, in the<lb/>
area from the Rio Grande to Yucatan.</p>
<p>This year, as you probably know, there have been com-<lb/>
petent Mexican physicians stationed in the principal towns and<lb/>
cities for the sole purpose of making a study of the diseases<lb/>
movement and to be observers in the hospitals, sanatoriums as well<lb/>
as consulting with the local physicians. This effort has been well<lb/>
worth while giving the Departamento de Salubridad and ourselves a<lb/>
better knowledge of actual existing conditions more especially for<lb/>
localities where no anti-larvae measures had been apllied and where<lb/>
there was a possibility that the infection could have smouldered,<lb/>
the city of Monterrey for instance.</p>
<p>In Merida and Veracruz we have fortified our-selves<lb/>
by having a physician in each city who had recently received train-<lb/>
ing in yellow fever pathology under Doctor Noguchi. In January<lb/>
Doctor Ayuse will receive a fellowship from the Board for a similiar<lb/>
course, upon his return to Tampico we will have the Gulf well<lb/>
supplied with trained physicians who will be of great aid to the<lb/>
local &lsquo;medices&rsquo; when it comes to studying suspected yellow fever<lb/>
cases.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01119012"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Your suggestion of the Maracaibo district rather than the Bucaramanga-<lb/>
Cucucta district is a logical one and to me it aids in clearing a previous<lb/>
doubt as to the infection existing in the latter district over a term of years<lb/>
either unrecognized or ignored. It worried me for a time to understand how the<lb/>
infection could remain smouldering for a long time in or near cities as large as<lb/>
Bucaramange or Cucuta even though the authorities tried to conceal it, they could<lb/>
conceal isolated and long interval cases but an epidemic forces acknowledgement<lb/>
as even the layman can diagnose classical cases. Now if we include in our perspec-<lb/>
tive the Maracaibo district I can understand the infection existing for a long<lb/>
time unrecognized or ignored until it reached a large city with a good supply<lb/>
of non-immunes to work on when an &lsquo;explosion&rsquo; is bound to occur. This is seeming-<lb/>
ly what happened in Columbia.</p>
<p>I knew that Doctor Guitera had reported finding y.f. at <unclear>Core</unclear> in 1917,<lb/>
as I had been selected to go Venezuela in the event arrangements were made but<lb/>
that Government decided to handle the situation with its own personnel.</p>
<p>What you say relative to secondary occuring in Huigra is true from all<lb/>
that I could learn from the records in Eucador and the same appears to be true<lb/>
Mexico City and the plateau.</p>
<p>I am glad that you approve of my stressing the absence of &ldquo;sporadic&rdquo;<lb/>
yellow fever. Many physicians in Mexico still cling to the telluric poison theory<lb/>
as the cause of this infection but there is increasing evidence that our work<lb/>
has convinced many that the disease can be eradicated by anti-larvae measures directed<lb/>
against the aedes aegypti. Further, the medical men are coming around to depend upon<lb/>
the laboratory to aid them in making a diagnosis in doubtful cases. I regard this<lb/>
latter change of view-point on the part of the older physicians as a real achieve-<lb/>
ment resulting from our work and will be of great service to us in the coming year<lb/>
where it is quite certain that cases of y.f. will announced.</p>
<p>As you know most of the physicans practicing in the gulf region have<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01119013"/>
-3-<lb/>
been graduated from the Mexico City Medical School and where until recently there<lb/>
were few or no facilities for the study of tropical diseases. These men had been<lb/>
trained to regard a <del><unclear></unclear></del> show of blood from the mouth or nose accompanied by<lb/>
fever and vomiting as either yellow fever or paludismo <unclear>hemmorragca</unclear>, for instance<lb/>
I was called yesterday to see a case that had been announced as yellow fever based<lb/>
unpon the presence of fresh blood in the sputum. A careful examination of the<lb/>
patient revealed a <del><unclear></unclear></del> lobar pneumonia.</p>
<p>You will be interested to know that the soap in lejia continues to<lb/>
give good results in destroying aedes aegypti larvae before the stage of pupation<lb/>
and is quite successful as a mosquito repellent. Some Inspectors have reported un-<lb/>
favorably <del><unclear></unclear></del> upon this measure but I have been able in these cases to discover<lb/>
that the fault lay with the man and not the soap, some were placing a piece of<lb/>
soap in the lejia and it immediately settled to the bottom of the container where<lb/>
<del>carefully</del><add>it became</add> covered by the ashes which prevented it from dissolving or else they were<lb/>
not using enough soap for the quanitity of lejia to be treated.</p>
<p>Here in Tampico we have decided upon the following method: ten drops<lb/>
of concentrated liquid soap to the average small container or a teaspoonful of powdered<lb/>
soap or flakes or rub the soap between the hands latering immersing them in the<lb/>
lejia.</p>
<p>I have found that the use of soap in lejia permits us to reduce our<lb/>
field personnel nearly 50% that is the ayudante are no longer employed as their<lb/>
principal function was to carry oil used in mosquito-proofing lejias.</p>
<p>I hope that you have fully recovered and are now enjoying your usual<lb/>
good oft expressed wish to see Mexico free of yellow fever appears to be realized.</p>
<p>With very good wishes to Miss Laura and the kindliest personal regards<lb/>
for yourself, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>sincerely yous,</salute>
<signed>M E Connor</signed>.
Dr. H.R. Carter.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
