<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01114001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, August 15, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01114001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-08-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Medina, Garcia</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, L.H.</name>
<name type="place">Bogata (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Barranquilla (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Cartagena (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Cucuta (Colomia)</name>
<name type="place">Magdelena (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Venezuela</name>
<name type="place">Maracaibo (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-08-15">August 15, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01114001</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, August 15, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson reports on yellow fever in Colombia. He also discusses financial matters.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-08-15">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, August 15, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01114001"/>
<opener>
ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF<lb/>
----<lb/>
FREDERICK F. RUSSELL, M.D.<lb/>
GENERAL DIRECTOR<lb/>
JOHN A. FERRELL, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE UNITED STATES<lb/>

VICTOR G. HEISER, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE EAST<lb/>
H. H. HOWARD, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE WEST INDIES<lb/>
MEMBERS<lb/>
----<lb/>
GEORGE E. VINCENT<lb/>
CHAIRMAN<lb/>
WALLACE BUTTRICK<lb/>
DAVID L. EDSALL<lb/>
SIMON FLEXNER<lb/>
RAYMOND B. FOSDICK<lb/>
EDWIN O. JORDAN<lb/>
VERNON KELLOGG<lb/>
T. MITCHELL PRUDDEN<lb/>
JOHN D. ROCKEFELLER, JR.<lb/>
WICKLIFFE ROSE<lb/>
VICTOR C. VAUGHAN<lb/>
WILLIAM H. WELCH<lb/>
EDWIN R. EMBREE<lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
FLORENCE M. READ<lb/>
ASSISTANT SECRETARY<lb/>
<dateline>
THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION<lb/>
INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD<lb/>
61 BROADWAY, NEW YORK<lb/>
Bogata, Colombia.<lb/>
<date value="1923-08-15">August 15, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>We are still in Bogata, have been<lb/>
here one week, and still have not gotten the things done <unclear><del>in</del></unclear><lb/>
which are necessary before going down into the fever section<lb/>
Today is a &ldquo;fiesta&rdquo; and everything is closed up tight and no<lb/>
one is to be<del>e</del> seen on business. We expected to get our arrange-<lb/>
ments made with the Minister today so as to be able to pre-<lb/>
sent all our wants to the President to-morrow, but I fear<lb/>
that it is going to take another day now. However we will<lb/>
get away from here on Saturday at the latest. As we go we<lb/>
expect to look <unclear>Girardot</unclear> over as it is a town of consider-<lb/>
able size, and the terminus of the river travel. Honda is<lb/>
probably what might be called a key point in the upper river<lb/>
but it does not have a very large population. It does have<lb/>
a lot of transient population, i.e., travellers.</p>
<p>There are practically no confirmed reports coming<lb/>
in at the present time, but one does hear rumors of sickness<lb/>
in different points. When I came up the river I was told about<lb/>
three or four deaths in Puerto Santos, some of which were<lb/>
said to have had black vomit, there was also a report of cases<lb/>
of pernicious fevers in Barranca Bermeja, notwithstanding the<lb/>
fact that the physician of the Tropical Oil and the native<lb/>
physician who was there denied anything suggestive of yellow<lb/>
fever. As we go down the river we expect to spend one or two<lb/>
days there looking up any case of suspicious illness which<lb/>
may exist. There was also a report of suspicious cases of<lb/>
illness at Puerto Wilches. As the situation appears to me<lb/>
there is a probability of the fever walking down the river<lb/>
to Barranquilla dn Cartagena, as all points with these rumors<lb/>
are on the river and there are numerous villages along the<lb/>
banks which can readily serve as relaying points.</p>
<p>The quarantine referred to by Dr. White is just so many<lb/>
words and will have about the same effect inpreventing the<lb/>
spread of the fever as our &ldquo;Cordon Sanitario&rdquo; in Peru.</p>
<p>Dr. Garcia Medina, the Director of Health, spoke very<lb/>
highly of you and values your contributions to the subject<lb/>
very highly. He appears to be a very fine man, quite a con-<lb/>
trast to what we had to deal with in Peru. Our impressions<lb/>
so far are that these Colombians are quite superior to the<lb/>
Peruvians.</p>
<p>It is very evident however that it is going to be most<lb/>
difficult to get about in this country. The transportation is<lb/>
(so far as I can judge) much more difficult that that in Peru.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01114002"/>
<p>Dr. Carter</p>
<p>2</p>
<p>August 15, 1923</p>
<p>This difficulty in transportation however does not<lb/>
prevent the peones from travelling from place to place, and<lb/>
I consider them the principal conveyers of the disease from<lb/>
one village or town to another. They go from one village to<lb/>
another in canoes on the river, and from what I saw of the<lb/>
river traffic I do not see any reason why the fever should<lb/>
not get to Barranquilla and Cartagena. From the brief in-<lb/>
vestigation made by Dunn and myself togather with the local<lb/>
municipal Medicos, it seems that every house in Barranquilla<lb/>
is breeding an abundance of Stegomyia. With such conditions<lb/>
I do not feel that it is afe to leave these places without<lb/>
cleaning them up. This especially in view of the fact that<lb/>
Puerto Santos is quite some distance north of the Bucara-<lb/>
manga region, and if it was yellow fever which they reported<lb/>
to me they will certainly relay it down the river. El Banco<lb/>
is a town on the river which has 5167 population, and is o<lb/>
one of the main ports for the river traffic. Puerto Santos<lb/>
is not far from Puerto Wilches, but is on the LeBrija river<lb/>
and could easily carry infection down to Banco, which would<lb/>
serve as an easy distributing point for the lower part of<lb/>
the valley and to the larger coast towns and cities.</p>
<p>Calamar is another town on the river with over 6000<lb/>
population and is only about six hours from Barranquilla<lb/>
by steamer going down the river. What should be done with<lb/>
these places I will not be able to decide until after the<lb/>
investigation of the Bucaramanga sector, and the investigation<lb/>
of these outside places which are said to have had cases. If<lb/>
it proves true then in my opinion the only rational thing<lb/>
to do will be to protect Cartagena, Barranquilla, Puerto<lb/>
Colombia by doing stegomyia work there and at the same time<lb/>
cleaning up the key points on the river, such as Calamar,<lb/>
Banco, Puerto Berrio, Honda and Girardot, and also Barranca<lb/>
Bermeja on account of the increasing activities there of the<lb/>
Tropical Oil Co.,. I beleive this Magdelena section should<lb/>
be organized before attempt to do anything in the Cucuta<lb/>
section. If the fever came from there it has already spread<lb/>
its seed. The communication between Cucuta and the Magdelena<lb/>
sector <del><unclear></unclear></del> is over the mountains and a most difficult<lb/>
journey, henec of no importance as far as further propaga-<lb/>
tion of the fever towards the west or north is concerned,<lb/>
and is of less importance to Colombia than to Venezuela.</p>
<p>As soon as I have things running fairly satisfactorily<lb/>
here I shall go to Cucuta either by the Bucaramanga route<lb/>
or by sea via Maracaibo. One can make the trip from Barran-<lb/>
quilla by sea in less time than over the mountains by the<lb/>
Bucaramanga route.</p>
<p>This job is no flowery bed of roses. A man earns about<lb/>
twice what he is paid for being here, and I certainly am not<lb/>
going to invigle anybody else into this thing without <unclear>insistin</unclear><lb/>
on proper pay. Both Dunn and I are stung on the pay.</p>
<p>Everything here is extremely expensive.</p>
<p>I have not heard a word from my folks since I left Sioux City.</p>
<p>With the kindest regards to Laura and yourself,</p>
<closer>
<salute>As ever your disciple and admirer,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
