<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01117003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Kenneth Maxcy to Henry Rose Carter, September 5, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01117003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-09-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Maxcy, Kenneth F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Howard, H. H.</name>
<name type="person">Coogle, C. P.</name>
<name type="person">Bass, C.C.</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">Pike County (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-09-05">September 5, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01117003</idno>
<title>Letter from Kenneth Maxcy to Henry Rose Carter, September 5, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Maxcy is glad that Carter is recovering. He discusses the difficulties of distinguishing between re-infection and relapse in malaria, and encloses tables on Coogle's research.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-09-05">
<head>Letter from Kenneth Maxcy to Henry Rose Carter, September 5, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01117003"/>
<opener>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MALARIA INVESTIGATIONS<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
<dateline>
Care of State Health Officer,<lb/>
Montgomery, Ala.<lb/>
<date value="1923-09-05">September 5, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
U.S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Badin Hospital,<lb/>
Badin, N.C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter was a real joy - to know that<lb/>
you were well on the road to recovery and that your intellect<lb/>
was just as keen as ever, in spite of your illness.<lb/>
I sincerely trust, however, that you will &ldquo;take it easy&rdquo; for<lb/>
a long time and give Nature her full chance to make the<lb/>
needed repairs. She is a wonderful doctor,- if the patient<lb/>
is not too <unclear>obstroperous</unclear>!!!</p>
<p>The approach which you suggest to the<lb/>
problem of relapses is strategic. It ought to yield<lb/>
information much more valuable than any that we have at<lb/>
the present time in this country.</p>
<p>I have the &ldquo;Digest of the Literature on<lb/>
Malaria Relapses&rdquo; prepared by the Rockefeller Foundation.<lb/>
The abstracts are rather meager, but give me some idea of the<lb/>
work that has been done by foreigh observers. I note the<lb/>
observations of Caccini, referred to by you, but Sella is<lb/>
not quoted (Could it by any chance have been Celli?).<lb/>
The observations of Stott in Mandalay I should like to look<lb/>
over more carefully. Perhaps they are better than the others.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01117004"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
Dr. Carter -<lb/>
It is perfectly obvious that every one is stumped by the difficulty<lb/>
of distinguishing between reinfections and relapses. This has<lb/>
<del>been</del><add>was</add> overcome by removing the primary infections to a location<lb/>
where reinfection was impossible as at <unclear>Dagshai</unclear>.</p>
<p>In this country, Dr. Bass and Dr. H.H. Howard have made<lb/>
an <unclear>effort</unclear> to calculate the relapse rate. Dr. Bass and Dr. Dedwylder<lb/>
have a very large group to deal with, but their results are<lb/>
deductions by inference. They calculate the percentage of<lb/>
new infections by determining the number of cases of malaria which<lb/>
occurred in a group of persons who gave negative histories for the<lb/>
preceding year, and apply this percentage to the persons who <hi>did</hi><lb/>
have malaria the preceding year. It is <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>questionable whether</add> the two<lb/>
groups <del><unclear></unclear></del> lived under equal conditions of exposure to new<lb/>
infections. A priori one might reason that those who had malaria<lb/>
the preceding year where those persons so located as to have<lb/>
maximum exposure and vice versa for the group with negative histories.<lb/>
I believe that even in the Delta a careful study would show that<lb/>
the distribution of malaria is not uniform,- that there are definite<lb/>
foci of infection where the rate is high,- on a single plantation,-<lb/>
perhaps, or even a single part of a plantation,- while the rate is<lb/>
very low or perhaps only relapses occur in a neighboring plantation.<lb/>
If then, our group of negative histories represented those persons<lb/>
living in the areas where there was very little exposure to malaria,<lb/>
the <del><unclear></unclear></del> 241 cases might be very much more than<lb/>
10% of those actually exposed to new infections. This, and the fact<lb/>
that he is dealing with negro &ldquo;histories&rdquo; render the data uncertain.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01117005"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>Dr. Howard, delt with a very small group, 108 positive<lb/>
smears in his controlled area and 37 positives in his non-controlled<lb/>
area. He speaks only of &ldquo;apparent relapses&rdquo;, meaning by this<lb/>
persons who had &ldquo;definite attacks&rdquo; of malaria during the preceding<lb/>
season,- as ascertained by clinical histories usually confirmed.<lb/>
In 1919, of 33 positive smears in the controlled area, he classes<lb/>
20 as &ldquo;new infections&rdquo; and 13 as &ldquo;relapses&rdquo; (40% relapse rate).<lb/>
In 1920, of 31 positive smears in his controlled area, he classes<lb/>
12 and &ldquo;new&rdquo; and 19 as &ldquo;relapses&rdquo; (61% relapse rate). These<lb/>
figures are very small and chance variation might modify them<lb/>
considerably. Moreover, the &ldquo;apparent relapses&rdquo; may contain<lb/>
a considerable number of reinfections and the &ldquo;new cases&rdquo; may<lb/>
contain a considerable number of the previous seasons undiscovered<lb/>
infections. In his uncontrolled area, he found in 1919,<lb/>
14 &ldquo;new&rdquo; and 8 "relapses; in 1920, 21 &ldquo;new&rdquo; and 22 &ldquo;relapses&rdquo;.<lb/>
In other words, all of the clinical cases discovered in 1919<lb/>
must have relapsed in 1920, or there was re-infection to balance<lb/>
every case of recovery. If the latter hypothesis is true, I<lb/>
would surmise that his &ldquo;relapses&rdquo; might contain a considerable group<lb/>
of re-infections, and <del><unclear></unclear></del> a matter of two or three would change<lb/>
the percentage considerably.</p>
<p>The method which you propose for approaching this<lb/>
problem would insure the same conditions of exposure for all.<lb/>
Up to May, we would be fairly sure of small risk of reinfection;<lb/>
it would not be practical to protect a large group artificially<lb/>
after the first flight of Anopheles. On the positive side<lb/>
then, we could show the proportion which relapse up to the time<lb/>
of the first flight; on the negative <unclear>side</unclear>, the proportion <add>of the <unclear>original portions</unclear></add> which<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01117006"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
remain apparently free from malaria as determined clinically and<lb/>
by repeated examinations throughout the following season.<lb/>
Obviously the negative group is of greater value than the positive.<lb/>
The positive group would contain <add>a large part of</add> the tertian relapses but not the<lb/>
aestivo-autumnal. The negative grooup, on the other hand,<lb/>
after the first flight, would be constantly depleted by new<lb/>
infections. (or relapse?). The first would give us the<lb/>
lower limit or relapses; the second (<unclear>subtracting</unclear> the total number<lb/>
of negatives surviving at the<del><unclear>n</unclear></del> end of the second season from the<lb/>
original total positives) would give the upper limit.</p>
<p>As to the original total negatives, part are those<lb/>
missed by the technique of the examination and part are those<lb/>
who harbor the parasite in their bodies but not in <del><unclear>the</unclear></del> sufficient<lb/>
numbers in the peripheral blood at the time of the examination<lb/>
to be discoverable by the method. The first error could be<lb/>
determined by making an original examination, fixing the per cent<lb/>
of positives, retaining all the negatives for repeated examination<lb/>
by other observers to thus pick up any positive that were missed<lb/>
on the original examination,- and finally comparing the original<lb/>
total positives with the corrected total positives. The second<lb/>
error, as you suggest would appear in the number of these<lb/>
&ldquo;negatives&rdquo; (corrected) who relapsed before the Spring flight,-<lb/>
at least in part,- for here again, would we get the aestivo-<lb/>
autumnal relapses?.</p>
<p>In my studies here in Alabama, I am finding the<lb/>
disease extremely focal in character. I am hoping to<lb/>
find some isolated focus with the Anopheline production<lb/>
centered in a single pond which can be readily and completely<lb/>
controlled. If I could locate such a place, it might<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01117007"/>
-5-<lb/>
be possible to control the breeding during the second season and<lb/>
follow through without the complication of &ldquo;new infections&rdquo;.<lb/>
I have in mind a place in Pike County to investigate for this purpose.</p>
<p>I hope you will be able to locate a copy of the equation<lb/>
which you evolved for determining the proportion of infections<lb/>
missed by careful examination. The article from Pearl's<lb/>
department by Anthony Lotka was, - I confess - too deep for me.<lb/>
I could not sustain my interest. All of the values with which<lb/>
he starts are &ldquo;unknowns&rdquo; and I do not see any prospect of their<lb/>
becoming &ldquo;known&rdquo; in the near future. I cannot seem to take the<lb/>
mathematicians delight in dealing so at length with the abstract,-<lb/>
to no apparent practical purpose beyond the mental gymnastics involved.</p>
<p>I am enclosing a preliminary <xref id="f01117009">table</xref> of the results of<lb/>
Dr. Coogle's work in Mississippi this past winter. You will<lb/>
note the spleen rate is considerably larger than the parasite rate.<lb/>
The slides were examined by Miss Barrier in Dr. Krauss' laboratory,-<lb/>
thick smear technique. I am getting up a little report of this<lb/>
for the Public Healt Reports.</p>
<p>I hope I have not tired you by this long-winded letter,<lb/>
but I wanted to be sure I understood the problem, and hope you will<lb/>
write me again when you feel able and have a little spare time to chat.<lb/>
Please thank Miss Laura for me. I am sending copies of your letter<lb/>
and memorandum.</p>
<p>With all best wishes for your continued improvement<lb/>
and complete recovery of your strength, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Kenneth Maxcy</signed>
(over)<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01117008"/>
C1<lb/>
<unclear>B</unclear>21<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. at first opportunity I will discuss<lb/>
with Dr. Fricks and Dr. <unclear>Barter</unclear> the<lb/>
problem which you have so kindly<lb/>
suggested and, if they agree,<lb/>
we will try <unclear>to</unclear> set the conditions of the<lb/>
experiment.<lb/>
<unclear>KTM</unclear><lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
