<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01115002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum by Henry Rose Carter, [1923]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01115002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Mayne, Bruce</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="place">Monroe (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Newport News (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Houston (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">Scott (Ark.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-00-00">[1923]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01115002</idno>
<title>Memorandum by Henry Rose Carter, [1923]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses the seasonal presence and absence of mosquitoes, and the control of their breeding through the use of vegetation control, fish stocking, and maintenance of water level in ponds.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="193*-00-00">
<head>Memorandum by Henry Rose Carter, [1923]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01115002"/>
<p>Memorandum.</p>
<p><del>Another</del><add>Two</add> problems short: easy, and it may be of considerable <unclear>practical</unclear><lb/>
importance <del>is</del> are.</p>
<p>(X) For each bench man in the locality in which he happens to be<lb/>
in the late fall, to determine the last date at which Anopheles mosqui-<lb/>
toes (quads. especially) <add><del><unclear>are</unclear></del></add> <hi>infective to men</hi> can be found in nature</p>
<p>(Y) Of scarcely less value is it to determine the date at which<lb/>
the flight of the spring brood of quads begins.</p>
<p>#</p>
<p>The value of (x) is to determine when we can safely stop anti-<unclear>breeding</unclear><lb/>
<del>larval</del> methods at any place. Thus, Mayne determined that Anopheles infect-<lb/>
ive to men were not found after--say--Nov. 15th, at Monroe, La. <add>I have forgotten the exact date.</add> <add><del>now</del></add> <del>the mos-</del><lb/>
<add>xx now the mos-</add> quito infective on Nov. 15th. must have received infection prior to Nov. 4th.<lb/>
The egg from which she was evolved must have been deposited not less than<lb/>
17 days before <add>(16 days from egg to <unclear>imago &amp;</unclear> 1 day for <unclear>provocis to harden)</unclear></add> (not later than Oct. 12th.<unclear>).</unclear> Very obviously then, we could<lb/>
afford to stop anti-larval methods on that day, as eggs deposited after Oct 12<lb/>
<del>that</del> would not produce <unclear>imagoes</unclear> that would infect this year. In point of<lb/>
fact this allows for a large factor of safety, because in the interval from<lb/>
November 4th. to November 15th. (at which <add>data</add> it is cold enough for the para-<lb/>
site to die) we may be quite certain it is too cold to alow only 11 days<lb/>
for its development in the mosquito (extrinsic incubation of malaria.). It<lb/>
would take--say--25 to 30.</p>
<p>Similarly, between Oct. 12th. and Nov. 4th. the weather is too<lb/>
cold to allow only 16 days for <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>the</add> cycle from egg to imago (I have allowed<lb/>
one day for the hardening of the chitin so that the insect can feed on man).</p>
<p>I had, <del>at that time</del><add>in 1918</add> -it is <add>now</add> either in <unclear>the,</unclear> Central Office or<lb/>
Mayne has it<unclear>--a</unclear> chart from the Agricultural Department: I have forgotten its<lb/>
name, but it could well be called &ldquo;A Chart of Iso-biological <add><unclear>Phenomina Dates</unclear></add> <del><unclear>Dates</unclear></del>,&rdquo; in<lb/>
which the curves show the places in the U. S. where certain biological phe-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01115003"/>
phe-<lb/>
<unclear><del>b</del> 2</unclear><lb/>
nomena, such as I have <add><unclear>just</unclear></add> instanced, occur on the same dates.</p>
<p>Guided by this and allowing a fair factor of safety <add><unclear>18</unclear></add> I stopped my<lb/>
anti-larval work <add><unclear>on <hi>certain dates (different of course) thus determined,</hi></unclear></add> from Newport News to Houston, although Anopheles were<lb/>
then in flight and breeding. There was some argument about it, but I knew<lb/>
it was right. &amp; I think I saved at least $150,000.00 and, taking the factors<lb/>
of safety I did, with absolute safety.</p>
<p>In our records we have several determinations of th<del><unclear></unclear></del><add>e</add> date of this<lb/>
termination of infectivity, but a considerable number of others are needed to<lb/>
serve as checks on the above map when used for control of mosquito production.</p>
<p>It is very little trouble to make this determination and I know you<lb/>
can see how useful it may be.</p>
<p>(y) is advisable for the control of malaria on impounded water.<lb/>
A. quad. bred in the ponds is, we think, the main factor in the production<lb/>
of malaria from impounded water. (I will have rather an<del>d</del> interesting little<lb/>
piece to add to this, when I am able to sit up and write, on the role of<lb/>
punctipennis.) Now our accepted--and a very efficient--method of prevent-<lb/>
ing production in the large ponds is by holding the pond as high as pos-<lb/>
sible during the season when quads. are not in flight<unclear>,<del>/</del></unclear> lowering it before<lb/>
this flight begins, but as close to the time as may be. A pond thus handled--<lb/>
(as is the case here now<unclear>)--</unclear>having an absolutely clean shore line and decent-<lb/>
ly stocked with top-minnows gives no production.</p>
<p>You can see then how advisable it is to held the <add>high</add> water level as<lb/>
close to the first flight as possible, but on no account to go into it.<lb/>
We have in our Service literature, and a few notes of my own, these dates<lb/>
for probably 25 or 30 different places and years. Thibault of <add>Scott,</add> Arkansas--<lb/>
<del>I think of Scott</del>--gave me some data on it and everything he reports can be<lb/>
relied on. One would have to fish it out from Service publications and re-<lb/>
ports, but this is not hard to do and it gives us data which I judge will<lb/>
prevent from 5,000 to 10,000 cases of malaria per annum by the ponds, and<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01115004"/>
and<lb/>
<unclear>3c</unclear><lb/>
to do this is worth some days work.</p>
<p><unclear>(</unclear>I will ask you to send this memorandum, as well as the original letter,)<lb/>
<unclear></unclear> (to the Central Office so as to determine whether; when and by whom it would)<lb/>
(be taken up.)</p>
<p><add><unclear>Maxcy</unclear></add> I would also ask--if your typewriter is functioning well--if you would<lb/>
send me two copies for my own use. I want to send them to <del>field men (one</del><lb/>
to LePrince <add>&amp; Griffitts</add> to get his criticism on it) and would ask <del>both</del> for your own <del>cri-<lb/>
ticism and for that of Dr. Fricks.</del></p>
<p>Sincerely<lb/>
your friend<lb/>
H. R. Carter<lb/>
<del><unclear>Asst.</unclear> Surg. Gen'l</del><lb/>
<del><unclear>on</unclear></del></p>
<p>15<lb/>
<unclear>12 x</unclear></p>
<p>Nov 1<lb/>
Oct 21.<lb/>
<hi>17</hi><lb/>
4</p>
<p>Blue-green (<unclear>Anaebena</unclear> (<unclear>Anaebena</unclear></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
