<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01119021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Frederick F. Russell, September 13, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01119021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-09-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Russell, Frederick F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Serpa, Roberto</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="place">Maracaibo (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Cucuta (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-09-13">September 13, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01119021</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Frederick F. Russell, September 13, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson states that he does not think there is yellow fever in Bucaramanga and that the purported cases, which he describes, are not yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-09-13">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Frederick F. Russell, September 13, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01119021"/>
<opener>
<hi>Carter</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Bucaramanga, <date value="1923-09-13">September 13, 1923</date>
</dateline>
Dr. F.F. Russell, General Director,<lb/>
The International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York City.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I beg to acknowledge receipt of your letter<lb/>
of August 6th, with reference to the report of yellow fever near<lb/>
Lake Maracaibo in 1921, with copies of letters regarding the same.<lb/>
We will undoubtedly get further information on this when we go to<lb/>
Cucuta, which we expect to do by way of Maracaibo.</p>
<p>I expect Dr. Roberto Serpa to go to Cucuta next week, I<lb/>
had planned for him to leave this week, but have been unable to<lb/>
get the necessary arrangements made, on account of spending a<lb/>
great deal of time in the investigation of the sick of this place.</p>
<p>In so far as the sick of this place are concerned, none<lb/>
of those seen by me since my arrival have had symptoms which would<lb/>
allow a diagnosis of yellow fever. If this is yellow fever it is an<lb/>
entirely different different type of yellow fever from that which<lb/>
we had on the Pacific coast of Peru. What I think has happened is<lb/>
that, the epidemic here is over for the following reasons:</p>
<p>According<lb/>
to the information available here the epidemic of Bucaramanga be-<lb/>
gan sometime last year, some say in September, others say later, but<lb/>
by general consent it appears to have been before last December.<lb/>
Accepting such an assertion as true, and knowing that no work<lb/>
was done against the breeding of the Stegomyia, it is quite rea-<lb/>
sonable to conclude that the force of the epidemic had practically<lb/>
spent itself before the arrival of the Commission of Investigation,<lb/>
and the few typical cases seen by them were among the last to pre-<lb/>
sent themselves.</p>
<p>As I stated in a previous communication, the cases which I<lb/>
have seen, have not had black vomit, very few have had any noticable<lb/>
nausea, none have had the congestive gingivitis, nor any spontaneous<lb/>
bleeding from the gums, none have had nosebleed, none have had the<lb/>
congestion in the conjunctiva nor a subsequent yellow discolora-<lb/>
tion, none have had a typical albuminuria, and in fact in only one<lb/>
instance was there a marked amount of albumen, and that paitent<lb/>
was in a washerwoman who was found at her work on the second day<lb/>
after this observation was made. None have been found with a brady-<lb/>
cardia in convalescence nor has the typical prostrated condition<lb/>
been seen. The priest of whom I spoke in a former letter I am<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01119022"/>
Dr. F.F. Russell<lb/>
2<lb/>
September 13, 1923.<lb/>
considering as a doubtful or possible case in as much as I did<lb/>
not see him until the 11th day, I do not feel that I am in a<lb/>
position to say one way or the other.</p>
<p>The waiter at the Hotel Contenintal, who was taken sick<lb/>
last Friday evening, and was diagnosed as yellow fever by Dr.<lb/>
McCormick, did not have albuminuria, nor bleeding gums not with-<lb/>
standing the fact that he has considerable pyorrhea, he did not<lb/>
have the congestion of the eyes nor a subsequent interic dis-<lb/>
coloration, nor the prostration characteristic of yellow fever.<lb/>
In examining the blood Dr. McCormick found the organism which he<lb/>
has reported in these cases which have presented themselves here<lb/>
lately. I also took <unclear>bilod</unclear> smears as I thought from the initial<lb/>
symptoms that it might be a case of malaria, but on examination<lb/>
I found the spirochaete of relapsing fever, on two successive da<lb/>
days. He ran a fever for a little over four days, yesterday and<lb/>
today he has been up and waiting on the table, and does not show<lb/>
any of the characteristic prostration following yellow fever. We<lb/>
are looking for the relapse to occur next week when we will take<lb/>
more blood smears and also administer some<unclear>neacsalvarsan</unclear>. I be-<lb/>
lieve that many of the recent febrile cases here are cases of<lb/>
relapsing fever, as we have received such <unclear>histories</unclear> in several<lb/>
and have obtained the spirochaete in three. This spirochaete is<lb/>
an entirely different organism from the one which McCormick is<lb/>
reporting. Dr. Serpa who has seen most of the recent fever cases<lb/>
with me states that they are different from those seen here in<lb/>
the earlier part of the epidemic.</p>
<p>At this very moment Dr. McCormick has just called here at<lb/>
the office to advise me that a child which was reported this mor-<lb/>
ning but which I could not see on account of wanting to get my<lb/>
mail ready, as we have outgoing mail tomorrow, but which I asked<lb/>
Dr. Serpa to see, has the organisms of relapsing fever, but she also<lb/>
has this other organism which McCormick is finding. Dr. Serpa's<lb/>
opinion was that it was not a case of yellow fever. I have blood<lb/>
smears from this case which I will stain and examine tomorrow.</p>
<p>The curious thing about this organism of McCormicks is<lb/>
that it is not seen in very large numbers immediately upon taking<lb/>
the blood smear. The technique is the following:</p>
<p>A drop of blood is<lb/>
taken either by the ordinary lancet, or a few drops are drawn<lb/>
from the vein, this is mixed with a solution of sodium citrate in<lb/>
normal saline, and as far as I have been able to note the propor-<lb/>
tions of blood and the saline-citrate mixture is about 1 to 2 or<lb/>
varying between that on up to about 1 to 4 dilution. A slide is<lb/>
cleaned cleaned free from grease, coverslip cleaned and then placed<lb/>
on the slide in such a manner that one edge of the coverslip just<lb/>
coincides with the edge of the slide, the two sides of the cover<lb/>
slip which are perpendicular to the edge of the slides are sealed<lb/>
with parrafine wax, leaving the <del><unclear></unclear></del> the other two edges (oppo-<lb/>
site one another) free so as to form a sort of broad flat capill-<lb/>
ary space, but very thin. The edge of the slide and slip is then<lb/>
touched to a large drop of the blood-citrate mixture, and a very<lb/>
fine film of the mixture is obtained. The remaining two edges of<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01119023"/>
Dr. F.F. Russell<lb/>
3<lb/>
September 13, 1923<lb/>
of the coverslip are sealed in the same way, and the preparation<lb/>
is then examined under the Special high dry of the <unclear>Zeiss</unclear> Micro-<lb/>
scope, with the high oculars, using the dark field.</p>
<p>When these preparations are first seen under the scope,<lb/>
or rather when first prepared there often is very little to be<lb/>
seen, after about 15 to 20 minuits a filamentous &ldquo;spirochaetoid&rdquo;(?)<lb/>
organism is seen, which has an appearance as is proceeding from<lb/>
the redblood corpuscle. As time advances these increase. Some<lb/>
are found free in the plasma of the preparation, usually rather<lb/>
small, about four to seven micra in length. I have not been able<lb/>
to satisfy myself that this &ldquo;organisms&rdquo; has a true motility, it<lb/>
appears to me to be a Brownonian motion. A curious thing is that<lb/>
he finds these &ldquo;spirochaetes&rdquo; in all the cases which he examines,<lb/>
whether early in the disease or as late as the 24th day (<unclear>ywenty-</unclear><lb/>
fourth day). He states that they are also found in the guinae<lb/>
pigs here.</p>
<p>Last night he called me to see a new feature of this thing,<lb/>
stating that he had found a way of fragmenting the redblood<lb/>
cells and in such fields he had very large numbers of these<lb/>
long thin filiform structures, which in the portion next to the<lb/>
red cells, the portion which appeared to be attached, was rather<lb/>
straight in appearance for a distance of about 8 to 12 micra,<lb/>
and then beyond that they appeared twisted, or coiled like a<lb/>
closely coiled spring, and others seemed as if doubed back on<lb/>
on themselves in the distal portions. The movement was of a<lb/>
wavy nature, with a tendency to coiling and unceiling. It is<lb/>
very difficult to give you anything like a clear word picture<lb/>
of this phenomenon, and what significance it has I do not pre-<lb/>
sume to say. A great deal of publicity has been given to the<lb/>
thing here. They at first seemed to have the impression that<lb/>
it was the organism of Noguchi, and were inclined to accept<lb/>
this finding as diagnostic. This I think I have succeeded in<lb/>
dispelling. Since I gave McCormick two of Noguchi's pamphlets<lb/>
to read, he is satisfied that he is not dealing with the Lepto-<lb/>
spira icteroides. The impression now is that they have something<lb/>
entirely new, and the author of the phenomenon insists that it<lb/>
(the disease) is the same as that which the Commission saw<lb/>
when here.</p>
<p>Some of the men want the Board to send an expert<lb/>
bacteriologist to investigate the discovery, and have asked me<lb/>
<unclear>to take the matter up with you. Were it not so difficult</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>get her with the necessary apparatus it might be worth while you</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>to send some one, as there is a world of materials here of</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>study,</unclear> it may be advantageous to clear this thing up as there<lb/>
is some tendency to question whether or not there was yellow<lb/>
fever, in as much as this thing is claimed to occur among the<lb/>
present febrile cases.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
I am inclosing some extra copies of this letter as Drs. Noguchi,<lb/>
<unclear>White</unclear> and Carter may be interested.<lb/>
H.H.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
