<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01119002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, October 12, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01119002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-10-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hanson, Henry</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Von Ezdorf, Rudolph H.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Dunn Lawrence H.</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Scotland</name>
<name type="place">Gibraltar</name>
<name type="place">England</name>
<name type="place">Ireland</name>
<name type="place">Gold Coast (West Africa)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Caribbean</name>
<name type="place">Magdalena River (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Cucuta (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Maracaibo (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-10-12">October 12, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01119002</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, October 12, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses diseases similar to yellow fever. He suspects Cucuta, Colombia is a yellow fever focal point. He comments on the origins of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-10-12">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Henry Hanson, October 12, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01119002"/>
<opener>
File<lb/>
<hi>I. H. B.<lb/>
Hanson</hi><lb/>
Note this kind of mark (&ldquo;<unclear>/</unclear>&rdquo;) means<lb/>
this (&ldquo;.&rdquo;) Fault of typewriter<lb/>
(machine not Laura)<lb/>
<dateline>
The Johns Hopkins Hospital,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md/,<lb/>
<date value="1923-10-12">Oct/ 12, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
/LC<lb/>
<salute>Dear Hanson:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of Sept. 9th/ reached here yesterday/</p>
<p>What you say about finding relapsing fever at Bucaramanga is<lb/>
to me extremely interesting/</p>
<p>Gillespie <add>or Gilchrist- I forget which</add> reported as &ldquo;<hi>febris incognita</hi>&rdquo; an epidemic at Dum-<lb/>
fries, Scotland, in January and February 1826 (?) which he was positive,<lb/>
&ldquo;both from clinical symptoms and autopsy, was identical with the yellow<lb/>
fever that <del>"</del>the eminent Frenchman&rdquo;, Louis, <del>"</del> had &ldquo;so well described at Gibraltar&rdquo;<lb/>
Its marked characteristics were black vomit and jaundice/ It was, how-<lb/>
ever, clearly relapsing fever/</p>
<p>Arnott and MacCormack reported the same fever at Glasgow and<lb/>
Edinburg the same year, <add>in winter &amp; early spring</add> the hemorrhagic symptoms still characterizing it/</p>
<p>Wilkes and Stokes--very great clinicians--reported an epidem-<lb/>
ic (21 cases and 18 deaths) of &ldquo;yellow fever of the West Indies&rdquo; in the<lb/>
Dublin hospital (December and January of about the same time/ jaundice &amp;<lb/>
haematamesis</p>
<p>Noc and Nogu&eacute; reported in 1921 a &ldquo;<hi>fi&egrave;vre recurrent</hi>&rdquo; about<lb/>
Da<del>k</del>kar at <add>first</add> considered yellow <del>fever</del><add>stet</add> and the<del>ir</del> cases characterized by jaun-<lb/>
dice and the<del>ir</del> dying cases by gastric hemorrhage/</p>
<p>Stevanel has reported this <del>last</del> year, on the Gold Coast of<lb/>
Africa, an &ldquo;epidemic of spirochaetosis resembling yellow fever/&rdquo; If I had<lb/>
only his clinical <del>symptoms</del><add>history</add> to go by I would have accepted it as yellow<lb/>
fever/. As he reports finding a &ldquo;small number of spirochetes&rdquo; &ldquo;rarely over<lb/>
<hi>20</hi> per field.&rdquo; Both Dr/ Russell, who was down to see me yesterday, and<lb/>
myself think that he must have been working with the organism of Ober-<lb/>
meier--certainly no leptospiral infection has ever given smears or sec-<lb/>
tions like that. He, however, states that it was not the "<hi>fi&egrave;vre recurrent</hi></p>
<p>I suggested, in a portion of my much-neglected History, that the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01119003"/>
the<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
&ldquo;Mat<add>la</add>zahuatl&rdquo; on the Mexican Plateau <add>16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century</add> which our American archaeologists are<lb/>
claiming for yellow fever, was almost certainly a mixture of typhus and re-<lb/>
lapsing fever/</p>
<p>Keep these things in your mind, and look for spironema even in cases<lb/>
in which you do see black vomit and jaundice/</p>
<p>I dare not hope that this explanation will hold for all, but I<lb/>
would give $1,000.00 ($800.00 of which I'd have to borrow!) if it could be<lb/>
so/</p>
<p>You are very right to take up Stegomyia control of the key-points on<lb/>
the Magdalena <add>to render them uninfectable</add> as a preliminary, along with, of course, the Caribbean<lb/>
ports/</p>
<p>I am exceedingly glad to get your letters/ I do not know where<lb/>
Puerto Santos is/ Is Le Brija the same place we used to call La Brea, where<lb/>
the oil men are at work?</p>
<p>I still suspect Cucuta/ Have no reason, except it is in the Mara-<lb/>
caibo basin, which included La Cura where yellow fever was reported in<lb/>
1916, and Bucaramanga quite certainly got its last big epidemic--my re-<lb/>
collection is in /12 or /14--from Cucuta (<hi>fiebre d'aclimaccion)</hi>, which<lb/>
(&ldquo;protected against the Maracaibo fever&rdquo;) was endemic there/ I am giving<lb/>
you a poor reason to suspect it now, as everybody who <add>was</add> is past early child-<lb/>
hood in 1910 or 1911 must be immune.</p>
<p>About Maracaibo, of course, you have a perfect control in the<lb/>
American and English (and I fear me German) oil and asphalt men/</p>
<p>Heao--a man whom I totally respect and like--reported several cases<lb/>
at Puerto Berrio about 1914/ Guiteras and myself stopped at this place to<lb/>
see him and, form his further description, felt quite certain that the<lb/>
cases were not yellow fever/ White, I think, accepts them, but we were<lb/>
closer to the event by some seven years and I cannot/ The specimen He&atilde;o<lb/>
sent to London was also pronounced negative (I <hi>think</hi>, but am not sure, by<lb/>
Andrew Balfour/ He <add><unclear>Herao</unclear></add> is an honest man, however, and a gentleman/</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01119004"/>
<p>gentleman/</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>If you see anything of my old friend, Dr. Vengoechia, give<lb/>
him both my kindest regards and best respects. He is, or was, at Baranquilla</p>
<p>Espundia in Peru (the <hi>Ferida brava</hi> of the Amazon Valley) is not<lb/>
an elephantiasis--it is the American Leis<add>h</add>maniasis/ It is absolutely<lb/>
different in its <add>latter</add> manifestations from the Leishmaniasis of Asia and East<lb/>
Africa (the &ldquo;Aleppo button&rdquo; <hi>et al</hi>). They have both forms in Brazil--the<lb/>
latter almost confined to the Coast (introduced I think, by Syrian im-<lb/>
migrants,)<lb/>
while <add>there is only</add> espundia <del>is</del> in the back country: up the Amazon and on the<lb/>
Parana <add>and</add>--I am absolutely certain <add>this is</add> native to America. No morphological<lb/>
or cultural differences have been found in the parasites. In Brazil,<lb/>
at any rate, it is quite certainly conveyed by some suctorial fly (nature unknown,)<lb/>
that lives in <del>some</del> wooded regions <del>and</del> Tartar emetic (intra-venously)<lb/>
is welnigh as much a specific against it as salvarsan is to syphilis.<lb/>
I saw 143 cases in the Bahia Hospital.</p>
<p>The British entomologists have reported from the Gold Coast<lb/>
(Salt Pond especially) the free--or rather profuse-breeding of A. (Ste-<lb/>
gomyia) aegypti in lagoons and tracks of boys around <add>lagoons</add> <del>them</del> and in mud<lb/>
puddles generally/ Please have Dunn keep his eyes and mind open to<lb/>
see if this thing ever occurs in the Americas:-- I mean from egg to<lb/>
imago. We have hitherto not so found it/ At the same time, both of<lb/>
us have seen enough of mosquitoes not to refuse to accept what seems<lb/>
to be a well attested fact because it contravenes the experience we<lb/>
ourselves have had: For instance, I and none of my gang, have found<lb/>
Anopheles producing <add>in artificial containers</add> so as to be of sanitary importance in any place<lb/>
east of the Mississippi. Von Ezdorf: LePrince and Taylor claim that<lb/>
this is common in Arkansas, even where other breeding places are a-<lb/>
vailable and where they are not in excessive numbers. I believe it.</p>
<p>Please also, if you can, keep your eyes open <del>of</del> for one, or it<lb/>
may be two things:</p>
<p>1. For Schistosomiasis mansoni (Bilharsia <add><hi>Mansoni</hi>)</add>. This was quite<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01119005"/>
quite<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
common in Caracas. <unclear>Iturbe</unclear> found one of the snail hosts,<lb/>
<hi>Bullinis contortes</hi>, at Caracas</p>
<p>2/ Anything called &ldquo;el bicho&rdquo; or &ldquo;la bicha/&rdquo; This is the name<lb/>
that is given by F/ X/ Sigaud (1840-45) to a Brazilian disease, which<lb/>
I suspect was No/ 1./ The cases are characterized by gangrene of the<lb/>
rectum. The same disease is described by early Dutch and Portuguese<lb/>
writers as existing at San Thome and Angola in West Africa in the 16th.<lb/>
Century. This name, &ldquo;la bicha,&rdquo; was the name given by the Brazilian<lb/>
historians to the first epidemic of yellow fever they had (1586-7) <add>(I am doubtful of this date)</add> in<lb/>
Pernambuco and Bahia. <add>(&ldquo;The Epidemic of <unclear>Celinda</unclear>&rdquo;)</add> There is absolutely no question of the nature<lb/>
of the disease in the Bahia epidemic/ It is beautifully reported by<lb/>
da Rocha Pitta and <del>probably</del><add>possibly</add> came to Pernambuco from Sao Thiago <add>,Azores,</add> in Fer-<lb/>
rera de Andrade's expedition.</p>
<p>P&egrave;re Labat, who, as you know, reported our first generally re-<lb/>
cognized epidemic of yellow fever in the Americas (1648)--&ldquo;<hi>mal de<lb/>
Siam</hi>&rdquo; <add>Martinique,--</add>--afterwards went to Angola where he claims to have recognized<lb/>
the same illness and said it should more properly be called &ldquo;<hi>mal<lb/>
d'Afrique</hi>&rdquo;. He stated that <del>because</del> &ldquo;a bicha&rdquo; is among its names in Angola.<lb/>
If you remember, it was the name given to the epidemic --whatever it<lb/>
was--at Callao that Leblond and your Peruvian friend (the one who sent<lb/>
me his monograph criticizing Leblond) differed <unclear>on.</unclear> The word was also<lb/>
used--according to <del>Wm.</del><add>Willem</add> <unclear>Pico</unclear>, for small-<add><unclear>pox</unclear></add><del><unclear></unclear></del> <del>(?)</del>. Of course, it really<lb/>
means &ldquo;the creature&rdquo; <add>and</add> in a very derogatory sense.</p>
<p>About myself, I have had two attacks of angina pectoris. The<lb/>
first followed what I judge was possibly over-exertion, though I did not<lb/>
feel it at the time. The second was not. I am here with Tom Brown and<lb/>
Thayer. <add>No better men could be found.</add> Both attacks were associated with a pylorospasm and I'll give<lb/>
them a Xmas present if they'll say that the whole thing was only an unu-<lb/>
sually violent one/ I expect to go to Washington shortly, as soon as I<lb/>
can, but no sooner than I <del>can</del><add>should</add>, and as soon as I can finish the section<lb/>
that I have almost completed, on the &ldquo;Place Origin of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, I<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01119006"/>
I<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
will send you a copy of it for your criticism thereon/. I have made an<lb/>
absolute volte face from the position I held before I began investigating<lb/>
and while I would not like to say that anything is <hi>proven</hi>, I am certain-<lb/>
ly disinclined to accept it as being of American origin. However, you<lb/>
will see what evidence I have when I send you the paper. It has involved<lb/>
a good deal of work, some of it--to me--very difficult. I judge I have<lb/>
been over over ten thousand pages on this subject from Nauhuatl and Maya<lb/>
to Flemish and Latin. I can read Portuguese--thank God!--fairly well,<lb/>
and Dutch (Holland) to some extent.<lb/>
I think a weeks work as I was working last spring, or--say--six weeks<lb/>
as I will work now, will enable me to finish this Section and you will<lb/>
be able to judge then whether my evidence justifies my tentative--it can<lb/>
be only a tentative--conclusion.</p>
<p>Thayer's examination this moring--he went over me last spring--<lb/>
was I judge, from the little he said, his expression etc/ favorable. I<lb/>
will attempt no more field work, however.</p>
<p>I have not written to Mrs/ Hanson, but will do so when I get to<lb/>
Washington. But for Laura I could not write to you.</p>
<p>One other thing:--and this is the end: If you can find any old<lb/>
books on Jimenez' Quesada's expedition from Santa Marta to Bogot&aacute; or (more<lb/>
important still) of the two Germans' (Alfinger and ?) from Coro,<lb/>
one of whom (I think Alfinger) met Quesada at Bogota and the other went<lb/>
across country to the Magdalena <add>lower down.</add> I will be enormously your debtor if you<lb/>
will get them for me.</p>
<p>Adios amigo, te doy buenas dichas.</p>
<p>Your letters interest me exceedingly and I will be glad to hear<lb/>
from you whenever you have time/</p>
<closer>
<salute>Your friend,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) H. R. Carter</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
