<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01110001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01110001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01110001</idno>
<title>Memorandum by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses ways to modify a pond in order to minimize mosquito infestation.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Memorandum by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01110001"/>
<p><unclear>Sinks Waters</unclear><lb/>
N. M. C<lb/>
<unclear>Mid West</unclear><lb/>
Mountain<lb/>
Island</p>
<p>- COPY -</p>
<p>(This was for the Mountain Island Project - to be installed<lb/>
on the Catawba.)</p>
<p>MEMORANDUM<lb/>
for<lb/>
Preparing Area for - a Pond.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>(1) Cutting Brush and Trees.</p>
<p>Cutting all brush from just above the flowage contour- say <add><unclear>25' hor- '2'L</unclear></add><lb/>
to a little below the lowest contour at which the pond will stand.</p>
<p>Brush must be cut so far below this contour that it<lb/>
will <del>(a)</del> either not project above <del>below the</del><add>the low</add> level of the water <del>or<lb/>
(b) by some ways -25' to 30' - from the bank.</del></p>
<p>All Pine trees, and saplings growing in groups close to-<lb/>
gether, should be cut as brush <del>except that</del> <unclear>all</unclear> <add>Pine trees</add> should be cut which<lb/>
project above the water; no matter how far they are from the bank.<lb/>
Pine needles are bad floatage.</p>
<p>Hardwood trees <add><del>out in the pond</del></add> are of little importance. It may be<lb/>
advisable to cut them but it scarcely necessary.</p>
<p>There is no advantage in cutting anything which will<lb/>
always be covered by water or in cutting hardwood cut in the pond.</p></item>
<item><p>(2) Removal of Things Cut.</p>
<p>Remove or burn completely all the logs: branches etc.,<lb/>
of the stuff cut on the pond. It is not a bad plan when the pond<lb/>
is filling and any stuff overlooked is floating ashore to haul it<lb/>
out. This is the easiest way to remove logs as they will float<lb/>
up to the bank. &amp; <unclear>save</unclear> will be <unclear>over-looked</unclear> in a large pond,</p>
<p>Insert par: <hi>2'</hi> <unclear>see - same</unclear> S. P. Co</p></item>
<item><p>(3)Bulrushes.</p>
<p>Where there is a growth of bulrushes on the <unclear>edges</unclear><lb/>
of the pond which will stick out of the water, they will not die,<lb/>
and they furnish excellent protection to mosquitoes against fish.<lb/>
These should be grubbed up with a hoe, and thrown above pond level.<lb/>
This is a smaller job than it seems as it will only need to be<lb/>
done about the heads of a very few bights. On the Bridge-water<lb/>
lake, a survey of probably 12 miles of bank only showed two places<lb/>
needing it. Whether cutting bulrushes close to the ground, so<lb/>
that they would be entirely covered <del>wit</del> by water for some months,<lb/>
will kill them or not I do not know. It is worth trying as an ex-<lb/>
periment.</p></item>
<pb n="2" id="f01110002"/>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item><p>(4) BURNING THE FLOWING AREA.</p>
<p>Burn over the flowing area or as much as possible of it<lb/>
and as late as you can before filling the pond - generally - during<lb/>
the early winter before. This is to get the dea<del>g</del><add>d</add> grass, leaves,<lb/>
etc. off the ground. This is not always possible,</p></item>
<item><p>(5) SPROUTS.</p>
<p>The stumps of saplings and brush cut down for the pond<lb/>
will in many cases send up a lot of sprouts. These that grow on<lb/>
the edge of the pond, from the flowage contour to below the minimum<lb/>
level, should be cut again just before the pond is filled. If the<lb/>
water stays above the cut stumps few - I think no - sprouts will<lb/>
start again. This is very important.</p>
<p>This was for a large pond<lb/>
<unclear>for which the preperation would n-e-<lb/>
guine 2 to 4 years</unclear></p></item>
<item><p>(5) FISH.</p>
<p>Make arrangements for stocking the pond with fish so<lb/>
that they may be inabundance while it is being filled and as soon<lb/>
as it is filled. The Alabama Power Company, at the instance of<lb/>
Mr. LePrince has done this for their pond under construction at Lock<lb/>
#8 on the Coosa, so that when the water rises the <unclear>minnows</unclear> (Gambusia)<lb/>
will be let out in the pond.</p>
<p>You can get information on this from Mr. Thurlow,<lb/>
Alabama Power Company, Birmingham, or information and assistance by<lb/>
<unclear>appkying</unclear> to Surgeon L. D. Fricks, U. S. Public Health Service, Room<lb/>
17, Court House Building, Memphis, Tenn., asking him if he could let<lb/>
you have assistance in this matter of Mr. J. A. LePrince or Mr.<lb/>
Hildebrand. There would be no charge for the service of either of<lb/>
these men.</p></item>
<item><p>(7) POOLS.</p>
<p>Where it is obvious that a fall of the pond will leave<lb/>
pools of water in hollows in the ground <hi>which will last over two<lb/>
weeks,</hi> ditches should be cut which would empty them.</p>
<p>I confess that I have seen little Anopheles production<lb/>
from this cause, (a) because such depressions holding water for the<lb/>
two weeks necessary for Anopheles production have not been common,<lb/>
(b) because fish are usually left in such pools as the water goes<lb/>
down. They, the pool, are more common on flat banks than steep<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01110003"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
ones. This work can economically be left and is generally<lb/>
left until the pond is full and falls and then these pools may<lb/>
be easily seen. They <hi>must</hi> be attended to however - either be-<lb/>
fore or after the pond is filled.</p></item>
<item><p>(8) AFFECT OF THESE MEASURES ON BREEDING.</p>
<p>This is about all that is necessary or advisable to<lb/>
be done to the flowage area for the prevention of malaria, and I am<lb/>
sorry to say that this will not prevent it entirely. All the large<lb/>
ponds I have seen constructed in a country in which Anopheles quad.<lb/>
can breed, have eliminated some breeding places and made others and<lb/>
the balance between the benefit and injury produced depends to an<lb/>
extent upon the balance between them. Generally for the first two<lb/>
or three years, at any rate, the injury has been greater than the<lb/>
benefit, although not always. The above measures however, will<lb/>
unquestionably <hi>minimize</hi> the production of Anopheles.</p></item>
<item><p>(9) FLUCTUATION OF THE POND.</p>
<p>Of at least as much, probably of greater, importance<lb/>
in preventing Anopheles production, than the preparation of the<lb/>
flowage area, is the provision for fluctuation of the levels of<lb/>
the pond. The idea is to keep it as high as possible in the<lb/>
non-breeding season - Nov. 1st to June 15th or July 1st here -<lb/>
and lower during the breeding season the remainder of the year <unclear><del>o</del></unclear><lb/>
and during the breeding season to fluctuate as much as practical;<lb/>
saving every rise of the river and running your water off between<lb/>
the rises.</p>
<p>This was <unclear>for Charlotte N. C.</unclear><lb/>
You <unclear>one for-the-south</unclear></p>
<p>A slight fluctuation is a little value; 1' to 2' and<lb/>
3' is of much and once in two weeks is often enough to change.</p></item>
<item><p>(10) EFFECT OF TIME.</p>
<p>In generally, the first 2 or 3 years of the pond is<lb/>
the worst for malaria. Frequently it gets better from the first<lb/>
year. After that the banks become cleaner and the fish more<lb/>
numerous and naturally both the wave-action and the fish-control<lb/>
less <del>in</del><add>en</add> the production of Anopheles.</p></item>
</list></p>
<pb n="4" id="f01110004"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>Of the end result of large ponds on the incidence of<lb/>
malaria I have not had an opportunity of studing a sufficient<lb/>
number to advise you.</p>
<p>The growth of aquatic plants should become consider-<lb/>
able; giving protection to Anopheles larvae. The upper reaches of<lb/>
the pond itself should shoal and become more or less marshy. The<lb/>
lower parts of creeks emptying into the pond might also fill up<lb/>
causing them, the creeks, to overflow more easily and making the<lb/>
drainage of their valleys more difficult. This would be especially<lb/>
apt to occur if the creek carries much sand - indeed in the sand-<lb/>
carrying creeks it frequently occurs without any pond.</p>
<p>In 1921 at the instance of General Beach, Chief of<lb/>
U. S. Engineers, I wrote a memorandum on this same subject for<lb/>
use in the preparation of the large pools, of which his corps has<lb/>
supervision; Muscle Shoals was the immediate consideration. This<lb/>
although brief is naturally better systemized than the foregoing<lb/>
and I will send it to you when I reach Washington.</p>
<p>Time of Filling Pond.</p>
<p>The best time to fill the pond, in this section, would<lb/>
be in October - say October 15th or later if need be. This is too<lb/>
late for A. quad., the species which especially breeds in ponds, to<lb/>
breed to as to do any harm that year and before the beginning of<lb/>
their breeding season the next year - say June 15th to 30th. Most<lb/>
of the small trash and flotage would be stranded or sunk and the<lb/>
grasses at the water edge dead and worn away.</p>
<p>This was for<lb/>
Charlotte &amp; for a big pond,</p>
<p>The worst time would be in early summer, May or June<lb/>
for reasons the reverse of those given above.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) H. R. Carter</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
