<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01114006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter fragment from [Henry Rose Carter] to William E. Deeks, August 28, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01114006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-08-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Deeks, William E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="place">Mitchell County (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">East Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-08-28">August 28, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01114006</idno>
<title>Letter fragment from [Henry Rose Carter] to William E. Deeks, August 28, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] believes that malaria is best controlled by attacking mosquitoes and explains why. He notes that community sterilization of malaria carriers by quinine is a recognized method advocated by physicians, but not by entomologists.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-08-28">
<head>Letter fragment from [Henry Rose Carter] to William E. Deeks, August 28, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01114006"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1923-08-28">August 28, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. W. E. Deeks, General Manager,<lb/>
Medical Department, United Fruit Company,<lb/>
17 Battery Place,<lb/>
New York, N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Deeks:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In reply to your letter of August 22nd., I would say that the com-<lb/>
munity sterilization of malaria carriers by quinine is a recognized method<lb/>
of malaria control. In all places it can be used as an adjuvant and in<lb/>
some places may be the method of election. The same method, of course,<lb/>
is not equally applicable to all communities.</p>
<p>My own feeling is in general for the control by lessening Ano-<lb/>
pheles production where this is economically practicable. In some places<lb/>
it is not.</p>
<p>There are a few things in the method by sterilization of car-<lb/>
riers I would ask you to note:</p>
<p>1/ If the work be undertaken while infected Anopheles are<lb/>
in flight, not only must all carriers be freed from parasites, but the<lb/>
quinine must be continued (I do not say in the same dose) long enough to<lb/>
prevent their reinfection while they are still exposed to infected Ano-<lb/>
pheles. This, I am quite sure, was the reason for the continuation of the<lb/>
treatment by Koch at Stephansort for some weeks after the disappearance of<lb/>
parasites in the blood--although he does not mention it as a reason in his<lb/>
report, simply states that he did continue the treatment for some time.</p>
<p>2/ If one wants permanent results in a community--not simply<lb/>
for a single season--very obviously steps must be taken to prevent immi-<lb/>
gration into this community of people infected outside of it.</p>
<p>The reason that Bass' work in Bolivar County was so non-perma-<lb/>
nent was because his community consisted mainly of negro tenant farmers<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01114007"/>
farmers<lb/>
renting by the year and something over 60% of the community was changed<lb/>
after the crop was gathered.</p>
<p>In Mitchell County, Ga., the result was more lasting: the community<lb/>
consisting of white farmers handling and working their own little places,<lb/>
so there was little change of population at the end of the year.</p>
<p>Koch's report, and the method used at Stephansort and in German<lb/>
East-Africa, implies that he consideres the inability to find parasites<lb/>
in the cutaneous blood after a single careful examination as proof that the<lb/>
patient is free<del>f</del>from them. It is, of course, untenable. The observations<lb/>
of many British Commissions during the war showed that a man might be nega-<lb/>
tive for parasites on more than one careful examination and yet be infected.<lb/>
In this connection I would especially note the work of Acton <hi>et al</hi> at <unclear>Dagahai</unclear>.<lb/>
It was <del>p</del> published in the Indian Journal of Research about two years ago. You<lb/>
do not, however, need any warning on that ground.</p>
<p>The treatment most advisable--i. e. the dosage and method of ad-<lb/>
ministration of quinine--you can tell better than anyone else. You know<lb/>
what other men have used and with what results and you can make your own ob-<lb/>
servations upon carriers under good control--observing both parasite and<lb/>
symptomatic relapse--and will be able to give us very valuable information<lb/>
as to the choice of method for the use of quinine as well as important data<lb/>
as to the immediate efficacy: the permanent efficacy and the cost of this gener-<lb/>
al method, on which exact extensive knowledge is lacking.</p>
<p>Without question it will--at the very least--be of assistance to<lb/>
you in malaria control even if you use it combined with other methods.</p>
<p>I note that Orenstein reported against its efficientcy at Dar-es-<lb/>
Salaam when he went there soon after he left Panama. It is, as you know--<lb/>
and naturally--the method most generally advocated by physicians and en-<lb/>
entirely reprobated by entomologists.</p>
<p>With best remembrances to you and your, in which Larua and</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
