<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01113009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from F. E. Pettman to The Rockefeller Foundation, May 25, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01113009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-05-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">Gold Coast (Africa)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-05-25">May 25, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01113009</idno>
<title>Letter from F. E. Pettman to The Rockefeller Foundation, May 25, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Pettman is nearly out of yellow fever vaccine. He describes the case of an Italian who died of yellow fever and lists yellow fever deaths among whites in the Gold Coast.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-05-25">
<head>Letter from F. E. Pettman to The Rockefeller Foundation, May 25, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01113009"/>
<p>COPY<lb/>
Carter<lb/>
GOLD COAST HARBOURS<lb/>
Seccondee, <date value="1923-05-25">May 25, 1923.</date>
Gold Coast, British West Africa.<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York City.<lb/>
Gentlemen:</p>
<p>I am sending you, under separate cover, 72 forms filled in with<lb/>
the individual vaccinations records of all the men I have inoculated against<lb/>
yellow fever. It will be seen that although in some cases the reaction was<lb/>
severe, there were no alarming symptoms, and of the two abscesses, one at<lb/>
least might have been avoided.</p>
<p>I have only two vials of vaccine on hand now, and am asking Stewart<lb/>
&amp; McDonnell to apply to you for a further supply which will be used for our<lb/>
men here, and also for any others who care to take it. Dr. Palmer, the S.M.O.<lb/>
at Secondee is not yet convinced of its virtue, but I feel sure that if a<lb/>
serious outbreak occurs there will be an urgent demand for it. I am asking<lb/>
for enough to inoculate about 100 men.</p>
<p>I am enclosing copy of letter from Dr. White, Cape Coast, along with<lb/>
serum treatment record of J. F. Hanney. This case was evidently not a suitable<lb/>
one for serum treatment, being too far advanced, although apparently only in<lb/>
the third day of the disease.</p>
<p>On the 23rd. inst. I was called to see a case in consultation with<lb/>
Dr. Bell. An Italian, eight months in the country, sent down from Huni Valley<lb/>
(16 miles from Tarquah) the previous night, diagnosis not made. He spoke little<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01113010"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
English, and his native servant less, so that it was difficult to get<lb/>
definite history of the case. He had been ill five days before being sent<lb/>
down. Had severe headache but only slight pain in the back. Vomited<lb/>
almost from the first. Complained of pain in the stoach. When I saw him<lb/>
he was slightly jaundiced, features pinched, restless, mentally alert,<lb/>
nauseated but not vomiting, marks of blood or blood stained vomit on his<lb/>
lips, pulse small and soft, rate 80 temp. 99, gums not markedly swollen<lb/>
nor congested. The stomach was dilated, epigastrium very tender on pressure,<lb/>
tenderness extending to the right. Scrotum and penis much congested. He<lb/>
had voided no urine since his arrival so we passed soft rubber catheter and<lb/>
got only a few drops of turbid urine.</p>
<p>He died a few hours later and a P.M. was done. Dr. Palmer, who<lb/>
did the P.M., states that it was typical yellow fever. The liver, kidneys<lb/>
and spleen were yellow, and on section the liver showed fatty degeneration,<lb/>
the kidneys much swollen and congested. The stomach was greatly dilated and<lb/>
about half full of blood stained material. The mucosa showed numerous petechial<lb/>
haemorrhages as did also the duodenum and to a less extent the small intestine.<lb/>
The dependent parts of the body were markedly congested.</p>
<p>Since November last deaths among whites from Y.F., or reported<lb/>
Y.F. on the Gold Coast that I have heard of are as follows,<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Saltpond - McMaster, In Nov.<lb/>
Frenchman, in Nov.<lb/>
Mrs. Besant, in Jan.<lb/>
Englishman, in March.</item>
<item>Accra - Mr. Ford, in Feby.</item>
<item>Winnebah- Englishman, in May.</item>
<item>Seccondee- Stocks, in Nov.<lb/>
Irving,<lb/>
Italian, in May.</item>
<pb n="3" id="f01113011"/>
<item>-3-</item>
<item>Cape Coast - J. F. Hanney, April.<lb/>
Three others.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Those who died in Seccondee were brought down from Tarquah or<lb/>
vicinity, distant about forty miles. Some of these cases have had the<lb/>
diagnosis confirmed from Accra. With some yellow fever in the vicinity,<lb/>
and between three and four hundred non-immune whites in Seccondee, an<lb/>
outbreak here is not at all unlikely.</p>
<p>With many thanks for your kindness and generosity in supplying<lb/>
the serum and vaccine, I remain</p>
<p>Yours Sincerely,<lb/>
(Signed) F. E. Pettman<lb/>
S.M.O. G.C.H.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01113012"/>
<p>COPY<lb/>
GOLD COAST HARBOURS<lb/>
Seccondee, <date value="1923-05-30">May 30, 1923.</date>
The Rockefeller Foundation,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York, U.S.A.<lb/>
Gentlemen:</p>
<p>Your letter of April 26th. has just been received. Only today<lb/>
I received a request to inoculate the Europeans of Cape Coast, but un-<lb/>
fortunately am unable to comply with their request until a further supply<lb/>
of vaccine has been received.</p>
<p>There is also the possibility that a similar request may come<lb/>
from the people of Seccondee, although Dr. Palmer, their S.M.O., is at<lb/>
present not greatly in favour of it.</p>
<p>I am sending you a specimen of liver from one of the cases that<lb/>
died in Seccondee.</p>
<p>Since writing you on May 25th. the diagnosis of yellow fever on<lb/>
the Italian who died here, has been confirmed at Accra.</p>
<p>I remain,</p>
<p>Yours Sincerely,<lb/>
(Signed) F. E. Pettman<lb/>
S. M.O.<lb/>
May 31st.<lb/>
P.S. I regret exceedingly that Dr. Palmer, who said he could let me have<lb/>
a specimen of liver, states it has been sent to London without his<lb/>
knowledge. I shall use every effort to get you a specimen at the<lb/>
first opportunity.<lb/>
F.E.P.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
