<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01113035">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter extract from Oliver L. Pothier to Frederick F. Russell, July 19, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Pothier, Oliver L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01113035</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-07-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Russell, Fredrick F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Magdelena River (Colombia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-07-19">July 19, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01113035</idno>
<title>Letter extract from Oliver L. Pothier to Frederick F. Russell, July 19, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Pothier describes yellow fever outbreaks in Bucaramanga, Colombia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-07-19">
<head>Letter extract from Oliver L. Pothier to Frederick F. Russell, July 19, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01113035"/>
<p>Extract of letter of July 19, 1923 from Dr. O. L. Pothier to Dr. F.F. Russell.</p>
<p>&ldquo;When we met in Washington last Saturday week Dr. Carter<lb/>
and you inquired into the vital statistics of Bucaramanga, of which<lb/>
I was unable to give you definite information for the reasons given.<lb/>
As for that of the epidemic of the fever of Bucaramanga here are<lb/>
some additional facts which may be of some utility. In 1910 and<lb/>
1911 there was an epidemic of fever, of the same character as the one<lb/>
of 1923, in Bucaramanga and adjoining towns, which was more virulent<lb/>
and more extensive, it was characterized by its large incidence and<lb/>
its great mortality, during this invasion there were 341 fatal cases.<lb/>
From the description of this epidemic, it corresponds in all its<lb/>
aspects to the one that we found this year in Bucaramanga. This year<lb/>
according to the report of Drs Daniel Peralta, Martin Carvajal,<lb/>
Franciscao Pradiall Gonzelez, Andres Gomez, Julio Valdivieso, Roberto<lb/>
Serpa, and Luis Ardila Gomez, they report 200 cases seen by them, of<lb/>
which 80% were benign cases which recovered, 5% of the serious and<lb/>
virulent cases who recovered, giving a total mortality of 15%. These<lb/>
statictics only cover the cases seen by these Physicians. These<lb/>
cases were only the cases seen by these Physicians, as I told you in<lb/>
Washington when we arrived in Bucaramanga we were given a mortality<lb/>
of 50% which we afterward interpreted to mean the mortality of severe<lb/>
cases only, as I explained many of the mild cases had not been con-<lb/>
cidered as many did not come under the observation of any physician.<lb/>
On reading over the thesis of Dr. Carlos Esguerra, written in 1889<lb/>
for his degree at the Medical School of Paris, he mentions epidemics<lb/>
of yellow fever occurring at that period along the Magdelena river<lb/>
and in Baranquilla. Since that time we have indications of peculiar<lb/>
epidemics occurring in different ports along the Magdelena, Puerto<lb/>
Berrio, The Fever of Tacamocho, a report of Dr. Emiliano Henao M.<lb/>
which have all the characteristics of yellow fever, this report is<lb/>
of 1917. It would seem that this fever must have existed for a long<lb/>
period as an endemic condition for several years, and after disappearing<lb/>
in the other foci remained endemic in the area of Bucaramanga and the<lb/>
adjoining towns. I think I have covered all the information that<lb/>
I have at my disposal that may elucidate the condition of endimicity at<lb/>
Bucaramanga.&rdquo;</p>
<p>* * *</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
