<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01111002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: A Resume of the Anti-malarial Operations at Cristobal-Colon from 1917 to 1922, Inclusive, by J.L. Byrd, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01111002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Canal Zone (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Cristobal, Canal Zone (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Manzanillo Island</name>
<name type="place">Gatun, Canal Zone (Panama)</name>
<name type="hospital">Colon Hospital, Colon (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-00-00">1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01111002</idno>
<title>Report: A Resume of the Anti-malarial Operations at Cristobal-Colon from 1917 to 1922, Inclusive, by J.L. Byrd, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Byrd's paper discusses the control of mosquito breeding as the most effective way to reduce the incidence of malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-00-00">
<head>Report: A Resume of the Anti-malarial Operations at Cristobal-Colon from 1917 to 1922, Inclusive, by J.L. Byrd, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01111002"/>
<p><hi>A RESUME OF THE ANTI-MALARIAL OPERATIONS<lb/>
At Cristobal-Colon<lb/>
From 1917 to 1922, inclusive.*</hi><lb/>
By<lb/>
<hi>Dr. J. L. Byrd, Health Officer, Cristobal - Colon.</hi></p>
<p>Cristobal-Colon has a population of 37,500, and is located on<lb/>
Manzanillo Island near the Atlantic entrance of the Panama Canal. The<lb/>
island was once a tidal swamp which is now filled in great part. This<lb/>
was once widely known as one of the most unhealthy ports of the world,<lb/>
yellow fever being rife until 1905, when it was eradicated by General<lb/>
Gorgas and his co-workers. Malaria was very prevalent in Colon until<lb/>
1920. The following table gives the number of cases of malaria report-<lb/>
ed among the employees of the Panama Canal and the Panama Railroad in<lb/>
Cristobal-Colon, from 1916 to 1922, inclusive:</p>
<p>1918?</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="3">
<row>
<cell><hi>Year</hi></cell><cell><hi>Number of cases reported</hi></cell><cell><hi>No. Emp</hi>.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1916</cell><cell>143</cell><cell>-</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1917</cell><cell>148</cell><cell>9,000</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1918</cell><cell>53</cell><cell>9,000</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1919</cell><cell>149</cell><cell>8,500</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1920</cell><cell>58</cell><cell>7,500</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1921</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>5,000</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1922</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>3,500</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>In 1917 the anti-malaria work had been extended only about<lb/>
one-half mile from the inhabited sections. This limited area was<lb/>
thoroughly sanitated; all vegetation was kept closely trimmed; swampy<lb/>
areas were either filled or carefully drained, and all drains were oiled<lb/>
regularly every seven days. As a result, anopheles breeding was elinin-<lb/>
(*) Read before the Medical Association of the<lb/>
Isthmian Canal Zone, May 18, 1923.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01111003"/>
2<lb/>
ated within the area which included all of Manzanillo Island and a part<lb/>
of what is now known as the Mt. Hope District. Nevertheless, the malarial<lb/>
rate continued to remain very high in spite of the fact that no anopheles<lb/>
were breeding within a radius of one-half to three-quarters of a mile of<lb/>
the city.</p>
<p>Extensive swamps surround the city on three sides. On investiga-<lb/>
tion, these were found to be breeding anopheles in countless numbers, and as<lb/>
this breeding was occurring only one-half mile from the inhabited sections,<lb/>
and as the adult mosquito catch in such sections was very high with a cor-<lb/>
responding high malarial rate, it became necessary to control mosquito<lb/>
breeding in these swamps. <hi>During 1917-1918</hi> extensive drainage systems<lb/>
were installed in them and anopheles breeding was controlled for a distance<lb/>
of approximately <hi>one mile from</hi> the city. As a result, the malarial rate<lb/>
for 1918 was lower than ever before, only 53 cases among the employees being<lb/>
reported in Cristobal-Colon during the entire year, as compared with 148<lb/>
cases for 1917.</p>
<p>In 1917, 1918, and 1919, great swarms of mosquitoes, largely<lb/>
anophelines, appeared on the screens at Colon Hospital and the Hotel Wash-<lb/>
ington. The swarms came regularly every year about two weeks after the<lb/>
beginning of the rainy season and would continue for about three months.<lb/>
The mosquitoes were so numerous that it was necessary to detail a laborer<lb/>
for the purpose of killing them with larvacide applied with a knapsack<lb/>
sprayer. The older sanitary inspectors stated that these swarms had ap-<lb/>
peared every year since 1905.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01111004"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>This was at first very difficult to explain. Colon Hospital<lb/>
is located on the extreme northern end of Manzanillo Island. The entire<lb/>
area for a distance of over one mile from the hospital is thoroughly sani-<lb/>
tated, and all anopheles breeding eliminated therefrom. The nearest<lb/>
anopheles breeding area to Colon Hospital was located directly across Man-<lb/>
zanillo Bay, a distance of approximately one mile and three quarters from,<lb/>
and to the leeward of, the hospital. Many night observations were made<lb/>
along Colon Beach and from boats anchored in the bay, and it was definitely<lb/>
proven that the swarms of anophelines on the hospital and hotel screens were<lb/>
coming from the Margarita swamps which begin one mile and three quarters<lb/>
east and across Manzanillo Bay from the hospital. The bay is one mile wide.<lb/>
The evidence of these long flights of anophelines was only accepted after<lb/>
repeated observations and catches, since in view of the fact that prior to<lb/>
1915 the concensus of opinion among sanitarians was that the anopheles<lb/>
mosquito was not a strong flier and as a general rule did not travel over<lb/>
200 yards from the breeding area. General Gorgas states (&ldquo;Sanitation in<lb/>
Panama&rdquo;, page 182):</p>
<p>&ldquo;all brush and undergrowth were cleared within<lb/>
200 yards of houses and villages and the grounds<lb/>
carefully drained within this area.&rdquo;</p>
<p>However, on page 202 of the same book the author records a flight of<lb/>
anopheles at Gatun of over one mile. Evidently this was considered at<lb/>
that time as very unusual. The many flight observations made about Cris-<lb/>
tobal-Colon during the past five years clearly show that long flights of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01111005"/>
4<lb/>
albimanus tarsimaculata anopheles are not unusual, it being found that<lb/>
they will fly against an eight mile breeze for a distance of over two<lb/>
miles. Margarita swamp was drained by sea-level canals during 1920-21,<lb/>
and Colon Hospital has not been visited by these swarms of mosquitoes since<lb/>
this work was well begun, although there have been several relatively small<lb/>
Flights since that time. Apparently these are from swamps located more<lb/>
than two miles from the hospital.</p>
<p>On May 2, 1919, all the colored workers at the Cristobal docks<lb/>
and the coaling station walked out on strike. They were immediately re-<lb/>
placed by native labor which was recruited from the interior, i. e.,<lb/>
unsanitated sections of the Republic of Panama. It has been estimated<lb/>
that over 80 percent of these laborers harbored the <hi>plasmodium malariae</hi><lb/>
in their blood, either as chronic malaria or as carriers. About 2,000<lb/>
of them were brought to Cristobal-Colon during the strike and many of them<lb/>
developed acute malaria within a week after their arrival in the city.<lb/>
During June, July, and August, the labor camp, known as Camp Bierd, was<lb/>
visited by the usual large flights of anopheles mosquitoes from Telfer's<lb/>
Island swamps and the swamps near the Arcia dairy, a distance of one to two<lb/>
miles from the camp. The chart of <hi>the number of adult anopheles mosquitoes</hi><lb/>
caught in quarters, shows that there <hi>were no more anopheles mosquitoes</hi> at<lb/>
Camp Bierd in 1919 than in former years, and that the flights were about as<lb/>
usual. However, the presence of the large number of natives greatly in-<lb/>
creased the plasmodium index in the camp. Many of the natives had never<lb/>
been in a hospital; they were superstitious and had a dreadful fear of all<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01111006"/>
5<lb/>
hospitals, and as a result many of them would remain sick in camp for<lb/>
several days and would not seek medical attention. The Jamaican jani-<lb/>
tors first reported several sick men in camp and on investigation it was<lb/>
found that they were suffering from malaria. They had to be forced in-<lb/>
to the hospitals under guard, but many of the mild cases evaded the camp<lb/>
inspections. The result of this unusual condition was an epidemic of<lb/>
malaria in Camp Bierd and vicinity. As many as 21 cases were reported<lb/>
in a single week from this locality. In order to control this outbreak<lb/>
the following measures were taken:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Drainage work was immediately begun in the anopheles<lb/>
breeding areas on Telfer's Island and vicinity.</item>
<item>2. Splenic Index: A blood smear and splenic examina-<lb/>
tion was made on every person living in Camp Bierd, and<lb/>
those found with large spleens, or showing signs or symptoms<lb/>
of clinical malaria, were hospitalized.</item>
<item>3. Quinine sterilization and immunization: Every person<lb/>
living in Camp Bierd was given ten grains of quinine in<lb/>
liquid form every day for three months.</item>
<item>4. A dusk and dawn catch of adult mosquitoes was made in<lb/>
all screened quarters in that section in order to destroy<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, and as an index to the effectiveness of<lb/>
the drainage work.</item>
</list></p>
<p>180</p>
<p>Very little oil was used in controlling breeding since the swamps<lb/>
were too extensive and the cost would have been prohibitive. It would also<lb/>
have been necessary to remove all vegetation before oiling, the cost of this<lb/>
would have been very great, and the measure only temporarily efficacious.<lb/>
The method used to control breeding was as follows: Trochas (paths six<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01111007"/>
6<lb/>
feet wide) were cut through the swamp at 50-yard intervals. Sea-level<lb/>
drains, varying in size according to carrying capacity required, were<lb/>
dug along the center of the trochas; most of them were only eight inches<lb/>
wide, i. e. &ldquo;spade wide.&rdquo; These drains were kept free from vegetation.</p>
<p>These control measures were very effective and the results were<lb/>
more than gratifying. The adult anopheles catch in the camp was reduced<lb/>
from a monthly catch of 3,700 in July to 1,100 in August and to 600 in<lb/>
September, which was the lowest catch ever recorded for that season of<lb/>
the year.</p>
<p>The malarial rate in July was the highest recorded since 1915.<lb/>
The epidemic reached its height in that month when 67 cases were reported<lb/>
among the 8,500 employees living in the Cristobal-Colon district. How-<lb/>
<unclear>67/88</unclear><lb/>
ever, this rate was immediately reduced within one month, and in August<lb/>
only 19 cases were reported, as compared with 21 for August, 1918. The<lb/>
malarial rate has been very low since the termination of this epidemic.<lb/>
The greatest number of cases reported in one month during 1920 was 15,<lb/>
the greatest number reported in any one month during 1921 was 7, and in<lb/>
1922, 12 cases. Therefore, the once seemingly impossible task of con-<lb/>
trolling malaria in Cristobal-Colon has almost been accomplished.</p>
<p><hi>SUMMARY</hi></p>
<p>Colon presented one of the most difficult problems of sanitation<lb/>
on the entire Isthmus of Panama. The city was almost surrounded by exten-<lb/>
sive swamps in which anophelines were breeding in countless millions. The<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01111008"/>
7<lb/>
filling or drainage of these swamps would have necessitated an almost<lb/>
prohibitive expense. One million dollars was, at one time, requested<lb/>
for the filling of one of the swamps near the Army and Navy posts, but the<lb/>
expenditure was not made and the swamp still exists, although breeding has<lb/>
been successfully controlled therein by drainage. Since there were no<lb/>
funds for the filling of these swamps, drainage was relied upon to solve the<lb/>
problems. As the swamps were only from a few inches to two or three<lb/>
feet above sea-level, large open sea-level canals with connecting laterals<lb/>
forming a kind of checkerboard effect, were cut through the center of the<lb/>
swamps. This was done for the purpose of draining off the fresh water ac-<lb/>
cumulations and allowing salt water to circulate freely through the entire<lb/>
system with each ebb and flow of the tide, and to admit top minnows to the<lb/>
anopheles breeding areas. It was not necessary to oil these drains since<lb/>
the salt water and minnows rendered them unfavorable for anopheles breeding.<lb/>
This work was begun in 1917 and continued until 1922 when the various drain-<lb/>
age systems were practically completed.</p>
<p>The cutting and removal of all vegetation inside the so-called sani-<lb/>
tated zone was continued until 1919. In 1919 the cutting of grass and other<lb/>
vegetation by the Health Department was discontinued except for the prevention<lb/>
of mosquito breeding in wet areas until drains have been installed. The cut-<lb/>
ting of vegetation for the purpose of eliminating mosquito harborage was not<lb/>
considered as a justifiable routine measure, and was a useless expense which<lb/>
not only did no good but diverted funds and effort from the more important<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01111009"/>
8<lb/>
work of controlling mosquito breeding by drainage. The use of &ldquo;spade-<lb/>
wide&rdquo; tide water drains for controlling anopheles breeding in swamps<lb/>
near tide water has given excellent results. By the use of these drains<lb/>
mosquito breeding is controlled over large areas at a minimum expense.</p>
<p>The administration of prophylactic doses of quinine (5 grains)<lb/>
was a routine anti-malaria measure in Cristobal-Colon until 1918, when the<lb/>
malarial rate reached such a low level that it was considered safe to dis-<lb/>
continue this measure. However, during the 1919 epidemic at Camp Bierd<lb/>
10 grains of quinine in liquid form was given each person in this camp<lb/>
daily for three months.</p>
<p>The routine daily catching of adult anopheles in quarters was<lb/>
discontinued on September 7, 1921, and at present only periodic catches<lb/>
are made. The attached chart of the anopheles catch shows that it was<lb/>
reduced to almost nil, even during the rainy season of 1921.</p>
<p>The mosquito control force for this district, which covers an<lb/>
area of approximately 18 square miles and contains 55 miles of drains,<lb/>
consists of one white sanitary inspector, one colored foreman and 23<lb/>
colored laborers. Although this small force is about 50% less than the<lb/>
mosquito control force of 1917, the sanitated area has been increased<lb/>
more than four times <add>the size</add> it was in that year and breeding therein has been<lb/>
successfully controlled. One of the laborers has been trained as an<lb/>
anopheles larva hunter; he inspects all drains and fresh water accumu-<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01111010"/>
9<lb/>
lations in the district once each week, taking a sample of any larvae<lb/>
found, and if he finds any anopheles he reports it immediately so that<lb/>
the oiling man may destroy the breeding at once.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>CONCLUSIONS.</hi></head>
<item>1. In order to successfully control malaria at Cristobal-Colon<lb/>
it is first necessary to control mosquito breeding within mosquito flight<lb/>
distance which at Cristobal-Colon may extend for at least two miles. The<lb/>
installation of ditches which permit the free circulation of sea water is<lb/>
an economical and efficient method of accomplishing this.</item>
<item>2. The elimination of mosquito harborage by cutting and removal<lb/>
of vegetation is not now necessary since the most favorable harboring<lb/>
place for <add>adult</add> mosquitoes is in and under houses. The great desideratum is<lb/>
the elimination of mosquito breeding by methods which act continuously<lb/>
and almost permanently.</item>
<item>3. The administration of sterilizing doses of quinine (10 grains)<lb/>
every day for a period of twelve weeks is a useful adjuvant to anopheline<lb/>
control during an epidemic, since it reduces the plasmodium index and the<lb/>
opportunity for mosquito infection.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
