<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01113002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, July 3, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01113002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-07-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Scannell, E.J.</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
<name type="place">Mexico City (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Cucuta (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Panuco (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Texas</name>
<name type="place">Brazil</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-07-03">July 3, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01113002</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, July 3, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor discusses his theories regarding the origins of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-07-03">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, July 3, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01113002"/>
<opener>
Book<lb/>
PODER EJECUTIVO FEDERAL<lb/>
<unclear>ESTADOS-UNIDOS-MEXICANOS</unclear><lb/>
MEXICO<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO<lb/>
DE<lb/>
SALUBRIDAD PUBLICA<lb/>
----<lb/>
COMICION ESPECIAL PARA LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
----<lb/>
PRIMERA ZONA<lb/>
----<lb/>
TAMPICO, TAMAULIPAS<lb/>
<dateline>
Tampico Tamps.<lb/>
<date value="1923-07-03">Jjly 3rd. 1923.</date>
</dateline>
Connor<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am returning your MSS. <del><unclear></unclear></del> "the History on Place<lb/>
of origin of Yellow Fever', Have read it as you suggest-<lb/>
ed, first with the notes and again without the notes. I<lb/>
have done this not once but several times.</p>
<p>This history as you have compiled it and your<lb/>
analysis of the data is intensely interesting and ill-<lb/>
uminating and probably as definite as such a <del>a</del> work can<lb/>
be at this time. Conclusive evidence indicating the<lb/>
place of origin of yellow fever or the evolution of<lb/>
this infection into a separate entity is probably con<lb/>
tained in the carving and picture writings on the mon-<lb/>
uments scattered through out Mexico and Central America.<lb/>
Doctor Marinez once told me that this is his opin-<lb/>
ion also.</p>
<p>I should be inclined to accept as yellow fever the<lb/>
cases reported by Bernal Diaz occuring in his command<lb/>
in Mexico city in which the vomiting of &lsquo;blood and mud&rsquo;<lb/>
was noted as a symptom. It is true that these cases<lb/>
may have been pneumonia but the instances have been<lb/>
rare where pneumonia with the vomiting of blood have<lb/>
taken on epidemic characteristics even in Mexico city.<lb/>
The reading of this particular part of the MSS. would<lb/>
lead me to think that Diaz was walking away from an<lb/>
epidemic of yellow fever rather than pnuemonia. Again<lb/>
I do not think that you can ignore the fact that there<lb/>
may have been an epidemic of yellow fever in Mexico<lb/>
City during a long hot summer. The only transmisor of<lb/>
the Leptospira Icteroides is present there to-day and<lb/>
was there in all probabilities when the conquistadores<lb/>
visited the city.</p>
<p>We are probably justified in assuming that the<lb/>
yellow fever infection has not undergone any marked<lb/>
change in its symptom-complex in the last five hundred<lb/>
or thousands years and to-day we are observing, if the<lb/>
report of Doctor White re- yellow fever in Cucuta is<lb/>
correct, this infection lying dormant, that is in a very<lb/>
mild form, in a large city for nearly ten years without<lb/>
having attracted attention to it and only then when the<lb/>
infection invaded another city. Could not this same<lb/>
thing have happened in Mexico during the Aztec reign?<lb/>
I think it could.</p>
<p>From the little that we know of the habits of the<lb/>
ancient Mexican peoples it appears clear to me that<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01113003"/>
-2-<lb/>
they only interested themselves in affairs of disease when an infection<lb/>
had taken on epidemic proportions. This is not unlike the attitude that<lb/>
we note to-day in certain section of our own country.</p>
<p>Only last year in Panuco the mild and moderately severe cases<lb/>
of what later proved to be yellow fever were called paludismo hemmoragica<lb/>
and had been so-called for years and would in probability have con-<lb/>
tinued to be so classified if we had not studied the infection and place<lb/>
it in its proper <del><unclear></unclear></del> catagoria. The same thing may have happened in the<lb/>
time of the aztecs. For this reason I do not think that a definite state-<lb/>
ment can be made one way or the other nor are dedu<add>c</add>tions sound when based<lb/>
on the evidence at hand at this time.</p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del> As a side issue to the Panuco outbreak- we were<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> inclined to think at the begining of the epidemic that it was not<lb/>
yellow fever because the white foreigners were <add>not</add> coming down but here we over<lb/>
looked the fact that the white foreigners are nearly all oil men working in<lb/>
the camps during the day and only coming into the key center (panuco) at<lb/>
night when the &lsquo;steg&rsquo; <del><unclear></unclear></del> to say the least is only passively active. This obse-<lb/>
ervation is proven to a certain extent by finding that the first two white<lb/>
foreigners to be infected were oil men who had<del>e</del> lived in Panuco during the<lb/>
day-light hours for one week before coming down sick. Here in Mexico the<lb/>
aedes egypti is essentially a day-biter. The white foreigners really played<lb/>
a very <unclear>small</unclear> part in the last epidemic here. Might not there have been a similar<lb/>
state of affairs present during the early years of the conquistadores?</p>
<p>Now let us look at what occured in Texas last year. There was an epi-<lb/>
demic of dengue, so-called, in which there was vomiting of digested blood<lb/>
in many cases and in certain areas the death rate was high, so high in fact<lb/>
that your own service became suspicious. Fortunately the winter came on<lb/>
and checked the spread of the infection.</p>
<p>It seems to me, Doctor, that there is much <del><unclear></unclear></del> to <add>be</add> work out regarding<lb/>
yellow fever, past and present, that the best we can do at this time is<lb/>
to guess and that is where I would leave the question of origin of<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<p>I wish I could interest you in the matter of suggesting to our Board<lb/>
to furnish a paleopatholgist to work here in Mexico for a few years. Many<lb/>
archeologist, including your friend Morely, are agreed that such a move would<lb/>
be productive of good results.</p>
<p>I greatly appreciate your sending me this MSS. and have truly enjoy-<lb/>
ed reading it. My regret is that I can not offer you <add>real</add> constructive critic-<lb/>
ism of same.</p>
<p>Doctor Scannell as you know has left Mexico to accompany Doctor<lb/>
White to Brazil and therefore there was not time to shown him the MSS.<lb/>
before his departure. You mention in your letter that a section of<lb/>
the Mss. has been sent to Dr. Martinez. I would be glad to see this if you<lb/>
can send it to me.</p>
<p>The month <unclear>od</unclear> June passed without a case of y.f. and the outlook<lb/>
is good.</p>
<p>With all good wishes, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>M E Connor</signed>.
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
2121 California St. N.W.<lb/>
Washington D.C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
