<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01123003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on Marie D. Gorgas' manuscript by [Henry Rose Carter], [1923]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01123003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Brazil</name>
<name type="place">Veracruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Asia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-00-00">[1923]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01123003</idno>
<title>Notes on Marie D. Gorgas' manuscript by [Henry Rose Carter], [1923]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] gives corrections on a manuscript. He comments extensively on Gorgas, Havana around 1900, Finlay, his own work on extrinsic incubation and its influence on Reed, and the immediate influence of Reed's work</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-00-00">
<head>Notes on Marie D. Gorgas' manuscript by [Henry Rose Carter], [1923]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01123003"/>
<p>Mem.</p>
<p>Page 1: Status of Gorgas in Habana.</p>
<p>When I first met Gorgas in Havana, in January /99, <del>has</del><add>he was</add> reporting to<lb/>
General Brooks, Governor General of the Island, and could scarcely have<lb/>
been Chief Sanitary Officer of the City of Havana, of which General Ludlow<lb/>
was Military Governor. A Dr. Davis--a Contract Surgeon from Illinois--<lb/>
was at this time doing the sanitary work in Havana. I came often in<lb/>
contact, and sometimes in conflict, with him and his gangs on the water-<lb/>
front.</p>
<p>Davis reported to Ludlow and was regarded, by Gorgas and myself, as<lb/>
as his &ldquo;man - Friday.&rdquo; He left the Service in <hi>May</hi>, or <hi>possibly</hi> very <hi>early</hi><lb/>
June and Gorgas succeeded him--reporting then to Ludlow. I then met<lb/>
him (Gorgas) and his gangs (but without conflict) on the water-front.</p>
<p>Gorgas waived his claim to a higher position (both places becoming<lb/>
vacant at about the same time) in favor of Major Kean and took this<lb/>
one. He did this because Kean did not wish to do yellow fever sanitary<lb/>
work and Gorgas did.</p>
<p>Gorgas had been Chief Sanitary Officer of Havana some time Reed came<lb/>
down. The sanitary work then done in the winter and spring of /99--<lb/>
mainly with Electrozone etc.--was by Davis. Gorgas must have begun in<lb/>
May or very early June the same year. I do not know that any sanitary<lb/>
work against yellow fever was done in /98. If so, I judge it was done<lb/>
by Davis.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01123004"/>
<p>-1-</p>
<p>First called &ldquo;Yellow Fever,&rdquo; <del>so far as I can find</del>, in <hi>1750</hi><lb/>
Pag 1 (A) - by Griffitts Hughes in Nat. History of Barbados &amp; of no importance.</p>
<p><hi>Page 1: (1)</hi>: I would not use title before Gorgas' name nor that of<lb/>
any other well known man. He is sufficiently well known not to need it:<lb/>
No one says &ldquo;Monsieur Pasteur&rdquo; or &ldquo;Doctor Jenner.&rdquo; This for the whole<lb/>
paper.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (2)</hi>: 1800 was, I think, the date of leClerc's expedition<lb/>
to Haiti. <unclear>(P</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (3)</hi>: I am afraid this is going a little too far. Save<lb/>
myself<unclear>,</unclear> I think the American origin of yellow fever is accepted by all who<lb/>
hold, or at least by all who have recently expressed, an opinion on this<lb/>
matter, &amp; <hi>I</hi> have not published yet. The last publication I have seen is<lb/>
an article by Spinden, in the World's Work of November 1921, <add>(with whose deductions I cannot agree)</add> <hi>strongly for</hi><lb/>
its pre-Columbian existence in America (Mexico and Yucatan). Frankly, I<lb/>
would hesitate to put this in as positively as you have done.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (4):</hi> The number of deaths in this force is given as 1411,<lb/>
or rather &ldquo;only 89 remained.&rdquo; The second statement, from Keating<del>,</del> as I<lb/>
recall, is probably not true. He gives no reference.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (5)</hi>--No yellow fever in Asia. That reported by Baron Larrey:<lb/>
Pugnet etc. in Syria was quite certainly not yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (6)</hi>--This is <hi>extremely</hi> good. Many cities in which yellow fever<lb/>
prevailed (Rio: Havana etc.) were great and prosperous. Never thus where<lb/>
malaria seriously prevailed. One attack of malaria does <hi>not</hi> produce im-<lb/>
munity to another.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (6')</hi>--Good.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (6'')</hi> Guiteras has shown that quite a number of native<lb/>
children died of yellow fever in Havana--especially in epidemic years.<lb/>
None were so recorded, their deaths being ascribed to other causes, and<lb/>
thus since they <hi>believed</hi> it caused no deaths among natives, the Havanese,<lb/>
as you have stated, were not afraid of it. The number of children thus<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01123005"/>
thus<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
dying, however, was small compared to the number it would have killed a-<lb/>
mong susceptible adults, yellow fever being far milder among children than<lb/>
adults.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (7)</hi>--Omit &ldquo;Spaniards, mostly immigrants,&rdquo; or <del>at least</del> trans-<lb/>
pose to end of sentence.</p>
<p><hi>Page 3: (?<add>C</add>)</hi>--Verify. I think not true. <unclear>Far more</unclear> malaria than y. f in Shafter's <add>army</add> <unclear>ar</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Page 4: (8)</hi>--Mathew &ldquo;Carey&rdquo; is, I think, the name you want, as his<lb/>
is the most lurid account I know.</p>
<p>Page 4 (<unclear>8 1/2</unclear>) The Great Plague of London began 1664 &amp; lasted<lb/>
nearly through 1665.</p>
<p><hi>Page 7: (<unclear><del>?</del>8 1/2</unclear>)</hi>--Pencil insert is correct.</p>
<p><hi>Page 7: (9)</hi>--Not nearly so bad as Philadelphia was described by<lb/>
Carey, but bad enough. (Keating).</p>
<p><hi>Page 8: (10)</hi>--<hi>1901</hi> is right. Statement <add>following is</add> rather too strong.</p>
<p><hi>Page 8: (?<unclear>C)</unclear></hi>--Only natives of 10 years or over were considered &ldquo;certain-<lb/>
ly immune to yellow fever&rdquo;--i. e. <unclear><add>had had the disease.</add> <del>by</del> (U. S. Quarantine Regulations)</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Page 8: (?<unclear>C)</unclear></hi>--Insert &ldquo;much of&rdquo; between &ldquo;of&rdquo; and &ldquo;that.&rdquo;<unclear>?</unclear> as the young<lb/>
children still furnished material.</p>
<p><hi>Page 9: (?<unclear>C)</unclear></hi>--Was this true? Finlay considers it to have been extra-<lb/>
ordinarily healthful in early times and quotes many in support of this<lb/>
opinion. See also Page 3: <unclear>M. S S.</unclear> (top of page)</p>
<p><hi>Page 9: (?'<unclear>C)</unclear></hi>--There were both sewers and piped water when we arrived<lb/>
and had been for many years: Neither, indeed, complete.</p>
<p><del>Jan 2/97</del></p>
<p><hi>Page 9: (?'<unclear>C)</unclear></hi>--The fact of the city being dirty had nothing to do with<lb/>
it being a danger to other places.</p>
<p><hi>Page 9: (?"<unclear>C)</unclear></hi>--Don't think harbor was foul, except about Tallapiedra<lb/>
wharf: Doubt smell of city off shore, or even in harbor, <add><del><unclear>on</unclear></del></add> about which, be-<lb/>
ing Chief Quarantine Officer, I spent a great deal of my time. (Cubans<lb/>
will resent this and will attack this statement. Unless both true and cer-<lb/>
tainly provable it is a question about making it<unclear>!</unclear>) The city <hi>was</hi> extremely<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01123006"/>
extremely<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
dirty, however, especially from human excreta, in streets and on sidewalks,<lb/>
and full of evil smells.</p>
<p>Page 10 (10 <unclear>1/12</unclear> Many cases so recorded were the effect of starvation among<lb/>
the <hi>reconcentrados.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Page 10: (11)</hi>--Either retain pencil insert or replace it by &ldquo;the means<lb/>
to control&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 10: (12)</hi>-- Omit &ldquo;all&rdquo; and insert &ldquo;most.&rdquo; At this time the be-<lb/>
lief that yellow fever was a filth disease, although fairly general, was<lb/>
by no means universal. It was not generally held in New Orleans nor by<lb/>
the majority of the most esteemed writers (Ferguson: Louis: Pym: Chisholm:<lb/>
Faget <add><unclear>Biranger Firande, Connor, Cornilloe</unclear></add> etc.).</p>
<p><hi>Page 11: (?<unclear>C)</unclear></hi>-- &ldquo;recesses&rdquo; vice &ldquo;resources&rdquo;</p>
<p>" 13 12 1/2 &ldquo;Chloride of lime&rdquo; is <unclear>connection <add>of typographical</add></unclear> &ldquo;chlorinated lime&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 13: (13)</hi>--This seems to me too strong, unless it is intended to<lb/>
apply only to the <hi>latter</hi> part of the summer (and the fall) of 1900, which<lb/>
<hi>was</hi> bad.</p>
<p><hi>Page 13: (13')</hi>--There was also considerable yellow fever where the<lb/>
Spanish immigrants went (which was rarely in the better parts of town):<lb/>
and along the water front among crews of foreign vessels. Of course, a<lb/>
case in a prominent American or European would be <hi>more noticed</hi> than a num-<lb/>
ber among these poorer classes. <add>Page 15 (<unclear>11</unclear>)</add> <add>During</add> <del>At</del> this time every house in which a case<lb/>
of yellow fever was found was fumigated with sulphur, which must have<lb/>
somewhat lessened the rapidity of spread, by killing its infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes. It continued to spread however.</p>
<p><hi>Page 15: (14 <unclear>1/2</unclear>)</hi>--Finlay's character was such that he would never have<lb/>
been &ldquo;sardonic&rdquo; in his aspect toward any misfortune to others as grave<lb/>
as this.</p>
<p><hi>Page 16: (15)</hi>--Date of this assertion was 1881 (Aug. 14th.) <add>at</add> Habana,<lb/>
not Washington. In Feb. 1881, at the International Sanitary Conference<lb/>
at Washington, D. C., he read a paper predicating the presence of an &ldquo;a-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01123007"/>
a-<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
gent entirely independent&rdquo; &ldquo;both of the sick man and the disease&rdquo; as a<lb/>
necessity for the propagation of yellow fever. He did not mention the<lb/>
mosquito in this paper, but clearly had a &ldquo;host&rdquo; of some kind in his mind<lb/>
and probably the mosquito. (<unclear>Trabajos selectos del</unclear> Doctor Carlos Finlay - Havana 1912</p>
<p><hi>Page 16: (16)</hi> &ldquo;theory&rdquo; is, I think, better than &ldquo;discovery.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 16: (17)</hi>--Why the erasure?</p>
<p><hi>Page 17: (18)</hi>--I do not recall that Finlay said anything about moist-<lb/>
ure, although he may have done so. Yellow fever has frequently prevailed<lb/>
when the land is dry--e. g. as in the desert coast of Peru (1919-20 &amp;/21<lb/>
and formerly).</p>
<p><hi>Page 17: (19)</hi>--Substitute the word &ldquo;discredit&rdquo; for &ldquo;demolish.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 17: (20)</hi>--Substitute the word &ldquo;proven&rdquo; for the word &ldquo;actual.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 18: (21)-</hi>-Substitute the word &ldquo;discredit&rdquo; for the word &ldquo;disproved.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 18: (22)</hi>--It was rather, I think, a splendid example of medical<lb/>
Vision, and, although not proved, of decided scientific value as suggest-<lb/>
ing the proper line of research. It was a logical deduction from observed<lb/>
data (see Page 17 MSS) &amp; a beautiful example of the use of a scientific imagination</p>
<p><hi>Page 18: (23)</hi>--Ross' first discovery of the malaria organism in a<lb/>
mosquito was Aug. 20, <unclear>1897</unclear>. His report, claiming mosquito conveyance:<lb/>
(British Medical Journal,) Dec. 18, 1897.</p>
<p><hi>Page 18: (24)</hi>--Is it wise to so stress the nationality of the early<lb/>
American observers (Carter: Reed et al) as against the Cuban; Finlay? - <unclear>A man so U-<lb/>
niversally loved &amp; respected, - I would prefer it not done -</unclear> so far as I am concerned</p>
<p><hi>Page 18: (25)</hi>--Finlay was <hi>not</hi> a convincing talker, yet I would feel<lb/>
like omitting (<del>(25)</del>).</p>
<p><hi>Page 19: (26)</hi>--Omit title of Reed and other members of Commission<lb/>
wherever they occur.</p>
<p><hi>Page 19: (27)</hi>--Reed graduated in medicine <add>Degree of</add> (M. D.) at the University<lb/>
of Virginia: was afterwards interne at Bellevue.</p>
<p>Page 20 <del><unclear>27 &amp;</unclear></del> (27 1/2) <unclear>Insert &ldquo;an&rdquo; in place of &ldquo;the&rdquo;</unclear> before American Medical Journal - there is no Journal of that name<lb/>
It was the <unclear>J'l</unclear> of the A. M. A.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (28)</hi>-- Please make this read: &ldquo;<del><unclear>ome</unclear></del><add>one</add> of the most important.&rdquo;<lb/>
Much, (and very important) work had been done on yellow fever before this.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f01123008"/>
<p>this.</p>
<p>-5-</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (29)</hi>--Why the erasure? Reed stated that the data in Carter's<lb/>
paper suggested to him the conveyance by an insect host and the direction of<lb/>
his research. He came down with the advice of his superiors to investigate the<lb/>
intestinal flora of men dead of yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (30)</hi>--&ldquo;when a man developed yellow fever aboard ship that none<lb/>
others became sick, even in the crowded forecastle with him, until a time con-<lb/>
siderably in excess of the period of incubation of the disease in man; leading<lb/>
him to believe that yellow fever could not be contracted from the environment<lb/>
of a sick man for a considerable time after he became sick in it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Please insert the above in place of &ldquo;a considerable time--his own<lb/>
sickness.&rdquo; It better expresses <hi>what was observed</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (31)</hi>--Please insert: &ldquo;finally obtained sufficient data to<lb/>
feel that its publication would be convincing to others&rdquo; in place of: &ldquo;sub-<lb/>
jected this interval to minute mathematical observation,&rdquo; which, however,<lb/>
was done.</p>
<p>He had been working on this matter, as occasion offered, since 1888<lb/>
and convinced of the doctrine, as stated above, since 1893, but could con-<lb/>
vince no one else whose opinion he valued.</p>
<p><hi>Page 21 (31 1/2)</hi>--Insert &ldquo;only&rdquo; between &ldquo;house&rdquo; and &ldquo;within&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 21: (32)</hi>--</p>
<p>Carter thus formulated it: &ldquo;When a man developed yel-<lb/>
low fever in a clean but infectable environment, this environment became <hi>in-<lb/>
fected</hi> at once--within a few hours--but did not become <hi>infective</hi>--i. e. <del>cap-</del><lb/>
capable of producing yellow fever in other men, until a considerable period<lb/>
of time had elapsed.&rdquo; This period of time he called the &ldquo;period of extrinsic<lb/>
incubation of yellow fever&rdquo; and later determined it tentatively as &ldquo;minimally<lb/>
somewhat in excess of ten days.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This is, I think, correct and might be substituted for <hi>part</hi> of the<lb/>
of the MSS between AA and BB, Page 21 (MSS), which does not seem to be en-<lb/>
tirely so--e. g. &ldquo;evidently the yellow fever patient was not a menace to his<lb/>
environment when he first fell ill.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Page 21: (33) The sick man <hi>was</hi> dangerous to his environment (in-<lb/>
fecting it) when he <hi>first</hi> became ill. He was at no time <hi>directly</hi> a danger<lb/>
ger to people. Even his environment was not a danger to them until &ldquo;somewhat<lb/>
over 10 days&rdquo; after the beginning of his sickness in it. The danger to well<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01123009"/>
well<lb/>
-6-<lb/>
people in the infected environment was, as you say, independent of the sick<lb/>
man's continued presence. This last, of course, had been known for years,<lb/>
but not that the environment was not dangerous from the beginning of his<lb/>
sickness in it. The essence of Carter's discovery was the existence of the<lb/>
period of extrinsic incubation (during which the environment although <hi>infected</hi><lb/>
was not <hi>infective</hi>).</p>
<p><hi>Page 21: (33')</hi>--Is this sentence correct? &ldquo;The sick man <hi>was</hi> dangerous&rdquo; etc.<lb/>
(See Page 5 (Notes) Page 21: (33)--MSS)</p>
<p><hi>Page 21: (34)</hi>--&ldquo;dates,&rdquo; not &ldquo;figures,&rdquo; was the word Reed used.</p>
<p><hi>Page 22: (35)</hi>--Considering the data in Carter's paper with the then<lb/>
recent work of Ronald Ross on the transmission of malaria their meaning was<lb/>
at once clear to Reed.</p>
<p>Ross had shown that an Anopheles mosquito feeding on men sick of mal-<lb/>
aria took the organisms of malaria into her stomach and that these organ-<lb/>
isms underwent a special developement in her body. After this developement<lb/>
is complete, and <hi>not until then,</hi> the developed organism can be conveyed to<lb/>
a well man by the mosquito biting him.</p>
<p>Ross had also shown, and <hi>emphasized</hi>, that this developement <hi>required<lb/>
time.</hi> In fact it usually takes (in hot weather) about 11 days from the in-<lb/>
fecting feeding for the full developement of the malaria organism in the<lb/>
mosquito and for her to <hi>become infective.</hi> Until this developement of the<lb/>
organism is complete she cannot convey malaria.</p>
<p>Reed then had made the deduction that the explanation of Carter's<lb/>
findings was that the mechanism of the transmission of yellow fever from<lb/>
man to man was similar to that of malaria: Ross' <hi>mosquitoes</hi> were <hi>in-<lb/>
fected</hi> as soon as they had bitten a man sick of malari, but not <hi>infective</hi><lb/>
to other men until after the full developement of the malarial organism in<lb/>
their bodies had taken place, which required considerable time: Carter's<lb/>
<hi>&ldquo;environment&rdquo;</hi> became <hi>infected</hi> &ldquo;at once, within a few hours,&rdquo; when a case<lb/>
of yellow fever developed in it, but not &ldquo;<hi>infective</hi>&rdquo; to other men until a<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01123010"/>
a<lb/>
-7-<lb/>
considerable time had elapsed--the &ldquo;period of extrinsic incubation of<lb/>
yellow fever.&rdquo; <del>Was</del><add>Could</add> the infection of the &ldquo;environment to <add>be</add> due to infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes&rdquo; in it! <unclear>(</unclear>The parallelism between <unclear>these, <hi>phenomena</hi> seemed <del>very</del></unclear> close.</p>
<p>Reed's <add>immediate</add> deduction then was that the organism of yellow fever was<lb/>
taken into the body of some suctorial insect., <del>probably</del> by its feeding on<lb/>
a man sick of that disease, and underwent a special developement in the<lb/>
body of that insect <hi>after</hi> which (and only after which) it could be con-<lb/>
veyed to a well man (by the insect feeding on him) producing the dis-<lb/>
ease in him and that this developement required <hi>time</hi>--represented by<lb/>
Carter's period of extrinsic incubation. <add>(corresponding to the 11 days for malaria)</add> That the time elapsing between<lb/>
the developement of the disease in Carter's houses by the men who in-<lb/>
fected them and the dates the houses acquired the power of transmitting<lb/>
the disease (&ldquo;period of extrinsic incubation of yellow fever&rdquo;) represented<lb/>
the time necessary for the developement of the organism to take place in<lb/>
the body of the insect which, until this was completed, was not infective<lb/>
to man. During this time the houses might harbor any number of <hi>infected</hi><lb/>
insects, not yet <hi>infective</hi><unclear><del>,</del></unclear> and hence <hi>as yet</hi> incapable of transmitting yel-<lb/>
low fever, but which in time, at the end of the period of extrinsic in-<lb/>
cubation, would become <hi>infective</hi> to man and dangerous.</p>
<p><hi>Page 22: (36)--</hi> Is this correct? The organism, once ingested, re-<lb/>
mains in the infected insect's body indefinitely: we believe all her life--<lb/>
certainly for 57 days in one instance.</p>
<p><hi>Page 22: (37)</hi>-- Is this true? Reed told me that he was, indeed, ad-<lb/>
vised by Sternberg &ldquo;to investigate the intestinal flora, especially that<lb/>
of the upper part of the canal,&rdquo; which he <add>later said he</add> was glad that he had not attempt-<lb/>
ed. It had been well, over one year's job--possibly several. I think,<lb/>
that the only thing he had investigated prior to our conversation at<lb/>
Quemados (July 4th.) was the role of the Sanarelli organism. &amp; soon after <add><unclear>exactly</unclear></add> when I dont<lb/>
recall, he began his mosquito experiments</p>
<p><hi>Page 22: (37')</hi>--I had carried larvae of Stegomyia from Finlay to<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01123011"/>
to<lb/>
-8-<lb/>
Lazear, whom I knew well and liked, before Reed's arrival.</p>
<p><hi>Page 22: (38)</hi>--five days is less than the period of extrinsic in-<lb/>
cubation of yellow fever and these insects were not yet <hi>infective</hi> to<lb/>
other men: <add>might have become so if kept longer</add> Like Noble, I also fail to understand the little piece he puts<lb/>
in (    ).</p>
<p><hi>Page 23: (39)</hi>-- In the official account (Reed and, I think, Carroll also)<lb/>
Lazear is quoted as saying<del>: "</del> it &ldquo;was some species of Culex.&rdquo; At that time<lb/>
Stegomyia had not been differentiated from the genus Culex.</p>
<p><hi>Page 23: (40)</hi>--&ldquo;usual&rdquo; <hi>vice</hi> &ldquo;unusual.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 23: (41)--</hi>Is this criticism on the previous experiments of the<lb/>
Commission just? I do not know, being then <add>absent</add> with a yellow fever epidemic<lb/>
in (1st) Key West and (2nd.) New Orleans.</p>
<p><hi>Page 24: (42)</hi>-- Why &ldquo;microscopic process?&rdquo; How about using &ldquo;the<lb/>
mechanism of conveyance of yellow fever&rdquo;? <del>from man to man," or leaving out<lb/>
the last three words?</del></p>
<p><hi>Page 24: (43)</hi>-- At that time few, if any, <add>save Seidelin &amp; Connal</add> believed that animals were<lb/>
susceptible to yellow fever. At present Noguchi (Rockefeller Institute):<lb/>
Russell and, I judge, the bulk of well informed scientists believe that<lb/>
several species of animals can be <add>thus</add> infected--among them guinea pigs. The<lb/>
use of men, however, was <add>then</add> necessary because the production of yellow fever<lb/>
in animals would have been little credited.</p>
<p><hi>Page 24: (X)</hi>--What really was proved was that a mosquito fed on a sick<lb/>
man during the first three days (2nd. and 3rd. day to be exact) frequently<del>y</del><lb/>
(<del>or even</del><add>indeed</add> generally) became <hi>infective</hi> (when kept long enough), but that of<lb/>
those fed on the sick man <hi>only after three</hi> days <del>he found</del><add>had passed</add> none <add>were found</add> to convey<lb/>
yellow fever to others. It is a question, however, if there were enough<lb/>
of these observations then to say that this <hi>negative</hi> proposition was proven.</p>
<p>This is simply for your own information. I do not know that I would<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f01123012"/>
would<lb/>
-9-<lb/>
change the MSS. There is more evidence for this now than there was<lb/>
then, although I would not like to say that the end of the 3rd. day of<lb/>
illness is <hi>certainly</hi> the limit of infectivity of a man with yellow fever<lb/>
to the mosquito.</p>
<p><hi>Page 25: (X)</hi>--Good.</p>
<p><hi>Page 26: (44)</hi>--Stegomyia, as Noble says, is essentially a house mos-<lb/>
quito and she does not &ldquo;swarm.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 27: (45)</hi>-- Did you mean &ldquo;well man&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;invalid<del>?</del>&rdquo; referring to<lb/>
infective<lb/>
<unclear>mosquitos</unclear></p>
<p><hi>From Page 27: (XX) to Page 28: (YY)</hi>-- All of this is true, but no<lb/>
one appreciated the difficulty of eliminating yellow fever by isolation<lb/>
of men sick of it from mosquitoes and killing those in the house which<lb/>
may have fed on them (control of the human host) until we tried it in<lb/>
Panama and found it to fail. Both methods of attack (control of the<lb/>
human host and <add>that</add> of the insect host as well) were, as you state, used in<lb/>
Havana, but the main stress was laid on the control of the human host<lb/>
(isolation etc. of sick man) and the destruction of Stegomyia breeding<lb/>
places, although well done, was regarded rather as an adjuvant to the<lb/>
main attack. I am afraid that you have rather given the reverse impres-<lb/>
sion. We did not (any of us) recognize the comparative efficacy of<lb/>
these contrasting methods until after eighteen months experience in<lb/>
Panama.</p>
<p><hi>Page 27: (Y)--</hi> Your meaning is to <hi>me</hi> clear and what you mean is cor-<lb/>
rect--i. e. that there are many cases of yellow fever not easily diag-<lb/>
nosticated--especially in <add>young children babies &amp;</add> negroes <unclear>In</unclear> <del>young</del> negro babies -- diagnosis<lb/>
would in general be. to me, impossible except from the conditions un-<lb/>
der which the disease occurred. I think however, that the <unclear>characterization</unclear><lb/>
<del>tic</del> of yellow fever as &ldquo;preeminently a disease of the <hi>walking</hi> variety&rdquo;<lb/>
would be very generally rejected by Southern practitioners familiar with<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f01123013"/>
with<lb/>
-10-<lb/>
it. There <hi>are</hi> walking cases--that generally die--but most cases (prac-<lb/>
tically all those recognized) among adult whites and in whites near<lb/>
puberty, go down like a shot from the first. I know of no other dis-<lb/>
ease <add>generally</add> as sudden <add>and severe</add> in onset, save dengue.</p>
<p><unclear>c</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Page 29: (?)</hi>-- Was it Miss &ldquo;Mass&rdquo; or &ldquo;Maas?&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 30: (46)</hi>-- It is, indeed, a very pretty insect, but lacks the<lb/>
brilliant coloring (red: blue: purple etc) of <hi>Megarrhinus.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Page 32: (47)</hi>-- This paragraph is rather more than the truth, but is<lb/>
near enough and is so graphic and well told that I think it should stand.</p>
<p><hi>Pages 33 and 34: (48)</hi>-- Best ask LePrince as to the detail methods<lb/>
employed to destroy larvae in Havana.</p>
<p>In Panama, undertaken just afterwards, he <hi>mainly</hi> depended on empty-<lb/>
ing the water containing larvae out into the street (except from cisterns).</p>
<p>Oiling is less efficient against Stegomyia than any mosquito <add>I know</add> except<lb/>
Mansonia.</p>
<p><hi>Page 33: (48')</hi> --&ldquo;Breathing tube&rdquo; is correct. It is in the <hi>tail</hi><lb/>
of the larva--has no &ldquo;nose&rdquo; on head end.</p>
<p><hi>Page 35: (49)</hi>--Extremely good and true.</p>
<p><hi>Page 36: (50)</hi>--&ldquo;Who treated her with consideration,&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;with-<lb/>
out being cuffed,&rdquo; A <hi>blow</hi>, save with a knife, and intended to kill, is<lb/>
given with extreme rarity in Latin America--even by an official to a<lb/>
negro.</p>
<p><hi>Page 37: (b)</hi>--All, or practically all, of the Spanish immigrants on<lb/>
arrival joined a &ldquo;Centro&rdquo;--Catalan: Asturian etc., according to the<lb/>
Province from whence they came. These were Hospital Associations, giv-<lb/>
ing them the right to free medical treatment (in hospital if necessary)<lb/>
of which they were extremely prompt to avail themselves. They were<lb/>
handled easily, as they wanted to enter hospital if yellow fever were<lb/>
suspected.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f01123014"/>
<p>suspected.</p>
<p>-11-</p>
<p><hi>Page 37: (c)</hi>--This may well have been, and probably was, the popular<lb/>
opinion, and we, of course, knew less of <del>her</del><add>its</add> biology than we do now,<lb/>
but Finlay's selection of this mosquito as the vector of yellow fever<lb/>
was primarily on account of <del>her</del><unclear><add>its</add></unclear> being a &ldquo;house mosquito.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 38: (d)</hi>-- Noble's statement in pencil here is correct. This<lb/>
epidemic was eliminated by sanitary measures similar to those in 1900.</p>
<p><hi>Page 40: (e)</hi>-- The entomological name of the yellow fever carrying<lb/>
mosquito (U. S. Bureau of Entomology) is <hi><unclear>A&euml;des</unclear></hi> (<hi>Stegomyia</hi>) <hi>aegypti</hi>, but<lb/>
as this is the only member of this sub-genus found in the Americas it is<lb/>
usually called simply &ldquo;<hi>Stegomyia</hi>&rdquo; by American writers. <del>I, however, have<lb/>
called it &ldquo;<hi>aegypti.</hi>.&rdquo;</del> in</p>
<pb n="13" id="f01123015"/>
<p>Reed's findings were accepted promptly by scientific men, and<lb/>
not only the findings themselves, but their practical application as<lb/>
well. The requirements of the Maritime Quarantine of the U. S. were modi-<lb/>
fied that spring (1900) to conform thereto: Of those of the State Quaran-<lb/>
tines some changed at once, and all within a short time, to the same end.<lb/>
Ribas and de Sousa of Sao Paolo, Brazil, began work against yellow fever<lb/>
in Santos, based solely on Stegomyia conveyance, also in 1900, using<lb/>
practically the same methods Gorgas used in Habana. Liceaga soon after-<lb/>
wards began work in Vera Cruz, by the same methods and for the same pur-<lb/>
pose, as did Oswaldo Cruz in Rio <unclear>de Janeiro</unclear>.</p>
<p>Such prompt, one one may immediate, acceptance of a medical<lb/>
discovery had not been usual, but Reed's experiments had been complete<lb/>
and convincing and the clinching of the matter by the elimination of yel-<lb/>
low fever from Habana left no room for cavil.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
