<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01124050">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Samuel Taylor Darling to Frederick F. Russell, December 11, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Darling, Samuel Taylor</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01124050</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-12-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Russell, Frederick F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">Columbia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-12-11">December 11, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01124050</idno>
<title>Letter from Samuel Taylor Darling to Frederick F. Russell, December 11, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Darling concludes after examining tissues that one man died of yellow fever and the other did not.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-12-11">
<head>Letter from Samuel Taylor Darling to Frederick F. Russell, December 11, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01124050"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
<dateline>
Leesburg, Ga.<lb/>
<date value="1923-12-11">Dec. 11-1923</date>
</dateline>
Dr. F. F. Russell, General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York City.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have examined the sections of tissue of the cases<lb/>
of Jose Antonio Viviesca, 28 years of age, a citizen of Piedacuesta,<lb/>
Colombia, and David Manrique, 52 years of age, citizen of Onzaga,<lb/>
Colombia, referred to in Dr. Miller's letter from Bucaramanga, Colombia,<lb/>
September 11th, 1923, and Miss Read's letters of October 31st and<lb/>
November 14th.</p>
<p>The slides in question had been very kindly sent me by<lb/>
Dr. Noguchi. As a result of the examination of these sections I am of<lb/>
the opinion that Jose Antonio Viviesca died of yellow fever, but that<lb/>
David Manrique did not. A brief description of the sections follows:</p>
<p>Case of Jose Antonio Viviesca,</p>
<p>-</p>
<p>Liver</p>
<p>-</p>
<p>The section is rather pale and the architecture of the lobule<lb/>
is ill defined, this is due to fatty metamorphosis and swelling of the<lb/>
hepatic cells. There is a diffuse cellular necrosis of the hepatic cells<lb/>
which contain much fat in the form of very small droplets. The nuclei<lb/>
in places do not stain at all. In others they are somewhat swollen and<lb/>
pale. There appears to be a slight proliferation of stroma cells and<lb/>
there is a conspicuous collection of round cells in the portal spaces.<lb/>
Scattered over the field are polynuclear leucocytes some of which are<lb/>
fragmented giving the appearance of very minute cellular necroses. The<lb/>
necrosis is diffuse and not particularly zonal in arrangement. Beneath<lb/>
the capsule there is some hemorrhage and atrophy of the parenchyma due<lb/>
to collapse of the lobules, possibly as a result of external compression.<lb/>
The hepatic necrosis is extremely severe and while the lesions in my<lb/>
experience are somewhat atypical they are undoubtedly due to the virus<lb/>
of yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01124051"/>
<p>Dr. Russell</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Case of David Manrique,</p>
<p>Liver</p>
<p>The sections stain well with hematoxylin excepting for the<lb/>
central zone, and the architecture of the lobule is well defined.<lb/>
There is no hyaline necrosis of the hepatic cells. In the center of<lb/>
the lobule there is a considerable amount of fat enclosed within the<lb/>
hepatic cell but apparently not associated with hyaline necrosis. The<lb/>
fat droplets are of small, medium and some of large size, surrounded<lb/>
by a rather normal staining cytoplasm. There is some bile pigment-<lb/>
ation of the hepatic cells, some granular pigment in the endothelial<lb/>
cells and in the veins. There is also some extraneous pigment appar-<lb/>
ently due to the fixing agent.</p>
<p>Kidney</p>
<p>-</p>
<p>There is a good deal of cloudiness of the renal epithelium<lb/>
which may be due to post-mortem changes. Some of the tubular epithelial<lb/>
cells when stained with scarlet R. contain rather deeply staining globules,<lb/>
some of which may be fat. There is no indication, from the sections, that<lb/>
yellow fever is the cause of death in this case.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very truly,</salute>
<signed>(signed) Samuel T. Darling</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
