<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01124025">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">English translation [from French] of a report extract: Report on the yellow fever epidemic in Grand Bassam, by [s.n.] Bauvallet, October 25, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01124025</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-10-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="place">Bassam (Ivory Coast)</name>
<name type="place">French West Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-10-25">October 25, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01124025</idno>
<title>English translation [from French] of a report extract: Report on the yellow fever epidemic in Grand Bassam, by [s.n.] Bauvallet, October 25, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Bauvallet reports on the use of Noguchi serum and vaccine to treat yellow fever cases in Bassam, Ivory Coast. </p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-10-25">
<head>English translation [from French] of a report extract: Report on the yellow fever epidemic in Grand Bassam, by [s.n.] Bauvallet, October 25, 1922 (See <xref id="f01124022">French original</xref>.)</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01124025"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>Extract from a report by Dr. Bauvallet on the use of the Noguchi<lb/>
serum and vaccine during the yellow fever epidemic in Bassam<lb/>
(Ivory Coast) in French West Africa in 1922. (1)</p>
<p>Grand Bassam<lb/>
<date value="1922-10-25">October 25, 1922.</date></p>
<p>Report on the yellow fever epidemic in Grand Bassam,<lb/>
<hi>August 18 - September 8, 1922.</hi></p>
<p>The physician stationed in Bassam, which is a city<lb/>
particularly exposed to epidemics, had already entered into<lb/>
personal correspondence with Mr. Hideyo Noguchi of the Rocke-<lb/>
feller Institute in 1921, and had received from him early in<lb/>
1922 a certain amount of anti-yellow-fever serum and vaccine<lb/>
preserved in ice.</p>
<p>At the very beginning of the epidemic a circular<lb/>
letter was published informing the inhabitants that anyone who<lb/>
wished it would be vaccinated in accord with the results<lb/>
published by the eminent Japanese biologist.</p>
<p>From August 18 to 24, 140 Europeans out of a population<lb/>
of about 200 were vaccinated with dead cultures of Leptospira<lb/>
incteroides from lot 15, prepared on December 9, 1921. One<lb/>
hundred and thirty-one received two injections of 2 cc. at an<lb/>
interval of 6 days, according to the author's technique; 9 did<lb/>
not appear for the second injection.</p>
<p>Practically all of the persons vaccinated presented<lb/>
the following reaction on the evening of the day on which they<lb/>
had received the injection between 8 and 10 A.M.; light fever<lb/>
with pain in the small of the back, more or less marked rachialgia,<lb/>
typical picture of the &ldquo;coup de barre&rdquo;, consisting of very severe<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(1) This serum and vaccine had been sent directly to Dr. Bauvallet by<lb/>
the Rockefeller Institute, to which he had sent anatomical specimens.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01124026"/>
4.<lb/>
pain in the lumbar region. The intensity of the rachialgia was<lb/>
what kept 8 of the 9 that had the first injection from returning for<lb/>
the second. The ninth of these persons is mentioned in a special<lb/>
report at the end of this one.</p>
<p>Four of the persons vaccinated presented sterile <unclear>abcesses</unclear>,<lb/>
indicated by Noguchi as being due to the presence of agar-agar in<lb/>
the culture medium, after 15-20 days and appearing at the point of<lb/>
innoculation in spite of systematic massage immediately after the<lb/>
penetration of the skin by the vaccine. These <unclear>abcesses</unclear> were cured<lb/>
by simple cupping and left no scars.</p>
<p>At the same time serotherapy with Noguchi's serum, kept at<lb/>
a temperature of minus 4 degrees Centigrade, was applied to all the<lb/>
patients, in addition to the classical and purely symptomatic treatment.</p>
<p>The results of this serotherapy were as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>Case No.1, - The diagnosis of yellow fever was not absolute<lb/>
until the appearance of the black vomit. The patient received im-<lb/>
mediately, at 4:30 P.M., an intravenous injection of 60 cc. of serum.<lb/>
Death occurred at 5.43 P.M. This injection was given in extremis,<lb/>
after the third day, when it is said by Noguchi to be no longer of<lb/>
any value.</item>
<item>Case. 2. - The disease made its appearance in the evening<lb/>
of August 18, with a very high fever. The patient said that he<lb/>
had had a temperature of 39.9 degrees C. at the time. The case<lb/>
was not reported until the next morning, when the patient was<lb/>
isolated in the Ambulance hospital. Pain in the back, &ldquo;coup de<lb/>
barre&rdquo;, congestion of the face, epigrastralgia, scant urine with<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01124027"/>
5.<lb/>
no albumen. Temperature of 39.4. Received 60 cc. of serum at<lb/>
8.30 A.M. Decrease in temperature and diuresis in the afternoon;<lb/>
cure.</item>
<item>Case 3. - High fever during the night of the 17-18.<lb/>
Seen by the physician on the 18th at 9 A.M. Temperature of 39.2,<lb/>
extreme pain in the lumbar region, cramps in the legs, bilious<lb/>
vomit and internal epigastralgia, albuminaria. Received 60 cc.<lb/>
of serum intravenously. The temperature fell to 38.6 in the<lb/>
afternoon. Decrease in the vomiting, appearance of a subicteric<lb/>
condition that persisted until August 24. Disappearance of the<lb/>
albuminuria; defervescence; cure.</item>
<item>Case 4. - Patient fell ill on August 15, but her husband did<lb/>
not call a physician, as he thought that it was merely a fever due<lb/>
to acclimatization. Isolated only in the evening of the 17th,<lb/>
actually later than case 1, although the symptoms suggested a<lb/>
malarial attack. On the 19th the diagnosis became evident; slight<lb/>
uterine hemorrhages, epigastralgia, bilious vomit, congestion of<lb/>
the face, prostration, subicterus, scant urine with albumen. Was<lb/>
given an intravenous injection of 60 cc. of serum. On the 20th<lb/>
the icterus was general and the prostration still more marked;<lb/>
there were subcutaneous sanguineous effusions and the anuria was<lb/>
total. A second intravenous injection of 60 cc. of serum was<lb/>
administered; a few drops of very albuminous urine were expelled<lb/>
after the injection. Death at 7:10 P.M. The serotherapeutic<lb/>
treatment was late and useless.</item>
<item>Case 5. - The patient took to bed on the 21st about<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01124028"/>
6.<lb/>
10 A.M. Was seen at once and sent to the Ambulance hospital<lb/>
to be isolated. No pain in the lumbar region, but epigastralgia,<lb/>
bilious vomit. congestion of the face. The temperature remained<lb/>
at from 39.2 to 39.6 during the whole day of the 21st. The<lb/>
patient passed a restless night, with a temperature of 39.8 at<lb/>
7 A.M. on the 22nd. Received 60 cc. of serum less than 4 hours<lb/>
after the beginning of the disease. The vomiting continued and<lb/>
was tinged with blood. Death at 1:45 P.M. The treatment was not<lb/>
totally unsuccessful; autopsy was not performed on account of lack<lb/>
of time.</item>
</list></p>
<p>One case must receive special mention, that of the ninth<lb/>
person who had only one injection.</p>
<p>Mr. B..., living at the Atlantic Hotel, and a neighbor<lb/>
of Mr. X... and Mr. Y... received 2 cc. of vaccine on August 22, but did not appear for the second injection on the 23rd. The<lb/>
proprietor of the Atlantic Hotel, on being asked over the telephone<lb/>
as to why Mr. B... remained absent, replied guardedly that Mr. B...<lb/>
was not well. The patient was seen at 10:30 A.M. He had had no reaction<lb/>
after the first injection, but on the night of the 27-28 he had a fever<lb/>
and a back-ache. He did not take his temperature at the time. When<lb/>
seen his temperature was 39.2, &ldquo;coup de barre&rdquo;, cramps in the legs,<lb/>
congestion of the face that was in marked contrast to his usual pallor,<lb/>
gums edged with white, a symptom that appeared only in this case,<lb/>
vomiting, albuminaria. Was isolated in the Ambulance hospital, and<lb/>
received an intravenous injection of 60 cc. of serum at 1 P.M. The<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01124029"/>
7.<lb/>
patient immediately presented an intense seric reaction, pruritus,<lb/>
generalized erythrosis, very grave syncope. An intravenous injection<lb/>
of 1 mg. of adrenaline caused the disappearance of the analhylactic<lb/>
phenomena. The fever and the disturbing symptoms disappeared during<lb/>
the night.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
