<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01124011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, October 31, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01124011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-10-31</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">Segou (Mali)</name>
<name type="place">Dakar (Senegal)</name>
<name type="place">French West Africa</name>
<name type="place">Sudan</name>
<name type="place">Accra (Gold Coast)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-10-31">October 31, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01124011</idno>
<title>English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, October 31, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Seguin reports on possible yellow fever deaths and public health response in French West Africa.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-10-31">
<head>English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, October 31, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01124011"/>
<opener>
Seguin <del>1 &amp; 3</del> 2<lb/>
<hi>Copy</hi><lb/>
<hi>FRENCH SUDAN</hi>.<lb/>
<hi>HEALTH SERVICE</hi>.<lb/>
<dateline>
Bamako,<lb/>
<date value="1922-10-31">October 31, 1922</date>
</dateline>
No. 337<lb/>
</opener>
<p>S&eacute;guin, chief physician, 2nd class, Head of the Health Service of the<lb/>
French Sudan, to the Medical Inspector and Director of the Health Service of<lb/>
French West Africa. Dakar.</p>
<p>******************</p>
<p>I have the honor to confirm my telegram No. 121 of October 28, announcing<lb/>
the death of the postal employee Mr. N., who had taken to his bed on the 23rd, the<lb/>
morning of the day on which I left S&eacute;gou, with a high fever. This fever had come<lb/>
on slowly with light back-ache, headache without facial congestion, a very slightly<lb/>
coated tongue, little or no lumbar pain, nothing that resembled the classic &ldquo;coup<lb/>
de barre&rdquo; in the small of the back.</p>
<p>Summing up, Mr. N. presented nothing but the symptoms of a very ordinary<lb/>
feverish gastric disturbance, with nothing that would have made it possible to make<lb/>
a diagnosis of yellow fever, no matter how much one might have been justly preju-<lb/>
diced in favor of this latter hypothesis.</p>
<p>Mr. N. thought that he had got a light sunstroke from working in front of<lb/>
a door in the full sunshine, which was not at all improbable. I made an examination<lb/>
of his blood, and the results were negative as far as the hematozoa of malaria and<lb/>
the spirochetes of recurrent fever were concerned.</p>
<p>In the evening, half an hour before my leaving S&eacute;gou, I went back to see<lb/>
Mr. N., whose condition had remained absolutely unchanged. I left him in the care<lb/>
of Dr. Fortin, advising him to repeat the blood examinations and to watch the patient<lb/>
very carefully for signs of yellow fever.</p>
<p>On passing through Koulikoro on October 25, we were informed by the<lb/>
Governor of the content of the following telegram, which was waiting for him there,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01124012"/>
-2-<lb/>
&ldquo;Dr. Fortin announces state of postal employee N. is stationary; temperature morning<lb/>
39.4, evening 39.6; complexion slightly more congested than at first; tongue very<lb/>
much coated; no icterus; normal urine; no vomit.&rdquo; The diagnosis of yellow fever was<lb/>
becoming more probable.</p>
<p>On the 27th Dr. Fortin telegraphed, &ldquo;Condition of postal employee N.<lb/>
isolated in Maternity must be considered very serious. Slight black hemorrhagic<lb/>
vomit appeared this morning, as well as stools of the same hemorrhagic type. Urine<lb/>
albuminous, but normal in quantity. Prognosis very reserved.&rdquo;</p>
<p>From then on the diagnosis of yellow fever could be made with complete cer-<lb/>
tainty and the sanitary measures already arranged for in S&eacute;gou could be carried out.</p>
<p>In fact, the Governor immediately issued the decree which was transmitted<lb/>
to Dakar by telegraph, which has certainly come to your knowledge by this time, and<lb/>
to which some modification were made in accordance with instructions from Dakar.</p>
<p>I have already sent you my report No. 329, which will inform you as to the<lb/>
beginning of the little epidemic of yellow fever in S&eacute;gou. I am firmly convinced<lb/>
that it will quickly be extinguished on the spot.</p>
<p>The question now is to seek the origin of this little local epidemic, aris-<lb/>
ing in the midst of the Sudan, and far from the limits of our jurisdiction beyond<lb/>
which yellow fever might flourish. A case of yellow fever was undoubtedly reported<lb/>
at Accra on the Gold Coast last July, but there is no connection between S&eacute;gou or<lb/>
the Sudan with the Gold Coast, and this origin seems very unlikely.</p>
<p>I have been told that the natives of S&eacute;gou are in the habit of going into<lb/>
the forests of the Ivory Coast of Liberia and the Gold Coast to gather kola nuts.<lb/>
Could they have brought back more or less attenuated germs of yellow fever from<lb/>
there? This is however no more than a supposition, as I am completely ignorant of<lb/>
the health conditions of the native populations of those regions.</p>
<p>For my own part, I think it is much simpler to admit that yellow fever is<lb/>
definitely a disease endemic in the Sudan, that the yellow fever germ develops in a<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01124013"/>
-3-<lb/>
latent fashion in the negro, remaining moderately virulent for a longer or shorter<lb/>
time, and becoming suddenly active at considerable intervals when the successive<lb/>
transferences from one person to another bring it to new organisms, especially<lb/>
whites, who have no natural or acquired immunity. It may therefore be true that the<lb/>
mild cases of icterus that are sometimes found in negroes aside from all infection<lb/>
with the Obermayer spirochete or the Laveran hematozoon are very mild manifestations<lb/>
of yellow fever, and I believe that from now on such cases of icterus, that have no<lb/>
evident source of origin, should be considered as <hi>very probably</hi> yellow fever, and be<lb/>
isolated.</p>
<p>As far as S&eacute;gou is concerned, the measures required by the sanitary regu-<lb/>
lations have already been taken, as I said before. Dr. Alexandre has been kept in<lb/>
S&eacute;gou to assist Dr. Fortin, less to care for the patients than to assist in controlling<lb/>
the measures that must be directed and inspected by a physician in order to produce<lb/>
the required results.</p>
<p>At the last moment I have received a telegram from the Governor informing<lb/>
me of the death of Mr. O. of the Niger Mission.</p>
<p>Mr. O. was isolated from the 20th on the day of our arrival in S&eacute;gou, in<lb/>
a tent at Banankora, 10 kilometers down the river from S&eacute;gou. According to the tele-<lb/>
grams, he was transported sick to the Maternity Hospital at S&eacute;gou on the 28th, and died<lb/>
on the 31st. This case clearly proves that a period of observation of 6 days is<lb/>
<hi>absolutely insufficient</hi> for discovering the disease. For I do not assume that Mr. O.<lb/>
was infected at Banankora, but that he went there already in a state of incubation<lb/>
on the 20th, having been infected by a mosquito in the house of the C.F.A.O., where<lb/>
he lived with Mr. A. and Mr. B., who both died of yellow fever. This fact speaks de-<lb/>
finitely enough in favor of a period of incubation longer than the one generally<lb/>
accepted, and I propose that the period of observation be extended to 10 days, as had<lb/>
first been agreed upon with the Governor of the Sudan. I think that in such a serious<lb/>
matter, and considering the difficulty of watching the suspects from hour to hour,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01124014"/>
-4-<lb/>
a wider margin should be allowed for the period of observation, and that the regu-<lb/>
lation that reduced it to 6 days was perhaps imprudent.</p>
<p>I am giving you my honest opinion, according to the facts of the case,<lb/>
so that you can present them to the Governor-General, to whom the Governor of the<lb/>
Sudan has already telegraphed the same suggestion, and so that you can make the<lb/>
necessary decision.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
