<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01122001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: The Effect of Variation of Level of Impounded Water on the Control of Anopheles Production, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01122001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">North Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Parr Shoals (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Coosa River (Alabama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<idno rend="suppress">01122001</idno>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<title>Report: The Effect of Variation of Level of Impounded Water on the Control of Anopheles Production, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter describes the effect of impounded water level variation on the control of Anopheles breeding, reviewing work done by himself and others in North Carolina, South Carolina, and Alabama.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report: The Effect of Variation of Level of Impounded Water on the Control of Anopheles Production, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01122001"/>
<opener>
John Hopkins Hospital<lb/>
<unclear>Joven</unclear> 11/23<lb/>
</opener>
<p>The Effect of Variation of Level of Impounded Water on the Control<lb/>
of Anopheles Production.<lb/>
H. R. Carter.</p>
<p>The problem of the effect of impounded water upon the incidence of<lb/>
malaria was formulated in the fall of 1913, about ten years ago, and the<lb/>
first work in its investigation was undertaken the next year at Blewetts<lb/>
Falls, N. C. on the Pee Dee river.</p>
<p>The original plan for this investigation, which was purposed to in-<lb/>
clude a determination of the methods for the control of this incidence<lb/>
<del>space</del><lb/>
to, an extent at least, of the evaluation of the effect of the methods re-<lb/>
commended for this purpose, was expected to require not less than five<lb/>
years' <add>or rather seasons'</add> investigations, We thought that the evaluation of the methods for<lb/>
control of malaria above alluded to <hi>might</hi> well require three or four years<lb/>
longer time.</p>
<p>The problem was a large as well as an important one as on it, to<lb/>
some extent, depended whether the water power in the malarial sections of<lb/>
the U. S. could be developed economically or whether the damage which its<lb/>
developement would cause to health would be so great <del>and so unavoidable</del><lb/>
that this developement would not be economically possible or <add>at least</add> greatly lessen<lb/>
its value</p>
<p>It was purposed that the research on the ponds as normally made and<lb/>
that of the methods to control the production of Anopheles thereby should<lb/>
go hand in hand as soon as we had enough knowledge of the first to warrant<lb/>
institution of the second.</p>
<p>Only three seasons (1914-15-16) were available for this research<lb/>
before the War stopped us: some little data was collected incidentally on<lb/>
this subject during the War--very little. Griffitts and myself, however,<lb/>
made one survey in 1919 and I <add>sometimes</add> by myself <del>or</del><add>sometimes</add> with others <del>(Fisher and Bold-<lb/>
ridge)</del> have done some surveying within the last three years. Dr. Fricks<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01122002"/>
Fricks<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
this year has also formally taken up this problem again &amp; I presume will fin-<lb/>
ish it,</p>
<p>It was determined during the surveys of 1914-15 that, except where<lb/>
floating-islands:; log rafts etc. existed. Anopheles production in these large<lb/>
ponds occurred only about their edges and, indeed, far the greater propor-<lb/>
tion occurred on their edges, even in those like Parr Shoals and Stevens<lb/>
Creek where rafts and floating islands were abundant.</p>
<p>Naturally means of control of production in the ponds were practi-<lb/>
cally two:--wave action, which drowned the larvae and fish which ate<lb/>
them. Of course there were cases where predatory insects assisted the<lb/>
fish, but as compared with them these insects were of very minor sanitary<lb/>
importance.</p>
<p>All large ponds that we came across, by the third year at any rate,<lb/>
were fairly well stocked with top minnows. In many <add><unclear>derived of you</unclear> those which</add> <del>those had</del> existed in<lb/>
pools covered by the pond, in others they had been artificially introduced.<lb/>
Nevertheless, even in ponds, like Parr Shoals, where <hi>Gambusia</hi> were abund-<lb/>
ant there was frequently large production of Anopheles on account of the<lb/>
protection furnished the larvae along shore by the drift and floatage<lb/>
which naturally accumulated <del>along the shore</del><add>there</add>, and especially in the bights<lb/>
and bays of the shore-line.</p>
<p>Taking into consideration then the two means for the natural con-<lb/>
trol of production on the ponds it was easily seen<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1/ That we could do nothing to increase the efficiency of wave ac-<lb/>
tion save to draw out a few obstructing log rafts and heavy drift. This<lb/>
was a question of topography.</item>
<item>2/ That our best, and almost only, chance for control lay in get-<lb/>
ting a clean water<del>s</del> edge for our pond so that the larvae<del>,</del> having no pro-<lb/>
tection against the fish would be destroyed by them.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Beyond the preparation of the flowage area before the <del>building</del><add>filling</add> of<lb/>
the <del>pond</del><add>dam</add><add>stet</add>, for which we had formulated specifications, it is very obvi-<lb/>
ous that this edge cannot economically be kept clean of floatage and<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01122003"/>
and<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
drift by mechanical means. This was indeed attempted at <del>Blewetts Falls</del><add><unclear>Parris Shoals S.C</unclear></add>.<lb/>
a large body of men being employed all of one spring and summer in rakingt<lb/>
the edges of the pond. Of course it did some good, but it had been<lb/>
cheaper to buy and abandon for settlement all the land within the dis-<lb/>
tance of flight of the pond than to have continued it indefinitely <del>and,</del><lb/>
naturally, it would have to be continued indefinitely and the banks raked<lb/>
<del>at very short intervals</del>. This was a small pond: Lock No. 17, Black<lb/>
Warrior, was estimated (LePrince and myself) from the plans submitted by<lb/>
the U. S. Engineers, to have over 132 miles of edge. Hand raking was ob-<lb/>
viously not to be considered for this <del>pond</del><add>distance</add>.</p>
<p>As early as 1915 a plan for clearing these edges, economically feas-<lb/>
ible, was formulated and recommended to the Alabama Power Co. at Lock #12<lb/>
of the Coosa. This pond had been filled some two years previously, and be-<lb/>
ing accredited--<del>to an extent justly</del>--with having caused a very large a-<lb/>
mount of malaria in its environment--was the defendant in a number of suits<lb/>
<add>totaling</add> <del>to</del> a large amount. The plaint made against the pond: that it had been high<lb/>
in the spring of the year and, as it had been lowered from the use of the<lb/>
water it left all its edges covered with &ldquo;offensive mud bared to the hot<lb/>
sun and thus had produced a miasma which caused the malaria.&rdquo;</p>
<p><del>There was little doubt of the increase of malaria in some places<lb/>
after the pond was filled.</del> To obviate this alleged cause <add>of the malaria</add> the Company then<lb/>
put in <add>a</add> telephone line from <add>near</add> the <add>headwaters</add> <del>dam</del> to <del>get connection with</del> the power <add>plant</add> so they<lb/>
might be forewarned of the <del>arrival</del><add>coming</add> or <add>the</add> passing of high water. Whenever this<lb/>
was threatened they opened their weir and lowered the pond in advance so<lb/>
that there would be no rise beyond what they counted their normal level.<lb/>
They put in <del>elsewhere</del><add>also</add> a supplemental steam plant and whenever the use of<lb/>
the water threatened to leave bare these &ldquo;malaria producing mud flats&rdquo;<lb/>
they drew on their water power the least possible, supplementing it by<lb/>
steam, thus doing all that was possible to keep the pond at constant lev-<lb/>
el and incidentally, by <unclear>Keeping</unclear> the drift at the banks afloat, removed any<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01122004"/>
any<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
possibility of fish control and thus increased the production of Anopheles<lb/>
from their pond as much as was humanly possible--and at very considerable<lb/>
expense to themselves.</p>
<p>It was recommended to them for the present to let the pond fluctu-<lb/>
ate as much as possible: to catch every rise, so as to bring the floatage<lb/>
high up on the bank and <del>to</del><add>then</add> lower the pond by use or otherwise as much as<lb/>
was possible so as to strand <del>its</del><add>this</add> floatage on the banks with the larvae that<lb/>
it sheltered, as the pond went down.</p>
<p>The <del>full</del><add>general</add> recommendations<del>,</del> for a pond already in existence, as agreed<lb/>
to by LePrince: Griffitts and myself, were formulated as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1/ To hold the level of the pond as high as possible during the<lb/>
season when <unclear>A.</unclear> quad. were not producing, i. e. the late fall: winter and<lb/>
as long as we could into the next season. This would kill the land vege-<lb/>
tation up to this level. The drift and floatage accumulated during this<lb/>
period would also be collected along <add>this</add> <del>the</del> margin of the water, extending a<lb/>
certain distance therefrom.</item>
<item>2/ Just prior, and as close as possible, to the first flight of A.<lb/>
quad. from pond water: lower the pond as much as is reasonably possible.<lb/>
This would leave all--or nearly all--floatage and drift <add>then floating</add> against the banks<lb/>
stranded on the <add><unclear>on</unclear></add> <del>banks</del> when the pond went down: the aim being (a) to kill<lb/>
the larvae in this floatage and (b) to leave <add>a</add> clean water's edge around the<lb/>
pond.</item>
<item>3/ During the summer to catch and hold every rise of the river<lb/>
<del>for a few days</del><add>as long as possible</add> (<add>but</add> less than two weeks) and then run the pond down to clean<lb/>
edges again.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Obviously, it might take more than one season of high level to kill<lb/>
<hi>all</hi> the land vegetation: two, or at most three, would, however, do so.</p>
<p>Similarly, it might not be economically feasible to lower the pond<lb/>
enough to land <hi>all</hi> the trash <add>floating</add> around its edges at the beginning of the<lb/>
Anopheles production season. We have found, however, that <del>a</del>- the greater<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01122005"/>
greater<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
proportion of this floatage could be thus landed--<del>all we cannot say</del>, ex-<lb/>
cept where the banks are steep. Indeed, contra<del>t</del><add>r</add>y to our first judgement,<lb/>
mosquito production on the gently sloping banks was more easily controlled<lb/>
than on the steep ones, as even a small fall of the level would, on the<lb/>
former, land a large area of floatage while<del>,</del> on the steep banks a much<lb/>
less one would be landed for the same <unclear>&amp;</unclear> all of the pond.</p>
<p>One can easily see-knowing the biology of Anopheles--how this<lb/>
plan <hi>ought</hi> to work for control of their <del>breeding</del><add>production</add>: As the water fell the<lb/>
larvae would be left stranded on the land: as it rose--especially if it<lb/>
rose rapidly--the masses of floatage would be, to an extent, broken up<lb/>
and the Anopheles larvae exposed to fish, and, for the great majority of<lb/>
the time, the water's edge would be clean and free from floatage:--in<lb/>
the worst possible condition for mosquito production. It is not neces-<lb/>
sary to tell you field men, however, that we have never been satisfied<lb/>
with a method, however good it might be in theory, that had not been<lb/>
checked up in the field. We indeed saw a little of this around Talladega<lb/>
Springs, but not enough to be called a check of the method and it is<lb/>
this that I now wish to present to you:</p>
<p>In the spring of 1921, on my return from Peru, I was asked by the<lb/>
Superintendant of a large hydro-electric plant what measures could be then<lb/>
taken with his pond <add><del>at</del></add> to prevent it being a source of malaria. His state-<lb/>
ment was that at that time (in May, I believe) that the pond was level<lb/>
with the spillway. I advised him to hold it up as high as he could--to<lb/>
that level if possible--to about the <del>middle</del><add>end</add> of June, or even a little<lb/>
later--and then lower it (whether by use or <hi>wastage</hi>) 2 ft. or even 3 ft.<lb/>
and thereafter hold the rises and lower the level after them, as per the<lb/>
<del>previous</del> recommendation given above,</p>
<p>I visited this place on Aug. 10th. and lived with two other men<lb/>
in a tent on its bank in the upper reaches (about 50 ft. from the water). I<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01122006"/>
I<lb/>
-6-<lb/>
stayed at this place for six days:--the working days of one week. During<lb/>
that time only one mosquito was found in the tent. This was, unfortunate-<lb/>
ly mashed and its genus could not be determined. A considerable por-<lb/>
tion of the pond--its upper reaches--was examined during these six days:<lb/>
The edges were practically bare, the floatage being landed well above the<lb/>
water and, except where <del>creeks and</del> streams entered and on a log-raft, Ano-<lb/>
pheles larvae were not found. There was, in places a slight collection of<lb/>
drift along the edges, evidently come since the pond had been lowered<lb/>
(about July 10th.) but this was so slight that it seemed to furnish in-<lb/>
sufficient protection to larvae, at any rate none were found in it. Top-<lb/>
minnows were fairly abundant, especially near the mouths of streams and<lb/>
in bights: <del>nor were</del> Imagoes <add>were not</add> found in the houses that <del>the</del><add>were</add> examined <del>more or<lb/>
less</del> adjacent to the pond &amp; a fair number were examined.</p>
<p>Griffitts and myself had been over this pond in 1919 somewhat later<lb/>
in the year, but with far less pains and taking less time than I put on it<lb/>
in 1921. We had found the edges far from clean and breeding in several<lb/>
places: also in some houses a fair number of A. quad. All the places<lb/>
which had been found breeding in <hi>1919</hi> were examined <add>in/21</add>--and examined pains-<lb/>
takingly--and in no single one was breeding found. In mouths of streams<lb/>
there was <del>sometimes</del><add>occasionally</add> found a fair amount of floatage: sometimes due to the<lb/>
banks being steep at this place so that it was not landed: sometimes,<lb/>
doubtless, from being washed down the streams since the pond had been<lb/>
lowered. Where Spirogy<del>ria</del> alga<del>e</del> was found in this floatage we were apt<lb/>
to find larvae. A few of these developed into quads. and hence were<lb/>
doubtless from pond breeding, the majority were punctipennis and pro-<lb/>
bably washed down from the stream.</p>
<p>This same pond was visited again this year, in early August. It<lb/>
had been lowered intentionally <add>about</add> 16 ft. Two days careful examination by<lb/>
three people (Dr. Boldridge: Mr. Gage and myself) resulted in finding<lb/>
five larvae just below the mouths of <del>the</del> creeks which, in running water,<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01122007"/>
water<lb/>
-7-<lb/>
were breeding--scantily, indeed, but many fold more than the pond was.<lb/>
The banks were generally free from drift and floatage: in some bights,<lb/>
however, this was found, especially near the mouths of streams. None of<lb/>
of the larvae taken were large enough to justify attempts to develope them.</p>
<p>This examination on, on account of my becoming sick, was not com-<lb/>
pleted:--I had expected to give at least six more days to it, but Le-<lb/>
Prince examined this pond in what seemed to be the most favorable places<lb/>
for mosquito production for some days and Mr. Gage also (the latter both<lb/>
before and after my imperfect examination). (They will tell you what they<lb/>
found. (If they are not here, I will tell you that their results were<lb/>
<unclear>negative-</unclear> up to the time of my leaving Oct 8/)</p>
<p>Omit</p>
<p>Another large pond (in S. C. was examined by Dr. Boldridge and my-<lb/>
self with some pains in 1921 (I was there about 3 weeks). The pond was<lb/>
some 3 ft. or 4 ft. below the spillway at this time and the edges (ex-<lb/>
cept in the back-water of creeks) were clean. There was no breeding of<lb/>
sanitary importance found in the pond, or even in the back-water of the<lb/>
creeks, which were alive with Gambusia. Portions of the same pond were<lb/>
examined by myself for six days in the summer of 1922 with the same re-<lb/>
sult--it being then some 2 ft. below level &amp; with clean <unclear>banks,</unclear></p>
<p>Naturally, these observations are not nearly so extensive as<lb/>
should be made, yet they are a beginning and I think the findings from<lb/>
them are sufficient to, tentatively, justify the recommendations made in<lb/>
1915 and to show that the change of level of a pond lessens its production<lb/>
of Anopheles and can be so handled as well-nigh to prevent it. This, of<lb/>
course, applies only to production on the banks of ponds--not to log-<lb/>
rafts and floating islands, which would be but little, <add>or not at all,</add> affected by it<unclear>.</unclear><lb/>
And, unlike hand-cleaning <add>of</add> the banks, this method of getting clean water-<lb/>
edges is always feasible and probably in general economically practicable.</p>
<p>Obviously, the lowering of a pond from its early summer high-water<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01122008"/>
high-water<lb/>
-8-<lb/>
mark, if done simply by the use of the water, costs nothing and cleans<lb/>
the banks fairly efficiently.</p>
<p>If the use of the water does not accomplish this and the pond is<lb/>
cleared by wastage through the weir this is done at considerable cost to<lb/>
the Power Company, yet it may be well worth doing as a sanitary measure.<lb/>
It was so done--intentionally I mean--at the pond of which I first gave<lb/>
the history and I cannot but think that the production of Anopheles pre-<lb/>
vented thereby justified the expenditure. Indeed, from the little I saw<lb/>
and from LePrince's verbal reports I think it is fair to say that at this<lb/>
time a unit area of the pond was producing fewer Anopheles than a unit<lb/>
of its land environment: it was lessening not increasing <del>proda</del> Anopheles production</p>
<p>This method awaits and calls for further observation and devel-<lb/>
opement. It is &ldquo;up to&rdquo; you Field Men.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
