<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01124005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, October 27, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01124005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-10-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">Segou (Mali)</name>
<name type="place">Dakar (Senegal)</name>
<name type="place">French West Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-10-27">October 27, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01124005</idno>
<title>English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, October 27, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Seguin reports on possible yellow fever deaths and public health response in French West Africa.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-10-27">
<head>English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, October 27, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01124005"/>
<opener>
Seguin <unclear><del>L</del></unclear><lb/>
1 2 &amp; 3 all at S&eacute;guo in Sudan<lb/>
by<lb/>
Seguin<lb/>
<hi>FRENCH SUDAN</hi><lb/>
<hi>HEALTH SERVICE</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Bamako,<lb/>
<date value="1922-10-27">October 27, 1922</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>No. 329.</p>
<p>S&eacute;guin, chief physician, 2nd class, and Head of the Health Depart-<lb/>
ment of the French Sudan, to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health<lb/>
Service of French West Africa. Dakar.</p>
<p>*******************</p>
<p>I have the honor to inform you that on October 19, immediately on<lb/>
receiving a telegram from S&eacute;gou informing me that Mr. A. of the Niger Mission<lb/>
was suffering from a serious disease similar to the one that had caused the<lb/>
death of Mr. B., also of the Niger Mission, three days before, I waited on the<lb/>
Governor, who had already planned to go to S&eacute;gou, and proposed that I accompany<lb/>
him, in order to carry out on the spot a sanitary investigation that seemed to<lb/>
me to be demanded by circumtances and to take the steps that the situation<lb/>
required.</p>
<p>On arriving at S&eacute;gou on the morning of the twentieth, I immediately<lb/>
obtained from Dr. Fortin the following clinical observations: Mr. B. and Mr. A.,<lb/>
who belonged to the same group of the Niger Mission, had reached S&eacute;gou some two<lb/>
weeks before and both lived at the C.F.A.O., taking their meals with Mr. Rolland,<lb/>
agent of the C.F.A.O., and with Mr. Collin, a tradesman of S&eacute;gou.</p>
<p>On October 12, Mr. B. fell ill with a fever that was very high from<lb/>
the first, reaching 40.3 degrees and accompanied by the following symptoms:<lb/>
excitement, red complexion, conjunctiva injected but without ecchymosis, pre-<lb/>
cordial pain, negative auscultation, bilious vomit. The urine was normal in<lb/>
quantity and in quality from the beginning to the end, and icterus appeared<lb/>
at the end of the fourth day. On the morning of the fourth day, October 15,<lb/>
the patient showed a remission of the symptoms, the temperature fell to 37<lb/>
degrees, and the patient felt well enough to want to get up and eat.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01124006"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>During this same fourth day the fever returned with agitation and<lb/>
delirium, and there was a fairly abundant black vomit that adhered to the<lb/>
sides of the basin and formed a &ldquo;s&eacute;milique&rdquo;, almost pasty mass that resembled<lb/>
<hi>wet soot.</hi></p>
<p>Ecchymosis appeared on the chest and the abdomen, and there was<lb/>
anuria during the very last hours, but never any black urine.</p>
<p>Death at 10 o'clock in the morning of October 16.</p>
<p>Treatment: As much as three grams of quinine a day from the first,<lb/>
for three or four days, by mouth and by injection; subcutaneous injections of<lb/>
1.30 of Novarsenobenzol; bleeding by scarified leaches followed by injections<lb/>
of artificial serum (three injections of 350 to 400 C. each) that were rapidly<lb/>
resorbed and each time brought up the pulse.</p>
<p>Mr. A., who left S&eacute;gou on October 16 at 9 o'clock in the morning, one<lb/>
hour before the death of Mr. B., felt the first symptoms of the disease about<lb/>
noon.</p>
<p>On coming back to S&eacute;gou in the forenoon of the 17th, he was immediately<lb/>
examined by Dr. Fortin, who found in him the same symptoms as the ones presented<lb/>
previously by Mr. B., but perhaps even more clearly marked; headache, flushed<lb/>
face, injected eyes, tongue very white in the middle but with a red line around<lb/>
the edges, very few bilious vomits, stomach tolerance for liquids, normal urine,<lb/>
fever of about 40 to 40.5 degrees for three days, lessening of the symptoms at<lb/>
the end of the third day. Similarly to Mr. B., Mr. A. wanted to get up and eat.</p>
<p>The fever returned on the fourth day, with abundant black hemorrhagic<lb/>
vomit, ecchymosis under the conjunctiva, abundant, clear but very albuminous urine,<lb/>
final excitation with delirium, then coma.</p>
<p>The icterus that appeared during the period of remission grew rapidly<lb/>
worse and reached its greatest intensity after the death on the 19th at 12.30,<lb/>
noon.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01124007"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>Mr. A., who normally took 1.75 gr. of quinine daily as a preventive,<lb/>
recieved during the course of the illness large doses of quinine and of 914.</p>
<p>Summing up, Mr. A. and Mr. B., who belonged to the same group and<lb/>
therefore lived under identical conditions, had been living for two weeks at<lb/>
the C.F.A.O., when one of them, Mr. B., fell ill on October 12. He died on<lb/>
October 16 after having revealed the symptoms described above, and on the same<lb/>
day Mr. A. fell ill with a disease that presented a picture practically iden-<lb/>
tical with that of Mr. B's.</p>
<p>It is permissible to regret the fact that no blood examination was<lb/>
made in the case of these two patients when there was at S&eacute;gou a microscope and<lb/>
staining material that I was able to use. Such an examination, seeking to<lb/>
determine the Obermayer spirochetes or the &ldquo;hematozosis&rdquo; would have given<lb/>
certainty where there is at present only a probability, by bringing to bear<lb/>
an important diagnostic element. <hi>This probability is that Mr. A. and Mr. B.<lb/>
died from attacks of yellow fever</hi>, but it would be imprudent to affirm this<lb/>
diagnosis with only the clinical information that I received as a basis.</p>
<p>The diagnosis of yellow fever is even more doubtful in the following<lb/>
cases:</p>
<p>Mr. C., employed by the firm of Maurel and Prom, died on August 16,<lb/>
at 1 p.m., from the results of attacks of pernicious congestion, according to<lb/>
the report of Dr. Malaussene, who treated Mr. C. from the beginning of his<lb/>
illness, that is to say, the forenoon of August 4, without thinking of making<lb/>
a blood examination that would have made it possible to confirm the diagnosis<lb/>
of pernicious attacks.</p>
<p>The observations reported by Dr. Malaussene speak of &ldquo;h&eacute;m&aacute;tom&egrave;s&rdquo;<lb/>
and melena, but make no mention of the urine or of icterus.</p>
<p>During these three days of illness there was no fall in temperature<lb/>
nor remission of the other symptoms, which would render the diagnosis of yellow<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01124008"/>
-4-<lb/>
fever much more doubtful in case one ever tried to assimilate Mr. C's case to<lb/>
those of Mr. A. and Mr. B.</p>
<p>Mr. D., of the Niger Mission, died on September 9 of pernicious coma-<lb/>
tose attacks.</p>
<p>Mr. E., Postal Receiver, died October 5 of bilious hemoglobinuric<lb/>
fever, according to the diagnosis of Dr. Fortin, who treated the patient and<lb/>
gave me the following information as to his case:</p>
<p>High fever of about 40 degrees for 5 days; bilious vomit from the<lb/>
first; slight icterus from the third day on, but not accentuated after death;<lb/>
oliguria from the first day; dark red urine; anuria for over 24 hours before<lb/>
death.</p>
<p>Toward the last the vomit became very dark green, but was never black.<lb/>
There was no fall in temperature, no injection of the eyes, and no subcutaneous<lb/>
hemorrhage.</p>
<p>While regretting again that the blood was not examined, some important<lb/>
differences will be noted between the symptoms of Mr. E. and those of Messrs. A.<lb/>
and B.</p>
<p>Child F. died on September 13 of <hi>gastroenteritis</hi>.. Mrs. G., who was<lb/>
seen on the third day of illness of Dr. Fortin on his arrival in S&eacute;gou on Septem-<lb/>
ber 13, presented symptoms that resembled those of Messrs. A. and B. The fever<lb/>
was from 38.6 to 39.4 degrees. There was a single scant attack of hemorrhagic<lb/>
vomit. On the third day there appeared subicterus that got much darker in two<lb/>
days. <hi>The gums bled slightly the whole time. There was ecchymosis on the thighs,<lb/>
metrorrhagia in the beginning, psychic disturbances and an extraordinary fear of<lb/>
death</hi>.</p>
<p>There was a very short remission during the fifth day of illness, after<lb/>
which the fever returned, oscillating between 38.6 and 39.4 degrees for about<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01124009"/>
-5-<lb/>
twelve days. The quantitatively normal urine was albuminous and had a slight-<lb/>
ly bilious appearance. The patient had been convalescent for a week when she<lb/>
was sent to the hospital of Bamako, where she arrived still subfebrile in<lb/>
the afternoon, with 37.4 to 37.5 degrees of temperature, mental debility and<lb/>
subicterus.</p>
<p>At present, after (word omitted in original) days of treatment, the<lb/>
patient is fully convalescent. Her psychic troubles and the icterus have<lb/>
almost entirely disappeared.</p>
<p>Mrs. G.'s little girl, 5 months old, who was put on a bottle from<lb/>
the beginning of her mother's illness, is perfectly well and has at no<lb/>
time revealed any morbid symptoms.</p>
<p>Mr. G., the husband, who was in continual contact with the patient<lb/>
and who accompanied her to Bamako, was seen by me on his return to S&eacute;gou.<lb/>
He is perfectly well.</p>
<p>In view of these facts, and since it was impossible to make any<lb/>
affirmative statement, it seemed necessary to isolate the persons who had been<lb/>
in contact with the patients and to submit them to 10 days' observation, a<lb/>
long enough period, as the length of the period of incubation of yellow fever<lb/>
is from 2 to 5 days according to some, and 6 days according to the sanitary<lb/>
regulations of December 16, 1909.</p>
<p>Therefore the following persons who had been on contact with the<lb/>
patients were isolated <hi>right where they were, in a tent</hi>:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. At Banankoro, Mr. H., of the C.F.A.O., and Mr. I., tradesman.</item>
<item>2. At Sama Markalan, 22 kilometers up the river, on the left bank,<lb/>
where they were at the time, Mr. J., who had cared for Mr. B. and brought<lb/>
Mr. A. back to Segou, sick, and Mr. K., who took his meals at the Caron<lb/>
house during Mr. A.'s illness and had assisted in caring for him.</item>
<item>3. Two kilometers from S&eacute;gou, on the Barou&eacute;li road, Mr. L., junior,<lb/>
and Mr. M., who were taking their meals at the Caron house at the time when<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01124010"/>
-6-<lb/>
Mr. A. came back there to die. The buildings they occupied were closed and<lb/>
the mosquitoes in them destroyed by the use of <hi>tobacco leaves</hi>.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Since then sulphur sticks have been sent from Bamako, and for still<lb/>
further security a second disinfection will be performed with sulphur fumes<lb/>
before the suspected buildings are reopened.</p>
<p>Furthermore, isolation rooms hermetically closed with mosquito<lb/>
nothing have been prepared in the maternity hospital in course of construction,<lb/>
the only building in S&eacute;gou that offered good conditions for the isolation of<lb/>
patients. After this suspected patients from the cities and from the outside<lb/>
will be brought there. They would be placed there under double mosquito pro-<lb/>
tection, and would therefore not be a source of danger for the inhabitants of<lb/>
S&eacute;gou.</p>
<p>These are the measures that have been taken on the very admissible but<lb/>
not verifiable hypothesis that Mr. B. and Mr. A. died of yellow fever, the origin<lb/>
of which would however remain unknown. These measures, in addition to a<lb/>
careful observation of the sanitary condition of the city and its surroundings,<lb/>
an order prohibiting anyone from going into the native village from sunset to<lb/>
sunrise, and the organization of mosquito control, although mosquitoes are rare<lb/>
in S&eacute;gou, where I was unable to find any Stegomyia, are of such a nature as to<lb/>
protect at the same time the health of the community, which is our principal<lb/>
preoccupation, and the economic condition of the country, concerning which no<lb/>
one could be indifferent.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Signed, S&eacute;guin</signed>.
P.C.C.<lb/>
Dakar, November 10, 1922.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
