<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01124015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, February 1, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01124015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-02-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="place">Segou (Mali)</name>
<name type="place">Dakar (Senegal)</name>
<name type="place">French West Africa</name>
<name type="place">Grand Bassam (Ivory Coast)</name>
<name type="place">Sudan</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-02-01">February 1, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01124015</idno>
<title>English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, February 1, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Seguin reports on the use of Noguchi serum and vaccine in French West Africa, and discusses its prophylactic value.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-02-01">
<head>English translation [from French] of letter from [s.n.] Seguin to the Medical Inspector, Director of the Health Service of French West Africa, February 1, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01124015"/>
<opener>
Seguin 3<lb/>
<hi>FRENCH SUDAN</hi>.<lb/>
<hi>HEALTH SERVICE</hi>.<lb/>
<dateline>
Bamako,<lb/>
<date value="1923-02-01">February 1, 1923.</date>
</dateline>
No. 37.<lb/>
(Copy)<lb/>
Seguin, chief physician, 2nd class, Head of the Health<lb/>
Service of the French Sudan, to the Medical Inspector,<lb/>
Director of the Health Service of French West Africa.<lb/>
Dakar.<lb/>
******<lb/>
</opener>
<p>In reply to your letter No. 149 asking for &ldquo;exact information<lb/>
as to the conditions under which the stock of Noguchi serum and vaccine<lb/>
is used&rdquo;, which stock was sent to me by the Governor of the Ivory Coast<lb/>
when I expressed a wish for it in telegram No. 121 of October 8, 1922,<lb/>
confirming the death of Mr. N., postal employee, from yellow fever, I<lb/>
have the honor of sending you the following information.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. The amount of vaccine received was 800 cc., and the amount<lb/>
sent to S&eacute;gou was 420 cc. The amount of serum received amounted to 1800 cc.,<lb/>
of which 600 cc. were sent to S&eacute;gou.</item>
<item>2. These products, which were sent from Grand-Bassam by<lb/>
Dr. Bauvallet, director of the bacteriological laboratory, were trans-<lb/>
ported in an improvised ice-box first by railway to Bouake, where the supply<lb/>
of ice was renewed, then by automobile from Bouake to Sikasso, where an<lb/>
automobile sent by the Governor of the Sudan from Bamako with a sufficient<lb/>
supply of ice met them and carried them to Bamako, where they were immediately<lb/>
placed on November 8 in the ice-box of the bacteriological laboratory. The<lb/>
serum and the vaccine were therefore transported under the most favorable<lb/>
conditions of speed and temperature possible for the perfect conservation.</item>
<item>3. The first parcel of serum and vaccine reached S&eacute;gou on<lb/>
November 9, where the last European to die had been Monsieur.<unclear>X</unclear>....of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01124016"/>
Niger Mission, on October 31. A first injection of 2 cc. of vaccine<lb/>
was given to the inhabitants of S&eacute;gou, about 40 in number, on November 10.<lb/>
The second injection was given on the 14th, or four days later.</item></list></p>
<p>It also seemed necessary to vaccinate the nine members of<lb/>
the Niger Mission, of whom six were in Niamina and three in Sansanding.<lb/>
These vaccinations were made by Major Alexandre, at whose disposal the<lb/>
Governor of the Sudan placed a steamer, and they were completed on<lb/>
November 20.</p>
<p>A Liberian in the service of Dr. Y....., a member of the Niger<lb/>
Mission, was the last to die of yellow fever, on November 9, the same day<lb/>
that the first parcel of vaccine was leaving Bamako. This death occurred<lb/>
in S&eacute;gou.</p>
<p>It was therefore impossible to give this Liberian either serum<lb/>
or vaccine. Since there has been no further case of yellow fever in S&eacute;gou,<lb/>
no trial of the Noguchi serum has been made. I can thus have no opinion<lb/>
as to the value of the serum, having had no patients on whom to try it.</p>
<p>As to the prophylactic value of the vaccine, the conditions<lb/>
under which it was used do not permit of any definite conclusions. The<lb/>
vaccine may have helped to destroy the small focus of yellow fever that<lb/>
existed in S&eacute;gou, but it would not be scientific to affirm it. In fact,<lb/>
11 days had already gone by since the last European death definitely due<lb/>
to yellow fever when the vaccine was first injected, and thirteen or<lb/>
fourteen days had passed since quarters inhabited by the preceding patients<lb/>
had been abandoned and disinfected, first by burning tobacco leaves and then<lb/>
by the use of sulphur.</p>
<p>In addition to this, the season was already advanced and the<lb/>
mosquitoes had become very rare. All these reasons make it impossible to<lb/>
draw any conclusions as to the value of the vaccine from the anti-yellow-fever<lb/>
vaccination practiced in S&eacute;gou.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01124017"/>
<p>In order to determine its efficiency it would be necessary to<lb/>
vaccinate only a portion of the population in a more intense yellow fever<lb/>
center, keeping as controls a few persons who had voluntarily offered<lb/>
themselves for the purpose, and allowing all other conditions to remain<lb/>
the same for the two groups.</p>
<p>I do not fail to recognize the difficulty of this kind of<lb/>
experimentation on human beings with a disease as severe as yellow<lb/>
fever, but this is the only way in which the efficiency of the Noguchi<lb/>
serum can be definitely determined. Such an experiment is hardly possible<lb/>
except in permanently endemic centers of yellow fever.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) Dr. Seguin</signed>.
True copy.<lb/>
(stamp) &ldquo;for the inspector of the<lb/>
civilian health service,&rdquo;<lb/>
p.o. the Assistant physician,<lb/>
(signature illegible)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
