<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01129001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Suggestions for the Control of Malaria on the Plantations of the United Fruit Company, by Joseph A. LePrince and Henry Rose Carter, September 7, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01129001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-09-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">Canal Zone (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Eustis (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-09-07">September 7, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01129001</idno>
<title>Report: Suggestions for the Control of Malaria on the Plantations of the United Fruit Company, by Joseph A. LePrince and Henry Rose Carter, September 7, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>LePrince and Carter offer suggestions for the control of malaria on the plantations of the United Fruit Company.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1928-09-07">
<head>Report: Suggestions for the Control of Malaria on the Plantations of the United Fruit Company, by Joseph A. LePrince and Henry Rose Carter, September 7, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01129001"/>
<opener>
/LC<lb/>
PLEASE RETURN TO FILE.<lb/>
Dr. H.R. Carter,<lb/>
<dateline>
2122 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1928-09-07">Septem 7/28</date>
</dateline>
Suggestions for the Control of Malaria<lb/>
on the Plantations<lb/>
of the United Fruit Company:<lb/>
Agreed on by<lb/>
J. A. LePrince and H. R. Carter.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>It is understood that the malaria here considered is that oc-<lb/>
curring among the colored and native laborers, employees of the<lb/>
Fruit Company, living in quarters controlled by the Company, and the<lb/>
following methods are suggested as being at the same time practicable<lb/>
and as capable of giving a reasonable amont of control of the malaria<lb/>
among them:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>I: As much prevention of Anopheles production as is economically<lb/>
possible.</item>
<item>II: The use of repellants about the quarters of employees.</item>
<item>III: Daily hand-killing of Anopheles in quarters.</item>
<item>IV: Attempting the cure (i. e. freeing from infection) of em-<lb/>
ployees treated for malarial fever.</item>
</list></p>
<p>I: Prevention of Anopheles Production.</p>
<p>Since cost has to be considered as well as health, it is imprac-<lb/>
ticable to carry this method out fully, as was done on the Canal Zone<lb/>
for example. We must therefore select such breeding places the cost<lb/>
of control of which is justified by the prevention of the injury from<lb/>
the malaria they would have produced.</p>
<p>The <hi>advisability</hi> of the control of any particular breeding place<lb/>
then should depend on (1) the cost of its control and (2) the amount<lb/>
of malaria it, uncontrolled, will produce.</p>
<p><hi>The Cost of Control</hi> depends on the nature of the breeding place:<lb/>
the surrounding topography: cost of labor and other factors determina-<lb/>
ble only by the man on the ground. The cost of up-keep must be con-<lb/>
sidered in the cost.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01129002"/>
<p>cost.</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p><hi>The Amount of Malaria</hi> caused by a breeding place depends mainly on<lb/>
the following factors:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Species of Anopheles produced:</item>
<item>(b) Number of Anopheles produced.</item>
<item>(c) Proximity of breeding place to quarters.</item>
</list></p>
<p>(a) <hi>Species of Anopheles</hi>. Naturally a place produc-<lb/>
ing species that are efficient vectors of malaria causes more malaria<lb/>
than one producing the same number of a less efficient vector.</p>
<p>On the Canal Zone, <hi>A. albimanus</hi> and <hi>A. tarsimaculata</hi><lb/>
(both are Cellia in Theobald's classification) were certainly our<lb/>
principal (possibly almost our only) vectors of malaria. They were<lb/>
very abundant: easier to infect than the other species: much more gen-<lb/>
erally found in houses and capable of long flights.</p>
<p><del>I</del> If the species of Anopheles on the plantations <del>on the<lb/>
plantations</del> be the same and present the same biology as on the Canal<lb/>
Zone and if we have to differentiate between the control of the pro-<lb/>
duction of the different species it would be advisable to give prece-<lb/>
dence to control of places producing these two species --i. e. to con-<lb/>
centrate on them. Research on this matter on the plantations seems ad-<lb/>
visable as all of them may not show the same Anopheles, or their Ano-<lb/>
pheles may not show the same characterists as on the Canal Zone.</p>
<p>(b) <hi>The number of Anopheles produced</hi>. This needs no<lb/>
discussion.</p>
<p>(c) <hi>Proximity to quarters.</hi> Nor does this need dis-<lb/>
cussion, although we cannot assert that the amount of malaria produced<lb/>
at any place is always proportional (inversely) to its distance from<lb/>
the breeding place causing it. (Foot note)</p>
<p>_______________________________________________</p>
<p>(Foot note): Proximity of the breeding place to quarters is, of course,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01129003"/>
, of course,<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
only one factor in the accessibility of the men we wish to protect to<lb/>
the Anopheles produced from this breeding place. With this might be<lb/>
included a number of others: as intervening woods: hills: collections<lb/>
of residenced: the direction, time <add>of</add> day and strength of winds: whether<lb/>
the quarters are screened etc. All of these things may be considered<lb/>
by the man on the ground, but the data on most of them are decidedly<lb/>
unsatisfactory and certainly to discuss them would make this Memorandum,<lb/>
intended to be simple, unduly complicated. (End of Foot note).</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>II: The Use of Repellants about the Quarters.</p>
<p>This method is suggested tentatively only. It is cheap and the<lb/>
results reported by Coogle in the Mississippi Delta were good. It is<lb/>
suggested that Dr. Deeks get in touch with Dr. Fricks at Memphis (or<lb/>
with the Bureau of the U. S. Public Health Service, Washington, D. C.)<lb/>
to obtain the results of this method to date, including those of 1924.</p>
<p>III: The Daily Hand-killing of Anopheles in Quarters.</p>
<p>This gave good results on the Canal Zone and at the Resevoir at<lb/>
Camp Eustis, Va. Men skilled in finding the Anopheles would be ne-<lb/>
cessary in the beginning. Whether the people living in the house,<lb/>
after being taught to find the insects, could be trusted to keep the<lb/>
house free of them is a question. It would be a great advantage if they<lb/>
could, but even if this has to be done in perpetuity by men paid by the<lb/>
Company it still ranks as a method cheap in proportion to its efficacy.</p>
<p>IV: Attempt to Cure (Free from Infection) Patients Treated for<lb/>
Malaria.</p>
<p>This will quite frequently be impossible, the patient refusing, or<lb/>
failing, to continue proper treatment long enough. Yet, with the greater<lb/>
resistance of negroes to malaria, cure possibly would be less infrequent<lb/>
than our observations on white men have led us to expect. Here <add>too</add> is need<lb/>
for research and in a virgin field.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01129004"/>
<p>field.</p>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>The regular administration of quinine to well people to immunize<lb/>
them against the bites of infective Anopheles is not recommended except<lb/>
in a temporary emergency when the exposure to a malignant malaria is<lb/>
very great, as in gangs opening up new lands: the occurrence of an unu-<lb/>
sually severe and general epidemic of malaria etc.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
