<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01124048">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 26, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01124048</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-12-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William H.</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">Pennsylvania</name>
<name type="place">Jacksonville (Fla.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-12-26">December 26, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01124048</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 26, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson writes about his search for new work and his discouragement at not being offered public health positions. He notes that sanitary work in Peru has almost stopped due to financial issues.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-12-26">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, December 26, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01124048"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN EL PERU<lb/>
----<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
----<lb/>
----<lb/>
<dateline>
3014 Winfield Ave.,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md. <date value="1922-12-26">December 26, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just received your two letters relating your inter-<lb/>
view with Dr. Rose. I am not much surprised at the result,- in fact it is just<lb/>
what I expect from Dr. Rose. From the time of my first interview with him in<lb/>
New York after my return from Peru I have been trying to figure him out. My<lb/>
solution is still somewhat vague, but there are several things which have sug-<lb/>
gested themselves to me and I think I am not far wrong.</p>
<p>Last Friday evening I had a long talk with Dr. Welch, and during this<lb/>
conversation naturally your name came up, and brought from Dr. Welch the following<lb/>
remark. &ldquo;I think Dr. Carter is one of the most delightful and <hi>most clear thinking<lb/>
men</hi> I have ever met&rdquo;, I said Amen, twice.</p>
<p>The interview referred to with Dr. Welch was very much along the lines<lb/>
I have been writing you, and also about the proposed future work. He said that<lb/>
Dr. Bloodgood had spoken to him about it, and he wanted to get my point of view.<lb/>
He stated that he would very much like to see me continue with the public health<lb/>
work, but there were so few positions which at the present time paid a salary<lb/>
which would justify me in taking them. He said that it seemed to him that the<lb/>
I.H.B. ought to hesitate in letting me go, and surely they ought to have a place<lb/>
for me. I told him about the Mexican proposition and some of the reasons for<lb/>
not taking it, which he seemed to accept as O.K. I then told him about the<lb/>
Jacksonville proposition, and to that he remarked, &ldquo;That is not bad, that is not<lb/>
bad&rdquo;, but still he thought there ought to be some good place in the public<lb/>
health work. We then discussed the African situation, and I told him that you felt<lb/>
that I ought to go in charge of the field work in Africa, and that the diplo-<lb/>
matic stuff could be handled by some one else. He did not seem to be fully infor-<lb/>
med as to the plans for the African work, and asked several questions, which I<lb/>
answered as best I could. He then asked me not to decide anything definitely<lb/>
until he should have a chance to take the matter up. He then gave me some con-<lb/>
fidential information in regard to some expected changes, and also spoke of<lb/>
Pennsylvania as if there was to be a new Health Commissioner there, and rather<lb/>
intimated that I might have a chance at that if nothing else turned up.</p>
<p>If I had the time and could afford the expense I think I could spend a<lb/>
couple of years here at the Public Health School to great advantage, and come<lb/>
out a pretty we<del>e</del>ll equipped man for most any line of the work. There are so<lb/>
many points which I see that I would like to work out a bit, and as things are<lb/>
here, I could work out most of my problems right here. During hese years that I<lb/>
have been out there have been constant presentation fo problems and conditions<lb/>
which I did not have the means on the ground to solve. In fact with two years<lb/>
of contact with the way they are teaching things here I even think that I could<lb/>
contribute something to the curriculum here which would tend to make the men<lb/>
better and more practical men on leaving here,- I mean the students.</p>
<p>I had a letter from Dr. Lavoreria today in which he seems rather discour-<lb/>
aged about the situation in Peru. He seems to think that I had better postpone my<lb/>
return, which he will find confirmed in a letter I wrote him but which he had<lb/>
not received when he wrote this one to me. They have been obliged to discontinue<lb/>
practically all the outside sanitary work, even the peones were not paid for 5<lb/>
weeks, so they ahd to lay them off too.</p>
<p>In view of all these things I am and have been planning my work here so<lb/>
as to fit in with the work in Jacksonville,-and yet I feel as you do that there<lb/>
are not too many men with real experience in yellow fever work. With the aim of the<lb/>
final ultimate elimination of this disease from the world, and it could be done in<lb/>
about five years if properly handled, the men who have had experience and have seen<lb/>
the dangerous mistakes in the work are worth more than new inexperienced men!!</p>
<p>I most sincerely appreciate your efforts in my behalf; my association with<lb/>
you is and always will be worth more to me than any other. However I may still have<lb/>
the good fortune to meet up with you in work of mutual interest.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely &amp; gratefully yours</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
