<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01134001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum for L.L. Williams, Jr., [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01134001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">America</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01134001</idno>
<title>Memorandum for L.L. Williams, Jr., [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This memorandum discusses the possibility that malaria originated in the Americas.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Memorandum for L.L. Williams, Jr., [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01134001"/>
<opener>
File<lb/>
Biographic<lb/>
C<lb/>
O<lb/>
P<lb/>
Y<lb/>
Malaria<lb/>
Place of Origin<lb/>
1924 (?)<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Memorandum for Dr. L.L. Williams, Jr.<lb/>
Place of Origin of Malaria.<lb/>
America.</p>
<p>The writer is inclined to think that malaria did<lb/>
not exist in America prior to its discovery. Anopheles mosquitoes<lb/>
did however--the American species differ from those in the old<lb/>
world,--and when the parasites were introduced by European and<lb/>
African carriers it quickly spread both from them and from the In-<lb/>
dians infected directly and indirectly from them.</p>
<p>The evidence for this is:</p>
<p>(1) That in none of the early expeditions of Euro-<lb/>
peans coming from reasonably healthful regions and simply <hi>passing<lb/>
through</hi> hitherto unvisited Indian country have I found that exten-<lb/>
sive sickness is recorded, except that due to hardship and starvation.<lb/>
This is true even when the region traversed by the expedition is<lb/>
now malarious and was at the time physically well suited for the<lb/>
production of Anopheles mosquitoes and doubtless was then producing<lb/>
them. In a number of such cases the absence of sickness is im-<lb/>
plied and in some is specifically mentioned.</p>
<p>(2) When, however, a fairly prolonged stay or a<lb/>
settlement was made by Europeans in places which are now malarious<lb/>
&ldquo;fevers and calenturas&rdquo; very generally developed and in many cases<lb/>
were deadly. This was especially the case when the expeditions<lb/>
came from, or via, places (usually in America) where such fevers<lb/>
were prevalent. Even a somewhat prolonged stay at one place--as<lb/>
-<pb n="2" id="f01134002"/>
-2-<lb/>
when Orellana remained &ldquo;the whole of Lent&rdquo; at one place on the<lb/>
Amazon--did not lead to sickness when the Europeans had been long<lb/>
resident in regions free from malaria.</p>
<p>For example:</p>
<p>(1) The implication is strong that there<lb/>
was no serious sickness--if there was any--in Oxeham's expedition<lb/>
of 1575 across the Isthmus of Darien and return until he had gone into<lb/>
fairly permanent camp on the North Coast in the Country of the Syme-<lb/>
roons (Cimaroons) -- negro slaves who had run away from the Spaniards.<lb/>
Yet Isaac Strain in 1854, with all the facilities of that much<lb/>
later period, lost a number of his men from fevers on crossing one<lb/>
way and could not have made the return journey.</p>
<p>(2) Drake's Darien expedition of 1572 report-<lb/>
ed no sickness until they had been long in permanent camp on the north<lb/>
coast of the Isthmus and practically in communication with Spanish<lb/>
settlements. They had been in the country about six months before the<lb/>
outbreak of &ldquo;calenturas&rdquo; showed -- which may, or may not, have been<lb/>
malaria.</p>
<p>(3) Raleigh's expedition of 1595, by boat<lb/>
and on foot, up the Orinoco for 400 miles. To quote him: &ldquo;Moreover<lb/>
the country is healthful as 100 persons and more which lay (without<lb/>
shift most sluttishly and were evry day almost melted with heat in<lb/>
rowing and marching and suddenly wet againe with greate showers and<lb/>
did eat all sorts of corrupt fruits and made meales of fresh fish<lb/>
without seasoning: Of Tortugas: of Lagartos and of al sorte good and<lb/>
bad without either order or measure and besides did lodge in the open<lb/>
air evry night) we lost not any one, nor had one ill disposed to my<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01134003"/>
-3-<lb/>
knowledge, nor found anie Calentura or other of those pestilent<lb/>
diseases which dwell in all hote regions so near the Equinoctial line.&rdquo;<lb/>
He entered the river the latter part of March or early in April--<lb/>
was there in the rainy season--and made it his business to stop at<lb/>
Indian villages.</p>
<p>(4) Orellana's long vayage down the Amazon in 1541<lb/>
entailed little, apparently no, loss from sickness, although the<lb/>
men were broken by privation and starving before they started--<lb/>
seven dying of hunger. They made at least two prolonged stops--<lb/>
one of not less than 47 days near the mouth of the Napo and one<lb/>
of 18 days, repairing the boats some months later. They had much<lb/>
communication--hostile generally, with the Indians and got their<lb/>
provisions from their villages.</p>
<p>At present from such a trip of over seven months, and<lb/>
without quinine we would expect a loss of over 75% of the expedition.</p>
<p>(5) The first invasion of Tabasco by Cortez in 1519<lb/>
was apparently not followed by sickness among his men, yet in 1529<lb/>
when Montejo wished to use this province as a base for the invasion<lb/>
of Yucatan, it was so unhealthful that the Spaniards, occuping it since<lb/>
1523, were on the point of abandoning it.</p>
<p>(6) There were deaths, probably a number of them in the<lb/>
expedition Cortez led across the wet lands of Tehuantepec and southern<lb/>
Campeche and Yucatan to Honduras in 1524-5, but they seem to have<lb/>
been due to privation and hardships--they even ate their guides--<lb/>
rather than to disease. Had that country been as malarious as it<lb/>
is now, these Spaniards and Mexicans from the highlands had probably<lb/>
never reached the Honduran Coast.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01134004"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>(7) The sanitary conditon of the country adjacent to<lb/>
the port of Vera Cruz (Medallin) changed much for the worse both for<lb/>
Spanish and Indians after its occupation as a permanent settlement<lb/>
from --say--1519 when it was first occupied and when we hear nothing<lb/>
of its unhealthfulness, to 1537 when Bishop Marroquin complained so<lb/>
bitterly of it.</p>
<p>For the second part: settlements once established<lb/>
in places now recognized as malarious became unhealthful--sometimes ex-<lb/>
tremely so--as Isebela: Nombre de Dios: Vera Cruz: Sta. Marta: Mar-<lb/>
tinique: The Guianas: Jamestown: Biloxi: Port Royal, S. C.: New Orleans:<lb/>
Savannah, etc. It is to be noted that almost as soon as these settle-<lb/>
ments in Spanish and French America were established, negroes direct<lb/>
from Africa were introduced. (Foot note)</p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<p>(Foot note) Sometimes several expeditions visited the same region, each<lb/>
for only a short time. In such cases the fact that the later ones<lb/>
experienced an epidemic in no wise militates against our contention.<lb/>
The first expeditions could have introduced malaria. Similarly when<lb/>
a stop was made by an expedition containing malaria carriers long<lb/>
enough for the Anopheles at that place to become infective--usually<lb/>
about 11 days--further infections could be produced among them. (End<lb/>
of foot note).</p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<p>Compare this with Africa. Europeans visiting the<lb/>
West Coast of Africa--even the first visitors--came away with fevers,<lb/>
although the visit may have been very brief. No stay on any West<lb/>
African river comparable to Raleigh's on the Orinoco or Orellana's<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01134005"/>
-5-<lb/>
on the Amazon was possible without an enormous loss of life--<lb/>
possibly of the whole expedition judging from the loss from<lb/>
staying a shorter time. When in the voyage to America vessels<lb/>
stopped at West African ports, whether mainland or on the adja-<lb/>
cent islands, we find almost always, I recall no <hi>expressed</hi> exceptions,<lb/>
that they suffered from fevers during the remainder of the voyage before<lb/>
reaching America. Such was the case with Hawkins in 1567: with<lb/>
Drake and Carleisle in 1588 and with very many others.</p>
<p>COPY</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
