<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01133001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: A Review of the North Manchurian Plague Prevention Service Reports between 1918-1922, by H. Mcg. Robertson, [1922]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01133001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Manchuria</name>
<name type="place">Mongolia</name>
<name type="place">Siberia</name>
<name type="place">Russia</name>
<name type="place">Vladivostock (Russia)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-00-00">[1922]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01133001</idno>
<title>Report: A Review of the North Manchurian Plague Prevention Service Reports between 1918-1922, by H. Mcg. Robertson, [1922]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robertson reviews recent reports on plague prevention in northern China.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-00-00">
<head>Report: A Review of the North Manchurian Plague Prevention Service Reports between 1918-1922, by H. Mcg. Robertson, [1922]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01133001"/>
<p>Miss Plague</p>
<p>A Review of the North Manchurian Plague Prevention Service<lb/>
Reports (1918 - 1922)<lb/>
by<lb/>
H. McG. Robertson, Surgeon.</p>
<p>This interesting report is edited by Wu Lien Teh, M. A.,<lb/>
M. D., B.C. (Cantab), Director and Chief Medical Officer of the North<lb/>
Manchurian Plague Prevention Service, It seems that the province of<lb/>
Manchuria had been practically free from plague of any type from the<lb/>
time of the great pneumonic epidemic of 1910 and 1911 until the fall<lb/>
of 1920. However, in Mongolia and Siberia between the periods just<lb/>
mentioned plague had been reported present nearly every year. In 1911<lb/>
5 bubonic cases were reported at Scharasone; in 1912 3 pneumonic cases<lb/>
were reported in Chita; in 1913 some bubonic cases were reported in the<lb/>
Kirghiz Steppes; in 1914 there were 16 bubonic cases in Transbiakalia;<lb/>
in 1917 bubonic cases were recorded at Patsebelong in Mongolia, resulting<lb/>
in the Shansi outbreak (pneumonic) with 16000 deaths; in 1919 2 bubonic<lb/>
cases both fatal were reported at Ikievskaya. This brings the report<lb/>
down to the 1920 and 1921 pneumonic epidemic. It seems that in August<lb/>
<del>of this year</del><add>1920</add> there were 13 bubonic cases reported in Mongolia and Siberia<lb/>
near the Manchurian border and that later, in October and November, there<lb/>
were 8 bubonic cases found in Hailar, in northwestern Manchuria. Of<lb/>
these 8 cases 6 presented the buboes in the arm pit or about the neck and<lb/>
2 in the groin. In late November and to December 3, so called septic<lb/>
cases were reported in Hailar. The disease spread as the pneumonic form<lb/>
slowly, and during the winter caused 52 deaths in this city which has a<lb/>
population of 10,000 people. From Hailar the disease spread in epidomic<lb/>
form along the railways and other routes of travel in Manchuria as far<lb/>
south as Harbin and as far east as Vladivostock, although cases were<lb/>
reported still farther south in smaller numbers. In a population of<lb/>
20,000,000 persons in Manchuria there were 9300 deaths including 600<lb/>
Russians. The epidemic reached its height in February, 1921, and had<lb/>
practically subsided by May 15, although in Vladivostock there were 48<lb/>
deaths which occurred from pneumonic plague between June 15 and October 15.</p>
<p>It is gathered from this Report that practically all of the<lb/>
human cases of bubonic plague seen in Asiatic Russia and northern China<lb/>
are traceable to infection acquired through skinning the Siberian marmot<lb/>
for its fur.</p>
<p>The editor makes the following statement as to the evolution<lb/>
of this disease: &ldquo;During our stay at Hailar we noted a gradual evolution<lb/>
of the plague from the bubonic through the septicemic to the pneumonic<lb/>
form, due principally to promiscuous spitting and huddling together of<lb/>
coolies day and night in unvenitlated inns.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is interesting to note that while this pneumonic epidemic<lb/>
is accredited as resulting from the bubonic form, that in Vladivostock<lb/>
the bubonic form is reported at the end of this epidemic of 1921, there<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01133002"/>
-2-<lb/>
being reported one human bubonic case and 5 infected rats in July, and<lb/>
one human case and 2 infected rats on August 10. The occurrence of bubonic<lb/>
cases during the winter months while the pneumonic epidemic was in force<lb/>
was occasionally reported, though all but one of these are reported as<lb/>
doubtful. The one positive bubonic case reported resulted from an infected<lb/>
wound of the foot in one who presumably occupied quarters in which pneumonic<lb/>
plague had been found. It is noted in the bubonic cases reported in the<lb/>
beginning of this review that the dates of occurrence are not given except<lb/>
those which occurred in 1920. These are all in August, October and early<lb/>
November.</p>
<p>The author of this report, who was in charge of the preventive<lb/>
measures instituted in the epidemic of 1920 and 1921, has this to state in<lb/>
regard to therapeutic measures: &ldquo;No form of treatment was found of any<lb/>
avail&rdquo;. He given a list of drugs given and measures taken to effect a cure<lb/>
or amelioration but states: &ldquo;They did not cure the patients nor did they<lb/>
prolong life&rdquo;. It is evidently the opinion of Dr. Teh that the mortality<lb/>
of pneumonic plague is 100%. He says: &ldquo;the prognosis is well nigh hopeless,<lb/>


as no authentic case of pulmonary plague in either of the two great epidemics<lb/>
has been known to survive.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As an example of the number of patients sent to the plague<lb/>
hospital at Harbin who must not have had plague, if the mortality is 100%,<lb/>
it may be stated that of 227 cases only 178 were diagnosed as plague. Many<lb/>
persons were sent to the plague hospital during the epidemic as suspocted<lb/>
plague cases who upon observation were found to have some other disease, and<lb/>
it is interesting to note that few of these non-plague cases thus admitted<lb/>
to these hospitals developed the disease.</p>
<p>Pneumonic plague is rightly considered a disease which is highly<lb/>
infectious and under certain circumstances of poor ventilation, overcrowding<lb/>
and lack of proper precautionary measures it undoubtedly is. Yet the ex-<lb/>
perience of the Director of this Service would indicate that it need not<lb/>
necessarily be so.</p>
<p>The Director in comparing the experience of his own force of<lb/>
workers in Manchouli with that of the local workers in this place, says:<lb/>
&ldquo;The Russians had 5 doctors, six nurses and 15 sanitary attendants on<lb/>
their staff. Our Plague Service personnel consisted of three doctors and<lb/>
four nurses among others. On the Russian side there died of plague 3 nurses<lb/>
(one woman), 15 sanitary attendants and 1 police. We lostnone. The Russian<lb/>
Sanitary Staff was mostly untrained and very careless about wearing masks in<lb/>
the presence of the sick and dead. They smoked cigarettes while handling<lb/>
the dead, drank more alcohol than was good for them and many were struck<lb/>
down unnecessarily. It was a sad story.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He further says, &ldquo;The mortality among the sanitary squads was<lb/>
high, especially in Dalainor where it reached 50%, - the highest figure<lb/>
reached in the previous epidemic (1911). When comparing this high mortality<lb/>
among the sanitary coolies with the clear record of our dressers one must<lb/>
bear in mind the fact that the coolies were certainly more exposed to<lb/>
infection than the dressers. Moreover, the dressers were more aware of the<lb/>
danger and took care to follow the precautionary measures exactly.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01133003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>The practical measures given to prevent contracting the<lb/>
disease are these: wear a mask and hood when going into the presence<lb/>
of the sick (infection only comes through the nose and mouth; no antiseptics<lb/>
are necessary for the mask); rinse mouth with warm thymol water afterwards;<lb/>
rubber gloves, overalls, goggles and rubber boots are also to be worn and<lb/>
are to be discarded, along with the mask and hood, on leaving the sick room.</p>
<p>In speaking of the infective period the editor says: &ldquo;We can<lb/>
say without hesitation that as a rule there is a non-infective period of<lb/>
about 24 hours during which the patient has fever and quick pulse but no<lb/>
cough or bloody expectoration. This is the time when he may be moved to<lb/>
the hospital without danger to others.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In regard to the dead he says: &ldquo;Don't be afraid of dead bodies,<lb/>
for once the sick cease to breathe the bacilli cannot escape from the body.<lb/>
The danger from clothes of the newly dead is great&rdquo;. &ldquo;Such bodies should be<lb/>
covered with lime or sprayed with a disinfectant&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In speaking of the influenza epidemic in Harbin in the fall of<lb/>
1918 this report says: &ldquo;at least 10 to 20% of the population have been<lb/>
attacked this autumn&rdquo;. At this time Harbin must have had a population of<lb/>
about 275,000 as in 1921 there were 300,000 persons in the city. There were<lb/>
thus, at the least 27,000 cases of influenza in Harbin in the fall of 1918,<lb/>
while the epidemic of pneumonic plague in the winter of 1920-21 resulted in<lb/>
3125 deaths. The mortality is, of course, not comparable, but it is<lb/>
interesting to compare in this way the infectiousness of the two diseases.<lb/>
It may be said that the rapid spread of influenza and the almost total<lb/>
inability to determine the source of the infection in any outbreak is in<lb/>
strong contrast with the rather slow spread of pneumonic plague and the<lb/>
relative cease of locating the person who introduced it into a locality and<lb/>
his connection with some known focus of the disease. (Easy because the<lb/>
patient always dies)</p>
<p>This ability to determine the source of infection is shown in<lb/>
the following statements of the Director: &ldquo;the first case (in Tsitsihar)<lb/>
occurred in a petty shop assistant who escaped from Dalainor and lived in<lb/>
the house of a friend who was later affected and died&rdquo;; also, &ldquo;The first<lb/>
plague case in Harbin was recorded on January 22, when an ex-miner died<lb/>
suddenly in a house near the hospital after having arrived from Delainor<lb/>
the day before. In a small village four miles from the City another miner<lb/>
from Delainor died on January 26.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is stated in the chapter of this book which deals with the<lb/>
influenza epidemic, that in Harbin &ldquo;among Russians (exclusive of jews)<lb/>
eighty to ninety persons have died of influenza on its after effects from<lb/>
October 1 to November 10, 1918.&rdquo; From this it will be gathered that<lb/>
influenza did not need for its spread the marked overcrowding seen in<lb/>
the Chinese coolie population, which contributed so materially to tho<lb/>
spread of the pneumonic plague epidemic. In this plague epidemic only<lb/>
600 Russians died in the whole of Manchuria.</p>
<p>It remains to mention some laboratory experiments made as to<lb/>
the viability of the bacillus pestis under differing circumstances. This<lb/>
viability was tested by exposing the sputum under different conditions of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01133004"/>
2.4<lb/>
216<lb/>
<hi>32</hi><lb/>
-4-<lb/>
sunlight and temperature, and when exposed along in petri dishes, mixed with<lb/>
earth or exposed on various articles of furniture or clothing.</p>
<p>The outstanding observations along this line are probably not<lb/>
new. They are:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. that the bacillus pestis cannot be cultivated from dried sputum<lb/>
after 21 hours in diffused daylight if exposed on a petri dish<lb/>
at a temperature of 12 degrees C.=53.6&deg;F</item>
<item>2. in an unheated room, exposed to diffused daylight at a temper-<lb/>
ature of 3 degrees C. (37.4 degrees F.), cultures are found<lb/>
negative at the end of the 96 hours.</item>
<item>3. sputum exposed on gauze in the corner of a slightly heated room<lb/>
was sterile at the expiration of 96 hours.</item>
<item>4. sputum exposed <hi>on</hi> earth in shady corner of a slightly heated<lb/>
room was negative after 8 hours.</item>
<item>5. Sputum mixed with or covered by earth showed a &ldquo;few&rdquo; plague<lb/>
organisms at the end of 12 hours, at a laboratory temperature<lb/>
of 17 degrees centigrade. It is stated that these experiments<lb/>
were &ldquo;purposely discontinued&rdquo; at the end of 12 hours. It would<lb/>
be interesting to know if such earth would not have been entirely<lb/>
free from plague organisms at the end, say, of 96 hours. This<lb/>
might have given a rather good idea of the possible length of<lb/>
time that the floors of the Manchurian houses could retain the<lb/>
infection.</item>
</list></p>
<p>It may be mentioned that dry sputum in an icebox and in<lb/>
ice cellars (&ldquo;artificial cold&rdquo;) were negative only after 208 days.</p>
<p>Another experiment made by this service had to do with the<lb/>
length of time which plague might exist in a Siberian marmot, or<lb/>
tarabagan as they are called, under the condition of hibernation. It<lb/>
is stated in this report that in 1911 Dujardin-Beaumetz and Mosny<lb/>
inoculated 3 hibernating marmots with bacillus pestis. One of these died<lb/>
soon after; the two others survived for 61 and 115 days respectively,<lb/>
showing &ldquo;enormous numbers of plague bacilli in their organs&rdquo;. Others<lb/>
report similar results and this Service mentions one marmot dying after<lb/>
6 months. It is the opinion of the director that &ldquo;subacute or chronic<lb/>
plague may exist among the tarabagans (marmots) in Siberia and Mongolia<lb/>
and thus form a connecting link in the epidemiology of the disease&rdquo;. The<lb/>
Director states, in this connection, that the Indian Plague Commission had<lb/>
&ldquo;twice stated that the chronic (resolving) form of rat plague could not<lb/>
become acute&rdquo;.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01133005"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>Note.</p>
<p>In view of certain opinions expressed by me recently as to<lb/>
the reasons for the absence or practical absence in human beings, of<lb/>
bubonic plague in cold countries, I may be pardoned for making a<lb/>
personal comment on the subject considered in the last paragraph of<lb/>
this review. It seems to me that the Director of the Manchurian Plague<lb/>
Prevention Service and the Indian Plague Commission may both be right,<lb/>
their views being reconciled by the different habits of the rat and the<lb/>
Siberian marmot. The latter animal begins its hibernation in November and<lb/>
emerges in May, with possibly longer periods in this condition - depending<lb/>
upon the weather. It is the habit of the marmot to burrow deeply into<lb/>
the ground and carry into the depths of his retreat a quantity of dried<lb/>
grass. Upon going into winter quarters the entrance to the burrow is<lb/>
closed and the entire family - male, female and the summers brood -<lb/>
dispose themselves in a pile beneath the hay to pass away the winter<lb/>
months in a state of &ldquo;suspended animation&rdquo;. The rat does not hibernate<lb/>
nor does he lay up food for the winter months. It is thus necessary for<lb/>
him even in the cold season to be out in the open in search of food. In<lb/>
cold countries he will in this way lose his fleas and the next in which<lb/>
he sleeps will probably not be heavily infested if at all. There is also<lb/>
the probability that in an active animal only such lesions as chronic<lb/>
&ldquo;buboes&rdquo; can last for a period of any great length, the septicemic cases<lb/>
dying out in a relatively short time. Thus possibly the bacillus pestis<lb/>
is not in the circulating blood of this animal and the spread of the<lb/>
disease would be unlikely. In the marmot on the other hand we are told<lb/>
that at the end of several months &ldquo;enormous numbers of plague bacilli are<lb/>
found in the organs&rdquo;, in which case the bacilli will probably be in the<lb/>
peripheral circulation.</p>
<p>It is possible that the marmot takes with it into its winter<lb/>
burrow adult fleas. These may not only survive the winter but may<lb/>
multiply in the dried grass under which the hibernating animal has<lb/>
ensconsed itself. If this is so it is highly probable that a marmot which<lb/>
after several months of hibernation has &ldquo;enormous numbers of plague<lb/>
bacilli in its organs&rdquo;, and its fur possibly teeming with adult fleas<lb/>
can give rise in the &ldquo;summer colonies&rdquo; of these animals to an epidemic of<lb/>
bubonic plague and in this way perpetuate the disease from year to year.<lb/>
This could hardly happen in a rat population where the cold reduced the<lb/>
number of fleas below the number necessary to keep the disease alive (over<lb/>
this winter in Cool or Cold countries).</p>
<p>To one uninitiated into the deeper mysteries of bacteriology<lb/>
and into the possibilities of continuing infection in hibernating animals,<lb/>
it is hardly conceivable that the infecting organism would not die out<lb/>
or lose its virulence or that the infected animal would live thus for<lb/>
months with its organs teeming with plague bacilli. Yet such seems to be<lb/>
the case.</p>
<p>It would be interesting to note the temperature at the depth<lb/>
of the marmots' burrows in mid-winter and to ascertain if fleas are found<lb/>
on these animals when they emerge from their burrows at the end of the<lb/>
hibernating period; and if so to compare the number in the spring with the<lb/>
number found at the beginning of the hibernating period.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
