<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01137003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on the Williamson manuscript, by Henry Rose Carter, [1924]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01137003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Connor, M.E.</name>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="place">Coosa River (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Quantico (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Plymouth (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-00-00">[1924]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01137003</idno>
<title>Notes on the Williamson manuscript, by Henry Rose Carter, [1924]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter comments on Williamson's manuscript, entitled "The Use of Fish for Mosquito Control."</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-00-00">
<head>Notes on the Williamson manuscript, by Henry Rose Carter, [1924]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01137003"/>
<p>To accompany MSS on &ldquo;The Use of Fish for Mosquito Control&rdquo;</p>
<p>/LC</p>
<p>-1-</p>
<p><hi>Page 1: (1)</hi>-- As expressed: &ldquo;it is thought,&rdquo; this is correct, but it<lb/>
is becoming less and less held as observations increase.</p>
<p><hi>Page 1: (2)</hi>-- The <hi>time limit</hi> of the infectivity of man to Stegomyia<lb/>
is not certainly established as being 3 days: (See Noguchi and Carter):<lb/>
Might insert &ldquo;<hi>about</hi>&rdquo; before &ldquo;the first three days.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 1: (3)</hi>-- This is very true. The evidence to the contrary is<lb/>
necessarily negative and is, I think, of not sufficient mass to be con-<lb/>
vincing.</p>
<p><hi>Page 1: (4)</hi>-- Absolutely true and good. This meets the opposition of<lb/>
McGregor and a number of British (and some French) medical entomologists.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (5)</hi>--All the arguments, that I have seen, against the use of fish<lb/>
have been against their use in <hi>Anopheles control</hi> and your own argument,<lb/>
on the previous page, is for fish in Anopheles control. Why then quote<lb/>
Connor who has used them solely in Stegomyia control, in which the prob-<lb/>
lem is absolutely different from that of control of Anopheles by fish?</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (6)</hi>--Some species of Aedes (as in Saskatchewan: Minnesota<lb/>
etc.) oviposit <hi>far</hi> from water, but in depressions in the earth, which<lb/>
will be filled with water (from melting snow) in the early summer in<lb/>
which their eggs hatch. This is of no importance as the mosquitoes<lb/>
with which we are concerned, lay eggs either on water or at the water's<lb/>
edge.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (7)</hi>--I think that only the eggs of Anopheles have these<lb/>
&ldquo;floaters.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (8)</hi>-- This is, I think, true of a number--probably of all--<lb/>
of the genus Aedes. Bacot has hatched eggs of Stegomyia after more than<lb/>
eight months drying.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01137004"/>
<p>drying.</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (9)-</hi>-This is most true. Yet later on page 2 (12) surface feeding<lb/>
fish are specially recommended for containers <unclear>i,e,</unclear> for the control of <unclear>aegypt</unclear><lb/>
feeding the larvae of which mosquito is a <hi>bottom</hi> species</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (10)</hi>-- Small trash floating in masses, we have called it<lb/>
&ldquo;floatage.&rdquo; is as bad as aqueous vegetation. In my experience, the alga<lb/>
<hi>Spirogyra</hi>, binding floatage, or delicate floating vegetation (like <hi><unclear>Vallisneria</unclear><lb/>
<del>lerina</del> spiralis)</hi> together, or sometimes even by itself, is of all things<lb/>
the most efficient protection for Anopheles larvae against fish.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (11)</hi>-- This is most true--only in the U. S. we have no Ano-<lb/>
pheles which breeds in the <hi>swift part</hi> (the ripple) of a stream. The <hi>A.<lb/>
maculatus</hi> (the old <hi>Wilmori</hi>) in the Malay States breeds in swift water.</p>
<p>We have found no fish suitable to control stream-breeding in the U. S.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (12)</hi>-- Why a &ldquo;surface feeder&rdquo;? If used for Anopheles control,<lb/>
as in the underground cisterns and wells in Palestine, yes: But the use of<lb/>
fish in containers is especially for Stegomyia control. This is not a sur-<lb/>
face larva, like Anopheles, and a bottom-feeding fish would theoretically<lb/>
be the best. Certainly the fish named by Connor (the &ldquo;<hi>Mojarra</hi>&rdquo;) (Page 7 (X)):<lb/>
<add><unclear>Caldwett. p 7 (X) M.SS</unclear></add> Hanson (the &ldquo;<hi>Life</hi>&rdquo;) and Houle (the &ldquo;<hi>Chalaco</hi>&rdquo; and others) as being especial-<lb/>
ly suitable have been bottom-feeders. LePrince (Page 7. (L.P) a line <unclear>selected</unclear> a top<lb/>
<unclear>feeder</unclear> &ldquo;as likely to give the best results&rdquo;</p>
<p>Bottom-feeding fish too, are less apt to be dipped out of the contain-<lb/>
er or injured by the vessel used to dip water from it <add>than</add> those living on the<lb/>
top of the water. They are less affected by change of temperature (See<lb/>
Page 7 MSS). They would also be less snesitive to the absence of<lb/>
light--as was found to be the case at Merida (See Page 8 MSS).</p>
<p><hi>Page 2: (13)</hi>-- In some places sunfish are the only kind possible, as<lb/>
the game fish eat all kind not protected by spines <add>&amp; these to <unclear>some although a less-extent</unclear></add>. Except &ldquo;Pumpkin Seed,&rdquo;<lb/>
however, they have, in my experience, been failures, as the others draw<lb/>
too much water and hence do not go into the shallows or among weeds and<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01137005"/>
weeds and<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
floatage.</p>
<p><hi>Page 3: (X)</hi>--I applied to the Bureau of Fisheries in 1914 for Gambusia,<lb/>
or other larviporous fish, for use in the Pool of Lock No. 12, Coosa River,<lb/>
Alabama. They had none and stated that there was no appropriation for<lb/>
hatcheries for any save game fish. The need of hatcheries whence such<lb/>
fish could be procured was taken up by a number of prominent business men,<lb/>
interested in such pools, in Alabama: Georgia and North Carolina and in<lb/>
1915 I was notified that such hatcheries were started at Edenton, N. C.<lb/>
and Palestine, Texas.</p>
<p><hi>Page 5: (14)-</hi>- In the large bodies of water impounded for power,<lb/>
collections of floating trash (what we have called &ldquo;floatage&rdquo;), especially<lb/>
if associated with the alga <hi>Spirogyra,</hi> have been found more efficient in<lb/>
protecting Anopheles larvae than vegetation. Certainly in recent ponds.<lb/>
Larvae have not been found in other kinds of algae and only with <hi>Spirogyra</hi><lb/>
when it is alive. Some kind of alga--a dense blue-green plant--has at<lb/>
times so completely covered the water--like a blanket--that no larvae<lb/>
could live on, or in, it. No larvae are found in <add>recently</add> dead or dying algae.</p>
<p><hi>Page 5: (Y)</hi>-- This man's name is Parker, not Park.</p>
<p><hi>Page 7: (15) and Page 8: (16)</hi>-- Soap--a solution of soft soap in al-<lb/>
chohol--proved 100% efficacious in Peru (Piura and Paita) and either Con-<lb/>
nor or Scannell reported the same from Mexico last spring. Laundresses<lb/>
<hi>like</hi> this to be added. They forget to replace copper only too often;<lb/>
(Scannell or Connor). Soap-powder would do as well as the solution.</p>
<p><hi>Page 8: (17)</hi>-- Hanson says that his favorite, the &ldquo;<hi>Life,</hi>&rdquo; feeds at<lb/>
the bottom during the day and on the surface at night. May fear light.</p>
<p><hi>Page 8: (18)</hi>-- Have seen Gambusia, in the U. S., eat Anopheles lar-<lb/>
vae within 12 hours of birth by Ceasarian section.</p>
<p><hi>Page 8: (19)</hi>-- <hi>&ldquo;Chata&rdquo;</hi> is said to both a top and bottom-feeder--like<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01137006"/>
like<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
Hanson's &ldquo;<hi>life</hi>.&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>Chalaco</hi>&rdquo; is a bottom-feeder.</p>
<p><hi>Page 9: (20)</hi>-- Were Stegomyia breeding in these streams and ditches?<lb/>
Connor told me he confined his work to water in artificial containers, as<lb/>
he found Stegomyia larvae nowhere else.</p>
<p><hi>Page 10: (21)</hi>--Fish were not used in Cuba in the <hi>first</hi> campaign a-<lb/>
gainst Stegomyia (1901), but they were so used there tentatively, in<lb/>
that of 1905 and intensively, by McMillan, in 1908 in Camaguey.</p>
<p><hi>Page 10: (22)</hi>-- Absolutely true wherever proper fish are available.</p>
<p><hi>Page 11: (23)</hi>-- The <hi>Life</hi>, especially favored of Hanson, is a species<lb/>
of cat-fish (Eigenmann).</p>
<p>Page 11: (24)--Of all vegetation in the U. S., the alga <hi>Spirogyra</hi> is,<lb/>
in my experience, the worst. In no other kind of alga have I ever found<lb/>
Anopheles larvae. &ldquo;Floatage&rdquo; (i. e. small trash floating in masses) is<lb/>
as bad as vegetation. When vegetation hanging over--or floating on or<lb/>
just under--the surface of the water, is covered with fine floatage and<lb/>
bound together with <hi>spirogyra,</hi> it is the worst possible--as was the case<lb/>
at Quantico, Va., in 1917 &amp; '18, with <hi>Vallisneria spiralis</hi> (wild celery)<lb/>
for the vegetation.</p>
<p><hi>Gambusia</hi> will, however, work their way in among both vegetation and<lb/>
floatage to a considerable extent and even into clumps of <hi>Spirogyra,</hi> if<lb/>
they are loose enough. They even occasionally have jumped into the boat-<lb/>
like lotus pads holding water. The above combination of vegetation:<lb/>
floatage and alga, however, was too much for them.</p>
<p><hi>Page 12: (25)</hi>-- Considering how close Barbadoes is to Trinidad and the<lb/>
Main, it would seem perfectly possible that Anopheles <hi>imagos</hi> might be in-<lb/>
troduced by vessel, but this genus, unlike Stegomyia and <hi>C. fatigans</hi>,<lb/>
is not much of a sea-farer. It had not been found in Hawaii up to 1912.</p>
<p><hi>Page 12: (26)</hi>-- It is worth noting that there being no Anopheles in<lb/>
Hawaii, the fish control is used only against Stegomyia and some species of<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01137007"/>
of<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
<hi>Culex</hi>--especially <hi>quinquefasciatus</hi> (<hi>fatigans</hi>).</p>
<p><hi>Page 13: (27)</hi>-- How can one clear a swamp of vegetation and debris<lb/>
without converting it into something else than a swamp? Many fish (as<lb/>
<hi>Gambusia affinis</hi>, in the U. S.) will give a good percentage of control--<lb/>
not 100%, however, in the presence of considerable vegetation, if there<lb/>
be enough of them.</p>
<p><hi>Page 15: (27 1/2)</hi>-- This is common of the half-dead lotus leaves<lb/>
around Quantico, Va., and Plymouth, N. C. They float high and are like<lb/>
boats. They hold water on their upper surface, hence give perfect protect-<lb/>
ion to larvae in such water: yet they occasionally hold <hi>Gambusia,</hi> which<lb/>
must have jumped in.</p>
<p><hi>Page 16: (28)</hi>-- There are laws in Italy against the culture of rice<lb/>
withing certain distances of a town or village: the distance varying as<lb/>
the <hi>size</hi> of the town up to a certain limit (Celli).</p>
<p>The same has been true in South Spain from the Xlllth. Century--the<lb/>
limit being three miles from the centre of the plaza. This, however--<lb/>
a decree of Don Martin of Aragon--was from a religious motive--&ldquo;only the<lb/>
Infidels ate this malificent grain.&rdquo; (Vi<add>l</add>lalba)</p>
<p><hi>Page 17: (28')</hi>-- This paper of Dubois was extremely interesting, but<lb/>
elvers (as young eels are called) are rarely seen in this hemisphere in<lb/>
sufficient numbers for use and, very obviously, they cannot be bred arti-<lb/>
ficially. I judge that their use is confined to Western Europe.</p>
<p><hi>Page 19: (29)</hi>--This is true for Anopheles control. The fish most<lb/>
suitable for Stegomyia control (i. e. for water in containers) in the<lb/>
U. S. has not been worked out. I think, however, that <hi>Gambusia affinis</hi><lb/>
or <hi>Fundulus notatus</hi>--the latter an extremely tough fish--would do fairly<lb/>
well, although both are top-feeders and probably a better (bottom-feeder)<lb/>
could be found.</p>
<p>Nor have we yet found found a satisfactory fish--for the control<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01137008"/>
control<lb/>
-6-<lb/>
of Anopheles in fairly swift streams in the U. S.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (30)</hi>-- In the large bodies of water, impounded for power or<lb/>
for improvement of navigation, some of which cover from 6,000 to 10,000<lb/>
acres, top-minnows have been found <hi>extremely</hi> efficient in preventing the<lb/>
production of Anopheles, when proper measures have been taken to enable<lb/>
them to have access to such larvae. This is done most practically by oc-<lb/>
casionally lowering the pond so as to leave all floatage etc. stranded on<lb/>
the bank above water--so that a clean water's edge, with no protection<lb/>
for larvae, is presented to the fish. A high percentage of efficiency by<lb/>
fish control is thus secured.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (31)</hi>-- This is very true. What you say of shallow edges--<lb/>
which, indeed, generally obtain--is true for all kind of Anopheles: The<lb/>
pollution by chemicals, so far as I have observed, applies only to <hi>A. cru-<lb/>
cians</hi>, which will breed in water too acid for fish. I do not think that<lb/>
<hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi> or <hi>A. punctipennis</hi> will.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (32)</hi>-- Some fish (as <hi>Gambusia</hi> and <hi>Fundulus</hi>) will work into a<lb/>
fairly dense growth of vegetation or floatage and give a good percentage<lb/>
of control. Much depends on the nature of the vegetation: Plants with<lb/>
single, stiff stems at the water's surface offer little obstruction to fish<lb/>
control--unless they be extremely close together (like a bunch of bulrushes).<lb/>
Plants with flexible stems much longer than the depth of the water, the<lb/>
tops of which float on, or just under, the surface as a dense mat, may<lb/>
give <hi>absolute</hi> protection. The worst that I have seen is the wild celery<lb/>
<hi>(Vallisneria spiralis</hi>) as it occurs in some bights of the Potomac, and<lb/>
Naialis flexibilis <add>in ponds</add> in North Alabama <add>is also bad.</add> The ordinary water-lily rarely<lb/>
gives much protection: while the dying pads of the American lotus hold<lb/>
water in the cavity of their upper surface like boats and thus protect<lb/>
larvae.<lb/>
The <unclear>Silnuleaf gross Hydrochloa carolin</unclear> in <add><unclear>Ponds in</unclear></add> Georgia and South<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01137009"/>
South<lb/>
-7-<lb/>
Carolina is also bad, but less so than these two. The Burr Reed, <add><unclear>Sparganium Americanus</unclear></add> found<lb/>
near Birmingham, Ala. and in the S. W. part of Virginia (east of the Blue<lb/>
Ridge) spite of its <add>stiff</add> straight stems, is <add>very</add> bad <add>for a short time</add>. The seed--much like those of<lb/>
the wild garlic--fall in the water in September <add>&amp; October</add> and spread out as a float-<lb/>
ing mucilaginous mass, catching all kinds of small floatage and specks of<lb/>
alga, which grow well on it, and furnishes a perfect protection for larvae<lb/>
against fish.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (33)</hi>-- My experience has been that the breeding in the tracks<lb/>
of the cattle about the edges of the pond <hi>much</hi> overbalances the good they<lb/>
do in keeping vegetation down about the edges of the pond and, naturally,<lb/>
they have no effect on the trash on the pond, which also protects larvae.<lb/>
On the Canal Zone they were (and are now) regarded as doing only harm.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (34)</hi>-- All of this is extremely good.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20: (35)</hi>--Were these Anopheles larvae? They (<hi>A.</hi> larvae) are<lb/>
usually killed directly by the contact with the oil, not by drowning.<lb/>
Stegomyia larvae will live in cheese-cloth bags over 24 hours under water.<lb/>
I have tried them.</p>
<p>I agree that really efficient oiling is frequently difficult, and at<lb/>
times well nigh impossible. It is at best a temporary thing--a make-shift.<lb/>
Against Anopheles. Paris green is very much better? Cheaper &amp; <unclear>more</unclear> generally <unclear>efficacious</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Page 21: (36)</hi>-- Once in 12 or 14 days is generally often enough to<lb/>
apply oil--whether there is wind or rain--if it be thoroughly done. If<lb/>
thus applied, it will kill all eggs: larvae and pupae and while it may be<lb/>
gone entirely within 4 or 6 hours and the place may show breeding again<lb/>
within a few days, yet there will be no production of imagos for--say--<lb/>
14 to 16 days. The aquatic forms <add>of Anopheles</add> do no harm. We do not try to prevent<lb/>
<hi>breeding</hi>, only <hi>the production of the winged insect</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Page 21: (37)</hi>-- I doubt if the size of the pond is an absolute deterrent.<lb/>
Saw good results on the Wateree Pond (S. C.) of, I think, 8,000 acres.</p>
<p><hi>Page 21: (38)</hi>-- Even if some larvae escape, we may thus get a good per-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01137010"/>
per-<lb/>
-8-<lb/>
centage of control--say 80% to 90%.</p>
<p><hi>Page 21: (39)</hi>-- Not only vegetation (in which, I presume, algae are in-<lb/>
cluded) but &ldquo;floatage&rdquo; on the pond as well, must be cared for.</p>
<p>Page 21: (40)--For Anopheles control, yes, top-feeders by all means: for<lb/>
Stegomyia control--<hi>probably</hi> not.</p>
<p><hi>Page 21: (41)</hi>-- As true as Gospel.</p>
<p>End.</p>
<p>H. R. Carter</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
