<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01139003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, February 5, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01139003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-02-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-02-05">February 5, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01139003</idno>
<title>Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, February 5, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fricks details his malaria investigation in the southern United States.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-02-05">
<head>Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, February 5, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01139003"/>
<opener>
Mal<lb/>
Report<lb/>
<dateline>
Headquarters:<lb/>
Field Investigations of Malaria,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Room 17, Court House,<lb/>
Memphis, Tenn.<lb/>
----<lb/>
<date value="1924-02-05">February 5, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
Monthly Progress Report,<lb/>
<hi>January 1923.</hi><lb/>
The Surgeon-General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Division of Scientific Research,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to forward herewith monthly progress report<lb/>
of malaria investigations conducted during the month of January,<lb/>
1924, under the direction of this office.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Crowley, Louisiana:</hi> Personnel - Special Expert<lb/>
M. A. Barber, Asst. San. Eng. W. H. W. Komp and Asst. San. Eng.<lb/>
J. G. Foster.</p>
<p>Dr. Barber completed special observations of malaria in Central<lb/>
American ports early in January, returning to Crowley January 12th.<lb/>
Activities at Crowley Laboratory consisted of: (1) Preparation<lb/>
of papers and reports; (2) Identification of mosquito specimens<lb/>
collected in Central America; (3) Inspection of salt marsh Week's<lb/>
Island, Louisiana, January 29th, where a few A. Crucians were<lb/>
found flying; (4) Mosquitoes collected in image stage, A. quadrimac-<lb/>
ulatus 11, A. crucians 20; adults and larvae much less numerous<lb/>
than during January 1923; (5) 177 blood specimens examined for<lb/>
malaria parasites; of 62 smears collected locally 3 were found<lb/>
positive.</p>
<p><hi>Memphis Laboratory:</hi> Personnel - A.A. Surgeon Wm. A. <unclear>Eraues</unclear>, Micros-<lb/>
copists Ethel Barrier and Retha Kitchens.</p>
<p>633 blood smears examined for malaria parasites. 72 smears col-<lb/>
lected locally showed 4 positives; 203 smears from Tunica, Miss.<lb/>
showed 35 P. falc., 4 P. vivax; 115 smears from Stuttgart, Ark.,<lb/>
showed 8 P. falc., 10 P. vivax; 100 smears from Greenwood, Miss.<lb/>
showed 3 P. falc., 2 P. vivax; 143 smears from Gulfport, Miss.<lb/>
showed 7 P. falc.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Savannah, Ga</hi>.: Personnel - Technical Assistant<lb/>
Bruce Mayne.</p>
<p>Mr. Mayne conducted a study of the winter habits of Anopheles in<lb/>
this region to determine primarily in what stage and under what<lb/>
conditions Anopheles over winter. Anopheline larvae were frequent-<lb/>
ly found in bottom mud of ice-covered streams, no pupae encountered.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01139004"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
February 5, 1924.<lb/>
under these conditions until last week of January, in every in-<lb/>
stance these proved to be A. crucians. Not more than six adult<lb/>
mosquitoes were found hibernating after careful search in fav-<lb/>
orable localities. Mr. Mayne concludes, that for <unclear>Che</unclear> tham Coun-<lb/>
ty Georgia in all probability Anopheles overwinter commonly in<lb/>
the aquatic forms and not in the imago stage. Two specimens of<lb/>
adult A. punctpennis were collected in January, the first en-<lb/>
countered since July 1923. 34 blood specimens collected locally<lb/>
were examined, all negative for malaria parasites.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemiological Studies of Malaria: Personnel</hi> - Asst. Surgeon K.F.<lb/>
Maxcy.</p>
<p>During the month a spot map was prepared, showing locations from<lb/>
which positive malaria slides were sent in for examination by pub-<lb/>
lic health laboratories in the state: Case reports of malaria in<lb/>
Alabama for 1923 were tabulated according to counties and nearest<lb/>
town, this data is being put on a spot map. Dr. Maxcy spent con-<lb/>
siderable time in the preparation of a paper dealing with the<lb/>
&ldquo;Epidemiological Principles Affecting the distribution of Malar-<lb/>
ia in the southern United States&rdquo;.</p>
<p><hi>Impounded Waters in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Epidemiologist T.H.D.<lb/>
Griffitts and Asst. San. Eng. E. H. Gage.</p>
<p>Dr. Griffitts engaged in making mosquito surveys in and around<lb/>
Tampa, Florida. No impounded water studies made in Alabama.</p>
<p>Inspections of ponds in Aiken County South Carolina by Mr. Gage<lb/>
yielded moderate number of anopheline larvae, all sizes, and one<lb/>
pupa; non-anopheline larvae were found in shallow ponds, but no<lb/>
anopheline larvae noted there; water temperature at time of col-<lb/>
lections varied between 45 and 50 degrees F.; the pupa collected<lb/>
emerged, after being kept at room temperature for 48 hours, as a<lb/>
female A. crucians.</p>
<p><hi>Major Drainage in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Assoc. San.<lb/>
Eng. A. W. Fuchs.</p>
<p>Mr. Fucha made analysis of data obtained by malaria survey of<lb/>
school children and from census card distribution, covering res-<lb/>
idents of McKinney Lake Drainage District in Tunica County, Miss.:<lb/>
224 blood smears collected from school children showed 17.2% posi-<lb/>
tive; spleen rate of same children 18.7% positive; spleen and<lb/>
blood combined 29% positive; history rate for 1923 46% positive;<lb/>
the blood rate among white children was 7.4% positive, among<lb/>
colored children <unclear>19.2%</unclear>.</p>
<p><hi>Rural Malaria Investigations:</hi> Personnel - Asst. San. Eng. J. C.<lb/>
Carter, A.A. Surgeon C.P. Coogle, Assoc. San. Eng. L.M. Fisher,<lb/>
Asst. San. Eng. H.N. Old, Asst. San. Eng. F.R. Shaw, Surgeon L.L.<lb/>
Williams.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01139005"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>February 5, 1924.</p>
<p>Mr. Carter (Alabama): Mr. Carter visited Lowndes, Butler, Conceuh,<lb/>
Monroe, Escambia, Clark and Baldwin Counties for the purpose of se-<lb/>
lecting these localities which have serious malaria problems, and<lb/>
outlining a program of malaria control for each.</p>
<p>Mr. Old (Georgia): Mr. Old spent the first half of the month search-<lb/>
ing for hibernating anopheline mosquitoes, only three adults found,<lb/>
2 A. punctipennis and 1 A. crucians; last half of the month spent<lb/>
in making malaria school surveys with Dr. Coogle.</p>
<p>Mr. Shaw (Louisiana): Mr. Shaw gave malaria talks and showed parish<lb/>
malaria exhibit to children of six rural schools in Tangipahoa Par-<lb/>
ish; study made of winter habits of Anopheles in this locality; Hib-<lb/>
ernating imagoes of A. Punctipennis, A. quadrimaculatus <del><unclear></unclear></del> and A.<lb/>
crucians found in out-houses, A. quadrimaculatus most abundant, 6 to<lb/>
1 of each of the others; half grown Anopheles larvae found active<lb/>
on January 11th, following five days of unusually cold weather, dur-<lb/>
ing which the thermometer reached 10 degrees F. on January 6th. Pre-<lb/>
liminary survey made of St. Mary's Parish.</p>
<p>Mr. Fisher (South Carolina): Study of malaria distribution in<lb/>
South Carolina continued by means of school census cards; malaria<lb/>
census cards mailed to all school children in six counties; the<lb/>
data collected from Charleston County indicates that from a pop-<lb/>
ulation of 3.987, 14.4% had malaria in 1923; this same method in-<lb/>
dicated 15% history index for Orangeburg County.</p>
<p>L. L. Williams (Virginia): Study of control of mosquito production<lb/>
by means of raising and lowering water level alone being conducted<lb/>
by Dr. Williams in five ponds in James City County.</p>
<p>Dr. Google continued malaria school surveys in Florida, Georgia<lb/>
and South Carolina; 1243 school children examined for enlarged<lb/>
spleens, Florida 626, Georgia 573, South Carolina 44; 696 blood<lb/>
smears collected for examination, Florida 104, Georgia 548, South<lb/>
Carolina 44.</p>
<p><hi>Conferences and Inspections</hi>: No malaria conferences nor inspections<lb/>
made from headquarters during January. Mr. LePrince and the Medi-<lb/>
cal Officer in Charge engaged in preparing program for 1924 malaria<lb/>
field investigations and conducting routine administrative duties.</p>
<p><hi>Expenditures:</hi> During the month approximately $3,821.77 was expend-<lb/>
ed from the Malaria Allotment in connection with field investiga-<lb/>
tions of malaria.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>L. D. Fricks, Surgeon,<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
