<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01138008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Joseph H. White to Frederick F. Russell, January 8, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>White, Joseph H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01138008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-01-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Russell, Fredrick F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Walcott, Alan</name>
<name type="place">Bahia (Brazil)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-01-08">January 8, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01138008</idno>
<title>Letter from Joseph H. White to Frederick F. Russell, January 8, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>White writes about his field work to control the spread of yellow fever in Brazil.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-01-08">
<head>Letter from Joseph H. White to Frederick F. Russell, January 8, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01138008"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
<dateline>
DEPARTAMENTO DE SA&Uacute;DE PUBLICA<lb/>
BAHIA, BRASIL<lb/>
<date value="1924-01-08">January 8, 1924</date>
</dateline>
COPY<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You will be interested to know that the work here is progressing at a<lb/>
very satisfactory rate, despite propaganda, and that the people are apparently<lb/>
entirely satisfied. In many instances they ask for fish (of course they are<lb/>
given) and I think the anti-fish campaign will die a natural death in a few<lb/>
weeks more.</p>
<p>We found yellow fever for Noguchi in the village of Bella Palmyra<lb/>
west of here one day by rail and then by mule and altho it is not necessary<lb/>
I have sent a man, Dr. Studart, out there, to please the Brazilians and he<lb/>
can temporize with it until it dies out - I doubt if he does much more than that.</p>
<p>It probably got there from Lincon just above the rail head and Lincon<lb/>
was infected from Bahia last summer and I understand has now smoldered out or<lb/>
nearly so. Lincon has 10,000 and Bella Palmyra 3,000 inhabitants.</p>
<p>Of course we will probably meet a dozen or so of such temporary and<lb/>
localized flares and I am sorry to say that here as in Mexico they seem to<lb/>
cause more consternation than the big cities.</p>
<p>Scannell starts soon for a trip up to Para and intermediate points<lb/>
while I stay here and I think he will leave Ormachia at Pernambuco as I am<lb/>
doubtful about the capacity of Walcott to get his machine well organized and<lb/>
moving strongly and smoothly at the same time. He gets the good will of the<lb/>
local men but we need much more than that so in as much as Pernambuco is a<lb/>
large center I am justified in putting in an extra man (a tremendous worker)<lb/>
without having to explain anything.</p>
<p>I shall later cover the whole circuit myself but just now, feel that<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01138009"/>
-2-<lb/>
this place must be very carefully held - not from the mosquito standpoint, but<lb/>
the standpoint of medical politics, of which there is plenty.</p>
<p>Noguchi has gotten his new strain and was adroit enough to have a Bra-<lb/>
ailian find it first, then demonstrate to all the Professors in the local medical<lb/>
school.</p>
<p>He now says he can't finish here and go to Pernambuco before February<lb/>
21, in which case I told him he probably would find nothing there and would just<lb/>
as well go on to Ceara to get the data he wants and thence to Para where he can<lb/>
get the Booth Line to N.Y.</p>
<p>I hope Chagas comes up on 16th with Dr. Frazu, the Bahia congressman<lb/>
on whom he (Chagas) is relying to straighten out matters here. They need no at-<lb/>
tention now as since he would not come we have helped ourselves and he will on<lb/>
arrival find nothing to do but to open his eyes and see for himself that the work<lb/>
is done - well done, and the people content. That sort of thing is so unusual<lb/>
here that he will find it hard to believe.</p>
<p>We simply sat steady, never answered a word of criticism, were courteous<lb/>
to all, redoubled our precautions and won the people to our side.</p>
<p>Finally our sharpost critic, Prof. Valladam, comes out and says that<lb/>
while he &ldquo;never wanted the Yankees here because Brazilians are able (?) and will-<lb/>
ing (?) to help themselves, they should be treated courteously and respectfully<lb/>
hecause the man who thinks these Yankees don't know their business most thoraly,<lb/>
is a fool.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We are still running about 7% and the larvae met are 90% stegs.</p>
<p>I am beginning to suspect that this is the place that re-infected Africa<lb/>
(4 days away) was she ever was clean, and I want to make some maps and study my<lb/>
data with great care - but that is another story and subject matter for another<lb/>
letter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) J. H. White</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
