<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01138021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Frederick F. Russell, January 20, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01138021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-01-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Russell, Frederick F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Read, Florence M.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">British Guiana</name>
<name type="place">French Guiana</name>
<name type="place">Curacao</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-01-20">January 20, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01138021</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Frederick F. Russell, January 20, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] responds to a report on yellow fever outbreaks in the Guianas.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-01-20">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to Frederick F. Russell, January 20, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01138021"/>
<opener>
Surinam -- quoted by Corre<lb/>
1863- 6 or 9?<lb/>
Date of Maxcys paper?<lb/>
I. H. B.<lb/>
/LC<lb/>
Epidemiology (the)<lb/>
of<lb/>
Yellow Fever<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1924-01-20">January 20, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am in receipt of the letters and reports relative to fever<lb/>
in the British Guianas, forwarded me by Miss Read on January 5th.,<lb/>
and would thank you for the same--especially for the report by<lb/>
Flu. This is extremely good and instructive--as, indeed, have<lb/>
been all the papers that I have seen by him: above all his experi-<lb/>
ments with <hi>aegypti</hi> mosquitoes in refrigerator ships.</p>
<p>No criticism or report on these letters is called for, and yet<lb/>
there are one or two things in them to which I would invite your<lb/>
attention:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1/ On Page 2 of Dr. Muensch's letter he quotes Dr. Blin,<lb/>
Surgeon General of Cayenne, for there having been no yellow fever<lb/>
in French Guiana since 1902. This, of course, may be correct,<lb/>
but in 1916 <add>- on the trip of the Y. F. Commission-</add> both Guiteras and myself carried copies of the U. S.<lb/>
Public Health Reports stating that there had been &ldquo;----cases:<lb/>
----deaths&rdquo; from yellow fever at <hi>Maroni</hi> in French Guiana, occurring<lb/>
the earlier part of that year or the latter part of 1915. Of<lb/>
course, I don't guarantee the diagnosis, but yellow fever was re-<lb/>
ported. Maroni is in the extreme north-western part of French Gui-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01138022"/>
Gui-<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
ana, close to the Dutch.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Corre quotes Bajon that yellow fever was introduced into French<lb/>
Fuiana in 1763, lasting to 1769, and Augustin quotes the same author,<lb/>
and Campet, that it caused 1,143 deaths out of 2,361 Europeans in 1764,<lb/>
Into Georgetown in the latter part of the XVlllth. Century--I could find<lb/>
the exact date in my notes if worth while: Into Dutch Guiana (Surinam)<lb/>
1760, according to, quoted by Corre.</p>
<p>British Guiana ceased to be a, more or less, permanent focus in the<lb/>
latter quarter of the XlXth. Century, following--and probably on account<lb/>
of--the introduction of water in pipes.<add>-see Boyce</add></p>
<p>It is reasonably sure that all of these places had earlier intro-<lb/>
ductions of yellow fever. They could hardly have escaped the wide-spread<lb/>
&ldquo;Epidemic of the Oriflamme&rdquo; of 1690-'70, unless they had no <hi>aegypti</hi> at<lb/>
that time.</p>
<p>With regard to that in Surinam (Dutch Guiana) I know much less.<lb/>
There are reports in the latter part of the XVlllth. Century of its<lb/>
occurring in Curacao and the mainland. It was, however, regarded as<lb/>
an intense marsh poison and Moncey (Dutch Naval Surgeon) writing from<lb/>
Curacao quotes, with his approbation &ldquo;the judicious Pringle&rdquo; (Sir John<lb/>
Pringle, Chief Surgeon of the British Admiralty in these waters) to the<lb/>
effect that there was no difference--save in intensity and the tempera-<lb/>
ment of the patient--between the yellow fever; the marsh fevers; dysen-<lb/>
teries and <hi>scurvy</hi>! Unless then we can make the diagnosis from the des-<lb/>
cription given there is little use in investigating any <add>what may have been called</add> yellow fever in<lb/>
the Guianas prior to Blair (1836 or '37), who was really a great epidem-<lb/>
iologist.</p>
<p>With regard to Dr. Blin on the relation between the <hi>fievre bilieuse<lb/>
inflammatoire</hi>--as doubtless you know--Guiteras and myself had been de-<lb/>
tailed in 1917 to investigate this and other things in the French An-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01138023"/>
An-<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
tilles and <add>(<unclear>le fiebre naya</unclear>)</add> in the Maracaibo: Cucuta and Coro region in Venezuela. The<lb/>
War prevented this, but there is no doubt that this diagnosis is a kind<lb/>
of omnium gatherum in French Latin America: It includes mild cases of<lb/>
yellow fever, when yellow fever is present: dengue when dengue is pres-<lb/>
ent: malarial fever, where blood examination is not made or recurrent<lb/>
attacks do not do not make that diagnosis obligatory: <hi>embarras gastrique</hi>;<lb/>
slight attacks of the sun among the newly arrived and any other acute<lb/>
febrile attack which is not definitely something else. Thus, when it<lb/>
<hi>was</hi> yellow fever it protected against yellow fever. Some cases clearly<lb/>
did not, as witness a batallion (Corre) of 200 men raised in Martinique<lb/>
and Guadeloupe in 1864, and supposed to be acclimatized by this fever,<lb/>
198 of whom died of yellow fever in Vera Cruz: One had deserted and the<lb/>
survivor was &ldquo;disbanded&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>par merci</hi>.&rdquo;</p>
<p>One other thing: The over-lapping of dates alluded to by Dr.<lb/>
Muensch (Page 3 of his report) simply implies that the three Guianas<lb/>
plus the adjacent island had been a regional focus, some--maybe more<lb/>
than one--part of which had been always infected and some always not in-<lb/>
fected.</p>
<p>If the statement made by Flu is true--that the population is im-<lb/>
munized after residence for a few years without the apparent presence of<lb/>
yellow fever, we will have to admit that yellow fever was present in<lb/>
such population sufficiently often for all--or practically all--of them<lb/>
to have had the disease within the limits of residence found protective.<lb/>
I can't think that any modern sanitarian is willing to go back to the<lb/>
old idea of <hi>Mithridatism</hi> as a mechanism for Creole immunity. To quote<lb/>
myself--which one should rarely do: &ldquo;The <hi>visible</hi> links in the chain of<lb/>
infections in a mixed black and white community--the blacks being in<lb/>
large majority--should thus occur among the whites--generally newly ar-<lb/>
rived whites. These visible links are not generally joined with each<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01138024"/>
each<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
other, but have, it maybe, between them a considerable number of invis-<lb/>
ible links--the unrecongized infections in the blacks (especially<lb/>
in the black children).&rdquo; It is, however, we believe, a continuous<lb/>
chain from one little out-break to another through these unrecogniz-<lb/>
ed infections.</p>
<p>There are two fundamental errors--which seem to me very im-<lb/>
portant ones--in the present French epidemiology of yellow fever and<lb/>
which appear to be generally held in Latin America:--<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1/ The one that has come down to us from old times that yel-<lb/>
low fever is a mysterious disease developed from the soil and cli-<lb/>
matic conditions (&ldquo;telluric emanation&rdquo;), to which one living in a<lb/>
place where it is endemic, from the gradual empoisonment occurring<lb/>
there acquires an immunity to the disease; which immunity will be<lb/>
lost certainly by a prolonged or even moderate residence in a<lb/>
place where it is <hi>not</hi> endemic or, according to some, even by moving<lb/>
<add>In 1899 &amp; 1900 the <unclear>Havanas</unclear> beleived that they would contract y.f. in Vera Cruz &amp; Vice Versa Beranger Fernaud <unclear>(around 1875) preached the same</unclear> doctrine<lb/>
of <unclear>Negrians</unclear> changing their residence in W. Africa</add><lb/>
from this endemic focus to another. This is the old &ldquo;Mithridatism&rdquo;<lb/>
(the origin of the term is easily seen) which I thought had been<lb/>
entirely set to rest by the work of Chaille and Guiteras, ably sup-<lb/>
plemented by some of the French writers from St. Pierre.</item>
<item>2/ The absolute acceptance of the dictum of the Commission<lb/>
of the Pasteur Institute, working at Rio (1903-'04) (or rather of<lb/>
Simond and <unclear>Salembini</unclear>, for Marchoux had left them before this was<lb/>
put out): viz--<lb/>
&ldquo;That the disease is continued in endemic areas by recurrent<lb/>
attacks among the indigenes.&rdquo; There is a further statement as-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01138025"/>
as-<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
serting the common existence of carriers--the man not being sick of<lb/>
the disease although infected with it.</item>
</list></p>
<p>For neither of these beliefs did these gentlemen advance one<lb/>
single observation nor--so far as I know--has any ever been advanc-<lb/>
ed, save by Seidelin, who regarded the presence of his <hi>Paraplasma<lb/>
flavigenum</hi> as proof of infection with yellow fever.</p>
<p>There is much loose data to the contrary of the statement<lb/>
given in &ldquo; &rdquo; in the experience and writings of men familiar with<lb/>
this disease, although the only systematic argument against it is, I<lb/>
think, that on &ldquo;Immunity to Yellow Fever,&rdquo; Journal of Tropical Medi-<lb/>
cine and Parisitoloty, April, 1916, a copy of which you have. This<lb/>
is, I think, fairly convincing, though as it is necessarily nega-<lb/>
tive evidence, each one must judge for himself on this.</p>
<p>It grieves me to find the French--of all people!--abandoning<lb/>
their own great writers: Dutrolau: Moreau de Jonn&eacute;s: Cornilliac:<lb/>
Rufz de <unclear>Lav:</unclear> <del><unclear>???</unclear></del> <add>Late</add> Corre: B&eacute;ranger F&eacute;raud: Roux, and even the French-<lb/>
men who wrote (in French) from U. S. experience, like Faget; old<lb/>
Touatre and Chaill&eacute;--men who spent all their professional lives with<lb/>
yellow fever--and accepting without any question a statement by<lb/>
men who had seen very little of it and who advanced not a single<lb/>
observation to confirm that statement.</p>
<p>This last heresy is as obvious in West Africa as it is in the<lb/>
Guianas.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
