<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01137011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter, [1924]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01137011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Connor, M.E.</name>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, L.H.</name>
<name type="person">Caldwell, Bert W.</name>
<name type="person">Houle, E.C.</name>
<name type="person">Scannell, E.J.</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-00-00">[1924]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01137011</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter, [1924]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter comments on Williamson's manuscript, entitled "The Use of Fish for the Control of Mosquitoes."</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-00-00">
<head>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter, [1924]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01137011"/>
<p>/LC</p>
<p>Memorandum.</p>
<p>I want to add that this is a good paper: On the history of what has<lb/>
been, and is being, done with fish control of mosquitoes a most excel-<lb/>
lent one.</p>
<p>Would it not, however, have been better to have divided the sub-<lb/>
ject squarely into two parts: Control of Anopheles and Control of Stego-<lb/>
myia? Both the characteristics necessary in the fish themselves and the<lb/>
measures the sanitarian must take in aid of the fish to render them ef-<lb/>
ficient are frequently entirely different according to which of these<lb/>
genera we wish to control:</p>
<p>For instance, since the aquatic forms of Anopheles are exclusively<lb/>
surface dwellers, the fish for Anopheles control then should be (1) top-<lb/>
feeders: And, since Anopheles breed <hi>almost</hi> exclusively in natural col-<lb/>
lections of water and the larvae shelter themselves in vegetation and<lb/>
floatage collected mainly around the edges of the water, the fish should<lb/>
be (2) able to work themselves into such vegetation and floatage so as<lb/>
to have access to the larvae. Since almost the only risk these fish are<lb/>
exposed to (supposing the climate and water are suitable) is their des-<lb/>
truction by larger fish, they should be (3) very small (hence as little<lb/>
temptation as possible) and (4) inclined to frequent very shallow water<lb/>
and so get out of the way of larger fish. Working their way into thick<lb/>
vegetation and floatage is also a protection against larger fish.</p>
<p>About all that is required of, or is possible to, the sanitarian in<lb/>
aid of fish-control of <hi>Anopheles</hi> (after stocking the breeding area proper-<lb/>
ly) is to (a) so remove vegetation and floatage as to give the fish access<lb/>
to the larvae and (b) to see that the laviporous fish are not destroyed<lb/>
and to replace them when they are.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01137012"/>
<p>are.</p>
<p>Mem. (con) Page 2.</p>
<p>Stegomyia larvae, on the contrary, although they come to the top<lb/>
for air, spend most of their time at the bottom: Hence either a bottom<lb/>
or top-feeding fish may be (and indeed has been) efficient against them,<lb/>
but the former would seem preferable.</p>
<p>Since Stegomyia, in the Americas, breeds practically <add>only</add> in artificial<lb/>
containers, there is no question of access of fish <add><unclear>pload</unclear></add> in them to the larvae<lb/>
(although larvae are reported as occasionally hiding in dark corners of<lb/>
the container). There is therefor no need of characteristic (2) in fish<lb/>
for Stegomyia control nor is there any need for the sanitarian to remove<lb/>
protection for the larvae from the fish.</p>
<p>Fish used for Stegomyia control--i. e. in containers, are subject<lb/>
to the following risks:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Since only a few are allowed in each container, they must be<lb/>
moved often <add><unclear>for another hatchery</unclear></add> to replace those that die.</item>
<item>(2) They are liable to jump out of the container, especially when<lb/>
water is dipped out of it, or to be washed out when overflowing from rain.</item>
<item>(3) To be dipped out with the water.</item>
<item>(4) To be injured when the utensil, used for dipping water, is drop-<lb/>
ped in.</item>
<item>(5) Injured by sudden change (fall) of temperature and</item>
<item>(6) Die for (or fail to thrive from insufficient) light.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Very obviously then, the measures to be taken by the sanitarian to<lb/>
protect these fish and thus insure Stegomyia control, as well as the char-<lb/>
acteristics necessary in the fish themselves, are very different from those<lb/>
necessary for Anopheles control. In point of fact, while we all agree<lb/>
that a very small top minnow is best for Anopheles control: practically all<lb/>
the fish especially recommended for Stegomyia control by Connor: Hanson:<lb/>
Dunn: Caldwell: Houle and Scannell have been bottom-feeders: many of them es-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01137013"/>
es-<lb/>
Mem. (con) Page 3.<lb/>
pecially recommended on account of lessoned risk of (1) (i. e. tougher):<lb/>
(2): (3): (4): (5)&amp; (6) as enumerated in the last paragraph, as compared<lb/>
with top minnows, which, however, have given good, although less good, re-<lb/>
sults.</p>
<p>It seems to me then that a primary division into Control of Anopheles<lb/>
Production and Control of Stegomyia (<hi>Aedes (Stegomyia) aegypti</hi>) Production<lb/>
might have been better, with your geographical division following.</p>
<p>The Control of the brackish-marsh Aedes could have also differnetiated<lb/>
to itself. It is an extensive problem, but simple--(fish: ditches and<lb/>
tide-gates) and rarely a sanitary one, although we found letting in &ldquo;Killi-<lb/>
fish&rdquo; both needed and efficient against <hi>A. crucians</hi> at Langly Field and vi-<lb/>
cinity in Virginia (1918).</p>
<p>I think too, one might note that we have no fish very suitable for<lb/>
the stream (and small pool) breeding of Anopheles--which is no small<lb/>
sanitary problem.</p>
<p>About the only advantage I can see in using top-feeding fish in<lb/>
artificial containers is that one can see them more readily on inspection<lb/>
and thus know that they are alive. As, however, any fish when dead would<lb/>
soon float up to the surface, not seeing the bottom-feeder on top would<lb/>
would be good evidence <add>that</add> it was yet alive. In moderate sized containers<lb/>
they would also be visible by a flash light.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
