<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01138033">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter and report with appendixes from Oliver L. Pothier to Joseph H. White, August 20, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Pothier, Oliver L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01138033</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-08-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">White, Joesph H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish">YES</term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Read, Florence M.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Pareja, Wenceslao</name>
<name type="person">Miller, Frederick A.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Medina Pablo Garcia</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Serpa, Roberta</name>
<name type="person">Valdivieso, Julio</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Bucaramanga (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Cartagena (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Colombia (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Wilches (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Barranquilla (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Bogota (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Cucuta (Colombia)</name>
<name type="place">Maracaibo (Venezuela)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D. C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>25 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-08-20">August 20, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01138033</idno>
<title>Letter and report with appendixes from Oliver L. Pothier to Joseph H. White, August 20, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Pothier sends White his final report on the 1923 Yellow Fever Commission inspection tour of Colombia. He describes travel, meetings with government officials, and incidence of yellow fever and mosquitoes. A series of appended documents [two in Spanish] discuss preparations for the trip, the suspected epidemic in Bucaramanga, individual yellow fever cases, and further details of the tour.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-08-20">
<head>Letter and report with appendixes from Oliver L. Pothier to Joseph H. White, August 20, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01138033"/>
<p>C O P Y<lb/>
New Orleans, <date value="1923-08-20">August 20, 1923.</date>
Dr. Joseph H. White<lb/>
Chief of Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission sent to<lb/>
Colombia, S.A.<lb/>
Dear Doctor:</p>
<p>In compliance with your request transmitted to me by Miss<lb/>
Florence M. Read, Assistant Secretary, International Health Board, in<lb/>
her letter of June 21, 1923, you will find herewith appended my report<lb/>
including the period from April 5, 1923 to July 9, 1923.</p>
<p>In this report I have included not only the work done, but also<lb/>
the traveling from day to day, as well as I could gather from the notes<lb/>
that I had taken during this period. I have appended to the report all<lb/>
correspondence and telegrams received and forwarded to the Foundation by<lb/>
me.</p>
<p>I trust that you will find it satisfactory, the correspondence<lb/>
etc., is appended as exhibits A,B,C,D,E,F,G,H,I.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted,<lb/>
(Signed) O. L. Pothier, M.D.<lb/>
P.S. Though this report is dated August 20, 1923, on account of the<lb/>
pressing amount of work that I found on my return I had to postpone<lb/>
until now the finishing of it. January 19, 1924.<lb/>
O. L. P.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01138034"/>
<p>REPORT OF<lb/>
Doctor Olivier L. Pothier<lb/>
New Orleans, La.<lb/>
Member of the Commission<lb/>
Sent to Colombia for the<lb/>
Investigation of the epidemic of<lb/>
Bucaramanga, by the International<lb/>
Health Board of the Rockefeller<lb/>
Foundation,<lb/>
From April 5th, 1923, to July 9th, 1923.<lb/>
New Orleans, <date value="1923-08-20">August 20, 1923.</date></p>
<p>On April 5, 1923, I received the following telegram from the<lb/>
International Health Board, of the Rockefeller Foundation, 61 Broadway,<lb/>
New York, N.Y.:-</p>
<p>Dr. Oliver L. Pothier, 124 Baronne St., N.O. La.</p>
<p>&ldquo;International Health Board sending yellow fever Commission to Colombia<lb/>
to investigate rumored epidemic Bucaramanga Doctor Joseph White and two others<lb/>
stop Doctor White recommends you for member of commission stop could you<lb/>
join White Colon about April eighteenth stop time needed approximately two<lb/>
months salary offered six hundred dollars monthly and expenses Wire reply.&rdquo;</p>
<p>International Health Board.</p>
<p>(See exhibit &ldquo;A&rdquo; herewith appended).</p>
<p>On April 5, 1923, I replied by night letter as follows:-</p>
<p>&ldquo;Will meet Doctor White Colon about April eighteenth stop Confirm<lb/>
wire by letter and give further instructions stop Am preparing to leave<lb/>
by first steamer available.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Oliver L. Pothier.</p>
<p>(See exhibit &ldquo;B&rdquo; herewith appended).</p>
<p>On April 6, 1923, I received the following in answer to above:-</p>
<p>&ldquo;Apply immediately emergency passport Somerset Owen Custom House New<lb/>
Orleans explaining nature of emergency and requesting him telegraph Washington<lb/>
stop Have requested Colombian minister to telegraph Consul New Orleans<lb/>
facilitate visa stop Wiring four hundred dollars as travel advance letter<lb/>
follows.&rdquo;</p>
<p>International Health Board.</p>
<p>(See exhibit &ldquo;C&rdquo; herewith appended).</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01138035"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>On April 9, 1923, I wired the International Board that I was leaving<lb/>
on the 11th, 1923, by the S.S. Parismina, which was due in Colon April 18, 1923.</p>
<p>On April 9, 1923, I received from the International Health Board a<lb/>
letter of confirmation with further instructions, by special delivery, dated<lb/>
April 6, 1923. (See exhibit &ldquo;D&rdquo; herewith appended).</p>
<p>On April 11, 1923, I sailed on S.S. Parismina, United Fruit Line, via<lb/>
Havana for Colon. The trip after stopping over in Havana one day was uneventful<lb/>
and we arrived in Colon on Wednesday, April 18, 1923, and went to Washington<lb/>
Hotel to await Dr. J. H. White whose ship the Carillo was due in the afternoon.<lb/>
I met Dr. White about three that afternoon and then met Dr. W. Pareja through<lb/>
Dr. White. Spent that night at Hotel Washington, and sailed on 19, 1923, on<lb/>
S.S. Carillo in company of Drs. White and Pareja, arriving in Cartagena on 20th.<lb/>
We were received by the Governor and officials who took us on a tour of inspec-<lb/>
tion of the city. Their reception was very cordial and full of deference for<lb/>
our commission, they took pains in showing us all the different points of in-<lb/>
terest and their method of storing water for drinking and cooking purposes.<lb/>
They actually do not have a system of water work, but are establishing now a<lb/>
system which will probably be finished in the next two years, when they will<lb/>
have adequate water supply. On my return trip I had the pleasure to meet<lb/>
Mr. Jenks the engineer in charge of the work who told me that the water supply,<lb/>
when the work would be finished, would not only be adequate but would be of<lb/>
fine quality, with running water in all houses of the city. This will be un-<lb/>
doubtedly the greatest improvement of that city from a sanitary view point, and<lb/>
incalculable to establish sanitary conditions both as to yellow fever and<lb/>
malaria, but also a great help in eradicating uncinariasis.</p>
<p>After taking leave of our hosts in Cartagena we left and arrived in<lb/>
Puerto Colombia the next day April 21, 1923, in the afternoon. On our arrival<lb/>
we were taken in charge by a delegation composed of Dr. Del Rio, Dr. Arango,<lb/>
representing the Governor of The State of Atlantico, Sr. Sr. Commandante<lb/>
Eduardo B. Gerlein, Commandante of the Port, the Health Officer of the Port,<lb/>
the Custom House officer, and taken to our train which took us to Barranquilla.<lb/>
At the depot we were met by the Governor of the State of Atlantico, and escorted<lb/>
to the Pension Inglesa where quarters had been reserved for us. On arriving at<lb/>
the Pension we met Dr. F. A. Miller who had come by hydroplane from Bogota to<lb/>
meet us. To Dr. Miller, his knowledge of the country and customs, and his<lb/>
congenial ways of doing things the Commission owe a great deal in arranging,<lb/>
preparing and assisting us in our trips through the Republic. I cannot say how<lb/>
much I appreciated all that he did to facilitate our work during our stay in<lb/>
Colombia. So that the next day we found that he had already arranged for our<lb/>
river trip to Puerto Wilches on our way to Bucaramanga, and on Monday, April 23,<lb/>
1923, after spending Sunday and Monday in Barranquilla, making the final arrange-<lb/>
ments for our trip to Bucaramanga, and returning official calls, we left<lb/>
Barranquilla on board the Caldas between nine and ten P.M. Our trip up the<lb/>
Magdalena was uneventful and we reached Puerto Wilches on Thursday, April 26, 1923,<lb/>
at about four P.M.</p>
<p>Instructions had been given the Mayor of the town to put a special<lb/>
train at our disposal but through some misunderstanding there was no train on<lb/>
our arrival. However after our arrival a telegram was sent to kilometer 27,<lb/>
and we were informed that a train would be sent for us. This train finally<lb/>
arrived between eight and nine P.M. and after getting our luggage and baggage aboard<lb/>
we started on our trip to La Ceiba (kilometer 27), which we reached at about ten P.M.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01138036"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
it was nearly twelve before we finally retired. After a rather eventful night<lb/>
and after taking our early breakfast, and our pack mules ready we left La Ceiba<lb/>
between seven and eight, on mule back, accompanied by our guide. About two or<lb/>
three hours later in the neighborhood of La Cristalina we met Drs. Serpa and<lb/>
Valdivieso, who had been sent to escort us to Bucaramanga, and who did not<lb/>
expect us until that day at Puerto Wilches, the Caldas being one day ahead of<lb/>
schedule. We continued on our way in their company and stopped for our noon<lb/>
meal. After which we went on without stop to Jasmin, which we reached at about<lb/>
six P.M. after a very trying and hot trip through the Savana del Torres, and we<lb/>
spent the night there. After a rather comfortable night we left Jasmin the<lb/>
morning of Saturday April 28, 1923, at about six A.M. This second day of our trip<lb/>
was rather pleasant in the morning hours, and after crossing the Lebrija at<lb/>
Puerto Santos we stopped there, it was then ten A.M. At about twelve M. we stopped<lb/>
for our noon meal, after which we proceeded on our way along the Lebrija until we<lb/>
reached Tambor by five thirty thoroughly exhausted after this day's ride. I had<lb/>
to be assisted off my mule I was so stiff. After being rested and taking a<lb/>
refreshing bath we went to supper which we all enjoyed, as well as the cool even-<lb/>
ing. It was then, at the suggestion of Dr. White considering that we were all<lb/>
rather tired of our mule trip, that we decided to remain over Sunday and rest<lb/>
ourselves before taking the last lap of our trip. So Monday morning, April 30, 1923,<lb/>
after a day's rest we resumed our trip leaving Tambor at six A.M. We felt very<lb/>
grateful to Mr. Puyana, the owner of Tambor, for the way he received us and for<lb/>
the comforts his place afforded us.</p>
<p>From Tambor we ascended along the trail which brought us to the plateau<lb/>
of Las Palmas, and the inn of that name, where we stopped about ten A.M. after<lb/>
giving our animals and ourselves a blow and a rest we resumed our trail and<lb/>
reached the end of the pleateau, and came down along the Tirabozon trail to<lb/>
Las Bocas about twelve M. Here we were met by Drs. Pradilla, brother of the<lb/>
Governor of Santander, and Ardila Gomez, both having been sent by the Governor<lb/>
to escort us to Bucaramanga. We took lunch at Las Bocas and after left on our<lb/>
last lap to Bucaramanga. Just before crossing the river we stopped at a wayside<lb/>
inn and went across the bridge and started our last ascent to the plateau of<lb/>
Bucaramanga, which we reached at about four P.M.</p>
<p>As we emerged on the plateau we were met by a delegation composed of<lb/>
the Governor and his staff, the mayor and several aldermen, doctors, and committee<lb/>
of citizens. After dismounting and meeting these Gentlemen we were taken up in<lb/>
automobiles to our quarters in the city, which the Government had provided for us.<lb/>
They were installed in a new office building, and were composed of a suite of<lb/>
rooms composed of a reception room with a bed room back of it, these two rooms<lb/>
were separated from two other rooms on the other side by a central hall. These<lb/>
two other rooms were an office and bedroom in the rear of it. The suite opened<lb/>
on the street and were on the second floor, they were well furnished with new<lb/>
furniture and all requirements, making them quite homelike. The place was well<lb/>
ventilated and flooded with light and was quite cool at night. Every pains<lb/>
had been taken for our comfort. The building was central which made it very<lb/>
convenient for our work being at proximity to the hospital and other points of<lb/>
importance to us. Drs. Miller and Pareja occupied the room back of the reception<lb/>
room, and Dr. White and myself that back of the office.</p>
<p>We arrived in Bucaramanga in the evening of Monday April 30, 1923, and<lb/>
were escorted to our quarters, as already stated, and while Dr. White, Dr. Miller,<lb/>
and myself were getting things ready and receiving the Governor and delegation of<lb/>
Citizens, Dr. Pareja, accompanied by Drs. Valdivieso and Serpa, went to the<lb/>
Hospital to see a suspicious case. On his return he informed us that he was<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01138037"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
convinced that he had seen a case of Yellow Fever. The next morning Tuesday,<lb/>
May 1, 1923, we all went to the Hospital and confirmed the diagnosis of<lb/>
Dr. Pareja.</p>
<p>When we arrived in Bucaramanga, and while riding in, I rode with<lb/>
Dr. David D. McCormick, a native of Bucaramanga, who very graciously invited<lb/>
me to his office and laboratory, and assured me that I would be welcome to do<lb/>
whatever work I desired. Before our arrival Dr. McCormick had reported having<lb/>
found the Leptospira Icteroides in the blood of several cases. His laboratory<lb/>
though small, was sufficiently equipped to allow us to do the necessary laboratory<lb/>
examinations, that is, the agglutination in vitro and Pfeiffer reaction, and we<lb/>
gladly accepted his offer. Consequently we busied ourselves immediately to<lb/>
obtain guinea pigs, which unfortunately were very scarce, as we succeeded to<lb/>
purchase only three. Dr. McCormick had two, but one was a female in profit,<lb/>
and the other was a male which had been used before and consequently neither<lb/>
could be used. So we had to be satisfied with the three that we had bought.</p>
<p>On Tuesday morning, May 1, 1923, the Commission went to the Hospital,<lb/>
accompanied by several physicians among which were Drs. Valdivieso, Serpa,<lb/>
McCormick, Ardilo Gomez, Pradilla, etc. in their presence we confirmed the<lb/>
diagnosis of Dr. Pareja, which was Yellow Fever. The case was that of a<lb/>
Policeman, Esteban Figueroa, who was in the sixth day of the disease. He was<lb/>
one of many from the same precinct who had taken sick. He presented the follow-<lb/>
ing symptoms: Marked jaundice, marked cutaneous stasis, which is apparent on<lb/>
pressure, giving the body the peculiar color which the red and yellow mixture<lb/>
gives in those cases, marked epigastric pain on pressure, marked gingival<lb/>
haemorrhage, marked epitaxis, marked albuminuria. Temperature 39C pulse 60.<lb/>
No enlargement of liver nor of spleen. The patient presents a typical picture<lb/>
of a classic case of yellow fever, and seems in a very precarious condition, our<lb/>
prognosis on this day was not very favorable, as he seemed very depressed. He<lb/>
rallied however in the next days and finally recovered. We took blood from him<lb/>
on this morning, ten cubic centimeters.</p>
<p>On the same morning, Tuesday, May 1, 1923, at the same hospital, in<lb/>
another ward we saw another case, Cristobal Rueda, a mild case, who had been<lb/>
admitted on Sunday, April 30, 1923, with fever, giving a history of having been<lb/>
taken sick with a sudden chill, and, according to the report of the Sister in<lb/>
charge, of having been sick two days before being admitted. When we saw him,<lb/>
he was free from fever, was slightly jaundiced, pulse 100, was up, had marked<lb/>
albuminuria, and was quite weak. We took his blood, ten cc. The blood of these<lb/>
two cases were immediately separated from the clot to obtain clear serum for our<lb/>
reactions, and stored on ice until the next day for the reactions, as we expected<lb/>
to have guinea pigs. The next day, Wednesday, May 2, 1923, not having been able<lb/>
to obtain guinea pigs, we decided to make agglutinations in vitro. We therefore<lb/>
subjected both sera to this form of reaction and obtained in both a positive<lb/>
agglutination in vitro, with Leptospira Icteroides. The culture used was one of<lb/>
the cultures sent to us by Dr. Noguchi, and it was the Arias Strain, it was used<lb/>
with equal parts of serum from the patients.</p>
<p>The next day having obtained some guinea pigs, both sera were submitted<lb/>
to Pfeiffer reaction, this was on Thursday, May 3, 1923. Both sera gave a positive<lb/>
Pfeiffer reaction.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f01138038"/>
<p>- 5 -</p>
<p>On Friday, May 4, 1923, the Commission went to the College of San<lb/>
Pedro Claver, where an outbreak of fever had occurred in February, and where<lb/>
they had many cases, necessitating the closing of the college. Among these<lb/>
cases was a very severe one, the case of Father Hidalgo, and an exceedingly<lb/>
mild one that of one of the Brothers of the Order. We took the blood of both<lb/>
cases and after separating the serum from the clot, it was sealed in ampoules,<lb/>
and packed for future examination in Bogota, as our supply of guinea pigs was<lb/>
exhausted and that we could not procure any more in Bucaramanga, and that we<lb/>
were promised better equipment in Bogota. We left the following Sunday, May 6,<lb/>
1923, for Bogota.</p>
<p>Bucaramanga is situated on a plateau at about 2994 feet altitude,<lb/>
73 - 12', west of Greenwich, lattitude 7 - 5'. It has a mean temperature of<lb/>
26 C, a rainfall of 7.2. A population of about 25,000.</p>
<p>Surrounding the plateau on which is Bucaramanga and adjoining it are<lb/>
seven smaller towns their population varying from 8,000 to 15,000, below is<lb/>
given the names and situation of these towns as regards Bucaramanga.</p>
<p>Giron about six miles from Bucaramanga, on the east, with an altitude of<lb/>
1689 feet.</p>
<p>Florida Blanca about six miles southeast from Bucaramanga, with an altitude<lb/>
of 2619 feet.</p>
<p>Piedecuesta, about twelve miles southwest of Bucaramanga, with an altitude<lb/>
of 3027 feet.</p>
<p>Lebrija mean temperature of 24 C. at about nine miles from Bucaramanga.</p>
<p>Matanza at about twenty-one miles north east of Bucaramanga with an altitude<lb/>
of 4815 feet.</p>
<p>Surata twenty-four miles south east of Bucaramanga with an altitude of<lb/>
5730 feet.</p>
<p>Tona twenty-one miles southeast of Bucaramanga, with an altitude of<lb/>
6840 feet.</p>
<p>Rionegro de Santander southeast from Bucaramanga, with an altitude of<lb/>
4500 feet, fensely populated, unhealthy and damp climate, variable temperature<lb/>
21 - 29 C. An important coffee center.</p>
<p>These data were obtained through Dr. Martin Carvajal, and it was also<lb/>
through him that we obtained our interview at the College of San Pedro Claver.<lb/>
Dr. Carvajal, like all the members of the medical profession of Bucaramanga,<lb/>
was always ready to assist us in all our work of investigation, and facilitated<lb/>
the obtaining of these data. We owe a great deal to these gentlemen for their<lb/>
cordial and courteous assistance, in our work.</p>
<p>These smaller towns with Bucaramanga, would give a total population of<lb/>
about 100,000 inhabitants, which would be sufficient to establish an endemic focus,<lb/>
as about four of them are of the proper altitude to propagate the Stegomyia<lb/>
(Aedes Egyptus), and the others to furnish new material for infection. This is<lb/>
well shown in the report of the seven physicians of Bucaramanga, in their article:<lb/>
&ldquo;La Epidemia Actual&rdquo;. A report by Drs. Daniel Peralta, Martin Carvajal, Francisco<lb/>
Pradilla Gonzalez, Andres Gomes, Julio Valdivieso, Roberto Serpa, y Luis Ardila<lb/>
Gomez.---Where several cases reported as coming to Bucaramanga from these higher<lb/>
altitude towns surrounding it.</p>
<p>During our stay in Bucaramanga the Governor of the State of Santander<lb/>
entertained us to a dinner, a day or two before we left, to which most of the<lb/>
physicians of Bucaramanga were invited to meet us, though we had probably met<lb/>
them all before. It happened to be Dr. White's birthday, and also the day that<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01138039"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
Dr. White received the telegram recalling him to New York, to go to Brazil.</p>
<p>On Sunday, the sixth of May, 1923, we left Bucaramanga to go to Bogota,<lb/>
over land. We left at about six in the morning in automobiles, escorted by a<lb/>
delegation of doctors who accompanied us to Piedecuesta, which we reached at<lb/>
about nine A.M. and where we were received by a local physician while our mules<lb/>
were being prepared for the rest of our daily trip. We resumed our way by ten<lb/>
A.M. on our mules and went up to La Mesa de Los Santos and lunched at La Cruz,<lb/>
on the Mesa. After lunch we proceeded along the Mesa the rest of the day until<lb/>
we reached the end of it and began our descent toward the town of Los Santos,<lb/>
where we stopped for our dinner and to spend the night. The next morning, Monday<lb/>
May 7, 1923, after our early breakfast we left Los Santos, and started a long<lb/>
descent along the side of the mountains to Sube on the river at the bottom of the<lb/>
valley, and after passing through Sube ascending the long slope to El Corregidor<lb/>
where we stopped at about eleven thirty for lunch. We left El Corregidor at one<lb/>
P.M. and continued our ascent to the top of the range and then started down again<lb/>
until we reached Cureti, where we took dinner and spent the night. The next<lb/>
morning, Tuesday, May 8th, 1923, we left Cureti after breakfast and proceeded<lb/>
on our way to Mogotes, which we reached at about eleven and had lunch. After<lb/>
leaving Mogotes we began the ascent of Los Cacaos range which we had to go over<lb/>
before coming to San Joaquim which is situated on the other side of it. We<lb/>
reached San Joaquim at about four P.M. leaving behind us a raging rain and thunder<lb/>
storm which we barely escaped coming down the range. We rested ourselves and had<lb/>
dinner at San Joaquim and spent the night there. Wednesday May 9, 1923, we left<lb/>
San Joaquim and proceeded to ascent to Onzaga, where we had lunch, and after lunch<lb/>
we kept on going up to Suza, which we reached about six and had dinner and spent<lb/>
the night. The most disagreeable night of the whole trip on account of the<lb/>
altitude. The next morning at about five A.M. we took breakfast and were under way<lb/>
by six. We continued to ascent until we reached the Paramo, at an altitude of<lb/>
about 14,000 feet, we lunched at about eleven o'clock on our way through the<lb/>
Paramo, and went on until we came down from it and reached Belen at or about three<lb/>
P.M. Thursday, May 10, 1923. We alighted from our mules for the last time as<lb/>
it was our last day of mule back traveling. As we arrived we were met by the<lb/>
mayor of Belen who informed us that he expected at any moment our automobiles<lb/>
which were to take us to Tunja that evening. Through some misunderstanding the<lb/>
automobiles did not come up before night fall, and we decided to remain in<lb/>
Belen and spend the night, and to leave the next morning very early. We were<lb/>
up at four A.M. on Friday, May 11, 1923, had breakfast and were ready to start<lb/>
in our machines at five A.M. We consequently left Belen at that time and were<lb/>
on our way to Tunja, which we reached at nine thirty. As we drove up to the hotel<lb/>
we were received by the minister of Agriculture Senor Pareides, and the National<lb/>
Director of Hygiene Dr. Pablo Garcia Medina, both having driven from Bogota to<lb/>
meet us. They entertained us to breakfast, and we left Tunja at ten thirty on<lb/>
our last lap to Bogota, which we reached in the evening and were quartered at the<lb/>
Hotel Continental and Hotel Cote, after a long and tedious trip from Tunja.</p>
<p>The next morning Saturday May 12, 1923, we had an audience with the<lb/>
President of the Republic, Gen. Nel Ospina, to whom we reported our findings<lb/>
in Bucaramanga, which he graciously received. It was also at this audience<lb/>
that Dr. White proposed to establish a campaign, the expense of which would be<lb/>
shared by the Government and the Rockefeller Foundation, in which each party<lb/>
would share equally in the estimated cost of the campaign, half being paid by<lb/>
the Government and the other half being paid by the Rockefeller Foundation.<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01138040"/>
- 7 -<lb/>
This proposition carried with it the proviso that the work would be carried<lb/>
on by a representative of the Foundation according to the ideas of the Foun-<lb/>
dation and that all salaries would be paid by the Foundation. The estimated<lb/>
cost of such campaign was estimated at $50,000, half of which would be met<lb/>
by the Government. The President acceeded to such an arrangement and a<lb/>
telegram was sent to the Foundation reporting our findings and the offer<lb/>
made by Dr. White.</p>
<p>Sunday May 13, 1923, was spent in conferences with Dr. Medina and<lb/>
Senor Pareides and meeting several physicians whom Dr. Medina had brought<lb/>
to meet us or who called to see us. As proposed by Dr. Medina on Sunday<lb/>
he met me at the Hotel at eight thirty and together we went to Dr. Samper's<lb/>
laboratory on Monday, May 14, 1923,. After meeting Drs. Samper and Martini<lb/>
and being shown their well equipped plant, we prepared for the work that we<lb/>
intended to do the next day. So Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, and Friday<lb/>
I made the different Pfeiffer tests on the sera that I had brought from<lb/>
Bucaramanga. I repeated in Bogota the reactions I had made in Bucaramanga<lb/>
on the serum of Figueroa and Rueda, and they again gave positive Pfeiffer<lb/>
reactions. I submitted the serum of Father Hidalgo and that of the Brother<lb/>
to Pfeiffer test and they both gave a positive reaction. These reactions<lb/>
were made with Leptospira Icteroides (Arias Strain), for reasons given in<lb/>
the appended exhibit &ldquo;E&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Reactions were also made with Leptospira Icterohaemorrhagica<lb/>
with the serum of Father Hidalgo and that of Figueroa, both gave negative<lb/>
results. These last reactions were made as detailed in appended exhibit<lb/>
&ldquo;E&rdquo; in 1-50 dilutions, one of serum to fifty of culture.</p>
<p>On Monday May 21, 1923, we left Bogota at seven thirty A.M.<lb/>
on our return trip to Barranquilla. Before leaving, on Saturday May 19, 1923,<lb/>
we had an audience from the President at which we took leave from him<lb/>
and confirmed the proposition which Dr. White had suggested as a favorable<lb/>
answer to Dr. White telegram to the Foundation had been received. On Sunday<lb/>
Dr. Pareja and myself called on the Minister of Ecuador and the Minister<lb/>
of Venezuela relative to our voyage to Cucuta and Maracaibo. It is thanks<lb/>
to these gentlemen that our mission to Cucuta was very much facilitated.<lb/>
Leaving on Monday, May 21, 1923, at seven thirty A.M. we proceeded to Girardo<lb/>
which we reached at about six P.M. We had our dinner and spent the night<lb/>
and at six thirty the next morning Tuesday, May 22, 1923, we boarded the<lb/>
river boat Ocania to Beltran which we reached by one P.M. then by train to<lb/>
Laderrado where we arrived by eight P.M. and boarded the lower river boat<lb/>
Pradilla, which put us in Barranquilla on Saturday, May 26, 1923, at about<lb/>
seven A.M. Dr. White left that afternoon for Puerto Colombia to sail on<lb/>
the Venezuela which was leaving for Colon. Dr. Pareja accompanied him to<lb/>
go to Cartagena to inspect for Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>On Monday, May 28, 1923, we called, Drs. Miller, Serpa and myself,<lb/>
on the Governor of the State of Atlantico, and at his request, we offered to<lb/>
go to Puerto Colombia to inspect it for a reported outbreak of Smallpox and<lb/>
also for Yellow Fever. The Governor accepted our offer and told us he<lb/>
would have put at our disposal a special motor car to facilitate our<lb/>
expidition. It was agreed that we would go to Puerto Colombia on Wednesday.<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01138041"/>
- 8 -<lb/>
Dr. Pareja having returned from Cartagena Tuesday, we left Wednesday,<lb/>
May 30, 1923, in the forenoon on a special motor car for Puerto Columbia,<lb/>
Drs. Miller, Pareja, Serpa and myself. In Puerto Colombia we were met by<lb/>
The Mayor, the Port Physician, the Commandant of the Port, and made a<lb/>
thorough inspection of the town, both for smallpox and yellow fever also<lb/>
for mosquitoes. We found the place free from smallpox and yellow fever,<lb/>
but a rather marked incidence of mosquitoes, though not as great as we<lb/>
anticipated. We returned to Barranquilla the same day and prepared a<lb/>
written report to the Governor, which is appended as exhibit &ldquo;F&rdquo;. The<lb/>
report was written in Spanish by Dr. Pareja as he was more familiar with<lb/>
the language. This report was presented to the Governor on the following<lb/>
day, Thursday, May 31, 1923. On Monday when we called on the Governor and<lb/>
at this call we discussed the means of preventing infection of Barranquilla<lb/>
from Bucaramanga and the river ports. These conferences were attended by<lb/>
Drs. Miller, Serpa, Pareja and myself. We recommended a point of observation<lb/>
located at Tambor on the way to Puerto Wilches from Bucaramanga, the reporting<lb/>
of all passengers from points on the river from Puerto Wilches down, and all<lb/>
passengers from Bucaramanga, the taking of temperature of all passengers on<lb/>
arrival at Barranquilla, the daily report of passengers from Bucaramanga<lb/>
or points from Puerto Wilches down, to have their temperature taken until<lb/>
the five days of incubation had elapsed. These recommendations were accepted<lb/>
by the Governor and the Port Physician, and a telegram was sent to the National<lb/>
Director of Hygiene, informing of the precautions taken. We made on that<lb/>
day an inspection of Barranquilla for yellow fever and for the incidence of<lb/>
mosquitoes. We found a very great incidence of Stegomyia, 98%. The City was<lb/>
free from Yellow Fever. This completed our work in Barranquilla.</p>
<p>There being no ships sailing before the fourth of June for<lb/>
Curacao, Dr. Pareja and myself were compelled to remain in Barranquilla<lb/>
until then. We used Friday and Saturday for our official calls to take leave<lb/>
of the Governor and other Officials, a matter of great importance in those<lb/>
countries, where they are exceedingly punctillious concerning courtesies and<lb/>
which mean a great deal to them and also to those whom they have received.<lb/>
To forget to return such calls in unpardonable to them. So we were careful<lb/>
not to forget any, and we did not.</p>
<p>Having been notified that our ship the Venezuela was to sail<lb/>
Monday, June the 4th, 1923, in the afternoon, Dr. Pareja and myself left<lb/>
Barranquilla in the morning, leaving Drs. Miller and Serpa who were to sail that<lb/>
night going up the river to Puerto Wilches. As we arrived in Puerto Colombia<lb/>
Dr. Pareja and myself were informed that our ship had not come in and that<lb/>
it was not expected before the next morning. We had to wait therefore until<lb/>
Tuesday noon before boarding the Venezuela and sailed that evening, Tuesday,<lb/>
June 5, 1923. Our trip to Curacao was rather disagreeable, the sea being<lb/>
rough, and we arrived in Curacao on Thursday, June 7, 1923, at six A.M. As<lb/>
it was we missed the connection for Maracaibo the ship having sailed on the<lb/>
Wednesday, so we had to remain in Curacao until Saturday, June 9, 1923, before<lb/>
we could get accommodations. We consequently boarded the <unclear>Bri</unclear> on Saturday at<lb/>
ten A.M. and sailed about one P.M. reaching Maracaibo on Sunday, June 10, 1923,<lb/>
at about three P.M. We were met on the ship by Drs. Arrangunin and Irarazabal,<lb/>
detailed by the Governor to look for us and advise him of our arrival, which<lb/>
was done and he sent the Secretary of State to escort us to the hotel where<lb/>
quarters had been retained for us, they were very courteous and remained with<lb/>
us the rest of the evening, taking us for a drive through the City and to the<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f01138042"/>
- 9 -<lb/>
points of interest, after which they took us to dinner. As we had missed<lb/>
the weekly river boat to Encontrados, they assisted us in chartering a small<lb/>
tug to take us there, from which point, as suggested by the Secretary of<lb/>
State, we could get a special train by making a request for it from the<lb/>
Governor. At our official visit the next day, Monday June 11th, 1923, when<lb/>
we were received by Governor Gomez he informed us that he had sent a special<lb/>
telegram to the station Master at Encontrados, requesting to put a special train<lb/>
at our disposal on our arrival there. We therefore completed our arrangements<lb/>
to leave that night so as to arrive in Encontrados on Wednesday morning. We<lb/>
were to leave Monday night at nine P.M. but on account of the shortage of fuel<lb/>
wood we did not leave until one A.M. Tuesday morning, June 12, 1923. We spent that<lb/>
day on our trip and arrived in Encontrados at about three in the morning of<lb/>
Wednesday. At about six that morning we called on the station Master who in-<lb/>
formed us that he had received instructions from the Governor and that our train<lb/>
would be ready by seven or seven thirty, we left at about eight that morning.<lb/>
We were accompanied by the station Master and a physician of Encontrados as<lb/>
far as the station where we stopped for breakfast, and we continued along from<lb/>
there to Tachira Station, which we reached about four in the afternoon. As<lb/>
provided by the station Master in Encontrados there was waiting for us an<lb/>
automobile in which we made the trip from Tachira Station to Cucuta. We<lb/>
reached Cucuta at six P.M. Wednesday, June 13, 1923.</p>
<p>The next morning Thursday June 14, 1923, we called on the Governor<lb/>
of the State of North Santander, and as he had not yet arrived at his office<lb/>
we went with his Secretary and the Health Officer to the Hospital which we<lb/>
inspected for Yellow Fever and mosquito incidence. The hospital was free<lb/>
from Yellow Fever, but the mosquito incidence was great. After our visit<lb/>
to the hospital we returned to the Governor's palace and were introduced to<lb/>
him. He was exceedingly cordial, and immediately put himself at our disposal.<lb/>
Doctor Cote, the Governor, was a practicing physician before being elected<lb/>
to the post of Governor, and for that reason our intercourse with him was<lb/>
easier and he appreciated the situation more fully. From his office we<lb/>
went to the barracks which we visited minutely without discovering any sus-<lb/>
picious cases. This is detailed in our report from Cucuta sent Dr. J. H. White,<lb/>
and appended herewith as exhibit &ldquo;G&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Having finished our inspection of the city for yellow fever and<lb/>
mosquito incidence, we went to the Governor's office and in conference with<lb/>
him recommended an active mosquito campaign, as we had found an incidence of<lb/>
100%, and at his request we signed a telegram to the National Director of<lb/>
Hygiene, reporting our findings of indemnity of yellow fever and high mos-<lb/>
quito incidence and recommending a mosquito campaign. This completed our<lb/>
mission in Cucuta, and we decided to leave the next day.</p>
<p>The reason for our rapid traveling was due to the fact that if we did<lb/>
not get in Curacao before the 21st of June we could not get any ship before<lb/>
the fifth or sixth of July for Colon. It would mean almost a month delay in<lb/>
our return trip home. So we were anxious to get in Maracaibo at the latest<lb/>
on June 18, 1923, to make connection for Curacao.</p>
<p>We therefore left Cucuta Friday June 15, 1923, at about two P.M.<lb/>
accompanied by the Governor and the Health officer, who came with us as<lb/>
far as the Venezuelan frontier and took leave of us there. We continued<lb/>
on our way to Tachira Station which we reached at about six P.M. and slept<lb/>
there that night and left by train the next morning Saturday, June 16, 1923,<lb/>
reaching Encontrados that afternoon at about two or three P.M. Leaving the<lb/>
train we embarked on the river steamer Progresso upon which we made an un-<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f01138043"/>
- 10 -<lb/>
eventful return trip to Maracaibo, where we arrived Sunday evening June 17,<lb/>
1923, and went to the hotel. The next morning Monday June 18, 1923, we<lb/>
made reservations for our passage to Curacao, and spent the rest of the<lb/>
forenoon making official calls to the Governor of the State of Zulia and<lb/>
other officials who had received us on our arrival. Before leaving for Cucuta<lb/>
we had sent a telegram of thanks to the President of Venezuela for the cordial<lb/>
way in which we had been received in Maracaibo, which telegram was duly ack-<lb/>
nowledged by him. After these calls we embarked on the Carna on which we were<lb/>
to sail for Curacao early the next morning. After spending the night on<lb/>
board we sailed at four thirty on Tuesday June 19, 1923, and arrived in Curacao<lb/>
on Wednesday, June 20, 1923, in the afternoon. We spent that night at the<lb/>
hotel and the next morning having secured our passage on the Van Ranselaer,<lb/>
and having attended to all the formalities regarding our baggage and ourselves<lb/>
we embarked on the steamer and sailed in the evening of Thursday, June 21, 1923,<lb/>
for Colon, which we reached, after passing through Puerto Colombia and Cartagena,<lb/>
on Tuesday, June 26, 1923, in the evening. After spending the night at the<lb/>
hotel Washington, the next morning Wednesday, June 27, 1923, I secured my passage<lb/>
on the Albangares direct for New Orleans, which was to sail on Thursday noon.<lb/>
I than reported to the health officer for my mail and also to talk over the<lb/>
situation, Doctor Pareja having left for Panama that morning. This call at the<lb/>
Health Officer was at his request as they were anxious to have more definite<lb/>
news of the conditions as we had left them. There being nothing else for me<lb/>
to do I busied myself getting my baggage in shape to leave the next morning<lb/>
at the earliest moment.</p>
<p>The next morning Thursday, June 28, 1923, after breakfast and about<lb/>
nine I received a telephone call from the Quarantine office stating that they<lb/>
had mail for me of an urgent nature. When I called I was handed a special<lb/>
delivery letter from the International Health Board requesting me to return<lb/>
via New York, it was then ten thirty, and immediately called at the United<lb/>
Fruit office, where I was handed another letter from the same source, and<lb/>
exchanged my passage from New Orleans to New York on the Tivives. I sailed<lb/>
that afternoon for New York via Kingston, I took leave from Dr. Pareja<lb/>
that morning after breakfast, as he was also sailing that noon for his home.<lb/>
After a rather disagreeable voyage, that is from the rough sea, I reached<lb/>
New York Thursday, July 5, 1923, in the afternoon.</p>
<p>After reaching the Hotel Pennsylvania and securing my quarters, I<lb/>
immediately reported at the office of the International Health Board at<lb/>
about four-thirty the same day. I met Miss F. Read who informed me that<lb/>
Dr. Russell was in Washington and that he would like for me to stop there and<lb/>
see him. I made a partial verbal report to Miss Read of the work that we had<lb/>
done. As I mentioned that I wanted to see Dr. Noguchi, Miss Read took an<lb/>
appointment with him for the next day at two P.M. As it was after office<lb/>
hours I took an appointment with Miss Read for the next day at ten A.M. as<lb/>
there were other matters to be taken up. The next day Friday, July 6, 1923,<lb/>
I called at the International Health Board and after going over some of<lb/>
work of the Commission in Colombia, and getting my reservations for Washington,<lb/>
I had an interview with Mr. R. Kirk concerning money matters, from there went<lb/>
to lunch and then to my appointment with Dr. Noguchi at the Rockefeller Institute.<lb/>
Dr. Noguchi was very cordial and we had a long conference over the work accom-<lb/>
plished by the Commission, after nearly two hours with Dr. Noguchi, I returned<lb/>
to see Mr. Kirk at the International Health Board at about four thirty, at five<lb/>
I took leave of Mr. Kirk and went to the Hotel to prepare to leave that night<lb/>
for Washington. I left at one A.M. and arrived in Washington at seven thirty<lb/>
the next morning Saturday, July 7, 1923. After breakfast I went to the Cosmos<lb/>
Club to meet Dr. Russell, it was then eight thirty.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f01138044"/>
<p>- 11 -</p>
<p>At about nine thirty Dr. Russell met me at the Cosmos Club, we had<lb/>
a long talk about the work in Colombia. Went over to meet Dr. Carter at the<lb/>
Congressional Library with whom we talked about yellow fever and the condi-<lb/>
tions in South America. We left Dr. Carter at about twelve noon and went to<lb/>
lunch, Dr. Russell and myself. After lunch Dr. Russell having other engage-<lb/>
ments left me at about two P.M. I spent the rest of the afternoon at the<lb/>
Club and boarded my train at nine thirty and left Washington at nine forty<lb/>
five for New Orleans. The trip to New Orleans was uneventful and I arrived<lb/>
on Monday morning July 9, 1923. I notified the International Health Board<lb/>
of my arrival in New Orleans, by wire.</p>
<p>So much for the report of the time spent on the work accomplished<lb/>
and the travel entailed. I wish now to add a report of the conditions as we<lb/>
found them.</p>
<p>When we reached Bucaramanga the epidemic had abated and we found two<lb/>
typical cases of yellow fever at the Hospital, which I have already described,<lb/>
there were none in the City at large among the practice of the local physicians.<lb/>
What was uppermost in our mind, after seeing these cases at the Hospital, and<lb/>
hearing of the report of the two hundred or more cases that they had had, was<lb/>
where did the epidemic come from? We knew that Cartagena, Puerto Colombia,<lb/>
Santa Marta, and Barranquilla, all coast ports, were absolutely free from yellow<lb/>
fever, it was impossible for an inland town like Bucaramanga to develop an<lb/>
epidemic of yellow fever, without being infected from an endemic focus. It was<lb/>
while disucssing this point among ourselves that Dr. White suggested the possi-<lb/>
bility of infection from Cucuta. We did not at first realize that Bucaramanga<lb/>
with its surrounding towns could be an endemic focus. It was only after further<lb/>
information that we realized that these towns with their aggregated population<lb/>
added to that of Bucaramanga would furnish a population of 100,000 or more, and<lb/>
consequently could become an endemic focus. This is well brought out in the<lb/>
body of this report in describing the situation of Bucaramanga. However to<lb/>
make things doubly sure it was then decided that we would investigate the con-<lb/>
ditions in and around Cucuta, and in passing the state of things in Maracaibo.<lb/>
This at the suggestion of Dr. White. We had in view then to establish the<lb/>
origin of the epidemic; as detailed in the body of this report, Dr. Pareja<lb/>
and myself fully demonstrated that this area from Maracaibo to Cucuta was<lb/>
entirely free from infection with yellow fever, though it presented a high<lb/>
mosquito incidence.</p>
<p>In reading over several of the reports, by different authors, concern-<lb/>
ing these recurring epidemics, not only in Bucaramanga, but also in other<lb/>
places, in some of these reports dating as far back as 1889, I have come<lb/>
to the conclusion that yellow fever has existed in these parts for a number<lb/>
of years, probably even further back than 1889. That it became established<lb/>
here, in the Bucaramanga area, as an endemic focus. This area is of commercial<lb/>
importance, and is frequented by a transient population, coming from the adja-<lb/>
cent towns, some of which are of a higher altitude and colder climate than<lb/>
Bucaramanga and furnishing new material for the propagation of the disease.<lb/>
That yellow fever is an insidious disease in its mild forms, especially in<lb/>
children, and very difficult, even for an expert, to diagnose. In the young<lb/>
infant born in an endemic focus I have frequently heard the experts speak of<lb/>
acclimating fever, which we now know was nothing but a mild type of yellow<lb/>
fever, which could give rise in a non-immune adult to a virulent type of<lb/>
yellow fever. It is probable, that in this area, that many mild and<lb/>
unobtrusive cases occurred continually for a period of years and were not<lb/>
recognized, until for some reason or other, probably an increase of population<lb/>
from new people coming there to reside, or for commercial purposes, and then<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f01138045"/>
- 12 -<lb/>
an outbreak would flare up. This is what happened in 1910 and 1912, not only<lb/>
in Bucaramanga, but in Cucuta and Maracaibo, along the Magdalena in Puerto<lb/>
Berrio. After this flare up of 1910-12, the infection spent itself in<lb/>
Maracaibo, Cucuta, and that neighborhood, on account of lack of new material.<lb/>
In Bucaramanga the epidemic apparently died down also, though, from time to<lb/>
time since, small outbreaks took place, until the last two or three years<lb/>
when the cases became more frequent, when this year two or three hundred cases<lb/>
occurred, the end of which epidemic we saw when we arrived in Bucaramanga April 30, 1923<lb/>
During the six days that we remained in Bucaramanga, May 6, 1923, there were no new<lb/>
cases. During the five days that we journeyed to Bogota, on our arrival there<lb/>
we received a report that there had been forty three new cases, from this report<lb/>
to the time that Dr. Pareja and myself passed through Puerto Colombia and Cartagena,<lb/>
June 23 - 25, 1923, we were informed that there had not been any new cases since<lb/>
that week in May.</p>
<p>It is my conviction that the Bucaramanga area became infected years<lb/>
ago, most probably from the coast, and on account of its transient population<lb/>
and its situation between warm and cold zones, received new material from the<lb/>
cold zones frequently, and in that way the infection has been carried on to this<lb/>
year. Once Bucaramanga will be cleared of its mosquito incidence it will become<lb/>
safe from Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>In submitting this report I have tried to be exact in the statements<lb/>
that I have presented. In closing I wish again to refer to the courteous and<lb/>
cordial reception that we experienced from the different officials, physicians,<lb/>
and other gentlemen who had been delegated to meet us at the different points<lb/>
that we visited. I want also to thank Dr. F. A. Miller, who met us in Barran-<lb/>
quilla on our arrival there in April, and who was our constant companion, for<lb/>
his undefatigable assistance in facilitating our work and our travel back to<lb/>
Barranquilla, he was invaluable to us.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted,<lb/>
(Signed) O. L. Pothier, M.D.</p>
<pb n="14" id="f01138046"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: A<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23.<lb/>
Copy telegram received April 5, 1923, by<lb/>
Dr. O. L. Pothier.<lb/>
NA427 54 NL<lb/>
New York NY <date value="1923-04-04">April 4, 1923</date>
PM. 4.43<lb/>
DR. OLIVER L POTHIER<lb/>
124 BARONNE ST NEW ORLEANS LA</p>
<p>INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD SENDING YELLOW FEVER COMMISSION TO COLOMBIA<lb/>
TO INVESTIGATE HUMORED EPIDEMIC BUCARAMANGA DOCTOR JOSEPH WHITE AND TWO<lb/>
OTHERS STOP DOCTOR WHITE RECOMMENDS YOU FOR MEMBER OF COMMISSION STOP COULD<lb/>
YOU JOIN WHITE COLON ABOUT APRIL EIGHTEENTH STOP TIME NEEDED APPROXIMATELY<lb/>
TWO MONTHS SALARY OFFERED SIX HUNDRED DOLLARS MONTHLY AND EXPENSES WIRE REPLY</p>
<p>INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD.</p>
<p>EXHIBIT: B<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23.<lb/>
Copy telegram sent by Dr. O. L. Pothier on receipt<lb/>
of telegram Exhibit A.<lb/>
New Orleans, La. <date value="1923-04-05">April 5, 1923.</date>
International Health Board<lb/>
NEW YORK, N.Y.</p>
<p>WILL MEET DOCTOR WHITE COLON ABOUT APRIL EIGHTEENTH STOP CONFIRM<lb/>
WIRE BY LETTER AND GIVE FURTHER INSTRUCTIONS STOP AM PREPARING TO LEAVE<lb/>
BY FIRST STEAMER AVAILABLE.</p>
<p>OLIVER L POTHIER.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f01138047"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: C<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23.<lb/>
COPY TELEGRAM RECEIVED APRIL 6, 1923.<lb/>
B179FX RE 39<lb/>
FX NEW YORK NY 220P <date value="1923-04-06">APL 6 1923.</date>
DOCTOR OLIVER L POTHIER<lb/>
124 BARONNE ST NEW ORLEANS LA</p>
<p>APPLY IMMEDIATELY EMERGENCY PASSPORT SOMERSET OWEN CUSTOM HOUSE NEW<lb/>
ORLEANS EXPLAINING NATURE OF EMERGENCY AND REQUESTING HIM TELEGRAPH<lb/>
WASHINGTON STOP HAVE REQUESTED COLOMBIAN MINISTER TO TELEGRAPH CONSUL<lb/>
NEW ORLEANS FACILITATE VISA STOP WIRING FOUR HUNDRED DOLLARS AS<lb/>
TRAVEL ADVANCE LETTER FOLLOWS</p>
<p>INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD<lb/>
<unclear>136P</unclear></p>
<pb n="16" id="f01138048"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: D<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23.<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
International Health Board<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York.<lb/>
<date value="1923-04-06">April 6, 1923.</date>
Dear Doctor Pothier:</p>
<p>This will confirm our telegram to you, dated April 4, as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;International Health Board sending yellow fever commission to Colombia<lb/>
to investigate rumored epidemic Bucaramanga Doctor Joseph White and two<lb/>
others stop Doctor White recommends you for member of commission stop<lb/>
could you join White Colon about April eighteenth stop time needed approx-<lb/>
imately two months salary offered six hundred dollars monthly and expenses<lb/>
wire reply.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In reply we have received the following telegram from you, dated<lb/>
April 5:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Will meet Doctor White Colon about April eighteenth stop confirm wire<lb/>
by letter and give further instructions stop am preparing to leave by<lb/>
first steamer available.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We are glad to know that you will be free to join Doctor White to make<lb/>
this yellow fever survey of Colombia. An epidemic has appeared in the city of<lb/>
Bucaramanga in the state of Santader, Colombia, and the symptoms of the disease<lb/>
as described by four Colombian physicians who went to investigate it sound much<lb/>
like yellow fever. (See copy of clipping enclosed.) There have been no suspi-<lb/>
cious cases in Barraquilla or in any of the coast cities and the altitude of<lb/>
Santander is high; but in view of the reports received, a thorough investigation<lb/>
of conditions seems advisable. The International Health Board has received an<lb/>
invitation from the President of Colombia to send specialists to study the situa-<lb/>
tion. Doctor Joseph H. White, who, as you doubtless know, has charge of the yellow<lb/>
fever work in Mexico and Central America is to sail from New York on the steamship<lb/>
&ldquo;Carilla&rdquo; of the United Druit Line on April 11. Doctor White has recommended you<lb/>
for a member of the commission and would like to have you join him in Colon on<lb/>
April 18. We understand that there is a United Fruit Line steamer, the &ldquo;Parismina&rdquo;,<lb/>
leaving New Orleans on April 11 to arrive Colon April 17. With that in mind, we<lb/>
are sending you the following telegram today:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Apply immediately emergency passport Somerset Owen Custom House New Orleans<lb/>
explaining nature of emergency and requesting him telegraph Washington stop<lb/>
have requested Colombian Minister to telegraph consul New Orleans facilitate<lb/>
visa stop wiring four hundred dollars as travel advance letter follows.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="17" id="f01138049"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: D (Continued)<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23.</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Doctor W. Pareja, Chief Health Officer in Guayaquil, is also to<lb/>
join Doctor White in Colon on April 18.</p>
<p>We are asking our Comptroller to send you an advance of $400 on<lb/>
account of travel to cover expenses from New Orleans to Colon. Doctor<lb/>
White will have a letter of credit on which to draw for expenses of the<lb/>
Commission after arrival in Colombia.</p>
<p>We are asking Doctor White to write directly to you if he has<lb/>
any further suggestions. He is planning to take cultures for Pfeiffer<lb/>
tests, and counts on you and Doctor Pareja to make the tests.</p>
<p>Yours very sincerely,<lb/>
(Signed) F.F. Russell<lb/>
Doctor Oliver L. Pothier,<lb/>
124 Baronne Street,<lb/>
New Orleans, Louisiana.<lb/>
FRR:BR</p>
<pb n="18" id="f01138050"/>
<p>Enclosure to<lb/>
EXHIBIT: D<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23.<lb/>
(Copied from &ldquo;Diario del Commercio&rdquo;, March 10, 1923, Barranquilla,<lb/>
(Colombia).<lb/>
Bucaramanga, <date value="0000-03-09">Marzo 9.</date>
Los Sintomas de la Epidemia de Bucaramanga<lb/>
Detallado informe de los medicos</p>
<p>Los doctores m'Cormick, Serpa, Valdivieso y Feralta han rendido a<lb/>
la Direccion Nacional de Higiene el siguiente informe, sobre la epide mia<lb/>
de esta ciudad: &ldquo;Epidemia caracterizase asi: Ataca particularmente a los<lb/>
forasteros. Sintomas: Calofrio, ascenso rapido; temperatura, de treinta y<lb/>
nueve a quaranta grados; dolores intensos frontales, oculares por presion y<lb/>
movimientos citura y musculares; piel encendida muy seca, ligera rasquina;<lb/>
an orexia, embarazo gastrico, constipacion; descenso temperatura tercer dia,<lb/>
para caer con sudores quinto y sexto; generalmente tercer dia presentase<lb/>
fuerte dolor epigastrico y hepatico, subictericia generalizada, estado nauseoco,<lb/>
vomitos alimenticios que duran hasta remision definitiva. Algunos casos agra-<lb/>
vanse tercer dia y presentanse vomitos negros, deposiciones melenicas, angustia,<lb/>
estado general grave, albuminuria intensa y rapidamente creciente hasta murete;<lb/>
pulso lento, al principio amplio, fuerte; despues depresible, inapreciable;<lb/>
icteria hemafeica; orines sin pigmentos biliarios, albuminuria abundante hasta<lb/>
doce por mil; oxaluria y anuria en varios casos; hemorragia en todas las mucosas<lb/>
y ecchymosis, delirio, terminacion en coma. Casos vomito negro, approximadaments<lb/>
veinte, todos <unclear>fatalles</unclear>. Autopsias solo revelaron existencia liquido hematico vias<lb/>
digestivas; congestiones mucosa gastrica, intestinal, higado palido.&rdquo;</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Bogot&aacute;, Marzo 9</p>
<p>La peste de Bucaramanga.</p>
<p>La direccion Nacional de Higiene se ha dirigido por telegramo<lb/>
extraordinario a la Direccio Departmental de Higiene de Bucaramanga<lb/>
ecigiendole que remita un informe lo mas detallado possible sobre la epidemia<lb/>
reinante en aquella poblacion, con el objeto de dictar las me didas profilacticas<lb/>
del caso para impedir la propagacion.</p>
<pb n="19" id="f01138051"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: E<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23<lb/>
COPY REPORT SENT DR. WHITE CONCERNING REACTIONS.<lb/>
Barranquilla <date value="1923-05-26">May 26th, 1923.</date>
Dr. J. H. White,<lb/>
Chief of the Commission<lb/>
sent to Colombia.<lb/>
Dear Sir:</p>
<p>I wish to report as follows on the reactions obtained from the<lb/>
sera of the cases of Yellow Fever that we saw in Bucaramanga.</p>
<p>The first case was that of Esteben Figueroa, who had been sick<lb/>
five or six days and who presented the cardinal symptoms of yellow fever,<lb/>
in the most typical and classical way. This case was seen by the commission<lb/>
<unclear>on</unclear> May the first 1923 and his blood taken the same morning. On account of the<lb/>
impossibility of obtaining guinea pigs that day, a reaction was made in vitro,<lb/>
using equal parts of serum and a culture of Leptospira Icteroides, (Noguchi<lb/>
Arias Strain). The specimen was observed for a period of half an hour to an<lb/>
hour and gave what appeared to be a complete agglutination. Two days after<lb/>
May 3rd, 1923, having obtained guinea pigs, Pfeiffer test was made and it gave<lb/>
a positive reaction with equal parts of serum and culture of Leptospira<lb/>
Icteroides (Noguchi, Arias Strain).</p>
<p>On May 1st, 1923, we saw another case, Cristobal Rueda, a mild<lb/>
case who was then without fever, after being sick three days. His blood was<lb/>
taken on the same date and submitted also to a reaction in vitro it being<lb/>
impossible on that date to obtain any guinea pigs. It gave a positive reaction<lb/>
with a mixture of equal parts of serum and culture of Leptospira Icteroides<lb/>
(Noguchi, Arias Strain). On May 3/23 having obtained guinea pigs, Pfeiffer<lb/>
test was made and it gave a positive reaction. The reactions of this serum<lb/>
were weaker and appeared after a longer period of time, not before forty-five<lb/>
minutes and were observed one hour and a half.</p>
<p>The Arias Strain was used because these cultures were the best,<lb/>
the others presenting contaminations. The difficulties of transportation<lb/>
that we had to reach Bucaramanga and the transportation on mule back of these<lb/>
cultures by one of us, who had them continually with him did not prevent the<lb/>
action of excessive heat on them, and also the more or less jarring in riding,<lb/>
may have accounted for the contamination of several of the cultures, the<lb/>
Arias Strain were all free from contaminations.</p>
<p>On May 4, 1923, we went to the College San Pedro, where several<lb/>
cases had appeared in February. We saw two of these cases, one a very severe<lb/>
case Father Hidalgo, and the other one a mild case, one of the brothers of<lb/>
the order, Jesuits. Their blood was taken and carried to Bogota, in sealed<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f01138052"/>
EXHIBIT: E (Continued)<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23.<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
ampoules, that is the serum. These were subjected to Pfeiffer reaction<lb/>
in Bogota at the laboratory of Drs. Samper and Martinez. They gave positive<lb/>
reactions with equal parts of serum and cultures of Leptospira Icteroides<lb/>
(Arias Strain).</p>
<p>The cross-reaction with Leptospira Icterohaemorrhagica, were<lb/>
made with the serum obtained from Figueroa and from Father Hidalgo, only.<lb/>
These Pfeiffer reactions with Leptospira Icterohaemorrhagica were negative,<lb/>
the reaction was made one part of serum to fifty parts of culture.</p>
<p>We would have made a series of reactions at different titers had<lb/>
it not been the difficulties that we had in obtaining the proper light and<lb/>
other accessories. We deemed however that these reactions were sufficiently<lb/>
clear to establish a positive diagnosis, they were seen by all of the commission<lb/>
and Drs. Samper and Martiniz, in whose laboratory we were working.</p>
<p>I wish to state that I owe many thanks to Dr. McCormick, in<lb/>
Bucaramanga for the use of his laboratory and apparatus, and his kind assis-<lb/>
tance in my work and in procuring guinea pigs. In Bogota to Drs. Samper and<lb/>
Martini who put their exceptionally well equipped laboratory at my disposal<lb/>
and that of the commission, and furnished all the guinea pigs that I needed.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted,<lb/>
(Signed) O. L. Pothier.</p>
<pb n="21" id="f01138053"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: F<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT: 8/20/23.<lb/>
COPY OF REPORT SENT BY DR. PAREJA AND MYSELF TO THE<lb/>
GOVERNOR OF THE STATE OF ATLANTICO COLOMBIA, RELATIVE TO OUR<lb/>
INVESTIGATION OF PUERTO COLOMBIA FOR SMALLPOX.<lb/>
Barranquilla <date value="1923-05-30">30 de Mayo de 1923.</date>
Snor Gobernador del Departamento del Atlantico<lb/>
Presente:<lb/>
Muy Senor Nuestro:</p>
<p>Accediendo al deseo que Ud nos manifesto verbalmente, hemos<lb/>
visitado ayer la poblacion de Puerto Colombia, en donde, acompanados del<lb/>
Senor Alcade, del Medico del Puerto, del Senor Comandante del Resguardo<lb/>
y de otras personas mas recorrimos proligamente todas las casas del barrio<lb/>
de la carretera, en donde se suponia la existencia de casos de viruela, sin<lb/>
encontrar un solo enfermo, ni siquiera sospech oso de tal infeccion. Tambien<lb/>
visitamos otras casas del centro de la ciudad con el mismo resultado.</p>
<p>Lo cual nos es grato communicar a Ud para las fines que a bien<lb/>
tenga.</p>
<p>Somos de Ud. atentos y seguros servidores,</p>
<p>(Signed) W. Pareja,<lb/>
O. L. Pothier.</p>
<pb n="22" id="f01138054"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: G<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT 8/20/23.<lb/>
LOYALA UNIVERSITY.<lb/>
Department of<lb/>
BACTERIOLOGY AND CLINICAL LABORATORY.<lb/>
PROF. O. L. POTHIER, Director.<lb/>
6363 St. Charles Ave.<lb/>
Address all communications to<lb/>
Dr. O. L. Pothier, 124 Baronne St.<lb/>
New Orleans, La.<lb/>
Cucuta, <date value="1923-06-14">June 14, 1923.</date>
Dr. J. H. White,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway,<lb/>
New York, N.Y.<lb/>
Dear Sir:</p>
<p>We arrived here yesterday, in the evening, June the thirteenth,<lb/>
after a delayed voyage from Barraquilla. We were delayed two days in<lb/>
Curacao, leaving there on Saturday, June the tenth (should be the ninth, as<lb/>
the rest of this report will indicate), and arriving in Maracaibo Sunday,<lb/>
the eleventh (should be the tenth, as the rest of this report will indicate).<lb/>
As we could not leave Maracaibo until the following Thursday, by the weekly<lb/>
mail boat, we chartered a small tug boat which took us to Encontrados.<lb/>
Leaving Maracaibo at one A.M. Tuesday, June the twelfth, we arrived at<lb/>
Encontrados Wednesday morning the thirteenth. From Encontrados, due to the<lb/>
kindness of the President of the State of Zulia, a special train was put at<lb/>
our disposal to take us to Tachira Station, from whence we came to Cucuta in<lb/>
automobile.</p>
<p>This morning, in company of the Chief of Hygiene, we visited the<lb/>
hospital, which we found free from yellow fever or any suspicious cases.<lb/>
After we called on the Governor, in whose company we visited the Barracks<lb/>
infirmary, which we also found free from yellow fever or suspicious cases.<lb/>
From the report of several of the physicians, whom we met, and who were very<lb/>
cordial, we obtained the information that there were no cases in the city<lb/>
of a suspicious nature. On the other hand they informed us of the great<lb/>
incidence of stegomyia, a fact verified by personal observation.</p>
<p>When we called on the Governor we impressed the necessity of mosquito<lb/>
campaign, on account of the proximity to Bucaramanga, and of the danger of in-<lb/>
fection. At the request of the Governor, we agreed to sign a telegram to the<lb/>
National Chief of Hygiene, concerning the status of Cucuta, and our recommenda-<lb/>
tion of a mosquito campaign. This telegram was a joint one to Dr. P. Garcia<lb/>
Medina, and Dr. F. A. Miller, and sent from the office of the Governor, after<lb/>
having been signed by Dr. W. Pareja and Dr. O. L. Pothier.</p>
<p>This completes our mission to Cucuta<unclear>.</unclear> We are leaving tomorrow<lb/>
afternoon, June the fifteenth, on our return to Maracaibo, and thence to<lb/>
Curacao, to take the earliest steamer to Colon, from which we respectively<lb/>
will return home.</p>
<pb n="23" id="f01138055"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: G (Continued)<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT 8/20/23.</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>In Maracaibo we were extended a courteous and cordial reception<lb/>
by the President of the State of Zulia, through the offices of Drs. Aranguren<lb/>
and Irarazabal, respectively Port Physician and Inspector of Customs, and the<lb/>
Secretary General of the State. After this cordial reception we sent a tele-<lb/>
gram of thanks to the President of the Republic which was duly acknowledged.<lb/>
Here in Cucuta the Governor and other officials, and physicians were cordiality<lb/>
itself.</p>
<p>Trusting that this report will meet with your approval, we wish<lb/>
to remain,</p>
<p>Respectfully,<lb/>
(Signed) Dr. W. Pareja,<lb/>
Dr. O. L. Pothier.<lb/>
(Original to Dr. J. H. White)<lb/>
(Copies to Drs. Pareja and Pothier)<lb/>
N.B. In the first paragraph of this report there is a typographical error<lb/>
instead of the tenth of June it should be the ninth, and the date of arrival<lb/>
in Maracaibo should be the tenth instead of the eleventh. The days mentioned<lb/>
will prove this to be an error in writing, as Saturday and Sunday were respect-<lb/>
ively the ninth and the tenth of June.</p>
<pb n="24" id="f01138056"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: H<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT. 8/20/23.<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
International Health Board<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York.<lb/>
<date value="1923-06-12">June 12, 1923</date>
Dear Doctor Pothier:</p>
<p>Doctor White reached New York yesterday, and gave us an interesting<lb/>
account of conditions in Colombia. He is planning to sail for Brazil the last<lb/>
of this month. Since Doctor White is not returning to Colombia at this time,<lb/>
we think it would be desirable for you to return to New Orleans, by way of<lb/>
New York after the completion of the survey. Please let us know by cable<lb/>
when to expect you.</p>
<p>I am sending a similar letter to you care of the Chief Health Officer,<lb/>
Balboa Heights, Canal Zone, and another care of the United Fruit Company, Colon.</p>
<p>Very sincerely yours,<lb/>
(Signed) F. F. Russell.<lb/>
Doctor O. L. Pothier<lb/>
c/o C. A. Hearn<lb/>
Quarantine Officer<lb/>
Colon, Panama<lb/>
FRR:EP</p>
<pb n="25" id="f01138057"/>
<p>EXHIBIT: I<lb/>
APPENDED DR. O.L.P.<lb/>
REPORT. 8/20/23.<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
International Health Board<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York.<lb/>
<date value="1923-06-21">June 21, 1923.</date>
Dear Doctor Pothier:</p>
<p>I am writing to confirm Doctor White's request that you<lb/>
telegraph this office when you reach home, in order that your salary<lb/>
payments may be adjusted.</p>
<p>Doctor White asks also that you and Doctor Parejo send<lb/>
individual reports of your work in Colombia, so that he can consolidate<lb/>
them with his own statement into one report which can be signed by all<lb/>
three members of the commission.</p>
<p>Very sincerely yours,<lb/>
(Signed) Florence M. Read.<lb/>
Doctor O. L. Pothier,<lb/>
124 Baronne Street,<lb/>
New Orleans, La.<lb/>
FRR:EP</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
