<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01138002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from H. Muench to H. H. Howard, December 4, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Muench, H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01138002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-12-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Howard, H.H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">British Guiana</name>
<name type="place">French Guiana</name>
<name type="place">Dutch Guiana</name>
<name type="place">Surinam</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-12-04">December 4, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01138002</idno>
<title>Letter from H. Muench to H. H. Howard, December 4, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Muench summarizes data that he collected on yellow fever in the Guianas. He mentions the great ignorance or diffidence displayed by the sanitary authorities.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-12-04">
<head>Letter from H. Muench to H. H. Howard, December 4, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01138002"/>
<opener>
<hi>Copy</hi><lb/>
ANKYLOSTOMIASIS COMMISSION<lb/>
Paramaribo-Surinam.<lb/>
P.O.B. Box 349<lb/>
<dateline>
St. Johns, Antigua,<lb/>
Tuesday, 4.xii. 23<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Howard:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am enclosing the various data on yellow fever in the Guianas<lb/>
which I have been able to collect. In order to save time, I am giving<lb/>
below a short resume of the main points brot out.</p>
<p>BRITISH GUIANA (Demerara):</p>
<p>Enclosed are papers, collected by Dr. J.F.C. Haslam, Medical<lb/>
Officer of Health of Demerara. These are copies of the most important<lb/>
replies received by him in answer to an inquiry sent out when it was<lb/>
announced that a yellow fever committee would probably visit Demerara.</p>
<p>Two of these papers are by old inhabitants of the colony;<lb/>
laymen. The other is from the oldest practising physician.</p>
<p>Apparently, yellow fever was not prevalent, or not recognized<lb/>
to any extent before 1800 or thereabouts. From then on it seems to have<lb/>
become increasingly common in Georgetown until the great fires in 1864,<lb/>
after which it seems to have decreased somewhat. There seem to have been<lb/>
epidemics in the 1880s and '90s, after which the disease gradually died<lb/>
down, and, according to all available information, has not been heard of<lb/>
since in the colony.</p>
<p><unclear>ravan<lb/>
Big - often<lb/>
1892</unclear></p>
<p>FRENCH GUIANA:</p>
<p>No papers are enclosed. I called on Dr. Blin, Surgeon General,<lb/>
in Cayenne. In spite of the fact that I had announced my coming some weeks<lb/>
previously, he knew nothing about it and had no data available. Besides,<lb/>
he had only recently arrived in French Guiana, and was not familiar with<lb/>
the past history to any great extent. He promised, however, to have all<lb/>
data on old outbreaks collected and sent to me. So far, they have not<lb/>
arrived.</p>
<p>According to Dr. Blin, yellow fever was endemic in the colony<lb/>
until 1902. There would be outbreaks, from time to time, of &ldquo;<unclear>fievro</unclear> bilieuse<lb/>
inflammatoire&rdquo;, which would gradually change into yellow fever. These out-<lb/>
breaks usually followed the digging of ditches, graves, etc., in old ceme-<lb/>
teries where yellow fever patients had been buried, sometimes a generation<lb/>
before.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01138003"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>This &ldquo;bilious inflammatory fever&rdquo; would start somewhere farther<lb/>
north; probably in the West Indies, and be carried down by way of Dutch<lb/>
Guiana, by which time it would have been transformed into yellow fever.<lb/>
1902, the year of the last outbreak, was a year of general yellow fever<lb/>
epidemics all over the West Indies.</p>
<p><unclear>maroni</unclear></p>
<p>Since 1902, there has been no yellow fever in the colony; only<lb/>
suspected cases of &ldquo;bilious inflammatory fever&rdquo;. However, within two months<lb/>
before my visit (end of September, 1923) there had been two cases of undoubted<lb/>
yellow fever on one of the <hi>Iles de Salut</hi>. One of the cases died and showed<lb/>
typical lesions at autopsy. The other recovered, but ran a typical clinical<lb/>
course.</p>
<p>This information is extremely interesting in that the Iles de Salut<lb/>
are penitentiary islands along the coast (Devil's Island is one), with which<lb/>
there is no communication except for an occasional boat from and to Cayenne.<lb/>
Dr. Blin's explanation for the occurrence is that the convicts on this is-<lb/>
land had just been digging in an old disused graveyard in which yellow fever<lb/>
cases had in olden times been buried. The cases were the first in fifteen<lb/>
years to be diagnosed as yellow fever.</p>
<p>DUTCH GUIANA:</p>
<p>Two copies of a translation of a report by Prof. Flu, on a yellow<lb/>
fever epidemic in Surinam in 1908, are enclosed. This report, tho detailed<lb/>
and long, is worth reading, as it was made by a trained epidemiologist who had<lb/>
apparently been studying the question rather closely. Without going into<lb/>
the report here, the main points are as follows:</p>
<p>Yellow fever, formerly prevalent, disappeared from the colony in<lb/>
1866 and did not reappear until a deadly epidemic in 1902. It then was un-<lb/>
heard-of until the epidemic described in the report, in 1908-09, which occurred<lb/>
in a batch of new recruits just out of Holland. Since then, it has again<lb/>
been unheard-of.</p>
<p>Flu stresses the point that there were a good many borderline cases<lb/>
some time after the epidemic, and some quite a while before, which could very<lb/>
well have been yellow fever; also, that the 1908 epidemic not only did not<lb/>
attack those who had been thru the 1902 epidemic, but left alone all who had<lb/>
been in the colony for longer than a year or so.</p>
<p>Aside from Flu's report, there was nothing to be found out. Appar-<lb/>
ently, it comprised the sole yellow fever records in the Medical Inspector<lb/>
General's office. In fact, it appeared to be news to the Medical Inspector<lb/>
General that there had been another epidemic in 1902, and that there had been<lb/>
yellow fever in the colony before 1866.</p>
<p>GENERAL SUMMARY:</p>
<p>The most striking point, when trying to collect yellow fever statis-<lb/>
tics, is the great ignorance (or diffidence) exhibited by sanitary authorities<lb/>
regarding the occurrence of the disease. Some appear to regard it almost as<lb/>
treason to admit the occurrence of an epidemic which was known thruout the<lb/>
world. I have even had denials that the epidemic in Surinam in 1902 was one<lb/>
of yellow fever -- in spite of the 29 deaths.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01138004"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>Another striking point is the overlapping of dates. By this I<lb/>
mean that one observer will note yellow fever during certain years, but<lb/>
deny it in the interim; while another will cite other years of incidence.<lb/>
For instance, Flu says that there was no yellow fever in Surinam from<lb/>
1866 to 1902. Blin, however, says that yellow fever was constant in<lb/>
French Guiana until 1902, kept alive by importations from Surinam. Thru<lb/>
such overlapping dates, one acquires the suspicion that yellow fever may<lb/>
have been pretty constant thruout over long periods of time, altho indi-<lb/>
vidual medical observers may have seen none for years on end.</p>
<p><unclear>region<lb/>
elfauns<lb/>
gistahian<lb/>
as a whole</unclear></p>
<p>Finally, the point brot out by Flu, namely, the immunization<lb/>
of a population to yellow fever without the (apparent) presence of the<lb/>
fever, points to some sort of constant condition. Either a mild form of<lb/>
the disease is continually present, as Flu suggests. This would explain<lb/>
the immune population; also the two cases on the Iles de Salut, which<lb/>
would otherwise be hard to explain without adopting the French graveyard<lb/>
theory.</p>
<p>Or, there is some closely allied and prevalent disease which<lb/>
gives immunity also to yellow fever. There is a sort of mild &ldquo;dengue&rdquo;<lb/>
very common in Surinam, which might be an extremely mild yellow fever, or<lb/>
a very similar disease; perhaps almost or quite as nearly related as vaccinia<lb/>
is to variola. Some support of this theory could be found in recent work<lb/>
done by some Dutch scientists in Java, who are isolating spirillae of the<lb/>
&ldquo;icteroides&rdquo; type from a number of tropical fevers of different kinds, which<lb/>
may thereby prove to bear some sort of relation to each other.</p>
<p>1917</p>
<p>In any case, there seems to be little possibility of tracing any<lb/>
course of yellow fever infection thru the Guianas. Yellow fever is supposed<lb/>
to be extinct; whether it really is, or is lying dormant in a much attenuated<lb/>
form awaiting the arrival of favorable conditions, including a large importa-<lb/>
tion of non-immune population, is questionable. It will probably be impossi-<lb/>
ble to answer the question until we have a definite and delicate means of<lb/>
diagnosing extremely mild cases.</p>
<p>* * * * *</p>
<p>I am sorry that it seems impossible to get more definite information<lb/>
along the lines the Board desired. In view of the fact, however, that officially<lb/>
there is no yellow fever, and that there has been none for many years, it is<lb/>
hard to trace down any course of infection.</p>
<p>If this report is of any use whatever to the Board, I shall be<lb/>
greatly pleased.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) H. Muench</signed>
Dr. H. H. Howard,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, N.Y.C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
