<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01139020">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Hideyo Noguchi to Frederick F. Russell, January 31, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Noguchi, Hideyo</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01139020</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-01-31</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Russell, Frederick F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Scannell, E.J.</name>
<name type="person">Walcott, Alan</name>
<name type="person">Muller, Henry R.</name>
<name type="place">Bahia (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Recife (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Fortaleza (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Para (Brazil</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-01-31">January 31, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01139020</idno>
<title>Letter from Hideyo Noguchi to Frederick F. Russell, January 31, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Noguchi discusses his leptospira work in Brazil.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-01-31">
<head>Letter from Hideyo Noguchi to Frederick F. Russell, January 31, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01139020"/>
<opener>
COPY.<lb/>
<dateline>
Bahia,<lb/>
<date value="1924-01-31">January 31, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Colonel Russell:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I ought to have written you before this, but I knew you were<lb/>
abroad and I have waited also until I had something worth while writing.<lb/>
Leaving the minor details for personal reports to be made on my return<lb/>
I have this much to say: We reached Bahia, via Rio, on November 29,<lb/>
last year and were comfortably located in a rented house where Dr. White<lb/>
is also staying. Thanks to the effective cooperation of Dr. <unclear>Strode;s</unclear> of-<lb/>
fice through Dr. Janney, and Dr. Scannell who preceded us by two months<lb/>
in Bahia, a practically new laboratory called &ldquo;Oswaldo Cruz Institute of<lb/>
Bahia&rdquo; was placed at our disposal at once. The director, Dr. Augusto Vianna,<lb/>
came over to our house and handed over the whole building. We found the<lb/>
plans of the laboratory unsurpassed and that by equipping up with our ma-<lb/>
terial it would make an excellent place for any kind of research work.<lb/>
It took nearly two weeks to do this, but we soon commenced to start.<lb/>
Since our arrival there has not been a single case of yellow fever and no<lb/>
Stegomyia either. Thus, we decided to make the Pfeiffer reaction with<lb/>
the convalescents' serums from cases that occurred during the year of 1923<lb/>
--and there were 156 cases in all. We soon found that to obtain serums for<lb/>
the Pfeiffer tests we had to reach the patients through their physicians.<lb/>
This necessitated the cooperation of some Brazilian physicians and we en-<lb/>
gaged a few young University Professors to work with us. We finally got<lb/>
nine serums from convalescents and four normal serums. The tests were made<lb/>
with several strains of Leptospira icteroides on one hand and Leptospira<lb/>
icterohemorrhagica on the other, in parallel series at the same time. It<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01139021"/>
Colonel Russell -<lb/>
- Page 2 -<lb/>
was previously announced so as to invite the entire faculty of the Medi-<lb/>
cal School here to see the tests actually carried out. After showing the<lb/>
technique I requested the Brazilian bacteriologists and pathologists to per-<lb/>
form the tests themselves and this was done. Muller worked with them.<lb/>
The results were clear out. All the convalescents' serums gave a <unclear>positive</unclear><lb/>
and the normal a negative Pfeiffer. On the other hand, Letospira ictero-<lb/>
hemorrhagiae remained absolutely unaffected either by the convalescents' or<lb/>
normal human serums. This occurred on December 20th and ever since we are<lb/>
having a whole hearted cooperation of the medical profession of Bahia in<lb/>
search of yellow fever cases. The bitterest of &ldquo;icteroides&rdquo; opponents--<lb/>
of whom there were many in Bahia and Brazil in general--frankly came to<lb/>
accept the fact. They also came to realize why Borges-Vieira and a few<lb/>
others failed--they saw the difference in technic and even the handling of<lb/>
the dark field microscope. In fact, there were three dark field microscopes<lb/>
in Bahia, but none was fitted up so as to see Leptospira icteroides. I made<lb/>
one out of the different parts from these three microscopes, then it worked.<lb/>
In addition we brought with us two darkfields and used all three for the de-<lb/>
monstration on that day. Our own animals came in good <unclear>condition<del>s</del></unclear> and this<lb/>
was another factor contributing to the useful results. I can understand<lb/>
why they have been so unsuccessful in their attempts along this line of work.<lb/>
It cannot be done unless properly equipped and <hi>thoroughly trained</hi>.</p>
<p>The second episode occurred on January 4 this year. Dr. Godofredo<lb/>
Vianna and Dr. Mario Biao, two selected yellow fever experts belonging to the<lb/>
Prophylaxia Rural Nacional (a Federal branch at Bahia) went into the interior<lb/>
at the urgent request of the Mayor of <unclear>Len&ccedil;oes</unclear>, some hundred miles away from<lb/>
Bahia, to combat the yellow fever situation in a near-by town (3000 Population)<lb/>
called Palmeiras. They went there in the middle of December and took with<lb/>
them culture media tubes to make culture from yellow fever patients. One of<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01139022"/>
Colonel Russell -<lb/>
- Page 3. -<lb/>
the men (Dr. Vianna) came back on January 4 with the tubes inoculated with<lb/>
the blood from five typical cases. These tubes were at once examined by the<lb/>
members of the Oswaldo Cruz Institute staff. That day Leptospira was found<lb/>
in one of the tubes (30 in number). A few days later another tube showed<lb/>
the leptospira. The first positive culture came from a case in which blood<lb/>
was drawn on the 1st day of the disease and the second positive one from<lb/>
another in which blood was taken on the 2nd day of illness. Thus two out<lb/>
of five cases studied Leptospira was isolated. In fact, if contaminations<lb/>
had not occurred in so many tubes we might have had more strains. Animals<lb/>
were subsequently inoculated with these two strains and some of them came<lb/>
down with typical symptoms and lesions. The convalescents' serums from Ba-<lb/>
hia cases gave a clear positive Pfeiffer reaction with both strains from Pal-<lb/>
meiras. I am now awaiting the return of the other man, who will bring back<lb/>
the convalescents' serums from Palmeiras cases to test the other as well as<lb/>
the Palmeiras strains of L. icteroides. This will complete, for the time<lb/>
being at least, our immediate work in Bahia. Chagas has been wiring me at<lb/>
frequent intervals telling me of his intention to come up and I hope he will<lb/>
make the trip before we get away from Bahia. The failures of the Brazilian<lb/>
workers previous to our expedition were <hi>solely</hi> due to inadequate preparations<lb/>
to undertake this kind of work. They used full grown native guinea pigs and<lb/>
in small numbers at that. Their culture media were untested before use for<lb/>
their suitability and they always omit any reference as to the number of cul-<lb/>
ture tubes used or how many of them remained uncontaminated. No leptospira<lb/>
will grow where another organism is growing--they will quickly disappear even<lb/>
if they started to grow as soon as a mould gets in. And you must know how<lb/>
difficult it is to keep out moulds in tropics! I am wasting so many culture<lb/>
tubes here only through this uncontrollable fungus invasion through every<lb/>
kind of stopper. These things are not well understood by most people. Why<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01139023"/>
Colonel Russell -<lb/>
- Page 4. -<lb/>
every man who fails to obtain a positive transmission or a culture of L.<lb/>
icteroides feels it his duty to conclude that there was no leptospira be-<lb/>
cause he did not find it or isolate it, is a matter hard to understand.<lb/>
Lebredos negative results in Merida in 1919 have been keenly read here and<lb/>
taken as a grave indictment for L. icteroides. But, he had no darkfield to<lb/>
see a leptospira even taken from a rich culture and placed under it. He<lb/>
used old Havana guinea pigs for transmission and all his cultures were con-<lb/>
taminated either with a bacterium or a mould--I saw them in his own labor-<lb/>
atory in 1919 just after his expedition to Merida. I came to Brazil partly<lb/>
because I wanted to show them the possible sources of failure and how to<lb/>
get a positive result. I believe I succeeded in both.</p>
<p>In Recife there has been rumors that there have been some cases<lb/>
of yellow fever not officially reported. Through Dr. Walcott we sent up two<lb/>
batches of culture media for obtaining cultures. Altogether four cases were<lb/>
studied by this way, every one of the tubes sent back by him was found con-<lb/>
taminated with all kinds of microorganisms from cocci down to moulds. We are<lb/>
planning to go up there some time in February and, if there are some cases,<lb/>
to study them there. From there we will go to Fortaleza and get some reliable<lb/>
statistics regarding the use of the vaccine and serum during the epidemic of<lb/>
1922-1923. From there to Par&aacute; and then back to New York by the Booth Line.<lb/>
Probably we will be back about the middle of March. During my stay here I<lb/>
have been giving some practical instructions to some of the young Brazilian<lb/>
physicians connected with the Medical Faculty and Department of Health and this<lb/>
has been mutually beneficial in so far as to know each other more intimately.<lb/>
It is one thing to read one's published articles and another to watch him in<lb/>
his actual working at a close range. Some of them are very promising. Dr. Wells<lb/>
can do much for developing good men, I think. There is altogether too little<lb/>
American medical influence here and that should not be.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01139024"/>
<p>Colonel Russell -</p>
<p>- Page 5 -</p>
<p>I meant to be brief, but after a few words many more followed,<lb/>
so you have more than you want to read.</p>
<p>I hope you have had a pleasant and interesting trip to Europe and<lb/>
that you are well as usual.</p>
<p>Muller is one splendid man and has been a great strength and com-<lb/>
fort to me all through these days.</p>
<p>With kindest regards and best wishes, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
<signed>Sgd. Hideyo Noguchi</signed>.
Give my regards to Dr. Rose, please.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
