<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01142001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Article: Reed, Gorgas and Yellow Fever, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 7, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01142001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-04-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Eliot, Charles W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-04-07">April 7, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01142001</idno>
<title>Article: Reed, Gorgas and Yellow Fever, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 7, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean writes about the campaign against yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-04-07">
<head>Article: Reed, Gorgas and Yellow Fever, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 7, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01142001"/>
<opener>
<hi>Pub. in N. Y. Times Ap. 17/24</hi><lb/>
Sent first to Mr Hendrick, Editor of the<lb/>
World's Work-<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1924-04-07">7 April 1924.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p><hi>REED</hi>, <hi>GORGAS AND YELLOW FEVER</hi></p>
<p>In June 1902 President Charles W. Eliot of Harvard University gave<lb/>
to Major Walter Reed the honorary degree of M.A. with the citation, &ldquo;he gave<lb/>
to man control over that dreadful plague, yellow fever&rdquo;. This is the in-<lb/>
scription on Reed's tombstone in Arlington Cemetery and its truth has not been<lb/>
challenged until now. Therefore the friends of Reed and Gorgas and persons<lb/>
interested in the history of medicine have been surprised recently to see what<lb/>
was the crowning accomplishment of Reed's life, the demonstration that the<lb/>
Stegomyia mosquito was the infecting agent of yellow fever and the only one,<lb/>
claimed for another and that other, Gorgas.</p>
<p>In a very clever and entertaining article in a current magazine,<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Fever meets its Master&rdquo;, by Marie Doughty Gorgas and Burton J.<lb/>
Hendrick, occurs the statement, &ldquo;Even when Reed had completed his work,<lb/>
Gorgas's position was still one of extreme caution. That the Stegomyia<lb/>
mosquito could transmit the disease was unassailably proved; but was this<lb/>
the only way in which it could be conveyed? Was it even the ordinary way?<lb/>
That, Gorgas held, had not been demonstrated----------. In the next few<lb/>
months, however, it was clearly to be shown that the Stegomyia, and the<lb/>
Stegomyia only, was the infecting agent and the man who was to make this<lb/>
clear for all time <hi>was Gorgas himself</hi>&rdquo;.</p>
<p>This statement arrived at its conclusion by ignoring the admirable<lb/>
and convincing series of experiments of Reed <hi>with infected bedding and cloth-<lb/>
ing and with the discharges from patients</hi>, which made it as clear as the<lb/>
noonday that the Stegomyia was the ordinary and the only normal way of trans-<lb/>
mitting the disease. If these experiments did not convince Gorgas, neither<lb/>
could conviction be drawn from his own experience in the next few months,<lb/>
1.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01142002"/>
for he continued, until the middle of August 1901, the disinfection of bedding<lb/>
and clothing of yellow fever cases which Reed had shown to be unnecessary.<lb/>
This claim is introductory to a statement in the beginning of the fourth chapter<lb/>
which is equally erroneous. It is that Reed's demonstration was a mere academic<lb/>
performance which Reed himself saw no practical way of applying. The intimation<lb/>
clearly is that the methods of warfare against the mosquito were unknown until<lb/>
devised and put into operation by Gorgas about February 15, 1901. This is,<lb/>
however, far from being the fact. The writings of the distinguished Entimolo-<lb/>
gist, L. O. Howard, had made the use of kerosene to control mosquito breeding<lb/>
well known to Army Sanitarians. Under the stimulation of Reed's influence the<lb/>
Chief Surgeon of the Department of Western Cuba had, on October 15, 1900, three<lb/>
months before the acceptance by Gorgas of the mosquito theory, published a<lb/>
circular to medical officers calling attention to the fact that mosquitos were<lb/>
known to convey malaria and filarial disease and were suspected of conveying<lb/>
yellow fever also, and directing the prevention of mosquito breeding by the<lb/>
use of kerosene on deposits of water. On December 21, 1900, still before the<lb/>
conversion of Gorgas, General Order No.6 was issued from General Leonard Wood's<lb/>
Headquarters directing, with minuteness of detail, the warfare against mosquitos.<lb/>
As Gorgas began to put in practice <add>more than</add> two months later the procedures specified<lb/>
in this order, it cannot be claimed that he was the discoverer of anything not<lb/>
already known. The General Order above mentioned was published in Havard's<lb/>
Military Hygiene, 2nd Edition, Wm. Wood &amp; Co. What he did do is well stated<lb/>
in a letter he wrote to Reed, dated August 26, 1901, in which he says, &ldquo;I am<lb/>
very happy to shine in the more humble role of being the first to put your<lb/>
discovery to extensive practical application&rdquo;.</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01142003"/>
<p>The fame of Gorgas is secure in the performance of the greatest<lb/>
feat of sanitary administration that the world has seen. It does not need<lb/>
augmentation by claiming for him what belongs to his brilliant and unreward-<lb/>
ed friend, Walter Reed.</p>
<closer>
<signed>J. R. Kean,<lb/>
Colonel, Medical Corps, U.S. Army,<lb/>
Corps Area Surgeon</signed>.
Boston April 7, 1924.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
