<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01140001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, March 5, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01140001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-03-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">Georgia</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Tennessee</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-03-05">March 5, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01140001</idno>
<title>Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, March 5, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fricks reports on malaria investigations conducted in the southern United States.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-03-05">
<head>Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, March 5, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01140001"/>
<opener>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MALARIA INVESTIGATIONS<lb/>
FIELD HEADQUARTERS<lb/>
ROOM 17, COURTHOUSE<lb/>
<dateline>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
MEMPHIS, TENN.<lb/>
<date value="1924-03-05">March 5, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
FB<lb/>
COPY<lb/>
Monthly Progress Report,<lb/>
<hi>-----February 1924-----</hi><lb/>
The Surgeon General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Division of Scientific Research,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to forward herewith monthly progress re-<lb/>
port of malaria investigations conducted during the month of<lb/>
February, 1924, under the direction of this office:</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Crowley, La.:</hi> Personnel - Special Expert<lb/>
M. A. Barber, Asst. San. Eng. W. H. W. Komp and Asst. San. Eng.<lb/>
J. G. Foster.</p>
<p>Activities at the Crowley Laboratory consisted of: (1) Prepa-<lb/>
ration of reports and papers for publication; (2) Observations<lb/>
on winter incidence of Anopheles, Anopheles collected thirteen,<lb/>
of which eleven were A. quadrimaculatus and two A. crucians,<lb/>
twelve females and one male (A. crucians); larvae and pupae col-<lb/>
lected and bred out one hundred and thirty-two, of which one<lb/>
hundred and twenty-five were A. crucians and seven A. quadrimacu-<lb/>
latus; (3) Sixty-six blood specimens examined for malaria para-<lb/>
sites, nine positive, two P. vivax and seven P. falc.; four of<lb/>
these positives were positive last year.</p>
<p><hi>Memphis Laboratory:</hi> Personnel - A. A. Surgeon Wm. A. Krauss,<lb/>
Microscopists Ethel Barrier and Retha Kitchens.</p>
<p>Six hundred and thirty-three smears were examined for malaria<lb/>
parasites; sixty-six collected locally showed four positives;<lb/>
one hundred and six from Greenwood, Miss., showed thirteen posi-<lb/>
tives; four hundred and sixty-one from Gulfport, Miss., showed<lb/>
thirty positives, of the sixty-seven positives sixty were<lb/>
P. falc., six P. vivax and one P. falc and P. vivax.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01140002"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>March 5, 1924.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Savannah, Ga.:</hi> Personnel - Technical Assistant<lb/>
Bruce Mayne.</p>
<p>Study of winter activities of Anopheles continued: Findings a-<lb/>
bout the same as previously reported; apparently Anopheles pass<lb/>
the winter largely in the aquatic stages in this locality; what<lb/>
appeared to be two-day larvae of A. crucians were observed; ex-<lb/>
cept around midday larvae were collected in greatest numbers from<lb/>
bottom mud; no male Anopheles observed; no adult Anopheles found;<lb/>
one hundred and twenty-eight blood smears examined, one positive.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemiological Studies of Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Asst. Surgeon<lb/>
K. F. Maxcy.</p>
<p>Compilation of data collected last year regarding malaria preva-<lb/>
lence in Alabama; three maps were prepared showing location of<lb/>
malaria based on positive slides, based on physicians' reports<lb/>
and based on malaria deaths; analysis made of two hundred and<lb/>
seven death certificates attributed to malaria, cause of death<lb/>
doubtful in 50% of cases.</p>
<p><hi>Impounded Waters in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Epidemiolo-<lb/>
gist T. H. D. Griffitts and Asst. San. Eng. E. H. Gage.</p>
<p>No impounded water studies conducted by Dr. Griffitts during Feb-<lb/>
ruary. No observations reported.</p>
<p>Mr. Gage reports finding Anopheles larvae and pupae in many ponds<lb/>
and seepage pools of Aiken County, South Carolina, full grown<lb/>
larvae and pupae predominating, occasionally small larvae were<lb/>
found; all emergences A. crucians, 58% of which were males. No<lb/>
adult Anopheles found until February 28th, when one female puncti-<lb/>
pennis was found in a hollow tree.</p>
<p><hi>Major Drainage in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Assoc. San.<lb/>
Eng. A. W. Fuchs.</p>
<p>Data collected in McKinney Lake District in Tunica County, Miss.,<lb/>
analyzed and summarized. Hibernation observations made February<lb/>
21 and 22, freezing temperature at night, in Crittenden County,<lb/>
Ark., and Tunica County, Miss.; one A. punctipennis and one<lb/>
A. quadrimaculatus caught under bridges, three A. quadrimaculatus<lb/>
in one house and three in one barn. Study was made of tempera-<lb/>
ture and humidity records in relation to malaria distribution.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01140003"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>March 5, 1924.</p>
<p><hi>Rural Malaria Investigations:</hi> Personnel - Asst. San. Eng. J. C.<lb/>
Carter, A. A. Surgeon C. P. Coogle, Assoc. San. Eng. L. M. Fisher,<lb/>
Asst. San. Eng. H. N. Old, Asst. San. Eng. F. R. Shaw, and<lb/>
Surgeon L. L. Williams, Jr.</p>
<p>Mr. Carter (Alabama) conferred with county health officers of<lb/>
Houston, Barbour and Covington Counties relative to malaria con-<lb/>
trol program for 1924, and with county health officials of Dothan<lb/>
and Eufaula. Made survey of drainage project in Autauga County;<lb/>
collected nineteen adult Anopheles in Houston County, five A.<lb/>
crucians, fourteen A. punctipennis (female); collected three adult<lb/>
A. punctipennis (female) in Covington County February 27th.</p>
<p>Mr. Old (Georgia) assisted Dr. Coogle in malaria school surveys;<lb/>
one thousand three hundred and sixty-four Chatham County school<lb/>
children examined, less than one-half one one per cent enlarged<lb/>
spleens found, thorough inspection made of borrow pits along the<lb/>
A. C. L. Railway; malaria spot map of county being prepared;<lb/>
establishment of a full-time county health department recommended<lb/>
by the Frand Jury.</p>
<p>Mr. Shaw (Louisiana) reports: Program of urban and rural malaria<lb/>
control in Tangipahoa Parish outlined to parish health officer<lb/>
and local officials; study of winter habits of Anopheles contin-<lb/>
ued, many Anopheles larvae but no pupae collected; a screen cage<lb/>
was erected over a lumber pile at Hammond in an effort to col-<lb/>
lect hibernating adults, none found during several days observa-<lb/>
tions.</p>
<p>Mr. Fisher (South Carolina): Studies of malaria prevalence in<lb/>
eighteen counties continued; seventy-five thousand school census<lb/>
cards sent out; study of winter habits of Anopheles continued;<lb/>
on February 15th eight adult Anopheles, six A. quadrimaculatus<lb/>
and two A. punctipennis collected from Crystal Lake and Adams<lb/>
Pond; on February 28th, three A. punctipennis and two A. quadri-<lb/>
maculatus collected at Adams Pond; on February 14th, two larvae<lb/>
and one pupae collected near Georgetown.</p>
<p>Surgeon L. L. Williams (Virginia): Detached from Virginia and<lb/>
temporarily assigned to duty in South Carolina.</p>
<p>Dr. C. P. Coogle continued malaria school surveys in Georgia and<lb/>
South Carolina; thirty-four schools visited during the month;<lb/>
one thousand five hundred and thirty-four children examined for<lb/>
enlarged spleens; one thousand four hundred and fifty-five<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01140004"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
March 5, 1924.<lb/>
blood smears made and sent to Memphis Laboratory for examination.<lb/>
Dr. Coogle observed many adult crucians, males and females, in<lb/>
Charleston and Georgetown Counties, South Carolina, approximate-<lb/>
ly two hundred were observed under one bridge and many were<lb/>
found in barns and under house porches.</p>
<p><hi>Conferences and Inspections:</hi> Senior Sanitary Engineer J. A.<lb/>
LePrince delivered two lectures to the classes of the Medical<lb/>
Department of the University of Tennessee during the month;<lb/>
attended conference of the New Jersey Mosquito Extermination<lb/>
Association February 13-16th.</p>
<p>Medical Officer in Charge delivered a series of lectures on in-<lb/>
sect-borne diseases in the United States to classes of the<lb/>
Medical Department of the University of Tennessee; delivered<lb/>
two lectures to classes at the University of Georgia Medical<lb/>
School at Augusta, Georgia, on malaria and other insect-borne<lb/>
diseases in the United States February 20-21st; conferred<lb/>
with Dr. Farmer, County Health Officer of Aiken County, South<lb/>
Carolina, relative 1924 malaria program February 21; conferred<lb/>
with Dr. Coogle, Mr. Old, Mr. Mayne and local health authori-<lb/>
ties of Chatham County, Georgia, and inspected activities in<lb/>
the County, February 22; conferred with State Health Officer<lb/>
of Alabama and malaria field force in Montgomery, Alabama, Feb-<lb/>
ruary 23rd.</p>
<p><hi>Expenditures:</hi> During the month approximately $3,128.40 was<lb/>
expended from the Malaria Allotment in connection with field<lb/>
investigations of malaria.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>L. D. Fricks, Surgeon,<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
