<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01202001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Summary of Progress for Yellow Fever for the Six Months Ending June 1, 1924, by [Henry Rose Carter?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01202001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-06-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hoffmann, W.H.</name>
<name type="person">Connor, M.E.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Froes, J.A.G.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Brazil</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-06-01">June 1, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01202001</idno>
<title>Report: Summary of Progress for Yellow Fever for the Six Months Ending June 1, 1924, by [Henry Rose Carter?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter?] summarizes the progress of the work against yellow fever, considering the factors of pathology, mosquito control, and the causative organism.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-06-01">
<head>Report: Summary of Progress for Yellow Fever for the Six Months Ending June 1, 1924, by [Henry Rose Carter?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01202001"/>
<p>/LC</p>
<p>Summary of Progress for Yellow Fever<lb/>
for the Six Months Ending June 1, 1924.</p>
<p>During the six months ending June 1/24 the editor has seen only<lb/>
one paper in the medical press which, in his opinion, may markedly in-<lb/>
crease our knowledge of yellow fever.</p>
<p>This is by Hoffmann (1) of Havana, reporting <hi>lime casts</hi> as of well<lb/>
nigh constant occurrence in the kidneys (in the convoluted tubules and<lb/>
the loops of Houle especially) of men dead of yellow fever.</p>
<p>His work was done on old material from autopsies made in Havana<lb/>
in 1905 to 1908, mainly or exclusively by Guiteras. Specimens from 30<lb/>
cases were examined and in nearly all lime casts were found; a later com-<lb/>
munication (1b) states that &ldquo;although only very limited material was a-<lb/>
vailable&rdquo;---&ldquo;these casts were found in 24 out of 28 cases without any<lb/>
difficulty in the first preparation.&rdquo; He used haematoxylin as a stain.</p>
<p>Hoffmann has not found lime casts in the kidneys of those dead<lb/>
of other diseases than yellow fever except in cases of bichloride of mer-<lb/>
cury poisoning and in the paper last quoted. He especially notes their<lb/>
non-occurrence in Weil's disease: black-water fever: malaria and relapsing<lb/>
fever, some of which diseases may give autopsies confusable with yellow<lb/>
fever. They were found also in dogs <add>or rather in a dog</add> inoculated with Leptospira icteroides,<lb/>
but not in guinea pigs.</p>
<p>Hoffmann regards these casts as being much the most distinctive<lb/>
sign of yellow fever found at autopsy--as well nigh pathognomonic. How-<lb/>
ever this may be, if these findings (including the absence of these casts<lb/>
in other diseases possibly confusable with yellow fever) are confirmed<lb/>
there is no question but that he has made an extremely valuable con-<lb/>
tribution to the pathology of that disease: And one of no less value to<lb/>
the sanitarian also, giving him a more certain, or it may be a certain,<lb/>
differential diagnosis for this disease after death.</p>
<p>Hoffmann suggests that possibly these same casts may be found<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01202002"/>
found<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
in the urine of yellow fever patients. If so, and if this be confined<lb/>
to yellow fever, <del>this</del><add>such a</add> determination would be as valuable to the clini-<lb/>
cian in the differential diagnosis during life as would be the presence<lb/>
of these casts in the kidneys after death to the pathologist. It would<lb/>
be equally valuable to the sanitarian, indeed more so, than the post mor-<lb/>
tem determination as many cases suspected of being yellow fever are seen<lb/>
which do not come to autopsy.</p>
<p>The existence of lime casts in the kidney should admit of ready<lb/>
verification as old yellow fever material is abundant and available for<lb/>
examination in many places and reports on this matter should even now be<lb/>
appearing. The examination of the urine for lime casts is possible only<lb/>
where yellow fever is occurring and this is without doubt being made in<lb/>
such places. We await the reports from both sets of investigators with<lb/>
much interest and some impatience.</p>
<p>A few other articles <add>appearing during</add> <del>in</del> the six months specified should be noted:</p>
<p>An article by Connor (2) is valuable, it may be counted invaluable<lb/>
to the field sanitarian, in that it gathers into one article the detail ne-<lb/>
cessary and advisable for the elimination of yellow fever by control of<lb/>
the breeding places of its insect vector. It summarizes Connor's exper-<lb/>
ience in yellow fever campaigns for the past seven years in Spanish America<lb/>
and gives in one paper the digested substance of many reports and scattered<lb/>
articles.</p>
<p>There were two papers published, bearing on the still disputed ques-<lb/>
tion: the identity of Leptospira icteroides with the causative organism of<lb/>
yellow Fever: One of them by Froes (3) writing from Brazil, notes the ex-<lb/>
tremely close resemblance between yellow fever in man and the experimental<lb/>
infection with Leptospira icteroides taking special account of the post-mortem<lb/>
appearances in each case. This does not agree with the observations of<lb/>
Hoffmann of Havana as published about two years ago (See the Summary for<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01202003"/>
Summary for<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
Yellow Fever from Oct. 1/22 to April 1/23: Page 455 this Volume). (Foot<lb/>
note)</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>(Foot note): It does, however, agree with a recent note of the same<lb/>
writer (Hoffmann). He writes <add>(10</add>: &ldquo;Though my study&rdquo; of yellow fever in man<lb/>
&ldquo;has a purely anatomical character, the results are now in accordance with<lb/>
the Leptospira icteroides as the aetiological agent of yellow fever. After<lb/>
my first study there remained several doubts which now have been fully ex-<lb/>
plained.&rdquo; Note too his finding of lime casts, which in men he considers<lb/>
almost pathognomonic of yellow fever, in dogs infected with Leptospira ic-<lb/>
teroides. (End of foot note).</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>On the same lines as Froes--i. e. as tending to confirm the identi-<lb/>
ty of these organisms, Noguchi (4) collects a number of reports of Pfeiffer<lb/>
reactions of cultures of Leptospira icteroides and the serum of men who<lb/>
had recently recovered from yellow fever, some made by himself and some by<lb/>
others. The reactions were almost all positive, three negative ones be-<lb/>
ing reported in this series of 52--all 3 of which were during his first<lb/>
work in Guayaquil in 1918.</p>
<p>The reactions were positive for convalescents in Brazil with<lb/>
strains of organisms from Ecuador: Mexico and Peru. See also in this con-<lb/>
nection similar results reported by Perez Grovas of Mexico (Summary for<lb/>
Yellow Fever for six months ending Oct. 1/23: P. 721 this volume). The<lb/>
reactions of these men, positive to Leptospira icteroides were negative to<lb/>
Leptospira icterohemorrhagica whenever the latter was tried: It was not<lb/>
tried in every case.</p>
<p>Both of these last two articles give data in favor of Leptospira<lb/>
icteroides being the causative organism of yellow fever and the editor<lb/>
has for some time accepted it as such. It may not have been quite logical<lb/>
to do so without reserve as a number of men as well qualified to judge as<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01202004"/>
as<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
himself are not convinced of it. Yet he thinks all who have kept in<lb/>
close touch with this matter will admit that the evidence for the causal<lb/>
role of this organism has been increasing steadily, if not spectacularly,<lb/>
since this was first claimed for it by Noguchi in 1918; so too he thinks<lb/>
has increased the number of men who accept it. In his judgment he causal<lb/>
role of this organism in yellow fever is at present rather generally, but<lb/>
by no means universally accepted. If the statements of Hoffmann quoted in this<lb/>
summary imply that the Havana School is prepared to accept this doctrine,<lb/>
there will be very few left to oppose it.</p>
<p>1: Hoffmann, Prof. W. H., Habana. Marine General obera<add>r</add>zt.</p>
<p>(a): Kalkzylinder in den Nieren beim Gelbfieber Munchener medi-<lb/>
zinischen Wochenschritt 1924: Nr. 27: S. 898 und 899.</p>
<p>1 (b): Is there Yellow Fever in Africa? Journal Trop. Med. and<lb/>
Hygiene (London) July 15/24.</p>
<p>1 (c): The Histopathology of Yellow Fever. Journal Trop. Med.<lb/>
and Hygiene (London): No. 17: Vol. XXVII: pp. 235-240.</p>
<p>2: Connor, M. E. Suggestions for Developing a Campaign to<lb/>
Control Yellow Fever. Am. Journal. Trop. Med. 4: 277, 1924.</p>
<p>3: Froes, J. A. G. Etiologia de Febre Amarella. Medicina <del>Bra-</del><lb/>
Brazil<del>l</del>iera, 38: 245, 1924.</p>
<p>4: Noguchi, Hideyo. The Pfeiffer Reaction in Yellow Fever.<lb/>
Am. Jour. Trop. Med., 4: 131.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
