<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01208002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, August 6, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01208002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-08-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Barber, M. A.</name>
<name type="person">Hayne, Theodore B.</name>
<name type="person">Mayne, Bruce</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Gage, E. H.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Fuchs, A. W.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, J. C.</name>
<name type="person">Old, H. N.</name>
<name type="person">Shaw, F. R.</name>
<name type="person">Coogle, C. P.</name>
<name type="person">Foster, J. G.</name>
<name type="person">Fisher, L. M.</name>
<name type="person">Williams, Jr. Louis L.</name>
<name type="place">Crowley (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Leflore County</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Crittenden County (Ark.)</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">Georgia</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Leflore County (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-08-06">August 6, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01208002</idno>
<title>Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, August 6, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fricks reports on the progress of the malaria campaign in the southern United States.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-08-06">
<head>Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, August 6, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01208002"/>
<opener>
The File<lb/>
Malaria<lb/>
Reports.<lb/>
FB<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1924-08-06">August 6, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
Monthly Progress Report,<lb/>
<hi>July 1924.</hi><lb/>
The Surgeon General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Division of Scientific Research,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to forward herewith monthly progress<lb/>
report of malaria investigations conducted during the month<lb/>
of July, 1924, under the direction of this office.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Crowley, Louisiana</hi>: - Personnel- Special<lb/>
Expert M. A. Barber, Assoc. San. Eng. W. H. W. Komp and Tech-<lb/>
nical Assistant Theo. B. Hayne.</p>
<p>Activities of this laboratory consisted of: (1) Preparation<lb/>
of a paper for the International Conference on Health Prob-<lb/>
lems in Tropical America, to be read at Kingston, Jamaica;<lb/>
(2) Tests on mosquito repellents for personal protection in<lb/>
the open and creosote in dwellings; (3) <unclear>Tests</unclear> of various lar-<lb/>
vicides; (4) Study of the nutrition of Anopheles; (5) Observ-<lb/>
ations on the production of Anopheles in rice fields; (6) Ob-<lb/>
servations on incidence of Anopheles in rice growing region:<lb/>
collected in image stage 3,235, A. quadrimaculatus 57%, A.<lb/>
crucians 43%; bred out 383, percentage about the same; (7)<lb/>
Blood specimens examined for malaria parasites 112, positive<lb/>
20, P. vivax 19, P. falciparum one.</p>
<p><hi>Memphis Laboratory:</hi> Personnel - A.A. Surgeon Wm. A. Krauss and<lb/>
Microscopists Ethel Barrier and Retha Kitchens.</p>
<p>630 blood smears were examined for malaria parasites, of which<lb/>
433 were sent in locally for diagnosis, of these 53 were posi-<lb/>
tive P. vivax, 24 positive P. falciparum and three double in-<lb/>
fections; 156 blood specimens were collected in Leflore County,<lb/>
Mississippi, of which twelve were positive P. vivax and one<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01208003"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
August 6, 1924.<lb/>
positive P. falciparum; the remaining 41 slides sent in for<lb/>
examination from Tennessee, Arkansas and Missouri showed six<lb/>
positive P. vivax and three positive P. falciparum. One<lb/>
hundred house visits were made in the study of malaria cases<lb/>
under treatment.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Savannah, Georgia:</hi> Personnel - Technical<lb/>
Assistant Bruce Mayne.</p>
<p>Activities at this laboratory consisted of: observations on<lb/>
Anopheles incidence, 300 imagoes collected, 40% of which were<lb/>
A. quadrimaculatus, a decided increase, but A. crucians re-<lb/>
mains predominant around salt marsh areas; A. crucians observ-<lb/>
ed to prefer animal quarters, but several instances of house<lb/>
infestation noted, especially in temporary dwellings; about<lb/>
the middle of July resting Anopheles first observed in hollow<lb/>
logs and tree stumps; 160 mosquitoes dissected, one A. quadri-<lb/>
maculatus observed with immature <unclear>oocysts</unclear> on stomach wall; 101<lb/>
blood specimens examined for malaria parasites, two positive<lb/>
P. vivax, one positive P. falciparum.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemiological Studies of Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Asst. Surg.<lb/>
Kennth F. Maxcy.</p>
<p>Dr. Maxcy detached for Brill's disease studies during greater<lb/>
part of month. Prepared a paper on malaria for publication<lb/>
in Florida State Medical Journal.</p>
<p><hi>Impounded Waters in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Epidemio-<lb/>

logist T. H. D. Griffitts and Asst. San. Eng. E. H. Gage.</p>
<p>Dr. Griffitts (Alabama), activities consisted of (1) inspection<lb/>
of pond near Cowarts, Houston County, ten-acre pond impounded<lb/>
last spring, pond site cleared but not maintained, fine flotage<lb/>
and algae abundant, production of Anopheles quadrimaculatus pro-<lb/>
fuse, Gambusia abundant, but unable to cope with mosquito pro-<lb/>
duction, County Health Officer advised of situation and meas-<lb/>
ures which should be enforced to control mosquito production; (2)<lb/>
inspection of Golden Bridge Pond, no anopheles production, ap-<lb/>
parently being controlled by oiling; (4) inspection of River<lb/>
Falls Power Company Pond at Gantt's, free production of A. quad-<lb/>
rimaculatus observed in the pond; (5) inspection of Mitchell's<lb/>
Reservoir, Coosa River, flotage scarce, few mosquito larvae found<lb/>
except in drift on Hatchett Creek; (6) inspection of Muscle<lb/>
Shoals Reservoir, water being slowly impounded by the U. S. Gov-<lb/>
ernment, mosquito production profuse.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01208004"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>August 6, 1924.</p>
<p>Mr. Gage (South Carolina), activities consisted of: contin-<lb/>
uation of observations of Anopheles prevalence, increased<lb/>
production observed in impounded waters with slight decrease in<lb/>
production in small breeding areas in the same locality; emer-<lb/>
gences from collections of larvae and pupae yielded 73% A.<lb/>
crucians, 16% A. punctipennis, 11% A. quadrimaculatus; emer-<lb/>
gence from collections made in larger ponds yielded 82% A.<lb/>
Crucians and 18% A. quadrimaculatus; adults collected per rest-<lb/>
ing place in vicinity of ponds remains about the same as for<lb/>
June while the number per resting place at a greater distance<lb/>
from the pond was almost double - the proportions being adjac-<lb/>
ent to ponds A. crucians 87%, A. punctipennis 4%, A. quadri-<lb/>
maculatus 9%, distant from ponds A. crucians 42%, A. puncti-<lb/>
pennis 26%, A. quadrimaculatus 32%.</p>
<p><hi>Major Drainage in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Personnel- Assoc. San.<lb/>
Eng. A. W. Fuchs.</p>
<p>Mr. Fuchs continued observations of Anopheles production and<lb/>
physical conditions of ditches in Drainage District No. 6,<lb/>
Crittenden County, Arkansas; lateral ditches have become a<lb/>
series of separate pools because of continued draught; Anophe-<lb/>
les production five times as prolific as in June, of 393<lb/>
imagoes collected 93% were A. quadrimaculatus, 2% A. puncti-<lb/>
pennis; Gambusia present in all ditches, abundant in some,<lb/>
vegetation abundant; Gambusia unable to fully cope with mos-<lb/>
quito production.</p>
<p><hi>Cooperative Fish Studies:</hi> Mr. Samuel F. Hildebrand of the<lb/>
Bureau of Fisheries continued his cooperative fish control<lb/>
investigations around Augusta, Georgia. Heavy rainfalls<lb/>
and abnormally high temperatures have seriously interfered<lb/>
with these studies during the month.</p>
<p><hi>Rural Malaria Control Investigations:</hi> Personnel - Asst. San.<lb/>
Eng. J. C. Carter, A. A. Surg. C. P. Coogle, Assoc. San. Eng.<lb/>
L. M. Fisher, Asst. San. Eng. J. G. Foster, Assoc. San. Eng.<lb/>
A. W. Fuchs, Asst. San. Eng. H. N. Old, Asst. San. Eng. F. R.<lb/>
Shaw and Surgeon L. L. Williams, Jr.</p>
<p>Mr. Carter (Alabama), activities consisted of: screen survey<lb/>
continued in Houston County; shallow wells or holes dug in two<lb/>
intermittent ponds and stocked with Gambusia for observation;<lb/>
malaria surveys made around thirteen saw mills in Houston,<lb/>
Barbour, Clarke, Escambia and Montgomery Counties; observation<lb/>
made of the effect of distillate from a gas tar plant on mos-<lb/>
quito larvae, Anopheles larvae killed by distillate in three<lb/>
minutes; stegomyia deposited eggs in barrel two days after ap-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01208005"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
August 6, 1924.<lb/>
plication of distillate.</p>
<p>Mr. Old (Georgia), activities consisted of: continued ob-<lb/>
servations of mosquito production; 1.91 inches excess rain-<lb/>
fall during month, practically all thunder showers, rapid<lb/>
run-off; no great increase in potential breeding areas, no<lb/>
increase observed in mosquito production; 1555 dips at 41<lb/>
stations gave only 42 larvae and four <unclear>pupae;</unclear> enormous in-<lb/>
crease in Gambusia undoubtedly responsible for the scarc-<lb/>
ity of mosquito larvae, A. quadrimaculatus becoming more<lb/>
prevalent though not yet <unclear>predominating</unclear> over A. crucians<lb/>
except in one section of the County; 407 adult mosquitoes<lb/>
collected from 66 locations including dwellings, outhouses<lb/>
and animal sheds showed A. quadrimaculatus more abundant<lb/>
in dwelling houses, A. crucians in animal sheds.</p>
<p>Mr. Shaw (Louisiana), activities consisted of rural malaria<lb/>
control studies in Tangipahoa and St. Mary's Parishes: study<lb/>
of the effect of screening of rural homes being made; survey<lb/>
of drainage canal at Patterson in St. Mary's Parish; 350<lb/>
cisterns in Patterson stocked with Gambusia; Gambusia surviv-<lb/>
ed three weeks in steel water barrel with temperature ranging<lb/>
up to 100 degrees.</p>
<p>Dr. Coogle and Asst. San. Eng. J.G. Foster (Mississippi), act-<lb/>
ivities consisted of: continuation of malaria and mosquito<lb/>
study in Leflore County, Mississippi, 192 houses treated with<lb/>
creosote oil during 1923 were inspected; study of the effect<lb/>
of screening on malaria prevalence in group of twenty planta-<lb/>
tion houses continued; collection of information relative to<lb/>
malaria prevalence in the localities under observation.</p>
<p>Mr. Fisher (South Carolina), activites consisted of: rural<lb/>
malaria control investigations continued; study of fish con-<lb/>
trol of mosquito production in shallow pond near Columbia<lb/>
continued, star head minnows abundant in this pond, mosquito<lb/>
production profuse; at Chester, S.C. where only A. punctipennis<lb/>
have been observed, one female A. crucians was collected; mal-<lb/>
aria survey made in Charleston County as help <unclear>ionty</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>B</unclear>for-<lb/>
<unclear>of</unclear>. Branchville, Harleyville,</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01208006"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>August 6, 1924.</p>
<p>Mr. Fuchs in addition to major drainage studies was assign-<lb/>
ed to rural malaria control investigations in Gibson and<lb/>
Obion Counties, Tennessee, and Dunklin and New Madrid Coun-<lb/>
ties, Missouri. Mr. Fuchs visited these four counties<lb/>
during July and advised the county health officers relative<lb/>
to handling their malaria control problems.</p>
<p>Surgeon L. L. Williams (Virginia) - No report received.</p>
<p><hi>Conferences and Inspections:</hi> Medical Officer in Charge<lb/>
remained at field headquarters preparing annual report.</p>
<p>Senior Sanitary Engineer J. A. LePrince on leave, attending<lb/>
International Conference on Health Problems at Jamaica.</p>
<p><hi>Expenditures</hi>: During the month approximately $4,391.00<lb/>
was expended from the Malaria Allotment in connection with<lb/>
field investigations of malaria.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>L. D. Fricks, Surgeon,<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
