<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01204010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Merritte W. Ireland to E.L. Ruffner, June 18, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Ireland, Merritte W.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01204010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-06-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ruffner, E.L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-06-18">June 18, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01204010</idno>
<title>Letter from Merritte W. Ireland to E.L. Ruffner, June 18, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ireland reviews the military career of Jefferson Randolph Kean. He discusses Reed's yellow fever work and the reorganization of the Army Medical Corps.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-06-18">
<head>Letter from Merritte W. Ireland to E.L. Ruffner, June 18, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01204010"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
WAR DEPARTMENT<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON GENERAL<lb/>
Washington<lb/>
<date value="1924-06-18">June 18, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
Lieut. Colonel E. L. Ruffner, M. C.,<lb/>
Station Hospital,<lb/>
Fort Banks, Massachusetts.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Colonel Ruffner:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Upon my return to the office I find your letter of June 7th in my mail<lb/>
inviting Mrs. Ireland and myself to a dinner the medical officers of the First Corps<lb/>
Area are to give at Wayside Inn, South Sudbury, Massachusetts, on the evening of July<lb/>
2, 1924, for Colonel and Mrs. Kean.</p>
<p>I regret very much that Mrs. Ireland and I cannot find it possible to<lb/>
attend this dinner, for nothing would give us greater pleasure than to help the officers<lb/>
of the Department do honor to Colonel Kean. Mrs. Ireland joins me in affectionate<lb/>
greetings to them.</p>
<p>I apprehend that it is possible that the medical officers of the First<lb/>
Corps Area are not entirely familiar with the distinguished record of the officer to<lb/>
whom they are saying goodbye, and for that reason I am going to review in a very meagre<lb/>
way some of his accomplishments in the Medical Department.</p>
<p>I want to say, to start with, that in my opinion Colonel Kean has done<lb/>
more for the advancement of the interests of the Department than any other officer who<lb/>
ever belonged to the Corps. He has done more to establish the present satisfactory<lb/>
condition of the Medical Department than any living man.</p>
<p>I did not become acquainted with Colonel Kean until the fall of 1902, but<lb/>
I am sure some of you know his history in the Spanish American war. He commanded the<lb/>
largest hospital in the Seventh Corps. in a most successful way, where hundreds of cases<lb/>
of typhoid fever were treated in a manner which called forth most favorable comment. He<lb/>
went to Cuba with the Seventh Corps and was General Fitzhugh Lee's chief surgeon. He<lb/>
was offered the position of Sanitary Officer of the City of Havana, which he refused, to<lb/>
remain with his Corps. He was finally appointed Director of Charities by General Wood,<lb/>
and this distinguished officer has made of record his estimate of Colonel Kean's valuable<lb/>
service in this position.</p>
<p>Colonel Kean was intimately associated with Walter Reed in his investiga-<lb/>
tions which proved the transmission of yellow fever, and did a great deal of work for<lb/>
this board, for which he did not receive special credit because he was not a member of<lb/>
the board. He was mentioned by the Secretary of War in his annual report for 1902 for<lb/>
his exceptional service during the time he was in Cuba.</p>
<p>Colonel Kean became the Executive Officer for Surgeon General O'Reilly<lb/>
in September, 1902, and immediately set to work in applying to the Medical Department<lb/>
the lessons of the Spanish American War. It is fair to say that the Medical Department<lb/>
of the Army was the only Department which took these lessons to heart and made adjustments<lb/>
on that basis. As a result the Medical Department had to be reorganized. This was accom-<lb/>
plished, after a four years' campaign, by the Act of Congress of April 23, 1908, which<lb/>
gave the Medical Department its present status. This act, among other very radical<lb/>
changes, created the Medical Reserve Corps, which was of Colonel Kean's initiative.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01204011"/>
<p>Colonel Ruffner - 2</p>
<p>Strange as it may seem today, this tremendous step in advance was obtained<lb/>
after most serious opposition, because the rest of the Army apparently could not understand<lb/>
what the Medical Corps was going to do with an officers' reserve corps. And now, since<lb/>
this corps has really become the bulwark of our national defense, the rest of the Army is<lb/>
only too prone to forget that the Medical Department had a reserve corps for eight years<lb/>
before they did, and that Colonel Kean was the father of this corps.</p>
<p>The Spanish American War demonstrated that if we were to meet the first emer-<lb/>
gencies of another war we had to have field supplies and equipment prepared and stored in<lb/>
advance. Colonel Kean started in to rectify this defect of the Medical Department at the<lb/>
beginning of the Spanish American War, and initiated the schemed of setting aside certain<lb/>
field equipment every year. This enabled us to meet the emergencies of the mobilization<lb/>
of the National Guard on the Border in 1916, and made it possible for us to get through<lb/>
the World War from the supply standpoint.</p>
<p>In the early days of the World war many of the professional men of this<lb/>
country went to France and served in the hospitals there. Upon their return to the United<lb/>
States two of them in particular (George Crile of Cleveland and Karl Connell of New York)<lb/>
stated that general hospitals should be organized in time of peace for an emergency. For-<lb/>
tunately for the Medical Department of the Army, Colonel Kean was at this time on duty with<lb/>
the American Red Cross. One of the first things he undertook upon assuming his work with<lb/>
that organization was to organize 500-bed base hospitals. He used various large civil gen-<lb/>
eral hospitals throughout the country as parent institutions for these organizations, and<lb/>
before he left the American Red Cross in August, 1917, he had started the organization of<lb/>
forty-three of these hospitals. It was this foresight which enabled our Government to give<lb/>
six base hospitals at once for service back of the English lines when the English mission<lb/>
demanded them upon their visit to the United States in April, 1917. It should always be<lb/>
remembered that these base hospitals were the first military organizations of the American<lb/>
Army to fly the American flag in Europe during the World War.</p>
<p>The tripod upon which the suggess of the Medical Department of the Army<lb/>
rested in the World War consisted of the <hi>Medical Reserve Corps</hi>, the <hi>accumulation of field<lb/>
supplies for an emergency</hi>, and the <hi>organization of base hospitals,</hi> and Colonel Kean was<lb/>
responsible for all of these activities. He went to France in August, 1917, to command the<lb/>
United States Army Ambulance Service on duty with the French, and remained with that organ-<lb/>
ization until he had placed it on a thoroughly efficient basis, before reporting for duty<lb/>
with the American Expeditionary Forces.</p>
<p>These are only some of the many activities of importance connected with the<lb/>
Medical Department in which Colonel Kean was the leader, but they are enough to mark him<lb/>
as the greatest living benefactor of the Department. His work as the Chief Sanitary Officer<lb/>
of the Second American Occupation in Cuba is a matter of history. It was during this time<lb/>
that he compiled the sanitary code which is in operation not only in Cuba, but in Porto Rico.</p>
<p>The officers of the Medical Corps do themselves great honor in remembering<lb/>
Colonel Kean upon the eve of his retirement. An officer of any other government of the world<lb/>
who had done as much for humanity as Colonel Kean has done would have been handsomely recog-<lb/>
nized, and it is a sad commentary upon our system of awards for service that he should be<lb/>
retired without the recognition due him. He should have been the Chief of the Corps.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,</salute>
<signed>M. W. Ireland,<lb/>
Major General,<lb/>
The Surgeon General</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
