<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01201021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, May 27, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01201021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-05-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Pothier, Oliver L.</name>
<name type="place">British Guiana</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-05-27">May 27, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01201021</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, May 27, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor reports on mosquito breeding and the need to introduce fish for mosquito control. He notes that there is public pressure on the government for mosquito reduction.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-05-27">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, May 27, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01201021"/>
<opener>
<unclear><del>Book</del></unclear> I H. B. guiana<lb/>
Stegomyia<lb/>
Breeding<lb/>
ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF<lb/>
----<lb/>
FREDERICK F. RUSSELL, M.D.<lb/>
GENERAL DIRECTOR<lb/>
JOHN A. FERRELL, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE UNITED STATES<lb/>
VICTOR G. HEISER, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE EAST<lb/>
H. H. HOWARD, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE WEST INDIES<lb/>
MEMBERS<lb/>
----<lb/>
GEORGE E. VINCENT<lb/>
CHAIRMAN<lb/>
JOHN G. AGAR<lb/>
WALLACE BUTTRICK<lb/>
DAVID L. EDSALL<lb/>
JOHN G. FITZ GERALD<lb/>
SIMON FLEXNER<lb/>
RAYMOND B. FOSDICK<lb/>
EDWIN O. JORDAN<lb/>

VERNON KELLOGG<lb/>
T. MITCHELL PRUDDEN<lb/>
JOHN D. ROCKEFELLER, JR.<lb/>
WICKLIFFE ROSE<lb/>
VICTOR C. VAUGHAN<lb/>
WILLIAM H. WELCH<lb/>
EDWIN R. EMBREE<lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
FLORENCE M. READ<lb/>
ASSISTANT SECRETARY<lb/>
INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD<lb/>
OF<lb/>
THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION<lb/>
61 BROADWAY, NEW YORK<lb/>
CABLE ADDRESS &ldquo;INTERCOM&rdquo;<lb/>
<unclear>O</unclear>
Book<lb/>
Stegomyia<lb/>
<dateline>
Paramaribo, Surinam<lb/>
Dutch Guiana.<lb/>
<date value="1924-05-27">May 27, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>While in British Guiana I made it a special point<lb/>
to look for Aedes Aegypti in mud puddles but in no instance did I<lb/>
succeed in finding them. This confirms what Doctor Wise found some<lb/>
years ago in the same Colony and more recently by Mr. Cleare, Government<lb/>
Entomologist.</p>
<p>There is no need for the stegomyia aegypti to seek<lb/>
breeding in a mud puddle in British Guiana as receptacles holding clean<lb/>
water are available every where even on the Sugar estates. With family of<lb/>
means their water is stowed in large surface cisterns similar to those<lb/>
in use at New Orleans. About 52% of the 300 hundred premises inspected<lb/>
were infested with &lsquo;stegs&rsquo;.</p>
<p>It seems strange, but never-the-less true, that the<lb/>
value of fish have not been appreciated here by the medical authorities<lb/>
and by failure here it follows that the public have not been <unclear>enligthened</unclear>.</p>
<p>In the smaller towns I found several blacks using fish<lb/>
in their water barrels not as a protection aginst &ldquo;wigglers&rdquo; but to de-<lb/>
termine the suitability of the water for drinking purposes which is a<lb/>
relic from Africa where one tribe tries to destroy the other by poisoning<lb/>
the water supply and which they test by placing a fish in it, which if<lb/>
it lives everything is o.k. otherwise not.</p>
<p>The East Indian coolies were also using fish with the<lb/>
thought of keeping all insects out and they were successful.</p>
<p>There would no trouble to bring fish into general use<lb/>
in this Colony if proper propaganda were made and as the varities of<lb/>
fishes are<del>x</del>almost unlimited good results would sure to follow.</p>
<p>We could not find any definite evidence of recent<lb/>
yellow fever in the Colony but every<add>thing</add> indicates that the infection has been<lb/>
present <del>a</del>t<del>a</del> later date than is officially reported (1909) It would not be-<lb/>
come endemic as immigration into the Colony has practically ceased.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01201022"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>The Medical Service, the present one, has never seen a case of<lb/>
Schistomiasis Mansoni but of course this does mean that it is not<lb/>
present as the post-mortems are not carefully made due to the great<lb/>
amount of work placed on each officer, for instance, at the time of<lb/>
our visit the Bacteriologist and Pathologist was also Acting Quarantine<lb/>
Officer (Boarding Vessels) also radiologist and attempting to conduct a<lb/>
study of Filariasis which is very prevelent here and increasing at a<lb/>
rather alarming rate.</p>
<p>The cadavers are sent to the autposy room where a boy<del>s</del> opens them and<lb/>
and lays out the organs on a table for the Doctor to view, these are<lb/>
not generally opened therefore it is easy to see that bilharzia might<lb/>
get by them.</p>
<p>The hope for Georgetown from a mosquito standpoint lies in the fact<lb/>
that there is a growing public opinion pressing the Government to under<lb/>
take a general mosquito reduction and the alarming increase of filariasis<lb/>
is interesting the planter in mosquito reduction. The <unclear>Government</unclear> has approv<lb/>
ed a plan for a modern system of sewerage disposl which work is already<lb/>
underway, also an elaborate scheme for surface drainage independent of the<lb/>
present tidal drains.</p>
<p>I think that as a result of our visit there will <del><unclear>fulls</unclear></del> develop an<lb/>
interest in fish as larvae consumers and that the surface cisterns in<lb/>
place <add>of</add> be<unclear>ing</unclear> covered, really partially covered, as hereto fore, will be fished<lb/>
with good results.</p>
<p>I will write you again from this Colony, so far Dengue is admitted and<lb/>
also a confusion in the minds of some physicians as to whether some of<lb/>
the so-called cases of dengue were not really <unclear>mild</unclear> yellow fever. <unclear>OI am</unclear><lb/>
sorry that Doctor Flu is not here, his report of the 1908 and 09 cases<lb/>
are intensely interesting but I wonder why he did not note Faget's sign.</p>
<p>During 1923 and part 1924 several cases of Weil's disease were reported<lb/>
in Paramaribo. Dr. Pothier hopes to get some of the survivors and try<lb/>
the reaction, both organisms.</p>
<p>With continued good wishes, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>M E Connor</signed>
Please commend me to Miss Laura.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
