<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01206001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, July 5, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01206001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-07-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">Crowley (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Chatham County (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
<name type="place">Georgia</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-07-05">July 5, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01206001</idno>
<title>Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, July 5, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fricks reports on the progress of malaria investigations conducted in the southern United States.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-07-05">
<head>Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, July 5, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01206001"/>
<opener>
Malaria<lb/>
Report<lb/>
FB<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1924-07-05">July 5, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
Monthly Progress Report,<lb/>
June, 1923.<lb/>
The Surgeon-General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Division of Scientific Research,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to forward herewith monthly progress<lb/>
report of malaria investigations conducted during the month<lb/>
of June, 1923, under the direction of this office.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Crowley, Louisiana:</hi> Personnel - Special<lb/>
Expert M. A. Barber, Assoc. San.Eng. W.H.W.Komp and Tech.<lb/>
Asst. Theo. B. Hayne.</p>
<p>Activities at the Crowley Laboratory consisted of: (1) Study<lb/>
of effect of hydrogen-ion concentration and of different foods<lb/>
on the development of mosquito larvae; (2) Observations and ex-<lb/>
periments with larvicides, mosquito repellents and top-feeding<lb/>
minnows; (3) Surveys of malaria rates and anopheline intensi-<lb/>
ty: (a) Anopheles bred out from larvae or pupae, practically<lb/>
all from rice fields, 743, of which approximately 38% were A.<lb/>
quadrimaculatus, 63% A. crucians and one specimen A. walkeri;<lb/>
(b) Anopheles caught in imago stage, nearly all from the vic-<lb/>
inity of rice fields, 3752, of which approximately 30% were<lb/>
A. quadrimaculatus, 70% A. crucians and three specimens A.<lb/>
walkeri ( a group of imagoes identified in a cypress swamp were<lb/>
practically all A. quadrimaculatus); (c) Blood specimens exam-<lb/>
ined for malaria parasites, 21 specimens submitted by physi-<lb/>
cians showed four positive, all P. vivax; 31 specimens exam-<lb/>
ined from a logging camp, none positive.</p>
<p><hi>Memphis Laboratory:</hi> Personnel - A.A.Surg. Wm. A.Krauss and<lb/>
Microscopists Ethel Barrier and Retha Kitchens.</p>
<p>618 blood smears were examined for malaria parasites, of which<lb/>
226 were collected from school children in Chatham County, Ga.,<lb/>
four of these were positive P. vivax; 69 smears were sent in<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01206002"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
July 5, 1924.<lb/>
for examination by Surgeon L.L.Williams, Richmond, Va.,<lb/>
eleven of these were positive, P. <unclear>felc</unclear>., and five posi-<lb/>
tive P. vivax; 325 smears were sent in for diagnosis from<lb/>
Memphis and its vicinity, of which seven were positive, P.<lb/>
<unclear>felc</unclear>. and 36 positive, P. vivax. Fifty home visits were<lb/>
made in the study of malaria carriers under treatment.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Savannah, Georgia:</hi> Personnel - Techni-<lb/>
cal Asst. Bruce. Mayne.</p>
<p>Activities consisted of (1) observations on incidence and<lb/>
distribution of Anopheles; imagoes collected 393, A. cruc-<lb/>
ians 281, A. quadrimaculatus 112, distributed as follows:</p>
<p><table rows="5" cols="4">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>A. crucians</hi></cell><cell><hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Inside and under residences</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Out houses</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>98</cell><cell>32</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Lumber-camp bunk-houses</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>18</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Animal quarters</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>142</cell><cell>60</cell></row></table></p>
<p>A decided proportional increase of A. quadrimaculatus during<lb/>
the month; (2) 87 specimens A. crucians and 12 A.quadrimacu-<lb/>
latus dissected, none found infected; (3) 121 blood specimens<lb/>
submitted for diagnosis showed only one positive, P. vivax;<lb/>
(4) observed that the drying of natural breeding places has<lb/>
resulted in abundant Anopheles production in water troughs,<lb/>
concrete vats and roadside puddles; (5) No special geometri-<lb/>
cal pattern observed in collections of Anopheles eggs.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemiological Studies of Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Asst. Surg.<lb/>
Kenneth F. Maxcy.</p>
<p>Dr. Maxcy visited eight southern state health departments dur-<lb/>
ing the month for the purpose of (1) ascertaining what informa-<lb/>
tion has been collected by them regarding the distribution of<lb/>
malaria in the different states; (2) studying the methods em-<lb/>
ployed in the different states for collecting malaria statis-<lb/>
tics; (3) interesting the various state health departments in<lb/>
securing more accurate registration of malaria deaths and im-<lb/>
proving malaria morbidity reporting; (4) and increasing inter-<lb/>
est in the diagnosis of malaria by blood examinations.</p>
<p><hi>Impounded Waters in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Epidemio-<lb/>
logist T.H.D. Griffitts and Asst. San. <unclear>Eng</unclear>. E.H. Gage.</p>
<p>Dr. Griffitts (Alabama), activities consisted of (1) Inspec-<lb/>
tions of Golden Bridge Pond June 9, 24 and 25th, water low,<lb/>
much floatage stranded, pond oiled every ten days with oil<lb/>
under 120 pound pressure, very little mosquito production,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01206003"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
July 5, 1924.<lb/>
no house infestation; (2) Inspection of Gentt's Quarry Pond<lb/>
June 8th, much floatage, extensive growth of algae, light<lb/>
anopheline breeding; (3) Inspection of Mitchell Reservoir<lb/>
June 12th, 13 and 14th, water turbid, drift and floatage<lb/>
less than last season, gambusia apparently less numerous,<lb/>
no full grown larvae found; (4) Inspected fishing pond at<lb/>
Selma, June 17th, Anopheles producing freely, light house<lb/>
infestation, A. quadrimaculatus.</p>
<p>Mr. Gage (South Carolina) continued observations of preva-<lb/>
lence of Anopheles larvae in Horse Creek Valley, Aiken<lb/>
County: (1) nearly thirteen times as many larvae found per<lb/>
dip in areas other than impounded waters than in the ponds<lb/>
themselves; a marked increase in relative production observed<lb/>
during June, which was due more to a decrease in breeding in<lb/>
the impounded waters, although the production in the small<lb/>
bodies of water was actually nearly doubled; (2) the number<lb/>
of adults found per resting place examined was about half<lb/>
the number found in May, but the proportion of <unclear>from</unclear> away<lb/>
from to one adjacent to impounded water projects held good;<lb/>
the majority of adults collected were A. crucians with a<lb/>
noticeable increase in A. quadrimaculatus; (3) A house-to-<lb/>
house survey was begun in an attempt to locate malaria foci<lb/>
in Horse Creek Valley.</p>
<p><hi>Major Drainage in Relation to Malaria</hi>: Personnel - Assoc. San.<lb/>
Eng. A. H. Fuchs.</p>
<p>Mr. Fuchs continued the study of major drainage in relation<lb/>
to malaria by making an inspection of Drainage District No. 6<lb/>
in Crittenden County, Arkansas, to determine the amount of<lb/>
Anopheles production in drainage ditches under delta condi-<lb/>
tions; Observations are being recorded with a view to estab-<lb/>
lishing the relation which exists between Anopheles produc-<lb/>
tion in these ditches and such conditions as size of ditch,<lb/>
soil, velocity of flow, obstruction, vegetation, floatage,<lb/>
top minnows, and so forth.</p>
<p><hi>Cooperative Fish Studies:</hi> Mr. Samuel F. Hildebrand of the<lb/>
Bureau of Fisheries resumed his cooperative fish control in-<lb/>
vestigations at Augusta, Georgia: (1) A ceries of experi-<lb/>
ments was begun for the purpose of gaining further knowledge<lb/>
of the true value of Gambusia as eradicators of mosquito<lb/>
larvae under a variety of conditions; (2) Mr. LePrince and<lb/>
Mr. Hildebrand inspected, June 18th and 19th, twenty-five<lb/>
Gambusia hatcheries constructed in the Cherokee Basin (Dr.<lb/>
Griffitts reported these hatcheries as producing Anopheles<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01206004"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
July 5, 1924.<lb/>
freely last month). Mr. Hildebrand and Mr. LePrince found<lb/>
that only a few of the twenty-five ponds created were serv-<lb/>
ing their purpose well, due primarily to faulty location<lb/>
and construction.</p>
<p><hi>Rural Malaria Control Investigations:</hi> Asst. San. Eng. J. C.<lb/>
Carter, A.A. Surg. C. P. Coogle, Assoc. San. Eng. L. M. Fisher,<lb/>
Asst. San. Eng. J.G. Foster, Asst. San. Eng. H. N. Old, Asst.<lb/>
San. Eng. P. R. Shaws and Surg. L.L. Williams, Jr.</p>
<p>Mr. Carter (Alabama), activities consisted of (1) Survey of<lb/>
malaria prevalence in and around saw mills in Dale County;<lb/>
(2) Continuation of screen investigations in Houston County;<lb/>
(3) Survey of saw mills in relation to malaria continued in<lb/>
Clarke County.</p>
<p>Mr. Old (Georgia), activities consisted of continuation of<lb/>
observations of mosquito breeding at 56 stations scattered<lb/>
over the county, seven of the 56 stations found producing,<lb/>
21 dry because of scant rainfall; 622 larvae and pupae col-<lb/>
lected, of which 600 were collected at two stations; 115<lb/>
resting places searched for adult mosquitoes, 506 female and<lb/>
seven male A. crucians collected, 100 female and four male<lb/>
A. quadrimaculatus collected; the most important resting<lb/>
places reported were:</p>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="5">
<row>
<cell><hi>Resting Place</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>No. Searched</hi></cell><cell>A. crucians</cell><cell><hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Inside houses</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>15</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Under houses</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>47</cell><cell>9</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>animal quarters</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>372</cell><cell>25</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Out houses</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>58</cell><cell>53</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Culverts &amp; bridges</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table></p>
<p>Investigations of bamboo <unclear>ane</unclear> as drain tile undertaken.</p>
<p>Mr. Shaw (Louisiana) continued malaria control investigations<lb/>
in Yangipahos and St. Mary's Parishes; (1) Investigation of<lb/>
malaria prevalence in St. Mary's arish by school census,<lb/>
11,571 persons reached, malaria history rate of 8.3%, 5.1% for<lb/>
screened houses and 10.4% for unscreened houses; survey of<lb/>
Patterson Swamp completed, recommended the digging of a large<lb/>
outlet ditch through swamp; mosquito control campaign inaugur-<lb/>
ated at Patterson.</p>
<p>Dr. Coogla and Mr. Foster (Mississippi), rural malaria control<lb/>
investigations continued in Leflore County (1) Observations of<lb/>
Anopheles incidence; four inspections of selected mosquito rest-<lb/>
ing places made, enormous increase of Anopheles noted between<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01206005"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
July 5, 1924.<lb/>
June 9th and 15th, more than twelve times as many Anopheles<lb/>
mosquitoes noted as during the month of May, one A. puncti-<lb/>
<unclear>pennis</unclear> female and no crucians encountered; (2) Anopheles<lb/>
larvae and pupae became suddenly abundant the second week in<lb/>
June.</p>
<p>Mr. Fisher (South Carolina), rural malaria control investiga-<lb/>
tions continued, profuse mosquito breeding observed in seepage<lb/>
area containing salamanders; observations of effectiveness of<lb/>
star head minnows in controlling mosquito production under obs-<lb/>
ervation in large pond near Columbia, Anopheles larvae found<lb/>
along with these fish throughout the pond; county health in-<lb/>
spector of Newberry County instructed in differentiating mos-<lb/>
quitoes, in dipping and in collecting adults.</p>
<p>Surgeon L.L. Williams (Virginia), investigation of rural malaria<lb/>
control continued in Accomac, <unclear>Hansemond</unclear>, Northampton, James City,<lb/>
Henrico, Isle of Wight, Greensville, and Halifax Counties; pre-<lb/>
vailing mosquitoes A. punctipennis and A. crucians until late in<lb/>
June, except in <unclear>Hansemond</unclear> County which has had A. quadrimacula-<lb/>
tus since May; from the middle of May there has been a slow,<lb/>
steady increase in the number of adult Anopheles observed.</p>
<p><hi>Conferences and Inspections</hi>: Senior Sanitary Engineer J. A. Le<lb/>
Prince inspected the impounded water projects on Horse Creek,<lb/>
Aiken County, S.C.; surveyed Bridge Water Pond, McDowell County,<lb/>
H.C.; inspected Chatham County, Ga. studies; inspected Gambusia<lb/>
Hatcheries in Cherokee Basin, Alabama; inspected <unclear>Muscle</unclear> Sloals<lb/>
Lake.</p>
<p>Medical Officer in Charge conferred with the State Health Offi-<lb/>
cer of Georgia at Atlanta, Ga.; conferred with Asst. San. Eng.<lb/>
E. H. Gage at Augusta, Georgia; conferred with Asst. San. Eng.<lb/>
H. N. Old and Tech. Asst. Bruce Mayne at Savannah, Ga.; conferred<lb/>
with state health officials and Mr. Carter in Montgomery, Ala.;<lb/>
conferred with Dr. Maxcy, Memphis, Tennessee.</p>
<p><hi>Expenditures</hi>: During the month of June approximately $5,788.10<lb/>
was expended from the Malaria Allotment in connection with field<lb/>
investigations of malaria.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>L. D. Fricks, Surgeon,<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
