<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01204001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Monthly Progress Report to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, by Lunsford D. Fricks, June 5, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01204001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-06-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Komp, W. H. W.</name>
<name type="person">Barber, M. A.</name>
<name type="person">Hayne, Theodore</name>
<name type="person">Mayne, Bruce</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Gage, E. H.</name>
<name type="person">Fisher, L. M.</name>
<name type="person">Williams, Jr., Louis L.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Krauss, William A.</name>
<name type="person">Barrier, Ethel</name>
<name type="person">Kitchens, Retha</name>
<name type="person">Maxey, Kenneth F.</name>
<name type="person">Fuchs, A. W.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, Samuel F.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, J. C.</name>
<name type="person">Coogle, C. P.</name>
<name type="person">Foster, J. G.</name>
<name type="person">Old, H. N.</name>
<name type="person">Shaw, F. R.</name>
<name type="place">Crowley (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Tennessee</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Missouri</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-06-05">June 5, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01204001</idno>
<title>Monthly Progress Report to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, by Lunsford D. Fricks, June 5, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fricks reports on malaria investigations in the southern United States. He details laboratory work, epidemiological studies, and impounded water investigations.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-06-05">
<head>Monthly Progress Report to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, by Lunsford D. Fricks, June 5, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01204001"/>
<opener>
Mal<lb/>
Report<lb/>
<hi>C O P Y</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Hdq: Field Investigations of Malaria,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Room 17, Court House,<lb/>
Memphis, Tennessee.<lb/>
<date value="1924-06-05">June 5, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
FB<lb/>
----<lb/>
Monthly Progress Report,<lb/>
May, 1924.<lb/>
The Surgeon-General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Division of Scientific Research,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to forward herewith monthly progress<lb/>
report of malaria investigations conducted during the month<lb/>
of May, 1924, under the direction of this office.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Crowley, Louisiana:</hi> Personnel - Special<lb/>
Expert M. A. Barber and Assoc. San. Eng. W. H. W. Komp.</p>
<p>Activities at the Crowley Laboratory consisted of: (1) Exper-<lb/>
iments on staining methods for malaria plasmodia; (2) Effect<lb/>
on Anopheles larvae of the hydrogen-ion concentration of the<lb/>
water in which they are breeding; (3) Observations on larval<lb/>
food; (4) Observations on incidence of Anopheles, largely pro-<lb/>
duced in rice fields; bred out from larvae or pupae A. quad-<lb/>
rimaculatus 61, A. crucians 221; collected imago stage A.<lb/>
quadrimaculatus 851; A. crucians 632, A. walkeri two; (5) Blood<lb/>
specimens examined for malaria parasites: school children 107,<lb/>
of which four were positive, P. vivax, three P. falciparum;<lb/>
physicians' specimens examined 27, of which seven were positive,<lb/>
P. vivax, one P. falciparum; reexamination of positives in 1923<lb/>
three, of which one was positive, P. falciparum.</p>
<p><hi>Memphis Laboratory:</hi> Personnel - A. A. Surgeon Wm. A. Krauss,<lb/>
Microscopists Ethel Barrier and Retha Kitchens.</p>
<p>798 blood smears examined for malaria parasites, of which 540<lb/>
were collected from school children in Chatham County, Georgia,<lb/>
seven of these positive, P. vivax, six positive, P. falciparum;<lb/>
82 collected from Leflore County, Mississippi, of which one was<lb/>
positive P. vivax, two positive P. falciparum; five specimens<lb/>
sent in from Tennessee State Board of Health, of which two were<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01204002"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
June 5, 1924.<lb/>
positive, P. vivax; 231 specimens were sent in locally, of which<lb/>
29 were positive P. vivax, eleven positive, P. falciparum, and<lb/>
two found with double infection.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Savannah, Georgia:</hi> Personnel - Technical<lb/>
Asst. Bruce Mayne.</p>
<p>Activities at this laboratory consisted of: (1) Observations on<lb/>
incidence of Anopheles; collected in imago stage A. quadrimacula-<lb/>
tus males four, females 21, A. crucians males 19, females 261,<lb/>
habitat of these mosquitoes as follows: animal sheds A. crucians<lb/>
203, A. quadrimaculatus 7; lumber-camp bunk-houses A. crucians<lb/>
51, A. quadrimaculatus 15; under school houses and out house<del>s</del><lb/>
A. crucians 22, A. quadrimaculatus three; inside residences A.<lb/>
crucians four; no adult punctipennis encountered; 51 specimens of<lb/>
A. crucians were taken from human habitations; (2) 56 specimens<lb/>
A. crucians and eight A. quadrimaculatus were dissected, none<lb/>
found infected; (3) Effect of drying of Anopheles' eggs of A.<lb/>
crucians were found to hatch after being removed 24 days from<lb/>
water; (4) 84 blood specimens collected locally were examined<lb/>
for malaria parasites, of which two were found positive, P.<lb/>
vivax.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemiological Studies of Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Asst. Surgeon<lb/>
F. F. Maxcy.</p>
<p>Dr<del>.</del> Maxcy's activities consisted of; (1) Malaria surveys around<lb/>
six saw mills in Clark and Baldwin Counties; study being made of<lb/>
Anopheles production and effect of screening and quinine in con-<lb/>
trolling malaria among saw mill employees (in conjunction with<lb/>
Asst. San. Eng. J. C. Carter); (2) malaria surveys of two <unclear>saw</unclear><lb/>
mills in Barbour County; (3) Continued the collection and analy-<lb/>
sis of malaria mortality figures from all of the Southern States.</p>
<p><hi>Impounded Waters in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Epidemiolo-<lb/>
gist T. H. D. Griffitts and Asst. San. Eng. E. H. Gage.</p>
<p>Dr. Griffitts' (Alabama) activities consisted of: (1) Inspection<lb/>
of Golden Bridge Pond, May 1-3, five A. punctipennis and two A.<lb/>
crucians developed from larvae collected, no house infestation<lb/>
observed; (2) Inspection of Gambusia hatcheries Cherokee Basin,<lb/>
Tallapoosa County, May 5-9; 24 ponds were created, four found<lb/>
dry, sixteen contained gambusia, some well stocked, fourteen of<lb/>
these were producing Anopheles; (No mention made by Dr. Griffitts<lb/>
of size of larvae or condition of vegetation); all mosquitoes<lb/>
which emerged from larvae and pupae collected in fish ponds were<lb/>
A. punctipennis; (3) Inspection of recently impounded pond near<lb/>
Gantt's Qarry, Talladega County; recommendations made for mosqui-<lb/>
to control; (4) Inspection of mosquito control around Veterans'<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01204003"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
June 5, 1924.<lb/>
Bureau Hospital, Lake City, Florida, May 14-16; recommendations<lb/>
submitted to Medical Officer in Charge; May 20-23 drainage sur-<lb/>
vey made at Selma, <unclear>Dallas-County</unclear>; recommendations submitted for<lb/>
antimalaria campaign.</p>
<p>Mr. Gage (South Carolina). Mr. Gage's activities consisted of<lb/>
observations on incidence of Anopheles in Horse Creek Valley,<lb/>
Aiken County, South Carolina: marked increases in all forms of<lb/>
aquatic life; maximum water temperature 82 degrees; approximate-<lb/>
ly three times as many Anopheles larvae taken per average dip as<lb/>
were taken in April; six times as many adult Anopheles were found<lb/>
per resting place examined as were found in <unclear><del>A</del></unclear>pril, the proportions<lb/>
being A. crucians 57%, A. punctipennis 41%, and A. quadrimaculatus<lb/>
2%; the proportion of emergence from larvae collected A. crucians<lb/>
54%, A. punctipennis 44%, and A. quadrimaculatus 2%, the latter<lb/>
from a seepage area; Anopheles larvae three times as abundant in<lb/>
producing areas other than impounded waters and four times as<lb/>
many adult Anopheles were found per resting place away from imp-<lb/>
ounded water projects as in resting places adjacent to these ponds.</p>
<p><hi>Major Drainage in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Assoc. San. Eng. A. W.<lb/>
Fuchs.</p>
<p>Mr. Fuchs' activities consisted of: Malaria survey<del>s</del> of North Little<lb/>
Rock, Arkansas, at the request of Mr. Van Hovenberg and in support<lb/>
of anti-malaria program of the Missouri Pacific Railway; collec-<lb/>
tion of drainage data from the Mississippi Delta Counties from<lb/>
Bureau of <unclear>Candus</unclear>; study made of plan through which the agricultur-<lb/>
al agent of Shelby County, Tennessee, cooperating with the County<lb/>
health officials proposes to score communities doing mosquito con-<lb/>
trol and award prizes at the Tri-State Fair; advice and assistance<lb/>
furnished.</p>
<p><hi>Rural Malaria Investigations:</hi> Personnel - A.A. Surgeon C.P. Coogle,<lb/>
Asst. San. Eng. J.C. Carter, Assoc. San. Eng. L.M. Fisher, Asst. San.<lb/>
Eng. J. G. <unclear>Foster</unclear>, Asst. San. Eng. H. N: Old, Asst. San. Eng. F. R.<lb/>
Shaw, and Surgeon L.L. Williams.</p>
<p>Mr. Carter<del>'s</del> (Alabama) activities consisted of study of rural mal-<lb/>
aria control in Clark, Baldwin, Barbour, Houston, and Dallas<lb/>
Counties; surveys made around five saw mills in Clarke County show-<lb/>
ed high incidence of malaria, with mosquito control economically<lb/>
impossible; effort made to interest mill operators in screening<lb/>
and quinine administration; Malaria surveys made around saw mills<lb/>
in Baldwin County, malaria foci located and plotted on county map;<lb/>
similar malaria surveys made of two saw mills in Barbour County;<lb/>
screen surveys continued in Houston County; malaria school survey<lb/>
completed in Dallas County.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01204004"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>June 5, 1924.</p>
<p>Mr. Old (Georgia) activities consisted of study of mal-<lb/>
aria mosquito conditions continued in Chatham County;<lb/>
(1) Adult Anopheles collected as follows: 80 observations<lb/>
made, five of which were in occupied houses, others out<lb/>
houses and bridges, A. crucians collected, males 36, females<lb/>
758, A. quadrimaculatus males four, females 17; the five<lb/>
occupied houses gave 29 A. crucians females and one A. quad-<lb/>
rimaculatus male; (2) Emergence from larvae collected: A.<lb/>
crucians male 20, females 20, A. quadrimaculatus female one,<lb/>
A. punctipennis female one; (3) Observations go to show that<lb/>
Anopheles producing areas in Chatham County are purely local<lb/>
and not wide spread; in many parts of the County Anopheles<lb/>
are rarely seen;, (4) Observations of drainage ditch mainte-<lb/>
nance and methods of removing vegetation therefrom contin-<lb/>
ued; (5) Observations conducted of malaria conditions around<lb/>
three lumber camps; (6) Study of bamboo for sub-soil drainage<lb/>
undertaken.</p>
<p>Mr. Shaw (Louisiana) activities consisted of rural malaria<lb/>
control investigations in Tangipahoa and St. Mary's Parishes:<lb/>
Study made of screening situation in Tangipahoa Parish; stu-<lb/>
dy of quinine administration by Natalbany Lumber Company con-<lb/>
tinued; of 376 adult A. quadrimaculatus and 546 A. crucians<lb/>
collected in out houses only three were males; anophelines larvae<lb/>
very scarce and difficult to find; malaria school census com-<lb/>
pleted in St. Mary's Parish; malaria lecture delivered at three<lb/>
rural schools; tide levee and tide gate study being made at<lb/>
Patterson; study of method by which water temperature in metal<lb/>
cisterns may be reduced.</p>
<p>Dr. C. P. Coogle and Asst. San. Eng. J. G. Foster, activities<lb/>
consisted of malaria and mosquito studies in Leflore County<lb/>
continued: weekly inspection of mosquito resting places; 263<lb/>
adult Anopheles collected, A. quadrimaculatus 24 male, 175<lb/>
female, A. punctipennis ten male, 53 female, A. crucians one<lb/>
female; gradual, uniform increase in Anopheles noted; a marked<lb/>
decrease in adult catches noted for two days after each heavy<lb/>
rain; diligent search made for Anopheles larvae; apparently<lb/>
much more rare than adults; emergence<del>s</del> of larvae collected, all<lb/>
A. punctipennis; 50 tenant houses selected for screening studies.</p>
<p>Mr. Fisher (South Carolina), activities consisted of rural<lb/>
malaria control investigations continued in counties having<lb/>
health organizations; malaria school census completed in<lb/>
eighteen counties; mosquito survey made at Chester, South<lb/>
Carolina.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01204005"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>June 5, 1924.</p>
<p>Surgeon L. L. Williams (Virginia) activities consisted of<lb/>
locating malaria foci and mosquito producing areas and de-<lb/>
termining the relative importance of A. punctipennis, A.<lb/>
crucians and A. quadrimaculatus in conveying malaria in<lb/>
Virginia<unclear>;</unclear> only A. punctipennis and A. crucians emerged from<lb/>
larvae collected during May; mosquito production definitely<lb/>
began in all breeding areas under observation the last week<lb/>
in May.</p>
<p><hi>Conferences and Inspections:</hi> Senior Sanitary Engineer J. A.<lb/>
LePrince visited Field Laboratory at Crowley, Louisiana, May<lb/>
1st; Inspection at Franklin, La. May 2nd; Inspection of<lb/>
Shelby county rural malaria control May 6-12th, apparently<lb/>
adult Anopheles not yet emerged in this locality; inspection<lb/>
Leflore County, Mississippi, May 19-22; inspection Columbia,<lb/>
South Carolina, May 28-31; prepared paper for International<lb/>
Conference of Sanitary Engineers at London, England; prepared<lb/>
paper for International Health Conference on Health Problems,<lb/>
at Kingston, Jamaica, B.W.I.</p>
<p>Medical Officer in Charge attended conference of field direc-<lb/>
tors, Scientific Research Division, Washington,, D.C., May 7th;<lb/>
attended the Mississippi Medical Association, Jackson, Miss.,<lb/>
May 14th-15th; conference with Dr. W. V. King, Bureau of En-<lb/>
tomology, Mound, La., May 17th.</p>
<p><hi>Expenditures:</hi> During the month approximately $4,637.52 was<lb/>
expended from the Malaria Allotment in connection with field<lb/>
investigations of malaria.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>L. D. Fricks, Surgeon,<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
