<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01201018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from G. Jameson Carr to Henry Rose Carter, May 22, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carr, G. Jameson</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01201018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-05-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Scannell, E.J.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-05-22">May 22, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01201018</idno>
<title>Letter from G. Jameson Carr to Henry Rose Carter, May 22, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carr reports on observations of Aedes aegypti breeding.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-05-22">
<head>Letter from G. Jameson Carr to Henry Rose Carter, May 22, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01201018"/>
<opener>
File<lb/>
PRA&Ccedil;A 1817 N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 181<lb/>
<dateline>
DEPARTAMENTO DE SAUDE PUBLICA<lb/>
COMMISS&Atilde;O DA FEBRE AMARELLA<lb/>
PARAHYBA DO NORTE--BRASIL<lb/>
<date value="1924-05-22">May 22. 1924.</date>
</dateline>
CAIXA POSTAL, N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 41<lb/>
<del>Boo</del><lb/>
I. H. B.<lb/>
Breeding<lb/>
<hi>Places</hi>,<lb/>
File with <unclear>Carbon</unclear> of Deeks<lb/>
pice,<lb/>
<salute>Sir.</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honour to submit that I received an order from Dr Scannell<lb/>
dated Bahia, April 17. to report to you any observations I might have made<lb/>
regarding the question as to whether Aedes AEgypti would breed in mud puddles.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>(1) Since January 1. 1924 I have ordered my personel to report to me at once<lb/>
any larvae they found in mud puddles.</p>
<p>In no case so reported and visited at once personally, have I been able to<lb/>
verify Aedes Aegypti, all cases have been either, Culex Fatigans or Aedes<lb/>
(Howardina) Aureostriatus, or collections of water recently emptied from<lb/>
deposits where there already <add>were</add> larvae or pupae.</p>
<p>This investigation was stimulated after reading West African reports in<lb/>
November last year.</p></item>
<item><p>(2). A tin basin .55 cm in diameter by .14 cm deep was filled with a mixture,<lb/>
half and half, of clean dry sand, yellow in colour, and top layer black humus<lb/>
from my garden and packed tightly including the edges, so that no tin was<lb/>
exposed.</p>
<p>One half of the edge was covered with the sand to leave a choice in colour<lb/>
the other half being black.</p>
<p>The center was scooped out to form a concavity 40 cm in diameter and 9 cm<lb/>
deep at the center.</p>
<p>Water was carefully added so as not to disturb the surfaces of the edges<lb/>
and filled the concavity to a depth of 8 cm. leaving an edge of 75 cm not<lb/>
covered but which quickly became moist by capillarity, showing a fine film<lb/>
over the sand and humus. (by magnifying glass, times 14).</p></item>
</list></p>
<pb n="2" id="f01201019"/>
<p>PRA&Ccedil;A 1817 N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 181</p>
<p>DEPARTAMENTO DE SAUDE PUBLICA<lb/>
COMMISS&Atilde;O DA FEBRE AMARELLA<lb/>
PARAHYBA DO NORTE--BRASIL</p>
<p>CAIXA POSTAL, N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 41</p>
<p>The water was allowed to stand under protective netting for twenty four hours<lb/>
and then tested by Phenol red giving a Ph. of 7, 6. and after acidification<lb/>
by a drop of HNO3, in 20 cc, plus AgNO3 3 drops, gave slight turbidity of NACl.<lb/>
The temperature of the water through-out the experiment varied between 22&deg; and 25&deg;C.<lb/>
ON May 7. 1924. A male hare and 5 male and 6 female Aedes Aegypti were put,<lb/>
together with the artificial mud puddle, into my experimental cage, size 1.10 m.<lb/>
square, means being employed to protect the puddle from the hare.</p>
<p>The females had been bred out two days before under lantern jars, had had no<lb/>
blood or other feed, but copulation was frequent.</p>
<p>AS soon as the hare had settled down to his quarters, which was half an hour,<lb/>
the first females were seen to be feeding on his ears (8.30 am).</p>
<p>(Here I might mention that I have found white hares the best for blood feeds<lb/>
as the mosquitos show up well and the ears being long and heavy they cannot<lb/>
be waggled so as to dislodge the insect as in the case of rabbit or pig,<lb/>
but it is well to place a buck and dam together as the buck tends to become<lb/>
very wild and will tear down netting and other erections seemingly out of<lb/>
sheer exuberance).</p>
<p>At 10.30 pm two females were seen to be depositing eggs, one on the sand and<lb/>
the other on the humus, 3 and 5 cm respectively, away from the actual body of<lb/>
water, there- after eggs were deposited by all the females indescriminately<lb/>
over both sand and humus edges but no further than 5 cm away from the water<lb/>
in any case, nor nearer than 1 cm, until the 18th when the last female died.<lb/>
(All males had died by the 14th).</p>
<p>On the 11th, 10 am, the first larvae was seen to be wriggling down to the water<lb/>
in the film and it took exactly 3 hours and 10 minutes to reach the main body<lb/>
a distance of 4 and a half cms.</p>
<p>This phenomenon was witnessed and is still progressing to the date of writing<lb/>
the puddle being now literally alive with larvae in all periods, and pupae.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01201020"/>
<p>PRA&Ccedil;A 1817 N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 181</p>
<p>DEPARTAMENTO DE SAUDE PUBLICA<lb/>
COMMISS&Atilde;O DA FEBRE AMARELLA<lb/>
PARAHYBA DO NORTE--BRASIL</p>
<p>CAIXA POSTAL, N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 41</p>
<p>On the 19th at 2 pm the first pupa was seen.</p>
<p>On the 21st the same had become an adult male (9.30 pm.)</p>
<p>On the 22nd, to-day, 10 more pupae have become adults, 7 males and 3 females.</p>
<p>I realize that this experiment can only demonstrate that Aedes Aegypti will<lb/>
lay, if forced, on the edge of mud puddles and thereafter the eggs will develope<lb/>
and the larvae migrate through the surface film to the main body of water<lb/>
to complete the full cycle, protected against rain, sun, natural enemies<lb/>
and disturbances of animals and man, especially against ants <add>(</add> in the egg<lb/>
stage), which I have found particularly fond of them.</p>
<p>In another experiment I found that Aedes Aegypti preferred plain wooden barrels<lb/>
against 14 other recepticles offered, including muddy water in an earthenware<lb/>
jar.</p>
<p>I shall continue to watch for the natural phenomenon and report at once if found<lb/>
while deeming it a favour if I can carry out any particular experiment for you.<lb/>
Neither my training nor the means at my disposal are such as to enable me to<lb/>
do other than very simple observations but each day brings the joy of something<lb/>
new seen and registered.</p>
<p>I have the honour to be</p>
<p>Sir</p>
<closer>
<salute>your obedient servant</salute>
<signed>G. Jameson Carr</signed>.
Dr H.R. Carter.<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General<lb/>
United States Public Health Service<lb/>
Washington. D.C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
