<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01206012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Reports by Rudolph E. Thompson, M.A. Barber and Joseph A. LePrince, July 12, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01206012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-07-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Barber, M. A.</name>
<name type="place">Scotland</name>
<name type="place">Great Britain</name>
<name type="place">Iowa</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Crowley (La.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-07-12">July 12, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01206012</idno>
<title>Reports by Rudolph E. Thompson, M.A. Barber and Joseph A. LePrince, July 12, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Thompson reports on the sanitary condition of the water supply in Great Britain. Barber provides information regarding malarial conditions in Louisiana. LePrince discusses mosquito control efforts in Tennessee and Alabama.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-07-12">
<head>Reports by Rudolph E. Thompson, M.A. Barber and Joseph A. LePrince, July 12, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01206012"/>
<opener>
315<lb/>
<hi><unclear>WATER</unclear> SUPPLIES</hi><lb/>
<hi>PAGE FIFTY-FOUR</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Treasury Department<lb/>
BUREAU OF THE PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
Washington<lb/>
<date value="1924-07-12">July 12, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
PUBLIC HEALTH ENGINEERING ABSTRACTS<lb/>
</opener>
<p><hi>SCRAPING WATER MAINS, HELENSBURGH, SCOTLAND</hi>. Jas. W. Stirling. Surveyor,<lb/>
Vol. 65, No. 1691, June 13, 1924. p. 554.</p>
<p>The water supply of Helensburgh is obtained from the Ballyvoulin Burn,<lb/>
3 miles distant from the reservoirs. The water, after settlement, does<lb/>
not require filtration and the existing filter beds, which are inadequate<lb/>
to deal with the present consumption, are to be emptied and used as storage<lb/>
tanks. Trouble has been experienced with the growth of a variety of chara<lb/>
in the reservoirs, necessitating occasional emptying and cleaning. The weed<lb/>
does not flourish on the pitched surface of the banks, in those parts oc-<lb/>
casionally exposed to air and sun, or at depths greater than 12 feet. Greater<lb/>
difficulty is caused by the growth in the mains of a fairly soft nodule of<lb/>
rusty appearance composed of hydrated ferric oxide and vegetable matter. In<lb/>
one instance a 5-in. pipe on a gradient of 1 in 7 was rendered impenetrable<lb/>
to water under pressure of 75 lbs. Surfaces completely coated with nodules<lb/>
1-1 1/4 inches in thickness are frequently encountered. The two g-in. pipes<lb/>
which convey the water from the fountain head to the reservoirs were scraped<lb/>
in 1909 and in 1920, the capacity being increased from 40,000 gals. per hour<lb/>
to 52,500 in the former year and from 35,000 to 51,000 in the latter. In 1920<lb/>
the scraping was carried out with a Glenfield scraper at a cost of 3d. per<lb/>
yard. The town pipes were scraped by hand, 85 yards in each direction being<lb/>
dealt with from one opening, at an approximate cost of 3 d. per yard per inch<lb/>
in diameter. The scraping considerably more than doubled the discharge from<lb/>
certain hydrants and the day pressure was increased from 45 lbs. to 82 and<lb/>
the night pressure from 85 to 106. The per capita consumption is 70 gals.<lb/>
per day for domestic and 5 gals. for other purposes.</p>
<p>Rudolph E. Thompson.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p><hi>VARIATIONS IN CONSUMPTION OF WATER IN TOWNS</hi>. John Bowman, Surveyor, Vol. 65,<lb/>
No. 1693, June 27, 1924. p. 589.</p>
<p>The per capita consumption of water in 58 areas in Great Britain is given,<lb/>
with a few statistics for American Cities for comparison. The consumption in<lb/>
the areas quoted ranges from 14.26 to 70 gals. per day, 29 being lower than<lb/>
25 gals. and 29 higher. Eighteen of the 29 higher consumptions are in towns<lb/>
in Scotland, this being due to the larger number of fittings per house as<lb/>
compared with towns in England. A table is included showing the results of<lb/>
measurements recently made in Edinburgh of the consumption in different types<lb/>
of districts and in various institutions.</p>
<p>Rudolph E. Thompson.</p>
<p>_________________________________________________</p>
<p><hi>OPERATION RECORDS FOR SMALL WATER WORKS.</hi> Earle L. Waterman, Associate Professor<lb/>
of Sanitary Engineering, University of Iowa. Canadian Engineer, Vol. 46, No.<lb/>
20, May 13, 1924. p. 521-2.</p>
<p>The value of water works operation records is emphasized and the existing<lb/>
situation, particularly in the State of Iowa is discussed. Details that should<lb/>
be embodied in the records are reviewed and the many ways in which such records<lb/>
may be used to advantage are pointed out.</p>
<p>Rudolph E. Thompson.</p>
<p>________________________________________________</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01206013"/>
<p>F. Malaria La</p>
<p>Book</p>
<p><unclear>Le Prince</unclear></p>
<p>J-840</p>
<p><hi>MALARIA, OTHER INSECT BORNE DISEASES AND INSECTS</hi>.</p>
<p>7 - 19 - 24</p>
<p><hi>PAGE TWENTY-SIX</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>MALARIA IN THE SEVENTH DISTRICT OF LOUISIANA.</hi> M. A. Barber, U.S. Public Health Service. New Orleans Medical &amp; Surgical Journal, Vol. 77, No. 1,<lb/>
July, 1924. p. 16-20.</p>
<p>The Seventh Congressional District includes a group of parishes in south-<lb/>
west Louisiana, in some of which rice is cultivated extensively. In the rice<lb/>
fields, covered with water during a large part of the summer, myriads of<lb/>
Anopheles are produced. The immense area under irrigation, would make pro-<lb/>
hibitive the cost of preventing the Anopheles production. In spite of large<lb/>
numbers of Anopheles the malaria rate of this region is not high. The examina-<lb/>
tion of the blood of 1235 school children gave a parasite index of only 3.2%.<lb/>
The spleen rate of 190 school-boys was only 3.7%. In both sorts of survey many<lb/>
children from outside the rice region are included, some of whom gave a much<lb/>
higher malaria rate than those in the rice region. A search for malaria cases<lb/>
in the vicinity of Crowley, La., a work in which the physicians of Crowley<lb/>
cooperated, yielded during 1923 only about 90 cases in which parasites could<lb/>
be found in the blood. According to the testimony of physicians malaria has<lb/>
been rapidly decreasing during recent years.</p>
<p>Houses in the rice region are fairly well built, a large proportion of<lb/>
them screened and bed nets are commonly used in unscreened houses. The rural<lb/>
population is fairly well-to-do and the negro population is largely confined<lb/>
to towns. It is quite possible that the relatively high general standard of<lb/>
living is an important factor in the prevention of malaria in the rice region<lb/>
notwithstanding the abundance of Anopheline carriers. In the term &ldquo;standard<lb/>
of living&rdquo; is included more adequate treatment of the sick and some knowledge<lb/>
of the method by which malaria is transmitted. The important question is<lb/>
raised as to whether a very moderate rise in the general standard of living<lb/>
may not greatly reduce the malaria rate. It is emphasized that the improve-<lb/>
ment should be general. A neglected group may harbor carriers and tend to<lb/>
vitiate the whole community.</p>
<p>M. A. Barber.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p><hi>MALARIA CONTROL AS APPROACHED BY AN ALABAMA INDUSTRIAL CORPORATION</hi>. C. H.</p>
<p>Kibbey, M.D., Director of Sanitation, Tennessee Coal, Iron &amp; R.R.Co. Transactions<lb/>
Fourth Annual Conference Malaria Field Workers, Chattanooga, Tenn., November 14-16,<lb/>
1922. Public Health Bulletin No. 137. p.25-40.</p>
<p>The Tennessee Coal, Iron &amp; Railroad Company has demonstrated that conser-<lb/>
vation of the health of employees indemnifies large employers of man power.</p>
<p>Large areas of Naias flexilis, which were responsible for much anopheles breed-<lb/>
ing in a large impounding reservoir, were successfully eradicated. The method used<lb/>
is described.</p>
<p>The destruction of mosquito larvae by the wave action from a power launch is<lb/>
reported as being entirely successful. Vegetation, along the water margin which<lb/>
is calculated to interfere with violence of wave motion, is removed. Daily trips<lb/>
with the motor boat are made around a pond having some 22 miles of shore line.<lb/>
Control is considered 100% perfect without the use of other larvacidal measures.</p>
<p>The use of fish as a malaria control measure can no more be left in the hands<lb/>
of the public than can any other sanitary procedure. Removal of vegetation, other<lb/>
than some of the algae, not considered necessary to effective fish control, es-<lb/>
pecially if game fish abound. Predatory fish apt to herd gambusia into that por-<lb/>
tion of the water where they are most needed.</p>
<p>A campaign to control malaria through mosquito reproduction should include<lb/>
the control of the pestiferous mosquitoes also. Success of health work is largely<lb/>
dependent upon the attitude of the public toward the work. No advertising is<lb/>
better calculated to increase the popularity of a health department <unclear>that</unclear> is the<lb/>
eradication of mosquitoes.</p>
<closer>
<signed>J. A. LePrince</signed>.
___________________________________________________<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
