<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01214001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes from Henry Rose Carter to M.J. Rosenau, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01214001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rosenau, M.J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01214001</idno>
<title>Notes from Henry Rose Carter to M.J. Rosenau, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter provides Rosenau with notes from his book on yellow fever. He discusses the origins of yellow fever, as well as other points about yellow fever and malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Notes from Henry Rose Carter to M.J. Rosenau, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01214001"/>
<p>Book<lb/>
Rosenau</p>
<p>Notes, For Dr. Rosenau<lb/>
(On Section 111. History of Yellow Fever.)</p>
<p><hi>Page 1, MS</hi>: Your suggestion that the original place of origin of yellow<lb/>
fever (&ldquo;where the triple alliance between mosquito: parasite and man<lb/>
established itself&rdquo;) may have ceased to be an endemic focus before<lb/>
the West Coast of Africa and the Americas became infected, is entirely<lb/>
possible.</p>
<p>One can easily conceive of a region infected with yellow fever be-<lb/>
ing freed from it by some change--sociological: biological or climat-<lb/>
ic--but which prior to this had infected some other place where the<lb/>
infection remained permanently. The present infection in Brazil<lb/>
quite surely came from New Orleans or Havana (1849) both of which are<lb/>
now free from it, <hi>the first spontaneously</hi>, while that in Brazil still<lb/>
exists. The island of Grenada infected the Guianas and freed itself<lb/>
long before they did.</p>
<p>I think when I said &ldquo;origin&rdquo; I was thinking less of where the in-<lb/>
fection--the paracitism pathogenic to man of this organism--was evolv-<lb/>
ed-than where it was first found in historic (or traditional) times.</p>
<p>It is a question to me, however, if the &ldquo;mosquito, the micro-organ-<lb/>
ism and man&rdquo; were the original group which determined the parasitism<lb/>
of this organism--I think we can assume it as originally free living.<lb/>
I should think that the parasitism of any organism would be more apt<lb/>
to be developed in a host to which it was not pathogenic, or at least<lb/>
not seriously pathogenic. If so, the probabilities are (1) that if<lb/>
the parasitism of this organism was developed with man as a host it<lb/>
was not at that time pathogenic to man: or (2) its developement of<lb/>
parasitism took place in some animal other than man to which it was<lb/>
not pathogenic.</p>
<p>If the 1st.: pathogenicity to man was a subsequent evolution in<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01214002"/>
in<lb/>
Notes. Page 2.<lb/>
man: If the 2nd., although not pathogenic to its host in which para-<lb/>
sitism was developed, it may have been so to man from the beginning.</p>
<p>For the first we have indeed the analogy of the change of virulence<lb/>
of a number of infections, indeed of yellow fever itself, but I know<lb/>
of nothing that would lead us to think that at one time the yellow<lb/>
fever organism was not pathogenic to man and generally so. It is pos-<lb/>
sible, but does not seem at all <unclear>probable</unclear>.</p>
<p>For the 2nd. there is the analogy we now find in a number of in-<lb/>
fections: Rocky Mountain fever: sleeping sickness: Chagas' disease etc.<lb/>
Such a host-of-evolution (resevoir host?) might (a) have ceased to<lb/>
exist or (b) if still existent to be looked for especially in the re-<lb/>
gions in which this evolution took place, or in regions in which bio-<lb/>
logical conditions are similar to those then existing in that region.</p>
<p>It is fair to say that for man to have been a necessary link in<lb/>
the survival of this organism--the conditions for this being the same<lb/>
as to-day--implies so dense a population, or so much intercommunica-<lb/>
tion among men that this could not have occurred among what we are<lb/>
accustomed to call &ldquo;primitive men.&rdquo; A population of hunters or fish-<lb/>
ers could not have maintained as a second host the life of this organ-<lb/>
ism if the requisites for this were the same as at present.</p>
<p>The evidence seems then to be ( ) that yellow fever did not ex-<lb/>
ist among primitive men and hence is not a very old human infection or<lb/>
( ) if it did, that it was kept alive by some other animal besides<lb/>
man acting as second (and resevoir?) host.</p>
<p>Note in this connection that its mosquito vector is considered by<lb/>
entomologists one of the more recent mosquitoes--not old like Anopheles<lb/>
and some others.</p>
<p>See how far afield this has carried me. Nevertheless I am inclined<lb/>
to think (note the &ldquo;inclined,&rdquo; I am not really thinking it) that the<lb/>
evolution to parasitism of the causative organism of yellow fever took<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01214003"/>
took<lb/>
Notes. Page 3.<lb/>
place in some animal other than man as the third member of your tri-<lb/>
ple alliance and probably its pathogenicity to man as well.</p>
<p><hi>Page 4, MS:</hi> Stegomyia in Asia:</p>
<p>(1) See quotation from Edward's letter, &ldquo;very rare&rdquo; in Asia &ldquo;except<lb/>
in seaports&rdquo; etc.</p>
<p>(2) Had the south-eastern part of Asia, where Stegomyia now abound,<lb/>
ever been infected, with the dense population it has had for centu-<lb/>
ries and the vector as numerous as, if indigenous, they would be from<lb/>
the universal habit of storing water for domestic use, the chance of<lb/>
its spontaneous elimination therefrom had been practically nil. Yet<lb/>
we have not found it in Asia--and we have a very long history of south-<lb/>
eastern Asia.</p>
<p>Also I am going to send you a carbon of a paper I wrote some time<lb/>
ago, at the request of the Australians, on this subject.</p>
<p><hi>Page 7, MS:</hi> 600,000 Indians in Jamaica. It may be; the most one can<lb/>
say is that these are guess estimates.</p>
<p><hi>Page 13, MS:</hi> &ldquo;yellow fever possibly endemic in tierra caliente without<lb/>
provoking epidemics to come to special notice in codices or anales.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Not permanently endemic there, I think, without epidemics appearing<lb/>
from time to time among the expeditions sent down from the plateau,<lb/>
which, I judge, would have been noticed. These were frequent after<lb/>
1458, &ldquo;when Moctecuma subjugated the province of <unclear>Chicoaque</unclear> near Panuco.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 39, MS:</hi> &ldquo;community depopulated by malaria?&rdquo;</p>
<p>This is practically true for white people in the rural section of<lb/>
much of tide-water Virginia: of the coast of South Carolina and Ga.; of<lb/>
the Yazoo delta etc. Negroes live there--too few whites to count. I<lb/>
judge that we can put much of Greece: the Roman Campagna and some other<lb/>
parts of Italy in the same category. &ldquo;Things of continuance or of fre-<lb/>
quent recurrence be in two categories: to the one we become accustomed;<lb/>
the other we become tired of:&rdquo; And malaria falls distinctly in the lat-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01214004"/>
lat-<lb/>
Notes. Page 4.<lb/>
ter class.</p>
<p>Page 40, MS: &ldquo;neither yellow fever nor malaria about Vera Cruz&rdquo; when<lb/>
Cortez came. I agree. I think that there was no malaria in the Ameri-<lb/>
cas before the Spaniards (and negroes) came. Wrote a <unclear>memo</unclear>, for L. L. Williams<lb/>
on this subject.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01214005"/>
<p><hi>Obiter Dicta</hi>.</p>
<p>Again your &ldquo;triple alliance.&rdquo; Does not the West Coast of Africa<lb/>
seem to be the very home of spirochetes (or is spironemata the up-<lb/>
to-date word?) pathogenic to man? There have been reported from this<lb/>
region a variety of infections of men with (reportedly) different spi-<lb/>
rochetes and there seem to be here more different species of this or-<lb/>
ganism pathogenic to man, and in greater abundance, than in any other<lb/>
part of the world. Many of these infections in man are somewhat like,<lb/>
and some (as reported) are very like, yellow fever; and, if we accept<lb/>
the organism of Noguchi as the one causative of yellow fever, the num-<lb/>
ber of species of spirochetes pathogenic to man in this region might<lb/>
be the basis of an argument for this being the region in which a spi-<lb/>
rochete causing yellow fever in man was evolved!</p>
<p>Whether the similarity of the human reactions to these West African<lb/>
infections and <add>in</add> yellow fever could be held to imply a general similar-<lb/>
ity in their toxins is doubtful. If so, it would, more or less, cor-<lb/>
respond to the similarity of the biology of Stegomyia aegypti and the<lb/>
some other African coast Stegomyia.</p>
<p>Fanciful? yes; and I don't know enough about the West African<lb/>
spirochetes nor the possibilities of the evolution of any spirochete<lb/>
to have an opinion on this matter. Only it seems to dove-tail in<lb/>
with all the rest.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
