<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01216002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Study of Cases Reported by Colonial Authorities at Stann Creek, British Honduras, by [Emmett I. Vaughn], [1924]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01216002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Harwood, C.S.</name>
<name type="place">Stann Creek (British Honduras)</name>
<name type="place">Belize</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-00-00">[1924]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01216002</idno>
<title>Study of Cases Reported by Colonial Authorities at Stann Creek, British Honduras, by [Emmett I. Vaughn], [1924]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Vaughn describes possible yellow fever cases in Stann Creek, British Honduras. He includes fever charts of one case.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-00-00">
<head>Study of Cases Reported by Colonial Authorities at Stann Creek, British Honduras, by [Emmett I. Vaughn], [1924]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01216002"/>
<p>COPY</p>
<p>STUDY OF CASES REPORTED BY COLONIAL AUTHORITIES AT STANN CREEK, BRITISH HONDURAS</p>
<p>CASE NO. I - LUCIANO GAMBOA - This man's illness dates from November 3 but he<lb/>
was not seen by Dr. C. S. Harwood, Assistant Medical Officer, until November 17<lb/>
upon which date he also saw Case No. II - Nicasio Mena - for the first time.</p>
<p>Dr. Harwood had been called to Belize as a witness in a murder trial<lb/>
the early part of November and did not return until the above date. Gamboa was<lb/>
not admitted to the local hospital as he was convalescent when seen on the<lb/>
seventeenth. Investigation shows that he returned to work at the lumber camp on<lb/>
November 24.</p>
<p>Gamboa has spent his whole life in Stann Creek and has not visited, met<lb/>
nor seen, to his knowledge, anyone from Mexico, Guatemala, Salvador or Honduras.<lb/>
Before his illness he returned to Stann Creek from the lumber camp on Saturday,<lb/>
October 25, and returned on Monday, October 27. The week previously he arrived<lb/>
on Saturday, October 18 and returned on Monday, October 20.</p>
<p>Investigation fails to reveal an illness resembling his in houses near-<lb/>
by or in his immediate neighborhood. At the camp his quarters were one-quarter<lb/>
of a mile from those occupied by Nicasio Mena. If his case were yellow fever he<lb/>
was infected between October 29 and November 1, during which time he was in the<lb/>
lumber camp, and the female Aedes Aegypti biting him became infected between<lb/>
October 17 and 20. November 3 to 6 represents the period in which he was in the<lb/>
infective stage and a secondary case should have appeared in the period between<lb/>
November 17 and 25. Careful investigation does not show a secondary case in<lb/>
this period.</p>
<p>CASE NO. II - NICASIO MENA - This man's illness dates from Monday, November 10,<lb/>
when he returned to the lumber camp where he was employed. As mentioned above<lb/>
he was not seen by Dr. Harwood until November 17 when his condition was so grave<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01216003"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
that he was admitted to the hospital. He was in Stann Creek for the week-end,<lb/>
Saturday, October 25, to Monday, October 27, and from Saturday, November 1, to<lb/>
Monday, November 3.</p>
<p>One year ago he returned to Stann Creek from Honduras where he had<lb/>
spent five years. Since his return his only absences from Stann Creek have been<lb/>
to Newtown on Commers Bight (7 miles away) and to the lumber camp - 19 miles<lb/>
distant. His family states that he had neither seen nor visited anyone, to the<lb/>
best of their knowledge, from Mexico, Guatemala, Salvador or Honduras. Investi-<lb/>
gation did not reveal any illness resembling his in nearby or neighboring houses<lb/>
at any recent period.</p>
<p>If his case were yellow fever he was infected in the period November 5<lb/>
to 8 during which time he was working at the lumber camp, and the Aedes Aegypti<lb/>
biting him probably became infected between October 24 and 27.</p>
<p>His infective stage is represented by the period November 10 to 13 and<lb/>
a secondary case would probably have appeared between November 24 and December 2<lb/>
and to date such case has not appeared.</p>
<p>There is no information to suggest that either Mena or Gamboa were<lb/>
friends or ever visited each other. It is further noted that Mena and Gamboa<lb/>
lived in widely separated parts of Stann Creek.</p>
<p>CASE NO. III - ADOLFO MENA - This child of nine years was not a relative or friend<lb/>
of either of the above two cases; lived in a distant part of town and both mother<lb/>
and child stated that they did not know Mena or Gamboa and had never seen them.</p>
<p>The first day of the child's illness was November 18 and the infection -<lb/>
if any - took place between November 13 and 16 and the Aedes Aegypti should have<lb/>
become infected in the period November 1 to 4. During these periods the child<lb/>
was in Stann Creek and must have become infected in that place.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01216004"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>The infective stage of the child being November 18 to 21 a secondary<lb/>
case could have been expected between December 2 and 10 but no such case has<lb/>
appeared after the most careful investigation.</p>
<p>This child had never been outside of Stann Creek and the mother states<lb/>
they know no one from Mexico, Guatemala, Salvador or Honduras.</p>
<p>GENERAL COMMENTS: It is obvious after scrutinizing the first dates of illness<lb/>
(see charts attached) in each case that these cases are separate infections and<lb/>
not a chain, or series, of cases from a single original infection. Seven days<lb/>
elapsed between Gamboa's and Mena's first day of illness and eight days between<lb/>
Mena and the child Mena. To have been a series beginning with Gamboa the first<lb/>
day of Mena's illness should have been between November 17 and 25 and the child<lb/>
Mena between November 24 and December 2.</p>
<p>The child Mena actually fell ill on November 18 and chronologically,<lb/>
by a great stretch of imagination could have been considered a secondary case<lb/>
from Gamboa but the history - both clinical and personal - renders this assumption<lb/>
improbable - if not impossible.</p>
<p>It is obvious that an epidemiological connection between these three<lb/>
cases is extremely improbable. A careful study of the clinical history of these<lb/>
cases (to be discussed later) and an epidemiological study of them almost con-<lb/>
vinces the writer that they were not yellow fever.</p>
<p>It must be borne in mind that Dr. Wilson, the Principal Medical Officer,<lb/>
and Dr. Harwood, the Assistant Medical Officer, although having wide experience<lb/>
in tropical diseases in the Far East were not familiar with yellow fever. Gamboa<lb/>
was not seen until he was practically convalescent and the child Mena was probably<lb/>
diagnosed as yellow fever as a measure of safety. To the writers mind only one<lb/>
case of the three reported assumed aspects that were unusually suggestive of the<lb/>
disease.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01216005"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>The dates given as for probable secondary cases were based on the<lb/>
below table:</p>
<p>
<table rows="13" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Day of ill-<lb/>
ness bitten</cell><cell>Mosquito<lb/>
incubation</cell><cell>Human in-<lb/>
cubation</cell><cell>No. of days later<lb/>
secondary case<lb/>
should appear</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Days - 3</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>17</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>18</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>19</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>A 20</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>16</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>17</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>18</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>19</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>B 15</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>16</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>17</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>18</cell></row></table></p>
<p>A - Maximum number of days with 12 days mosquito incubation</p>
<p>B - Minimum " " " " 12 " " "</p>
<p>In order to trace these cases towards source of origin it is nec-<lb/>
essary to approximate certain dates during which (if these cases were yellow<lb/>
fever) the Aedes Aegypti biting them became infected. These approximate dates<lb/>
are October 17 - 20; October 24 - 27, and November 1 - 4, and are based on the<lb/>
assumption that the mosquito incubation period being twelve days and the female<lb/>
Aedes feeding promptly at the end of this period. According to Bulletin 1354 -<lb/>
Department of Agriculture - 1923 the female Aedes feeds 12 times in 31 days or<lb/>
once in each two and one-half days - in other words at the end of the twelfth<lb/>
day or beginning of the thirteenth she is ready to feed and this period cor-<lb/>
responds with the completion of the incubation period.</p>
<p>A scrutiny of hospital records and interrogations in every direction<lb/>
do not bring to light any case of illness in any manner resembling yellow fever<lb/>
during the periods above mentioned.</p>
<p>It being impossible to establish an epidemiological chain in Stann<lb/>
Creek attention was turned to the personnel of the Tidewater Lumber Company,<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01216006"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
located 19 miles west of Stann Creek, where two of the cases were employed. On<lb/>
December 29 a list of all the employees of the company with notes regarding cer-<lb/>
tain employees was mailed to you. These notes referred to employees coming from<lb/>
Mexico and Honduras. Of the employees noted only one has given a history that<lb/>
merits further investigation:</p>
<p>ALMANAC RICKETTS - Mosquito Indian - aged 23 years and by occupation a<lb/>
worker in mahogany camps. He had been employed in the mahogany camps on the Rio<lb/>
Hondo, a river separating British Honduras from Mexican territory, and came to<lb/>
Belize from Corazal about June 15 and on June 24 was admitted to the Belize Hos-<lb/>
pital with a provisional diagnosis of Pernicious Anemia. He was discharged on<lb/>
July 20 and his clinical history was not that of yellow fever. His temperature<lb/>
chart from June 24 to July 5 is herewith attached.</p>
<p>His temperature from July 5 to 20 (date of discharge) is not furnished<lb/>
as it was practically normal during that period. There is no record of his<lb/>
whereabouts between this time and when he returned to Belize about October 15<lb/>
when he &ldquo;signed on&rdquo; for work with the lumber company and came to Stann Creek dur-<lb/>
ing the latter part of the month. On November 1 he was seen by Dr. Harwood and<lb/>
stated that he had been ill for four days i.e. from October 28 with fever, ab-<lb/>
dominal pain and vomiting. Mr. Mullins, his superintendent, informed me that he<lb/>
saw Ricketts on the 30th and his sclerae were badly jaundiced. Ricketts shortly<lb/>
afterwards returned to work and worked continuously until December 13 when the<lb/>
camp closed down for the holiday season.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f01216007"/>
<p>
</p>
<pb n="7" id="f01216008"/>
<p>
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
