<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01219002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on the William E. Deeks manuscript, by [Henry Rose Carter], [1925]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01219002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Bass, C. C.</name>
<name type="person">Darling, Samuel Taylor</name>
<name type="person">Mayne, Bruce</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="place">Ancon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi Valley (U.S.)</name>
<name type="place">Cairo (Ill.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-00-00">[1925]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01219002</idno>
<title>Notes on the William E. Deeks manuscript, by [Henry Rose Carter], [1925]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] critiques Deeks' manuscript on malaria. He discusses the use of quinine and anti-mosquito methods.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1925-00-00">
<head>Notes on the William E. Deeks manuscript, by [Henry Rose Carter], [1925]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01219002"/>
<p>/LC</p>
<p>Comments &amp; Suggestions (Deeks MSS)<lb/>
(on)<lb/>
(Malaria.)</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><hi>1: Page 2:</hi> This, <hi>I</hi> believe, is correct, yet Bass holds that the serum of<lb/>
the blood immediately destroys the malaria parasite and Mary Rowan Walker,<lb/>
I think her name is, has submitted a number of preparations, which Welch<lb/>
said were &ldquo;extremely suggestive,&rdquo; to show that the parasites pass directly<lb/>
from corpuscle to corpuscle, the latter being in contact.</item>
<item><hi>2: Page 2:</hi> David Thomson has some work <unclear>on this</unclear>, I think, more accurate<lb/>
than Darling's.</item>
<item><hi>3: Page 3:</hi> I didn't know that the zygote went anywhere except to the out-<lb/>
side of the stomach wall (not penetrating the last coat). I do not know<lb/>
that oocysts form among the muscles. Although the <unclear>sporozoites after the oocysts has to</unclear> go<lb/>
everywhere in the mosquito.</item>
<item><hi>4: Page 3:</hi> Do you think there are ever as many as 1,000 sporozoits to 1<lb/>
oocyst? There are many, <del>I think</del>, but 1,000 is a large number.</item>
<item><hi>5: Page 3</hi>: They make their way into all parts of the mosquito's body as<lb/>
well as into the salivary glands, where <add>only</add>, however, they are, as you say,<lb/>
<del>only</del> efficient for infecting the man.</item>
<item><hi>6: Page 4:</hi> Both Roubaud and Mayne have data upon the longevity of Ano-<lb/>
pheles under different conditions. The imago <add>of many species</add> hibernates <add>and hence lives longer than <add>the winter</add></add><unclear>-</unclear> Neither in the<lb/>
Balkans nor in the U. S. does the infection hibernate anywhere.</item>
<item><hi>7: Page 5:</hi> Same was, I think, true in Panama and is true in the south of<lb/>
the U. S., though <add>the</add> forms <add>were</add> not as sharply divided as reported in Italy.</item>
<item><hi>8: Page 6:</hi> In some 13 (I think) experimental cases tried by Mayne the<lb/>
period of incubation in man was about 14 1/2 days. In a considerable num-<lb/>
ber observed by Ross: Darling: Craig: Mayne and others the period of ex-<lb/>
trinsic incubation (in the mosquito) was minimally 11 days.</item>
<item><hi>9: Page 7:</hi> Cannot the word &ldquo;immune&rdquo; <add><unclear>(immune=to fortifys)</unclear></add> be properly used for a partial pro-<lb/>
tection against (a) the infection and (b) the toxine of the parasite as<lb/>
well as the complete protection against infection by the parasite itself?<lb/>
When we speak of the &ldquo;racial immunity&rdquo; of the negro to yellow fever we mean<lb/>
a greatly lowered susceptibility to the <add>toxin of the</add> microorganism of that disease <add>not to the infection by <add>it</add></add>.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f01219003"/>
<item>disease.</item>
<item>2</item>
<item><hi>10: Page 7</hi>: It may be worth noting that four several times parasites (EA)<lb/>
were found in my own blood (Kendall and Darling) when I was feeling decid-<lb/>
edly out of sorts, but with no elevation of temperature found, taking it<lb/>
four or five times a day for some days. Symptoms and parasites disap-<lb/>
peared on taking quinine (30 to 60 grains per day).</item>
<item><hi>11: Page 10:</hi> Is it on account of a more virulent toxine made by the <unclear>EA<del>A</del></unclear> para-<lb/>
site that the infected red cells become plugged in capillaries? That they<lb/>
do is certain and I am inclined to think that their sporulation in the po-<lb/>
tal circulation is a reason why they are more directly amenable to cure by<lb/>
quinine than simply tertian.</item>
<item><hi>13: Page 11:</hi> I think in such cases blood examination should always show<lb/>
parasites, but their presence does not of itself negative other sickness.</item>
<item><p><hi>14: Page 11:</hi> I count you absolutely <add>right in this</add>, so far as the Americas are concerned,<lb/>
and, Stevens: Craig <hi>et al</hi> to the contrary, <unclear><del>believe</del></unclear><add>I think</add> you are right for Africa.<lb/>
It is no wise impossible, however, that a disease <unclear>named</unclear> simply from its<lb/>
symptom complex may in different places have different etiologies.</p>
<p>I did not think that our mortality of blackwater at Ancon was as<lb/>
great as 20% after we stopped the huge doses of quinine (Bre<add>h</add>m) and the not<lb/>
quite so fatal treatment of tincture of chloride of iron (Connor) had been<lb/>
abandoned and we reverted to symptomatic treatment. I think it fell then<lb/>
to between 8% and 12 1/2%.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>15: Page 12:</hi> See &ldquo;Immunity&rdquo; <hi>supra</hi>.</p>
<p>The use of the words &ldquo;nor symptoms result&rdquo; accepts complete immunity<lb/>
to toxines as immunity. This is not immunity to infection.</p></item>
<item><hi>16: Page 13:</hi> This is immunity to infection.</item>
<item><hi>17: Page 13:</hi> Good and true.</item>
<item><hi>18: Page 14:</hi> If this means recent paper of Yorke and MacFie I thoroughly<lb/>
agree with you.</item>
<item><hi>19: Page 14:</hi> Good and true.</item>
<item><hi>20: Page 15:</hi> Very true. Uining Aitken's System of Medicine as text book I<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01219004"/>
I<lb/>
3<lb/>
used these pills and some similar ones during my first four years of prac-<lb/>
tice in Cairo, Illinois and Memphis, Tenn.</item>
<item><hi>21: Page 15</hi>: True.</item>
<item><p><hi>22: Pages 15 &amp; 16</hi>: Bass would never give his protocols: implied the I.H.B.<lb/>
asked him not to do so as it implied human experimentation.</p>
<p>I advocated the use of his standard treatment, and in this Kraus<lb/>
agreed with me, not as being the best, but as being infinitely better--es-<lb/>
pecially in its length--than anything that was done by the average practi-<lb/>
tioner in the malarious districts or that could be obtained from them, and<lb/>
the Committee on Medical Research was asked to continue its work.</p></item>
<item><hi>23: Page 16:</hi> Correct, but I think not the only indication for hypodermic<lb/>
medication.</item>
<item><hi>24: Page 16</hi>: Why ever give it subcutaneously? Isn't it apt to make necro-<lb/>
biosis in the subcutaneous tissue? This is less apt to occur in the muscle from<lb/>
which <unclear>too absorption</unclear> is in general <unclear>more rapid.</unclear></item>
<item><hi>25: Page 17:</hi> In the spring and early summer of 1905 we found that the ab-<lb/>
solutely neutral solutions put up by Ames at Ancon quite frequently caused<lb/>
necrobiosis in the tissue, even the muscle, while the slightly acid am-<lb/>
pules used at San Tomas practically never did so. When the solutions were<lb/>
made so as slightly to redden litmus Ames' <add>solutions</add> ceased to give us much trouble.<lb/>
I ascribed this to the alkalinity of the tissues precipitating the alka-<lb/>
loid in the absolutely neutral solution and not doing so in the faintly<lb/>
acid. Excess of acid also caused necrobiosis. This happened, I think,<lb/>
before you came to the Isthmus.</item>
<item><hi>26: Page 17:</hi> Good.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Note:</p>
<p>I think I may be said to have introduced hypodermic quinine into<lb/>
the Mississippi Valley. The bisulphate had been used in Italy, giving much<lb/>
local trouble and an occasional case of tetanus. Gubler introduced the solu-<lb/>
tion of the hydrobromate of quinine <hi>(&ldquo;Th&eacute;rapeutique General&rdquo;)</hi>. Marion Sims<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01219005"/>
Sims<lb/>
4.<lb/>
brought it over from Paris to the Womans' Hospital in New York, using it,<lb/>
following Binz and the Germans, as an anticeptic in septic operative cases,<lb/>
naturally, with no result.</p>
<p>It was brought to Baltimore about 1868 or /69 by William T. Howard,<lb/>
who had worked as an assistant with Sims. He had practiced in eastern N. C.<lb/>
and used it for fulminant cases of malaria. I used it extensively, in doses<lb/>
of from 5 to 15 grains during my time as interne and &ldquo;assistant <del>"</del> house&rdquo; in the<lb/>
hospital of University of Maryland (/77 to /79). When I went to Cairo, Ills.,<lb/>
in the fall of /79, I carried a supply with me and, finding it unknown in<lb/>
that section, I got the formula from Andrew Silver Thompson in Balti-<lb/>
more and had it put up by Parke Davis of Chicago and used it freely. Go-<lb/>
ing to New Orleans, in the spring of /83, I found this preparation un-<lb/>
known there. A few men (Shepherd: Loeber and some others in Charity Hos-<lb/>
pital) were occasionally using the bisulphate and as there had been more<lb/>
than one case of tetanus following such use the preceeding fall, it was<lb/>
considered a last resort. Before I left the solution of hydrobromate was<lb/>
not regarded as specially dangerous. I had taken it myself on two occa-<lb/>
sions--once 15 and once 45 grains (5 grains = 20 minim solution)--deep in<lb/>
the muscles (pectoral and deltoid. At the second time I was vomiting pro-<lb/>
fusely, with tempearature 107 8/10, and gave it to myself. I took 25 grains<lb/>
and in the course of 3 hours another 15 and 3 hours later 5. Painful, but<lb/>
no abcess or necrobiosis. Have seen, however, a necrobiosis with shrunken<lb/>
scar without abcess formation over it.</p>
<p>Other preparations--the double salt of quinine and urea and the di-<lb/>
hydrochloride--have taken the place of the one Gubler introduced and hence,<lb/>
I presume, are better. I have given, however, possibly 500 doses of it be-<lb/>
fore these others were introduced. It hurt, but to me and many others was<lb/>
less distressing than the <hi>malaise</hi> produced by quinine by the mouth, of which<lb/>
it produced very little. Spite of knowing that it is absorbed less read-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01219006"/>
read-<lb/>
5<lb/>
ily than by the mouth, I am sure, from clinical observation, that some-<lb/>
times it will act to cure an <hi>attack</hi> (I don't say infection) when <del>the</del> large<lb/>
doses, even of solution, by the mouth have failed. Possibly this may be<lb/>
due to the fixation of quinine by the liver and other tissues as demonstra-<lb/>
ted by Ramsbottom: Nierstien <hi>et al.</hi>, which, naturally, eliminate from the<lb/>
blood current (all save the <unclear>po<add>r</add>tal</unclear> <add>blood)</add>) part of the quinine taken by the mouth,<lb/>
but would not affect <add>so directly</add> that absorbed from the tissues or taken intravenously.<lb/>
Independently of explanation, clinically I am sure that the fact remains.<lb/>
Nevertheless, I think that the mouth is the way of election to administer<lb/>
quinine unless (1) vomiting forbids: (2) time presses, in which case the<lb/>
vein is the preferential route and (3) the rare cases in which sufficient<lb/>
results have not been obtained by this route.</p>
<p>I say this, though I suppose, from my history both as giver and<lb/>
taker of quinine, I should be strongly prejudiced in favor of quinine by<lb/>
the needle.</p>
<p>End of note.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><hi>27: Page 18:</hi> Good and true, all four of them. I have had many a steam-<lb/>
boat man whom I could not cure <add>while working</add> in the Arkansas trade, <del>get better</del> after--<lb/>
say--a year on the upper Missouri and 4 months of Aitkin's pills looking<lb/>
like a prize fighter!</item>
<item><p><hi>28: Pages 19-20:</hi> I have found an enema of water (not saline) very gener-<lb/>
ally efficient in blackwater fever--keeping the hypodermaclysis as a last<lb/>
resort. These cases were common in Memphis--from the &ldquo;Mississippi Bottoms&rdquo; in<lb/>
Arkansas and Mississippi just south of it, and in Norfolk <add>(coming</add> from Suffolk) in<lb/>
Virginia.</p>
<p>I have never believed that I had a death from hemorrhage from these<lb/>
cases, though I had one with between 8% and <add>9%</add>% haemoglobin (a German in-<lb/>
strument used--I forget its name). This was in /83, Memphis, Tenn <add>&amp; after recovery</add>. I<lb/>
thought my deaths were from kidney stoppage.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f01219007"/>
<p>stoppage.</p>
<p>6.</p>
<p>I too, in Memphis and Cairo, gave small (from 2 1/2 to 5 grains)<lb/>
doses of quinine hypodermatically, watching the urine as the cases im-<lb/>
proved. None was given during the attack. I have probably treated 50 to<lb/>
60 cases, but the best results I ever saw were, as I said before, in those<lb/>
at Ancon after the large doses of quinine and <add>the</add> tincture of iron were stopped.</p></item>
<item><hi>29: Page 21</hi>: Fully 100 different drugs<del>:</del> and methods of treatment have been<lb/>
used. Some recover under all, usually the first ones so treated, and some<lb/>
die. The best results that I have ever seen were, as I have said twice be-<lb/>
fore, with the later ones at Ancon.</item>
<item><hi>30: Page 21:</hi> I think this true if you mean that quinine given before the<lb/>
infection of malaria does not prevent that infection. If, however, you<lb/>
mean does not prevent malarial fever in men--i.e. the effect of the toxine<lb/>
of the parasites, I cannot agree. The paper of Yorke and MacFie, I think<lb/>
shows the latter. A few <add>less than a</add> dozen, experiments detailed by Ross in his &ldquo;Preven-<lb/>
tion of Malaria.&rdquo; the experiments on a large scale of Celli in Italy: the<lb/>
Sargeants in Algiers: Chagas and others in Brazil and, finally, Malco<add>l</add>m<lb/>
Watson's change of <del>belief</del><add>teaching</add>, to my mind give an amount of evidence suffi-<lb/>
cient to establish the latter. True enough, the quinine that is efficient<lb/>
in preventing malarial fever (<add>not malarial</add><del>in</del> <hi>infection</hi>) is that taken after the infect-<lb/>
ion is begun--i. e. the parasites are in the corpuscles <add>but before the recognizables <unclear>of plains</unclear> show in the man infected</add>. I could instance<lb/>
a few--10 <add>or 12</add>--observations of my own which are evidence--not enough for proof--<lb/>
of the same thing, the quinine being continued for some ten days after last<lb/>
exposure. hence curing <hi>early</hi> infections <unclear>before</unclear> appearance of notable symptoms</item>
<item><hi>31: Page 22:</hi> You practically say the above here.</item>
<item><hi>32: Page 22</hi>: True. Beautifully brought out in Ramsbottom's etc. observations.</item>
<item><hi>33: Page 23</hi>: See No. 25 <hi>supra.</hi> &ldquo;Well diluted and slowly&rdquo; is right.</item>
<item><hi>34: Page 23:</hi> Theoretically quite certainly true. Spite of taste in my own<lb/>
experience and observation quinine in solution is less often vomited than in<lb/>
solid form.</item>
<pb n="7" id="f01219008"/>
<item>form.</item>
<item>7.</item>
<item><hi>35: Page 23: Very</hi> true! Doubt Howell's claim.</item>
<item><hi>36: Page 24:</hi> From oviposition to imago in the U. S. in summer time is<lb/>
rarely under 14 to 16 days: have <unclear>hatched out</unclear> over 25 to 50 batches</item>
<item><hi>37: Page 24:</hi> Female Anopheles cannot bite men for about 24 hours after<lb/>
developement--chitin of probosis too soft to penetrate skin. About 11 days<lb/>
(<add><unclear>longer-</unclear> may be much <unclear>longer-</unclear></add> in cold weather) thereafter, before sporozooits reach salivary glands. &amp; insect is<lb/>
infective. Darling gives about sometime for Isthmus.</item>
<item><hi>38: Page 25</hi>: Generally true. A. punctipennis, however, quite frequently<lb/>
bite in the day time <add>as do crucians</add> and some of cellia did so on the Isthmus.</item>
<item><hi>39: Page 25:</hi> I said this, yet I doubt if it be true. Roubaud, in France,<lb/>
has shown that A. Maculipennis kept in a house with a calf and plenty of<lb/>
water quickly die. Barber has done the same in the U. S. for A. quadrima-<lb/>
culatus with a pig <add>in place of calf</add>. It may be then that their &ldquo;evening flight&rdquo; is neces-<lb/>
sary for survival, though this is not consonant with their living so long<lb/>
in cages.</item>
<item><p><hi>40: Page 25:</hi> I think you should say &ldquo;doors <hi>must</hi> be so constructed as to<lb/>
open outwards.&rdquo; They &ldquo;should&rdquo; be on the windward side of the house. I<lb/>
doubt if French windows be a good type as I have never seen many that shut<lb/>
so tight as to prevent mosquitoes.</p>
<p>Take out the screens and clean the windows--say twice a year--in<lb/>
the day time.</p>
<p>Frequently difficult to put shutters inside screening.</p></item>
<item><hi>41: Page 25</hi>: Right.</item>
<item><hi>42: Page 26:</hi> Number 16 wire, ordinary guage, which I think is English,<lb/>
will keep out all Anopheles. #18, same guage, necessary for Stegomyia. The<lb/>
closer the guage the less ventilation and the #18 mesh screen cuts it down<lb/>
decidedly.</item>
<item><hi>43: Page 26:</hi> Hope this is so: <add>rather</add> expect it is, but I don't know enough about<lb/>
it yet. It is bound to do some good.</item>
<item><hi>44: Page 27:</hi> The daily killing of mosquitoes found by day in barracks has<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01219009"/>
has<lb/>
8<lb/>
been so very successful in the prevention of malaria that one cannot but<lb/>
think that nearly all such &ldquo;house mosquitoes&rdquo; (A. quad. and the cellia on the<lb/>
Isthmus) stay for at least the first day after feeding in the houses in which<lb/>
they fed.</item>
<item><hi>45: Page 27:</hi> We have not found Anopheles breeding so as to be of sanitary<lb/>
importance in any artificial container or tree hole. This is reported, how-<lb/>
<unclear>Kligler &amp; (I thank) Ames his</unclear><lb/>
ever, of the <del><unclear>pharodenzis</unclear></del><add>bifurcatus</add> in the underground cisterns in Palestine and,<lb/>
during the winter of 1922 and /23, in an unamed Anopheles in water barrels<lb/>
<unclear>in houses</unclear> in southeastern Russia. Such collections of water, however, do<lb/>
breed Stegomyia and had best be eliminated. Neither on the Isthmus nor in<lb/>
the U. S., however, are they of sanitary importance for malaria.</item>
<item><hi>46: Page 28:</hi> If by &ldquo;stagnant&rdquo; you mean water that has stood until it has be-<lb/>
come offensive and covered by a metallic-like scum I would say that <add>I have never <unclear>sen</unclear></add> Anophe-<lb/>
les <del><hi>never</hi></del> breed in such water. The larvae die very soon after being in-<lb/>
troduced into it. Such water lacks oxygen and Darling could only raise<lb/>
Anopheles larvae in it by bubbling water through it. The stagnant pool is<lb/>
safe until it rains and breaks up the film.</item>
<item><hi>47: Page 28:</hi> Good. A small amount of castor oil enormously increases the<lb/>
spread as does heating even the crude oil, which is now being done for the<lb/>
spraying of portions of ponds by air pressure from a motor boat.</item>
<item><hi>48: Page 28:</hi> Paris green is extremely good. Dust, however, is hard to<lb/>
get in the wet season in the tropics. must store supply in dry season</item>
<item><hi>49: Page 28:</hi> True. Good fish <add>-as Gambusia-</add> are efficient even in the presence of con-<lb/>
siderable vegetation--not, however, where there is much of the alga <hi>spi-<lb/>
rogyra.</hi> which <unclear>mats things-</unclear> vegetation or <unclear>floatage-up</unclear> so as to be <unclear>impraticable.</unclear></item>
<item><hi>50: Page 29:</hi> Neither cisterns nor wells nor roof gutters have been found,<lb/>
in the U. S., producing Anopheles so as to be of sanitary importance. Nor,<lb/>
I think, was this found on the Isthmus. They do breed Stegomyia, however.<lb/>
Reinforced concrete is the best material for lining ditches. I doubt if it<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01219010"/>
it<lb/>
9<lb/>
be generally suitable for roof gutters.</item>
<item><hi>51: Page 29:</hi> I doubt if Anopheles <unclear>will breed</unclear> in latrines. In the Americas<lb/>
they will not breed in sewage until it is very much diluted and not offen-<lb/>
sive.</item>
<item><hi>52: Page 29:</hi> Very true.</item>
<item><hi>53: Page 30:</hi> True: especially is we say &ldquo;control&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;eradication.&rdquo;<lb/>
This last is as yet not in sight.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
