<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01212007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to Henry Rose Carter, September 9, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Griffitts, T.H.D.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01212007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-09-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hazlehurst, G.H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Gage, E. H.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, Samuel T.</name>
<name type="place">Houston County (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-09-09">September 9, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01212007</idno>
<title>Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to Henry Rose Carter, September 9, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Griffitts discusses malaria, mosquitoes and ponds.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-09-09">
<head>Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to Henry Rose Carter, September 9, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01212007"/>
<opener>
Mal.<lb/>
Griffitts<lb/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
<dateline>
519 Dexter Avenue,<lb/>
Montgomery, Ala.,<lb/>
<date value="1924-09-09">September 9, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Some time ago I wrote you what, I know, you must<lb/>
have taken as a rather doleful letter, and I promised<lb/>
then to write you of business later.</p>
<p>Two ponds I followed as closely last year and this<lb/>
as could well be done in an unassisted way. The mistake,-<lb/>
and I am sure you fully recognized it at the time- was in-<lb/>
not putting Gage with me. I have heard that his last<lb/>
season's work was of little avail, and Hildebrand tells<lb/>
me that he is not accomplishing much at Augusta this year.<lb/>
But that is &ldquo;water that's over the dam.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I wrote you last year of the impounded lake of 250 <del><unclear>acs</unclear></del><lb/>
acres near Newton, Houston County (Houston borders on Flor-<lb/>
ida) on the Little Choctawhatchee River. It was a bad, un-<lb/>
clean pond made in January 1921. That fall sho<add>w</add>ed a decided<lb/>
increase in malaria; 1922 much more (history index in 1921,<lb/>
59% of 168 persons;-1922, 79% of 203 persons). Blood index<lb/>
(thick) in April, 1923, showed 32.18%. This before flight<lb/>
of quads. Free &ldquo;standard treatment&rdquo; was given under con-<lb/>
tinuous supervision and very well taken, with still a <del>po</del>i-<lb/>
positive blood of 26.14 within ten days from <add>and after</add> the last<lb/>
dose was given. However, 92% of those treated failed to<lb/>
have any paroxysms after beginning the treatment. I have<lb/>
written a paper on this work and submitted to Dr. Fricks<lb/>
some weeks ago. I don't know what he is going to do with<lb/>
it. I would like for you to read it and criticise it, but<lb/>
my copy is lent out about the office somewhere just now.</p>
<p>On the pond we cut down production considerably (didn't<lb/>
have a house check the previous year, so can't say how much)<lb/>
by the use of Paris green. It wasn<del>o</del><add>'</add>t as effective as I ad<lb/>
hoped for, due largely to the imperfect way it was applied<lb/>
with $1.25 worth of brain per day. The pond is and was<lb/>
literally teeming with Gambusia. <del>While the</del></p>
<p>While the physical condition of the pond was still<lb/>
very bad at the beginning of the present season--the prev-<lb/>
alent pine trees shedding much of their bark this year,<lb/>
I decided it necessary to work out some other and better<lb/>
method of control. I have succeeded. Am having kerosene<lb/>
applied under pressure from tanks mounted on Evinrude <unclear>driven</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01212008"/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
2<lb/>
or man propelled small boat, as occasion demands. I took<lb/>
a 40 gal. ordinary hot water tank, provided an air valve<lb/>
like on an automobile tube. We put 25 gals. of oil in the<lb/>
tank and give it 120 lbs. pressure. With a rubber hose <unclear>of</unclear><lb/>
convenient length and a seven foot iron pipe extension,<lb/>
the man standing in the boat can raise the misty spray<lb/>
to sufficient height for a fair breeze to carry the oil<lb/>
for as much as 150 to 200 feet. He raises and lowers t<del><unclear>es</unclear></del>t<lb/>
conditions, or turns on the coarser stream. Lanes are cut<lb/>
through the brush to permit of weaving in and out. Pro-<lb/>
duction has been practically nil this season. There is-<lb/>
no wasteage of oil, its application is not laborious, but<lb/>
oil, of course, is more expensive than P.g. On this par-<lb/>
ticular pond we have an electrically driven pump rigged<lb/>
up with a pressuse tank at the power house, so all there<lb/>
is to do is to return for a new supply of oil<unclear>s</unclear> and air<lb/>
pressure for each 25 gals. It takes 125 gals. each appli-<lb/>
cation, and through the small hole of the Meyers spray<lb/>
nozzle, it puts out 1 gal. every 2 1/2 minutes.</p>
<p>As you<del>b</del>probably know, something had to be done all<lb/>
of a sudden at Muscle Shoals in July. We started five<lb/>
boat gangs with the same kind of outfits there, and have<lb/>
gotten rather good results. I made an inspection of that<lb/>
filling reservoir the last week in July and it was pro<del><unclear>dox</unclear></del>-<lb/>
quads. profusely <hi>as it filled</hi>. For instance, the day be-<lb/>
fore I was there, there was a rise of six feet, and at <unclear>pra</unclear><lb/>
tically every selective dip larvae could be dipped. If <del>fb</del><lb/>
flotage broke anchorage it soon engaged other nearby ob-<lb/>
struction<del>n</del> and larvae had little free swimming.</p>
<p>Another thing of practical interest and of money<lb/>
value in connection with Gambusia development ponds for<lb/>
new reservoirs. At a great expense the A.P. Co. located 75<lb/>
Gamb. ponds in the various parts of the basin at Mitchell<lb/>
Dam. Before the water had reached the maximum level, Gam-<lb/>
busia had distributed themselves as far as four miles<lb/>
from the development ponds. In my opinion this is a better<lb/>
method of distributing them than by scattering their ponds<lb/>
all about. So, when it came to putting in ponds in the<lb/>
Cherokee Bluff basin--three times the size of Mitchell-- I<lb/>
located only 25, and probably cut their expense $10,000.</p>
<p>And speaking of these &ldquo;hatcheries&rdquo;. Most of them have<lb/>
produced Anophelines practically all summer, punctipennis<lb/>
early, of course. It is naturally punctipennis country;<lb/>
very limited conditions for quads.-- but note the August<lb/>
results on the enclosed memo. as to quads. Quads. got in,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01212009"/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
3<lb/>
and got in thick and fast. I have seen enough to be con-<lb/>
vinced that the promiscuous location of even well-stocke-<lb/>
ponds for minnows may be a serious malaria hazard.</p>
<p>At Muscle Shoals no artificial ponds were located, yet two<lb/>
or three ponds located near old locks six and seven supplied<lb/>
the reservoir up to July 25 with enough Gambusia to make<lb/>
them appear more numerous than in Mitchell reservoir this,<lb/>
the second, season (It is apparent that they have decidedly<lb/>
diminished at Mitchell reservoir since last year) the pod<lb/>
has a good many bass, and the water carries a great deal<lb/>
of silt for a great deal of the time.</p>
<p>It is getting late and I must go home, but one more<lb/>
thing on new ponds: In spite of all the preliminary prep-<lb/>
aration on large ponds, there occurs enough flotage the<lb/>
first year to call for additional work, minnows or no min-<lb/>
nows. And the easiest and best method is by pressure tank<lb/>
oiling!</p>
<p>With best wishes,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Griffitts</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
