<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01211001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: What the Engineer Can and Should Do Toward Prevention of Malaria and Mosquito Nuisances, by Joseph A. LePrince, September 1, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01211001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-09-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">South (U.S.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-09-01">September 1, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01211001</idno>
<title>Report: What the Engineer Can and Should Do Toward Prevention of Malaria and Mosquito Nuisances, by Joseph A. LePrince, September 1, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>LePrince reports on the role of the engineer in regards to malaria prevention.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-09-01">
<head>Report: What the Engineer Can and Should Do Toward Prevention of Malaria and Mosquito Nuisances, by Joseph A. LePrince, September 1, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01211001"/>
<p>{This was original copy &amp; was}<lb/>
{modified later}</p>
<p>WHAT THE ENGINEER CAN AND SHOULD DO TOWARD<lb/>
PREVENTION OF MALARIA AND MOSQUITO NUISANCES.</p>
<p>________</p>
<p>J. A. LePrince, Chairman, Committee on Engineering,<lb/>
National Malaria Committee, September 1, 1924.</p>
<p>________</p>
<p>Prominent engineering journals recently commented on the Memoirs<lb/>
of Ronald Ross, the pioneer in malaria elimination, but omitted mentioning<lb/>
the fact that much of the future success to be achieved along this line as<lb/>
well as the methods to be followed must be devised or created by engineers.</p>
<p>Ross did not stress the point, although it is true, that due to<lb/>
engineering practice as now carried on, the engineer is frequently responsi-<lb/>
ble for the creation of mosquito pest nuisances as well as the spread of mal-<lb/>
aria, or as an American malaria field worker stated, &ldquo;How long will it be<lb/>
before our engineers stop building malaria in, instead of building it out&rdquo;?</p>
<p>Much man made malaria or &ldquo;engineer made Anopheles production&rdquo; is<lb/>
going on in other countries as well as in our own, and the time appears to<lb/>
be appropriate for our engineering societies to inquire why this is so and<lb/>
to determine what should be done about it.</p>
<p>Some of our engineers at Panama, during the canal construction<lb/>
period, considered the anti-yellow fever <unclear>abd</unclear> anti-malaria measures as more<lb/>
or less of a joke and referred to the field workers as &ldquo;mosquito chasers&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Eight years later the chief engineer of one of our largest<lb/>
American corporations working in a foreign country was selected and appoint-<lb/>
ed to direct measures against yellow fever that threatened his and other<lb/>
American business interests. He promptly ordered one thousand tents, em-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01211002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
ployed several hundred men to do work that had no relation to the problem<lb/>
involved, and wasted many thousand dollars but did not accomplish one cents<lb/>
worth of results toward yellow fever control or elimination.</p>
<p>During the recent epidemic of dengue fever that swept through our<lb/>
Southern States from the Atlantic Ocean to Texas, no reference was made by<lb/>
our public press, engineering publications, or engineering societies, to the<lb/>
fact that our street storm water catch basins, present by hundreds in many<lb/>
cities and towns, are sources of millions of the mosquitoes involved in mos-<lb/>
quito borne disease. Yet without question a well selected committee of our<lb/>
American sanitary engineering associations could devise an economical modi-<lb/>
fication for these catch basins in use so they would become self draining and<lb/>
no longer a potential or actual menace to the health of the communities where<lb/>
now in use.</p>
<p>An earnest effort was recently made by the Committee on Engineer-<lb/>
ing of the National Malaria Committee to correct these and other defects and<lb/>
to so arrange that engineering students of our technical schools could learn<lb/>
in a short time, by a single lecture if necessary, not to permit engineering<lb/>
construction operations to become a source of serious epidemic disease out-<lb/>
breaks.</p>
<p>Unquestionably, more far reaching results could be obtained if some<lb/>
of our prominent engineering associations could be interested in this matter,<lb/>
and determine what is being taught in our technical schools relative to that<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01211003"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
part of applied public health that will be of actual use to our future en-<lb/>
gineers and to determine what portion of such schools show the students<lb/>
where they can get the information and facts rapidly later, if they ever<lb/>
have occasion to need them.</p>
<p>Also these same associations through their professional journals<lb/>
could at least invite attention to the need of practicing and consulting<lb/>
engineers considering the public health problems involved or connected with<lb/>
many engineering operations, such as in irrigation, major drainage projects<lb/>
for agricultural drainage, impounding of water, extension of town suburbs,<lb/>
construction of highways and railroads, sewer outlets, borrow pit construc-<lb/>
tion, etc.</p>
<p>Apparently the essentials of this subjects or the relation of en-<lb/>
gineering construction to public health problems should in a brief way be<lb/>
presented to all students in our army engineering school so that any small<lb/>
but very necessary item of expenditure necessary for malaria control in con-<lb/>
nection with Government impounded water projects, or other large engineer-<lb/>
ing project, could and would be made and included in the appropriation or<lb/>
budget before the project is started. It would be too late to try to ap-<lb/>
ply a remedy after the country surrounding the project is rendered unfit to<lb/>
live in.</p>
<p>In order to make this paper brief and to the point, a partial<lb/>
list of what the engineer can do is given below and it is hoped that your<lb/>
association cooperating with other engineers will determine what should be<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01211004"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
done and then start devising means for accomplishment.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Devise a means of presenting this subject before the national and state<lb/>
engineering associations.</item>
<item>(b) Obtain the cooperation of these associations so that a practical plan<lb/>
can be adopted to prevent the constantly changing county highway commission-<lb/>
ers and county highway engineers allowing borrow pits and roadside ditches<lb/>
to be so constructed that they become intermittent or permanent sources of<lb/>
malaria bearing mosquitoes and sources of potential <unclear>focii</unclear> of malaria.</item>
<item>(c) In this connection in each state, both for the benefit of the roads as<lb/>
well as the proper drainage thereof, there should be a State Association of<lb/>
County Highway Commissioners and the County and State Highway Engineers<lb/>
should attend the annual meeting of that association.</item>
<item>(d) A strong effort should be made to interest the general managers and<lb/>
chief engineers of the railroads in the malaria belt of the United States,<lb/>
in the financial losses now caused to railroads by malaria, including -<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Inefficient labor employed,</item>
<item>Increased labor turnover,</item>
<item>Retarded development of territory served,</item>
<item>Decreased output of mills and manufacturing agencies,</item>
<item>Reduction of freight hauled.</item>
</list></item>
<item>(e) The state engineering associations should be invited to investigate the<lb/>
anti-malaria operations as being carried out by the state board of health of<lb/>
their state, and act as a body in endorsing or giving constructive criticism<lb/>
on what is now being done toward malaria elimination, rate of control progress,<lb/>
etc.</item>
<item>(f) Interest consulting and municipal engineers in the mosquito problem and<lb/>
let sufficient of them understand that a relatively mosquito free community<lb/>
will suffer from heavy mosquito infestation as soon as water of natural drain-<lb/>
age courses become <add>sufficiently</add> polluted with sewage water. That the production of pestif-<lb/>
erous mosquitoes in clear water as against strong sewage polluted water may<lb/>
be as 1 to 1000.</item>
<item>(g) The engineering profression must let the local Government officials and<lb/>
the public know that sluggish water courses in town suburbs are a public nui-<lb/>
sance, often the main source of our town mosquito pest problem, and frequently<lb/>
a menace to health. In the malaria belt of out country the normal (non-<lb/>
storm water) flow should travel through a properly devised concrete lined sec-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01211005"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
tion in the bottom of the water course or by pipe line to a point beyond<lb/>
mosquito flight range.</item>
<item><p>(h) Our underground culverts used in place of large pipe and carrying a<lb/>
small normal flow of water should not have flat bottoms. A depressed<lb/>
rounded central channel along the center line of the floor and gently<lb/>
sloping sides will prevent mosquito production.</p>
<p>Long culverts with flat grades to convey storm water under town suburbs are<lb/>
yet being built and are sources of our mosquito pest. They are frequent-<lb/>
ly so designed or constructed that it is not practical to prevent mosquito<lb/>
production in them.</p></item>
<item>(i) In view of the fact that state development will rapidly follow the<lb/>
proper development of hydro electric power, impounded water projects con-<lb/>
structed by our federal government should be so planned as to produce a<lb/>
practical minimum of malaria, and the methods of malaria control used there-<lb/>
on should be a standard for private enterprises to follow. In the past<lb/>
this plane of the public health problem has not been given consideration.</item>
<item>(j) Most of our practising engineers, engineering construction corpora-<lb/>
tions, and contractors, have not been taught what a serious malaria prob-<lb/>
lem is, and don't recognize them at sight. The engineer can build mal-<lb/>
aria into a community for all time to come, or build it out of a community.<lb/>
Which is he going to do and why?</item>
<item>(k) Such small items as the location of municipal swimming pool, recrea-<lb/>
tion park, or auto tourist camp, etc., where no consideration is given to<lb/>
the Anopheles problem near it, can seriously affect the annual malaria sick<lb/>
rate of the nearby town.</item>
<item>(l) Sir Ronald Ross states that it takes ten years for a nation to get<lb/>
a new idea. It was twelve years after the first successful anti-malaria<lb/>
campaign carried on by Americans in Cuba before we started any worthwhile<lb/>
similar work in our own country</item>
</list></p>
<p>Nevertheless, the writer does not accept the idea that it will<lb/>
be another ten years before the engineering profession of our country ap-<lb/>
preciate the commercial and financial value of malaria elimination.</p>
<p>Possibly greater progress has been made in our country than in<lb/>
any other in devising more economic and more rapid control measures, but<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01211006"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
the rate of progress can be increased tenfold if our American engineers<lb/>
become seriously interested in this subject which affects the normal<lb/>
development of thirteen states and the comfort of the public in many<lb/>
others.</p>
<p>_________________</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
