<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01212001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, September 5, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01212001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-09-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Mayne, Bruce</name>
<name type="person">Maxcy, K. F.</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Gage, E. H.</name>
<name type="person">Fuchs, A. W.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, Samuel F.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, J. C.</name>
<name type="person">Old, H. N.</name>
<name type="person">Shaw, F. R.</name>
<name type="person">Fuchs, A. W.</name>
<name type="person">Coogle, C. P.</name>
<name type="person">Foster, J. G.</name>
<name type="person">Fisher, L. M.</name>
<name type="person">Williams, L. L.</name>
<name type="place">Crowley (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Aiden County (S. C.)</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Chatham County (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Georgia</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Missouri</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-09-05">September 5, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01212001</idno>
<title>Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, September 5, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fricks reports on malaria work in the southern United States.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-09-05">
<head>Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, September 5, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01212001"/>
<opener>
File<lb/>
<hi>Malaria</hi> Reports<lb/>
Reports<lb/>
<dateline>
Headquarters: Field Investigations of Malaria,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Room 17, Court House,<lb/>
Memphis, Tenn.<lb/>
----<lb/>
<date value="1924-09-05">September 5, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
August 1924.<lb/>
The Surgeon-General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Division of Scientific Research,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to forward herewith monthly progress report<lb/>
of malaria investigations conducted during the month of August, 1924,<lb/>
under the direction of this office.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Crowley, Louisiana:</hi> Personne; - Special Expert M. A.<lb/>
Barber, Assoc. San. Eng. W. H. W. Komp and Technical Asst. Theo. B.<lb/>
Hayne.</p>
<p>Activities at the Crowley Laboratory consisted of: (1) Continuation of<lb/>
experiments on conditions affecting growth of Anopheline larvae; (2)<lb/>
Continuation of larvicide experiments; (3) Continuation of experiments<lb/>
with mosquito repellents; (4) Continuation of plantation surveys for<lb/>
Anopheline intensity and malaria prevalence; (Blood specimens examined<lb/>
for malaria parasites sent in by physicians twelve, all negative; col-<lb/>
lected on plantations 240, eleven positive P. vivax, seven positive P.<lb/>
falc.; (6) Study of incidence of Anopheles - collected imago stage<lb/>
3,961, A. quadrimaculatus 47.1%, A. crucians 52.9%; bred out 64, A.<lb/>
quadrimaculatus 31%, A. crucians 69%; all larvae collected in water<lb/>
which has now become salt proved to be A. crucians.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory: Personnel</hi> - A. A. Surgeon Wn. A. Krauss and Micros-<lb/>
copist Retha Kitchens.</p>
<p>501 blood smears were examined for malaria parasites, of which 450<lb/>
were sent in locally for diagnosis, of these 41 were positive P. vivax<lb/>
and 58 positive P. falc; 28 blood specimens from Aiken County, South<lb/>
Carolina, showed one positive P. vivax, one positive P. falc.; 23 blood<lb/>
specimens sent in by Tennessee State Board of Health showed three<lb/>
positive P. vivax, four positive P. falc.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Savannah, Georgia</hi>: Personnel - Tech. Asst. Bruce Mayne.</p>
<p>Activities at this laboratory consisted of: (1) Observations of Anopheles<lb/>
incidence, a definite predominance of A. quadrimaculatus now noted along<lb/>
the Savannah River, in other sections of Chatham County quads appeared<lb/>
where not previously observed; (2) Meagre numbers of larvae and pupae obs-<lb/>
erved, continued activity of Gambusia constantly noted; Sixty blood<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01212002"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
September 5, 1924.<lb/>
specimens sent in for diagnosis examined during the first two<lb/>
weeks in August, all negative; (4) Malaria mosquito survey made<lb/>
of Okefenoke Swamp during the last two weeks in August at request<lb/>
of the State Health Officer, special report.</p>
<p><hi>Epidemiological Studies of Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Asst. Surg. K. F.<lb/>
Maxcy.</p>
<p>Dr. Maxcy's activities consisted of: (1) Study of typhus-like dis-<lb/>
ease; (2) Tabulation of malaria school survey data collected last<lb/>
winter; (3) Investigation of malaria focus at <unclear>Teasley's</unclear> Mill, Mont-<lb/>
gomery County, where three cases of malaria hematuria with two<lb/>
deaths occurred within past three weeks; (4) Instructing Dr. Makin,<lb/>
Epidemiologist of the Texas State Board of Health.</p>
<p><hi>Impounded Waters in Relation to Malaria</hi>: Personnel - Epidemiologist<lb/>
T. H. D. Griffitts, Asst. San. Eng. E. H. Gage and Microscopist Ethel<lb/>
Barrier.</p>
<p>Dr. Griffitts (Alabama), activities consisted of: (1) Inspection of<lb/>
River Falls Power Company Pond, Covington County, three adult mos-<lb/>
quitoes found in two dwellings and one barn inspected; (2) Inspec-<lb/>
tion of Forest Lake, Tuscaloosa County, recommendations for correc-<lb/>
tion made to State Health Officer; (3) Inspection of Golden Bridge<lb/>
Pond, Houston &amp; Dale Counties, mosquito breeding being controlled<lb/>
by oil applied under pressure; (4) Inspection of Dothan City Power<lb/>
Project Geneva, Houston and Dale Counties, clearing of basin begun<lb/>
several months ago, quinine being sold at wholesale prices during<lb/>
preliminary construction around this project; (5) Inspection of<lb/>
Mitchell Reservoir, Coosa River, Anopheles breeding in very limited<lb/>
numbers.</p>
<p>Mr. Gage (South Carolina) activities consisted of: (1) Obsercations<lb/>
continued of Anopheles prevalence and distribution in Horse Creek<lb/>
Valley, Aiken County, marked increase in numbers of A. quadrimacu-<lb/>
latus observed, but A. crucians still the predominating type; (2)<lb/>
Malaria History sensus continued in this locality, blood speci-<lb/>
mens collected for examination.</p>
<p>At the request of the State Health Officer of Alabama Microscopist<lb/>
Ethel Barrier was ordered to Florence, Alabama, to investigate mal-<lb/>
aria prevalence among the population within mosquito flight range<lb/>
of the Muscle Shoals impounded water project. Miss Barrier visited<lb/>
290 families, consisting of 1682 individuals from whom she collected<lb/>
1225 blood smears, to be examined for malaria parasites.</p>
<p><hi>Major Drainage in Relation to Malaria</hi>: Personnel - Assoc. San. Eng.<lb/>
A. W. Fuchs.</p>
<p>Mr. Fuchs' activities consisted of: (1) Observations of Anopheles<lb/>
production and physical conditions in drainage ditches of Critten-<lb/>
den County, Arkansas, New Madrid and Dunklin Counties, Missouri<lb/>
and Bolivar County, Mississippi; (2) Inspection of ditch maintenance<lb/>
in Mississippi County, Arkansas and Bolivar County, Mississippi.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01212003"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>September 5, 1924.</p>
<p>Cooperative Fish Studies: Samuel F. Hildebrand of the Bureau of<lb/>
Fisheries continued his cooperative fish control investigations<lb/>
around Augusta, Georgia, conditions influencing Gambusia density<lb/>
are being studied, a series of sixteen experiments is now under<lb/>
way. At the request of the Medical Officer in Charge and the<lb/>
State Health Officer of Alabama, Mr. Hildebrand and Mr. LePrince<lb/>
made an inspection of the fish hatcheries constructed in con-<lb/>
nection with the Cherokee Bluffs impounded water project, re-<lb/>
commendations were made for the construction of additional hat-<lb/>
cheries and proper maintenance of the old ones.</p>
<p><hi>Rural Malaria Investigations</hi>: Personnel - Asst. San. Eng. J.C. Carter,<lb/>
A.A. Surg. C. P. Coogle, Assoc. San. Eng. L. M. Fisher, Assoc. San.<lb/>
Eng. A. W. Fuchs, Asst. San. Eng. J. G. Foster, Asst. San. Eng. H.N.<lb/>
Old, Asst. San. Eng. F. R. Shaw and Surgeon L. L. Williams, Jr.</p>
<p>Mr. Carter (Alabama), activities consisted of: (1) Investigation<lb/>
of severe malaria outbreak at Clayhatchie, Geneva County, 27% of<lb/>
population affected, quinine placed in rural stores to be sold at<lb/>
cost - this method of control to be checked against a community<lb/>
five miles distant where quinine was distributed free; (2) Instruction<lb/>
in mosquito control given to cotton mill operators in Bullock County;<lb/>
(3) Investigation of malaria outbreak at Teasley's Mill, Montgomery<lb/>
County, house-to-house survey of 17 families made, of 80 people ques-<lb/>
tioned 40 report having had malaria this season.</p>
<p>Mr. Old (Georgia) activities consisted of: continued observations of<lb/>
mosquito production in Chatham County, 34 out houses searched for<lb/>
adult mosquitoes, 110 A. crucians and 174 A. quadrimaculatus collect-<lb/>
ed; ten dwellimgs searched inside, no crucians and one quad found,<lb/>
relative increase of A. quadrimaculatus continues.</p>
<p>Mr. Shaw (Louisiana), activities consisted of: (1) Encouraging exten-<lb/>
sive drainage around Patterson, St. Mary's Parish, Louisiana, and en-<lb/>
couraging control of mosquito breeding in 585 cisterns in Patterson;<lb/>
(2) Study of relative efficiency of Gambusia, cat fish and turtles<lb/>
in control of mosquito production in cisterns; (3) Studies of ditching<lb/>
by dynamite in St. Mary's Parish; (4) Screening studies continued<lb/>
in Tangipahoa Parish.</p>
<p>Mr. Fuchs (Missouri), activities consisted of: malaria and mosquito<lb/>
surveys in Dunklin and New Madrid Counties; effort being made to de-<lb/>
termine amount of Anopheles production and locate malaria foci in<lb/>
these counties.</p>
<p>Dr. Coogle and Mr. Foster (Mississippi) continued study of housing<lb/>
conditions in relation to malaria in Leflore County, Mississippi;<lb/>
Twenty tenant houses have been completely screened and exact cost<lb/>
data od screening is being prepared; 26 houses have been treated<lb/>
with creosote oil, 135 inspections of houses were made, 119 blood<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01212004"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-4<lb/>
September 5, 1924.<lb/>
specimens were collected and examined, of which 24 were found posi-<lb/>
tive, nine P. vivax and 15 P. falc.; spleen examinations of the<lb/>
sa,e group gave 17 enlarged spleens.</p>
<p>Mr. Fisher (South Carolina), activities consisted of: (1) Continued<lb/>
observation of fish control of mosquito production in pond near<lb/>
Columbia; (2) Screening observations continued in 25 houses at<lb/>
Sellars, Marion County, screened last spring; no cases of malaria<lb/>
have occurred this summer although last year fifteen cases occurred<lb/>
in these same houses; (3) Study of value of school malaria census<lb/>
card continued in Marion, Beaufort and Charleston Counties.</p>
<p>(Dr. Williams (Virginia), activities consisted of; Continuation of<lb/>
<unclear>study</unclear> of rural malaria control methods in Henrico, James City, Isle<lb/>
of Wight, Nansemond,. Accomac and Northampton Counties; during August<lb/>
6600 feet of drainage was completed, mosquito breeding in three<lb/>
ponds was controlled; 40 houses were screened and mosquito produc-<lb/>
tion was controlled by oiling in seven localities; mosquito control<lb/>
by drainage continued in Nansemond County, in each instance results<lb/>
being checked by history index; screening program continued in Isle<lb/>
of Wight County, all malaria cases reported are visited and surveys<lb/>
made to determine probable source of infection; both screening and<lb/>
drainage programs continued in <unclear>Accomac</unclear> County; house-to-house survey<lb/>
made around impounded power reservoir in Halifax County; all seven<lb/>
Counties have completed spot maps of malaria cases; types of mosqui-<lb/>
to breeding in seven counties show very few changes, although A.<lb/>
quadrimaculatus are appearing in localities which have been free<lb/>
heretofore.</p>
<p><hi>Conferences and Inspections</hi>: Inspection of Muscle Shoals Project by<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge and Senior Sanitary Engineer J.A. LePrince;<lb/>
Inspection of housing studies in Leflore County Mississippi by Medical<lb/>
Officer in Charge, Dr. M. A. Barber and Senior Sanitary Engineer J.A.<lb/>
LePrince.</p>
<p><hi>Expenditures:</hi> During the month of August approximately $4,885.15<lb/>
was <unclear>exponded</unclear> from the Malaria Allotment in connection with field<lb/>
investigations of malaria.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>L. D. Fricks, Surgeon,<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
