<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01217025">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Wade Hampton Frost to Henry Rose Carter, December 22, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Frost, Wade Hampton</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01217025</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-12-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-12-22">December 22, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01217025</idno>
<title>Letter from Wade Hampton Frost to Henry Rose Carter, December 22, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Frost comments on Carter's yellow fever manuscript.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-12-22">
<head>Letter from Wade Hampton Frost to Henry Rose Carter, December 22, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01217025"/>
<opener>
Book<lb/>
Frost.<lb/>
<dateline>
THE JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY<lb/>
SCHOOL OF HYGIENE AND PUBLIC HEALTH<lb/>
310-312 WEST MONUMENT STREET<lb/>
BALTIMORE, MD. <date value="1924-12-22">December 22, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
DEPARTMENT OF EPIDEMIOLOGY AND<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH ADMINISTRATION<lb/>
Dr. H. R. Carter,<lb/>
2122 California Street,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am at last returning your manuscripts with a<lb/>
memorandum of notes which are much too lengthy for their<lb/>
insignificant import.</p>
<p>In reviewing your manuscript I have taken it<lb/>
for granted that it has not yet been finally edited for<lb/>
publication and have accordingly made no note of such<lb/>
minor matters as typographical errors, etc. which will<lb/>
readily be checked up in the final editing.</p>
<p>As regards the epidemiological argument I felt<lb/>
sure before seeing the manuscript, as I still feel, that<lb/>
your reasoning would be straighter and your conclusions more<lb/>
precise and conservative than mine, so that while I have<lb/>
tried to examine the argument critically it has been with<lb/>
no thought that I could find any fault with your conclu-<lb/>
sions or could make any suggestions for modifying them.<lb/>
It has seemed to me that any service which I might be able<lb/>
to render would be solely in letting you know how readily<lb/>
your evidence would be grasped and your argument followed<lb/>
by one who, like myself, starts in with only a limited know-<lb/>
ledge of the facts. Therefore, in the first part of my<lb/>
memorandum I have made a few notes and suggestions which<lb/>
have nothing to do with the validity of your argument but<lb/>
relate only to making it a little easier to follow. However,<lb/>
I do not consider these suggestions of any importance and<lb/>
if they would involve any considerable amount of work on<lb/>
your part which would delay completion of the history,<lb/>
I think it would be much better to disregard them entirely.<lb/>
The rest of my notes, referring to the argument itself, are<lb/>
merely to let you know how it impresses me, that is, to<lb/>
show you how nearly I may have grasped or failed to grasp<lb/>
the significance of your facts. If these notes have any<lb/>
value at all to you it will be chiefly to show you how<lb/>
far a reasonably intelligent person previously unfamiliar<lb/>
with the facts may be expected to assimilate them after<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01217026"/>
Dr. Carter<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
12-22-24<lb/>
a fairly careful reading.</p>
<p>My notes, having been written at odd times and<lb/>
somewhat hurriedly, are not in precise language, so that<lb/>
I am expecting you to understand what I mean rather than<lb/>
precisely what I say in passages which are ambiguous or<lb/>
incomplete. If you find from my notes that I have been<lb/>
able to follow your arguments with fair directness I think<lb/>
you may be sure that the average reader who is sincerely<lb/>
interested and open-minded will also follow them. If I<lb/>
have misinterpreted them or overlooked the salient points<lb/>
I judge this will mean nothing except that you will have<lb/>
to depend for full understanding upon those who will read<lb/>
it more keenly than I have been able to do.</p>
<p>It has been many a day since I have <del>regarded</del><add>enjoyed</add> any<lb/>
reading so much. I do not know of anything with which<lb/>
I can compare your manuscript except Snow's Monograph on<lb/>
Cholera. Your work is equal<del>ly</del> <add>to</add> his in its reasoning and<lb/>
greatly exceeds it in material. I shall be interested to<lb/>
know what the African history shows, but as I have said<lb/>
in my notes, I do not see how the facts from that side or<lb/>
any other facts which may subsequently come to light can<lb/>
have any other effect than to confirm conclusions which<lb/>
already seem inevitable.</p>
<p>I am still hoping to be able to get over to Wash-<lb/>
ington before the New Year and to have a chance to see you.<lb/>
It is, however, a little difficult, because I have less<lb/>
business in Washington this year than in previous years;<lb/>
and if one is fully occupied every day it is hard to find<lb/>
opportunities for even short trips except under necessity.</p>
<p>Wishing you and Miss Laura a very happy Christmas<lb/>
and <add>a</add> <del>the</del> New Year which will see your history completed<lb/>
and ready for publication,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>W. H. Frost</signed>.
WHF:G<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
