<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01213008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, October 6, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01213008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-10-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Barber, M. A.</name>
<name type="person">Komp, W. H. W.</name>
<name type="person">Hayne, Theodore B.</name>
<name type="person">Krauss, William A.</name>
<name type="person">Mayne, Bruce</name>
<name type="person">Maxcy, K. F.</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Gage, E. H.</name>
<name type="person">Barrier, Ethel</name>
<name type="person">Fuchs, A. W.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, Samuel F.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, J. C.</name>
<name type="person">Coogel, C. P.</name>
<name type="person">Fisher, L. M.</name>
<name type="person">Foster, J. G.</name>
<name type="person">Old, H. N.</name>
<name type="person">Shaw, F. R.</name>
<name type="person">Williams, L. L.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">Crowley (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Lake City (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Tennesee</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Georgia</name>
<name type="place">Aiken County (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">South Carolina</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">Augusta (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-10-06">October 6, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01213008</idno>
<title>Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, October 6, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fricks reports on the malaria campaign in the southern United States.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1924-10-06">
<head>Report: Monthly Progress Report from Lunsford D. Fricks to the Surgeon General, U.S. Public Health Service, October 6, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01213008"/>
<opener>
C-O-P-Y<lb/>
FB<lb/>
<dateline>
Headquarters:<lb/>
Field Investigations of Malaria,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Memphis, Tennessee.<lb/>
<date value="1924-10-06">October 6, 1924.</date>
----------<lb/>
</dateline>
Monthly Progress Report,<lb/>
September, 1924.<lb/>
The Surgeon General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Division of Scientific Research,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to forward herewith monthly progress report of<lb/>
malaria investigations conducted during the month of September 1924, un-<lb/>
der the direction of this office.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Crowley, Louisiana:</hi> Personnel - Special Expert M. A.<lb/>
Barber, Assoc. San. Eng. W. H. W. Komp and Technical Assistant Theo. B.<lb/>
Hayne.</p>
<p>Activities at the Crowley Laboratory consisted of: (1) Continuation of<lb/>
work on larvicides and mosquito repellents; (2) Experiments with tallow<lb/>
and lanolin as possible mosquito attractants, results negative; (3)<lb/>
Study continued of effects of hydrogen-ion concentration and various foods<lb/>
on the growth of Anopheline larvae; (4) Observations continued of in-<lb/>
cidence of Anopheles in an irrigated region; 3,334 imagoes collected, of<lb/>
which 84.1% were A. quadrimaculatus and 15.9% A. crucians; 182 bred out<lb/>
from larvae and pupae, of which 17.6% were A. quadrimaculatus and 82.4%<lb/>
were A. crucians; (5) Study of malaria prevalence continued by surveys of<lb/>
plantations and schools and by examination of blood specimens, 128 blood<lb/>
smears collected around Crowley examined, of which three were positive<lb/>
P. vivax all from one negro school; (6) Special inspection by Mr. Hayne<lb/>
of Paris green larvicide work at Lake City, Fla.</p>
<p><hi>Memphis Laboratory:</hi> Personnel - A.A. Surgeon Wm. A. Krauss and Microscopist<lb/>
Retha Kitchens.</p>
<p>418 blood smears were examined for malaria parasites, of which 363 were<lb/>
sent in locally for diagnosis, of these 33 were positive P. vivax and 29<lb/>
positive P. falc.; 32 blood smears collected in Mississippi and 17 sent in<lb/>
by the Tennessee State Board of Health - each lot showing three positives<lb/>
P. falc.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01213009"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>October 6, 1924.</p>
<p><hi>Field Laboratory, Savannah, Ga.:</hi> Personnel - Technical Assistant Bruce<lb/>
Mayne.</p>
<p>Mr. Mayne's activities consisted of: (1) Completion of malaria and mosquito<lb/>
survey in Okefenokee Swamp; (2) A two weeks' study of mosquito production<lb/>
with Mr. Gage in Aiken County, South Carolina; (3) Two lectures delivered<lb/>
at the University of Georgia Medical School, Augusta, Georgia, on the entomo-<lb/>
logical aspects of malaria.</p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. In his malaria survey around Billy's Island in the Okefenokee<lb/>
Swamp, Mr. Mayne questioned 245 white and 190 colored persons, no<lb/>
clinical malaria was observed; history of residents going back<lb/>
forty years all negative for malaria contracted in the Swamp,<lb/>
Anopheline mosquitoes abundant; 4,292 Anopheles collected, all<lb/>
A. crucians, females greatly predominated in ratio of 130 to<lb/>
one male; house infestation by A. crucians common, 520 specimens<lb/>
collected from interior of one four-room house.</item>
<item>2. In his two weeks' study of mosquito production around impound-<lb/>
ed waters in Aiken County, South Carolina, Mr. Mayne found what<lb/>
appeared to be ideal Anopheles breeding and harborage conditions,<lb/>
but very few Anopheline larvae or pupae, A. crucians predominated,<lb/>
A. quadrimaculatus very scarce; Gambusia and predatory insects<lb/>
abundant (special reports to follow).</item>
</list>
<p><hi>Epidemiological Studies of Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Asst. Surg. K. F. Maxcy.</p>
<p>Dr. Maxcy engaged in the study of a typhus-like disease, and was trans-<lb/>
ferred to the Mexican Border early in the month.</p>
<p><hi>Impounded Waters in Relation to Malaria</hi>: Personnel - Epidemiologist T.H.D.<lb/>
Griffitts, Asst. San. Eng. E. H. Gage and Microscopist Ethel Barrier.</p>
<p>Dr. Griffitts (Alabama), activities consisted of: (1) Inspection of W. H.<lb/>
Hill Pond near Montgomery; 40-acre pond, no floatage, clean edges, some<lb/>
grass, no mosquito production; (2) Inspection of Mitchell Dam Reservoir,<lb/>
water low, <unclear>banks</unclear> of Reservoir clean, very little mosquito production noted;<lb/>
(3) Inspection of Golden Bridge Pond, mosquito production still being con-<lb/>
trolled by spraying oil; (4) Location of Gambusia hatcheries on River Falls<lb/>
Power Company Project near River Falls; (5) Inspection of River Falls Power<lb/>
Company Pond near Gantt, water level low, small amount of flotage, consider-<lb/>
able amount of mosquito production.</p>
<p>Mr. Gage (South Carolina), activities consisted of: (1) Continued observa-<lb/>
tions of Anopheles prevalence and distribution in Horse Creek Valley, Aiken<lb/>
County, South Carolina; an increase in aquatic forms and adult Anopheles<lb/>
noted during the month, but apparently not coming from large bodies of im-<lb/>
pounded water; adults collected, A. crucians 27%, A. punctipennis 18% and<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01213010"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
October 6, 1924.<lb/>
A. quadrimaculatus 55%, (2) Inspections of several impounded water projects<lb/>
in North Carolina. Special reports to follow.</p>
<p>Miss Barrier (Alabama), Microscopist Ethel Barrier continued the investiga-<lb/>
tion of malaria prevalence around Muscle Shoals Lake, Alabama; 176 families<lb/>
consisting of 887 persons were visited during the month, 738 blood smears<lb/>
collected, and a spot map completed of all houses within mosquito flight<lb/>
range of Muscle Shoals Lake.</p>
<p><hi>Major Drainage in Relation to Malaria:</hi> Personnel - Assoc. San. Eng. A. W.<lb/>
Fuchs.</p>
<p>Mr. Fuchs' activities consisted of: (1) Continued observations of Anopheles<lb/>
production in and physical conditions of drainage ditches in Crittenden<lb/>
County, Arkansas and Washington County, Mississippi; (2) Continued study of<lb/>
ditch maintenance in Washington County, Mississippi, special report to<lb/>
follow.</p>
<p><hi>Cooperative Fish Studies:</hi> Mr. Samuel F. Hildebrand of the Bureau of Fisheries<lb/>
continued the investigation of fishes in relation to mosquito control at<lb/>
Augusta, Georgia. A detailed report of the season's studies will be prepared<lb/>
by Mr. Hildebrand at a later date. The following is an interesting example<lb/>
of his methods and observations:</p>
<p>A small pond containing a growth of <hi>Myriophyllum</hi> and well<lb/>
stocked with Gambusia was divided into two sections early<lb/>
this summer by means of a dam. Gambusia were removed from<lb/>
one side and left on the other, all other conditions re-<lb/>
mained the same. Twenty-four impartial dippings were made<lb/>
in each pond at weekly intervals throughout the season. On<lb/>
September 23rd, the following record of dippings was made:<lb/>
In the control pond which contained Gambusia in 24 dips<lb/>
16 Anopheles larvae were found, two were half grown, 16<lb/>
Culex larvae were found, of which one was half grown, the<lb/>
other larvae were all small. In the pond without <del>n</del> fish in<lb/>
the same number of dippings. 248 Anopheles pupae or larvae<lb/>
were found, consisting of two pupae, twelve large, 20 half<lb/>
grown and 215 small larvae; also 834 Culex larvae or pupae<lb/>
were found, consisting of 14 pupae, 47 large, 107 half<lb/>
<unclear>grown</unclear> and 666 small larvae.</p>
<p><hi>Rural Malaria Investigations:</hi> Personnel - Asst. San. Eng. J. C. Carter,<lb/>
A. A. Surg. C. P. Coogle, Assoc. San. Eng. L. M. Fisher, Assoc. San. Eng.<lb/>
A. W. Fuchs, Asst. San. Eng. J. G. Foster, Asst. San. Eng. H. N. Old, Asst.<lb/>
San. Eng. F. R. Shaw and Surg. L. L. Williams, Jr.</p>
<p>Mr. Carter (Alabama) activities consisted of: (1) Study of mosquito pro-<lb/>
duction around Jackson, Clarke County, continued; (2) Study of malaria<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01213011"/>
Monthly Progress Report<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
October 6, 1924.<lb/>
outbreak which occurred in Geneva County during August was made with a<lb/>
view ti determining the relative efficiency of quinine when sold as<lb/>
compared with its free distribution; (3) Study of malaria control meth-<lb/>
ods by Houston County Health Officer continued; (4) Study of malaria<lb/>
control methods by Barbour County Health Officer continued.</p>
<p>Mr. Old (Georgia) activities consisted of: (1) Continued observations<lb/>
of mosquito production in Chatham County; unusually heavy rainfall from<lb/>
September 16th to 30th, during which time precipitation amounted to 22.88<lb/>
inches, eleven inches within 24 hours on September 16th and 17th (Record<lb/>
rainfall); rainfall probably too late in summer to greatly increase mos-<lb/>
quito production and malaria rate; 521 A. quadrimaculatus and 22 A. cru-<lb/>
cians collected in out houses and animal sheds. City Health Officer of<lb/>
Savannah states that only 25 cases of malaria reported this summer, seven<lb/>
from outside the city; eight of these cases confirmed by blood examina-<lb/>
tion.</p>
<p>Mr. Shaw (Louisiana), activities consisted of: (1) Continued study of<lb/>
drainage and effects of dynamite around Patterson, St. Mary's Parish;<lb/>
(2) Study of mosquito incidence around Patterson; (3) Study of drainage<lb/>
and screening around Natalbany and Tangipahoa.</p>
<p>Dr. Coogle and Mr. Foster (Mississippi) continued the study of housing<lb/>
conditions in relation to malaria in Leflore County.</p>
<p>Dr. Coogle's activities consisted of: Ten houses treated with creosote<lb/>
oil; 151 houses inspected; 208 blood specimens collected for examination,<lb/>
of which 31 were found positive. Same persons examined for enlarged<lb/>
spleens, twenty-five found enlarged. A noticeable decrease in Anophe-<lb/>
line prevalence was observed in Leflore County this summer. Dr. Coogle<lb/>
also made malaria school surveys of three schools in Dunklin County,<lb/>
Missouri; examined 96 school children for enlarged spleens, finding<lb/>
eight enlarged, and collected 82 blood specimens for examination.</p>
<p>Mr. Foster: The twenty tenant houses screened by Mr. Foster and an equal<lb/>
number of controls were kept under observation by him during the month.<lb/>
The average cost of screening these tenant houses was $19.50 per house.<lb/>
Mosquito counts of screened and unscreened houses have been made at week-<lb/>
ly intervals - records not yet tabulated.</p>
<p>Mr. Fisher (South Carolina), activities consisted of: (1) Study of malaria<lb/>
control methods continued in Marion, Beaufort and Charleston Counties; (2)<lb/>
Observations on relative importance of A. crucians to malaria prevalence<lb/>
continued in Lexington County; (3) Study of use of school census cards con-<lb/>
tinued in Marion and Beaufort Counties.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01213012"/>
<p>Monthly Progress Report</p>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>October 6, 1924.</p>
<p>Dr. Williams (Virginia), activities consisted of: (1) Continued in-<lb/>
vestigation of malaria prevalence and malaria control methods in<lb/>
Henrico, James City, Isele of Wight, Nansemond, Brunswick, Accomac<lb/>
and Northampton Counties; during the month 28,960 feet of drainage<lb/>
was completed; one pond controlled (by drainage), 25 homes were screen-<lb/>
ed; ten cases of malaria investigated; 24 ponds controlled by oiling;<lb/>
(2) Study of control of mosquito production in Lake Prince, near Norfolk,<lb/>
by changing water level apparently effective; observations, the prevail-<lb/>
ing type of Anopheles in James City County continued to be A. puncti-<lb/>
pennis.</p>
<p><hi>Malaria Control Around U. S. Veterans' Hospitals:</hi> During the month<lb/>
Asst. San. Eng. F. R. Shaw inspected mosquito control operations around<lb/>
the following U. S. Veterans' Hospitals: Hospital #84, Algiers, Louisiana;<lb/>
conditions extremely dry, some mosquito breeding in artificial containers-<lb/>
recommended reduction of ditching crew as mosquito conditions found very<lb/>
good; Hospital #74, Gulfport, Mississippi; conditions extremely dry, no<lb/>
mosquito breeding, no adults found - recommended that ditching crew be<lb/>
reduced at this hospital; Hospital #27, Alexandria, Louisiana; conditions<lb/>
extremely dry, no mosquito breeding nor adult mosquitoes found - program<lb/>
of mosquito control operations found entirely satisfactory.</p>
<p><hi>Conferences and Inspections:</hi> Senior Sanitary Engineer J. A. LePrince<lb/>
inspected malaria investigations being conducted in Virginia, South<lb/>
Carolina, Chatham County, Georgia, Alabama, and Louisiana; also inspected<lb/>
impounded water projects in Davidson County, North Carolina; and con-<lb/>
ferred with State Health Officer of South Carolina.</p>
<p>Medical Officer in Charge in conference with state and county health<lb/>
officials at Montgomery, Alabama.</p>
<p><hi>Expenditures:</hi> During the month of September approximately $4,715.48<lb/>
was expended from the Malaria Allotment in connection with field inves-<lb/>
tigations, of malaria.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>L. D.<unclear>!</unclear> Fricks, Surgeon,<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
