<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01218001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: The Preferential and Compulsory Breeding Places of Some Disease Bearing Mosquitoes and the Limits Which Determine the Latter, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01218001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Coosa River (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Parr's Shoals (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Russia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01218001</idno>
<title>Report: The Preferential and Compulsory Breeding Places of Some Disease Bearing Mosquitoes and the Limits Which Determine the Latter, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter reports on the breeding habits of the Anopheles mosquito.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report: The Preferential and Compulsory Breeding Places of Some Disease Bearing Mosquitoes and the Limits Which Determine the Latter, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01218001"/>
<p>What of the breeding places preferential or compulsory of the<lb/>
mosquitoes vectors of malaria? The problem here is quite different from<lb/>
that on which we have just touched. The vector of yellow fever we may<lb/>
assume to be, in the Americas at least, a single species of a single<lb/>
genus and subgenus. The vector of malaria is, so far as our present know-<lb/>
ledge and probability goes, confined to a single genus indeed, but a number<lb/>
of species of that genus convey malaria. These different species might<lb/>
naturally have different breeding places both preferential and of compulsion,<lb/>
and it is rather the variation in the choice of their breeding places when<lb/>
there is choice and the utilization of less preferable ones where there is<lb/>
no choice of a few species of malaria carrying anopheles, that I shall touch<lb/>
on in the remaining 10 minutes.</p>
<p>For the first, one might instance a species - anopheles cruzii - as<lb/>
I recall, but am not sure - breeding in the axils of certain arborescent plants<lb/>
- biomelias - in Southern Brazil and reported by Chagas as efficient malaria<lb/>
vectors, and one, at least, in the Philippines, also a vector, is reported as<lb/>
breeding in <unclear>hamboo</unclear> stumps and similar places by choice not to mention A. Macu-<lb/>
latus breeding in the current of mountain streams in the Federated Malay<lb/>
States. I have no first-hand knowledge of either.</p>
<p>I will confine myself then to the malaria vectors of the U. S. of<lb/>
which I have some first-hand knowledge. Smith of New Jersey, a careful man<lb/>
and a good entomologist, said some years ago that anopheles were found in<lb/>
every kind of collection of water. As he was referring to the species of<lb/>
Anopheles, crucians, punctipennis and quadrimaculatus, prevalent in New Jersey<lb/>
and to normal breeding, he probably was not confining himself to breeding places<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01218002"/>
-2-<lb/>
of sanitary importance. As this is the only class of breeding we consider<lb/>
we certainly cannot accept this dictum for the states south and southwest<lb/>
of New Jersey. For quadrimaculatus we have ponds, large pools, seepage<lb/>
outcrops and certain marshes as breeding places of election; for puncti-<lb/>
pennis, eddies and pools in streams, even swift streams, especially if<lb/>
there is floatage present or grass hanging over in them, small pools,<lb/>
<unclear>cow</unclear> tracks, and etc.; for curcians, water somewhat contaminated, with sea<lb/>
water, (Even a higher salinity than normal sea-water in pools made so by<lb/>
evaporation and refilling with sea-water) brackish or absolutely undrinkable<lb/>
on the Atlantic Coastal plain, with acid, as Metz found them near Montgomery,<lb/>
Ala. in 1918, and as the result of vegetable decomposition, if not too much<lb/>
of it - just short of that suitable for full Urataeneus saphirrhims breed-<lb/>
ing. This is not a requisite, however, only a preference. Crucians<lb/>
breed freely in what we consider clean water.</p>
<p>Yet, while there is over-lapping of crucians into other than its<lb/>
preferential breeding places on very moderate compulsion, the choice of the<lb/>
other two species in a place for oviposition is well marked. In our work<lb/>
for determining the effect of impounding water on the production of Anophe-<lb/>
les, we found punctipennis larvae (except A. punctipennis in spring and<lb/>
fall) so rarely in the large ponds that when we found them we looked for<lb/>
the <unclear>streams</unclear> down which they might have washed and very generally found it.</p>
<p>The preference of quadrimaculatus for pond breeding leads to an<lb/>
entirely logical but unexpected result. I say entirely logical. Imagine<lb/>
a herd of cattle on a Texas prairie (thin feeding places); they gather and<lb/>
feed in the swales when it is dry, on the hillocks when it is wet; but let<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01218003"/>
-3-<lb/>
someone remove the fence from around a field of alfalfa, in the<lb/>
prairie, they forsake both swales and hillocks and gather in the<lb/>
alfalfa. So it seems that if a breeding place of election is made<lb/>
sufficiently available to our Anopheles she will, or may, abandon other<lb/>
breeding places which, while not her first choice, were sufficiently<lb/>
acceptable to her to use.</p>
<p>So in the survey of the pool of lock No. 12 on the Coosa in<lb/>
Alabama, a pool with over 25 miles of back water, we found breeding of<lb/>
Anopheles quadrimaculatus in only one place (a large pool close to the<lb/>
pond and which possibly had been joined to it) within say one-quarter<lb/>
or one-half mile of the pool, while at a distance- as at Shelby, three<lb/>
miles distant - and in country in all respects the same as that close<lb/>
to the pool this species was breeding in every place (seepage outcrop<lb/>
and large pool) we would expect to find them. So far the pond at<lb/>
Parr's Shoals on Broad River, South Carolina, the same absence of quadri-<lb/>
maculatus was found near the pool while a survey made at Eau Claire, some<lb/>
15 miles distant and later at Camp Jackson - both in country so far as<lb/>
we could see, like that adjoining Parr's Shoals showed this species fairly<lb/>
common. Both of these ponds were breeding quadrimaculatus in places pro-<lb/>
tected from fish and wave action. Never have I seen quadrimaculatus breed-<lb/>
ing of sanitary importance close to one of the large hydro-electric ponds.</p>
<p>In the fall of 1921 - in a survey - I found a series of large<lb/>
pools close to a fair-sized pond on Broad River at Lockhart, South Carolina.<lb/>
These pools were large, some, I judge 40 by 20 feet - and there were at<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01218004"/>
-4-<lb/>
least 20 of them. I fully expected to find quadrimaculatus in them but<lb/>
I did not. I cannot say, of course, that this was due to the proximity<lb/>
of the pond, because I made no survey in this immediate country at a<lb/>
distance from this pond. Still, I did expect to find quads there and<lb/>
would have found them in such ponds almost anywhere else in similar country.</p>
<p>I would give other examples from my own observations.</p>
<p>Data illustrating this principle, although it is not enunciated<lb/>
as a principle, is given by the Swellengrebels and by Schuffner in the re-<lb/>
ports of the Health Service of Dutch East Indies, No. 7 of 1919.</p>
<p>The Swellengrebels give data to show that, while sea-water is an<lb/>
obligatory condition for the breeding of the coast strain of Anopheles<lb/>
ludlowi, the principal vector for malaria about the coast of the Dutch<lb/>
East Indies, the presence of a certain algae determines its preferential<lb/>
breeding place - larvae of this species having been found in no fresh water<lb/>
ponds, and in numbers in all salt-ponds containing this algae and in only<lb/>
three out of 98 which did not contain it.</p>
<p>Schuffner at Deliwan found ludlowi breeding in a number of salt<lb/>
ponds, in the grass growing and hanging over in them, in a few, freely. When<lb/>
this algae appeared in <unclear>some</unclear> of these ponds, ludlowi bred profusely in them<lb/>
and breeding ceased in the others.</p>
<p>An instance is also given when on the construction of a sea-fish pond,<lb/>
(planted with the algae) breeding ceased in the natural salt-ponds in which<lb/>
some breeding had been going on, the sea-fish pond breeding profusely.</p>
<p>Although as I said there was no enunciation of the principle we have<lb/>
just formulated, yet the data these men give is good evidence for its existence.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01218005"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>No other species of Anopheles breeds in artificial containers<lb/>
in the U. S. so as to be of sanitary importance. They do breed with us<lb/>
in such containers - fire-barrels, buckets and in some sections more than<lb/>
others, but nowhere have we seen them or doing so sufficiently to be a<lb/>
sanitary problem. The same, from the report of others, seems to be true in<lb/>
Europe, France, Spain, Italy, the Balkans and Greece. Indeed it may be<lb/>
taken as a general characteristic of this genus - I cannot say a universal<lb/>
one as I do not know, yet a strange tale comes to us from Russia. There<lb/>
was a severe epidemic of malaria in Southeastern Russia in 1922 and 1923,<lb/>
in which the vectors for much of the time were Anopheles bred in artificial<lb/>
containers.</p>
<p>An account of this is given in the London Lancet of December 8,<lb/>
1923, by Dr. Melville D. Mackensie, Medical Officer of the Friends' Russian<lb/>
Famine Relief Unit, South East Russia. The district of which he was imme-<lb/>
diately in charge was that of Buzuluk Ooyezd in the lower Volga valley, and was,<lb/>
he stated, about the size of Wales, with a population of about 400,000.<lb/>
He states that this epidemic extended over enormous areas in this valley in<lb/>
which subtertian malaria had been previously unknown and where simple tertian<lb/>
had been rare, making it at the time the most malarious region on the earth.</p>
<p>The infection was introduced in the fall of 1922 by human carriers<lb/>
returning from Turkestan where malaria of all types is endemic and where they<lb/>
had been to get wheat on account of the famine. They returned infected and<lb/>
began to infect the home people in November. The epidemic continued throughout<lb/>
the whole winter until May, when this account closes, although the temperature<lb/>
recorded varied between -20 C to -30 C from 4 F to 22 F below zero. The<lb/>
disease not only developed during this time in those already infected but was<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01218006"/>
-6-<lb/>
contracted all during the winter. The houses were kept very close and<lb/>
both the Anopheles vectors were breeding in the water-butts - larvae being a-<lb/>
bundant in them and imagoes abundant in the dark corners of the houses.</p>
<p>He states that taking the average of all districts from 60 to 70<lb/>
percent of the population were affected: in some 90 to 100 percent. It<lb/>
was of all types - tertian, sub-tertian, and quartian - 14000 blood examinations<lb/>
were made in the clinic at Buzuluk - and it was severe.</p>
<p><unclear>Mackenzie</unclear> does not give the morbidity in his district, unless we<lb/>
take it at 65% of 400, 000, which would give 260,000, nor the mortality al-<lb/>
though he says it was high, nor - and more important to us - although an M. D.<lb/>
and A. D. T. M. and a D. P. H. he did not think to mention the species of<lb/>
Anopheles he found breeding in the water-butts - the vector responsible for<lb/>
this malaria<unclear>.</unclear> Until we know the normal breeding habits of this mosquito<lb/>
we cannot tell whether the water-butts were utilized from compulsion or were<lb/>
its normal breeding places. There is nothing in this account to show why<lb/>
they should have been utilized this winter - 1922 and 1923 - rather than<lb/>
any previous one, and until we know more about its normal breeding habits<lb/>
during the winter in this region we cannot claim that a change of such habits<lb/>
were a factor in this epidemic. One would rather ascribe it to: (1) the<lb/>
advent of carriers - especially as they brought an unaccustomed type of ma-<lb/>
laria; (2) the debilitated state of the population -having thus no re-<lb/>
sistance to even the tertian malaria, to which they were partly accustomed:<lb/>
(3) the scarcity of quinine intensifying 2.</p>
<p>Naturally the house breeding of the Anopheles present was a factor,<lb/>
and a necessary factor for new infections after cold weather set in, but I see<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01218007"/>
-7-<lb/>
no reason why this should have been greater than in other years, unless<lb/>
the people were too debilitated to fight against them. Naturally a man<lb/>
on the ground should be the best judge of what measures are feasible and<lb/>
McKensie says that was impossible to control this production of Anopheles<lb/>
in the houses. Admitting that he was in a better position to judge yet<lb/>
to the writer this looks as if it had been ridiculously easy by putting spigots in<lb/>
the barrels low down and covering them with cloth or oiling the surface of the water<lb/>
in them.</p>
<p>One would like much to have further news from this region and to<lb/>
know (1) the species of anopheles concerned in this epidemic: (2) whether it<lb/>
habitually bred in houses in previous winters and, if not, what condition was<lb/>
changed so as to induce it to do so the winter of 1922 and 1923: (3) whether<lb/>
it breeds in the house during the summer also; this seems to be a marshy country<lb/>
with an abundance of possible breeding places, outside. We will watch for the<lb/>
translation of the report of the Pan-Russian Malaria Conference at Moscow in<lb/>
January last. It may be noted here that to it were reported 4,887,207 cases of<lb/>
malaria in Russia, from January to October, 1923. This, say the local authori-<lb/>
ties must be multiplied by 2 1/2 to obtain anything like the correct figure - giving<lb/>
what seems to be good reasons therefore. This would give 12,218,000 cases of<lb/>
malaria for these ten months. Well there are many people in Russia.</p>
<p><hi>COPY</hi>:H</p>
<pb n="8" id="f01218008"/>
<p>THE PREFERENTIAL AND COMPULSORY BREEDING PLACES OF SOME DISEASE BEARING<lb/>
MOSQUITOES AND THE LIMITS WHICH DETERMINE THE LATTER <hi>BY DR. ROSE CARTER</hi></p>
<p>DISCUSSION</p>
<p>DR. <unclear>AGRAMONTEn</unclear> said he would like to call attention to a means that<lb/>
has been carried out for the first time in Santiago, for combatting the breeding<lb/>
places of mosquitoes under conditions where the people had to keep reservoirs.<lb/>
All water, <del><unclear></unclear></del> had fish introduced so as to destroy the larvae in such places.</p>
<p>The discussion by Dr. Carter is one more example in our science of what<lb/>
the intelligent man can do in combatting the mosquito. In this case the excellent<lb/>
results are to be expected, particularly for the reason that the intelligent and<lb/>
<unclear>ingenuity</unclear> are of a character far superior to the ordinary man.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f01218009"/>
<p><unclear>THE PREFERENTIAL AND COMPULSORY BREEDING PLACES</unclear> OF SOME DISEASE BREEDING<lb/>
MOSQUITOES AND THE LIMITS WHICH DETERMINE THE LATTER BY DR. ROSE CARTER</p>
<p>DISCUSSION</p>
<p>DR. HORN opened the discussion with regard to the breeding of mosquitoes in lagoons.<lb/>
He said covering 20 years experience, he carefully examined the whole range of<lb/>
mosquitoes and he was never able to find any stagomia.........</p>
<p>We know that the stagomia is practically a in mosquito<lb/>
In a town of perhaps 4,000 inhabitants, we kept the water supply free from mos-<lb/>
quitoes and the water containers destroyed that would gather stagomia.</p>
<p>As to the question of the drainage, one of the greatest points I think....<lb/>
...........</p>
<pb n="10" id="f01218010"/>
<p>THE PREFERENTIAL AND COMPULSORY BREEDING PLACES OF SOME DISEASE-BEARING<lb/>
MOSQUITOES AND THE LIMITS WHICH DETERMINE THE LATTER By Dr. Carter</p>
<p>DISCUSSION</p>
<p>DR. CARTER said that Dr. Horn has just said he would not mind the<lb/>
mosquitoes breeding in or about the lagoons, my report did not assert that, it<lb/>
applied to the draining of the lagoon and the cure of the mosquito breeding, in<lb/>
connection with yellow fever. As I said, we can eb a slight change of our methods<lb/>
control stagomia and and induce them not to form these outlying breeding places.<lb/>
Their normal breeding places are pools, etc.</p>
<p>Dr. Carter quoted a letter from a Dr. Carr with regard to breeding in<lb/>
puddles. They placed sand and packed it around as tightly as possible, he had<lb/>
induced captive stagomia to deposit eggs about the centre above the sand.<lb/>
I wrote him at once that this might start a strain that might breed on sand insta<lb/>
instead of on land.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
