<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01217035">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 26, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01217035</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-12-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="place">El Salvador</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-12-26">December 26, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01217035</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 26, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor discusses the yellow fever work in El Salvador.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-12-26">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 26, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01217035"/>
<opener>
Copy.<lb/>
6a. Seccion de la<lb/>
Direccion General de Sanidad:<lb/>
Sub-Seccion Especial de Lucha<lb/>
y Control Contra el Aedes<lb/>
Aegypti<lb/>
Rep. de el Salvador C.A.<lb/>
<dateline>
San Salvador, Salvador<lb/>
<date value="1924-12-26">December 26, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Subject - Plan of Campaign to Control Yellow Fever<lb/>
in the Republic of El Salvador.</p>
<p>The yellow fever infection has appeared at varying intervals as an<lb/>
epidemic in El Salvador. The recent outbreak was first recognized on June<lb/>
5th., and the epidemic appears to have been controlled by the third week of<lb/>
October since when no case of the infection has been found or reported.<lb/>
During the epidemic 80 cases with 27 deaths were reported from three cities.<lb/>
The reporting system in the country is regarded as average.</p>
<p>Unquestionably there were cases of yellow fever present before the<lb/>
formal announcement. The failure of knowledge of these earlier cases may be<lb/>
laid to the fact that many patients ill with very mild attack do not call for<lb/>
the services of a physician and in the absence of an efficient house inspections<lb/>
service the Health Authorities must remain in ignorance of the presence of the<lb/>
disease until the infection acquires a virulence calling for the physicians<lb/>
aid. I subscribe to the above rather than to the thought that this can and<lb/>
does exist in a community in an unrecognizable form.</p>
<p>It is not difficult to understand the reluctance sometimes exhibited<lb/>
by physicians in refraining to announce early suspicious cases of yellow fever<lb/>
because of the upset produced in the community by such announcement. With a<lb/>
more complete knowledge of the value of the Noguchi vaccine it may develop that<lb/>
it can be applied to supersede the present quarantine restrictions, if so, one<lb/>
would expect earlier announcements of suspicious cases of yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01217036"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>The present co-operative campaign to control yellow fever in Salvador<lb/>
was entered upon between Direccion General de Sanidad and the International<lb/>
Health as of October 1, 1924. The basis of work is the reduction of the aedes<lb/>
aegypti by attacking the insect in its aquatic stage. In brief, anti-larvae<lb/>
measures.</p>
<p>Former campaigns had been planned and conducted with the fish playing<lb/>
a leading role as larvae consumers. The present campaign was first projected<lb/>
with fish as an important ally but once upon the ground this measure was<lb/>
abandoned in favor of the &ldquo;System of fines&rdquo; as developed by the National Health<lb/>
Department and from which very satisfactory results are flowing. This system<lb/>
is being continued without causing any hardship to the people.</p>
<p>It is not the intention to convey the impression that fish are not<lb/>
used, to the contrary, we recommend their efficiency to people who depend upon<lb/>
wells or stow the domestic water supply in open concrete tanks, barrels and<lb/>
similar receptacles and who prefer fish, to practicing the measures prescribed<lb/>
by the Service for mosquito proofing water receptacles, in which case the<lb/>
people are obligated to secure the fish for their own account.</p>
<p>The Anti-Aedes aegypti service aims to secure the reduction of this<lb/>
mosquito through the co-operation of the people who are requested to empty<lb/>
and clean at least once each week all receptacles used in and near the home<lb/>
for stowing the domestic water supply the only exceptions being indoor tanks<lb/>
which must be properly covered and shallow wells for which fish are recommended.<lb/>
For failure to co-operate the Service imposes a fine of two colones for the<lb/>
first remission with increasing penalties for persistent infractions. Each<lb/>
home is visited by an Inspector who notes if the instructions are being carried<lb/>
out.</p>
<p>The usual method followed in assigning area to an Inspector is to<lb/>
allocate to each man a sector based on a daily inspection of between 50 and 75<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01217037"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
homes the entire area to be completed in six consecutive days. In some instances<lb/>
the Inspector is accompanied by an assistant as is necessary when oil is<lb/>
sprayed in a general anti-mosquito service. In strictly anti-aedes aegypti<lb/>
work oil plays no part, and its use is misleading.</p>
<p>The inspection system in Salvador has been modified and we are now<lb/>
practicing an improved &ldquo;group plan&rdquo; and designated as &ldquo;Brigadas Volantes&rdquo; or<lb/>
&ldquo;Ambulantes&rdquo;, we have two such Brigadas, each comprising six inspectors and<lb/>
a Supervisor. The Brigadas Volantes are on a schedule to visit all large<lb/>
centers of population based on the findings of our mosquito survey, at intervals<lb/>
of about three weeks. No additional anti-larvae measures are applied in the<lb/>
centers during the interval of visits by the Brigadas. For one week each month<lb/>
both Brigadas are assembled in San Salvador for inspections in this city.</p>
<p>Our preliminary mosquito survey in Salvador clearly proves that all<lb/>
communities have not as yet been invaded by the aedes aegypti notwithstanding<lb/>
that some of the towns and villages inspected have a population of two and three<lb/>
thousand people but the &ldquo;aegypti free&rdquo; towns have no permanent water containers,<lb/>
that is to say, that the people have only small earthenware containers for<lb/>
stowing water which are refilled daily from a nearby river or stream.</p>
<p>In communities where public pilas serve the people we find that the<lb/>
aegypti are established and that people carry the larvae from the pilas to<lb/>
their homes where they continue development. With the mosquito proofing of<lb/>
the pila by emptying the pila and scrubbing the inside surface to remove eggs<lb/>
we eliminate it as a permanent breeding place and this process repeated for a<lb/>
time should extinguish the species in such communities.</p>
<p>The development of the Brigada Volante is a natural result of the<lb/>
thought that there is little, if anything, to be gained, by continuing intensive<lb/>
work regularly in a city when the house index has been lowered to below 5% and<lb/>
maintained there for a reasonable time. I think that we are justified in assuming<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01217038"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
that the rate of rise in the house index is a relatively slow process during<lb/>
the dry season and this factor alone permits of the temporary withdrawal of<lb/>
inspectors from an &ldquo;intensive area&rdquo; and utilizing them for extensive work. We<lb/>
are hoping to secure accurate data on the rate of rise in the house index from<lb/>
this procedure.</p>
<p>The disposition of the Brigadas is as follows:</p>
<p>The Republic of El Salvador is divided into two sectors, East and West,<lb/>
one brigada is assigned to each sector with a schedule of centers to be<lb/>
inspected. All municipalities here have been planned on the block or manzana<lb/>
system, that is, the streets are at right angles and parallel to each other, a<lb/>
row of manzanas is selected and each inspector is given a block to inspect and<lb/>
upon finishing his detail he passes to another manzana designated by the supervisor<lb/>
and this continues until the row of manzanas has been inspected when the group<lb/>
repeats the process in another column of blocks. It will be noted that the<lb/>
inspector is never more than six blocks away from the Supervisor and this factor<lb/>
permits easy and complete check on the work of the individual inspector and<lb/>
should develop increased efficiency. With this system we have reduced our personnel<lb/>
from 60 to 25.</p>
<p>The Central office notifies the local authorities of the expected<lb/>
arrival of the Brigadas and requests for them all aid possible. This<lb/>
assistance takes the form of providing the men with a place to sleep and a<lb/>
civil guard to accompany to the group while at work, the guard is a guarantee<lb/>
to the public that the inspectors are authorized to make the visit. The<lb/>
assistance from the local authorities is most willingly given.</p>
<p>Later I will report in detail on the rate of rise in the house index<lb/>
as observed during the present dry season. The accompanying views will show<lb/>
the average water container in use in Salvador.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) M.E. Connor</signed>
International Health Board<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York, N.Y.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
