<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01215004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from M.A. Barber to Henry Rose Carter, November 5, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Barber, M.A.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01215004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-11-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-11-05">November 5, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01215004</idno>
<title>Letter from M.A. Barber to Henry Rose Carter, November 5, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Barber discusses his experiments and provides his observations on the longevity, breeding, and feeding habits of the Anopheles mosquito.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-11-05">
<head>Letter from M.A. Barber to Henry Rose Carter, November 5, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01215004"/>
<opener>
Malaria<lb/>
Barber-<lb/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
<dateline>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
Crowley, La. <date value="1924-11-05">Nov. 5, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter Oct. 29 received this morning, and, as always,<lb/>
I was much pleased to hear from you.</p>
<p>As regards the question of longevity of confined Anopheles.<lb/>
In cages one gets not only protection from enemies but also a high degree<lb/>
of moisture. Again those of us who have had a large experience in infection<lb/>
experiments find that it is usually only the strong which survive. Often<lb/>
whole batches will die<del>s</del> early in spite of our care. Dr. King, who<lb/>
visited us here recently, told us that in his experience Anopheles usually<lb/>
died when put into a large screened cage, but survived much better in<lb/>
test tubes-one to a tube. In cages too, we usually see that our Anopheles<lb/>
are well fed, although many will survive a long time if given only the<lb/>
initial blood feed. Last summer we had a good chance to repeat<lb/>
the experiment of longevity of Anopheles (mostly quads) when shut in a room.<lb/>
Water was provided in the room and sacking hung so that part of it<lb/>
kept moist. In spite of this additional moisture, in four days there were only<lb/>
3 survivors (females) out of an original number of nearly 500 both sexes.</p>
<p>As you suggest, it would seem that Anopheles do not often survive<lb/>
long in ships at sea. I do not think that the danger of the wider distribution<lb/>
of harmful <del><unclear></unclear></del> species though<lb/>
steamers is eliminated by the short life of mosquitoes<lb/>
in rooms, etc., but it does not seem to be great in case of the longer distances.<lb/>
Your have doubtless noticed the work of Mac Gregor in Mauriti<del>o</del>us. He found<lb/>
there, 1922, maculipalpis and funestus as well as costalis. Funestus<lb/>
occured in large numbers and hd been overlooked in previous surveys.<lb/>
Ross in commenting on this paper thinks it likely that funestus<lb/>
is a recent importation. But does it not seem more<del>l</del> likely that<lb/>
all these species have always been there and that the outbreak of malaria<lb/>
1865 or thereaboutswas due to some other cause?</p>
<p>I have long been interested in the suggestion of Gill that humidity<lb/>
may be an important factor in malaria epidemics through increasing<lb/>
the average longevity of Anopheles and thus increasing the mathematical<lb/>
chances of transmission. There seems to be an impression among observers<lb/>
in this country that nearness to a wood promotes malaria independently<lb/>
of the intensity of Anopheles. One reason why we chose this locality for work<lb/>
was to test this question. Anopheles are so numerous everywhere here<lb/>
on account of irrigated rice fields that the intensity factor<lb/>
is to some extent eliminated. But it does not appear in our surveys<lb/>
that nearness to the numerous wooded bayous here makes any material difference<lb/>
in the malaria rate. There is so little mal<add>a</add>ria here anyhow, that our observations<lb/>
are not very convincing, but in houses a few hundred feet from woods<lb/>
there does not seem to be any more mal<add>a</add>ria than elsewhere.</p>
<p>I should be glad to get the photostats of the Russian data when you no<lb/>
longer have any use for them. However, I have made summaries of them, and do not<lb/>
need the original greatly. I suspect that when all the returns from<lb/>
the Russian epidemic are in we will not find it necessary to attribute much<lb/>
<del>b</del>of their malaria to barrel breeding or breeding on wet wood. The literature is<lb/>
so full of half-baked observations of the habits of mosquitoes that I never<lb/>
open a journal now without a small bag of salt handy. The more observations we<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01215005"/>
2.<lb/>
make the less we seem to know. Here is an example of this <unclear>thesias</unclear><lb/>
This summer I have been trying to get something fundamental on the food of<lb/>
Anopheline larvae. You know that stomach contents of larvae in nature gives<lb/>
but little valid information, for they will ingest anything that comes along-<lb/>
be it algae or arsenic. So I have begun with ova made free of bacteria and<lb/>
other microorganisms through alcohol sterilization. Eggs thus treated are<lb/>
transferred to sterileserum broth. Those tubes which remain clear three<lb/>
days or so are transferred to media in sterilized flasks-tubes now have<lb/>
numerous very lively larvae in them. To the sterilized flasks are added<lb/>
pure cultures of certain organisms or sterile food-sometimes chlorophyl, sterile,<lb/>
from the inside of <del><unclear></unclear></del> plant tissue. Beuatiful growths on media plus<lb/>
paramecium only, certain unicellular algae-pure culture also, and certain<lb/>
bacteria. Also on combinations of these. On all of these, mosquitoes have<lb/>
emerged beautifully. But when sterile blood cells, egg yolk and white,<lb/>
and a great variety of things autoclaved of heated just enough to kill<lb/>
them are added, there is very little development, no emergences thus far<lb/>
and in only one case full grown larvae. It looked as if I had something<lb/>
but here is the fly in the ointment, or rather a reason why the<lb/>
fly did not appear in the ointment. If instead of a motile alga one uses<lb/>
a living, non-motile form in pure culture as Scenedesmus growth is also<lb/>
meager. Again in one culture I placed sterilized ground-up bodies of<lb/>
Anopheles adults. Flask with very little water so that larvae had the food<lb/>
placed under their noses, so to speak. Here I got full-grown larvae, and the<lb/>
usual tests made of flask contents, microscopical examination, cultures in<lb/>
various media show that my flask remained sterile of microorganisms.<lb/>
So it seems that a large factor is the accessibility of the food, and it may<lb/>
not be its digestibility at all. Dead bacteria and infusoria killed at low tem-<lb/>
peratures fail to nourish, possibly because they sink to the bottom and<lb/>
are not eaten by the young larvae.</p>
<p>But I have had so many larvae remain living but with little growth<lb/>
of dead food placed convenient to them that it is possible that<lb/>
accessibility is not the only factor. <unclear>P ssibly</unclear> in nature larvae commonly feed<lb/>
on living things and only secondarily on dead materials because they<lb/>
feed so largely at the surface. But the moral thus far is that an apparently<lb/>
definite result may have to be reviewed in a different light.</p>
<p>So I have come to hesitate about publishing anything on the habits<lb/>
of mosquitoes until I have made a good many observations.</p>
<p>I am sorry I can give you nothing first-hand on costalis. We did not<lb/>
see this species in the P.I. or Malay States.</p>
<p>As regards breeding in barrels. One may see this not only when<lb/>
other breeding places are few but also when the numbers of Anopheles are large.<lb/>
In Stuttgart, 1920, it was often observed although other breeding places<lb/>
were plentiful. I am inclined to agree with Van Dine that barrel breeding,<lb/>
when it does occur, does not produce any large number of adults.</p>
<p>I hope I will get to see you in New Orleans this month. Immediately<lb/>
after the meeting Mr. Komp and I expect to spend about two months on the<lb/>
plantations of the United Fruit Company-invitation of Dr. Deeks. I spent a few<lb/>
weeks there last winter. Main thing will be to get more information regarding<lb/>
the epidemiology of malaria. It seems to me that one of our greatest needs<lb/>
in this country is to know how much malaria there is in different places<lb/>
and to correlate malaria intensity with numbers of Anopheles -or to see<lb/>
what the one has to do with the other. Here in the rice country we have untold<lb/>
A. quad. but comparatively little malaria. Wish I could talk it over with you.</p>
<p>We will probably be in Greenwood, Miss. next year.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With sincere personal regards,</salute>
<signed>M.A. Barber</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
