<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01217031">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from E.J. Scannell to Henry Rose Carter, December 24, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Scannell, E.J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01217031</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-12-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="place">Ceara (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Fortaleza, Ceara (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Brazil</name>
<name type="place">Recife (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Catharina (Brazil)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-12-24">December 24, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01217031</idno>
<title>Letter from E.J. Scannell to Henry Rose Carter, December 24, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Scannell reports on the yellow fever work in Brazil. He offers his opinion on the methods by which the yellow fever work is conducted.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-12-24">
<head>Letter from E.J. Scannell to Henry Rose Carter, December 24, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01217031"/>
<opener>
RUA DA CAMELLEIRA, <unclear>N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>1.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></unclear> ANDAR<lb/>
TELEPHONE CENTRAL<lb/>
CAIXA POSTAL, <unclear>N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></unclear> 387<lb/>
I. H. B<lb/>
Brazil<lb/>
<dateline>
DEPARTAMENTO DE SA&Uacute;DE PUBLICA<lb/>
COMMISS&Atilde;O DA FEBRE AMARELLA<lb/>
BAHIA, BRASIL<lb/>
<date value="1924-12-24">December 24, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On my return from the northern states (Cear&aacute; and <unclear>Maranh&acirc;o</unclear>)<lb/>
I found your letter dated October 29th. awaiting me.<lb/>
The immense amount of work you put into the communication<lb/>
demonstrates clearly that you yet are able to do a great deal<lb/>
of work. I am glad that is so for I feel that the service needs<lb/>
you but also it appears to me you should be very careful about<lb/>
overdoing. I only recently heard that you were at Panama - that may<lb/>
however have been an error since things frequently become twisted<lb/>
or changed enroute here. If you were there you must have found many changes<lb/>
since the days when you walked the ties on the old Panama railroad-<lb/>
good days they were too, many of them but now going back and finding new<lb/>
faces everywhere must be rather distressing. I have never been back<lb/>
although I should enjoy passing through the cut near where I was stationed<lb/>
by your orders during the last days of 1905.</p>
<p>I am so glad you were kind enough to enlighten me as to some of your<lb/>
methods in arriving at certain conclusions from old and at the best<lb/>
confusing histories. As you state, those cases with anemia and with<lb/>
a long history of illness, many dying months later after arrival<lb/>
at home must have been malaria.</p>
<p>I am sorry I did not see your &lsquo;Place of Origen of Yellow Fever&rsquo; but<lb/>
Doctor White has not mentioned it so perhaps he did not receive a copy.<lb/>
We here are all very ignorant of what is going on outside our own<lb/>
province - I really wish we might be allowed to know more as to what is<lb/>
taking place. Down here we all feel isolated and are obliged to get what<lb/>
information we can from the A. M. A. Journal and similar publications.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01217032"/>
RUA DA CAMELLEIRA, <unclear>N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>1.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></unclear> ANDAR<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO DE SA&Uacute;DE PUBLICA<lb/>
COMMISS&Atilde;O DA FEBRE AMARELLA<lb/>
BAHIA, BRASIL<lb/>
TELEPHONE CENTRAL<lb/>
CAIXA POSTAL, <unclear>N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></unclear> 387<lb/>
2.<lb/>
I have just returned from Cear&aacute; where I spent some three weeks<lb/>
with Doctor Smith.</p>
<p>As you perhaps know we are working the capital of Cear&aacute; (Fortaleza)<lb/>
only but I thought we should know something as to the interior of the<lb/>
state so with Doctor Smith I visited most of the big towns and cities<lb/>
there - a most interesting country I found it but wild- mostly desert<lb/>
and both hot and dry.</p>
<p>I had two very interesting visits with the Governor of Cear&aacute; and he<lb/>
was pleased to recall the fact that he was acquainted with you - it<lb/>
seems he travelled with you and Doctor Guiteras when you were down<lb/>
here on the survey.</p>
<p>As to the situation here - we do not know of any cases of Yellow Fever<lb/>
at the present time any where in the country- the last case I saw in<lb/>
the interior of Bahia during October. The work goes well and it appears<lb/>
to be a case of holding on now. All our people have done well and<lb/>
since Doctor Beeuwkes came all are anxious to get away to Africa.<lb/>
You mentioned hearing from Carr - yes, he has done quite a bit of<lb/>
research along old lines- all new to him however and always interesting.<lb/>
I have been working up a survey which I hope to publish later on, showing<lb/>
various features of our work, giving hazards (mosquito breeding)<lb/>
as we have found them in different localities, containers found in the<lb/>
homes favoring the development of Aedes perhaps is the better term,<lb/>
and our methods of handling them.</p>
<p><unclear>Here</unclear> in Bahia we have two chief hazards - the water box, usually up under<lb/>
the roof in kitchen and one or two earthern ware jars (called porrao) which<lb/>
I am sure you are acquainted with.</p>
<p>The water boxes have been sealed and the jars are covered - the few cisterns<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01217033"/>
RUA DA CAMELLEIRA, <unclear>N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>1.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></unclear> ANDAR<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTO DE SA&Uacute;DE PUBLICA<lb/>
COMMISS&Atilde;O DA FEBRE AMARELLA<lb/>
BAHIA, BRASIL<lb/>
TELEPHONE CENTRAL<lb/>
CAIXA POSTAL, <unclear>N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></unclear> 387<lb/>
3.<lb/>
tanks and barrels have been fished. Our index here is running something<lb/>
under one per cent. To better secure the cooperation of the people<lb/>
we have been working to eliminate all mosquitoes and I am sure it has been<lb/>
a good investment. Bahia and Cear&aacute; were our two hard places. Cear&aacute;<lb/>
with a population of about 80, 000 has no running water and as you know<lb/>
that means the storing in the home of whatever water the people can<lb/>
get hold of- in fact there it meant anywhere from two to five of the<lb/>
big water jars to a house. The jars here stand about a meter high and<lb/>
favor Aedes. Doctor Smith had quite a problem on his hands especially<lb/>
in view of the fact that the disease was not actually present which<lb/>
is a big factor in getting the cooperation of the people.</p>
<p>However he (Doctor Smith) has his index around 3 and everything appears<lb/>
satisfactory.</p>
<p>Recife (index about 2.7) is also making a good showing but that is an<lb/>
easy town to work since there is an abundance of water in about 50 per cent<lb/>
of the city limits.</p>
<p>After two years without a vacation I feel the need of some cold weather<lb/>
and on Doctor White's return I am in hopes to get away north - he really<lb/>
does not need me more since we have plenty of local Directors and they<lb/>
should be well able to carry on with an occasional word from Doctor White<lb/>
at Rio. Doctor White has not been well the past year here and I am in<lb/>
hopes he will be permitted to remain there some time for I am satisfied the<lb/>
cold air will do him a world of good.</p>
<p>I trust this finds you carrying on. A Happy New Year to Miss Carter,<lb/>
yourself and Henry - too late for wishing you all a Merry Christmas<lb/>
but no doubt you all and one anyhow.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01217034"/>
<p>RUA DA CAMELLEIRA, <unclear>N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>1.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></unclear> ANDAR</p>
<p>DEPARTAMENTO DE SA&Uacute;DE PUBLICA<lb/>
COMMISS&Atilde;O DA FEBRE AMARELLA<lb/>
BAHIA, BRASIL</p>
<p>TELEPHONE CENTRAL<lb/>
CAIXA POSTAL, <unclear>N.<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></unclear> 387</p>
<p>4.</p>
<p>Catharina is doing well apparently - it is interesting to know that<lb/>
nearly every state here has some Katarina or other- some indian<lb/>
maid or other who saved some shipwrecked person and helped establish<lb/>
this wonderful country. Iracema of Cear&aacute; is the most pathetic<lb/>
case it appears to me. &lsquo;The land of Iracema and the Carna&uacute;ba tree&rsquo;<lb/>
applies to all Cear&aacute; territory.</p>
<p>In spite of an occasional setback, as you state, I too, feel that we will<lb/>
win through. But Doctor, dont you think we should go slower and not<lb/>
rush in and out of a country? Just because we do not get reports<lb/>
of the disease for some months does not necessarily mean that the<lb/>
disease has been exterminated. For instance here - the city of<lb/>
Bahia was cleared up something over a year ago - it was as you well know<lb/>
the big endemic centre yet only this last October on getting rumors of<lb/>
the disease as being present in the interior I had no difficulty in<lb/>
finding it within 50 or 60 miles of here - it had been running about<lb/>
from <unclear>fazenda</unclear> to fazenda for some six months or more - in the region of<lb/>
Santo Antonio de Jes&uacute;s. It was one of your regional endemicity<lb/>
affairs. No doubt we still have cases there unrecognized, unreported<lb/>
or both.</p>
<p>Again thanking you for all your trouble in advising me as to some of your<lb/>
deductions, I beg to remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>E. J. Scannell</signed>
Doctor H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General,<lb/>
United States Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
