<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01215013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Theodore C. Lyster to Henry Rose Carter, November 18, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lyster, Theodore C.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01215013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-11-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Darling, Samuel Taylor</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Eugenia Hook</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="place">India</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">America</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-11-18">November 18, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01215013</idno>
<title>Letter from Theodore C. Lyster to Henry Rose Carter, November 18, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lyster comments on Carter's manuscript. He agrees with Carter's theory regarding the origins of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-11-18">
<head>Letter from Theodore C. Lyster to Henry Rose Carter, November 18, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01215013"/>
<opener>
Section III<lb/>
Below<lb/>
THEODORE C. LYSTER, M. D.<lb/>
EUGENE R. LEWIS, M. D.<lb/>
ISAAC H. JONES, M. D.<lb/>
SAMUEL D. INGHAM, M. D.<lb/>
<unclear>1020</unclear> WILSHIRE BOULEVARD<lb/>
LOS ANGELES<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1924-11-18">November 18, 1924.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. H. R. Carter,<lb/>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
2121 California Street, N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have read with great interest and delight<lb/>
Section III of the History of Yellow Fever. It has always been a great<lb/>
pleasure to read your articles in their course of preparation because it<lb/>
gives me a double standard from which to form an opinion. Your suggestion<lb/>
that I read the text and omit the foot notes is far easier said than done,<lb/>
however, I sincerely did my best to read the text, tempted at all times to<lb/>
stray to the foot notes, and on the second reading I settled down to<lb/>
thoroughly enjoy the article with the foot notes. While we were in Washington<lb/>
as a family we always had a great desire to be able to follow Florida Avenue<lb/>
from one end of the town to the other; on looking back, I do not believe we<lb/>
were ever successful, always at some point being diverted on to a side street,<lb/>
such as &ldquo;T&rdquo; street or &ldquo;W&rdquo; street. If you have tried this little stunt you<lb/>
will understand why I refer to it in connection with trying to read the text<lb/>
of your article without a diversion towards the foot notes.</p>
<p>It seems to me that you have covered the subject<lb/>
so thoroughly that it does not leave me much upon which to base an argument.<lb/>
As you know, with Dr. Finlay, I have always been inclined to believe the<lb/>
American origin. Now that you have assembled the facts, which I must admit<lb/>
as facts, I am beginning to fear that the Old World interpretation is the more<lb/>
correct. There are some points of special interest to me:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Your explanation of the reason for the<lb/>
mildness of the disease in the Negro is interesting and is in line with our<lb/>
knowledge of the lessened susceptibility of those who live in endemic centers;<lb/>
it seems strange, however, that they would not have acquired an immunity<lb/>
rather than a lessened susceptibility.</item>
<item>2. The absence of allied species of Aedes<lb/>
aegypti points strongly to an Old World origin of the yellow fever vector.<lb/>
Under this heading, do you recall whether any of these allied species have<lb/>
been used in the attempt to transmit yellow fever? I believe that the common<lb/>
Stegomyia of India is the lancellotus (I am not quite sure whether this is its<lb/>
technical name or not). It has always seemed strange to me that the disease<lb/>
has never spread to India from Africa, and it would argue against this allied<lb/>
species being a possible vector. I remember some time ago urging Noguchi to<lb/>
try out this Stegomyia of India, which came about after a discussion between<lb/>
Darling and myself as to why it has not played a part in the spread of yellow<lb/>
fever. As far as I know, Noguchi has not had a chance to do this.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f01215014"/>
<item>Dr. H. R. Carter.</item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>3. The historical close association<lb/>
in early times between tropical America and West Africa is certainly<lb/>
brought out well in your quotation from Governor Ovando's petition to<lb/>
Charles V in 1503. Certainly if Ovando complained of too many slaves<lb/>
in the colonies, there is little doubt that the slave trade had early<lb/>
been established.</item>
<item>4. Another interesting point is the<lb/>
absence of early Mayan and Nahuatl descriptions of yellow fever. While<lb/>
in Mexico in 1920, Mrs. Nuttall and I thoroughly discussed the possibility<lb/>
of Nahuatl literature having some reference to a disease such as yellow<lb/>
fever prior to the Conquest. She has so far been unable to locate any<lb/>
mention of disease which could be interpreted as yellow fever, which bears<lb/>
out your opinion.</item>
<item>5. The absence of yellow fever from Cuba<lb/>
for 138 years after its settlement is decidedly against even a possibility<lb/>
of an endemic Caribbean center.</item></list></p>
<p>When you have completed your notes for the<lb/>
West Africa side of the question, please be sure and send them to me before<lb/>
making me make up my mind. There are many points that are far from clear<lb/>
in the African situation which no doubt will be brought out in your notes.<lb/>
I will look forward to your article in the Annals of Tropical Medicine and<lb/>
Parisitology.</p>
<p>With best regards to Miss Laura, and tell<lb/>
her from me to so regulate your habits of life that you will go through<lb/>
this winter without endangering yourself <del>to</del><add>from</add> another pneumonic attack. You<lb/>
have now a mission to complete and it may take several years, and until<lb/>
that is done, you know, you must remain with us.</p>
<p>We have been having a little flurry of<lb/>
pneumonic plague, as you know. Perry was here, but I am sorry I did not<lb/>
have a chance to see him. I have been in hopes he would call me up. He<lb/>
may do so sometime when he is here in town. I would certainly like to<lb/>
see him again.</p>
<p>Love to Mrs. Gorgas when you see her, and<lb/>
best wishes to you and yours.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Theodore C. Lyster, M. D.</signed>
TCL:HH<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
