<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01217046">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 31, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01217046</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-12-31</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">El Salvador</name>
<name type="place">Honduras</name>
<name type="place">Nicaragua</name>
<name type="place">Guatemala</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-12-31">December 31, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01217046</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 31, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor discusses his yellow fever campaign in El Salvador; as well as the work of his colleagues in Honduras, Nicaragua and Guatemala.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-12-31">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, December 31, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01217046"/>
<opener>
-1-<lb/>
<unclear>6a</unclear>. SECCION DE LA<lb/>
DIRECCION GENERAL DE SANIDAD:<lb/>
Sub-Secci&oacute;n Especial de Lucha<lb/>
y Control Contra el<lb/>
AEDES AEGYPTI<lb/>
-----<lb/>
REP. DE EL SALVADOR<lb/>
C. A.<lb/>
----<lb/>
<dateline>
San Salvador,<lb/>
<date value="1924-12-31">December 31, 1924</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The Home Office cables that you do not endorse the Internittant<lb/>
Plan of Control in reducing the aedes aegypti in Salvador nor leaving this<lb/>
country for Guatamala.</p>
<p>I do not think that I have ever discussed with you this<lb/>
plan of control probably because I had never before found a place in<lb/>
which it was applicable and my motive here primarily was to increase<lb/>
efficiency rather than economy. The results obtained to date indicate in<lb/>
no uncertain terms that it can be safely apllied in Salvador.</p>
<p>Since your last <add>visit</add> to this <unclear>coast.</unclear> Salvador, more than any other<lb/>
Central American <add><unclear></unclear></add>, has advanced remarkably in road construction and in ex-<lb/>
tending her railroads until now one can journey east and west the entire<lb/>
length of the Republic c and by good dirt roads every village can be easily<lb/>
reached from the Capital or the nearest <unclear>railroad</unclear> station in one or two<lb/>
days. The railroads touch nearly all our key positions, only Gotera and<lb/>
<unclear>Chalatenango</unclear> being off the usual line of travel. I am calling these cities<lb/>
key positions for the time until our survey of the areas are complete, the<lb/>
history of the regions of which these cities are capitals is that the<del>y</del> only<lb/>
<add><unclear>people</unclear></add><lb/>
contract yellow fever when they come to San Salvador.</p>
<p>Salvador as you probably know is quite unlike other<lb/>
Latin Republics in that it is a <unclear>better</unclear> organized and the people respond<lb/>
more readily to the mandates of the Government. Many communities derive<lb/>
their water supply from streams which have been <unclear>dammed</unclear> and the water is<lb/>
carried to the community by underground pipes with taps located at <unclear>convienent</unclear><lb/>
places or else it has been <unclear>arranged</unclear> to empty into a public place and to this<lb/>
the people come daily for the domestic supply. The barrel is not <unclear>in general</unclear><lb/>
use in the interior towns and not very popular in the cities either. By<lb/>
<unclear>far</unclear> the most used water receptacle in the home is the <unclear>cantaroj or olla</unclear><lb/>
and this is not of large size either as compared with similiar <unclear>receeptacles</unclear><lb/>
found in Mexico and Ecuador. In the indian home one rarely finds more than<lb/>
one olla and away from the cities the indian homes predominate.</p>
<p>In the large cities we have to contend with the indoor<lb/>
pila but very few tanks and these only in the homes of the well-to-do,<lb/>
the poorer people here also resort to the cantaro or olla, again we have no<lb/>
haciendas comparable with those of Yucatan either in size or number of<lb/>
people maintained. Salvador is a <unclear>country</unclear> of urban population and governed<lb/>
directly by the <unclear>officials</unclear> and not by the &lsquo;haciendado&rsquo; which explains why we<lb/>
are able to secure almost complete co-operation by having local officals<lb/>
issuing proclamations. The failure to comply with the proclamation calls for<lb/>
a small fine which is increased in the case of refractory persons. Again<lb/>
Salvador is unlike other latin countries in that a fine imposed is collected<lb/>
from the highest to the lowest citizen, of course, great care is being ex-<lb/>
ercised to see that the system is not abused but I must confess that it had <add><unclear></unclear></add><lb/>
seemed feasible to me to conduct a campaign with a <unclear>system of fines</unclear> as an<lb/>
ally until I came to Salvador <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>here</add> it is an undoubted success.</p>
<p>In the early weeks of the present campaign I stationed men at<lb/>
all key positions which appeared to me to be favorable for the propogation of<lb/>
yellow fever and which gave a history of having had the infection in recent<lb/>
years i.e. San Salvador, Sonsonate, Santa Ana, Ahuachapan, Atquizaya,, the ports,</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01217047"/>
<p><unclear>6a</unclear>. SECCION DE LA<lb/>
DIRECCION GENERAL DE SANIDAD:<lb/>
Sub-Secci&oacute;n Especial de Lucha<lb/>
y Control Contra el<lb/>
AEDES AEGYPTI<lb/>
-----<lb/>
REP. DE EL SALVADOR<lb/>
C. A.<lb/>
----</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Cojutepeque, San Vicente, <unclear>Zacataxoluca</unclear>, Usulutan, San Miguel, then<lb/>
the twenty or more towns which feed directly into San Salvador. In addition<lb/>
to the foregoing I started men into the interior towns to make mosquito sur-<lb/>
verys as I could find no record <del><unclear></unclear></del> of this having been done before as only in<lb/>
t<add>h</add>is way could I know what the exact condition of affairs was.</p>
<p>As the mosquito survey advanced it became apparent that the small<lb/>
interior towns were not a factor, as, in many instances, no aedes aegypti<lb/>
could be found therein, in the larger communities but below the rank of a<lb/>
city it was noted that the permanent aedes aegypti breeding place was the<lb/>
public pila and this is especially true of the towns near the Capital and<lb/>
the emptying and scrubbing the interior of the pila has nearly extinguished<lb/>
the specie. It is fair to assume in these instances that the people were<lb/>
carrying larvae from the pila to their homes <unclear>hwere</unclear> many bred out but fortu-<lb/>
nately the vast majority of homes do not possess more than one water contain-<lb/>
er therefore it quite out of the question for the mosquito to establish a perm<lb/>
anent breeding place in such homes except the chance of forgotten vase, etc.<lb/>
and here the doctrine of chances <unclear>operates</unclear> against it becoming permanent.<lb/>
Salvador is essentially a country of people who just enough to continue from<lb/>
day to day but are seemingly unable to accumulate. And this factor works in<lb/>
our favor.</p>
<p>You will see that our problem is narrowing down to the cities and<lb/>
here again the old story of permanence attracts the aedes aegypti. In the<lb/>
established homes and by this I mean homes of the well-to-do, the water will<lb/>
be conserved in large containers such as the tank, pilas and the flower<lb/>
garden will have from ten to one hundred antguards protecting the flower trees<lb/>
and all of these ant guards were breeder until an order was i<del>n</del>ssued requiring<lb/>
their destruction. The fringe of the city is mosquito infested but does not<lb/>
have the permanence of the central area and can usually be eliminated for re-<lb/>
gular inspection after thwo or three vueltas. It may seem strange that barrels<lb/>
are not in use here but the fact remains that they are not popular possibly<lb/>
because they cost money and this the average Salvadorean does not have and<lb/>
possibly because the cantaro holding from one to five gallons answer their<lb/>
needs.</p>
<p>As stated <unclear>earlier</unclear> in this letter the first motive for adopting the<lb/>
intermittant control plan was to increase effciency at the same time it was<lb/>
obvious that if successful economies would be effected. With the permanent<lb/>
brigadas the results were not satisfactory as the native is unable to work<lb/>
well unless closely supvervised and this meant a larger foreign personel, and<lb/>
I was not planning for this unless it was absolutely necessary. There <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>are</add><lb/>
good reasons for keeping our foreign staff at a minimum. I had used Brigadas<lb/>
Volantes in Ecuador and decided to try them here. Our house index in the<lb/>
Capital was down to less than 2% and the key positions to nearly 5% and we were<lb/>
at the begining of the dry season and it appeared to me that here was the<lb/>
place and the time to <unclear>try</unclear> out again the brigadas volantes.</p>
<p>I was perhaps influenced in part by the observation that the Salvado-<lb/>
reans are a high strung independent people who like many latins are inclined<lb/>
to find fault with the firemen after the fire has been smothered and so it<lb/>
is in the present campaign, the weekly visits had begun to annoy the people<lb/>
altho I have no doubt but that they could have been continued but the ten-<lb/>
dency would have been for the <unclear>snnoyance</unclear> to increase until the Government had<lb/>
been appealed and the most probable results would have been an order to stop<lb/>
the visits<unclear>,</unclear> At first thought it may seem<del><unclear>s</unclear></del> that this is far fetched but the<lb/>
facts are that this Government still maintains that there was no yellow fever<lb/>
in the country, &ldquo;only a few suspicious cases&rdquo;. The physycology which prompts an<lb/>
individual to announce the elimination of an infection which he will not admit<lb/>
as having existed is to my mind one to be anticipated</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01217048"/>
<p><unclear>6a</unclear>. SECCION DE LA<lb/>
DIRECCION GENERAL DE SANIDAD:<lb/>
Sub-Secci&oacute;n Especial de Lucha<lb/>
y Control Contra el<lb/>
AEDES AEGYPTI<lb/>
-----<lb/>
REP. DE EL SALVADOR<lb/>
C. A.<lb/>
----</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>The report of our last inspection of San Salvador has <add>just</add> come to<lb/>
my desk and it shows the house index to be 0.41% and this after<lb/>
and interval of 21 days during which no anti-larvae measures were<lb/>
applied except for special inspections of places like hotels, pen-<lb/>
sions, stables soldier <del><unclear></unclear></del> barracks, jails and hospitals and<lb/>
school buildings which places I regard as requiring closer supervision<lb/>
in Salvador than the home. We stopt inspections in San Salvador<lb/>
on December 6th, the house index was 0.53%.</p>
<p>If Salvador were a country of tins cans, bottles and barrels, etc.<lb/>
I doubt if the Internittant control plan would be applicable but I<lb/>
think that if you could be here at this time that you would agree<lb/>
to this plan of control for the dry season at least.</p>
<p>From the records that I can gather <del>t</del>here the aedes aegypti index<lb/>
has <add>never</add> been very high, it is estimated that early in this year it<lb/>
might have been up to 20% house index in the capital and less than<lb/>
50% in nearby towns that had not been treated in the past two years<lb/>
or more.</p>
<p>The center of endmicity appears to have been in and around the<lb/>
capital with temporary centers in Sonsonate, San Miguel and Santa Ana<lb/>
to which place the infection had been carried at various times by<lb/>
the soldiers at least we can connect them up with certain outbreaks and<lb/>
trace the spread to other towns by their movements.<lb/>
I am quite convinced that the disease has been present here <unclear>contin</unclear>-<lb/>
iously for the last four years, the evidence is not complete but we<lb/>
are getting at it <unclear>piecemeal</unclear> and hope to complete the chain of events<lb/>
in the very near future.</p>
<p>My gneral plan is to maintain one and possibly two white inspectors<lb/>
in Salvador and as many native inpsectors as conditions indicate,<lb/>
the Chief of the Service is Doctor Carlos <unclear>E.</unclear> Larde' and he is quite<lb/>
competent to handle the situation with the two foreign inspectors and<lb/>
occassional supervision by myself. I will not be away from Salvador<lb/>
at any time over three weeks and I am quite sure that the work can be<lb/>
left in their hands for that length of time without slackening.</p>
<p>Mr. Hulse in Honduras is concentrating at Amapala, San Lorenzo and<lb/>
Nacaome, Molloy in Nicaragua will continue anti-larvae measures during<lb/>
a part of the coming year at least and Guatamala has indicated its<lb/>
<unclear>intention</unclear> to continue the present campaign. I the Government of Salva-<lb/>
dor will want to continue the present measures until the end of the<lb/>
next rainy season.</p>
<p>I will be glad to hear from you and to know your reasons en contra<lb/>
the internittant control plan.</p>
<p>With very best wishes for the coming year for your-<lb/>
self and Miss Carter, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>M. E. Connor</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
