<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01217027">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Samuel Taylor Darling to Henry Rose Carter, December 22, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Darling, Samuel Taylor</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01217027</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-12-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">South Africa</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-12-22">December 22, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01217027</idno>
<title>Letter from Samuel Taylor Darling to Henry Rose Carter, December 22, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Darling discusses pneumonia in South Africa and its transmission. He mentions the recent malaria conference and the paper that he presented.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-12-22">
<head>Letter from Samuel Taylor Darling to Henry Rose Carter, December 22, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01217027"/>
<opener>
ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF<lb/>
----<lb/>
FREDERICK F. RUSSELL, M.D.<lb/>
GENERAL DIRECTOR<lb/>
JOHN A. FERRELL, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE UNITED STATES<lb/>
VICTOR G. HEISER, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE EAST<lb/>
H. H. HOWARD, M.D.<lb/>
DIRECTOR FOR<lb/>
THE WEST INDIES<lb/>
MEMBERS<lb/>
----<lb/>
GEORGE E. VINCENT<lb/>
CHAIRMAN<lb/>
WALLACE BUTTRICK<lb/>
DAVID L. EDSALL<lb/>
JOHN G. FITZGERALD<lb/>
SIMON FLEXNER<lb/>
RAYMOND B. FOSDICK<lb/>
EDWIN O. JORDAN<lb/>
VERNON KELLOGG<lb/>
JOHN D. ROCKEFELLER, JR.<lb/>
WICKLIFFE ROSE<lb/>
VICTOR C. VAUGHAN<lb/>
WILLIAM H. WELCH<lb/>
EDWIN R. EMBREE<lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
FLORENCE M. READ<lb/>
ASSISTANT SECRETARY<lb/>
INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD<lb/>
OF<lb/>
THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION<lb/>
61 BROADWAY, NEW YORK<lb/>
CABLE ADDRESS &ldquo;INTERCOM&rdquo;<lb/>
STATION FOR FIELD STUDIES IN MALARIA<lb/>
AT LAKEBURG, GEORGIA<lb/>
S. T. DARLING, M. D., DIRECTOR<lb/>
<dateline>
Leesburg, Georgia,<lb/>
<date value="1924-12-22">December 22 - 1924.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Henry R. Carter,<lb/>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was very glad to get your letter this morning<lb/>
and the Xmas greetings for Mrs. Darling, the children and myself,<lb/>
and to learn that you are so well and as keenly interested as<lb/>
ever in epidemiology of pneumonia and malaria.</p>
<p>With regard to pneumonia on the Rand I performed<lb/>
a number of autopsies while I was there and found that the lesions<lb/>
were those of straight lobar pneumonia or empyema and meningitis<lb/>
with suppurative involvement of the accessory nasal sinuses and of<lb/>
the mastoid cells exactly what I found among the recently arrived<lb/>
West Indian negroes in Panama during the epidemic of pneumococcus<lb/>
infection there beginning in 1905. From the circumstance of the<lb/>
lesions and the involvement of the accessory sinuses and mastoid<lb/>
cells I assumed that there was first an infectious respiratory<lb/>
condition in the Rand just like what we had in Panama, besides<lb/>
in the barracks and in the mines there was a great deal of sputum<lb/>
in evidence.</p>
<p>Maynard's study of the incidence of pneumococcus<lb/>
infection in the mines showed that the disease broke out among<lb/>
recently arrived Kaffirs before they had actually gone to work<lb/>
underground. Noble and I investigated the recruiting of these<lb/>
Kaffirs and found that healthy recruits were mixed with unhealthy<lb/>
and diseased carrier<del>s</del> <add>repatriates on their way back to the <unclear>tracks</unclear> after working and becoming <unclear>infected</unclear> on the mines</add> at a compound at <unclear>Rosnagarcia</unclear>. The men at<lb/>
night indulged in tribal dances. Both recruits and carrier<lb/>
repatriates danced together in one compound and a couple of thousand<lb/>
or more overheated men drank water from the two or three only<lb/>
available water taps by placing the tap in their mouths. On the<lb/>
mines the black miner drank tea from the bottle recently used by<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01217028"/>
Dr. Carter<lb/>
Dec. 22-1924<lb/>
2<lb/>
the white miner who had sent his boy <del>to</del> &ldquo;up the drive&rdquo; with a tea<lb/>
bottle to be filled with water. At the shaft the Kaffir boys<lb/>
filled the bottle with water and drank from the water tap by placing<lb/>
it in their mouths. It was easy to see how the Kaffirs picked<lb/>
up pneumococci from the white miners. It was easy to see how the<lb/>
recruits in turn picked up pneumococci as well as meningococci and<lb/>
tubercle bacilli from the repatriates in the detention compound.</p>
<p>The Kaffirs did not <add>at first</add> suffer from <unclear>pneumococcus</unclear> infections in<lb/>
their kraals. They acquired them directly and indirectly from the<lb/>
white miner on the Rand. In the small commensal units,-barracks<lb/>
holding 10 or 12 men, the death rates were low. In the large ventilated<lb/>
barracks holding 60 men the rates were high for when infectious material<lb/>
entered the larger barracks there were <del>a</del> greater numbers of men to become<lb/>
infected.</p>
<p>At this stage of the investigation General Gorgas expressed the<lb/>
opinion that pneumonia rates began to improve in Panama after the men<lb/>
were scattered or permitted to live in cabins in the bush. This was<lb/>
entirely new to me. I had no data to confirm it and several years later<lb/>
in Panama Colonel Mason looked up the facts and told me that they did<lb/>
not bear out General Gorgas' contention. I have always believed that<lb/>
the epidemic wore itself out on the Isthmus because of lack of suscepti-<lb/>
ble new material. General Gorgas always maintained that scattering<lb/>
in Panama did the work. I recall very well the circumstances of our<lb/>
investigation and report of pneumonia on the Isthmus. As a matter of<lb/>
fact you did practically all of it and I merely contributed the<lb/>
pathological and bacteriological end. General Gorgas recommended<lb/>
in South Africa that the mine authorities place their Kaffirs in small<lb/>
barracks, but the mine authorities have been unable to do this because<lb/>
it would reduce the returns to the stockholders, and the mines, with<lb/>
a certain few exceptions, will not live long enough in a productive<lb/>
way to warrant such a change.</p>
<p>The conveyance in the Rand was a conveyance of pneumococci as<lb/>
I have described. These were derived in the first instance from the<lb/>
white man with <unclear>the</unclear> production of an infection of the respiratory passages<lb/>
including the accessory sinuses and mastoid cells, and involving the<lb/>
meninges, pleura, lungs and other organs, sometimes primarily and<lb/>
sometimes secondarily.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01217029"/>
<p>Dr. Carter<lb/>
Dec. 22-1924</p>
<p>3</p>
<p>I regret that I could not attend the Congress at Kingston. The<lb/>
summer's work at the Station here required my presence to study the<lb/>
problems and to give some instruction in malariology. About 55 persons<lb/>
have visited the Station the past year. Most of them stayed here for<lb/>
study.</p>
<p>In my discussion at the meeting at New Orleans on &ldquo;The Relative<lb/>
Importance in Transmitting Malaria of <hi>A. quadrimaculatus</hi>, <hi>A. punctipennis</hi><lb/>
and <hi>A. crucians&rdquo;</hi> I referred to your paper on &ldquo;The Effect of <hi>A. punctipennis</hi><lb/>
on the Natural Conveyance of Malaria Fever&rdquo; Public Health Report, April, 1918<lb/>
reprint No. 464, and I quoted your remark that &ldquo;to spend a dollar on<lb/>
sanitation and get less that 100 cents benefit is not only bad business<lb/>
but bad sanitation&rdquo;, and I then argued in favor of differentiating species<lb/>
and breeding places, determining the specific nature of the problem<lb/>
instead of attempting to use general measures,-in other words, species<lb/>
control or species sanitation. I know it will be difficult to get the<lb/>
engineers and the ordinary health officer to apply species control but our<lb/>
two years work here has shown that it is possible and I hope that the<lb/>
future will prove that it is practicable.</p>
<p>I shall be glad to read the biographical account of General<lb/>
Gorgas. Mrs. Darling will send it to me. I have always been curious<lb/>
to know what immediately led to the mosquito control operations in<lb/>
Havana. Was it on xx General Gorgas' own initiative or did it come<lb/>
from another person. I have heard that General Leonard Wood was the one<lb/>
who initiated the movement.</p>
<p>I hope to have an opportunity of meeting you either in February<lb/>
or May of next year.</p>
<p>With best wishes for yourself and Miss Laura,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>S. T. Darling,<lb/>
Leesburg, Ga.</signed>
STD:H<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
