<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01225002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from M.A. Barber to Henry Rose Carter, June 29, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Barber, M.A.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01225002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-06-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Hayne, Theodore</name>
<name type="person">Wright, Orville</name>
<name type="place">Rome (Italy)</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-06-29">June 29, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01225002</idno>
<title>Letter from M.A. Barber to Henry Rose Carter, June 29, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Barber queries Carter on the history of malaria in Virginia. He describes his anti-malaria work and his preparation for a conference, in Rome.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1925-06-29">
<head>Letter from M.A. Barber to Henry Rose Carter, June 29, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01225002"/>
<opener>
Malaria<lb/>
Barber<lb/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
<dateline>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
Greenwood, Miss. <date value="1925-06-29">June 29, 1925.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was delighted to get your letter June 22 and all the<lb/>
good information it contained.</p>
<p>About the <unclear>diminution</unclear> of malaria in the U.S. I was delighted to<lb/>
get the notes malaria Eastern Virginia following the Civil War and again<lb/>
following the introduction of tobacco culture. But I am not sure that I get<lb/>
the full reason for its increase at the time of discontinuing<lb/>
wheat culture in Virginia and the introduction of tobacco. <del><unclear>Did</unclear></del> Was this<lb/>
change associated with an economic depression? Did it coincide with<lb/>
reconstruction disturbances?</p>
<p>I am enclosing a rough-right-off-the-bat summary<lb/>
of what I shall try to get together for the Rome meeting on the<lb/>
subject: The Diminution of Malaria in the U.S. I chose that topic<lb/>
because I thought it would be of more general interest. I have a hunch<lb/>
that there will be some discussion on that topic at the Rome meeting. Maybe<lb/>
Roubeud will be there with his zoo hilic theory. AS you know, he holds<lb/>
that it is the increased prosperity of domestic animals and their<lb/>
stables, not of humans and their dwellings that has brought about the<lb/>
diminution of malaria in Europe.</p>
<p>I will make the paper short and will bring in something<lb/>
about the present economic status of the cotton plantation renters.<lb/>
A sentence or two about automobile ownership among them<lb/>
ought to interest the down-trodden of Europe? My <hi>Hayne</hi> is now with us<lb/>
and it will be part of his work to see with his <unclear>on</unclear> own eyes<lb/>
something about the status of laborers here. I do not know any other way<lb/>
of finding out what they eat, for example.</p>
<p>Yes, we are going on with the work on breeding places.<lb/>
Would like to get at the bottom of the matter, but may not get so far.<lb/>
Just back from Stuttgart, Ark. Immense numbers of Anopheles now breeding t<lb/>
there, apparently more than usual. Of many observations we did not see<lb/>
one Gambusia in the rice fields, although we found them in pools on the<lb/>
outside. It has been so dry this spring that <hi>fish-containing pools</hi><lb/>
were probably dry when the well water was brought onto the fields.<lb/>
We found some very alkaline water breeding heavily. And the species was<lb/>
now nearly all quad. Seems to be more quads there than in the Louisiana<lb/>
fields.</p>
<p>The John Scott medal ceremonies were very simple, for us.<lb/>
Just a bow-and-smile affair-no speech expected. Mine was for the invention<lb/>
of a method of isolating single microorganisms and of injecting<lb/>
microorganisms or chemical substances into living cells-work I did many years<lb/>
ago when I was in Bacteriology. I still use the method for<lb/>
some of my algal and infusoria <del>injections</del><add><unclear>inciations</unclear></add>. Dr. Chambers improved the methods<lb/>
so as to make it more practicable for microdissections, so the prize<lb/>
of $1000 was divided between us. He was not present at the Commencement-<lb/>
absent in Europe. Orville Wright was also an awardee but missed his train,<lb/>
and he was absent. My old friend Dr. Ross Harrison was one of the beneficiar<lb/>
ries and was there, also a Mr. Norton, inventor of a method of grinding steel<lb/>
which has made possible the present abundance of automobiles. If we had only<lb/>
gone in for automobiles instead of microbes! But the most enviable men there<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01225003"/>
Malaria (Barber)<lb/>
OFFICE OF<lb/>
MEDICAL OFFICER IN CHARGE<lb/>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
UNITED STATES<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE<lb/>
was a Penn Bishop of the Episcopalian church. He has a robe<lb/>
of Oxford resplendent with horizontal red stripes and he got<lb/>
a fine hood to go over it. We did not have to wear any special clothes.</p>
<p>I am afraid I cannot get hold of much definite<lb/>
information based on blood examinations regarding the decrease of malaria in<lb/>
the U.S. I shall be most glad of any suggestions you can make-you really<lb/>
ought to be the one to write the paper. Especially I should be glad to<lb/>
learn of places where there has been an increase or failure to decrease in<lb/>
malaria. I will continue to collect data on this matter, but have to<lb/>
get a sort of preliminary anyhow. I shall be most glad of your criticism and<lb/>
shall refer to your information freely in the paper.</p>
<p>With best wishes to you and Miss. Carter.</p>
<closer>
<signed>M.A. Barber</signed>.
Mrs. Barber and I would surely be delighted to stop in and<lb/>
see<lb/>
see you on our way to Italy, but do not know what will happen in the<lb/>
final rush. We will probably leave N.Y. Sept. 19th. I may take my<lb/>
annual leave, or what is left of it, in Italy and so return about<lb/>
the second week in November. I should like to see some of the malarious<lb/>
regions of Italy. I know some of the I.H.B. men who are working there.<lb/>
And do you suppose we will be able to get any light on the truth or<lb/>
falsity of the thesis: &ldquo;An Italian scientist never tells the truth<lb/>
unless he is drunk&rdquo;. Maybe Ronald Ross has some new data on this<lb/>
interesting topic.<lb/>
<unclear>Cause in Va</unclear><lb/>
mal in M.C.<lb/>
<unclear>M</unclear> after war<lb/>
Self &amp; family<lb/>
<unclear>Poor</unclear> drainage<lb/>
<unclear>for own up-stack</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Wheat</unclear> V. <unclear>Tobaco</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>it on. Depression</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Stand should W corn</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>hence Dec growth</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>stock ex</unclear><lb/>
<unclear><hi>cept. H. M,</hi></unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Main M.C</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Quantico</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Ross (+Marcon</unclear><lb/>
<unclear><hi>Witsny</hi></unclear><lb/>
<unclear>To shis - Pond</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>natalic</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>near Burmington</unclear><lb/>
(T. S &amp; I<lb/>
<unclear>&amp; pond- near</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Mong near Ponds,</unclear><lb/>
Hachett,<lb/>
<unclear>grassi</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>tell</unclear> adults<lb/>
in water &amp;<lb/>
<unclear>Hallard</unclear> &amp; <unclear>S. I'z</unclear><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
