<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01227003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, August 7, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01227003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-08-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-08-07">August 7, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01227003</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, August 7, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson informs Carter that he plans to go to Africa to fight yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1925-08-07">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Henry Rose Carter, August 7, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01227003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
ROOM 2701<lb/>
61 BROADWAY<lb/>
NEW YORK<lb/>
<date value="1925-08-07">August 7, 1925</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It is some time since I have written you, even though<lb/>
I have thought and do think of you every day. Now as you know I am getting<lb/>
ready for the African venture to &ldquo;do my bit&rdquo; in the last fight, as we all<lb/>
hope, against yellow fever. Naturally I always associate you with this great<lb/>
project. To conceive the idea of eliminating something from nature, wheter it<lb/>
be an evil or some other factor, to me appears one of the boldest of concepts<lb/>
which our profession has ever undertaken. It is a great thing, and you are<lb/>
seeing this now at a stage when it appears almost a certainty - a success.<lb/>
Personally I believe that it is only a question of about five years to the<lb/>
time when we can look back and see the thing as history. I feel considerable<lb/>
pride in having had a very considerable part to play in this work, and I some<lb/>
times wonder how it all happened. When I think of this phase of it I also<lb/>
recognize the source of the success I have had which has been the kind and<lb/>
friendly, fatherly advice which I have received from you. I want to tell you<lb/>
this now before I go away again, this time on a longer tour than I have ever<lb/>
taken before.</p>
<p>The program which I have adopted in the countries where I have worked<lb/>
has been shaped to conform with your ideas as closely as it has been possible<lb/>
to do so. As far as I have been able to determine all our work has been done<lb/>
to conform with your ideas and theories (theories which have been proven to<lb/>
be facts) and from the present indications with a successful issue.</p>
<p>I have preserved all your letters, and have translated into Spanish all<lb/>
your writings, i.e. the early ones, with the exception of the one on &ldquo;House In-<lb/>
fection&rdquo; which I have about half done but will finish it on the first opportunity.</p>
<p>Your letters and advice have been a great help to me, except for the fact<lb/>
that it or they sort of make me despair of ever attaining more than a very small<lb/>
fraction of the knowledge which they represent. However I expect to &ldquo;keep a tryin&rdquo;<lb/>
We cant all be great savants, nor can we do everything.</p>
<p>I should think that one of the great satisfactions which you have is in<lb/>
knowing that you have initiated a program which has been instrumental in the<lb/>
saving of thousands of lives in many countries; which has been a great boon to<lb/>
commerce and to seafaring men and all who visit the tropics, this especially<lb/>
as a result of your work in yellow fever. Your work in malaria also will go<lb/>
down to posterity as one of the classics, and I am not competent to comment on<lb/>
your other lines of activities which your own Service, The U.S.PH.S., always<lb/>
speak of with great reverence and respect. I have heard no other man in your<lb/>
service spoken of with the same admiration and respect as that with which they<lb/>
always speak of you.</p>
<p>Now before I am leaving I want to thank you for your very many kindnesses<lb/>
and helps to me, I am muchly indebted.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely a friend and disciple,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
