<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01223005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to L.L. Williams, Jr., April 26, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01223005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-04-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Williams, Jr., Louis L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Griffitts, T. H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Hayne, Theodore</name>
<name type="person">Von Ezdorf, Rudolph H.</name>
<name type="person">Darling, Samuel Taylor</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Talladega Springs (Ala.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-04-26">April 26, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01223005</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to L.L. Williams, Jr., April 26, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] discusses the comparative efficacy, as a malaria vector, of three main species of Anopheles mosquitos in the United States.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1925-04-26">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to L.L. Williams, Jr., April 26, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01223005"/>
<opener>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
2122 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1925-04-26">April 26, 1925.</date>
</dateline>
Surgeon L. L. Williams Jr., U. S. P. H. S.<lb/>
% State Board of Health,<lb/>
Richmond, Va.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Louis:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of April 7th. gave me great pleasure and I had ans-<lb/>
wered it sooner but for a couple of heart attacks forbidding all writing.<lb/>
This is dictated.</p>
<p>What you have to tell me about Virginia is surely interesting. Your<lb/>
statement that quads. were mainly responsible for the malaria in Virginia<lb/>
and that they were--so far as Virginia is concerned--practically a pond<lb/>
production is, I am quite sure, true; and while I know and have preached<lb/>
that there is considerable regional variation in the biology of Ano-<lb/>
pheles in the U. S., it is also measurably true for all parts of it<lb/>
that I have seen.</p>
<p>You will find your statements set forth or suggested in the report<lb/>
Of LePrince: Griffitts and myself on the impounded water survey of 1915.<lb/>
It was published in 1916. Also in a little brocheur attempting to eval-<lb/>
uate the proportional efficacy of quads and puncts in nature in the U. S.<lb/>
put out in the spring of 1917, beginning with the survey of the Camp<lb/>
Meade district and which should have been--but was not--accompanied with<lb/>
a map showing the relation between breeding places by species and mal-<lb/>
aria cases.</p>
<p>The first little paper is really of value in what it suggested--<lb/>
more it may be than in what it proved:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1/ That puncts produced earlier in the spring (first flight)<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01223006"/>
flight)<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
and later in the fall than quads.; the interval of time being considerable<lb/>
in both cases.</item>
<item>2/ That these species differed also in the nature of their breeding<lb/>
places: quads. practically confining themselves to ponds and large pools,<lb/>
including--it may be--seepage areas also; while puncts. were essentially<lb/>
stream breeders--taking also pools; cow-tracks <hi>et</hi>. <hi>al</hi> and little marshes.</item>
<item>3/ That during the day-light in summer weather puncts. were practi-<lb/>
cally not found within occupied residences of men: stables: cow houses:<lb/>
under railroad culverts and in cool places around walled-up springs: in<lb/>
woods and banks of streams etc. all being preferred by them.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The deduction was drawn that unless they came into residences by night<lb/>
and left them at day-light they would not be a serious vector of malaria<lb/>
as compared to quads. We had planned observations to determine if this<lb/>
occurred, as well as to determine if they had marked preference for the<lb/>
blood of animals as compared with that of man (Roubaud and von Wesselfeld--<lb/>
I think this is the name--had not then written). Leprince: Griffitts and<lb/>
Hayne got considerable-- though not entirely satisfactory-- data on the<lb/>
problem the next year, I being in South America. The War stopped all<lb/>
research on this problem.</p>
<p>Dr. (Miss) Ludlow, the Entomologist for the Army Medical Museum, was<lb/>
quite certain <add>that</add> they entered residences at night and left before full day-<lb/>
light, but had no sufficient evidence therefor. There is an Indian species<lb/>
that does this, however. Also they were found quite freely in residences<lb/>
in the spring and late fall,<lb/>
but were certainly not a domestic mosquito in the sense that quad. is.</p>
<p>As possibly you know, I have been pressing ever since that time:</p>
<p>1: To determine the comparative efficacy as vectors of malaria in na-<lb/>
ture of the three main species we have in the U. S. and if for any one of<lb/>
them this should be so low that it could reasonably be neglected to limit<lb/>
our control measures to those of which this was not so: their breeding hab-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01223007"/>
hab-<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
its being quite certainly so different that this could be done economically.</p>
<p>I have kept my eyes and mind open for this since that time, though only<lb/>
incidental observations have been made, until, I judge, last year.</p>
<p>In 1915 I had a perfect place for reliable and sufficient data by the<lb/>
dissection of puncts and quads. At Talladega Springs we had 100% infection<lb/>
of men (history index). Both species were abundant (puncts in excess) and<lb/>
I asked von Ezdorf if he could send Mitzmain up there to do this work.<lb/>
This, it seems, was not practicable and his work there later was only when<lb/>
malaria had enormously diminished and Anopheles of both species also.</p>
<p>I must confess, however, that I do not go as far as I understand Darl-<lb/>
ing and yourself went at the New Orleans Conference: I say &ldquo;understand&rdquo; be-<lb/>
cause I have received no account save a verbal report of this meeting, because<lb/>
I have seen some places un which there was considerable--or even much--mal-<lb/>
aria in which only punctipennis could be accused.</p>
<p>As a general rule, however, especially where money is scarce, I think<lb/>
that punctipennis may be neglected. Whether this is as true of crucians is<lb/>
rather more of a question. The sea-coast crucians, I think, have shown them-<lb/>
selves fairly efficient malaria carriers. Root says, however, that it is<lb/>
doubtful if they be the same species as the crucians in the higher country.<lb/>
Against this latter I have no data.</p>
<p>I would add two other things only to this matter:</p>
<p>1/ In attempting to determine if puncts. feed freely on human blood<lb/>
(I know the results obtained at Mound) LePrince and Hayne in 1916 found that<lb/>
all of the bites they received on porches, of which they could identify the<lb/>
species (110) were punctipennis. No bites received by them in the house.</p>
<p>Barret of Charlotte, however, a careful observer and most reliable man,<lb/>
reports himself and his wife both bitten in the house--in the spring, how-<lb/>
ever, by puncts. Not many times, however.</p>
<p>I am sending you a reprint of mine and an unfinished article that I in-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01223008"/>
in-<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
tended to read in Jamaica. I send the first simply that you may under-<lb/>
stand what the second means, for this latter only is concerned with Ano-<lb/>
pheles. When I got into the second paper I found that I did not know e-<lb/>
nough to make any wise a complete paper of it, and that even what I knew<lb/>
would make--with the other--a small book rather than a paper.</p>
<p>I am quite sure that an investigation as to the preferential and com-<lb/>
pulsory breeding places of the different species of Anopheles will well pay<lb/>
us. I think, however, that this had best be done incidentally, keeping one's<lb/>
eyes open while going about ordinary malaria work, for there is much to be<lb/>
done and few to do it, and done incidentally this way a good deal can be<lb/>
learned with <hi>no</hi> added expense. The object, of course, is to determine what<lb/>
breeding we can afford to neglect, remembering that we are not trying to<lb/>
<hi>eliminate</hi> even the vector species, only to control them so that there are<lb/>
left none of sanitary importance.</p>
<p>There are four points in the Impounded Water matter I feel an ob-<lb/>
ligation to take up<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1: The consideration of the effects which determine the production<lb/>
of malaria by impounding a large body of water:</item>
<item>2: The effect of filling the pond on the mosquitoes in a flooded<lb/>
area:</item>
<item>3: What influence--if any--does the existence of a pond have on Ano-<lb/>
pheles production outside of its flowage contour?</item>
<item>4: What deduction as to the effect of the pond production of its dis-<lb/>
trict can be drawn from a comparison of the production from the same sized<lb/>
area outside the pond and in the pond?</item>
</list></p>
<p>I am purposing to undertake this as soon as I finish a Section of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever History on which I am working. I think I will not make an ar-<lb/>
ticle of it for publication as it will require more pains and time than is<lb/>
apparently available therefor, but if I do not, it will be written out in<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01223009"/>
in<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
several copies and one sent you: LePrince: Griffitts and Maxcy. It will<lb/>
be more suggestive than determinative--I mean what I am going to write<lb/>
will be--and it will be up to you fellows to work it up.</p>
<p>Love to Gertrude: &ldquo;Louis-Lu&rdquo; and yourself.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly your friend,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
