<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01224011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from G. Jameson Carr to Joseph H. White, March 26, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carr, G. Jameson</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01224011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-03-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">White, Joseph H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">Parahyba (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Recife (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Campina Grande (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Itabayanna (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Natal (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Pernambuco (Brazil)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-03-26">March 26, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01224011</idno>
<title>Letter from G. Jameson Carr to Joseph H. White, March 26, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carr sends White his clinical history and autopsy report on a Brazilian yellow fever case and describes several other cases.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1925-03-26">
<head>Letter from G. Jameson Carr to Joseph H. White, March 26, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01224011"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
1.<lb/>
A<lb/>
Carr to White<lb/>
B<lb/>
From Dr G J Carr<lb/>
to Dr White<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1925-03-26"><hi>March 26th, 1925.</hi></date>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honour to submit the enclosed report of the autopsy on<lb/>
Robert Sherman, the second case of Yellow Fever which has died in Parahyba<lb/>
during this month.</p>
<p>I am also enclosing the letters of the President which are self-explanatory<lb/>
and show the cooperation which exists between the Authorities and the<lb/>
Officials of the Board, as represented by the Commission in this State.<lb/>
Already, as you know, scouting has been done by Dr. <unclear>Bi&atilde;o</unclear> in Itabayanna<lb/>
who will proceed to Campina Grande to continue his work, but the real<lb/>
offensive will be launched on Monday the 30th, by myself and Mr. Cabral<lb/>
in both cities.</p>
<p>By consulting the map it can be seen that Itabayanna is the key position<lb/>
on the direct line, Recife---Parahyba---Campina Grande, while Campina<lb/>
Grande is the key position to the entire central portion of the state.<lb/>
By an effective barrage being established at those points and Parahyba<lb/>
(Capital) I am of the opinion that infection can be prevented from spreading<lb/>
northward. As you have heard from Mr. <unclear>Tebyric&aacute;</unclear>, he has taken stringent measures<lb/>
to protect Natal, but I shall shortly include that city in my round of in-<lb/>
spections and make further report.</p>
<p><hi>EPIDEMIOLOGY</hi></p>
<p>Taking as a basis for my epidemiological study the findings og the &ldquo;Yellow<lb/>
Fever Commission&rdquo; to Quayaquil as reprinted from the &ldquo;Journal of Experimental<lb/>
Medicine&rdquo; June 1st, 1919, the following are the facts of the movements<lb/>
of the three reported cases in Parahyba and Recife, of the case reported from<lb/>
Triumpho in the State of Pernambuco I have no details but shall get them in<lb/>
due course.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01224012"/>
<p>COPY</p>
<p>2.</p>
<p><hi>O'Donnell</hi>. 1st case.</p>
<p>He was in Recife during the nights of February 22nd, 23rd, 24th, arriving<lb/>
there on the evening of the 22nd, and leaving the morning of the 25th,<lb/>
his movements there are in your hands.</p>
<p><unclear>23 - 26 To</unclear></p>
<p>In Parahyba the evening of the 25th, and that night slept in the Luzo-Brasi-<lb/>
leiro Hotel where he had had his room since December 1924.</p>
<p>He proceeded to Alag&ocirc;a Grande on the 27th, and slept there in the Hotel N&eacute;<lb/>
Costa returning to Parahyba on the afternoon of the 28th.</p>
<p>From that time until his death he slept in the Luzo in Parahyba and remained<lb/>
in this city with the exception of the two hours which he spent in Itabayanna<lb/>
on March the 1st, not including the time spent on the journey.</p>
<p>As you have read in my previous report his foreman states that he complained<lb/>
in Alag&ocirc;a Grande of &ldquo;headache&rdquo; and pains in the body" (27th-28th).</p>
<p>He was ill enough to stop work on the day of March 3rd, and was acutely<lb/>
ill that night.</p>
<p>Within these dates, taking the incubation period as from 3 to 6 days, he<lb/>
might have got his infection:</p>
<p>In Recife.</p>
<p>In Parahyba.</p>
<p>In Alag&ocirc;a Grande (this place least likely).</p>
<p>It must be remembered however the biting habits of the Aedes aegypti and<lb/>
consider the fact that the train stops for some time at Itabayanna during<lb/>
its passage from Recife from which place he travelled on the day of the<lb/>
25th, and being an official of the railroad he might have been in the<lb/>
station house, this they could not remember.</p>
<p><unclear>March 1 or 2 <hi rend="superscript">d</hi><lb/>
Feb Feb<lb/>
23 or 24 to 26 or 27<lb/>
Recife 23 &amp; 24<lb/>
Al- 27 &amp; 28 a day<lb/>
Paraheba 25 - 27 2d</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Gerifs.</hi> 2nd case suspect, in Recife.</p>
<p>This woman started definitely with a rigor on the night of March the 4th.<lb/>
In Timba&uacute;ba, a town in the state of Pernambuco on the line of the Great<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01224013"/>
3.<lb/>
Western and one station nearer Recife than Itabayanna.</p>
<p><unclear>F m<lb/>
26 - 1<lb/>
Feb. March 2 night<lb/>
no<lb/>
Itabay Feb 27-mal<lb/>
parchia Feb 25-26<lb/>
possible</unclear></p>
<p>She arrived in Timba&uacute;ba on the afternoon of March 2nd, from Itabayanna<lb/>
where she had been since about noon of February 27th, staying there in the<lb/>
&ldquo;Hotel Avenida&rdquo;.</p>
<p>She had stayed in Parahyba in the &ldquo;Pens&atilde;o D. Maria&rdquo; since the 23rd.<lb/>
Within these dates, she might have got her infection in,<lb/>
Parahyba,</p>
<p>Itabayanna,</p>
<p><unclear>night<lb/>
night<lb/>
no<lb/>
Feb 26-March 1<lb/>
noon appt<lb/>
I F. 27 - March 2<lb/>
Parahyba<lb/>
March 23-<lb/>
" <del>26+1/2</del><lb/>
night of 26 &amp; noon of 27</unclear></p>
<p>This case was, if a true one, very light, I myself saw her on the 13th,<lb/>
with no symptoms and the history of her medical attendants is both<lb/>
contradictory and, in the case of her urine, false in the second examination,<lb/>
and I was told her Doctor had never seen a case previously, while I am<lb/>
convinced that the Doctors of the Prophylaxia Rural are not competent to<lb/>
diagnose so light a case.</p>
<p>Furthermore a report of her blood taken by Dr. <unclear>Bi&atilde;o</unclear> and sent to Bahia was<lb/>
returned &ldquo;Negative&rdquo;, this latter however must be taken with due regard<lb/>
to the period of the disease and the known percentage of failures with<lb/>
a clear clinical picture.</p>
<p><hi>Sherman</hi> 3rd case.</p>
<p>This man arrived in Parahyba on the early morning of the 16th, complaining<lb/>
of a &ldquo;headache.&rdquo;</p>
<p>On the 17th, he sent for a Doctor, the rest of his clinical history I have<lb/>
already reported.</p>
<p>He had arrived in Itabayanna on the 16th, about noon and remained there in<lb/>
the Hotel Avenida until 2 a.m. on the morning of the 16th, when he took<lb/>
train for Parahyba, arriving about 7 a.m.</p>
<p><unclear>16 early<lb/>
10-13 (11-14)<lb/>
I? - 16<lb/>
" ? - 10-16<lb/>
R-9-12<lb/>
:.10:11.12<lb/>
9<lb/>
m. 10-13</unclear></p>
<p>He had stayed in the &ldquo;Recife Hotel&rdquo; Recife from the 9th to the 12th.<lb/>
according to an inquiry from the Director in Recife.</p>
<p>(From 4th-9th in Hotel Boa Vista, Recife.)</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01224014"/>
<p>4.</p>
<p>This case is more definite, within these dates he might have got his infection in,<lb/>
<hi>Recife,</hi></p>
<p><hi>Itabayanna.</hi></p>
<p>Taking all three,<lb/>
The lines of O'Donnell and the Gerifs case cross at <hi>Itabayanna</hi> and <hi>Parahyba.</hi></p>
<p>The lines of Gerifs and Sherman cross at <hi>Itabayanna</hi>.</p>
<p>The lines of Sherman and O'Donnell cross at <hi>Recife</hi> and <hi>Itabayanna</hi>. (The latter<lb/>
for two hours only in the case of O'Donnell).</p>
<p><unclear><hi>R</hi> - I improbable</unclear></p>
<p><hi>PROVISIONAL DEDUCTIONS</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Itabayanna</hi> would appear by the case of Sherman to be the most likely place<lb/>
in terms of the minimum incubation period, and in the case of O'Donnell<lb/>
<hi>Parahyba</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Recife,</hi> in the case of <hi>Sherman</hi> and <hi>O'Donnell</hi> in terms of the longer incubation<lb/>
while, <hi>Itabayanna</hi> in the former terms and <hi>Parahyba</hi> in the latter for the case<lb/>
of <hi>Gerifs.</hi></p>
<p><hi>FOR AND AGAINST THESE PLACES</hi></p>
<p><hi>Parahyba</hi>.</p>
<p>No cases reported for several years.</p>
<p>The index for the last 6 months.</p>
<p>The fact that both O'Donnell and the Gerifs woman had been living in the<lb/>
same hotel and <unclear>pens&atilde;o</unclear> previously, the former since December, the latter<lb/>
since February 8th to 20th. (vide previous report).</p>
<p><hi>Itabayanna</hi>.</p>
<p>An apparently confirmed death from Yellow Fever in May 1924 which had not<lb/>
been away from Itabayanna for two months previous to his death. The diagnosis<lb/>
however was not that of Yellow Fever at the time, and only now does the<lb/>
Doctor admit that it had the typical symptoms, this must be taken for what<lb/>
it is worth. No further suspicious cases are admitted to have occurred<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01224015"/>
5.<lb/>
either before or after this case.</p>
<p><hi>Recife.</hi></p>
<p>Known cases in the spring of 1924.</p>
<p>Known cases in the small towns along the lines of the Great Western Railroad<lb/>
together with actual epidemics in <hi>Caruaru</hi> and <hi>Alagoa de Monteiro</hi> and their<lb/>
immediate neighborhood, (vide previous reports.)</p>
<p>The great influx of &ldquo;<hi>Carnavalistas</hi>&rdquo; at these particular times after which<lb/>
cases began to appear outside as well as inside <hi>Recife.</hi> (previous report)</p>
<p>The <hi>index</hi>.</p>
<p>No cases have been reported since April 1924.</p>
<p>At the moment of writing no cases have been reported in Parahyba, which<lb/>
indicates that apparently the mosquitoes or mosquito which may have bitten<lb/>
either O'Donnell or Gerifs and caused their infection were not encountered<lb/>
here, while any which bit O'Donnell during his first three days, provided<lb/>
any did so, have not yielded secondary cases.</p>
<p>Neither Dr. <unclear>Bi&atilde;o</unclear> nor myself have been able to trace any cases in <hi>Itabayanna</hi><lb/>
I have not yet had time to examine <hi>Timbauba</hi> but this town would appear to<lb/>
be ruled out by the dates.</p>
<p>The Director of Recife has not reported any further suspicious cases having<lb/>
been reported to him.</p>
<p>As is well known up until the present the authorities of this district<lb/>
generally have made it difficult to get accurate reports of cases but I<lb/>
am glad to think that now they realize the urgency and, at least in Parahyba,<lb/>
will be more frank and cooperative.</p>
<p>I regret to say that, according to hearsay evidence, the Prophylaxia Rural<lb/>
is not in a position to give much assistance but at the present time we<lb/>
have established friendly and cordial relations, which I have always taken<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01224016"/>
6<lb/>
care to pursue.</p>
<p>With the President behind us I think I am justified in expecting a full<lb/>
measure of success in our new work and renewed vigor in our old endeavours.</p>
<p>I have the honour to be<lb/>
Sir</p>
<closer>
<salute>your obedient servant,</salute>
<signed>Sgd. G.J. Carr<lb/>
Director</signed>
The General Director<lb/>
The Yellow Fever Commission<lb/>
Brazil.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
