<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01226007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to M.A. Barber, July 30, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01226007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-07-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Carter, Laura Eugenia Hook</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Ohio</name>
<name type="place">Illinois</name>
<name type="place">Indiana</name>
<name type="place">Wisconsin</name>
<name type="place">Michigan</name>
<name type="place">Norfolk (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Portsmouth (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">Rome (Italy)</name>
<name type="place">Cairo (Ill.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-07-30">July 30, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01226007</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to M.A. Barber, July 30, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter describes malaria and living conditions in Virginia after the Civil War.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1925-07-30">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to M.A. Barber, July 30, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01226007"/>
<opener>
(Barber) (Malaria<lb/>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
2122 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1925-07-30"><hi>July 30, 1925.-</hi></date>
</dateline>
<unclear>(his last<lb/>
illness began Aug 1/25<lb/>
Retired<lb/>
23/ AU</unclear><lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Barber</salute>
</opener>
<p>I delayed answering your letter of June 29th. because both Laura and<lb/>
I were much pressed for time and I wanted to answer it fully. I cannot<lb/>
do this even now, but I have put it off long enough and I can give you<lb/>
two pieces of information for which you asked:</p>
<p>1: There was a great increase of malaria after the Civil War in my<lb/>
section of Virginia--just above tide-water. This country had never been<lb/>
free from malaria, but, on our plantation at least, it had not been of<lb/>
sanitary importance for a number of years. After the war several of the<lb/>
family had it: myself: <add>and</add> two little sisters, and it was fairly general,<lb/>
though not severe, all over our neighborhood.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Living conditions were hard. From the time Sherman went through,<lb/>
in April/65, we had no meat of any kind--save a few birds and two rabbits<lb/>
that we boys killed with stones (fire-arms had been taken away)--until<lb/>
November 18th. when we killed a wild hog (a descendent of tame ones) in a<lb/>
trap. We had a little flour and our family lived practically on partially<lb/>
spoilt corn (the &ldquo;nubbin pile&rdquo;--all the rest had been taken): potatoes and<lb/>
wild salad plants--especially water cress. In land our people were rich--<lb/>
there were some 1600 acres in this plantation<add>--</add>and I judge our neighbors fed<lb/>
no better than we.</item>
<item>(b) Ditches were filled up and cleared land overgrown.</item>
<item>(c) If Roubaud insists on it: Live stock had practically been removed<lb/>
Save mules and horses, however, they had never been housed and the latter<lb/>
not much<del>i</del> in the summer time.</item>
<item>(d) Quinine was scarce: high priced and difficult to obtain.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Malaria gradually disappeared here as the country resumed its former<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01226008"/>
Nata-<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
lie: Halifax and some others that I don't remember: Two associated with the<lb/>
formation of ponds: three, where there were old ponds, with the introduction<lb/>
of a considerable bodies of men presumably malaria carriers.</p>
<p>About your paper: &ldquo;A low malaria rate is possible where quads. are<lb/>
very abundant.&rdquo; True, but I think rather exceptional.</p>
<p>&ldquo;C. Diminution from change in economic status.&rdquo;</p>
<p>1. Disappearance in Middle West with disappearance of pioneer<lb/>
conditions."</p>
<p>Practically all of northern and middle Ohio: Indiana and Illinois<lb/>
where malaria was common was tile drained early.</p>
<p>Your 3rd. &ldquo;Present economic condition Delta cotton plantations.&rdquo; A<lb/>
comparison of the prosperous and unprosperous ones should give you dif-<lb/>
ferential data for argument. I have none on it.</p>
<p>Your &ldquo;<unclear>1N</unclear>&rdquo; that diminution of malaria coincides with improved living<lb/>
conditions both in the U. S. and Europe does not allow you to differenti-<lb/>
ate between the direct causes of this. Malaria is essentially a rural dis-<lb/>
ease, hence in agricultural communities. Improved living conditions of<lb/>
such necessarily imply increased prosperity, which in turn implies better<lb/>
farming--i. e. better drainage: better clearing etc. <add>and</add> in a dairy country--<lb/>
as southern Wisconsin and Michigan (once malarious) with large numbers<lb/>
of <add>housed</add> cattle.</p>
<p>The better nutrition of the people would also greatly assist the com-<lb/>
plete cure of those infected (See Yorke and MacFie's paper, and common<lb/>
knowledge) as would the better medical attendance that such people would<lb/>
receive.</p>
<p>I doubt if we can differentially evaluate these factors and theoret-<lb/>
ically their action in the diminution of malaria is by multiplication, not<lb/>
by addition and each one is greater than unity. Their combined action<lb/>
then would be decidedly greater than if any one of them were left out.</p>
<p>I myself am inclined to lay most value upon those that lessen the <unclear>pro-</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01226009"/>
pro-<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
duction of Anopheles and the access of Anopheles to <del>to</del> men, but un-<lb/>
questionably they together make an endless chain for good, accomplishing<lb/>
a result decidedly in excess of what any one would do. (See my little<lb/>
paper &ldquo;Malaria in North Carolina&rdquo; 1913 or /14, to which you refer).</p>
<p>From ponds breeding &ldquo;A. quad.&rdquo; I fear good living conditions give<lb/>
little protection. The same has been my observation against the Tide-<lb/>
water crucians--Root says a different species from the upland crucians.</p>
<p>2: The flat country around Norfolk and Portsmouth, Virginia, which<lb/>
used to be uninhabitable is now entirely tile drained and practically<lb/>
free from malaria. The living conditions, however, are good, although<lb/>
during the berry picking and harvest times the quarters are tremendously<lb/>
crowded: work is either very long or hard and they pay little attention to<lb/>
getting rained on.</p>
<p>3. Certainly the camps during the War were practically free from<lb/>
malaria. The nutrition, of course, was good, but the conditions were<lb/>
otherwise pioneer.</p>
<p>Labor camps, such as those at Crockett(?), Ark: at Electric Mills,<lb/>
Miss. and some others show practically no malaria after Anopheles con-<lb/>
trol, although it was abundant there before this with the same living<lb/>
conditions. I do not, however, understand you to mean that Anopheles<lb/>
control, even as a single factor, will not free a community from malaria,<lb/>
only that your question is whether that was the main factor in the diminu-<lb/>
tion which has taken place in the U.S. and Europe.</p>
<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
2 enclosures.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01226010"/>
<p>P. S.</p>
<p>A propos of your going to Rome, I understood from Hackett<lb/>
two years ago that the Italians have absolutely no faith in any method<lb/>
of malaria control save (a) general improvement in living conditions and<lb/>
(b) as an adjuvant to the use of quinine.</p>
<p>I think that these are adjuvants--very valuable adjuvants--to Anophe-<lb/>
les control--whether by control of production or control of access (screen-<lb/>
ing. I especially hold this for tropical conditions, possibly where one's<lb/>
nutrition is generally low from other infections or directly from the cli-<lb/>
mate--and in the direct effect of the climate I believe.</p>
<p>Be sure to stop by to see me, if only for an hour or so, as you pass<lb/>
by to New York. I want to talk differential conveyance and differential<lb/>
control of Anopheles.</p>
<p>Very truly your friend,</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01226011"/>
<p>Mem. for Dr. Barber.</p>
<p>1: In the country just north of Cairo, Illinois, in 1879 malaria<lb/>
was <hi>excessively</hi> prevalent. Few were living in that country save negroes.<lb/>
They only were farming it. The food in this country--I have eaten at<lb/>
their houses--was coarse <unclear>and</unclear> with little variety, but rather more than a-<lb/>
bundant. The houses of the whites were good to fairly good. Few screens.<lb/>
I visited it again in the fall of 1887. Malaria still prevailed here, but<lb/>
not more than 25% of what I had seen before. The negroes, who had cleared<lb/>
and partly ditched the land, had been replaced by white farmers. In 1910<lb/>
I visited Cairo a third time and was told, although I did not go up into<lb/>
the &ldquo;bottoms,&rdquo; that while there was malaria there there was no great deal.<lb/>
Very few negroes and the land was mainly drained. It was not a stock country<lb/>
corn and hay being the crops--the first mainly.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
