<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01232001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from H. Carter Redd to Laura Armistead Carter, December 2, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Redd, H. Carter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01232001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-12-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Laura Armistead</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">the Rockefellers</name>
<name type="person">Williams, Ennion G.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Hayne, Mr.</name>
<name type="person">Martin, James</name>
<name type="place">Ashland</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal</name>
<name type="place">Portsmouth, Va.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-12-02">December 2, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01232001</idno>
<title>Letter from H. Carter Redd to Laura Armistead Carter, December 2, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Redd discusses Carter's estate and mentions the appreciation of his work during a Kiwanis Club function.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-12-02">
<head>Letter from H. Carter Redd to Laura Armistead Carter, December 2, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01232001"/>
<opener>
Miscl-<lb/>
Carter Redd<lb/>
Life Insurance<lb/>
Waiver-<lb/>
SAMUEL R. CARTER<lb/>
WM. E. CRAWFORD<lb/>
H. CARTER REDD<lb/>
COMMISSIONERS IN CHANCERY, CIRCUIT COURT<lb/>
OF HANOVER COUNTY.<lb/>
<dateline>
CARTER, CRAWFORD &amp; REDD<lb/>
ATTORNEYS-AT-LAW<lb/>
700 TRAVELERS BUILDING<lb/>
RICHMOND, VA., <date value="1925-12-02">December 2, 1925.</date>
</dateline>
&amp;<lb/>
Ennion Williams' speech<lb/>
about Father<lb/>
<salute>Dear Laura:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your letter of the first and am extremely sorry<lb/>
to know that you are feeling so badly, but I do not wonder at<lb/>
it. The remarkable thing is that you have held up as long as<lb/>
you have. I hope you will soon be feeling all right and can<lb/>
get to work on your book as I know you are anxious to do. Aunt<lb/>
Mary told me that the Rockefellers also wished you to write a<lb/>
life of Uncle Henry. I, too, hope that you will be able to do<lb/>
this.</p>
<p>On last Monday night at our Kiwanis Club in Ashland, we<lb/>
had a &ldquo;Health Night&rdquo; and Dr. Ennion G. Williams, Health Commis-<lb/>
sioner of Virginia, made the speech of the evening, in which he<lb/>
referred to Gorgas and his work on the Panama Canal. He told<lb/>
how Yellow Fever had been practically stamped out, and then he<lb/>
stopped and said to the audience: &ldquo;It may be interesting for<lb/>
you to know that while Gorgas was an administrator, he only did<lb/>
the things that he was told to do by Dr. Henry R. Carter, a na-<lb/>
tive of your County, who was a short time ago laid to rest in<lb/>
your cemetery here. Dr. Carter was probably the most celebrat-<lb/>
ed scientest the world has ever known. He mapped out the work<lb/>
which Gorgas did. Dr. Carter was the moving spirit, who said<lb/>
what was to be done, and he, Gorgas, carried it out.&rdquo; He also<lb/>
referred to Uncle Henry's originating the ideas later carried<lb/>
out by Reed in the Yellow Fever work.</p>
<p>Coming back to yourself, I hope you will take every pre-<lb/>
caution possible and necessary to bring yourself back to your<lb/>
normal health again. You should do this not only for your own<lb/>
sake, but for us; and there is a big work before you which I<lb/>
pray you may be &ldquo;physically fit&rdquo; to do. I know that you are<lb/>
fitted in every other way.</p>
<p>I got the letter from Mr. Hayne with a $500.00 note pay-<lb/>
able to your order. I will have to advance this out of Uncle<lb/>
Henry's estate as I have only about $125.00 in bank to your cre-<lb/>
dit at this time. Shall I send this note on to you or keep it<lb/>
in my safe? In this connection, have you not the other notes<lb/>
given by Mr. Hayne, if any? If you have, and they are payable<lb/>
to Uncle Henry, they should be appraised as a part of his estate.<lb/>
If you have, and they are payable to you, then Uncle Henry's es-<lb/>
tate is not interested in them and would not have to include them<lb/>
in the appraisal. Have you any other notes, bonds or obligations<lb/>
of any kind due to Uncle Henry's Estate?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01232002"/>
<p>Page #2.</p>
<p>L. A. C.</p>
<p>I shall bear in mind Ed's expense and keep the money<lb/>
on hand to meet it. I got $100.00 through James Martin, and<lb/>
he writes me that there is some more coming from the Govern-<lb/>
ment later. He also said that all of the Portsmouth lots are<lb/>
sold; therefore, I did not have any taxes to pay in Ports-<lb/>
mouth this year and am awaiting the receipt of the further<lb/>
payment of Martin when collected by him, unless he will send<lb/>
it direct to you. I, like you, am afraid that he will have<lb/>
to pay it to me because the Government will refuse to pay it<lb/>
otherwise.</p>
<p>There are so many things we can think of which would<lb/>
have saved trouble if we had only known before. When I went<lb/>
to the hospital, I signed my name to checks, and showed Jen-<lb/>
nie where they were with directions that if anything happen-<lb/>
ed to me, to cash those checks immediately. Thus, she would<lb/>
have in her own name all money that I had on deposit immedi-<lb/>
ately available without waiting for her qualification and the<lb/>
giving of bond to cover it &amp; without the incidental legal red<lb/>
tape. She of course, went right up in the air and did not<lb/>
want to hear anything of the kind. I told her that I expect-<lb/>
ed to come back (as I did do), but she would find the simple<lb/>
little things that I had mentioned a great convenience and<lb/>
help and also a saving of money and time if anything should<lb/>
happen, and that such precautions did not hasten my passing<lb/>
out one moment, as she has since found out.</p>
<p>I am sending you herein a letter from the insurance<lb/>
company and a waiver for you to sign, after which I would be<lb/>
glad if you would send it on to Ed to sign. In further ex-<lb/>
planation of the letter, it seems that the insurance company<lb/>
is not sure of its position in regard to one of the policies,<lb/>
to-wit, the one in the old Washington Company, and wishes<lb/>
waivers by the heirs of Laura E. Carter (as a double precau-<lb/>
tion, I think) before they will pay the money over to me. I<lb/>
hope, upon getting these waivers, that I can then close up<lb/>
this insurance matter. It is hard luck that the first compa-<lb/>
ny in which Uncle Henry took a policy went bad and the one tak-<lb/>
ing that over went bad, and that the other company in which he<lb/>
took a policy also went band, and that the Metropolitan took<lb/>
over both. The Metropolitan, however, has made good with<lb/>
them and has informed me that there would be a little over<lb/>
$11,000.00 coming to the estate from these policies.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Affectionately yours,</salute>
<signed>H.C. Redd</signed>
HCR: CEH<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
