<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01238003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Mazyck P. Ravenel to William S. Thayer, April 26, 1926</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Ravenel, Mazyck P.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01238003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1926-04-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Thayer, William S.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Eugenia Hook</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Cumming, Hugh S.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1926-04-26">April 26, 1926</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01238003</idno>
<title>Letter from Mazyck P. Ravenel to William S. Thayer, April 26, 1926</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ravenel writes that he doubts the influence of Carter's work on Reed. He believes Reed was inspired by Finlay.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1926-04-26">
<head>Letter from Mazyck P. Ravenel to William S. Thayer, April 26, 1926</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01238003"/>
<opener>
Copy.<lb/>
(Confidential: not to be used)<lb/>
<dateline>
University of Missouri,<lb/>
Columbia.<lb/>
<date value="1926-04-26">April 26, 1926.</date>
</dateline>
Bacteriology and Preventive Medicine<lb/>
Dr. W. S. Thayer,<lb/>
1208 Eutaw Place,<lb/>
Baltimore, Maryland.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Thayer:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am very much obliged to you for your letter of April 19th., enclos-<lb/>
ing a copy of your letter to Miss Carter under date of April 14th.</p>
<p>I had the pleasure and honor of knowing Dr. Reed quite well and he<lb/>
told me personally a good deal about his work in Cuba, though I cannot re-<lb/>
call his having discussed the particular point in which I have been inter-<lb/>
ested. The information upon which I based my statements was not taken en-<lb/>
tirely from Kelly's book, though I did consult it and used some of the<lb/>
statements made by Reed himself which Dr. Kelly reproduced. I, therefore,<lb/>
do not think that anything I took from Kelly's book is misleading, or that<lb/>
I have obtained any incorrect ideas from it.</p>
<p>I knew Dr. Carter for a great many years and was one of his great<lb/>
admirers. I would, therefore, be the last one to wish to belittle anything<lb/>
that he did, and my own interest in this entire matter has been to get the<lb/>
truth. I wrote a letter to &ldquo;Science&rdquo; hoping that it would bring out corres-<lb/>
pondence and possibly some definite facts which would prove the matter one<lb/>
way or the other. After the material was in print, I determined to suppress<lb/>
it on account of the letters from Miss Carter and other material sent to<lb/>
me by General Cumming. Professor Cattell has asked me to write more fully<lb/>
on the subject and sometime or other I may do so, though probably I will not.</p>
<p>The matter seems to me to be entirely beyond an absolute settlement.<lb/>
Reed told me personally, what he published a number of times, that he went<lb/>
to Finlay, got all of his ideas, and even the larvae from which the experi-<lb/>
mental mosquitoes were grown. It is, therefore, inconceivable that Reed did<lb/>
not know all of Finlay's work. It is equally inconceivable to me that a man<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01238004"/>
Dr. "W. S. Thayer<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
April 26, 1926<lb/>
(Copy: confidential)<lb/>
man<lb/>
like Reed would start on an investigation of this kind without a full knowl-<lb/>
edge of all that had been done before, but in this I may be mistaken. You<lb/>
will remember also Reed's own account of the death of the prisoner from<lb/>
yellow fever, one of a half dozen or more who had been confined in a small<lb/>
jail for approximately the same length of time, and none of whom had been ex<lb/>
posed to infection, as it was then understood. Reed surmised that the only<lb/>
possible source of infection was an insect which could have gotten in through<lb/>
the window.</p>
<p>I do not bring these things up to argue over the facts you have given<lb/>
me, and I am entirely disposed to accept all that you say without question.<lb/>
I am entirely willing to believe that Carter's observations had much to do<lb/>
with Reed's latter investigation, but it seems to me equally clear that other<lb/>
things influenced him also. It seems to me that we are entirely in accord,<lb/>
as far as the facts go. You admit that &ldquo;there is not the slightest doubt&rdquo;<lb/>
that Finlay's observation led them to study the mosquito at the outset, and<lb/>
this I know also from Reed's own lips.</p>
<p>I wonder if General Cumming ever showed Miss Carter the obituary notice<lb/>
I wrote for the A. J. P. H. of her Father? I asked him to show it to her as<lb/>
I was satisfied that it would show her that I was not trying to detract from<lb/>
the excellent work he did. If you have not read it yourself, I wish you<lb/>
would do so. It is in November, 1925, issue of the A. J. P. H., page 994.</p>
<p>I would like to discuss this matter further in the public prints for the<lb/>
sake of getting all of the material possible on it, but I can readily under-<lb/>
stand how Miss Carter and other members of the family feel, and I would not<lb/>
for the world do anything to hurt them, so that for the present at least, I<lb/>
have decided not to say anything more about it.</p>
<p>With kind regards and thanking you, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Mazyck P. Ravenel,<lb/>
Mazyck P. Ravenel, M. D.</signed>
MPR:LP<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I have always felt that Finlay had been unjustly deprived of credit due<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
