<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01234001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter to M.A. Barber, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01234001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Barber, M.A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-00-00">1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01234001</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter to M.A. Barber, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter discusses life in Virginia, between 1865 and 1870.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1925-00-00">
<head>Memorandum from Henry Rose Carter to M.A. Barber, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01234001"/>
<p>/LC</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head>Memoranddum for Dr. M. A. Barber, 1925.</head>
<item>1: There was a great increase of malaria after the Civil War<lb/>
in my section of Virginia--just above tide-water. This country had never<lb/>
been free from malaria, but, on our <unclear>poantation</unclear> at l ast, it had not<lb/>
been of sanitary importance for a number of years. After the war several<lb/>
of the family had it: myself and two little sisters, and it was fairly<lb/>
general, though not severe, all over our neighborhood.</item></list>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Living conditions were hard. From the time <del>Sherman</del><add>Sheridan</add> went<lb/>
through, in April 1865, we had no meat of any kind--save a few birds and<lb/>
rabbits that we boys killed with stones (fire-arms had been taken away)<lb/>
until November 18th., when we killed a wild hog (a descendent of tame<lb/>
ones) in a trap. We had a little flour and our family lived practically<lb/>
on partially spoilt corn (the &ldquo;nubbin pile&rdquo;--all the rest had been taken)<lb/>
potatoes and wild salad plants--especially water cress. In land our<lb/>
people were rich--there were wome 1,600 acres in this palntation--and I<lb/>
judge our neighbors fed no better than we.</item>
<item>(b) Ditches were filled up and cleared land overgrown.</item>
<item>(c) Live stock had practically been removed. Save mules and<lb/>
horses, however, they had never been housed and the latter not much in<lb/>
the summer time.</item>
<item>(d) Quinine was scarce: high priced and difficult to obtain.<lb/>
Malaria gradually disappeared here as the country resumed its former<lb/>
status, retreating toward the east.</item></list>
<list type="ordered">
<item>2: Up to about 1870 our country was mainly engaged in the<lb/>
raising of wheat as a money crop, considerable corn, however, being also<lb/>
raised for the horses and mules used to plow for the wheat. With the<lb/>
opening up of the North-West (Minnesota and Dakota) as wheat States and<lb/>
the drop in transportation rates on the land-grant roads from this sec-<lb/>
tion and from Iowa about this time, wheat was no longer profitable in<lb/>
Virginia and was, to an extent, substituted by tobacco and by cattle.</item>
</list></p>
<pb n="2" id="f01234002"/>
<p>cattle</p>
<p>-(2)-</p>
<p>Naturally this led (a) to economic depression: (b) to<lb/>
neglect of drainage and growing up of cultivated land---especially low<lb/>
land. Wheat was raised on fairly high--always well drained--land, corn,<lb/>
indeed, on low ground, but, little corn being now needed, much of this<lb/>
was also turned out. (c) Cattle were increased, but were not housed in<lb/>
summer. Quinine if anything cheaper. (d) A decided diminution in<lb/>
poputlation.</p>
<p>Malaria increased considerably. Not to the same extent as<lb/>
directly after the war, but it has continued more or less ever since<lb/>
as have, indeed, the other conditions.</p>
<p>Take your choice as to the weight of the different factors.<lb/>
We thought--and I still think--the abandonment of the land, and especially<lb/>
of the bottome land, leading to poor drainage, was the most efficient.<lb/>
Tobacco, <del><unclear></unclear></del> you know, is cultivated only on well drained land and usu-<lb/>
ally in small patches as one cannot attend to a large area.</p>
<p>(Signed) H. R. Carter.</p>
<p>Memorandum (No. 2) for Dr. Barber.</p>
<p>In the country just north of Cairo, Illinois, in 1879, malaria<lb/>
was <hi>excessively</hi> <add>prevalent.</add> <del>preveldnore</del> <add>Few were</add> living in that country save negroes. They<lb/>
only were farming it. The food in this country--I have eaten at their<lb/>
houses--was coarse and with little variety, but rather more than abundant.<lb/>
The houses of the whites were good to fairly good. Few screens. I visited<lb/>
it again in the fall of 1887. Malaria still prevailed here, but not more<lb/>
than 25% of what I had seen before. The negroes, who had cleared and part<lb/>
ly ditched the land, had been replaced by white farmers. In 1910 I visit-<lb/>
ed Cairo a third time, and was told, although I did not go up into the<lb/>
&ldquo;bottoms,&rdquo; that while there was malaria there, there was no great deal.<lb/>
Very few negroes and the land was mainly drained. It was not a stock<lb/>
country, corn and hay being the crops--the first mainly.</p>
<closer>
<signed>H. R. C.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
