<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01308008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Blanton P. Seward to Laura Armistead Carter, November 27, 1931</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Seward, Blanton P.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01308008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1931-11-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Laura Armistead</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Strobel, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Nott, Josiah C.</name>
<name type="person">Bell, Agrippa Nelson</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Redd, H. Carter</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1931-11-27">November 27, 1931</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01308008</idno>
<title>Letter from Blanton P. Seward to Laura Armistead Carter, November 27, 1931</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Seward inquires about maritime quarantine regulations. He also requests information regarding Henry Carter's opinion of Strobel's, Nott's and Nelson's yellow fever work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1931-11-27">
<head>Letter from Blanton P. Seward to Laura Armistead Carter, November 27, 1931</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01308008"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
LEWIS-GALE HOSPITAL<lb/>
ROANOKE, VIRGINIA<lb/>
<date value="1931-11-27">November 27, 1931.</date>
</dateline>
DEPARTMENT OF SURGERY<lb/>
W. R. WHITMAN, M. D.<lb/>
PAUL DAVIS, M. D.<lb/>
M. A. JOHNSON, JR., M. D.<lb/>
UROLOGY<lb/>
S. BEVERLY CARY, M. D.<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF INTERNAL MEDICINE<lb/>
C. D. NOFSINGER, M. D.<lb/>
D. P. SEWARD, M. D.<lb/>
<unclear>ROENTOEXOLOGY</unclear><lb/>
J. T. McKINNEY, M. D.<lb/>
Miss Laura A. Carter,<lb/>
2030 Highland Ave.,<lb/>
Birmingham, Ala.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Carter:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you so much for loaning me the reprint of the editorial<lb/>
concerning your father. No doubt you have been thinking that I would not<lb/>
return it since I have kept it so long. I have been looking over other<lb/>
references and was delayed in getting to it. I appreciate very much the<lb/>
use of it and I hope my tardiness in returning it to you has not<lb/>
interrupted any of your work.</p>
<p>Dr. Carter was one of the world's great men; the work he did<lb/>
in preventing yellow fever and malaria was of inestimable value. Some day<lb/>
I presume a biography of him will be written and I am quite sure it will<lb/>
be an interesting one. Perhaps you are working on it. As soon as I get a<lb/>
chance I shall read the book which was begun by your father. I am sure it<lb/>
is a valuable one, both from a historical and epidemiological standpoint.<lb/>
I shall mention his work in my paper.</p>
<p>Near the end of the first column on the second page of the<lb/>
editorial it is stated that &ldquo;Regulations having been issued,----there was<lb/>
thus begun under his charge the present system of maritime quarantine by the<lb/>
service.&rdquo; Did that apply to quarantine of ships carrying yellow fever until<lb/>
the disease was eradicated, or to maritime quarantine in general? If it<lb/>
applied to the latter, do you know whether the same system is employed now,<lb/>
sixteen years after the editorial was written?</p>
<p>What opinion did your father have of the work of Strobel, of<lb/>
South Carolina, Josiah C. Nott and Agrippa Nelson Bell? Strobel wrote an<lb/>
interesting article on yellow fever about 1840, but he thought that the<lb/>
disease was conveyed by fomites. Nott believed that insects, &ldquo;animalcules&rdquo;,<lb/>
had something to do with the spread of the disease, but he did not say<lb/>
anything, as far as I have learned, about the mosquito being the inter-<lb/>
mediary host. As Dr. Robert Wilson stated in his article, &ldquo;Dr. J. C. Nott<lb/>
and the Transmission of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, in the September issue of the Annals<lb/>
of Medical History, one wonders how Nott failed to associate the disease with<lb/>
the mosquito. Bell believed that yellow fever was transmitted by fomites.<lb/>
However, he was one of the first, if not the first, to believe in strict<lb/>
quarantine for the prevention of the spread of the disease. As you know, he<lb/>
discovered the value of steam as a disinfecting agent in 1848, and put it to<lb/>
use on the vessels, the &ldquo;Vixen&rdquo; and the &ldquo;Mahones&rdquo;. After that time he<lb/>
believed that disinfection by steam should be employed along with quarantine.<lb/>
He also believed that sulphur in the proportion of 3-4 pounds to 1000 square<lb/>
feet was efficient for fumigating purposes. As far as I have learned Bell<lb/>
was the first to disinfect ships, so he might be called the originator of<lb/>
maritime sanitation. Is that correct? I have made notes on the work of each<lb/>
of those three men to be included in my article.</p>
<p>If you have reprints of Dr. Carter's articles, &ldquo;The Interval<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01308009"/>
LEWIS-GALE HOSPITAL<lb/>
ROANOKE, VIRGINIA<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF SURGERY<lb/>
W. R. WHITMAN, M. D.<lb/>
PAUL DAVIS, M. D.<lb/>
M. A. JOHNSON, JR., M. D.<lb/>
<unclear>UROLOGY</unclear><lb/>
S. BEVERLY CARY, M. D.<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF INTERNAL MEDICINE<lb/>
C. D. NOFSINGER, M. D.<lb/>
D. P. SEWARD, M. D.<lb/>
<unclear>ROENTOEXOLOGY</unclear><lb/>
J. T. McKINNEY, M. D.<lb/>
Miss Carter - 2<lb/>
between Infecting and Secondary Cases of Yellow Fever&rdquo;; &ldquo;The Extrinsic<lb/>
Incubation of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, and &ldquo;The Effect of Impounded Water on the<lb/>
Incidence of Malaria&rdquo;, I shall appreciate it if you will loan them to me.<lb/>
I should like very much to read them. Which one of the two articles on<lb/>
yellow fever led Reed and his co-workers to believe that the disease was<lb/>
conveyed by a host, or did both play an equal part?</p>
<p>The editorial stated that in 1904 Dr. Carter's name was<lb/>
presented conjointly with that of Finlay, for the Nobel prize. I presume<lb/>
that prize was awarded.</p>
<p>After the cause of yellow fever was discovered, measures were<lb/>
instituted for its eradication. No doubt Dr. Carter played a large part in<lb/>
the institution of those measures, both in Cuba and in Panama. Do you<lb/>
recall how long he was in Cuba and what the nature of his work was during<lb/>
the five years he spent in Panama?</p>
<p>You were kind enough to ask for a reprint of my paper. I will<lb/>
be glad to send you one, although it will be several months before it will<lb/>
be completed. I am writing on the &ldquo;Contributions of Southern Men to<lb/>
Medicine and the Natural Sciences&rdquo;, and my progress on it is slow because<lb/>
the references are scattered and it takes a great deal of time even after<lb/>
locating the references to go over them and to evaluate them. The article<lb/>
has already attained greath length and there is much more to be added.</p>
<p>About a year before I came to Roanoke I met your cousin, Mr.<lb/>
Carter Redd, of Richmond. I saw him a number of times and became very fond<lb/>
of him. I remember hearing him say that he was a nephew of Dr. Carter and<lb/>
was named for him.</p>
<p>Sometime when you come to Virginia you no doubt will be passing<lb/>
through Roanoke, and when you do so I hope you will let me know as I<lb/>
should like very much to have the pleasure of meeting you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed><unclear>Blanton P. Seward</unclear></signed>
BPS/h<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
