<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01307001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to William S. Thayer, September 26, 1930</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01307001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1930-09-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Thayer, William S.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Wade Hampton</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Brown, Miss</name>
<name type="person">Redd, Henry Carter</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1930-09-26">September 26, 1930</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01307001</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to William S. Thayer, September 26, 1930</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Laura Carter writes that she is thankful the work on her father's book is complete. She comments on her financial situation and her health.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1930-09-26">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to William S. Thayer, September 26, 1930</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01307001"/>
<opener>
Miscl <unclear>Thayer<lb/>
File.</unclear><lb/>
Carbon<lb/>
<dateline>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
2122 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1930-09-26">September 26, 1930.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Thayer:</salute>
</opener>
<p>When last I had the privelege of seeing you, you asked me to<lb/>
promise to write you frankly this fall just how things would be with me<lb/>
when the work on Father's book was completed.</p>
<p>I am profoundly thankful to be able to tell you that the work is<lb/>
really completed, save for a few minor details, Dr. Frost having devoted<lb/>
the greater part of the past few months to the completion of the final edit-<lb/>
ing. Indeed, I trust that by the time this letter reaches you, the MS,<lb/>
maps, tracings etc. will all be on their way to New York. <del><unclear></unclear></del> in advance<lb/>
of &ldquo;the October meeting <unclear>of</unclear> the Board.&rdquo; Just when this occurs, I do not<lb/>
know, but I judge that at that time everything left to be decided on about<lb/>
the book will be finally settled.</p>
<p>Dr. Frost has done a <hi>beautiful</hi> piece of work, as was, of course,<lb/>
to have been expected. In the <unclear>truest</unclear> sense of the word, then: &ldquo;<hi>it is well</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
with <add><unclear>me,</unclear></add> although by no means so well as if the work could have been completed<lb/>
at the time of our original estimate. The many unavoidable delays will<lb/>
always be a source of profound regret to me: a regret far more keen on ac-<lb/>
count of disappointing the expectations of our friends of the Rockefeller<lb/>
Foundation (who had made the work possible) than for its effect on my-<lb/>
self. It has been, however, a solace during this time of anxiety and stress,<lb/>
to realize that the MS of the book (as Father left it) was always available<lb/>
to them for reference, even though the book &ldquo;as Father wished it&rdquo; was de-<lb/>
layed.</p>
<p>As to myself, I should <del><unclear></unclear></del> like to take back my promise to<lb/>
you and end my letter <hi>here</hi> with the tidings I know will be so welcome to<lb/>
you! Happy Pheidippides! The &ldquo;anti-climax of the future,&rdquo; presented no<lb/>
problem to him, no solicitude to his friends! For myself, owing to cir-<lb/>
cumstances beyond anyone's control, it seems inevitable that my future will<lb/>
be somewhat in the nature of an anti-climax.</p>
<p>When Father decided to take up the work on the book (which he did<lb/>
with my most whole-hearted assent!) he told me that he expected that its<lb/>
completion (or the completion of so much of it as was possible to him)<lb/>
would &ldquo;about use up our joint working capacity.&rdquo; This, however, seemed the<lb/>
best use to which we could put our combined efforts and I shall always be<lb/>
thankful for his decision. At first Father was unwilling to receive<del><unclear>d</unclear></del> re-<lb/>
muneration for his work (lest he die before completing enough of it to be<lb/>
of use). Later, through the delicacy and generosity of Dr. Rose and Dr.<lb/>
Russell the matter of salary was settled on a basis which he felt he could<lb/>
accept, and Father was able (prior to developing angina) to add materially<lb/>
to his savings, which was a great comfort to him on my account. At this<lb/>
time Father expected to leave me about $235.00 a month. Later, after he<lb/>
developed angina, our living expenses in Washington were greatly increased.<lb/>
This was chiefly on account of having to give up our rooms in the little<lb/>
frame house on California St., and taking an apartment at the Westmoreland.<lb/>
Here the elevator service made it possible for Father to get out of doors<lb/>
and continue his work at the Library of Congress when necessary. This<lb/>
did not often happen, as he had the privelege of using most of the Library <unclear>b</unclear><lb/>
books at home. There were times, however, when he felt it essential to his<lb/>
work to go to the Library in person.</p>
<p>Father's last illness too was a time when we had to draw heavily<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01307002"/>
heavily<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
upon our resources, but, thanks to the forethought of the arrangement<lb/>
made about his salary, this could be readily done. That it would have<lb/>
been done in any event is true. Still, I shall always be grateful <add><unclear>that</unclear></add>, it re-<lb/>
lieved him of material anxieties during that long and dreadful time.</p>
<p>After Father's death, when my health was considered sufficiently<lb/>
improved for me to resume work on the preparation of Father's MS for<lb/>
publication (for which privelege I shall always be grateful to Dr. Vincent)<lb/>
it was again necessary (despite the generosity of the International Health<lb/>
Board) for me to go into my capital on several occasions: Twice on account<lb/>
of <del><unclear></unclear></del> long illnesses (on sick leave without pay) and at other times on<lb/>
account of matters (inherited responsibilities etc.) which I paid to have<lb/>
handled by others, in order to keep all of my time free, in anticipation<lb/>
of the early completion of the book. A bad bargain, as things turned out.<lb/>
Still, Father had been brilliantly successful in &ldquo;buying time&rdquo; (from his<lb/>
own capital) to press the yellow fever work in Peru, and I felt that I could<lb/>
do no less if, by thus pushing aside all personal problems, I could keep<lb/>
my time entirely free for the book.</p>
<p>Also, from January 1, 1930 to September 1, 1930 I have been going<lb/>
regularly into my capital each month in order to keep my apartment at the<lb/>
Westmoreland, with its office equipment in connection with the book, as<lb/>
a &ldquo;workshop&rdquo; for Miss Brown and myself. This, in anticipation of the<lb/>
&ldquo;winding up&rdquo; of details in connection with the final editing. This ex-<lb/>
tra inroad into my capital has been necessary, in order to keep the apart-<lb/>
ment, because, in the expectation that the book would go to press before<lb/>
the end of 1929, there was no budget item for my salary, on a half pay<lb/>
basis, for 1930. This was perfectly natural, as we all thought that the<lb/>
book would go to press before the end of 1929 and I consider it a privelege<lb/>
to have been able to continue my share of the work under any conditions.<lb/>
However, on my return from a stay of several weeks in Baltimore this Au-<lb/>
gust (during which time the book had reached an almost completed form) I<lb/>
had a chance to give up my apartment and share one with <add><unclear></unclear></add> Brown and her<lb/>
Mother, without feeling that the change would interfere with what was left<lb/>
of the work. It was a good deal of wrench, as I had hoped to &ldquo;salvage&rdquo;<lb/>
my small bit of personal privacy out of much that I had come to realize<lb/>
must go. Still, I am very thankful for the present arrangement, which<lb/>
should enable me to stay on in Washington, with lessened financial anx-<lb/>
iety, at least until the completion of the book, including the reading of<lb/>
the galley and page proof, which I hope we will be allowed to go over, in<lb/>
addition to the work of the proof readers of the publishers.</p>
<p>My cousin, Mr. H. Carter Redd, of Richmond, Virginia, who handles<lb/>
the business affairs of the family, tells me that my income has been re-<lb/>
duced to about $125.00 a month. Of this sum, about $20.00 a month will<lb/>
have to <add>be</add> set aside for taxes (D. C. personal tax and my share of the taxes<lb/>
of our (apparently unsaleable!) plantation in Virginia. If only my health<lb/>
were better. I might (after the completion of the book) try to get some<lb/>
work to supplement my income. I doubt, however, if I can ever do regular<lb/>
routine work again. Certainly not unless I improve beyond my present ex-<lb/>
pectations and those that Father held about me. I hope to be able to<lb/>
get your opinion on this later, since you are infinitely better able to<lb/>
judge about this than I. I regret to say that I am by no means so well<lb/>
as when I saw you last, having lost 13 lbs. since the 5th. of last August,<lb/>
at which time I weighed 114 lbs. When I left the Hopkins, after being un-<lb/>
der your care, I weighed <unclear>126</unclear> lbs. However, I judge I am too old for &ldquo;T. B.&rdquo;<lb/>
and too modern to &ldquo;go into a decline!&rdquo; Also, I am at present too thank-<lb/>
ful about the completion of the book and too grateful to all those who<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01307003"/>
who<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
have helped to make it possible to dwell on personal &ldquo;anti-climaxes,&rdquo;<lb/>
and have only written at you such length on the subject, because of my<lb/>
promise to do so. That I have also done so in rather a rambling manner<lb/>
is due to the fact that I have been feeling wretchedly for the past three<lb/>
weeks, beginning with a digestive <unclear>upset</unclear>, one of the most unpleasant <hi>se-<lb/>
quelae</hi> of my long years of chronic appendicitis. My eyes also have been<lb/>
giving me considerable trouble, not in pain, but in the inability to see<lb/>
things clearly. This, I trust can be corrected with stronger glasses<lb/>
later on. During the past summer I could only do close reading with a<lb/>
hand magnifying glass in addition to my spectacles. I must admit to some<lb/>
apprehension about my eyes. Any serious trouble to them would be &ldquo;the<lb/>
ultimate calamity,&rdquo; so far as I personally am concerned.</p>
<p>However, my personal concerns matter little to me in comparison<lb/>
with the thought of the completion of <del><unclear></unclear></del> the book and though<lb/>
it comes too late for &ldquo;Jubilates!&rdquo; it is with a profoundly thankful &ldquo;<unclear>Nunc<lb/>
dimittis!</unclear>&rdquo; that I face the future!</p>
<p>All good be with you always! The inspiration and help of<lb/>
your friendship have been among the best things Life has given me, and I<lb/>
have much for which to be grateful!</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Laura A. Carter</signed>
<seg>
P. S. I hope that you got my note, of last July, thanking you for &ldquo;paving<lb/>
the way&rdquo; for me to write about the Marie Daughty Gorgas collection of<lb/>
Peruvian silver. Mr. Forbes was away at the time, but I have recently<lb/>
received a <hi>most</hi> kind letter from him, telling me that, although the col-<lb/>
lection is not available for the Fogg Art Museum, he is trying to inter-<lb/>
est other institutions or collectors in it. I need not tell you how much<lb/>
Aileen Gorgas Wrightson and I appreciate this.<lb/>
<hi>L. A. C.</hi><lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
