<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01308006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to William S. Thayer, May 19, 1931</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01308006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1931-05-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Thayer, William S.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Edward Champe</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Brown, Miss</name>
<name type="person">Redd, Henry Carter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1931-05-19">May 19, 1931</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01308006</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to William S. Thayer, May 19, 1931</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Laura Carter comments on her financial situation and mentions her brother Edward, who is in a sanitarium.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1931-05-19">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to William S. Thayer, May 19, 1931</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01308006"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
2122 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1931-05-19">May 19, 1931</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Thayer:</salute>
</opener>
<p>If circumstances occur according to your <unclear>so=kind</unclear> hope that you<lb/>
can, in the natural course of conversation, speak of me to Dr. Russell,<lb/>
it may be well for me to recapitulate for you a few points: not with any<lb/>
idea of your taking up <unclear>matters</unclear> <hi>in extenso</hi>, but for your own information.</p>
<p>When I wrote you last September, in compliance with your request<lb/>
to learn how things would be with me on the completion of the book, I<lb/>
told you that Father had hoped to leave me about $235.00 a month. Indeed,<lb/>
I did have nearly that amount. Last September, at the time I wrote you,<lb/>
my income had been reduced to about $125.00 a month, of which $20.00 a<lb/>
month had to be put aside for taxes. This income is now still further<lb/>
reduced as I found I could not continue to live and work on the book<lb/>
during the past winter and spring without continuing to go into my capi-<lb/>
tal. When my cousin, Mr. H. Carter Redd, sent me my last check for my<lb/>
expenses for May. he wrote that, after drawing it, there remained a bal-<lb/>
ance of $25.41 to my credit in the Richmond bank. I trust that he may be<lb/>
able to collect some more money before my June expenses must be met. How-<lb/>
ever, I have written him asking if this be impossible, to try to borrow<del><unclear>s</unclear></del><lb/>
enough on my securities to keep things afloat until the lease for this<lb/>
apartment is up (August 31st.) Naturally, the loan will also have to be<lb/>
deducted from my principal when enough of it becomes available. That he<lb/>
will have to negociate such a loan seems inevitable, since even if he<lb/>
does manage to collect enough money for my monthly expenses through August<lb/>
there will still have to be additional money raised for me to do the thing<lb/>
I least wish to do--break up the remanant of what I have called &ldquo;home&rdquo;<lb/>
and dispose of possessions, of little intrinsic value 'tis true, but<lb/>
precious to me from association and the assurance that so long as I had<lb/>
them I retained the personal privacy and independance of which they were<lb/>
&ldquo;the outward and visible sign.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am sure that Dr. Russell has meant to be more than just, that<lb/>
it has been his intention to be both kind and generous in the matter of<lb/>
the work on the book. Also, <del><unclear></unclear></del> he had me on the payroll far longer than<lb/>
either he or I anticipated. That the earlier completion of the book would<lb/>
have been to my financial advantage, as well as his, sounds strange, but<lb/>
my whole manner of living had to be so changed, on account of the pres-<lb/>
sure of the work, my own poor health (prohibiting the &ldquo;cross-cuts&rdquo; and<lb/>
economies of most women in moderate circumstances) <del><unclear>had</unclear></del> family responsi-<lb/>
bilities, which had to be met with money (as I had no time available for<lb/>
anything save the book) that the longer I worked the less I had. Of<lb/>
course, the Rockefeller pay (and later, half pay) were a god-send, and<lb/>
it has been <hi>much</hi> harder since the half pay stopped (Dec. 1929). My long<lb/>
sick leaves without pay (and with greatly increased expense) had, of<lb/>
course, to come out of my capital.</p>
<p><del>From</del><add>At</add> the time of Father's death, my younger brother was in a sani-<lb/>
tarium, where he was very unhappy, and which was becoming increasingly<lb/>
expensive (beyong what could be met with the interest on the money Father<lb/>
left in trust for him). I made up the deficit, as I felt it would be<lb/>
impossible for me to take enough time and thought from the book to inves-<lb/>
tigate other places and find one more suitable for him. I also gave him<lb/>
additional money for incidental expenses, in order to make things a little<lb/>
more endurable for him until I could carry out my promise to him of mov-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01308007"/>
mov-<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
ing him to another place: &ldquo;Just so soon as the book&rdquo; should be<lb/>
finished. Finally, after several years of waiting, he took matters in<lb/>
his own hands and ran away. It was a great shock, but a mercy in the end,<lb/>
as he is now in a sanitarium where he no longer needs my help. The money<lb/>
Father left for his care is amply sufficient there. This is a great<lb/>
relief, as I should deplore having him suffer from lack of the things<lb/>
I used to to be able to do for him.</p>
<p>Another thing: In the pressure of the work on the book, I did<lb/>
not feel justified to take off even enough time to make out vouchers<lb/>
for my incidental expenses in connection with the work. These, in the<lb/>
spring, summer and fall of 1928 sometimes exceeded my half pay salary:<lb/>
taxis to and from the Library with books and other heavy material: Miss<lb/>
Brown's meals when we were working together: travelling expenses to<lb/>
Baltimore etc. etc. Being assured, however, that the book would be com-<lb/>
pleted that fall or winter, I was more than willing to meet the financial<lb/>
loss in order to have more time for Miss Brown and myself to push our<lb/>
work on the book. I was always promptly reimbursed by the International<lb/>
Health Division for the few incidental expenses that I reported.</p>
<p>I have no claim and no complaint to make. I am quite sure, how-<lb/>
ever, that Dr. Russell has never had a chance to realize what the book<lb/>
has cost me, and will continue to cost, in the loss of financial se-<lb/>
curity and of living as Father so happily and confidently felt that he<lb/>
had arranged that I should live after his death. He greatly wanted me<lb/>
to be free to go back to my own writing and rejoiced that he had se-<lb/>
cured me &ldquo;a future free from the obligation of having to do routine work<lb/>
for a living.&rdquo; The time left for my own work is already much shortened.<lb/>
Whether I shall be free to use any of what remains is a question. Still,<lb/>
the thought of the passing of time also brings a solace o' sorts. Remem-<lb/>
ber the legend of Solomon's seal?</p>
<p>With happiest recollections of that glimpse through &ldquo;the Door to<lb/>
Paradise&rdquo; last Saturday afternoon!</p>
<closer>
<salute>Ever yours,</salute>
<signed>Laura A. Carter</signed>
<seg>
P. S. Sorry for the appearance of this letter, but my typewriter<lb/>
needs drastic repairs. I had a man come up and make an estimate which was<lb/>
appalling. We &ldquo;compromised&rdquo; on a new ribbon.<lb/>
</seg>
L. A. C.<lb/>
1 enclosure.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
