<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01302007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Carter, Henry Rose (August 25, 1852 - September 14, 1925), Sanitarian and epidemiologist, by James M. Phalen, [1927]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01302007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carter family</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Eugenia Hook</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Jr., Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Edward Champe</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Wade Hampton</name>
<name type="place">England</name>
<name type="place">Scotland</name>
<name type="place">Caroline County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Cairo (Ill.)</name>
<name type="place">Ship Island (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-00-00">[1927]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01302007</idno>
<title>Carter, Henry Rose (August 25, 1852 - September 14, 1925), Sanitarian and epidemiologist, by James M. Phalen, [1927]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Phalen's biographical sketch describes H.R. Carter's family, education, career, appearance, and personality.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1927-00-00">
<head>Carter, Henry Rose (August 25, 1852 - September 14, 1925), Sanitarian and epidemiologist, by James M. Phalen, [1927]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01302007"/>
<p>By Colonel James M. Phalen<lb/>
Medical Corps. U. S. A -</p>
<p>CARTER, HENRY ROSE (August 25, 1852 - September 14, 1925), Sanitarian and<lb/>
epidemiologist.</p>
<p>The first Carters of Virginia came out from Hertfordshire, England,<lb/>
in 1649. They were Lords of the Manor of Garston in the old country and<lb/>
have always been land owners and people of consequence in the new. From<lb/>
the highlands of Scotland came to Virginia the family of Rose. Hill Carter<lb/>
of Mine Hill married Mary Rose and to the union was born the first Henry<lb/>
Rose Carter, father of the subject of this sketch. He married Emma Coleman<lb/>
and to them was born the younger Henry Rose Carter at Clifton plantation in<lb/>
Caroline County, Virginia.</p>
<p>After a preliminary education obtained at home and in the local schools<lb/>
of his community, young Carter was sent to the University of Virginia, where<lb/>
he pursued a scientific course, with special attention to mathematics. Here<lb/>
he was graduated in 1873 as a civil engineer. An injury, at the time regarded<lb/>
a permanent disability, turned him from an engineering career and toward the<lb/>
study of medicine. After three years of teaching, one as assistant in applied<lb/>
mathematics at the University of Virginia, he entered the University of Mary-<lb/>
land and graduated in medicine in 1879. He entered the Marine Hospital Ser-<lb/>
vice in May of the same year.</p>
<p><unclear>Mem. <hi>Re</hi></unclear> incubation periods (a) in man<lb/>
(b) &ldquo;extrinsic incubation <unclear>yr. &amp;</unclear>.&rdquo; See Frost's notes on<lb/>
Carter pp. 11 - 17 -</p>
<p>For Dictionary American Biography</p>
<p>Shortly after his assignment to Cairo, Illinois, in the fall of 1879<lb/>
began Dr. Carter's contact with yellow fever, which was to occupy so much<lb/>
of his official career. The next few years, however, were devoted to clini-<lb/>
cal medicine. His assignment to the Gulf Quarantine Station at Ship Island in<lb/>
1888 brought him into contact with the problems of maritime quarantine and<lb/>
particularly that of yellow fever exclusion. By systematic observation he<lb/>
satisfied himself of the efficiency of sulphur fumigation and provisionally<lb/>
fixed the incubation period of yellow fever at not to exceed six days. From<lb/>
these observations he introduced the principle that detention of ship person-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01302008"/>
Ph<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
nel should be for seven days following fumigation. He found maritime quar-<lb/>
antine <unclear>prodedure</unclear> a haphazard system without central control and subject to<lb/>
no uniform regulations. He was largely instrumental in causing the transfer<lb/>
of quarantine stations from municipal or State control to that of the Govern-<lb/>
ment and in having formulated uniform regulations based upon rational grounds.</p>
<p>When in 1893, and again in 1897-98, yellow fever gained foothold in the<lb/>
Southern States, Carter was the Government's representative to cooperate with<lb/>
the State authorities in fighting the disease. From his observations in these<lb/>
epidemics, he definitely fixed the incubation period of yellow fever in man<lb/>
at not more than six days, confirming the <unclear>profisional</unclear> conclusion which he had<lb/>
drawn from his quarantine experience. In May 1900, he published <hi>A Note on<lb/>
the Interval between Infecting and Secondary Cases of Yellow Fever</hi>, calling<lb/>
attention to the &ldquo;extrinsic incubation&rdquo; of the disease, which accounted for<lb/>
the discrepancy between the incubation period and the observed time elapsing<lb/>
between original and secondary cases. This discrepancy (10 to 17 days) was<lb/>
declared necessary for &ldquo;infection of the environment&rdquo; or, as was later shown,<lb/>
for the development of the yellow fever virus in the mosquito. The publica-<lb/>
tion of thi article was coincident with the order for convening the so-called<lb/>
Army Yellow Fever Commission for research upon the disease in Cuba. In its<lb/>
first report, the Commission credits the observations of Carter, together<lb/>
with those of Carlos Finlay on yellow fever and those of Ross and the Italian<lb/>
workers on malaria, with having materially influenced the decision to under-<lb/>
take investigation of mosquito transmission. Following the proof of this<lb/>
mode of transmission by Reed and his colleagues, Carter took up the presen-<lb/>
tation of the epidemiology of the disease from the new viewpoint. His papers<lb/>
on yellow fever, though neither numerous nor long, are classical.</p>
<p>Following the Spanish-American War, Carter organized the quarantine ser-<lb/>
vice for the new government of Cuba. In 1904 he went to Panama, where, after<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01302009"/>
-3-<lb/>
organizing the quarantine service of the Canal Commission, he became Direc-<lb/>
tor of Hospitals, which position he held for four years. In recognition of<lb/>
his distinguished work in sanitation, he was commissioned Assistant Surgeon<lb/>
General of the Public Health Service in 1915. The University of Maryland<lb/>
conferred upon him the degree of LLD in 1910.</p>
<p>In the field of malariology, Carter was also a commanding figure. In<lb/>
1913, he conducted with conspicuous success the first campaign for the con-<lb/>
trol of malaria attempted in the United States and from that time until his<lb/>
retirement from active duty in the Public Health Serfice in 1919, was constant-<lb/>
ly engaged in directing studies and supervising <unclear>connrol</unclear> of malaria in the<lb/>
Southern States.</p>
<p>The last ten years of Carter's life were closely identified with the<lb/>
yellow fever campaign of the International Health Board. He served on its<lb/>
special councils and in 1920, while observing an epidemic in Peru was asked<lb/>
by the Peruvian Government to act as its sanitary advisor. Because of his<lb/>
three decades of acquaintance with yellow fever and his position as leading<lb/>
authority on the subject, he was asked by the International Health Board to<lb/>
prepare a <hi>History of Yellow Fever</hi>, which was well on toward completion when<lb/>
he died in Washington of angina pectoris, after a protracted illness.</p>
<p>Carter was of medium height with a slight figure. He was of delicate<lb/>
constitution all his life and suffered frequent illnesses. However he was<lb/>
not only able to continue his activities, but he spared himself no inconven-<lb/>
iences nor physical hardship in the pursuit of his work. He had an aptitude<lb/>
and a bent toward clinical medicine, but was forced by circumstances into the<lb/>
sanitary field. He was sociable and <unclear>companiable</unclear>, with a mind of Celtic com-<lb/>
plexity in which love of nature and the arts combined with dependability and<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01302010"/>
-4-<lb/>
devotion to duty. His portrait shows a thoroughly human personality, a<lb/>
relatively large head, a full face with a drooping <hi>fer <unclear>a'cheval</unclear></hi> <unclear>mustache</unclear>.</p>
<p>Dr. Carter was married in 1880 at Cairo, Illinois, to Laura Eugenia<lb/>
Hook, a resident of that place. Mrs. Carter died in 1820, leaving three<lb/>
children, Henry Rose, Laura Armistead and Edward Champe.</p>
<closer>
<signed>J. M. P.</signed>
The obituary notices following Dr. Carter's death relate more to his<lb/>
work than to his life history. A sketchy autobiography taken from the files<lb/>
of the Public Health Service appears in the <hi>Virginia Medical Monthly</hi>, Vol. 53,<lb/>
Richmond 1926. <hi>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine</hi>, Vol. V, Washington,<lb/>
<unclear>1923</unclear> contains a biographical sketch with portrait. Much of the material for<lb/>
the present article was obtained from family sources and from <unclear>manuscripts</unclear> of<lb/>
Dr. Wade H. Frost of Baltimore, yet unpublished.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
