<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01314001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report fragment: Diseases Which Have, or Might Have, Been Confused with Yellow Fever in the Past, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01314001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">La Roche, Rene</name>
<name type="person">Chisholm, Colin</name>
<name type="person">Pym, William</name>
<name type="person">Audouard, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Oviedo y Valdez, Goncalo Fernando</name>
<name type="place">Pernambuco (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Guadeloupe</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">Spain</name>
<name type="place">America</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">West Indies</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Rico</name>
<name type="place">Brazil</name>
<name type="place">Grenada</name>
<name type="place">Barbados</name>
<name type="place">Senegal</name>
<name type="place">San Domingo</name>
<name type="place">Plymouth (Mass.)</name>
<name type="place">Jamestown (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Martinique</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>43 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01314001</idno>
<title>Report fragment: Diseases Which Have, or Might Have, Been Confused with Yellow Fever in the Past, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter describes early epidemics of various diseases, some of them mistaken for yellow fever. He differentiates between yellow fever and malaria, describes different mortality rates, and lists characteristics of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report fragment: Diseases Which Have, or Might Have, Been Confused with Yellow Fever in the Past, by Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01314001"/>
<opener>
men.<lb/>
Do not use<lb/>
in retyping<lb/>
Page 40 missing<lb/>
-49-<lb/>
Section II<lb/>
_____________<lb/>
Compare with<lb/>
MSS <unclear>inserted part</unclear><lb/>
_____________<lb/>
3<lb/>
Diseases Which Have, or Might Have, Been Confused with<lb/>
Yellow Fever in the Past.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>In looking over past history one finds accounts of the existence<lb/>
of diseases and of epidemics. Not a few of these--since 1492 especial-<lb/>
ly, and some before--have been considered by medical historians to have<lb/>
been yellow fever. The earlier accounts--up to near the end of the<lb/>
XV11th. Century--are none of them by physicians (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Dr. Chancas--the physician to the second voyage of Colum-<lb/>
bus--indeed mentions in a letter (1493), given by Las Casas, that &ldquo;a<lb/>
third part of the people have sickened in four or five days,&rdquo; (the im-<lb/>
plication is after landing), but beyond ascribing it to &ldquo;work and a bad<lb/>
voyage&rdquo; and the pious &ldquo;hope to God that all will get well,&rdquo; gives no ac-<lb/>
count of the disease. Besides this, the first account by a physician of<lb/>
<unclear>I'd</unclear> which hear<lb/>
any epidemic in the New World that I am able to find is that of the &ldquo;Fever<lb/>
of Olinda&rdquo; (Pernambuco) 1685 and '86, by Dr. Jo&atilde;o Ferreyra da Rosa (1694):<lb/>
Lisbon--200 years later. <del>The writer regrets to say that he has not been<lb/>
able to see this account. The book is not in America--or at least he can-<lb/>
not find it--although a copy is in the library of the British Museum. (End<lb/>
of foot note).</del> Rewrite Rewrite<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
and even when a description is given one is rarely able to recognize the<lb/>
malady by it with any certainty. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The account of the &ldquo;<hi>coup de barre</hi>&rdquo; of 1635 at Guadaloupe by P&egrave;re du Tertre (1667), (who seems to have copied it almost verbatim<lb/>
from P&egrave;re Br&eacute;ton, an eye-witness), is considered the first account of yel-<lb/>
low fever which can be recognized as such--in spite of the fact that du<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01314002"/>
du<lb/>
-50-<lb/>
Tertre did not mention vomiting, far less black vomit, as among the symp-<lb/>
toms and considered &ldquo;<hi>la peste</hi>&rdquo; of 1648 an entirely new disease. Yet &ldquo;<hi>la<lb/>
peste</hi>&rdquo; was quite certainly yellow fever and was characterized by exces-<lb/>
sive vomiting. After this it is comparatively plain sailing. (End of<lb/>
foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Quite frequently the description evidently covers several dis-<lb/>
eases considered by the chronicler as different manifestations of one;<lb/>
with, at times, additions as evidently imaginary. The taste for the<lb/>
grotesque and the horrible seems ingrained in men of a certain stage of<lb/>
culture. More often no description is attempted, the prevailing epi-<lb/>
demic simply classed as &ldquo;<hi>una peste</hi>:&rdquo; <hi>una fiebre pestilencial</hi>" etc.<lb/>
These are the most common terms used, although <hi>&ldquo;la modorra</hi>&rdquo;--&ldquo;the le-<lb/>
thargy&rdquo;--meaning, I presume, an ultimate comatose state, or maybe simply<lb/>
weakness, was common in early Spanish writing and evidently covered more<lb/>
than one disease: &ldquo;<hi>el contagio</hi>&rdquo; is also used, implying the opinion that<lb/>
the disease in question was communicable and &ldquo;<hi>la epidemia</hi>,&rdquo; implying its<lb/>
prevalence.</p>
<p>Now doubtless some of these epidemics were yellow fever and, as<lb/>
undoubtedly, some of them were not and to judge between them with even an<lb/>
approach to accuracy it seems advisable to consider what epidemics be-<lb/>
sides yellow fever one might expect to find in the countries and at the<lb/>
times covered by these accounts and also what would be the points of<lb/>
difference between them either in occurrence or in such symptomatology as<lb/>
would be apt to be noted by the chroniclers of that day; premising that<lb/>
the latter must be quite obvious to be so noted.</p>
<p><hi>Peste</hi>: <hi>Bubonic Plague</hi>.</p>
<p>During the time with which we are concerned this was always present<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01314003"/>
present<lb/>
-51-<lb/>
in the Levant and from time to time prevailed as extensive and deadly<lb/>
epidemics in most parts of Europe. By these <add>characteristics</add> then it could not be dis-<lb/>
tinguished from yellow fever. It can occur, however, in cold weather<lb/>
as well as in hot and is less apt to be a ship-disease.</p>
<p>The symptomatology is different enough and one might expect ex-<lb/>
cessive vomiting; hemorrhages from the mouth and jaundice to be noted<lb/>
in yellow fever and the bubo in <hi>peste</hi>. This latter was well known as<lb/>
a sign of peste to both laity and physicians in Europe; Where the des-<lb/>
cription, however, includes syphilis as well as some other disease (or<lb/>
diseases) under one head--&ldquo;<hi>la epidemia</hi>:&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>la enfermadad</hi>&rdquo;--as was the<lb/>
case with that of all early epidemics in America, the presence of bu-<lb/>
boes need not imply <hi>peste</hi>. They were invariably sought for, as <hi>peste</hi><lb/>
was then the type of a pestilential disease and the general teaching<lb/>
was that all fevers were identical in kind, differing only in degree.<lb/>
(Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Arejula, even in 1806, is just bold enough to differen-<lb/>
tiate between <hi>peste</hi>: <hi>epidemia</hi> and <hi>contagio</hi>. The first is bubonic plague--<lb/>
characterized by buboes: the second typhus--by eruptions--&ldquo;the condi-<lb/>
tions not being sufficient in intensity to produce true buboes&rdquo; With<lb/>
this he ranks the &ldquo;<hi>calentura pestilencial&rdquo;</hi>--yellow fever as it occur-<lb/>
ed in Spain--as an <hi>epidemia</hi> modified by tropical conditions: &ldquo;buboes<lb/>
being quite common in this disease in America&rdquo; and &ldquo;effusions of blood<lb/>
under the skin often seen even in Spain.&rdquo; In the third division is<lb/>
&ldquo;pleuritis&rdquo;--evidently sometimes pneumonia and sometimes pneumonic plague--<lb/>
&ldquo;in which the determination is to the lungs&rdquo;--&ldquo;blood comes from the lungs<lb/>
instead of the gums and stomach&rdquo; and &ldquo;some epidemics show many buboes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He cautiously suggests that they are &ldquo;as it were&rdquo; four species of<lb/>
the same genus--although &ldquo;the teaching of the schools is that they differ<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01314004"/>
differ<lb/>
-52-<lb/>
only by the existence in greater or less degree of the conditions produc-<lb/>
ing them.&rdquo; (End of foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Quite certainly there was never plague in America before 1898 and<lb/>
the Levantine &ldquo;<hi>peste</hi>,&rdquo; which Warren claims was brought to Martinique and<lb/>
later to Barbadoes from Martinique in 1721 was as certainly yellow fever.<lb/>
On the other hand, whether the &ldquo;<hi>pestes</hi>&rdquo; of 1512:/31:/52 and 1601 in the<lb/>
Canary Islands were none of them yellow fever may be a question.</p>

<p>There is to me no question but that the epidemic of 1694 at Roche-<lb/>
fort--a very celebrated one as leading to the first maritime quarantine<lb/>
against yellow fever from the French Antilles--reported by Chirac and<lb/>
accepted by La Roche and by Audouard as yellow fever--was plague. Chi-<lb/>
rac speaks of axillary and parotid buboes as common--although fewer in<lb/>
the groins. It seems rather strange that the earliest protective meas-<lb/>
ures against the introduction of yellow fever should have been taken un-<lb/>
der a misapprehension.</p>
<p><hi>Relapsing Fever</hi> (<hi>&ldquo;Famine Fever&rdquo;</hi>) <hi>and Spirochetal<lb/>
Diseases Generally</hi>:--<hi>Other than Yellow Fever.</hi></p>
<p>}Double space<lb/>
these lines.</p>
<p>These are host-borne diseases--lice or ticks being the vectors.<lb/>
&ldquo;Famine fever&rdquo; was a scourge in the Middle Ages and up to the early part<lb/>
of the X1Xth. Century. It occurred in wide spread epidemics with the<lb/>
misery following wars and with a high mortality among the half starved<lb/>
people. Todd (1922) gives it as 60% among Roumanian prisoners during<lb/>
the Great War and 80% in India where the native treatment is strict diet.<lb/>
Lind, on the authority of Sir John Elliott, gives the mortality at<lb/>
Naples in 1764 as &ldquo;400,000 out of 2,000,000 population&rdquo;--doubtless an es-<lb/>
timate only, but undoubtedly of a severe epidemic.</p>
<p>They occur both in cold and in hot weather--lice naturally thriving<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01314005"/>
thriving<lb/>
-53-<lb/>
best in the former and ticks in the latter. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Relapsing fever--lice-borne--is prevalent in the Punjaub,<lb/>
but only in the cold season. (Cragg, 1922). The same is true for North<lb/>
Africa (E. and E. Sergeant, 1922). (End of foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
The symptoms in some epidemics may be quite like those of yellow fever:<lb/>
profound jaundice: hemorrhages, including gastric hemorrhages and hence<lb/>
black vomit, and unless the occurrence of relapses was noted or that<lb/>
death came less quickly in such cases no difference in symptoms from<lb/>
those of yellow fever would be apt to be recorded by lay historians, or<lb/>
even by physicians. Unless then they occurred in cold weather it might<lb/>
not be easy for us to differentiate such epidemics from those of yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>A diagnostic differential in epidemics among a mixed population of<lb/>
whites and negroes would be that it is as fatal among the latter as the<lb/>
former. It is also less apt to be confined to towns and cities--i.e. may<lb/>
be a rural as well as a civic disease, which is less usual with yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>The fever La Roche mentions, on the authority of Arnott, as occur-<lb/>
ring at Dundee (1843), &ldquo;with all the symptoms of yellow fever,&rdquo; and the<lb/>
small epidemic--21 cases and 17 deaths--in the winter of 1826 and /27<lb/>
at Dublin were quite certainly spirochetal infections--probably &ldquo;famine<lb/>
fever.&rdquo; Yet both Graves and Stokes--clinicians of the first order, but<lb/>
unfamiliar with yellow fever--considered the latter as &ldquo;the yellow fever<lb/>
of the West Indies.&rdquo; (Foot note).<lb/>
_________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Arnott says: &ldquo;The similarity of the symptoms during life<lb/>
and the morbid appearances after death so nearly agree with the descrip-<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01314006"/>
descrip-<lb/>
-54-<lb/>
tion of the yellow fever of the West Indies and with the minute account<lb/>
of the Gibralta<add><unclear>r</unclear></add> epidemic of 1828 by Louis that the only difference be-<lb/>
tween these diseases, <hi>if difference there be&rdquo;</hi> (italics my own) &ldquo;is a dif-<lb/>
ference in degree and not in kind.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Cormack--of the same fever in Glasgow--&ldquo;corresponded closely with<lb/>
Blan&eacute;s description of yellow fever of the West Indies.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Neither Craigie nor David Smith, who reported epidemics the same<lb/>
year in Edinburg and Leith, regarded it as &ldquo;the yellow fever of the West<lb/>
Indies.&rdquo; The mortality was not high enough and &ldquo;many patients showed no<lb/>
vomiting of blood.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was clearly relapsing fever: Craigie gives 110 relapses out<lb/>
of 182 cases after being up and about for from 4 to 6 days. The first<lb/>
cases observed in Edinburg were in January (Edinburg. Med. &amp; Surg. Jour.<lb/>
1843 &amp; 1844: Pages 410 &amp; '62 respectively.)</p>
<p>These cases are common in old medical literature and nearly al-<lb/>
ways in cold weather (See Page 58, infra discussion of the nature of<lb/>
the Matlazuhuatl of the Mexican Plateau). (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>That at Quebec, reported as yellow fever by Walsh in 1806 and the<lb/>
subject of considerable controversy, was clinically a spirochetosis (it<lb/>
is well described), but probably not from the organism of Obermeier.<lb/>
The recent epidemic of spirochetosis in Senegal--reported by Noc and<lb/>
Nogu&eacute; (1921)--was, except from its occurrence in a hot country (tick<lb/>
borne?) more like the one in Dundee. It showed black vomit, which the<lb/>
Quebec epidemic did not: relapses and a greater mortality among blacks<lb/>
than whites.</p>
<p><hi>Typhus Fever.</hi></p>
<p>This, also a host-borne disease, was at this time more widely dis-<lb/>
tributed even than plague and--especially when epidemic--had a high mor-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01314007"/>
mor-<lb/>
-55<lb/>
tality. What it can do under unfavorable sanitary conditions even in<lb/>
modern times is shown by the Serbian out-break in 1914-15. It was not<lb/>
differentiated from typhoid until modern times.</p>
<p>Its vector being the body-louse, naturally, it occurs by prefer-<lb/>
ence in cold weather. It is also less essentially a civic disease than<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<p>The symptomatologies of the two diseases--yellow fever and typhus--<lb/>
would seem to be very different--almost contrasting--yet they were re-<lb/>
garded as the same--or at the least as kindred diseases--&ldquo;modified by<lb/>
climate and marine conditions&rdquo;--by many of the leaders of the medical<lb/>
profession in Europe, <del>(Foot note)</del> most of whom had little experience with<lb/>
yellow fever. (Foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Even as late as 1866, Anstie (Notes on Epidemics. London)<lb/>
writes that &ldquo;from the histories of West Indian epidemics&rdquo; he believes<lb/>
that &ldquo;this disease&rdquo; (yellow fever) &ldquo;has strong affinities with our Eng-<lb/>
lish typhus&rdquo;-----&ldquo;that were these fevers&rdquo; (typhus and relapsing fevers)<lb/>
&ldquo;transported to the tropics&rdquo;--------&ldquo;they would develope there those fea-<lb/>
tures on which so much stress is laid&rdquo; (jaundice and black vomit) &ldquo;with<lb/>
constancy, instead of occasionally and be indistinguishable from the yel-<lb/>
low fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In the early and middle part of the X1Xth. Century the medical pro-<lb/>
fession in Europe was divided into two camps on yellow fever:--the &ldquo;con-<lb/>
tagionists,&rdquo; many of whom considered it &ldquo;a typhus,&rdquo; and the &ldquo;non-conta-<lb/>
gionists,&rdquo; who held it to be an intensified paludal (malarial) fever.<lb/>
Some few, like Chisholm: Pym and Fergusson, with American and African<lb/>
experience, recognized it as a disease <hi>sui generis</hi> and as communicable.<lb/>
(End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
&ldquo;American typhus&rdquo;: &ldquo;typhus icteroides&rdquo; were designations for yellow<lb/>
fever for many years. Indeed, the latter is still common in the mor-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01314008"/>
mor-<lb/>
-56-<lb/>
tality records in Spanish America.</p>
<p>The differential here is unusually clear: Typhus <hi>never</hi> contin-<lb/>
ues in a hot climate nor yellow fever in a cold one.</p>
<p>It is interesting to note the observation of an English Army Sur-<lb/>
geon: &ldquo;The Infection showed again almost as soon as the troops came a-<lb/>
board at Plymouth.&rdquo; It had previously &ldquo;been engendered&rdquo; in crowded bar-<lb/>
racks in that city. &ldquo;It was severe at first, but lessened as warm<lb/>
weather allowed less crowding between decks. We thought it had entire-<lb/>
ly disappeared when we reached Port Royal&rdquo; (Jamaica), &ldquo;but its seed was<lb/>
not dead and it showed again soon after landing, taking on the aspect<lb/>
of the <del>"</del>American Typhus.&rdquo; The explanation is obvious.</p>
<p>In 1793 the celebrated &ldquo;Fever of Bulam&rdquo; was introduced into the<lb/>
Island of Granada and Colin Chisholm's report is illuminating, both<lb/>
as to what occurred and as to the medical opinion of the time. He<lb/>
was an acute observer and a logical, hard-headed Scotchman, congizant<lb/>
of, but in no wise fettered by, the &ldquo;teachings of the schools.&rdquo; A man<lb/>
who did his own thinking.</p>
<p>This fever he thought was generated aboard the British ship &ldquo;Han-<lb/>
key&rdquo; by over-crowding and lack of cleanliness and ventilation while<lb/>
she lay about nine miles off the Island of Bulam, off Portuguese West<lb/>
Africa. In colder latitudes &ldquo;jail fever&rdquo; was habitually generated this<lb/>
way. This, however, was not jail fever, which is not a disease of hot<lb/>
climates. Evidently, the same conditions which would have produced<lb/>
jail fever in a cold climate had, under that of West Africa, gener-<lb/>
ated a fever analogous to jail fever in its pestilential nature--i. e.<lb/>
its ability to propagate itself--but differing from it by showing<lb/>
this characteristic in hot climates and in clean places, which jail<lb/>
fever does not do.</p>
<p>He thought at first that it was &ldquo;the <del>"</del>yellow fever of the West<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01314009"/>
West<lb/>
-57-<lb/>
Indies&rdquo; (by which he understood malarial fever, not yellow fever) &ldquo;en-<lb/>
grafted on the jail fever of Europe&rdquo;--&ldquo;but it does not partake in the<lb/>
least of the nature of the former.&rdquo; He and his colleagues finally<lb/>
classed this <hi>nova pestis</hi> with typhus--&ldquo;of whose nature it evidently<lb/>
partook.&rdquo; It was, of course, yellow fever and the &ldquo;nature&rdquo; to which<lb/>
he referred was its communicability.</p>
<p>We may exclude typhus from our consideration of epidemic dis-<lb/>
eases in the endemic yellow fever zone of America. In the Old World,<lb/>
however, the case is different and typhus may well have been reported<lb/>
as yellow fever in Europe. It was certainly typhus and not yellow<lb/>
fever which ravaged Catalonia in 1764 and later, as described by Mos-<lb/>
deval.</p>
<p>Whether the fever with jaundice: black vomit and petechiae of<lb/>
1822 in Paris was a typhus &ldquo;modified by the heat,&rdquo; as La Roche thinks,<lb/>
may be a question. Lassis and Robert, who was familiar with yellow<lb/>
fever, reported it as yellow fever and Majendie (who mentioned 11 cases<lb/>
in hospital) and Andral confirmed the existence of these symptoms.</p>
<p>It was not yellow fever--case mortality too low and patients<lb/>
sick too long --and more probably some spirochetal infection than ty-<lb/>
phus. The single autopsy, reported by La Roche (Andral's), may have<lb/>
been typhoid--not then differentiated from typhus. This probably is<lb/>
the basis of his, La Roche's, opinion.</p>
<p>Villaba states, on the authority of Dr. Francisco Bravo de Osuna<lb/>
(1570) that this disease--&ldquo;<hi>el tabardillo</hi>&rdquo;--epidemic in Spain since a-<lb/>
bout 1557, &ldquo;had been introduced into Mexico that year&rdquo; (1570) &ldquo;from<lb/>
Spain and made great ravages in the City of Mexico,&rdquo; in which Bravo<lb/>
was then a physician.</p>
<p>Was the famed &ldquo;<hi>Matlazahuatl,</hi>&rdquo; accredited with such ravages on the<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f01314010"/>
on the<lb/>
-58-<lb/>
Mexican Plateau in <del>1545</del><add>1545</add>: 1576: 1736: /37: /61 and /62, the typhus<lb/>
thus introduced, or was it some indigenous disease, existing from pre-<lb/>
Columbian times? The general belief is the latter. This the writer is<lb/>
inclined to doubt. It is true that one of these epidemics is recorded<lb/>
in Mexico in 15<del>45</del><add>45</add>, <add><del>Insert x</del></add> which is prior to the reported introduction of <hi>el<lb/>
tabardillo</hi> from Spain and, indeed, prior to the date (1557) given for<lb/>
the mother epidemic in that country. Yet, as this disease had exist-<lb/>
ed in Spain at the siege of Grenada in 1489-90--brought by soldiers<lb/>
from Cyprus--and appeared again &ldquo;soon after the Civil Wars&rdquo; (1518-20)<lb/>
it might have been introduced into Mexico earlier than Bravo reports.</p>
<p>This whole matter will be considered later in the discussion of the<lb/>
&ldquo;Origen of Yellow Fever&rdquo;: It is enough to say here that (1) Spite of<lb/>
the hemorrhagic symptoms accredited to it (see Page    ) it was not yel-<lb/>
low fever, as it prevailed on the high plateau where yellow fever has<lb/>
never been known to spread and, in 1576 at least, during a period of<lb/>
unusual cold even for that altitude (Page    ). There is no account of<lb/>
it in the <hi>tierra caliente</hi>. (2) The epidemic of 1576 was called &ldquo;<hi>tabardillo</hi>&rdquo; by Mendieta, a<lb/>
contemporary historian. (3) The typhus now existing in the Mexican highlands is known as<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi>el tabardillo</hi>,&rdquo; and seems to be identical with that in Europe and<lb/>
North Africa, and we know of no other very fatal disease there. The<lb/>
great epidemic which swept the Peruvian Andes from Potos&iacute; to Quito and<lb/>
Popayan in and about 1759--for it lasted some years--was, from the<lb/>
rather incomplete description of La Condamine y Ulloa, quite certainly<lb/>
typhus. It is this epidemic that gave rise to the statement, so of-<lb/>
ten ascribed to Humbolt, that yellow fever had been contracted in Quito.<lb/>
I cannot find that he ever made it. Certainly even the Andean foot-<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f01314011"/>
foot-<lb/>
-59-<lb/>
hills in Peru were free from <hi>aegypti<del>s</del></hi> in 1920 and 1921. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The Mexican epidemics may well have been a mixed one of<lb/>
typhus and relapsing fever--or some other spirochetosis--such as is<lb/>
now (1922) prevailing in Poland and the Ukraine. They have the same<lb/>
vector. The whole subject will, however, be discussed later. (End of<lb/>
foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>4) <hi>Scurvy.</hi></p>
<p>This could scarcely occur except aboard ships, and yet might e-<lb/>
normously increase the disability, and indeed the mortality, of even<lb/>
mild diseases in men just landed with it. It is doubtless this which<lb/>
Dr. Chancas had in mind when he instanced the bad voyage--&ldquo;<hi>la mala pa-<lb/>
sada del camino</hi>&rdquo;--as being a cause of the <del>epidemic</del><add>sickness</add> occurring in the<lb/>
second expedition of Columbus when they landed in 1493 on Hispaniola<lb/>
and he was in all probability right--no matter what other causes may<lb/>
also have been active.</p>
<p>The same may well have been a principal factor in the sickness, as-<lb/>
sociated with &ldquo;want and privation,&rdquo; in the Dutch garrison at Valdivia<lb/>
(Chile) in 1643, which B&eacute;ranger F&eacute;raud counts as probably yellow fever--<lb/>
why I do not know. They had just completed a very long and arduous voy-<lb/>
age and had landed on a desolate coast.</p>
<p>On the other hand, scurvy would never last any length of time a-<lb/>
shore in the tropics of America (Valdivia is far south--40&deg; S) there is<lb/>
too much vegatation available.</p>
<p>Scurvy was little, if at all, known as a ship disease prior to the<lb/>
discovery of America: prolonged voyages were rare before that time. Villal-<lb/>
ba (1802) quotes from an early Portuguese writer a description of a se-<lb/>
vere outbreak of scurvy aboard the squadron of Vasco da Gama after pass-<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f01314012"/>
pass-<lb/>
-60-<lb/>
ing the Cape of Good Hope in 1498. The narrator evidently regards it<lb/>
as a higherto unknown disease and Villalba thinks the same. It soon,<lb/>
however, became too well known aboard ship to be there mistaken for any-<lb/>
thing else; but when we have no account of the <hi>nature</hi> of a sickness a-<lb/>
board ship--as when we are simply told that the fleet of Gomez Freyre<lb/>
(1684), from Lisbon to Brazil, &ldquo;lost many men when becalmed under the<lb/>
Line,&rdquo; although he <hi>may</hi> have picked up yellow fever at the <del>Canaries</del><add>Cape Verde Islands</add>, one<lb/>
naturally thinks of scurvy. Similarly, the loss of 50 out of 66 colonists<lb/>
for Guadaloupe (from Brest) aboard the &ldquo;Cardinal&rdquo; <hi>before</hi> they landed, and<lb/>
&ldquo;the sixteen left half dead,&rdquo; implies scurvy. It was certainly not yel-<lb/>
low fever.</p>
<p>It may be noted here that the dead of scurvy in some points re-<lb/>
semble those dead of yellow fever and that hemorrhages from the gums<lb/>
and into the cutaneous connective tissue are common in both scorbutics<lb/>
and yellow fever patients.</p>
<p>Even as late as 1762, Monchy, a Dutch Naval Surgeon, who should<lb/>
have been familiar with scurvy and yellow fever as well, opines that<lb/>
&ldquo;the malignant fevers&rdquo; of the West Indies, &ldquo;are of the same nature as<lb/>
scurvy,&rdquo; and quotes with approval the grouping of &ldquo;the judicious Prin-<lb/>
gle&rdquo; (Sir John Pringle, a British Naval Surgeon) of &ldquo;all these putrid<lb/>
diseases: scurvy: putrid and malignant fevers and dysentery&rdquo; into one<lb/>
class. Monchy also had &ldquo;seen the simple remittents degenerate into the<lb/>
putrid yellow fever of the West Indies&rdquo;--from an increase of intensity of<lb/>
the causal agent.</p>
<p>5) <hi>Dengue.</hi></p>
<p>Another host-borne disease and, since it is conveyed by the <hi>aegyp-<lb/>
t<del>us</del><add>i</add></hi>--possibly not exclusively--naturally it occurs under much the same<lb/>
conditions as yellow fever. The parasite has, however, a much wider<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f01314013"/>
wider<lb/>
-61-<lb/>
geographical distribution. The first definitely recognizable account<lb/>
of dengue in America is that of Stedman at St. T<add>h</add>omas in 1828. It was<lb/>
reported as having been brought by a vessel from Africa, but &ldquo;this was<lb/>
not at all certain.&rdquo; Whether it existed in America before may be a<lb/>
question. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The account of the <hi>coup de barre</hi> at Guadeloupe in 1635,<lb/>
<hi>as given by du Tertre</hi>, fits dengue better than yellow fever. This will<lb/>
be taken up in its place. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
Since that time it has quite certainly been frequently present in trop-<lb/>
ical America, but has been rarely noted, except in the U. S.</p>
<p>It is extremely like mild yellow fever, so like that, in the first<lb/>
stage, differentiation is generally impossible.</p>
<p>To judge by the records it has been of wider dissemination and<lb/>
more frequent occurrence in the Levant: Eastern Asia and North Africa--<lb/>
in which it was recognized earlier than in the Americas and in which<lb/>
it probably originated. The writer thinks that its occurrence in trop-<lb/>
ical America has frequently not been recognized. When not epidemic it<lb/>
has been grouped with the &ldquo;acclimating fevers&rdquo; by the Spanish and with<lb/>
the &ldquo;inflammatory fevers&rdquo; by the French, with which when yellow fever<lb/>
existed were also grouped many mild cases of yellow fever. One epi-<lb/>
demic at least--that of 1860 at Martinique, reported by Ballat (1870)<lb/>
as &ldquo;<hi>fi&egrave;vre inflammatoire</hi>&rdquo; was unquestionably dengue. Rufz de Lavison<lb/>
states that a previous epidemic of dengue there had been known as &ldquo;<hi>la<lb/>
giraffe</hi>.&rdquo; (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Dutroulau--one of the princes in American tropical medi-<lb/>
cine--says of the <hi>fi&egrave;vre inflammatoire</hi>: &ldquo;<hi>C'est la racine de la fi&egrave;vre<lb/>
jaune dans ce climat&rdquo;</hi>--he is speaking of that of the French Antilles.<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f01314014"/>
Antilles.<lb/>
-62-<lb/>
The claim of Simond: Aubert and Noc (1909) that yellow fever existed<lb/>
continuously in the French Antilles as the <hi>fi&egrave;vre inflammatoire</hi>--the<lb/>
so-called &ldquo;larval form of yellow fever&rdquo;--is, I think without basis of<lb/>
fact. These islands freed themselves from infection from time to time<lb/>
as did others. As to the <hi>fi&egrave;vre inflammatoire</hi> it included mild cases<lb/>
of yellow fever, when yellow fever was present: dengue, when dengue<lb/>
was present: some cases of <hi>embarras gastrique</hi> and any other acute fe-<lb/>
brile minifestation--an <hi>omnium gatherum</hi> of acute febrile attacks not<lb/>
otherwise classified.</p>
<p>The writer saw dengue, in Porto Rico (1915) mistaken for, and re-<lb/>
ported as, yellow fever. As &ldquo;<hi>el trancaso</hi>&rdquo; it was quite well known on<lb/>
the island, to the laity at all events, occurring from time to time as<lb/>
epidemics of greater or less extent in the towns, villages and large<lb/>
plantations. This one was at San Juan and the town was full of <hi>ae-<lb/>
gypt<del>us</del><add>i</add></hi>--i. e. &ldquo;the soil prepared for yellow fever.&rdquo; This Porto Rican<lb/>
term, &ldquo;<hi>trancaso</hi>&rdquo;--&ldquo;a lick&rdquo; (meaning a blow)--is identical with that<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi>coup-de-barre</hi>&rdquo; used to designate the fever of Guadaloupe in 1635. Both<lb/>
express the sudden onset of the crippling pains which mark dengue and,<lb/>
quite generally, yellow fever as well. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Dengue is practically not a fatal disease and <hi>this</hi> is our dif-<lb/>
ferential for epidemics of yellow fever and dengue. When Fernan del<lb/>
Busto (1864) gives an epidemic of yellow fever in Tenerife in 1828<lb/>
with over 5,000 cases and 60 deaths--dengue is the first thing of which<lb/>
one thinks. Although McKinlay (1852) is quite sure that the &ldquo;Polka<lb/>
Fever&rdquo; of Brazil (1845-48) was yellow fever: &ldquo;this name&rdquo; (&ldquo;Polka Fever&rdquo;)<lb/>
&ldquo;had never entered into medical nosology had it not been a cherished tra-<lb/>
dition that yellow fever could not exist in Brazil.&rdquo; Yet when he adds<lb/>
that &ldquo;except as a contributing cause of death in very weak people, it<lb/>
was practically without mortality&rdquo; one questions his diagnosis.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f01314015"/>
<p>diagnosis.</p>
<p>-63-</p>
<p>This continued, he states, until 1849 when &ldquo;a fatal yellow fever&rdquo;<lb/>
appeared, &ldquo;either developed from the polka fever or for which this had<lb/>
prepared the ground.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This idea--the transformation of dengue into yellow fever or its<lb/>
role as a forerunner of yellow fever--is common in the American liter-<lb/>
ature of the last half of the X1Xth. Century (see Dutroulau's state-<lb/>
ment in foot note of Page 61). This is natural: The presence of den-<lb/>
gue implies the prevalence of <hi>aegypt<del>us</del><add>i</add></hi> and only the introduction of<lb/>
the micro-organism of yellow fever is necessary for an epidemic of<lb/>
that disease. The &ldquo;Polka Fever&rdquo; was evidence of an infestation of the<lb/>
Brazilian Coast towns with <hi>aegypt<del>us</del><add>i</add></hi> and, to that extent, a sign that<lb/>
the ground was prepared for the propagation of yellow fever when in-<lb/>
troduced.</p>
<p>At times doubtless the two diseases coexist. If this is recog-<lb/>
nized, light cases of yellow fever will be reported as dengue and,<lb/>
even if there be no dengue, a community being usually extremely loath<lb/>
to admit yellow fever, the light cases of yellow fever, and even the<lb/>
others in the first stage of the disease, may be diagnosticated den-<lb/>
gue, which will &ldquo;turn into yellow fever&rdquo; as deaths become common--a<lb/>
few deaths would be explained away.</p>
<p>6) <hi>Malarial Fever</hi>.</p>
<p>Host borne, by a mosquito, the Anopheles: prevalent in hot cli-<lb/>
mates and with some of its manifestations very like yellow fever, it<lb/>
would be a wonder if these diseases were not confounded. Also, since<lb/>
it was well known in Europe, the tendency would be to consider yellow<lb/>
fever malaria rather than the reverse. This was done; and it was not<lb/>
until well into the X1Xth. Century that we find them generally recog-<lb/>
nized as distinct in nature and yellow fever not merely an intense form<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f01314016"/>
form<lb/>
-64-<lb/>
of paludism.</p>
<p>William Ferguson, Inspector General of Army Hospitals (1820) groups<lb/>
the famous Walcheren fever in Zealand, that crippled the Earl of Chat-<lb/>
ham's army: that on the Plains of Estremadura, in Wellington's army:<lb/>
and that he had seen on the table lands of Barbadoes in the West Indies<lb/>
as one.</p>
<p>He sums up: &ldquo;the intensity&rdquo; of the paludal fevers produced &ldquo;from<lb/>
the common agues of the fens of Lincolnshire up to the aggravated yel-<lb/>
low fever or Malignant Remittent of the West Indies, may be measured<lb/>
almost to a certainty by the solar heat of the countries.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Chishol<del>d</del><add>m</add>, on the other hand, made no mistake in his pathology<lb/>
when, in 1793, he pronounced the &ldquo;Fever of Bulam&rdquo; as absolutely dis-<lb/>
tinct from the fevers hitherto prevailing in Grenada and the adjacent<lb/>
Windward Islands. He did err in his nosology when he called the latter<lb/>
&ldquo;the yellow fever of the West Indies&rdquo; and &ldquo;typhus icteroides.&rdquo; Yel-<lb/>
low fever <hi>had</hi> existed in these islands certainly in the latter part<lb/>
of the XV11th. Century, from the so-called &ldquo;epidemic of the Oriflamme&rdquo;--<lb/>
the &ldquo;<hi>mal de Siam</hi>.&rdquo; It had been confounded with the paludal fevers and<lb/>
the severer cases of these were called by its name--first given it in<lb/>
Barbadoes in 1750 (Griffith Hughes). It had evidently disappeared en-<lb/>
tirely from these islands and only the malarial fevers left, to which<lb/>
its name was still applied. So long had it been absent that, on its<lb/>
reintroduction from Africa, it was absolutely unknown to the local<lb/>
physicians and its ravages in the generally susceptible population,<lb/>
grown up since its last prevalence, fully justified Chisholm's quo-<lb/>
tation:<lb/>
------&ldquo;<hi>nova pestis adest</hi>,<lb/>
<hi>cui nec virtute resisti<lb/>
nec telis armisque potest</hi>.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="17" id="f01314017"/>
<p><hi>potest</hi>."</p>
<p>-65-</p>
<p>The point is that the malarial fevers of the Windward Islands--<lb/>
possibly only the severer cases of them--were then called yellow fever<lb/>
by both physicians and laity, even when no yellow fever was present--<lb/>
i. e. malarial fever and yellow fever were considered identical, dif-<lb/>
fering, if at all, only in intensity.</p>
<p>The opinion of Ferguson--i. e. the identity of malarial and yel-<lb/>
low fever, received the powerful official endorsement of the Board,<lb/>
which formulated the so-famous &ldquo;Second Report on Quarantine (Yellow<lb/>
Fever)&rdquo; of 1852. This Board was apparently called for the purpose of<lb/>
pronouncing that yellow fever was not communicable from man to man or<lb/>
from ship to shore and simply declined to consider any evidence to the<lb/>
contrary. The Report, indeed is simply an <hi>ex-parte</hi> argument against<lb/>
the communicability of yellow fever anywhere and under any circumstances.<lb/>
(Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) This decision was reached despite the powerful opposi-<lb/>
tion of Sir Wm. Pym--Inspector General of Naval Hospitals and Super-<lb/>
intendant General of Quarantine (1815 and 1848)--who knew more of the<lb/>
nature and epidemiology of yellow fever than any other man in Europe<del>.</del> of<lb/>
his time, and the definite and logically sustained conclusions of the<lb/>
French Commissions, which had studied the great Spanish epidemics.<lb/>
Pym's arguments (1848), with the array of admitted facts on which they<lb/>
were based, should have convinced St. Thomas himself, as should Au-<lb/>
douard's, but did not influence the decision of men who were deter-<lb/>
mined to allow no maritime quarantine against yellow fever. (End of<lb/>
foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>From this time on--in British Africa especially--these two fevers<lb/>
were <hi>officially</hi> identical and were officially non-communicable, and,<lb/>
doubtless, a certain number of deaths were caused by this ruling--es-<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f01314018"/>
--es-<lb/>
-66-<lb/>
pecially in vessels on the African stations.</p>
<p>While this was true of the leaders of the medical profession in<lb/>
Europe, few of whom, until the Spanish epidemic of 1820, had much chance<lb/>
to study yellow fever at first hand, a number of men in America, early<lb/>
brought into intimate relation with yellow fever, saw in it--as did<lb/>
Chisholm and Pym--a disease different in kind from malarial fever.</p>
<p>- The early Spanish accounts ascribe all their epidemics to the<lb/>
same conditions of excessive heat and moisture as they associate with<lb/>
paludism, adding privation: hardship and the sinfulness of the colonists<lb/>
as being contributary. As buboes were always included among the mani-<lb/>
festations of <hi>la peste</hi> the latter was doubtless, to an extent, causal.<lb/>
(Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Oviedo is the only one of the early chroniclers who recog-<lb/>
nized syphilis as a specific entity and how it is contracted. He was<lb/>
a soldier, a Captain, and had served with Gonsalvo de Cordova in Na-<lb/>
ples. The others, except Bernal Diaz, were ecclesiastics. (End of<lb/>
foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>The same is true of the causes of the <hi>coup de barre</hi> as given by<lb/>
P&egrave;re du Tertre and by Br&eacute;ton (whom the former copies) yet du Tertre<lb/>
speaks later--some years later--of intermittent fevers, tertian and<lb/>
quotidian, as existing in Guadeloupe, and Br&eacute;ton in his Dictionary<lb/>
gives a Carib word--&ldquo;<hi>tiouahonochea&rdquo;</hi>--as equivalent to &ldquo;<hi>la fi&egrave;vre inter-<lb/>
mittent.</hi>&rdquo; These French ecclesiastic then, certainly from 1648 when<lb/>
la peste appeared in Guadeloupe--and possibly from 1635--recognized<lb/>
yellow fever as distinct from paludism and this view continued in the<lb/>
French Antilles. So in Barbadoes, Gamble (1691): Towne (1726): War-<lb/>
ren (1739)-(who thought it was the Levantine plague): Hughes (1750):<lb/>
and Hillary (1759)--ordinary practitioners or laymen--all recognized<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f01314019"/>
recognized<lb/>
-67-<lb/>
their epidemics as different from paludic fevers--as, I judge, did many<lb/>
naval surgeons, whose vessels were infected at Bridgetown. This was<lb/>
natural at Barbadoes, there being, I presume, no malaria on the island<lb/>
then, as there is none now. Indeed, the absence of paludic fevers of<lb/>
local origen is asserted by several of the writers above quoted: there<lb/>
being &ldquo;during the absence of this infectious fever no essential fevers<lb/>
of any kind on this island.&rdquo; (Hughes).</p>
<p>In most places in which yellow fever occurred in America, how-<lb/>
ever, malaria was prevalent and in many of them severe. It happened<lb/>
then that, except in sharp epidemics, the diseases were not differen-<lb/>
tiated and not always in epidemics. Thus, taught by the Philadelphia<lb/>
epidemics, the celebrated La Roche regarded the diseases as distinct.<lb/>
(Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) La Roche believed in the spontaneous origen of both yellow<lb/>
fever and malaria from heat and the decomposition of organic matters--<lb/>
the first mainly from animal, the second from vegetable--and that<lb/>
neither was communicable from man to man. His contemporary and rival,<lb/>
Rush, believed them the same disease--indeed, he held the doctrine of<lb/>
the &ldquo;unity of disease&rdquo;--in their spontaneous origen, as above--and, un-<lb/>
til his later years, in the communicability (&ldquo;contagion&rdquo;) of both.<lb/>
Later he became a non-contagionist and was exceedingly vehement in this<lb/>
view, as he had been in the opposite one. (End of foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
Yet we find Nott (Mobile) in 1848 and /53 and Faget (New Orleans) as<lb/>
late as 1879, arguing for the <hi>specificity</hi> of yellow fever. The former<lb/>
evidently considers himself as being distinctly on the minority side<lb/>
when he argues against it being caused by a gaseous miasm &ldquo;like the palu-<lb/>
dic fevers.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The writer, however, is quite sure that malaria did not exist in<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f01314020"/>
exist in<lb/>
-68-<lb/>
America prior to its discovery. It would of necessity have been intro-<lb/>
duced early by the Europeans <add>and Negroes</add> and would have spread rapidly, especially<lb/>
wherever they went. Still this spread was not immediate nor universal<lb/>
and the absence of malaria in some places must have made the strange<lb/>
disease--&ldquo;<hi>peste</hi>:&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>modorra</hi>:&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>contagio</hi>:&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>fi&egrave;vre pestilentielle</hi>,&rdquo; or even<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi>la enfermedad</hi>&rdquo;--more easily recognized as peculiar to the country.</p>
<p>On the other hand, about Senegal and the Gulf of Guinea, the regions in<lb/>
which we first suspect and first definitely find, yellow fever in Africa,<lb/>
malaria was prevalent and severe--very prevalent and very severe--when<lb/>
first visited by Europeans. Indeed, it is generally held that malaria<lb/>
was indigenous to Africa; not necessarily to this part of it. Moreover,<lb/>
until about the middle of the XV111th. Century Europeans, who alone would<lb/>
show it, were not numerous enough at any place on this coast to make an<lb/>
epidemic of yellow fever distinguishable from those occurring from mal-<lb/>
arial fevers. Differentiation of these diseases then, would be less<lb/>
readily--and hence later--made here than in America and in point of fact<lb/>
was not accepted until after, and doubtless on account of, their recog-<lb/>
nition as different diseases in America. The first definite, accepted<lb/>
account of yellow fever in Africa is that of Lind (in Senegal) in 1759.<lb/>
(Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) B&eacute;ranger F&eacute;raud is of the opinion that there was yellow<lb/>
fever aboard ships in the Bight of Benin as early as 1520 and again in<lb/>
1553-58 and /88. This will be discussed later. (End of foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>African fevers in early times had been considered malaria--with<lb/>
which Europeans were familiar at home--but of a more malignant type.<lb/>
Lind, himself, did not consider these fevers that he reported as dif-<lb/>
ferent from the &ldquo;Coast Fevers&rdquo; he had seen in Batavia and India, with<lb/>
which he grouped them. Indeed, the cases he reported aboard H. M. S.<lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f01314021"/>
H. M. S.<lb/>
-69-<lb/>
Weasel were some, if not all, of them malarial. These he grouped with<lb/>
others--as those aboard the Merlin--quite certainly yellow fever.</p>
<p>The first recongnition of this disease in Africa, as distinct from<lb/>
malarial fever was by Schotte (1782) in the severe epidemic among Brit-<lb/>
ish troops at St. Louis de Senegal in 1778. He called it &ldquo;<hi>synochus<lb/>
atrabiliosus.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>Moreau de Jonn&eacute;s, however, from the histories given, recognized<lb/>
both &ldquo;the yellow fever of the Antilles&rdquo; as occurring in the ill-fated<lb/>
expedition of Captain Tuckey, to discover the source of the Zaire (Con-<lb/>
go) in 1816, and discussed the question whether it was produced spon-<lb/>
taneously where found or brought from America by slavers. He recog-<lb/>
nized it as frankly communicable.</p>
<p>(1838)</p>
<p>Wm. Fergusson (not the Wm. Ferguson of Page 64) made the same<lb/>
differentiation <del>(1838)</del> from his own observations on the West Coast of<lb/>
Africa and is as definite as to the communicability of yellow fever as<lb/>
de Jonn&eacute;s or Pym. Nevertheless, that malarial fever and yellow fever<lb/>
were identical, differing only in degree, and not communicable from<lb/>
the well to the sick in any way, was made as the official decision in<lb/>
1852 and was quite generally accepted in British West Africa for some<lb/>
time later.</p>
<p>Pym used the terms &ldquo;Fever of Bulam:&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>V&oacute;mito Negro</hi> Fever:&rdquo; re-<lb/>
serving, as did Chisholm, &ldquo;yellow fever&rdquo; for malaria of a severe type.<lb/>
Fergusson used the term &ldquo;yellow fever&rdquo; in the sense we do now and was sharply<lb/>
criticized by Pym for so doing.</p>
<p>Even after the two diseases were differentiated the tendency wherever<lb/>
yellow fever was known was to consider all severe--general and fatal--epi-<lb/>
demics as yellow fever and the less severe ones paludism. In the U. S.<lb/>
isolated severe cases, whether of malaria or of yellow fever, were usu-<lb/>
ally reported as &ldquo;sporadic cases&rdquo; of yellow fever and interpreted as show-<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="f01314022"/>
show-<lb/>
-70-<lb/>
ing a tendency of &ldquo;the atmosphere,&rdquo; sometimes--more conservatively--<lb/>
&ldquo;of diseases,&rdquo; &ldquo;to take on a malignant aspect,&rdquo; which, if the cases oc-<lb/>
curred in the early part of the summer, was not unfrequently verified.<lb/>
This was not common in Europe. The great epidemic of malaria in the<lb/>
Earl of Chatham's army at Walcheren, in Zealand, was, indeed, called yel-<lb/>
low fever by Ferguson and, in the so-famous Second Report of Quarantine.<lb/>
Also, Sir. Wm. Burnett gave the same name to the malarial fevers of the<lb/>
Mediterranean Islands. Besides these I know of no others. (Foot note)<lb/>
_________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The small epidemics reported as yellow fever by Baron<lb/>
Larrey (1800), on the authority of Dr. Witman's Journal, among British<lb/>
troops near Jaffa, in Syria, was quite clearly malaria. That reported,<lb/>
tentatively, by Larrey: des Guettes and by Pugnet among the French a-<lb/>
round St. Jean d'Arcre and at Damietta about the same time (1798-99)<lb/>
was probably some of it plague, some malaria, and, apparently, some of<lb/>
it hospital gangrene. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
In some regions, however, and notably in the U. S., quite a number of<lb/>
outbreaks of severe malaria--especially of black-water fever--have been<lb/>
reported as yellow fever. That mentioned by Drake at Memphis in 1828<lb/>
must have been one of these, as yellow fever failed to propagate it-<lb/>
self here even in 1853. The writer has investigated a number of such.<lb/>
He has, however, rarely seen yellow fever called malaria in the U. S.<lb/>
It is more apt to masquerade as dengue. In Africa, on the contrary,<lb/>
the tendency has been in the British Colonies until very recently to<lb/>
report yellow fever as malarial fever. Of this, I think, there can<lb/>
be no doubt. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Ross seems inclined to think that most (if not all) of<lb/>
the yellow fever reported from Africa in recent years was severe mal-<lb/>
aria. On the contrary Guiteras (1921) doubts if the high death rate<lb/>
<pb n="23" id="f01314023"/>
rate<lb/>
-71-<lb/>
reported for malaria in Africa may not have been due to the inclu-<lb/>
sion of cases of yellow fever under that name. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Do not use in retyping</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head>Differentiation between Yellow Fever and Malaria.</head>
<item>1: In Epidemiology.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item><hi>A/ General</hi>.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>1) Yellow fever is essentially a disease of towns and cities:<lb/>
Malaria as essentially rural, or at most suburban.</p>
<p>For instance, it seems scarcely reasonable to consider the<lb/>
<hi>modorra</hi>, so destructive to the Guanches of Tenerife in 1494 as yellow<lb/>
fever. They were a distinctively rural people, while the Spaniards,<lb/>
living together in a fortified camp and seaport, were not attacked.</p></item>
<item><p>2) Yellow fever is contracted aboard ship off shore and on<lb/>
the high seas: is conveyed from ship to ship and from ship to shore.</p>
<p>Malaria is not contracted aboard ship, unless lying--or having<lb/>
very recently lain--close inshore. It may, however--contracted else-<lb/>
where--develope aboard ship, even some time after leaving land, under<lb/>
conditions which may lead one to mistake its source. It is not con-<lb/>
veyed, as an infection, from ship to ship off-shore, because active<lb/>
Anopheles mosquitoes, unless confined in some closed compartment, as<lb/>
the hold, would not remain aboard ship more than 36-48, possibly 60 hours.<lb/>
(Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The writer has seen vessels--and many vessels--with mal-<lb/>
arial fever contracted at Colon, come into the Gulf Quarantine Station:--<lb/>
&ldquo;No one on the sick list until ------days out,&rdquo; &ldquo;when a cold wind com-<lb/>
ing up,&rdquo; or &ldquo;all hands wet in a cold squall,&rdquo; &ldquo;------men went down with<lb/>
fever.&rdquo; In one case--the German bark Jacobine--the days out were 10 and<lb/>
the number of men sickening within a few days were 15--all there were<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f01314024"/>
there were<lb/>
72<lb/>
aboard--with 4 deaths before arrival. Two of the dead men (autopsied)<lb/>
and the 11 living ones certainly had malarial fever. In a vessel from<lb/>
Lagos (the American bark Zingara) no one was sick until over three<lb/>
weeks out, yet all came into the Marine Hospital at Chelsea with mal-<lb/>
arial fever, except the negro cook and and the master. The latter went<lb/>
home sick and, my recollection is, died. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p></item>
<item>3) Yellow fever is contracted in some places on land known to be<lb/>
free from malaria--as Barbadoes: Ascension Island: Paita etc.</item>
<item><p>4) Limited duration of epidemic, or even infection, of yellow<lb/>
fever at any place, <hi>unless new human material be supplied</hi>, and this in-<lb/>
dependently of climatic conditions.</p>
<p>Malaria lasts, or recurs, year after year, unless the conditions<lb/>
of Anopheles production, or protection from them, are changed.</p>
<p>Yellow fever at Cadiz, severe the first year, lasted only two<lb/>
years (1730 and /31), while the epidemics of tertians at and about Car-<lb/>
tagena are noted from 1764 to /71 and again from 1776 to /79 and from<lb/>
1781 to /87. There are hundreds of such instances and this is a re-<lb/>
liable index of which disease prevails <hi>if they prevail separately.</hi></p></item>
</list></item>
<item><hi>B/ Special</hi> (<hi>for Yellow Fever</hi>)<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1) Immunity to the disease of old residents in places where<lb/>
it was of frequent and recent occurrence.</item>
<item>2) Extreme rarity of recurrent attacks.</item>
<item><p>3) High death rate among those attacked.</p>
<p>Malaria is usually far less fatal, to whites at any rate, than<lb/>
yellow fever, yet some forms of it are fatal enough. It would be more<lb/>
correct to say that its <hi>case-mortality</hi> is much less than that of yellow<lb/>
fever: The <hi>community-mortality</hi> of men continuously exposed to severe<lb/>
malaria, from <hi>repeated attacks</hi>, may show as high a ratio to the population.<lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f01314025"/>
population.<lb/>
73<lb/>
This was especially true before quinine was in general use. The ele-<lb/>
ment of time is important here:--a high community death rate in a<lb/>
short time would point to yellow fever: in a longer one it need not.<lb/>
(Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) How great a death rate malaria can cause in a non-European<lb/>
population long free from it may be seen from the epidemic in Mauritius<lb/>
in 1867 and /68. In Port Louis, out of 80,000 people, 22,231 died in<lb/>
13 months: 234 in a single day: 31,920 on the island. (Balfour (1922)).</p>
<p>This reads like yellow fever: A large town was severely stricken<lb/>
and the use of quinine was well known at that time. Moreover we are<lb/>
told (Fowler (1908) that the variety of soil, &ldquo;<hi>which is most common&rdquo;</hi>--<lb/>
italics mine--&ldquo;is porous, allows water to drain rapidly through it and<lb/>
has few springs, a healthy&rdquo; (not malarious) &ldquo;soil.&rdquo; Balfour (1922)<lb/>
&ldquo;firmly believes&rdquo; that &ldquo;if Mauritius had not possessed in many parts<lb/>
so porous a soil and such a remarkable winter climate&rdquo;--warm weather is<lb/>
not continuous here--&ldquo;it might easily have been ruined as was ancient<lb/>
Greece and as were large tracts of ancient Italy and Spain.&rdquo; One cannot<lb/>
but agree with him. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p></item>
<item><p>4) Markedly lower death rates among negroes than among whites<lb/>
or (as far as we know) any other race.</p>
<p>Both diseases are less severe and the death rates of both are less<lb/>
in negroes than in whites, but the difference is very much greater in<lb/>
the case of yellow fever than with malaria. In pure blooded negroes,<lb/>
yellow fever is of low mortality--almost a non-fatal disease. An epi-<lb/>
demic then with a high mortality among negroes is little apt to be yel-<lb/>
low fever. If both races are involved the white case-death-rate should<lb/>
be higher for both yellow fever and for malaria, but the <hi>ratio of dif-<lb/>
ference</hi> should be markedly higher for yellow fever. This might not al-<lb/>
<pb n="26" id="f01314026"/>
al-<lb/>
74<lb/>
ways be true if the negroes, from long residence in a malarious local-<lb/>
ity, had acquired a great degree of immunity to the local disease and<lb/>
the whites were new comers. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) An epidemic with a decidedly higher mortality among blacks<lb/>
than whites is apt to be small-pox: influenza: pneumonia: plague or<lb/>
certain spirochetal infections--as recently occurred in Senegal. Whoop-<lb/>
ing cough too is very fatal among negroes under five years of age. (End<lb/>
of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>A smaller case incidence would also have been <hi>reported</hi> among the<lb/>
blacks. Probably the case incidence is smaller, but certainly light<lb/>
cases are not recognized among them.</p></item>
<item>5) Lower death rate among children than among adults. The re-<lb/>
verse is true of malaria and the difference for both is greater in young<lb/>
children. The difference here is, however, less than that between the<lb/>
black and white races.</item>
</list></item></list></item>
<item>11: In Symptomatology..<lb/>
(which would probably have been noted by the older historians)<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1) Sudden attack of a man in full health with severe pains.</item>
<item><p>2) Short duration of attack--to either death or recovery.</p>
<p>Death usually comes quicker with yellow fever than with malaria.<lb/>
The great majority of deaths are on the 6th. and 7th. days and many on<lb/>
the 5th., yet the deaths that occur within 12 to 24 hours of the seizure<lb/>
are nearly all due to malaria. I say &ldquo;nearly all,&rdquo; for fulminating<lb/>
cases of yellow fever --&ldquo;<hi>el acceso pernicioso</hi>&rdquo;--do occur: a number in<lb/>
some epidemics. Far more commonly &ldquo;walking cases,&rdquo; sick for some days<lb/>
and dying suddenly are reported as fulminating cases. Both together, in<lb/>
my observation, are rare compared with the deaths due to the fulminant<lb/>
<pb n="27" id="f01314027"/>
fulminant<lb/>
75<lb/>
forms of malaria. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Good old P&egrave;re Labat in 1694, with the optimism of one im-<lb/>
mune (by attack)---and doubtless to partly make up for the rather hor-<lb/>
rific picture he had drawn of it--speaks this good word for &ldquo;<hi>le mal de</hi><lb/>
Siam:&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>Ce que cette maladie avoit de commode</hi>, <hi>c'est qu'elle emportoit<lb/>
les gens en fort peu de temps</hi>--<hi>six ou sept jours tout au plus termi-<lb/>
noient l'affaire.</hi>&rdquo; (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p></item>
<item>3) Death frequently in convulsions--and often in coma.</item>
<item>4) Extreme weakness in early convalescence, but convalescence<lb/>
is rapid and complete.</item>
<item><p>5) Persistant vomiting: black vomit: (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) It is worthy of note that black vomit is not mentioned<lb/>
as a symptom of the <hi>Peste</hi> in Guadeloupe in 1648, although persistent<lb/>
vomit is. This is generally accepted as yellow fever, and I think<lb/>
was. See Page on this subject. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p></item>
<item><p>6) Hemorrhages from about the mouth and yellowness of the eyes and skin<lb/>
during the attack and in convalescence. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The effect of treatment at times must have profoundly<lb/>
influenced the symptomatology of both diseases, and their death rate<lb/>
as well. Where antimony was used to any extent vomiting was to be ex-<lb/>
pected and sufficient bleeding might produce temporary anaemia in even<lb/>
a patient convalescent from yellow fever--that is if he convalesced!<lb/>
It is fair to say, however, that tropical practitioners were very gen-<lb/>
erally opposed to both of these agents as being in their experience in-<lb/>
jurious in fevers, spite of the &ldquo;teachings of the schools&rdquo; of the time.</p>
<p>The surgeon to Drake's Darien expedition (1573) &ldquo;instructed&rdquo; by<lb/>
<pb n="28" id="f01314028"/>
by<lb/>
76<lb/>
the necropsy he had performed on his leader's brother, &ldquo;did devise a<lb/>
certain remedium----for the cure of this distemper.&rdquo; Of which, when<lb/>
he had prepared it &ldquo;he did partake himselfe a full quantum&rdquo; with dis-<lb/>
astrous results, for &ldquo;he never spake more.&rdquo; Nor did his boy, who had<lb/>
only tasted it, &ldquo;recover his good health which once he had until he a-<lb/>
gain saw England.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is also noted that soon after the death of the surgeon the<lb/>
&ldquo;distemper&rdquo; ceased; although there is no allegation of cause and ef-<lb/>
fect. Yet such a practitioner might well have raised the mortality<lb/>
rate. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p></item>
</list></item></list></p>
<p>In malaria convalescence is slow and imperfect, and one is apt<lb/>
to be weak and anaemic for a long time. Anaemia is in no wise a se-<lb/>
quel of yellow fever. Convalescents from yellow fever are frequently<lb/>
very yellow at first, but this does not last. The pasty, puffed face<lb/>
with, it may be, prolonged jaundice, follows malaria, not yellow fever.<lb/>
The Spaniards returning from San Domingo, whom Oviedo (1535) noted as<lb/>
&ldquo;of such a bad color:&rdquo; &ldquo;of the color, but not the lustre of gold:&rdquo;<lb/>
&ldquo;citron&rdquo; (colored) &ldquo;and of the color of safron or of treacle&rdquo; were<lb/>
quite certainly not in this condition as the result of yellow fever,<lb/>
for it was some months from Hispaniola to Spain. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Since this passage is so frequently quoted (by Moreau de<lb/>
Jonnes: Cornilliac: Finlay and others) as evidence that &ldquo;<hi>la enfermedad</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
at San Domingo was yellow fever it seems fair to give it in its en-<lb/>
tirety:</p>
<p>&ldquo; Thus, in order to live, from no beast or animal, of the number<lb/>
I have mentioned, did they abstain, because as many as they could ob-<lb/>
tain went to the fire and, boiled or roasted, there was not lacking to<lb/>
their necessity appetite to eat these things so inimical to health<lb/>
<pb n="29" id="f01314029"/>
health<lb/>
77<lb/>
and so terrifying to sight.&rdquo; He is referring to dogs: wood-rats:<lb/>
lizards: jutias: iguanas (&ldquo;a serpent with four feet&rdquo;): &ldquo;serpents many<lb/>
colored, but not poisonous,&rdquo; etc.</p>
<p>&ldquo;From the which, and from the humidity and the fatness of the land,<lb/>
followed many illnesses grave and incurable to those who were left<lb/>
with life. And from this cause those first Spaniards who came here,<lb/>
when they returned to Spain, some of those who came in this search for<lb/>
gold, if they returned there, it was with the same color of it, but<lb/>
not with its lustre, but citroned and of the color of safron or treacle<lb/>
and so infirm that immediately, or shortly after they returned there,<lb/>
they died on account of what they had suffered here and because the<lb/>
provisions and the bread of Spain are of stronger digestion&rdquo; (I think<lb/>
he means &ldquo;more nourishing&rdquo;) &ldquo;than these herbs and bad viands they eat<lb/>
here and the airs more delicate and cold than those of this land. So<lb/>
that, although they returned to Castile, soon they gave an end to their<lb/>
lives&rdquo; (after) &ldquo;having arrived there.&rdquo; (Literal translation. Account<lb/>
evidently written at Hispaniola). &ldquo;<hi>Hystoria general y natural de las<lb/>
Indias por el Capit&aacute;n Gon&ccedil;alo Fernando de Oviedo y Valdez</hi>.&rdquo; <hi>Tomo 1</hi>:<lb/>
<hi>Libro 11</hi>: <hi>Cap</hi>. <hi>X111</hi>: <hi>P</hi>. <hi>50 et seq</hi>. Printed 1535.</p>
<p>To the writer this speaks strongly for malaria. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>In general then, an epidemic of malaria can be distinguished from<lb/>
one of yellow fever. The first is especially marked by debility: The<lb/>
second by deaths. As we have said, however, if the exposure to mal-<lb/>
aria be continued there may be many deaths. The experience of Shafter's<lb/>
army at Santiago in 1898 illustrates the first: that of the British at<lb/>
Havana in 1762 the second: the rather exceptional Mauritius epidemic<lb/>
of 1867 (Page 73, foot note) the effect of continuous exposure to se-<lb/>
vere malaria. In the first case there was only a moderate death rate,<lb/>
<pb n="30" id="f01314030"/>
rate,<lb/>
78<lb/>
but an almost complete destruction of the army as a fighting machine.<lb/>
Albermarle lost half of this force, but captured Havana. Had Shafter<lb/>
remained in Cuba, his mortality would have increased and might <hi>possibly</hi><lb/>
have in time approached that of Mauritius.</p>
<p><hi>Smallpox.</hi> Naturally when any description of the disease itself<lb/>
is given, no matter by whom made, there would be no possibility of mis-<lb/>
taking smallpox for yellow fever nor the reverse. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The picture-writings of the Aztecs (Codex Aubin 1576 and<lb/>
Codex Telleriano-Remensis about 1561) very plainly show the terrible<lb/>
epidemic of small-pox introduced into Mexico by a negro sick of that<lb/>
disease, in the train of Navaez, and which did much to break their re-<lb/>
sistance to Cortez. It was known as &ldquo;great-fire&rdquo; (&ldquo;<hi>noh-kakil</hi>&rdquo;) by<lb/>
the Mayas after it came to them, and is mentioned in their chronicles<lb/>
as occurring between 1511 and 1520. Even the far less cultured<lb/>
tribes in North America soon learned, to their sorrow, to know it well.<lb/>
(End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Introduced to America by the Europeans, it was a scourge to its<lb/>
native races, far less so to the Europeans, numbers of whom were im-<lb/>
mune by previous attack.</p>
<p><hi>Measles.</hi> What is said of smallpox applies to measles, to a less<lb/>
degree maybe. It was less certain of recognition, less deadly to the<lb/>
Indians and negligible in its effects on Europeans. While not by any<lb/>
means the scourge smallpox was, it was quite fatal to the American<lb/>
natives, even in the tropics. Where it was cold, it was to them a dead-<lb/>
ly pestilence.</p>
<p>When one hears then of fatal epidemics among the Indians, or any<lb/>
primitive race, following their contact with Europeans, one must--un-<lb/>
less the descriptions of the disease negative them--consider smallpox<lb/>
<pb n="31" id="f01314031"/>
smallpox<lb/>
79<lb/>
and measles as possibilities. Where there is no description and the<lb/>
disease does not seriously affect, and is not noticed by, the Euro-<lb/>
peans who are in contact with it, the evidence for it being <add>one</add> or the<lb/>
other is strengthened.</p>
<p>Such was &ldquo;<hi>la modorra</hi>&rdquo; (&ldquo;the lethargy&rdquo;) which destroyed a good<lb/>
part of the Guanches of Tenerife in 1494 after the battle of Laguna.<lb/>
The Spaniards went freely into the stricken territory, bringing back<lb/>
some captives--&ldquo;owing to the pestilence our men met little resistance&rdquo;--<lb/>
and are not noted as suffering any sickness, except &ldquo;from the rough-<lb/>
ness of the country and the scarcity of provisions,&rdquo; nor as being con-<lb/>
cerned about that among the Guanches. Finlay suggests this epidemic<lb/>
as being yellow fever and as such it is accepted by B&eacute;ranger F&eacute;raud<lb/>
and Augustin. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The latter quotes Oviedo to the same effect, but I can-<lb/>
not find his reference. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
No description is given of this disease, but from its epidemiology<lb/>
(see also Page 71) it could not have been yellow fever and smallpox:<lb/>
typhus or measles seems the most probable diagnosis. One of the first<lb/>
two may seem necessary to account for the heavy mortality, and there<lb/>
had been a severe epidemic of typhus in Spain in 1489 and /90 at the<lb/>
seige of Granada. Yet its rapid progress (foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) &ldquo;The woman called to us, from the top of the rock, to come<lb/>
on in: &lsquo;There is no one left to fight, all are dead who would resist<lb/>
you.&rsquo;&rdquo; Ezpinosa (1594). (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
and the fact that the chronicler does not mention that it was smallpox<lb/>
and that the Spaniards paid absolutely no attention to it seems, to<lb/>
the writer, to make measles at least as probable. Measles in a virgin<lb/>
<pb n="32" id="f01314032"/>
virgin<lb/>
80<lb/>
race, in a mountain climate and aided by the privations following an<lb/>
unsuccessful war--&ldquo;the land was not cultivated and there was no sus-<lb/>
tenance of bread therein&rdquo;--might well make a heavy mortality.</p>
<p><hi>Influenza</hi>. This disease is recorded as epidemic in Europe--in<lb/>
France: Germany or England a number of times, certainly six or eight--<lb/>
from 1403 to 1600. In Spain, Villalba (1802) reports it as first<lb/>
epidemic in 1580 as <hi>&ldquo;el catarro</hi>&rdquo; and many times thereafter. Judging<lb/>
from our recent experience, it would have had a good chance to cross to<lb/>
North America from the northern countries--by Breton: Scandanavian and<lb/>
British fishermen especially--much less to reach the lower latitudes<lb/>
in the yellow fever zone.</p>
<p>The writer is sure that no epidemic of influenza in Europe was<lb/>
reported as yellow fever, nor was the contrary mistake made. The same<lb/>
seems to have been true for tropical America in early times. Yet in-<lb/>
fluenza must be considered as a probability in the great epidemic oc-<lb/>
currring among the Indians on the New England Coast about 1618 and which<lb/>
was the salvation of the Plymouth Colonists. Noah Webster gives a de-<lb/>
tailed account of this and considers it to have been yellow fever.<lb/>
Since it occurred during the winter, this disease need not be consid-<lb/>
ered, spite of the statement of his Indian informants that the sick<lb/>
were as yellow as the piece of yellow cloth he showed them. It could<lb/>
well have been influenza, being in the part of America into which it<lb/>
would have been most readily introduced: measles is another tenable--<lb/>
<unclear>was</unclear><lb/>
probably less tenable--supposition. Smallpox Webster had specifically<lb/>
excluded. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) The experience of the writer with the American aborigines,<lb/>
both in investigating an epidemic<del>,</del> which had occurred among the San<lb/>
Blas Indians, suspected of having been yellow fever, and at other<lb/>
times, is that they, when really friendly, carry their courtesy so far<lb/>
<pb n="33" id="f01314033"/>
far<lb/>
81<lb/>
that one is pretty apt to get the information <hi>they think</hi> he wants,<lb/>
let the facts be as they may. We were assured, by the San Blas, that<lb/>
black-vomit had been frequent and abundant: that most deaths were in<lb/>
convulsions--dramatically illustrated--that the eyes of the sick and<lb/>
dead were as yellow as the gold coin exhibited. Yet, from epidemio-<lb/>
logical evidence and the examination of three convalescents, we were<lb/>
able to determine positively and without any doubt this epidemic as<lb/>
having been grippe. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Whether &ldquo;<hi><del>a</del><add>el</add> bicho</hi>&rdquo; (&ldquo;the creature&rdquo;), epidemic at Lima (according<lb/>
to Leb<add><unclear>e</unclear></add><unclear>nd</unclear>.) in 1781, was yellow fever, as reported by him, or<lb/>
grippe is disputed by some Peruvian writers (Eyzaguire, 1906). The<lb/>
evidence is not definitely determinative, but to the writer renders<lb/>
the diagnosis of yellow fever <add>much the</add> more probable.</p>
<p>Clinically the diseases seen as epidemics are sufficiently dis-<lb/>
tinct, yet the writer investigated, in 1920, two small epidemics of<lb/>
grippe in Peru reported as yellow fever and in 1921 a larger one of<lb/>
yellow fever, reported (among other things) as grippe--&ldquo;<hi>&aacute; la forma<lb/>
g&aacute;strica</hi>.&rdquo; In Louisiana in 1918 a number of physicians familiar with<lb/>
yellow fever regarded the influenza epidemic with suspicion and a few<lb/>
were near reporting it as yellow fever. To the writer, there seems<lb/>
no reason to mistake them clinically--seen in fair sized groups.</p>
<p><hi>Dysentery</hi>. With a clinical description of either disease,<lb/>
dysentery and yellow fever would never be confounded. Yet in the ac-<lb/>
counts of epidemics among English troops and, to a less degree, colo-<lb/>
nists in America, &ldquo;fevers and fluxes&rdquo; are frequently grouped in both<lb/>
the morbidity and mortality reports. Dysentery too, seems to have been<lb/>
one of the diseases which, with syphilis and fevers, was frequently<lb/>
grouped as one morbific entity by the early American historian. Ob-<lb/>
<pb n="34" id="f01314034"/>
Ob-<lb/>
82<lb/>
viously then, when we simply hear of a great sickness--especially in<lb/>
an army--in the tropics with no description of its nature, the chance<lb/>
of dysentery being a factor in it is to be considered.</p>
<p><hi>Sickness and Mortality among Early Colonists in New Countries</hi>.</p>
<p>There seems to be an unconscious bias among writers on the<lb/>
early history of yellow fever to ascribe to that disease all undue<lb/>
mortality among new comers to places in the tropics. Yet we know that<lb/>
this occurred habitually among colonists and in expeditions to new<lb/>
countries under conditions where yellow fever could not possibly be<lb/>
accused.</p>
<p>Fiske (1900) states that Lan<unclear></unclear>'s Colony (1585) on Pamlico Sound<lb/>
lost half of their number before taken off by Drake. The early set-<lb/>
tlers at Jamestown lost about one half--between May 13th., when they<lb/>
landed, and September 30th. &ldquo;over 50 were in their graves&rdquo; --out of<lb/>
104 who landed. One hundred and twenty men landed at the mouth of<lb/>
the Kennebec, August 1607: So many died that those left abandoned the<lb/>
colony. Of the &ldquo;100 of the most vigorous who sailed in the Mayflower,&rdquo;<lb/>
51 died the first winter at Plymouth: at one time only seven men, in-<lb/>
cluding Elder Brewster and Miles Standish, were able to be about. The<lb/>
mortality among the early settlers in Australia, in modern times, was<lb/>
nearly as high as those just given.</p>
<p>The Jamestown Colony seems to be especially a case in point.<lb/>
There had been no trouble with Indians, by whom some food was supplied:<lb/>
it was noted that they had &ldquo;an abundance of crabs and some sturgeon&rdquo;<lb/>
from the river: they had brought chickens with them, which should have<lb/>
increased. Also being a small number, yet large enough to defend them-<lb/>
selves, it had been easier to live off a wild country than if they were<lb/>
<pb n="35" id="f01314035"/>
were<lb/>
83<lb/>
a larger body. Yet &ldquo;of hardships: unaccustomed mode of life: starva-<lb/>
tion and <hi>fevers</hi>&rdquo; over a half died in four and a half months. Indeed,<lb/>
the last element, if they were malarial fevers, could not have been active<lb/>
more than two months--or at most two and a half--as paludal fevers in<lb/>
that region rarely show to any extent until in August. Yet only 37 of<lb/>
the original 104--a little over one third--were found by Newport when<lb/>
he returned in Jan. 1608, and only 2 had been killed by Indians. (Ty-<lb/>
ler 1900). Independently of yellow fever, the conditions in the colo-<lb/>
nies in the tropics should have been less healthful tha<del>t</del><add><unclear>n</unclear></add> at Jamestown,<lb/>
both from climate and environment.</p>
<p>Much depends on the preparation for settlement and more on the<lb/>
men sent out. Guadeloupe and Martinique were colonized by the French<lb/>
in 1635, in June and July respectively. The colonists for the former<lb/>
(about 600) are characterized by du Tertre as &ldquo;<hi>gens pauvres de la ville</hi>,&rdquo;<lb/>
to which he ascribes the death of 50 out of 66 on one vessel (the Car-<lb/>
dinal) before landing; showing that he meant poor in physique and morale<lb/>
as well as in money. After two months the supplies brought from France<lb/>
being consumed, a famine--characterized as &ldquo;horrible&rdquo;--began. This,<lb/>
he says, was followed by a heavy mortality due (1) to the famine: (2) to<lb/>
sickness--the &ldquo;<hi>coup de barre</hi>&rdquo;--and (3) to the cruelty of the overseers<lb/>
of the work, forcing the colonists &ldquo;by blows and by severity to work in<lb/>
clearing the woods and in all weathers.&rdquo; To this last, indeed, he as-<lb/>
cribes the greater part of the mortality--&ldquo;because the French were<lb/>
much enfeebled and were treated worse than slaves in Barbary.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Martinique was settled by d'Enambuc, who had been long in the<lb/>
West Indies, with 100 men--note the small number who could therefor<lb/>
live off the country--&ldquo;old inhabitants of St. Kits:&rdquo; <hi>&ldquo;tous gens de<lb/>
mains</hi>:&rdquo; &ldquo;accustomed to the climate, to the work and the fatigues of<lb/>
<del>of the country." They were "very ski</del><lb/>
<pb n="36" id="f01314036"/>
of<lb/>
84<lb/>
the country.&rdquo; They were &ldquo;very skilful in clearing land, planting and<lb/>
cultivating provision and adroit in building houses.&rdquo; They brought<lb/>
with them, &ldquo;as provision and to plant, all things necessary,&rdquo; among<lb/>
which is mentioned &ldquo;manioc: yams: peas: beans and other grains&rdquo;--proba-<lb/>
bly Indian corn. It is expressly stated that the Guadeloupe colonists<lb/>
made no provision for future crops, depending entirely on supplies from<lb/>
France that never came.</p>
<p>No special mortality was reported at Martinique (until the &ldquo;<hi>Mal<lb/>
de Siam</hi>&rdquo; of 1690) and it may be that the men from St. Kits--some of whom<lb/>
were quite certainly buccaneers--were immune to yellow fever. Yet<lb/>
the fact that both they and d'Enambuc were used to tropical conditions<lb/>
and were &ldquo;men of their hands&rdquo; cannot be left out of consideration in<lb/>
accounting for this.</p>
<p>It is common enough then to have much sickness and many deaths<lb/>
in a newly planted colony due simply to ignorance: lack of good ad-<lb/>
ministration and personnel unsuited to pioneer conditions. This<lb/>
should not continue, however, without some pathogenic reason. When,<lb/>
after some years. Plymouth had been well organized, the disproportion-<lb/>
ate mortality ceased. This lasted longer with Virginia (Tyler 1900)<lb/>
partly at least on account of the prevalence of malaria; yet as the<lb/>
colony became self-supporting and prosperous it disappeared, although<lb/>
&ldquo;agues: epidemicals and fluxes&rdquo; are reported each fall and, indeed,<lb/>
there was an excessive mortality among the new comers for a long time.<lb/>
<del>Indeed,</del> Tide-water Virginia abounding in Anopheles mosquitoes and the<lb/>
life being essentially rural, there was an excessive mortality among<lb/>
new comers for a long time, to which we will recur later. Even in<lb/>
Guadeloupe after the famine and things had settled down one hears no<lb/>
more of excessive sickness until the advent of &ldquo;<hi>la peste</hi>&rdquo; in 1648: of<lb/>
none in Martinique until the <hi>&ldquo;Mal de Siam</hi>&rdquo; in 1690. (Foot note)<lb/>
<pb n="37" id="f01314037"/>
1690. (Foot note)<lb/>
85<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) P&egrave;re Bouton, writing in 1640 of Martinique, which he left<lb/>
that year, does not mention the &ldquo;<hi>coup de barre</hi>&rdquo; or any dangerous dis-<lb/>
ease on the island, although he gives a rather full account of those<lb/>
that occur: yaws: ulcers and malaria. The language used seems to be<lb/>
intended for both islands--Martinique and Guadeloupe: &ldquo;It is marvel-<lb/>
ous if each one who arrives <hi>in these islands</hi>&rdquo; (italics mine) &ldquo;has not<lb/>
four or five attacks of fever,&rdquo; which he regards as of small import-<lb/>
ance, advising to continue about and not pay too much attention to<lb/>
them. (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>When then in an established colony with a fairly settled life<lb/>
one finds much sickness and many deaths among new comers, and among<lb/>
new comers only, the conclusion is justifiable that this is due to<lb/>
some disease producing immunity against its own attacks. In the Ameri-<lb/>
can and West African tropics that would most likely be yellow fever,<lb/>
although a certain immunity is produced by malaria, almost everywhere<lb/>
present, but far less complete than by yellow fever.</p>
<p>If there be also regularly an excessive mortality among the<lb/>
young children of the colonists, malaria is more probably the cause<lb/>
than yellow fever, especially if this occurs under rural or suburban<lb/>
conditions of life. Yellow fever, indeed, does raise the death rate<lb/>
of children, but not with the steady persistence of malaria.</p>
<p>The sickness and heavy death rate among new comers--and the<lb/>
latter confined to them--during much of the XV111th. and early part<lb/>
of the X1Xth. Centuries in Jamaica: Barbadoes and the French Antilles:<lb/>
the same conditions existing to the beginning of the XXth. in Havana:<lb/>
Rio Janiero and Vera Cruz is, even by itself, very strong evidence of<lb/>
the presence of yellow fever in those places during the time stated.<lb/>
<pb n="38" id="f01314038"/>
stated.<lb/>
86<lb/>
One must lay stress on the &ldquo;much sickness&rdquo; and the &ldquo;many deaths&rdquo;<lb/>
because new comers do not know how to take care of themselves, and<lb/>
do not take care of themselves, in the tropics as do old residents.<lb/>
There is an acclimatization to custom and to climate when the changes<lb/>
in them are great--which lessens one's susceptibility to disease--<lb/>
as well as to disease by previous attack. This is seen even in new<lb/>
troops as compared with old ones when there is no change of climate,<lb/>
only of conditions of life.</p>
<pb n="39" id="f01314039"/>
<p>For End of Section II?</p>
<p>Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>Having gone rather extensively into the differentiation from yel-<lb/>
low fever of the diseases which might have been confused with it, it<lb/>
seems advisable to gave a very brief resume of such characteristics of<lb/>
of yellow fever itself, liable to be noted by our old chroniclers which<lb/>
distinguish it from them:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1) It occurs (in epidemics) only in hot, or fairly hot, weather.</item>
<item>2) It is apt to occur in epidemics. Certain to do so in a crowd<lb/>
of white (susceptible) new comers.</item>
<item>3) It is a disease of collections of men--civic rather than rural.<lb/>
It not only developes, but is contracted and propagated aboard ships on<lb/>
the high seas and under some conditions is communicable from ships to<lb/>
places ashore and vice versa.</item>
<item>4) It is a disease of high, or fairly high, case-mortality among<lb/>
all races except negroes, and especially among robust adults. Among<lb/>
negroes the death rate is quite low absolutely: very low comparatively.</item>
<item>5) The deaths are usually from the 5th. to the 8th. day, grouped<lb/>
on the 6th. and 7th.</item>
<item>6) Convalescence once established is <hi>complete</hi> and rapid. Anaemia<lb/>
is not produced by yellow fever, or &ldquo;found only,&rdquo; to quote Pym, &ldquo;in the<lb/>
fortunate few who survive venesection.&rdquo;</item>
<item>7) The characteristic <hi>symptoms</hi> which would be noticed are (a) sud-<lb/>
den attack: (b) severe pains head: back and limbs and <hi>extreme</hi> prostration:<lb/>
(c) jaundice: (d) hemorrhage--especially showing at, not necessarily from,<lb/>
the mouth and nose and (e) black vomit.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Of the <hi>symptoms</hi>, sudden attack and the pains mentioned are too com-<lb/>
mon to other diseases to be distinctive.</p>
<p><hi>Jaundice</hi> is, of course, a symptom common to many diseases of hot<lb/>
<pb n="40" id="f01314040"/>
hot<lb/>
climates, nor is it confined to those of such climates. The dead are<lb/>
always yellow.</p>
<p><hi>Hemorrhages</hi>, as we have seen, occur in certain epidemics of typhus<lb/>
and spirochaetosis.</p>
<p><hi>Black vomit</hi>, which is merely blood altered by the acid contents of<lb/>
the stomach, may, of course, occur among the hemorrhagic mainfestations<lb/>
of the diseases of the last paragraph, although in fact the gastric hem-<lb/>
orrhage when it occurs in them has usually been so profuse, or the gas-<lb/>
tric acid in so small an amount, that it has rarely been reported by the<lb/>
older writers as black vomit, but as blood. In the cases of Graves and<lb/>
Stokes--trained clinicians--true black vomit was reported and so those of<lb/>
Noc and Nogu&eacute;.</p>
<p>In no other epidemic disease except yellow fever does this symptom<lb/>
occur at all frequently. If the spirochetosis be louse borne it (like<lb/>
the typhus) will not continue in a hot climate.</p>
<p>Black vomit, the lesser degrees of it at any rate, is also occa-<lb/>
sionally produced by prolonged straining vomiting, as in sea-sickness:<lb/>
after ether etc. and full black vomit occurs in some cases of intesti-<lb/>
nal obstruction and peritonitis and from the ingestion of irritant poi-<lb/>
sons: alchoholism etc. The occurrence of isolated cases of black vomit<lb/>
then is not sufficient evidence of yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>On the Negative Side</hi>--i. e. the non-report--of this symptom, one<lb/>
must note that not a few of the earlier writers who lay stress on hemor-<lb/>
rhage from the mouth do not mention black vomit. They either fail to<lb/>
notice it, or fail to distinguish it from the very dark green--&ldquo;bilious&rdquo;--<lb/>
vomit so common in malarial fevers. Towne, a physician, who wrote (1726)<lb/>
an otherwise extremely good description of yellow fever in Barbadoes,<lb/>
states that &ldquo;the vomit in bad cases becomes bilious.&rdquo;</p>
<p>P&egrave;re du Tertre mentions excessive vomiting, but not black vomit, in<lb/>
<pb n="41" id="f01314041"/>
in<lb/>
3y<lb/>
the Peste of 1648 of Guadaloupe, which is generally accepted as being<lb/>
yellow fever. The <hi>mal de Siam</hi> of 1690, and later, in Martinique was cer-<lb/>
tainly yellow fever. P&egrave;re Labat, who was on the island from 1694 to<lb/>
1707, in his general description of it speaks of hemorrhages--&ldquo;the over-<lb/>
flowing of blood from all the orifices of the body, even by the pores&rdquo;<lb/>
and of the excessive vomiting &ldquo;even of worms,&rdquo; but does not specifically<lb/>
mention black vomit. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) In his own case the &ldquo;much blood from his mouth&rdquo; showed<lb/>
early on the 2nd. day of his illness and must have been a hemorrhage from<lb/>
the posterior nares and nasopharynx. Much vomiting occurred later, so<lb/>
that he could not take the sacrament, but no more is heard of hemorrhage<lb/>
and nothing of black vomit and his physician did not regard him as dan-<lb/>
gerously ill. A large gastric hemorrhage on the 2nd. day had been death.<lb/>
(End of foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
It is not probable that the good father would have recognized black vomit<lb/>
<unclear>except</unclear><lb/>
as being blood. Its appearance does not at all suggest blood, unless, of<lb/>
course, in those extremely rare--and always fatal--cases in which the<lb/>
hemorrhage is so profuse that the vomit is of <hi>red</hi> unaltered blood. In-<lb/>
deed, La Roche states that it was not until 1750 that Henry Warren show-<lb/>
ed that black vomit was blood altered by the gastric juices. (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) &ldquo;I ought to observe here that the fatal black Stool and<lb/>
Vomitings are vulgarly supposed to be only large Quantities of black<lb/>
Bile or Cholor, which false Notion seems to be owing to that fixed un-<lb/>
happy Prejudice that the Fever is purely <hi>Bilious</hi>. But let any one only<lb/>
dip in a Bit of white Linen Cloth and he will be soon undeceived and con-<lb/>
vinced that scarce anything but mortified Blood is then voided, for the<lb/>
Cloth will appear tinged a deep bloody Red or Purple, of the which I<lb/>
have made many Experiments.&rdquo; (Malignant Fever in the Barbadoes in 1734<lb/>
<pb n="42" id="f01314042"/>
1734<lb/>
4y<lb/>
to 1738. Letter to Dr. Meade by Henry Warren M. D., 1738: p. 39) (End of<lb/>
foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Yet even in 1806 and '07 &ldquo;the learned Bancroft,&rdquo; in his Gulston-<lb/>
ian Lectures of those years argues <hi>in extenso</hi> for this black vomit being<lb/>
gastric hemorrhage and James Johnson (Treatise on Tropical Climates) in<lb/>
1827, is only &ldquo;inclined to accept&rdquo; this view which &ldquo;nearly coincided with<lb/>
the opinions of some other accurate observers.&rdquo; Its nature was evidently<lb/>
not considered beyond dispute even then.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the Spanish Americans knew the disease as<lb/>
<hi>V&oacute;mito Prieto</hi>--black vomit--long before this symptom was given prominence<lb/>
by the English. Indeed, a statement as to the nature of the vomit, iden-<lb/>
tical to that made by Warren, appears in the description of the <hi>Peste</hi><lb/>
of 1648 in Yucatan--&ldquo;there followed some vomits as of rotted blood.&rdquo; (Foot<lb/>
note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) &ldquo;Sequ&iacute;anse unos v&oacute;mitos como de sangre podrido.&rdquo; Historia de<lb/>
Yucatan escrito en el Siglo XV11 por el R. P. Fray Diego Lopez Cogalludo.<lb/>
Libro X11, Cap&iacute;tulo 14. (End of foot note).<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
This <hi>Peste</hi> was quite certainly yellow fever.</p>
<p>For the Positive Side of the question, however, we can say that a<lb/>
fever epidemic in a hot climate in which either of these two symptoms,<lb/>
hemorrhage from about the mouth (Foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
(Foot note) Always excluding scurvy (End of foot note)<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
or black vomit, the latter especially, was noted as of fairly frequent<lb/>
occurrence must, in the present state of our knowledge, be considered as having<lb/>
been either yellow fever or one of the tick-borne spirochetoses and very gen-<lb/>
erally the former. The writer knows of but two instances of such an epi-<lb/>
<pb n="43" id="f01314043"/>
epi-<lb/>
5y<lb/>
demic being other than yellow fever: one in Senegal, reported by Noc<lb/>
and Nogu&eacute; in 1921, and one in Barbadoes, investigated by Guiteras in<lb/>
1916, which probably was also a spirochetosis. Both showed a greater<lb/>
mortality among negroes than whites and a longer survival of fatal cases<lb/>
than is normal for yellow fever. There may have been others of the<lb/>
same kind, however, not recognized.</p>
<p>Black vomit under such conditions, in the Americas at least, is<lb/>
well nigh pathognomonic of yellow fever. The Spanish Americans early<lb/>
crystalized this idea in the name of the disease, &ldquo;<hi>v&oacute;mito prieto</hi>,&rdquo; and<lb/>
Sir William Pym--<hi>nomen clarum et venerabile</hi> in the history of yellow<lb/>
fever--laid stress on it above all things. To <hi>him</hi> black vomit <hi>was yel</hi>-<lb/>
low fever and hedging a very little and expressing what I think he real-<lb/>
ly intended, we may say that an epidemic fever in which black vomit is<lb/>
at all common is, in tropical America, almost certainly yellow fever--<lb/>
but for the Barbadoes fever of 1916 one would strike out the &ldquo;almost.&rdquo;</p>
<p>If this epidemic gives a much lower mortality among negroes than<lb/>
other races: if it be decidedly a civic rather than a rural disease: if<lb/>
death is usually from the 5th. to the 7th. day and second attacks do not<lb/>
occur the evidence for it being yellow fever seems impregnable, although<lb/>
it was strong enough before.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
