<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01315001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Ordinance for the Control of Mosquito Production, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01315001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Florida</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>12 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01315001</idno>
<title>Ordinance for the Control of Mosquito Production, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This Florida ordinance forbids untreated water collection, specifies treatments for collected water, and permits inspection and charges for violations.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Ordinance for the Control of Mosquito Production, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01315001"/>
<p>F.<lb/>
Misc.<lb/>
<hi>Florida</hi><lb/>
H R C<lb/>
<hi><unclear>the</unclear></hi></p>
<p>(HEADING)</p>
<p><hi>ORDINANCE FOR THE CONTROL OF MOSQUITO PRODUCTION</hi></p>
<p>Be it ordained by the __________________________________<lb/>
______________ of the _______________ of _______________Fla.</p>
<p><hi>ORDINANCE FOR THE PREVENTION OF MOSQUITO PRODUCTION</hi></p>
<p>Be it ordained by the __________________________________<lb/>
______________of the _______________of ___________________________Florida.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01315002"/>
<p>MOSQUITO PREVENTION OF PROPAGATION</p>
<p><hi>Section 1</hi>. It shall be unlawful to (have, keep, maintain, cause)<lb/>
or permit, within the incorporated limits of , Florida,<lb/>
any collection of water, standing or flowing, in which mosquitoes breed<lb/>
or are likely to breed, unless such collection of water is treated so as<lb/>
to effectually prevent such breeding.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01315003"/>
<p><hi>Section 2</hi>. The natural presence of mosquito larvae in any<lb/>
water, standing or running, shall be evidence that mosquitoes are<lb/>
breeding therein</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01315004"/>
<p><hi>Section 3</hi>. The collection of water considered by Section 1 of<lb/>
this ordinance shall be held to be those contained in sluggish streams,<lb/>
pools in streams, ditches, ponds, pools, excavations, holes, depressions,<lb/>
open cess pools, catch basins, privy vaults, fountains, cisterns, tanks,<lb/>
shallow wells, barrels, troughs (except horse and chicken troughs in fre-<lb/>
quent use), urns, cans, boxes, bottles, tubs, buckets, defective house<lb/>
roof gutters, tanks of <del>rarely used</del> flush closets, or other similar water<lb/>
containers.</p>
<p><unclear>S</unclear></p>
<pb n="5" id="f01315005"/>
<p><hi>Section 4.</hi> The methods of treatment of any collections of<lb/>
water, that are specified in Section 2, directed toward the prevention<lb/>
of breeding of mosquitoes shall be approved by the health officer and<lb/>
may be any one or more of the following:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Screening with wire netting of at leat 18 meshes to the<lb/>
inch each way or any other material which will effectually<lb/>
prevent the ingress or egress of mosquitoes.</item>
<item>(b) Complete emptying every 7 days of unscreened containers,<lb/>
together with their thorough drying or cleaning.</item>
<item>(c) Using a larvacide approved and applied under the direction<lb/>
of the health officer.</item>
<item>(d) Covering completely the surface of the water with kerosene,<lb/>
petroleum or paraffin oil once every seven days.</item>
<item>(e) Cleaning and keeping sufficiently free of vegetable growth<lb/>
and other obstructions, and stocking with mosquito destroy-<lb/>
ing fish; absence of half grown mosquito larvae to be evi-<lb/>
dence of compliance with the measure.</item>
<pb n="6" id="f01315006"/>
<item>Section 4.<lb/>
(Continued)</item>
<item>(f) Filling or draining to the satisfaction of<lb/>
the health officer.</item>
<item>(g) Proper disposal of tin cans, tin boxes, broken<lb/>
or empty bottles and similar articles likely to<lb/>
hold water.</item>
</list></p>
<pb n="7" id="f01315007"/>
<p><hi>Section 5</hi>. Should the person or persons responsible for the conditions<lb/>
giving rise to the breeding of mosquitoes fail or refuse to take the<lb/>
measures necessary to prevent their breeding within three (3) days after<lb/>
due notice given by the Health Officer, or his Agent, they shall be deemed<lb/>
guilty of a violation of this ordinance and the Health Officer is also<lb/>
authorised to prevent such breeding himself, and all necessary costs in-<lb/>
curred by him in so doing shall be a charge against the owner of the<lb/>
property, the tenant, or other person responsible as the case may be.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f01315008"/>
<p><hi>Section 6.</hi> Should the person or persons responsible for the<lb/>
conditions likely to give rise to the breeding of mosquitoes (Section 3)<lb/>
fail or refuse to take the measures necessary to prevent their breeding,<lb/>
as indicated by Section 4, within 10? days after due notice<lb/>
given by the Health Officer, or his Agent, (<del>_______days after the<lb/>
passage of the ordinance)</del> they shall be deemed guilty of a violation of<lb/>
this ordinance and the Health Officer is also authorised to prevent such<lb/>
breeding himself, and all necessary costs incurred by him in so doing<lb/>
shall be a charge against the property owner, the tenant, or other person<lb/>
responsible as the case may be.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f01315009"/>
<p>A failure to comply with this ordinance<lb/>
within the limits of time set by each subse-<lb/>
quent notice shall be deemed a separate<lb/>
violation of this ordinance</p>
<p>Insert a for <del>page</del> section 7</p>
<pb n="10" id="f01315010"/>
<p><hi>Section <del>6</del>-</hi>7. The health officer shall enforce the provisions of<lb/>
this ordinance, and for this purpose the health officer, person or persons<lb/>
acting under his authority may at all reasonable times enter in and upon<lb/>
any premises within his jurisdiction; and any person or persons charged<lb/>
with any of the duties imposed by this ordinance failing within the time<lb/>
designated by this ordinance or within the time stated in the notice of<lb/>
the health officer, as the case may be, to perform such duties, or to<lb/>
carry out the necessary measures to the satisfaction of the health officer,<lb/>
shall be deemed guilty of violation of this ordinance, and <add>Insert <hi>a</hi></add> for each (day<lb/>
after the expiration of this time that said person fails to comply with<lb/>
this ordinance shall be deemed guilty of a separate violation of this<lb/>
ordinance.)</p>
<p><unclear>6</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>6</unclear></p>
<pb n="11" id="f01315011"/>
<p><hi>Section <del>7</del>-</hi>8. The person held under this ordinance to be responsible<lb/>
for the correction of conditions on premises giving rise to or likely to<lb/>
give rise to breeding of mosquitoes, shall be the owner, and in his absence,<lb/>
the agent of owner of said premises; <hi>provided</hi>, any tenant, causing or per-<lb/>
mitting said conditions without the consent of the owner or agent shall be<lb/>
held responsible. Where a trespasser or other person is known to cause<lb/>
or to have caused said conditions without the consent of owner, agent, or<lb/>
tenant, then such person will be held responsible.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f01315012"/>
<p><hi>Section <del>8</del>-</hi>9 Any person who shall violate any provision of this<lb/>
ordinance shall on each conviction be subject to a fine of not more<lb/>
than $_____________, or be imprisoned for not more than ________days,<lb/>
or both, in the discretion of the court. All acts or parts of acts<lb/>
in conflict with this ordinance are hereby repealed, and this ordinance<lb/>
shall be in full force and effect ________days after its approval.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
