<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01327001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memoranda of Physical Survey of Portions of the Site to be Covered by the Water Impounded at Badin, North Carolina, by Henry Rose Carter and Joseph A. LePrince, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01327001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Badin (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01327001</idno>
<title>Memoranda of Physical Survey of Portions of the Site to be Covered by the Water Impounded at Badin, North Carolina, by Henry Rose Carter and Joseph A. LePrince, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter and LePrince describe a planned pond and the mosquito control measures that should be undertaken in constructing and maintaining it.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Memoranda of Physical Survey of Portions of the Site to be Covered by the Water Impounded at Badin, North Carolina, by Henry Rose Carter and Joseph A. LePrince, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01327001"/>
<p>MEMO OF PHYSICAL SURVEY OF PORTIONS OF THE SITE<lb/>
TO <hi>BE COVERED BY THE WATER IMPOUNDED AT BADIN, NORTH CAROLINA</hi></p>
<p><hi>PRESENT CONDITION</hi></p>
<p>From conversation with Mr. Hardaway and the Assistant<lb/>
<unclear>Warden</unclear> at the convict camp, we learned that there had evidently<lb/>
been much malaria in this immediate vicinity of recent years.<lb/>

We also heard of this disease on the upper part of Beaver Dam<lb/>
Creek. Even without this information we came across- we were<lb/>
not looking for them- so considerable a number of places physically<lb/>
well suited for breeding anopheles that we would have come to<lb/>
the same conclusion. As these will generally be destroyed by<lb/>
filling the pond they will not be especially enumerated. There<lb/>
is no question that where people are thick enough there should be<lb/>
considerable malaria in this country.</p>
<p><hi>GENERAL MEASURES</hi>:</p>
<p>We aim to prevent or lessen the breeding of mosquitoes<lb/>
and to do this by exposing their larvae (wiggle-tails) to wave<lb/>
action and fish, which are the main agents that destroy them.</p>
<p>We can do little to influence wave-action as it depends<lb/>
mainly on the shape of the shore. The removal of heavy drift<lb/>
wood, however, will help this to some extent. To increase<lb/>
the action of fish we can do much and at this place fish will be<lb/>
in many portions of the pond our sole dependence against mosquitoes.</p>
<p>The larvae are protected against fish by small floatage next<lb/>
<add>to or</add> against the bank, and our object is- first, to prevent its<lb/>
formation, and second, to strand it up on the bank above water.<lb/>
The latter method is by far the most efficacious. Naturally<lb/>
all floating material that stays in the pond any length of time<lb/>
will reach the bank unless prevented by some obstruction from<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01327002"/>
No. 2<lb/>
doing so. If this happens when the pond is high it will be left<lb/>
stranded upon the bank when the pond falls. We must then not allow<lb/>
obstructions to exist, which will prevent this floatage reaching<lb/>
the bank.</p>
<p>I will take then two datum lines- one, the 544 contour,<lb/>
your ordinary maximum level, the lower contour <del>515</del><add>505</add>, not left bare<lb/>
more than ten consecutive days.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Trees and brush completely submerged at all times are<lb/>
of no importance and can be left. The same is true of such in the<lb/>
pond (away from the bank) that do not reach above contour 505.<lb/>
Hardwood trees anywhere in the pond are a matter of small importance<lb/>
and need not be cut for sanitary reasons, though I understand<lb/>
it is proposed to do so to prevent interference with the operation<lb/>
of the plant. Pine trees, whose tops come above 505, should be<lb/>
&ldquo;<unclear>ringed</unclear>&rdquo; (belted) or cut down <hi>this spring</hi> so that they may not cast<lb/>
pine needles in the pond in the summer of 1917, and laps of trees<lb/>
anywhere in the pond that will float up to the surface, are to be<lb/>
removed or destroyed.</item>
<item>(2) Clear the edges of the pond of brush. Taking the<lb/>
544 contour go up- say- three feet above it on very steep banks and<lb/>
10 or 15 feet above it on sloping banks- measured on the surface.<lb/>
Cut all brush that will stop floatage down to the contour 505 and<lb/>
below <unclear>it-say-</unclear> three feet on steep slopes and 10 ft. on gentle<lb/>
slopes. This stuff that is cut must be removed from the pond either<lb/>
by dragging above the clear space or by a complete burning. All laps<lb/>
down in this clear space must of course be removed.</item>
<item><p>(3) When there are thick groves of hardwood sapplings<lb/>
growing at any point within the clear edge, whose tops project above<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01327003"/>
No. 3<lb/>
contour 505 and are so thick as to stop a considerable amount of<lb/>
drift they should be cut down and removed. The same for the<lb/>
brushy tops or trees not far from the shore line.</p>
<p>In our judgment this is all of the cutting that will do any<lb/>
good as a sanitary measure, but I cannot lay too much stress upon the<lb/>
necessity of removing the things cut from the pond. The stumps<lb/>
on the upper contours of this edge should be cut as low as<lb/>
possible, because if the water covers it most of the time the<lb/>
stump will not throw up sprouts. If it does not, it will., It will<lb/>
be necessary, I think, once or possibly twice a year, for the first<lb/>
few years, to go over this edge above your ordinary high water line<lb/>
to cut off the sprouts that come up.</p>
<p>It will not be necessary to do any of this work in such<lb/>
parts of the pond as are- say- 1-1/4 miles from a residence, an<lb/>
occupied house. This distance is in excess of what is deemed<lb/>
generally necessary, but is specified as giving quite a factor of<lb/>
safety.</p></item>
<item>(4) If it be practicable, weather conditions may prevent it,<lb/>
it would be of very great advantage to burn over the pond site, the<lb/>
whole of it, just before it is filled, as close to the filling as<lb/>
possible. This will get rid of leaves, pine needles and small<lb/>
brush generally which would otherwise rise up and float on the<lb/>
pond. It will also tend to kill the stumps that are above high<lb/>
water level.</item>
<item>(6) With a pond in which there will be as large fluctuations<lb/>
of level as this one it will be advisable to lockout and see if it<lb/>
will leave pools or ponds as it falls, and if so, to drain them<lb/>
by suitable ditches. Likely enough it will be impracticable to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01327004"/>
No. 4<lb/>
judge of this over all parts of the pond until after the pond is<lb/>
filled and you see whether it does leave such pool. A pool<lb/>
drained within fourteen or sixteen days of its formation does no<lb/>
harm and a pool that does not last that <unclear>time,</unclear> by drying up or<lb/>
otherwise, does no harm.</item>
<item>(7) Since you are depending mainly on fish for control<lb/>
of the mosquito breeding in this pond I would advise you to make<lb/>
arrangements for getting such fish, either this fall or at least<lb/>
very early next spring, the former being preferable.</item>
<item>(8) The U. S. Fish Commission has a hatchery of mosquito<lb/>
eating fish at Elizabeth City, N.C. Note that the fish you want<lb/>
are <hi>TOP MINNOWS</hi>. Game fish would be a disadvantage to you<lb/>
as they would eat the minnows instead of the mosquito larvae.<lb/>
The minnows are needed in large quantities.</item>
<item>(9) <hi>SPECIAL LOCALITIES</hi>.<lb/>
Referring to property map-<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. I do not think any of the willows here except those<lb/>
next to the bank and next to the Whitney Dam are high enough to<lb/>
require attention. Those next to the bank on both sides are<lb/>
to be cut.</item>
<item>2. There is a lot of debris here, old trestles, etc.,<lb/>
which should be removed, as they will float up when the pond is<lb/>
low. Burn them.</item>
<item>3 &amp; 4. Measures to be taken- Clearing of the brush, etc.,<lb/>
are provided for in the general measures but they should be<lb/>
taken with <hi>extreme pains</hi> and more brush removed than seems<lb/>
necessary on account of their proximity to Whitney, which doubtless<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01327005"/>
No. 5<lb/>
will have considerable population.</item>
<item><p>5. The old canal and bights that go off from it will likely<lb/>
be <add>a</add> <hi>very</hi> troublesome proposition. Indeed a good part of the bottom<lb/>
of this canal, especially towards the lower part, was probably<lb/>
breeding profusely the last few summers. It is in every way<lb/>
well fitted physically for breeding mosquitoes now. It, too, will<lb/>
have to be cleaned more than ordinary and the edges and banks<lb/>
kept clean more than is necessary for the rest of the pond.</p>
<p>This place is dangerous for three reasons.</p>
<p>It is close to considerable villages, Palmerville and<lb/>
Whitney. It is so narrow that wave action will have no effect<lb/>
and we will have to depend entirely upon fish. The sides are<lb/>
so steep- vertical in many places- that the fluctuations of the<lb/>
pond will not rid us of floatage.</p>
<p>The measures devised for the rest of the pond must<lb/>
be acentuated for this canal and bights. It must be very carefully<lb/>
cleared. The bank must be kept clear of floating material, by<lb/>
hand I expect, and it must be especially stocked with fish.<lb/>
I believe however that these places are in their natural con-<lb/>
dition, producing many anopheles.</p></item>
<item>6. Is simply marked because all along the edge of this<lb/>
cliff there is a very large amount of tree laps in the woods, some<lb/>
of which would float up and hence should be removed.</item>
<item>7. In the lower reaches of Beaver Dam Creek most of the<lb/>
stuff will be completely submerged and needs no attention. I<lb/>
think the edges will require cutting.</item>
</list></item>
<item>10. The upper reaches of Beaver Dam Creek and Reynolds Fork<lb/>
are in quite flat country and there are a number of farm houses<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01327006"/>
No. 6<lb/>
empty around them. These places will probably be dangerous<lb/>
as they are too narrow for wave action to do much good.<lb/>
They are far less dangerous however than the canal.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1st. Because there are not nearly so many people.</item>
<item>2nd. In shoal water the fish have a great deal more<lb/>
control of the mosquitoes.</item>
<item>3rd. The gentle slope of the banks allows floatage<lb/>
to strand; hence, we should have clean edges.<lb/>
An extra planting of minnows in this locality<lb/>
is very advisable; also lookout for pools left<lb/>
by the falling pond.</item>
</list></item></list></p>
<p>For the convenience of anyone making a biological survey of<lb/>
this place during the summer, which should be done, as it would<lb/>
throw much light upon its present condition in the productions<lb/>
of malaria breeding mosquitoes. We would enumerate such of these<lb/>
places which seem to us physically well suited for breeding<lb/>
anopheles, as we have noticed. (See numbers on map).</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Back of the old Whitney Office site there are a number of<lb/>
pools physically well suited for breeding.</item>
<item>2. Behind railway fill just below Whitney- two places<lb/>
in upper part- one in lower.</item>
<item>3. Second bight below Whitney beyond the Winston-Salem<lb/>
Southbound, a large area physically well suited for breeding.</item>
<item>4. In the valley of Beaver Dam Creek where the road crosses<lb/>
it, not far from the river, at No. 7.</item>
<item>5. At No. 8 from the mouth of Buffalo Creek down to Beaver<lb/>
Dam and between them, a large area are well suited for production.</item>
<item>6. At Glady Fork, where it joins Beaver Dam, the creek<lb/>
spreads out into a number of pools extremely well suited for<lb/>
breeding.</item>
<pb n="7" id="f01327007"/>
<item>No. 7</item>
<item>7. A small place, Spring Head and Marshy Stream, to the<lb/>
rear of Elliott's house, about 200 yards off. This may dry up<lb/>
in summer time.</item>
<item>8. At saw mill beyond Elliott's house, a large breeding<lb/>
place.</item>
<item>9. Beyond the abandoned house of J.C. Russell, a series of<lb/>
pools in the woods.</item>
<item>10. At the crossing of Reynolds Fork near a saw mill, beyond<lb/>
this place and at the crossing of the last fork of Beaver Dam Creek<lb/>
where the land is very flat, are several large areas.</item>
<item>11. At two crossings of Reynolds Fork going back towards<lb/>
the Yadkin, several pools on the side of the road in the woods<lb/>
on the uplands going towards the Yadkin; one place in cat-tails,<lb/>
in the race of the power plant.</item>
</list></p>
<p>It is not pretended that these are all or even any<lb/>
considerable proportion of the breeding places in the area to be<lb/>
covered by the pond. They are simply some that we noted as we<lb/>
passed along part of its periphery.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>CARE OF THE POND AFTER IT IS FILLED</hi>.</head>
<item>1. Keep the winter level of the pond from October 1st to<lb/>
June 15th or 30th as high as possible so as to strand all of the<lb/>
floatage that comes to the banks at this time of the year when the<lb/>
pond falls towards the summer level.</item>
<item>2. Save the summer floods, July 1st to Oct. 1st, as<lb/>
much as you can so as to have the pond level fluctuate during this<lb/>
season. It is understood that the summer level is less, by<lb/>
some feet, than the normal winter level. The pond should not<lb/>
be kept up during the summer time into the line of already stranded<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01327008"/>
No. 8<lb/>
drift as long as three weeks, preferably not over two weeks. It<lb/>
will generally be impossible to do this even if you wish it.</item>
<item>3. For the first few years we judge it will be necessary<lb/>
to cut down the sprouts that will come up above your 544 contour.<lb/>
Below that contour it should be kept clean of living growth, the<lb/>
pond itself.</item>
<item>4. The edge of the pond should be examined from time to time,<lb/>
between July 1st and Oct. 1st, so that collections of logs and heavy<lb/>
drifts that may possibly land against the bank, and yet be floating,<lb/>
can be dragged out. This will probably not be necessary after the<lb/>
first <del>of the</del> year.</item>
</list></p>
<p>If collections of small floatage are seen resting against<lb/>
the bank it, too, should be dragged out. The banks of the canal<lb/>
and its bights from Whitney down should be given very special<lb/>
attention in this respect, and will we fear require much attention.<lb/>
It all depends on how efficacious the fish will prove here.</p>
<p>Nothing is advised to prevent the growth of aquatic plants<lb/>
which in future may be a problem. This condition will have to<lb/>
be met when it arises, if it does arise. We do not know enough<lb/>
of this yet to advise general <del>maneuvers</del><add>measures</add> in advance.</p>
<p>The measures we have indicated above are about all that are<lb/>
applicable for the control of mosquito (Anopholes) production<lb/>
by this pond within allowable economic limits. They are in excess<lb/>
of what we would feel justified in requiring, but are as specified<lb/>
for the following reasons:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. The very considerable number of people who will be<lb/>
adjacent to the pond at Whitney, Palmerville and Badin.</item>
<item>2. The unusual risk of mosquito production entailed by the<lb/>
canal and the bights behind the Winston-SalemRR track.</item>
<pb n="9" id="f01327009"/>
<item>No. 9</item>
<item>3. The statement that you were prepared to carry out all<lb/>
measures which would do good at any reasonable expense.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Even with these measures carried out it is not pretended<lb/>
that there will be no anopholes production in the pond. There<lb/>
will be. The total production of the pond site will likely be<lb/>
no greater or less than at present, but the location of breeding<lb/>
will be changed, and malaria may be increased in some places.<lb/>
The measures advised should however minimize mosquito production and<lb/>
this with proper screening, and possibly the use of quinine should<lb/>
minimize the malaria in the community.</p>
<p>It must be noted that the increase in population adjacent to<lb/>
the canal would increase the number of malaria cases among them,<lb/>
even with no change in the condition of the breeding places.<lb/>
This increase will be out of proportion to the increase in population,<lb/>
rather as a funtion of the square, or possibly of the third power of<lb/>
that increase, and this must be discounted in estimating the<lb/>
malaria due directly to mosquitoes produced in the pond. It will<lb/>
be the more noticeable as people come in from non-malarious<lb/>
communities.</p>
<closer>
<signed>H. R. Carter<lb/>
ASST. SURGEON-GENERAL, U.S.P.H.S.<lb/>
<hi>J. A. LePrince</hi><lb/>
(Per H. R. C.)<lb/>
SANITARY ENGINEER, U.S.P.H.S.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
