<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01324019">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Outline on malaria in the United States, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01324019</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Minnesota</name>
<name type="place">Kentucky</name>
<name type="place">Maryland</name>
<name type="place">New York</name>
<name type="place">New England</name>
<name type="place">England</name>
<name type="place">Germany</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Memphis General Hospital, Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01324019</idno>
<title>Outline on malaria in the United States, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The writer outlines the reduction in malaria in the United States and discusses probable causes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="[19**-00-00">
<head>Outline on malaria in the United States, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01324019"/>
<p>The Diminution of Malaria in The U.S.<lb/>
(Very) tentative outline.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>I. Where and to what extent diminution.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1) Osler-former prevalence Ontario.</item>
<item>2) Johns Hopk. hosp. Thayer.</item>
<item>3) Charity Hosp. N.O. (Data here less r<add>e</add>liable, but I went over some of<lb/>
their records myself, selecting those with blood examinations. In all hosp.<lb/>
compare blood diag. malaria with total amount of disease)</item>
<item>4) Memphis General, here possibly a case of no diminution in amount of<lb/>
malaria.</item>
<item>5) Personal communication Mayo people Rochester, Minn. as to<lb/>
cases Minnesota 1900 and diminution in Minn.</item>
<item>6) Possibly something dependable Delta region Miss. 1925 rate-blood<lb/>
exam. compared with earliest blood examination records- Bass, Mayne.<lb/>
Something from records of plantation doctors of cases now and formerly<lb/>
same plantation.</item>
<item>7) Writers own recollection malaria middle west early times and now,<lb/>
although too young to remember much of earliest pioneer times.<lb/>
General, caution as regards validity of figures not based <unclear>on</unclear> positive<lb/>
findings, but testimony seems very strong to effect that there has been<lb/>
almost total disappearance north of S. Mo. Ky. and Md.(except small<lb/>
epidemics N.Y. and N. England) and in general a diminution in more<lb/>
southerly regions. Compare <unclear>Diminution</unclear>. England, Germany, France etc.<lb/>
Here mention of regions where a parently no diminution.</item>
<item>My <unclear>M. C.</unclear> paper,<lb/>
Anebec?<lb/>
<hi>name</hi><lb/>
N. W. Ohio=Austin<lb/>
&amp; <del>control</del><lb/>
<unclear>N. OC.</unclear> Ind, Cairooll 1879-little 1887-N. replaced by <unclear>White-Sand cleaned</unclear><lb/>
<hi>Md</hi> almost now <hi>in</hi><lb/>
<unclear>now; H. O.</unclear><lb/>
<hi>Va</hi>-our family after war<lb/>
<unclear>now known now</unclear><lb/>
H. C. H.<lb/>
<unclear>TV. E.</unclear><lb/>
Cattle not<unclear>pls on</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>sed in Va s. Starter serita</unclear> except Milch <unclear>korn</unclear><lb/>
<unclear><hi>invited</hi></unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Quantico pgs</unclear></item>
</list></item>
<item>II. Cause of Diminution.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>A. Cheaper quinine, heavier dosage, longer treatment.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1) Quote Dr. Carter paper P.H.R.</item>
<item><p>2) Opinion of Osler malaria Ontario, disappearance due to cinchonizat.<lb/>
Quebec name-date; Cairooll, 1879-1<lb/>
Quinine <unclear>probably</unclear> an important factor but has time of diminution<lb/>
in general coincided with any change in dosage or cheapness of quinine?</p>
<p>Quote paper German writer diminution malaria Germany before any change in<lb/>
dosage of quinine.</p></item>
</list></item>
<item><del>III. Diminution Anopheles</del></item>
<pb n="2" id="f01324020"/>
<item>2.</item>
<item>B. Diminution due to <unclear>diminution</unclear> of Anopheles due to drainage<lb/>
incident on imporvement in Agriculture? &amp; <unclear>always</unclear><lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1) MIddle west (where author grew up) same history of disappearance of malar.<lb/>
but little water to drain.-</item>
<item><p>2) Diminution (certainly at present a low rate) S. Louisiana, Ark.<lb/>
where rice and very numerous A. quadrimaculatus. Also undrained regions<lb/>
where cane cultivation-little malaria and abundant Anopheles.<lb/>
Persistence malaria edge of rice region in Ark. where little improvement<lb/>
in dwellings, etc.</p>
<p>Va<lb/>
Cairo<lb/>
<unclear>humanitarian</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>pools</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Quantico</unclear></p>
<p>Probably diminution of Anoph. an important factor some regions, but not<lb/>
generally important as commonly supposed? Certainly a low rate possible where<lb/>
A. quad. very abundant. but (only in a far places) in the U. S. this is<unclear>I than<lb/>
rather X'tieval</unclear></p></item>
</list></item>
<item>C. Diminution due to change in economic status of people?<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>1) Disappear. of mal. northern states coincided roughly with<lb/>
diacontinuance of pioneer conditions of life. (My own experience<lb/>
pioneer conditions middle west and changes in manner of living)</p>
<p>good</p></item>
<item>2) Compare prosperous rice country ArK, with regions bordering on it.</item>
<item><p>3)Present economic condition delta coton plantations.</p>
<p><unclear>How,</unclear> is this,</p></item>
<item><p>4)Brief analysis as to just what economic changes have taken place<lb/>
Western U.S. (writer's own recollections and other information)<lb/>
IN general both in this country and in Europe diminution of mal.<lb/>
has in time more nearly co<del>n</del>incided with improved conditions of living<lb/>
than with change in any other factor. Examples of effect of adverse<lb/>
change conditions life on malaria-military, construction camps,<lb/>
change of crops, etc. Rise of indig. mal. Europe following war, but rapid<lb/>
return to normal. Improvement should be <hi>general</hi> for best results.</p>
<p><unclear>Prove in Md</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Camps day War</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>at crosselt</unclear><lb/>
has it done so in S R<lb/>
Diminution in <unclear>many plexes from A. Central.</unclear></p></item>
</list></item>
<item><p>D. Diminution due to animal husbandry-zoophilism.</p>
<p>Probably not an important factor S. U.S. for no stables to conform to<lb/>
Roubaud hypothesis. (maybe in Middle West, N. O. Ind, <unclear>I'll &amp; W is</unclear></p>
<p>Summary. Of different factors that of improvement in living conditions<lb/>
probably of most weight in this country. Other <unclear>factors</unclear> not to be neglected.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01324021"/>
<p>3.</p>
<p>History of malaria in the U.S. any guide to direction of anti-malaria<lb/>
work? Not easy to improve conditions of life, but education and the like may<lb/>
help. In the south, at least, one would be pulling with the tide, because<lb/>
already present a strong tendency to improvement. Anyhow, well to<lb/>
make clear to a community to what extent their salvation depends<lb/>
on themselves and that it is not necessary to wait on the State, the Govt.<lb/>
or the I.H.B. to improve their conditions. Probably generally true<lb/>
that a people gets the sort of government that it deserves. Is it not<lb/>
also true that a people (in this country, at least) has about as much malaria as<lb/>
(of malaria.<lb/>
it deserves? Assuming that it has been instructed as to method of transmission</p>
<p>Is my own observation generally correct, that a comparatively small<lb/>
improvement in general social status is followed by a relatively large<lb/>
diminution in <unclear>mix</unclear> malaria? Optimistic, but, I think, generally true.</p>
<p>Yes</p>
<p>You see that there is plenty that one can say on the subject, but<lb/>
so little definite information as to how much and where the malaria diminution<lb/>
has occurred and where it has not diminished but increased. I think our obser-<lb/>
vations on the present status of this region will be about the best part of<lb/>
the paper. I should much appreciate any guide as to where I could get<lb/>
more information regarding localities still highly malarious and regarding<lb/>
economic conditions there.</p></item>
</list></item></list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
