<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01328002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Pioneering in Panama, by Mayme Ober Peak, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01328002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Eugenia Hook</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">United States, Cuba, Canal Zone, Russia, South America</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Brunswick (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">McHenry (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">South (U.S.)</name>
<name type="place">Ship Island (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Ancon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>16 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01328002</idno>
<title>Pioneering in Panama, by Mayme Ober Peak, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Peake's story on the work of Henry Rose Carter and William Gorgas in ridding Panama of yellow fever includes excerpts from Laura Armistead's Panama diary.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Pioneering in Panama, by Mayme Ober Peak, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01328002"/>
<p>Miscl<lb/>
Biographic<lb/>
H. R. C.</p>
<p>Miss M. O. Peak,<lb/>
1722 H. St.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>PIONEERING IN PANAMA.</p>
<p>Excerpts from the <unclear>Panama</unclear> diary of Miss Laura Armstead Carter,<lb/>
first American girl on the Isthmus, and only daughter of General<lb/>
Henry Rose Carter:</p>
<p>Dec. 5, 1904.....When we got to our quarters and shut the screen<lb/>
door behind us, Father said: "Now listen, children! If a <unclear>boa</unclear><lb/>
constrictor or tiger gets in the house, it doesn't make much<lb/>
difference, but if a mosquito gets in, you must stop <unclear>everything</unclear> else<lb/>
and look for that mosquito until you find it and kill it, no matter<lb/>
how <unclear>long</unclear> it takes. During our whole stay on the Isthmus, we never<lb/>
left water in glasses, left a screen door or window other than tightly<lb/>
closed, or did anything that would in any way aid and abet our worst<lb/>
enemy - the mosquito.</p>
<p>It was a simple and patriarchal life we led at the beginning. The<lb/>
<unclear>mess</unclear> hall, under our quarters, consisted of a few long tables - one<lb/>
for the doctors with Colonal Gorgas and Father at opposite ends,<lb/>
Mother and Mrs. Gorgas and I being the only things feminine <unclear>there at</unclear>,<lb/>
and the others for the nurses, more doctors, the quartermaster and clerks.<lb/>
We lived at that <unclear>mess</unclear> four years and its weekly and unchangeable menus<lb/>
are indelibly graven on my memory...We went down to coffee at 6:30 a.m. --<lb/>
an orange <unclear>a piece</unclear>, peeled and stuck on a fork -- it requires some dexterity<lb/>
to eat them -- cold-storage eggs (very musty as to taste and improved<lb/>
by orange marmalade) excellent crusty bread. None of us liked eggs.<lb/>
Indeed, it was only after a solemn assurance of Father's that we<lb/>
couldn't come to Panama if we didn't eat eggs that we had mournfully<lb/>
begun rehearsing to see which way we disliked them least. <unclear>Scrambled</unclear>,<lb/>
with orange <unclear>marmalade</unclear> was endurable, and we never got much beyond this<lb/>
point tho we ate them steadily for four and a half years.</p>
<p><unclear>All in cookings or the mess</unclear> and the patients is done in a large<lb/>
concrete building with &ldquo;Cuisine&rdquo; inscribed above the door. It is fitted<lb/>
with great ovens, has a concrete floor, wonderful copper <unclear>kettles</unclear> and<lb/>
is a most picturesque affair. The Chef who abides there, to <unclear>Quote Father:</unclear><lb/>
&ldquo;Knows more ways of spoiling a fish than any man living.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Opposite is the Yellow Fever Ward, just up the road is the<lb/>
&ldquo;Folie Dinglier&rdquo;-- the beautiful quarters built by one of the<lb/>
French Chief Engineers for his family, who all died there of yellow fever,<lb/>
and at the top of the hill, Anconcita, the nurses have their quarters.<lb/>
It is the best location on the grounds and Father chose it for them for<lb/>
that reason as being the persons best entitled to it. Between Anconita<lb/>
and ourselves are some pavillion wards, in some of which the insane<lb/>
have been put temporarily. One Frenchman, with a tremendous voice,<lb/>
sings selections of Grand Opera for <unclear>days</unclear> without a break.....</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01328003"/>
<p>Miss Mayme Ober Peak,<lb/>
1722 H. St.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>PIONEERING IN PANAMA,</p>
<p>Authority on Yellow Fever Tells How they Conquered the Foe in the Tropics.</p>
<p>By Mayme Ober Peak.</p>
<p>(Suggestion for editor's note:</p>
<p>In this article will be found heretofore <hi>unpublished theory on<lb/>
collections of water as breeding places for mosquitoes</hi>. It upsets some<lb/>
age-old traditions).</p>
<p>**********************</p>
<p>If Diogenes were looking for the most modest man, he would find<lb/>
<unclear>him</unclear>, after considerable search, in an old-fashioned frame house in<lb/>
Washington, tucked behind a fashionable apartment on one of the Capital's<lb/>
famous Avenues. He would find a strong link between the old-fashioned<lb/>
frame house with its rambler rose over the porch, and the fashionable<lb/>
apartment hotel with its canopied porte cochere.</p>
<p>In a top suite of the apartment hotel, the widow of Surgeon<lb/>
General Gorgas <unclear>has</unclear> been living for two years in quiet seclusion writing<lb/>
the biography of her husband and his eminent work. While in the frame<lb/>
house up the hill, Dr. Henry Rose Carter, Assistant Surgeon General-at-<lb/>
Large of the U. S. Public Health Service, and Gorgas' devoted friend and<lb/>
collaborator, is writing the history of yellow fever, which it will take<lb/>
him perhaps two years yet to complete.</p>
<p>To get General Carter - or Dr. Carter, as he prefers to be calle<lb/>
to talk about himself and his distinguished honors, is as impossible as <unclear>to</unclear><lb/>
walk through a thick wall. To get him to talk malaria or yellow fever <unclear>is</unclear><lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> to vault the wall in <unclear>to</unclear><lb/>
jumps.</p>
<p>For an informative sketch of his unique experience in hospital,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01328004"/>
2.<lb/>
quarantine and epidemic work -- in the United States, Cuba, the Canal<lb/>
Zone, Russia, South America -- the writer was forced to refer to medical<lb/>
journals. Often spoken of by General Gorgas as &ldquo;one of the great pioneers<lb/>
in malaria and yellow fever work,&rdquo; and now considered with Juan Guitteras<lb/>
one of the two ranking living authorities <unclear>on</unclear> the subject of yellow fever,<lb/>
Dr. Carter is as distinguished as he is modest. He will go down in history<lb/>
with America's great peace heroes.</p>
<p>His work on &ldquo;The Determination of the Period of Extrinsic Incubation<lb/>
of Yellow Fever,&rdquo; placed him among such immortal physicians as Finlay,<lb/>
Lazear, Reed and <unclear>Carroll</unclear>, who demonstrated the mosquito transmission of<lb/>
Yellow fever, upon which was based Gorgas' work <del><unclear></unclear></del> in freeing<lb/>
Cuba from the disease for the first time in a century; upon <add>which</add> depended the<lb/>
sanitation of the Canal Zone, and which has resulted in practically driving<lb/>
the scourge from the face of the earth.</p>
<p>In malaria suppression, Dr. Carter established new principles that<lb/>
were of far-reaching importance in the development of Southern streams.<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> He has written numerous articles on malaria and yellow fever<lb/>
and the Sections of Yellow Fever in several Systems of Medicine, both here<lb/>
and abroad, including that in the Nelson Loose-Leaf Medicine, of which<lb/>
Section he is the Editor.</p>
<p>During the war, this eminent sanitarian was in charge of the control of<lb/>
malaria in the Extra-Cantonment areas of the camps and in the regions<lb/>
around the big industrial plants engaged in the production of war material.<lb/>
In 1920<add>-21</add> he served as Sanitary Advisor to the Peruvian <unclear>Government</unclear>, and at<lb/>
present is a member of the Yellow Fever Council of the International Health<lb/>
Board of the Rockefeller Foundation.</p>
<p>Briefly summarizing the most notable of his achievements, <del><unclear>is to</unclear></del> quote<lb/>
from the Southern Medical Journal of June, 1915; which gives them, as <unclear>follow</unclear></p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. The determination of the period of extrinsic incubation of Yellow<lb/>
Fever.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f01328005"/>
<item>2. The institution of a rational relation between the disinfection<lb/>
of vessels and the detention of their personnel, permitting the fixing of<lb/>
minimum periods of detention in quarantine.</item>
<item>3. The encouragement of uniformity in quarantine practice, resulting<lb/>
in the adoption of a system of Federal quarantine regulations.</item>
<item>4. The transfer of the Brunswick, Georgia, quarantine station to<lb/>
the Federal Government, the first state or municipal quarantine to be<lb/>
thus surrendered.</item>
<item>5. The control of numerous yellow fever epidemics in the Southern<lb/>
States, and especially that of McHenry, Miss., which was the first<lb/>
epidemic of yellow fever to be suppressed in the South in the summer time.</item>
<item>6. The inauguration of the quarantine systems of Cuba and the Canal<lb/>
Zone.</item>
<item>7. The enunciation of principles relating to the bearing of<lb/>
impounding reservoirs on malaria incidence.</item>
</list></p>
<p>For his conspicuous service rendered in the construction of the<lb/>
Panama Canal, Congress created for Dr. Carter the position of Assistant<lb/>
Surgeon General-at-Large of the U. S. Public Health Service, thus breaking<lb/>
all precedents in recognizing the work of a member of that service.</p>
<p>Since many people hold that public health is a problem for engineers<lb/>
rather than doctors, Dr. Carter's accomplishment as a scientific worker in<lb/>
sanitation is probably largely due to the fact that he is both an engineer<lb/>
and a doctor. Member of <unclear>the</unclear> well-known &ldquo;Cawtah&rdquo; family of Virginia, he <unclear>was</unclear><lb/>
graduated from the University of Virginia, in 1873, as an engineer. A few<lb/>
<unclear>years</unclear> later, he graduated in medicine at the University of Maryland and,<lb/>
in 1879, entered the Marine Hospital Service. In the fall of that year, he<lb/>
saw his first case of yellow fever, being ordered to Ship Island Quarantine<lb/>
Station in the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
<p>To this Federal refuge station, came all vessels infected or thought<lb/>
to be infected. Many of them were sailing vessels from Rio, Santos, Havana,<lb/>
and Colon, which at that time were especially dangerous. Opportunity was<lb/>
afforded him not only to study a disease of far-reaching public health and<lb/>
economic importance, but to prevent its entrance into the country.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01328006"/>
<p>4.</p>
<p>Here on this lonely island, cut off from communication with the outside<lb/>
world except by boat call, Dr. Carter, with a young family growing up <unclear>around</unclear><lb/>
him, began the study of yellow fever and laid the foundation of his great<lb/>
work for its control and prevention.</p>
<p>It was a far cry from Ship Island to Panama, where Dr. Carter was<lb/>
detailed for duty in 1904 and where he organized the quarantine service an<lb/>
later served as Director of Hospitals and Chairman of the Board of Diagnos<lb/>
He remained with the Panama Canal Commission five years, and was connected<lb/>
with much of the organization and early work on the Isthmus.</p>
<p>Reminiscing of his Panama experiences, the writer caught the General<lb/>
one night in a mellow mood. It was immediately after dinner, his cigar<lb/>
was lighted, and the low card table on which he does his work was tempo-<lb/>
rarily <unclear>empty</unclear> and pushed back from its accustomed place in the middle of <unclear>the</unclear><lb/>
room. A pile of letters ready for the mail box reposed peacefully on the<lb/>
radiator; chairs and couch of the impromptu office were filled with gapin<lb/>
letter files and Spanish reference books, and an overflow of pamphlets<lb/>
spilled on the floor.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We were just three old codgers,&rdquo; he said, resting his cane against<lb/>
the fireplace and lifting his glance to the finely chiseled features of<lb/>
&lsquo;the chief&rsquo; - General Gorgas, framed on the wall, "when we went down to<lb/>
Panama to clean up yellow fever. Gorgas, then Colonel, came to me when <unclear>he</unclear><lb/>
was appointed chief sanitary officer of the canal and asked me to go <unclear>alone</unclear><lb/>
He said that Surgeon LaPrince, who had done mosquito work with us in<lb/>
Havana, had promised to go if I would, and that as it would probably be<lb/>
the last work we old codgers would do, he thought we ought to go.</p>
<p>"I agreed with him, and we set forth on the adventure in high spirit<lb/>
Rear Admiral John Ross, of the Navym who had had experience with yellow<lb/>
fever on the ships, joined us. We reached Panama in extremely hot<lb/>
weather, in June. It rained four times a day. When it stopped raining,<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01328007"/>
5.<lb/>
and the sun would come out, it was like opening the door of a furnance.</p>
<p>"We were assigned quarters in an old French building in Ancon<lb/>
which had formerly been used as a hospital for the officers of the<lb/>
French Canal Company. We were on the second floor, under us was the<lb/>
officers <unclear>mess</unclear>, and under that the chapel where we held the yellow fever<lb/>
funerals.</p>
<p>"Gorgas, LaPrince and I shared the same room -- and the same bureau.<lb/>
Gorgas had the top drawer, I had the middle, LaPrince the bottom. If any<lb/>
guests came, they put their things on the floor! We hung our top clothes<lb/>
on the wall, covering them with a gorgeous flowered curtain purchased from<lb/>
a Chinaman in Panama.</p>
<p>"The private bath was my trunk, turned upside down, with bowl and <unclear>pitch</unclear><lb/>
on top. The washstand proper had to be used for a desk. We slept on cots<lb/>
and had pillows that you blow up. Everybody had to turn in at the same<lb/>
time at night. There were no lamps then and, as I was the only one who<lb/>
had thought to bring candles, they had to be made to go a long way. For<lb/>
each of the four sleeping rooms, occupied by fifteen other officers and<lb/>
employees, the nightly allotment was a fourth of a candle. No man dared<lb/>
to go to bed without first killing all the mosquitoes in his net, and there<lb/>
had to be quick work before the candle flickered out.</p>
<p>"Galleries ran all round the building, <unclear>upstairs</unclear> and down. We bought <unclear>all</unclear><lb/>
the wire <unclear>nesting</unclear> we could find in Panama and screened off a small portion<lb/>
of the upper gallery, dubbing it &lsquo;the cage.&rsquo; Here we sat after dinner,<lb/>
talking shop and enjoying the soft, cool breezes and the lovely view. We<lb/>
looked over the royal palms and flat plains of the sabanas, across the<lb/>
harbor with its twinkling lights, into the city of Panama. Behind us,<lb/>
rising almost perpendicularly, we could see the green wall of Ancon, so<lb/>
densely wooded that it was favorite haunt of the &lsquo;tigres&rsquo; who be heard<lb/>
crying far into the night and who made frequent descents upon our <unclear>storehouse</unclear></p>
<pb n="7" id="f01328008"/>
<p>6.</p>
<p>"For the Americans, the food and the lack of ice were the greatest<lb/>
hardships. A tall, thin Frenchman <unclear><add>Spaniard?</add></unclear> by the name of <del><unclear>LaGorde</unclear></del><add>Fraga</add> was the steward<lb/>
of the <unclear>mess</unclear>, catering according to his own anaemic tastes. Of a <del>thirteen</del><add><unclear>7</unclear></add><lb/>
course dinner, bread and water would be served as a separate course. Even<lb/>
Gorgas, who never complained about anything, cried out one day: &lsquo;Here, this<lb/>
is too much.&rsquo; We lived on rice and canned stuff and musty eggs. Meat had<lb/>
to be eaten the same day it was killed, and the sooner the better. No<lb/>
ice could be purchased in Ancon. As a special treat, when one of my friends<lb/>
was ill, I went to Colon and bought $5 worth of ice. It was barely enough<lb/>
to cool his parched throat and make a pitcher of lemonade.</p>
<p>"The first thing we had to do before starting to work was to find out<lb/>
what <add>sanitary</add> laws or regulations there were to work under. General Davis, Governor<lb/>
of the Isthmus, informed us that President Roosevelt did not want any work<lb/>
done on the Canal until the sanitary men had had their say. But that the<lb/>
Commission had adjourned without making any legislation to go by.</p>
<p>"When we asked what laws had already been enacted, he said: &lsquo;Nothing but the old Colombian laws and you can imagine what they are.&rsquo;</p>
<p>"I suspected that they were pretty good laws but that where they had<lb/>
failed was in execution. We went to see President Amador. He spoke almost<lb/>
no <unclear>English</unclear> and <add>most of us</add> <del>we</del> spoke <unclear><add>but</add></unclear> little Spanish, <del>but</del> <unclear>Fortunately</unclear> no two of us had the<lb/>
same vocabulary so among us managed to piece out enough conversation to make<lb/>
ourselves understood. We had to have the help and authority of the Panama<lb/>
President in order to proceed as only the Canal Zone was under the United<lb/>
States, the cities being exempted.</p>
<p>"We asked if he would sign a decree - first to prevent the introduction<lb/>
of yellow fever and bubonic plague, and, second, for control and elimination<lb/>
if found in the cities. He said he would sign it if we would write out the<lb/>
decree &lsquo;in terms.&rsquo; Because it was very annoying to sign a decree Monday,<lb/>
explain it Tuesday, write an <unclear>amendment</unclear> to it on Wednesday and have to repeal<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01328009"/>
7.<lb/>
it on Thirsday or Friday.</p>
<p>"That night we wrote out two decrees, one for President Amador, in<lb/>
which we asked for Gorgas' appointment as Chief Sanitary Officer with<lb/>
authority to take such measures as were necessary to prevent the intro-<lb/>
duction of communicable diseases, <unclear><del>and for</del></unclear> the control and elimination of<lb/>
such if found in the cities. In the other decree, for Governor Davis,<lb/>
we took pains to state that he would give to Gorgas all such authority<lb/>
as he possessed for this purpose in the Canal Zone.</p>
<p>"Amador signed <unclear>his</unclear> decree in due time, but Davis demurred, stating<lb/>
that he didn't know what authority he had to give. We told him we didn't<lb/>
either, but that he had offered to help us in <hi>anyway</hi> he could and this was<lb/>
asking him to do that very thing. He demurred again<unclear>,</unclear> saying he feared we'd<lb/>
get him into trouble. It wasn't exactly like buying a pig in a poke but<lb/>
selling one. We told him that he could only give us what authority he had<lb/>
under the law and that if he went without it, it would not be his lookout but<lb/>
ours. He agreed and signed the decree. But Davis didn't believe in the<lb/>
theory of mosquito transmission of yellow fever. And while he didn't do<lb/>
anything to hinder us, he didn't do anything to help. <unclear>Combined.</unclear> with<lb/>
the natural disadvantages, we had much opposition <add>at first</add> on our own side to meet.</p>
<p>"With great difficulty, we succeeded in translating into English as much<lb/>
of the sanitary code of the Colombian laws as was necessary for our purpose.<lb/>
The laws were in <unclear>folios</unclear>, in pamphlet form, running back fifteen years.<lb/>
We found, as I expected, that they were extremely good laws - far more<lb/>
efficient than we have in the States, because <del><unclear></unclear></del> the Spanish haven't<lb/>
any idea of what we call &lsquo;personal liberty.&rsquo; The only trouble was that<lb/>
the laws had been enacted, printed and then filed away and forgotten.</p>
<p>"After getting the necessary legal authority, the next difficulty<lb/>
as to get the necessary sanitary supplied. <unclear>We</unclear> had personally <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> seen to it that the tons of sulphur, acids, alcohol<lb/>
<unclear>and</unclear> sulphur pots purchased were carried to the New York wharf of the Panama<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01328010"/>
8.<lb/>
Steamship Company and put on the same ship with us only to find it<lb/>
tied up on arrival in red tape that took us months to unwind. LaPrince<lb/>
<del><unclear>had</unclear></del> billed his consignment to the Isthmian Commission; I billed mine to<lb/>
myself at LaBoca. He got his by the requisition route in the spring.<lb/>
I got mine by cart as I could personally haul it away.</p>
<p>"At Ancon, there was a small hospital - remnent of the French <unclear>hospital</unclear><lb/>
run by Sisters, devoted women who made every edge cut and did wonders<lb/>
with the funds allowed. There was no hospital ready for treatment of<lb/>
yellow fever when our first case showed up, July 3rd. The victim was<lb/>
an American named Cunningham who had come to Panama seeking a position<lb/>
on the police force.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We segregated him in a small house, screening the windows<unclear>. as</unclear> best<lb/>
we could. Unable to find enough sulphur in Panama to kill the mosquitoes<lb/>
in a single room, LaPrince and I took a cart and rattled over to LaBoca,<lb/>
bringing back a barrell of sulphur and some sulphur pots<unclear>.</unclear> for fumigation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did the man die?&rdquo; I interrupted.</p>
<p>"Very promptly. But we never saw a yellow fever case then in terms of<lb/>
one but hundreds. It was more important to kill the mosquitoes that had<lb/>
bitten him before they could infect others than it was to save the patient<lb/>
himself. The work against yellow fever was done on two lines; first, to<lb/>
isolate the man who had yellow fever so the mosquitoes couldn't get to him<lb/>
and to kill with the fumes of sulphur all mosquitoes that had bitten him;<lb/>
and, second, to destroy mosquito breeding places.</p>
<p>"In the beginning we paid too much attention to isolating the<lb/>
patient. Having proved the responsibility of the Stegomyia fasciate<lb/>
for the carriage of yellow fever, we know that there is no danger from<lb/>
close contact with the patient - even from sleeping in the same bed with<lb/>
him. The only danger is from the mosquitoes that have bitten him.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f01328011"/>
<p>9.</p>
<p>"<hi>Another thing we have proved is that mosquitoes do not breed<lb/>
in swamps, mud puddles or street gutters unless they are lined with<lb/>
something and have no mud sides. We have formulated that they do not<lb/>
breed in any collection of water, the sides of which at the water's edge<lb/>
are of mud</hi>. They <hi>do</hi> breed in <del><unclear></unclear></del> collections of water in articial<lb/>
containers and in similar things such as cisterns, tin pans, water put<lb/>
out for the chickens to drink, saucers under the legs of tables to keep the<lb/>
ants off, and so-on.</p>
<p>"In Panama, the Stegomyia bred in just these things. There was<lb/>
no water supply. Everybody stored water in their houses in artificial<lb/>
containers. They saved rain water or bought <del><unclear>water</unclear></del> from the aguedoras --<lb/>
carriers who obtained water from the wells and peddled it on the backs<lb/>
of mules through the streets.</p>
<p>"In the dry season, from January to April, water would sell as high<lb/>
as <unclear>350</unclear> a gallon. There only six wells in Ancon, and from this limited<lb/>
water supply political capital was made. During the prolonged drought<lb/>
of our first year in Panama, water tickets were issued, limiting the natives<lb/>
to two quart bottles of water a day. When it was discovered that the<lb/>
Constitutionalistas were getting all the tickets and the Liberals none,<lb/>
there was a riot and the whole town had to be given free access to the<lb/>
wells.</p>
<p>"The first step was to introduce a plentiful supply of water in pipes.<lb/>
This took a year and even after the system was installed, water had to be<lb/>
very carefully conserved during the dry season. The water was turned on in<lb/>
the hospitals and quarters half-hour in the morning and an hour at night,<lb/>
and no bath was allowed to be taken except on doctor's prescription!</p>
<p>"Of course, we didn't have time to wait for the water system to be put<lb/>
in. We screened the water containers, turned them over or took them away<lb/>
wherever possible. Naturally, we met with opposition on the part of the<lb/>
natives - especially among the women, who said they preferred rain water,<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f01328012"/>
10.<lb/>
it made the hair so <unclear>lustroou</unclear>.</p>
<p>"We were constantly on the alert for breeding places but the mosquito<lb/>
often outwitted us. Walking one day with a sanitary officer, we accidental<lb/>
came across a fine nest in the trunk of a tree, where water had gathered.<lb/>
&lsquo;Looks like mosquitoes have more sense than we have?&rsquo; I remarked. &lsquo;No,&rsquo;<lb/>
he corrected, &lsquo;as much sense and more time.&rsquo;</p>
<p>"A dishpan came very near causing the death of the personnel of a<lb/>
battleship. I was called out of bed one night by an orderly from the<lb/>
Boston - then in the harbor, stating that the Captain wanted me to come<lb/>
out in the morning to see some sick men aboard. Questioning him, the<lb/>
symptoms sounded so suspicious, I decided not to wait till morning but<lb/>
<unclear>returned</unclear> with <unclear>him</unclear> in the launch to the ship.</p>
<p>"I found six men ill - four with yellow fever, the <unclear>ship's a</unclear> doctor,<lb/>
two lieutenants and the <unclear>mess</unclear> steward. When the Captain appeared protestin<lb/>
at my unnecessary <add>hurry,</add> <del><unclear></unclear></del>, I informed him that we hadn't been quick<lb/>
enough; that one man would die before morning, two were too ill to be<lb/>
moved, and two more would die if they were not taken to the hospital at<lb/>
once.</p>
<p>"The Doctor died that night, moaning to the last: &lsquo;I ought to have<lb/>
Known; I ought to have known!&rsquo; <del>One other</del><add>Another</add> man died but we saved the others<lb/>
and the whole ship from infection. On searching the ship, I found outside<lb/>
the cook's quarters a dishpan of water that was almost a soup of <unclear>wiggletale</unclear><lb/>
of Stegomyia. On New Year's night we had been invited to a sing-song on<lb/>
board the ship. Evidently there had been a walking case of yellow fever<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> among the numerous guests. The Stegomyia that had bitten him<lb/>
were breeding death for the whole ship in a dishpan!</p>
<p>"Before this incident, we had been working at loggerheads in the<lb/>
Sanitary Department, which came under Governor Davis. After the quick<lb/>
clean-up of yellow fever on the Boston, the Governor was convinced that<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f01328013"/>
11.<lb/>
the mosquito theory was correct, and we had his active support as<lb/>
long as he stayed.</p>
<p>"It was difficult for the natives to get used to our treatment of<lb/>
yellow fever. Though immune themselves, having had yellow fever when<lb/>
they were children, they remembered the <del><unclear></unclear></del> toll it had exacted<lb/>
from the French and were terrified at &lsquo;the risks&rsquo; the Americans took.<lb/>
When Mrs. Gorgas and my family joined us, six months after arriving on<lb/>
the Isthmus, we shared quarters on the second floor of an old French<lb/>
building formerly <del><unclear></unclear></del> used as a hospital for the officers of the<lb/>
French Canal Company. Under us was the officers mess, where we all ate<lb/>
together, and under that was the chapel where we had the yellow fever<lb/>
funerals.</p>
<p>"Diagnoally across the road was the yellow fever hospital, the doors<lb/>
and windows always open. While the windows had no glass and the doors <unclear>only</unclear><lb/>
shutters, they were both thickly screened. There were double screen doors<lb/>
at the entrance, with a smudge fire burning between, and an orderly constant-<lb/>
ly on duty to keep them going and to brush off the clothes of the doctors<lb/>
and nurses as they went in and out. Also the Yellow fever patients were<lb/>
in mosquito proof cages, so that it was <unclear>really</unclear> impossible for Stegomyia<lb/>
to get in and become infected by them. But, to the horror of the<lb/>
Panamenians, my daughter would sit on the steps of the hospital and wait<lb/>
for me whenever she felt inclined. &ldquo;You must wish her to become an angel,&rdquo;<lb/>
they protested.</p>
<p>"When an official died with yellow fever, there was a general panic.<lb/>
If an Italian laborer died, no notice was taken of it, though there was as<lb/>
much danger from one as the other. Those who were case-hardened or<lb/>
educated up to the mosquito theory of course could joke about it. I<lb/>
remember when the Isthmian Canal Commission came to Panama - or rather six<lb/>
of them, the seventh member being in Paris at the time, one of the<lb/>
Commissioners noticed six metallic coffins that had been unloaded from the<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f01328014"/>
<unclear>lock</unclear></p>
<p>"&lsquo;Why the six metallic coffins?&rsquo; he asked of an official.</p>
<p>"&lsquo;Well, you know Mr. Parsons didn't come,&rsquo; was the quick reply.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Commissioner slept on board that <unclear>nigh't</unclear>, and every other night<lb/>
while in Panama.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Just what are the symptoms of yellow fever?&rdquo; I queried, curious <unclear>to :</unclear></p>
<p>&ldquo;Similar to the first stages of acute alcoholism -- red, flushed face<lb/>
swollen lips, vomiting, headache. As the temperature rises, the pulse<lb/>
falls away from it. <hi>If the pulse rises and crosses the temperature</hi>, as<lb/>
you will see by this chart, then it <add>is</add> le noeud fatal -- the fatal knot, as<lb/>
the French say.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;What is the treatment?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It rests upon a tripod -- abbsolute rest in bed; complete<lb/>
starvation for reasonable time, and as much water as patient can be made <unclear>to</unclear><lb/>
take without vomiting.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Are there any ill effects?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;None whatever. <unclear>Yellow</unclear> fever has no sequence. The poison passes<lb/>
rapidly through the system, either killing you in five or seven days or<lb/>
leaving entirely. There is little suffering connected with it. The<lb/>
victim lies in a coma or stupor, and is very, <del><unclear>.</unclear></del><add>very weak.&rdquo;</add></p>
<p>&ldquo;Did you ever have it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, in the summer of 1897, following our campaign in the fever<lb/>
infected districts of Louisiana and Mississippi. I knew I had it and<lb/>
spent the first day winding up official matters. For days after I entered<lb/>
the hospital at New Orleans, I was so weak that <del><unclear></unclear></del> only when the thirst<lb/>
became more than I could bear would I expend enough strength to lift my<lb/>
thumb, to which a bell was tied, to call the nurse. I figured it out that<lb/>
while water was a word of two syllables, it required <del>less</del><add>more</add> effort to say<lb/>
&lsquo;drink&rsquo; and this was the one mental effort <add><unclear>I</unclear> made</add> and the one word I uttered.</p>
<pb n="14" id="f01328015"/>
<p>13.</p>
<p>&ldquo;During the Panama campaign, I jolly well <unclear>sympathized</unclear> with one of<lb/>
the patients who had black water fever. He insisted upon going home<lb/>
before he was well enough. &lsquo;Don't you know you are a mighty weak man?&rsquo;<lb/>
the Colonel reminded him. &lsquo;That's just it,&rsquo; he replied; &lsquo;let me go home<lb/>
and get a little strength, and then I'll come back and you can doctor me<lb/>
all you want.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did any of the nurses or doctors contract yellow fever - in Panama?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Only one - a nurse. She didn't get it from the patients but went<lb/>
down town - strictly against orders for non-immunes, and contracted it<lb/>
there. She had an unusually bad case. I had been away for a few days<lb/>
and when I got back was hustled in a cab to the nurses quarters at<lb/>
Anconcita. I found her <unclear>tossing</unclear> from one side of the bed to the other;<lb/>
neither morphia nor cocaine quited her. Finally, I said to her: 'Now,<lb/>
child, you've got a fine constitution and you ought to get well. But<lb/>
if you don't lie still in that bed, you're going to die.</p>
<p>&ldquo;She insisted that she couldn't keep still but suggested that if<lb/>
Major ----- (calling the name of one of the younger doctors on duty)<lb/>
would hold her hand, she would try. I gave Major ---- a call, and stationed<lb/>
him at his post. She <unclear>qu<add>e</add>ited</unclear> down immediately, and the Major sat by all<lb/>
night. The girl got well, and it wasn't many <del>years</del><add>weeks</add> after that when I got<lb/>
cards to their wedding.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;So there's romance - even in yellow fever,&rdquo; I laughed. &ldquo;Didn't<lb/>
General Gorgas and his wife meet in a yellow fever epidemic?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Not wanting to give away any secrets of Mrs. Gorgas' book, Dr. Carter<lb/>
refused to affirm or deny, but he did get launched into a eulogy of General<lb/>
Gorgas that <del><unclear>was</unclear></del><add>is</add> worth recording here.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Except Dr. Ross, I think no man knew Gorgas as I did, and Ross is<lb/>
dead. I knew him and was closely associated with him always as a friend<lb/>
and as collaborator or trusted subordinate almost continiously from 1893<lb/>
to that April day in 1920 when I bade him good-bye in the harbor, starting<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f01328016"/>
14.<lb/>
for the West African trip he was destined never to take.</p>
<p>"No one was so close to him during the early days of the Canal as<lb/>
I was or as much in his counsel. And those years of stress, with every<lb/>
man in the Sanitary Department pulling every ounce that was in him, were<lb/>
years formative not only for our organization but for our chief as well.<lb/>
I saw him grow. Men who stood together in those times were close together.</p>
<p>"He was one of the two kindest men I have known, beautifully un-<lb/>
selfish and thoughtful of others, not only willing, but seeking occasion<lb/>
to do kindnesses, always courteous and with a most equable temper. Some of<lb/>
us thought, and still think, that he was too quick to forgive derelictions<lb/>
and overlook faults, especially against himself. Yet he could be firm<lb/>
enough when he thought it necessary.</p>
<p>"If discipline be the unapproachableness of <unclear>petty</unclear> chiefs and an<lb/>
unbending routine, there was little in the Sanitary Department in its best<lb/>
days. If it be absolute loyalty to a chief and a persistent zeal to carry<lb/>
out his orders in letter and in spirit, then Gorgas had it. And it was<lb/>
his <del><unclear></unclear></del> kindly, gracious personality to which this spirit<lb/>
in his corps was due and to which in no small degree he owed his success on<lb/>
the Isthmus. Men did for love of him and bore for the love of him what they<lb/>
had never done or borne for pay or the ordinary obligation of official <unclear>duty</unclear><lb/>
If &lsquo;the Colonel&rsquo; wanted a thing done, it was done and at once, without any<lb/>
thought of whether it was &lsquo;overtime&rsquo; or more serious still &lsquo;not my business&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In my judgment, his choice of men and the attitude of his corps,<lb/>
their loyalty and their steady, unlimited devotion to him and his ideals<lb/>
were determining factors in his success on the isthmus. Men did for him<lb/>
what they had not done for sense of duty or for reward.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A year from the time the Sanitary Department got to work, Panama<lb/>
was free from yellow fever. The last case occurred in Colon, in December, <del><unclear>1</unclear></del><lb/>
<unclear>1905</unclear>. The following January the Isthmus was given a clean bill of health,<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f01328017"/>
15.<lb/>
and <add>the construction of the</add> Panama Canal was made possible. Without the spirit of &lsquo;the chief&rsquo;<lb/>
and the comradely work of &lsquo;the three old codgers&rsquo; for the prevention<lb/>
of the baffling scourge of the tropics, this greatest engineering feat<lb/>
of the ages <del>might</del><add>would</add> never have been completed.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
