<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01326001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes From Malaria Surveys, [19--?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01326001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Rock Hill (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Tarboro (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Quantico (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01326001</idno>
<title>Notes From Malaria Surveys, [19--?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The author discusses the breeding of Anopheles mosquitoes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Notes From Malaria Surveys, [19--?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01326001"/>
<p><hi>NOTES<lb/>
FROM<lb/>
MALARIA SURVEYS</hi>.</p>
<p>During the past season no attempt at investigation of malaria<lb/>
field problems was attempted, our work being concentrated on<lb/>
measures for the control of malaria which would affect the troops,<lb/>
Army and Navy, in the different camps. The following observations<lb/>
however seem worth recording:</p>
<p>(A) <hi>EFFECT OF DENSE SHADE ON BREEDING OF ANOPHELES:</hi></p>
<p>Everyone has noticed how much more commonly Anopheles<lb/>
are found breeding in a stream about the place where a road<lb/>
crosses it than in the general course of the stream away from the<lb/>
road crossing. Of course there is usually a pool just above the<lb/>
crossing and it may be that the blood supply furnished by men and<lb/>
animals crossing may make it a favored resort of these mosquitoes.<lb/>
Nevertheless this increase of breed <unclear></unclear> at fords over <add>other</add> parts of the<lb/>
stream is quite common even when there are pools in the stream and<lb/>
side pools and when the same road which crosses the stream also<lb/>
parallels it close on the bank, although with thick brush between<lb/>
it and the stream.</p>
<p>At Rock Hill, S.C. where many small streams are covered<lb/>
with a dense growth of &ldquo;green-brier&rdquo; and honeysuckle it was noted<lb/>
that while at the crossings, just above and below them, Anopheles<lb/>
larvae were quite abundant, they were absolutely absent under the<lb/>
dense growth a few yards above and a few yards further below (they<lb/>
were probably washed down a short distance). In two cleared streams<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01326002"/>
-2-<lb/>
they were found along their course quite generally. The same was<lb/>
noted at Tarboro, N C. and since then at a number of other places<lb/>
until our field parties do not attempt to make collections of<lb/>
larvae from such densely shaded streams.</p>
<p>The following observations at Quantico, Va., the second<lb/>
especially, have almost the precision of an experi<add>r</add>ent. A clea<del>n</del><add>r</add>ing<lb/>
had been made across Little Creek (creek #1) for a street in 1914<lb/>
or '15. This was about 120 feet wide and was across a valley 300<lb/>
to 400 feet wide, flat and marshy. This clearing was partly grown<lb/>
up but on either side above and below the clearing the brush was<lb/>
extremely thick and matted <del>in the</del><add>with</add> vines. The bottom on either side<lb/>
of the clearing was about like that in the clearing. This place<lb/>
was examined twice in July (6th and 17th) and was breeding (A.<lb/>
Punctipennis) moderately both times, while the dense brush above<lb/>
and below was not breeding or rather only breeding near the edge of<lb/>
the cut. The &ldquo;street&rdquo; was breeding more freely near its north ends<lb/>
as it came out into a stock pasture.</p>
<p>The valley of Creek #2 bounded the camp on the South. It had a<lb/>
flat bottom about 180' wide which was in fact a marsh. It was<lb/>
covered in the fairly thich brush, but decidedly less thick than<lb/>
creek #1. A clearing was made across this valley the latter part of<lb/>
June 1917 for a trestle to carry a sewer pipe. This clearing was<lb/>
roughly 250' wide. Examination on July 18, 22 and 25 showed that<lb/>
practically every pool in this cleared place, not covered by scum,<lb/>
was breeding Anopheles freely and profusely. Above the clearing,<lb/>
in the edges of the brush, breeding was plentiful; well up in the<lb/>
brush it was scant or lacking. Below the clearing the same<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01326003"/>
-3-<lb/>
condition was found in the brush but it is fair to say that the<lb/>
ground here was less marshy than in the clearing. The species<lb/>
developed were punctipennis. <add><unclear>P</unclear></add> As I have said this last observation<lb/>
was almost like an experiment and as far as one observation goes<lb/>
would show the influence of dense shade in preventing the breeding<lb/>
of this species of Anopheles. If further observations corroborate<lb/>
this it is possible that many densely shaded streams may be left<lb/>
undisturbed as not producing Anopheles and a considerable amount<lb/>
of work hitherto regarded as necessary to prevent mosquito production<lb/>
saved. Even with what is now known I would advise against the<lb/>
clearing off of small, densely shaded streams unless it is purposed<lb/>
to train or oil them as I think it would be removing a protection<lb/>
against breeding. Of course the removal of brush is necessary as<lb/>
a preliminary to training or oiling. Two points may be noted<lb/>
in the above observations (1) The examination was made in hot<lb/>
weather. It is reasonable that in cool weather pools exposed to the<lb/>
sun should be preferential breeding places and so we find it in the<lb/>
beginning of end of the breeding season. But the weather was hot<lb/>
and had been hot sometime when creek #2 was examined. So this<lb/>
influence can be eliminated. Indeed the breeding was most abundant<lb/>
in a seepage area, hence in cool water, and at the partially shaded<lb/>
pools on the edge of the clearing. (2) A number of the pools in<lb/>
the clearing were &ldquo;scummed&rdquo; - covered with a film brown or<lb/>
iridescent. This was especially so in pools containing the leaves<lb/>
of the cut brush. This is natural as this film (anaerobic bacteria)<lb/>
is evidence of the exhaustion of oxygen in the water and the<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01326004"/>
-4-<lb/>
decomposition of the leaves would hasten this. In the seepage area<lb/>
this did not occur and was rare in the pools in the uncut brush,<lb/>
both of which were breeding profusely.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
