<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01322030">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Minutes of a conference at the Rockefeller Institute, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01322030</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Flexner, Simon</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">[Rose, Wickliffe]</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01322030</idno>
<title>Minutes of a conference at the Rockefeller Institute, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The conference includes Noguchi, Flexner, White and Rose and involves yellow fever in West Africa.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Minutes of a conference at the Rockefeller Institute, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01322030"/>
<p><hi>Luncheon Conference - Rockefeller Institute -- Present: Doctor Flexner,<lb/>
Doctor Noguchi, Doctor J H White and WR</hi></p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item> Recommendations of the yellow fever commission to West Africa were<lb/>
read; the situation analyzed and the questions for consideration defined</item>
<item>(2) Concerning the question as to the probable menace of the infection<lb/>
in Africa to the rest of the world, Doctor White stated with positive convic-<lb/>
tion that the presence of the infection in Africa should be regarded as a seri-<lb/>
ous menace so long as it exists; within his own experience he has had under ob-<lb/>
servation a case of yellow fever brought from Africa across the Atlantic Ocean;<lb/>
it is quite possible for it to travel by easy stages from the present infected<lb/>
region in West Africa to Cape Town, up the East Coast and across to the Orient;<lb/>
once introduced into the dense, non-immune populations of the Orient, its con-<lb/>
trol would be practically impossible and the loss of life one would not care to<lb/>
contemplate</item>
<item>(3) It was agreed that the final determination of the question as to whe-<lb/>
ther the infection in Africa is yellow fever depends upon the application of<lb/>
the Noguchi technic; the experience of the British commission appointed to sub-<lb/>
mit a report on the question of yellow fever in West Africa is a ground for be-<lb/>
lieving that the question cannot be determined upon the basis of clinical evi-<lb/>
dence alone. If the Board should send another commission to Africa, it should<lb/>
rely upon a <hi>competent</hi> personnel to apply the Noguchi technic under field condi-<lb/>
tions</item>
<item>(4) Doctor Flexner and Doctor Noguchi agree that they should have about<lb/>
twelve months for the thorough training of men for this work. Doctor Robinson<lb/>
and Doctor Cross are now in training; after completing their laboratory work<lb/>
with Doctor Noguchi, they are to be sent to the field with a view to acquiring<lb/>
command of the <hi>technic under field conditions</hi>; their work thus far is promising.<lb/>
Doctor Flexner advises that additional men be placed in training in order to<lb/>
give opportunity for the selection of the best for the work in Africa</item>
<item>(5) Doctor White was given opportunity for a thorough examination of Doc-<lb/>
tor Noguchi's material in his laboratory; the examination included specimens of<lb/>
livers, hearts, lungs, stomachs, intestines, with microscopic examination of<lb/>
tissues from these organs, from <hi>human</hi> and animal <hi>victims</hi> of <hi>Leptospira icteroides</hi>;<lb/>
slides showing the organism embedded in human and animal tissues. After this<lb/>
examination Doctor White expressed himself as convinced this material gives the<lb/>
pathological picture of yellow fever</item>
<item>(6) Doctor Noguchi then exhibited a specimen given to him by Doctor Simp-<lb/>
son; the specimen was taken from a man who died of yellow fever in New Orleans<lb/>
in 1905; the specimen shows the spirochaete embedded in the tissue; this spiro-<lb/>
chaete Doctor Simpson himself discovered at that time; Doctor White stated that<lb/>
he had charge of the yellow fever epidemic in New Orleans at that time; that it<lb/>
was one of the most severe epidemics New Orleans ever experienced; that there<lb/>
could be no doubt as to its being yellow fever; that Doctor Simpson was working<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01322031"/>
-2-<lb/>
under him when this specimen was secured; he regarded this as confirming the<lb/>
other findings of Doctor Noguchi</item>
<item>(7) Out of this grew the suggestion that perhaps additional pathological<lb/>
material may have been preserved in New Orleans from this and other yellow fe-<lb/>
ver epidemics together with clinical histories of the cases; that Doctor Nogu-<lb/>
chi will probably be able to secure this material for examination. Doctor White<lb/>
is to take the matter up by correspondence with his friends in New Orleans; if<lb/>
any other specimens should be found the cumulative evidence would have tremen-<lb/>
dous weight</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
