<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01322001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on the article: On Molecular Changes More Particularly in Relation to Epidemic Diseases, by John Snow, 1853, [19--?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01322001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01322001</idno>
<title>Notes on the publication: On Molecular Changes More Particularly in Relation to Epidemic Diseases, by John Snow, 1853, [19--?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a review of Snow's work published by John Churchill in 1853. The author of these notes is unknown.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Notes on the article: On Molecular Changes More Particularly in Relation to Epidemic Diseases, by John Snow, 1853, [19--?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01322001"/>
<opener>
Snow, John, M. D., Vice President, Medical Society of London<lb/>
on<lb/>
<hi>Molecular Changes</hi><lb/>
More Particularly in Relation to Epidemic Diseases.<lb/>
<dateline>
John Churchill,<lb/>
Princess Street,<lb/>
Soho, London.<lb/>
1893<lb/>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>** Little relation is apparent between the title of this article and<lb/>
its theme, which is the nature of communicable diseases. The general re-<lb/>
lation is, however, this--that continuous molecular changes are recog-<lb/>
nized as a property peculiar to living organisms, always and necessarily<lb/>
originating from previous living organisms of the same kind, and Dr.<lb/>
Snow recognizes very clearly, as shown in some of the extracts following,<lb/>
that the specific cause of communicable diseases is material, exhibiting<lb/>
two fundamental characteristics of living organisms; namely, the power of<lb/>
reproduction and necessary origin from previous vital matter of the same<lb/>
kind.</p>
<p>Page 6.</p>
<p>There are, however, changes of a more complicated nature--<lb/>
those to which plants and animals owe their development and continuance--<lb/>
that have never commenced anew within the experience of man. The most<lb/>
characteristic property, indeed, of vital actions probably is, that they<lb/>
are always caused by similar processes which have preceded them, whilst<lb/>
all other molecular changes may arise, occasionally at least, from other<lb/>
causes. A species of plant or animal consists, in fact, of a number or<lb/>
collection of continuous molecular actions.</p>
<p>Page 12-13.</p>
<p>In addition to the series of continuous molecular changes<lb/>
having for their result the preservation of the individual and the spe-<lb/>
cies, there are others occurring in living beings, which have an opposite<lb/>
tendences; they divert part of the substance of the individual from the<lb/>
actions which are natural to the species to another kind of action, in<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01322002"/>
in<lb/>
2.<lb/>
consequence of which this substance is employed in the multiplication<lb/>
and increase of the materies morbi of communicable diseases,--an extensive<lb/>
group of maladies, each case of which is caused by some material that, as<lb/>
a general rule, has been produced in the system of another individual.<lb/>
The origin of these disease, for aught we can tell, may be as remote as<lb/>
that of the beings they infest and exist on.</p>
<p>The communicable diseases--I use this term in preference to contagi-<lb/>
ous, for various reasons*--the communicable diseases, to which the human<lb/>
species is liable, are chiefly as follow:--syphilis, smallpox, measles,<lb/>
scarlet fever, typhus, typhoid and relapsing fevers, erysipelas, yellow<lb/>
fever, plague, cholera, dysentery, influenza, whooping cough, mumps,<lb/>
scabies and the entozoa.</p>
<p>Pages 14-15-16-17.</p>
<p>The material cause of every communicable disease<lb/>
resembles a species of living being in this, that both one and the other<lb/>
depend on, and in fact consist of, a series of continuous molecular changes,<lb/>
occurring in suitable materials. The organized matter, as must presume it<lb/>
to be, which induces the symptoms of a communicated disease, except in the<lb/>
case of the entozoa, can hardly ever be separately distinguished, like the<lb/>
individuals of a species of plant or animal; but we know that this organ-<lb/>
ized matter ossesses one great characteristic of plants and animals--that<lb/>
of increasing and multiplying its own kind." In the instances of syphilis,<lb/>
smallpox and vaccinia, we have physical proof of this increase, and in<lb/>
other diseases the evidence is not less conclusive.</p>
<p>The molecular changes taking place in the materies morbi of some di-<lb/>
seases resemble the changes in many living beings in another respect also:<lb/>
they permit of being suspended, under certain circumstances, and re-commence<lb/>
at the point at which they ceased. Thus the matter of variola and of vac-<lb/>
cinia can be carried, in the dry state, to distant parts of the world with-<lb/>
out injury, like the seeds of a plant.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01322003"/>
<p>plant.</p>
<p>3</p>
<p>No evident effects are produced at first by the reception of the ma-<lb/>
terial cause of any of these diseases. There is always a definite period,<lb/>
of longer or shorter duration, before the illness commences, which is<lb/>
called the period of incubation. As regards the materies morbi itself,<lb/>
this is a period of something more than incubation; it is a period of re-<lb/>
production. All substances capable of causing a disturbance in the ani-<lb/>
mal functions produce symptoms from the moment of their absorption or in-<lb/>
hibition, when introduced in sufficient quantity; but the specific animal<lb/>
poisons, as they are called, are very rarely, if ever, introduced in such<lb/>
quantity as to produce sensible effects; the disturbance in the system,<lb/>
which constitutes the diseases they induce, being due to crop or progeny<lb/>
of the matter first introduced.</p>
<p>******</p>
<p>So far as can be learnt from what remains of ancient medical lit-<lb/>
erature, the communication of diseases was not generally recognized till<lb/>
a recent period. Even Sydenham did not recognize the communicability of<lb/>
any acute febrile disease except the plague. He did not even recognize<lb/>
the communicability of smallpox. Sydenham, however, was fully aware of<lb/>
the resemblance between the material cause of an epidemic disease and a<lb/>
species of animal or plant, but he was not aware that animals and plants<lb/>
proceed only from procreation by their own kin; and this is probably the<lb/>
reason why the communication of most diseases was unknown to him.</p>
<p>Pages 18-19:</p>
<p>It is quite possible, and, indeed, almost certain, that<lb/>
the material cause of some communicable diseases may be wafted a short<lb/>
distance through the air, like the seeds and spores of many plants. The<lb/>
matter of smallpox pustules, for example, retains its powers after being<lb/>
dried, and may be shaken from articles of clothing, and thus wafted through<lb/>
the air. This is probably true of other diseases. It is, however, only a<lb/>
mode of communication of the disorders in question, and would not warrant<lb/>
us in speaking of their atmospheric origin, any more than of the atmospheric<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01322004"/>
atmospheric<lb/>
4.<lb/>
origen of plants.</p>
<p>Pages 20-23</p>
<p>There is one class of diseases--intermittent fevers--which<lb/>
are so fixed to particular places that they have deservedly obtained the<lb/>
name of endemics. They spread occasionally, however, much beyond ordinary<lb/>
localities and become epidemic. Intermittent fevers are undoubtedly often<lb/>
connected with a marshy state of the soil; for draining the land frequently<lb/>
causes their disappearance. They sometimes, however, exist as endemics,<lb/>
where there is no marshy land or stagnant water within scores of miles.</p>
<p>Pages 22-23.</p>
<p>It must be acknowledged, however, that there is no direct<lb/>
proof of the existence of malaria or miasmata, much less of their nature.<lb/>
Intermittent fevers were attributed to such agents from the absence of any<lb/>
known cause, especially as they were observed to come on after exposure to<lb/>
the air of certain localities, more particularly at night.</p>
<p>Pages 26-27.</p>
<p>There is one circumstance which seems to indicate that<lb/>
the specific cause of intermittent fevers undergoes a development or mul-<lb/>
tiplication within the system of the patient,--that is, that a period of<lb/>
dormancy or incubation, has been observed, in many cases, between the<lb/>
visit to the unhealthy locality and the illness which followed; for, as I<lb/>
have already remarked, every poisonous or injurious substance causes symp-<lb/>
toms as soon as it has been absorbed in sufficient quantity.</p>
<p>The communication of ague from person to person has not been observed,<lb/>
neither has that of tape-worm, although in this latter disease there is<lb/>
proof of communication that hardly anyone disputes, viz. the evidence that<lb/>
the creature is only found in the bowels, and the general principle, &ldquo;Omne<lb/>
vivum ex ovo.&rdquo; Supposing ague to be communicable, it may be so only indi-<lb/>
rectly, for the materies morbi eliminated from one patient may require to<lb/>
undergo a process of development or procreation out of the body before it<lb/>
enters another patient, like certain flukes infesting some of the lower ani-<lb/>
mala, and procreating by alternate generations.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
