<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01325068">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: The Establishment of a Settlement for Lepers, [19--?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01325068</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Balboa (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Panama City (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01325068</idno>
<title>Report: The Establishment of a Settlement for Lepers, [19--?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The unknown author describes the settlement for lepers that Carter established in Panama.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report: The Establishment of a Settlement for Lepers, [19--?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01325068"/>
<p>
Biographic<lb/>
Palo Seco.<lb/>
</p>
<p>When the Americans reached Panama the condition of the lepers was<lb/>
a pitiable one. They were isolated on a stretch of beach between Panama<lb/>
City and La Boco (now Balboa). Arrnagements had been made to deliver<lb/>
food to them there, but, in the dry season, they frequently suffered<lb/>
from an insufficient supply of water and as a result of the hardships of<lb/>
their life, many cases of leprosy were concealed from the authorities<lb/>
by the relatives of the sufferers.</p>
<p>Dr. Carter (the Director of Hospitals) under whom the charge of<lb/>
these unfortunates fell, decided both for humanitarian and administrative<lb/>
purposes to make the conditions of their isolation as pleasant as possi-<lb/>
ble. After a thorough and, at times hazardous, exploration of the coast<lb/>
and the neighboring islands, he discovered a beautiful fruit farm, slop-<lb/>
ing down to a broad beach (all Panamenians are very fond of swimming &amp;<lb/>
also sea bathing <add>is</add> recommended in leprosy). <add>There was no approach possible from the <unclear>mainland back of it</unclear> - only from the sea, which gave it the desired <unclear>isolation.</unclear></add> This place--most inappropri-<lb/>
ately named &ldquo;Palo Seco&rdquo; (Dry Stick) was purchased from its owners (two<lb/>
Italians) and in order to make it as homelike as possible the buildings<lb/>
were erected after the plan of their own villages--a chapel with a<lb/>
&ldquo;plaza&rdquo; (square) in front of it and the dwelling houses on the other<lb/>
side of the plaza. Care was taken in thinning out the fruit trees <add>in order</add> to<lb/>
erect the buildings to keep all the finest <del>specimens</del><add>ones</add>, <add>a specimen of</add> the fruit from<lb/>
each tree being picked: labled and sampled before the tree was cut down.<lb/>
Also, new fruits were introduced from Central and South America and the<lb/>
southern part of the U. S. until the place became a horticultural curios-<lb/>
ity as well as a source of pride and gastronomic delight to its inhabitants.</p>
<p>The lepers were <del><hi>also</hi></del> allowed either to eat <add>at</add> a mess the food prepared<lb/>
for them or to draw their ration uncooked and do their own housekeeping.<lb/>
Also, if they wished to do any farming, implements: seeds etc. were<lb/>
provided and the produce bought at market price for the use of the colony.<lb/>
Similarly, they were allowed to raise chickens. No Pigs! The line had to<lb/>
to be drawn somewhere and &ldquo;pigs is pigs&rdquo; the world over!</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01325069"/>
<p>over!</p>
<p>2.</p>
<p>There were several children on in the settlement and one leper<lb/>
girl was made &ldquo;school teacher,&rdquo; her pride in the title and salary<lb/>
being beyond words. The children, who had been like frightened little<lb/>
animals on their arrival, became fat and happy and when, on their first<lb/>
Fourth of July at Palo Seco Dr. Carter gave each of <add>them a</add> toy and a box of<lb/>
candy (and each of the women a parasol!) I think there were no more<lb/>
contented <unclear>people</unclear> <del>youngsters</del> on the Isthmus! There was also a large supply<lb/>
of fireworks for the whole settlement on that <unclear>auspicious</unclear> occasion</p>
<p>The Superintendant, who lived at Palo Seco in a pretty cottage<lb/>
across a small stream a few yards outside the settlement, took a very<lb/>
real and kindly interest in his charges: the good P&egrave;re Allot (a saintly<lb/>
French priest) came over once a week to hold confession and mass for<lb/>
them: and &ldquo;Maria&rdquo; (Miss Maria Arias) came frequently also to hear such<lb/>
small troubles as they did not care to confide directly to the Superin-<lb/>
tendant or to Dr. Carter, who also made frequent trips to the island,<lb/>
always with little remembrances for the <del>c</del> children or any of them who<lb/>
might especially need sympathy.</p>
<p>The result of this change in their condition was that more and<lb/>
more lepers began to <hi>wish</hi> to go to Palo Seco. Mysterious little notes<lb/>
would be found in the morning on Dr. Carter's desk, <add><unclear>such</unclear></add> as:&ldquo;Juan, who has<lb/>
&ldquo;<unclear>la informidad</unclear>&rdquo;<lb/>
(<del>&ldquo;</del>the sickness<del>&rdquo;</del>)" (they never mentioned the dread disease by name!) &ldquo;would<lb/>
like to go to Palo Seco, if the <hi>policia</hi>&rdquo; (police)--whom he had long been<lb/>
evading! &ldquo;are not informed.&rdquo; If this <add>were permitted,</add><del>could be done</del>, &ldquo;Maria&rdquo; <add>(Miss <del>Maria</del> Anas)</add> was to be<lb/>
notified to that effect and &ldquo;a way would be found&rdquo; for him to get to Palo<lb/>
Seco.&rdquo; &ldquo;Maria&rdquo; being duly &ldquo;informed&rdquo; <add>by Dr. Carter</add> &ldquo;Juan&rdquo; would appear some morning,<lb/>
strolling calmly up the beach <add> at Palo Seco</add>, brought, of course, in <del><hi><unclear>xxx</unclear></hi></del><add>a</add> sail boat<lb/>
procured by &ldquo;Maria&rdquo; and another number would be added to the colony.<lb/>
Indeed, pitiful requests from adjacent territory began to come in, people<lb/>
with &ldquo;the sickness&rdquo; who had heard of the place and hoped they were entitled<lb/>
to go there. One man, who had, apparently been completely cured refused to<lb/>
leave as he said he had &ldquo;a better life&rdquo; there than he could ever hope to<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01325070"/>
hope to<lb/>
3.<lb/>
have elsewhere and<del>s</del> stayed on as a boatmen, drawing the same salary as<lb/>
other Canal employees in that position. Of course, the <unclear>money</unclear> paid the<lb/>
lepers was never put in general circulation, simply used at Palo Seco.<lb/>
Still, it made them feel that they were like other people, not merely<lb/>
objects of dread, pity or morbid curiosity. No one, by the way, was al-<lb/>
lowed to go to Palo Seco for this latter reason--it was not included in<lb/>
the &ldquo;sight seeing&rdquo; curriculum of visitors to the Isthmus. Only those<lb/>
who could benefit the colony or who wished to collect data for <add>scientific or administra-</add> <del>similary</del><lb/>
<add>tive</add><lb/>
work were <unclear></unclear> allow<del>o</del><add>e</add>d <add>to visit</add> there</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
