<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01331001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Connor, Michael E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01331001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Rose, Wickliffe</name>
<name type="person">Pareja, Wenceslao</name>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="place">Guayaquil (Ecuador)</name>
<name type="place">Merida (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Veracruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01331001</idno>
<title>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Connor describes the progress against yellow fever in Mexico. He would like to have Carter's yellow fever articles translated into Spanish.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Letter from Michael E. Connor to Henry Rose Carter, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01331001"/>
<opener>
R<lb/>
Connor<lb/>
<dateline>
Hotel Madrid.<lb/>
Merida Yucatan Mexico.<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carter:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your welcome letter of April 7th., reached today.</p>
<p>Dr. Rose had forwarded me a copy of your report to the<lb/>
Board on the out<hi>-</hi>break in the Department of Lambayeque and<lb/>
together with your letter I can visualize the entire sit-<lb/>
uation. I am hoping that no back fire will take place into<lb/>
Piura, for if it does, Guayaquil will be re-infected.</p>
<p>I had supposed that Pareja would be appointed after the<lb/>
sad news of Dr. Becerra's death reached me but I have not<lb/>
heard of the appointment officially because the mails to<lb/>
are subject to all sorts of delays.</p>
<p><unclear>there parts</unclear></p>
<p>We are making progress in our work and receiving full<lb/>
co-operation both from the public and Government. Our<lb/>
position with the Government has greatly improved in the<lb/>
last week by their giving us official standing as Delegados,<lb/>
and this had helped us with the public in general.</p>
<p>I have not seen a case of y.f. since coming here altho<lb/>
the stegomyia index was quite high, nearly 60%, at the<lb/>
begining of the work. Of course the local <add><unclear>authorities</unclear></add> had done some<lb/>
good work up to the end of 1919 and the results of this<lb/>
are still effective in certain sections of the city.</p>
<p>Our containers here are tanks, cisterns and the lejia tins?<lb/>
the cesspools are pouring out culex but I have not been<lb/>
able to find <del>any</del> stegomyia in any cesspool up to the<lb/>
present. This is in line with your statement in your lect-<lb/>
ures of 1914 that they do not breed in cesspools.</p>
<p>The present crisis, which has lasted since 1918 has been<lb/>
a factor in the control of the disease in Merida as immigra-<lb/>
tion has practically ceased. The movement of people is out<lb/>
of the country to other parts of the Republic and especi-<lb/>
ally to Cuba.</p>
<p>In the event Dr. Rose has not mentioned it to you I would<lb/>
like you to know that I have suggested to him that our<lb/>
Board should have your articles on yellow fever, more<lb/>
especilally those issued by your service in phamphlet form<lb/>
as well the ones appearing in the Liverpool Journal, trans-<lb/>
lated into Spanish. I feel that it will be well worth while<lb/>
as the Doctors in Yucatan and I think in the rest of the<lb/>
Republic know so very little of the fundamentals of the<lb/>
disease and especially regarding the habits of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01331002"/>
2.<lb/>
Stegomyia that the articles referred too would give the<lb/>
Doctors here a good understanding on the points that are<lb/>
now very obscure. For instance, they still believe that fumigation<lb/>
is the prime measure <del><unclear>and only undertake</unclear></del> together with early<lb/>
isolation of cases and only undertake anti-larvae measures when<lb/>
there is an abundance of money to be spent. THe antilarvae<lb/>
measures was a new thing to them and only now are they be-<lb/>
gining to accept it. This may seem strange in the view of <del><unclear>the</unclear></del><lb/>
of the generally accepted fact that Yucatan is generally con-<lb/>
sidered progressive for a Latin country. But it is a fact<lb/>
never-the-less.</p>
<p>You will be interested to know that the Mayan Code, of the old<lb/>
civilization of course, makes mention of eidemics of black vomit,<lb/>
and prescribes remedies. It is saidv that history written at the<lb/>
time of the landing of the Conquistadores makes mention of an<lb/>
<unclear>epidemic</unclear> of this disease then present amongst the Mayans in the<lb/>
southeren part of the State. I am on the trail of some supposed<lb/>
authentic data on this point and am wondering if you would<lb/>
be interested in having <add>it</add> or perhaps you have it already.</p>
<p>I am writing for this next mail to Doctor Rose suggesting that he<lb/>
send some one down the West Coast to go over the Southern Ecuador<lb/>
and to observe conditions in general. Pareja is a good man but<lb/>
personally I do not feel safe with him, in the first instance he<lb/>
is related to <add><unclear>too</unclear></add> many people and in the second he had not grasped<lb/>
the importance of the <unclear>sammaler</unclear> details of the application of<lb/>
anti-larvae measures, and as you know one must be on the job every<lb/>
minute of the time to get ahead of the Stegs.</p>
<p>I am glad that Hanson is going to look after the situation in<lb/>
Peru as against a new man. Is he going to be able to give the<lb/>
time to the work? You remember when we talked over the situation<lb/>
in Piura his family affairs were taking up so much of his time<lb/>
and the work was left to the native men that little or no head-<lb/>
way was made. This was before you came on the field.<lb/>
I am naturally anxious and a little worried bout Ecuador and am<lb/>
asking you <unclear>to</unclear> give a little thought to the situation <unclear>and</unclear> let<lb/>
me have your opinion. Should we not have a man down there some-<lb/>
where, either in Ecuador or working with Hanson.</p>
<p>I am not anxious to return but would gladly do so, <del><unclear>if by doing so</unclear></del><lb/>
if it appeared neceesary. This <del><unclear>filed could</unclear></del> field could be<lb/>
placed in charge of a new man as the<del><unclear>y</unclear></del> work is now well organize<lb/>
and can be carried to a successful conclusion within a reasonable<lb/>
time.</p>
<p>In a letter from Caldwell he states that the last case in Vera was<lb/>
Febrary but since that time two cases have shown up in Papantla<lb/>
some 120 miles north of Vera Cruz. He further reports that co-<lb/>
operation is excellent and the prospects are good for a success<lb/>
ful campaign. We are using fish and the reults are ecellent.</p>
<p>With the kindest personal regards and the hope that<lb/>
you are resting and gaining strength.</p>
<p>Please convey to Miss Carter my sincere good wishes.</p>
<closer>
<signed>M E Connor</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
