<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01331021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to S.W. Welch, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01331021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Welch, S.W.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Fricks, Lunsford D.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01331021</idno>
<title>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to S.W. Welch, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] advises the chairman of the National Malaria Committee to reconsider abolishing a subcommittee that helps promote education in the fight against malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Letter from [Henry Rose Carter] to S.W. Welch, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01331021"/>
<opener>
N. M. C.<lb/>
Welch<lb/>
/LC<lb/>
<dateline>
2121 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</dateline>
Dr. S. W. Welch,<lb/>
Chairman, National Malaria Committee,<lb/>
State Health Officer,<lb/>
Montgomery, Ala.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Welch:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In compliance with your circular letter to the members of the<lb/>
National Malaria Committee inviting suggestions, I would say that<lb/>
I am inclined to think that it would be advisable for you as<lb/>
Chairman and Dr. Fricks as Secretary to reconsider the action of the<lb/>
Committee at Chatanooga in abolishing the Sub-Committee of Educa-<lb/>
tion and Publicity. The reason urged therefor was that this Com-<lb/>
mittee had not functioned. If its functioning was desireable this<lb/>
seems a reason for strengthening rather than for doing away with<lb/>
it.</p>
<p>When I say <hi>reconsider</hi> I do not mean that you would necessari-<lb/>
ly decide that this action of the Committee was inadvisable, only<lb/>
that you would give this matter consideration which I think it did<lb/>
not receive prior to passage. <add>Your opinion on this matters <hi>after</hi> considerations will have much influence on my own'</add> Neither LePrince: van Hovenberg<lb/>
nor myself approved of it, yet none of us were so registered. I<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01331022"/>
I<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
was waiting for its reference to the Sub-Committee on Resolutions--<lb/>
as probably were others--and the vote came as a surprise to me.<lb/>
I do not quite understand how it was passed without reference to<lb/>
this Sub-Committee. Has that requirement been rescinded?</p>
<p>My recollection is that Dr. Leathers, whose resolution it was,<lb/>
rather objected to any publicity save that directed by a State Health<lb/>
organization. Personally, I cannot see the reason for this. I am<lb/>
for anything that will result in the diminution of malaria. I feel<lb/>
very much like St. Paul expresses himself in Phil. 1:18 about preach-<lb/>
ing the Gospel. The <hi>control of malaria</hi> is the end I aim at. I am<lb/>
willing for it to be done by any agency, including Germans and Bolsheviks.</p>
<p>Dr. Leathers objections, if he entertains the objections I have<lb/>
indicated, could be met, however, in one of two ways:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1/ In confining this Sub-Committee to <hi>education</hi>--leaving pub-<lb/>
licity out.</item>
<item>2/ In making him Chairman of it--permanent if need be--in which<lb/>
case, I am sure, its activities would not offend him.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Under a resolution adopted at the Memphis meeting of the N. M. C.<lb/>
(1917) all resolutions must go to a Sub-Committee on Resolutions and<lb/>
are to be voted on in full Committee on their report. This resolu-<lb/>
tion was not so submitted. I do not know whether this was through<lb/>
inadvertence (of the Secretary and Chairman) or whether this rule of<lb/>
proceedure has been rescinded. I note too that in the list of Com-<lb/>
mittees, sent me recently by the Secretary, no Sub-Committee on Reso-<lb/>
lutions is featured. Has this rule been rescinded.</p>
<p>I am so little in the malaria work at present--my <hi>whole</hi> time be-<lb/>
ing taken up with what I am at present engaged in, that honestly I<lb/>
scarcely feel like expressing an opinion or writing on any malarial<lb/>
matter. Nevertheless, it does seem advisable to bring this matter to<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01331023"/>
to<lb/>
3<lb/>
your consideration. Indeed, the last malaria work I was engaged in--<lb/>
abstracting and editing the malaria articles from current journals<lb/>
for the men in the field--was distinctively educative work, and work<lb/>
which I purpose to again take up when (if) I ever finish my present<lb/>
job.</p>
<p>With highest regards, I remain</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>National Malaria Committee</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
