<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01605001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie B. Lawrence, July 18, 1874</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Reed, Walter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01605001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1874-07-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lawrence, Emilie B.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship">YES</term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Hope, Miss</name>
<name type="person">Bennett, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1874-07-18">July 18, 1874</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01605001</idno>
<title>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie B. Lawrence, July 18, 1874</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed plans to enter the U.S. Army Medical Corps, and gives his rationale. He describes his experiences in the city. He explains his later plans for marriage and his philosophy of life.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1874-07-18">
<head>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie B. Lawrence, July 18, 1874</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01605001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Brooklyn, <date value="1874-07-18">July 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 74.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Miss Lawrence,</salute>
</opener>
<p>Another mes-<lb/>
sage has been gladly welcomed,<lb/>
and again the happy privilege<lb/>
of replying, as best I may, is<lb/>
permitted me. I, too, have chosen<lb/>
the hour of night which you so<lb/>
beautifully alluded to in your<lb/>
letter; but though I acknowledge<lb/>
its bewitching influence, I feel<lb/>
that something more than its en-<lb/>
chantment would be required<lb/>
to make to living expression the<lb/>
sluggish thoughts of my dull<lb/>
brain, If, perchance, a thought<lb/>
flashes dimly and fitfully<lb/>
upon the horizon of my mind, &amp;<lb/>
I begin to trace it on the paper<lb/>
before me, it is instantly blighted<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01605002"/>
by the jingling bells and noisy rattle of some street-<lb/>
car that goes tearing past my window, and ere I can<lb/>
return <del>and</del> to gather up the broken links and bind them<lb/>
together, the wished-for idea has vanished forever. Nor<lb/>
am I blessed with the &ldquo;sighing zephyrs as they rustle<lb/>
amid the branches of the old oaks&rdquo; to lull me with their<lb/>
plaintive moanings. Ah! what an indescribable difference<lb/>
there is between night in the city and night in the country;<lb/>
far greater than feeble words of mine can begin to tell.<lb/>
Here the ever bustling day is crowded into the busy<lb/>
night; nor can we draw the line of separation between<lb/>
the two. Both are equally characterized by the increasing<lb/>
roar of humanity struggling in the race of life, and<lb/>
many a poor, aching heart, by day, &ldquo;bowed down with<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01605003"/>
weight of woe,&rdquo; seeks, at night, its humble home, but not to<lb/>
cease its aching; no, never! till that last, long night that<lb/>
knows no earthly waking! But, how different in the country!<lb/>
An evening of quiet repose succeeds a day of well-spent,<lb/>
<hi>honest</hi> labor. The lowing herd winds slowly o'er the lea<lb/>
and leaves the world to darkness and to me-&rdquo; Yes, to<lb/>
<hi>nature</hi> and to me; and then how slight a step from na-<lb/>
ture &ldquo;up to nature's God&rdquo;! This is the hour of contempla-<lb/>
tion; of holy thoughts and sweet communion with self and<lb/>
friends, undisturbed save by the &ldquo;watch-dog's honest<lb/>
bark.&rdquo; Surely, if happiness is ever decreed to mortals<lb/>
here below, it is at such moments that we experience<lb/>
it to the fullest extent- Blot them out, and life to me<lb/>
would be an uninviting blank!</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01605004"/>
<p>I had anticipated much pleasure in<lb/>
reading the account of the commence-<lb/>
ment exercises, and especially in read-<lb/>
ing Miss Hope's poem. But, alas! &ldquo;how<lb/>
vain are all things here below&rdquo;! for<lb/>
the good Doctor Bennett, seated in<lb/>
his easy editorial chair, for some<lb/>
unaccountable reason, has neglec-<lb/>
ted to send <del>me</del> my Advocate during<lb/>
the past 3 weeks, and I must sit<lb/>
<unclear>ang</unclear> sigh!</p>
<p>You must pardon me if<lb/>
I offer a slight correction of a<lb/>
line contained in your letter. You<lb/>
state, &ldquo;we had an original poem by the<lb/>
College Poetess, Miss Hope, whose<lb/>
face so fascinated you while<lb/>
you were here&rdquo;! I would amend by<lb/>
substituting <hi>pleased</hi> for fascina-<lb/>
ted, for it was reserved for <hi>an-<lb/>
other</hi> &amp; <hi>brighter</hi> face than Miss Hope's<lb/>
to fascinate me. Were you an ex-<lb/>
pert at guessing, you might find<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01605005"/>
out its owner. Modesty prevents<lb/>
me from saying, but it does not<lb/>
lessen the fascination one iota.<lb/>
&ldquo;Out of the fullness of the heart<lb/>
the mouth speaketh.&rdquo; This is as much<lb/>
as I dare say, at present, and I must<lb/>
ask your indulgence for the <del>rest</del> <add>remainder</add> of my<lb/>
letter. I pray you, bear with me while I<lb/>
grow uninteresting.</p>
<p>I have been recently<lb/>
contemplating a departure from Brook-<lb/>
lyn. My friends will consider me unwise<lb/>
in this, perhaps, but after due atten-<lb/>
tion given to the matter, I believe I<lb/>
will be justified in so doing. I have<lb/>
about made up my mind to make a stren-<lb/>
nuous effort to enter the Medical<lb/>
Corps of the U.S. Army. The Examining<lb/>
Board which has not met before in six<lb/>
(6) years, assemblies in New York City, Aug-<lb/>
ust 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> next. I should not desire to remain<lb/>
longer than 3 or 4 years, at the outside.<lb/>
And now for my reasons. In the first<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01605006"/>
place, the Board of Health are requiring more work of the inspec-<lb/>
tors every day, and to such a degree that the idea of the private<lb/>
practice cannot be thought of- in fact they desire that the<lb/>
whole of an Inspector's time be devoted to the interest of<lb/>
the Health of his District. This is doubtless right enough in<lb/>
a strict interpretation, but it is such a &ldquo;new departure&rdquo;<lb/>
that I, for one, fail to appreciate it. Secondly, these great cities<lb/>
have lost the fascination which formerly held me so fast.<lb/>
Four years ago, I would have remained here, &ldquo;though the<lb/>
Heavens should fall.&rdquo; I gave my hopes and ambition a<lb/>
free rein and applied the whip &amp; <unclear>spir</unclear> unsparingly. To<lb/>
live in any other place than New York or Brooklyn, never<lb/>
entered my head, and if a person had advised me to<lb/>
go to some small town, I would have certified to his insanity.<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01605007"/>
To such an extent does our folly mislead us! But since then<lb/>
a few more springs have come and gone, and though no gray<lb/>
hairs adorn my head, I have become a little wiser, I hope.<lb/>
I have carefully noted the success or failure of those<lb/>
around me and have watched them in their sorrows and joys.<lb/>
Yet during this time I have been unable to discover the great<lb/>
advantages of living in Metropolitan Cities, except it be in<lb/>
the &ldquo;wear and tear&rdquo;. It is true, I never worked harder, but I can't say<lb/>
that it has brought me an equal amount of comfort. I have<lb/>
still a third reason- Having entered my profession about<lb/>
4 years earlier than is the custom, I have experienced all<lb/>
the troubles of a youthful aspirant for honors. As long as<lb/>
my success depended upon actual knowledge and experience,<lb/>
I managed to overcome all obstacles, but the moment that I<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01605008"/>
entered upon the race of life, I found<lb/>
out, at once, the disadvantages of a youth-<lb/>
ful appearance. It is a remarkable fact<lb/>
that a man's success during the first de-<lb/>
cade depends more upon his beard than<lb/>
<del>upon</del> his brains. And inasmuch as I<lb/>
could boast of none of the former and but<lb/>
an infinitesimal quantity of the latter, I<lb/>
found &ldquo;Jordan to be a hard road to travel.&rdquo;<lb/>
Yet notwithstanding these many draw-backs,<lb/>
my success has been greater than I could<lb/>
have expected, and unless I can obtain the<lb/>
sanction of homefolks, I will not leave.<lb/>
My stay in these cities has done me<lb/>
an incomparable good<del>e</del> By it I have<lb/>
obtained an extensive hospital and<lb/>
sanitary experience which is worth to<lb/>
me more than I can now estimate.<lb/>
It has also given me a truer in-<lb/>
sight into human nature than I would<lb/>
have acquired in an equal number<lb/>
of years elsewhere, while it has added<lb/>
to my respect for truth and morality.<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01605009"/>
So that I count myself more than<lb/>
fortunate so far. On the other<lb/>
hand, I had thought that, as I<lb/>
have no anxiety to plunge, at once,<lb/>
into the cares of life, a few years<lb/>
spent in travelling from<del>s</del> one part<lb/>
of the country to another, would be of prof-<lb/>
it to me. Of course, all depends upon<lb/>
my ability to pass the examination<lb/>
which is a very rigid one. (I must con-<lb/>
fess that I dread it.) If at the end<lb/>
of that time (3 or 4 years hence) I could<lb/>
find some fair damsel who was<lb/>
foolish enough to trust me, I think<lb/>
I would get -- married, and settle<lb/>
down to sober work for the rest of<lb/>
my days in some small City where<lb/>
one could enjoy the advantages of<lb/>
a City &amp; at the same time not feel as<lb/>
if lost. For in what does life con-<lb/>
sist? what is its true philosophy?<lb/>
Is it to win the applause of the<lb/>
rabble? or to pit no &ldquo;high places&rdquo;?<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f01605010"/>
Do we not arrive nearer to true hap-<lb/>
piness in striving to accept what<lb/>
Divine Wisdom allots to us- doing all<lb/>
we can to assist our fellow-men<lb/>
in being happy, and submitting<lb/>
uncomplainingly to the will of Him<lb/>
who gave us breath and life?<lb/>
Ever remembering that &ldquo;he that hum-<lb/>
bleth himself, the same shall be<lb/>
exhalted&rdquo;.</p>
<p>But really the hour has<lb/>
grown very late, &amp; here am I phi-<lb/>
losophizing! &amp; what a dry &ldquo;hash&rdquo;<lb/>
                  (for I can find no other name to expression)<lb/>
<del>I</del> have <add>I</add> set before you! My first<lb/>
impulse is to tear it up &amp; spare<lb/>
you so many details, but on second<lb/>
thought I refrain from so doing,<lb/>
and beg that you will accept it<lb/>
in the same spirit in which it was written.</p>
<closer>
<salute>I remain, with much<lb/>
respect,</salute>
<signed>Walter Reed</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
