<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01743001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, May 25, 1879</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Reed, Walter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01743001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1879-05-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Harrison, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">McPherson, Dorsey</name>
<name type="person">Compton, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, John N.</name>
<name type="person">Heutig, Mrs.</name>
<name type="place">Norfolk (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Santa Fe (N.M.)</name>
<name type="place">Murfreesboro (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Arizona</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1879-05-25">May 25, 1879</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01743001</idno>
<title>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, May 25, 1879</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed describes a carriage ride.  He responds to a letter from Emilie Lawrence Reed, giving her financial advice and offering news of acquaintances.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1879-05-25">
<head>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, May 25, 1879</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01743001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Fort Apache, A.T.<lb/>
<date value="1879-05-25">May 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1879.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My own precious &ldquo;Oomantee&rdquo;,</salute>
</opener>
<p>This is Sunday<lb/>
morning, and as I have had a good bath, been<lb/>
to sick-call and eaten my breakfast, I know<lb/>
of no more pleasant duty than writing to<lb/>
my own darling wife- I am expecting a real<lb/>
long letter from my little darling to-day; yes<lb/>
at least <hi>two</hi> of them, telling me all about<lb/>
her arrival &amp; what she has been doing with<lb/>
her sweet little self &amp; what papa's darling little<lb/>
Laurie has been doing with his &ldquo;ittle tef,&rdquo; for<lb/>
the past two weeks- (I had reached this stage of<lb/>
my letter, when a chariot rolled up to the door-<lb/>
&ldquo;Mrs. Harrison's Compliments, and would the Doctor<lb/>
like to take a ride-&rdquo; well, what was to be done?<lb/>
As much as I wished to continue talking<lb/>
with my own little Emilie, love, I couldn't<lb/>
well refuse my first invitation and that<lb/>
too from Mrs. Harrison- So I accepted, put<lb/>
away my letter, and Dr McPherson &amp; I jumped<lb/>
aboard- we stopped at Mrs. Compton's<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01743002"/>
casa &amp; took her as a passenger also, &amp; there<lb/>
&ldquo;all aboard&rdquo; for the North Fork- we had quite<lb/>
a pleasant drive &amp; as we were fortunately<lb/>
all chatty, barring the dust, our ride<lb/>
was enjoyable)- I could but think of the<lb/>
last time I had ridden out to the North<lb/>
Fork- Then I was with my own darling<lb/>
Emilie &amp; sweet &ldquo;bad daddies&rdquo;- &amp; such a long<lb/>
journey as we had before us- Have you,<lb/>
my little pretty bride, forgotten that terrible<lb/>
journey with all its annoyances &amp; dust &amp;<lb/>
wind &amp; husband's crossness? Emilie, love,<lb/>
my own pretty, smart wife, you don't treas-<lb/>
-ure up any thing against your poor<lb/>
Mantee, who is away out here in Arizona,<lb/>
all by his &ldquo;ittle teffie,&rdquo; do you? Please<lb/>
darling, forgive his crossness, this time,<lb/>
&amp; you will find that he will be a heap<lb/>
sweeter &amp; better &ldquo;mantee&rdquo; to you, when<lb/>
he comes East- Now won't you, my &ldquo;ittle&rdquo;<lb/>
pet? Husband gives you one <hi>sweet</hi> kiss<lb/>
right on those pretty, cherry lips, and asks<lb/>
your pardon! <hi>Now</hi>, you have forgiven<lb/>
him haven't you? Ah! you pretty<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01743003"/>
little darling, if you haven't done so, it's<lb/>
just because you want &ldquo;mantee&rdquo; to give you<lb/>
<hi>another</hi> kiss! you pretty little, lovie, you shan't<lb/>
have it though! yes, you shall! husband<lb/>
takes it all back- She &ldquo;sal have jes as<lb/>
mausig as tee wants&rdquo;- Now its alright, ain't<lb/>
it, darling! you had better mind, I'll &ldquo;fow<lb/>
you in the teet &amp; let the old Mexitan dit oo&rdquo;!<lb/>
<hi>I</hi> know something that <hi>you</hi> don't know- I guess<lb/>
my little wifie would like to take a peep<lb/>
into the tray of my trunk &amp; see whose <hi>photo-<lb/>
graph</hi> I've got- <hi>Two</hi> of them too, &amp; she is just<lb/>
as pretty and sweet as she can be! I just<lb/>
go to my trunk every morning &amp; evening &amp;<lb/>
give both of them a dozen kisses a piece-<lb/>
Now ain't you sorry you've gone away,<lb/>
and left your mantee to flirt with two other<lb/>
gals! Do you know who they are? why,<lb/>
nobody but &ldquo;mama&rdquo;, her darling little self-<lb/>
Papa found them in the letter pocket in his<lb/>
trunk &amp; he was so glad to see his precious<lb/>
darling again, that he just took both of them<lb/>
out, gave them a good, rousing kiss &amp; hug,<lb/>
and put them in the tray of his trunk, side<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01743004"/>
by side, &ldquo;right side up with care,&rdquo; so that<lb/>
every time he goes to his trunk, there shines<lb/>
forth &amp; beams upon him <hi>two</hi> sweet &ldquo;mamas&rdquo;,<lb/>
&amp; then he gives them both a darling kiss &amp;<lb/>
tells them if they don't &ldquo;<unclear>have</unclear> deir ittle teffies&rdquo;<lb/>
he will &ldquo;frow dem in de teet&rdquo;- &ldquo;Deys two mighty<lb/>
dood&rdquo; little gals &amp; lots of company to papa-<lb/>
And then besides, papa has too little girls-<lb/>
in his trunk -- &ldquo;little mamas&rdquo;, when his pre-<lb/>
-cious little wifie wore shoes with the<lb/>
<hi>toes out</hi>! These are lots of company too-<lb/>
If he only had a picture of his precious<lb/>
little son to place just between your two<lb/>
darling pictures, he would then have<lb/>
both mother &amp; son, so that he could go<lb/>
to his trunk &amp; have a gambol every day.<lb/>
Hurry up, my little wife, &amp; send me a pho-<lb/>
-tograph of both yourself &amp; Laurie- <hi>I am<lb/>
so anxious</hi> to see <hi>my darlings</hi>! Mrs. Harri-<lb/>
-son says you promised her one of &ldquo;bad<lb/>
daddie&rdquo; &amp; that you must be sure to send<lb/>
it- She says she never hears retreat<lb/>
without thinking of Lawrence &amp; how he<lb/>
used to shake his little head- Does he still<lb/>
wake the hills with retreat? Now, &ldquo;dood bye&rdquo; my<lb/>
&ldquo;itsy oomsey&rdquo;, a big &ldquo;tiss&rdquo; for you- I won't write any more till the<lb/>
mail comes -- a great big &ldquo;tiss&rdquo; for papa's boy too-<lb/>
your affect. Papa.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01743005"/>
Monday morning, may 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. A nice, sweet, long letter<lb/>
from my darling wifie, written may 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-<lb/>
But, lovie, dear, ain't you going to write to your<lb/>
poor old mantee but <hi>once</hi> in <hi>eight days</hi>!<lb/>
why, my pretty E, don't treat old &ldquo;hubby&rdquo; that<lb/>
way! However, I think I can account for<lb/>
this apparent forgetfulness on the part of my<lb/>
precious Emilie. Love her heart, she has seen<lb/>
so much that is pretty &amp; interesting in Norfolk<lb/>
and has had so much to talk about, that the<lb/>
hours &amp; days have fled on such rapid wings<lb/>
that my little darling didn't really know how<lb/>
much time had gone by- Isn't it so, my pretty wife?<lb/>
How happy your letter made me -- my darling. To<lb/>
know that you are happy and that the faces about<lb/>
you are smiling ones &amp; that my darling Laurie<lb/>
has a good kind <del><unclear></unclear></del>nurse; all these things make<lb/>
<add>me</add> just as happy as I can be, away from my loved<lb/>
ones. So Pa comes to see Lawrence very often<lb/>
and thinks him very fine- I can commend<lb/>
his good taste- I told Altman last eve-<lb/>
ning, that all the homefolks thought Law-<lb/>
rence perfectly splendid- His reply was,<lb/>
&ldquo;if they are used to seeing fine children,<lb/>
Doctor, they couldn't say anything else&rdquo;.<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01743006"/>
Altman just takes it for granted that any<lb/>
body <hi>with eyes</hi> will say at once that Law-<lb/>
rence is a fine boy. He won't listen to<lb/>
any other opinion. I am not astonished that<lb/>
our little darling loves his colored mama.<lb/>
you know, my darling, how he likes out-of-<lb/>
door life, &amp; you may rest assured that he<lb/>
will love anybody who will take him out.<lb/>
If my darling little wifie will allow a sug-<lb/>
-gestion from far Arizona, I would advise<lb/>
you to let his nurse dress him too- you<lb/>
know, darling, how much labor you had<lb/>
to do out here, &amp; you should, my love, take<lb/>
all the rest you can- Give my regards<lb/>
to Aunt Mary &amp; tell her to take good care<lb/>
of Lawrence- not to spoil him, by rocking<lb/>
him to sleep at night, &amp; not to let him trou-<lb/>
ble his mother any. Do you hear, my wifie?<lb/>
I was so much amused &amp; interested at what<lb/>
my little wifie had to say about her nice new<lb/>
grenadine or &ldquo;bombazine&rdquo;, I forget which. Love<lb/>
your precious <add>heart,</add> husband knows who looked just<lb/>
as pretty &amp; sweet as an angel in that dress-<lb/>
And then, next week, &ldquo;see was doing to has a feet<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01743007"/>
tummer tilk&rdquo; to dress in- Husbands wishes that<lb/>
he had the money to dress his &ldquo;feetning&rdquo; wife<lb/>
as fine as any other woman- you know this<lb/>
don't you, darling? He had to laugh heartily at<lb/>
your allusion to the money running short by<lb/>
August- Poor little darling, she <hi>shall</hi> have some<lb/>
more money by August- Husband says so. Now<lb/>
don't borrow any, my little darling, whatever you <add>do</add>.<lb/>
I can pay for your nec<add>k</add>lace in June &amp; can send<lb/>
you <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>75 out <add>of</add> my July pay- Now, don't forget it.<lb/>
I wouldn't have you, under any circumstances,<lb/>
borrow of John Vaughan or any one- Make your<lb/>
money go as far as it will, &amp; when it is running<lb/>
low, I will replenish your purse- you &ldquo;Sabe&rdquo;?<lb/>
Speaking of your nec<add>k</add>lace, when I came back<lb/>
through Santa Fe, I went into Mr Luca's Store<lb/>
&amp; saw Mr Pegram &amp; the little gentleman- Mr L. was<lb/>
not in- They said that your necklace would be<lb/>
made by middle of June or before- I gave them<lb/>
your address as No. 66 Freemason St. Care<lb/>
John Vaughan, to which address it will be<lb/>
sent by express- I thought it better to have<lb/>
it addressed to Norfolk, as Murfreesboro is<lb/>
rather out of the way- Wasn't that right?<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01743008"/>
Tuesday morning, 8 o'clock- I have just read over<lb/>
my little darling's letter for about the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> time,<lb/>
and I don't believe I've got enough of it yet- Its<lb/>
the only real letter I've got from my &ldquo;itsy nemp-<lb/>
sy&rdquo; since &ldquo;sees been done&rdquo;- &ldquo;Boodigs&rdquo;! Of course Pa<lb/>
is right about my hair resembling Lawrence's-<lb/>
there was a <hi>slight</hi> difference, it is true- mine<lb/>
was as white as <hi>cotton</hi> and as straight as<lb/>
a well conducted <hi>poker</hi>, but with <add>the exception of</add> this little<lb/>
difference, there is a very great resemblance- we<lb/>
were all, last night, at an entertainment at<lb/>
the Trader's new billiard room last &amp; had a real<lb/>
pleasant evening -- didn't get into my couch<lb/>
till after midnight- Mrs. Harrison &amp; I had a<lb/>
tete-a-tete during the evening -- the theme of our<lb/>
conversation was my darling wife &amp; boy-<lb/>
Mrs. H. she misses you <hi>so much</hi> -- that you must be<lb/>
sure to send her a photograph of Lawrence as<lb/>
soon as taken- Mrs. H. &amp; Hentig send their best love-<lb/>
&amp; Mrs. H. a kiss for baby- Mr Staples told me to tell you<lb/>
that the only regret of the evening was that Mrs.<lb/>
Reed was not present- He sends his kindest<lb/>
regards, as well as all the others- &amp; Now papa must<lb/>
close his long letter to mama with oceans of<lb/>
love &amp; billions of kisses- Be a good little wifie,<lb/>
&amp; tell Laurie to be a good little son &amp; not to forget papa.<lb/>
Mother must give him a real good kiss for papa &amp; then he<lb/>
must give mama a good kiss for papa<del>s</del> too- Best love to mother,<lb/>
Sister, Doctor John &amp; all the others- write very often to your devoted &ldquo;hub.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>
<signed>Walter de Arizona</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
