<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01746001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, June 23, 1879</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Reed, Walter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01746001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1879-06-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Harrell, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Lawrence, Hannah</name>
<name type="person">[s.n.] Ellen</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Annie, Miss</name>
<name type="person">mcPherson, Dorsey</name>
<name type="person">Compton, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Compton, Mrs.</name>
<name type="place">Fort Apache (Arizona Territory)</name>
<name type="place">Otero [s.l.]</name>
<name type="place">Harrisonburg (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Rawly Springs [s.l.]</name>
<name type="place">Thomas [s.l.]</name>
<name type="place">Santa Fe (N.M.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort McKinney (Wyoming Territory)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>12 pp.</extent>
<date value="1879-06-23">June 23, 1879</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01746001</idno>
<title>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, June 23, 1879</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed teases Emilie Lawrence Reed. He offers news from the base. He is glad to hear that she is feeling better.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1879-06-23">
<head>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, June 23, 1879</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01746001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Fort Apache, A.T.<lb/>
<date value="1879-06-23">June 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1879.</date>
</dateline>
Tell papa's boy<lb/>
&ldquo;digger, digger, dig-<lb/>
-ger&rdquo;- Mama<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi>Boodigs</hi>&rdquo;!<lb/>
<salute>My pretty little picture:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The mail brought<lb/>
Papa a real long, sweet letter from Mama,<lb/>
yesterday afternoon, dated June 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>; and old papa<lb/>
is up, this morning, real early, answering it.<lb/>
He is ever so much obliged to his darling little<lb/>
wifie for writing so punctually, for every mail<lb/>
brings papa a letter &amp; makes him feel so happy.<lb/>
So if you don't get your letters promptly, my<lb/>
pretty darling is <hi>coming back to Apache</hi>? What<lb/>
lovey? Coming <hi>all the way</hi> back to <hi>old Apache</hi>?<lb/>
No, No! You can't do that, my pretty picture.<lb/>
Somebody said that if she once got east, she'd<lb/>
<hi>never</hi> come back! Who was that little darling?<lb/>
Is she beginning to get tired this soon? My, this will<lb/>
<hi>never</hi> do- Although there is a nice, fat ox team<lb/>
at Otero, that can make about 3 miles a day, ready<lb/>
to bring you to Apache whenever you start.<lb/>
Never mind, lovey dear, mantee won't joke<lb/>
any more- He knows you are just as happy<lb/>
as you can be east &amp; don't wan't to come<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01746002"/>
back to old, lovely Apache; and that you are<lb/>
just as pretty &amp; sweet &amp; precious &amp; apple pie<lb/>
&amp; good as you can be &amp; are going to enjoy<lb/>
your darling self &amp; be a good dear little<lb/>
wifie, till mantee comes, however distant in<lb/>
the future that may be- What does Miss Tib-<lb/>
-bie think of that darling boy of Papa's &amp; Mama's?<lb/>
It must have seemed strange to you, my dar-<lb/>
-ling wife, to have seen your own little son,<lb/>
romping about in the old home- The old home<lb/>
where mantee <del>y</del> used to come up the brick<lb/>
walk as straight as a ram-rod, &amp; with his<lb/>
plug hat so slick that it was sure death to<lb/>
any fly that dared attempt to perch thereon:<lb/>
The old home where mantee used to ring the<lb/>
door-bell &amp; ask, if &ldquo;Miss Lawrence was in&rdquo;,<lb/>
the old home where &ldquo;chiquita sofa&rdquo; mama &amp;<lb/>
papa used to sit on &amp; do so much courting,<lb/>
where papa offered his hand to darling mama,<lb/>
&amp; where mama accepted it, &amp; then <hi>wanted papa<lb/>
to kiss her</hi>, &amp; papa, like a great idiot, didn't<lb/>
have sense enough to do it! A few years<lb/>
gone by, &amp; then to return &amp; see your own little<lb/>
&ldquo;Laurie&rdquo; running about &amp; making things merry<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01746003"/>
with his happy prattle &amp; laughter! How papa<lb/>
should liked to have seen him! One thing is<lb/>
very sure, he is an ornament into whatever<lb/>
house he may go; &amp; there never was but one<lb/>
finer child in the old home, &amp; that was my<lb/>
own precious wifie, who <hi>would wear shoes<lb/>
with the toes all out</hi>! Do you know, lovey<lb/>
dear, that you haven't so much as told me<lb/>
what any one of your family think of the<lb/>
boy, except Col. Harrell-? not a word about<lb/>
your mother's opinion- or Sister Ellen's or<lb/>
Dr John's or Mr Charles' or any one of the homefolks.<lb/>
&amp; this after my darling wife had promised to<lb/>
write Papa just what homefolks said. The<lb/>
only conclusion I can draw is that they haven't<lb/>
yet seen the boy, or if the have, they said noth-<lb/>
ing at all! Never mind Mama, dear, Papa won't<lb/>
send you any sweet kisses, if you forget to<lb/>
tell him anything about his darling boy - Papa<lb/>
does so hope that Mr Grimes has had good<lb/>
success with his photographs, &amp; he expects<lb/>
certainly to get one next Sunday- But you<lb/>
said nothing about your own, my darling<lb/>
wifie- Now, remember that your old &ldquo;hubby&rdquo;<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01746004"/>
is just as anxious to get his pretty, precious<lb/>
wife's picture as he is to have that of his dar-<lb/>
-ling boy - &amp; if you haven't already had one<lb/>
taken, you must be <hi>sure</hi> to do so, when you get<lb/>
to Harrisonburg- I know my darling wifie<lb/>
is looking forward to a happy time, this summer,<lb/>
at Grand-ma Reed's- Couldn't you get your<lb/>
mother to consent to go?- It would have been<lb/>
such a splended visit &amp; such a pleasant<lb/>
one for her- Wouldn't she come up to H'burg,<lb/>
if you &amp; Miss Annie shared the expense? If<lb/>
so, don't fail to make the offer- How papa<lb/>
wishes that he could<del>n</del> have been ordered out<lb/>
this summer &amp; could be with his darlings in the<lb/>
valley- What <hi>times</hi> we would have had, &amp; what<lb/>
stories we would have told of Arizona ad-<lb/>
-venture! But although Papa can't be there,<lb/>
he knows that his pretty wife &amp; her Sister will<lb/>
have a very happy time- Grow fat, my pretty<lb/>
little darling, &amp; &ldquo;Kick&rdquo; all &amp; everybody you please!<lb/>
Husband will be responsible for anything you<lb/>
do. If Sister Annie will consent, he wants you<lb/>
to take a flying trip to Rawley Springs, to<lb/>
stay a week or two, or just as long as you<lb/>
could stay away from our darling Laurie-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01746005"/>
Papa knows it would do his little dar-<lb/>
ling good &amp; help her to pass away the time-<lb/>
Go where you please, my lovey, so you<lb/>
don't hurt yourself &amp; if anybody bothers<lb/>
you, just double up your little &ldquo;fistigs&rdquo; &amp;<lb/>
give them a good &ldquo;whack&rdquo;, &amp; charge it to mantee!<lb/>
I must here stop awhile, as guard-mount is<lb/>
over &amp; it is time for breakfast- Our mess is,<lb/>
just at present, rather small- Mr Gatewood &amp;<lb/>
Dr McPherson away on a scout &amp; Lt. Mills<lb/>
gone to Thomas on a short tour- We are thus<lb/>
reduced to Lt. Stanton, Cap't. Mc Gowan, &amp; Lt. Reed,<lb/>
<hi>11 o'clock A.M</hi>. Well I didn't think it would be<lb/>
so late before I got another chance to con-<lb/>
-tinue my letter- I've had to go to the Tailor's,<lb/>
lance an inflamed gum, interview a pris-<lb/>
-oner as to whether he will plead &ldquo;guilty&rdquo; or<lb/>
not, and sold my chairs since breakfast time.<lb/>
At 1 P.M. lunch comes &amp; at 1.30 a Garrison<lb/>
Court, of which I am Recorder, so that I<lb/>
must make the best of the next two hours<lb/>
that I possibly can. The chairs, my sweet<lb/>
wifie, I sold to a Mormon butter-dealer- He<lb/>
gave me three dollars a piece for the four chairs<lb/>
&amp; four dollars for the Rocker- or <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>16.00 for the lot;<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01746006"/>
I was glad enough to get rid of them at that<lb/>
price- I had tried to sell them to various<lb/>
parties, but without success, &amp; had begun<lb/>
to think that I had an &ldquo;Elephant&rdquo; on my<lb/>
hands, when lo! The Stranger appeared &amp; took<lb/>
them. I offered them at <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>20.00, but he would<lb/>
only give <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>16.00- I could have fallen on<lb/>
his neck &amp; wept. Henceforth the cut of his<lb/>
<hi>noble</hi> countenance will ever be before me.<lb/>
May his &ldquo;olive-branches&rdquo; luxuriate &amp; climb<lb/>
all over him; which will doubtless be the<lb/>
case, as he has many wifes- The little rifle<lb/>
was purchased by the Nuncio of his Holiness<lb/>
for the sum of <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>25.00 cash, paid down-and I<lb/>
think I can sell the gun that Lt. Ray gave<lb/>
me for <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>20.00, certainly for <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>15.00- I have just<lb/>
put it in good order, &amp; have two Agents can-<lb/>
-vassing the garrison with the view of disposing<lb/>
of it- to wit: Ned. Altman, alias the &ldquo;Nuncio&rdquo;, and<lb/>
John Alberti, alias the &ldquo;Russian bear&rdquo;. If I only<lb/>
get <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>15.00 it will give me <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>56.00 for the 2 guns &amp;<lb/>
chairs, which completely meets my satisfaction.<lb/>
What does the sweetest woman in the world<lb/>
think about it? I have taken the old carpet<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01746007"/>
back &amp; bottom out <add>of</add> the large folding chair,<lb/>
which <del>we</del><add>you</add> had your worked strip on in the parlor,<lb/>
my darling Emilie, &amp; sent it over to the Carpenter<lb/>
shop to be re-glued &amp; an extension put on it,<lb/>
so as to make it a real comfortable reclin-<lb/>
-ing chair - when it is done, I shall try to beg<lb/>
enough leather of W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>, the conqueror, to put<lb/>
a good bottom &amp; back to it- If can't get it, I<lb/>
will put it away &amp; when we get east, we<lb/>
can have <del>an</del> a nice bottom of rep or carpet<lb/>
put in it, &amp; then it will be a good, strong chair.<lb/>
That &amp; our 2 dining-room chairs, &amp; the <hi>larger</hi> one<lb/>
of the two small folding chairs, &amp; the leather, folding<lb/>
chair that I bought of Lt. Gatewood, making<lb/>
<hi>five</hi> in all, I shall pack up &amp; bring with me.<lb/>
They are all real, sound, serviceable chairs<lb/>
&amp; there is no use selling them out here at<lb/>
a sacrifice &amp; then having to buy them again<lb/>
when we start house-keeping east, Don't you<lb/>
thin<del>g</del>k I am right, my precious wife? Concerning<lb/>
your gold necklace, I haven't received the bill<lb/>
from Mr Lucas yet. When I was in Santa Fe,<lb/>
May 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>, on my return, I saw Mr Lucas' clerk<lb/>
Mr Pegram, &amp; they said that it would be done<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01746008"/>
by June 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>, but added that they had some<lb/>
work in the shop which wished to get rid<lb/>
of, before beginning your's &amp; Mr. Mill's necklace-<lb/>
I presume they may have been out of gold<lb/>
dust, just at the time, &amp; this would of course delay<lb/>
it- I think it likely that you will get it by last<lb/>
of June or 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of July- You will remember, lovey,<lb/>
that I told Mr Lucas that I would not have<lb/>
the money till the end of June &amp; this may be<lb/>
<add>is</add> why he is not in a great hurry- He told me that<lb/>
he would do just as handsome a job &amp; fit as he<lb/>
could- Have patience, Mantee's pretty little Em-<lb/>
ilie, wifie, it will be alright, &amp; then you will<lb/>
have several real pretty presents from<lb/>
Mantee, won't you my love? Husband wishes<lb/>
that they were a thousand times more valuable,<lb/>
&amp; then they would not be what his pretty,<lb/>
precious little bride deserves! <hi>Love her heart</hi>!<lb/>
I have real sad news to tell you about poor<lb/>
little Undina! You remember that I wrote<lb/>
you, my darling, that she was going to have<lb/>
puppies- Well, I was mistaken - she was only<lb/>
growing fat &amp; stout- It was a case of <del>Miss</del><lb/>
&ldquo;miss fire&rdquo; on the part of the hairless brute-<lb/>
She has been very lively &amp; full of fun &amp; on<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f01746009"/>
(page 9-)<lb/>
last Saturday morning,(To-day is Monday) on my re-<lb/>
turn from Sick - Call, I never saw her more<lb/>
playful- She was, as usual tearing around<lb/>
&amp; trying to bite my legs all the way from the<lb/>
Hospital- When I got home I sat down on<lb/>
the porch to- read, &amp; Undina laid down by my<lb/>
chair &amp; apparently went to sleep- About<lb/>
an hour after, when I started to breakfast,<lb/>
I noticed that she was not very lively &amp; would<lb/>
eat nothing at the mess- During the day she be-<lb/>
came very much cramped about her belly &amp;<lb/>
I gave her a dose of castor oil, which opera-<lb/>
-ted freely- At night time she could hardly stand<lb/>
on her hind legs, &amp; yesterday morning, when I<lb/>
got up I found the poor little thing complete-<lb/>
ly paralyzed, from the middle of her body back-<lb/>
wards- She couldn't move her hind legs or wag<lb/>
her tail- She is now in the same condition-<lb/>
Can raise up on her fore paws &amp; drag her-<lb/>
self only about six inches at a time- She lies<lb/>
quietly in my room on the bear's skin &amp; looks<lb/>
up at me so pitifully &amp; pleadingly that it<lb/>
makes me real sad- Isn't it too bad, my pre-<lb/>
cious wifie? I am certain that she ate some-<lb/>
-thing that poisoned her, but I am in great<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f01746010"/>
<add>hopes</add> that she will recover- She takes milk very<lb/>
well- Says &ldquo;tell mittie I'se so tick&rdquo;. Sends<lb/>
her best love &amp; a kiss to little Mottie &amp; Mittie.<lb/>
You say, my darling, that I must keep you<lb/>
posted on Army news- Well, I don't know<lb/>
much, except that there have been a great<lb/>
many Retirements &amp; Promotions during the<lb/>
month of June- A new Colonel,(Col. Carr.)<lb/>
Lieut. Col.(I forget his name) &amp; a new major,<lb/>
(David A. Perry.) come to the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> cavalry- Major<lb/>
Perry will, we think, come to Apache as Comman-<lb/>
-ding Officer. I told you, I believe, that, <add>Major</add> <del>colonel</del><lb/>
Compton had been promoted to be Lieutenant<lb/>
Colonel of the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> cavalry, an excellent Regiment<lb/>
He &amp; Mrs. C. will leave about two weeks, from<lb/>
this time, &amp; probably be stationed at Fort Mc<lb/>
Kinney, in Wyoming Territory- I tell you<lb/>
what, my little lovie, our new Captain, McGow-<lb/>
-an, is just bucking right up to the fair<lb/>
widow- Adam has had his <del>kno</del> nose knocked<lb/>
&ldquo;clean out of joint&rdquo; &amp; has taken a &ldquo;back seat&rdquo;,<lb/>
&ldquo;We cannot, always tell&rdquo;, but Mrs. Compton,<lb/>
the Col. &amp; I think that the Captain will propose,<lb/>
&amp; we are not sure that the buxom lass<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f01746011"/>
will give him the mitten! That's just how<lb/>
the matter stands- &ldquo;May the brave only win<lb/>
the fair&rdquo;! It is only 12.20 P.M. but I must stop,<lb/>
my precious wifie, in order to see the witnesses<lb/>
who will testify before the Court this afternoon.<lb/>
Tuesday afternoon, 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>- Well, husband must conclude<lb/>
his &ldquo;ittle etter&rdquo;, &amp; after filling it with a heap of<lb/>
love &amp; kisses for papa's little darlings, must then<lb/>
seal it up &amp; send it on its way- &ldquo;Hubby&rdquo; has<lb/>
been busy all the morning, making a beautiful<lb/>
fishing pole with which to &ldquo;yerk&rdquo; (or &ldquo;yank,&rdquo;) the<lb/>
festive trout from his pensive lair - &amp; to-morrow,<lb/>
perhaps, he will try a &ldquo;spin up the creek-&rdquo; Do you<lb/>
remember, lovey, dear, how the bugs served the<lb/>
gardens, last year? If anything, they have been<lb/>
worse this year - All of my seed were peeping<lb/>
forth very nicely &amp; had raised their tiny heads<lb/>
about one inch high, when along came the<lb/>
bugs &amp; ate them <hi>all</hi> down - nothing whatever<lb/>
left. Fortunately, I had not planted all my<lb/>
seeds- I have sown again &amp; things once<lb/>
more look a little promising. As the rainy<lb/>
season will soon set in, (indeed we had<lb/>
a slight shower night before last,) I am<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f01746012"/>
hoping that my garden will be a success,<lb/>
although of necessity it needs must be late-<lb/>
Little wifie, dear, I &ldquo;pec&rdquo; will have plenty of<lb/>
nice vegetables in the valley &amp; good things to put<lb/>
in her &ldquo;ittle <hi>tummy</hi>.&rdquo; Papa is so glad to have Ma-<lb/>
-ma write that her health has much improved-<lb/>
May you get all of the miserable Arizona mala-<lb/>
-ria out of your darling little &ldquo;carcass;&rdquo; and may<lb/>
your precious cheeks grow pink &amp; rosy like those<lb/>
of a peach; may your sweet little legs grow<lb/>
as plump as a spring chicken's, &amp; your darling<lb/>
little &ldquo;tummy&rdquo; become as round as a butter ball!<lb/>
And when you have reached the stage just de-<lb/>
-scribed, your old mantee is coming east to<lb/>
take a good -- <hi>look at you</hi>! Ha! Ha! <hi>love</hi> its<lb/>
<hi>pretty</hi> heart, mantee thinks its the <hi>dearest</hi>,<lb/>
<hi>sweetest wife</hi> &amp; <hi>mother</hi> in <hi>all this world</hi>, and he<lb/>
wouldn't take <hi>20 yoke</hi> of <hi>oxen</hi> for his lovely<lb/>
precious darling- She is <hi>all</hi> in <hi>all</hi> &amp; <hi>over all</hi><lb/>
in this world! He loves her more than he loves<lb/>
his life, &amp; he knows his love increases everyday!<lb/>
He could <hi>eat her up bone</hi> &amp; <hi>muscle</hi>! First Comes<lb/>
<hi>mother</hi>, <hi>darling mother</hi>, then papa's <hi>precious little Son</hi>,<lb/>
&amp; these <hi>two</hi> are his <hi>own</hi> &amp; <hi>only jewels</hi>! Brighter than<lb/>
diamonds to his eye, &amp; sweeter than the honey in the Comb,<lb/>
to his heart! Love &amp; kisses, love &amp; kisses, love &amp; kisses for Mama &amp; son!<lb/>
Love to all - write soon &amp; often, my pretty darling, to your fond, loving &amp; devoted<lb/>
husband.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Walter of Arizona</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

