<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01752001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, September 8, 1879</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Reed, Walter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01752001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1879-09-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Gatewood, Charles B.</name>
<name type="person">Biddle, Colonel</name>
<name type="person">Alberti, Steward</name>
<name type="person">McKee, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Norfolk (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Harrisonburg (Va.?)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Apache (Ariz.)</name>
<name type="place">Murfreesboro (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1879-09-08">September 8, 1879</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01752001</idno>
<title>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, September 8, 1879</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed's letter to his wife includes his thoughts on scouting, his work to get the hospital property ready for inspection, an upcoming court martial, and his side-whiskers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1879-09-08">
<head>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, September 8, 1879</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01752001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Fort Apache, ???<lb/>
<date value="1879-09-08">Sept 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1879.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My own precious little wifie:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You may think from the magnitude and extent<lb/>
of my paper, that I am going to write a very extended communication,<lb/>
but I assure my little darling that I <add>have</add> not any news at all, &amp; what little<lb/>
I did intend to say, has been frightened away by this terrific paper!<lb/>
Now, <hi>you</hi> talk, <unclear>lovie</unclear>, about <hi>your</hi> nice <hi>large</hi> paper, but what do think<lb/>
of <hi>mine</hi>! Isn't it a &ldquo;<hi>noble</hi>&rdquo; sheet of paper (<unclear>a la Jerimei Almanach</unclear>!) I just<lb/>
thought I would look around <unclear>now</unclear> if I couldn't find something<lb/>
that would give me &ldquo;Elbow room&rdquo;, &amp; I <hi>almost</hi> think I have found it!<lb/>
Your precious letter of Aug. 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> came yesterday. <unclear>Mantee</unclear> was<lb/>
very glad to hear that his letters always made his darling <unclear>Emi-<lb/>
-lie</unclear> happy and afforded her a few <unclear>tittillatious</unclear> of the diaphragm.<lb/>
He couldn't help from being made sad by the thought that perhaps<lb/>
his very next letter, which his <unclear>lovie</unclear> was complaining of having<lb/>
to wait for a whole week, would make her very unhappy-<lb/>
Love her precious, trusting heart! <unclear>Mantee</unclear> wishes that it had<lb/>
been in his power to tell her that he would come this fall,<lb/>
but his darling <unclear>wifie</unclear> knows that it is a matter over which<lb/>
he has no control, and he hopes <hi>so much</hi> that his little <hi>brave</hi><lb/>
<unclear>wifie</unclear> didn't give way to too many tears! I &ldquo;<unclear>pec</unclear>&rdquo;, at first.<lb/>
She <unclear>had</unclear> a good &ldquo;<unclear>boohoo</unclear>&rdquo;, but then I &ldquo;<unclear>find</unclear>&rdquo; she afterwards &ldquo;<unclear>dot</unclear>&rdquo; <unclear>mad</unclear>,<lb/>
&amp; said, &ldquo;<unclear>Mean old Mantee</unclear>, I won't cry one bit&rdquo;! Why just to think,<lb/>
<unclear>lovie</unclear>, it has been a whole month, lacking only a <hi>few</hi> days, <unclear>will</unclear><lb/>
I wrote you that I couldn't come till next May? Would you<lb/>
believe it? When my darling receives this big-<unclear>sheeteds</unclear> individual,<lb/>
it will be after the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of the month, and then <unclear>Mantee</unclear> will only<lb/>
have 7 months to stay; &amp; by the time, <unclear>lovie</unclear>, you answer this<lb/>
letter &amp; <unclear>Mantee</unclear> replies to yours, why <hi>another</hi> month will have<lb/>
<unclear>Come</unclear> &amp; gone, &amp; then the New Year will soon be here! I was<lb/>
sorry that I had not addressed my letter of the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Sept, &amp; which<lb/>
left here on the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>, direct to <unclear>norfolk</unclear>- I thought about it quite<lb/>
awhile, but as you had said that you, sometime about the<lb/>
Middle of <unclear>Sept-</unclear> or after, would leave Harrisonburg, I thought<lb/>
it would reach you before you started. If you leave on<lb/>
the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, however, you will miss it, <unclear>lovie</unclear>, dear- as it cannot<lb/>
reach H'burg before 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. It will reach <unclear>Norfolk</unclear> about<lb/>
the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> or 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>, &amp; on opening it, my little <unclear>lovie</unclear> will find a<lb/>
<unclear>Sung</unclear> little <unclear>Check</unclear> <add>(<unclear>$108<hi rend="superscript">00</hi></unclear>)</add> for her &ldquo;<unclear>Teffigs</unclear>&rdquo;! Poor, sweet little <unclear>wifie</unclear>, how<lb/>
the narration of her expenses amused <unclear>old Mantee</unclear>! Had<lb/>
only <unclear>$40</unclear>, with which to pay nurse &amp; washing for Aug. &amp; <unclear>Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></unclear><lb/>
&amp; pay her expenses to <unclear>Norfolk</unclear>! Well, my pretty Emilie,<lb/>
<unclear>Mantee</unclear> takes all the blame upon himself for letting your<lb/>
purse get so low; but it <unclear>shout</unclear> occur again, darling. Why<lb/>
on the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of October, my pretty <unclear>wifie</unclear> didn't have as much as <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>100!<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01752002"/>
Did she, my pretty pet? Well never mind, my darling, your own husband<lb/>
will send you another nice check by the middle of November, sure!<lb/>
Don't write to husband, darling, about <hi>hating</hi> to spend your money<lb/>
so much. Husband is perfectly satisfied with our finances - thinks<lb/>
his darling Emilie has done wonderfully well with her money,<lb/>
&amp; wants her to feel, when she spends a dollar, that old &ldquo;<unclear>tension</unclear>&rdquo;<lb/>
will supply its place with another. I expect to send Pa <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>50 or<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">$</hi>75 out of our September pay to add to our little <unclear>mite</unclear>. Another <unclear>Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></unclear><lb/>
pay belongs to darling mama &amp; son. Now that you know you will<lb/>
spend the <unclear>writes</unclear> East, you will, of course, get a nice <unclear>cloak</unclear>, my dar-<lb/>
ling, and a new hat too- Yet just what you need, my <unclear>wifie</unclear>, dear, and<lb/>
don't hesitate a moment on account of money- You must be<lb/>
as well dressed &amp; pretty as any other lady- Do you intend to re-<lb/>
main long in <unclear>Norfolk</unclear> before going up to <unclear>Murfreesboro</unclear>? Write<lb/>
me just what your plans are for the winter. <unclear>Mantee</unclear> will<lb/>
be so much interested in his precious Emilie's movements, and<lb/>
if she will tell him before hand just where she will be, he<lb/>
will always know just where to see his darlings, in his <unclear>mind's</unclear><lb/>
eye, and enjoy it so much more. I know <unclear>Romefolks</unclear> in <unclear>Murfreesboro</unclear><lb/>
are very anxious to see you again. Take very good care of your<lb/>
health &amp; papa's boy's health wherever you may be, my <unclear>lovie, dear.</unclear><lb/>
Papa is reminded of his darling Laurie, every day, by seeing Mrs.<lb/>
Kingsburg's little boy, who is just 20 months old &amp; a very fine<lb/>
little fellow. I frequently have a romp with him, but I don't<lb/>
think he quite comes up to Papa's boy. By the way, is this<lb/>
not Pa's <hi>last</hi> year on the <unclear>Norfolk</unclear> Circuit? I wonder where<lb/>
he will be sent. Am sorry that he will not be in <unclear>Norfolk</unclear><lb/>
all the winter with you- How long will <unclear>tita</unclear> remain<lb/>
up the Country? All winter? Poor Mollie Robinson<unclear>!</unclear> What<lb/>
can make her <add><unclear>dis</unclear></add>like you, my precious? I thought she con-<lb/>
-sidered you her friend when you were in Harrisonburg<lb/>
before. Speaking of Harrisonburg, reminds me that Mr. Gate-<lb/>
-wood has, at last, returned from his long scout-says his<lb/>
Mother wrote him that she had met you &amp; that you were<lb/>
a mighty nice lady, (which <hi>I</hi> &ldquo;fought&rdquo; wasn't anything <hi>very</hi><lb/>
hard to find out, piggie, diggie) and relieved her uneasiness a<lb/>
good deal by telling her that scouting in Arizona was<lb/>
not very dangerous. Says that you told her that <hi>you</hi><lb/>
would not be uneasy, if your husband went scouting! Well,<lb/>
I am glad to hear that my little <unclear>wifie</unclear> looks upon it in<lb/>
that light, which is the sensible way to look as it- not that<lb/>
I think of going on a scout, for I have <hi>no desire whatever</hi>-<lb/>
I find it is much better to remain at home &amp; have something<lb/>
good to eat &amp; a good <unclear>Mattrose</unclear> to sleep on, than to go climbing<lb/>
over <unclear>mesas</unclear>, eat bacon &amp; yeast powder bread, &amp; then sleep<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01752003"/>
on the ground at night! Although M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gatewood only returned<lb/>
on Friday, he was ordered out again on a scout, to-day, &amp; left<lb/>
about noon. He had been away from June 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to <unclear>Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></unclear> 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>,<lb/>
&amp; left again, to-day. <unclear>Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></unclear> 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> for New Mexico- Don't know when<lb/>
he will be back- I think he is getting a little tired of life in<lb/>
the field, &amp; will ask to be relieved, <add>from Indian Company</add> when he gets back again.<lb/>
M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mills is in to see us very frequently- In fact he reminds me<lb/>
very forcibly of the old woman who never went to visit her son<lb/>
but twice each year, but stayed six months each time. As his company<lb/>
is now at Black River, only 18 miles away, and Captain M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gowan gives<lb/>
him permission to absent himself whenever he likes, he <unclear>does</unclear> nothing<lb/>
else but loaf around Apache. Turkey Creek Hill, my darling, is no<lb/>
more- I went over the new road just made, and it is a beautiful<lb/>
grade-easy of ascent &amp; decent- &amp; Black River will soon follow suit.<lb/>
<hi>Tuesday</hi>, <unclear>Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></unclear> 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> - <hi>noon</hi>- Well, <unclear>lovie</unclear>, dear, old <unclear>Mantee</unclear> has been hard<lb/>
at work all the morning, trying to get a lot of Hospital Property<lb/>
ready for inspection, as <unclear>Col. Biddle</unclear> is expected, to-morrow, or next day-<lb/>
and a big job I have had of it- Steward Alberti, alias old &ldquo; it shall<lb/>
be most excellent,&rdquo; is simply the most annoying old &ldquo;<unclear>tea-pot</unclear>&rdquo;<lb/>
that I ever had to deal with! He has no idea of keeping things<lb/>
in order, and doesn't know where to find anything- I wrote to <unclear>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi><lb/>
Kee</unclear> last week, &amp; asked to have him sent somewheres else, &amp; I do hope<lb/>
my request will be granted, as I am heartily sick of the old &ldquo;<unclear></unclear>&rdquo;<lb/>
By the way, <unclear>lovie</unclear>, I had a letter from D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> <unclear>Oldmixon</unclear>, last week. He<lb/>
is still at M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Dowell &amp; says the <unclear>heat</unclear> is prostrating; wishes that<lb/>
he was back at Apache. Sends his very kindest regards to &ldquo;Madame<lb/>
and Kid&rdquo;. I presume he is &ldquo;going&rdquo; out of the Territory, &ldquo;next spring&rdquo;, as he<lb/>
has been making arrangements to go every spring since I have been<lb/>
in the Department. We are going to have a &ldquo;General Court Martial&rdquo;<lb/>
here- will meet next Saturday, 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> (I believe I was born on that<lb/>
day!). Col. Biddle, 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <unclear>cav.</unclear> is president, &amp; the immortal &ldquo;Billy&rdquo;, the<lb/>
ex-conqueror &amp; ex-quartermaster, is judge advocate- As there are<lb/>
5 or 6 long <unclear>windeds</unclear> cases to be <unclear>tried</unclear>, &amp; as <unclear>won</unclear> &ldquo;The lazy,&rdquo; dislikes<lb/>
to do any work, I think we will be in session about 40 years,<lb/>
more or less. Lt. Scott, 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <unclear>cav.</unclear>, whom you met at Thomas, comes<lb/>
over from Verde as a member of the Court- I don't know whether<lb/>
he will bring his wife or not- M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> <unclear>Overton</unclear> is engaged in building<lb/>
the Telegraph line <unclear>amend</unclear> from Thomas to Apache, &amp; has his wife &amp; child<lb/>
along with him- These I believe are about all the Army matters<lb/>
that I can make &amp; <unclear>scrape</unclear>- Our rifle-match for <unclear><hi rend="superscript">$</hi></unclear>50 medal, which<lb/>
was postponed till Captain <unclear>Heutig's</unclear> return from Scouting, <unclear>Ames</unclear><lb/>
off Friday &amp; Saturday of this week- I don't know whether I will<lb/>
shoot or not, as in a little match that we had, a few days ago,<lb/>
I became so nervous that, out of 30 who fired, I stood only<lb/>
No. 6- five others having better scores- No. <hi>6</hi>. <unclear>seems</unclear> a favorite number<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01752004"/>
with me, lovie. You remember that my standing in my class in the<lb/>
Army was also No. 6. and to make the matter <hi><unclear>perfectly</unclear> conclusive</hi>, I was<lb/>
appointed District Physician in New York to ward No. 6, and I am <unclear>No</unclear>.<lb/>
<hi>6</hi> feet high! Hesche! <unclear>lovie</unclear>. This last exclamation reminds me of Papa's<lb/>
boy- Has he, mother, forgotten how to say &ldquo;hesche&rdquo;? He used to say it so<lb/>
sweetly- Old Juanita, alias &ldquo;Transportation&rdquo;, still <unclear>clings</unclear> to Apache, &amp;<lb/>
<unclear>does</unclear> a &ldquo;vast quantity&rdquo; of washing- <unclear>Natsin</unclear>, alias &ldquo;The <unclear>Liar</unclear>,&rdquo; also pays<lb/>
me a visit occasionally, &amp; always makes inquiries of my &ldquo;<unclear>Motash-</unclear>&rdquo;<lb/>
I believe his &ldquo;lady&rdquo; has quite recovered her health &amp; beauty, &amp; once<lb/>
more graces &amp; chances Apache circles with her loveliness and <unclear>wit</unclear>.<lb/>
The <unclear>rumor</unclear> concerning Se&ntilde;or Don Miller leading the <del><unclear>the</unclear></del> fair &amp; petit<lb/>
<unclear>Hosey to Hymeu's Alter</unclear>, seems to have been premature, and she is still<lb/>
the prize whom many valorous admirers are <unclear>striving</unclear> to win- (Length<lb/>
of her neck, at percent, 12 inches-wrinkles, 40 million- eye still <unclear>peering</unclear><lb/>
into the &ldquo;for beyonds&rdquo;- you can recall the look- &ldquo;why, lady, I hadn't<lb/>
begun to show you what I could do&rdquo;!) She still continues to <unclear>darn</unclear> my<lb/>
socks with fragments of clothes line- Adrian, my new striker, (you<lb/>
remember, <unclear>lovie</unclear>, the polite, blond young gentleman, who always took<lb/>
off his hat &amp; said &ldquo;good morning&rdquo; so sweetly,) I think will <unclear>man</unclear> my<lb/>
laundress a race in sewing- He is quite an <unclear>adopt</unclear> at <unclear>wielding</unclear> the<lb/>
needle, &amp; I no sooner shed a button, so to speak, than he <unclear>fastens</unclear><lb/>
it on again. I think he <unclear>does</unclear> equally as well as <unclear>altonan</unclear>, although<lb/>
he does not possess that profound insight into human nature that<lb/>
the latter wields with such perfect mastery; but as he wears slip-<lb/>
-pers &amp; makes no noise when he <unclear>news</unclear> about the house, I like him.<lb/>
I have reserved the most &ldquo;stumming&rdquo; piece of intelligence, my pre-<lb/>
cious piggie, for the last of my letter- Can you guess, what it is, <unclear>beauty?</unclear><lb/>
not in a century!- Well, <unclear>lovie</unclear>, dear, I have got the handsomest<lb/>
pair of <hi>side-whiskers</hi> to be seen at <unclear>Fort</unclear> Apache! Real, live,<lb/>
blooming &ldquo;<unclear>siders</unclear>&rdquo;, such as catch the passing breeze &amp; <unclear>detain</unclear><lb/>
it in their depths! Oh! if you could only behold them, my little<lb/>
<unclear>wifie</unclear>, you would fall upon them- &amp; weep! They have the most<lb/>
delicate <unclear><hi>auburn</hi> tint</unclear>, shading into my favorite &ldquo;<unclear>solferma</unclear>,&rdquo; and are<lb/>
the admiration of all the ladies at Apache! Its all I can do, <unclear>lovie</unclear>,<lb/>
to keep them away from them! They have such a desire to <unclear>tangle</unclear><lb/>
their fingers in their silken webs! <hi>Hesche</hi>! I allow them now<lb/>
to float on the breeze, but when the cold weather comes, will <unclear>tie</unclear><lb/>
them under my chin, to serve as a kind of comforter! &ldquo;<unclear>Boodigs</unclear>&rdquo;!<lb/>
Will, perhaps, send you a &ldquo;lock&rdquo; of them, one of these days, if<lb/>
my little <unclear>wifie</unclear> will be very &ldquo;<unclear>dood.</unclear>&rdquo; My mustache is as rampant<lb/>
as <del><unclear>hour</unclear></del> ever! &ldquo;<unclear>Boodigs</unclear>&rdquo;! And this is every single thing I can think<lb/>
of to write; except to add that <hi>you</hi> are <hi>beyond</hi> a <hi>doubt</hi>, the<lb/>
very <hi>sweetest <unclear>lovie</unclear></hi>, the very <hi>dearest <unclear>wifie</unclear></hi>, that <hi>ever lived</hi>! &ldquo;<unclear>Boodigs</unclear>&rdquo;-<lb/>
Best love to Sister <unclear>Amie</unclear>. M<unclear><hi rend="superscript">r</hi> V</unclear>. &amp; Children &amp; Pa Reed- also to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Charles Lawrence.<lb/>
Kiss papa's boy forty times for him. Be a dear, good little <unclear>wifie</unclear>; love husband and <unclear>hosp</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>think of him arround, normal &amp; right as your band never</unclear></p>
<closer>
<salute><unclear>Devoted husband,</unclear></salute>
<signed><unclear>Walter, of Arizona</unclear></signed>
<seg>
P. S. <unclear>Susie</unclear><lb/>
in all <unclear>&ldquo;humbly<lb/>
doing&rdquo;- as far<lb/>
as better in growing<lb/>
like &ldquo;good-boy<lb/>
horse&rdquo;- nice</unclear><lb/>
tell you more<lb/>
of her in my<lb/>
next- forgot<lb/>
it this time-<lb/>
<hi>&ldquo;<unclear>Boodigs</unclear>&rdquo;</hi>!
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
