<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01764001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, December 16, 1879</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Reed, Walter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01764001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1879-12-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Heutig, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Annie, Miss</name>
<name type="person">Reed, James</name>
<name type="person">Blincoe, Laura Reed</name>
<name type="place">Arizona</name>
<name type="place">San Francisco (Calif.)</name>
<name type="place">Tucson (A.T.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1879-12-16">December 16, 1879</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01764001</idno>
<title>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, December 16, 1879</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed corrects Emilie Lawrence Reed's misapprehension about the date of his reassignment. He expects to return east by June 30.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1879-12-16">
<head>Letter from Walter Reed to Emilie Lawrence Reed, December 16, 1879</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01764001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Fort Apache, A.T.<lb/>
<date value="1879-12-16">December 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1879.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My own precious wifie;</salute>
</opener>
<p>We waited long<lb/>
and patiently, on Sunday last, for the arrival<lb/>
of the mail, but all our waiting was in vain.<lb/>
Of course, old mantee got quite out of humor<lb/>
at not receiving a letter from darling little<lb/>
lovie, especially as he had waited all day<lb/>
for it, just like a little man. And as it turned<lb/>
out, we had to endure the privation of<lb/>
news till Monday evening at sunset-(yesterday)<lb/>
This is written on Tuesday morning, &amp; a beau-<lb/>
tiful, bright, warm morning it is- But I've<lb/>
got just the least touch of a headache, due<lb/>
to the fact that I did not sleep well last<lb/>
night. And would precious wifie like to<lb/>
know why my sleep was disturbed and broken?<lb/>
Doesn't she already surmise? Ah! wifie<lb/>
dear, what had got into that sweet, little<lb/>
head of yours, when you wrote those <hi>two</hi><lb/>
last letters, dated 24 &amp; 29 November? Was<lb/>
my pretty wifie suffering from &ldquo;acidity<lb/>
of the stomach&rdquo; when she wrote them?<lb/>
What did old ugly mantee write in<lb/>
<del>your</del><add>his</add> last letter that should have set<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01764002"/>
that little brain to thinking so wildly &amp;<lb/>
that pretty tongue to wagging at such a<lb/>
rate? Who told you, precious wifie, that<lb/>
I wasn't coming East till next Fall? I cer-<lb/>
-tainly could not have written such a<lb/>
thing in any of my letters- If I remember<lb/>
correctly, you asked me if I could tell my<lb/>
pretty wifie about what time I would be<lb/>
ordered out of Arizona, and I, like a &ldquo;feetning&rdquo;<lb/>
little mantee, sat down and pumbled my head<lb/>
for half an hour or so, &amp; gave in writing the<lb/>
only ideas that I could deduce- I said, lovie,<lb/>
dear, (if I can recall my former statements<lb/>
to memory,) that, <hi>if</hi> my tour was reckoned from<lb/>
the date of my departure from the East, <hi>then</hi><lb/>
I would be relieved about <hi>May</hi> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>- But<lb/>
<hi>if</hi> it was reckoned from the date of my<lb/>
assignment to duty in Arizona, <hi>then</hi> my tour<lb/>
would expire <hi>June 21</hi><hi rend="superscript">st</hi>- And then I went<lb/>
on to tell my darling (and I didn't think that<lb/>
she would pounce upon this one date as<lb/>
a settled thing,) that <hi>if</hi> I was required to serve<lb/>
out my leaves, <hi>then</hi> I would not be relieved<lb/>
till <hi>Octr 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi>. Now, darling Nemps, how you<lb/>
have found out that I will not be or-<lb/>
-dered out till Octr 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>, I really don't<lb/>
know- Why, my little wifie, should have<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01764003"/>
skipped May and June &amp; pitched upon <hi>Octr</hi><lb/>
so <hi>savagely</hi>, I really don't know, unless it<lb/>
be that she wants to see her ugly old mantee<lb/>
so badly and is <hi>determined</hi> to look on the dark<lb/>
side of the picture! Of course, lovie, dear, you<lb/>
well know, that mantee is not mad with<lb/>
you or at all inclined to be angry or<lb/>
displeased, but he can't keep from feel-<lb/>
ing worried and anxious about his loving<lb/>
little wifie, when he reads such heart-<lb/>
-rending letters as your last two were-<lb/>
When he thinks that his darling wifie is<lb/>
happy and cheerful &amp; enjoying her stay East,<lb/>
then he too, feels bright &amp; gay; but when<lb/>
he reads <del>what</del> <add>that which</add> tells him that his poor<lb/>
little darling's very heart-strings are break-<lb/>
-ing and her life filled with gloom, why<lb/>
then his thoughts must partake of the melan-<lb/>
-cholic, too- Now, my own precious, Emilie,<lb/>
now that your unhappiness must have given<lb/>
way to more hopeful thoughts, lets you<lb/>
and mantee talk this matter over, like a<lb/>
sensible man and woman ought to do- And<lb/>
in the very first place, let me <hi>beseech</hi><lb/>
&amp; implore my darling not to be so <hi>rash</hi><lb/>
as to write to the Surgeon General about<lb/>
my stay in Arizona! <del><unclear></unclear></del> For he would not<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01764004"/>
tell you, &amp; besides, it might annoy him<lb/>
&amp; in order to satisfy his annoyance, he<lb/>
might keep me, even beyond my time, in<lb/>
Arizona- The tour is <hi>four</hi> years in this<lb/>
department- I've been informed of that<lb/>
fact, &amp; that is all that I can possibly ex-<lb/>
tract from any one- Any inquiries from<lb/>
you or myself, could only result in dam-<lb/>
-age to my prospects- I trust, loving lit-<lb/>
-tle wifie, that this brief allusion to that<lb/>
matter will check any intentions of yours<lb/>
of writing to the Surgeon General- <hi>The thing<lb/>
must not</hi> be done! Now, In the next place,<lb/>
my darling wifie, you must remember that<lb/>
the return of Mrs. Hentig, Mrs. Overton, &amp;<lb/>
other ladies to this Department is quite a<lb/>
different thing from <hi>your</hi> return- <hi>They</hi><lb/>
are <hi>compelled</hi> to return, or else remain<lb/>
absent from their husbands for the bal-<lb/>
-ance of their lives. <hi>Their</hi> husbands are<lb/>
stationed out in these territories <hi>all</hi><lb/>
their lives, whereas <hi>your's</hi>, after a defi-<lb/>
-nite tour here, is ordered East- The<lb/>
two cases are entirely dissimilar- Again,<lb/>
suppose, I say you can come back to Apa-<lb/>
che &amp; just for argument's sake- We will leave<lb/>
out of view the difficulty of transportation<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01764005"/>
<hi>Page 5</hi>) for the time being- It is now Decr<lb/>
16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; by the time this letter reaches you, it<lb/>
will be sometime in January 1880 -- very good-<lb/>
Now, to bring you back to Arizona, (&amp;<lb/>
there is only one route for you to take, and<lb/>
that is, by way of <hi>San Francisco</hi> and <hi>Tuson</hi>)<lb/>
would cost every dollar of <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>400, and to raise<lb/>
that amount, would require, at least Jan &amp;<lb/>
February pay- Very good, we will suppose<lb/>
that on the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of march you should start<lb/>
for Arizona, how long would it take you<lb/>
to reach apache? Certainly <hi>twenty days</hi>,<lb/>
my precious wifie, at the shortest reckon-<lb/>
ing. Well say you would reach here March<lb/>
20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Now suppose after all that money<lb/>
is spent, (and bear in mind, my darling wifie,<lb/>
that husband would not begrudge the<lb/>
money, even if it was <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>5,000!) suppose that<lb/>
I should be ordered out in <hi>May</hi>, only<lb/>
a month &amp; a half after you arrive,<lb/>
then, don't you perceive that we would<lb/>
have made a terrible mistake! All that<lb/>
trip, with its tediousness &amp; fatigue to<lb/>
you and Lawrence (&amp; you know, you couldn't<lb/>
bring a nurse with you,) would have<lb/>
been so much trouble for nothing! Is<lb/>
it not every word true, my darling wifie?<lb/>
Even suppose that I remained six months<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01764006"/>
longer, till Octr, would that short stay<lb/>
repay you, for all your trouble? And when<lb/>
we went East, what would we have to<lb/>
fix our home up sweetly with? I really<lb/>
didn't think you wanted to spend any<lb/>
more money on Arizona, my precious wife!<lb/>
Where would our <hi>crockery</hi> come from,<lb/>
my darling wife? Where would a cook come<lb/>
from? Surely, my precious wifie hasn't so<lb/>
soon forgotten how <hi>much</hi> trouble we had<lb/>
with cooks, and she knows that I would be<lb/>
distressed to death if she had to take upon<lb/>
her darling self, the same old drudgery!<lb/>
Has anything gone wrong in your rela-<lb/>
tions with any of your family to cause<lb/>
any unpleasantness? I certainly think not.<lb/>
Surely, no one is trying to treat you slight-<lb/>
-ingly, my darling! Your visit must be<lb/>
pleasant to your sister Annie, aint it?<lb/>
You surely haven't quarrelled? I know<lb/>
that it is very foolish in me to write in<lb/>
such a style, as there is not a shade of<lb/>
a possibility. I know, that you are not<lb/>
having the most pleasant time at your<lb/>
Sister's- Certainly Lawrence's row's with<lb/>
little May are not going to drive my<lb/>
darling wifie back to Arizona-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f01764007"/>
Get a nice, supple <hi>quince</hi> switch (Mr. Gate-<lb/>
wood, who has just entered &amp; is lying flat<lb/>
on his back on my bed, suggested the <hi>quince</hi><lb/>
switch, as he says that he knows, <hi>from ex-<lb/>
perience</hi>, that there is no <hi>article</hi> superior<lb/>
to the <hi>quince</hi> for tickling &ldquo;kidlings&rdquo;,) and &ldquo;inter-<lb/>
-view&rdquo; his little &ldquo;shanks&rdquo; out in the woodshed.<lb/>
But seriously, my darling wife, don't let your<lb/>
life be worried by thoughts of returning<lb/>
to Arizona- I know no good reason why<lb/>
you should <add>not</add> expect me by June 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, at<lb/>
the outside- Just make up your mind<lb/>
like a sensible wifie, that I am coming<lb/>
home by June and <hi>fix your thoughts on<lb/>
that time</hi>- It is more than likely that I<lb/>
will come east then- When that time shall<lb/>
have arrived, &amp; I do not come, <hi>then</hi> &amp; <hi>not<lb/>
till then</hi>, will it be time for you to begin<lb/>
to trouble your darling self about it.<lb/>
Indeed, my precious wife, there is no ex-<lb/>
-cuse for your <hi>borrowing</hi> trouble in<lb/>
this way. It will only make your life<lb/>
wretched and you are going on a false<lb/>
assumption about my stay in Arizona,<lb/>
Do pray, lovie, I beseech you, by all<lb/>
the love you bear toward your poor<lb/>
ugly old mantee, don't conjure up fright-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f01764008"/>
-ful visions of my staying forever out<lb/>
here, and then frighten all the life out of<lb/>
your young heart by these phantoms<lb/>
of your own uneasy mind! Come, pre-<lb/>
-cious wifie, <hi>that</hi> will never do! You will<lb/>
only render both yourself &amp; your mantee<lb/>
miserable, &amp; all to no purpose- It will <add>be</add><lb/>
better, cheaper, less troublesome, more pleas-<lb/>
-ant and more sensible for my darling to<lb/>
stay east, than to come to Arizona, &amp; then<lb/>
have to return in June- After you have<lb/>
spent Jan &amp; Feb. with Sister A., go to see<lb/>
brother Jimmie &amp; Sister Laurie- They would<lb/>
both be more than delighted to see my<lb/>
sweet wife &amp; boy- Husband wishes to<lb/>
see his darlings just as badly as they<lb/>
wish to see him, but he has made up<lb/>
his mind to wait patiently &amp; trust in<lb/>
the Lord -- and he knows his Emily wifie will<lb/>
do the same- She is too sweet &amp; loving &amp;<lb/>
brave to write in so melancholic a strain.<lb/>
Mrs Hentig is longing to get away from<lb/>
Apache, &amp; says she would give anything to<lb/>
be able to get away- The mail leaves to-<lb/>
morrow morning &amp; I have several other letters<lb/>
to write -- so precious wifie <hi>must excuse</hi> this<lb/>
short note- Very best love to all- Write often<lb/>
and think of me always as your fond husband,<lb/>
who loves you <hi>more</hi> &amp; <hi>more</hi> every day,</p>
<closer>
<signed>Walter</signed>-
<seg>
P.S. Kisses<lb/>
&amp; love for<lb/>
Mama &amp;<lb/>
Laurie-<lb/>
W.-
</seg>
<seg>
P.S. Please tell<lb/>
me the <hi>No</hi>. &amp;<lb/>
<hi>Street</hi> of your<lb/>
<hi>new</hi> Home,<lb/>
or I will write<lb/>
Care Vaughan,<lb/>
Barnes &amp; Co.<lb/>
W.
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
