<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01801001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Essay by William H. Welch concerning Walter Reed's work at Johns Hopkins University, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01801001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Pasteur, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Koch, Robert</name>
<name type="person">Behring, Emil von</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01801001</idno>
<title>Essay by William H. Welch concerning Walter Reed's work at Johns Hopkins University, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Welch extensively describes Reed's work at Johns Hopkins.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Essay by William H. Welch concerning Walter Reed's work at Johns Hopkins University, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01801001"/>
<opener>
FROM DR.HOWARD A. KELLY
</opener>
<p><hi>Dr. Welch</hi> has supplied me with the following account of<lb/>
Dr. Reed's work at the Johns Hopkins Hospital and<lb/>
University.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dr. Reed was sent to Baltimore in October 1890 as<lb/>
Attending Surgeon and Examiner of Recruits and he<lb/>
remained there until the following October. He<lb/>
was granted permission by the Surgeon General of<lb/>
the Army to undertake professional studies at<lb/>
the Johns Hopkins Hospital, but the Surgeon<lb/>
General did not <del>wish him</del><add>encourage</add> him to take lab-<lb/>
oratory courses. [insert figure here] The Medical Department of<lb/>
the Johns Hopkins University was not opened<lb/>
until October 1893, but the Hospital was in<lb/>
full operation in 1889 and the Pathological Labor-<lb/>
atory of the Hospital and <add>the</add> University had<lb/>
been equipped and opened for the reception<lb/>
of <del>students</del> physicians and advanced students<lb/>
and for research since 1885. Here systematic<lb/>
laboratory courses were given in pathology and<lb/>
bacteriology, and it was here that Dr. Reed<lb/>
received his fundamental training in these<lb/>
subjects.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed began his work on the clinical<lb/>
side of the Hospital, but after a few weeks,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01801002"/>
a new Surgen-General having in the meantime been appointed, he was<lb/>
enabled to follow his own inclination and to enter the regular<lb/>
courses in pathology and bacteriology in the Pathological Labor-<lb/>
atory. I well recall with what eagerness and enthusiasm he<lb/>
turned his attention to the new fields of scientific medicine,<lb/>
thus first opened to him, which from that time until the<lb/>
end of his life became the centre of his professional inter-<lb/>
est and activity and which he himself was destined to<lb/>
cultivate with such signal benefits to medical science<lb/>
and to the welfare of mankind.</p>
<p>The decade preceding the time when Dr. Reed began<lb/>
his practical studies in the Laboratory had been a<lb/>
period of marvellous progress in our knowledge of<lb/>
infectious diseases. Upon the basis of the discoveries<lb/>
of Pasteur and of Koch, and particularly as a result<lb/>
of the new methods introduced by Koch for the<lb/>
cultivation and study of bacteria, there had followed<lb/>
in rapid succession <add>within this period</add> such important discoveries<lb/>
as those of the specific germs causing tuberculosis,<lb/>
cholera, leprosy, glanders, erysipelas, surgical infec-<lb/>
tions, tetanus, pneumonia, typhoid fever, malaria,<lb/>
amoebic dysentery, cerebro-spinal meningitis, diphtheria,<lb/>
and a large number of animal diseases. Pasteur<lb/>
had discovered methods of rendering animals artificially<lb/>
immune from chicken cholera, <del>and from</del> anthrax <add>and other diseases,</add> and<lb/>
had devised his method of protective inoculation<lb/>
against rabies which has been the means of saving<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01801003"/>
many human lives. A great impetus was given by these<lb/>
discoveries to the establishment of hygienic and other<lb/>
laboratories where the new science of bacteriology<lb/>
was actively cultivated. Medicine both as a science and<lb/>
an art had entered upon a new era already rich in<lb/>
achievement and still richer in promise of future good.</p>
<p>While Dr. Reed took the regular courses in pathology<lb/>
given in the Laboratory and was interested in the subject,<lb/>
his special interest was in bacteriology which is in-<lb/>
cluded in the Department of Pathology. In the con-<lb/>
duct of these courses there were associated with me<lb/>
at that time Drs. Councilman, Abbott, Nuttall and<lb/>
Flexner and among <del>those</del><add>others</add> then engaged in research<lb/>
work in the Laboratory I call to mind Drs. Halsted,<lb/>
Lafleur, H. M. Thomas, Berkeley, W. T. Howard, Jr., Bar-<lb/>
ker, Robb, Ghriskey, Randolph, Clement, Blackstein,<lb/>
Gilchrist and Thayer.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed soon made a place for himself in<lb/>
this intimate group of active worker. <del>It was</del><add>We</add><lb/>
<del>soon</del><add>early</add> recognized that he possessed unusual apti-<lb/>
tude for the work which he had undertaken, and<lb/>
that he combined with excellent natural endowments<lb/>
of mind a sincere, manly and winning person-<lb/>
ality. The friendships formed with his teachers<lb/>
and co-workers at this period were strong and<lb/>
enduring.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01801004"/>
Dr. Reed applied himself with great energy to his work in<lb/>
the Laboratory, devoting to it daily a large part of his<lb/>
time and carrying it much beyond the regular<lb/>
class exercises. After he had acquired familiarity<lb/>
with technical methods he undertook advanced and<lb/>
independent work. He attended post-mortem exam-<lb/>
inations and sometimes conducted these, and was<lb/>
accustomed to study for himself pathological ma-<lb/>
terial and cultures which he had obtained from<lb/>
autopsies. He followed and profited by the<lb/>
various investigations which were at the time in<lb/>
progress in the Laboratory and the Hospital, and<lb/>
he was a regular attendant at the Hospital<lb/>
Medical Societies. Drs. Abbott, <add>Flexner</add> and I were at that<lb/>
time <del>particularly</del> engaged in the study of diphtheria,<lb/>
the toxin of which had been discovered two years<lb/>
previously, and the antitoxin of which was discov-<lb/>
ered by Behring in 1890. The investigations of<lb/>
hog cholera at this time by Dr. Clement and myself<lb/>
enabled Dr. Reed to become familiar with the<lb/>
hog cholera bacillus, so that he later had no<lb/>
difficulty in recognizing the resemblance <add>to this bacillus</add> of<lb/>
the <del>bacillus</del><add>microorganism</add> claimed erroneously by Sanarelli<lb/>
to be the cause of yellow fever. <del>with</del> He also<lb/>
followed with great interest the studies of Drs.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01801005"/>
Councilman and La fleur on amoebic dysentery, as<lb/>
well as investigations in the Hospital on the malarial<lb/>
parasite.</p>
<p>During the latter part of his stay in Baltimore<lb/>
Dr. Reed was assigned at his request a special<lb/>
subject for research. This was the microscopical<lb/>
and experimental study of the so-called lymphoid<lb/>
nodules which are found in the liver in cases of<lb/>
typhoid fever. He succeeded in producing these nodules<lb/>
experimentally and demonstrated that they originate<lb/>
as small foci of dead liver cells. His paper upon<lb/>
this subject published in the Reports of the Johns<lb/>
Hopkins Hospital is a valuable contribution, and<lb/>
it embodies the results of his first original<lb/>
scientific investigation.</p>
<p>When Dr. Reed left Baltimore in October 1891<lb/>
he was well trained in pathological and bacteri-<lb/>
ological methods, he had acquired a considera-<lb/>
ble amount of experience, and he was thor-<lb/>
oughly fitted to make the best use of <add>such</add> opportunities<lb/>
<del>which</del> as might present themselves to add to this<lb/>
experience <add>and training</add> and to undertake original investiga-<lb/>
tions. This was apparent to us at the time<lb/>
and was <del>suff</del> fully demonstrated by his <add>subsequent</add> career.</p>
<p>When Dr. Reed was assigned to duty in 1893 as<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01801006"/>
Curator of the Army Medical Museum and Profes-<lb/>
sor of Bacteriology and Clinical Microscopy in the<lb/>
Army Medical School he at once reestablished<lb/>
relations with the Pathological Laboratory in Balti-<lb/>
more. He was a frequent visitor, together with his assoc-<lb/>
iate Dr. Carroll, at the Laboratory and he kept in<lb/>
touch with the men and the work there. <add>He often came to the Hospital Medical Society at which he occasionally made contributions.</add> I was often<lb/>
consulted by him regarding his own <del>work and</del> investigations,<lb/>
and his relations were likewise <del>pa</del> very intimate and<lb/>
cordial with Drs. Flexner, Abbott and Thayer. He<lb/>
talked over with me the plan of the yellow fever work<lb/>
to be undertaken by the Commission of which he was<lb/>
the head, and he kept me informed by letter <add>and by conversation</add> of the<lb/>
results of this work while it was in progress. It<lb/>
is one of the greatest satisfactions and pleasures of<lb/>
my life to have enjoyed the relations of teacher<lb/>
and of friend with a man <del>whose</del> who has left a<lb/>
memory so respected and beloved <del>as Dr. Reed</del> and<lb/>
who has conferred such inestimable benefits upon<lb/>
his country and all mankind &ldquo;As has Dr. Reed&rdquo;.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
