<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t01811001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report: A Pr&eacute;cis of the United States Quarantine Regulations for Domestic Ports with Reference to Preventing the Introduction of Yellow Fever into the United States, by Preston H. Bailhache, [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Bailhache, Preston H.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01811001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="0000-00-00"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">01811001</idno>
<title>Report: A Pr&eacute;cis of the United States Quarantine Regulations for Domestic Ports with Reference to Preventing the Introduction of Yellow Fever into the United States, by Preston H. Bailhache, [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>These regulations describe the inspection, quarantine, and disinfection procedures to be implemented at ports to prevent the introduction of yellow fever into the United States. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="0000-00-00">
<head>Report: A Pr&eacute;cis of the United States Quarantine Regulations for Domestic Ports with Reference to Preventing the Introduction of Yellow Fever into the United States, by Preston H. Bailhache, [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01811001"/>
<p>A PR&Eacute;CIS OF THE UNITED STATES QUARANTINE REGULATIONS<lb/>
FOR DOMESTIC PORTS WITH REFERENCE TO PREVENTING THE<lb/>
INTRODUCTION OF YELLOW FEVER INTO THE UNITED STATES.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>By Surg. PRESTON H. BAILHACHE.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>As yellow fever is not an endemic disease of this country, regula-<lb/>
tions for the prevention of its introduction from abroad have been<lb/>
prepared by the Surgeon-General of the Marine-Hospital Service,<lb/>
under the direction of the Secretary of the Treasury, and promulgated<lb/>
by the Department under date of April 26, 1894.</p>
<p>PRIMARY MEASURES.</p>
<p>The primary measure to be adopted to prevent the introduction of<lb/>
this disease into the United States is the establishment at the principal<lb/>
ports of the country of completely equipped quarantine stations for<lb/>
the inspection and treatment of vessels, their passengers, crews, and<lb/>
cargoes. At smaller stations, where it is impracticable to fully equip<lb/>
and maintain a complete establishment, provision should be made for<lb/>
the inspection of such vessels, and these inspections should be main-<lb/>
tained at every port throughout the year.</p>
<p>PERSONNEL SHOULD BE IMMUNE.</p>
<p>The personnel of Southern quarantine stations should be immune<lb/>
to yellow fever, and all articles liable to convey infection should be<lb/>
handled only by the employees of said station, if practicable.</p>
<p>INSPECTION.</p>
<p>Vessels arriving at ports of the United States under the following<lb/>
conditions shall be inspected by a quarantine officer prior to entry:</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<item>A. Any vessel with sickness on board.</item>
<item>B. All vessels from foreign ports.</item>
<item>C. Vessels from domestic ports where yellow fever prevails.</item>
<item>D. Vessels from foreign ports carrying passengers having entered a<lb/>
port of the United States without complete discharge of passengers<lb/>
and cargo. Such vessels shall be subject to a second inspection before<lb/>
415<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01811002"/>
416<lb/>
MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.<lb/>
entering any other port. Vessels from ports suspected of infection with<lb/>
yellow fever, having entered a port north of the southern boundary of<lb/>
Maryland without disinfection, shall be subjected to a second inspec-<lb/>
tion before entering any port south of said latitude during the quaran-<lb/>
tine season of such port.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The inspections of vessels shall be made by daylight, except in case<lb/>
of vessels in distress.</p>
<p>In making the inspection of a vessel, the bill of health and clinical<lb/>
record of all cases treated during the voyage, crew and passengers'<lb/>
lists and manifests, and, when necessary, the ship's log shall be exam-<lb/>
ined. The crew and passengers shall be mustered and examined and<lb/>
compared with the lists and manifests and any discrepancies investi-<lb/>
gated.</p>
<p>No person except the quarantine officer, his employees, United States<lb/>
customs officers, or agents of the vessel, shall be permitted to board<lb/>
any vessel subject to quarantine inspection, until after the vessel has<lb/>
been inspected by the quarantine officer and given its discharge.</p>
<p>VESSELS SUBJECT TO QUARANTINE MEASURES.</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<item>A. Vessels arriving with yellow fever on board.</item>
<item>B. Having had such on board during the voyage or within thirty<lb/>
days next preceding arrival, or, if arriving in the quarantine season,<lb/>
having had yellow fever on board after March 1 of the current year,<lb/>
unless satisfactorily disinfected thereafter.</item>
<item>C. Vessels from noninfected ports, but bringing persons or cargo<lb/>
from places infected with yellow fever.</item>
<item>D. From ports where yellow fever prevails, unless disinfected in<lb/>
accordance with these regulations, and not less than five days have<lb/>
elapsed since such disinfection.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Exceptions to C and D</hi>.--Vessels arriving during certain seasons of the year, to<lb/>
wit, from November 1 to April 1, may be admitted to entry.</p>
<p>Vessels bound for ports in the United States <hi rend="italic">north of the southern boundary of Mary-<lb/>
land</hi>, with good sanitary condition and history, having had no sickness on board at<lb/>
ports of departure, en route, or on arrival, provided they have been five days from<lb/>
last infected or suspected port, may be allowed entry at port of destination. But if<lb/>
said vessels carry passengers destined for places south of this latitude the baggage<lb/>
of said passengers shall be disinfected.</p>
<p>In making an inspection of a vessel, if from a port where yellow fever prevails,<lb/>
and between April 1 and November 1 of any year, the inspector shall ascertain the<lb/>
destination of each passenger thereon, and if bound for places south of the southern<lb/>
boundary of Maryland, the baggage of such passenger shall be disinfected accord-<lb/>
ing to the rules for such articles infected with yellow fever. Such baggage shall be<lb/>
labeled.</p>
<p>Vessels engaged in the fruit trade from ports declared safe for this purpose by the<lb/>
Supervising Surgeon-General Marine-Hospital Service, may be admitted to entry<lb/>
without detention, provided that they carry no passengers and have carried no<lb/>
passengers from one port to another, and have no household effects or personal<lb/>
baggage in cargo, and have complied with the special rules and regulations made by<lb/>
the Secretary of the Treasury with regard to vessels engaged in said trade.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01811003"/>
<p>MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.<lb/>
417</p>
<p>PASSENGER TRAFFIC.</p>
<p>Passenger traffic may be allowed during the quarantine season from any port<lb/>
infected with yellow fever to any port of the United States south of the southern<lb/>
boundary of Maryland under the following conditions:</p>
<p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Vessels to be of iron, and clean immediately prior to taking on passengers.</p>
<p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The vessel must lie at moorings in the open harbor and not approach the<lb/>
wharves, nor must the crew be allowed ashore at the port of departure.</p>
<p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) All passengers and crew must be immune to yellow fever, and so certified by<lb/>
the United States medical officer.</p>
<p>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) All baggage which has not been disinfected at the port of departure by the<lb/>
United States medical officer, or which is not in bond for points north of the south-<lb/>
ern boundary of Maryland, shall be disinfected at the quarantine at the port of<lb/>
arrival; no bedding or household effects to be allowed to enter.</p>
<p>GENERAL REQUIREMENTS AT QUARANTINES.</p>
<p>Pilots bringing infected vessels will be detained in quarantine a suffi-<lb/>
cient time to cover the period of incubation of the disease for which<lb/>
the vessel is quarantined if, in the opinion of the quarantine officer,<lb/>
such pilots have been exposed to infection. The dunnage of pilots<lb/>
shall be disinfected when necessary.</p>
<p>No direct communication shall be allowed between quarantine, or any<lb/>
vessel in quarantine, with any person or place outside, and no indirect<lb/>
communication except under the supervision of the quarantine officer.</p>
<p>No ballast shall be allowed to leave the quarantine station unless<lb/>
disinfected.</p>
<p>Where it is impossible to disinfect cargo in situ, it shall be removed<lb/>
and disinfected in the manner provided for articles of their class in<lb/>
these regulations; such articles to be unpacked and so arranged as to<lb/>
allow the disinfectant used to reach every part of all surfaces of said<lb/>
articles.</p>
<p>Vessels arriving at any port of the United States, having yellow<lb/>
fever aboard during the quarantine season, shall be remanded to an<lb/>
anchorage set apart for infected vessels, and there to remain until after<lb/>
the discharge of the passengers and purification of the vessel.</p>
<p>All passenger baggage disinfected under the requirements of these<lb/>
regulations shall be labeled.</p>
<p>Vessels detained at any national quarantine will be subject to such<lb/>
additional rules and regulations as may be promulgated from time to<lb/>
time by the Supervising Surgeon-General.</p>
<p>The following is the form of certificate which shall be issued to the<lb/>
vessel by the health officer when she is released from quarantine:</p>
<p>-----,--------, <hi rend="italic">189</hi>------.</p>
<p>I certify that ----------, of ----------, from ----------, has in all respects complied with the<lb/>
quarantine regulations prescribed by the Secretary of the Treasury, and that in my</p>
<p>---------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>* The evidence of immunity which may be accepted by the sanitary inspector is:</p>
<p>First. Proof of continued residence in an endemic focus of yellow fever for ten<lb/>
years.</p>
<p>Second. Proof of previous attack of yellow fever.</p>
<p>10918-----27</p>
<pb n="4" id="f01811004"/>
<p>418<lb/>
MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.</p>
<p>opinion she will not convey quarantinable disease. Said vessel is this day granted<lb/>
free pratique.</p>
<p>---------- ----------,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Health (Quarantine) Officer</hi>,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Port of</hi> ----------.</p>
<p>SPECIAL REGULATIONS RELATING TO NAVAL VESSELS.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. At domestic ports such communication may be allowed with ves-<lb/>
sels of the United States Navy as the certificate of the medical officer<lb/>
of said vessel shows will not be liable to convey infection.</item>
<item>2. The certificates of the medical officers of the United States Navy<lb/>
that the United States quarantine regulations have been complied<lb/>
with may be accepted for naval vessels.</item>
<item>3. Vessels of the United States Navy, having entered the harbors<lb/>
of ports infected with yellow fever, and having held no communication<lb/>
which is liable to convey infection to the vessel or her crew, may be<lb/>
exempted from the quarantine restrictions imposed on merchant vessels<lb/>
from such ports.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>TREATMENT OF VESSELS INFECTED OR SUSPECTED OF BEING<lb/>
INFECTED WITH YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>Where practicable, at once remove the sick to hospital; remove and<lb/>
isolate all persons not required for the care of the vessel.</p>
<p>If the hold is deemed infected, there shall be a preliminary disinfec-<lb/>
tion as hereinafter provided.</p>
<p>The bilge should be cleansed with sea water, if possible, before disin-<lb/>
fection, and the hold rendered mechanically clean.</p>
<p>All ballast except close grained hard rock must be discharged. This<lb/>
may be retained aboard if disinfected by immersion in an acid solution<lb/>
of bichloride of mercury, 1 to 800.</p>
<p>After discharge or disinfection of ballast the vessel should be disin-<lb/>
fected.</p>
<p>If it is so stowed as to admit of disinfection, the cargo and the hold<lb/>
may be disinfected without breaking bulk, except to such a degree as to<lb/>
render disinfection practicable.</p>
<p>The personnel of the vessel shall be detained five days from comple-<lb/>
tion of the disinfection, or three days if all baggage, etc., is handled<lb/>
exclusively by quarantine employees.</p>
<p>If the vessel has been disinfected under the supervision of an accred-<lb/>
ited medical officer of the United States at the port of departure, the<lb/>
period of quarantine may date from completion of such dininfection,<lb/>
and shall not be less than five days.</p>
<p>The following regulations are provided for the disinfection of a vessel<lb/>
infected or suspected of being infected with yellow fever:</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01811005"/>
<p>MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.<lb/>
419</p>
<p>DISINFECTION BY SULPHUR DIOXIDE.</p>
<p>Holds to be treated with sulphur dioxide, 10 per cent strength per<lb/>
volume, forty-eight hours' exposure for iron vessels, and seventy-two<lb/>
hours' for wooden vessels.</p>
<p>Empty holds to be disinfected as follows:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) If of iron, by sulphur dioxide gas, 10 per cent strength per vol-<lb/>
ume, for twelve hours' exposure, followed by washing with an acid solu-<lb/>
tion of bichloride of mercury, 1 to 800, applied under pressure to all<lb/>
surfaces by means of a hose.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) If of wood, by the same methods as the preceding, save that the<lb/>
exposure to sulphur dioxid gas shall be for forty-eight hours; air<lb/>
streaks to be open.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Cabin, forecastle, etc., after mechanical cleaning, to be first treated<lb/>
with sulphur dioxid, not less than 6 per cent strength per volume,<lb/>
twenty-four hours' exposure. Then, after cleansing with water if<lb/>
desired, wash all exposed surfaces with a solution of bichlorid of<lb/>
mercury, 1 to 800, or pure carbolic acid, 3 per cent.</p>
<p>DISINFECTION BY STEAM.</p>
<p>Clothing, bedding, and all fabrics which can be removed, not injured<lb/>
by steam, shall be disinfected:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) By exposure to steam at a temperature of 100&deg; to 102&deg; C. for<lb/>
thirty minutes after such temperature has been reached.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) By boiling for fifteen minutes; all articles to be submerged.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) By a thorough saturation in a solution of bichlorid of mercury,<lb/>
1 to 1,000, and allowed to dry before washing.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Articles injured by steam (rubber, leather, etc.), and containers, to<lb/>
the disinfection of which steam is inapplicable, shall be disinfected by<lb/>
(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) thoroughly wetting all surfaces with a solution of bichlorid of mer-<lb/>
cury, 1 to 800, or a 5 per cent solution of pure carbolic acid, and allowed<lb/>
to dry in open air; or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) by exposure to the sulphur fumigation in<lb/>
cabin, forecastle, or hold.</p>
<p>DISINFECTION BY FORMALDEHYD GAS.</p>
<p>Since the introduction of formaldehyd gas as a disinfector, additional<lb/>
regulations were promulgated August 5, 1897, as follows:</p>
<p>DISINFECTION OF STEERAGE, FORECASTLE, AND CABIN OF VESSELS.</p>
<p>After the removal of the bedding, carpets, and furnishings, all aper-<lb/>
tures being tightly closed, the steerage, forecastle, and cabin of a ves-<lb/>
sel may be disinfected by formaldehyd gas in a percentage of not less<lb/>
than 2 per cent per volume strength, the time of exposure to be not less<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f01811006"/>
420<lb/>
MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.<lb/>
than twelve hours. The gas may be generated by one of the following<lb/>
methods:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) From methyl (wood) alcohol by means of special lamps, using not<lb/>
less than 600 grams (750 cubic centimeters=1&frac45; pints) of methyl alcohol<lb/>
for each 25.5 cubic meters (1,000 cubic feet) of space, the time of expos-<lb/>
ure to be not less than twelve hours.<lb/>
Lamps used for generating formaldehyd gas from methyl alcohol<lb/>
should change not less than 1 liter (1.01 quarts) of the alcohol within<lb/>
an hour.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) From an aqueous solution, containing 40 per cent of the gas,<lb/>
known under the names of formalin, formol, or formalose. The gas is<lb/>
best evolved from these solutions by the addition of from 10 to 30 per<lb/>
cent of a neutral salt, preferably calcium chloride or sodium nitrate,<lb/>
and heating the mixture in a special boiler. One liter of a 40 per cent<lb/>
solution of formaldehyd gas will evolve about 1,425 liters (50.1 cubic<lb/>
feet) of the gas at 20&deg; C. (68&deg; F.), and will be sufficient for 71 cubic<lb/>
meters (2,505.5 cubic feet) of space.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) From the substance known as trioxymethylene, by means of a<lb/>
special lamp, not less than 2 grams (30 grains) to be used for each<lb/>
cubic meter (35.29 cubic feet) of space.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>After the disinfection of apartments (steerage, cabin, and forecastle)<lb/>
by formaldehyd gas, the latter should be neutralized by ammonia gas<lb/>
evolved from water of ammonia by heat or by evaporation from water<lb/>
of ammonia sprinkled upon the floor.</p>
<p>NOTE.--The quantity of water of ammonia required for neutralization after each<lb/>
of the above-named methods is as follows: After method (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), 1 liter (1.01 quarts) of<lb/>
water of ammonia for each 1,000 cubic centimeters (1.01 quarts) of wood alcohol<lb/>
used; after method (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), 1&frac14; liters (1.26 quarts) of water of ammonia for each liter<lb/>
(1.01 quarts) of formalin; after method (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>), 1 liter of water of ammonia for each 150<lb/>
grams (5 ounces) of trioxymethylene.</p>
<p>DISINFECTION OF CLOTHING, BEDDING, UPHOLSTERED FURNITURE, ARTICLES OF<lb/>
LEATHER, ETC.</p>
<p>These may be disinfected by formaldehyd gas in the ordinary steam<lb/>
disinfecting chamber, the latter to be provided with a vacuum appa-<lb/>
ratus and special apparatus for generating and applying the gas. The<lb/>
gas should be applied in a dry state in not less than 20 per cent per<lb/>
volume strength, the time of exposure to be not less than one hour.<lb/>
Clothing bedding, etc., thus disinfected should be exposed in situ to an<lb/>
equal amount of ammonia gas generated by the special apparatus<lb/>
attached to the chamber, using 1 liter of water of ammonia to each liter<lb/>
of formalin; or compressed ammonia gas may be used.</p>
<p>NOTE.--The special apparatus must consist of a generator, constructed of copper,<lb/>
for evolving formaldehyd gas from its solutions, and a similar one of iron for evolv-<lb/>
ing ammonia gas for neutralization. The principle upon which this apparatus is<lb/>
constructed is described and illustrated in Public Health Reports, Marine-Hospital<lb/>
Service, January 29, 1897, Vol. XII, No. 5.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
