<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t01812001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report: Therapeutic Treatment of Yellow Fever, by Henry Downes Geddings, 1894</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Geddings, Henry Downes</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01812001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1894-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1894-00-00">1894</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01812001</idno>
<title>Report: Therapeutic Treatment of Yellow Fever, by Henry Downes Geddings, 1894</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Geddings' discussion of the treatment of yellow fever includes baths, purgatives, coal-tar products, cocaine, carbonated beverages, perchloride of iron, ice, counter-irritation, tisane of orange leaves, enemas, and quinine. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1894-00-00">
<head>Report: Therapeutic Treatment of Yellow Fever, by Henry Downes Geddings, 1894</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01812001"/>
<p>THERAPEUTIC TREATMENT OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>By P. A. Surg. H. D. GEDDINGS.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>[From Annual Report of Marine-Hospital Service, 1894.]</p>
<p>In discussing the therapeutic treatment of yellow fever,<lb/>
it is not proposed, indeed it is impossible, to here present<lb/>
any long array of cases, with records of temperature and<lb/>
pulse and detailed symptoms of each particular case. It<lb/>
shall be my endeavor to present nothing that has not been<lb/>
of real value in the hands of my colleagues or myself, and<lb/>
anyone taking the trouble to read this and not finding any<lb/>
particular line of treatment laid down will please bear in<lb/>
mind that this is a record, not of what might have been,<lb/>
but of what has been, done. The writer believes that the<lb/>
treatment of yellow fever, like that of other acute specific<lb/>
febrile diseases, should be symptomatic and directed<lb/>
toward meeting plain and specific indications. The symp-<lb/>
toms may be divided, for convenience, into those (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)<lb/>
belonging to the onset of the disease and those (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) which<lb/>
arise during the course of the illness.</p>
<p>TREATMENT OF INITIAL STAGE.</p>
<p>Under the first head may be included the chill and sub-<lb/>
sequent fever, the distressing headache and pain in the<lb/>
back, loins, and limbs. For the relief of these, as well as<lb/>
for properly initiating a systematic treatment, it is believed<lb/>
that the old plan of administering a hot footbath contain-<lb/>
ing mustard is an eminently proper one. The bath hastens<lb/>
reaction from the chill, markedly relieves the headache<lb/>
and pains in the back and legs, promotes diaphoresis, in<lb/>
this way accomplishing good, and being perfectly incapa-<lb/>
ble of doing any harm. The patient, being then restored<lb/>
to bed, should be covered warmly but not too heavily, and<lb/>
gradually uncovered as diaphoresis proceeds, in order that<lb/>
too great prostration should not ensue. Care of course<lb/>
313<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01812002"/>
314<lb/>
MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.<lb/>
should be exercised to prevent sudden chilling of the sur-<lb/>
face. As soon as the patient is made comfortable in bed<lb/>
the remedial treatment should be begun. At this stage<lb/>
this should consist of a sharp purge, preferably mercurial.<lb/>
I have found calomel 0.33 grams, compound powder jalap<lb/>
0.66 grams, administered in capsules, most efficient. Others<lb/>
prefer the compound cathartic pills (U. S. P.), of which one,<lb/>
two, or three may be administered, according to the age<lb/>
and general condition of the patient. Should either of<lb/>
these remedies fail to move the bowels freely within six<lb/>
or eight hours it may be followed by a moderate dose of<lb/>
castor oil, a seidlitz powder, or a bottle of citrate of<lb/>
magnesia.</p>
<p>TREATMENT OF FEBRILE AND NERVOUS CONDITIONS.</p>
<p>Closely following the first purgative should be adminis-<lb/>
tered one of the coal-tar febrifuges, phenacetin 0.50 grams,<lb/>
or antipyrin or antifebrin 0.66 grams, either of which may<lb/>
with advantage be combined with 0.12 grams to 0.18 grams of<lb/>
citrate of caffeine. It will be well to discuss here the effect<lb/>
of the coal-tar series of febrifuges in yellow fever. Possess-<lb/>
ing as they do analgesic properties of the highest order,<lb/>
being second in this respect only to preparations of opium,<lb/>
in addition to their well-known power of reducing tempera-<lb/>
tures, they fill a most important place in the treatment of<lb/>
yellow fever. By their use in moderate doses at the incep-<lb/>
tion of the attack we relieve headache and the racking<lb/>
pain in back and limbs, diminish restlessness, and reduce<lb/>
temperature within twelve hours to a point, not nor-<lb/>
mal, but considerably below that at which it stood when<lb/>
reaction from the chill had fully taken place. Indeed, it<lb/>
has seemed to me that the action of the first dose of the<lb/>
antipyretic furnished, in some sort, an index of the course<lb/>
of the particular case under observation. Given a case in<lb/>
which after the administration of the antipyretic the patient<lb/>
passes into an easy sleep and wakes with diminished head-<lb/>
ache and other pains, a moist skin, and a reduced temper-<lb/>
ture, I feel encouraged to hope, though I do not say that<lb/>
the case will be mild or of moderate severity and will end<lb/>
in recovery. Given, on the contrary, a case in which the<lb/>
antipyretic produces but slight influence on the tempera-<lb/>
ture, where restlessness is not diminished or controlled,<lb/>
where pain persists, and the skin, though moist, has a<lb/>
burning, pungent feeling, I fear the worst and expect trouble<lb/>
to the very end. Repeated doses of the antipyretic are not<lb/>
needed, or indeed indicated. It is my belief that one, two,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01812003"/>
MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.<lb/>
315<lb/>
or at most three, doses in the first twenty-four hours of<lb/>
the disease will accomplish all that is to be gained from<lb/>
this series of remedies. Administered later in the disease,<lb/>
they exercise too depressing an effect on a heart already<lb/>
weakened as a consequence of a tox&aelig;mia more or less<lb/>
profound.</p>
<p>TREATMENT OF GASTRIC SYMPTOMS.</p>
<p>The gastric irritability, which is often extreme at the<lb/>
onset of an attack of yellow fever, may be controlled by<lb/>
sinapisms to the epigastrium, abstention from fluids, and<lb/>
frequent ingestion of small pieces of ice, which not only<lb/>
allay thirst, but also tend in themselves to relieve nausea.<lb/>
Should nausea or vomiting persist, the administration of<lb/>
cocaine hydrochlorate, in doses of 0.015 gram to 0.030<lb/>
gram every hour or two, will often act almost magically.<lb/>
Small quantities of carbonated beverages, as vichy, seltzer,<lb/>
or appollinaris water, ginger ale, or very dry champagne,<lb/>
administered ice cold, will often prove of service. Creosote<lb/>
has also been highly recommended, and also a mixture con-<lb/>
taining hydrocyanic acid and morphia. Considerable relief<lb/>
is also derived from the application to the epigastrium of<lb/>
a liniment composed of olive oil and menthol.</p>
<p>IMPORTANCE OF RENAL SYMPTOMS.</p>
<p>On the afternoon of the second or morning of the third<lb/>
day the presence of albumen in the urine may be noted,<lb/>
unless the case be of the most ephemeral mildness. I believe<lb/>
that no case of yellow fever can occur without presenting<lb/>
albuminuria at some time, though that time be limited to a<lb/>
few hours, perhaps. It is argued by some that as cases do<lb/>
occur presenting a quantity only recognizable by chemical<lb/>
tests of great delicacy, it is possible that some occur with-<lb/>
out any. On the other hand, it is argued that a disease so<lb/>
terrible when severe must give some sign, even when very<lb/>
mild. The quantity present on first detection, and its in-<lb/>
crease or diminution from day to day, form, perhaps, a fairly<lb/>
good guide to prognosis. If it appears, increases gradually,<lb/>
and then begins to diminish, prognosis is good. If, on the<lb/>
contrary, it appears at first in large amount, persists or<lb/>
increases abruptly, trouble may be anticipated.</p>
<p>&ldquo;BLACK VOMIT.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The two gravest symptoms that can arise during the<lb/>
course of a case of yellow fever are undoubtedly black<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01812004"/>
316<lb/>
MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.<lb/>
vomit and suppression of urine. Black vomit is caused<lb/>
by rupture of walls of capillaries or venous and arterial<lb/>
radicles, and the discharge of blood into the cavity of the<lb/>
stomach, where, coming into contact with hyperacid gastric<lb/>
juice, it becomes altered into small masses of brownish-<lb/>
black color, somewhat resembling coffee grounds in gross<lb/>
appearance. Its advent may also indicate a general hemor-<lb/>
rhagic diathesis, which may be manifested by hemorrhages<lb/>
from the nose, gums, fauces, rectum, or by extravasations<lb/>
into the connective tissue of the scrotum. The abrupt<lb/>
appearance of black vomit in large quantities without warn-<lb/>
ing is unusual. Careful search will often show minute<lb/>
brown or black particles floating in clear fluid, and pre-<lb/>
senting the appearance described by some authors as<lb/>
&ldquo; bee's or butterfly wings.&rdquo; It is not uncommon, however,<lb/>
that patients just before death should vomit a large quan-<lb/>
tity of black vomit, and that after death the stomach<lb/>
should be found to contain several quarts of the fluid. It<lb/>
would seem probable that in these cases the hemorrhage<lb/>
which produces it was more of an active hemorrhage than<lb/>
a capillary oozing, and that death comes quickly as the<lb/>
result of shock.</p>
<p>TREATMENT OF &ldquo;BLACK VOMIT.&rdquo;</p>
<p>How shall we best treat the condition resulting in black<lb/>
vomit? The problem being both to arrest vomiting and to<lb/>
treat the condition giving rise to it, it follows that treat-<lb/>
ment should be directed toward the general hemorrhagic<lb/>
diathesis. Probably the most efficient remedy is found in<lb/>
the tincture of the perchloride of iron. That should be<lb/>
given in large doses, 1 to 2 c. c. every hour or two, or, if<lb/>
vomiting is frequent, after each act of emesis. Counter<lb/>
irritation to the epigastrium, the administration of stimu-<lb/>
lants, preferably champagne or good brandy administered<lb/>
in carbonated water and given cold, swallowing of ice, and<lb/>
administration of cocaine, make up about the sum of our<lb/>
remedial agents. While enough has been said to show that<lb/>
black vomit is a most serious symptom, it does not follow<lb/>
that every patient who vomits black matter will necessarily<lb/>
die. A fair proportion of cases recover after the symptom<lb/>
has manifested itself. Still, the ejection of black vomit<lb/>
makes a most profound mental impression on a patient, and<lb/>
for this reason has often hastened a fatal termination in a<lb/>
case which up to the appearance of this accident had done<lb/>
well.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01812005"/>
<p>MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.<lb/>
317</p>
<p>TREATMENT OF RENAL SYMPTOMS.</p>
<p>Of far graver importance to my mind is the train of symp-<lb/>
toms which leads to ur&aelig;mia, and which are announced by<lb/>
partial or complete suppression of urine. I believe this to<lb/>
be the gravest accident that can happen in the course of<lb/>
yellow fever. The amount and character of the urinary<lb/>
secretion should be a matter of frequent inquiry in every<lb/>
case, grave or mild, from the inception to convalescence.<lb/>
A sudden and irregular increase in the amount of albumen<lb/>
should put us on our guard against possible urinary sup-<lb/>
pression, and prompt treatment should be instituted and<lb/>
maintained. Counterirritation over the region of the kid-<lb/>
neys with turpentine or mustard, dry cups, the application<lb/>
of hot-water bags, all should be tried. A <hi rend="italic">tisane</hi> of water-<lb/>
melon seeds has long enjoyed the reputation of being<lb/>
almost a specific among the Creole population of New<lb/>
Orleans, and I can bear personal testimony to its efficacy<lb/>
alone or given in combination with spirits of nitrous ether.<lb/>
Of almost equal reputation is a <hi rend="italic">tisane</hi> of orange leaves,<lb/>
preferably of the bitter variety, given in large quantities<lb/>
and frequently. A remedy much used in Brunswick in<lb/>
1893, and vaunted as almost specific by those very success-<lb/>
ful in the management of the disease, was spirits of tur-<lb/>
pentine, which was sometimes given in heroic quantity, as<lb/>
much as a teaspoonful at a dose and repeated. I can not<lb/>
speak of the remedy from personal experience, but the<lb/>
results claimed for it warrant its more extended use.</p>
<p>TREATMENT OF BOWEL CONDITIONS.</p>
<p>A point in the treatment of yellow fever, with the impor-<lb/>
mata.<lb/>
tance of which I am much impressed, is the frequent wash-<lb/>
ing out of the lower bowel with enemata of warm water and<lb/>
soap. Constipation is the rule in yellow fever, and no one<lb/>
who has noted the exceedingly fetid, almost putrid, char-<lb/>
acter of the stools of a yellow-fever convalescent can fail to<lb/>
see the wisdom of removing the chances of septic absorp-<lb/>
tion by frequent washing away of this fermenting mass.<lb/>
Pass a well-oiled rectal tube as far up into the bowel as<lb/>
possible, and with a fountain syringe elevated not more<lb/>
than a foot or two force slowly 2 or 3 pints of warm,<lb/>
soapy water into the bowel. The whole operation should<lb/>
be performed with the patient upon a bedpan, not seated<lb/>
upon a vessel or close stool. The effect upon the tempera-<lb/>
ture and general condition of the patient is most marked.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f01812006"/>
<p>318<lb/>
MARINE-HOSPITAL SERVICE.</p>
<p>USE OF ANTIMALARIAL REMEDIES.</p>
<p>As to the use of quinia or allied preparations in yellow<lb/>
fever, I concur in the generally accepted verdict that they<lb/>
are without specific effect. But as yellow fever almost<lb/>
always occurs in regions where malarial diseases are also<lb/>
rife, and as the intercurrence of a malarial paroxysm is one<lb/>
of the most disagreeable incidents that can mar the course<lb/>
of a case of yellow fever, I consider it good practice in such<lb/>
regions to administer 2 to 3 grams of quinine or cinchonidia<lb/>
in the first twenty-four hours, exhibiting the drug per<lb/>
rectum if the stomach is irritable.</p>
<p>DIETETIC MANAGEMENT.</p>
<p>A most important point in the management of yellow<lb/>
fever is the diet. Many a patient, his crisis past and the<lb/>
borders of convalescence reached, has been hurried into<lb/>
an untimely grave by the misplaced kindness of an appar-<lb/>
ently simple meal. The yellow fever patient should never<lb/>
be starved; on the contrary, he should be well nourished,<lb/>
but the most scrupulous care should be exercised in the<lb/>
selection and administration of his diet. &ldquo;A little and<lb/>
that often&rdquo; should be the rule. For the first few days milk<lb/>
with limewater given cold, then animal broths, concen-<lb/>
trated but free of fat, should be the regimen. The fever<lb/>
being reduced, soft-boiled eggs, milk toast, and small bits<lb/>
of the white meat of chicken and tenderest steak may be<lb/>
permitted. Probably at least ten days or two weeks should<lb/>
elapse before the convalescent, by the easiest stages, should<lb/>
be permitted to resume ordinary diet.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
