<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01827001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George Miller Sternberg to Stanford E. Chaille, February 15, 1898</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Sternberg, George Miller</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01827001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1898-02-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Chaille, Stanford E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1898-02-15">February 15, 1898</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01827001</idno>
<title>Letter from George Miller Sternberg to Stanford E. Chaille, February 15, 1898</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Sternberg writes about yellow fever infection from soiled linen and flies. He proposes measures for disinfection and quarantine to control epidemics.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1898-02-15">
<head>Letter from George Miller Sternberg to Stanford E. Chaille, February 15, 1898</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01827001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
War Department,<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE.<lb/>
Washington,<lb/>
<date value="1898-02-15">February 15, 1898.</date>
</dateline>
Subject:<lb/>
Prof. S. E. Chaille,<lb/>
Medical Department, Tulane University,<lb/>
New Orleans, Louisiana.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I entirely agree with you as regards the measures which should be<lb/>
taken to prevent the development of an epidemic of yellow fever when cases<lb/>
are discovered in any locality where conditions are favorable for the ex-<lb/>
ternal multiplication of the germ. While the disease is not as a rule di-<lb/>
rectly communicated from one individual to another, there can be no doubt<lb/>
that bedding and soiled clothing which has been used with one sick with the<lb/>
disease often contains the infectious element and consequently requires dis-<lb/>
infection. The same is true in cholera and typhoid fever, and instances are<lb/>
known where these diseases have been directly contracted by laundresses who<lb/>
were handling the soiled linen of such patients. There is every reason to<lb/>
believe that in yellow fever, as in the diseases mentioned, the infectious<lb/>
agent is contained in the excreta of the sick, and our preventive measures<lb/>
should include the disinfection of excreta and of all articles which may pos-<lb/>
sibly be soiled with the discharges of the sick. If the infectious agent<lb/>
is present in the blood of yellow fever patients, even in very small numbers,<lb/>
it must necessarily be present in the black vomit and in the contents of the<lb/>
intestine after hemorrhages have occurred. One method in which the infec-<lb/>
tious agent may be transported from the sick room and transplanted to a fa-<lb/>
forable nidus for its external development is by means of flies; and I am<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01827002"/>
disposed to believe that they constitute a very important factor in the<lb/>
propagation of the disease. While, therefore, yellow fever, cholera and<lb/>
typhoid fever are not usually contracted by direct contagion, what is known<lb/>
of the etiology of these diseases indicates the importance of isolating the<lb/>
sick and of disinfecting all articles which may possibly have been soiled<lb/>
by their discharges. I can easily understand how a susceptible person<lb/>
visiting the sick room might act as a carrier of the infectious material<lb/>
and sow the seed upon a favorable soil in another locality without himself<lb/>
contracting the disease. While flies are much more likely to convey the<lb/>
infection, because they at once go to any soiled spot upon the clothing or<lb/>
bedding, the clothing of individuals visiting the sick room may be contam-<lb/>
inated by the same material, and it is therefore prudent, especially at<lb/>
the outset of an epidemic, to establish a rigid house quarantine when the<lb/>
patients remain for treatment in their own homes. In view of the great<lb/>
liability to the propagation of the disease through the agency of flies<lb/>
it is evident that disinfection should be carried out in the sick room in<lb/>
the most thorough manner. Soiled bedding and underclothing should be<lb/>
promptly treated with a suitable disinfecting solution. In my opinion<lb/>
failure to arrest the development of an epidemic is usually due first, to<lb/>
a failure to recognize the early cases, and, second, to the failure of<lb/>
physicians and sanitary officials to recognize the true source of danger,<lb/>
viz., the excreta of the sick.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>G.M. Sternberg</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
