<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t01838001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Military Orders for Walter Reed, Victor C. Vaughan, and Edward O. Shakespeare, August 18, 1898 [selected pages]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01838001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1898-08-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Reed, Walter </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1898-08-18">August 18, 1898</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01838001</idno>
<title>Military Orders for Walter Reed, Victor C. Vaughan, and Edward O. Shakespeare, August 18, 1898 [selected pages]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>These special orders include a section appointing Reed, Vaughan, and Shakespeare to a board for the purpose of investigating the cause of the prevalence of typhoid fever in U.S. military camps. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="military orders" n="1898-08-18">
<head>Military Orders for Walter Reed, Victor C. Vaughan, and Edward O. Shakespeare, August 18, 1898 [selected pages]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01838001"/>
<p>SPECIAL ORDERS, }<lb/>
No. 194. }</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
ADJUTANT GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Washington, August 18, 1898</hi>.</p>
<p>1. Private <hi rend="italic">Ernest F. Thomas</hi>, Company C, 4th U. S. Volun-<lb/>
teer Infantry, now in this city, will be sent to the station of<lb/>
his company, Jacksonville, Florida.</p>
<p>The Subsistence Department will pay commutation of ra-<lb/>
tions in advance at the prescribed rate for two days, it<lb/>
being impracticable for this soldier to carry rations of any<lb/>
kind.</p>
<p>2. Private <hi rend="italic">James A. Pownell</hi>, Company B, 15th Infantry,<lb/>
now at Fort Grant, Arizona Territory, is transferred as 2d<lb/>
class private to the Signal Corps, U. S. A. He will be as-<lb/>
signed to duty in charge of the military telegraph office at<lb/>
Cedar Springs, Arizona Territory.</p>
<p>3. Private <hi rend="italic">Charles W. Brown</hi>, Troop A, 7th Cavalry, now<lb/>
at Fort Du Chesne, Utah, is transferred as 2d class private to<lb/>
the Signal Corps, U. S. Army, and assigned to duty at the<lb/>
military telegraph office at that post.</p>
<p>4. Private <hi rend="italic">Corwin M. Ferguson</hi>, Company G, 4th Virginia<lb/>
Volunteer Infantry, now at Jacksonville, Florida, having<lb/>
enlisted under false pretences, will be discharged without<lb/>
honor from the service of the United States on receipt of this<lb/>
order by the commanding officer of his station. Under para-<lb/>
graph 1386 of the Regulations the soldier is not entitled to<lb/>
pay or allowances, and final statements, except for deposits,<lb/>
shall not be furnished him.</p>
<p>5. Private <hi rend="italic">Ora G. Spencer</hi>, Company D, 1st U. S. Volun-<lb/>
teer Infantry, now at Santiago, Cuba, will be discharged from<lb/>
the service of the United States by the commanding officer of<lb/>
his station. Under paragraph 1386 of the Regulations the<lb/>
soldier is not entitled to pay or allowances, and final state-<lb/>
ments, except for deposits, shall not be furnished him.</p>
<p>6. Private <hi rend="italic">Richard M. Williamson</hi>, Company A, 2d Ala-<lb/>
bama Volunteer Infantry, now at Jacksonville, Florida, will<lb/>
be discharged the service of the United States by the com-<lb/>
manding officer of his station. This soldier is not entitled to<lb/>
travel-pay.</p>
<p>7. Private <hi rend="italic">Jesse Hood Bullock</hi>, Company M, 1st Georgia<lb/>
Volunteer Infantry, now at Camp George H. Thomas, Georgia,<lb/>
will be discharged the service of the United States by the</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01838002"/>
<p>6</p>
<p>35. Captain <hi rend="italic">William F. Lewis</hi>, assistant surgeon, U. S.<lb/>
Army, now at Sullivans Island, South Carolina, will proceed<lb/>
at once to Tampa, Florida, and report in person to the com-<lb/>
manding officer, 5th U. S. Infantry, to accompany that regi-<lb/>
ment to Santiago. The travel enjoined is necessary for the<lb/>
public service.</p>
<p>36. Acting Assistant Surgeon <hi rend="italic">Compton Wilson</hi>, U. S. Army,<lb/>
will proceed from Norfolk to Fort Monroe, Virginia, and re-<lb/>
port in person to Major <hi rend="italic">Calvin De Witt</hi>, surgeon, U. S. Army,<lb/>
in charge of U. S. General Hospital at that post, to await<lb/>
transportation by the U. S. Steamer &ldquo;Obdam,&rdquo; to Ponce,<lb/>
Porto Rico, and, upon arrival there, will report in person to<lb/>
the commanding general of the troops at that place, for as-<lb/>
signment to duty. The travel enjoined is necessary for the<lb/>
public service.</p>
<p>37. Majors <hi rend="italic">Merrill W. Lang</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jacob M. Longnecker</hi>, ad-<lb/>
ditional paymasters, U. S. Volunteers, now on temporary duty<lb/>
in this city, under verbal instructions from the Secretary of<lb/>
War, are assigned to station in Washington, District of<lb/>
Columbia, to date from August 11, 1898.</p>
<p>38. Lieutenant Colonel <hi rend="italic">Edward B. Ives</hi>, U. S. Volunteer<lb/>
Signal Corps, having reported to the Chief Signal Officer of<lb/>
the Army, <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to Camp Russell A. Alger, Virginia, will<lb/>
proceed to Middletown, Pennsylvania, and report in person<lb/>
to the commanding general, 2d Army Corps, for assignment<lb/>
to duty as Chief Signal Officer of that corps. The travel en-<lb/>
joined is necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>39. Acting Assistant Surgeon <hi rend="italic">Harry Streett</hi>, U. S. Army,<lb/>
will proceed from Baltimore, Maryland, to Charleston, South<lb/>
Carolina, and await transportation by U. S. Steamer &ldquo;Obdam&rdquo;<lb/>
to Ponce, Porto Rico, and, upon arrival there, will report in<lb/>
person to the commanding general of the troops at that place,<lb/>
for assignment to duty. The travel enjoined is necessary for<lb/>
the public service.</p>
<p>&check; 40. A board of medical officers, to consist of--</p>
<p>Major <hi rend="italic">Walter Reed</hi>, surgeon, U. S. Army;<lb/>
Major <hi rend="italic">Victor C. Vaughan</hi>, division surgeon, U. S. Volun-<lb/>
teers; and<lb/>
Major <hi rend="italic">Edward O. Shakespeare</hi>, brigade surgeon, U. S. Vol-<lb/>
unteers,<lb/>
is appointed to meet in this city at the earliest date practica-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01838003"/>
7<lb/>
ble for the purpose of making an investigation into the cause<lb/>
of the extensive prevalence of typhoid fever in the various<lb/>
military camps within the limits of the United States, under<lb/>
such instructions as it may receive from the Surgeon General<lb/>
of the Army. The board will call the attention of the proper<lb/>
commanding officers to any insanitary conditions which may<lb/>
exist at the camps visited by it, and will make recommenda-<lb/>
tions with a view to their proper correction. The report of<lb/>
the board will be forwarded to the Surgeon General as soon<lb/>
as practicable after the completion of the investigation con-<lb/>
templated.</p>
<p>Such journeys as may be required under the above order &darr;<lb/>
are necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>41. Private <hi rend="italic">Emil Ballhaus</hi>, Company A, 1st Ohio Volunteer<lb/>
Infantry, now at Fernandina, Florida, is, upon his own ap-<lb/>
plication, transferred to the 2d Kentucky Volunteer Infantry,<lb/>
and will be sent to the station of that regiment, Camp George<lb/>
H. Thomas, Georgia. The expenses of the transfer will be<lb/>
borne by the soldier, and transportation will not be furnished<lb/>
by the Quartermaster's Department.</p>
<p>42. Sergeant <hi rend="italic">George L. Rubadon</hi>, Company C, 31st Michi-<lb/>
gan Volunteer Infantry, now at Camp George H. Thomas,<lb/>
Georgia, will be discharged the service of the United States<lb/>
by the commanding officer of his station. This soldier is not<lb/>
entitled to travel-pay.</p>
<p>43. Private <hi rend="italic">Benjamin E. Sprague</hi>, Company G, 35th Michi-<lb/>
gan Volunteer Infantry, now at Island Lake, Michigan,<lb/>
will be discharged the service of the United States by the<lb/>
commanding officer of his station. This soldier is not entitled<lb/>
to travel-pay.</p>
<p>44. Principal Musician <hi rend="italic">Charles J. Rulo</hi>, 4th Ohio Volunteer<lb/>
Infantry, now in Porto Rico, will be discharged the service<lb/>
of the United States by the commanding officer of his station.<lb/>
This soldier is not entitled to travel-pay.</p>
<p>45. Private <hi rend="italic">Louis F. Wurster</hi>, Company E, 20th Infantry,<lb/>
now at Fort McPherson, Georgia, will be discharged the<lb/>
service of the United States by the commanding officer of<lb/>
his station. This soldier is not entitled to travel-pay.</p>
<p>46. Private <hi rend="italic">Amos R. E. Pinchot</hi>, Troop A, New York Vol-<lb/>
unteer Cavalry, now in Porto Rico, will be discharged the<lb/>
service of the United States by the commanding officer of his<lb/>
station. This soldier is not entitled to travel-pay.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
