<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t01849003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Sketches of the Virginia Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church, South, by John J. Lafferty, 1880</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Lafferty, John J.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01849003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1880-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, James C.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1880-00-00">1880</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01849003</idno>
<title>Sketches of the Virginia Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church, South, by John J. Lafferty, 1880</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lafferty gives brief biographical sketches of Lemuel S. Reed and James C. Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1880-00-00">
<head>Sketches of the Virginia Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church, South, by John J. Lafferty, 1880</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01849003"/>
<p>SKETCHES<lb/>
OF THE<lb/>
VIRGINIA CONFERENCE,<lb/>
METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH, SOUTH.</p>
<p>BY<lb/>
REV. JOHN J. LAFFERTY.</p>
<p>WITH INTRODUCTION BY BISHOP DAVID S. DOGGETT, D. D.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>RICHMOND, VA.:<lb/>
CHRISTIAN ADVOCATE OFFICE,<lb/>
1880.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01849004"/>
<p>68<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">SKETCHES OF THE VIRGINIA CONFERENCE</hi>,</p>
<p>REV. LEMUEL SUTTON REED.</p>
<p>THE Commonwealth of North Carolina claims another son in Mr. Reed, and one whose record<lb/>
will honor the old North State. He is a native of Perquimans county, his birth dating from the<lb/>
5th of May, 1819. His ancestral trunk surely is of English oak. Mr. Reed has the build of the<lb/>
proverbial representative of Brittannia. There is a show of the poise and solidity of the Briton--<lb/>
a man of collected powers, and fitted for the conduct of affairs. He was taken from the local ranks<lb/>
with a considerable family and put in the itineracy--a strong proof that some wise head had dis-<lb/>
covered good timber. He was converted on the 13th day of August, 1838, at Oak Grove church,<lb/>
in his native county, under the ministry of Rev. Gervas M. Keesee, and joined the church at once.<lb/>
His youth and diffidence made him keep silence as to his call to preach for some time. He followed<lb/>
the vocation of a teacher. In 1846 he began as a local preacher, and continued for three years.<lb/>
He entered the Virginia Conference in 1849; ordained deacon in 1851 by Bishop Andrew, and Elder<lb/>
by Bishop Paine in 1853. He has served in some of the hardest work and many of the most<lb/>
pleasant appointments in the Conference, ranging from the mountains to the North Carolina coast.<lb/>
One year, for the sake of being near an aged female connection, he served a circuit in the Baltimore<lb/>
Conference. He has been one of the advisers of the Bishop for twelve years, and is now the Elder<lb/>
of the Danville district. His work as acting Bishop through these years have proven of permanent<lb/>
value to the Church. He has not lost a month by sickness since his connection with the Conference.<lb/>
He has served three times in the General Conference--1866, 1874, and 1878. He has used books<lb/>
to advantage, but is not a bookish man. His expositions are lucid and the language is well-fitted<lb/>
to the thought; he uses brief notes.</p>
<p>Mr. Reed has been married twice. His first wife was Miss White of Pasquotank, North Caro-<lb/>
lina, and his second Mrs. Kyle, of Harrisonburg, Virginia. He was fortunate in his selections ;<lb/>
they were helpmeets to him. A daughter is the wife of the Rev. J. W. Blincoe, of the Conference,<lb/>
and a son is a member of the body. Three others are prosperous and honorable citizens of the<lb/>
West. A bright little girl of a dozen summers is the only issue by the second marriage. His two<lb/>
oldest boys served through the war and surrendered at Appomattox. One of these, the Rev. James<lb/>
C. Reed lost an arm in the conflict.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f01849005"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH, SOUTH</hi>.<lb/>
157</p>
<p>During the first year he was instrumental in building three churches. In 1873, he was stationed on<lb/>
Princess Anne circuit; many were added to the church. In 1874, he was appointed to Lunenburg<lb/>
circuit; in 1875, to Dinwiddie circuit; in 1876-'77-'78, to West Hanover circuit, and in 1879, to<lb/>
Goochland circuit.<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p>REV. JAMES CLAYTON REED.</p>
<p>HE was a gallant Confederate, leaving a hand on the field of Sharpsburg, torn off by a shell. Of<lb/>
the heroic little band, that succumbed to overwhelming numbers, Reed was one. He entered<lb/>
the army in July of 1861. The mention of his career as a soldier hints of the fine qualities of his<lb/>
native fiber. It is not too much to say that even his great leader had not deeper reverence for the<lb/>
word--Duty. Whatever the Conference commits to the charge of Mr. Reed, all know it will have<lb/>
his faithful attention. He declares the whole counsel of God to the people. No man's blood will be<lb/>
upon his garments. Nothing is slurred over. Thrift in all departments follows his oversight and labor.</p>
<p>He is the son of the Rev. L. S. Reed, of the Conference. He was raised on the march and in<lb/>
the rank. North Carolina is his native State. He was born in Perquimans, on the 1st of November,<lb/>
1842. He professed religion when he was about twelve, but camp life vitiated his piety, and he be-<lb/>
came neglectful of his Christian duties. In 1866, he was reclaimed and revived during a meeting<lb/>
held by his brother-in-law, Rev. J. W. Blincoe, at South Hill, Mecklenburg county, Va.</p>
<p>He spent two sessions at Randolph Macon College, prior to the war, and a session and a half<lb/>
at the University of Virginia after the surrender. He says that he carried off no sheepskin, but a<lb/>
calfskin, having received the &ldquo;boots&rdquo; as the ugliest man in the University. He would hardly carry<lb/>
off such a prize in the Conference.</p>
<p>He was licensed to preach, September 8th, 1868, by the Quarterly Conference, of Charlottes-<lb/>
ville station, and admitted on trial in November of the same year. He has served Nelson one year,<lb/>
Powhatan two years, and Atlantic one year. He was sent to Southampton in 1872, but changed by<lb/>
the Elder to Edenton, North Carolina, and served a year; Norfolk circuit, three years, and is filling<lb/>
out his fourth year on Nottoway.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
