<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t01849007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Memoirs: Rev. L. S. Reed, by T. M'N. Simpson, November 16, 1898</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Simpson, T. M'N.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01849007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1898-11-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="place">Durant's Neck (Perquimans County, N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Farmville (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1898-11-16">November 16, 1898</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01849007</idno>
<title>Memoirs: Rev. L. S. Reed, by T. M'N. Simpson, November 16, 1898</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a biography of Lemuel S. Reed, the father of Walter Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1898-11-16">
<head>Memoirs: Rev. L. S. Reed, by T. M'N. Simpson, November 16, 1898</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01849007"/>
<p>MINUTES<lb/>
OF THE<lb/>
ONE HUNDRED AND SIXTEENTH SESSION<lb/>
OF THE<lb/>
VIRGINIA<lb/>
ANNUAL CONFERENCE<lb/>
OF THE<lb/>
METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH, SOUTH,<lb/>
HELD AT<lb/>
PORTSMOUTH, VA., NOVEMBER 16-23, 1898.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">MEMOIRS, REPORTS AND DIRECTORY</hi>.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>EDITED AND PUBLISHED FOR THE CONFERENCE BY<lb/>
BERNARD F. LIPSCOMB.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>RICHMOND:<lb/>
J. W. FERGUSSON &amp; SON, PRINTERS.<lb/>
1898.</p>
<p>University of Virginia Library<lb/>
BX 8213 .v5</p>
<pb n="2" id="f01849008"/>
<p><add>Virginia Conference Annual 1898</add></p>
<p>V.</p>
<p>MEMOIRS.<lb/>
-----<lb/>
REV. L. S. REED.<lb/>
BY T. M'N. SIMPSON.</p>
<p>REV. LEMUEL SUTTON REED was one of North Carolina's sterling sons, and one<lb/>
of nature's noblemen. To me, as to many, he was a father in Israel, and a friend<lb/>
indeed. Upon his knees, in the little country school of their neighborhood, my<lb/>
mother learned her A B C's; and, upon his counsel and support, I took my first<lb/>
steps in the itinerant ministry. He presided at the Quarterly Conference that<lb/>
licensed me to preach, and recommended me to the Annual Conference; he gave<lb/>
me work on his district, encouraged my discontinuance to pursue a course at<lb/>
Randolph-Macon College, received me again into his district, and continued to the<lb/>
hour of his death my faithful friend and affectionate adviser. Upon his new-made<lb/>
grave, I would place to-day the sweetest flower in the garden of my heart; and to<lb/>
his memory, I would give the tenderest tribute of my love.</p>
<p>Brother Reed was born in Durant's Neck, Perquimans county, N.C., May 5, 1819,<lb/>
and he died in Farmville, Prince Edward county, Va., December 18, 1897. Between<lb/>
those dates, embracing nearly four-score years, he fought the good fight of faith,<lb/>
and he kept the faith. His early years were largely spent in school work, first<lb/>
as a pupil, then as a teacher; but his advantages were limited to the facilities of<lb/>
his own and an adjoining county, and he never had the privilege of a college course.<lb/>
He was, however, a thoughtful observer and a careful student of men and books;<lb/>
and being naturally well endowed, mentally, morally and physically, he acquired a<lb/>
competent furnishing, and he showed himself a workman that needed not to be<lb/>
ashamed. Having been religiously trained by his parents, Thomas Walke and<lb/>
Elizabeth Reed, he publicly professed saving faith in Christ, August 13, 1838, at<lb/>
Oak Grove Church, in his native county, under the ministry of the Rev. Gervas<lb/>
M. Keesee, and joined, without delay, the Methodist Episcopal Church. On Octo-<lb/>
ber 16, 1846, under the conviction of a Divine call to the work, he applied for and<lb/>
obtained license to preach from the Quarterly Conference of the Pasquotank<lb/>
Circuit, to which he had moved after his marriage in 1839; and in November,<lb/>
1848, at the session of his Annual Conference, in Elizabeth City, N. C., he applied<lb/>
for admission, on trial, into the traveling connection; but being pale and thin<lb/>
from recent sickness, and being opposed by a leading member on the ground that<lb/>
he would soon be in his grave, and his dependent family a care upon the Church,<lb/>
he was rejected. Disappointed, but not disheartened, he accepted his defeat as a<lb/>
providential indication that his call was simply to the local ranks, and he set him-<lb/>
self anew to the tasks of the school-room. His Presiding Elder, however, Rev.<lb/>
Thomas Crowder, dissatisfied with the unfavorable action of the Conference,<lb/>
advised a renewal of his application; and, being improved in health, he stood<lb/>
again at the door of his Conference in November, 1849, at Petersburg, Va., and<lb/>
<lb/>
VIRGINIA CONFERENCE ANNUAL.<lb/>
31<lb/>
------------------<lb/>
was admitted without a dissenting vote, his former opponent giving him his sup-<lb/>
port, and continuing ever after his steadfast friend. In 1851, he was ordained a<lb/>
deacon by Bishop Andrew, and in 1853, an elder by Bishop Paine. Through fifty-<lb/>
one years he bore the title, and adorned the office of a Methodist preacher; and<lb/>
for more than forty of these, he went in and out among us an active, effective itin-<lb/>
erant, observing the injunction: &ldquo;Watch thou in all things; endure afflictions; do<lb/>
the work of an evangelist; make full proof of thy ministry.&rdquo; Every part of our<lb/>
territory has praise for him in its gates; and every kind of our regular work--<lb/>
missions, circuits, districts--bear witness to his faithful, practical hand. Currituck<lb/>
Mission, Gloucester, Princess Anne, Gates, N. C., Murfreesboro, N. C., Prince<lb/>
Edward (twice), Bedford, Nottoway, Brunswick, East Rockingham of the Balti-<lb/>
more Conference--where he spent the year 1870 to be near an aged relative--<lb/>
Amherst, Henrico, and Cumberland circuits, and Charlottesville, Murfreesboro,<lb/>
Norfolk, Danville, Farmville, and Petersburg districts, were the fields of his labors,<lb/>
the scenes of his toils and triumphs. Three times, he was elected by his brethren<lb/>
as a delegate, and once as an alternate, to the General Conference of his Church,<lb/>
and he represented them through the sessions of 1866, 1874, and 1878, and during<lb/>
a part of the session of 1886, when Dr. Bennett became too feeble to attend. He<lb/>
was married twice--first to Miss Pharaba White, of Pasquotank county, N. C.,<lb/>
February--, 1839, then on December 11, 1866, to Mrs. Mary C. Kyle, of Harrison-<lb/>
burg, Va., who survives him. Both were helpmeets indeed, and blessed the heart<lb/>
and brightened the home to which they gave themselves. Six children live and<lb/>
&ldquo;rise up to call him blessed &rdquo;--Mrs. J. W. Blincoe, Ashland, Va.; Rev. J. C. Reed,<lb/>
Virginia Conference; Judge Christopher Reed, St. Louis, Mo.; Mr. Thomas Reed,<lb/>
Kansas; Dr. Walter Reed, Georgetown, D. C., and Mrs. D. T. Elam, Farmville,<lb/>
Va. (the only child by his second marriage, and the one at whose home he breathed<lb/>
his last). The domestic relations of Brother Reed were most charmingly tender<lb/>
and sweet. He was revered as the worthy head of his family, and enjoyed as the<lb/>
cordial companion of its members. His children were the pride and joy of his<lb/>
heart, and he was their friend and associate. Few men have succeeded better in<lb/>
commanding their households after them, and few have left more creditable repre-<lb/>
sentatives of their names. His home was ever the sphere of bright and happy<lb/>
fellowship, and the scene of generous and unaffected hospitality. His door never<lb/>
closed against &ldquo;an angel unawares,&rdquo; and his beds and his board were never more<lb/>
enjoyed than when shared by his friends. His conversation was free and easy,<lb/>
and instructive. He never lowered the standard of true ministerial dignity; yet,<lb/>
he never restrained nor repressed &ldquo;the feast of reason and the flow of soul.&rdquo;<lb/>
&ldquo;His speech was always with grace, seasoned with salt.&rdquo; In the councils of his<lb/>
Church and the advisory boards of his community, he was esteemed for his strong<lb/>
common sense, and for his fine practical wisdom. He was gifted with unusual<lb/>
powers of penetration and discrimination, and his knowledge of men and measures<lb/>
was exceedingly accurate. Bishops availed themselves of his counsels, and young<lb/>
men sought and followed his advice.</p>
<p>In manner, Brother Reed was frank, candid, transparent. You knew where he<lb/>
stood on all important questions, and which side he espoused in all serious contro-<lb/>
versies. He made no concealments, practiced no diplomacy, but exercised himself<lb/>
to have a conscience void of offence. His convictions were always positive, and his<lb/>
methods straightforward; but his spirit was kind and considerate. He was a scion<lb/>
of English stock, and his build and his bearing were those of the sturdy Briton.</p>
<p>In the pulpit, he was grave, deliberate, impressive. His sermons gave evidence<lb/>
of patient study and careful preparation. He avoided all ostentation, and devoted<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01849009"/>
1898<lb/>
32<lb/>
VIRGINIA CONFERENCE ANNUAL.<lb/>
----------<lb/>
himself to a plain exposition of the Word, and a practical application of the truth.<lb/>
Souls were nourished by his ministry, conscienes were quickened, sinners were<lb/>
saved, and saints built up in their most holy faith.</p>
<p>At the session of his Conference in Danville, Va., November, 1893, he felt that<lb/>
perhaps the time had come for him to lay down the work of a regular itinerant<lb/>
preacher, and to seek the relation of a superannuate. But he was reluctant to<lb/>
give up his &ldquo;loved employ,&rdquo; and to enter a relation in which he had been restless<lb/>
in 1891; after consultation, however, with his son in the Conference, he asked to<lb/>
be retired, and he never had the privilege of assembling again with the brethren<lb/>
that he had loved so long and served with so faithfully. His Conference was to<lb/>
him as the apple of his eye. As the time for its annual session drew near, he<lb/>
would catch the spirit of its sacred reunions, as the war-horse sniffs the battle afar<lb/>
off, and he would plan and prepare to attend, with the enthusiasm of a school boy<lb/>
anticipating a return to his home. It was positively pathetic at times to see his<lb/>
strong, hopeful spirit attempt to assert itself over his weak and diseased body, and<lb/>
determine to drag its weary weight, at any cost, to the place of his brethren's assem-<lb/>
bling. But, as the date arrived, and he saw and felt that he could not go, he would<lb/>
meekly and uncomplainingly submit, and say: &ldquo;Tell the brethren I would be with<lb/>
them if I could. My heart is with them, my prayers are for them, but I am too<lb/>
feeble to leave home.&rdquo; As the last session of our Conference approached, he<lb/>
charged me with a message of love to the brethren, and said: &ldquo;You can say that<lb/>
though I am a great sufferer, I am happy in the love of God and in the sense of<lb/>
His favor.&rdquo; Often, as his paroxysms of pain would subside, he would quote: &ldquo;I<lb/>
reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with<lb/>
the glory that shall be revealed in us; &rdquo; and he would rest in hope. The walk that<lb/>
he had through the valley of the shadow of death was a long and weary one.<lb/>
Shortly after his superannuation, he began to break down in health, showing signs<lb/>
of serious heart disturbance. But his robust frame and vigorous constitution<lb/>
enabled him to keep at bay the last enemy through many months, and to take<lb/>
some part in the services of the Church at which he worshiped. He was the stead-<lb/>
fast friend and hearty supporter of the pastor, and he never allowed his seat in the<lb/>
sanctuary to be vacant if he was able to fill it. Frequently, in feebleness extreme,<lb/>
he was at the place of prayer, and his means were as generously offered as himself<lb/>
for the kingdom and glory of Christ. A more liberal, regular and conscientious<lb/>
contributor to the Church, we had not among us, and no more fair and just and<lb/>
high-toned man. He was the very soul of honor, and his name was a synonym<lb/>
for integrity and uprightness, fair dealing and manly bearing. His word was as<lb/>
good as his bond. Soon after the close of our last Conference session, he began to<lb/>
decline very rapidly--more rapidly than some of us knew; but he was not unaware<lb/>
of his progress, and he carefully set his house in order, giving direction concerning<lb/>
the smallest details of his affairs; then calmly and confidently awaited the issue,<lb/>
knowing that his calling and election had been made sure, and &ldquo;that if our earthly<lb/>
house of this tabernacle were dissolved, we have a building of God, an house not<lb/>
made with hands, eternal in the heavens.&rdquo; On Friday, the day before his depar-<lb/>
ture, he asked two or three times if he were not dying; being assured that he was<lb/>
not, he said the end was not far off; and on Saturday morning, December 18, 1897, as<lb/>
the morning light was breaking, and the dawn of a new day was driving back the<lb/>
darkness of the old night, his released spirit caught the wings of the morning of<lb/>
eternal day, and his shadowed eyes opened to the beauties and glories of a never-<lb/>
darkening world. All his children, except those in distant States, and all the mem-<lb/>
bers of his household, and his pastor, were with him, as he desired they should be,<lb/>
<lb/>
VIRGINIA CONFERENCE ANNUAL.<lb/>
33<lb/>
--------------------<lb/>
when he left the circle of earthly friends and loved ones, to join the company of<lb/>
those who had gone before. On Monday afternoon, December 20, 1897, at the<lb/>
Methodist Church in Farmville, Va., the solemn service for the dead was conducted<lb/>
by the writer, assisted by Revs. Jas. Cannon, Jr., R. F. Gayle, R. A. Compton, and<lb/>
William E. Grant, each of whom paid touching tribute to his memory, and all that<lb/>
was mortal of Rev. L. S. Reed was laid to rest in the quiet cemetery of the town.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The pains of death are past, Labor and sorrow cease.<lb/>
And life's long warfare closed at last, His soul is found in peace.<lb/>
Soldier of Christ, well done, Praise be thy new employ,<lb/>
And while eternal ages run, Rest in thy Saviour's joy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>REV. JACOB MANNING.</p>
<p>BY T. M's SIMPSON.</p>
<p>At ten minutes to ten o'clock Tuesday morning, February 15th, 1898, in the<lb/>
home of his son-in-law, Col. R. A. Booker, Farmville, Va., the pure and quiet<lb/>
spirit of REV. JACOB MANNING laid down its body and its charge, and entered into<lb/>
the rest that remains to the people of God.</p>
<p>The health of Brother Manning had been declining for some time. In Novem-<lb/>
ber, '97, while visiting his daughters in Cambridge, Md., an attack of bronchitis<lb/>
seriously prostrated him, and threatened the termination of his life; but he recov-<lb/>
ered sufficiently to return to Farmville, Va., and gave promise, for a time, of renew-<lb/>
ing his strength, and of re-entering the circle of his friends; but fresh cold was<lb/>
taken, and this arrested his progress, disturbed his respiration, and gradually broke<lb/>
down his enfeebled constitution. He was not ignorant of his danger, nor unmind-<lb/>
ful of the issue confronting him; but he had committed his way unto the Lord,<lb/>
and he was willing that He should direct his strife. On more than one occasion<lb/>
he said to me: &ldquo;It is all right. The will of the Lord be done. It is a pleasure to<lb/>
me to be with my children, and they want me to stay, but the Lord will do that<lb/>
which is best.&rdquo; His mind was stayed on God and he was kept in perfect peace.<lb/>
He walked through the valley of the shadow of death without fear. He never lost<lb/>
consciousness for any length of time, and he never exhibited impatience or distrust<lb/>
for a single moment. To the last, he was the same sweet, saintly brother that<lb/>
many of us had known and loved so long. It was a sacred privilege and honor to<lb/>
be with him in his last days and hours, and his exemplification in life and in death<lb/>
of the principles of our holy religion was an inspiring illustration of the excellence<lb/>
of the Gospel; and it lingers with us as a living light upon our path, and a cher-<lb/>
ished blessing upon our hearts. The final struggle was not without its signs of<lb/>
severe conflict, but the paroxysm was not long, and the failing eyes turned as if catch-<lb/>
ing visions of approaching forms, and the departing spirit went trustfully to the<lb/>
God who gave it.</p>
<p>Brother Manning was born near the city of Baltimore, Md., January 14th, 1816.<lb/>
At an early age, he was bereft of his father, and left to the care of a dependent<lb/>
mother. Feeling the necessity of supporting himself, he went from home for em-<lb/>
ployment, and, at 12 years of age, he realized that he was alone in the world, fath-<lb/>
erless, and practically motherless. Overwhelmed by the sense of his desolation<lb/>
and dependence, he went to God and asked Him to be his Father. From that time,<lb/>
he accounted himself the child of God. He did not always walk worthy, he told<lb/>
me in speaking of it, but he never abandoned the position he then took, nor recalled<lb/>
the consecration he then made. At fifteen, he publicly professed his faith in Christ,<lb/>
3</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
