<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t01850015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Military Orders for Walter Reed, October 28, 1898</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Sernberg, George Miller</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01850015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1898-10-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Reed, Walter </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="place">Natural Bridge (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Rico</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1898-10-28">October 28, 1898</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01850015</idno>
<title>Military Orders for Walter Reed, October 28, 1898</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed's letter and Sternberg's endorsement suggest that Natural Bridge, Virginia, is not a suitable location for an army hospital due to the condition of the buildings and transportation issues. The documents are dated October 28, 1898 and October 30, 1898. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="military orders" n="1898-10-28">
<head>Military Orders for Walter Reed, October 28, 1898</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01850015"/>
<p>OFFICE OF SURGEON GENERAL,<lb/>
OCT 23<lb/>
43178<lb/>
F<lb/>
1898<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT.</p>
<p>Filed with a.c.p. 2959-'80<lb/>
Surgeon General's Office,<lb/>
Army Medical Museum<lb/>
October 28, 1898.</p>
<p>OFFICE OF ADJUTANT GENERAL<lb/>
DEC 12<lb/>
172691<lb/>
1898<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT</p>
<p>Reed, Walter. Maj. &amp;<lb/>
Surgeon, U.S.A.</p>
<p>Report of Inspection of Build-<lb/>
ings at Natural Bridge, Va.<lb/>
for hospital purposes.</p>
<p>Filed with 143204. A.G.O.</p>
<p>FILE.<lb/>
DEC 20 1898<lb/>
<unclear>[UNCLEAR]</unclear><lb/>
143204<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p>1st INDORSEMENT<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
Surgeon Generl's Office.</p>
<p>October 30th, 1898.</p>
<p>Respectfully forwarded to the<lb/>
ADJUTANT GENERAL OF THE ARMY. The<lb/>
locality referred to in this report<lb/>
would be favorable so far as climate<lb/>
and other local conditions are con-<lb/>
cerned, but the buildings now upon<lb/>
the land are not suitable for hos-<lb/>
pital purposes. In my opinion a<lb/>
locality upon the sea-board as far<lb/>
north. as New York would be a better<lb/>
location for a general hospital in<lb/>
view of the fact that the sick from<lb/>
Cuba and Porto Rico could be brought<lb/>
to such a hospital by our hospital<lb/>
ships without being subjected to the<lb/>
hardships of railroad transportation.</p>
<p><unclear>G. M.</unclear>Sternberg<lb/>
Surgeon General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>Filed by a.g.o.<lb/>
<unclear>wrote</unclear><lb/>
aog<lb/>
Dec '18&sol;98</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="letter" n="1898-10-28">
<head>Letter from Walter Reed to the Surgeon General, October 28, 1898</head>
<pb n="2" id="f01850016"/>
<opener>
All communications to this Office should be addressed &ldquo;To the Surgeon General, U. S. Army, Washington, D. C.&rdquo;<lb/>
Subject: Inspection of buildings at Natural Bridge, Va.<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
U. S. ARMY MEDICAL MUSEUM AND LIBRARY,<lb/>
Corner 7th and B Streets S. W.,<lb/>
<dateline>
Washington, <date value="1898-10-28">October 28, 1898.</date>, 189 .</dateline><lb/>
TO THE SURGEON GENERAL,<lb/>
U. S. Army.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to report that in compliance with S.O., No. 247,<lb/>
Par. 80, Headquarters of the Army, A.G.O., Washington, October 19, 1898,<lb/>
I visited Natural Bridge, Va. on Oct. 22, 1898, and made a careful in-<lb/>
spection on the 24th and 25th insts. of the several buildings located<lb/>
at that point, inquiring also, into the character of the water supply,<lb/>
in accordance with verbal instructions received from the Surgeon General.</p>
<p>As a result of my inspection, I beg to report as follows: Natural<lb/>
Bridge (altitude 1500 ft.) is distant about three miles from Natural Bridge<lb/>
station, which is situated at the junction of the Shenandoah Valley Div-<lb/>
ision of the Norfolk and Western Rail Road; and the James River Division<lb/>
of the Chesapeake and Ohio R.R.</p>
<p>The following buildings were examined: 1. The Appledore Hotel, a 3 sto-<lb/>
ry frame building, weather boarded without, lathed and plastered within,<lb/>
with slate roof, and containing 44 rooms. This building, which is in<lb/>
good repair, faces South-east, each story being provided with a veranda<lb/>
front and rear, and on the South end. The width of the veranda in front<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01850017"/>
(2)<lb/>
is 10&prime; - on the rear and South end 6&prime; 3&Prime;. The height of stories is as<lb/>
follows: 1st story 10&prime;, 2nd and 3rd, each 8&prime; 7&Prime;. The <hi>1st story</hi> has 16<lb/>
rooms, as follows: one room (office) 17&prime; &times; 23&Prime; communicating with dining<lb/>
room 23&prime; &times; 14 1&sol;2&prime;, and 14 rooms, each 14&Prime; &times; 9&prime; 6&Prime;, convertible into suites<lb/>
of 2 rooms, by communicating door. The office and dining room and 4 of<lb/>
the smaller rooms are heated by open fire-places. The remaining 10 rooms<lb/>
have no means for heating.</p>
<p>The <hi>2nd story</hi> has 16 rooms as follows: A front parlor 17&prime;6&Prime; &times; 17&prime;6&Prime;:<lb/>
a rear parlor 17&prime;8&Prime; &times; 13&prime;, and 14 rooms 14&prime; &times; 9&prime;6&Prime;, convertible into suites<lb/>
of 2 rooms by communicating door. Six of these rooms have open fire-places,<lb/>
the others no means of heating.</p>
<p>The <hi>3rd story</hi> has 12 rooms as follows: one room 17&prime;6&Prime; &times; 17&prime;6&Prime;; one room<lb/>
17&prime;6&Prime; &times; 13&prime; and 10 rooms 14&prime; &times; 9&prime;6&Prime;, convertible into suites of 2 rooms by<lb/>
communicating doors. Six of these rooms have open fire-places.</p>
<p>The upper stories of the building are reached by a stair-way having a<lb/>
width of 4&prime;1&Prime;- width of hall on each floor 4&prime;6&Prime;.</p>
<p>All rooms are lighted and ventilated by one or more sash-doors with<lb/>
transom. Each story is provided with a water-closet and bath_tub, a<lb/>
small room 6&prime; &times; 7&prime;6&Prime; having been partitioned off on each rear veranda for<lb/>
this purpose. The water-closets are provided with flushing tanks and have<lb/>
only recently been placed in position. These closets are drained into a<lb/>
4&Prime; iron pipe which connects with a tile pipe passing beneath the building<lb/>
and emptying into a small creek, about 500 yards distant. As far as I<lb/>
could ascertain, the plumbing arrangements were satisfactory, but there is<lb/>
no means provided for heating the bath rooms, nor any measures taken to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01850018"/>
(3)<lb/>
prevent water pipes from freezing. 2. Adjoining this building on its<lb/>
North end and attached to it is an unfinished 3 story frame building,<lb/>
with attic, which was begun about five (5) years ago. It was not possi-<lb/>
ble to form any idea as to the interior of this structure, as there was<lb/>
simply the frame work with roof, but without flooring, stair-ways, plas-<lb/>
tering &amp;c.</p>
<p>3. Pavilion Hotel, a frame building, 2 stories in height, situated on a<lb/>
lower level than the Appledore Hotel, and about 45 yards distant. The<lb/>
entire first story consists of a dining room 78&prime; &times; 27&prime; &times; 12&prime;. This room<lb/>
has no windows, but is lighted by large, double, sliding sash-doors on both<lb/>
sides and ends. There is no provision for heating or ventilation. The<lb/>
second story is divided into 14 small rooms, each 12&prime;6&Prime; &times; 14&prime;, height of<lb/>
ceiling 10&prime;6&Prime;. These rooms are situated on either side of a hall 4&prime; in<lb/>
width, and each have one window and one door.</p>
<p>Each story has a veranda 10&prime; in width, on all sides. The building is<lb/>
supported on brick piers, about 7&prime;6&Prime; in height, enclosed with a lattice-<lb/>
work. A temporary kitchen has been fitted up underneath the North end of<lb/>
the building.</p>
<p>4. Private residence of Mrs. Parsons. This building, distant about 70<lb/>
yards from the main hotel, is a 2 story frame dwelling with attic and<lb/>
basement. Height of 1st &amp; 2nd stories 7&prime;6&Prime;. There are 22 rooms of various<lb/>
sizes, the majority being quite small.</p>
<p>In addition to the buildings already mentioned, there is a frame cottage<lb/>
of 7 rooms, situated about 100 yards from the hotels.</p>
<p>The several buildings are located on hill-sides, which insure perfect<lb/>
drainage.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f01850019"/>
<p>(4)</p>
<p>The water-supply for the Appledore hotel is obtained by means of a<lb/>
2&prime; pipe, from a spring about 1 1&sol;4 miles distant, and quite remote from any<lb/>
source of contamination. Its pressure is sufficient to carry it to any<lb/>
part of the building. I visited this spring and ascertained from inspection<lb/>
that approximately, one half of its flow is being used at present.</p>
<p>The Pavilion hotel is supplied from a very large spring, about 100 yards<lb/>
distant, the water being delivered by means of its own pressure.</p>
<p>As the result of my inspection, I am of the opinion that although an<lb/>
abundant supply of pure water could be easily obtained, none of the<lb/>
buildings located at Natural Bridge, Va. are suitable for hospital purposes;<lb/>
the rooms, with few exceptions; being quite small, and ceilings low. An-<lb/>
other objection to its selection for a hospital site is the distance from<lb/>
the Rail Road, viz:-three miles. An ordinary country road, rather rough<lb/>
in places, leads from the station to Natural Bridge. The latter is at an<lb/>
elevation of about 400 feet above the Rail Road, so that there is a grad-<lb/>
ual ascent for a greater part of the way.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Walter Reed,</signed>
Major &amp; Surgeon,<lb/>
U. S. Army.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
