<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t01936001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from P.S. Rossiter to the Surgeon General, October 1, 1899</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01936001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1899-10-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">Cabana Fortress (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Ludlow (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1899-10-01">October 1, 1899</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01936001</idno>
<title>Letter from P.S. Rossiter to the Surgeon General, October 1, 1899</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Rossiter reports on the recent epidemic of yellow fever at Cabana Fortress in Havana. He describes the patients and their symptoms as well as the disinfection of clothing, bedding, and property.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1899-10-01">
<head>Letter from P.S. Rossiter to the Surgeon General, October 1, 1899</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01936001"/>
<opener>
Ac<lb/>
K<lb/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
<dateline>
Field Hospital,<lb/>
Camp Ludlow<lb/>
<date value="1899-10-01">October, 1st, 1899.</date>
</dateline>
To the Surgeon General, U.S. Army,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.,<lb/>
<salute>Sir:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>In <unclear>complance</unclear> with par. 119. <unclear>Manual</unclear> for the Medical Department, 1899, I have the<lb/>
honor to make the following report of the recent epidemic of Yellow Fever <unclear>occurring</unclear><lb/>
at Cabana Fortress, Havana, Cuba. and at Camp Ludlow near Cabana Fortress to which the<lb/>
occupants of that post were removed to check the progress of the infection.</p>
<p>On August 10th, 1899, Priv. <unclear>Jas</unclear>. <unclear>Dougharty,</unclear> <unclear>Batt</unclear>. &ldquo;B&rdquo;. 2nd, Art. presented himself at<lb/>
the Post Hospital having <add>had</add> a slight chill at 12 M. associated with <unclear>nausea</unclear> and vomiting<lb/>
and intense pain in the head and lumbar region. Temperature on admission 103 <unclear>F.</unclear><lb/>
Pulse 110. Temperature throughout the following 24 hours ranged between 102 and <unclear>103.5</unclear><lb/>
Pulse 110 to 80. His conjunctivae were greatly injected, face and neck congested<lb/>
and gums slightly puffy. A diagnosis of Yellow Fever was made and albumen 4% appear-<lb/>
ing in the <unclear>urin</unclear> on the following morning, he was transferred to Las Animas Hospital.<lb/>
This <unclear>man</unclear> positively denies having been absent from the post for a period of 10 days<lb/>
previous to his attack, and the Battery records corroborate his statement.</p>
<p>At 8.30. P.M. Aug. 11th, Priv. Timothy <unclear>Realy</unclear>, Batt. &ldquo;<unclear>E</unclear>&rdquo;, was admitted to the hospital.<lb/>
He had had a slight chill at 11 A.M. <unclear>nausea</unclear>, no vomiting, intense <unclear>pain</unclear> in head and<lb/>
lumber region. Temperature on admission, 102.8 E. Pulse 105, conjunctivae <unclear>suffased</unclear>.<lb/>
<unclear>Face</unclear> and neck congested. During the following 20 hours his temperature ranged between<lb/>
101.5 and <unclear>103.5 F</unclear>. Pulse steadily falling to 70. A diagnosis of Yellow Fever was<lb/>
made and on Aug. 12th, he was transferred to Las Animas Hospital. No albumen appeared<lb/>
in his urine before his transfer.</p>
<p>The clothing of these men and the barrack rooms in which they slept were at<lb/>
once disinfected with <unclear>Formaldehyde</unclear> and Bichloride of Mercury solution; also the other<lb/>
barrack rooms, Officers quarters, store rooms etc.</p>
<p>No other suspicious cases occurred until Aug. 20th, when Priv. Reed Lucas, Batt. <unclear>K</unclear>.<lb/>
presented himself at the Hospital at 2 P.M., Temp. <unclear>103.8 F</unclear>. Pulse 114.</p>
<p>Corp. Henry <unclear>E</unclear>. Clay, Batt. K, had been sick in quarters and Hospital, off and on for<lb/>
two weeks on account of acute <del><unclear></unclear></del> Bronchitis. On Aug. 20th, he was re-admitted<lb/>
for the same cause, Temp. normal, Pulse 50. At <unclear>3</unclear> P.M. that date he had a slight chill<lb/>
Temp. rapidly rising to 102.6 F. Pulse <unclear>95</unclear>. Vomiting occurred at 6 P.M.</p>
<p>For the following 24 hours, his temp. ranged between 103 and 104 F. Pulse falling<lb/>
to 82. During this time Priv. Luces' temperature had <unclear>rises</unclear> to 104.8 F. Pulse falling<lb/>
to 84. Albumen appeared in the urine of both men on the evening of the 21st, A diag<lb/>
nosis of Yellow Fever was made, and on the following morning they were transferred.</p>
<p>On Aug. 22nd, at 7 A.M. Priv. Clifford <unclear>Calhoun</unclear>, Batt. <unclear>B</unclear>, was admitted to the Hospital,<lb/>
Temp. 101.5 F. Pulse 102. He had a slight chill at 3 <unclear></unclear> (A.M.) <unclear>nausea</unclear> and vomiting,<lb/>
headache, and pain in the back and legs. At 12 <unclear>N</unclear>. and 3 P.M. of the same day, the<lb/>
vomited matter contained 1-2 ounce of bright blood.</p>
<p>During the following 24 hours his temperature ranged between 100.8 and 103 F.<lb/>
Pulse steadily falling to 45. On Aug. 24th, On Aug. 24th, he was transferred, at which<lb/>
time his urine showed a trace of <unclear>albumen</unclear>.</p>
<p>On Aug. 25th, at 6 P.M. Priv. <unclear>Ed</unclear>. <unclear>Vragel</unclear>, Batt. I, was admitted to the Hospital. He had<lb/>
had a <del><unclear></unclear></del> chill, nausea and vomiting at at 1 A.M. but made no mention <unclear>thereof</unclear>, until<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f01936002"/>
the time of his admission to the Hospital, at which time he had Temp. 103.4 F. Pulse<lb/>
120. On the following morning his Temp. was 102.5 F. Pulse 88; albumen 2% showing in<lb/>
the urine; whereupon he was transferred.</p>
<p>On Aug. 26th, Sgt. Richard Graves, Batt E, was admitted to the Hospital at 7 A.M. Temp.<lb/>
102 F. Pulse 106, chill at 9 P.M., headache, pain in the back and legs, eyes markedly<lb/>
injected. During the following 48 hours his temperature ranged between 99.6 and 102.4<lb/>
F. Albumen appeared in the urine on Aug. 27th, and on Aug. 28th, he was transferred.</p>
<p>It having been decided by the Commanding General, Dept. of Havana, Chief Surgeon, and<lb/>
Post Surgeons that, in order to check the spread of the infection, it would be ad-<lb/>
visable to move the Command into camp, the move was begun on Aug. 28th, and a camp<lb/>
was pitched about three quarters of a mile N.E. of Cabana, and about 200 yds. from the<lb/>
Gulf, the men sleeping in camp the night of Aug. 29th,.</p>
<p>Several days were required for the disinfection and removal of clothing and<lb/>
property and, in doing this, details from the various batteries were obliged to enter<lb/>
the Fort at intervals, until Sept. 3rd,, when the gates were closed and locked.</p>
<p>On Aug. 29th, Priv. Clyde Sheets, Batt. I, appeared at the Hospital, headache and nausea<lb/>
no chill; he was admitted at 3 P.M. Temp. 103 F. Pulse 112. No albumen appeared in his<lb/>
urine before his transfer on Aug. 30th, P.M.</p>
<p>On Aug. <unclear>21st</unclear>, at 8 A.M. Priv. Chas. Shumway, Batt. E. appeared at sick call; slight<lb/>
chill at 2 A.M. nausea and vomiting, intense headache and pain in lumbar region, Temp.<lb/>
102.2 F. Pulse 95. He was transferred the same afternoon.</p>
<p>Priv. Jesse Hilton, Batt. E. was admitted to the Hospital at 11 P.M. Aug. 31st, Temp.<lb/>
103,6 F. Pulse 104. He had a chill at 9 P.M. while on guard, followed by nausea but no<lb/>
vomiting. During the following 36 hours his temperature ranged between 101.2 and<lb/>
104 F. Pulse falling to 70.</p>
<p>Sgt. Newton Goodwin, Batt. I, and Priv. John Thorsby, <unclear>B</unclear>.C. were admitted to the Hos-<lb/>
pital at Sick Call, Sept. 1st, Goodwin, Temp. 102.4 F. Pulse 84, no chill, <unclear>conjunctivea</unclear><lb/>
injected, slight nausea, Temp. during 36 hours 100.6 and 103 F. Pulse falling to 65.</p>
<p>Priv. Thorsby had been employed in nursing about two thirds of the cases of<lb/>
Yellow Fever which had been admitted to the Hospital, as he was the best suited member<lb/>
of the H.C. for such nursing. Great care was exercised however to prevent infection<lb/>
of nurses and others; methods will be described elsewhere in this report.</p>
<p>On admission his temperature was 103.4 F. Pulse 118. Slight chill at 3 A.M., con-<lb/>
junctivea injected, slight nausea and vomiting. Temp. and Pulse falling during 36 hours<lb/>
to 101 F. and 58. Albumen appeared in the urine of these cases on the morning of<lb/>
Sept. 2nd, on which day they were transferred.</p>
<p>On Sept. 3rd, were admitted four cases; Albert J. Adams, a civilian connected with<lb/>
the Y.M.C.A. and living with the Command, at 7 A.M.; Priv. J. Rogers, Batt. E. 6 P.M.; Corp.<lb/>
Mitchell, Batt. B, at 9 A.M.; and Priv. Daniel Coleman, Batt, K, at 4 P.M. Adams-no chill,<lb/>
intense headache and pain in calves of legs, conjunctivea slightly injected, Temp. 102 F<lb/>
Pulse 106, rising during 30 hours to 103.4 F. and Pulse falling to 54. Albumen 12% appea<lb/>
appeared on the following morning; he immediately entered a semi-comatose state from<lb/>
which he was never fully aroused. Transferred the following day.</p>
<p>Mitchell-no chill, conjunctivae slightly injected, slight headache and pain in<lb/>
lumbar region, Temp. 102 F. Pulse 70, falling during 30 hours to 101.4 F. and 54. Albumen<lb/>
2% appeared in the urine the following morning, during which evening he was transferre</p>
<p>Coleman-no chill, no nausea, intense headache and pain in lubar region coming on<lb/>
at 3.30 P.M. Temp. 103.8 F. Pulse 140, falling to 101.5 F. and 105 during 48 hours<lb/>
when he was transferred. No albumen before transfer.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f01936003"/>
Rogers- slight chill at 3 P.M. headache, nausea and vomiting, conjunctivea injected,<lb/>
face and thorax congested. Temp. 104.2 F. Pulse 120. During the following 36 hours<lb/>
his temperature ranged between 103 and 104.6 F. and pulse fall to 106. Albumen 5%<lb/>
appeared on the morning of Sept. 4th, and increased to 6% on Sept. 5th, when he<lb/>
was transferred.</p>
<p>On Sept. 4th, were admitted, Priv. F. <unclear>E. Cilliams</unclear>, Batt. <unclear>B</unclear>. at <unclear>8</unclear> A.M., <unclear>Crisance</unclear> Sgt.<lb/>
Z. T. Woodall at 11 P.M., Priv. Ernest Rubeck, Batt. K, at <unclear>13</unclear> M. and Priv. Linsay M. Cocksay,<lb/>
Batt. K. at <unclear>3</unclear> P.M.</p>
<p>Williams.-chill at 4 A.M., nausea and vomiting, intense pain in head and legs,<lb/>
Temp. 104.6, Pulse 90. Temperature and pulse falling during 36 hours to 103.6 F. and<lb/>
70. Albumen 2% appeared on the second morning, upon which day he was transferred.</p>
<p>Woodall.-no chill, slight headache, no nausea, or vomiting, Temp. 102.<unclear>5</unclear> F. Pulse<lb/>
108. He gave a history of chronic interstitial nephritis and, during the day, the<lb/>
urine showed 60% of albumen. Temp. and pulse falling to 101.8 F. and 73 during 31<lb/>
hours at which time he was transferred.</p>
<p>Rubeck.-chill at 9 P.M., nausea and vomiting, increasing prostration, Temp. 102.4<lb/>
F. Pulse <unclear></unclear> 100, falling to 101.8 F. and 69 during 30 hours. Conjunctivae injected,<lb/>
albumen 2% on morning of 5th, upon which day he was transferred.</p>
<p><unclear>Cooksay</unclear>.-no chill, headache and pain in back and legs coming on during after--<lb/>
noon, no vomiting. Temp. 102.8 Pulse 104. falling to normal and 62 on the evening of<lb/>
Sept. 5th, rising again on the morning of Sept. 6th, to 101.4 F. and 100, and ranging<lb/>
between 103.4 and 102 F. and pulse falling to 70 until 3 P.M. Sept. 8th, when he was<lb/>
transferred.</p>
<p>On Sept. 5th, 2nd, Lieut. Stanley D. Embick, Batt. B. while visiting the city on<lb/>
business was wet through by the rain and his clothing allowed to dry on him. One<lb/>
hour later he had a sever chill and a half hour later another chill. At the close<lb/>
of the second chill, 4 P.M. Temp. 101 F. Pulse 100. Intense headache and pain in lumbar<lb/>
region, nausea and vomiting, conjunctivae profusely injected. Temp. rising at 6 P.M. to<lb/>
104.4 F. and pulse falling to 90. Temperature falling to <unclear>102.6</unclear> F. and pulse rising<lb/>
to 95 on the following day, when he was transferred.</p>
<p>On Sept. 6th, Priv. Sernhardt Kraemer, Batt. K, appeared at sick call. Slight chill<del>l</del><lb/>
at <unclear>9</unclear> P.M., Temp. on admission 100 F. Pulse 102, conjunctivae slightly congested.<lb/>
Vomiting occurred soon after admission, Temp. rising to 103.8 F. and pulse falling to<lb/>
78. Albumen, a trace appeared on the following morning, temperature falling to 102.8<lb/>
F. pulse remaining at 78. Transferred on Sept. 7th,.</p>
<p>The last case of the epidemic was that of Hans Hansen, Priv. Batt E, who present-<lb/>
ed himself at the Hospital at 4 P.M. Sept. 8th, Temp. 102, Pulse 108, no chill; intense<lb/>
headache and pain in back coming on about 2 P.M. Conjunctivae well injected. Vomiting<lb/>
occurred twice during Sept. 9th,. Temp. fell 99 F. at 9 P.M. on Sept. 8th, pulse 70;<lb/>
ranging between 99 F. and 100.6 F. throughout the follwing day. On Sept. 10th, the<lb/>
temperature rose to 102.8 F. pulse remaining at 70, and from thence gradually<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> fell reaching normal on Sept. 11th. Albumen 5% appeared on the morning of<lb/>
the 10th, increased to 10% on the 11th, and then gradually decreased, disappearing<lb/>
on Sept. 15th. Prostration did not occur to a marked degree.</p>
<p>This patient was not transferred, but was treated in an isolated tent near the<lb/>
Hospital. A mercurial purgative and <unclear>Quinia Sul. gr.xxi</unclear> were given him on admission,<lb/>
followed by Magnesium Sul. 1-2 oz. the following morning. Nothing was permitted to<lb/>
enter his stomach thereafter except iced Appollinaris water until Sept. 13th, when<lb/>
a milk diet was cautiously commenced and gradually increased.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f01936004"/>
He was discharged from the Hospital as well on Sept. 21st,.</p>
<p>Before moving into camp all the personal effects of officers and men-with the<lb/>
exception of the actually worn by them-, all bedding, Quartermaster property and<lb/>
clothing were exposed in sealed casemates for four hours to the action of formal-<lb/>
dehyde. then hauled into camp.</p>
<p>The men, before opening their lockers, stripped in the Company streets and made<lb/>
their remaining clothing into bundles which were hauled into the Fort and disinfected<lb/>
in the same manner. They then entered their tents and put on their previously disin-<lb/>
fected clothing from their lockers.</p>
<p>All possible precautions were taken to prevent infection of the Hospital<lb/>
quarters and attendants.</p>
<p>The bedding of the patients was changed at least every 24 hours, and immediately<lb/>
immersed in a 1-1000 Bi-chloride solution. All feces and vomited matters were<lb/>
received in an 8% Carbolic solution.</p>
<p>Nurses, after handling a patient were instructed to wash their hands in a 1-1000<lb/>
Bi-chloride solution. After each patient was removed from the room, it was disinfec-<lb/>
ted with formaldehyde and Bi-chloride solution. The mattresses, blankets, bedding, etc.<lb/>
used by the patients, and the clothing and effects of the deceased were burned by<lb/>
order of the Chief Surgeon and Post Commander.</p>
<p>The route by which infection entered the command is doubtful.</p>
<p>The Battalion had been quartered in Cabana Fortress since May 15th, two months<lb/>
and twenty days before the first case of Yellow Fever appeared. No decided climatic<lb/>
changes had taken place during that period which could have had any effect upon the<lb/>
development of the infection.</p>
<p>About two thirds of the command was composed of recruits who had arrived in<lb/>
Cuba after June 10th, but no dispropotion existed among the men attacked by the<lb/>
fever between the recruits and the men who had been on the island since January 1st.<lb/>
All the men attacked stated positively (and the Post records confirm their state-<lb/>
ments) that they had not been off the reservation for at least ten days previous to<lb/>
entering the Hospital.</p>
<p>The slow and insidious progress of the epidemic, together with the length of<lb/>
time during which the command had occupied the Fortress, previous to the first<lb/>
appearance of the Fever, would lead us to beleive that the infection had been intro-<lb/>
duced from without, but, when we consider the fact that none of the men attacked had<lb/>
been away from the Post for a period of ten days previous to the onset of the diseas<lb/>
that the cases appeared in &ldquo;B&rdquo; Battery, then &ldquo;<unclear>B</unclear>&rdquo;, then &ldquo;K&rdquo;, then &ldquo;B&rdquo; again, and then &ldquo;I&rdquo;,<lb/>
the barrack rooms of the Batteries not being in the sequence of infection, that none<lb/>
of the Corral men nor Q.M. employes, who did not sleep in the Post, were attacked, and<lb/>
that no case occurred after communication with the Fort had been cut off for six<lb/>
days, I beleive the only conclusion at which we can arrive is that the infection was<lb/>
derived from somewhere within the Fort.</p>
<p>Of the 23 cases occurring during this epidemic, 10 had their onset between 6 A.M<lb/>
and 6 P.M. Eight had no manifestation of an initiatory chill. Abumen appeared in the<lb/>
urine of 13 of the cases within 30 hours from the onset; in 3, within 40 hours; in<lb/>
4, within 70 hours, and in one case not for 3 days.</p>
<p>Of the 23 men attacked, 8 died, a mortality of 34.8%.</p>
<p>Of those who died, only 2 had been addicted to the use of alcoholic liquors; 6<lb/>
were under 30 years of age. All were previously strong and hearty. In none of these<lb/>
cases did congestion of the gums appear to a marked degree before their transfer.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f01936005"/>
One case wherein infection was acquired in Cabana Fortress did not develop until<lb/>
arrival in the United States. Prvt. Hy.S. Waggoner, Batt. I, bought his discharge and<lb/>
left the Post on Aug. 20th. Upon arrival in New York he was feeling badly, but was<lb/>
allowed to his home at Vincennes, Ind. He died the day after his arrival there, Sept.<lb/>
1st, and, upon post-mortem, a diagnosis of yellow fever was made. This information<lb/>
is derived from the Vincennes papers, no official notice of it having been received<lb/>
here.</p>
<p>Pvt. Dougherty, after being returnef to the command from Las Animas Hospital was<lb/>
admitted to the Field Hospital on account of his diet. As he was allowed to walk<lb/>
about the camp for <del><unclear>excercise</unclear></del> exercise, he had been carefully warned to eat nothing<lb/>
except the diet furnished at the hospital. Four days after his return, disregarding<lb/>
the warning, he messed with his battery, afterwards going to the Canteen and eating<lb/>
cakes and a pound of raisins and drinking soda pop and native brandy. Since that<lb/>
night his temperature has ranged between 102 and 104.5 F. and he has fallen into<lb/>
a typhoid condition from which he will probably not recover. (Widal reaction nega-<lb/>
tive).</p>
<p>Before concluding this report, I cannot neglect to express my gratitude for the<lb/>
efficient services of Actg. Asst. Surgeon M.A.W. Shockley, my confrere throughout the<lb/>
epidemic, and my admiration for the conduct of this detachment of the Hospital<lb/>
Corps. The Corps men were non-immunes, and, when I asked for volunteers among them<lb/>
to nurse the Yellow Fever cases. every one instantly volunteered and conducted<lb/>
themselves with an earnest and cheerful devotion to their duties throughout as<lb/>
great a danger to themselves as was faced by any of our troops in battle.</p>
<p>In concluding. Sir. I have the honor to remain.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly<lb/>
Your obedient servant</salute>
<signed>(Signed) P. S. Rossiter<lb/>
Actg. Asst. Surgeon, U.S.A.<lb/>
Surgeon in Charge</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
