<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t01952001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Article: Life-History of the Parasites of Malaria, by Ronald Ross, [1901]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Ross, Ronald</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>01952001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1901-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1901-00-00">1901</date>
<idno rend="suppress">01952001</idno>
<title>Article: Life-History of the Parasites of Malaria, by Ronald Ross, [1901]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ross discusses the parasites that cause malarial fevers. A note on the article indicates that it was published in Nature in 1901.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1901-00-00">
<head>Article: Life-History of the Parasites of Malaria, by Ronald Ross, [1901]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f01952001"/>
<p>Published in nature 1901 <unclear>(i)</unclear><lb/>
3 August 1899 P. 322 Vol 60 no 1553<lb/>
<hi>47</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">LIFE-HISTORY OF THE PARASITES OF<lb/>
MALARIA</hi>.</p>
<p>THE parasites which cause malarial fevers in human<lb/>
beings belong to a very homogeneous group, other<lb/>
species of which are found in certain bats and birds.<lb/>
The life-history of the three species of this group which<lb/>
have been completely studied is as follows. The youngest<lb/>
parasites exist as am&oelig;bul&aelig; or myxopods within the<lb/>
red blood corpuscles of the vertebrate host. Each<lb/>
am&oelig;bula possesses a nucleus and nucleolus; and its<lb/>
movements vary in extent and rapidity with the species,<lb/>
but, in the case of birds, never encroach upon the<lb/>
nucleus of the corpuscle. The am&oelig;bul&aelig; increase in<lb/>
size; and, as they do so, tend to lose their movements<lb/>
and to accumulate in their ectoplasm certain black<lb/>
granules, the pigment or melanin, which are the product<lb/>
of assimilation of the h&aelig;moglobin of the corpuscle. In<lb/>
from one to several days the parasites reach their<lb/>
highest development within the vertebrate host, and<lb/>
become either (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) sporocytes or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) gametocytes.</p>
<p>The sporocytes, which are produced asexually, contain<lb/>
spores which vary in number according to the species.<lb/>
The spores do not possess any appreciable cell-wall.<lb/>
When they are mature the corpuscle which contains<lb/>
them bursts and allows them to fall into the serum. They<lb/>
then attach themselves to fresh blood corpuscles, and<lb/>
continue the propagation of the parasites indefinitely in<lb/>
the vertebrate host. The residuum of the sporocyte,<lb/>
consisting chiefly of the pigment, is taken up by the<lb/>
phagocytes of the host for eventual disposal in the host.</p>
<p>The gametocytes, while in the blood of the vertebrate<lb/>
host, are still contained in the shell of the corpuscle.<lb/>
In some species their general form and appearance<lb/>
is very like that of the sporocytes before the<lb/>
spores are differentiated; in another, however, they<lb/>
possess a special crescentic form. They continue to<lb/>
circulate in the blood for some days, or even weeks<lb/>
(according to the species) without change; but when<lb/>
they are drawn into the alimentary canal of certain suc-<lb/>
torial insects, they undergo further development. In a<lb/>
few minutes after finding themselves in their new position,<lb/>
they break from the enclosing corpuscle by a kind of<lb/>
expansion, swell up slightly, and then commence their<lb/>
sexual functions. The male gametocytes emit a variable<lb/>
number of microgametes, which escape into the serum of<lb/>
the ingested blood, leaving behind a residuum consisting<lb/>
chiefly of pigment--as in the case of the sporocytes. The<lb/>
individual microgametes are delicate, but very active<lb/>
filaments, consisting chiefly of chromatin, and sometimes<lb/>
seen to have a slight swelling at one point of their length<lb/>
--in the middle, when free, according to my observations.<lb/>
After escape from the male gametocyte, the microgametes<lb/>
seek the female gametocytes, which consist each of a<lb/>
single motionless macrogamete. One microgamete now<lb/>
enters bodily into a macrogamete and fertilises it, pro-<lb/>
ducing a zygote.</p>
<p>The further history of the zygote has been traced, as<lb/>
regards three species of this group of parasites, in certain<lb/>
kinds of mosquitoes. After being fertilised, it acquires<lb/>
the power of escaping the phagocytes of the ingested<lb/>
blood which surround it, of working its way through the<lb/>
mass of blood, of passing through the thickness of the<lb/>
stomach (middle intestine) of the mosquito, and of<lb/>
affixing itself to the outer surface of the organ. Here<lb/>
the zygotes are first found as oval cells about 8-10 &micro; in<lb/>
diameter. They still contain the granules of pigment<lb/>
which the macrogametes possessed before fertilisation.<lb/>
Growing rapidly, they soon acquire a capsule, and begin<lb/>
to protrude into the body cavity of the mosquito. From<lb/>
an early period the nucleus divides into a number of<lb/>
portions--zygotomeres--each containing a fragment of<lb/>
chromatin. As growth advances, the zygotomeres be-<lb/>
come spherical blastophores, bearing each a large<lb/>
number of delicate, filamentous zygotoblasts on their<lb/>
external surface--each zygotoblast being affixed to the<lb/>
surface of the blastophore by one extremity. As maturity<lb/>
is approached the zygote, though still attached to the<lb/>
outer wall of the insect's stomach, protrudes freely into<lb/>
the body cavity; its pigment tends to disappear; and<lb/>
lastly, the blastophores disappear, leaving the capsule<lb/>
packed with thousands of zygotoblasts. Maturity is<lb/>
reached in from one to three weeks, according to the<lb/>
external temperature, when the zygote reaches a size of<lb/>
60 &micro; or more. The capsule then ruptures, pouring the<lb/>
zygotoblasts into the insect's blood.</p>
<p>The zygotoblasts are now seen to be delicate flagel-<lb/>
lul&aelig; or mastigopods, about 12-16 &micro; in length, with the<lb/>
chromatin and one or two unstained areas in the middle,<lb/>
and two opposite tapering flagella. I have not, however,<lb/>
observed any notable movement in them, probably on<lb/>
account of the necessary dissecting medium. After<lb/>
being discharged into the insect's blood, these bodies<lb/>
are carried away by the current into all parts of the<lb/>
tissues, and finally effect an entry into the large grape-<lb/>
like cells of the salivary gland--especially the cells of<lb/>
the short middle lobe--where they accumulate in very<lb/>
large numbers. From the cells of this gland they pass<lb/>
into the duct which runs to the extremity of the middle<lb/>
stylet, the lingula, and thence escape during haustellation<lb/>
into the blood of a new vertebrate host. Here, it must<lb/>
be supposed, the flagellul&aelig; attack the corpuscles and<lb/>
become the intra-corpuscular am&oelig;bul&aelig; with which we<lb/>
started.</p>
<p>Four points require notice. (1) There are reasons<lb/>
for supposing that the gametocytes are or may be pro-<lb/>
duced by the conjugation of two or more am&oelig;bul&aelig; in<lb/>
one corpuscle. (2) The gametocytes of several species<lb/>
show, after escape from the corpuscle, one or more<lb/>
minute spherical bodies attached to their margin; which<lb/>
I assume to represent polar bodies. (3) The young<lb/>
zygote of at least one species (of crows) possesses,<lb/>
shortly after fertilisation, somewhat active powers of<lb/>
locomotion. (4) The mature zygotes of at least two<lb/>
species often contain large, brown, thick-shelled, cylin-<lb/>
drical bodies, the nature of which has not yet been<lb/>
elucidated, and which may be parasitic fungi of the<lb/>
mosquito.</p>
<p>A brief history of how these facts came to be ascer-<lb/>
tained may be of interest. Laveran discovered the<lb/>
human parasites in 1880; and Danilewsky those of<lb/>
birds, some years later. Golgi established the law of<lb/>
endogenous reproduction by means of spores, in 1885;<lb/>
and noted the differences in the various human species.<lb/>
Later, several Italian writers observed the distinction<lb/>
between the sporocytes and the gametocytes, but failed<lb/>
to understand the nature and object of these latter<lb/>
forms. The escape of the microgametes can be wit-<lb/>
nessed <hi rend="italic">in vitro</hi>; and a dispute now arose as to the<lb/>
meaning of these bodies. Antolisei, Grassi, Bignami,<lb/>
Labb&eacute; and others held that they are products of death<lb/>
and degeneration <hi rend="italic">in vitro</hi>. On the other hand, Laveran,<lb/>
Danilewsky and Mannaberg supposed them to represent<lb/>
the highest development of the organisms; while the<lb/>
last writer thought that they were meant for an ex-<lb/>
ogenous saprophytic existence--without, however, sug-<lb/>
gesting the mode of their escape. In 1894 Manson<lb/>
concluded that the gametocytes are intended to continue<lb/>
the species outside the vertebrate host; and that they<lb/>
escape into the stomach of a suctorial insect, and then<lb/>
give rise to flagellul&aelig;--as he considered the micro-<lb/>
gametes to be--which in turn develop in the tissues of<lb/>
the insect. He founded these views chiefly on the fact<lb/>
that the microgametes escape from the gametocyte only<lb/>
after abstraction of the blood from the vertebrate host.<lb/>
Laveran had already surmised that the mosquito is the<lb/>
alternative host of the human parasites; and Manson<lb/>
now claimed the mosquito as the suctorial insect<lb/>
referred to.</p>
<p>Early in 1895 I attacked the subject experimentally in<lb/>
Parasites<lb/>
2<lb/>
India, on the lines laid down by Manson. Owing to the<lb/>
difficulty of the investigation and to the use of wrong<lb/>
species of mosquitoes, I failed for more than two years<lb/>
in reaching positive results. In August 1897, however,<lb/>
on employing two species of Anopheles fed on patients<lb/>
containing the crescentic gametocytes, I found the zygotes<lb/>
in various stages of growth attached to the wall of the<lb/>
insects' stomach. My work was now interrupted; but<lb/>
next year I succeeded in following out the life-history of<lb/>
the zygotes of one of the parasites of birds in their de-<lb/>
velopment in <hi rend="italic">Culex pipiens</hi>. The zygotoblasts were<lb/>
found in the salivary glands of the mosquitoes; and<lb/>
lastly, in July 1898, I succeeded in infecting a large<lb/>
number of healthy birds by the bites of infected insects.</p>
<p>Meanwhile (1898) MacCallum had discovered the true<lb/>
nature of the microgametes by actually witnessing the<lb/>
sexual act <hi rend="italic">in vitro</hi>; while Metchnikoff and Simond had<lb/>
found microgamates also in <hi rend="italic">Coccidium oviforme</hi> and<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">C. salimandrae</hi>; so that the exact relationship between<lb/>
the gametocytes in the blood of the vertebrate (inter-<lb/>
mediary) hosts and the zygotes found by me in the<lb/>
mosquitoes (definitive hosts) became quite evident.</p>
<p>My results were published by Manson in August 1898,<lb/>
and were confirmed by Daniels, of the Malaria Commis-<lb/>
sion of the Royal Society in December. It was now easy<lb/>
to extend my observations to other species of the group,<lb/>
a work, however, which I was unable to undertake. In<lb/>
November and December 1898, Grassi, Bignami and<lb/>
Bastianelli cultivated two of the human parasites in a<lb/>
third species of Anopheles, <hi rend="italic">A. claviger</hi>, Fabr., and suc-<lb/>
ceeded in infecting several healthy persons. Shortly<lb/>
afterwards Koch confirmed the principal observations<lb/>
which had been made.</p>
<p>If we can exterminate the malaria-bearing species of<lb/>
mosquito in a locality, we may expect to prevent the pro-<lb/>
pagation of the parasites there; I trust, therefore, that<lb/>
these investigations will not remain without practical<lb/>
results.</p>
<p>It may be useful to add a note regarding the somewhat<lb/>
confused matter of the classification and nomenclature of<lb/>
the various species. I divide those of men and birds into<lb/>
two genera, named as follows:--</p>
<p>Family: H&AElig;MAM&OElig;BID&AElig;, Wasielewski.</p>
<p>Genus I. <hi rend="italic">Haemomoeba</hi>, Grassi and Feletti. <hi rend="italic">The mature<lb/>
gametocytes are similar in form to the mature<lb/>
sporocytes before the spores have been differentiated</hi>.</p>
<p>Species I: <hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba Danilewskii</hi>, Grassi and Feletti. Syn.:<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Laverania Danilewskii</hi>, Grassi and Feletti, in<lb/>
part; <hi rend="italic">Halteridium Danilewskii</hi>, Labb&eacute;; &amp;c.<lb/>
Several varieties--possibly distinct species. Parasite<lb/>
of pigeons, jays, crows, &amp;c.</p>
<p>Species 2: <hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba relicta</hi>, Grassi and Feletti. Syn.:<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba relicta</hi> &plus; <hi rend="italic">H. subpraecox</hi> &plus; <hi rend="italic">H. subim-<lb/>
maculata</hi>, Grassi and Feletti; <hi rend="italic">Proteosoma Grassii</hi>,<lb/>
Labb&eacute;; &amp;c. Parasite of sparrows, larks, &amp;c.</p>
<p>Species 3: <hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba malariae</hi>, Grassi and Feletti. Syn.:<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba Laverani</hi>, Labb&eacute;, in part. Parasite<lb/>
of quartan fever of man.</p>
<p>Species 4: <hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba vivax</hi>, Grassi and Feletti. Syn.:<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba Laverani</hi>, Labb&eacute;, in part. Parasite<lb/>
of tertian fever of man.</p>
<p>Genus II: <hi rend="italic">Haemomenas</hi>, gen. nov. Syn.: <hi rend="italic">Laverania</hi>, in part<lb/>
&plus; <hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba</hi>, in part, Grassi and Feletti. <hi rend="italic">The<lb/>
gametocytes have a special crescentic form</hi>.</p>
<p>Species: <hi rend="italic">Haemomenas praecox</hi>, Grassi and Feletti. Syn.:<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba praecox</hi> &plus; <hi rend="italic">H. immaculata</hi> &plus; <hi rend="italic">Laverania<lb/>
malariae</hi>, Grassi and Feletti; <hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba Laver-<lb/>
ani</hi>, Labb&eacute;, in part; &amp;c. Several varieties--pos-<lb/>
sibly distinct species. Parasite of the irregular,<lb/>
remittent, pernicious or &aelig;stivo-autumnal fever of<lb/>
man.</p>
<p>The two species lately discovered by Dionisi in bats<lb/>
appear to belong, one to one genus, and the other to the<lb/>
other genus. Two species described in frogs do not con-<lb/>
tain pigment, and require further study. Grassi and<lb/>
Feletti's arrangement is very confused, chiefly on<lb/>
account of their combining <hi rend="italic">H. Danilewskii</hi> with the<lb/>
crescentic gametocytes of <hi rend="italic">H. praecox</hi> in a separate<lb/>
genus, <hi rend="italic">Laverania</hi>. Labb&eacute; admits only one human<lb/>
species, and yet erects two genera for the avian species.<lb/>
The double spore-clusters of <hi rend="italic">H. Danilewskii</hi>, on which<lb/>
he lays much stress, are not always found, and are at<lb/>
the best due, I think, merely to the presence of the<lb/>
nucleus compressing so large a parasite. There is<lb/>
little to justify generic differences between the four<lb/>
species of <hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba</hi>. On the other hand, the last<lb/>
species given above is sharply divided from the rest.</p>
<p>The zygotes of three species have been found to<lb/>
develop in mosquitoes as follows:--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba relicta</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Culex pipiens</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Haemamoeba vivax</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Anopheles claviger</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Haemomenas praecox</hi> in two undetermined species of<lb/>
Anopheles in India, and in <hi rend="italic">Anopheles claviger</hi> in Italy.</p>
<p>The development is the same in all, but slight differ-<lb/>
ences in details have been noticed between <hi rend="italic">H. vivax</hi> and<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">H. falcipara</hi> in the mosquito.</p>
<p>The terminology employed above has been adopted in<lb/>
consultation with Prof. Herdman, F.R.S. Some of it<lb/>
has already been used in this connection by Mesnil, and<lb/>
Grassi and Dionisi. Nuttall has recently given a very<lb/>
full account of the subject in the <hi rend="italic">Centralblatt f&uuml;r<lb/>
Bakteriologie</hi>.<lb/>
RONALD ROSS.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
