<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="t02008001"> 
<teiHeader type="aacr2"> 
<fileDesc> 
<titleStmt> 
<title type="245">Military Orders regarding spread of yellow fever, March 5, 1900</title> 
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title> 
<author>Harbord, J. G.</author> 
<respStmt> 
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp> 
<name>Innodata Inc</name> 
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp> 
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/> 
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/> 
University of Virginia Health System<lb/> 
P.O. Box 800722<lb/> 
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722 
</name> 
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp> 
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/> 
University of Virginia Library<lb/> 
</name> 
</respStmt> 
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt> 
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the 
University of Virginia Health System</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace> 
<idno>02008001</idno> 
<availability> 
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p> 
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p> 
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability> 
<date>2003</date> 
</publicationStmt> 
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection 
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno> 
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc> 
</fileDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-03-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc> 
<change><date></date> 
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt> 
<item></item></change> 
</revisionDesc> 
</teiHeader> 
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Santiago (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-03-05">March 5, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02008001</idno>
<title>Military Orders regarding spread of yellow fever, March 5, 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report guards against the introduction and spread of yellow fever. The symptoms of yellow fever are clearly outlined.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="military orders" n="1900-03-05">
<head>Military Orders regarding spread of yellow fever, March 5, 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02008001"/>
<p>FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN</p>
<p>YF</p>
<p>CIRCULAR,<lb/>
No. 2.<lb/>
}</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS DEPARTMENT OF<lb/>
SANTIAGO AND PUERTO PRINCIPE.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Santiago, Cuba, March 5, 1900</hi>.</p>
<p>[Prepared by the Chief Surgeon.]</p>
<p>In order to guard against the introduction and spread<lb/>
of yellow fever in this Department, commanding officers,<lb/>
besides the provisions of Circular No. 22, of December 21,<lb/>
1899, will, on April 1, 1900, or as soon thereafter as practi-<lb/>
cable, carry out the following special instructions. For<lb/>
this purpose they will direct their medical officers to seek<lb/>
the co-operation of the officers of the Marine-Hospital Serv-<lb/>
ice and avail themselves of such hospital accommodations<lb/>
or disinfecting plants as may be offered by said service.</p>
<p>1st. In all garrison towns and their seaports a census<lb/>
will be made of all non-immune persons so that the extent<lb/>
of susceptibility to infection may be known and adequate<lb/>
preparations made. Such census will naturally include<lb/>
all persons, not native, who have never had the disease.</p>
<p>2nd. In seaboard towns especially, homeless and desti-<lb/>
tute non-immunes (mostly loafers and tramps) are the<lb/>
most dangerous element of the population and will, so far<lb/>
as practicable, be removed to the country, isolated or<lb/>
placed in confinement under medical supervision.</p>
<p>3rd. If a suitable building is not available, a sufficient<lb/>
number of tents will be pitched in an isolated spot and<lb/>
made ready for the admission and treatment of yellow<lb/>
fever cases. Near this hospital, but not connected with it,<lb/>
should be another set of tents (detention camp) for the re-<lb/>
ception of all suspicious cases or cases coming from an<lb/>
infected locality.</p>
<p>The tentage will be furnished by the Quartermaster's<lb/>
Department, and the furniture, supplies and medicines, by<lb/>
the Medical Department.</p>
<p>4th. The necessary personnel will be selected and in<lb/>
readiness. In the absence of an army medical officer, the<lb/>
commanding officer will make an agreement with the<lb/>
best civilian physician available, who will be prepared to<lb/>
take charge of the yellow fever hospital on the day the first<lb/>
case breaks out, his compensation to begin from that day,<lb/>
in accordance with contract to be made with him by the<lb/>
Chief Surgeon.</p>
<p>One immune attendant will be engaged and placed in<lb/>
charge as soon as the hospital is ready, at $30.00 per<lb/>
month and a ration, his pay to begin at once. If cases of<lb/>
yellow fever occur, the Chief Surgeon will authorize as<lb/>
many nurses and attendants as may be necessary.</p>
<p>5th. Upon completion of the preparations prescribed in<lb/>
the above paragraphs, a report describing the names of<lb/>
persons selected or engaged, and other action taken in<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02008002"/>
2<lb/>
carrying out the provisions of this Circular will be for-<lb/>
warded to these headquarters.</p>
<p>6th. Civilians under treatment will be charged one dollar<lb/>
($1.00) a day, or only 50 cents if employes of the Govern-<lb/>
ment. If unable to pay, bills in duplicate may be sent to<lb/>
the Chief Surgeon for settlement.</p>
<p>Ice for the sick and lime for disinfection can be pur-<lb/>
chased by medical officers as already provided by the Chief<lb/>
Surgeon.</p>
<p>7th. All buildings known to have been infected in pre-<lb/>
vious years will be carefully inspected and, if deemed<lb/>
necessary, subjected to a fresh disinfection.</p>
<p>8th. Where no steam plant is available, disinfection of<lb/>
bedding and clothing may be effected by a small portable<lb/>
formaldehyde generator, or by thorough boiling in a mild<lb/>
sublimate solution, followed by complete exposure to sun-<lb/>
shine. A hand pump, to throw a stream of sublimate<lb/>
solution against walls, floors, ceilings, etc., is always very<lb/>
useful and will be supplied on application to the Chief<lb/>
Surgeon.</p>
<p>9th. All persons coming from infected localities will<lb/>
be kept isolated for five days at the detention camp and<lb/>
disinfected before being discharged.</p>
<p>10th. Cases of fever in non-immunes should be carefully<lb/>
watched and, as soon as they become suspicious, promptly<lb/>
removed to the detention camp.</p>
<p>All physicians will be ordered to report, within 24 hours,<lb/>
any suspicious cases under their care to the medical<lb/>
officer in charge.</p>
<p>All cases of yellow fever will be promptly wired to the<lb/>
Chief Surgeon.</p>
<p>11th. According to general experience, the three most<lb/>
important symptoms upon which a diagnosis of yellow<lb/>
fever may be based, in the first stage, are:</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">First</hi>--Injection and glistening of conjunctiv&aelig;, together<lb/>
with general congestion of the skin.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Second</hi>--Steadiness or falling of pulse with rising tem-<lb/>
perature.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Third</hi>--Albumen in urine.</p>
<p>In order to appreciate properly the indications of pulse<lb/>
and temperature, they should be recorded not less than<lb/>
three times a day, upon the usual chart. Such a chart<lb/>
should, by itself, by the end of the first week, clear all<lb/>
doubts as to the nature of the fever.</p>
<p>BY ORDER OF COLONEL WHITSIDE:</p>
<p>J. G. HARBORD,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">1st Lieut. 10th U. S. Cavalry</hi>,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">A. A. D. C., A. A. A. G.</hi></p>
<p><add>Rep Q 27 Apr. 1946</add></p>
<p><add>Gen Kean says this was essentially what the cuban instructions<lb/>
were on yf</add></p>
<p><add>NP</add></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
