<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="t02030001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report: The Fever that was Epidemic in this Post Last Fall, by Najieb M. Saleeby, June 6, 1900</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Saleeby, Najieb M.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02030001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-06-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-06-06">June 6, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02030001</idno>
<title>Report: The Fever that was Epidemic in this Post Last Fall, by Najieb M. Saleeby, June 6, 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Saleeby writes about the epidemic that afflicted Columbia Barracks in late 1899 and describes the symptoms of the disease.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1900-06-06">
<head>Report: The Fever that was Epidemic in this Post Last Fall, by Najieb M. Saleeby, June 6, 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02030001"/>
<p>Saleeby</p>
<p>Saleebys 2nd Report on Dengue<lb/>
note p9 re Lazear's help</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks, Havana, Cuba,<lb/>
June 6th, 1900.</p>
<p>THE FEVER THAT WAS EPIDEMIC IN THIS POST LAST FALL.</p>
<p>Cases of the fever that was epidemic in this post from the mid-<lb/>
dle of September to the middle of November, 1899, kept straggling in<lb/>
all the latter part of November. Several cases occurred in December<lb/>
and January. One officer was attacked on the second day after his<lb/>
arrival here. His fever reached 103.4&deg; F. on the first day of the<lb/>
disease, then descended gradually to normal, lasting a little over<lb/>
five days. About half a dozen cases were observed in February and<lb/>
March. Two of themwere boys, both nine years old. In all these cases<lb/>
the blood was examined by Dr. J. W. Lazear, and the result was in-<lb/>
variably negative for Malaria. The urine presented no albumen. Dr.<lb/>
Lazear observed a few cases of fever in which the temperature drop-<lb/>
ped down to normal either on the first or second day after admission<lb/>
into the hospital, and in which he could not find the plasmodium<lb/>
malariae; but as I did not observe them I could not identify them<lb/>
with the fever under consideration. All the cases I include in the<lb/>
above occurred in the 8th Infantry Barracks, ran a course of more<lb/>
than three days, and are unaccounted for by any other cause except the<lb/>
specific cause of the fever under consideration, which they seem to<lb/>
identify.</p>
<p>Chart III,No.1, represents the only case I observed in April.<lb/>
The patient is an officer who contracted the disease at the termi-<lb/>
nation of a trip around the Island of Cuba, on board the Transport<lb/>
&ldquo;Ingalls.&rdquo; During that trip he visited Santiago and Cienfuegos on<lb/>
his way back. Previous to the trip, I treated him for a mild sub-<lb/>
chronic pharyngitis on several occasions. He had sore throat during<lb/>
the trip. The tout--ensemble of his symptoms resembled that of the<lb/>
fever under consideration. The first temperature registered in the<lb/>
chart was taken at 1:00 P.M., about two hours after his arrival home.<lb/>
The headache was severe but the rachialgia was <del>very</del> mild. His sore<lb/>
throat increased. The mucous membrane of the pharynx fauces and soft<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02030002"/>
(2)<lb/>
palate was red and swollen. The body of the tonsils was not enlarged,<lb/>
there was no soreness felt on the outside, but swallowing was pain-<lb/>
ful. This soreness passed away on April 3rd, though the redness and<lb/>
congestion of the mucous membrane <del>was</del><unclear><add>were</add></unclear> still notic<add>e</add>able on the 6th. He <del>h</del><lb/>
had nose bleed and vomited several times on both April 1st and 2nd.<lb/>
The temperature dropped down one degree April 3rd, and all the sym-<lb/>
ptoms improved. His temperature reached normal on the 4th. At about<lb/>
1:00 A.M. that day, he had critical perspiration, had three &ldquo;weak<lb/>
spells&rdquo; as he expressed it, changed his clothes three times during<lb/>
the night, and felt extremely weak. The picture of a systemic infec-<lb/>
tion; well defined cou<add>r</add>se of fever ending in crisis; ana<unclear><del>a</del></unclear>mia, sub-<lb/>
normal temperature, and unusual weakness during convalescense; and<lb/>
the unusually slow pulse<add>,</add> are characteristic features of this case.<lb/>
The blood was examined carefully for malaria and gave a negative<lb/>
result. The urine was examined four successive mornings and never<lb/>
presented any albumen. Both urine and blood were examined by Dr.<lb/>
Lazear.</p>
<p>The general character presented by all these cases <del>are</del><add>I</add> hereby<lb/>
refer<del>red</del> to, seems to me to be exactly the same as that of the fever<lb/>
of last fall. The rachialgia that was intense in the earlier part<lb/>
of the epidemic diminished considerably towards its end, and was so<lb/>
mild after that that it did not attract much attention. The major-<lb/>
ity had one single paroxysm of fever, but few presented that char-<lb/>
acteristic second or &ldquo;reactionary&rdquo; rise of the temperature that was<lb/>
termed a second paroxysm in the previous report.</p>
<p>All of these cases are primary attacks. None presented an<lb/>
eruption, none suggested dengue. It is a noteworthy fact that none<lb/>
of the ladies of the post contracted the disease.</p>
<p>Through the kindness of Dr. H. R. Carter, Surgeon, U. S. H. M.S.<lb/>
I am able to present a copy of the charts of six of the severest<lb/>
cases of a fever which occurred on board the U. S. T. S. &ldquo;Lancaster&rdquo;<lb/>
at the southern coast of Cuba, during the month of February. Dr. J.D.<lb/>
Gatewood, Surgeon, U. S. N., the medical officer in command, con-<lb/>
sidered them to be yellow fever cases and transferred them to the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02030003"/>
(3)<lb/>
charge of the U.S.M.H.S. at Cienfuegos for isolation purposes. The<lb/>
temperature line the charts present is very similar to that of my<lb/>
charts and shows very clearly the rapid rise, the characteristic<lb/>
descending line, the brief intermission, and the secondary rise of<lb/>
a &ldquo;reactionary fever,&rdquo; The lack of correlation between pulse and tem-<lb/>
perature is marked, and the severest two cases presented albumin in<lb/>
the urin<unclear><add>e</add></unclear>. Only these two cases when viewed separately were pronoun-<lb/>
ced &ldquo;suspicious cases&rdquo; of yellow fever by the U.S.M.H.S. Surgeons<lb/>
but on the whole the diagnosis of yellow fever was not corroborated.</p>
<p>, A heavy rain fall at the beginning of May declared the advent<lb/>
of the rainy season. It rained the greater part of the month, chief-<lb/>
ly during the first three weeks.</p>
<p>The first yellow fever case that occurred in this <add>post</add><lb/>
made its appearance on the 24th of May. This was a &ldquo;genuine&rdquo; case<lb/>
and is represented by No. 2, Chart IV. The patient did <hi rend="underline">not have the</hi><lb/>
fever of last fall. No. IV of the same chart is a case of mild<lb/>
yellow fever in an American girl, eleven years old, who lived in the<lb/>
neighboring village of Quemados, and whose father died of the same<lb/>
disease on May 31st. Her mother and another person contracted the<lb/>
disease in the same house. Her symptoms were very mild, she had no<lb/>
jaundice, and her urine presented no albumen. The Cuban doctors<lb/>
who saw her diagnosised the case &ldquo;infectious fever&rdquo;. These two<lb/>
cases are mentioned here simply for comparison.</p>
<p>No. III, <add>Chart IV</add> represents the case of an old soldier who took ill<lb/>
on the 27th of May and who was <hi rend="underline">not ill</hi> during the epidemic of last<lb/>
fall. He had fever all day and did not apply for treatment until<lb/>
3:00 P.M. He looked very ill then, the face was flushed and tremu-<lb/>
lous, the eyes suffused and red, moderate congestion extended down<lb/>
the neck to the shoulders. The headache was super<add>a</add>orbital and was the<lb/>
severest symptom. The rachialgia was very mild, anorexia, consti-<lb/> pation, no abdominal tenderness. The blood was carefully examined by<lb/>
Dr. Lazear for malaria with a negative result. The urine was acid<lb/>
and showed no album<unclear>e</unclear>n on the second day. Some album<unclear>e</unclear>n with few pus<lb/>
cells appeared on the third and fourth days. He had no symptoms of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02030004"/>
(4)<lb/>
of eystitis and his fever lasted more than two days. There was no<lb/>
cause to account for his illness except this specific fever. His<lb/>
pulse dropped in the evening of the second day from 96 to 64 while<lb/>
the temperature rose from 100&deg; to 101&deg;. Had it been possible to ex-<lb/>
amine the urine of all the cases of the epidemic of last fall as<lb/>
carefully as at present, I have reason to believe that a number of<lb/>
them would have presented some album<unclear>e</unclear>n in the urine during the lat-<lb/>
ter part of the disease.</p>
<p>No. I, Chart IV is the case of an American civilian who lived<lb/>
at Quemados and had severer symptoms than the preceding case<add>,</add> and had<lb/>
no albuminuria. No plasmodiae were found in the blood.</p>
<p>In the course of my inquiry about the cases of fever at Santi-<lb/>
ago during the late campaign of 1898, I learned from a number of<lb/>
sources that there were characteristic cases of <del>a</del> fever that are best<lb/>
expressed by the words of Major Gorgas, Surgeon, U.S.A., &ldquo;that<lb/>
they were not yellow fever; no one considered them dengue; most con-<lb/>
sidered them malarial; that the mortality was almost nil, and that<lb/>
there were a number of deaths from yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. C. Hamilton Tebault, Jr., of New Orleans, La., who was<lb/>
assigned to the Officers Hospital at Santiago, Cuba, referring to the<lb/>
same subject, describes a type of fever which he calls &ldquo;Calentura&rdquo;,<lb/>
adopting the common Cuban word for fever. &ldquo;Calenthura&rdquo;, he said,<lb/>
&ldquo;is a fever of one paroxysm. There usually is an initial chill<lb/>
which generally takes place in the morning, or late at night. The<lb/>
chill may be absent and only chilly sensations felt over the body.<lb/>
The temperature as a rule starts at a higher degree than one would<lb/>
look for in mild yellow fever. The pulse is often slow from the<lb/>
start, and falls steadily. It remains slow for a longer period than<lb/>
in mild yellow fever. There may be jaundice but this is unusual. If<lb/>
we pay attention to the headache, capillary stasis and calf pains,<lb/>
we are apt to be mislead.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The fever falls on the fourth or fifth day in severe cases,<lb/>
but in mild cases it disappears on the second day. I have never seen<lb/>
anything like secondary infection in this disease corresponding to<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02030005"/>
(5)<lb/>
Sanarelli's per iod of secondary infection of yellow fever.&rdquo;<lb/>
&ldquo;There may be vomiting at the outset, but this is usually gone by<lb/>
the second day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The urine, though often scanty, contains no albumen, or at<lb/>
least contains only a trace when the fever began at a very high de-<lb/>
gree.&rdquo; &ldquo;The mortality from Calentura at the Military Hospital<lb/>
and at the officers hospital was nil.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;That it is a specific disease of microbic origin is beyond<lb/>
question. It is non-contagious. Certain atmospheric conditions favor<lb/>
its rapid spread.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The above quotations show plainly that Dr. Teabault recognized<lb/>
a type of fever similar to the one under consideration. His views<lb/>
and statements concerning its relation to yellow fever and malaria<lb/>
seem to be uncertain and contradict each other. This I attribute to<lb/>
the fact that cases of malaria, calentura, and &ldquo;genuine&rdquo; yellow<lb/>
fever existed side by side all the time. His composite chart<add>, No 2, Chart III</add><lb/>
represents the type of the fever.</p>
<p>CONCLUSIONS.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">General Character</hi>. In summing up the results of my observations<lb/>
on the subject, I find that we have to deal with an acute infectious<lb/>
fever that is endemi<unclear>c</unclear> in this island. It occurs sporadically all the<lb/>
year around, and assumes epidemic proportions on favorable occasions.<lb/>
It is a non-contagious disease whose infectious agent seems to depend<lb/>
for its development upon certain atmospheric and telluric conditions.<lb/>
A certain degree of temperature and humidity favors its growth,<lb/>
while cold weather and storm ret ard it at least. The disease starts<lb/>
from an infected lacality and extends from that as a centre, appar-<lb/>
ently by soil cantiguity. Isolation of the sick in hospital did not<lb/>
seem to effect its spread. The epidemic seemed to start inside the<lb/>
limits of the camp, was restricted to foreigners and did not spread<lb/>
as such outside camp limits. There had not been any epidemic of any<lb/>
kind either in Havana or in this vicinity.</p>
<p>Three of the officers<add>'</add> children contracted the disease, two<lb/>
boys and one girl, all about nine years old. None of the ladies in<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02030006"/>
(6)<lb/>
camp had it. The mortality of the epidemic was nil.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Symptomatology</hi>. The incubation period varied between one day<lb/>
and two weeks. The duration of the disease varied from sixty hours<lb/>
to eight days. The greater number of the cases pre sented one paroxysm,<lb/>
the minority two. The second paroxysm whenever it occurred formed<lb/>
practically a continuous course with the first, was only separated<lb/>
by a brief intermission, and resembled very closely what is called<lb/>
the &ldquo;reactionary fever&rdquo;, or the &ldquo;second infection&rdquo; of yellow fever,<lb/>
thus giving rise to what might be termed a <unclear>xxxxxxxxxxxxxx</unclear> third stage<lb/>
of the disease.</p>
<p>The onset was always sudden. &ldquo;The acme of the temperature was<lb/>
reached at the outset (within thirty-six hours) and from this time<lb/>
the temperature line was a descending one&rdquo;. The termination was of<lb/>
course by lysis. There were twenty relapses in about 350 cases.</p>
<p>The first stage was always marked by distinct capillary conges-<lb/>
tion of the skin and the mucous membra<unclear><del>h</del></unclear>ne; especially the face, neck,<lb/>
eyes<add>,</add> and throat, but there were no hemorrhages either primary or<lb/>
secondary. The cephalalgia and rachialgia were severe and seemed to<lb/>
hang on with unusual tenacity, especially the latter. The gastric dis-<lb/>
turbances were mild. The pulse was marked<unclear>lyy</unclear> slow and often lacked<lb/>
correlation with the temperature. The urine was highly acid, dimin-<lb/>
ished in amount, but as a rule contained no albumen. The skin kept<lb/>
generally dry and presented neither ict<add>e</add>rus nor any characteristic<lb/>
eruption. The joints were not affected at all. There <add>were</add> cerebral un-<lb/>
easiness and marked systemic disturbance, the patients looked as <add>well</add><lb/>
<add>as</add> they would be in the first two days of either typhoid or yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Differential Diagnosis</hi>. Malaria. In view of our present knowl-<lb/>
edgw of malaria and in light of the aforesaid facts there is certainly<lb/>
no re ason to believe that this disease &ldquo;is one of the many turns<lb/>
malaria takes.&rdquo; This idea is a legend of the past.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Dengue</hi>. Dengue was discussed early during the first part of the<lb/>
epidemic and was given up. Later it was resumed by another party,<lb/>
but I am not aware of the occurrence of any case that was so diag-<lb/>
nosed since last December. It was the severity and unusual tena<del>c</del>-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02030007"/>
(7)<lb/>
cety of the rachialgia together with the benignity of the disease<lb/>
and the occasional occurrence of uncharacteristic eruptions that led<lb/>
to the proclamation of this diagnosis.</p>
<p>But in face of the facts that the diseaze <add><unclear>started</unclear></add> in camp, was trace-<lb/>
able to an infected l<del>a</del><add>o</add>cality from which it spread out<del>,</del> as aforesaid,<lb/>
was restricted to foreigners, and did not spread outside the limit<lb/>
of our camp; and in view of the fact<del>s</del> that there was not at the same<lb/>
time either dengue or any other epidemic disease either in Havana<lb/>
or in our vicinity, or on the Island that I am aware of; and in view<lb/>
of the facts that no ladies in camp contracted the disease; that the<lb/>
joints were not affected at all, that there was no characteristic<lb/>
er<add>u</add><del>p</del>ption (a symptom that I did carefully investigate); in face of<lb/>
all that I feel that I cannot <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add> refrain</add> from refuting this diagnosis.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Calentura and Yellow Fever</hi>. Calentura may be what the Cubans<lb/>
call &ldquo;infectious Fever&rdquo;. The adoption of the term calentura that some<lb/>
have suggested means the recognition of a disease that is unsatis-<lb/>
factorily described as yet, and whose relations and differential di-<lb/>
agnosis from yellow fever are not yet established. This is a diffi-<lb/>
cult problem for whose solution we must wait for future developments<lb/>
and observations. And we have already plain indications that such de-<lb/>
velopments may soon appear and help to dispel certain clouds of un-<lb/>
certainty that seem to hang over this vexed question. It is therefore<lb/>
proper to reserve the decision to the future, and simply point out<lb/>
at present the several points where in this disease simulates or dif-<lb/>
fers from yellow fever as we know it.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">It would certainly seem ridiculous to state before the profes-<lb/>
sion that we have had an epidemic of yellow fever without any mor-<lb/>
tality, icterus, h<del>h</del>aemorrhages, or a sign of a haemorr<add>h</add><del>a</del>age<del>x</del>, an</hi>d that<lb/>
as a rule there was not any amount of albumen in the urine that is<lb/>
worth mentioning. Yet it is a fact that some <hi rend="underline">physicians who had con-<lb/>
siderable experience with yellow fever have declared to me that the<lb/>
epidemic was yellow fever in spi</hi>te of all that. In their opinion Cal-<lb/>
entura would simply be very mild yellow fever and persons attacked<lb/>
with it obtain immunity from the latter disease.</p>
<p>Uninfluenced by any opinion except the facts that are before<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02030008"/>
<add>(8)</add><lb/>
me, I can not overestimate the evidence that the course of the fever<lb/>
bears. The variations of the temperature are not always given the con-<lb/>
sideration they should be credited with. The charts show very vividly<lb/>
that the life - cycle of the germ of this disease is very similar<lb/>
indeed to that of yellow fever. The period of incubation, invasion,<lb/>
acme, decline, intermission, and secondary rise are not only indi-<lb/>
cated but simulate and correspond with those of yellow fever very<lb/>
closely. The secondary rise of th<unclear>e</unclear> fever is a characteristic clinical<lb/>
peculiarity of yellow fever, that La Roche states is &ldquo;of itself al-<lb/>
most sufficient to enable us to diagnosis the case.&rdquo; It certainly<lb/>
speaks of an undoubted similarity between the <del>cause</del><add>course</add> of the two fevers.</p>
<p>The rise of the epidemic, the localization of the infection,<lb/>
its endemicity, its spread, its restriction to strangers, the ex-<lb/>
emption of the female sex, the influence of atmospheric and telluric<lb/>
conditions upon its progress, all are very indicative. It is not nec-<lb/>
essary to say that all the subjective and objective symptoms mentioned<lb/>
in the former report could be easily interpreted by yellow fever<lb/>
and that any deviation from the genral character could be easily ex-<lb/>
plained <unclear>a</unclear>s a peculiarity of the individual epidemic. I cannot pass<lb/>
on without remarking on the resemblance between the symptoms of the<lb/>
mild yellow fever of Jamaica as described by I. Anderson and those of<lb/>
the symptoms of this disease.</p>
<p>The cutaneous and mucous membrane congestions were marked, that<lb/>
of the throat being very mild, and no hemorrhages occurred. The pulse<lb/>
was slow out of all proportion to the temperature and very<unclear>h</unclear>often<lb/>
presented marked lack of correlation with the latter though not to<lb/>
the same extent as in severe yellow fever.</p>
<p>But here the relation stops, the infection does not seem to<lb/>
cause any marked internal congestion or tissue degeneration, con-<lb/>
sequently we do not find either the expected amount of albumen in<lb/>
the urine, or icterus, or passive hemmorrhage; neither is there any<lb/>
real collapse or prolonged prostration.</p>
<p>The life history of the germs certainly simulate each other close<unclear>-</unclear><lb/>
ly, but their toxicities differ considerably. Now do the toxines<lb/>
differ in kind or in degree<unclear>?</unclear> Is the degree of toxicity proportional<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02030009"/>
<add>(9)</add><lb/>
to the rise of the temperature? Can the same toxine that determines<lb/>
the rise of the temperature and the degree of toxicity lose one <del>qual-</del><add>pro-</add><lb/>
<del>ity</del><add>perty</add> and maintain the other?</p>
<p>The poison of yellow fever seems to undergo considerable atten-<lb/>
uation in children. Some writers speak of having treated one hundred<lb/>
and even two hundred cases of yellow fever in children without a sin-<lb/>
gle death; but even then there is albumen in the urine as a rule and<lb/>
occasional icterus and passive hemorrhages from the mucous membranes.<lb/>
It is generally conceded that the epidemics that occur later in the year<lb/>
especially those that come in the fall are mild and have a low mor-<lb/>
tality. But I do not know whether any epidemic of yellow fever has<lb/>
ever been reported with no mortality. Still it should not be forgot-<lb/>
ten that we are encamped on the crest of a hill one of the most sa-<lb/>
lubrious spots on the Island. The hill is of limestone rock and the<lb/>
soil has no depth to it, and has not been tilled. The place is iso-<lb/>
lated from the city and was not inhabited before. All our buildings<lb/>
are of wood and new, our hygenic surroundings are practically perfect.<lb/>
The men are we<del>e</del><add>l</add>l disciplined, the sewer system is complete, and the<lb/>
kitchens and dining rooms are kept scrupulously clean.</p>
<p>It would be of considerable interest to study in this light yel-<lb/>
low fever cases as they appear this summer, and watch to see whether<lb/>
the men that were attacked last fall have obtained any immunity from<lb/>
yellow fever or not. No matter what decision shall be arrived at<lb/>
concerning this disease, it is bound to add some light to our present<lb/>
knowledge of yellow fever, acclimation and acquired immunity from it,<lb/>
and the relation of yellow fever to both dengue and calent<del>h</del>ura if<lb/>
the latter be confirmed.</p>
<p>I feel greatly indebted to Dr. H. R. Carter, Surgeon, U.S.M.H.S.,<lb/>
for many valuable lessons and suggestions, and for the great interest<lb/>
he took in repeated discussions on the subject in hand. In apprecia-<lb/>
tion of all that and with full respect to his ideas and opinion I<lb/>
hereby present his letter in toto. <hi rend="underline">I also feel very thankful to Dr.<lb/>
J. W. Lazear, A.A. Surgeon, U.S.A., for his valuable aid</hi> and pro-<lb/>
fe<hi rend="underline">ssional he</hi>lp.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1900-06-06">
<head></head>
<pb n="10" id="f02030010"/>
<p>MEMO <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="underline">from the Desk of . . .</hi></hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">DR. P. S. HENCH</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">To__________ Date_______</hi></p>
<p>SUBJECT:</p>
<p>See under<lb/>
H R Carter file.</p>
<p>Dr Carters opinion<lb/>
of this report</p>
<p>His letter of May 3, 1900</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
