<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="t02033001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report from Alexander N. Stark to the Surgeon General, June 15, 1900</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Stark, Alexander N.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02033001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-06-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="receipient">Surgeon General</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Sherwood, Charles E.</name>
<name type="person">Balentine, James W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">King, Mrs. Henry S.</name>
<name type="person">Teeter, E. A.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Major</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reilly, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Schenck, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Walker, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">McNeer, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Fanning, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Colbey, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Obrien, Anne E.</name>
<name type="person">Girault, Phoebe</name>
<name type="person">Ledlie, Kate S. M.</name>
<name type="person">Gillen, Ella M.</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-06-15">June 15, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02033001</idno>
<title>Report from Alexander N. Stark to the Surgeon General, June 15, 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Stark gives a detailed report on the outbreak of yellow fever in Quemados, Cuba and Columbia Barracks, Cuba. Stark claims that Mrs. Henry S. King is the first case of yellow fever. A Medical Board with Ames, Lazear, and three Cubans is created to investigate the outbreak. Stark highly commends the doctors and staff at Post Hospital. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1900-06-15">
<head>Report from Alexander N. Stark to the Surgeon General, June 15, 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02033001"/>
<opener>
Starks first report on the Quemados<lb/>
epidemic - summer 1900 June 15, 1900<lb/>
(see Howard's report of June 18<lb/>
<dateline>
POST HOSPITAL COLUMBIA BARRACKS<lb/>
<date value="1900-06-15">June 15th, 1900.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
TO THE<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL, U.S. ARMY,<lb/>
WASHINGTON, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>SIR:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to submit the following special report upon<lb/>
an outbreak of yellow fever in the town of Quemados, Cuba, and Columbia<lb/>
Barracks.</p>
<p>On Monday, May 21st, 1900, two local physicians of Quemados reported<lb/>
to the Chief Surgeon of the Department that they were in attendance<lb/>
upon a suspicious case of fever at number 20 General Lee St., the pa-<lb/>
tient being a packer in the 7th Cavalry corral at Columbia Barracks.<lb/>
By Tuesday night it was definitely decided that the case was genuine<lb/>
yellow fever. On Wednesday morning, May 23rd, the patient and his wife<lb/>
were removed to the infectious wards at Columbia Barracks.</p>
<p>In addition to the two removed, the house was occupied by a Sig-<lb/>
nal Sergeant, his wife and little daughter, an American dentist, several<lb/>
young clerks, and the lessee of the house, also an American, all of whom<lb/>
were promptly placed in quarantine.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, May the 23rd, Sergeant Sherwood developed suspicious<lb/>
symptoms. On Thursday, May 24th, he was removed to the infectious wards<lb/>
at Columbia Barracks. The dentist and other occupants of the house <unclear><add>save Mrs. Sherwood &amp; daughter</add></unclear>, were<lb/>
removed to other quarters for observation, their effects being retained.</p>
<p>On the evening of May 24th, Private Balentine, Co. &ldquo;D&rdquo; 8th Infantry,<lb/>
was admitted to the receiving ward at Post Hospital with very suspicious<lb/>
symptoms, and on the morning of the 26th of May, the diagnosis of yellow<lb/>
fever being definitely settled<add>,</add> he was removed to the infectious wards.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02033002"/>
Page.2.<lb/>
In the interim the quarters of Co. &ldquo;D&rdquo; 8th Infantry were carefully dis-<lb/>
infected.</p>
<p>On May 27th, the little daughter of Sergeant Sherwood had an attack<lb/>
of indigestion from the ingestion of a large quantity of guava paste,<lb/>
but the trouble not yeilding promptly to treatment and other symptoms<lb/>
of extremely suspicious nature arising, on the morning of may 31st, she<lb/>
was removed to the infectious wards accompanied by her mother who on<lb/>
that day showed a slight elevation of temperature. Sergeant Sherwood<lb/>
died on the same day, May 31st. The autopsy was performed by A.A. Surgeon<lb/>
Lazear, U.S.A., and the diagnosis of yellow fever was confirmed. Mrs.<lb/>
Sherwood developed the characteristic symptoms of the disease on June<lb/>
3rd, 1900. A careful examination into the probable origin of the infec-<lb/>
tion established the fact that the house number 20 General Lee St. was<lb/>
the focus beyond doubt.</p>
<p>Mrs. King, the wife of the packer, acknowledged on close questioning<lb/>
that she had been sick for several days prior to her husband's seizure,<lb/>
had bled profusely from the gums, and though she felt exhausted attribu-<lb/>
ted her <del><unclear>s</unclear></del><add>w</add>eakness and loss of blood to carious teeth, and therefore did<lb/>
not deem the services of a physician necessary. She is beyond doubt the<lb/>
first case of yellow fever in the present outbreak. The Kings lead a<lb/>
blameless existence, did not visit the city of Havana, nor had these pa-<lb/>
tients <add>purchased</add> any clothing or bedding <del>purchased</del> in any Cuban town. They arrived<lb/>
on April 1st, having just left the town of Santa Clara where an outbreak<lb/>
of yellow fever among those soldiers who had married native women began<lb/>
on May 10th. In addition to their clothes, the Kings brought with them<lb/>
from Santa Clara two bed quilts.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02033003"/>
<p>Page.3.</p>
<p>While it is thought by some that the effects of the Kings were<lb/>
responsible for the introduction of yellow fever I cannot entertain that<lb/>
view, beleiving as I do that the infection was latent in the house, re-<lb/>
quiring only suitable conditions for its development, which conditions<lb/>
were provided by the incessant rain of nineteendays duration previous<lb/>
to the first case of sickness. While the house and its cess-pools were<lb/>
in excellent condition (sanitary), and while the same may be said of<lb/>
some of the other <add>r</add>esidences in which infection occurred, it is well to<lb/>
remember that the sub-soil of Cuban towns has through several genera-<lb/>
tions become honey-combed with cess-pools that having served their time<lb/>
of usefulness have been closed and their location forgotten. In addi-<lb/>
tion to this, I hold it impossible to thoroughly disinfect any house here<lb/>
in which infection has probably occurred frequently in the past, the<lb/>
disease being denominated<unclear>,</unclear> infection fever or el borras, if the infection<lb/>
were in the first instance a child or in the second an adult Cuban, when<lb/>
in fact both these diseases are yellow fever pure and simple, and when<lb/>
the house is constructed of heavy mason<unclear><del>a</del></unclear>ry with tiled floors.</p>
<p>Sergeant Sherwood was employed at the Cable Office in Havana be-<lb/>
tween the hours of 8 A.M. and 4 P.M., and his habits were ex<del>a</del><add>e</add>mplary. The<lb/>
other occupants of the house had not been exposed to any infection, nor<lb/>
have they been sick up to the present time.</p>
<p>The house is situated near the corner of Real and General Lee Sts.<add>,</add><lb/>
and is at the summit of a slight hill, General Lee St. terminating with a<lb/>
gentle fall at the Marianao railroad track which forms the boundary be-<lb/>
tween town and reservation.</p>
<p>Careful interrogation and investigation has failed to discover the<lb/>
source of Private Balentine's infection, and this case must remain one<lb/>
of those whose origin is merged in obscurity.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f02033004"/>
<p>Page 4.</p>
<p>On May 31st, a teamster employed by the Chief Quartermaster and<lb/>
living at a corral in the rear of Department Headquarters was admitted<lb/>
to the receiving ward suffering with general pain and fever, presumably<lb/>
due to a slight orchitis following a recent attack of mumps, but the dis-<lb/>
covery of albumen and bile stained casts in his urine, together with de-<lb/>
pressed pulse and congested conjunctivae, warranted his removal to the<lb/>
infectious wards with the diagnosis of yellow fever, which diagnosis was<lb/>
subsequently confirmed. This teamster had been in Quemados but a month<lb/>
and lived in a well cared for camp, though his duties compelled his pre-<lb/>
sence at all manner of localities. Interrogation has failed to assign<lb/>
any cause for this teamster's infection beyond the fact that he worked<lb/>
for several days at the dumping ground of the town. The veracity of in-<lb/>
dividuals of this man's class cannot always be depended upon, and it is<lb/>
presumed that with his fellows he was in the habit of visiting ques-<lb/>
tionable resorts in pursuit of recreation.</p>
<p>On June 3rd, Private Teeter, orderly for the Chief Surgeon and liv-<lb/>
ing at 102 Real St., in close proximity to number 20 General Lee St.<add>,</add> was<lb/>
admitted to the receiving ward with suspicious symptoms, and on June 4th<lb/>
was removed to the infectious wards with the diagnosis of yellow fever,<lb/>
which diagnosis was subsequently confirmed. The focus of infection in<lb/>
this case is presumably the house. This house was occupied by Sergeant<lb/>
Reilly and wife, several young men employed in the Post Quartermaster's<lb/>
office, and Private Teeter. The remaining occupants, save Sergeant<lb/>
Reilly and wife, were removed on June 5th into tents with only the cloth-<lb/>
es they wore, the rest being retained for disinfection. On the same day<lb/>
Sergeant Reilly complained of severe head-ache and pains in his back,<lb/>
and on June 6th he and his wife were removed to the infectious wards,<lb/>
he with yellow fever, and she for observation.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f02033005"/>
<p>Page 5</p>
<p>On Friday, June 8th, two young Hebrews owning a talior shop on Gene-<lb/>
ral Lee St. directly opposite number 20, the first focus, were taken to<lb/>
the Municipal Hospital with yellow fever, one dying the following day<lb/>
and the other on Monday June the 11th, both having been ill three days<lb/>
prior to their appeal for medical assistance at the Post Hospital where<lb/>
the disease was recognized.</p>
<p>On June 8th, Mr. Schenck, Quartermaster employe<unclear><del>d</del></unclear>, one of the occupants<lb/>
of number 102 Real St., was taken ill, displaying suspicious symptoms<lb/>
which speedily developed into yellow fever.</p>
<p>On June 9th, teamster Hoagland, an employe in the Post corral and<lb/>
living in the corral, was admitted to the receiving ward with suspicious<lb/>
symptoms, and on June 10th was removed to the infectious wards with<lb/>
yellow fever. This man had been in <add>the</add> habit of frequenting houses of pros-<lb/>
titution and undoubtedly contracted the disease in one of them.</p>
<p>Corporal Walker, Troop &ldquo;H&rdquo; 7th Cavalry, living in barracks<unclear>,</unclear> was admit-<lb/>
ted to the receiving ward on the evening of June 10th with temperature,<lb/>
and on <unclear><del>as</del></unclear> June 12th <add>was</add> removed to the infectious wards with yellow fever.<lb/>
Interrogation disclosed the fact that this man had a native mistress<lb/>
living on Real St., directly across the street from number 20 General Lee<lb/>
St., and was in the habit of visiting her after roll-call at night.</p>
<p>On Sunday, June 10th, a Hebrew tailor owning a shop opposite No.<lb/>
&ldquo;20 General Lee St was admitted to the Municipal Hospital with yellow<lb/>
fever, the house being the focus of infection.</p>
<p>On the evening of June 11th, Major Edmunds, 1st. Infantry, living at<lb/>
at number 27 General Lee St., was taken sick, and on Wednesday morning the<lb/>
diagnosis of yellow fever was made. On Wednesday night Mrs. Edmunds was<lb/>
taken sick, and on Thursday her case was diagnosed as yellow fever, the<lb/>
diagnosis in both cases being subsequently confirmed. Again the house<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02033006"/>
Page 6.<lb/>
was a focus of infection.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, June 13th, an aged lady of American birth living at<lb/>
number 16 General Lee St., directly opposite the residence of Major Ed-<lb/>
munds, was taken sick, and on Thursday the diease was pronounced yellow<lb/>
fever. Three months prior to the illness of this lady a young Cuban girl<lb/>
whose family occupied this house died suddenly after an illness of a few<lb/>
days, the di<add>s</add>ease being promuonced by the local physicians &lsquo;perniciosa&rsquo;.<lb/>
This aged lady had been in the house but 10 days before her illness,<lb/>
having come from New York for the purpose of visiting her Cuban grand-<lb/>
children.</p>
<p>On Friday, June 15th, an Austrian, proprietor of a small restaurant<lb/>
on General Lee St. four doors from the railroad, was removed to the Muni-<lb/>
cipal Hospital with yellow fever, having been ill four days before the<lb/>
fact was discovered. The house in this instance was constructed of wood<lb/>
and the back-yard was filthy.</p>
<p>On Friday evening, June 15th, a German carpenter working on the new<lb/>
wards at the Post Hospital was admitted to the receiving ward, and exam-<lb/>
ination disclosed the fact that though ill for several days previous he<lb/>
had attempted to work in a desultory manner until compelled to desist<lb/>
from exhaustion. His case was easily diagnosed as yellow fever, and he<lb/>
was immediately removed to the infectious wards. This man lived on San<lb/>
Ygnacio St. in Havana, a noted locality in the past for yellow fever, and<lb/>
unquestionably contracted the disease there.</p>
<p>A Board, composed of three Cuban physicians, A.A. Surgeons Ames and<lb/>
Lazear, was immediately formed at the appearance of the first case to<lb/>
pronounce upon all subsequent cases deemed suspicious, and by this Board<lb/>
the diagnosis was made in every case.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f02033007"/>
<p>Page 7</p>
<p>Every precaution was immediately taken in both town and Post to<lb/>
prevent the spread of the disease, and it is believed that this end has<lb/>
been attained. A supplemental report will be rendered later.</p>
<p>In conclusion, I desire to commend to your consideration A.A. Surgeon<lb/>
Roger Post Ames, U.S.A., to whose excellent judgement and professional<lb/>
skill the low mortality is large<add>ly</add> due, A.A. Surgeon Jesse W. Lazear, by whose<lb/>
skill in microscopy and chemistry the diagnosis of all cases was faci-<lb/>
litated, Privates Lambert, McNeer, Fanning, and Colbey, Hospital Corps U.S.A.,<lb/>
for their untiring attention to duty, Private Lambert alone being immune,<lb/>
Contract nurses Anne E. Obrien, Phoebe Girault, Kate S.M. Ledlie, and Ella M<unclear>.</unclear><lb/>
Gillen, for their devotion to duty.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,<lb/>
Your obedient servant,</salute>
<signed>A. N. Stark,</signed>
Capt. &amp; Asst. Surgeon, U.S. Army.,<lb/>
<unclear>R G E O N.</unclear><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
