<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="t02035001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report from Valery Havard to the Adjutant General, June 18, 1900</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Havard, Valery</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02035001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-06-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="receipient">Adjutant General</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Sherwood, Charles E.</name>
<name type="person">Balentine, James W.</name>
<name type="person">King, Mrs. Henry S.</name>
<name type="person">Teeter, E. A.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Major</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-06-18">June 18, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02035001</idno>
<title>Report from Valery Havard to the Adjutant General, June 18, 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Havard details the outbreak of yellow fever in Quemados, Cuba in May 1900. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1900-06-18">
<head>Report from Valery Havard to the Adjutant General, June 18, 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02035001"/>
<opener>
Havard's report on YF epidemic in Quemados<lb/>
up to June 18, 1900 MAP<lb/>
See Starks 2 reports<lb/>
<hi>Copy</hi><lb/>
L.S.233.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS<lb/>
DIVISION OF CUBA<lb/>
OFFICE OF L.S.233.<lb/>
HAVANA.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1900-06-18">June 18th. 1900.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
To the Adjutant General,<lb/>
Division of Cuba,<lb/>
<salute>Sir:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to state that, in accordance<lb/>
<unclear>from whom ?</unclear> <hi rend="underline">with instructions received on the 15th.</hi> inst., I went on the same<lb/>
day to Quemados to examine into all the facts and circumstances<lb/>
connected with the outbreak of yellow fever at that place, and<lb/>
to submit the following report:</p>
<p>So far as known to the Medical Department, there were no<lb/>
cases of yellow fever at Quemados in 1899, and after the many<lb/>
sanitary improvements made in that town it was confidently ex-<lb/>
pected that none would occur this year. There were many cases<lb/>
of an infectious fever among the troops at Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
last fall, but they have been identified as Dengue fever. <add>see Saleeby file</add></p>
<p>From the mode of origination of the cases in the present<lb/>
outbreak, and the absence of any history of recent introduction<lb/>
of infection, it is fair to assume that the yellow fever at<lb/>
Quemados is attributable to the presence of old germs existing<lb/>
in the occupied buildings. Why such germs should suddenly be-<lb/>
come active after such a long period of quiescence, is still an<lb/>
unanswerable question, and one about which it would now be profit<lb/>
less to speculate.</p>
<p>The first case (Mrs. King) began on May 16th., but it was<lb/>
mind, no physician was called in and it passed unrecognized.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02035002"/>
L.S.233. (2)<lb/>
Her husband (King, Quartermaster's employe) was taken sick on<lb/>
the 19th., seen by a Cuban physician on the 21st. and by Major<lb/>
Kean on the 22nd., first date on which the existence of yellow<lb/>
fever was recognized. It was then that the illness of Mrs. King<lb/>
was inquired into and found to be yellow fever.</p>
<p>Three more cases (Signal Serg't. Sherwood, child and wife)<lb/>
occurred in the same house (20, General Lee Street), on the 23rd.<lb/>
30th. and June 3rd. respectively.</p>
<p>On May 30th. Private Valentine, Co. &ldquo;D&rdquo; 8th. Cavalry, was taken<lb/>
sick in his quarters (Columbia Barracks) and admitted to hosp-<lb/>
ital on the 31st.</p>
<p>The next three cases (Private Teeter, Hospital Corps, Qmr's.<lb/> 
Serg't. Reilly and Shenk, Qmr's. employe) occurred in a house near-<lb/>
ly adjoining the first<add>,</add> (102, Real Calzada), on June 3rd., 6th. and<lb/>
8th. respectively. All subsequent cases occurred <unclear>on</unclear> General Lee<lb/>
Street, with the exception of one Qmr's. employe who apparently<lb/>
contracted the disease at the Headquarters Corral. It is thus<lb/> 
seen, as the accompanying sketch indicates, that the foci of con-<lb/>
tagion are limited to a well defined district.</p>
<p>The total number of cases, to date, is 19, namely 13 civil-<lb/>
ians (all Americans), l U.S.A. officer and 5 enlisted men. The<lb/>
officer (Major Edmunds), a man of excellent habits, lives in one<lb/>
of the cleanest and best ventilated houses in town, and in which<lb/>
Major Kean <add>and family</add> lived last summer with impunity. He very likely caug-<lb/>
ht the disease from the house; this opinion is strengthened by<lb/>
the fact that he and his wife contracted it almost simultaneous-<lb/>
ly, and that so far as known, they did not visit any infected<lb/>
place or person.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02035003"/>
<p>L.S.233.<lb/>
(3)</p>
<p>The mode of infection of the 5 enlisted men, so far as as-<lb/>
certainable, is as follows:-</p>
<p>1. Serg't. Sherwood, Signal Serg't., from his residence (General<lb/>
Lee Street)</p>
<p>2. Private Teeter, Hospital Corps, from his residence (Real <add>Calzada</add> St.)</p>
<p>3. Serg't. Reilly, Qmr's. Serg't. from his residence (Real St.)</p>
<p>4. Private Valentine, Co. &ldquo;D&rdquo;, 8th. Inft'y., unknown: he claims to<lb/>
have slept every night in his quarters. Close watch of every<lb/>
other man of his Co. has failed to discover another case.</p>
<p>5. Corp. Walker, Troop &ldquo;H&rdquo;, 7th. Cavalry, <hi rend="underline">from house in town (Gener-<lb/>
al Lee Street) where he kept a mistress</hi>.</p>
<p>The mortality thus far has only been 3, namely Signal Serg't<lb/>
Sherwood and 2 civilians, <del>thus</del> indicating a rather mild type of<lb/>
infection.</p>
<p>There is no sign or indication that any part of Columbia<lb/>
Barracks is or has been infected.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">The post isolation hospital is situated across the rail-<lb/>
road track at a safe distance from the Barracks and is well<lb/>
equipped and furnished</hi>.</p>
<p>I find that all necessary measures of isolation and dis-<lb/>
infection have been thoughtfully planned and diligently carried<lb/>
out by the Chief Surgeon, Major Kean.</p>
<p>A strict quarantine is maintained by Columbia Barracks<lb/>
against Quemados. Of course it is of the utmost importance that<lb/>
as little intercourse as possible should exist between the two<lb/>
places and that no officer or enlisted man be allowed to enter<lb/>
Quemados except on strictly official business and by special<lb/>
orders.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f02035004"/> 
<p>L.S.233. (4)</p>
<p>A measure <hi rend="underline">immediately required</hi> is the establishment of a<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">detention camp</hi> where all non-immunes are to be at once removed<lb/>
when exposed, or when suspected to have been exposed, to infect-<lb/>
ion. I am informed by Chief Surgeon Kean that steps are being<lb/>
taken to that end and I recommend that there be no delay about<lb/>
it.</p>
<p>The question of vacating the barracks and removing the<lb/>
troops to a camp, naturally suggests itself. I do not believe<lb/>
that <add>such</add> a serious and radical measure is necessary at present, and<lb/>
trust it will never be; but as it might become necessary, it is<lb/>
advisable that a suitable camp be selected now and that all the<lb/>
required canvas be made available.</p>
<p>All necessary arrangements have been made to vacate any<lb/>
individual set of quarters showing signs of infection, that is<lb/>
in which a case of yellow fever originates.</p>
<p>In conclusion, I wish to say that the medical personnel,<lb/>
under the direction of Major Kean, is unusually able and effic-<lb/>
ient and that every medical officer may be relied upon to do<lb/>
his duty.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) V Havard</signed>
Major and Surgeon, U.S.A.<lb/>
Chief Surgeon.<lb/>
******************************************************************<lb/>
Copy respectfully <hi rend="underline">furnished the Surgeon General U.S.A.</hi> for his<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">information</hi>.<lb/>
V. Havard<lb/>
Major and Surgeon U.S.A.<lb/>
Chief Surgeon.<lb/>
Had the SG asked for it?<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
