<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02104001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report from J. F. Dunshie to the Chief Surgeon, August 25, 1900</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Dunshie, J. F.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02104001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-08-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Chief Surgeon</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Walker, Samuel</name>
<name type="person">Courtney, John E.</name>
<name type="person">Vance, Harry</name>
<name type="person">Gallinania, Loius</name>
<name type="person">Smith, George H.</name>
<name type="person">Davidson, William</name>
<name type="person">Haines, Sylvester</name>
<name type="place">Guanajay Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-08-25">August 25, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02104001</idno>
<title>Report from J. F. Dunshie to the Chief Surgeon, August 25, 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Dunshie lists the cases of yellow fever at Guanajay Barracks, Cuba. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1900-08-25">
<head>Report from J. F. Dunshie to the Chief Surgeon, August 25, 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02104001"/>
<opener>
Post Hospital, Guanajay Barracks, Cuba,<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1900-08-25">August 25, 1900</date>
</dateline><lb/>
To the<lb/>
Chief Surgeon, Dept Western Cuba,<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba.<lb/>
Duplicate<lb/>
<salute>Sir,</salute>
</opener>
<p>In compliance with paragraph 119, Manual for the Medical<lb/>
Department, I have the honor to report the following list of patients that<lb/>
have had and are new suffering from Yellow Fever at this Post.</p>
<p>1- On Wednesday, July 4th. Pvt. Samuel Walker, Co. &ldquo;I&rdquo; 1st. U.S. Infty. was admit-<lb/>
ted to receiving tent at Post Hospital, Guanajay Barracks with some tem-<lb/>
perature; he complained of pains in head, back of neck, back and was vomit-<lb/>
ing at time of admission. On July 6th albumen was found in<lb/>
his urine in large quan<add>t</add>ities; that and other symptoms enabled the Surgeon<lb/>
in charge to make a diagnosis of Yellow Fever; then upon the recommanda-<lb/>
tion of the Post Commander he was moved to Civil Hospital in Guanajay <unclear><del>&sol;</del></unclear> C<lb/>
City <unclear><del>,</del></unclear> where there had been a case of Yellow Fever under treatment some<lb/>
time previous. The patient was moved with the object of preven-<lb/>
ting infection of Hospital and Post and the spread of the disease.<lb/>
Doctor Louis Gallinania, a thouroughly competent Cuban Physician, who is in<lb/>
charge of said Hospital,treated the above named soldier until the time of<lb/>
his death which was July 9th at 3.30 P.M.</p>
<p>The company quarters in which his Company was stationed was cleared of<lb/>
all bedding and company property, and the interior of building white wash-<lb/>
ed. The bedding etc. was disinfected in a solution of Mercury<lb/>
Bichloride.</p>
<p>All efforts on the part of the Surgeon and Post authorities to trace the<lb/>
origin of the disease proved fruitless. Soldier was inclined to<lb/>
intemperance and probably concealed some of his movements during the few<lb/>
days prior to his being taken sick.</p>
<p>Although he denied emphattically that he had visited any of the houses<lb/>
of prostitution where women from the infected district of Havana are at<lb/>
times temporarily quartered, it was the opinion of the Surgeon and others<lb/>
that he had done so and very probably contracted the disease during one<lb/>
of his visits to some one of said houses.</p>
<p>2-On July 20th Sergt. George Smith, Co. &ldquo;I&rdquo; 1st. U.S. Infty. was admitted to<lb/>
receiving tent at Post Hospital, Guanajay Barracks, with a temperature of <unclear>I00</unclear><lb/>
100f. He complained of severe head ache and pains in back, legs ect.</p>
<p>Albumen was found in urine July 20 in large quan<add>t</add>ity. When admitted<lb/>
patient was suffering from a severe case of Generrhea. He had<lb/>
visited the City of Havana, Cuba a few days before he was taken sick and<lb/>
probably contracted the Yellow Fever at that place. Patient<lb/>
remained in Hospital until July 29th, at which time he was returned to<lb/>
quarters and returned to duty August 5th. 1900.</p>
<p>3-On July 20th, 1900, Pvt. William Davidson, Co. &ldquo;I&rdquo;? 1st. U.S. Infty. was admitt<lb/>
ed to receiving tent at Post Hospital, Guanajay Barracks, with a tempera-<lb/>
ture of 100f. He complained of severe pains back of head, eyes, back<lb/>
and legs. No albumen was found in his urine. Patient had been in<lb/>
the City of Havana, Cuba a few days before he was taken sick and probably<lb/>
contracted the disease at that place. He remained in Hospital<lb/>
until July 29 at which time he was returned to quarters and returned to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02104002"/>
--2--<lb/>
duty August 5, 1900.</p>
<p>4- On July 21st, 1900 Pvt. Arthur Fastheff, Co &ldquo;M&rdquo; 1st. U.S. Infty., a patient in<lb/>
hospital had a temperature of 103f. at 4 o'clock P.M. he was first admitted<lb/>
to Post Hospital July 9th &sol; suffering from Generrhea and Chancreids. He<lb/>
was circumcised July 16th and had been confined to his bed from this time<lb/>
to date of first temperature. On July 21st Patient complained of<lb/>
severe pains in head and general pains or soreness all over body.</p>
<p>He was removed from ward after examination of blood had been made for<lb/>
Malarial Plasmodium, and placed in a receiving tent. Albumen appeared<lb/>
in his urine in large quan<add>t</add>ity July 25th, urine was examined daily and urine<lb/>
appeared in more and less quan<add>t</add>ities at each examination.</p>
<p>On July 30th. patient became delirious and remained in that condition <unclear><del>unt</del></unclear><lb/>
until 5 o'clock August 5th. 1900, at whitch time death occurred</p>
<p>5- On July 21st. Pvt Harry b Watson, Co. &ldquo;M&rdquo; 1st. U.S. Infty., a patient in<lb/>
Hospital had a temperature of 102 f. at 4 o'clock P.M. He was taken from<lb/>
the ward and placed in a receiving tent and urine examined.. No album<lb/>
men was found but other symptoms warranted diagnosis of yellow fever<lb/>
being made. Patient complained of severe pains in head and <unclear><del>ANGs</del></unclear>.<lb/>
He was first admitted to Hospital July 16th. suffering from Diarrhoea and<lb/>
probably contracted disease in the Hospital. He has now entire-<lb/>
ly recovered and is waiting transportation to join his organization.</p>
<p>6- On July 21st. Pvt. John D. Schweiger, Hospital Corps was admitted to<lb/>
receiving tent with a temperature of 102.6f. He complained of<lb/>
pains in head and soreness of legs and was vomiting when admitted to<lb/>
Hospital. Albumen was found in his urine on July 26th. and in-<lb/>
creased in quan<add>t</add>ity for three or four days, then began to decrease.<lb/>
Pvt. Schwieger had been on duty as nurse at the Post Hospital up to the<lb/>
time of being taken sick and probably contracted the disease while on<lb/>
duty. His temperature became normal July 31st. and he is now rapid-<lb/>
ly recovering and will be able for duty in a few days.</p>
<p>7- On July 21st Pvt Nels Rasmussen, Hospital Corps was taken sick and place<lb/>
in the receiving tent. His temperature on being admitted was 101f.<lb/>
and he was vomiting, but had no pains except a severe head ache.</p>
<p>No albumen was found in his urine. His highest temperature<lb/>
was 102.8f July 22, and decreased steadily until normal was reached July<lb/>
27. Patient was returned to duty August 9th. 1900.</p>
<p>8- On July 28 Pvt Owen Mercer, Co. &ldquo;I&rdquo;, 1st U.S. Infty. was admitted to receiv-<lb/>
ing tent at Post Hospital, Guanajay Barracks, with a temperature of 99.4f. He complained of severe head ache and Constipation. TTemperature in-<lb/>
creased until August 8th. when 103.8f. was reached; after this temperature de<lb/>
decreased. Albumen first appeared July 31st and increased for <unclear>s</unclear><lb/>
for several days. Patient is this date normal and recover-<lb/>
ing rapidly.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02104003"/>
<p>9-- On July 28th Act. Hosp. Steward Claude M. Cook, Hosp Corps, was admitted<lb/>
to receiving tent with a temperature of 103f. He complained of pains<lb/>
in head, back of eyes and kidneys. Albumen first appeared in urine<lb/>
July 31st and increased in quantity for three days then quantity began to<lb/>
decrease. Steward Cook had been on duty at the Hospital contin-<lb/>
uosly and had not been away from the Post and it is probable that he<lb/>
contracted the disease while on duty connected with the Hospital.<lb/>
He is now fully recovered and returned to duty this date.</p>
<p>10-- On August 7th Pvt John E Courtney, Hosp. Corps, was admitted to<lb/>
receiving tent with a temperature of 101f. He was suffering pains<lb/>
in head, back and lower portion of legs. Albumen found in urine Augus<lb/>
8th. Patient is now rapidly recovering and will be able for duty in<lb/>
a few days.</p>
<p>11-- On August 7th Sergt. Sylvester Haines, Co, &ldquo;I&rdquo; 1st. U.S. Infty. was admit-<lb/>
ted to receiving tent at Hospital with a temperature of 102.8f. He was<lb/>
suffering severe pains in head and back and was vomiting when admitted<lb/>
No albumen was found in his urine. Patient is now doing well<lb/>
and will be out of the Hospital in a few days.</p>
<p>12-- On July 16, 1900 Pvt. Harry Vance, Co? &ldquo;M&rdquo; 1st U.S. Infty. was admitted to<lb/>
Post Hospital, Guanajay Barracks, Cuba with a duoble fracture of lower Jaw<lb/>
He was kept in General Ward with other patients untill July 24th, when<lb/>
all patients were taken from the wards and placed in tents.<lb/>
On August 7 at 7 o'clock he complained of severe head ache,, temperature<lb/>
was taken and found to be 101 f. He was put in a seperate tent and urine<lb/>
examined and albumen found. Later in the day he complained of severe<lb/>
pains in back and lower portions of legs. His highest tempera-<lb/>
ture was<lb/>
On August 14th patient had a severe attack of Uremic Coma, due to suppres-<lb/>
sion of Urine. His temperature at this date is normal and he wi<lb/>
will be ready for duty in a short time.</p>
<p>No <add>new</add> cases of yellow fever nor temperatures <add>since</add> August 7, 1900.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully submitted,</salute>
<signed>J.F. Dunshie</signed>
Ac&sol;Asst. Surgeon, U.S. Army,<lb/>
Surgeon.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
