<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02118001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Article: Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine: Yellow Fever Expedition, by Herbert E. Durham and Walter Myers, September 8, 1900</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Durham, Herbert E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02118001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-09-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Durham, Herbert E.</name>
<name type="person">Myers, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-09-08">September 8, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02118001</idno>
<title>Article: Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine: Yellow Fever Expedition, by Herbert E. Durham and Walter Myers, September 8, 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Durham and Myers discuss the investigation of yellow fever by the American commission in Cuba and the perplexing nature of the disease.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1900-09-08">
<head>Article: Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine: Yellow Fever Expedition, by Herbert E. Durham and Walter Myers, September 8, 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02118001"/>
<p>656<lb/>
THE BRITISH]<lb/>
MEDICAL JOURNAL]</p>
<p>LIVERPOOL YELLOW FEVER EXPEDITION.</p>
<p><unclear>Bran</unclear></p>
<p>[SEPT. 8, 1900.</p>
<p>LIVERPOOL SCHOOL OF TROPICAL MEDICINE:<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER EXPEDITION.</p>
<p>SOME PRELIMINARY NOTES<lb/>
BY<lb/>
HERBERT E. DURHAM and WALTER MYERS,<lb/>
F.R.C.S. M.B., B.C. Camb.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>NOTWITHSTANDING the acumen and the number of those who<lb/>
have attacked the question of the prevalence of yellow<lb/>
fever, much mystery and uncertainty still enshroud the<lb/>
epidemiology of the disease. The etiology, also, is not yet<lb/>
determined with certainty; the claim of Sanarelli that his so-<lb/>
called &ldquo;bacillus icteroides&rdquo; is the true cause of yellow fever<lb/>
has not found favour with several workers who have made<lb/>
search in this direction. By the kind invitation of<lb/>
Dr. Sternberg, Surgeon-General of the U.S. Army, we had the<lb/>
opportunity of conferring with the commission (Drs. Reed,<lb/>
Carroll and Lazear) appointed by him to study the question in<lb/>
Cuba. We may here express our gratitude to these gentlemen<lb/>
for the most kind and courteous reception that they extended<lb/>
towards us, as well as to Major Gorgas (U.S. Army), the head<lb/>
of the bureau of inspection of infectious diseases in the city of<lb/>
Havana. We also had the pleasure and advantage of<lb/>
meeting Dr. Carter (of the U.S. Maine Hospital Service).<lb/>
Dr. Guiteras (now Professor in the Havana School of<lb/>
Tropical Diseases), Dr. Finlay, and Drs. Bango and Martinez<lb/>
(practitioners in the city.)</p>
<p>Amongst the many conflicting opinions and statements<lb/>
concerning the disease it appears certain that neither the<lb/>
handling of or contact with yellow fever patients nor the per-<lb/>
formance of necropsies is capable <hi rend="italic">per se</hi> of conveying the disease<lb/>
to non-immunes. It also appears probable that general ship's<lb/>
cargoes and the fomites of patients are also not directly<lb/>
infective; here, however, the evidence is not conclusive, and<lb/>
the present quarantine regulations require disinfection of all<lb/>
clothes and personal effects before they may be introduced<lb/>
into the United States.</p>
<p>It seems to be fairly definitely established that a yellow-<lb/>
fever patient may become a danger by &ldquo;infecting the house&rdquo;<lb/>
in which he is placed. Given that a house is &ldquo;infected,&rdquo; a<lb/>
visit by a non-immune person entails considerable risk of<lb/>
contracting the malady. It is alleged by some that visits<lb/>
made at night are more dangerous than those made during<lb/>
the daytime; but here the evidence is not very clear, and is<lb/>
more of the nature of an opinion. The nature of the essen-<lb/>
tial factor present in an &ldquo;infected house&rdquo; is as yet mys-<lb/>
terious. One house after another in a street may become<lb/>
&ldquo;infected&rdquo; without any apparent intercommunication of the<lb/>
inmates; the infection may skip over one or more houses and<lb/>
reappear at some distance. There are those who are bold<lb/>
enough to predict in a village that such and such a house will<lb/>
yield one or more cases of the fever on or about a certain day;<lb/>
and naturally they claim to be true prophets.</p>
<p>Of the interesting and important facts which have been<lb/>
ascertained, those elucidated by Dr. Carter in his study of<lb/>
outbreaks at Orwood and Taylor (Miss) in 1898 are second to<lb/>
none.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The conditions were such that the intervals between<lb/>
the introduction of &ldquo;infecting&rdquo; cases and the onset of<lb/>
secondary cases could be followed with accuracy. Dr. Carter<lb/>
finds that an interval of about fourteen to twenty-one days<lb/>
obtains before the first secondary cases occur. The house is<lb/>
then in an &ldquo;infected&rdquo; condition, and exposure for a few<lb/>
hours (for example, in one case four hours and a half) can lead<lb/>
to infection, with the incubation interval up to the normal<lb/>
four or five days. This was exemplified to us by the history of<lb/>
a case at Quemados, for which we are indebted to Dr. Reed.<lb/>
In a house which had been occupied by non-immune officers<lb/>
all last year, two cases of yellow fever occurred this summer; one<lb/>
of these was unfortunately fatal. However, a male and<lb/>
a female nurse who had been occupied in tending the<lb/>
patients did not acquire the disease until about a fortnight<lb/>
after the death occurred. Other sources of infection could be<lb/>
excluded in these cases. No further cases occurred, as the<lb/>
house was cleared and liberally treated with perchloride.<lb/>
The slight epidemic, however, spread to other houses down<lb/>
the street, although they were detached and surrounded by a<lb/>
small amount of garden space.</p>
<p>This curious and somewhat prolonged interval is suggestive<lb/>
of a development of the infecting factor in or about some<lb/>
agent or matter in the domicile. What may be the nature of<lb/>
this supposed agent is not yet demonstrated, but the sugges-<lb/>
tion propounded by Dr. C. Finlay, of Havana, some twenty<lb/>
years ago, that the disease was spread by means of mosquitos<lb/>
hardly appears so fanciful in the light of recent discoveries in<lb/>
ague convection as appeared in the days when the idea was<lb/>
first broached. Dr. Finlay's hypothesis is able to account for<lb/>
several curious points which obtain with yellow fever. Thus<lb/>
the limitation of the disease to the &ldquo;yellow fever zone,&rdquo; where<lb/>
frost is unknown, the coincidence of yellow fever and rainy<lb/>
seasons, the cessation of the disease when the temperature<lb/>
falls below a certain point, and its non-recrudescence in an<lb/>
infected locality after a frost, are all compatible with an<lb/>
agency, such as a gnat, which becomes too sluggish to bite, or<lb/>
indeed which dies out in unfavourable climatic conditions.<lb/>
Such a theory also explains the curious spread of the disease<lb/>
from house to house, which has already been referred to.<lb/>
Another point is that the sanitary condition of a house may<lb/>
be good, and yet it may be severely &ldquo;infected.&rdquo; An example<lb/>
of this was shown by the case of one of the leading hotels in<lb/>
Havana, of good sanitary repute, but the source of many<lb/>
fever cases this summer. The above sketch will suffice<lb/>
to show that some means of transmission by the aid of an<lb/>
intermediate host--a town-loving host for this town-loving<lb/>
disease--is to some extent more plausible than might be<lb/>
anticipated. Whether that hypothetical host is of the nature<lb/>
of a gnat remains unknown.</p>
<p>It is commonly stated that one attack of the fever confers a<lb/>
long and lasting immunity against further attacks. The com-<lb/>
pleteness of this immunity, however, is called in question by<lb/>
the cases which we had the opportunity of seeing. Thus out<lb/>
of the two or three dozen cases we saw, no fewer than four<lb/>
were reputed to have had previous attacks; the previous<lb/>
attacks were not believed in as genuine yellow fever by those<lb/>
physicians who accept a rigid immunity as the fact. A few<lb/>
words may be said of one of these cases as illustrative <unclear>of</unclear><lb/>
several points.</p>
<p>A lady had an attack of yellow fever in New Orleans, at the age of 19. <unclear>in</unclear><lb/>
1866; her account of the symptoms she experienced, and the fact that <unclear>his</unclear><lb/>
sister had a &ldquo;typical&rdquo; attack at the same time tend to the conclusion<lb/>
that the illness was indeed yellow fever. Last year she was occupied <unclear>a</unclear><lb/>
an &ldquo;immune&rdquo; in nursing yellow fever cases in Cuba during July and<lb/>
August, and then remained in the outskirts of Havana (Cerro) for <unclear>the</unclear><lb/>
winter and spring. This summer she went to live in an insanitary <unclear>house</unclear><lb/>
close to the hotel we have already alluded to as an infected house<lb/>
situated in an &ldquo;infected&rdquo; neighbourhood. She soon contracted an <unclear>illue</unclear><lb/>
of the nature of which there could be no doubt--a severe and <unclear>prolonge</unclear><lb/>
attack of yellow fever.</p>
<p>But our knowledge of infectious diseases all goes to <unclear>show</unclear><lb/>
that a complete and absolute immunity is never acquired <unclear>be</unclear><lb/>
a single attack, though second attacks are usually of a <unclear>com</unclear><lb/>
paratively mild, or at any rate recoverable, type.</p>
<p>The coloured people and natives are also supposed to <unclear>escape</unclear><lb/>
the disease, but we are informed that this is a statement<lb/>
which is not true, although so frequently repeated in <unclear>text</unclear><lb/>
books. We were lucky enough to see one negro during <unclear>the</unclear><lb/>
course of a typical attack. The Cubans and the <unclear>Cuban</unclear><lb/>
doctors are in the habit of asserting that the Cuban <unclear>system</unclear><lb/>
is not capable of having yellow fever. It appears, however<lb/>
that they are not unknown to suffer from a disease <unclear>call</unclear><lb/>
&ldquo;borras.&rdquo; Clinically &ldquo;borras&rdquo; is like yellow fever--some-<lb/>
times with black vomit and death with suppression of <unclear>urin</unclear><lb/>
pathologically the lesions of yellow fever are said to be <unclear>prese</unclear><lb/>
in fatal cases. The Cubans also suffer and die from <unclear>&ldquo;p</unclear><lb/>
nicious malarial fever,&rdquo; the symptomatology and <unclear>pathological</unclear><lb/>
anatomy of which are very suggestive of yellow fever. <unclear>[unclear]</unclear><lb/>
were informed that the Cuban children frequently suffer from<lb/>
mild attacks of fever, which our informants believe are <unclear>rea</unclear><lb/>
mild attacks of yellow fever, and which give a <unclear>comparat</unclear><lb/>
immunity in after-life.</p>
<p>It has already been mentioned that a sojourn of a <unclear>non-immu</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02118002"/>
SEPT. 8, 1900.]<lb/>
AMPUTATION AT HIP-JOINT FOR GUNSHOT.<lb/>
[THE BRITISH<lb/>
MEDICAL JOURNAL<lb/>
657<lb/>
for some hours in an infected house is very liable to lead to<lb/>
an attack; and that this is supposed to be especially the case<lb/>
at night. Since many of the cases we saw were soldiers, their<lb/>
movements could be traced to some extent, and in more than<lb/>
one instance there was evidence of a single exposure after<lb/>
breaking bounds for a single night. Similar experiences are<lb/>
told of ship's crews under similar circumstances; another<lb/>
example is to be found in the case of ICO American military<lb/>
prisoners who were confined in a barrack in which there had<lb/>
been several hundred deaths through yellow fever during the<lb/>
previous year of Spanish occupation; none of these prisoners<lb/>
acquired the disease, but some 25 of their custodians fell ill or<lb/>
died of the fever.</p>
<p>Through the courtesy of Major Gorgas we were enabled to<lb/>
see the distribution of the fatal cases of yellow fever in the<lb/>
city for the past ten years. In these it was rather striking<lb/>
that the more disreputable quarters of the town were free from<lb/>
deaths from this cause. Immigrant women are few, and pre-<lb/>
sumably the inhabitants are all &ldquo;immunes;&rdquo; still it is not<lb/>
improbable that the infective agent is harboured amongst<lb/>
them.</p>
<p>These few notes on some epidemiological points are sub-<lb/>
mitted in the hope that they may be of some interest to stu-<lb/>
dents of the perplexing questions and of the unravelled<lb/>
natural history of yellow fever.</p>
<p>REFERENCE.<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><hi rend="italic">New Orlcans Medical and Surgical Journal</hi>, May, 1900.</p>
<p>==========</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
