<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02158001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from William Ludlow to the Adjutant General, October 27, 1900</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Ludlow, William</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02158001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-10-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Adjutant General</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Brooke, Roger</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-10-27">October 27, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02158001</idno>
<title>Letter from William Ludlow to the Adjutant General, October 27, 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ludlow defends his position against Wood's charges of concealing facts about yellow fever in Havana. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1900-10-27">
<head>Letter from William Ludlow to the Adjutant General, October 27, 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02158001"/>
<opener>
1744 G Street, N.W.<lb/>
WAR COLLEGE BOARD<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1900-10-27">October 27, 1900</date>
</dateline><lb/>
To the<lb/>
Adjutant General, U.S.A.,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>As a matter of official record I enclose certain publica-<lb/>
tions and correspondence, growing out of recent interviews with<lb/>
General Wood by newspaper correspondents, viz: a <xref id="N2158005">clipping</xref> from the<lb/>
New York Evening Post of October 23; my note of October 24 to<lb/>
General Wood; an extended <xref id="N2158004">interview</xref> with him in the Evening Post of<lb/>
October 24; his reply, dated October 25, to my note of the 24th,<lb/>
which reached me October 26, subsequent to his departure from the<lb/>
City; and my further letter to him of October 27;- there are also<lb/>
two <xref id="N2158005">clippings</xref> from the Evening Post of October 26, covering brief<lb/>
statements from General Brooke and me.</p>
<p>I am not concerned with explanations of the existing<lb/>
epidemic of yellow fever in Havana, or elsewhere in Cuba, having no<lb/>
responsibility in the Island and no more knowledge of current<lb/>
events there than I may derive from newspapers, but I am concerned<lb/>
with the refutation of any declaration or intimation of suppression<lb/>
or perversion of any material fact pertaining to my former official<lb/>
responsibility, and I desire to characterize as wholly false and<lb/>
pernicious the imputation that the data as to yellow fever were in<lb/>
any wise concealed or kept secret during my administration.</p>
<p>It was with the purpose of giving him the opportunity to<lb/>
make public correction or the misstatements attributed to him that<lb/>
my note to General Wood was made, and my expectation in the matter<lb/>
would have been met by an explicit and frank denial to me and to<lb/>
the press that he had either made such an accusation or believed it<lb/>
to be true.</p>
<p>His reply, I regret to say, does not do this, and in draft-<lb/>
ing it, as well as in his interview of the 24th,<lb/>
he has overlooked certain facts that must be officially known<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02158002"/>
-2-<lb/>
to him, and certainly should have been fully considered when<lb/>
the ignoring of them leads to erroneous and misleading statements<lb/>
reflecting injuriously upon other officers.</p>
<p>The facts are these:</p>
<p>1. The utmost endeavor was made to enforce with penalties any<lb/>
concealment of a suspicious case of infectious or contagious disease<lb/>
of any kind. All such were to be immediately reported by telephone<lb/>
or messenger to the Chief Sanitary Officer. All cases were im-<lb/>
mediately investigated and due measures taken, by isolation or removal<lb/>
of patient and thorough disinfection of premises and belongings.</p>
<p>2. A special yellow fever board was appointed of Army sur-<lb/>
geons and civil physicians of high standing for the express purpose<lb/>
of investigating and diagnosing cases and prescribing disposition.</p>
<p>3. Daily reports were made by the Chief Sanitary Officer to<lb/>
my office and forwarded to General Brooke, giving all particulars<lb/>
of cases, etc., and these data were open to public inspection and<lb/>
use and at the disposal of the press in all three offices.</p>
<p>4. Every month a printed report of vital statistics, of the<lb/>
form enclosed, was issued and widely distributed in the United<lb/>
States as well as in the Island, giving accurate and authentic parti-<lb/>
culars, and effecting full publicity as to all the data in question.</p>
<p>5. In addition, the annual reports gave the consolidated<lb/>
statistics in full, with analyses and discussions.</p>
<p>It would be difficult to provide a more effective and gen-<lb/>
eral means of distributing valid information in a matter of so much<lb/>
public interest, and in fact publicity was neither avoidable nor<lb/>
avoided.</p>
<p>The yellow fever had ceased to be a matter of serious con-<lb/>
cern, either to ourselves or to our friends in the United States.<lb/>
The command was free from it. Civil cases, due to the heavy non-<lb/>
immune importations, were entirely under control, no case being per-<lb/>
mitted to give rise to another, and the general conditions were<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02158003"/>
-3-<lb/>
so far satisfactory as to be matter of congratulation instead of<lb/>
apprehension. There was no &ldquo;panic&rdquo; of any kind, nor any &ldquo;deluge<lb/>
of anxious letters&rdquo; from the United States or elsewhere.</p>
<p>There was and could be no objection to the publication<lb/>
of this information, and official means were used to secure it.<lb/>
It was refused to no one, and the newspaper correspondents could<lb/>
have reported it every day had they thought it of sufficient inter-<lb/>
est and importance to cable.</p>
<p>General Wood has the right to protect himself from hostile<lb/>
criticism by any legitimate means at his disposal, but exceeds both<lb/>
his rights as an individual, and his obligations due to his service,<lb/>
in seeking to defend himself by impugning the administration of<lb/>
others and furnishing the material for public misrepresentation.</p>
<p>As this matter has been given so much publicity, I desire<lb/>
that this communication be laid before the Secretary of War and be<lb/>
made of record in the War Department.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Your obedient servant,</salute>
<signed>William Ludlow.</signed>
Brigadier General, U.S.A.<lb/>
8 Enclosures.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
