<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02237001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Henry Rose Carter, December 13, 1900</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Gorgas, William Crawford</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02237001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-12-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carter, Henry Rose</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="place">Havana (CUba)</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Cabanas (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Guanabacoa (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-12-13">December 13, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02237001</idno>
<title>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Henry Rose Carter, December 13, 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed's experiments have convinced Gorgas that the mosquito theory is valid. Gorgas discusses the implications for sanitation and non-immune troops.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1900-12-13">
<head>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Henry Rose Carter, December 13, 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02237001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Headquarters Department of Cuba.<lb/>
OFFICE OF CHIEF SANITARY OFFICER OF HAVANA<lb/>
Havana, Cuba,<date value="1900-12-13">December 13, 1900</date>
</dateline>
LA MAESTRANZA<lb/>
CALLE DE CUBA<lb/>
ENTRE CUARTELES Y CHACON<lb/>
Dr. H. R. Carter,<lb/>
Marine-Hospital Service,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md..
<salute>My Dear Carter,-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Yours of November 24th received. Am so much pleased at the<lb/>
news you give of your general health. While I have been pretty cer-<lb/>
tain that you had no serious cerebral organic lesion, I have been anx-<lb/>
ious to hear the opinion of such men as <unclear>Osl</unclear> or other equally good<lb/>
diagnosticians on the case. If it were possible, I think it would be<lb/>
a great thing for you and for <add>the</add> corps, for you to return to Havana and<lb/>
help us out. It seems to me we are on the high road toward revolu-<lb/>
tionizing sanitation, as far as yellow fever is concerned. Your ex-<lb/>
perienc<del>ed</del> <add>&amp;</add> skill on this subject, would be most valuable down here.<lb/>
Why could you not be attached for work in connection with yellow fever,<lb/>
and just be <del>given</del> a free lance? Have nothing to do with the Marine-<lb/>
Hospital work proper, of Havana; just act as a member of the Board and<lb/>
have a finger in the pie generally. I think it is a waste of time, and<lb/>
more than one man can do, for you to attempt to work as you did last<lb/>
summer. The Marine-Hospital work (excuse me for saying it) is unim-<lb/>
portant compared to the yellow fever work and the same man cannot at-<lb/>
tend to both.</p>
<p>Ross <del>is</del> <add>has</add> about conclud<del>ing</del><add>ed</add> <del>the contract and</del> <add>L-</add> joins us, and we are<lb/>
whetting our swords and patching our badly dilapidated armor for next<lb/>
summer's work.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02237002"/>
<p>I think yellow fever is about over for the season. We have<lb/>
this morning twenty six cases under treatment, and have had for the<lb/>
month, twenty seven new cases. This is less than we had for the simi-<lb/>
lar period last year.</p>
<p>Reed and his Board are making most extensive experiments in the<lb/>
line of Finlay's mosquito theory, and in the line of R<del><unclear>eds'</unclear></del><add>eeds</add> preliminary<lb/>
report. Evidence seems to point very strongly to the mosquito being<lb/>
the transmitter of the disease. There was so much evidence against<lb/>
it that I was not at all impressed with the few cases reported in his<lb/>
original article but his experiments since, have about convinced me.<lb/>
I think there is no doubt that the mosquito does transmit yellow fever<lb/>
and the probabilities seem to me that he is the intermediate <add>host</add><del>post</del>. In<lb/>
case this is proved, the probabilities, I think, would point to the<lb/>
fact that he is the only means of transmission. This fact establish-<lb/>
ed, you can see what an important effect it would have upon the sani-<lb/>
tary measures that would be taken for eradicating the disease. There<lb/>
are so many points that seem to me contrary to this theory, so many in<lb/>
my own experience, like the nurses at Las Animas Hospital and the ap-<lb/>
parent development of fever at isolated points such as those this year<lb/>
in Mississippi, that I was very averse to receiving the theory, <add>but</add><del>and</del> a<lb/>
few absolutely positive experiments outweigh any amount of negative<lb/>
evidence. So I think if you want to be in at the killing, you had<lb/>
better come down this winter. I think we are about to make a historic<lb/>
campaign against yellow jack in Havana next summer, and such a season-<lb/>
ed old veteran as you ought to have part in such a climax.</p>
<p>I have not included the military in the immigration statistics<lb/>
because I have not been able to determine a fair estimate for their<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02237003"/>
numbers. The whole number of troops arriving has not much bearing<lb/>
upon who remain in Havana. As far as I can find, the new troops were<lb/>
kept for only a few days at Caba&ntilde;as and the suburbs of Havana, and<lb/>
shipped at once to their destinations over the Island. According to<lb/>
a little work I have, published by a Spanish officer, the garrison of<lb/>
Havana includ<del><unclear>es</unclear></del><add>ing</add> Guanabac&oacute;a and a good many small forts around, not<lb/>
in the area at present included in Havana, was up to '95, 3,000, in-<lb/>
creased in '97 to 10,000 and in '98 to 30,000. I think it would be<lb/>
fair to have this garrison represent the maximum of the non-immune<lb/>
military population subject to fever in Havana. While they would ra-<lb/>
pidly acquire immunity, the non-immunes from other garrisons around<lb/>
the Island coming to Havana on business and pleasure, and the recruits<lb/>
yearly added to this number to replace men whose service has expired,<lb/>
will probably keep this garrison with its full <del>quarter</del><add>quota</add> of non-immunes.<lb/>
I shall soon be able to speak more definitely on this subject. The<lb/>
Spanish records give the designation of the commands stationed in Ha-<lb/>
vana <del>toward</del><add>during</add> this time. The records give the names of the commands to<lb/>
which the men who die in Havana belonged. In this way I can get a<lb/>
pretty fair idea of what the garrison of Havana furnished. I think<lb/>
the fairest comparison is the total number of non-immunes. To take<lb/>
1900 with 30,000 non-immune civilians present and compare it with '97<lb/>
when there were probably not 2,000 non-immunes present is no basis for<lb/>
comparison and to likewise take 1900 when there were less than 1,000<lb/>
soldiers within the limits of Havana, and compare it with '98 when<lb/>
there were 30,000, is unfair. I will publish the tables under the<lb/>
head of civil and military with the totals, leaving others to draw re-<lb/>
ductions. We get our immigration statistics from the books of the<lb/>
captain of the port previous to 1900, since Bliss has been keeping<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02237004"/>
them, we have gotten them, from him. I think the disinfection and<lb/>
isolation has had a very considerable effect in limiting the disease.<lb/>
You will see that there are a large number of cases in which only one<lb/>
case occurred in a house and while the majority of the people in most<lb/>
of these houses were immunes, I think it will be found in the majority<lb/>
of the cases that there were one or two other non-immunes in the house.<lb/>
Most of the cases occurred in the person of Spanish servants and very<lb/>
generally families who keep servants at all have more than one. In<lb/>
all small stores and <hi>bodegas</hi> there are several Spaniards.</p>
<p>We expect <del>Irene</del><add>Ailien</add> down for Christmas. Mrs. Gorgas is well and<lb/>
joins in kindest regards. Plummer, Lyster and Skockley are still in<lb/>
the office with me and ask to be remembered.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely your friend,</salute>
<signed><unclear>W. C.</unclear> Gorgas</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
