<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02265001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Memorandum of the Misstatements Attributed to General Wood in Published Interviews and Made by him in Formal Communication, by William Ludlow, December 1900</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Ludlow, William</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02265001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-12-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">General Wood</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Ludlow, William</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-12-00">December 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02265001</idno>
<title>Memorandum of the Misstatements Attributed to General Wood in Published Interviews and Made by him in Formal Communication, by William Ludlow, December 1900</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ludlow states he never concealed the yellow fever statistics, but that they were actually available to the public at all times. Ludlow then criticizes Wood for not giving accurate information to the newspapers. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1900-12-00">
<head>Memorandum of the Misstatements Attributed to General Wood in Published Interviews and Made by him in Formal Communication, by William Ludlow, December 1900</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02265001"/>
<p>ADJUTANT GENL'S OFFICE<lb/>
DEC 3 1900<lb/>
A. C. P. DIVISION.</p>
<p>MEMORANDUM OF THE MISSTATEMENTS ATTRIBUTED TO GENERAL WOOD<lb/>
IN PUBLISHED INTERVIEWS AND MADE BY HIM IN FORMAL<lb/>
COMMUNICATIONS.</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>New York Sun, October 22. &ldquo;There is nothing new in the yellow<lb/>
fever epidemic. It is not as large as last year, but the difference is<lb/>
that the number of cases were kept secret last December while now the<lb/>
figures are open to the public. Havana's yellow fever record last<lb/>
December and January was the largest in ten years, but it was concealed.<lb/>
Now everyone knows all about the number of cases.&rdquo; &ldquo;The immigration<lb/>
of non-immunes into Havana is largely responsible for the present yel-<lb/>
low fever outbreak, but considering that there are 300,000 people in<lb/>
Havana and only about 100 sick daily in the hospitals, the sick rate is<lb/>
not so very large.&rdquo;</p>
<p>New York Evening Post, October 23. &ldquo;Statistics of yellow fever<lb/>
were not given out last year as freely as they are this year.&rdquo; &ldquo;It is<lb/>
the effort of the &lsquo;existing&rsquo; government in Cuba to keep the public in-<lb/>
formed candidly on all subjects.&rdquo; &ldquo;The idea that Havana was well cleaned<lb/>
up a year ago is an error.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Evening Post, October 24. Asked why the figures of the yellow<lb/>
fever epidemic in Havana for last December and January had been concealed,<lb/>
General Wood said &ldquo;he had been misinterpreted; he did not say that the<lb/>
&ldquo;figures had been concealed, but that it had not been the practice to<lb/>
&ldquo;publish current reports. The representatives of two leading press<lb/>
&ldquo;associations came to him early in 1900 asking permission to print the<lb/>
&ldquo;yellow fever figures for the last six months. He had given them per-<lb/>
&ldquo;mission, and from that time forward the press always had access to the<lb/>
&ldquo;figures.&rdquo; The obvious intimation is that permission to print and<lb/>
access to figures had previously been denied, and General Wood accounts<lb/>
for this by saying that while &ldquo;he had never intended to intimate an<lb/>
attempt to deceive the public&rdquo;, probably &ldquo;the subject had been &lsquo;passed<lb/>
&ldquo;over&rsquo; with the assent of the press representatives on account of the<lb/>
&ldquo;&lsquo;panicky&rsquo; condition of public feeling in the United States. Army<lb/>
&ldquo;officers in Cuba had been deluged with anxious letters from relatives<lb/>
&ldquo;who assumed the fever was going to make great inroads in the Army,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02265002"/>
-2-<lb/>
&ldquo;and possibly it was to avert distress of innocent persons at a dis-<lb/>
&ldquo;tance that the matter was virtually ignored.&rdquo; For himself, &ldquo;he said<lb/>
&ldquo;the fever last December made a worse showing than at any time during<lb/>
&ldquo;the previous ten years; also that whereas the old Spanish mortality<lb/>
&ldquo;from yellow fever ran as high as 40 or 45 per cent of the cases, it<lb/>
&ldquo;now ranges about 9 or 10 per cent. One of the things made plain by<lb/>
&ldquo;the studies of the sanitarians was that the increase in the fever keeps<lb/>
&ldquo;uniform pace with the increase of immigration. His remark with regard<lb/>
&ldquo;to the cleanliness of the city a year ago was a misunderstanding. He<lb/>
&ldquo;meant to say that the Sanitary Corps had been at work steadily ever<lb/>
&ldquo;since, and necessarily the city must be in a much more wholesome state.</p>
<p>As a m<del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>a</add>tter of fact, not only had the yellow fever data been at<lb/>
all times freely at the disposition of the press, been circulated offi-<lb/>
cially and otherwise in the monthly and annual reports, and been sent<lb/>
all over the world every week in the Public Health Bulletins; but at the<lb/>
very time when these press associations were represented as seeking<lb/>
permission to print, an official report for the entire calendar year<lb/>
1899 and the decade from 1890 had been printed and issued from the<lb/>
Sanitary Office. A copy of this document is herewith.</p>
<p>General Wood's other misstatements as to the large December, 1899,<lb/>
and January, 1900, mortality and the present small per cent of fatali-<lb/>
ties to cases will be referred to further on.</p>
<p>Having no responsibility in Cuba since May 1, 1900, and having<lb/>
been abroad all summer, I was without specific information as to the<lb/>
present sanitary condition of Havana, but was directly concerned with<lb/>
the intimation of concealment or suppression of data during my adminis-<lb/>
tration.</p>
<p>To enable General Wood, then in Washington, to correct this mis-<lb/>
information, I wrote to him at once, October 24, enclosing the news-<lb/>
paper clippings, and requesting him to make his disclaimer and repudia-<lb/>
tion of the statement as direct and public as was the charge itself.<lb/>
His reply was dated October 25. He said that his statements had been<lb/>
misconstrued as making any reflection upon a previous administration<lb/>
in Havana. That the press were now publishing daily official bulletins<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02265003"/>
-3-<lb/>
which it had not done in the previous year, and &ldquo;consequently we see<lb/>
a great deal more of yellow fever news.&rdquo; &ldquo;The wisdom of publishing<lb/>
the exact situation is a matter of individual opinion&rdquo;, but he does not<lb/>
censure a failure to do this. On arrival in this country he had been<lb/>
questioned about yellow fever and found that the fever this year was<lb/>
considered rather extraordinary and in correcting this he had stated<lb/>
that. &ldquo;The sanitary condition of Havana today is better than ever; the<lb/>
total death rate from all causes is lower; the yellow fever situation<lb/>
in Havana is not serious, and is due entirely, in my opinion, to the<lb/>
large number of Spanish immigrants reaching Havana.&rdquo; He further states<lb/>
the civil death rate in Havana from yellow fever in December, 1899, was<lb/>
the heaviest of any December in ten years. As this letter of General<lb/>
Wood's was evasive and misleading, and by indirection tended to confirm<lb/>
the substantial correctness of the newspaper interviews, I wrote him<lb/>
again on the 27th, stating in reference to my first communication that<lb/>
my expectation in the matter would have been met by an explicit and<lb/>
frank denial, to me and to the press, that he had either made an accu-<lb/>
sation of suppression or concealment or believed it to be true. I re-<lb/>
gretted that his letter of the 25th, as well as his interview in the<lb/>
Evening Post of the 24th, did not do this, and stated that I should sub-<lb/>
mit the correspondence and other material for official information and<lb/>
record at the War Department.</p>
<p>On the 27th I wrote the Adjutant General, enclosing copies of<lb/>
the correspondence, clippings, etc., stating that in his communications<lb/>
General Wood had overlooked certain facts that must have been officially<lb/>
known to him, showing the means taken to secure publicity of all data,<lb/>
by the unrestricted access of newspaper people to the daily reports and<lb/>
records and by the numerous official publications of the facts. I<lb/>
stated that assertions of panic and anxiety and the &ldquo;deluge of anxious<lb/>
letters&rdquo; were entirely erroneous, no such conditions existing during my<lb/>
administration; and that General Wood had exceeded both his rights as<lb/>
an individual and his obligations to the military service in seeking to<lb/>
defend himself by impugning the administration of others and furnishing<lb/>
material for public misrepresentation.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f02265004"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>Subsequently General Wood, under date of November 3, made<lb/>
letters to the New York Evening Post and the New York Sun, which were<lb/>
printed in their issues of November 7.</p>
<p>In his letter to the Sun, he denies that he stated directly or<lb/>
indirectly that the fever situation had been concealed. He proceeds to<lb/>
state that in December, 1899, there were more deaths in the civil<lb/>
population from yellow fever than in any December in ten years. That<lb/>
the exact fever situation, under his direction, was given to the press<lb/>
for general publication daily. That in the Fall of 1899 this method<lb/>
was not adopted; that statements were then made monthly and compara-<lb/>
tively little was heard of yellow fever. He also states that the<lb/>
conditions this year were due to the enormous number of Spanish immi-<lb/>
grants. That Havana was cleaner today than ever and the sanitary con-<lb/>
dition of the city better than before, as shown by the reduction in the<lb/>
total death rate. He again declared that there was nothing in his<lb/>
published statements that could be properly construed as a charge of<lb/>
any concealment of yellow fever.</p>
<p>In his letter to the Evening Post he declares the interview in<lb/>
the Evening Post of the 24th unjust to General Ludlow, General Brooke,<lb/>
and to himself. That he had never made any statement from which in-<lb/>
ferences of the kind could be drawn, and desires the impression corrected.<lb/>
He again recites what he did say: that the sanitary condition of Havana<lb/>
is at present better than ever before; that on the whole Havana is<lb/>
cleaner today than ever; that the yellow fever situation is not<lb/>
especially serious and was due entirely to the enormous number of<lb/>
Spanish immigrants pouring through the Port; that in 1899 the month<lb/>
of December presented the heaviest death rate among the civil popula-<lb/>
tion from yellow fever of any December for ten years; that the fever<lb/>
continued all winter and &ldquo;all realized that the present summer would<lb/>
be a bad summer for fever&rdquo;; that he was now publishing daily the ex-<lb/>
act yellow fever situation; that in the Fall of 1899 there was not a<lb/>
general daily publication of the yellow fever situation, and conse-<lb/>
quently comparatively little was heard of it. That he had said<lb/>
nothing that implied there had been any concealment of the fever.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f02265005"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>Further under date of November 3, General Wood wrote to the<lb/>
Adjutant General enclosing copy of my letter to him, also of his commu-<lb/>
nications to the Sun and Evening Post. He states in this letter that<lb/>
he believes it will be seen on looking over the correspondence that<lb/>
&ldquo;a good deal of unnecessary importance&rdquo; has been attached to the<lb/>
matter; that it will be evident that he (General Wood) &ldquo;had said very<lb/>
little and the newspaper reporter had inferred a great deal&rdquo;; and that<lb/>
to correct this inference, for which he declares himself not responsible,<lb/>
he had written the within letters. In fact, examination of the corres-<lb/>
pondence and interviews leads to a conclusion the reverse of that<lb/>
stated by General Wood, viz., that he had said a great deal and the<lb/>
newspaper reporter had inferred very little.</p>
<p>On November 5, General Wood wrote to the editor of the Outlook<lb/>
Magazine, which had published a statement quoting General Wood as<lb/>
saying &ldquo;that the recent increase in yellow fever is attributable to a<lb/>
large immigration of Spaniards, and that in point of fact the epidemic<lb/>
is not more extensive than usual at this time of year nor than it was<lb/>
a year ago, although at that time a full report was not made to the public.&rdquo;<lb/>
He denies that he ever said that full reports were not made public, and<lb/>
he had stated only that the reports were not published last year &ldquo;in<lb/>
the same manner&rdquo; as at present; there was nothing in his remark to<lb/>
warrant any implication that yellow fever had been concealed; and that<lb/>
nothing could be further from the fact. He does not, however, correct<lb/>
the other misstatements attributed to him in the Outlook, and renews his<lb/>
assertion that the yellow fever situation is not serious.</p>
<p>In Collier's Weekly of November 3 an article by General Wood<lb/>
appears, containing the statement that the sanitary conditions, every-<lb/>
thing considered, are better today than ever before known in Havana;<lb/>
that the yellow fever is &ldquo;not so much to be feared&rdquo;, and that its pre-<lb/>
sence this year in Cuba, and especially in Havana, is due almost entirely<lb/>
to the number of Spanish immigrants.</p>
<p>By all these communications under his own name, General Wood<lb/>
denies imputing concealment or suppression, but repeats and adheres to<lb/>
several declarations which are equally in conflict with the facts, and<lb/>
tend to confuse and deceive the public.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02265006"/>
<p>-6-</p>
<p>These assertions by General Wood have been echoed in a few<lb/>
quarters.</p>
<p>For example, in the Washington Post of November 13 is a state-<lb/>
ment attributed to Dr. John Guiteras, represented as holding an ap-<lb/>
pointment under General Wood as yellow fever expert for Havana, to the<lb/>
effect that &ldquo;there is no more yellow fever in Havana this year than<lb/>
in former years;&rdquo; much more has been heard of it on account of the<lb/>
number of Americans in Havana; twenty four thousand immigrants had been<lb/>
landed in Havana last winter, and it was &ldquo;among them&rdquo; the fever had<lb/>
spread; that he thinks yellow fever will be stamped out in Havana in<lb/>
the course of three or four years; but closes with the singular declara-<lb/>
tion that with proper precautions there is no reason why it should exist<lb/>
now.</p>
<p>The actual current history of the matter<unclear>[unclear]</unclear> is contained, not only<lb/>
in the numerous Department of Havana reports, daily, monthly and semi-<lb/>
annual, but also and independently in the &ldquo;Public Health Reports&rdquo;,<lb/>
issued weekly by the Marine Hospital Service, which has charge of the<lb/>
quarantine service in Havana and elsewhere in the Island of Cuba and<lb/>
has no interest in perverting or ignoring the facts. Examination of the<lb/>
files of these bulletins discloses the following statements.</p>
<p>July 23, 1900, the yellow fever is referred to as &ldquo;now general<lb/>
and widely spread&rdquo; in Havana.</p>
<p>August 24. Yellow fever in Havana is declared &ldquo;widespread and<lb/>
serious.&rdquo;</p>
<p>September 3. &ldquo;The infection is well scattered over the entire<lb/>
city; the larger number of cases among the wealthier classes and in<lb/>
the better class of residences.&rdquo;</p>
<p>September 10. &ldquo;La Habana Medica&rdquo; is quoted as declaring that<lb/>
the &ldquo;gravity of the present epidemic is truly alarming, with the mortal-<lb/>
ity in the yellow fever cases exceeding thirty per cent, dominating the<lb/>
local pathology,&rdquo; Detention camps for immigrants were to be established,<lb/>
barracks built, etc.</p>
<p>October 1. Reference made to the death of several prominent<lb/>
Americans, among others Army Officers, Major Cartright, Dr. Lazier, etc.,<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02265007"/>
-7-<lb/>
Dr. Carroll, U.S.A., ill. The civilian employes to be kept out of the<lb/>
city, sleeping in camps and returning thereto at 4 P.M.</p>
<p>October 3. Havana is declared the &ldquo;distributing point for<lb/>
yellow fever&rdquo; and the attention of the Governor General has been official-<lb/>
ly called to the fact. Other cities in the Island taking precautions to<lb/>
quarantine against Havana.</p>
<p>October 8. Criticism of the official Havana report for August,<lb/>
in which the August mortality from yellow fever in 1900, 49, is favora-<lb/>
bly compared with the data for previous years for the same month. The<lb/>
high mortality in many preceding years of the decade was due to the enor-<lb/>
mous immigration of Spanish soldiers, 208,000 having been brought into<lb/>
the Island in '96 and '97; and the average civil mortality during the<lb/>
Spanish period from yellow fever was 36.6 per month. This should be the<lb/>
comparison made, as there are no importations of American troops in the<lb/>
Island corresponding to the Spanish importation.</p>
<p>October 8. Major Peterson died of yellow fever and his wife<lb/>
killed herself.</p>
<p>October 12. Neighboring cities, Cienfuegos and others, desir-<lb/>
ing protection against Havana. Colonel Noyes of the 2nd Cavalry be-<lb/>
lieves that such precautions should be taken against Havana for all<lb/>
other places in the Island. Yellow fever had been carried from Havana<lb/>
to Bataban&eacute;, Matanzas, Cienfuegos, and intermediate points.</p>
<p>October 1. The Havana sanitary report gives the yellow fever<lb/>
deaths for September, 1900, as 52, and compares this favorably with<lb/>
the average of the preceding decade, stated at 72.4. This comparison,<lb/>
however, still includes the fatalities among the Spanish soldiers im-<lb/>
ported, to which reference has already been made, and is again objected<lb/>
to by the Marine Hospital authorities, who refer back to the statement<lb/>
of October 8.</p>
<p>October 22. The Public Health Bulletin speaks of the &ldquo;gravity<lb/>
of the situation&rdquo;, and the &ldquo;deep concern&rdquo; locally and elsewhere felt<lb/>
therein; refers to the infection of the public buildings, the Governor<lb/>
General's Palace itself, the Military Governor's Palace, and other public<lb/>
offices and quarters where several Army officers had sickened and some<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02265008"/>
-8-<lb/>
of them died, as well as numerous employes. Recommendation made that<lb/>
the public and military offices be moved out of the city and the in-<lb/>
fected public buildings closed.</p>
<p>October 25. Captain Page died of yellow fever, and the<lb/>
Military Governor's Palace was abandoned, the offices being moved out<lb/>
to the Principe.</p>
<p>October 28. A norther had been blowing for several days<lb/>
and the temperature had fallen. The yellow fever conditions are declared<lb/>
&ldquo;epidemic&rdquo;. Out of 857 square blocks in the city, 332 had furnished<lb/>
cases, in number from 1 to 16 each. The sanitary office had computed<lb/>
the population at 242,000, and argued that there could not be an epidemic,<lb/>
properly considered, unless the number of cases and deaths should be<lb/>
much larger in proportion to this number. Of this population, however,<lb/>
at least 212,000 are immune, leaving not more than 25,000 or 30,000 as<lb/>
subject to yellow fever infection; the yellow fever was actually epi-<lb/>
demic and the influx of tourists should be discouraged.</p>
<p>November 2. A telegram from the quarantine officer gives the<lb/>
total yellow fever cases for October as 308 and 74 deaths, as reported,<lb/>
with 16 new cases and deaths recorded for November 1.</p>
<p>These references to the Marine Hospital reports show that as<lb/>
early as July the quarantine officers were concerned as to the situation<lb/>
and did not hesitate to state the facts to the public and to the Mili-<lb/>
tary Governor himself.</p>
<p>The Havana authorities had reason to be gratified with the re-<lb/>
sults of their labors in 1899, and had no interest in withholding the<lb/>
facts, even had concealment been possible. The disease could not at<lb/>
once be eradicated, but it was confined to sporadic and generally<lb/>
explainable cases, and before the summer of 1899 was over, had lost<lb/>
its terrors. In lieu of being a distributing focus of infection,<lb/>
Havana was quarantining for the first time in its history against Key<lb/>
West, Santiago, and other places where it was raging, and such was the<lb/>
confidence felt as the result of experience, that no restrictions were<lb/>
put upon the immigration, from Spanish or other non-infected ports,<lb/>
which was furnishing necessary labor to the Island. The remarkable exemp-<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02265009"/>
-9-<lb/>
tion from epidemics, whether of small-pox, typhoid, or yellow fever,<lb/>
was officially noted in the Marine Hospital Reports and the rapid fall<lb/>
in yellow fever deaths to 8 in January and to 0 in April of 1900, gave<lb/>
no reason to &ldquo;realise it was going to be a bad summer for fever&rdquo;, nor<lb/>
did any one specially apprehend or expect it. The difference this year<lb/>
is that an outbreak has prevailed, attacking all classes, occasioning<lb/>
widespread apprehension from the dramatic losses among American officers<lb/>
and others heretofore exempt, and involving the infection of hotels,<lb/>
public buildings, barracks, quarters, and suburbs which in 1899 were<lb/>
occupied with entire security, and without the loss of a single officer<lb/>
and but few of the men. The quarantine against Havana has been gen-<lb/>
eral and is still maintained, and the immigrants are isolated and not<lb/>
allowed to enter the city. It is this year that there has been panic<lb/>
among the Americans in Havana; that they have been &ldquo;deluged with<lb/>
anxious letters&rdquo; from relatives and friends; and that distress has been<lb/>
given to innocent persons at home.</p>
<p>An exhibit of the actual facts is due to all persons concerned.<lb/>
The accompanying exhibits have been prepared from official records:</p>
<p>1st. A consolidated record of deaths by months and years for<lb/>
1890 to November 1, 1900, showing totals in black and yellow fever in<lb/>
red. A similar schedule was printed in the annual report for the fiscal<lb/>
year 1899; for the full calendar year 1899; and in the annual report<lb/>
(not yet issued) for the fiscal year 1900 to May 1, when the Depart-<lb/>
ment of Havana was discontinued.</p>
<p>2nd. A schedule by months of arrivals and departures, immi-<lb/>
gration, <add>total</add> deaths, and yellow fever deaths, from January 1, 1899, to<lb/>
November 1, 1900.</p>
<p>3d. A diagram plotted to scale from official data, showing by<lb/>
graphic curves the relations of arrivals, immigrants, total deaths,<lb/>
and yellow fever deaths.</p>
<p>The first table shows the comparatively normal conditions from<lb/>
1890 to 1895, with the heavy increase during the years of war, '96 to '98,<lb/>
the frightful mortality in '98 to which the American occupation suc-<lb/>
ceeded, and the rapid reductions in 1899.</p>
<p>The total yellow fever mortality for 1899, notwithstanding the<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f02265010"/>
-10-<lb/>
heavy immigration of non-immunes, and the importation and reshipment of<lb/>
thousands of American troops at Havana, was not only the lowest of the<lb/>
decade, but one third only the number of the next lowest.</p>
<p>The worst yellow fever month in 1899, viz: October, with 25<lb/>
deaths, was better than any other October in the decade. October,<lb/>
1900, with 74 deaths, had three times as many, and nearly three-fourths<lb/>
of the 1899 total, and the four months July-October, 1900, have had<lb/>
double the number of the entire year 1899. October, 1900, has the<lb/>
worst record of civil cases in the history of Havana, the next<lb/>
highest being 63 in 1895.</p>
<p>General Wood, for some reason, has selected December, 1899,<lb/>
for invidious comparison, and repeatedly declared it the worst in<lb/>
ten years. This is not true; it was exceeded by three Decembers, viz:<lb/>
1892, 1894, and 1896, and even restricting the comparison to civil<lb/>
deaths only, it is still exceeded by December, 1892 and 1894, and not-<lb/>
withstanding the maximum immigration in December, 1899, there was a<lb/>
rapid fall of yellow fever deaths to 8 in January, 1900, and to 0 in<lb/>
April, where the Department of Havana left the record.</p>
<p>The second table is an instructive exhibit.</p>
<p>The total arrivals in 1899, which are exclusive of the large<lb/>
importations of American troops and others who swarmed in Havana during<lb/>
the first six months, were 46,132, with 12,380 immigrants. The arrivals<lb/>
reached their maximum, 6,553, in December, 1899, with 3,635 immigrants.<lb/>
In the Spring of 1900 the arrivals and immigrants and yellow fever<lb/>
diminish. The total arrivals during the sixteen months from January 1,<lb/>
1899, to May 1, 1900, which closed the Department of Havana, were<lb/>
59,604, and immigrants 18,795.</p>
<p>The total deaths in the same period were 10,232, with yellow<lb/>
fever deaths 124, a ratio of 1-1&sol;5 percent.</p>
<p>For the five months May-September, 1900, the arrivals in<lb/>
diminishing figures were 10,117, the immigrants 5,528, the total deaths<lb/>
2,590, and the yellow fever deaths 141, a ratio of 5-1&sol;2 per cent.</p>
<p>For the six months May-October the total arrivals were 15,470,<lb/>
the immigration 9,578, the total deaths 3,097, and the yellow fever<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f02265011"/>
-11-<lb/>
deaths 215, a ratio of 7 per cent.</p>
<p>The yellow fever deaths increase from 2 in May to 8 in June and<lb/>
then rise rapidly to 30 in July, 49 in August, 52 in September, with a<lb/>
ratio of 10 per cent, and to 74 in October, with a ratio of no less<lb/>
than 15 per cent.</p>
<p>In October the arrivals and immigration became exceptionally<lb/>
large, but that has no bearing upon the rapid epidemic rise in the four<lb/>
preceding months, and it is understood that provision has been made to<lb/>
detain and isolate the immigration so that it shall not enter the city<lb/>
population.</p>
<p>The arrivals during the 16 months of the Department of Havana<lb/>
were nearly four times greater than those for the succeeding six months,<lb/>
and the immigration was nearly double, while the yellow fever deaths for<lb/>
the six months May-October, 1900, 215, exceeded by 91 those for the<lb/>
entire 16 months preceding.</p>
<p>-----------</p>
<p>These particulars are more graphically shown on the diagram of<lb/>
curves, which shows in a conclusive and interesting manner the relations<lb/>
of the data recorded.</p>
<p>The bulk of the immigration was during 1899, the curve of total<lb/>
arrivals and immigration culminating in December, 1899, and continuing<lb/>
on a descending scale in 1900 until the rise in October.</p>
<p>The general death rate, falling rapidly from the beginning of<lb/>
the American administration, reaches its normal average of about 500<lb/>
per month with September, 1899, and continues thereafter substantially<lb/>
on that level. The average, 525, for the five months June-October, 1900,<lb/>
is considerably higher than that for the preceding nine months, 507, for<lb/>
September-May.</p>
<p>The yellow fever curve has from 0 to 2 cases a month for the<lb/>
first seven months of 1899, rises to 13 in August, to 18 in September,<lb/>
and reaches its maximum, 25, in October, 1899, diminishing to 18 in<lb/>
November, rising again to 22 in December, falling quickly to 8 in Janu-<lb/>
ary, 1900, 9 in February, 4 in March, and ends with a 0 record for<lb/>
April, the last month of the Department of Havana.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f02265012"/>
<p>-12-</p>
<p>The comparatively close relation between the yellow fever<lb/>
curve and the curve of non-immune immigration is well shown in this<lb/>
diagram. This relation is a normal one in the case of a persistent<lb/>
endemic infectious disease fed by the arrival of non-immune material,<lb/>
but it must be observed that the parallelism and normal relation of<lb/>
these lines are dependent entirely upon the rigid control of the disease;<lb/>
that until the local foci of infection can be by degrees eradicated,<lb/>
an increased number of sporadic cases must be expected with increase of<lb/>
importation, and conversely; but that the conditions of security re-<lb/>
quire that every case be isolated as it occurs and be not permitted<lb/>
to give rise to other cases; in other words, that the endemic disease<lb/>
shall not be allowed to escape control and become epidemic by expansion.</p>
<p>The contrast between the conditions obtaining during 1899 and<lb/>
to May 1, 1900, and the succeeding conditions, is clearly shown. In-<lb/>
stead of retaining its approximate parallelism with the immigration<lb/>
curves, the yellow fever line, disregarding diminution of immigration,<lb/>
and ignoring the total death rate, shoots upward from June, cutting<lb/>
both these lines nearly at right angles, and reaches unexampled altitudes<lb/>
in comparison with normal conditions and fresh non-immune material<lb/>
available.</p>
<p>With the yellow fever escaping control and become epidemic, not<lb/>
confined to the immigration class, but spreading generally over the city<lb/>
and suburbs, attacking the best class of residences and citizens,<lb/>
invading public buildings, barracks, and localities heretofore exempt,<lb/>
taking the lives of half a dozen American Army officers and their fam-<lb/>
ilies, spreading in numerous instances among the officers and soldiers,<lb/>
the clerks, and American employes and visitors; and with a general<lb/>
quarantine against the city; it is not difficult to understand why<lb/>
&ldquo;more is heard of yellow fever news now than formerly&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Since leaving Cuba I have not sought or expected controversy on<lb/>
these or any other points, but these statements have been made by an<lb/>
authority who both professionally, as a medical officer, and officially,<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f02265013"/>
-13-<lb/>
as a responsible administrator, must have special knowledge of the<lb/>
facts, and since they involve comparisons so made as to reflect dis-<lb/>
paragingly upon the American administration in Havana during my charge,<lb/>
I regard it as incumbent upon me, in the interest of all concerned<lb/>
during the continuance of the Department of Havana, to make formal<lb/>
correction.</p>
<p>It is not tolerable that officials in high position should<lb/>
deliberately disseminate misinformation. Such conduct is prejudicial<lb/>
to the public interest, injurious to the repute of the service, and in<lb/>
conflict with every tradition of the Army.</p>
<p>For these reasons I dissent from the opinion expressed by<lb/>
General Wood in his letter to the Adjutant General that &ldquo;a good<lb/>
deal of unnecessary importance&rdquo; has been attached to the matter of<lb/>
his misstatements, which are at variance with the official records<lb/>
and are inimical to the public interest and welfare.</p>
<p>William Ludlow.<lb/>
Brigadier General, U.S.A.</p>
<p>4 Enclosures.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
