<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02305001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Mortuary Record for yellow fever in Havana, 1884-1900, [1900?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02305001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Chaille, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Havana (CUba)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Punta (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Maestranza (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cabanas (Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>15 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-00-00">[1900?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02305001</idno>
<title>Mortuary Record for yellow fever in Havana, 1884-1900, [1900?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The author analyzes the death rates of Cubans from malaria and yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1900-00-00">
<head>Mortuary Record for yellow fever in Havana, 1884-1900, [1900?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02305001"/>
<p>Since the beginning of 1884 the mortuary statistics of this city have<lb/>
been kept in this office. These were kept for the purpose of keeping<lb/>
informed of the prevalence of epidemic diseases, yellow fever and small<lb/>
pox; but have extended of late years to include a number of others,<lb/>
and total mortality as well.</p>
<p>A clerk was sent each week to the Colon and Baptist<lb/>
cemeteries to copy the records of burial for yellow fever and small pox<lb/>
for that week, the record being made for each day's burials. For yellow<lb/>
fever and small pox the place as well as day of death is always specified,<lb/>
which not only enabled us to tell in what part of the city the disease<lb/>
was most prevalent, but is a very considerable check on our collector<lb/>
of statistics as having to specify each place, street and number, he<lb/>
would be little apt to make an erroneous record either of omission or<lb/>
commission.</p>
<p>There are three other cemeteries in the municipality of<lb/>
Havana besides the two mentioned: Calvario, Arroyo, <del>Naraja</del> Naranja<lb/>
and the Chinese. Of these, however, the last only has relation to the<lb/>
city of Havana as a port, the villages for which these cemeteries are<lb/>
used being 9 kilometres distant <add>from Havana proper-</add>. They also add nothing to the reported<lb/>
yellow fever mortality. The population contributary to the Chinese<lb/>
Cemetery is in the city and its omission lessens our total death rate<lb/>
by from 4 to 10 per month in normal years, and from 30 to 80 during the<lb/>
reconcentration, from what is proper for the city. Its omission is,<lb/>
however, without effect on the yellow fever statistics, as an examination<lb/>
of its records (by Major Gorgas) shows but a single burial there of<lb/>
which the death is assigned to that cause from 1890 to 1898 inclusive.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02305002"/>
<p>It will be noted that the division is made by periods<lb/>
of twelve months other than the calendar years. This is because the<lb/>
increase and decline of yellow fever does not coincide with the beginning<lb/>
and termination of the calendar years. Apparently the influence of the<lb/>
summer epidemic extends through the first trimester of the next year<lb/>
and in April (March, April or May) begins the increase for the ensueing<lb/>
summer.</p>
<p>This can be best seen by an inspection of Table II, where for<lb/>
the civil population the average number of deaths per month taking the<lb/>
last 10 normal years, 1885 to 1894, is given. It is seen that March<lb/>
is the lowest, with February, April and May nearly the same. Examining<lb/>
the Table in detail it will be seen, that any one of these <del>fou</del> 4 months<lb/>
may <add>be</add> the lowest, giving <hi>0</hi> deaths in certain years, that the increase<lb/>
of fever seems to begin in April, reaches its maximum in August and<lb/>
September, and slowly declines to a minimum, usually in March. This divi-<lb/>
sion then including the first trimester in the calendar year in the<lb/>
preceding year for yellow fever, seems to be justified by this table.</p>
<p>The mortality for January and February is evidently affected<lb/>
by the amount of fever in the preceding year,- a &ldquo;hold over&rdquo; in fact.<lb/>
Foot note A.</p>
<p>A. Foot note --. I felt that this division of the year for<lb/>
yellow fever had received the strongest possible endorsement, when I found<lb/>
that Dr. Carlos Findlay had for the same reason, and the same division,<lb/>
holding that &ldquo;the epidemic year usually ends with March.&rdquo; I frankly<lb/>
acknowledge Dr. Findlay's priority in this, although my statistics were<lb/>
tabulated before I saw his.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02305003"/>
<p>It will also be noted that from January to May inclusive<lb/>
are the months giving the least yellow fever, December and June having<lb/>
very nearly the same mortality, hence conveying the same risk.</p>
<p>The belief that seems prevalent among Americans then that it<lb/>
is safe to come to Havana in November and perfectly safe in December,<lb/>
but that they must leave with the early summer is absolutely without<lb/>
basis, May will average safer than January. In not a few years June<lb/>
is safer than December and it is fair to class from June to December<lb/>
inclusive as a period of danger and from January to May inclusive as<lb/>
comparatively safe, January being the most dangerous month of this division<lb/>
of the years.</p>
<p>It also seems right to consider the period prior to 1895 separate<lb/>
from that following. The large mass of soldiers brought over at irregular<lb/>
intervals consequent on the war, with the diminution, almost cessation,<lb/>
of Spanish immigration from the early part or middle of 1896, must affect<lb/>
the mortality of the two different classes in diametrically opposite<lb/>
ways and bend each one from its own normal -- if the military can be said<lb/>
to have a normal. I have therefore grouped the 10 years preceding<lb/>
1895 to themselves and from them we are most apt to get information<lb/>
as to the normal course of the yellow fever among the civilian population<lb/>
of Havana. The years from 1895 to 1900 however are not without their lesson.</p>
<p>In looking over table I the first thing that strikes the<lb/>
observer is the lack of the relationship between the civilian and military<lb/>
mortality. Thus in 1891 they were 219 and 147 respectively, while in<lb/>
1893 they were 124 and 379, the proportions being reversed. It is <unclear>from</unclear><lb/>
this reason I believe that no conclusion from mixed military and civilian<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02305004"/>
statistics as to the course of the disease among the civilian population<lb/>
can be drawn. If the period of the war were taken the discrepancies are<lb/>
more marked, 1897 giving 62 and 1099 for civilian and military mortalities<lb/>
respectively. Unquestionably a prime factor in the mortality among<lb/>
soldiers was the bringing in of masses of new troops, non-immunes, and<lb/>
quartering them in barracks virulently infected.</p>
<p>What, however, most impressed the writer when he first compiled<lb/>
these figures was the small number of deaths among the civilian population<lb/>
210.4 per annum being the average for the 10 normal years preceding<lb/>
1895 and 195 per annum for the last 17 years. We must note too that<lb/>
these figures for civilian deaths are somewhat too high, including as<lb/>
they do a few soldiers.</p>
<p>During this time then, 17 years, there has never been any<lb/>
death rate among the civilian population even approaching to the epidem-<lb/>
ics of our own country -- compare with 7,800&plus; deaths in New Orleans in<lb/>
1853. Yellow fever for 17 years has not been a market factor in the<lb/>
civil mortality per annum in Havana.</p>
<p>Since yellow fever among the native Cuban population is not<lb/>
recorded it is obvious that the Spanish immigrants, practically the only<lb/>
immigration to the Island, has furnished the yellow fever mortality.<lb/>
A knowledge of this movement then is necessary to interpret the statistics<lb/>
even from the civil population. We should know <del>fir</del> (1) the amount<lb/>
of immigration, and (2) the number that stay in Havana, for Havana is<lb/>
the port of entry for nearly all immigrants going to other parts of the<lb/>
Island. This matter is now being looked up, although it is a very<lb/>
troublesome problem. The first factor at least is determinable and with<lb/>
it afair estimate of the second. In the meantime I am informed by those<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02305005"/>
in a position to know (transatlantice transportation lines and others)<lb/>
that the immigration was fairly uniform except that one year of high<lb/>
mortality would decidedly diminish the immigration the next spring. B.</p>
<p>B. Foot note.---- I would estimate the number of immigrants<lb/>
before the war at from 15,000 to 20,000 per annum approximately. Three<lb/>
years during this period which I tabulated gave about 27,500 &ldquo;passengers<lb/>
arriving by vessels from Spanish ports&rdquo; per annum, as an average, but<lb/>
this includes both soldiers (estimated at 5000) and returning Spaniards<lb/>
(a neglectable quantity).</p>
<p>Comparing the years of the 10 normal years we see that 1884<lb/>
and 1893 were years of heavy mortality, 1893 the highest for the 17<lb/>
years, while for 1885, 1886, 1890 and 1891 the rate was low, that<lb/>
for 1885 being very low. With the data in hand no reason can be given<lb/>
for this.</p>
<p>The heavy mortality of 1895 can readily be accounted for by<lb/>
addition to the civil immigration(not yet stopped) of the families of<lb/>
officers and of the civilian attaches who accompanied the Army. I am<lb/>
informed that the epidemic of this year prevented the immigration of<lb/>
this class of people the next.</p>
<p>The books in my office show that civilian immigration nearly<lb/>
ceased after 1895 and that it was not resumed until in August 1899.<lb/>
This is doubtless the reason why 1896, 1897 and 1898 were years of small<lb/>
civilian mortality, while 1896 and 1897 pile up the highest military<lb/>
mortality ever known here.</p>
<p>1896, civil military</p>
<p>1897 " "</p>
<p>In 1898 the bulk of susceptibility among the soldiers must have<lb/>
be<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02305006"/>
been exhausted, as a garrison of 29,000 to 30,000 gave only deaths.<lb/>
the sae is true of civilians (Foot note. --As near as we can judge<lb/>
from the records of this office, the Spanish immigrant has fever nearly<lb/>
always within the fourth year of his arrival, generally in the second<lb/>
or third. In the examinations we make for &ldquo;immunity by residence&rdquo;,<lb/>
that is of Spaniards who show that they have been here more than ten<lb/>
years, those who claim to have had yellow fever almost always claim to<lb/>
have had it within the first two or three years) for whom we record<lb/>
only 32 the lowest number in the history of Havana which we have recorded.<lb/>
Among the deaths in November and December are those of a small number<lb/>
(6 I believe) of Americans who had come into Havana believing those<lb/>
months to be free from danger here.</p>
<p>In 1899 the military element was practically eliminated. In the<lb/>
beginning of the occupation the men were lodged in clean quarters (at first<lb/>
many of them were in tents) and kept under very strict discipline and<lb/>
excellent police and sanitary management. There was a case of yellow<lb/>
fever among the Marines in June at the Naval station in June, and three<lb/>
others the last part of July and <add>early</add> August at the same place. They <add>the Marines</add> were<lb/>
then sent north.</p>
<p>A case of yellow fever occurred <del>in them</del> <add>among the soldiers</add> on the Punta in early<lb/>
August and the command was immediately moved out of town. Those quartered<lb/>
in the Maestranza were also moved about the same time. In Cabanas in<lb/>
August, the 8th I believe, yellow fever developed, apparently from infection<lb/>
inside the building, and the troops not being moved immediately there<lb/>
was a total of 24 cases and 9 deaths (1 a civilian and 1 dying at Vincennes,<lb/>
Ind.) Fever ceased to spread soon after the command was moved to tents.<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02305007"/>
After August then there was an extremely small number of soldiers in<lb/>
Havana, and as I have said they ceased to be a factor in its conveyance<lb/>
and the formation of new foci.</p>
<p>Up to the end of August the civilian mortality for this year was<lb/>
extremely small and for August and September was decidedly less than the<lb/>
normal before the law, although greater than for the two preceding years.<lb/>
Instead of reaching its maximum however in August and September, the<lb/>
October mortality nearly doubled its September figure and December's<lb/>
was only 2 less. It suffered a marked change in January but extended<lb/>
into March and reached its lowest, 0, in April of this year. May has<lb/>
given us a mortality of only 2.</p>
<p>The run of the fever in 1898 was very like that of 1885, both<lb/>
giving exactly the same mortalitym, 111, the smallest of any in the normal<lb/>
10 year series. <del><unclear></unclear></del> In both there was the fairest promise, until<lb/>
August in 1885; September in 1899, and then an unusually rapid increase,<lb/>
dying down, however, more quickly in 1885 than in 1899. In the latter<lb/>
indeed we had a real winter epidemic as in 1888 and 1892, and with the<lb/>
exception of these two years the three winter months of 1899-1900 gives<lb/>
a higher mortality than the corresponding months of any of the 17 years<lb/>
I have here recorded.</p>
<p>The mortality for this year was low, not so low as 1897 and<lb/>
1898 but as low as the lowest of the 10 normal years. And yet I think<lb/>
Americans were disappointed in the increase of yellow fever in the fall.<lb/>
We hoped it to be much lower than 1885, as low as 1897 and 1898. In<lb/>
other words we expected it to be not only a good year, but a phenomenally<lb/>
good year, and were disappointed that it was not.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f02305008"/>
<p>To my mind the cause of the increase of mortality in the fall<lb/>
and winter was exactly the same, reversed, as caused the low mortality<lb/>
in 1897 and 1898, i. e. the changed movement of the Spanish immigration.<lb/>
Just as a cessation of this movement after 1895 by ceasing to supply sus-<lb/>
ceptible material gave us the low death rate (of yellow fever) of 1896;<lb/>
1897; 1898, and the early part of 1899.</p>
<p>X. (Foot note) See Havana report in Public Health reports<lb/>
of August 4, 1899.</p>
<p>So its recrudescence in the latter part of August by furnish-<lb/>
ing susceptible material exposed to infection gave us our winter epidemic<lb/>
of 1899. Y.</p>
<p>Foot note at Y.----The large number of passengers from Mexican<lb/>
and Venezuelan ports coming in last spring and summer were Cubans return<lb/>
ing home and added nothing to the non-immune population, similarly<lb/>
9/10 or 19/20 of the <del>cuban</del> Cabin passengers from Spain were former<lb/>
residents returning to Havana, and fully the same proportion of the immi-<lb/>
gration from the United States were tourists, returning per next boat.<lb/>
Up to August 15 the books of this office show less than 1000 Spanish<lb/>
immigrants properly speaking. From that time to December 1st<lb/>
and more to June 1st..</p>
<p>I say &ldquo;susceptible material<del>s</del> exposed to infection&rdquo;, because the<lb/>
Spanish immigrant is far more exposed to infection than an American in<lb/>
Havana. The latter is usually well-to-do, he is always afraid of yellow<lb/>
fever, and lives in the healthiest part of the city or in the suburbs,<lb/>
or when he cannot do this lives in the highest room he can get; in short<lb/>
takes a thousand precautions which the Spaniard neglects or of which he<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02305009"/>
is ignorant. The Spaniard is poor and he does not dread the fever,<lb/>
or rather he regards it as inevitable, and, I think it fair to say his<lb/>
exposures are many fold more than those of the American<del>s</del>.</p>
<p>As evidence that the population of the town residing here<lb/>
at the vacuation was to a great extent immune to yellow fever, I wil,<lb/>
say that only a very few of those who are recorded as having had yellow<lb/>
fever since August 1, 1899 to this date, claim to have been on the<lb/>
Island more than eight months, and most of them far less, the great<lb/>
majority under 4 months.</p>
<p>What effect or rather how much effect the sanitary work in<lb/>
Havana last summer had in lessening the prevalence of yellow fever<lb/>
among civilians I cannot estimate. The cleaning of the streets in the<lb/>
lower part of the city and the removal of garbage <del><unclear></unclear></del> I believe were of<lb/>
decided value. <del>We might well have had considerable more fevr but for this work.</del></p>
<p>The course pursued, however, (I do not mean the mortality per<lb/>
month) is what we would have expected without any sanitary work. Until<lb/>
the Spanish immigration began to be a factor the amount of the fever is<lb/>
about the same as that of the two previous years, the presence of sus-<lb/>
ceptible Americans tending to balance the decrease in the number of<lb/>
susceptible Spaniards. When this factor began to be felt there was an<lb/>
increase in mortality decidedly greater in ratio<del>n</del> (of increase) than<lb/>
normal but, beginning with presumably a smaller number of foci of infec-<lb/>
tion in town than usual certainly after a much smaller number of cases<lb/>
of yellow fever in town in civilian residences for over 3-1/2 years)<lb/>
the number of deaths in the fall did not reach the normal of ordinary<lb/>
years. Still the number from September to March inclusive, 102, compares</p>
<pb n="10" id="f02305010"/>
<p>Except the statistics in Chaille's report of 1880, a work which<lb/>
is perfection itself, all the statistics which I have seen on the <del>mor</del><lb/>
yellow fever mortality of Havana make no difference between those from<lb/>
the military and those from the civil<add>ian</add> population. Taken together, to<lb/>
my mind, these teach little of what we want to know, the <hi>normal course</hi><lb/>
of yellow fever in Havana in the past; how its prevalence was affected<lb/>
by season, meteorology, etc. and are absolutely valueless for any compari-<lb/>
son with the present and future from which the military element has been<lb/>
and doubtless will be elminated.</p>
<p>An observation of the military statistics shows frequently<lb/>
enormous waves of yellow fever among them, with no corresponding increase<lb/>
or even a decrease in the civilian <del>population</del><add>deaths</add>, due to arrival of and<lb/>
occupation of infected quarters by large number of non-immune soldiers.<lb/>
To have any conception of the normal course of yellow fever in Havana<lb/>
and especially to have any fair comparison of the past with the present<lb/>
and future, we must confine ourselves to the statistics of the civilian<lb/>
population, although it is fair to say that the removal of the military<lb/>
population is in itself a factor, of what value I can form no estimate,<lb/>
in the formation of new foci of infection, and, hence, the propagation<lb/>
of diseases among civilians.</p>
<p>Our method of recording the place of death enables us to<lb/>
separate these two classes. It will be found then that we record deaths<lb/>
in private residences, in private hospitals and in military hospitals.<lb/>
I have counted the first two as civilian deaths, the last as military<lb/>
and naval. This is not quite true as will be explained later..</p>
<p>A word as to the private hospitals or &ldquo;Quintas&rdquo; of Havana.<lb/>
The immigration to Havana which remains in the city is practically confined<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f02305011"/>
to Spaniards. These on arrival join certain mutual benefit societies,<lb/>
the Centro Gallego; the Centro Asturiano and the Centro de Dependientes<lb/>
being at present the principal ones, The latter ha<del>ving</del><add>s</add> at present some-<lb/>
thing over 12,000 members. This practice is practically universal for<lb/>
the newly arrived Spaniard. These societies furnish hospital treatment<lb/>
for their contributors when sick and a very large proportion, I should<lb/>
say 90 per cent, of the well marked cases of yellow fever among these<lb/>
men are treated in these hospitals. I would say here that the Spanish<lb/>
immigration is mainly confined to men, women and children but seldom<lb/>
coming, and having no domicile, properly so called, they are the more<lb/>
ready to go to hospitals when seriously sick. These Quintas are much<lb/>
esteemed for the treatment of yellow fever, and not a few go to them as<lb/>
pay patients who are not members of the societies.</p>
<p>I have said that my division in which I include all who<lb/>
were treated at residences or private hospitals <del>who were</del><add>asking</add> civilians<lb/>
is not entirely <del>true</del><add>correct</add>. I am informed by Havana physicians that a consid-<lb/>
erable number of Spanish officers were treated at their homes and a less<lb/>
number in these Quintas. My enumeration of deaths among civilians then<lb/>
will be somewhat too high and among soldiers somewhat too low.</p>
<p>Thus for the year ending March 31st, 1894, I give 17 more deaths<lb/>
in &ldquo;Residences and Private Hospitals&rdquo; than Major Gorgas does of &ldquo;Civilians,&rdquo;<lb/>
while he has 14 more of &ldquo;Militares&rdquo; than I have in the &ldquo;Military Hospi-<lb/>
tals&rdquo; -- our totals for the year differ<del><unclear></unclear></del>ing by only 3. This can only<lb/>
mean that a certain number between 14 and 17 of &ldquo;Militares&rdquo; were treated<lb/>
at their residences or in private Quintas during that year. So for<lb/>
such other years as I am enabled to compare our statistics, I have a few<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f02305012"/>
more in my &ldquo;Residences and <del>Private</del><add>Civil</add> Hospitals&rdquo; than Gorgas has &ldquo;Civilians&rdquo;<lb/>
balanced or nearly balanced by having less in the &ldquo;Military Hospitals&rdquo;<lb/>
than he has &ldquo;Militares&rdquo;, our totals agreeing very closely. In 1893 I<lb/>
have 11 <del><unclear></unclear></del> more in my &ldquo;Residences and Civil Hospitals&rdquo; than he has<lb/>
&ldquo;Civilians&rdquo; and 13 less in &ldquo;Military Hospitals&rdquo; than he has soldiers,<lb/>
our totals differ by 2..</p>
<p><del>There is also another factor to be considered in the military</del><lb/>
<del>statistics. The heirs of a soldier dying of yellow fever receive a</del><lb/>
<del>higher pension than one of ordinary disease</del></p>
<p>Also in 1896 and 1897 a certain number of petty officers<lb/>
were treated in the Quinta Dependientes, and some of the deaths in<lb/>
this institution recorded by me as from &ldquo;Private Hospitals&rdquo; are those<lb/>
of military men. As said before, then my enumeration of deaths of<lb/>
civilians is somewhat too high and that of soldiers is to the same extent<lb/>
too low, but the difference from the truth is slight.</p>
<p>There is also another factor to be considered f<del>rom</del> in the<lb/>
military statistics. The heirs of a soldier dying of yellow fever<lb/>
receive a higher pension than one of ordinary disease, and it is alleged<lb/>
that the balance of doubt among the Spanish military surgeons was always<lb/>
thrown in favor of the yellow fever diagnosis. I believe this to be<lb/>
true, at least I have heard it from Cuban physicians and others in a<lb/>
position to know wherever I have been in the Island. Neither of these<lb/>
factors will be great enough however to affect the lesson of these<lb/>
statistics.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f02305013"/>
<p>The statistics above referred to as obtained from the cemeteries<lb/>
are especially those of the civilian population. The records of the<lb/>
deaths at the Military Hospitals (including both soldiers and sailors)<lb/>
were also thus obtained until 1895. After that we received daily reports<lb/>
from these hospitals, duplicates of which were furnished the Captain</p>
<p>General, giving the number of patients on hand, admitted, discharged,<lb/>
died and remaining. These were received from an unofficial (but per-<lb/>
fectly reliable) source up to the beginning of the war.</p>
<p>These military statistics are regarded as accurate,<lb/>
although as will be seen but little importance is attached to them.</p>
<p>The total mortality is simply the total number burried<lb/>
in the Colon and Baptist Cemeteries, and although slightly less <del>than</del><lb/>
(by the burials in the Chinese cemetery) than it should be is proportion-<lb/>
ally correct and shows the increase or fall of mortality correctly<lb/>
and is given so that a comparison of the general mortality with that<lb/>
from yellow fever may be made.</p>
<p>So far as yellow fever is concerned, <del>they both</del><add>these statistics</add> agree<lb/>
very closely with those which Major Gorgas, the Chief Sanitary Inspector,<lb/>
has collected for that disease from 1891 to 1898 inclusive, from the<lb/>
records of the Judges, to whom the deaths are first certified by the<lb/>
attending physicians, with one difference which will be noted later.</p>
<p>Naturally this agreement by months is not absolute.<lb/>
Deaths are frequently reported by the physician the last day of the month<lb/>
and burials take place the first day of the next month. Some die in<lb/>
town who are burried elsewhere and we miss those who die in cloister.<lb/>
By months then the statistics are not the same, but the agreement for<lb/>
any two months is extremely close. They are believed then to be fairly<lb/>
correct -- for infectious diseases nearly absolutely so.<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f02305014"/>
with the normal for this period, 114, very fairly.</p>
<p>One deduction only I will venture to make from these statistics,<lb/>
namely: that the mortality of yellow fever in Havana is less than is<lb/>
generally believed, and that a considerable number, I believe a majority<lb/>
of the cases are light and not recognized as such.</p>
<p>From the hospital records the mortality is from 30 to 35 per<lb/>
cent. Taking the lesser figure an average death rate of 210 per annum<lb/>
and would give a morbility of 700 cases per annum.</p>
<p>We cannot fix definitely the number of non-immunes who came as<lb/>
immigrants to Havana and who remain until they have yellow fever. Yet<lb/>
the number who came can scarsely average less than 15,000 per annum.<lb/>
Except the Canary Islanders a majority, I think a considerable majority,<lb/>
of them remain in the city. What deductions to make for the Canary<lb/>
Islanders in time passed is again rather a ,atter of guess with the data<lb/>
I have on hand than reasonable estimate. Before the war that immigration<lb/>
was larger than it is at present; now they are possibly 1/4 or 1/5 of<lb/>
the whole. It would seem then within limits to say that 5000 per annum<lb/>
were added to the permanent population.</p>
<p>We (the quarantine officers of the United States) have agreed<lb/>
to consider a 10 years residence in Havana as &ldquo;conveying immunity&rdquo;,<lb/>
i. e. as being &ldquo;satisfactory evidence&rdquo; that one has had yellow fever,<lb/>
and our observation here would seem to show that very few Spanish immi-<lb/>
grants having yellow fever go <del>four</del> 4 years without it. Except than the<lb/>
very few, if there by any, who are in capable of having yellow fever,<lb/>
it is safe to say that all Spanish immigrants who remain in Havana 10<lb/>
years have yellow fever and nearly all who remain 4 years. We should<lb/>
deduce then that 5000 per annum should have yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f02305015"/>
<p>This is a far different morbility from any that we can get from<lb/>
hospital statistics, even if I halve my morbility, which although but a<lb/>
rough<del><unclear></unclear></del> estimate, is, I think, within limits, we still have a ratio of<lb/>
mortality very much less than that usually given.</p>
<p>It is also worthy of note that a large number of Spaniards of<lb/>
long residence make no claim to have had any yellow fever, although most<lb/>
of them claim the fever of acclimatization.</p>
<p>The above remarks have no reference to yellow fever among<lb/>
Cuban children as these probably add not a great deal to the mortality,<lb/>
and none to the <hi>reported mortality of this diseases.</hi></p>
<p>Believing as the writer does that immunity to yellow fever<lb/>
is conferred only by an attack of the disease, and also that the native<lb/>
Habanese is immune to yellow fever when he reaches adult life, he must<lb/>
hold that the average number of children born in Havana per annum gives<lb/>
the average number of cases of yellow fever among them per annum, making<lb/>
deduction for those who die (and move away) before they have the fever.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
