<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02324050">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Military Orders for James Pilcher and Guy Charles Moore Godfrey, October 16, 1900 [selected pages]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Corbin, H. C.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02324050</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-10-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Pilcher, James</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington Barracks (Washington, D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort McHenry (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-10-16">October 16, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02324050</idno>
<title>Military Orders for James Pilcher and Guy Charles Moore Godfrey, October 16, 1900 [selected pages]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Special Orders #243 directs Pilcher to Ft. McHenry for medical examination and Godfrey to the Philippines for duty. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="military orders" n="1900-10-16">
<head>Military Orders for James Pilcher and Guy Charles Moore Godfrey, October 16, 1900 [selected pages]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02324050"/>
<p>FROM THE NATIONAL ARCHIVES<lb/>
Spec Orders Vol 2<lb/>
1900</p>
<p>Pilcher - <hi>Godfrey</hi></p>
<p>SPECIAL ORDERS, }<lb/>
No. 243. }</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS OF THE ARMY,<lb/>
ADJUTANT GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Washington, October 16, 1900</hi>.</p>
<p>1. By direction of the Secretary of War, Acting Hospital<lb/>
Steward <hi rend="italic">Earl H. Eddy</hi> and six privates, Hospital Corps, Army<lb/>
General Hospital, Washington Barracks, District of Columbia,<lb/>
will be sent to Fort Columbus, New York, and will report upon<lb/>
arrival to the commanding officer of that post pending assign-<lb/>
ment to duty on transport service. The commanding general,<lb/>
Department of the East. Governors Island, New York, will<lb/>
assign Steward <hi rend="italic">Eddy</hi> and three of these privates to duty on<lb/>
the transport &ldquo;Buford;&rdquo; the other three and Acting Hospital<lb/>
Steward <hi rend="italic">Otto F. Frese</hi>, Hospital Corps, will be assigned by<lb/>
him to duty aboard the transport &ldquo;Kilpatrick.&rdquo; They will be<lb/>
sent aboard the vessels designated when their services are in<lb/>
the opinion of the medical superintendent, Army transport serv-<lb/>
ice, New York City, required thereon.</p>
<p>2. By direction of the Secretary of War, Corporal <hi rend="italic">Conrad<lb/>
Kuhleman</hi>, Battery L, 1st Artillery, Fort Barrancas, Florida,<lb/>
will be discharged from the Army, by way of favor, by the<lb/>
commanding officer of his station. This soldier is not entitled<lb/>
to travel-pay.</p>
<p>3. By direction of the Secretary of War, Private <hi rend="italic">William<lb/>
Hayes</hi>, Company E, 7th Infantry, now at the Army and Navy<lb/>
General Hospital, Hot Springs, Arkansas, will be discharged<lb/>
without honor from the Army by the commanding officer of<lb/>
that hospital, by reason of having become disqualified for<lb/>
service through his own fault. This soldier is not entitled to<lb/>
travel-pay.</p>
<p>4. By direction of the Secretary of War, Drum Major<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">George D. Kees</hi>, band, 1st Infantry, now at Fort Leavenworth,<lb/>
Kansas, is transferred as a private to the U. S. Military Acad-<lb/>
emy band, West Point, New York. He will be sent to that<lb/>
post and will report upon arrival to the commanding officer<lb/>
for duty. The expenses of the transfer will be borne by the<lb/>
soldier and transportation will not be furnished by the Quar-<lb/>
termaster's Department.</p>
<p>5. By direction of the Secretary of War, the retirement<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02324051"/>
2<lb/>
from active service by the President, to take effect November<lb/>
1, 1900, of Colonel <hi rend="italic">James W. Scully</hi>, assistant quartermaster<lb/>
general, U. S. Army, upon his own application, under the pro-<lb/>
visions of section 1244, Revised Statutes, he having attained<lb/>
the age of sixty-two years, is announced. Colonel <hi rend="italic">Scully</hi> will<lb/>
proceed to his home on or after the date specified. The travel<lb/>
enjoined is necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>6. By direction of the Secretary of War, Captain <hi rend="italic">Samuel<lb/>
A. Smoke</hi>, 5th U. S. Infantry, will report in person to the com-<lb/>
manding officer, Fort Leavenworth, Kansas, for examination<lb/>
by a medical officer at that post as to his present physical con-<lb/>
dition, and upon the completion of the examination will<lb/>
return to the place of receipt by him of this order. The travel<lb/>
enjoined is necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>7. By direction of the Secretary of War, <hi>Captain <hi rend="italic">James E.<lb/>
Pilcher</hi></hi>, assistant surgeon, U. S. Army, will report in person<lb/>
to the commanding officer, Fort McHenry, Maryland, for ex-<lb/>
amination by a medical officer at that post as to his physical<lb/>
condition, and upon the completion of the examination will<lb/>
return to the place of receipt by him of this order. The travel<lb/>
enjoined is necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>8. By direction of the Secretary of War, <hi>Captain <hi rend="italic">Guy C. M.<lb/>
Godfrey</hi></hi>, assistant surgeon, U. S. Army, now in Brooklyn,<lb/>
New York, <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to San Francisco, California, under para-<lb/>
graph 25, Special Orders, No. 185, August 8, 1900, is relieved<lb/>
from the further operation of the order specified and will<lb/>
report in person on or about November 7, 1900, to the com-<lb/>
manding general, Department of the East, for assignment to<lb/>
duty with recruits <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to the Philippine Islands on the<lb/>
transport &ldquo;Kilpatrick.&rdquo; Upon his arrival at Manila and the<lb/>
completion of his duty with the recruits he will report in per-<lb/>
son to the commanding general, Division of the Philippines, for<lb/>
further orders.</p>
<p>9. By direction of the Secretary of War, Major <hi rend="italic">John M.<lb/>
Carson, jr.</hi>, quartermaster, U. S. Volunteers, will proceed from<lb/>
this city to Fort Morgan and Fort Gaines, Alabama; Fort<lb/>
Barrancas, Fort Pickens, Fort Dade, and Fort DeSoto, Florida;<lb/>
Fort Screven, Georgia; Fort Moultrie and Fort Fremont,<lb/>
South Carolina; Fort Caswell, North Carolina, and Fort Mon-<lb/>
roe, Virginia, on official business pertaining to the Quarter-<lb/>
master's Department, under such instructions as he may</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
