<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02324037">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Military Orders for Guy Charles Moore Godfrey, Herbert J. Slocum, and Alexander N. Stark, September 27, 1900 [selected pages]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Corbin, H. C.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02324037</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-09-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Slocum, Herbert</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-09-27">September 27, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02324037</idno>
<title>Military Orders for Guy Charles Moore Godfrey, Herbert J. Slocum, and Alexander N. Stark, September 27, 1900 [selected pages]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Special Orders #227 relieves Godfrey of duty. Slocum is temporarily assigned duty as Acting Chief Quartermaster. Stark's leave of absence is extended. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="military orders" n="1900-09-27">
<head>Military Orders for Guy Charles Moore Godfrey, Herbert J. Slocum, and Alexander N. Stark, September 27, 1900 [selected pages]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02324037"/>
<p>FROM THE NATIONAL ARCHIVES<lb/>
Spec Orders Vol 2<lb/>
1900</p>
<p><hi>Godfrey</hi> - Slocum - Stark</p>
<p>SPECIAL ORDERS, }<lb/>
No. 227. }</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS OF THE ARMY,<lb/>
ADJUTANT GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Washington, September 27, 1900</hi>.</p>
<p>1. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, the follow-<lb/>
ing-named enlisted men, now at the stations designated after<lb/>
their respective names, will be discharged from the Army, by<lb/>
way of favor, by the commanding officers of their respective<lb/>
stations:</p>
<p>Private <hi rend="italic">Raymond E. Cornwell</hi>, Troop M, 7th Cavalry, Co-<lb/>
lumbia Barracks, Havana, Cuba;</p>
<p>Private <hi rend="italic">Alpha L. Walker</hi>, Battery C, 4th Artillery, Fort<lb/>
Caswell, North Carolina.</p>
<p>These soldiers are not entitled to travel-pay.</p>
<p>2. Private <hi rend="italic">James H. Kennedy</hi>, Troop F, 5th Cavalry, San<lb/>
Juan, Porto Rico, is transferred to Battery G, 5th Artillery,<lb/>
stationed at that post, and will report to the commanding officer<lb/>
thereof for duty. The expenses of the transfer, if any, will be<lb/>
borne by the soldier.</p>
<p>3. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Private <hi rend="italic">Paul<lb/>
Tatoolian</hi>, Troop G, 8th Cavalry, Guantanamo, Cuba, will be<lb/>
discharged from the Army by the commanding officer of his<lb/>
station, by reason of being unsuited to the service. This sol-<lb/>
dier is entitled to travel-pay.</p>
<p>4. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Private<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Hubert Howell</hi>. Company K, 23d Infantry, Fort D. A. Russell,<lb/>
Wyoming, is transferred to the Hospital Corps. Upon receipt<lb/>
of this order at the post the commanding officer will order the<lb/>
soldier to report to the surgeon for duty at the hospital.</p>
<p>5. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Private<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Oliver F. Vanaces</hi>, Light Battery B, 4th Artillery, Fort Riley,<lb/>
Kansas, will be discharged from the Army, by way of favor, by<lb/>
the commanding officer of his station. This soldier is not en-<lb/>
titled to travel-pay.</p>
<p>6. Private <hi rend="italic">Samuel L. Cohen</hi>, Troop L, 2d Cavalry, Matan-<lb/>
zas, Cuba, is transferred to Troop B, 7th Cavalry. He will be<lb/>
sent to the station of that troop, Havana, Cuba, and will re-<lb/>
port upon arrival to the commanding officer for duty. The<lb/>
expenses of the transfer will be borne by the soldier.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02324041"/>
<p>4</p>
<p>person to the commanding officer of the Army and Navy Gen-<lb/>
eral Hospital for treatment in that hospital. The travel en-<lb/>
joined is necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>15. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, 1st Lieu-<lb/>
tenant <hi rend="italic">William R. Smith</hi>, 1st U. S. Artillery, will remain on<lb/>
duty at the U. S. Military Academy, West Point, New York,<lb/>
until July 1, 1901, when he will proceed to join his battery.<lb/>
The travel enjoined is necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>16. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, <hi>Captain<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Guy C. M. Godfrey</hi></hi>, assistant surgeon, U. S. Army, is relieved<lb/>
from the further operation of paragraph 18,Special Orders,<lb/>
No. 194, August 18, 1900, from this office, and will comply<lb/>
with paragraph 25, Special Orders, No. 185, August 8, 1900,<lb/>
from this office.<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>17. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Captain<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">William R. Hamilton</hi>, 7th U. S. Artillery, is detailed tempo-<lb/>
rarily as a member of the examining board appointed to meet<lb/>
at Governors Island, New York City, by Special Orders, No.<lb/>
72, March 27, 1900, from this office, during the absence of<lb/>
Major <hi rend="italic">John M. K. Davis</hi>, 1st U. S. Artillery, who will resume<lb/>
his seat on the board upon his return to his proper station.<lb/>
Such journeys as may be required of Captain <hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi> from<lb/>
his station to Governors Island and return, in attending the<lb/>
meetings of the board, are necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>18. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Major<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Edward T. Comegys</hi>, surgeon, U. S. Army, medical supply<lb/>
officer at Taku, China, will ship all medical supplies not re-<lb/>
quired by the troops to remain in China to Manila, Philippine<lb/>
Islands, and then proceed to Manila and report in person to the<lb/>
commanding general, Division of the Philippines, for assign-<lb/>
ment to duty as medical supply officer at that place. The<lb/>
travel enjoined is necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>19. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Captain<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">William M. Ekin</hi>, assistant quartermaster, U. S. Volunteers,<lb/>
now at Nagasaki, Japan, will proceed to San Francisco, Cali-<lb/>
fornia, and report by telegraph to the Adjutant General of the<lb/>
Army for further orders. The travel enjoined is necessary for<lb/>
the public service.<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>20. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Captain<lb/>
<hi><hi rend="italic">Herbert J. Slocum</hi></hi>, 7th U. S. Cavalry, will report in person to<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02324042"/>
5<lb/>
the commanding general, Department of Western Cuba, for<lb/>
assignment to duty temporarily as acting chief quartermaster<lb/>
of that department.</p>
<p>21. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Acting<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon <hi rend="italic">W. J. S. Stewart</hi>, U. S. Army, now on leave<lb/>
of absence from Fort Slocum, New York, will report to the med-<lb/>
ical superintendent, Army transport service, Army Building,<lb/>
New York City, for assignment to temporary duty on the<lb/>
transport &ldquo;Rawlins,&rdquo; during the absence on leave of Acting<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon <hi rend="italic">William B. Orear</hi>, U. S. Army, and upon<lb/>
the return of that officer will rejoin his proper station.</p>
<p>22. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, leave of<lb/>
absence from about November 1, 1900, to and including Febru-<lb/>
ary 4, 1901, is granted Colonel <hi rend="italic">Albert Hartsuff</hi>, assistant sur-<lb/>
geon general, U. S. Army, and he is granted permission to go<lb/>
beyond sea.</p>
<p>23. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, the leave<lb/>
of absence granted <hi>Captain <hi rend="italic">Alexander N. Stark</hi></hi>, assistant sur-<lb/>
geon, U. S. Army, in Special Orders, No. 149, August 30, 1900,<lb/>
Division of Cuba, is extended seven days.<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>24. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Acting<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon <hi rend="italic">Cosam J. Bartlett</hi>, U. S. Army, is relieved<lb/>
from duty in the Department of California, and will proceed<lb/>
from San Francisco to Port Valdez, Alaska, and report in per-<lb/>
son to the commanding officer of that post for duty and by<lb/>
letter to the commanding general, Department of Alaska,<lb/>
relieving Acting Assistant Surgeon <hi rend="italic">Neil C. Trew</hi>, U. S. Army,<lb/>
who upon being thus relieved will proceed to San Francisco,<lb/>
California, and report in person to the commanding general,<lb/>
Department of California, for assignment to duty. The travel<lb/>
enjoined is necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>25. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Captain<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Samuel Reber</hi>, Signal Corps, U. S. Army, will proceed from<lb/>
Governors Island, New York, to this city, and will carry out<lb/>
such instructions as he may receive from the Acting Chief<lb/>
Signal Officer of the Army, and upon the completion of this<lb/>
duty will return to his proper station. The travel enjoined is<lb/>
necessary for the public service.</p>
<p>26. By direction of the Acting Secretary of War, Major<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Cunliffe H. Murray</hi>, inspector general, U. S. Volunteers,</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
