<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02423001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Harry Frederick Jackson to Chauncey B. Baker, January 17, 1901</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Jackson, Harry Frederick</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02423001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1901-01-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Baker, Chauncey B.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1901-01-17">January 17, 1901</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02423001</idno>
<title>Letter from Harry Frederick Jackson to Chauncey B. Baker, January 17, 1901</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Jackson lists all the properties that make up the Post of Columbia Barracks, along with their rental information. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1901-01-17">
<head>Letter from Harry Frederick Jackson to Chauncey B. Baker, January 17, 1901</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02423001"/>
<opener>
file<lb/>
FROM THE NATIONAL ARCHIVES<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS DEPARTMENT OF CUBA.<lb/>
Office of Assistant Engineer.<lb/>
<dateline>
Quemados, <date value="1901-01-17">January 17, 1901.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Major Chauncey B. Baker,<lb/>
Chief Quartermaster,<lb/>
Department of Cuba.<lb/>
<salute>SIR:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Replying to your letter of the 10th instant (Reference #3879),<lb/>
I have the honor to inform you that rent was last paid Tomasa<lb/>
Cardenas, deceased, to include June 30, 1900, by Captain H. J.<lb/>
Slocum, Disbursing Officer for the Department of Havana and Pinar<lb/>
del Rio. On that date the accounts were transferred by Captain<lb/>
Slocum to the Chief Quartermaster of that Department, and his office<lb/>
informs me that no rents have been paid since that time.</p>
<p>Referring to the second paragraph of your letter, the following<lb/>
is a list of the parcels of land comprised within the limits of the<lb/>
Post of Columbia Barracks, together with names of owners and amounts<lb/>
of rentals. I cannot give you the date on which last payment was<lb/>
made, as this was done by the Chief Quartermaster of the Department,<lb/>
or by the Disbursing Officer of the Department. He can probably<lb/>
give you the desired information.</p>
<p>First.- The parcel marked &ldquo;Benitez&rdquo; on enclosed map - should be<lb/>
marked &ldquo;Barreto&rdquo; - contains thirty two (32) acres; is owned by<lb/>
Do&ntilde;a Maria de la Salud de Benitez, a resident of San Antonio #32-1/2,<lb/>
Guanabacoa; amount of rent twenty (20) dollars per month. Copy of<lb/>
lease furnished Captain Slocum, and by him forwarded to you.<lb/>
Parcel 1</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02423002"/>
<p>(2)</p>
<p>Second.- &ldquo;Buena Vista&rdquo; -- The portion within the Post of Col-<lb/>
umbia Barracks is that part of the farm lying to the northwest of<lb/>
the Marianao railroad. This portion contains about sixty six (66)<lb/>
acres, is owned by Frank Montros, #35 Mercaderes, Havana; monthly<lb/>
rental forty (40) dollars. Copy of this lease was furnished Captain<lb/>
Slocum, and by him forwarded to you.<lb/>
Parcel 5</p>
<p>Third.- &ldquo;El Recreo de las Tres Rosas&rdquo;-- Portion northwest of<lb/>
the Marianao railroad is within the post of Columbia Barracks. This<lb/>
portion contains approximately one hundred (100) acres; is owned by<lb/>
Manuel Nogueira, present address not known - somewhere in Havana -<lb/>
attorney, Major Runcie; no lease, as owner refused to lease land<lb/>
since March 1, 1900 (?), at amount allowed by board of officers.<lb/>
It is understood that claim for rent and damages has been forwarded<lb/>
to Washington.<lb/>
Parcel 6</p>
<p>Fourth.- Portion marked &ldquo;Onina y Sitio San Antonio&rdquo; - correct<lb/>
name of this property is &ldquo;Larrazabal&rdquo;; portion northwest of the<lb/>
railroad is within the limits of the Post of Columbia Barracks.<lb/>
This portion contains approximately seventeen (17) acres, is owned<lb/>
by the Sociedad Economica de Amigos del Pais, of which Alfredo Zayas<lb/>
was president. This farm is leased by Melchor Bautista, and sub-<lb/>
leased by him to Pedro F. Diago. Rent was last paid on the portion<lb/>
of the land within the Post to Jos&eacute; M. Callejas, Galiano #50,<lb/>
Havana. This man leased from Diago the portion referred to, but<lb/>
was ordered off by the Military Authorities, and the land taken<lb/>
possession of by them. Rent since that date which seems to be due<lb/>
Diago has not yet been paid. I enclose herewith under separate<lb/>
envelopes correspondence relating to this subject. This tract of<lb/>
land is one of those mentioned in your letter of recent date to<lb/>
Parcel 11<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02423003"/>
(3)<lb/>
Captain H. J. Slocum. Monthly rental agreed to, seventeen (17)<lb/>
dollars Spanish gold.</p>
<p>Fifth.- The Farm &ldquo;Jesus Maria&rdquo; -- Portion lying to the north-<lb/>
west of the Marianao Railroad is within the limits of the Post of<lb/>
Columbia Barracks. This portion contains approximately eighty<lb/>
eight (88) acres, is owned by the Condesa Caledonia del Val, whose<lb/>
agent is Juan F. Urribari, Mercaderes 29, Havana; sub-leased by Juan<lb/>
Guerra, who resides upon the place. Lease for portion forming a<lb/>
part of Columbia Barracks has been made between Urribari, as the<lb/>
agent for the owner, Juan Guerra, the lessee, and the Military<lb/>
Government of the Island of Cuba, and forwarded to your office for<lb/>
signature. It is presumed that the matter was concluded in that<lb/>
office. The monthly rental specified was forty five (45) dollars.<lb/>
Parcel 10</p>
<p>Sixth.- &ldquo;Sitio la Serafina&rdquo; -- Portion lying to the northwest<lb/>
of the Marianao Railroad is within the limits of the Post of<lb/>
Columbia Barracks. Portion lying to the south of the Marianao<lb/>
Railroad is controlled by the Military Authorities in so far as<lb/>
the sale of intoxicants and the establishment of houses of prostitu-<lb/>
tion is concerned. Farm contains thirty three (33) acres; is owned<lb/>
by Jos&eacute; Dominguez y Lomus, Calzada Real #64, Quemados; leased by<lb/>
Government for fifteen (15) dollars per month. Copy of lease was<lb/>
given Captain Slocum, and by him forwarded to you.<lb/>
Parcel 8</p>
<p>Seventh.- Farm marked &ldquo;Hipodromo&rdquo;, properly called &ldquo;Las Hornos<lb/>
y Anona&rdquo;. Farm contains sixty six (66) acres, of which an irregular<lb/>
shaped piece containing <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> forty (40) acres is leased by the<lb/>
Government, and balance of farm controlled by the Government in so<lb/>
far as sale of intoxicants and establishment of houses of prostitu-<lb/>
Parcel 9<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02423004"/>
(4)<lb/>
tion is concerned; owned by Salvador Hernandez, who lives on the<lb/>
place; monthly rental (50) fifty dollars. <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>Owner refused to execute</add><lb/>
lease, but has regularly accepted fifty (50) dollars per month, for<lb/>
<del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>rent, which is amount allowed by board.</add></p>
<p>Eighth.- &ldquo;La Gomera&rdquo; (the one nearest the town of Quemados) -<lb/>
This farm contains thirty three (33) acres, is owned by the Marianao<lb/>
Railroad; monthly rental, twenty (20) dollars. Copy of lease<lb/>
delivered to Captain Slocum and by him forwarded to you.<lb/>
Parcel 7</p>
<p>Ninth.- Farm &ldquo;Padre&rdquo; -- Owner not known, no lease has been<lb/>
executed.</p>
<p>2</p>
<p>Tenth.- Farm marked &ldquo;Tuscano&rdquo; -- It is believed that this is<lb/>
improperly marked so on the map, and that it should be marked<lb/>
&ldquo;Vista Hermosa&rdquo;, which is shown on the map as the next piece of<lb/>
property. This farm is claimed by R. O. Williams of the North<lb/>
American Trust Company. He stated to me, however, that he would<lb/>
prefer not to have any rent from it if it necessitated his looking<lb/>
up his deeds. This piece of land is referred to in your letter of<lb/>
recent date to Captain Slocum.<lb/>
2<lb/>
Parcel 12</p>
<p>Eleventh.- &ldquo;La Gomera&rdquo; (the one farthest from the town of<lb/>
Quemados) -- Contains thirty three (33) acres, all in the Post of<lb/>
Columbia Barracks; is owned by Do&ntilde;a A&ntilde;a Callejas y Armenteros, power<lb/>
of attorney held by Carlos Callejas, #11 Tajadillo, Havana; monthly<lb/>
rental, ten (10) dollars. Copy of lease was delivered to Captain<lb/>
Slocum, and forwarded by him to you.<lb/>
Parcel 4</p>
<p>Twelfth.- A portion of the farms <del>&ldquo;<unclear>[unclear]</unclear>&rdquo;</del><add>&ldquo;Magulles&rdquo;</add> and &ldquo;San Armas&rdquo; --<lb/>
The portion within the Post of Columbia Barracks contains about<lb/>
forty five (45) acres; is owned by Rufino Otamendi, #19 General Lee<lb/>
Street, Quemados. It is believed that rent for this farm was<lb/>
Parcel 3<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02423005"/>
(5)<lb/>
paid Mr. Otamendi for the fiscal year ending June 30, 1900, at the<lb/>
rate of thirty (30) dollars per month. On that date he violated<lb/>
his agreement to renew his lease for as long as the Government<lb/>
desired, and has since then refused thirty (30) dollars per month.<lb/>
He has a claim against the Government for rent of farm and de-<lb/>
struction of a certain field of hennequen, which has already been<lb/>
adjudicated.<lb/>
Parcel 3</p>
<p>Thirteenth.- Portion of the farm &ldquo;San Augustin&rdquo;, &ldquo;San Antonio&rdquo;,<lb/>
or &ldquo;San Basilio&rdquo; -- This is the property of the late Tomasa Cardenas<lb/>
which has been referred to in previous correspondence.<lb/>
Parcel 2</p>
<p>Fourteenth.- Portion of land near La Playa de Marianao<lb/>
occupied as Military Cemetery -- This land is leased for a period<lb/>
of ninety nine (99) years, and payment in full for that time has<lb/>
been made. The owner has agreed to deliver to the Military Govern-<lb/>
ment or its successor a deed to the property at any time within the<lb/>
period of ninety nine years that it shall be asked of him, without<lb/>
extra compensation. A copy of this lease was forwarded to Division<lb/>
Headquarters.</p>
<p>Copies of all of these leases which have been forwarded to you<lb/>
are on file among my papers. They can be copied if necessary, but<lb/>
it is thought that you have copies of every one which I have made.</p>
<p>Referring to the third paragraph of your letter, I have to say<lb/>
that I have sent to you the only map which we at present have of<lb/>
this property. I am having a map of the Post of Columbia Barracks<lb/>
made, and will show upon that map the property leased. When it is<lb/>
completed I shall be pleased to send you a blue print if you desire<lb/>
it.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02423006"/>
<p>If I can give you any further information in regard to this<lb/>
matter, I shall be very glad to have you let me know.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,</salute>
<signed>H.J. Jackson</signed>
1st Lieutenant, 2nd Artillery,<lb/>
ASSISTANT ENGINEER<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="letter" n="1901-01-17">
<head>Letter from Harry Frederick Jackson to Chauncey B. Baker, January 17, 1901</head>
<pb n="7" id="f02423007"/>
<opener>
L. R.<lb/>
DEPT. OF CUBA.<lb/>
RECEIVED.<lb/>
27408<lb/>
418.<lb/>
190<del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>1</add>.<lb/>
<dateline>
Quemados, Cuba.<lb/>
<date value="1901-01-17">Jan. 17, 1901.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Jackson, M.F.<lb/>
1st. Lt., 2nd. Arty.<lb/>
Asst. Engr.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Replies to C.O.M.I.C. letter of<lb/>
10th. Inst., states rent (for<lb/>
part of land occupied by Columbia<lb/>
Barracks) was last paid to in-<lb/>
clude June 30th., 1900, and no<lb/>
rents have since been paid.<lb/>
Recites relative to list of<lb/>
parcels of land <hi>comprising Colum-<lb/>
bia Barracks</hi>. Name of owners<lb/>
and amounts of rentals.<lb/>
Encloses map of Post.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
