<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02463001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Military Orders, April 27, 1901</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Scott, Hugh L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02463001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1901-04-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1901-04-27">April 27, 1901</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02463001</idno>
<title>Military Orders, April 27, 1901</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In Circular #5, Scott specifies how to prevent the spread of yellow fever and malaria at military posts by controlling mosquitoes, and instructs physicians how to monitor possible yellow fever patients.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="military orders" n="1901-04-27">
<head>Military Orders, April 27, 1901</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02463001"/>
<p>FROM THE NATIONAL ARCHIVES</p>
<p>The former bureau of Insular affairs<lb/>
Records relating to YF.</p>
<p>File under Nat A.</p>
<p>ORDERS, BOOKS, BLANKS, &amp; D.C.DIV.<lb/>
REC'D MAY-6- 1901<lb/>
ADJUTANT GENERALS OFFICE.</p>
<p>CIRCULAR,<lb/>
No. 5.}</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS DEPARTMENT OF CUBA,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Havana, April 27, <hi>1901</hi></hi>.</p>
<p>Upon the recommendation of the Chief Surgeon of the<lb/>
Department, the following instructions are published and<lb/>
will be strictly enforced at all military posts in this Depart-<lb/>
ment:</p>
<p>The recent experiments made in Havana by the Medical<lb/>
Department of the Army having proved that yellow fever,<lb/>
like malarial fever, is conveyed chiefly, and probably ex-<lb/>
clusively, by the bite of infected mosquitoes, important<lb/>
changes in the measures used for the prevention and treat-<lb/>
ment of this disease have become necessary.</p>
<p>1. In order to prevent the breeding of mosquitoes and<lb/>
protect officers and men against their bites, the provisions<lb/>
of General Orders No. 6, Department of Cuba, December<lb/>
21, 1900, shall be carefully carried out, especially during<lb/>
the summer and fall.</p>
<p>2. So far as yellow fever is concerned, infection of a<lb/>
room or building simply means that it contains infected<lb/>
mosquitoes, that is, mosquitoes which have fed on yellow<lb/>
fever patients. Disinfection, therefore, means the employ-<lb/>
ment of measures aimed at the destruction of these mosqui-<lb/>
toes. The most effective of these measures is fumigation,<lb/>
either with sulphur, formaldehyde or insect powder. The<lb/>
fumes of sulphur are the quickest and most effective insec-<lb/>
ticide but are otherwise objectionable. Formaldehyde gas<lb/>
is quite effective if the infected rooms are kept closed and<lb/>
sealed for two or three hours. The smoke of insect powder<lb/>
has also been proved very useful; it readily stupefies mos-<lb/>
quitoes, which drop to the floor and can then be easily de-<lb/>
stroyed.</p>
<p>The washing of walls, floors, ceilings and furniture with<lb/>
disinfectants is unnecessary.</p>
<p>3. As it has been demonstrated that yellow fever cannot<lb/>
be conveyed by fomites, such as bedding, clothing, effects<lb/>
and baggage, they need not be subjected to any special<lb/>
disinfection. Care should be taken, however, not to re-<lb/>
move them from the infected rooms until after formaldehyde<lb/>
fumigation, so that they may not harbor infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes.</p>
<p>Medical officers taking care of yellow fever patients need<lb/>
not be isolated; they can attend other patients and as-<lb/>
sociate with non-immunes with perfect safety to the garri-<lb/>
son. Nurses and attendants taking care of yellow fever<lb/>
patients shall remain isolated, so as to avoid any possible<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02463002"/>
<unclear>INSULAR DIVISION,</unclear><lb/>
MAY 6<lb/>
162<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
1901<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT<lb/>
danger of their conveying mosquitoes from patients to non-<lb/>
immunes.</p>
<p>4. The infection of mosquitoes is most likely to occur<lb/>
during the first two or three days of the disease. Ambulant<lb/>
cases, that is, patients not ill enough to take to their beds<lb/>
and remaining unsuspected and unprotected, are probably<lb/>
those most responsible for the spread of the disease. It is<lb/>
therefore essential that all fever cases should be at once<lb/>
isolated and so protected that no mosquitoes can possibly<lb/>
get access to them until the nature of the fever is positively<lb/>
determined.</p>
<p>Each post shall have a &ldquo;reception ward&rdquo; for the admis-<lb/>
sion of all fever cases and an &ldquo;isolation ward&rdquo; for the<lb/>
treatment of cases which prove to be yellow fever. Each<lb/>
ward shall be made mosquito-proof by wire netting over<lb/>
doors and windows, a ceiling of wire netting at a height of<lb/>
seven feet above the floor, and mosquito bars over the beds.<lb/>
There should be no place in it where mosquitoes can seek<lb/>
refuge, not readily accessible to the nurse. Both wards can<lb/>
be in the same building, provided they are separated by a<lb/>
mosquito-tight partition.</p>
<p>5. All persons coming from an infected locality to a post<lb/>
shall be kept under careful observation until the comple-<lb/>
tion of five days from the time of possible infection, either<lb/>
in a special detention camp or in their own quarters; in<lb/>
either case, their temperature should be taken twice a day<lb/>
during this period of observation so that those who develop<lb/>
yellow fever may be placed under treatment at the very in-<lb/>
ception of the disease.</p>
<p>6. Malarial fever, like yellow fever, is communicated by<lb/>
mosquito bites and therefore is just as much of an infec-<lb/>
tious disease and requires the same measures of protection<lb/>
against mosquitoes. On the assumption that mosquitoes<lb/>
remain in the vicinity of their breeding places, or never<lb/>
travel far, the prevalence of malarial fever at a post would<lb/>
indicate want of proper care and diligence on the part of<lb/>
the Surgeon and Commanding Officer in complying with<lb/>
General Orders No. 6, Department of Cuba, 1900.</p>
<p>7. Surgeons are again reminded of the absolute necessity,<lb/>
in all fever cases, to keep, from the very beginning, a<lb/>
complete chart of pulse and temperature, since such a<lb/>
chart is their best guide to a correct diagnosis and the<lb/>
proper treatment.</p>
<p>BY COMMAND OF MAJOR GENERAL WOOD:<lb/>
H. L. SCOTT,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Adjutant General</hi>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
