<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY t02516009 SYSTEM "t02516009.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02516010 SYSTEM "t02516010.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02516011 SYSTEM "t02516011.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02516012 SYSTEM "t02516012.jpg" NDATA jpg>]>
<TEI.2 id="t02516001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report from Valery Havard to the Adjutant General, July 22, 1901</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Havard, Valery</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02516001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1901-07-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Scott, Hugh L.</name>
<name type="place">Cabana Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1901-07-22">July 22, 1901</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02516001</idno>
<title>Report from Valery Havard to the Adjutant General, July 22, 1901</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Havard reports on the health situation of the troops in Cuba for the fiscal year ending June 30, 1901.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1901-07-22">
<head>Report from Valery Havard to the Adjutant General, July 22, 1901</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02516001"/>
<opener>
22 July 1901<lb/>
With regards of<lb/>
V. Havard<lb/>
See pictures opposite p. 12 &amp; 18<lb/>
REPORT<lb/>
OF<lb/>
MAJOR VALERY HAVARD,<lb/>
SURGEON U. S. ARMY,<lb/>
CHIEF SURGEON<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF CUBA.<lb/>
-----<lb/>
1901.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02516003"/>
HEADQUARTERS DEPARTMENT OF CUBA,<lb/>
OFFICE OF CHIEF SURGEON,<lb/>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1901-07-22">July 22, 1901.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<hi rend="italic">To the<lb/>
Adjutant General,<lb/>
Department of Cuba,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba</hi>.<lb/>
<salute>SIR:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to submit the following report of the<lb/>
operations of this office for the fiscal year ending June<lb/>
30, 1901.</p>
<p>The health of the troops in Cuba during the year has<lb/>
been very good, showing a marked and steady improve-<lb/>
ment upon former years. Thus, while during the year<lb/>
ending June 30, 1900, the admissions to the sick report<lb/>
were 322 per cent., with 1.51 per cent. of deaths, the<lb/>
admissions during the past year are only 193 per cent.,<lb/>
with 1.25 per cent. of deaths. Comparing the results<lb/>
obtained in the appended table for the island of Cuba<lb/>
with the statistics in the last report of the Surgeon Gen-<lb/>
eral (calendar year 1899), we find that our ratio of ad-<lb/>
missions is less than that for all troops outside the Unit-<lb/>
ed States (252) but more than that for troops stationed<lb/>
in the United States (168). In like manner, our ratio of<lb/>
deaths is less than that for all islands (2.55) but more<lb/>
than that for the United States (0.79). Our mortality<lb/>
was largely increased by outbreaks of yellow fever, a<lb/>
disease not likely again to occur among troops in Cuba,<lb/>
except possibly in a scattering, sporadic manner; if we<lb/>
deduct the number of yellow fever cases from the total<lb/>
mortality, we obtain a percentage of 0.80, practically<lb/>
that of the United States.</p>
<p>Further comparison furnishes instructive details. In<lb/>
Cuba, the ratio of admissions for diarrhoeal diseases,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02516004"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
4<lb/>
dysentery, malarial fevers and yellow fever, as should<lb/>
be expected, is higher than in the United States, but<lb/>
that of the common infectious diseases, such as scarlet<lb/>
fever, measles, small-pox, influenza, mumps, diphtheria,<lb/>
is very much lower, the majority of cases under the<lb/>
heading of &ldquo;other infectious diseases&rdquo; in our tables<lb/>
being vaccinia, that is, the condition produced by vacci-<lb/>
nation. There was not a single case of small-pox during<lb/>
the year. The ratio of typhoid fever is about one-third<lb/>
that of the United States, and much greater in western<lb/>
Cuba, where are the large seaport towns, than in the<lb/>
eastern part of the island. Strangely enough, tuberculosis<lb/>
among our troops is more common in Cuba than in the<lb/>
United States, as 0.44 to 0.32, and about the same as in<lb/>
all the islands (0.45), which is remarkable in view of<lb/>
the fact that other diseases of the respiratory system,<lb/>
such as bronchitis and pneumonia, are almost unknown.<lb/>
This relative frequency of tuberculosis among soldiers<lb/>
in Cuba, and its great prevalence among civilians, would<lb/>
tend to show that a rather high and equable temperature<lb/>
all the year round is not by itself a factor of great im-<lb/>
portance in the prevention and cure of that disease.</p>
<p>Our record for syphilis and other venereal diseases is<lb/>
bad, being nearly double that of the United States, and<lb/>
apparently also worse than that for all the islands. This<lb/>
evil has always been one of the troublesome problems to<lb/>
confront post surgeons in Cuba and there is no satisfac-<lb/>
tory solution in sight. About one-eighth of soldiers on<lb/>
the sick report are victims of it. Were it possible to<lb/>
examine all prostitutes and subject them to treatment<lb/>
when necessary, these diseases would be much less<lb/>
prevalent; but in several garrison towns there is no law<lb/>
requiring examination, or else it is so loosely applied by<lb/>
the municipal authorities that it fails of its purpose;<lb/>
even when applied with ordinary diligence and intelli-<lb/>
gence it does not reach clandestine prostitution nor the<lb/>
many women living in a state of concubinage. It has<lb/>
been proposed to apply the remedy inside instead of<lb/>
outside, and subject all enlisted men to a weekly<lb/>
examination, those found diseased being placed under<lb/>
treatment and debarred from post-exchange and pass<lb/>
privileges. There is no question as to the excellent results<lb/>
of this plan wherever put into practice, but the objec-<lb/>
tions against it are so strong that it never extended<lb/>
beyond a few posts, and the wisdom and practicability<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02516005"/>
5<lb/>
of enforcing it as a general rule is very doubtful. The<lb/>
ratio of alcoholism is likewise high, at least double that<lb/>
of the United States. This is, in a large measure, attrib-<lb/>
utable to the cheap and wretched alcoholic beverages<lb/>
sold in all parts of the island, especially since the prohi-<lb/>
bition to sell intoxicating drinks in post-exchanges.</p>
<p>It is also interesting to compare the western half of the<lb/>
island, comprising four provinces, with the eastern half<lb/>
comprising the provinces of Santiago and Puerto Pr&iacute;nci-<lb/>
pe. In the western half, the mean strength of the com-<lb/>
mand is 3344 and the percentage of admissions only 150,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">which is less than in the United States</hi>. In the eastern half,<lb/>
on the contrary, with mean strength of 1772, the percen-<lb/>
tage of admissions is 274, not only more than in the Uni-<lb/>
ted States but greater than for all the islands. The<lb/>
difference depends mostly upon the much greater num-<lb/>
ber of cases of diarhoeal diseases and malarial fever, so<lb/>
that, after making due allowance for the personal equa-<lb/>
tion of medical officers and the smaller size of posts, it<lb/>
is safe to conclude, leaving yellow fever out of consider-<lb/>
ation, that the eastern half of the island does not enjoy<lb/>
as good hygienic and climatic conditions as the western<lb/>
half; thus, five deaths from malarial fever occurred in the<lb/>
province of Santiago and none in any of the other provin-<lb/>
ces. In my report for the fiscal year ending June 30,<lb/>
1900, it was also shown that malarial fever gradually<lb/>
increased in frequency and severity from the western to<lb/>
the eastern end of the island.</p>
<p>The ratio of deaths per 1000 is 13.6 for western and<lb/>
10.1 for eastern Cuba, a difference due to the 24 cases of<lb/>
yellow fever occurring in the western provinces; if we<lb/>
deduct these, the ratio of deaths will be less for the west-<lb/>
ern than for the eastern provinces.</p>
<p>With the acquisition of our recent knowledge of the<lb/>
propagation of malarial fever it may be taken for grant-<lb/>
ed that this preventable disease will be hereafter greatly<lb/>
reduced and, at most posts, practically eliminated. As an<lb/>
instance: For the week ending June 23, 1900, there were<lb/>
34 cases of malarial fever under treatment at Rowell<lb/>
Barracks (Cienfuegos); a year afterward, for the week<lb/>
ending June 22, 1901, chiefly in consequence of sanitary<lb/>
measures promoted by the post surgeon, Lieut. A. E.<lb/>
Truby, there was not a single case.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f02516006"/>
<p>AC<lb/>
K</p>
<p>6</p>
<p>YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>In my report for the fiscal year ending June, 1900,<lb/>
I described three outbreaks of yellow fever outside of<lb/>
Havana, involving American troops: at Santiago de Cu-<lb/>
ba, Santa Clara and Quemados. That of Santiago ended<lb/>
in October, 1899, and, thanks to the energetic measures<lb/>
carried out by the chief surgeon, Major L. C. Carr, not a<lb/>
single case has occurred since then in that city (troops<lb/>
and civilian population), although previously strongly<lb/>
contaminated. The other two outbreaks came to an end<lb/>
in July, 1900. In June, July and August, 1900, thirty<lb/>
cases occurred at Pinar del Rio Barracks, with nine<lb/>
deaths; the first few cases were unrecognized by the sur-<lb/>
geon and the infection allowed to spread before proper<lb/>
measures of isolation were taken. Five sporadic cases<lb/>
occurred at Hamilton Barracks between August and<lb/>
November, but none was permitted to become a focus of<lb/>
infection. The last cases recorded among enlisted men<lb/>
are the nine who were experimentally inoculated by<lb/>
infected mosquitoes at Quemados in December, January<lb/>
and February, without a single death. Since then all<lb/>
our posts have been absolutely free from yellow fever.</p>
<p>In the summer of 1900, on the recommendation of the<lb/>
Surgeon General, a board of medical officers consisting<lb/>
of Surgeon Walter Reed, U. S. A., and Contract Sur-<lb/>
geons Carroll, Agramonte and Lazear, U. S. A., was<lb/>
convened in Havana for the investigation of tropical<lb/>
diseases. The result of its experiments, as already well<lb/>
known, was one of the most brilliant medical discoveries<lb/>
of the age, namely the mode of transmission of yellow<lb/>
fever, and, as a natural consequence, a complete revolu-<lb/>
tion in the methods adopted to prevent and combat this<lb/>
disease. The doctrine of the transmission of yellow fever<lb/>
by the bite of mosquitoes having been proved by incon-<lb/>
trovertible experiments upon non-immunes, and fomites<lb/>
proved to be harmless, the following circular, having<lb/>
received the sanction of the Surgeon General, was pub-<lb/>
lished:</p>
<p>CIRCULAR, }<lb/>
No. 5. }</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS DEPARTMENT OF CUBA,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Havana, April 27, 1901</hi>.</p>
<p>Upon the recommendation of the Chief Surgeon of the Depart-<lb/>
ment, the following instructions are published and will be strictly<lb/>
enforced at all military posts in this Department:</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02516007"/>
<p>7</p>
<p>The recent experiments made in Havana by the Medical Depart-<lb/>
ment of the Army having proved that yellow fever, like malarial<lb/>
fever, is conveyed chiefly, and probably exclusively, by the bite of<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, important changes in the measures used for<lb/>
the prevention and treatment of this disease have become neces-<lb/>
sary.</p>
<p>1. In order to prevent the breeding of mosquitoes and protect<lb/>
officers and men against their bites, the provisions of General<lb/>
Orders No. 6, Department of Cuba, December 21, 1900, shall be<lb/>
carefully carried out, especially during the summer and fall.</p>
<p>2. So far as yellow fever is concerned, infection of a room or<lb/>
building simply means that it contains infected mosquitoes, that<lb/>
is, mosquitoes which have fed on yellow fever patients. Disinfec-<lb/>
tion, therefore, means the employment of measures aimed at the<lb/>
destruction of these mosquitoes. The most effective of these mea-<lb/>
sures is fumigation, either with sulphur, formaldehyde or insect<lb/>
powder. The fumes of sulphur are the quickest and most effective<lb/>
insecticide but are otherwise objectionable. Formaldehyde gas is<lb/>
quite effective if the infected rooms are kept closed and sealed for<lb/>
two or three hours. The smoke of insect powder has also been<lb/>
proved very useful; it readily stupefies mosquitoes, which drop to<lb/>
the floor and can then be easily destroyed.</p>
<p>The washing of walls, floors, ceilings and furniture with disin-<lb/>
fectants is unnecessary.</p>
<p>3. As it has been demonstrated that yellow fever cannot be<lb/>
conveyed by fomites, such as bedding, clothing, effects and bag-<lb/>
gage, they need not be subjected to any special disinfection. Care<lb/>
should be taken, however, not to remove them from the infected<lb/>
rooms until after formaldehyde fumigation, so that they may not<lb/>
harbor infected mosquitoes.</p>
<p>Medical officers taking care of yellow fever patients need not be<lb/>
isolated; they can attend other patients and associate with non-<lb/>
immunes with perfect safety to the garrison. Nurses and attend-<lb/>
ants taking care of yellow fever patients shall remain isolated, so<lb/>
as to avoid any possible danger of their conveying mosquitoes<lb/>
from patients to non immunes.</p>
<p>4. The infection of mosquitoes is most likely to occur during<lb/>
the first two or three days of the disease. Ambulant cases, that<lb/>
is, patients not ill enough to take to their beds and remaining un-<lb/>
suspected and unprotected, are probably those most responsible<lb/>
for the spread of the disease. It is therefore essential that all fever<lb/>
cases should be at once isolated and so protected that no mos-<lb/>
quitoes can possibly get access to them until the nature of the<lb/>
fever is positively determined.</p>
<p>Each post shall have a &ldquo;reception ward&rdquo; for the admission of all<lb/>
fever cases and an &ldquo;isolation ward&rdquo; for the treatment of cases<lb/>
which prove to be yellow fever. Each ward shall be made mos-<lb/>
quito-proof by wire netting over doors and windows, a ceiling of<lb/>
wire netting at a height of seven feet above the floor, and mos-<lb/>
quito bars over the beds. There should be no place in it where<lb/>
mosquitoes can seek refuge, not readily accessible to the nurse.<lb/>
Both wards can be in the same building, provided they are sepa-<lb/>
rated by a mosquito-tight partition.</p>
<p>5. All persons coming from an infected locality to a post shall<lb/>
be kept under careful observation until the completion of five days<lb/>
from the time of possible infection, either in a special detention<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02516008"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
8<lb/>
camp or in their own quarters; in either case, their temperature<lb/>
should be taken twice a day during this period of observation so<lb/>
that those who develop yellow fever may be placed under treat-<lb/>
ment at the very inception of the disease.</p>
<p>6. Malarial fever, like yellow fever, is communicated by mos-<lb/>
quito bites and therefore is just as much of an infectious disease<lb/>
and requires the same measures of protection against mosquitoes.<lb/>
On the assumption that mosquitoes remain in the vicinity of their<lb/>
breeding places, or never travel far, the prevalence of malarial<lb/>
fever at a post would indicate want of proper care and diligence<lb/>
on the part of the Surgeon and Commanding Officer in complying<lb/>
with General Orders No. 6, Department of Cuba, 1900.</p>
<p>7. Surgeons are again reminded of the absolute necessity, in all<lb/>
fever cases, to keep, from the very beginning, a complete chart of<lb/>
pulse and temperature, since such a chart is their best guide to a<lb/>
correct diagnosis and the proper treatment.</p>
<p>BY COMMAND OF MAJOR GENERAL WOOD:</p>
<p>H. L. SCOTT,</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Adjutant General</hi>.</p>
<p>HYGIENE OF POSTS.</p>
<p>All enlisted men are in comfortable, permanent bar-<lb/>
racks, with one exception; the cavalry troops at Camp<lb/>
Mackenzie, Puerto Pr&iacute;ncipe, are still under canvas, but<lb/>
with the benefit of every improvement that a camp ad-<lb/>
mits of. Five of our largest posts have been built on new<lb/>
selected sites since the American intervention, and com-<lb/>
bine as many favorable hygienic conditions as possible;<lb/>
the others occupy old Spanish quarters more or less ex-<lb/>
tended and renovated and answering their purpose very<lb/>
well. The disposal of garbage and refuse is simple and<lb/>
effective; most of our posts, being near the shore, dump<lb/>
everything into the sea; none has a crematory. All the<lb/>
posts built on new sites (Columbia Brks., Hamilton Brks.,<lb/>
Rowell Brks., Caba&ntilde;a Brks., Morro Castle Brks., San-<lb/>
tiago) are provided with modern sewerage with outlet<lb/>
into the sea. At other posts, the milk of lime and exca-<lb/>
vator system is successfully employed, while a few still<lb/>
use the old fashioned latrines.</p>
<p>The clothing is, in the main, well adapted to the clim-<lb/>
ate, with the exception of the campaign hat; this should<lb/>
have an all-round space outside the sweat-band for ven-<lb/>
tilation and, if possible, be made of rain-proof material.<lb/>
Since the helmet is impossible in the field, it seems neces-</p>
<pb n="8" id="f02516009"/>
<p>MEDICAL OFFICERS' QUARTERS, POST HOSPITAL, U. S. A., COLUMBIA BARRACKS, (HAVANA).</p>
<pb n="9" id="f02516010"/>
<p>WARDS AND OPERATING ROOM, POST HOSPITAL, U. S. A., COLUMBIA BARRACKS (HAVANA).</p>
<pb n="10" id="f02516011"/>
<p>Frame of wire cage, with vestibule, used<lb/>
at posts to protect fever patients from mosquitoes.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f02516012"/>
<p>POST HOSPITAL, U. S. A., CABA&Ntilde;A BARRACKS, (HAVANA).</p>
<closer></closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
