<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02520001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report: Proceedings of a Medical Commission Appointed By Circular Letter No. 59, by Valery Havard, September, 1901</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Havard, Valery</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02520001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1901-09-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1901-09-00">September, 1901</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02520001</idno>
<title>Report: Proceedings of a Medical Commission Appointed By Circular Letter No. 59, by Valery Havard, September, 1901</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Havard provides evidence that Caldas' and Bellingaghi's theories are unsound and should not be accepted. He includes a detailed time-line of events and a list of arguments to conclude his report against Caldas. Enclosed are charts, reports, and other documents used as evidence. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1901-09-00">
<head>Report: Proceedings of a Medical Commission Appointed By Circular Letter No. 59, by Valery Havard, September, 1901</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02520001"/>
<p>File under Caldas &amp; Bellingaghi</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF CUBA<lb/>
OFFICE OF CHIEF SURGEON,<lb/>
HAVANA.</p>
<p>PROCEEDINGS OF A MEDICAL COMMISSION APPOINTED<lb/>
BY THE FOLLOWING CIRCULAR LETTER.</p>
<p>Circular Letter, )<lb/>
(<lb/>
No. 59. )</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS DEPARTMENT OF CUBA,<lb/>
Havana, August 7, 1901.</p>
<p>A medical commission, to consist of:</p>
<p>Major Valery Havard, Surgeon, U.S. Army, Chief Surgeon of the<lb/>
Department;</p>
<p>The Physicians composing the Havana Yellow Fever Board;<lb/>
will meet at Las Animas Hospital in this city at 4 o'clock P.M.,<lb/>
August 9, 1901, or as soon thereafter as practicable, for the pur-<lb/>
pose of examining into the propositions and claims of Drs. Caldas<lb/>
and Bellinzaghi, and submit, in connection therewith, such recom-<lb/>
mendations as it may deem best for the interest of science and<lb/>
medicine.</p>
<p>BY COMMAND OF BRIGADIER GENERAL WOOD:</p>
<p>H. L. SCOTT,<lb/>
Captain 7th Cavalry,<lb/>
Adjutant General.</p>
<p>In compliance with the above letter, the commission met at<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital on August 9th at 4 P.M.; all the members<lb/>
present; Drs. Caldas and Bellinzaghi also present.</p>
<p>Dr. Caldas stated to the commission that he had discovered<lb/>
the pathogenic microbe of yellow fever and, from cultures there-<lb/>
of, prepared a curative serum and prophylactic vaccine; that he<lb/>
was convinced of the efficacy of his vaccine and desired to be<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02520002"/>
(2)<lb/>
furnished the opportunity of demonstrating this efficacy before<lb/>
the commission. He proposed that a certain number of non-<lb/>
immune persons be inoculated with his vaccine and when thus<lb/>
immunized against yellow fever that they should be bitten with<lb/>
infected mosquitoes; this he declared could be done with perfect<lb/>
impunity as it was impossible for persons immunized with his<lb/>
vaccine to contract yellow fever. He then described the pro-<lb/>
cess by which he immunizes the horse and obtains his curative<lb/>
serum, and the process by which he prepares his prophylactic<lb/>
vaccine, which is an attenuated culture of his microbe. He also<lb/>
explained his procedure to produce immunization in man; as his<lb/>
vaccine is liable to develop marked febrile movement and other<lb/>
yellow fever symptoms he previously injects a dose of his serum<lb/>
to ward off such symptoms. The commission then requested that<lb/>
he would demonstrate his pathogenic microbe and describe the<lb/>
method of its isolation and culture; this he formally declined<lb/>
to do, because of his pledge to the company organized to exploit<lb/>
his discovery, and also because he thought such demonstration<lb/>
would, at this time, result in nothing but useless scientific<lb/>
wrangles. This much, however, he was willing to divulge, namely,<lb/>
that his microbe is not found in the blood but always in the<lb/>
intestines, having been present in every case examined. If per-<lb/>
mitted, said he, to vaccinate non-immune persons, and these are<lb/>
subjected to the bite of infected mosquitoes and do not develop<lb/>
yellow fever, the causative relation of his microbe to the dis-<lb/>
ease would be indirectly proved.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02520003"/>
<p>(3)</p>
<p>Having been asked by what tests he had convinced himself<lb/>
of the efficacy of his vaccine, he stated that, during the past<lb/>
two years, he had inoculated with it 23 young men, mostly students,<lb/>
at Rio Grande do Sul, where yellow fever is unknown, previous to<lb/>
their going to Rio de Janeiro where yellow fever is endemic, and<lb/>
that none of these young men had, so far as he knew, contracted<lb/>
the fever. Upon the request of the commission, he submitted<lb/>
that statement in writing, but without any other evidence or<lb/>
proof than his own declaration. Referring to his curative<lb/>
serum, he informed the commission that in Brazil, as well as in<lb/>
Mexico, he and Dr. Bellinzaghi had obtained with it an average of<lb/>
85 per cent. of cures, a result which, even if correctly reported,<lb/>
did not appear to the commission sufficiently promising to jus-<lb/>
tify experimentation with it in Havana.</p>
<p>After careful discussion of the subject, the commission<lb/>
decided that, since Dr. Caldas did not intend to demonstrate his<lb/>
microbe and thus put his claim upon a true scientific basis, it<lb/>
should decline active cooperation in his tests; it, however,<lb/>
recommended that the necessary facilities be afforded him, and<lb/>
stood ready, in its official capacity, to watch result<add>s</add> and report<lb/>
upon them.</p>
<p>Thereupon, Dr. Bellinzaghi engaged four non-immune immigrants<lb/>
and, as required by the commission, made with them a written con-<lb/>
tract whereby they voluntarily offered themselves to be inocu-<lb/>
lated with Dr. Caldas' vaccine and then bitten by infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes, for a certain stipulated sum of money, to be paid on the<lb/>
termination of the experiment. These four men were sent to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02520004"/>
(4)<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital and kept in a mosquito-proof, wire-screened<lb/>
room.</p>
<p>August 14th. The commission met at 11.30 A.M. at Las<lb/>
Animas Hospital. They found that two of the four men selected<lb/>
by Dr. Caldas for his experiments were probably immunes. The<lb/>
other two named respectively Antonio Gomez and Paulino Alonso<lb/>
received each 12 c.c. of Dr. Caldas' serum, injected in the glute-<lb/>
al region by Dr. Bellinzaghi.</p>
<p>August 15th. The commission met at 11 A.M. at Las Animas<lb/>
Hospital. A very slight febrile reaction, and some local ten-<lb/>
derness had followed the injection of the serum. The two sub-<lb/>
jects were inoculated by Dr. Caldas, in the same region, with 3 c.<lb/>
c. of the vaccine obtained by Dr. Caldas from an attenuated and<lb/>
filtered culture of his bacillus. He explained that this vac-<lb/>
cine produces a very sharp reaction if it be not preceded by an<lb/>
injection of the antitoxic serum. The accompanying chart of<lb/>
Paulino Alonso shows that the so-called vaccine was followed by<lb/>
a slight reaction. Dr. Caldas declared that his subject would<lb/>
be immunized in five days. The commission decided that the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes should be applied one week after the vac-<lb/>
cination.</p>
<p>August 22nd. At 9.30 A.M. the commission met at the of-<lb/>
fice of the Chief Surgeon, Drs. Caldas and Bellinzaghi being<lb/>
present. It was resolved that the commission meet in the af-<lb/>
ternoon at Las Animas Hospital, and apply two infected mosquitoes<lb/>
to one of the subjects previously vaccinated by Drs. Caldas and<lb/>
Bellinzaghi; the other subject to remain under observation, and<lb/>
to be inoculated later if the first should appear to be protect-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02520005"/>
(5)<lb/>
ed by the supposed immunizing vaccine. The Brazilian gentlemen<lb/>
were warned that the experiment was a dangerous one; that the<lb/>
yellow fever that was being produced by the mosquitoes then a-<lb/>
vailable was of a grave type. They were further told that the<lb/>
experiment should not be performed without stating clearly to<lb/>
the subjects the probable dangers. The Brazilian gentlemen<lb/>
expressed themselves as absolutely certain that the subjects<lb/>
had been absolutely immunized against yellow fever by the vac-<lb/>
cine.</p>
<p>The commission met at 4 P.M. in the Inoculation Station of<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital, Drs. Caldas and Bellinzaghi being present.<lb/>
After the subject had been told the nature of the experiments,<lb/>
and the risk incurred, he, of his own free will subjected himself<lb/>
to the experiment. Two mosquitoes were then applied to his<lb/>
arm. One of the insects applied had previously produced a mild<lb/>
attack of yellow fever, and the other, when first applied with<lb/>
three other insects, had produced a mild case, and when applied<lb/>
the second time had produced, in conjunction with one other in-<lb/>
sect, a severe (subsequently fatal) case. The subject and his<lb/>
companion, who had also been vaccinated, but not bitten by in-<lb/>
fected mosquitoes, were then transferred to Hospital No. 1, and<lb/>
placed together in one of the wire-screened rooms in the wards<lb/>
of Dr. Agramonte. Drs. Caldas and Bellinzaghi were allowed free<lb/>
access to the ward.</p>
<p>August 24th. Drs. Finlay and Guiteras visited the subject<lb/>
at Hospital No. 1 and found him well.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02520006"/>
<p>(6)</p>
<p>August 25th. Dr. Albertini visited the patient at 4 P.M.<lb/>
and found that his temperature had risen a few tenths of a<lb/>
degree above the normal. The face and conjunctivae were slight-<lb/>
ly injected. The gums were red. The patient did not complain<lb/>
of any symptoms.</p>
<p>August 26th. At 9 A.M. the commission met at Hospital<lb/>
No. 1 to examine the case of Paulino Alonso, the subject who had<lb/>
been bitten by the infected mosquitoes. Drs. Caldas and Bellin-<lb/>
zaghi were present. The patient was found to have a tempera-<lb/>
ture of 39.8 and pulse 90. The invasion had commenced the<lb/>
preceding afternoon, exactly three days after the bite of the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes. The patient complained of some headache<lb/>
and backache. The headache was frontal. The face and con-<lb/>
junctivae were decidedly injected. There was some photofobia.<lb/>
The chest and arms also presented considerable peripheral hyper-<lb/>
aemia. The liver and spleen were not enlarged. There was no<lb/>
albumen in the urine. Dr. Caldas at once opined that the case<lb/>
could not be one of yellow fever, because there was no intense<lb/>
supraorbital pain and rachialgia, no albumen in the urine and no<lb/>
enlargement of the liver. The commission, differing with Dr.<lb/>
Caldas as to the presence or absence of some of the symptoms<lb/>
mentioned, and as to the importance of others, were of opinion<lb/>
that the symptoms present were those of yellow fever in the<lb/>
first day of the disease, but they concluded that a final diag-<lb/>
nosis should not be made until the disease was more fully de-<lb/>
veloped. See the temperature chart.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f02520007"/>
<p>(7)</p>
<p>August 27th. The commission met at Hospital No. 1, Dr.<lb/>
Bellinzaghi being present. The temperature of the patient was<lb/>
39.6, and the pulse 92. A distinct trace of albumen had appear-<lb/>
ed in the urine. The fever was a continued fever. An exam-<lb/>
ination of the blood had shown the absence of malarial para-<lb/>
sites. The patient was nauseated. On the previous day there<lb/>
had been a fall of the pulse corresponding with a rise of the<lb/>
temperature. See temperature chart. Other symptoms had be-<lb/>
come intensified. The commission, therefore, gave their opinion<lb/>
to the effect that the case was one of yellow fever.</p>
<p>August 28th. The commission met at Hospital No. 1 at 9.30<lb/>
A.M. The patient had vomited several times since the last<lb/>
visit. He had passed black fecal matter. The gums were<lb/>
spongy. There was slight icterus. The commission resolved<lb/>
to meet at the office of the Chief Surgeon, Col. Havard, to hear<lb/>
the views of Dr. Caldas.</p>
<p>August 28th. At 4 P.M. the commission met in the office<lb/>
of the Chief Surgeon, Drs. Caldas and Bellinzaghi being present.<lb/>
The Chairman, Col Havard asked the opinion of Dr. Caldas as to the<lb/>
nature of the case infected by mosquitoes. Dr. Caldas was most<lb/>
positive in his opinion that the case was not one of yellow<lb/>
fever, - that he had none of the pathognomonic symptoms of the<lb/>
disease. He was told that the opinion of all the physicians,<lb/>
outside of the commission, who had examined the case was unani-<lb/>
mous to the effect that the case was one of yellow fever. Dr.<lb/>
Caldas was sure that the case was one of septicaemia, - a putrid<lb/>
fever caused by infection from mosquito bites. His reasons for<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02520008"/>
(8)<lb/>
rejecting the diagnosis of yellow fever were: that the patient had<lb/>
had no initial chill, no supraorbital pain, no rachialgia, no<lb/>
nausea, no epigastralgia, no enlargement of the liver, and no dis-<lb/>
crepancy between the pulse and temperature. The commission<lb/>
differed from Dr. Caldas as to the absence of some of these symp-<lb/>
toms and as to the importance of others. Dr. Caldas was told<lb/>
that the patient had been vomiting since the previous evening,<lb/>
and a specimen of the last vomit, just before the meeting, was<lb/>
shown him. The vomit presented a dirty greenish color, and a<lb/>
deposit of dark red floculi. In the opinion of the commission<lb/>
this was the first stage of the black vomit of yellow fever.<lb/>
Dr. Caldas, however, appeared to attach no importance to the mat-<lb/>
ter. He seemed not to care to look at the specimen until he<lb/>
was made to do so. He was then shown the temperature chart,<lb/>
and his attention was called to the fall of the pulse corres-<lb/>
ponding with a rise of the temperature. It was very evident<lb/>
that Dr. Caldas had not followed carefully the course of the<lb/>
temperature during his visits to the hospital. The commission<lb/>
received the impression that Dr. Caldas had made up his mind to<lb/>
the effect that the case should not be one of yellow fever, and<lb/>
he would not study it with a scientific spirit. He was asked,<lb/>
however, to present, in writing, his reasons for not accepting<lb/>
the diagnosis of yellow fever. His statement accompanies this<lb/>
report.</p>
<p>In the opinion of the commission the vaccine prepared by<lb/>
Dr. Caldas had failed to immunize against yellow fever; and it<lb/>
was therefore decided to discontinue all experiments with the<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02520009"/>
(9)<lb/>
serum and vaccine prepared by Drs. Caldas and Bellinzaghi. It<lb/>
was also decided that other physicians should be invited to<lb/>
visit the patient.</p>
<p>August 29th. The visiting and resident staff of Hospital<lb/>
No. 1 including Drs. Diago, Duenas, Jacobsen, and others, and also<lb/>
Professor Castro, and Drs. Cabrera and Valdes, experienced physi-<lb/>
cians of Havana have examined the patient and confirmed the<lb/>
diagnosis of yellow fever. The temperature has fallen below<lb/>
the normal. The pulse is 80 and soft. There is some general<lb/>
icteric discoloration. The urine contains a very large quan-<lb/>
tity of albumen.</p>
<p>August 30th. The temperature rose yesterday for a few<lb/>
hours above the normal to fall again to-day. The urine con-<lb/>
tains about two grams of albumen.</p>
<p>September 3rd. The commission met at the office of the<lb/>
Chief Surgeon. A communication from Dr. Caldas defending his<lb/>
position that the case of Paulino Alonso was one of putrid<lb/>
fever produced by the bite of mosquitoes was read. The commis-<lb/>
sion did not deem it necessary to further discuss this communi-<lb/>
cation because they have already embodied in this report their<lb/>
reasons for the diagnosis of yellow fever.</p>
<p>In conclusion the commission would state</p>
<p>1st. That Dr. Caldas has kept his alleged discoveries from<lb/>
the study of other scientists;</p>
<p>2nd. That the claim made by Dr. Caldas that the pathogenic<lb/>
agent of yellow fever is found only in the intestinal tract is<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f02520010"/>
(10)<lb/>
in direct opposition to the evidence furnished by the mosquito<lb/>
inoculations and the direct blood inoculations made by the Board<lb/>
presided over by Major Walter Reed, U.S.A. and other experimen-<lb/>
tors.</p>
<p>3rd. That the attempt made by Dr. Caldas to immunize an<lb/>
individual against yellow fever, by means of a vaccine prepared<lb/>
by him, has failed.</p>
<p>The commission therefore recommends that all further exper-<lb/>
iments with the vaccine and the curative serum of Dr. Caldas<lb/>
should be discontinued.</p>
<p>There being no further business before it the commission<lb/>
adjourned sine die.</p>
<p>V. Havard<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Major &amp; Surgeon, U.S. <unclear>Army</unclear><lb/>
Chief Surgeon</hi></p>
<p>Juan Guiteras<lb/>
Carlos Finlay</p>
<p>AD Albertini<lb/>
W. C. Gorgas.<lb/>
Major &amp; Surg. U.S.A.</p>
<p>Four<lb/>
Enclosures.</p>
<p>{<xref id="t02520012">1&deg; - Temperature</xref> and pulse chart</p>
<p>{<xref id="t02518023">A - Reasons</xref> upon which Dr. Caldas bases his diagnosis of septic fever.</p>
<p>{<xref id="t02518026">B - Description</xref> of process to obtain serum and vaccine.</p>
<p>{<xref id="t02518031">C - Copy</xref> of contract made with non-immunes.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f02520011"/>
<p>No.<lb/>
3467</p>
<p>CIVIL DIVISION<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF CUBA<lb/>
Rec'd 9-6 1901.</p>
<p><unclear>Headquarters</unclear> Department of Cuba,<lb/>
<unclear>Received</unclear> SEP 6 1901</p>
<p><hi>T</hi></p>
<p>Havana, Cuba,<lb/>
Undated.</p>
<p>Major V. Havard,<lb/>
Chief Surgeon.</p>
<p>As President of Board called<lb/>
by Circular Letter 59, c. s., these<lb/>
Hdqrs., submits report of the<lb/>
Board on the claims of Doctors<lb/>
Caldas and Bellinzaghi as to their<lb/>
discoveries in connection with<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<p><unclear>OK</unclear><lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>4 encl.</p>
<p>3467</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
