<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02535001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Public Health Papers and Reports, volume XXVII, presented at the Twenty-Ninth Annual Meeting of the American Public Health Association, Buffalo, N.Y., September 16-20, 1901 [selected pages]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02535001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1901-09-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lee, Benjamin</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Doty, Alvah H.</name>
<name type="person">Bell, Agrippa Nelson</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wasdin, Eugene</name>
<name type="person">Formento, Felix</name>
<name type="place">Buffalo (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>51 pp.</extent>
<date value="1901-09-16">September 16-20, 1901</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02535001</idno>
<title>Public Health Papers and Reports, volume XXVII, presented at the Twenty-Ninth Annual Meeting of the American Public Health Association, Buffalo, N.Y., September 16-20, 1901 [selected pages]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Proceedings of the 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> American Health Conference include the &ldquo;President's Address&rdquo; by Benjamin Lee, &ldquo;The Results of Yellow Fever....&rdquo; by William Crawford Gorgas, &ldquo;Practical Discussion of Yellow Fever&rdquo; by Alvah H. Doty, &ldquo;Fomites and Yellow Fever&rdquo; by A. N. Bell, and the &ldquo;Official Report of the Proceedings....&rdquo;. </p>
</div1>
<div1 type="book">
<p></p>
</div1>
<pb n="i" id="f02535001"/>
<titlePage> 
<docTitle> 
<titlePart>PUBLIC HEALTH<lb/>
PAPERS AND REPORTS<lb/>
VOLUME XXVII<lb/>
PRESENTED AT THE TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE<lb/>
American Public Health Association<lb/>
BUFFALO, N. Y.<lb/>
LIBRARY<lb/>
Indexed<lb/>
S. G. O.</titlePart> 
</docTitle>
<docDate>SEPTEMBER 16, 17, 18, 19 AND 20.<lb/>
1901<lb/>
----------<lb/>
LIBRARY<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE<lb/>
FEB. <unclear>21. 1902</unclear><lb/>
181688.</docDate>
<docImprint>COLUMBUS, OHIO:<lb/>
THE BERLIN PRINTING COMPANY.<lb/>
1902.<lb/>
</docImprint>
<pb n="ii" id="f02535002"/>
<byline>Copyright, 1901,<lb/>
BY <docAuthor>DR. CHARLES O. PROBST</docAuthor>, SECRETARY AMERICAN PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION,<lb/>
Columbus, Ohio.<lb/>
All Rights Reserved.</byline>
</titlePage>
<div1 type="contents">
<pb n="iii" id="f02535003"/>
<list>
<head>TABLE OF CONTENTS.<lb/>
----------</head>
<item>PAGE</item>
<item>PRESIDENT'S ADDRESS. By BENJAMIN LEE, M. D........................<ref target="f02535001">1</ref></item>
<item>ADDRESS OF WELCOME. By ANSLEY WILCOX...........................<ref target="f02535139">14</ref></item>
<item>RESPONSE OF THE PRESIDENT TO THE ADDRESS OF WELCOME. By BEN-<lb/>
JAMIN LEE, M. D...................................................<ref target="f02535142">17</ref></item>
<item>ON THE PROGRESS OF PUBLIC HEALTH ORGANIZATIONS IN THE UNITED<lb/>
STATES. By STEPHEN SMITH, M. D.................................<ref target="f02535144">19</ref></item>
<item>REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON TRANSPORTATION OF DISEASED TISSUE BY<lb/>
MAIL. By F. F. WESBROOK, M. D., Chairman......................<ref target="f02535152">27</ref></item>
<item>REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON NATIONAL-LEPER HOMES. By HENRY M.<lb/>
BRACKEN, M. D., Chairman.........................................<ref target="f02535352">34</ref></item>
<item>THE BRITISH CONGRESS ON TUBERCULOSIS, JULY 22-27, 1901. By F.<lb/>
MONTIZAMBERT, M. D..............................................<ref target="f02535353">35</ref></item>
<item>REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON ANIMAL DISEASES AND ANIMAL FOOD. By<lb/>
D. E. SALMON, D. V. M., Chairman.................................<ref target="f02535363">45</ref></item>
<item>SUMMARY OF A PAPER GIVING SOME FACTS WHICH TEND TO SHOW THAT<lb/>
BOVINE TUBERCULOSIS CAN BE THE SOURCE OF THE SAME DISEASE<lb/>
IN MAN. By J&Eacute;SUS CHICO, M. D...................................78</item>
<item>TUBERCULOSIS: HEREDITY. By FELIX FORMENTO, M. D.................81</item>
<item>SUMMARY OF A PAPER ON SANATORIA FOR CONSUMPTIVES. By A. CAR-<lb/>
RIEDO, M. D........................................................85</item>
<item>REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON TEACHING OF HYGIENE AND GRANTING OF<lb/>
DIPLOMA OF DOCTOR OF PUBLIC HEALTH. By W. T. SEDGWICK,<lb/>
Chairman........................................................87</item>
<item>INSTRUCTION IN HYGIENE FOR ARCHITECTS AND ENGINEERS. By W. T.<lb/>
SEDGWICK ........................................................92</item>
<item>UNIVERSITY TEACHING IN HYGIENE. By A. C. ABBOTT, M. D............94</item>
<item>TYPHOID FEVER DEATH RATES IN AMERICAN CITIES. By GEORGE W.<lb/>
FULLER, Chairman................................................100</item>
<item>THE LEGAL ASPECTS OF WATER POLLUTION. By J. L. LEAL, M. D......103</item>
<item>THE PREVENTION OF YELLOW FEVER. By WALTER REED, M. D., AND<lb/>
JAMES CARROLL, M. D..............................................113<lb/>
iii<lb/>
<pb n="iv" id="f02535004"/>
iv<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">TABLE OF CONTENTS</hi>.</item>
<item>PAGE</item>
<item>THE RESULTS OF YELLOW FEVER SANITATION IN HAVANA, CUBA, FOR THE<lb/>
YEAR 1901 UP TO SEPTEMBER 1ST, CARRIED ON UPON THE BASIS THAT<lb/>
THE STEGOMYIA MOSQUITO IS THE SOLE MEANS OF ITS TRANSMIS-<lb/>
SION. By W. C. GORGAS, M. D....................................130</item>
<item>PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER. By ALVAH. H. DOTY, M. D..134</item>
<item>FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER. By A. N. BELL, M. D...................144</item>
<item>TENTH REPORT ON YELLOW FEVER IN MEXICO. By EDUARDO LIC&Eacute;AGA,<lb/>
M. D.............................................................152</item>
<item>A BRIEF STATEMENT OF THE SANITARY WORK SO FAR ACCOMPLISHED IN<lb/>
THE PHILIPPINE ISLANDS, AND OF THE PRESENT SHAPE OF THEIR SANI-<lb/>
TARY ADMINISTRATION. By CHARLES R. GREENLEAF, M. D.........157</item>
<item>SANITATION IN PORTO RICO. By WILLIAM F. SMITH, M. D..............166</item>
<item>VACCINAL IMMUNIZATION FROM THE HEALTH OFFICER'S STANDPOINT.<lb/>
By PETER H. BRYCE, M. D.........................................175</item>
<item>REMARKS INTENDED TO SHOW THE INNOCUOUS CHARACTER OF HUMANIZED<lb/>
VACCINE AS A PREVENTATIVE OF SMALLPOX. By FRANCISCO DE<lb/>
BERNALDEZ, M. D..................................................182</item>
<item>REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON DISPOSAL OF REFUSE MATERIALS. By<lb/>
RUDOLPH HERING, Chairman.......................................184</item>
<item>REFUSE DISPOSAL IN BOSTON. By HIBBERT WINSLOW HILL, M. D......186</item>
<item>REFUSE DISPOSAL IN THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA. By WILLIAM C.<lb/>
WOODWARD, M. D..................................................194</item>
<item>THE BACTERIAL PURIFICATION OF WATER BY FREEZING. By H. W.<lb/>
CLARK...........................................................204</item>
<item>REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON THE RELATION OF FORESTRY TO THE<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH. By PROF. WILLIAM H. BREWER, Chairman........209</item>
<item>CIRCULAR OF THE AMERICAN PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION ISSUED BY THE<lb/>
COMMITTEE ON CAR SANITATION. By PROF. S. H. WOODBRIDGE,<lb/>
Chairman.........................................................224</item>
<item>REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON CAUSE, PREVENTION AND DURATION OF<lb/>
INFECTIOUS DISEASES. By A. WALTER SUITER, M. D., Chairman....227</item>
<item>PRESENT STATUS OF DIPHTHERIA. By WILLIAM C. WOODWARD, M. D....238</item>
<item>TYPHOID FEVER. By FRANK W. WRIGHT, M. D.........................241</item>
<item>REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON DISINFECTANTS AND DISINFECTION. By<lb/>
HIBBERT WINSLOW HILL, M. D., Acting Chairman..................244</item>
<item>REPORT OF SUB-COMMITTEE ON STANDARD CULTURES AND THE METHOD<lb/>
OF USING THEM. By E. H. WILSON, M. D., Chairman...............247</item>
<item>OBSERVATIONS ON THE PRACTICE OF DISINFECTION IN THE FEDERAL DIS-<lb/>
TRICT OF MEXICO. By FERNANDO LOPEZ, M. D.....................253<lb/>
<pb n="v" id="f02535005"/>
<hi rend="italic">TABLE OF CONTENTS</hi>.<lb/>
v</item>
<item>PAGE</item>
<item>REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON PUBLIC HEALTH LEGISLATION. By U. O.<lb/>
B. WINGATE, M. D., Chairman......................................256</item>
<item>REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON SCHOOL HYGIENE. By HENRY MITCHELL,<lb/>
M. D., Chairman....................................................260</item>
<item>NOTES ON THE NECESSITY OF ATTENDING TO THE HYGIENE OF THE MOUTH<lb/>
AMONGST THE PUPILS OF SCHOOLS. By JUAN BRE&Ntilde;A, M. D..........286</item>
<item>THE INFLUENCE OF SCHOOL LIFE OVER HEALTH. By FRANK W. WRIGHT,<lb/>
M. D.............................................................297</item>
<item>A SUMM&Aacute;RY OF A PAPER ON THE ADVISABILITY OF ENTRUSTING TO PHY-<lb/>
SICIANS AND NOT TO TEACHERS, THE MEDICAL SUPERVISION OF PUPILS.<lb/>
By IGNACIO GUZMAN, M. D..........................................304</item>
<item>REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON DEMOGRAPHY AND STATISTICS IN THEIR<lb/>
SANITARY RELATION. By JOHN S. FULTON, M. D., Chairman........305</item>
<item>SOME OF THE CAUSES OF INFANT MORTALITY IN NURSERIES AND ASYLUMS,<lb/>
AND THEIR PREVENTION. By ELIAS H. BARTLEY, M. D..............306</item>
<item>SUMMARY OF A PAPER ON CREMATION IN RELATION TO SANITARY LEGIS-<lb/>
LATION. By LUIS G. ESPINOZA, M. D...............................314</item>
<item>SOME RESULTS OF THE ARMY CANTEEN OR POST EXCHANGE FROM THE<lb/>
STANDPOINT OF DISCIPLINE AND HYGIENE. By EDWARD L. MUNSON,<lb/>
M. D.............................................................315</item>
<item>ANTI-RABIC DEPARTMENT OF THE SUPREME BOARD OF HEALTH OF MEXICO.<lb/>
By EDUARDO LIC&Eacute;AGA, M. D........................................318</item>
<item>OFFICIAL REPORT OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL<lb/>
MEETING.........................................................319</item>
<item>PROCEEDINGS OF THE SECTION OF BACTERIOLOGY AND CHEMISTRY.........377</item>
<item>REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON STANDARD METHODS OF WATER ANALYSIS.<lb/>
By GEORGE W. FULLER, Chairman..................................377</item>
<item>STUDIES OF MEDIA FOR THE QUANTITATIVE ESTIMATION OF BACTERIA<lb/>
IN WATER AND SEWAGE. By STEPHEN DEM. GAGE AND EARLE B.<lb/>
PHELPS...........................................................392</item>
<item>IS THE COLON BACILLUS A NORMAL INHABITANT OF THE INTESTINES OF<lb/>
FISHES? By JOHN A. AMYOT, M. B.................................400</item>
<item>SOME COMMON BACTERIA IN AMERICAN STREAMS, INCLUDING SOME NEW<lb/>
SPECIES ISOLATED AT NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA. By ROBERT SPURR<lb/>
WESTON AND ARTHUR I. KENDALL...................................402</item>
<item>ABSTRACT OF &ldquo;REMARKS REGARDING THE INVESTIGATION OF BACILLUS<lb/>
COLI IN WATER.&rdquo; By GONZALES FABELA............................408</item>
<item>THE SIGNIFICANCE OF THE PRESENCE AND AMOUNT OF CARBON DI-OXIDE<lb/>
IN POTABLE WATERS. By ELLEN H. RICHARDS......................411<lb/>
<pb n="vi" id="f02535006"/>
vi<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">TABLE OF CONTENTS</hi>.</item>
<item>PAGE</item>
<item>REFINED AND IMPROVED ANTITOXIN PREPARATIONS. By JOSEPH McFAR-<lb/>
LAND, M. D........................................................414</item>
<item>ANTITOXINS AND AGGLUTININS. By THORVALD MADSEN.................417</item>
<item>SOME WORK ON A CURATIVE SERUM FOR TYPHOID FEVER. By WILLIAM<lb/>
ROYAL STOKES, M. D., AND JOHN S. FULTON, M. D..................423</item>
<item>ABSTRACT OF A PAPER ENTITLED &ldquo;DEMONSTRATION OF THE EXISTENCE OF<lb/>
TYPHOID FEVER IN THE CITY OF MEXICO BY THE WIDAL METHOD.&rdquo;<lb/>
By ANGEL GAVI&Ntilde;O, M. D...........................................437</item>
<item>METHODS OF DIAGNOSIS IN GLANDERS. By HIBBERT WINSLOW HILL,<lb/>
M. D., AND ALEXANDER BURR, D. V. M.............................439</item>
<item>THE VIABILITY OF THE PLAGUE BACILLUS IN ITS RELATIONS TO THE<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH. By M. J. ROSENAU, M. D.........................448</item>
<item>CULTIVATION OF THE BACILLUS INFLUENZA. By ADOLPH GEHRMANN.<lb/>
M. D................................................................458</item>
<item>THE BACTERIAL CONTAMINATION OF CITY MILK--IS IT HARMFUL?<lb/>
SHOULD IT BE CONTROLLED BY HEALTH AUTHORITIES? By WILLIAM<lb/>
HALLOCK PARK, M. D..............................................461</item>
<item>THE NON-NITRIFICATION OF SEPTIC SEWAGE IN CONTACT FILTERS. By<lb/>
H. W. CLARK.......................................................464</item>
<item>SOME POINTS IN THE LIFE HISTORY AND IN THE DECOMPOSITION OF BLUE-<lb/>
GREEN ALGAE AS ILLUSTRATED BY OSCILLARIA PROLIFICA (WITH<lb/>
SAMPLES). By ELLEN H. RICHARDS................................467</item>
<item>HYDROCYANIC-ACID GAS IN PUBLIC HEALTH WORK. By JOHN S. FULTON,<lb/>
M. D., AND WILLIAM R. STOKES, M. D.............................469</item>
<item>AIR TESTING FOR ENGINEERS. By ELLEN H. RICHARDS.................477</item>
<item>AN ENGINEER'S KIT FOR WATER INSPECTION. By ELLEN H. RICHARDS..478</item>
<item>CONSTITUTION........................................................i</item>
<item>BY-LAWS OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE................................v</item>
<item>OFFICERS AND COMMITTEES.............................................viii</item>
<item>REVISED LIST OF MEMBERS.............................................xvi</item>
<item>MEMBERS ELECTED AT BUFFALO MEETING...............................xxv</item>
<item>LIST OF MEMBERS BY GEOGRAPHICAL DISTRIBUTION....................."xxvii</item>
<item>SANITARY AUTHORITIES AND ASSOCIATIONS.............................."xxxv</item>
<item>INDEX..............................................................."xliii</item>
</list>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="chapter" n="1">
<head>PRESIDENT'S ADDRESS.</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02535007"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>BENJAMIN LEE, M. D.,</docAuthor>
SECRETARY STATE BOARD OF HEALTH, PHILADELPHIA, PENNSYLVANIA.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub H. A<lb/>
29th meeting Sept 1901</p>
<p>MR. CHAIRMAN AND MEMBERS OF THE AMERICAN PUBLIC HEALTH<lb/>
ASSOCIATION, LADIES AND GENTLEMEN--Bear with me a moment, I<lb/>
pray you, if I supplement the few hurried words in which at the close of<lb/>
our last session I tried to thank you for the distinguished honor con-<lb/>
ferred both upon my State and myself in my election to the responsible<lb/>
position of president of this eminent and learned body, by a farther ex-<lb/>
pression of my appreciation of the distinction of the compliment thus<lb/>
implied, and of the high value which I place upon the office.</p>
<p>One who has devoted the best years of his life to the study and prac-<lb/>
tice of Preventive Medicine, and who thoroughly believes that next to<lb/>
the ministry of religion the ministry of health constitutes the noblest<lb/>
calling in which man can engage, may be pardoned if he expresses the<lb/>
sentiment that, having thus received the verdict of approval from his<lb/>
long valued friends and deeply respected peers, the summit of his ambi-<lb/>
tion has been attained, and earth has no richer prize to offer him. It<lb/>
has been claimed by others, that this Association constitutes the most<lb/>
important permanently organized body of sanitarians in the world.<lb/>
And when we remember that both the practical and the scientific sides<lb/>
of sanitary work have here their due representation, and that here, year<lb/>
after year, the devoted subjects of his gracious majesty, King Edward<lb/>
VII, rub shoulders with the patriotic representatives of his Excellency,<lb/>
President Diaz, while both give the glad hand to the citizens of the Re-<lb/>
public which is ever eager to welcome them on their noble mission of<lb/>
good will to men; when it is considered that we have assurances that it<lb/>
may be our privilege to greet on this occasion, delegates from the far-<lb/>
distant Philippines, from storied Honolulu, from the Isles of the Antilles<lb/>
and from the immense domains of Central and South America, this cer-<lb/>
tainly will not be the time nor shall I be the individual to dispute the<lb/>
claim. What this Association has accomplished for the United States,<lb/>
and in this connection, I beg leave on behalf of the members from this<lb/>
country to acknowledge in the fullest and heartiest manner, the assist-<lb/>
ance which we have derived from the sagacious and fraternal counsels<lb/>
of our good neighbors, to the north and south of us,--what this Asso-<lb/>
ciation, I say, and the faithful workers both in the field of science and of<lb/>
administration who compose it, have accomplished for the United States,<lb/>
let the astounding results of the last census as recently furnished by the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02535008"/>
2<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PRESIDENT'S ADDRESS</hi>.<lb/>
Chief of the Vital Statistics Division, bear witness. Four years added<lb/>
to the average duration of human life in the brief period of ten years.<lb/>
In the aggregate, more than two hundred million years of life. The<lb/>
mind staggers under such figures. Well may we thank God and take<lb/>
courage.</p>
<p>Before proceeding to the discussion of the topic to which I shall<lb/>
briefly call your attention, this evening, it is fitting that reference<lb/>
should be made to those of our members who have passed from the<lb/>
sphere of their earthly labors since we last met together. Con-<lb/>
spicuous among them rises before your mind's eye, as I speak, the alert<lb/>
form and genial countenance of Henry B. Horlbeck, late Health Offi-<lb/>
cer of the city of Charleston, and one of your former presidents.<lb/>
This is not the place for his biography, nor am I competent to write<lb/>
his eulogy. It were well that one of his familiar friends should place<lb/>
the Association under obligation by preparing a sketch of his active<lb/>
life and his striking characteristics, for permanent record in our<lb/>
Transactions. But you all knew him, for he never failed to meet us<lb/>
year after year, and to bring to our discussions material of fresh and<lb/>
lively interest. His devotion to the study of the etiology of yellow<lb/>
fever, which he made the subject of his able presidential address at<lb/>
the meeting at Philadelphia, was unceasing and profound, and it must<lb/>
have been a matter of congratulation to him that it was permitted be-<lb/>
fore his end to see a ray of light thrown upon a subject which he had<lb/>
so long striven in vain to illuminate. His successful career as a<lb/>
health officer, is sufficiently attested by the long period during which<lb/>
he administered that office. &ldquo;<hi rend="italic">Justum ac tenacem propositi virum</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
&ldquo;An honest man and one tenacious of his opinions,&rdquo; may fairly be<lb/>
predicated of him. To say that we shall sadly miss him both in the<lb/>
arena of debate of which he was a master, and in the social gathering<lb/>
of which he was an ornament, is but coldly to express the esteem in<lb/>
which he was held.</p>
<p>It is not inappropriate, I trust, to mention in this connection the<lb/>
passing of one, who though not a fellow member, was devoted to the<lb/>
study of the same pursuits as ourselves, and who laid down his life a<lb/>
willing victim on the altar of sanitary science, in the effort, perhaps<lb/>
successful, to solve the very problem to which our friend Horlbeck<lb/>
had so long sought a solution. I refer to Acting Assistant Surgeon,<lb/>
Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, of the United States Army, whose death oc-<lb/>
curred in the city of Havana, just previous to our last meeting, as the<lb/>
result of the bite of a mosquito, infected by the blood of yellow fever<lb/>
patients in the Las Animas Hospital, while engaged in collecting<lb/>
blood from such patients for purposes of investigation and study. If<lb/>
Cuba does not belong to the list of those republics which are pro-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02535009"/>
<hi rend="italic">PRESIDENT'S ADDRESS</hi>.<lb/>
3<lb/>
verbially ungrateful, she should show her appreciation of three of<lb/>
those concerned in her sanitary regeneration by erecting a monument<lb/>
to the joint memory of Colonel George A. Waring, Surgeon Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear, and Brigadier-General William Ludlow. This last-named<lb/>
hero fully earned the honors that were showered upon him both in<lb/>
peace and war. He it was who initiated the sanitary work in the city<lb/>
of Havana, so successfully carried on later by General Wood. As<lb/>
Chief of the Water Department of the city of Philadelphia, he labored<lb/>
zealously, and with much success, to improve the water supply and<lb/>
restore the dilapidated works of that city. He was unable, however,<lb/>
to endure the interference of political leaders, who sought to control<lb/>
him for their own selfish ends, and this rendered his permanent<lb/>
occupancy of the position impossible. His whole career was one of<lb/>
honest and intelligent performance of duty.</p>
<p>Another whom we shall not again greet is Dr. J. H. Linsley, of<lb/>
Vermont, well known for his work in bacteriology.</p>
<p>The names also of Frank Paddock, Pittsfield, Mass.; Erastus J.<lb/>
Buck, Plattville, Wis.; Edward A. Guilbert, Dubuque, Io.; Allen A.<lb/>
Rawson, Coring, Io.; Katherine Miller, Lincoln, Ill.; must be men-<lb/>
tioned with respectful regret.</p>
<p>An appropriate theme for the presidential address of the first year<lb/>
of the New Century, before this august body would naturally be a<lb/>
retrospect of the advances made in the science and art of public<lb/>
hygiene or, to speak more correctly, in those arts and sciences which<lb/>
public hygiene is builded on, during the century just closed. Un-<lb/>
fortunately for me, however, but fortunately for the Association, my<lb/>
predecessor in office made so careful a study of this subject and pre-<lb/>
sented the results of his labors in so forceful, scholarly and exhaustive<lb/>
a shape in his own address a year ago, as to make it most unwise for<lb/>
me to follow him upon the same lines. The situation is a little like<lb/>
that described by the sailing-master of the late lamented Queen Vic-<lb/>
toria, of blessed and revered memory, who, when inquired of by Her<lb/>
Majesty, to whom he had announced that the yacht America had won<lb/>
the international race: &ldquo;Which yacht is second?&rdquo; sententiously re-<lb/>
plied &ldquo;Your Majesty, there is no second.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This particular point of time cannot be allowed to pass, however,<lb/>
without recognition. I hazard nothing in claiming that we stand not<lb/>
only on the threshold of a new century, but at the beginning of a new<lb/>
epoch in the history of sanitation. The past century has been one of<lb/>
preparation. We who have been permitted to live through many of<lb/>
its years have &ldquo;seen wondrous things whereof we are glad,&rdquo; advances<lb/>
in chemistry, physiology, pathology and biology, the discovery of new<lb/>
laws of nature and the development of new sciences such as sociology,<lb/>
<pb n="112" id="f02535118"/>
112<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">THE LEGAL ASPECTS OF WATER POLLUTION</hi>.<lb/>
gable. It does not naturally flow to the stream. It is gathered by<lb/>
the city in sewers from numerous buildings, cesspools, culverts and<lb/>
drains, over a large area of land, and by uniform artifically constructed<lb/>
grades is gravitated to and discharged into river. It is vastly more<lb/>
than the mere natural drainage of riparian owners. I cannot con-<lb/>
ceive of any tenable ground upon which such drainage can be classed<lb/>
as either a natural or a reasonable use of the river. It is not to be as-<lb/>
sumed that the statutes authorizing city to construct sewers mean to<lb/>
authorize a nuisance. The authority conferred is limited to mere con-<lb/>
struction of the sewers in accordance with the maps. It does not<lb/>
license either public or private nuisances through pollution of the<lb/>
waters of the river. As to private rights, I need only say that they<lb/>
have constitutional protection against any such legislative enactment.<lb/>
In England where the power of Parliament is omnipotent in matters of<lb/>
this kind, both as to public and private rights, it is well settled that<lb/>
legislative authority to merely drain into a stream does not authorize<lb/>
the contamination of the water. Legislative license to create a public<lb/>
nuisance of the kind considered must be given in express terms or by<lb/>
absolutely necessary implication. That the city has any right to pol-<lb/>
lute the waters of the river by the discharge of its sewage into them, is<lb/>
clearly an untenable proposition. Chancellor's opinion, Simmons et<lb/>
al. v. City of Paterson, N. J.</p>
<p>From the above the attitude of the courts at the present toward the<lb/>
pollution of water clearly appears. This attitude, which is of com-<lb/>
paratively recent origin, seems not so much a stricter enforcement of<lb/>
the principles of common law, as a better understanding on the part<lb/>
of the courts of the principles of sanitary science. The common law<lb/>
always existed and was always enforced according to the lights of the<lb/>
courts, but the trouble was that those lights were not bright enough to<lb/>
illumine the subject. The brighter rays of modern scientific sanita-<lb/>
tion, however, have dispelled the gloom of ignorance and have pictured<lb/>
the subject in its true aspect, its importance and its necessities to the<lb/>
minds of those whose province it is to place it upon its proper legal<lb/>
footing. That this is one of the most important results obtained by<lb/>
sanitary science cannot be disputed.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="2">
<head>THE RESULTS OF YELLOW FEVER SANITATION IN<lb/>
HAVANA, CUBA, FOR THE YEAR 1901 UP TO SEPTEM-<lb/>
BER 1ST, CARRIED ON UPON THE BASIS THAT THE<lb/>
STEGOMYIA MOSQUITO IS THE SOLE MEANS OF ITS<lb/>
TRANSMISSION.</head>
<pb n="130" id="f02535136"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>W. C. GORGAS</docAuthor>, M. D.,<lb/>
MAJOR AND SURGEON U. S. ARMY, CHIEF SANITARY OFFICER, HAVANA, CUBA.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub Health Assoc - 29 meet<lb/>
Buffalo Sept 1901</p>
<p>&check;</p>
<p>The results announced by the Yellow Fever Commission, of which<lb/>
Major Walter Reed was President, and which met in Havana in the<lb/>
fall of 1900, were accepted as conclusive by the Sanitary Department<lb/>
of that city. After a series of experiments, the Board succeeded in<lb/>
demonstrating that the mosquito is the medium for the transmission of<lb/>
yellow fever, and upon this fact has been based all our methods of sani-<lb/>
tation, since February of this year, when the conclusions of the Board<lb/>
were made known.</p>
<p>Accepting these as facts, it is evident that two elements are necessary<lb/>
for the transmission of yellow fever, viz.: First, a non-immune per-<lb/>
son who is capable of having the disease; second, infected mosquitoes,<lb/>
by which the disease may be transmitted to the non-immune.</p>
<p>In Havana, the problem of the person capable of having the disease<lb/>
is quite different from the problem which presents itself in the United<lb/>
States. In the United States practically the entire population is sus-<lb/>
ceptible to yellow fever, while in Havana we have about 230,000 per-<lb/>
sons who are not subject to the disease, and only about 30,000 who are.<lb/>
If we could take these 30,000 away from Havana, and prevent non-<lb/>
immunes going in, the problem would at once be solved and yellow<lb/>
fever be eradicated from the city. But it is, of course, impracticable to<lb/>
move out and care for so large a number of people; and to prevent the<lb/>
coming into the city of non-immunes would too seriously interefere<lb/>
with the commerce of the city.</p>
<p>A close supervision is, however, exercised over the large number of<lb/>
immigrants who arrive at this port. They are all taken to the immi-<lb/>
gration station and those intending to settle in the country are sent<lb/>
directly to their destinations without coming into Havana. Those<lb/>
coming into the city have to be vouched for by some reliable person,<lb/>
known to the immigration authorities, so that they can be followed up<lb/>
in case of need. They are required to matriculate at one of the hospi-<lb/>
tals for two months, with the expectation that, as their fees at these<lb/>
hospitals are paid, they will go there at once in case of sickness.</p>
<p>130</p>
<pb n="131" id="f02535137"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">RESULTS OF YELLOW FEVER SANITATION</hi>.<lb/>
131</p>
<p>In the smaller towns, the deportation of the non-immunes is the<lb/>
method principally relied upon for the stamping out of yellow fever.<lb/>
It has been entirely successful and satisfactory in the past.</p>
<p>Where the non-immunes amount to only a few hundred, as at San-<lb/>
tiago in 1899, and at Quemados in 1900, a camp is established at some<lb/>
convenient and healthy point, and all the non-immune population<lb/>
moved to this camp. In the two instances cited, the epidemic was at<lb/>
once cut short in midsummer by this measure.</p>
<p>Instances of epidemics in military garrisons being stopped in this<lb/>
way are very numerous. It has been resorted to many times in the<lb/>
army during the past twenty years, and in Cuba wherever it was evi-<lb/>
dent that a garrison had become infected.</p>
<p>But even with non-immunes in a community, to have yellow fever<lb/>
there must be present infected mosquitoes, and infected mosquitoes<lb/>
presuppose the previous existence of mosquitoes in the locality. It is<lb/>
obvious that if we can exterminate all mosquitoes we will be as free<lb/>
from yellow fever as if we had no non-immunes present. So, early in<lb/>
the season, we directed our energies towards the destruction of the<lb/>
mosquito.</p>
<p>For this purpose, a division of forty men has been organized; the<lb/>
city divided up into districts, and a foreman and two laborers desig-<lb/>
nated for work in each district. They make daily house-to-house in-<lb/>
spections, visiting each house in the district once in three weeks. Each<lb/>
laborer is supplied with oil, and a half pint is poured into each &ldquo;pozo<lb/>
negro&rdquo;; these connect with the cesspools with which all houses in<lb/>
Havana are provided, in the absence of any general sewer system; and<lb/>
this oil spreads over the surface of the cesspool and kills the larv&aelig;,<lb/>
which breed there in large numbers. Oil is also poured onto the sur-<lb/>
face of any water to which mosquitoes have access. About 2,000<lb/>
gallons of oil a month are used in this part of the work.</p>
<p>It was found that nearly every house was provided with some recep-<lb/>
tacle for rain water for washing purposes,--chiefly water-barrels,--<lb/>
and the fresh standing water was the best possible breeding place for<lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>--the yellow fever mosquito.</p>
<p>The mayor then issued an order that all barrels containing standing<lb/>
water should be made mosquito-proof; where this order is not com-<lb/>
plied with, the inspectors are instructed to break the barrel. This has<lb/>
had an excellent effect, and the order is now complied with in nearly<lb/>
all cases.</p>
<p>A second division, composed of fifty men, was organized, who are at<lb/>
work cleaning out the ditches, drains and streams around the city,<lb/>
draining low places wherever stagnant water is breeding mosquitoes;<lb/>
<pb n="132" id="f02535138"/>
132<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">RESULTS OF YELLOW FEVER SANITATION</hi>.<lb/>
and if drainage is impracticable, keeping the surface of the water well<lb/>
oiled.</p>
<p>The results have been very satisfactory, considering the short time<lb/>
during which this work has been in progress. But it is quite certain<lb/>
that our efforts could not entirely destroy mosquitoes in Havana; the<lb/>
best that can be done is to reduce the number.</p>
<p>The next logical step was to prevent the mosquito from becoming<lb/>
infected; and the first move in this direction was to make it impossible<lb/>
for the mosquito to bite any one suffering from yellow fever in Havana.<lb/>
With this object in view, as soon as a suspicious case of fever is re-<lb/>
ported to this office, the apartments of the patient are at once screened<lb/>
with wire screen doors and windows, which this department keeps on<lb/>
hand for the purpose, and which render the patient absolutely mosquito-<lb/>
proof. A guard is placed to see that the wire doors are kept closed<lb/>
and that no one goes in except certain immunes designated. The hos-<lb/>
pitals, also, are required to have their yellow fever wards made mos-<lb/>
quito-proof, and the patient kept under mosquito bars. Circulars<lb/>
recommending the use of mosquito bars have been very generally dis-<lb/>
tributed in the city, and the object explained.</p>
<p>Since, in these suspected cases, it is possible that mosquitoes may<lb/>
have become infected before the patient is screened, the disinfecting<lb/>
squad carefully goes over every room in the house; they are sealed, the<lb/>
cracks pasted and pyrethrum powder burned at the rate of a pound to<lb/>
1,000 cubic feet of air space. As pyrethrum powder, even in this<lb/>
quantity, frequently fails to kill all the mosquitoes, many being found<lb/>
on the floor stupefied, when the rooms are opened, at the end of three<lb/>
hours, those on the floor are killed, swept up and destroyed. The two<lb/>
or three adjoining houses are gone over in the same way,--to be certain<lb/>
that all infected mosquitoes in the neighborhood are killed.</p>
<p>Pyrethrum powder is used because it is not disagreeable and does<lb/>
not injure any fabric. Where nothing could be injured, sulphur is<lb/>
used, as it is more certain in its effects.</p>
<p>To prevent yellow fever from being introduced from outside the<lb/>
island, the Marine Hospital Service carefully supervises all arrivals<lb/>
from points from which infection might come.</p>
<p>To protect the city from interior towns, inspectors are placed on all<lb/>
roads entering the city, who take the names of non-immunes coming<lb/>
in, and the address of the house at which they will stop. These are<lb/>
reported to the Sanitary Department and an inspector is sent on the<lb/>
third and sixth days to see if they continue in good health. At the<lb/>
same time, blanks are left with them, and they are requested to send a<lb/>
report on these blanks to the Sanitary Department, in case they become<lb/>
sick. At the end of six days this supervision ends.</p>
<pb n="133" id="f02535139"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">RESULTS OF YELLOW FEVER SANITATION</hi>.<lb/>
133</p>
<p>We began the year with the usual amount of yellow fever in the<lb/>
city; in January there were twenty-five cases and seven deaths, and for<lb/>
February up to the 16th, four cases and three deaths. On February<lb/>
16th, the present method of disinfection was adopted; after that time,<lb/>
we had cases on the 22d, 23d and 27th of February, and on the 2d and<lb/>
8th of March. In all these cases the above described method of screen-<lb/>
ing and disinfection was strictly carried out, and no more cases occurred<lb/>
until April 21st and 22d, when two developed. Again we were free<lb/>
from fever until May 6th and 7th, when four cases occurred.</p>
<p>From that time until July 1st, the city was entirely free of fever.<lb/>
During July, we had four cases, occurring on the 1st, 20th, 21st and<lb/>
24th, with one death, and in August eight cases; one case taken sick<lb/>
July 27th and died August 5th, the others taken sick August 10th, 16th,<lb/>
20th, 21st, 24th (two), and the 25th; with two deaths.</p>
<p>Taking the yellow fever year as beginning April 1st and comparing<lb/>
the record of this year with that of preceding years since 1889, we find:</p>
<p>DEATHS OF YELLOW FEVER IN THE MONTHS OF APRIL, MAY,<lb/>
JUNE, JULY AND AUGUST.</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="13">
<row><cell>Months.</cell><cell>1890</cell><cell>1891</cell><cell>1892</cell><cell>1893</cell><cell>1894</cell><cell>1895</cell><cell>1896</cell><cell>1897</cell><cell>1898</cell><cell>1899</cell><cell>1900</cell><cell>1901</cell></row>
<row><cell>April ..............</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>71</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell>May ..............</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>88</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell>June ..............</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>41</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>46</cell><cell>174</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell>July ..............</cell><cell>67</cell><cell>66</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>118</cell><cell>77</cell><cell>88</cell><cell>116</cell><cell>168</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row><cell>August ...........</cell><cell>60</cell><cell>66</cell><cell>67</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>73</cell><cell>120</cell><cell>262</cell><cell>102</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>49</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell></row>
<row><cell>Total ...........</cell><cell>201</cell><cell>185</cell><cell>122</cell><cell>318</cell><cell>201</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>465</cell><cell>603</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>89</cell><cell>3</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The conditions in Havana this year as regards non-immunes were<lb/>
more unfavorable than at any previous time,--there being probably<lb/>
more present than in any of the years with which comparison is made.<lb/>
Infection was also present, as evidenced by the continued appearance<lb/>
of new cases of fever.</p>
<p>As I have stated above, these are the two requisites for the trans-<lb/>
mission of yellow fever, and yet the records show a condition as regards<lb/>
yellow fever never before seen in Havana.</p>
<p>As killing off infected mosquitoes is the only thing done now which<lb/>
was not done during previous years, and the other conditions being<lb/>
practically similar, I think we may fairly infer that we owe our present<lb/>
immunity to the destruction of the mosquito, both before and after<lb/>
infection.</p>
<p>We have a well-equipped hospital, to which all yellow fever patients<lb/>
may go, if they desire it. Dr. John W. Ross, of the U. S. Navy, is in<lb/>
immediate charge, with a corps of American trained nurses under him,<lb/>
and the patient receives the same care that any New York hospital<lb/>
would afford.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="3">
<head>PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER.</head>
<pb n="134" id="f02535140"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>DR. ALVAH H. DOTY</docAuthor>,<lb/>
HEALTH OFFICER PORT OF NEW YORK.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub H Assoc - 29th meet<lb/>
Buffalo Sept 1901</p>
<p>&check;</p>
<p>The stimulus which has been given to the study of infectious diseases<lb/>
from a scientific and practical standpoint, and which during the past<lb/>
fifteen or twenty years has furnished us with much definite and reliable<lb/>
information on this subject, has now, through the experiments of Dr.<lb/>
Walter Reed and his colleagues, presented indisputable evidence as to<lb/>
at least one of the means by which yellow fever is transmitted. It is in<lb/>
connection with this that I desire to present the practical side of the<lb/>
subject in order that it may be viewed from all points and that it may<lb/>
aid us in arriving at some definite conclusion regarding the treatment<lb/>
of yellow fever and of vessels and persons arriving from ports infected<lb/>
with this disease.</p>
<p>The history of yellow fever in the United States and elsewhere has<lb/>
shown that it is usually confined to geographical limits, and that sec-<lb/>
tions beyond these are as a rule free from the disease, although it has<lb/>
occasionally appeared outside of the yellow fever zone. For instance,<lb/>
between the years 1798 and 1805, many cases of yellow fever occurred<lb/>
in New York, first appearing at the lower end of the city in the vicinity<lb/>
<unclear>of</unclear> Peck Slip. Medical history indicates that the disease had shown<lb/>
itself here before that time, but it was not until the period I refer to<lb/>
that it was fully recognized and studied. I have been fortunate<lb/>
enough to secure a copy of the official medical statements relative to<lb/>
these outbreaks, and the opinions which are expressed are in such<lb/>
harmony with the conclusion of modern sanitarians that I submit the<lb/>
following extracts:</p>
<p>Dr. James Hardie, who in 1822 published an official account of<lb/>
these outbreaks, says in reference to cases of yellow fever at Bellevue<lb/>
Hospital in 1798:</p>
<p>&ldquo;There is one thing very remarkable, with respect to the attendants<lb/>
of this hospital, which ought not to be omitted. Their situation, to<lb/>
most people, must have, no doubt, appeared peculiarly dangerous, as<lb/>
they were literally surrounded by pestilence. It so happened, how-<lb/>
ever, that neither physicians, nurses, nor washerwomen caught the<lb/>
infection. The boatmen, too, belonging to the Health Office, who<lb/>
enter the hospital at all times, and were not only engaged in bringing<lb/>
the sick from the city and shipping, but, likewise, in removing them<lb/>
134<lb/>
<pb n="135" id="f02535141"/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
135<lb/>
from place to place, enjoyed a uniform state of good health; and of<lb/>
those persons who accompanied their friends and relations, stayed<lb/>
with them, and nursed them, there is not a single instance of an indi-<lb/>
vidual being infected. In short, Dr. Douglas, one of the assistant<lb/>
physicians, was the only person, residing there, who was seized with<lb/>
fever; but he had been in the habit of occasionally visiting his friends<lb/>
in the city and three days previous to his being taken ill had slept in a<lb/>
house the vicinity of which was highly infected, and it is more than<lb/>
probable that his sickness was occasioned by that cause.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The following extract is taken from the official report of the resi-<lb/>
dent physician at the Marine Hospital on Staten Island regarding the<lb/>
outbreak of yellow fever in 1799:</p>
<p>&ldquo;During the months of July, August, and October (1799), there<lb/>
were in all about two hundred and fifty (250) persons sick of yellow<lb/>
fever in the Marine Hospital, a great part of whom were from the<lb/>
shipping; the rest from the city. At that time, there were of physi-<lb/>
cians, nurses, washerwomen, boatmen, and my family, composed of<lb/>
myself, my wife, and three children, thirty-seven (37) persons, not one<lb/>
of whom, although daily and hourly amongst the sick, experienced<lb/>
the least indisposition.&rdquo;</p>
<p>From the official communication addressed to Governor Lewis,<lb/>
January 12, 1806, by Dr. Edward Miller, resident physician of Bellevue<lb/>
Hospital, I quote the following:</p>
<p>&ldquo;No communication of the disease was ever observed in yellow-<lb/>
fever hospitals, situated at a distance from the cities to which they<lb/>
belong. No exception to this has ever occurred in any of the numer-<lb/>
ous seasons of this pestilence, at our hospital, at Bellevue, the Marine<lb/>
Hospital on Staten Island, that of Philadelphia, or any other in the<lb/>
United States, provided the malignant air of the city had been avoided.<lb/>
The force of this fact seems never to have been duly considered or<lb/>
appreciated. The numerous retinue of medical attendants, nurses,<lb/>
washerwomen, servants, etc., which belong to our hospitals, must be<lb/>
known to everybody. How greatly they are exposed to contagion,<lb/>
if it could be supposed to exist in this case, is equally known. The<lb/>
most malignant cases of the disease are constantly found in these<lb/>
institutions. The exposure of physicians and their assistants is well<lb/>
understood. The duty of the nurses leads to an incessant and unre-<lb/>
served intercourse with the sick; they sleep and pass the greater part<lb/>
of their time in the apartments of the sick, the dying, and the dead.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The nurses at Bellevue Hospital became so entirely free from all<lb/>
apprehensions of the contagiousness of this disease that they often<lb/>
slept on the same bed with the sick, and it happened more than once,<lb/>
in the course of the season, that a nurse, overcome with fatigue and<lb/>
want of sleep, threw<unclear>.</unclear> herself in the night, for a little repose, on the<lb/>
<pb n="136" id="f02535142"/>
136<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
bed of a dying patient and continued there asleep until the patient was<lb/>
dead, and it became necessary to remove the corpse.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The official reports from which I have just quoted contain many<lb/>
statements similar to the above.</p>
<p>Fifty years after these statements were made, a most notable con-<lb/>
gregation of sanitarians took place in New York City (1859) under<lb/>
the name of the Third National Convention. After a most careful<lb/>
and exhaustive discussion of yellow fever, the following resolution<lb/>
was passed by a vote of eighty-five yeas to six nays:</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That in the absence of any evidence establishing the con-<lb/>
clusion that yellow fever has ever been conveyed by one person to<lb/>
another, it is the opinion of this convention that the personal quaran-<lb/>
tine of cases of yellow fever may be safely abolished provided that<lb/>
fomites of every kind be rigidly restricted.&rdquo;</p>
<p>To what I have presented above, I shall add my personal experience<lb/>
with this disease, and with persons and vessels arriving from yellow-<lb/>
fever-infected ports. This experience, which covers a number of<lb/>
years, is in full accord with the previous records of the New York<lb/>
Quarantine Station. Its special importance lies in the fact that prob-<lb/>
ably more than one-half of all foreign vessels coming to the United<lb/>
States reach the port of New York, which is in daily communication<lb/>
with yellow-fever ports.</p>
<p>For the purpose of better studying the statistics which I am about to<lb/>
present, it will be necessary to divide the vessels arriving at New York<lb/>
from yellow fever ports into two classes: (1) Those which are a<lb/>
week or less in transit, such as vessels from Cuban, Mexican, and<lb/>
Central American ports, and (2) vessels coming from ports far away,<lb/>
as Santos and Rio Janeiro (Brazil), which are three weeks or longer in<lb/>
passage. In the first class are found the greater number of vessels,<lb/>
and those with which we come in daily contact. These include both<lb/>
passenger and freight boats. The vessels from Havana, the most<lb/>
numerous, and on which we have heretofore found a large percentage<lb/>
of the yellow fever reaching this port, are from three to five days in<lb/>
transit. While at Havana they do not, as a rule, approach the docks,<lb/>
but discharge and receive their passengers and cargoes in the open bay.<lb/>
A still further restriction has been made. I have recommended that<lb/>
the crews of these vessels be detained on board and not allowed to go<lb/>
ashore. Some of the fast mail steamship lines carrying passengers<lb/>
have made this a rule of the company, and have required its strict<lb/>
enforcement. Vessels from Mexican and Central American ports,<lb/>
which are included in the first class, are about one week in transit to<lb/>
New York.</p>
<p>The yellow fever patients removed from these vessels have in every<lb/>
instance been taken sick within five days from the time of departure<lb/>
<pb n="137" id="f02535143"/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
137<lb/>
from the infected port; a large percentage of them showed the first<lb/>
symptoms of the disease during the first forty-eight hours, and some<lb/>
have stated that they were not feeling well at the time of embarkation.<lb/>
As a rule, these cases were found among the second cabin or steerage<lb/>
passengers, and although there was free exposure, in no instance has a<lb/>
secondary case ever occurred. I want to emphasize my statement<lb/>
regarding the exposure, as in the cases referred to it was practically<lb/>
unlimited. Sometimes the disease was not recognized, and the patient<lb/>
remained in the same apartment with others during the entire voyage;<lb/>
at other times, although the patient may have been removed to other<lb/>
quarters, passengers or members of the crew were detailed to care for<lb/>
him, as these vessels do not, as a rule, carry surgeons. The exposure<lb/>
was not only to the patient, but to his clothing, bedding, and dis-<lb/>
charges also. In instances where a member of the ship's crew con-<lb/>
tracted yellow fever, it was found that the patient had been on shore,<lb/>
but in no case, so far as I know, has the disease ever occurred among<lb/>
crews which have been kept on board vessels anchored in the bay of<lb/>
Havana. I have no reason to believe that members of the crews of<lb/>
Colon vessels are kept on board during the time that they are in that<lb/>
port. However, I am aware of no case which has occurred among<lb/>
them. This is easily explained by the fact that Colon, in recent years,<lb/>
has been free from yellow fever, and cases of this disease which vessels<lb/>
from Colon bring to the United States are from Panama, about thirty-<lb/>
five miles distant on the opposite side of the Isthmus.</p>
<p>Vessels coming from Rio Janeiro and Santos may be taken as ex-<lb/>
amples of the second class, which are long in transit. These ports are<lb/>
notorious for the prevalence of yellow fever, the bills of health having<lb/>
frequently shown the existence of four hundred to five hundred cases at<lb/>
one time. Some of the vessels from these ports carry passengers and<lb/>
have medical officers--the majority, however, do not. It is not uncom-<lb/>
mon for the captain or surgeon to report that while at Santos or Rio<lb/>
Janeiro, or within two or three days after leaving, a passenger or mem-<lb/>
ber of the crew became sick with symptoms clearly indicating yellow<lb/>
fever, and either died and was buried in port or at sea, or recovered.<lb/>
Their report also shows that in no instance were these followed by<lb/>
secondary cases after the boat had been five days at sea, although there<lb/>
was full exposure and no disinfection. But in no instance has a case of<lb/>
yellow fever been found on a vessel reaching here from these ports.<lb/>
This can easily be accounted for, as all who had yellow fever on these<lb/>
vessels were taken sick at Santos or Rio Janeiro, or within three or four<lb/>
days from departure, and either died or recovered long before the ves-<lb/>
sel reached this port, the voyage being about twenty-one days. Whereas,<lb/>
cases occurring on vessels of the first class reach here during the active<lb/>
<pb n="138" id="f02535144"/>
138<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
stages of the disease, neither have secondary cases ever occurred<lb/>
among those connected with the Swinburne Island Hospital in New<lb/>
York Bay, to which place all persons suffering with yellow fever are<lb/>
transferred from incoming vessels.</p>
<p>A careful analysis of these statistics clearly show that secondary<lb/>
cases have not occurred as the result of exposure to those who have<lb/>
contracted yellow fever in the infected area or to their clothing, bed-<lb/>
ding, etc., and that where persons have reached New York and are well<lb/>
after having been five (5) days or more from the port of departure,<lb/>
they have not afterwards developed the disease. Inasmuch as passen-<lb/>
gers and crews arriving on incoming vessels which have yellow fever on<lb/>
board are not detained at this station if they are well and have been five<lb/>
days from a yellow fever-infected area, it is naturally asked, how can<lb/>
I be certain that mild cases at least may not develop after they have<lb/>
left my jurisdiction? My answer is this: First--If secondary cases<lb/>
occurred as the result of personal contagion, or exposure to clothing,<lb/>
bedding, etc., there would be many of them, as there is full exposure--<lb/>
furthermore cases occurring as the result of this exposure would not all<lb/>
be mild, and some would surely present themselves in a typical and<lb/>
fatal type. If this occurred in New York City, or elsewhere, it would<lb/>
be known and the disease traced to its origin. Second--Those who<lb/>
are removed at this port sick with yellow fever are as a rule second-<lb/>
class or steerage passengers, and their apartments are on the same deck<lb/>
and in constant communication with the crew of the vessel and entirely<lb/>
separate from the cabin passengers who are on the deck above. There-<lb/>
fore the exposure is largely confined to the crew, who are frequently<lb/>
detailed to look after the sick and therefore are in close contact with<lb/>
the patient--moreover members of the crew are often detailed to look<lb/>
after those sick with the disease, and in this way freely handle the<lb/>
clothing, bedding, etc. The crews of the vessels upon which the cases<lb/>
are usually found are as a rule permanently employed by the companies,<lb/>
and although they visit their home while the vessel is in this port, they<lb/>
return again to the ship before sailing. If they were confined to their<lb/>
homes with yellow fever, or any disease resembling it, or were taken<lb/>
sick in transit to Havana, it would sooner or later be brought to my<lb/>
attention. Third--We have the experience of sanitarians during many<lb/>
years <hi>past</hi> to show that yellow fever is not transmitted by personal con-<lb/>
tagion, or by exposure to the clothing, bedding, etc., of those sick with<lb/>
this disease.</p>
<p>When we study the practical experience which I have just presented<lb/>
and which comes to us from different periods during the past century,<lb/>
we can reach but one conclusion, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>, that yellow fever is not con-<lb/>
tracted by personal contagion. This, however, is not by any means all<lb/>
<pb n="139" id="f02535145"/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
139<lb/>
that it shows, as the same evidence just as clearly proves that the cloth-<lb/>
ing, bedding, discharges, etc., are not media of infection. If those who<lb/>
are in constant attendance upon persons suffering from yellow fever,<lb/>
and are in close and prolonged contact with their clothing, bedding,<lb/>
discharges, etc., at all times and under all conditions are not infected<lb/>
through the medium of this material, when does it transmit infection?<lb/>
In order to make these views acceptable from a practical standpoint it<lb/>
has been necessary to show in what way, other than through the affected<lb/>
person, or his clothing, bedding, etc., yellow fever is transmitted. It<lb/>
would seem that the experiments of Dr. Reed have furnished this in-<lb/>
formation, inasmuch as the result of his work conclusively shows that<lb/>
the disease is transmitted by the mosquito and not by clothing, bedding,<lb/>
etc. This is in exact accord with our practical experience.</p>
<p>To those who have had but little practical experience in this matter,<lb/>
or those who live within the yellow fever zone, where extreme measures<lb/>
have been regarded as necessary to prevent the appearance or exten-<lb/>
sion of yellow fever, this view carries with it such a complete and<lb/>
abrupt change in the treatment of yellow fever, as well as persons and<lb/>
vessels arriving from yellow fever ports, that it can hardly receive un-<lb/>
biased consideration.</p>
<p>The opposing views regarding the means by which yellow fever is<lb/>
transmitted may briefly be summed up as follows: On the one hand,<lb/>
we have conclusive evidence, as the result of practical experience and<lb/>
scientific investigation, that yellow fever is not contracted by personal<lb/>
contagion, or by the clothing, bedding, discharges, etc., of persons<lb/>
suffering with this disease; furthermore, there is positive proof that<lb/>
yellow fever is transmitted through the medium of the mosquito. On<lb/>
the other hand, those who hold that the disease is transmitted either by<lb/>
personal contagion, or by the clothing, bedding, etc., of the sick, have<lb/>
had but little to support their theory aside from the fact that the true<lb/>
cause of infection was unknown. The result of the Havana experi-<lb/>
ments leaves practically no further justification for this belief.</p>
<p>I am well aware that from time to time evidence has been presented,<lb/>
which is intended to conclusively show that yellow fever is contracted<lb/>
by personal contagion, or through the medium of clothing, bedding,<lb/>
etc. In considering this, we must bear in mind that heretofore we have<lb/>
had no positive evidence as to the means by which yellow fever is<lb/>
propagated, and all have been free to form their own ideas regarding<lb/>
this subject, and very naturally persons, or clothing, bedding, etc., have<lb/>
been accepted as the medium of infection. However, I believe that it<lb/>
is pertinent to ask if, in the instances just referred to, the presence of<lb/>
the infected mosquito would not afford a full explanation for the<lb/>
appearance of the disease. Furthermore, do we not fully appreciate<lb/>
<pb n="140" id="f02535146"/>
140<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
the danger from mild or unrecognized cases as the cause of outbreaks<lb/>
not only of yellow fever, but also other infectious diseases, nor is it<lb/>
fully understood how frequently such mild cases occur. Again we do<lb/>
not consider the errors in diagnosis which may occur, even on the part<lb/>
of the best diagnosticians. Unconsciously, we are very apt, after hav-<lb/>
ing accepted a theory, to entertain only such evidence as tends to<lb/>
strengthen our belief in that direction. How can we reasonably en-<lb/>
tertain a statement that yellow fever follows the exposure to some<lb/>
garment, or other material, when we have such indisputable evidence as<lb/>
I have presented to show that the disease is neither contracted by per-<lb/>
sonal contagion or clothing, bedding, etc. The hospital reports of 1798<lb/>
to 1805, to which I have referred, are invaluable, as at that time disin-<lb/>
fection was not understood, and there is not the slightest evidence that<lb/>
any protection was afforded in this manner. Furthermore, I am unable<lb/>
to find any reliable or conclusive evidence to show that in the outbreaks<lb/>
of yellow fever, which from time to time have occurred in the South,<lb/>
disinfection has been of any value in abating the disease. In connec-<lb/>
tion with this, I will call attention to the fact that, in the experiments<lb/>
made by Dr. Reed, non-immunes were placed in prolonged contact with<lb/>
the bedding, clothing, etc., of those sick with yellow fever without the<lb/>
slightest evidence of infection; and is it not significant that those living<lb/>
within the yellow fever zone have learned to look forward to the appear-<lb/>
ance of frost, which terminates the activity of the mosquito, as the only<lb/>
prompt and sure means of ridding a community of yellow fever?</p>
<p>If we accept a sanitary science, we must abide by its teachings, and<lb/>
I know of no better time than the present to look this matter fairly and<lb/>
squarely in the face, and make such changes in our sanitary regulations<lb/>
as are necessary to conform to our present knowledge of yellow fever.<lb/>
What I am now advocating I put into practical operation five years ago,<lb/>
at the port of New York, as, after a careful consideration of the subject,<lb/>
I was convinced that yellow fever is contracted neither by personal<lb/>
contagion, nor the clothing, bedding, etc., of those suffering with this<lb/>
disease. Since the above time, many vessels have arrived here with<lb/>
persons sick with yellow fever, and with the bodies of those who have<lb/>
died of the disease during the voyage, but in no instance have those on<lb/>
board been detained if five days had elapsed since the departure of the<lb/>
vessel from the infected port, although there may have been free expo-<lb/>
sure to the patient, his clothing, bedding, etc.; however, no secondary<lb/>
cases have ever occurred. It is true that, after the removal of the<lb/>
patient, disinfection is performed in compliance with the existing quar-<lb/>
antine regulations, but this treatment on the arrival of the vessel can in<lb/>
no way affect those who had been in close contact with the patient while<lb/>
en route. I believe the value of Dr. Reed's experiments lies largely in<lb/>
<pb n="141" id="f02535147"/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
141<lb/>
the fact that they indicate a line of procedure in the treatment of yellow<lb/>
fever which, if promptly and properly carried out, limits at once the<lb/>
extension of the disease. I refer to the use of netting, and other means,<lb/>
to guard against the mosquito. Commerce has patiently suffered the<lb/>
enforcement of regulations which, in the present light of our knowledge,<lb/>
are uncalled for, and it is but just that we should give this subject<lb/>
prompt consideration.</p>
<p>There are some details regarding the relation between the mosquito<lb/>
and yellow fever which are yet to be made clear; for instance, why do<lb/>
not infected mosquitoes reach vessels lying in Havana harbor, not far<lb/>
from the shore, or vessels which lie at the dock at Santos, and other<lb/>
infected ports, and at some subsequent time, or at different periods,<lb/>
transmit the disease to those on board, or at the point of destination?<lb/>
Yellow fever does sometimes occur among the crew of vessels docked<lb/>
at yellow fever ports, but this is easily explained by the fact that the<lb/>
crews are allowed to enter the town. In explanation of this it may be<lb/>
said that all who have studied the habits of the mosquito fully agree<lb/>
that it prefers to remain in the immediate vicinity of its breeding or<lb/>
abiding place; this is also borne out by the fact that we do not see sec-<lb/>
ondary cases of yellow fever on shipboard, provided the vessel has left<lb/>
the infected port, and there is but little reliable evidence that infected<lb/>
mosquitoes are transmitted to foreign shores. It is not impossible for<lb/>
this to take place, and instances have been reported where secondary<lb/>
cases have occurred after leaving port. How many of these statements<lb/>
are authentic, I do not know, but of this I am sure, that it occurs only<lb/>
in rare instances, and we are surely not justified in making our rules<lb/>
conform to these possible exceptions. Suppose that it should be<lb/>
deemed necessary to take action against this possible danger, what can<lb/>
be done that is reasonable? We cannot assume that the mosquito is<lb/>
confined to any special part of the ship; it may be in the forecastle,<lb/>
saloon, engine room, or the hold of the vessel. Therefore, if we are<lb/>
consistent in carrying out such extreme measures, we cannot stop short<lb/>
of fumigating, or in some other manner treating every part of the ship.<lb/>
To those who are familiar with this work, I need say nothing; to those<lb/>
who have never undertaken it I say that such treatment is the most<lb/>
formidable and expensive that a quarantine officer is called upon to<lb/>
perform, besides the long delay to the vessel. Moreover, I do not<lb/>
believe that such action is justifiable unless there is satisfactory evi-<lb/>
dence that infected mosquitoes are on board, as would be indicated by<lb/>
the appearance of secondary cases of yellow fever after a departure of<lb/>
five days from an infected port.</p>
<p>Another question may here be presented for consideration, and it is<lb/>
this: Does five days represent the maximum period of incubation of<lb/>
<pb n="142" id="f02535148"/>
142<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
yellow fever, or may the disease develop after a longer period of time?<lb/>
I am aware that instances have been cited where the disease has ocurred<lb/>
after a period of incubation of six or seven days, or even longer, but<lb/>
none have come under my notice. I believe the early symptoms gen-<lb/>
erally present themselves on the third or fourth day. There is no<lb/>
doubt that errors are often made in computing the period of incubation,<lb/>
as persons may be passing through the early stage without any well-<lb/>
marked evidence of it. This I have detected a number of times by the<lb/>
use of the clinical thermometer. A reference to the opinion of many<lb/>
careful investigators, among whom we find Dr. George M. Sternberg,<lb/>
will show that it is the general opinion that five days is the maximum<lb/>
period of incubation. I believe this is sensible and safe, and that regu-<lb/>
lations should be made accordingly, notwithstanding the fact that evi-<lb/>
dence has been presented which tends to show that it occasionally covers<lb/>
a longer period.</p>
<p>If we believe that yellow fever is not transmitted by personal conta-<lb/>
gion or clothing, bedding, etc., of those sick with this disease, and that<lb/>
the medium of infection is the mosquito, we must admit that disinfection<lb/>
offers but little protection. No other view is reasonable or logical.<lb/>
Our efforts, therefore, should be turned toward the detection of cases of<lb/>
yellow fever and their treatment according to our present knowledge<lb/>
of the disease. There is no doubt that many outbreaks of yellow fever<lb/>
have been caused by the presence of mild or unrecognized cases where<lb/>
the infection was attributed to clothing, etc. For this reason special<lb/>
effort should be made to detect this type of the disease, which can be<lb/>
done only by a careful and thorough inspection. Moreover, each com-<lb/>
munity, particularly in the yellow fever belt, should be supplied with<lb/>
an apartment or hospital for the special care of yellow fever, where<lb/>
the most approved methods of protection against the mosquito are in<lb/>
operation. Furthermore, health officials should be familiar with the<lb/>
different variety of mosquitoes, and should, from time to time, make<lb/>
investigations to ascertain, if possible, the presence of the insects which<lb/>
transmit infectious material. I cannot agree with those who hold that<lb/>
a bad sanitary condition does not constitute an important factor in the<lb/>
propagation of either yellow fever or malaria. I am satisfied that it<lb/>
does, inasmuch as filth and bad drainage furnish the breeding places<lb/>
for the mosquito.</p>
<p>In accordance with the above views, the treatment of incoming ves-<lb/>
sels from ports infected with this disease becomes very simple: if they<lb/>
are five days or more in transit, and all on board are found to be well<lb/>
after a careful inspection and the use of the clinical thermometer, the<lb/>
vessel, its passengers, and crew shall be released without further deten-<lb/>
tion or treatment. If the vessel has been less than five days in transit,<lb/>
<pb n="143" id="f02535149"/>
<hi rend="italic">PRACTICAL DISCUSSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
143<lb/>
all on board who cannot present satisfactory evidence of immunity<lb/>
should be removed and held for observation until the completion of a<lb/>
period of five days from the time of departure from the infected port,<lb/>
and then released only after a careful inspection.</p>
<p>When yellow fever is found on incoming vessels, the procedure<lb/>
should differ only so far as it concerns the removal of the patient to a<lb/>
properly constructed hospital or apartment for treatment.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed's experiments have not conclusively shown that there may<lb/>
not be some other means than the mosquito by which yellow fever is<lb/>
transmitted. But when these experiments are considered in connection<lb/>
with the results of our practical experience it is clearly evident that this<lb/>
disease is not contracted by personal contagion or through the medium<lb/>
of clothing, bedding, cargoes of vessels, etc. Therefore, I believe we<lb/>
are justified in changing our quarantine regulations to conform to these<lb/>
views and that such a proceeding is safe and reasonable, particularly as<lb/>
we now have at hand a method which, if properly and scientifically<lb/>
carried out, can be depended upon to limit the extension of yellow fever.<lb/>
If the future shows that there are other means of infection it will then<lb/>
be time enough to add whatever restrictions are necessary for the pro-<lb/>
tection of the public health.</p>
<p>I am convinced that in following this line of action we are not only<lb/>
offering full protection to the public, but are extending to commerce<lb/>
a relief from unnecessary and unreasonable regulations.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="4">
<head>FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER.</head>
<pb n="144" id="f02535150"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>A. N. BELL</docAuthor>, M. D., BROOKLYN, N. Y.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub H. Assoc. 29th meet<lb/>
Buffalo Sept 1901</p>
<p>&check;</p>
<p>The purpose of this note is to invite attention to some personal obser-<lb/>
vations and verified knowledge of the agency of fomites in the propa-<lb/>
gation of yellow fever, overlooked or ignored by expert bacteriologists<lb/>
in recent researches and reports.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
<p>Assuming that every member of this Association is familiar with the<lb/>
substance of the investigation and reports here referred to, demon-<lb/>
strating the agency of a certain species of mosquito, as an intermediate<lb/>
host in the transmission of yellow fever, reference will be made to such<lb/>
portions of them only as appear to be in conflict with, or deficient in the<lb/>
recognition of, fomites as the hitherto accepted cause of many out-<lb/>
breaks of yellow fever, inexplicable by the alleged exclusive agency of<lb/>
mosquitoes.</p>
<p>I do not question the accuracy of the researches demonstrating the<lb/>
agency of the mosquito as an intermediate host and agent in the trans-<lb/>
mission of the infection, but I deny the sufficiency of this agency to<lb/>
account for the supersusceptibility to, and the retention of, yellow fever<lb/>
infection by unclean localities under climatic conditions favorable to the<lb/>
propagation of the disease; houses and ships in which yellow fever has<lb/>
prevailed and that have not been thereafter cleansed and aerated; cer-<lb/>
tain kinds of ballast and merchandise, taken from infected localities, or<lb/>
infected vessels, or from localities where and when yellow fever pre-<lb/>
vails; personal clothing and books that have been long exposed in<lb/>
infected vessels or houses and packed therein without previous disinfec-<lb/>
tion. Verifiable cases and even outbreaks of epidemics have occurred<lb/>
in connection with such conditions when no mosquitoes have been in<lb/>
evidence, nor any precursory <hi rend="italic">case of yellow fever</hi>--necessary according<lb/>
to the showing of the experts--whose infected blood must be sucked<lb/>
and transmitted as a condition of the propagation of the disease.</p>
<p>Concisely summed up and endorsed by Dr. Sternberg:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The inference drawn by Dr. Reed and his associates, from the ex-<lb/>
periments thus far made, was that yellow fever may be transmitted by<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The Etiology of Yellow Fever. <hi rend="italic">Yellow Fever produced by the bite of Culex fasciatus</hi>. By<lb/>
Major Walter Reed, Surgeon, U. S. Army; Dr. James Carroll, Contract Surgeon, U. S. A.;<lb/>
Dr. Agramonte, Contract Surgeon, U. S. A., and Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, Contract Surgeon,<lb/>
U. S. A. Read at the Pan-American Medical Congress, Havana, February, 1901. (Journal<lb/>
American Medical Association.) Sanitation and Yellow Fever in Havana. Report of Major<lb/>
V. Havard, Surgeon, U. S. Army, Chief Surgeon, Havana, February 8, 1901 (Sanitarian, July<lb/>
and August, 1901). The Transmission of Yellow Fever by Mosquitoes. By George M.<lb/>
Sternberg, Surgeon-General, U. S. Army (The Popular Science Monthly, July, 1901.)<lb/>
The Propagation of Yellow Fever; Observations Based on Recent Researches. By Walter<lb/>
Reed, M. D., Surgeon, U. S. Army (Medical Record, August 10, 1901).</p>
<p>144</p>
<pb n="145" id="f02535151"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
145</p>
<p>mosquitoes of the genus <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi>, but that in order to convey the infection<lb/>
to a non-immune individual the insect must be kept for twelve days or<lb/>
longer after it has filled itself with blood from a yellow fever patient in<lb/>
the earlier stages of the disease. In other words, that a certain period<lb/>
of incubation is required in the body of the insect before the germ<lb/>
reaches its salivary glands, and consequently before it is able to inocu-<lb/>
late an individual with the germs of yellow fever. This inference,<lb/>
based upon experimental data, received support from other observa-<lb/>
tions, and which have been repeatedly made with reference to the intro-<lb/>
duction and spread of yellow fever in localities favorable to its propaga-<lb/>
tion. When a case is imported to one of our Southern seaport cities,<lb/>
from Havana, Veracruz or some other endemic focus of the disease, an<lb/>
interval of two weeks or more occurs before secondary cases are devel-<lb/>
oped as a result of such importation. In the light of our present knowl-<lb/>
edge this is readily understood. A certain number of mosquitoes hav-<lb/>
ing filled themselves with blood from this first case, after an interval of<lb/>
twelve days or more bite non-immune individuals living in the vicinity,<lb/>
and these individuals, after a brief period of incubation, fall sick with<lb/>
the disease; being bitten by other mosquitoes they serve to transmit the<lb/>
disease through the &lsquo;intermediate host&rsquo; to still others. Thus the epi-<lb/>
demic extends, at first slowly, as from house to house, then more rap-<lb/>
idly, as by geometrical progress.&rdquo;</p>
<p>But whence and how the first case, whose blood is necessary for the<lb/>
mosquito before it can become intermediary--how did he become in-<lb/>
fected? True, part of the title of the Army Board report is, &ldquo;Yellow<lb/>
Fever <hi rend="italic">Produced</hi> by the Bite of <hi rend="italic">Culex Fasciatus</hi>.&rdquo; But evidence is<lb/>
wanting to show it. It is transmitted, but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> produced.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the board concludes:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yellow fever is not conveyed by fomites, and hence disinfection of<lb/>
articles of clothing, bedding or merchandise, supposedly contaminated<lb/>
by contact with those sick with this disease, is unnecessary.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A house may be said to be infected with yellow fever only when<lb/>
there are present within its walls contaminated mosquitoes capable of<lb/>
carrying the parasites of the disease.&rdquo;</p>
<p>And to these conclusions, Major Havard adds:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Disinfection becomes completely useless, since there are no infectious<lb/>
germs to destroy. In a house where a case of yellow fever has been<lb/>
under treatment, the problem is how to reach the mosquitoes which have<lb/>
become infected by biting the patient and are still lurking in the vicinity.<lb/>
* * * Since we may assume in practice that the infectious germs<lb/>
do not exist outside of a man or mosquito, the disinfection of trunks<lb/>
and baggage on account of yellow fever is no longer justifiable; all that<lb/>
is required will be the examination of non-immunes within the five days<lb/>
<pb n="146" id="f02535152"/>
146<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
immediately following their last exposure to infection, the danger of<lb/>
transmission being from their own persons and in no wise from their<lb/>
clothing or baggage. Ships, like houses, are liable to harbor infected<lb/>
mosquitoes and will continue to require fumigation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Moreover, he refers to the non-contagiousness of the disease as a <lb/>
&ldquo;<hi rend="italic">discovery</hi> by Major Reed and his associates, conclusively proved by<lb/>
direct experiment that recently soiled linen, bedding and effects of all<lb/>
kinds are powerless to convey the disease. This discovery,&rdquo; he says,<lb/>
&ldquo;must bring about a revolution in our methods of disinfection and<lb/>
quarantine in yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This knowledge of the non-contagiousness of yellow fever has been<lb/>
acted upon for more than half of the past century by physicians of actual<lb/>
experience in connection with yellow fever everywhere. The &ldquo;direct<lb/>
experiment&rdquo; of collecting a quantity of recently soiled linen and bedding<lb/>
by yellow fever patients and sleeping in them, was but a feeble imita-<lb/>
tion of what one of the surgeons of the French frigate <hi rend="italic">Gomer</hi> did in the<lb/>
naval hospital at Pensacola in 1838. For besides the bed and clothing<lb/>
in which he slept, and from which the dead body of a yellow fever<lb/>
patient had just been taken, the ward was full of cases of yellow fever.<lb/>
This he did in order to show the comrades of the sick, required to nurse<lb/>
them, that there was no danger in their so doing. The incident was<lb/>
described to me by the late Dr. Isaac Hulse, U. S. Navy, who was sur-<lb/>
geon of the hospital at the time. My own personal experience with<lb/>
yellow fever at the outset was scarcely less explicit, besides its subse-<lb/>
quent relation to fomites--an infected ship.</p>
<p>Fifty-four years ago, being an assistant surgeon in the Navy, during<lb/>
the war with Mexico, I was ordered to a hospital on Salmadina Island,<lb/>
in the vicinity of Veracruz, constructed of rough pine boards, where, in<lb/>
a &ldquo;ward&rdquo; about twenty feet square, I had for room-mates for a period<lb/>
of six weeks from two to six patients with yellow fever. We took our<lb/>
meals in the same room. In an adjoining room, about thrice as large,<lb/>
with an open doorway communicating, without a door, I had under my<lb/>
care for the same length of time from ten to forty cases--there was a<lb/>
daily increase in the number; and, during the last two weeks of the<lb/>
period, about forty more in a tent twenty feet distant, who were cared<lb/>
for during the day time by two visiting surgeons attached to vessels<lb/>
anchored near by. My health was excellent during the period, but at<lb/>
the end of it I was transferred to the infected frigate <hi rend="italic">Mississippi</hi>, on<lb/>
board which ship most of the cases orginated, in charge of as many of<lb/>
the sick as, in my judgment, could be safely taken on board--there were<lb/>
127--under orders to proceed to Pensacola and transfer them to the<lb/>
naval hospital at that place.</p>
<pb n="147" id="f02535153"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
147</p>
<p>My fourth night on board the <hi rend="italic">Mississippi</hi> was a restless one, with<lb/>
symptoms of yellow fever. Within the forty-eight hours before and<lb/>
subsequent to my attack twelve other new cases had developed--all of<lb/>
them of new-comers to the ship, some from the hospital attendants,<lb/>
and the others transferred from vessels of the squadron.</p>
<p>There were mosquitoes in the hospital during the whole period of my<lb/>
service there; they were also present in all the vessels of the squadron.<lb/>
But, admitting their agency in the transmission of the disease, the <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi><lb/>
seems to have been almost exclusively confined to the <hi rend="italic">Mississippi</hi>, where<lb/>
most of the cases occurred.</p>
<p>In the afternoon of the day following my attack in the night, the ship<lb/>
having arrived at Pensacola, all the sick, myself included, were trans-<lb/>
ferred to the naval hospital. Six weeks thereafter I returned to duty<lb/>
on board the same ship, she having been meanwhile &ldquo;broken out&rdquo; and<lb/>
limed. If mosquitoes were still present they were not in such evidence<lb/>
as to attract attention. Three weeks later, October 17th, she again put<lb/>
to sea for Veracruz. On the fourth day out a case of yellow fever occur-<lb/>
red on board, in a non-immune received on the day of her departure<lb/>
from Pensacola. She arrived at Veracruz October 22d, at the begin-<lb/>
ning of the first norther of the season--ever welcome as frost in New<lb/>
Orleans as an estop to yellow fever. Up to this time the fever had been<lb/>
increasingly prevalent in the city and squadron. The norther continued<lb/>
about a week with comfortably cool but rainy weather. Almost imme-<lb/>
diately following there was notable abatement of the fever on shore and<lb/>
in the squadron generally. But not so on board the <hi rend="italic">Mississippi</hi> to non-<lb/>
immune new-comers; one rarely escaped an attack within five days.<lb/>
And so she continued to the end of her service in the Gulf, went North,<lb/>
and was subjected to a freezing temperature; explicable, perhaps, by<lb/>
the possible continued presence of <hi rend="italic">Culex fasciatus</hi>.</p>
<p>But hardly so in the case of the U. S. Frigate <hi rend="italic">Susquehanna</hi>. This<lb/>
ship, after more than two years' service in the Mediterranean, October,<lb/>
1857, was ordered from Spezzia to San Juan de Nicaragua, where she<lb/>
arrived early in December; having touched by the way at Genoa,<lb/>
Madeira and Key West. She remained at San Juan until the first of<lb/>
the following April, having had during the whole period of time she<lb/>
lay there a constantly increasing sick list of a &ldquo;precursory&rdquo; fever. At<lb/>
first intermittent, then remittent, but all recovered until March 20th,<lb/>
when a case became malignant with symptoms of yellow fever, and<lb/>
died; other cases followed. The ship put to sea April 1st, and on the<lb/>
5th arrived at Port Royal, Jamaica, with one hundred and six officers<lb/>
and men down with yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="148" id="f02535154"/>
<p>148<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>Most of these were sent to the hospital, and on the third day after-<lb/>
ward she sailed for New York, where she arrived April 15th, with<lb/>
fifty-one cases on the sick list.</p>
<p>The remarkable feature in this instance is, that at San Juan, where<lb/>
the yellow fever first appeared on board the <hi rend="italic">Susquehanna</hi>, there was<lb/>
no yellow fever, and the disease had never been known to occur there.<lb/>
As before stated, she had been more than two years in service on the<lb/>
Mediterranean, but with no extraordinary sickness on board. She<lb/>
had had yellow fever on board during service in the Gulf Squadron<lb/>
the summer before she was ordered to the Mediterranean, nearly three<lb/>
years before, and was supposed to have been thoroughly cleansed<lb/>
before she was ordered to the Mediterranean station. But, as the<lb/>
sequel shows, she still retained the germs of the disease (or mosqui-<lb/>
toes?) until she returned to the conditions of the yellow fever habitat<lb/>
at the Port of San Juan.</p>
<p>It is conceivable that the advocates of the exclusive instrumentality<lb/>
of the mosquito in her case may contend that she might have shipped<lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi> when she touched at Key West. But there was no yellow<lb/>
fever there at the time, and no case intervened between that time and<lb/>
the first unequivocal case on board the <hi rend="italic">Susquehanna</hi>, March 20th,<lb/>
after several weeks' prevalence of a <hi rend="italic">precursory</hi> fever--a not very un-<lb/>
usual feature of yellow fever observed on other occasions; and promi-<lb/>
nently so at the first outbreak of the disease in Rio and Callao.</p>
<p>In 1849-52 the harbor of Rio was more or less crowded with vessels<lb/>
from American ports, most of them destined for the Pacific, on ac-<lb/>
count of the California &ldquo;gold fever.&rdquo; How many of them infected<lb/>
with yellow fever, contracted while in service as storeships or other-<lb/>
wise in the Gulf during the Mexican War, two or three years previous,<lb/>
when yellow fever was exceptionally prevalent there, arrived at Rio<lb/>
or touched at other Brazilian ports where yellow fever for the first<lb/>
time appeared is problematical, but that some were is beyond ques-<lb/>
tion. My interest in the subject on the first occurrence of yellow<lb/>
fever in Callao led me to make some inquiry.</p>
<p>I ascertained that about the middle of the year 1851 the steamer<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">New World</hi>, after having lost more than half her crew by yellow fever<lb/>
in Rio, on her way to California, touched at Callao. The steamer<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Pinto</hi> also, during the same season, lost several of her crew there,<lb/>
proceeding to the Pacific and arriving at Callao in April, 1852. Soon<lb/>
after her arrival a mild form of a peculiar fever broke out in Callao<lb/>
and Lima, which the natives called &ldquo;pelusa,&rdquo; similar to the precursory<lb/>
fever which prevailed in Rio in 1849; it was called &ldquo;polka.&rdquo; In both<lb/>
instances the disease speedily developed yellow fever. And consid-<lb/>
ering the voyages, so inconsistent with the continued presence of<lb/>
<pb n="149" id="f02535155"/>
<hi rend="italic">FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
149<lb/>
mosquitoes on board ship, it is hardly conceivable that they had any-<lb/>
thing to do with either its introduction or transmission.</p>
<p>The persistence of yellow fever-infection under conditions com-<lb/>
monly fatal to mosquitoes is particularly well shown in the history of<lb/>
the U. S. Steamer <hi rend="italic">Plymouth</hi>. She first became infected at St. Thomas<lb/>
in the summer of 1878. In November following she was sent to<lb/>
Portsmouth, N. H., and about a month afterward to Boston, where<lb/>
she remained four months. Meanwhile everything was removed<lb/>
from the ship; the crew were transferred, and she was fully exposed to<lb/>
intense cold for a month--for ten days of that time in dry-dock, with<lb/>
a temperature at times below zero. The water in the tanks was<lb/>
frozen, as it was in basins put in the store rooms of the ship, and for<lb/>
several days after the fires were rekindled on board the cold continued<lb/>
so intense that the water froze in the bilges at night. One hundred<lb/>
pounds of sulphur was burned below decks, the fumigation extending<lb/>
over two days; the berth deck, holds and store-rooms were thoroughly<lb/>
whitewashed with a mixture of lime and chloride of lime. March 15,<lb/>
1879, she left Boston for a cruise in the West Indies. On the night<lb/>
of the 19th, in a severe gale of wind, the hatches had to be battened<lb/>
down and the berth deck became very damp and stuffy. On the<lb/>
morning of the 22d (she had not touched at any port) Richard Saun-<lb/>
ders, machinist, was sick, but did not report until afternoon, when he<lb/>
had violent headache and fever. During the night of the 22d, Peter<lb/>
Eagan, boatswain's mate, was taken suddenly and violently sick with<lb/>
the same symptoms. On the 23d, at sea, latitude N. 27.48, longitude<lb/>
W. 57.59, the surgeon (Woolverton) reported both cases yellow fever,<lb/>
and recommended that the ship proceed no further on that cruise.<lb/>
The first case recovered; the second died on the third day of illness.<lb/>
The ship's course was changed to northward, and she arrived at<lb/>
Portsmouth, N. H., April 7th. No new cases appeared after she<lb/>
turned.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am convinced,&rdquo; said the surgeon, in his report, &ldquo;that the fever<lb/>
infection is confined to the hull of the ship, and especially to the un-<lb/>
sound wood about the berth deck; and that while the <hi rend="italic">Plymouth</hi> is a<lb/>
safe and healthy ship in a temperate climate, she cannot, for the pres-<lb/>
ent, be sent into a tropical climate without the certainty of an out-<lb/>
break of yellow fever occurring on board; and that no precautionary<lb/>
measures whatever could avail to avert such a result.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Soon after her return to Portsmouth, April 17th, she was surveyed<lb/>
by a board of medical officers, who reported that:</p>
<p>&ldquo;After careful consideration of all the facts, we have arrived at the<lb/>
conclusion that the infecting virus which gave rise to the last out-<lb/>
<pb n="150" id="f02535156"/>
150<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
break of fever must have been preserved in the rotten wood of the<lb/>
berth deck, or in the bedding or clothing of the crew.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Of Ballast</hi>.--July 12-18, 1878, yellow fever broke out on board the<lb/>
U. S. ship <hi rend="italic">Vermont</hi>, at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, of which there were<lb/>
eight cases, with three deaths. According to the investigation and<lb/>
report of a board of medical officers of the Navy, &ldquo;the disease seems<lb/>
to have originated from the ballast of the bark <hi rend="italic">Juanita Clar</hi>, which left<lb/>
Havana May 1st. This ballast, quarry clippings and sand was de-<lb/>
posited on the dock on either side of the <hi rend="italic">Vermont</hi>, and about one hun-<lb/>
dred yards distant from her.&rdquo; On this report the ballast was promptly<lb/>
disinfected and covered over with fresh earth, after which there was<lb/>
not another case.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Of Personal Effects</hi>.--During my service as medical superintendent<lb/>
of the floating hospital in the Lower Bay of New York, in September,<lb/>
1862, I was sent for by one of my colleagues of the Brooklyn hospital<lb/>
for consultation in a suspected case. I there found an unequivocal<lb/>
case of yellow fever, who died the third day thereafter. She was the<lb/>
widow of a seaman who had died in New Orleans two or three months<lb/>
before, whose clothing she had received and washed four days before<lb/>
she was taken sick.--Incidentally, it may here be remarked, this was<lb/>
when General Butler was in command at New Orleans, when, it has<lb/>
been frequently alleged, there was no yellow fever at that place. On<lb/>
the contrary, though there was no commerce with Havana or other<lb/>
yellow fever ports during General Butler's administration in New<lb/>
Orleans, &ldquo;there were two reported deaths by yellow fever in the civil<lb/>
population, and about one hundred cases in the river fleet.&rdquo;--Prof.<lb/>
Stanford L. Chaill&eacute;, M. D. (<hi rend="italic">Sanitarian</hi>, August number, 1882).</p>
<p>Not long after the case in Brooklyn, I met and had occasion to<lb/>
relate it to the late Dr. William Johnson, Surgeon U. S. Navy. He<lb/>
expressed no surprise, but related a still more strongly illustrative<lb/>
case of himself.</p>
<p>On the termination of a cruise on the west coast of Africa, some<lb/>
years before, when yellow fever occurred on board the ship to which<lb/>
he was attached, he packed his books in a barrel and so left them for<lb/>
about three months after they had been received and his arrival home.<lb/>
He then proceeded to unpack them, and three or four days thereafter<lb/>
he was taken with yellow fever and came near dying.</p>
<p>I have no need to be told that this recital is an epitome of ancient<lb/>
history. It would be easy to extend it and quote reports of outbreaks<lb/>
in the Gulf States in recent years, with which contemporary observers<lb/>
are familiar; but I do not deem it necessary. Such occurrences have<lb/>
been the foundation of our most intelligent quarantine practice, both<lb/>
<pb n="151" id="f02535157"/>
<hi rend="italic">FOMITES AND YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
151<lb/>
State and National, during recent years, and with such results as, in<lb/>
my judgment, justify their continuance.</p>
<p>Moreover, with regard to the relation of unclean localities, as well<lb/>
as foul ships, I think the remarks of John Simon, in his report to the<lb/>
commissioners of sewers of London, in 1854, with reference to cholera,<lb/>
are even more pertinent to yellow fever, and no less suitable today<lb/>
than they were fifty years ago:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The specific migrating power, whatever its nature, has the faculty<lb/>
of infecting districts in a manner detrimental to life <hi rend="italic">only when their<lb/>
atmosphere is fraught with certain products susceptible, under its influence,<lb/>
of undergoing poisonous transformation</hi>. * * * Through the un-<lb/>
polluted atmosphere of cleanly districts it migrates silently, without a<lb/>
blow; that which it can kindle into poison lies not there. To the foul,<lb/>
damp breath of low-lying cities it comes like a spark to powder. Here<lb/>
is contained that which it can quickly make destructive--soaked into<lb/>
soil, stagnant in water, griming the pavement, tainting the air--the<lb/>
slow rottenness of unremoved excrement to which the first contact of<lb/>
this foreign ferment brings the occasion to changing into new and<lb/>
more deadly combinations.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="5">
<head>OFFICIAL REPORT OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE<lb/>
TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMER-<lb/>
ICAN PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION.</head>
<pb n="319" id="f02535325"/>
<p>HELD AT BUFFALO, N. Y., SEPTEMBER 17, 18, 19 AND 20, 1901.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 17TH--FIRST DAY--MORNING SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association convened in the Seventy-fourth Regiment Armory,<lb/>
and was called to order by the President, Dr. Benjamin Lee of Phila-<lb/>
delphia, Pennsylvania, at 10 A. M.</p>
<p>In accordance with the wishes of the President all ex-Presidents of<lb/>
the Association, present at this meeting, took seats upon the platform.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--Many years ago--I cannot say how many because<lb/>
that would be giving away the ages of two elderly gentlemen present--<lb/>
many years ago, a trembling medical student stood before his examiners<lb/>
for graduation. He was obliged to pass seven subjects. Among those<lb/>
subjects I need hardly say hygiene was not included. In those days<lb/>
hygiene was not a part of the curriculum of any medical college. There<lb/>
were, however, men in the profession who felt even then that in simply<lb/>
attending their patients, administering pills and potions, and cutting off<lb/>
legs, they were not fulfilling their full duty to their profession, or to<lb/>
humanity. They felt that the knowledge which they acquired should<lb/>
be utilized for the benefit of the entire public and of the world.</p>
<p>Among those far-sighted men was Dr. Stephen Smith of the city of<lb/>
New York. He who addresses you was the trembling student. Pro-<lb/>
fessor Smith was his examiner. It is not necessary for me to say any-<lb/>
thing in regard to the prominent place which Dr. Smith, as the first<lb/>
President of this Association, and as an earnest worker in harmony<lb/>
with it ever since that time, has occupied in the minds of sanitarians.<lb/>
It is scarcely necessary for me to introduce him. I do so, however, with<lb/>
very great pleasure. (Applause.) (See p. 19.)</p>
<p>DR. A. L. GIHON, New York City.--Mr. President, in rising to move<lb/>
a vote of thanks to Dr. Stephen Smith, it may be permitted me to say<lb/>
that the child whose birth he witnessed in 1871 has now become triplets.<lb/>
It has two sisters--Canada and Mexico. It so happens that sitting on<lb/>
my right is the Director-General of Public Health of the Dominion of<lb/>
Canada, one of our honored ex-Presidents, and sitting on my left is<lb/>
the Supreme Head of the Sanitary Department of Mexico. Our two<lb/>
sisters have done that which Dr. Smith thinks the United States should<lb/>
319<lb/>
<pb n="346" id="f02535352"/>
346<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p>The motion was seconded by Dr. Stanton, and carried</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--The Chair will appoint Dr. Salmon, of Wash-<lb/>
ington; Dr. Bryce of Canada, and Dr. William M. Welch, of Phila-<lb/>
delphia, as such committee.</p>
<p>Mr. George W. Fuller of New York City, Chairman of the Com-<lb/>
mittee on the Pollution of Public Water Supplies, reported as follows:</p>
<p>This committee has decided that formal joint reports, such as made<lb/>
last year, had in the future best be submitted once in three to five<lb/>
years. In the meantime it is proposed by the committee to devote<lb/>
itself to the preparation of new evidence on those topics previously<lb/>
dealt with; and, further, to the development of those topics which<lb/>
are not yet in such form that the evidence can be set forth in conclu-<lb/>
sive and concise terms.</p>
<p>During the past year the committee has been gathering informa-<lb/>
tion relative to the various topics mentioned in our last report. Con-<lb/>
cerning the question of vital statistics, particularly typhoid fever death<lb/>
rates, in their relation to the pollution of public water supplies, the<lb/>
data are not as complete as hoped for, but for American cities of over<lb/>
30,000 population the typhoid fever death rate for each of the last<lb/>
three years can be submitted. If it meets the pleasure of the Asso-<lb/>
ciation, we would be glad to have these data printed in the Proceed-<lb/>
ings of this meeting. (See page 100.)</p>
<p>The principal work of the past year has been the accumulation of<lb/>
evidence referring to the legal status of water pollution. This has<lb/>
been undertaken by two members of our committee, Dr. Leal of Pat-<lb/>
erson, N. J., and Dr. Wesbrook of Minneapolis, Minn. In the origi-<lb/>
nal assignment of topics it was planned to have Dr. Leal investigate<lb/>
this subject particularly from the standpoint of litigation and with<lb/>
reference to leading court decisions; and to have Dr. Wesbrook com-<lb/>
pile the available evidence with regard to legislative measures upon<lb/>
which various health boards are now operating. Further, it was<lb/>
planned to have the evidence along these lines summarized in such<lb/>
form as to be of ready assistance in discussing this subject with the<lb/>
view to outlining improvements. In carrying out these arrangements<lb/>
it has been found that the subdivisions of this topic overlapped very<lb/>
considerably, and in fact it became necessary for Dr. Leal to consider<lb/>
it as a whole. The committee feels much obligated to Drs. Leal and<lb/>
Wesbrook for the information which they have secured and prepared<lb/>
in summarized form for presentation to this meeting.</p>
<p>In the field of water purification and sewage disposal the leading<lb/>
evidence stands now in substantially the same form as was the case a<lb/>
year ago. The intervening period has been chiefly characterized in<lb/>
<pb n="347" id="f02535353"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
347<lb/>
connection with water purification by actual construction work on a<lb/>
much larger scale than has been the case hitherto in this country.<lb/>
While the past year is notable for the application of principles pre-<lb/>
viously developed, there have been a number of important studies<lb/>
under way with especial reference to the preliminary clarification of<lb/>
turbid waters and to the removal of color, tastes and odors. The<lb/>
results of these investigations, however, are not yet available.</p>
<p>Dr. John L. Leal of Paterson, N. J., member of the Committee on<lb/>
the Pollution of Public Water Supplies, submitted a report prepared<lb/>
by himself, dealing with the legal status of water pollution. (See<lb/>
page 103.)</p>
<p>DR. F. F. WESBROOK, Minneapolis, Minn.--At the time when the<lb/>
work was originally assigned I had considerable amount of work to<lb/>
do, which was found to be included in Dr. Leal's report. I wish to<lb/>
ask that Dr. Leal be given full time and I will forego any remarks<lb/>
which I have to make on the subject. In making this suggestion I<lb/>
appreciate the value of what Dr. Leal has summarized.</p>
<p>DR. H. M. BRACKEN, Minneapolis, Minn.--Mr. President, I would<lb/>
like to make a motion. Mr. Fuller referred to having the death rate<lb/>
statistics for typhoid fever in cities having a population of 30,000 or<lb/>
more. I move you that the Publication Committee be urged to em-<lb/>
body those statistics in the report of this committee of which Mr.<lb/>
Fuller is Chairman.</p>
<p>The motion was seconded by Dr. Montgomery. Carried.</p>
<p>Dr. C. P. Wilkinson of New Orleans, La., Chairman of the Com-<lb/>
mittee on Etiology of Yellow Fever, reported as follows:</p>
<p>As acting Chairman of that committee, I have no report to make.<lb/>
The former Chairman, Dr. Horlbeck, recently deceased, had accumu-<lb/>
lated a large amount of data and promised us an interesting report.<lb/>
Owing to his lamentable death this report has not been presented,<lb/>
but I will endeavor to secure the data from his relatives so that it may<lb/>
be printed.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT: The Chair will appoint Dr. Wilkinson Chairman<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">pro tem.</hi> of that committee in consequence of the death of Dr. Horl-<lb/>
beck.</p>
<p>Dr. H. W. Hill of Boston, Mass., read a paper prepared by Dr.<lb/>
Alvah H. Doty, Health Officer, Port of New York, entitled &ldquo;Practical<lb/>
Discussion of Yellow Fever.&rdquo; (See page 134.)</p>
<p>Dr. Walter Reed, Surgeon, U. S. A., followed with a paper on<lb/>
&ldquo;The Prevention of Yellow Fever.&rdquo; (See page 113.)</p>
<p>On motion, an adjournment was taken to 3 p. m.</p>
<pb n="348" id="f02535354"/>
<p>348<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p>SECOND DAY--AFTERNOON SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association reassembled at 3 p. m., and was called to order by<lb/>
the President.</p>
<p>The Secretary announced that the Executive Committee had con-<lb/>
sidered the resolution that was handed in with reference to the general<lb/>
subject of Tuberculosis and would report back as a substitute the<lb/>
following resolutions and recommend their adoption:</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That notwithstanding the advances of sanitary science<lb/>
the mortality from tuberculosis continues to be appalling. It has<lb/>
been demonstrated that by the application of proper measures this<lb/>
mortality may be diminished rapidly and to a great degree. There-<lb/>
fore, every effort should be made by sanitarians to carry into effect all<lb/>
reasonable methods which have been shown by experience and re-<lb/>
search to be efficacious towards this end.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That the increase of tuberculosis in cattle and swine, as<lb/>
shown by investigations of recent years and by meat inspection sta-<lb/>
tistics, is a serious matter from a commercial as well as sanitary point<lb/>
of view, and calls for more systematic attention from those responsible<lb/>
for the integrity of the food supply and for the protection of the public<lb/>
health.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That this Association is of the opinion that sufficient facts<lb/>
have not been offered by Professor Koch or other investigators to<lb/>
prove that human and bovine tuberculosis are different diseases; it is<lb/>
further of the opinion that the variability under different environment<lb/>
common to microorganisms may, on further investigation, be found<lb/>
sufficient to account for the differences that have been noted, and that<lb/>
the germs of these diseases may yet be proved to be closely allied or<lb/>
identical. Irrespective of the question of the communicability of<lb/>
bovine tuberculosis to man, the inspection of animals and premises is<lb/>
absolutely necessary in order:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. That the meat and milk of animals suffering from this and other<lb/>
constitutional diseases be not used as human food;</item>
<item>2. That the sanitary condition of dairies, stables, etc., as regards<lb/>
cleanliness, water supply and ventilation may be maintained;</item>
<item>3. That the health of dairymen and other handlers be closely<lb/>
supervised to prevent the spread of diphtheria, scarlet fever, human<lb/>
tuberculosis, etc., through the milk supply.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That this Association, while desiring to express its posi-<lb/>
tive opinion as to the importance of dealing with animals and their<lb/>
products as indicated in the preceding resolutions, does, at the same<lb/>
time, insist upon the necessity for dealing with the still greater dan-<lb/>
gers now universally recognized, of the transmission of tuberculosis<lb/>
from one person to another by continued personal association through<lb/>
inhalation of the air of infected living rooms, the contamination of<lb/>
clothing, handkerchiefs and similar objects with sputum and other<lb/>
secretions and would therefore urgently recommend that munici-<lb/>
palities adopt regulations, as follows:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Against expectoration on pavements and in other public places.<lb/>
<pb n="349" id="f02535355"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
349</item>
<item>2. For the compulsory notification by physicians of cases of tuber-<lb/>
culosis in order that literature may be supplied to householders and<lb/>
municipal aid given where necessary to lessen the dangers to the fami-<lb/>
lies of infected persons.</item>
<item>3. For the establishment of municipal sanatoria for the benefit of<lb/>
persons and families of limited means.</item>
<item>4. For the regular inspection of tenements, factories, workshops,<lb/>
schools and other public institutions to promote cleanliness, ventila-<lb/>
tion and other sanitary conditions.&rdquo;</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>It was moved by Dr. Gihon that the resolutions be adopted. Sec-<lb/>
o0nded and carried.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--The Chair will announce the appointment of<lb/>
Major W. C. Gorgas as a member of the Advisory Council, represent-<lb/>
ing the Government of the Island of Cuba.</p>
<p>Dr. A. N. Bell of Brooklyn, N. Y., forwarded to the Association a<lb/>
paper entitled, &ldquo;Fomites and Yellow Fever.&rdquo; As Dr. Bell was not<lb/>
present, his paper was read by title. (See page 144.)</p>
<p>Dr. W. C. Gorgas of Havana, Cuba, contributed a paper entitled,<lb/>
&ldquo;Results of Sanitation of Yellow Fever in Havana, Cuba, Based on<lb/>
the Theory that the Stegomyia Fasciata is the Only Means of Com-<lb/>
munication of Yellow Fever.&rdquo; (See page 130.)</p>
<p>Dr. Eduardo Lic&eacute;aga, President of the Superior Board of Health<lb/>
of Mexico, Mexico City, presented a paper entitled, &ldquo;Tenth Report<lb/>
on the Cases of Yellow Fever which have been Observed on the two<lb/>
Coasts of the Mexican Republic from the 17th of September, 1900, to<lb/>
the 31st of August, 1901.&rdquo; (See page 152.)<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>DISCUSSION OF THE PAPER OF DRS. REED AND GORGAS.</p>
<p>DR. FELIX FORMENTO, New Orleans, La.--I listened with the<lb/>
greatest pleasure to the papers of Drs. Reed and Gorgas, and I thank<lb/>
them very much. It will be to a great many a revelation. No one<lb/>
admires more than I do the immense progress in sanitary matters in<lb/>
Havana since the American occupation, and hope what I will say will<lb/>
not be taken and cannot be taken as an unfair criticism. All honor<lb/>
to the one who was the first to advance the theory that yellow fever<lb/>
was communicated by mosquitos, and to you, gentlemen, who have<lb/>
demonstrated it. The result of these experiments in my mind is this:<lb/>
That it has been proven without a doubt that a certain mosquito is a<lb/>
carrier of yellow fever, which is thus communicated from man to man.<lb/>
Does this mean to say that there is no other way of communicating<lb/>
the disease? Is the mosquito the only agent by which yellow fever<lb/>
can be communicated? I beg to say that I think it is not the only<lb/>
means of communication of the disease. The experiments which<lb/>
<pb n="350" id="f02535356"/>
350<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
have been made on a few subjects are certainly of great importance,<lb/>
and prove that the mosquito transmits the disease. Had these experi-<lb/>
ments been repeated outside of the yellow fever country and where<lb/>
there could be no other possible suspicion of communication they<lb/>
would have had still more weight. For instance, if an infected mos-<lb/>
quito was carried to New York, and an experiment made at New<lb/>
York, outside of all local influence, and gave the same results, it<lb/>
would add a great deal to the experiments already made, which, how-<lb/>
ever, I accept as conclusive. It is not, however, for me the only<lb/>
method. How simple would the problem be if the disease could dis-<lb/>
appear by exterminating the mosquito. I am certain there is an<lb/>
analogy between this disease and tuberculosis, which we studied yes-<lb/>
terday. We should not by receiving the new discovery throw away<lb/>
at once as worthless the experience of centuries. There are many<lb/>
real examples of the transmission of yellow fever by fomites. I will<lb/>
give you one or two instances. Yellow fever broke out in Madrid a<lb/>
few years ago in a house where a trunk had arrived from Cuba, which<lb/>
had been closed for several months, and which belonged to an officer<lb/>
who had died in Havana. Two or three days after the trunk was<lb/>
opened well authenticated cases of yellow fever were discovered in<lb/>
the house. Could mosquitos have lived three or four months in that<lb/>
trunk? The length of life of the mosquito is said to be five days<lb/>
when enclosed in a box with no dampness or humidity. That is one<lb/>
case which cannot be explained by the mosquito theory.</p>
<p>How do you explain this other fact, just as remarkable? During<lb/>
the occupation of Mexico by the French a few years ago, a brig left a<lb/>
Mexican port for Brest in the north of France, where there are no<lb/>
mosquitos. During the voyage there occurred several deaths from<lb/>
yellow fever. They arrived at their destination, and before they<lb/>
landed, while in the port, the boat was fumigated and disinfected and<lb/>
it was noticed a few days after that workingmen who had no direct<lb/>
communication with the ship but who worked within a short distance,<lb/>
on the wharf, were taken down with yellow fever. They had no<lb/>
communication with the ship, but there was a current of air blowing<lb/>
in that direction. Two, I think, died. The others recovered and<lb/>
there were no other cases. And the epidemics of Cadiz, Barcelona<lb/>
and Livorno (1821)! Were they also due to mosquitos?</p>
<p>Therefore, I say that while admitting the possibility of the trans-<lb/>
mission of yellow fever by the mosquito we still admit its transmission<lb/>
by fomites. We should not, all at once, forget everything we have<lb/>
learned and known for centuries.</p>
<p>&check;</p>
<p>DR. EUGENE WASDIN, Buffalo, N. Y.--The words of Dr. Formento<lb/>
have given me the cue as to what I desire to say upon this question.</p>
<pb n="351" id="f02535357"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
351</p>
<p>To my mind there is a cloudiness about it which depends upon the<lb/>
fact that we have lost sight of the organism which produces the<lb/>
disease. The fact that Dr. Reed states that the organism has not yet<lb/>
been discovered does not make that true. The organism has been<lb/>
discovered, and it is not inconsistent with Dr. Reed's demonstration<lb/>
of the transmission of the disease by the mosquito, to accept the<lb/>
organism of Sanarelli as the cause of yellow fever. The real reason<lb/>
of this obscurity is that he has ignored the peculiarities of this organ-<lb/>
ism, an organism capable of giving rise to two developments, one<lb/>
extremely toxic, and the other of less toxicity but of marked septic<lb/>
power, and the diseases produced by the stegomyia are simply the<lb/>
septic types of the disease from the <hi rend="italic">convection</hi> of this bacillus into the<lb/>
circulation.</p>
<p>Yellow fever can be produced naturally by the entrance of this<lb/>
bacillus into the system <hi rend="italic">per vias naturales</hi>, and the passage of the<lb/>
organism into the blood is followed by the septic symptoms charac-<lb/>
teristic of the disease.</p>
<p>The cause of the disease, as I have said the bacillus icteroides, has<lb/>
been thoroughly experimented with, and the results demonstrate its<lb/>
etiologic value. This can all be done over again, and I guarantee that<lb/>
every observation made by the Commission of the Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service can be refulfilled.</p>
<p>Every postulate of Koch has been fulfilled, and more than that the<lb/>
organism has given rise to yellow fever in animals in epidemic form<lb/>
in the same way as we have found it to do in man.</p>
<p>The most important point before you is that of the possibility of<lb/>
the carriage of the bacillus in fomites. Dr. Formento has just<lb/>
declared that he believes that the disease can be conveyed in fomites,<lb/>
and so do I believe it, from the indubitable cases on record as derived<lb/>
from this source.</p>
<p>As to the influence of temperature in this disease, I will say that<lb/>
the bacillus icteroides has a characteristic entirely different from that<lb/>
of any organism which I have studied, in that it is quickly attenuated<lb/>
by exposure to cold. It will produce yellow fever at 62&deg;-65&deg; Fahr.,<lb/>
but it takes twice the length of time to produce the results at that<lb/>
temperature as at 75&deg;-80&deg; Fahr., while at 42&deg; Fahr., the frost line, the<lb/>
organism does not produce the disease at all from its attenuation by<lb/>
cold, nor does reheating the germ itself after such exposure to cold<lb/>
revive its power, as shown by Dr. Reed's experiments.</p>
<p>I will here make use of Dr. Reed's chart showing the influence of<lb/>
the temperature upon the mosquito, which will sting, and breed and<lb/>
transmit the disease <hi rend="italic">only</hi> when the temperature is considerably above<lb/>
42&deg; Fahr., or the frost line, since at this temperature the mosquito<lb/>
<pb n="352" id="f02535358"/>
352<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
becomes benumbed. At higher temperatures, say 62&deg; or 65&deg;, the<lb/>
mosquito, he says, shows a more pronounced power to transmit the<lb/>
disease, and at 75&deg; to 80&deg;, or a summer temperature, this transmission<lb/>
is most perfect, the disease taking place usually within twelve days<lb/>
after the sting of the mosquito.</p>
<p>It is plain that Dr. Reed's temperature chart for the mosquito cor-<lb/>
responds accurately with the facts of the attenuation of the bacillus<lb/>
icteroides as I have demonstrated them to the satisfaction of some of<lb/>
the best observers at the Pasteur Institute in Paris; and these facts<lb/>
correspond to the clinical and natural characteristics of the disease as<lb/>
we know it at the bedside. Whether the stegomyia may breed or not<lb/>
breed, live or not live at the temperatures shown by Dr. Reed, I do<lb/>
not know; I only know that the bacillus icteroides reacts to tempera-<lb/>
ture changes in the same manner.</p>
<p>The question of quarantine which comes up very naturally is one<lb/>
of the most important that can occupy the attention of this august<lb/>
body. Shall we displace all our well tried and known methods of<lb/>
quarantine?</p>
<p>The failure of Dr. Reed to find the bacillus causing the disease in<lb/>
the cases he studied is no proof whatever of there being none. For<lb/>
years New Orleans, and the South, has been kept free from yellow<lb/>
fever by the exercise of our present methods of quarantine without<lb/>
any regard for the welfare of the mosquito, and although Dr. Reed<lb/>
has demonstrated to my mind that the disease may thus be transmit-<lb/>
ted, it is not the only way by which we can contract the disease, and<lb/>
when contracted from the mosquito I deem it but an artificial infec-<lb/>
tion such as we produce in animals in our laboratories, and as Dr.<lb/>
Reed has produced in man with his hypodermic syringe independent<lb/>
of the stegomyia.</p>
<p>DR. WALTER REED, U. S. A.--Will Dr. Wasdin please tell me in<lb/>
the transmission of malaria by the bite of the mosquito, whether that<lb/>
is also simply a laboratory disease?</p>
<p>DR. WASDIN.--As we know the cause of malaria and Dr. Reed says<lb/>
that we do not know the cause of this disease, I do not think the<lb/>
question a fair one, for there are certain natural conditions of disease,<lb/>
and if we get them confounded with the artificial conditions the con-<lb/>
fusion may be lasting. However, if a mosquito, bearing the sporo-<lb/>
z&ouml;ides of the plasmodium malari&aelig; in its body, should die and become<lb/>
macerated in the water of her habitat, and if these coccidia or spores<lb/>
should become liberated in the air or water, and be taken into the<lb/>
system, is there any evidence to show that such spores may not<lb/>
germinate in the tissues and produce the disease naturally?</p>
<pb n="353" id="f02535359"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
353</p>
<p>These spores are the ultimate facts, with which we are acquainted,<lb/>
of a bygone malarial fever; we know nothing of their further possible<lb/>
germination save through the proboscis of the stegomyia, nor of the<lb/>
possible higher animalcular life of which the malarial plasmodium<lb/>
may be only a cycle. The fact of injecting these spores makes the<lb/>
disease artificial.</p>
<p>Therefore, I would appeal, as an officer of the Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service who has served at the National quarantine stations, and has<lb/>
honestly done his duty in investigating this disease--I appeal to this<lb/>
Association against the proposition to modify our quarantine restric-<lb/>
tions, since it is not reasonable to accept the unproved dictum that<lb/>
yellow fever is transmitted solely by the stegomyia fasciata, if by so<lb/>
doing we displace the theory that has given us safety during all these<lb/>
years.</p>
<p>DR. MILTON J. ROSENAU, Washington, D. C.--I wish briefly to<lb/>
add my words of congratulation to those of the whole scientific world<lb/>
in praise of Dr. Reed and his colleagues, who, in my opinion, have<lb/>
given us a work which has not been equalled, as far as its benefits to<lb/>
the public health are concerned, since Jenner gave us vaccinia. The<lb/>
mosquito carries yellow fever. There may be other means of carrying<lb/>
it. I believe that we can, from a sanitary standpoint and from a public<lb/>
health standpoint, disregard other measures until they are proven.<lb/>
They have not yet been proven. I would like it distinctly under-<lb/>
stood that my views are personal, although I am a member of the<lb/>
Marine Hospital Service. This map is the &ldquo;proof of the pudding.&rdquo;<lb/>
We could not have a better argument than that, and I think all honor<lb/>
should be given to Major Gorgas for the brilliancy of the work which<lb/>
results in a diagram and figure like this.</p>
<p>I have only one fact to add to what has been presented today con-<lb/>
cerning the transmission of the disease. It has been a time honored<lb/>
custom to disinfect baggage in order to prevent the spread of this<lb/>
disease. Now, it is a great question whether it is necessary to disin-<lb/>
fect or treat baggage in any way in order to prevent the disease<lb/>
spreading. Dr. Reed has told us today that baggage may carry the<lb/>
mosquito for five days. Major Havard, quoting a letter of Dr.<lb/>
Harvey, told us how the mosquito has been carried from Neuvitas,<lb/>
Cuba, to New York, a period lasting about thirteen or fourteen days,<lb/>
and in the experiments which have been conducted with the mos-<lb/>
quito in the hygienic laboratory of the Marine Hospital Service in<lb/>
Washington during the summer months, we have often kept mosqui-<lb/>
tos in trunks, in order to prove this very question, for a period of ten<lb/>
days. The condition, as Major Reed has already pointed out, essen-<lb/>
tial to keep them alive longer than a few days, is water. It is not<lb/>
<pb n="354" id="f02535360"/>
354<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
necessary that water be present in the trunk, as such. Moisture is<lb/>
sufficient. In our particular experiments we put the mosquitos in a<lb/>
little pill box. We replaced the pasteboard lid with one of mosquito<lb/>
netting, and then wrapped this little box up in a damp handkerchief<lb/>
or a dry towel, and then packed it away in our trunk, under different<lb/>
degrees of temperature and moisture in order to see whether the<lb/>
mosquito would live any length of time. The evidence seems to be<lb/>
plain that a mosquito can travel in a trunk or box, and therefore there<lb/>
is a certain amount of danger in carrying mosquitos from Cuba to<lb/>
parts of this country in baggage. It is not more than five days from<lb/>
Havana to New Orleans by boat. Just how great this danger is I<lb/>
cannot say. However, we have here a scientific justification of the<lb/>
time honored custom of the disinfection of baggage, which experience<lb/>
has taught us for many years to be one of the means in our fight<lb/>
against the spread of yellow fever.</p>
<p>DR. WALTER REED, U. S. A., closing the discussion: I, for one,<lb/>
thoroughly sympathize with the position taken by Dr. Formento<lb/>
in this discussion. We must look at the situation in the light in<lb/>
which the physicians of New Orleans view this matter. As I stated,<lb/>
this morning, that city has had more deaths from yellow fever than<lb/>
any other city in the United States, and hence if we find that the gen-<lb/>
tlemen in New Orleans, while prepared to accept the theory of the<lb/>
transmissibility of yellow fever by mosquitos, are not willing to<lb/>
accept this as the only method of transmission, we should not be<lb/>
much surprised at their attitude. It is perfectly natural that gentle-<lb/>
men who come from a city, so afflicted as New Orleans has been,<lb/>
should be unwilling to accept the mosquito as the only means of<lb/>
transmission of this disease. We should not expect that their views<lb/>
would undergo, all at once, such a radical revolution and that they<lb/>
should abandon fomites as a means of transmission. We have ex-<lb/>
pected much criticism on their part, and we certainly cannot object<lb/>
to this. Let me say here, that we have always invited the fullest criti-<lb/>
cism of our work in Cuba. It was for this reason that, during the<lb/>
time these observations were being made, we requested the most<lb/>
expert physicians in Havana, including the officers of the Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service, who have done such excellent work in keeping<lb/>
yellow fever out of the United States, to visit our Experimental<lb/>
Station, and to see for themselves everything that we were doing, for<lb/>
we fully realized that if our work would not withstand the most<lb/>
searching criticism, it could have no real value.</p>
<p>Dr. Formento has given an instance of the importation of yellow<lb/>
fever into Spain by fomites. I dare say this is the epidemic of 1878<lb/>
in Madrid, to which several writers have made reference. If so, the<lb/>
<pb n="355" id="f02535361"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
355<lb/>
facts are about as follows: 19,000 soldiers returning from Cuba<lb/>
were disembarked at a Spanish port, 10,000 of these going direct to<lb/>
Madrid by rail. Sometime thereafter yellow fever began at a point in<lb/>
the city where a small detachment of soldiers had lodged. If fomites<lb/>
is responsible for the outbreak, what seems remarkable is that only<lb/>
one small detachment should have carried infected clothing out of ten<lb/>
thousand soldiers who reached Madrid and dispersed throughout the<lb/>
city. Does not this appear, to say the least, highly improbable? Is<lb/>
it not more reasonable to believe that a case of mild yellow fever was<lb/>
imported amongst the men of this small detachment? Certainly, if<lb/>
gentlemen still believe that fomites can carry yellow fever, they<lb/>
should bear in mind that we left no means untried in order to produce<lb/>
the disease in this way.</p>
<p>DR. WASDIN, Buffalo, N. Y.--Was the experiment with fomites<lb/>
carried on at the time of the year in which the bacillus icteroides is<lb/>
most active or absolutely inactive?</p>
<p>DR. WALTER REED.--I was going to reach Dr. Wasdin's objec-<lb/>
tions in a little while, but perhaps I had better answer him now. So<lb/>
far as bacillus icteroides is concerned, our observations have shown<lb/>
that this bacillus has nothing to do with the causation of yellow fever.<lb/>
This was clearly brought out in those cases of experimental yellow<lb/>
fever which were produced by the subcutaneous injection of blood.<lb/>
In these cases, as soon as we had injected a certain quantity of the<lb/>
blood of a patient having yellow fever, under the skin of the non-<lb/>
immune subject, we immediately thereafter drew a somewhat larger<lb/>
quantity of blood and transferred it to sterile bouillon, diluting it<lb/>
fifteen or twenty times. Now the very same blood that, thus injected,<lb/>
produced yellow fever in the non-immune subject and hence must<lb/>
have contained the specific agent of the disease, did not contain<lb/>
bacillus icteroides, as shown by its failure to appear in any of our<lb/>
culture media. Bacillus icteroides is not a difficult organism to grow<lb/>
on our laboratory media and should not, therefore, be hard to isolate<lb/>
when present in the blood, Dr. Wasdin to the contrary notwithstand-<lb/>
ing. It seems to me a waste of time, with all due respect to Dr.<lb/>
Wasdin, who has labored so hard over this problem, to longer con-<lb/>
sider this bacillus as the cause of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Although we worked at the season of the year when yellow fever<lb/>
was on the decline in Havana, we took means in our infected clothing<lb/>
building, through artificial heat, to keep the temperature at an aver-<lb/>
age of nearly 80&deg; F. Not only that, we also kept the atmosphere<lb/>
moist. We never allowed sunlight to enter the building, and yet not<lb/>
one of the seven non-immunes who slept in this house and in the very<lb/>
<pb n="356" id="f02535362"/>
356<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
garments worn by yellow fever patients, during a period of sixty-five<lb/>
nights, contracted the disease. During this same period we were<lb/>
producing yellow fever at the ordinary temperature of the outside air<lb/>
by the bites of infected mosquitos, and the disease was still continuing<lb/>
in Havana.</p>
<p>Now, gentlemen, when you speak of fomites as a means of trans-<lb/>
mission and of the danger of a yellow fever patient infecting his bed-<lb/>
ding or clothing, you should not forget that yellow fever is such a<lb/>
 peculiar disease, that while a patient can infect his clothing in New<lb/>
Orleans, he cannot do so at Asheville, N. C., or at Atlanta, Ga., even<lb/>
though he die with black vomit! Perhaps some one present can<lb/>
explain why. In Philadelphia towards the close of the great epi-<lb/>
demics of 1793 and 1798, prior to the days when disinfectants were<lb/>
used, one could hardly say how many tons of infected bedding and<lb/>
clothing must have been contained in the houses of that city; and yet<lb/>
with the advent of cold weather yellow fever rapidly subsided,<lb/>
although there still remained such an abundance of fomites. Did<lb/>
the advent of frost so promptly disinfect the fomites or did it drive<lb/>
away the infected mosquitos?</p>
<p>There is one other point to which I would like to invite your atten-<lb/>
tion; it is this; whenever a case of yellow fever arises as the result of<lb/>
supposed exposure to fomites, the case develops promptly, that is<lb/>
after a few days, corresponding to the short period of incubation of<lb/>
this disease; but, on the other hand, when an individual sick with<lb/>
yellow fever enters a town, where the conditions are favorable for the<lb/>
propagation of the disease, a second case does not occur until after a<lb/>
considerable period--two to three weeks. I need hardly add that this<lb/>
interval corresponds to the mosquito interval, as our observations<lb/>
have shown.</p>
<p>DR. FELIX FORMENTO, New Orleans, La.--Do you consider the<lb/>
mosquito as the only means of transmission of yellow fever?</p>
<p>DR. REED.--Yes. I do not believe that nature works in two such<lb/>
radically different ways as would be required in the transmission of<lb/>
yellow fever by the bite of the mosquito and by contact with fomites.<lb/>
Moreover, the transmission of the disease by the mosquito meets<lb/>
every requirement of the case, whereas its propagation by fomites, or<lb/>
by other means, is vulnerable at every point.</p>
<p>As regards the danger of importing infected mosquitos in baggage,<lb/>
to which Dr. Rosenau has given his assent, based on certain obser-<lb/>
vations that he has made, let me say that the conditions under which<lb/>
Dr. Rosenau kept his insects in trunks are such as would not occur in<lb/>
the ordinary transmission of baggage. His observations are of inter-<lb/>
<pb n="357" id="f02535363"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
357<lb/>
est as bearing on the length of life of this mosquito under certain<lb/>
conditions, but it must not be forgotten that Dr. Rosenau was careful<lb/>
to supply his insects with water by means of a moistened handker-<lb/>
chief wrapped around his pill-boxes; and to insure access to this water<lb/>
by a single layer of mosquito netting placed between the insects and<lb/>
the wet handkerchief. In other words, Dr. Rosenau not only pro-<lb/>
tected his insects from injury but supplied them with the moisture<lb/>
necessary to keep them alive. But when one packs his trunk, he<lb/>
generally packs it with dry articles of clothing and he does not put his<lb/>
mosquitoes in pill-boxes nor provide water for them in transit. In<lb/>
our own experiments, the mosquitos were placed in large glass jars,<lb/>
covered with mosquito-netting, after having been permitted to fill<lb/>
themselves with blood. If under these favorable conditions, with<lb/>
plenty of air and facilities for exercise, they are all dead by the expira-<lb/>
tion of the fifth or beginning of the sixth day, we can hardly believe<lb/>
that they would survive so long when packed amongst articles of<lb/>
clothing and subjected to the rude handling of baggage. It is be-<lb/>
cause of the frailty of this insect and of its need for water, that we do<lb/>
not consider its importation in baggage as a source of danger.</p>
<p>Mr. Rudolph Hering, C. E., New York City, Chairman of the<lb/>
Committee on Disposal of Refuse Materials, made the following<lb/>
report: (See page 184.)</p>
<p>DISCUSSION ON MR. HERING'S REPORT.</p>
<p>DR. SAMUEL H. DURGIN, Boston, Mass.--I cannot help expressing<lb/>
a little surprise that at the end of so many years of investigation we<lb/>
cannot have something more definite as a conclusion. The country<lb/>
is looking for these conclusions from scientific sanitary bodies.<lb/>
Municipalities are impatiently waiting for these conclusions. I would<lb/>
like to ask the chairman of this committee whether or not it is a fact<lb/>
that two or three main questions involved have not been already<lb/>
regarded as fairly settled. First, we have the two systems, the reduc-<lb/>
tion system and the cremation system. I would like to ask the<lb/>
chairman if it is not a fact under his investigations and observations<lb/>
that the reduction system is one which always offends the sense of<lb/>
the people near it and whether it is not a very offensive process in<lb/>
every instance. I would like an answer, yes or no, to that.</p>
<p>MR. RUDOLPH HERING, New York City.--Mr. Chairman, this<lb/>
question cannot be answered by yes or no. If we had an ideal system<lb/>
we might possibly answer it.</p>
<p>DR. DURGIN.--Have you found any reduction process that is not a<lb/>
nuisance to the neighborhood?</p>
<pb n="362" id="f02535368"/>
<p>362<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p>SECOND DAY--EVENING SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association was called to order at 8 p. m. by the President,<lb/>
Dr. Benjamin Lee of Philadelphia.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--The first paper of the evening session is the<lb/>
report of the Committee on the Cause, Prevention and Duration of<lb/>
Infectious Diseases, by Dr. A. Walter Suiter, Chairman, Herkimer,<lb/>
N. Y. Dr. Suiter, however, has offered to give place to Dr. Hibbert<lb/>
W. Hill of Boston, Mass., who desires to make his report on &ldquo;Disin-<lb/>
fectants and Disinfection.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. Hibbert Hill, Boston, Mass., Chairman, then read the report<lb/>
of the Committee on &ldquo;Disinfectants and Disinfection.&rdquo; (See page<lb/>
244.)</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--As the paper of Dr. Suiter is somewhat on the<lb/>
same line as the report of this Committee, the Chair would suggest<lb/>
that discussion of the report just read be postponed until after the<lb/>
reading of Dr. Suiter's report.</p>
<p>Dr. A. Walter Suiter of Herkimer, N. Y., Chairman, then read the<lb/>
report of the Committee on the Cause, Prevention and Duration of<lb/>
Infectious Diseases. (See page 227.)</p>
<p>DR. A. W. SUITER, Herkimer, N. Y.--I have in my possession a<lb/>
few memoranda which have been presented by individual members of<lb/>
this Committee. Three of them are in the possession of the Secretary<lb/>
and are not now at hand. If there is time and patience on the part<lb/>
of those present, I will undertake to read these articles. (Reading<lb/>
memoranda.)</p>
<p>That concludes the memoranda that I have in my possession. As<lb/>
to those in the possession of the Secretary, I move you that they,<lb/>
together with these memoranda, be referred to the Committee on<lb/>
Publication.</p>
<p>The motion was seconded. Carried.</p>
<p>It was moved and seconded that a vote of thanks be extended to<lb/>
Dr. Suiter for his pains in preparing the paper just read. The motion<lb/>
was carried.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--If there is no discussion, I would like to say that<lb/>
a paper was passed which had a place on the program, and the dis-<lb/>
cussion which took place this afternoon on the Disposal of Refuse<lb/>
would scarcely be complete without the presentation of this paper.<lb/>
It is entitled, &ldquo;Refuse Disposal in the District of Columbia,&rdquo; by Dr.<lb/>
William C. Woodward, Health Officer of the District of Columbia.</p>
<pb n="363" id="f02535369"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
363</p>
<p>It was moved and seconded that Dr. Woodward's paper be read by<lb/>
title and printed in the proceedings. Carried.</p>
<p>On motion, the convention then adjourned until Thursday morn-<lb/>
ing, at 10 a. m.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 19, THIRD DAY--MORNING SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association was called to order by the President at 10 a. m.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--This being the day which the National and State<lb/>
authorities<unclear>.</unclear> have set apart as a day of humiliation in commemoration<lb/>
of our late lamented President, the ordinary business of the Associa-<lb/>
tion will be entirely given up. There are, however, one or two mat-<lb/>
ters which could be properly attended to, which will take very little<lb/>
time, before the resolutions are presented.</p>
<p>The Secretary presented a number of applications for membership,<lb/>
which having been acted upon favorably by the Executive Committee,<lb/>
were recommended to the Association for election.</p>
<p>DR. SAMUEL H. DURGIN.--I move that the Secretary be instructed<lb/>
to cast the ballot of the Association in favor of the election of these<lb/>
applicants. The motion was seconded and carried.</p>
<p>The Secretary then cast the ballot of the Association for the elec-<lb/>
tion of the new members whose names had been read, and they were<lb/>
declared elected.</p>
<p>Dr. Albert L. Gihon stated that it was customary to refer the report<lb/>
of the Treasurer to an Auditing Committee, and moved that this<lb/>
action be taken.</p>
<p>The motion was seconded. Carried.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--The Chair will name Drs. Bryce and Durgin as<lb/>
an Auditing Committee to report at a subsequent session.</p>
<p>The Chair will call upon Dr. Holton as a member of the Committee<lb/>
on Resolutions to present the resolutions of respect to the memory<lb/>
of our late President.</p>
<p>Dr. Holton then read the resolutions prepared by the Committee,<lb/>
as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your Committee appointed to draft resolutions regarding the<lb/>
death of President McKinley beg leave to submit the following reso-<lb/>
lutions:</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That the American Public Health Association has received<lb/>
with deep sorrow the intelligence of the sudden and tragic death of the<lb/>
beloved President of the United States.</p>
<pb n="364" id="f02535370"/>
<p>364<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That in President McKinley we recognize the highest<lb/>
type of modern civilization, a patriotic citizen, a Christian gentleman,<lb/>
and a sagacious and enlightened statesman.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That we respectfully extend our heartfelt sympathy to<lb/>
Mrs. McKinley in this her hour of bereavement, and to other members<lb/>
of the family.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That a copy of these resolutions be spread upon the rec-<lb/>
ords of this Association and given to the press for publication.&rdquo;</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<item>BENJAMIN LEE,</item>
<item>WILLIAM BAILEY.</item>
<item>HENRY D. HOLTON.</item>
<item>FREDERICK MONTIZAMBERT.</item>
<item>E. LIC&Eacute;AGA.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>It was moved by Dr. Durgin that the resolutions be adopted.<lb/>
Seconded.</p>
<p>The Chair would suggest that some members would possibly like<lb/>
to express themselves in regard to these resolutions, and I will call<lb/>
upon Ex-President Bailey.</p>
<p>DR. WILLIAM BAILEY.--Mr. President, and members of the Asso-<lb/>
ciation: I feel words must fail me to express the depth of sorrow<lb/>
that we all feel. Yet it is a sad pleasure to me to speak a word on<lb/>
this occasion. As expressed I think well in our resolutions, we recog-<lb/>
nize in the late President all that is best in modern civilization. In<lb/>
every relation in life, as a statesman, as a soldier, and as a Christian,<lb/>
and as to his family relations, we all doff our hats when we contem-<lb/>
plate the loyalty of this man to his afflicted wife.</p>
<p>Coming as I do from the South I would like simply to call attention<lb/>
to the fact that no man since the Civil War has done so much as<lb/>
President McKinley to unify this country of ours. Without partisan<lb/>
bias when it came to the Spanish War we found that a Wheeler, a<lb/>
Lee and a Breckenridge were his prominent agents in the carying on<lb/>
of this war, so that to-day in the South as never since 1860 have we<lb/>
had such feeling toward a President or towards the flag of our coun-<lb/>
try. So for this we may be thankful for this man.</p>
<p>The very heinous crime precludes almost its mention and yet allow<lb/>
me to express in this presence that this country since its organization<lb/>
has always been open to receive everybody from other climes who<lb/>
desire to come to us. While that is still our wish for those who come<lb/>
for the betterment of themselves and mankind and who desire to<lb/>
become Americanized, adopting the principles of this Government as<lb/>
their own, yet let me say that the day has come when it must be<lb/>
expressed that we have no place in this country for those who come<lb/>
with the view of promulgating principles that are so much at variance<lb/>
with the principles upon which this Government is founded, and that<lb/>
<pb n="365" id="f02535371"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
365<lb/>
there is no longer a place in this country for such spirits to come and<lb/>
concoct their damnable schemes.</p>
<p>Simply then, and briefly, I would urge the adoption of these resolu-<lb/>
tions in their full spirit, that we do recognize an irreparable loss, that<lb/>
we recognize in this man one worthy of our deepest love, and I am<lb/>
sure that we likewise congratulate ourselves and feelingly return<lb/>
thanks for the expressions that have come to us from our sister<lb/>
nations and I might say from the world. (Applause.)</p>
<p>DR. C. P. WILKINSON, New Orleans, La.--Mr. Chairman, in sec-<lb/>
onding the resolution I voice the sentiments of the people of the<lb/>
extreme South, the section from which I come. We were recently<lb/>
favored by a visit from our now deceased President. Our people<lb/>
turned towards him with smiles and extended hands. They held out<lb/>
arms full of flowers and rent the air with their cheers for the man, the<lb/>
citizen and the President. The same bells that then rang out p&aelig;ans<lb/>
for that man are now tolling dirges as his body lies just about ready<lb/>
to be consigned to the tomb. There is no section of the country that<lb/>
feels more acutely and more bitterly the killing of President McKinley<lb/>
than does the South. He was their friend. In the killing of Presi-<lb/>
dent Lincoln the South was visited with dire punishment for any<lb/>
hand she might have had in that assassination; and today the South<lb/>
mourns the loss of this President who was the first since that time to<lb/>
extend open fellowship and invite us to join in the house of our<lb/>
fathers in the Union. Today, sir, we find no place for any reflections<lb/>
upon the previous history of any party or any man in that party, but<lb/>
we do recognize the onward march of William McKinley towards<lb/>
prosperity, peace and protection to every citizen of the land regardless<lb/>
of State or sectional birth. We mourn his loss today more than we<lb/>
can express, and on behalf of the South I join in the deepest regret<lb/>
that we have to pass these resolutions; with the most heartfelt earn-<lb/>
estness in the truth of every word that they express. (Applause.)</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--The Dominion of Canada has already in words<lb/>
most fittingly spoken and full of the deepest sympathy, expressed<lb/>
itself on this question. It would not be inappropriate, however, if at<lb/>
this meeting a further expression should be presented, and I will call<lb/>
upon Dr. Bryce for a word.</p>
<p>DR. BRYCE, Toronto, Can.--Mr. President, Ladies and Gentlemen:<lb/>
It is appropriate that a representative from the Dominion of Canada<lb/>
should have expressed in open meeting here the feelings of admiration<lb/>
for the late President which we all hold and should likewise have<lb/>
expressed feelings of regret for his untimely decease.</p>
<pb n="366" id="f02535372"/>
<p>366<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p>At the request of your Executive Committee and your Chairman I<lb/>
am asked to add a few words in connection with this expression of<lb/>
condolence on the part of the Association in the resolution which has<lb/>
just been read. The death of the President is one which must be<lb/>
regretted not alone by the people of the United States, not alone by<lb/>
the people of Anglo-Saxon lineage, but by all the civilized peoples of<lb/>
the earth; but I suppose to no one does that death come nearer than<lb/>
to the people lying to the north, a people who are not only the same in<lb/>
birth and aspirations, but also the same in their daily relations, be-<lb/>
cause we are practically one with you, but especially because we see<lb/>
in the virtues of the life of the late President McKinley so many of<lb/>
those qualities which have been seen in our late Queen, a sort of load-<lb/>
star to draw every good Briton, and I will say every good citizen of the<lb/>
world, the highest sense, towards the ideal.</p>
<p>The fact that this Association is called upon to pass these resolu-<lb/>
tions has seemed to me an extremely appropriate thing, since the very<lb/>
aims and objects of this Association are to suppress those very irregu-<lb/>
larities, whether in society or not, which this sad circumstance has<lb/>
been an illustration of. Sad as the circumstance of the assassination<lb/>
is, it must come home to every one of us workers in the carrying out<lb/>
of the laws of the Almighty, as we understand them, to realize in it<lb/>
that it is one of the necessary results of an unalterable law, whether<lb/>
those catastrophes that we have seen striking society from time to<lb/>
time have affected some innocent person, some whole city, or some<lb/>
whole nation. To us, the work of regulating society comes as close<lb/>
as the regulating of an epidemic or of some catastrophe at sea through<lb/>
an imperfect vessel or some railway collison, which may be due to<lb/>
lack of knowledge of construction or lack of care in managing a train.<lb/>
When we point to the death of the President as an illustration of<lb/>
something, somewhere needing regulation, we feel that it devolves<lb/>
upon us not only to sympathize with the effects of such irregularity in-<lb/>
cident to the lack of harmony amongst the social elements, but points<lb/>
us still more, it seems to me, in the direction we have so long worked<lb/>
and impels us to work more earnestly and also shows us that in society<lb/>
we are subject to laws which are as unalterable as the movements of<lb/>
the planets, and that if we are ever to see evolved that harmony, which<lb/>
seems to be the purpose of the Creator, we will have to work along all<lb/>
the lines known to us whereby our labors shall go to make up the<lb/>
infinite harmony which are operant with the highest principles,<lb/>
whether of nature or of the Creator. I have only to add that I fully<lb/>
and heartily agree not only for myself but for my country in the reso-<lb/>
lutions which have been submitted.</p>
<pb n="367" id="f02535373"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS--TWENTY-NINTH ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
367</p>
<p>Dr. Eduardo Lic&eacute;aga of Mexico then spoke in Spanish, his re-<lb/>
marks being translated by Dr. Gihon. He said:</p>
<p>On the part of myself and my colleagues and my Government in<lb/>
Mexico, I desire to express our heartfelt participation in your sorrow.<lb/>
Referring to Dr. Bryce, I will say that he is practically one of the<lb/>
same people with yourselves and it would be natural for him to feel as<lb/>
you do, but the Mexican race is a different race, different people and<lb/>
speak a different language, but nevertheless our grief and sorrow are<lb/>
equally as profound as yours, and I desire you to feel that we are<lb/>
with you in all the sorrow that you feel yourselves. (Applause.)</p>
<p>The resolutions were adopted by a unanimous standing vote.</p>
<p>The Chairman announced that immediately upon adjournment the<lb/>
Advisory Council would hold a meeting, after which the Executive<lb/>
Committee would meet.</p>
<p>On motion, an adjournment was then taken until 10 o'clock, Friday<lb/>
morning.</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 20, FOURTH DAY--MORNING SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association reassembled at 10 a. m., and was called to order by<lb/>
the President.</p>
<p>The Secretary announced that the Executive Committee had<lb/>
recommended the adoption of the following resolution:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Executive Committee recommends the appointment of a<lb/>
special committee to prepare and publish, at an early date, a pamphlet<lb/>
for public circulation, containing the resolution of the Public Health<lb/>
Association in favor of the Army canteen, together with a concise<lb/>
statement of the data upon which this action was based, and definite<lb/>
references to the original sources from which such information is<lb/>
obtainable; such pamphlet to be issued in the name of the Associa-<lb/>
tion, and to be so prepared as to withstand keen and intelligent ex-<lb/>
amination.</p>
<p>This recommendation is made in view of the fact: (1) That an<lb/>
important function of this Association is to educate the public in<lb/>
matters of hygiene; (2) that the action above referred to is in disa-<lb/>
greement with the ideas of a very large number of good citizens;<lb/>
(3) that this is a possible opportunity of securing their understanding<lb/>
of our action, and, it is to be hoped, their intelligent co-operation in<lb/>
taking successive steps towards the betterment of existing condi-<lb/>
tions.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was moved and seconded that the resolution be adopted. Carried.</p>
<p>The Secretary then read the report of the Committee on Sanitary<lb/>
Aid Societies, as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Your Committee has been unable to wholly perfect any plan for<lb/>
the organization of sanitary aid societies, which could be submitted</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
