<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02645006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Military History of Major Walter Reed, [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Sternberg, George Miller</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02645006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1902-06-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Willets Point (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Harrisonburg (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Yuma (Calif.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Apache (Ariz.)</name>
<name type="place">Creedmoor (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Ontario (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort McHenry (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Omaha (Neb.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Omaha (Neb.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Sidney (Neb.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Robinson (Neb.)</name>
<name type="place">Mount Vernon Barracks (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Snelling (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">St. Paul (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Natural Bridge (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Principe (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Thomas (Ky.)</name>
<name type="place">Minneapolis (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">Tampa (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Indianapolis (Ind.)</name>
<name type="place">Buffalo (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington Barracks (Washington, D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Ann Arbor (Mich.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1902-06-02">June 2, 1902</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02645006</idno>
<title>Military History of Major Walter Reed, [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Surgeon General's Records listing military and personal history for Reed until June 2, 1902.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1902-06-02">
<head>Military History of Major Walter Reed, [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02645006"/>
<p>1.</p>
<p>To June 1902<lb/>
[Till death]<lb/>
<unclear>B</unclear><lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>MILITARY HISTORY of Major Walter Reed, Surgeon, U. S. Army, as<lb/>
far as shown by the records of the Surgeon General's Office.</p>
<p>-------------------------</p>
<p>Major Reed was appointed Assistant Surgeon, U. S. Army, with<lb/>
rank of 1st Lieutenant June 26, 1875; promoted Assistant Surgeon<lb/>
with the rank of Captain June 26, 1880; and Surgeon with the rank<lb/>
of Major December 4, 1893, and at the time of his death was first<lb/>
on the list of Majors in the Medical Department:</p>
<p>His record of service is as follows:</p>
<p>On duty at Willetn Point, N. Y., from July 23, 1875 to April 14, 1876;<lb/>
At General Recruiting Station, New York City, N. Y. Harrisonburg,<lb/>
Va., and accompanying Recruits to the Department of California, from<lb/>
April 15 to May 21, 1876;</p>
<p>In the Department of Arizona, from June 1, 1876 to May 10, 1880, dur-<lb/>
ing which period was at Fort Yuma, California, June 1 to August 5,<lb/>
1876;</p>
<p>Camp Apache, August 10, 1876 to May 10, 1880;</p>
<p>Awaiting orders and on leave of absence from May 10, 1880 to August<lb/>
31, 1880;</p>
<p>In the Department of the East, from September 1, 1880 to November<lb/>
17, 1882, during which period was on duty at Creedmoor, Long Island,<lb/>
with Rifle Team, September 1 to 18, 1880;</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02645008"/>
<p>2.</p>
<p>At Headquarters awaiting orders, September 19 to 23, 1880;</p>
<p>En route to and at Fort Ontario, N. Y., September 23, 1880 to Febru-<lb/>
ary 23, 1881;</p>
<p>At Fort McHenry, Maryland, and awaiting orders Feb. 24 to May 2, 1881;</p>
<p>At Washington Barracks, D. C. May 2, 1881 to November 17, 1882;</p>
<p>In the Department of the Platte, November 17, 1882 to July 31, 1887,<lb/>
during which period was on duty at Headquarters awaiting orders<lb/>
November 17, to December 4, 1882; On duty as Attending Surgeon Head-<lb/>
quarters Department of the Platte, Omaha, Nebraska, December 4, 1882<lb/>
to January 1, 1883;</p>
<p>At Fort Omaha, Nebraska, January 2 to October 4, 1883;</p>
<p>At Fort Sidney, Nebraska, October 5, 1883 to August 4, 1884;</p>
<p>At Fort Robinson, Nebraska, August 8, 1884 to July 31, 1887;</p>
<p>In the Department of the East, August 5, 1887 to October 31, 1891,<lb/>
during which period was on duty at Mt. Vernon Barracks, Alabama,<lb/>
August 5, 1887 to October 6, 1890;</p>
<p>At Baltimore, Maryland, as Attending Surgeon and Examiner of Recruits<lb/>
October 6, 1890 to October 31, 1891;</p>
<p>In the Department of Dakota from November 7, 1891 to August 31, 1893;<lb/>
during which time was on duty at Fort Snelling, Kinn., November 7,<lb/>
1891 to August 21, 1892; at Headquarters Department of Dakota, St.<lb/>
Paul, Minn., as Attending Surgeon and Examiner of Recruits, August 21,<lb/>
1892 to August 31, 1893;</p>
<p>In the office of the Surgeon General of the Army as Curator, Army<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02645007"/>
3.<lb/>
Medical Museum, from September 6, 1893 to November 23, 1902 and as<lb/>
Librarian in charge Library, Surgeon General's Office from November<lb/>
1, 1902 to November 23, 1902;</p>
<p>Was appointed a member of the Faculty of the Army Medical School in<lb/>
September 1893;</p>
<p>Member of the Army Medical Board at Washington, D. C., September 11,<lb/>
1893 to October 21, 1893 and October 1 to October 31, 1895, Septem-<lb/>
ber 23 to October 27, 1896, and September 27 to November 6, 1897,<lb/>
Member of Cholera hand Board May 2 to July 12, 1898;</p>
<p>On detached duty making inspections of Camps and Field Hospitals,<lb/>
August 1 to 8, 1898;</p>
<p>Member Typhoid Fever Board and to inspect certain Camps, August 20<lb/>
to September 18, 1898;</p>
<p>Member of board to investigate causes of Typhoid Fever, September<lb/>
25 to October 10, 1898;</p>
<p>Inspecting buildings at Natural Bridge, Va., October 18 to 25, 1898;</p>
<p>En route to and returning from inspection duty at Puerto Principe,<lb/>
Cuba, April 19 to May 9, 1899;</p>
<p>Detached duty at Fort Thomas, Ky., September 28 to 30, 1899;</p>
<p>Delegate to American Public Health Association at Minneapolis, Minn.,<lb/>
October 31 to November 3, 1899;</p>
<p>En route to and on duty at Tampa, Fla., and Havana, Cuba. On inves-<lb/>
tigation as to use of electrozone and germicide in Havana and return-<lb/>
ing March 7, 1900 to April 3, 1900;</p>
<pb n="4" id="f02645009"/>
<p>4.</p>
<p>Member of Board of Medical Officers at Camp Columbia, Cuba,<lb/>
for the purpose of pursuing scientific investigation with reference<lb/>
to infectious diseases prevalent in Island of Cuba, June 26 to July<lb/>
31, 1900.</p>
<p>En route to and on duty in Cuba investigating causes of Yellow Fever<lb/>
September 27 to October 13, 1900;</p>
<p>Delegate to American Public Health Association Indianapolis, Indiana,<lb/>
October 21 to 27, 1900.</p>
<p>On detached duty in Cuba investigating infectious diseases prevalent<lb/>
in the Island of Cuba, November 1, 1900 to February 12, 1901; during<lb/>
which period representied Medical Dept., of the Army at Pan American<lb/>
Medical Congress, Havana, Cuba, in February 1901;</p>
<p>Delegate to American Public Health Association, Buffalo, K. Y.,<lb/>
September 16 to 20, 1901;</p>
<p><hi>Died at U. S. Army General</hi> Hospital, Washington Barracks, D. C., at<lb/>
2 A. M. November 23, 1903 from appendicitis for which an operation<lb/>
was performed Monday <hi>the 17th instant</hi>.</p>
<p>Major Reed was born in Gloucester County, Va., September 13, 1851<lb/>
Graduated from the Medical Department, University of Virginia in<lb/>
1869 and Bellevue Hospital Medical College New York City, N. Y., 1872.<lb/>
Of Major Reed's work in the Medical Department and his scientific<lb/>
researches, it is probable a complete history can never be obtained.<lb/>
His eminence as a bacteriologist, and in practical hygiene as applied<lb/>
to military life (student of all forms of bacteria) led to his being<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02645010"/>
5.<lb/>
intrusted with special investigations, which were interrupted by his<lb/>
death, and which, it is now believed, will never be completed. He<lb/>
was regarded by his associates as a man who combined an unusual de-<lb/>
gree of scientific accuracy with calm judgment which rendered him<lb/>
invaluable in searching out the causes of epidemic diseases and trac-<lb/>
ing their progress.</p>
<p>In 1901 he began the investigation of the cause and the prev-<lb/>
alence of yellow fever, conducting his investigations at Quemados,<lb/>
near Havana, where he established headquarters and was given every<lb/>
facility for conducting his experiments.</p>
<p>The conditions in Cuba in 1901 were such as made the investiga-<lb/>
tions of Major Reed and his corps of assistants of special moment.<lb/>
An epidemic of yellow fever existed despite the efforts of the sani-<lb/>
tary experts, led by General Wood, who were endeavoring to stamp<lb/>
out the disease. The houses of persons infected were subjected to<lb/>
rigid disinfection. Furniture was destroyed and every possible pre-<lb/>
caution was taken to prevent the spread of the disease under the old<lb/>
treatment. Major Reed became convinced that proper sanitation was<lb/>
not all that was needed. He believed that some other agency than<lb/>
accumulations of filth was responsible for the spread of the dis-<lb/>
ease, and his attention was attracted to the fact that it took much<lb/>
longer for a house to become infected, than the usual time of incuba-<lb/>
tion. This suggested a biting insect as an intermediate host of the<lb/>
parasite, and he asked and promptly received from General Wood per-<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02645011"/>
6.<lb/>
mission to make experiments with mosquitoes, as the conveyers of<lb/>
yellow fever, and a liberal supply of money for these experiments. It<lb/>
was thus determined beyond question that through a certain species<lb/>
of mosquito the yellow fever germ was disseminated.</p>
<p>The degree of bachelor of arts was conferred on Major Reed by<lb/>
the Harvard University in June 1902, because, as President Eliot<lb/>
stated when the degree as awarded, Major Reed had demonstrated how<lb/>
to rid the world of yellow fever. About the same time the degree<lb/>
of master of arts was conferred upon Major Reed by the University of<lb/>
Michigan at Ann Arbor, Michigan.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
