<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02650001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Essay: Dr. Reed as a Medical Officer, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 31, 1902</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02650001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1902-12-31</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Arizona</name>
<name type="place">Dakota</name>
<name type="place">Nebraska</name>
<name type="place">Alabama</name>
<name type="place">Key West (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Yuma [s.l.]</name>
<name type="place">Camp Apache (Ariz.Territory)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1902-12-31">December 31, 1902</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02650001</idno>
<title>Essay: Dr. Reed as a Medical Officer, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 31, 1902</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean's remarks about Reed portray him as a great storyteller and as a doctor making heroic house-calls during his "Dakota winters".</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1902-12-31">
<head>Essay: Dr. Reed as a Medical Officer, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 31, 1902</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02650001"/>
<opener>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
MEMORIAL MEETING,<lb/>
UNDER THE AUSPICES OF THE<lb/>
MEDICAL SOCIETY OF THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA.<lb/>
IN HONOR OF<lb/>
Dr. Walter Reed, A. M., LL. D.,<lb/>
</opener>
<p>BORN SEPTEMBER 13, 1851.</p>
<p>DIED NOVEMBER 23, 1902.</p>
<p>INTRODUCTORY ADDRESS BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE SOCIETY,<lb/>
DR. SAMUEL S. ADAMS.</p>
<p>ADDRESSES: BY MEDICAL DIRECTOR ROBERT A. MARMION,<lb/>
U. S. NAVY; SURGEON J. R. KEAN, U. S. ARMY; PROFESSOR<lb/>
A. F. A. KING, PROFESSOR CH. W. STILES, GENERAL LEONARD<lb/>
WOOD, U. S. ARMY, AND PROFESSOR WM. H. WELCH.</p>
<p>LECTURE HALL OF THE GEORGETOWN LAW SCHOOL BUILDING.<lb/>
506 E STREET, N. W., WEDNESDAY EVENING, DECEMBER 31, 1902.<lb/>
AT 8.00 P. M. YOU ARE CORDIALLY INVITED TO BE PRESENT.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02650002"/>
<p>FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN</p>
<p>Dr Reed as a Medical Officer-<lb/>
J. R. Kean major Surg USA<lb/>
Dec 31, 1902-</p>
<p>In speaking of Dr. Reed as a Medical Officer we should consider especially<lb/>
that part of his career with which the members of this Society are least famil-<lb/>
iar, namely, from his entrance into the Army in 1875 to his assignment to duty<lb/>
in Washington in 1893. With the latter date began his career as a scientific<lb/>
man although much of his time during this last decade was given to Examining<lb/>
Boards and other work of a military rather than scientific character, and the<lb/>
race horse spent much time at the plough.</p>
<p>These 18 years of garrison duty were we may be sure not wasted, yet the<lb/>
official records tell but little of them. The records show 15 changes of<lb/>
station with 4 years in Arizona, 5 in the Department of the Platte, 2 in the<lb/>
Department of Dakota, 3 in the South, and 3 years in the East. There are a<lb/>
few brief commendations for professional zeal and devotion to his patients, and<lb/>
that is all.</p>
<p>The work of young Army Surgeons claims always little space in the gazettes<lb/>
or in the reports of Military Commanders, and in the '70's and '80's, the life<lb/>
was certainly not stimulating to intellectual effort.</p>
<p>The Surgeon shared with his comrades of the line, the tedium of long<lb/>
marches and the monotonous sameness of Arizona summers and Dakota winters.<lb/>
And those with whom bonne comaraderie outweighed studious industry shared also<lb/>
the afternoons of bottle-pool and beer, and the nightly seductions of draw<lb/>
poker. But for Medical Officers this life was redeemed by the study of our<lb/>
profession which was then beginning to broaden out from ancient channels into<lb/>
the full flood of recent progress, and it was saved from triviality by those<lb/>
stern responsibilities of life and death which practice brings to all physicians<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02650003"/>
2.<lb/>
To lesser minds the limitations of such a life might have been narrowing, but<lb/>
for the eager industry and professional devotion of a Reed they made the roots<lb/>
strike deep; and when we are surprised at the rapid growth and splendid fruit<lb/>
of his career as a scientist we must remember that in the post surgeon's un-<lb/>
marked life the seed was germinated and the roots were firmly set. But for the<lb/>
opportunities given him by his position in the Army, however distinguished he<lb/>
may have become in other ways, it is safe to say that the work with which his<lb/>
fame will always be inseparably connected would never have been accomplished<lb/>
by him. During this long apprenticeship he acquired too that perfect famil-<lb/>
iarity with the conditions and limitations of Army life which, combined with<lb/>
his scientific knowledge and sound judgment, made him the best sanitary inspec-<lb/>
tor in the Army, and the court of last resort on all sanitary questions.</p>
<p>I first learned to know Dr. Reed by reputation when in the Spring of '88<lb/>
I followed him in station at Fort Robinson, a two battalion post in the north-<lb/>
west corner of Nebraska. I learned much of his devotion to his patients, and<lb/>
their devotion to him was equally in evidence. The country about is thinly<lb/>
settled with families locally known as &ldquo;Grangers,&rdquo; who were attempting to sup-<lb/>
port themselves by farming in a grazing country where the rainfall was not<lb/>
sufficient for good crops except only about one year in three. The crop of<lb/>
babies, however, never failed, and the Klebs-Loeffler bacillus and the pneumo-<lb/>
coccus flourished perennially in their wretched cabins. To Reed's tender and<lb/>
generous spirit the call of these poor people never came in vain, and the trail<lb/>
was never so long or the night so dark as to deter him. In the winter these<lb/>
rides were really dangerous and a source of much uneasiness to his family and<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02650004"/>
3.<lb/>
friends for fear of his being overtaken by one of those blizzards in which the<lb/>
staunchest horse turns tail to the wind, and the most experienced frontiersman<lb/>
cannot see his way, and the danger to the lost traveler is greater than that<lb/>
of a battle.</p>
<p>Again we find him at Mount Vernon Barracks in Alabama, according to the<lb/>
official statement of his Commanding Officer, devoting himself with the same<lb/>
earnestness and patience to the sick of Geromino's band of Apaches, then held<lb/>
there as prisoners, and to the sick negroes of the surrounding country, as to<lb/>
his own patients in the garrison.</p>
<p>Of the first years of his service which he spent in Arizona I gained some<lb/>
knowledge when in the Summer of 1896 he came to Key West, my station at that<lb/>
time, to study the blood of variola, - there being an epidemic of small pox<lb/>
there at that time. All day he would sit over his microscope, but the even-<lb/>
ings we spent on the coolest corner of the porch looking out at the quiet<lb/>
tropical sea, while he told reminiscences, suggested it may be by the heat, of<lb/>
his service at Fort Yuma and Camp Apache. These stories were full of that<lb/>
humor which was so characteristic and so pleasing a trait of his daily conver-<lb/>
sation, and some of these were models of the short story. The history of<lb/>
Sally Ann a Gila monster, which the Chaplain captured in his kitchen, named<lb/>
after the two ladies of the post most conspicuous in church work, and under-<lb/>
took to tame, would have made a perfect magazine article just as Reed told it.<lb/>
His account of his Summer at Yuma, the hottest of Army posts, where the daily<lb/>
July maximum was from 112&deg; to 113&deg;, still brings back a clear cut picture to<lb/>
my memory, and I can see him with his messmate, a Captain of Infantry, who<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02650005"/>
<del>3.</del>4<lb/>
weighed 250 pounds, and the soldier, - or in Army parlance &ldquo;striker&rdquo; who filled<lb/>
the dual role of chef and butler. The Captain, a veritable Porthos, sat down<lb/>
to dinner in two garments, with a fan, a towel to wipe his face, and near at<lb/>
hand a pitcher of the largest size full of water from the olla - for there was<lb/>
no ice. Before him was a large roast of range beef which, after helping Reed,<lb/>
he would consume entirely and likewish empty the water pitcher.</p>
<p>On one occasion Reed took a leave, and in company with another officer<lb/>
and a lady of the garrison going home, drove in an ambulance 150 miles to the<lb/>
railroad. The other officer was charged with the commission of laying in the<lb/>
food for this trip of nearly a week. After they started they found that the<lb/>
provision consisted simply of crackers and sardines. Reed up to that time had<lb/>
never been able to eat sardines, but he learned on this trip. He had his<lb/>
share also of Indian campaigning and on one occasion brought into the post a<lb/>
little Indian girl of 4 or 5, who had been so horribly burned that her people<lb/>
had abandoned her to die. This child he succeeded in saving and brought her<lb/>
up in his family as a nurse for his children in spite of the warning of that<lb/>
keen old Indian fighter General Crook. When she was grown, the savage Apache<lb/>
blood asserted itself and she ran away after giving evidence that 15 years of<lb/>
gentleness and refinement had not modified the cruel and deceitful character of<lb/>
her race.</p>
<p>Memory often holds most fast to trivial things, but they are usually<lb/>
characteristic. So, though what has come into my mind to tell you of our dead<lb/>
friend is not of weighty matters, yet they show the odd vicissitudes of Army<lb/>
life and show him as he was, the pleasant comrade, the eager student and the<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02650006"/>
<del>4.</del>5<lb/>
devoted doctor, gentle, unselfish, modest and brave, as the gentle and devoted<lb/>
ever are. Over this earnest spirit and the high purposes of his life played<lb/>
always a merry and kindly humor like the dancing lights and reflections from<lb/>
the surface of a deep swift river. It was often keen but never bitter, and<lb/>
was his most striking social characteristic as was devotion to the duty which<lb/>
was before him the dominant feature of his professional life. For him, as<lb/>
for the great Duke -</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>&ldquo;The path of duty was the way to glory,</l>
<l>He that walks it only thirsting</l>
<l>For the truth and learns to deaden</l>
<l>Love of self, before his journey closes,</l>
<l>He shall find the stubborn thistle bursting</l>
<l>Into glossy purples which outreddens</l>
<l>All voluptuous garden roses.</l>
<l>He that ever follows her commands</l>
<l>On with toil of heart and knees and hands</l>
<l>Through the long gorge to the far light has won</l>
<l>His path upwards and prevailing;</l>
<l>Shall find the toppling crags of Duty scaled</l>
<l>Are close upon the shining table-lands</l>
<l>To which our God himself is moon and sun,</l>
<l>Such was he, - his work is done.&rdquo;</l>
</lg>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
