<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02651001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Essay: Value of Dr. Reed's Work, [by Jefferson Randolph Kean?], [1902?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02651001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1902-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Pasteur, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Lister, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">India</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1902-00-00">[1902?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02651001</idno>
<title>Essay: Value of Dr. Reed's Work, [by Jefferson Randolph Kean?], [1902?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Kean?] comments on the paucity of public praise that Reed has received. He maintains that his work should be recognized by the United States government, and ends with a call for a generous pension to Emilie Lawrence Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1902-00-00">
<head>Essay: Value of Dr. Reed's Work, [by Jefferson Randolph Kean?], [1902?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02651001"/>
<opener>
Kean<lb/>
<unclear>Ser 31 Dec</unclear><lb/>
<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Value of Dr. Reed's Work.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Popular appreciation of the value of the work of the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Commission has been singularly slow and imperfect. While nearly<lb/>
every educated person in the United States is familiar with the name<lb/>
and work of a distinguished Austrian surgeon who has recently demon-<lb/>
strated in this country an operation for the cure of a rather rare<lb/>
deformity in children, only a small fraction of them know anything of<lb/>
Walter Reed the conquerer of the &ldquo;Yellow Plague.&rdquo; And yet, distin-<lb/>
guished men have not been silent in regard to him. General Leonard<lb/>
Wood said in a recent address at a memorial meeting of scientific men<lb/>
held in honor of his memory in Washington, &ldquo;I know of no other man on<lb/>
this side of the world who has done so much for humanity as Dr. Reed.<lb/>
His discovery results in the saving of more lives annually than were<lb/>
lost in the Cuban war, and saves the commercial interests of the world<lb/>
a greater financial loss each year than the cost of the Cuban war. He<lb/>
came to Cuba at a time when one third of the Officers of my Staff died<lb/>
of yellow fever, and we were discouraged at the failure of our efforts<lb/>
to control the disease. In the months when the disease was ordinari-<lb/>
ly worst the disease was checked and driven from Havana. That was<lb/>
the first time in nearly 200 years that the city had been rid of it.<lb/>
The value of his discovery cannot be appreciated by persons who are<lb/>
not familiar with conditions in tropical countries. Hereafter it<lb/>
will never be possible for yellow fever to gain such headway that<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02651002"/>
2.<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
quarantine will exist from the month of the Potomac to the mouth of the<lb/>
Rio Grande. Future generations will appreciate fully the value of Dr.<lb/>
Reed's services. His was the originating, directing and controlling<lb/>
mind in this work and the others were assistants only.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In a letter dated November 24th, General Wood said: &ldquo;To Major<lb/>
Reed belongs the honor of having led in the greatest medical work of<lb/>
modern times, and the results be accomplished will live for all time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Prof. William B. Welch, of Johns Hopkins, said in a letter to<lb/>
the Secretary of War: &ldquo;Dr. Reed's researches in yellow fever are by far<lb/>
the most important contribution to science which have ever come from as<lb/>
Army surgeon. In my judgment they are the most valuable contributions<lb/>
to medicine and public hygiene which have ever been made in this coun-<lb/>
try, with the exception of the discovery of anaesthesia. They have<lb/>
led and will lead to the saving of untold thousands of lives. I am in<lb/>
a position to know that the credit for the original ideas embodied in<lb/>
this work belongs wholly to Walter Reed. Such work if done in Europe<lb/>
would receive substantial recognition from the Government.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He was last year given the degree of LL. D. by the University<lb/>
of Michigan, and the degree of M. A. by Harvard University. In confer-<lb/>
ring, the language used by President Eliot was: &ldquo;Walter Reed, graduate<lb/>
of medicine of the University of Virginia, the Army Surgeon who planned<lb/>
and directed in Cuba the experiments which have given man control over<lb/>
that fearful scourge yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02651003"/>
<p>3.</p>
<p>FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY</p>
<p>Recommendation of Secretary of War in Report for year 1902.<lb/>
(Page 10)</p>
<p>---------------------</p>
<p>&ldquo;The brilliant character of this scientific achievement, its in-<lb/>
estimable value to mankind, the saving of thousands of lives, and the<lb/>
deliverance of the Atlantic seacoast from constant apprehension, demand<lb/>
special recognition from the Government of the United States.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dr. Reed is the ranking major in the Medical Department, and<lb/>
within a few months will, by operation of law, become lieutenant-colonel.<lb/>
I ask that the President be authorized to appoint him assistant surgeon-<lb/>
general with the rank of colonel, and to appoint Major Gorgas deputy-<lb/>
surgeon-general with the rank of lieutenant-colonel, and that the re-<lb/>
spective numbers in those grades in the Medical Department be increased<lb/>
accordingly during the period for which they hold those offices.&rdquo; (In<lb/>
print but not published at the time of Major Reed's death.)</p>
<p>Precedents are abundant for state aid to public benefactors and<lb/>
their families. The English Government a century ago when the purchas-<lb/>
ing value of money was far greater than at present, gave to Jeaner, the<lb/>
discoverer of vaccination, grants amounting to thirty thousand pounds.<lb/>
He also received <unclear>37,383</unclear>, from a subscription in India.</p>
<p>Pasteur, the founder of the science of bacteriology, besides<lb/>
numerous honors and decorations and money donations from other sources,<lb/>
received from the French Government a pension of 12,000 francs.</p>
<p>Lister, the originator of antiseptic surgery has, besides<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02651004"/>
4.<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
numerous honors and decorations, been successively Knighted and ele-<lb/>
vated to the Peerage.</p>
<p>In this country a bill to donate a hundred thousand dollars<lb/>
to the discoverer of anaesthesia was twice passed by the Senate (in<lb/>
1853 and 1854) but failed in the House, probably because of the uncer-<lb/>
tainty as to which of the rival claimants was entitled to the credit<lb/>
of that discovery.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed has been cut off by death before he could reap any<lb/>
rewards of his beneficent work and has left his family in straightened<lb/>
circumstances. Surely it is not too much for this great and rich coun-<lb/>
try in recognition of a national benefactor to give his widow a decent<lb/>
and adequate support during her lifetime. A bill has been introduced<lb/>
into Congress to give Mrs. Reed a pension of $333.00 a month. This<lb/>
bill should be passed as it is without niggardly haggling or efforts to<lb/>
practice economy at the expense of the widow of a man whose services to<lb/>
the country and to humanity are inestimable.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
