<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02655001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Excerpt: A Bibliography of Walter Reed, [1902]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02655001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1902-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="place">Washington Barracks (Washington, D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1902-00-00">1902</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02655001</idno>
<title>Excerpt: A Bibliography of Walter Reed, [1902]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This excerpt discusses Reed's medical work and gives a listing of each publication authored by Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1902-00-00">
<head>Excerpt: A Bibliography of Walter Reed, [1902]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02655001"/>
<p>Same as<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
P 44 Senate<lb/>
Documents<lb/>
# 61</p>
<p>DR. WALTER REED<lb/>
17</p>
<p>zo&ouml;logist by training, his writings in applied zo&ouml;logy in connec-<lb/>
tion with yellow fever entitle him to rank as among the greatest<lb/>
of applied zo&ouml;logists.</p>
<p>It was the U. S. Bureau of Animal Industry which first clearly<lb/>
demonstrated the great importance of arthropods as intermediate<lb/>
hosts of epidemic diseases, and its reports on the tick (<hi rend="italic">Boophilus</hi>)<lb/>
as a transmitter of Texas fever of cattle will always remain classic.<lb/>
Then the writings of two English physicians, Ross and Manson,<lb/>
and of an Italian zo&ouml;logist, Grassi, carried the subject further in<lb/>
connection with mosquitoes and malaria.</p>
<p>Finally, the writings of our friend, Walter Reed, and of his asso-<lb/>
ciates demonstrated to us the relation of mosquitoes and yellow<lb/>
fever, and showed us how we could protect both life and com-<lb/>
merce from this scourge.</p>
<p>It is interesting to note that all three of these discoveries in<lb/>
applied zo&ouml;logy show certain parallels. All deal with diseases<lb/>
which are pre&euml;minently tropical or subtropical; all deal with dis-<lb/>
eases of unusual economic importance; and the actual positive<lb/>
experimental work upon transmission has been done chiefly by<lb/>
English-speaking investigators.</p>
<p>Might I add here, without misinterpretation, that the Texas<lb/>
fever work was done before the days of the <hi>Noble prize</hi>. The<lb/>
first medical awards of this prize of $40,000 were to Behring<lb/>
in recognition of his work for mankind in connection with diph-<lb/>
theria, and to Pawlow for his work in physiology; the next award<lb/>
was to Ross in recognition of his work for humanity in connec-<lb/>
tion with malaria. Are not Reed, Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte<lb/>
the natural candidates for the next award because of their work<lb/>
for mankind in connection with yellow fever, and in case the con-<lb/>
ditions of the grant permit it, should not each of the widows of<lb/>
two of these men receive the share which would have gone to<lb/>
her husband?<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>Our friend, Dr. Reed, was not what would be called a prolific<lb/>
writer. His numerous routine duties prevented him from furnish-<lb/>
ing the manuscript which we had a right to expect from a man of<lb/>
his ability. Still, beside short remarks in society discussions, his<lb/>
bibliography contains 27 original articles all printed between 1892<lb/>
and 1902. Ten of these articles dealt with yellow fever, three or<lb/>
four with typhoid, two each with malaria and erysipelas, and one<lb/>
each with cholera, pneumonia, trikresol, vaccine, artificial im-<lb/>
munity against vaccination, amoeboid bodies in the blood of vacci-<lb/>
nated monkeys and children and in variola, formaldehyde, splenic<lb/>
leukemia, and electrozone. All were in English and although they<lb/>
were all official Government work, it is a striking fact that only<lb/>
five, so far as I have been able to find, were published by the Gov-<lb/>
ernment.</p>
<p>Regarding the general style of the articles, there are three points<lb/>
in particular which are striking: First, the attention given to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02655002"/>
<hi>22 ems</hi><lb/>
8 point <unclear>Casbun</unclear><lb/>
18<lb/>
IN MEMORIAM<lb/>
details immediately reminds us of the writings of Dr. Theobald<lb/>
Smith of Harvard University; second, the directness of diction<lb/>
immediately reminds us of Dr. J. McKeen Cattell, Professor of Ex-<lb/>
perimental Psychology, Columbia University. In fact one of the<lb/>
characteristics for which Dr. Reed was noted among his friends<lb/>
was the absolute straight line of his thoughts and the orderly,<lb/>
lucid and logical development of his subject. Third, Dr. Reed<lb/>
was of a judicial temperament, and the judicial manner in which<lb/>
he handled his subject, even in controversy, forcibly reminds us<lb/>
of the same prominent characteristic in Professor William H.<lb/>
Welch of Johns Hopkins University.</p>
<p>In forecasting the time of the influence of Dr. Reed's writings,<lb/>
it is clear that his articles on yellow fever will far outlive his<lb/>
papers on other subjects. His other writings will be known to<lb/>
men only in certain lines of medical work, but his papers on yel-<lb/>
low fever will be known directly or indirectly to both physicians<lb/>
and zo&ouml;logists, and to both professional men and business men.<lb/>
They will be quoted for decades to come, both by government<lb/>
officials and by private practitioners, and they will be one of the<lb/>
most important factors in determining the future policy of civil-<lb/>
ized nations in dealing with yellow fever, a disease which we<lb/>
dreaded only a few years ago, but now one which, thanks to the<lb/>
work of Reed and his colleagues, will soon be little more than a<lb/>
medical curiosity.</p>
<p>BIBLIOGRAPHY.</p>
<p>REED, WALTER. [1851-1902.]</p>
<p>1892.--The contagiousness of erysipelas. <hi rend="italic">Boston M. &amp; S. J.</hi>, v. 126 (10),<lb/>
March 10, p. 237.</p>
<p>1893.--Remarks on the cholera spirillum. [An address before Ramsey<lb/>
County Medical Society, March 28.] <hi rend="italic">Northwest. Lancet</hi>, St. Paul (297), v.<lb/>
13 (9), May 1, pp. 161-164.</p>
<p>1894<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.--Association of <hi rend="italic">Proteus vulgaris</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Diplococcus lanceolatus</hi> in a<lb/>
case of croupous pneumonia. <hi rend="italic">Johns Hopkins Hosp. Bull.</hi>, Baltimore, v. 5<lb/>
(34), March, pp. 24-25.</p>
<p>1894<hi rend="italic">b</hi>.--The germicidal value of trikresol. <hi rend="italic">St. Louis M. &amp; S. J.</hi> (642),<lb/>
v. 66 (6), June, pp. 329-337.</p>
<p>1894<hi rend="italic">c</hi>.--Idem. <hi rend="italic">Proc. Ass. Mil. Surg. U. S.</hi> (Washington), St. Louis, v. 4,<lb/>
pp. 199-208.</p>
<p>1894<hi rend="italic">d</hi>.--A brief contribution to the identification of <hi rend="italic">Streptococcus erysipe-<lb/>
latos. Boston M. &amp; S. J.</hi>, v. 131 (14), October 4, pp. 339-340.</p>
<p>1895<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.--An investigation into the so-called lymphoid nodules of the liver<lb/>
in typhoid fever. <hi rend="italic">Johns Hopkins Hosp. Rep.</hi>, Baltimore, v. 5, pp. 379-396.</p>
<p>1895<hi rend="italic">b</hi>.--An investigation into the so-called lymphoid nodules of the liver in<lb/>
abdominal typhus. <hi rend="italic">Am. J. M. Sc.</hi>, Philadelphia, n. s., v. 110, pp. 543-559.</p>
<p>1895<hi rend="italic">c</hi>.--What credence should be given to the statements of those who<lb/>
claim to furnish vaccine lymph free of bacteria? [Read before the District<lb/>
of Columbia Med. Soc., June 5.] <hi rend="italic">J. Pract. M.</hi>, N. Y., v. 5 (12), July, pp.<lb/>
532-534.</p>
<p>1896<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.--[The character, prevalence, and probable causation of the malarial<lb/>
fevers at Washington Barracks and Fort Myer.] Rep. Surg. Gen. Army,<lb/>
Wash., pp. 65-77, 1 diagram, 1 table.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02655003"/>
<p>FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY</p>
<p>DR. WALTER REED<lb/>
19</p>
<p>1896<hi rend="italic">b</hi>.--The parasite of malaria. <hi rend="italic">J. Pract. M.</hi>, N. Y., v. 6 (9), Apr., pp.<lb/>
382-383.</p>
<p>1897<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.--Serum diagnosis in typhoid fever. Rep. Surg. Gen. Army, Wash.,<lb/>
pp. 68-73.</p>
<p>1897<hi rend="italic">b</hi>.--On the appearance of certain amoeboid bodies in the blood of vac-<lb/>
cinated monkeys (<hi rend="italic">Rhoesus</hi>) and children, and in the blood of variola. An<lb/>
experimental study. <hi rend="italic">Tr. Ass. Am. Physicians</hi>, Phila., v. 12, pp. 291-302,<lb/>
2 pls.</p>
<p>1897<hi rend="italic">c</hi>.--On the appearance of certain amoeboid bodies in the blood of vac-<lb/>
cinated monkeys (<hi rend="italic">Rhoesus</hi>) and children, and in the blood from cases of<lb/>
variola. An experimental study. <hi rend="italic">J. Exper. M.</hi>, N. Y., v. 2 (5), Sept., pp.<lb/>
515-527, pls. 38-40.</p>
<p>1897<hi rend="italic">d</hi>.--Typhoid fever in the District of Columbia; diagnosis: The value<lb/>
of Widal's test, the dried blood method. <hi rend="italic">Nat. M. Rev.</hi>, Wash., v. 7 (6),<lb/>
Nov., pp. 144-146.</p>
<p>1897<hi rend="italic">e</hi>.--[Experiments with Hollister's formaldehyde generator.] Rep.<lb/>
Surg. Gen. Army, Wash., pp. 103-104.</p>
<p>1898.--Splenic leukaemia. [<hi rend="italic">Trans. Med. Soc. District of Columbia</hi>, Oct.<lb/>
27, 1897.] <hi rend="italic">Nat. M. Rev.</hi>, Wash., v. 7 (9), Feb., pp. 265-266.</p>
<p>1900.--Report on the practical use of electrozone as a disinfectant in the<lb/>
city of Havana, Cuba. Rep. Surg. Gen. Army, Wash., pp. 178-186. [MS.,<lb/>
dated Apr. 20.]</p>
<p>1901<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.--The propagation of yellow fever; observations based on recent<lb/>
researches. [Address before 103d Ann. Meeting Med. and Chir. Fac., State<lb/>
of Md., Balt., Apr. 24-27.] <hi rend="italic">Med. Rec.</hi>, N. Y. (1605), v. 60 (6), Aug. 10,<lb/>
pp. 201-209, tables 1, 2.</p>
<p>1901<hi rend="italic">b</hi>.--Idem. Rep. Surg. Gen. Army, Wash., pp. 187-202, 1 pl., 6 fever<lb/>
charts.</p>
<p>1902.--Recent researches concerning the etiology, propagation and pre-<lb/>
vention of yellow fever, by the United States Army Commission. <hi rend="italic">J. Hyg.</hi>,<lb/>
Cambridge, Eng., v. 2 (2), Apr. 1, pp. 101-119, charts 1-3.</p>
<p>REED, WALTER, AND CARROLL, JAMES.</p>
<p>1899<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.--<hi rend="italic">Bacillus icteroides and Bacillus cholerae suis</hi>. A preliminary note.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Med. News</hi>, N. Y., v. 74 (17), Apr. 29, pp. 513-514.</p>
<p>1899<hi rend="italic">b</hi>.--The specific cause of yellow fever. A reply to Dr. G. Sanarelli.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Med. News.</hi>, N. Y., v. 75 (11), Sept. 9, pp. 321-329.</p>
<p>1900.--A comparative study of the biological characters and pathogenesis<lb/>
of <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi> X (Sternberg), <hi rend="italic">Bacillus icteroides</hi> (Sanarelli), and the hog-chol-<lb/>
era bacillus (Salmon and Smith). [Received for publication Feb. 25.] <hi rend="italic">J.<lb/>
Exper. M.</hi> [Balt.], v. 5 (3), Dec. 15, pp. 215-270, figs. a-o, pl. 19, figs.<lb/>
1-3.</p>
<p>1901.--The prevention of yellow fever. [Read at 29th Ann. Meeting, Am.<lb/>
Pub. Health Ass., Buffalo, Sept. 16-21.] <hi rend="italic">Med. Rec.</hi>, N. Y. (1616), v. 60 (17),<lb/>
Oct. 26, pp. 641-649, figs. 1-10.</p>
<p>1902.--The etiology of yellow fever. A supplemental note. [Read at 3d<lb/>
Ann. Meeting, Soc. Am. Bacteriologists, Chicago, Dec. 31, 1901, and Jan. 1,<lb/>
1902.] <hi rend="italic">Am. Med.</hi>, Phila., v. 3 (8), Feb. 22, pp. 301-305, charts 1-6.</p>
<p>REED, WALTER; CARROLL, JAMES, and AGRAMONTE, ARISTIDES.</p>
<p>1901<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.--The etiology of yellow fever. An additional note. [Read at Pan-<lb/>
Am. Med. Cong., Havana, Cuba, Feb. 4-7.] <hi rend="italic">J. Am. Med. Ass.</hi>, Chicago,<lb/>
v. 36 (7), Feb. 16, pp. 431-440, charts 1-6.</p>
<p>1901<hi rend="italic">b</hi>.--Experimental yellow fever. <hi rend="italic">Am. Med.</hi>, Phila., v. 2 (1), July 6, pp.<lb/>
15-23, charts 1-8, tables 1-2.</p>
<p>REED, WALTER; CARROLL, JAMES; AGRAMONTE, ARISTIDES, and LAZEAR,<lb/>
JESSE W.</p>
<p>1900.--The etiology of yellow fever. A preliminary note. [Read at<lb/>
Meeting of Am. Pub. Health Ass., Indianapolis, Ind., Oct. 22-26.] <hi rend="italic">Phila.<lb/>
M. J.</hi> (148), v. 6 (17), Oct. 27, pp. 790-796, tables 1-3, charts 1-2.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f02655004"/>
<p>B2</p>
<p>20<lb/>
IN MEMORIAM</p>
<p>REED, WALTER, and STERNBERG, GEORGE M.</p>
<p>1895.--Report of immunity against vaccination conferred upon the<lb/>
monkey by the use of the serum of the vaccinated calf and monkey. <hi rend="italic">Tr.<lb/>
Ass. Am. Physicians</hi>, Phila., v. 10, pp. 57-69.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Dr. Reed's Work in Cuba, by</hi> MAJOR GENERAL LEONARD WOOD,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">U. S. Army</hi>.</p>
<p>[Abstract.]</p>
<p>The work of Dr. Walter Reed is the most important work in<lb/>
the way of medical research and discovery which has been accom-<lb/>
plished by any one who has lived in this hemisphere. There is<lb/>
no other medical discovery to which it can be compared, unless it<lb/>
be that of anaesthesia. The results to humanity are incalculable<lb/>
and far-reaching. It is safe to say that this discovery has resulted<lb/>
in saving each year more lives than were lost in the war with<lb/>
Spain, and in a saving to commerce, and especially to the south-<lb/>
ern portion of our country, of an amount equal to the cost of the<lb/>
war with Spain.</p>
<p>The following letters and telegrams were received:</p>
<p>WASHINGTON, D. C., <hi rend="italic">Dec. 29, 1902</hi>.</p>
<p>Dr. S. S. ADAMS, Pres. District Medical Society.</p>
<p>My dear Dr. Adams: I regret exceedingly that an engagement<lb/>
made some time since, and from which I cannot excuse myself,<lb/>
will prevent me from attending the Reed memorial meeting on<lb/>
Wednesday evening.</p>
<p>No one appreciates more deeply than I do the loss to scientific<lb/>
medicine and to the medical corps of the army caused by Major<lb/>
Reed's death. His scientific work was eminently fruitful and<lb/>
far-reaching in its results. As the head of the medical corps dur-<lb/>
ing nine years of his most useful work, which was prosecuted<lb/>
under my general direction, I am of course entirely familiar with<lb/>
the results accomplished.</p>
<p>Major Reed was endowed by nature and by training with the<lb/>
essential qualifications for engaging in research work in the special<lb/>
field to which he devoted his talents and his energies. Conserva-<lb/>
tive, painstaking, thorough, persevering and ready in resources,<lb/>
he acquitted himself with credit in every task assigned to him,<lb/>
and has achieved great and deserved distinction by his successful<lb/>
demonstration of the method by which yellow fever is transmitted<lb/>
from man to man. In addition to this, he was a modest and<lb/>
courteous gentleman, who attracted all of those who came in<lb/>
contact with him. His death came to me, as to his other number-<lb/>
ous friends, as a great personal grief and irreparable loss.</p>
<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
GEO. M. STERNBERG.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
