<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02668001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Article fragment: The Military Government of Cuba, by Leonard Wood, [March, 1903]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Wood, Leonard</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02668001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1903-03-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Ludlow, William</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Santiago (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Santa Clara (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1903-03-00">March, 1903</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02668001</idno>
<title>Article fragment: The Military Government of Cuba, by Leonard Wood, [March, 1903]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Wood gives a history of the American occupation in Cuba and discusses the yellow fever outbreak and consequent investigation by Reed and Lazear. Article appears in &ldquo;The Annals of the American Academy.&rdquo; Only pages 16 and 17 are included.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1903-03-00">
<head>Article fragment: The Military Government of Cuba, by Leonard Wood, [March, 1903]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02668001"/>
<p>Leonard Wood - &ldquo;The Military Government of Cuba<lb/>
Annals of the American Academy of Political &amp; Social Science - March 1903<lb/>
(whole article 7 pp. These are pp. numbered 16-17)</p>
<p>16<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Annals of the American Academy</hi></p>
<p>quent spread of the disease among neighboring individuals was pre-<lb/>
vented. With yellow fever, the situation was different. The old<lb/>
theories in regard to the treatment of this dread disease were the<lb/>
theories upon which we worked in our endeavors to check yellow<lb/>
fever in Cuba during the first two years of our occupation. We<lb/>
believed that it was a filth disease largely and due to unsanitary con-<lb/>
ditions. Practically, the results obtained by this method of pro-<lb/>
cedure were <hi rend="italic">nil</hi>, so far as controlling the disease was concerned. It<lb/>
did result, however, in better sanitation, in reducing the general<lb/>
death rate, etc., but yellow fever appeared and continued in spite of<lb/>
our vigorous cleaning measures.</p>
<p>A most virulent epidemic broke out in Santiago during the sum-<lb/>
mer of 1899, and was controlled only by the most extreme measures,<lb/>
involving the removal of all non-immunes from the city, closing of<lb/>
all infected houses and liberal cleaning of the city with fire and dis-<lb/>
infectants, and the isolation of all persons with the fever. All<lb/>
infected material was burned, vaults and cesspools were cleaned and<lb/>
saturated with kerosene and fired. Disinfection was carried to the<lb/>
extent of sprinkling the streets with a solution of corrosive subli-<lb/>
mate. Triple disinfection at suitable intervals was carried out in all<lb/>
infected houses. Regulations were promulgated to the effect that<lb/>
all infected houses should be subsequently inhabited by immunes<lb/>
only. Ships were forbidden to approach the piers, and non-<lb/>
immune passengers were prohibited from landing in the city. Head-<lb/>
quarters and troops were sent to high ground fifteen miles inland.<lb/>
These measures were effective, as above stated, in removing all<lb/>
susceptible persons and in checking the disease, which was finally<lb/>
stamped out. Non-immunes were not allowed to return until the<lb/>
yellow fever season had passed. When this epidemic broke out,<lb/>
Santiago was as clean as a town can be kept. There was absolutely<lb/>
nothing in the condition of the city itself to account for the outbreak<lb/>
of the yellow fever. Methods such as were employed in Santiago<lb/>
are feasible in small towns or in cities of 40,000 to 50,000 people,<lb/>
as in Santiago, in times of great emergency, but they could not be<lb/>
effectually employed in a city the size of Havana without seriously<lb/>
and permanently injuring the commerce and industry of such a city.</p>
<p>In the spring and summer of 1899 there were few deaths from<lb/>
yellow fever in the city of Havana. General Ludlow had inaugurated<lb/>
a most thorough and efficient system of cleaning the city, and it was<lb/>
[168]<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02668002"/>
<hi rend="italic">The Military Government of Cuba</hi><lb/>
17<lb/>
believed that such measures would be effective in keeping out the<lb/>
fever. As a matter of fact, however, the fever was continually<lb/>
present during this period, but there was in Havana comparatively<lb/>
little non-immune material.</p>
<p>In the fall, however, Spanish immigration began, and during<lb/>
the fall and winter approximately 12,000 Spanish immigrants<lb/>
arrived at the port of Havana, about one-half of this number remain-<lb/>
ing in the city. The result was that in December there was, for<lb/>
that period of the year, a serious outbreak of yellow fever which<lb/>
lasted throughout the winter and increased in the spring and summer<lb/>
months and, although it was kept within bounds by most thorough<lb/>
and systematic house to house inspection and careful supervision<lb/>
of all sick persons, combined with the immediate removal to the<lb/>
yellow fever hospitals of all persons, without regard to class or posi-<lb/>
tion, who were taken sick with the disease, still there were in Havana<lb/>
approximately 1,400 cases of yellow fever during this summer. The<lb/>
existence of this condition in a perfectly clean city, compelled those<lb/>
who looked beneath the surface to realize that the spread of yellow<lb/>
fever could not be controlled simply by cleaning and disinfecting<lb/>
methods.</p>
<p>During the summer of 1900, the fever appeared in the garrisoned<lb/>
towns of Pinar del Rio and Santa Clara. The sanitation of these<lb/>
towns was under military supervision, and there was nothing in the<lb/>
condition of the towns themselves to account for the outbreak of the<lb/>
fever. Troops had to be sent out into camp and rigid local quaran-<lb/>
tine measures inaugurated. In this manner the spread of yellow<lb/>
fever was checked. The loss of officers during these epidemics was<lb/>
very serious, and there was also considerable loss of life among the<lb/>
enlisted men and civilians. In short, the situation was one of great<lb/>
discouragement. It was perfectly evident that we could control the<lb/>
disease in the small towns by controlling the local non-immunes and<lb/>
cutting off intercourse with infected districts, or, in extreme meas-<lb/>
ures, doing as has been done in Jamaica, that is, to send the non-<lb/>
immunes to the mountains above the fever level.</p>
<p>Affairs were in this condition when a systematic investigation<lb/>
of yellow fever was undertaken by Drs. Reed, Carroll and Lazaer.<lb/>
These officers took up the work in a very thorough and conscientious<lb/>
manner, starting at the point previously reached by Dr. Findlay.<lb/>
They accepted Dr. Findlay's idea that yellow fever was transmitted<lb/>
[169]</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
