<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02672001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from James Carroll to the Editor, June 26, 1903</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02672001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1903-06-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Koch, Robert</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1 (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1903-06-26">June 26, 1903</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02672001</idno>
<title>Letter from James Carroll to the Editor, June 26, 1903</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carroll writes that Agramonte was not present at the meeting where self-inoculation was discussed by Reed, Carroll and Lazear. Furthermore, he was only informed about the results of the experiments when Reed was about to leave Cuba, in October of 1900. He maintains that Finlay should not be awarded credit for the discovery of the mosquito theory.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1903-06-26">
<head>Letter from James Carroll to the Editor, June 26, 1903</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02672001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Washington, D.C. <date value="1903-06-26">June 26, 1903.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>To the Editor:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>In connection with my paper published in the<lb/>
Journal of May 23d several statements made by my esteemed colleague<lb/>
Dr. Aristides Agramonte in his letter published in the Journal of<lb/>
June 13th call for reply, and I beg to be permitted to submit the fol-<lb/>
lowing necessary explanations: With manifest feeling Dr. Agramonte<lb/>
takes exception to the omission of his name in the early part of<lb/>
my paper (and naturally too in view of his lack of knowledge of<lb/>
the facts,) and proceeds to show that I was in error in my state-<lb/>
ment that the decision to put the mosquito theory to a practical<lb/>
test was arrived at during a consultation between Drs. Reed, Lazear<lb/>
and myself. He then makes certain statements in regard to our late<lb/>
colleague, Dr. Lazear, with which <add>with one <unclear>exception</unclear>,</add> I heartily agree, and which no one,<lb/>
so far as I know, has ever (openly or tacitly,) attempted to deny<lb/>
or conceal. I am then accused of being an unbeliever at the time<lb/>
when I was bitten, and the letter closes with an arraignment of me<lb/>
for attempting to deprive Finlay of the &ldquo;glory of his discovery&rdquo;,<lb/>
and an emphatic assertion of Finlay's right of priority.</p>
<p>In the first place Dr. Agramonte's name was omitted because<lb/>
he was not present at the meeting referred to, which took place at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks, where we were quartered, on the eve of Dr. Reed's<lb/>
departure for the United States in the beginning of August 1900.<lb/>
As Dr. Agramonte resided in Havana and had a separate laboratory<lb/>
at Military Hospital No. 1, he was absent from many similar consul-<lb/>
tations. It is true, however, as he states, that he was present at<lb/>
a previous meeting, when the mosquito theory was brought up, and it<lb/>
is also true that the various theories and probabilities were the<lb/>
subjects of constant consideration and discussion. At the meeting<lb/>
in question Carter's observations pointing to a period of incubation<lb/>
or development in an intermediate host <del>was</del><add>were</add> brought up, so also was<lb/>
the erratic manner in which the disease seemed to jump from house<lb/>
to house, often across a street or farther, without intercommunica-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02672002"/>
2<lb/>
tion between the inhabitants, in other words the transmission of<lb/>
the disease through the atmosphere; the numerous points of resem-<lb/>
blance between the modes of dissemination and seasonal occurrence<lb/>
of yellow fever and malaria; etc. These were not new topics for<lb/>
they had been discussed almost daily, and a decision was promptly<lb/>
arrived at to put the mosquito theory to a practical test, and if<lb/>
that failed of result, to resort to anaerobic cultivations, parti-<lb/>
cularly from the intestine. The serious nature of the work decided<lb/>
upon and the risk entailed upon it were fully considered, and we all<lb/>
agreed, as <del><unclear>to</unclear></del> the best justification we could offer for experimen-<lb/>
tation upon others, to submit to the same risk of inoculation our-<lb/>
selves. The fact of the meeting, the conclusion arrived at and the<lb/>
agreement to submit ourselves to the bites of <del><unclear>and</unclear></del> contaminated mos-<lb/>
quitoes are susceptible of proof, for they were stated by me in a<lb/>
letter written, a few months later, to the widow of our devoted col-<lb/>
league (Dr. Lazear,) in response to her request for a detailed state-<lb/>
ment of the circumstances attendant upon her <del><unclear>her</unclear></del> husband's death.</p>
<p>I acknowledge frankly that I was, in a measure, an unbeliever<lb/>
at the time I submitted to inoculation, for the evidence Finlay pre-<lb/>
sented was far from convincing, chiefly because he had worked in a<lb/>
hot bed of the disease. I was perfectly willing however, to take<lb/>
a soldier's chances, and afterward enjoyed the satisfaction of<lb/>
being the first person to become aware, by actual proof, of the effi-<lb/>
cacy of the mosquito, and the first genuine case of experimental<lb/>
yellow fever on record. These facts are also susceptible of proof.</p>
<p>There was strong ground for the assumption on the part of cer-<lb/>
tain persons that I did not believe in the mosquito theory even<lb/>
after I suffered my attack. During my convalescence I was plied<lb/>
with questions by Doctors Finlay, Guiteras, <del>and</del> Agramonte and others<lb/>
who inquired whether the mosquito had anything to do with my at-<lb/>
tack. My replies were always evasive and intended to mislead, be-<lb/>
cause of the necessity for the strictest secrecy to avoid prema-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02672003"/>
3<lb/>
publicity. I made only one exception in a medical officer of<lb/>
the regular army, now in Washington, whom I knew to be an intimate<lb/>
and trusted friend of Major Reed. As a matter of fact the results<lb/>
were not communicated to Dr. Agramonte until Dr. Reed was about to<lb/>
leave the Island a second time, with the completed report to be read<lb/>
at the meeting of the American Public Health Association at Indiana-<lb/>
polis in October 1900. He then told me he was about to carry the<lb/>
paper into Havana and acquaint him with its contents; upon his re-<lb/>
turn he manifested much amusement over Dr. Agramonte's astonish-<lb/>
ment when the news was imparted to him.</p>
<p>Lastly, perhaps it is natural that the Cuban ex-member of our<lb/>
board should desire to see Dr. Finlay awarded credit for the dis-<lb/>
covery, but Finlay is no more entitled to credit for the discovery<lb/>
of the mosquito theory of the transmission of yellow fever than Man-<lb/>
son is for the discovery of a similar theory for malarial fever.<lb/>
The cases are precisely analogous except that Finlay attempted to<lb/>
prove his hypothesis <add>and failed</add>; Manson did not enjoy the opportunity, and he<lb/>
gives full credit to Ross. According to the article cited by<lb/>
Agramonte (Medical Record, New York, May 27, 1899,) Finlay is also<lb/>
entitled to credit for another discovery, viz.: that malarial infec-<lb/>
tion is transmitted by flies from the bloody dejecta of patients<lb/>
through the intermediation of food and beverages. Finlay here<lb/>
<unclear>se</unclear><lb/>
makes the statement that &ldquo;Koch's assertion that &lsquo;when there are no<lb/>
mosquitoes there is no malaria&rsquo;, is altogether too absolute&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Those who are interested in the subject of yellow fever are<lb/>
referred to the statements of Dr. George H.F. Nuttall of the Univer-<lb/>
sity of Cambridge, in No. 2. Vol. 3 of the Journal of Hygiene, which<lb/>
has just been brought to my notice.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
