<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY t02708406 SYSTEM "t02708406.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02708407 SYSTEM "t02708407.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02708408 SYSTEM "t02708408.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02708409 SYSTEM "t02708409.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02708410 SYSTEM "t02708410.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02708412 SYSTEM "t02708412.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t02708414 SYSTEM "t02708414.jpg" NDATA jpg>]>
<TEI.2 id="t02708001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Public Health Papers and Reports, volume XXIX, Presented at the Thirty-First Annual Meeting of the American Public Health Association, Washington, D. C., October 26-30, 1903 [selected pages]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02708001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1903-10-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Porter, Joseph Y.</name>
<name type="person">Stiles, Charles Wardell</name>
<name type="person">Ross, John W.</name>
<name type="person">Liceaga, Eduardo</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Lindsley, J. M.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kohnke, Quitman</name>
<name type="person">Nolte, Arthur</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>71 pp.</extent>
<date value="1903-10-26">October 26-30, 1903</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02708001</idno>
<title>Public Health Papers and Reports, volume XXIX, Presented at the Thirty-First Annual Meeting of the American Public Health Association, Washington, D. C., October 26-30, 1903 [selected pages]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>These selections from presentations given at the 1903 annual meeting of the American Public Health Association concern the scientific reception of the Yellow Fever Commission's work, particularly the etiology of yellow fever, quarantine procedures, and the discovery of the role of the mosquito. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">
<p></p>
</div1>
<pb n="1" id="f02708001"/>
<titlePage>
<docTitle>
<titlePart><unclear><hi>Rm</hi><lb/>
$3<hi rend="superscript">60</hi></unclear><lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH<lb/>
PAPERS AND REPORTS<lb/>
VOLUME XXIX</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<byline>PRESENTED AT THE THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING OF THE<lb/>
American Public Health Association<lb/>
WASHINGTON, D. C.<lb/>
OCTOBER 26, 27, 28, 29 AND 30,<lb/>
1903<lb/>
LIBRARY<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE<lb/>
APR 20, <unclear>1903</unclear><lb/>
-----<lb/>
188550.</byline>
<docImprint>COLUMBUS, OHIO<lb/>
PRESS OF FRED. J. HEER<lb/>
</docImprint>
<docDate>1904</docDate>
</titlePage>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="chapter" n="1">
<head>REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE ON THE ETIOLOGY OF<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER.</head>
<pb n="39" id="f02708029"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>DR. JOHN W. ROSS</docAuthor>, U. S. N., CHAIRMAN, WASHINGTON, D. C.</byline>
<p>Among the contributions to the study of the etiology of yellow fever<lb/>
which have appeared since the last annual meeting of the Association<lb/>
we would invite attention to the following:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>I. An article by Dr. Carlos J. Finlay in the <hi rend="italic">Revista de Medicina<lb/>
Tropical</hi>, of April, 1903,--&ldquo;Probable Nature and Life Cycle of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Germ.&rdquo; In this he infers from the analogy of the con-<lb/>
veyance of this disease with that of malaria--<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) That the germ in question is a protozo&ouml;n;</item>
<item>(b) That its phases of development are more or less similar to<lb/>
those of the malaria parasite;</item>
<item>(c) That as the infection by the yellow fever parasite of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi><lb/>
was indefinite in duration, while that of man was for a very short<lb/>
while, and the infection of man by the malarial parasite was indefinite<lb/>
in duration, and that of <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi>, probably, was short; the inference<lb/>
is that the role of these hosts is <hi rend="italic">interchanged</hi> for these two parasites<lb/>
and that the yellow fever parasite has its sexual reproduction in <hi rend="italic">man</hi><lb/>
and its schizogonic reproduction in the <hi rend="italic">mosquito</hi>: that man is its<lb/>
definitive and the mosquito its intermediary host;</item>
<item>(d) That it is ultra microscopic.<lb/>
The third conclusion is sufficiently original and has an obvious and<lb/>
direct bearing on the search for the micro-organism of yellow fever<lb/>
and to unravel its life history.</item>
</list>
</item>
<item>II. The report of the &ldquo;Working Party&rdquo; -- Parker, Beyer and Po-<lb/>
their -- at Vera Cruz, in Yellow Fever Bulletin No. 13, of March,<lb/>
1903; U. S. P. H. and M. H. S. Their findings (which are evidently<lb/>
regarded as yet tentative, and with which must be taken a paper by<lb/>
Parker in the Journal of the Association of Military Surgeons, of<lb/>
October, on the &ldquo;Etiology of Yellow Fever&rdquo;) are:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) That no specific organism was found in human blood during<lb/>
life or in any tissue after death;</item>
<item>(b) That the ovaries of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi>, after feeding on a yellow<lb/>
fever patient, first hypertrophy, as after a meal of normal blood, and<lb/>
then undergo complete atrophy;</item>
<item>(c) That the salivary glands of infected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi> undergo ex-<lb/>
cessive hypertrophy;<lb/>
39<lb/>
<pb n="40" id="f02708040"/>
40<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</item>
<item>(d) That in such mosquitoes a parasite was found -- &ldquo;a small<lb/>
fusiform protozo&ouml;n&rdquo; -- in the stomach three or four days after feed-<lb/>
ing. This parasite passes out of the stomach into the oesophageal<lb/>
diverticulum and there, in an albuminous mass derived from the last<lb/>
blood meal, undergoes a development analogous to that of the coccidia,<lb/>
and passes out into the connective tissues around the cells of the sali-<lb/>
vary glands, and, presumably, into the ducts of these glands, whence<lb/>
they would be naturally discharged by the insect feeding.</item></list>
The report is of great interest and further work along this line is<lb/>
exceedingly desirable; to determine:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) If the changes from the normal in infected mosquitoes, reported<lb/>
by these observers, is constant;</item>
<item>(b) The <hi rend="italic">certain</hi> explanation of the appearances, interpreted as<lb/>
phases of the development of a coccidium;</item>
<item>(c) If this be agreed, the role that coccidium plays in the etiology<lb/>
of yellow fever; and</item>
<item>(d) If possible, to complete the life history of the micro-organism<lb/>
in man.</item>
</list>
The findings of this report are absolutely at variance with the views<lb/>
of Finlay given above, as they make the sporogenetic cycle occur in<lb/>
the mosquito.</item>
<item>III. A paper on the distribution of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>, by Theobald, in<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Tropical Medicine</hi>, for August, 1903.<lb/>
This is concerned mainly with the Old World and gives this genus<lb/>
a wide-spread, well-nigh universal distribution in the low-lying lands<lb/>
of the Eastern Hemisphere within 43&deg; on each side of the Equator.<lb/>
That of the species <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> is as wide and almost as gen-<lb/>
eral. While only <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> has been proven to convey yellow<lb/>
fever, yet from analogy we should expect that other species of <hi rend="italic">Stego-<lb/>
myia</hi> (of which Theobald names 25) would do so. Theobald char-<lb/>
acterizes <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> as: &ldquo;Almost exclusively a tub and pot<lb/>
breeder.&rdquo;<lb/>
He found that adults lived two months, never having been fed,<lb/>
from the larval state and then died for want of water.</item>
<item>IV. In the same number of the <hi rend="italic">Revista de Medicina Tropical</hi> as<lb/>
Finlay's article, Guiteras observed eleven <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi> which had fed<lb/>
on a yellow fever patient. Of these seven lived over 64 days and one<lb/>
to 154 days. He, also, as an experiment in hybernation, placed 33<lb/>
female <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi> in an ice chest, kept at from 8&deg; to 10&deg; C., without<lb/>
food or water; three survived to the 87th day when they were de-<lb/>
stroyed by ants.<lb/>
There are to be presented at this meeting of the American Public<lb/>
Health Association, the following papers:<lb/>
<pb n="41" id="f02708041"/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
41<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>A. SOME CHARACTERISTICS OF STEGOMYIA FASCIATA WHICH<lb/>
AFFECT ITS CONVEYANCE OF YELLOW FEVER; by Surgeon H. R. Car-<lb/>
ter, U. S. Public Health and Marine Hospital Service.</item>
<item>B. CONCERNING THE GEOGRAPHIC DISTRIBUTION OF THE YELLOW<lb/>
FEVER MOSQUITO; by L. O. Howard, Ph. D., Chief Entomologist, U.<lb/>
S. Department of Agriculture; Hon. Curator of Insects, U. S. National<lb/>
Museum; Consulting Entomologist, U. S. Public Health and Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service.</item>
<item>C. PERIOD OF THE DISEASE IN MAN DURING WHICH YELLOW<lb/>
FEVER CAN BE TRANSMITTED TO THE MOSQUITO; by Colonel W. C.<lb/>
Gorgas, Assistant Surgeon-General, U. S. Army.</item>
</list>
</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>MINOR PROBLEMS IN THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER YET TO BE<lb/>
INVESTIGATED.</p>
<p>Although the paramount problem of the etiology of yellow fever,<lb/>
viz: Its conveyance to man solely by the genus <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>, is already<lb/>
solved, the committee believes that a statement of some of the minor<lb/>
problems yet remaining for solution may be of service to investigators.</p>
<p>We exclude the identification and life history of the long-sought-for<lb/>
but still undetermined specific micro-organism of yellow fever. That<lb/>
is a <hi rend="italic">major</hi> problem little less important, scientifically, than the dis-<lb/>
covery of its conveyance by the mosquito host.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. The determination of the period of the disease in man during<lb/>
which yellow fever can be transmitted to the mosquito. So far ex-<lb/>
periments have shown that it is transmitted somewhat over two days,<lb/>
i. e., in the first, second and third days; but there are no sufficient<lb/>
experiments to prove that the third day is the limit at which the<lb/>
mosquito can be infected. The importance of this determination is<lb/>
obvious.</item>
<item>2. The determination of the minimum period after feeding at which<lb/>
a mosquito can become infective.<lb/>
Reed has shown that this seems to depend on the temperature--<lb/>
being greater in low temperatures. The minimum period in his ex-<lb/>
periments was twelve days, in his first experimental case, and, judg-<lb/>
ing from observation on yellow fever as it occurs in nature, this is<lb/>
probably near the limit. Still no sufficient attempt has been made to<lb/>
show that mosquitoes contaminated less than twelve days cannot con-<lb/>
vey yellow fever in the summer.<lb/>
Since the determination of this point, experimentally, would involve<lb/>
producing yellow fever in probably a considerable number of human<lb/>
beings, and since the minimum in Reed's experiments agrees closely<lb/>
with previous observations on yellow fever, the committee does not<lb/>
think that experiments for this purpose are justifiable.<lb/>
<pb n="42" id="f02708042"/>
42<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</item>
<item>3. To determine if other mosquitoes than <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> convey yellow<lb/>
fever, and if other species of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> besides <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi><lb/>
can do so. The first is, from analogy, very improbable; the latter, for<lb/>
the same reason, is probable.</item>
<item>4. To determine if <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> is found breeding at a dis-<lb/>
tance from human habitations, i. e., if it is anywhere a true sylvan,<lb/>
campestral or palustral mosquito.</item>
<item>5. A closer study of the hibernation of this insect is desirable<lb/>
(especially the hibernation of infected females), to determine:</item>
<item>(a) What proportion of the infected females survive an ordinary<lb/>
winter in the Gulf States;</item>
<item>(b) Whether such as survive retain their power of transmitting<lb/>
yellow fever.</item>
<item>6. To determine if <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia faciata</hi> is capable of acclimitiza-<lb/>
tion in environments unfavorable to the immigrant mosquitoes also<lb/>
deserves observation and experimentation.</item>
<item>7. To determine the distance across water that this insect is aerially<lb/>
conveyed. If desired it will be easy to differentiate the blood-fed<lb/>
(not necessarily infected mosquitoes) by observing if they deposit<lb/>
eggs. If the finding of the Vera Cruz &ldquo;Working Party&rdquo; be correct,<lb/>
the infected mosquito deposits no eggs after a short time after be-<lb/>
coming infected.</item>
<item>8. Finally, it seems advisable to determine directly by observation<lb/>
whether this mosquito is carried by railroad trains, and if so, in what<lb/>
number, and generally the conditions of such transfer. On this may<lb/>
depend measures of land quarantine.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="2">
<head>REFLECTIONS ON THE DESIRABILITY OF AN AGREE-<lb/>
MENT BETWEEN THE SANITARY AUTHORITIES OF<lb/>
ADJOINING COUNTRIES FOR MUTUAL DEFENSE<lb/>
AGAINST TRANSMISSIBLE DISEASE.</head>
<pb n="43" id="f02708043"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>DR. EDUARDO LICEAGA,</docAuthor>
PRESIDENT OF THE SUPREME BOARD OF HEALTH OF MEXICO, MEXICO, D. F.</byline>
<p>Proc am Pub H A 31 meet<lb/>
Wash Oct 26-30, 1903</p>
<p>One of the subjects of special interest that occupies the attention of<lb/>
the American Public Health Association, is that of preventing the<lb/>
propagation and development of transmissible diseases. The interest<lb/>
in this subject is increased, when it becomes a question of preventing<lb/>
the transmission of such diseases from one nation to another. The<lb/>
Association has appointed committees of its members to study the<lb/>
question from the two points of view that I have just mentioned; but<lb/>
there is another from which I want it to be considered at the present<lb/>
moment and which I propose to formulate as follows:</p>
<p>The measures which are intended to avoid the transmission of an<lb/>
epidemic disease from one country to another, should be such that<lb/>
whilst they protect the health and interests of the nation which defends<lb/>
itself, they will not injure, or only as little as possible, the interests of<lb/>
the other nations, from which the danger is feared.</p>
<p>We have so understood it in Mexico, and by way of example, I will<lb/>
present a concrete case in the Mexican Republic, and its relations to<lb/>
this powerful nation, which now so hospitably receives us in the cap-<lb/>
ital city of its enormous territory.</p>
<p>In the month of December, last year, and whilst I was attending the<lb/>
meeting of this Association, I learned from the distinguished physician<lb/>
who here presides that in a small port of my own country, Ensenada<lb/>
de Todos Santos, in the southern part of Lower California, it was sus-<lb/>
pected that bubonic plague had appeared. I at once cabled to my<lb/>
Government to take the necessary steps to ascertain the truth of this<lb/>
report, and enforce such measures as might be thought desirable un-<lb/>
der the circumstances. As there was no telegraphic communication<lb/>
between New Orleans, where the meeting was being held, and the<lb/>
port of Ensenada, for the purpose of deciding the first problem and<lb/>
ascertaining whether the bubonic plague really existed in the port<lb/>
above mentioned, with the authority of my Government I accepted<lb/>
the offer made to me by Dr. Wyman, to send Dr. Grubbs, an officer of<lb/>
the Marine-Hospital Service, to study and investigate on the spot.</p>
<p>43</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="3">
<head>COMMENTS ON THE REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE OF<lb/>
THE ASSOCIATION ON THE ETIOLOGY OF<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER.</head>
<pb n="47" id="f02708047"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>DR. JUAN GUITERAS</docAuthor>,<lb/>
DIRECTOR OF LAS ANIMAS HOSPITAL, HAVANA, CUBA.</byline>
<p>Proc am Pub H. A. - 31st meet<lb/>
Wash Oct 26-30, 1903</p>
<p>Of the nine cases of yellow fever at Las Animas Hospital, tabulated<lb/>
in the report of the committee, three died. To these we should add<lb/>
the body of a man who died from yellow fever as the ship was enter-<lb/>
ing the harbor, and which was brought to Las Animas Hospital.<lb/>
These four bodies were laid out in the dead-house of the hospital,<lb/>
and were handled by a non-immune attendant, who assisted at the<lb/>
four autopsies, handling the viscera. This same man goes into the<lb/>
wards daily and obtains the blood from all patients, including those<lb/>
attacked with yellow fever, for hematologic studies. The urine, the<lb/>
feces, and the black vomit from said patients are examined in the lab-<lb/>
oratory without any attempt at disinfection. The attendant, a faith-<lb/>
ful <hi rend="italic">diener</hi>, who would not, however, allow himself to be bitten by an<lb/>
infected mosquito, works all day in the laboratory. Furthermore,<lb/>
scarcely a week goes by, summer or winter, without a visit to the<lb/>
wards and laboratory of Las Animas Hospital from Northern friends,<lb/>
and other non-immunes, who are interested in the work. The daugh-<lb/>
ter of the President of the Republic, and my own daughter, who lives<lb/>
on the grounds, both of them non-immunes, are frequent visitors.</p>
<p>The occurrence of exposure to undisinfected fomites is so frequent,<lb/>
it has become such a matter of course, so natural and uneventful, that<lb/>
no notice is now taken of the daily demonstrations.</p>
<p>How often have I wished, of late, that our friends of Texas, who<lb/>
have stampeded, carrying yellow fever over a State, utterly unpre-<lb/>
pared to meet the conditions, could witness the peaceful rounds of<lb/>
yellow fever life within a mosquito-barred house. I mean to say by<lb/>
this, and I wish to speak plainly, that the conditions now existing in<lb/>
Texas are solely due to the unpreparedness of those communities.</p>
<p>At the Conference of State and Provincial Boards of Health, held<lb/>
at New Haven last year. I begged the leaders of medical opinion in<lb/>
the Southern States to start a campaign of education on the principles<lb/>
of the mosquito doctrine; to send officers to Havana to learn prac-<lb/>
tically the specific methods of defense against this disease, and to es-<lb/>
tablish and maintain in active operation the mosquito brigades in<lb/>
the exposed places. Instead of doing this, the attempt was made to<lb/>
47<lb/>
<pb n="48" id="f02708048"/>
48<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
keep up the delusion of fomites infection, and, in the beginning of<lb/>
the present epidemic, it has not been possible to keep public opinion<lb/>
from demanding the disinfection of the mails. It is satisfactory to<lb/>
note that when the proper discipline has become at last established,<lb/>
the happy results that were to be expected are being obtained in<lb/>
southern Texas.</p>
<p>Let us fix our attention upon the fundamental difference between<lb/>
the work doing in Texas and the work doing in Havana. In Texas<lb/>
there was the usual wrangle over the nature of the first cases. To<lb/>
handle them as cases of yellow fever would create a panic. The re-<lb/>
sult is that the measures of prevention were not commenced until<lb/>
there was really some ground for a panic. In Havana we act other-<lb/>
wise. Every case in which there appears to be the remotest possibil-<lb/>
ity of yellow fever is treated as if it were a case of the disease. It<lb/>
is enough that our commission for infectious diseases be called upon<lb/>
to visit a case concerning which suspicions may have been advanced<lb/>
by anyone; the mosquitoes are destroyed in that house, although the<lb/>
commission may pronounce a very positive opinion that it is not<lb/>
yellow fever. Our specific treatment does no harm; it simply keeps<lb/>
our mosquito disinfecting brigade in practice. There are two cases of<lb/>
yellow fever in the tabulated list presented by the committee that de-<lb/>
serve special mention.</p>
<p>John Fay was admitted June 30 and discharged, cured July 14th.<lb/>
He was a passenger in transit to New York on the steamship Ma-<lb/>
tanzas. The case was detected at the time of inspection by our quar-<lb/>
antine officer. Now, our health department could have shirked all<lb/>
responsibility in connection with this case and allowed it to proceed<lb/>
on its way north. The captain and the patient himself were opposed<lb/>
to our interfering in the matter. Yet we decided upon the removal<lb/>
of the patient, with a view to preventing further infection of the ship.<lb/>
The health department of Havana, therefore, almost forcibly removed<lb/>
a case of yellow fever from a ship in transit, and brought him into<lb/>
the city and to Las Animas Hospital. This shows the thorough con-<lb/>
fidence we have in our methods to prevent the spread of yellow fever.</p>
<p>The other case is that of V. Baron, admitted July 11th, died July<lb/>
14th. This man had a false certificate of immunity, and was there-<lb/>
fore allowed to land without careful inspection. He was in the second<lb/>
day of the disease, on the day of landing, July 9th. He did not send<lb/>
for a physician, but went to the city hospital on the morning of July<lb/>
11th. There he was recognized at once as a case of yellow fever, and<lb/>
was sent to Las Animas Hospital. This man, therefore, remained<lb/>
in the city of Havana, exposed to mosquito bites during the second<lb/>
and third days of the disease. His place of residence was in the<lb/>
<pb n="49" id="f02708049"/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
49<lb/>
heart of the business portion, Inquisidor St., No. 28. He remained<lb/>
for a short while in my ward (mosquito-screened) of the Mercedes<lb/>
Hospital, whose protection against mosquito bites was far from being<lb/>
as certain as it is in Las Animas Hospital. Now, mark the advant-<lb/>
age we have over this disease. The mosquitos that had bitten this<lb/>
man could do no harm immediately. We had, when the patient was<lb/>
discovered, ten days at least, before us in which to destroy all the<lb/>
insects that had bitten the patient. You can well imagine how eagerly<lb/>
we took advantage of this opportunity. Mosquitoes were destroyed<lb/>
in the infected house, in the whole block, and in the hospital Mercedes.<lb/>
Though all this happened in the month of July, and in the city of<lb/>
Havana; though there were two non-immunes in the ward at Mer-<lb/>
cedes, eight in the house in Inquisidor St., and a much larger num-<lb/>
ber in the block, not one of them became infected.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="4">
<head>SOME CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA<lb/>
FASCIATA WHICH AFFECT ITS CONVEY-<lb/>
ANCE OF YELLOW FEVER.</head>
<pb n="50" id="f02708050"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>DR. HENRY R. CARTER</docAuthor>,<lb/>
U. S. PUBLIC HEALTH AND MARINE HOSPITAL SERVICE, BALTIMORE, MD.</byline>
<p>Proc am Pub Health Asso-<lb/>
31st meet - Wash. Oct 26-30, 1903</p>
<p>It is not proposed here to go into the life history of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fas-<lb/>
ciata</hi>, but simply to call attention to such of its peculiar characteristics,<lb/>
differentiated from mosquitoes in general, which seem especially to<lb/>
influence its role as a conveyer of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Here let me premise that only this species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi><lb/>
has been shown to act as a host for the conveyance of yellow fever to<lb/>
man. Following the analogy of malaria and <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi> we would<lb/>
expect that the other species of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> (of which there are many),<lb/>
or at least some general subdivision of the genus most closely allied<lb/>
to this species, would act in like manner. No attempt to determine<lb/>
this point has been reported. <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi>, other than <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fas-<lb/>
ciata</hi>, must then with our present knowledge, be regarded with sus-<lb/>
picion as <hi rend="italic">probable</hi> hosts for yellow fever, but against which the charge<lb/>
is not proven. Similarly analogy is against any other genus of mos-<lb/>
quitoes being able to act as host for the micro-organism of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Of the characteristics of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> which affect its role<lb/>
as a conveyer of yellow fever the first that we will consider is</p>
<p>(1) Its Distribution.</p>
<p>Obviously this is all important. Localities in which this mosquito<lb/>
breeds and feeds on man are &ldquo;infectable localities&rdquo; and in them yellow<lb/>
fever is a communicable disease and will spread if cases be introduced<lb/>
without prceautions. Here we must note that this form has been of<lb/>
special interest only a short time and that the account of its distribu-<lb/>
tion is necessarily lacking in completeness, and the fact that it has not<lb/>
been reported from a particular district, unless we know that careful<lb/>
and well planned search has been made, is not conclusive that it does<lb/>
not occur there.</p>
<p>All writers agree that it is widely distributed in tropical and sub-<lb/>
tropical countries. Theobald, in a recent monograph in Tropical Medi-<lb/>
cine, states that it is found generally between 43 North and 43 South.<lb/>
In North America, at least, we shall find its original habitat is much<lb/>
more limited and that even where introduced it does not make good<lb/>
its permanent settlement beyond North Lat. 38 or 381&sol;2. The writer<lb/>
above quoted gives its Old World distribution as follows:<lb/>
50</p>
<pb n="51" id="f02708051"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
51</p>
<p>Asia: India generally, Coast and Interior. Malay States, Farther<lb/>
India, Celebes, New Guinea, Japan, Palestine.</p>
<p>Australia: Queensland, New South Wales, Victoria and South Aus-<lb/>
tralia very abundant.</p>
<p>Africa: West coast from Senegambia to Nigeria. East coast<lb/>
from Port Said to Durbin. At Pretoria and British Central Africa<lb/>
generally; and Uganda, (As it has been found at the Savannah Quar-<lb/>
antine Station oboard a vessel direct from Cape Town, this district<lb/>
also must harbor it.)</p>
<p>Europe: Spain, Portugal, Italy and the Mediterranean Islands to<lb/>
Cypress. Especially abundant at Gibraltar.</p>
<p>Oceanic Islands: Fiji, Mauritius, Seychelles.</p>
<p>They are also found in Hawaii, having been introduced within the<lb/>
last generation.</p>
<p>It had not been reported in the Philippines, a matter of interest to<lb/>
us, nor on the Chinese coast, although other forms of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> are<lb/>
found in both places, and with the communication between these places<lb/>
and Japan; India and the Straits settlements it seems improbable that<lb/>
this form has not been introduced, and probably they do exist in both<lb/>
countries, at least in the coast cities.</p>
<p>Obviously the wide distribution here noted in countries hitherto free<lb/>
from yellow fever, makes it extremely important not to introduce men<lb/>
sick with yellow fever into them. If other forms of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> besides<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi rend="italic">fasciata</hi>&rdquo; can also convey yellow fever the territory to be guarded<lb/>
becomes considerably increased.</p>
<p>In America this form has been reported from a number of the West<lb/>
India Islands and east coast towns of Mexico, Central America and<lb/>
South America as far south as Montevideo. They have been so gen-<lb/>
erally reported where they have been looked for in these limits that<lb/>
they may be regarded as generally present in the coast towns from the<lb/>
Rio Grande to the La Plata.</p>
<p>They are also found at Panama and at Guyaquil on the west coast.<lb/>
But few reports, and I think but few examinations, have been made<lb/>
of the interior towns. They have been found in some of the interior<lb/>
towns of Cuba and in Orizaba and Linares, Mexico, and in Merida.<lb/>
At some interior towns they have been reported absent after search,<lb/>
as at Jalapa and Guatemala.</p>
<p>To determine its distribution in the United States correspondence<lb/>
was entered into with gentlemen in nearly every town on the Atlantic,<lb/>
Gulf, and Pacific Coasts; as well as in nearly all towns of any size on<lb/>
the Great Lakes and on the Mississippi and Ohio rivers, and a con-<lb/>
siderable number of towns inland. In quite a number of instances,<lb/>
especially outside of the so-called yellow fever district, no sufficient<lb/>
<pb n="52" id="f02708052"/>
52<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
search known to my correspondents had been made for this insect;<lb/>
but in the majority it was possible to obtain a satisfactory answer,<lb/>
negative or positive; and from quite a number specimens of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia<lb/>
fasciata</hi> were received.</p>
<p>To enumerate all the places at which it was found in the United<lb/>
States would take too long. Generally it was reported as found in<lb/>
all of the coast towns from Norfolk, Va., to Galveston, in which a<lb/>
sufficient search has been reported as made. It was also found at a<lb/>
number of interior towns; Houston, Texas; Shreveport, Franklin, and<lb/>
other towns in southwest Louisiana, in Biloxi and Pass Christian and<lb/>
in some other places, in the interior of Mississippi, in several towns--<lb/>
at all of which search was made--on the Mississippi River, up to,<lb/>
and including Cairo, Ill.; also some interior towns in eastern Georgia.<lb/>
It is the less necessary to give the details of this distribution as I had<lb/>
intended doing as I find Dr. Howard of the Department of Agriculture<lb/>
has also been engaged, with infinitely better facilities and success in<lb/>
collecting data on the distribution of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>, and as<lb/>
soon as his report is published we will have complete data on the sub-<lb/>
ject. He writes me; &ldquo;The list of localities from which I have received<lb/>
it is a long one. In general, I may state that, in my opinion, this in-<lb/>
sect will be found practically in all portions of the lower austral life<lb/>
zone in the United States. This includes all of the Gulf States, as<lb/>
well as portions of New Mexico and Arizona; it also includes the<lb/>
low-lying portions of South Carolina and North Carolina, and the<lb/>
southeastern portion of Virginia; it includes also southern Arkansas<lb/>
and southern Indian Territory, as well as western Tennessee and west-<lb/>
ern Kentucky, the extreme southeastern corner of Missouri and the<lb/>
extreme southern tip of Illinois.&rdquo; Obviously my determination is in-<lb/>
cluded in his more complete one.</p>
<p>Within this district they have been reported absent; that is, not<lb/>
found after sufficient search: At the Quarantine Stations at Ship Island,<lb/>
Mullet Key, Blackbeard Island, at the Savannah Quarantine Station,<lb/>
at the Cape Fear Station, and at the adjacent town of South Port, N.<lb/>
C.; nor have they been found on St. Catherine's Island, Ga. They<lb/>
have been found aboard incoming vessels at all save one of these sta-<lb/>
tions, but none have been found ashore. We may note that Ship<lb/>
Island has been notoriously &ldquo;non-infectable territory&rdquo;; at the others I<lb/>
know of fewer exposures. All of these stations are wind-swept, iso-<lb/>
lated places; with abundant marsh, fresh and brackish, in the vicinity;<lb/>
with artesian water at the first and last, and cisterns carefully screened<lb/>
at Mullet Key. I do not know the water supply at the Savannah<lb/>
Station. They were found at the Brunswick Station but have disap-<lb/>
peared under kerosening. Here cisterns were used.</p>
<pb n="53" id="f02708053"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
53</p>
<p>The answers received from north of the Ohio and Potomac were<lb/>
decidedly less satisfactory than from points south. The <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi><lb/>
having apparently excited little interest in the former, and hence not<lb/>
having been as carefully sought for. They are reported as absent,<lb/>
after careful search at Evansville, Cincinnati, Baltimore (except a few<lb/>
larvae which developed into <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> found at the fruit wharf in<lb/>
early September), Lewes, Delaware and the Quarantine Stations of<lb/>
Delaware Breakwater and Reedy Island. They were not found on<lb/>
Staten Island or Governor's Island; or at the New York Quarantine<lb/>
Station, or at Buffalo, or at Sault Ste Marie. The writer especially<lb/>
regrets that he cannot say definitely whether they are found in Wash-<lb/>
ington or Louisville, places which are on the border of their apparent<lb/>
range. He is sure that they are at least rare in both places, compe-<lb/>
tent observers, although not especially on the search for this form,<lb/>
not having seen them. Indeed considerable search has failed to show<lb/>
them at Louisville.</p>
<p>On the west coast of the United States they are reported absent at<lb/>
San Diego and at Angel Island in San Francisco harbor, and are not<lb/>
reported as <hi rend="italic">present</hi> at any port.</p>
<p>In spite of those found about the fruit wharf in Baltimore, it seems<lb/>
that practically they do not occur north of Cape Henry, and that they<lb/>
are found at all of the cities south of Cape Henry at which satisfactory<lb/>
search was made. Thus the old line of division for maritime quar-<lb/>
antine: a line founded empirically on the spread, in recent years, of<lb/>
yellow fever when introduced, &ldquo;The southern boundary of Maryland&rdquo;<lb/>
was a fairly correct division of infectable and non-infectable territory.<lb/>
Indeed the old rules of maritime quarantine for southern ports are,<lb/>
except the disinfection of baggage, very generally applicable under the<lb/>
theory of its conveyance by this mosquito.</p>
<p>In America this form has so far been reported as found only about<lb/>
the habitations of men (at least the writer has been able to find none<lb/>
elsewhere reported). This was to have been anticipated because (1)<lb/>
the conditions which prevail about houses are especially suitable for<lb/>
its propagation. (2.) Being easily found about houses in districts<lb/>
where it exists it may not have been looked for elsewhere. Yet it is<lb/>
a matter of importance to determine if it breeds in woods, fields, or<lb/>
swamps distant from human habitations. In the United States the<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">indirect</hi> evidence of yellow fever not spreading where introduced into<lb/>
new camps in the woods and fields -- and cypress swamps as well -- is<lb/>
against the natural occurrence of this form in such places in the<lb/>
United States.</p>
<p>If this be true of the tropics as well, Manson's proposition, to de-<lb/>
forest and drain a belt one-half mile wide on either side of the Isthmian<lb/>
<pb n="54" id="f02708054"/>
54<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASGIATA</hi>.<lb/>
Canal to prevent <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> boarding vesels in transit, is unnecessary.<lb/>
It would be wiser to depopulate it.</p>
<p>Next we consider (2) Its Conveyance from Place to Place.</p>
<p>Obviously if they are conveyed from one place to another, this sec-<lb/>
ond place becomes infectable, temporarily in proportion to the number<lb/>
received; and, if the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> breeds and thrives in its new home,<lb/>
a settlement, more or less permanent, is established; and places which<lb/>
hitherto have received yellow fever patients with impunity can do so<lb/>
no longer but become, as long as the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> prevails, &ldquo;infectable.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This change of infectability, not predicating the cause, is fairly com-<lb/>
mon in the history of towns in the interior of the Gulf and South<lb/>
Atlantic States and not uncommon even in that of coast towns. Thus<lb/>
prior to 1855, Norfolk, Virginia had had yellow fever introduced a<lb/>
number of times, &ldquo;almost every year,&rdquo; and occasionally there would<lb/>
be secondary cases -- around the wharves -- there was then a large<lb/>
coffee trade. In 1855 there was a severe and general epidemic. Fer-<lb/>
nandina was the place of refuge in '76 from the epidemics in Savannah<lb/>
and Brunswick and there was no spread of fever. In '77, following<lb/>
the advent of a vessel from Havana, a general epidemic arose; and<lb/>
again an epidemic in '88. Jessup, Georgia, gives a similar history.</p>
<p>(a). By railroads.</p>
<p>The writer has been able to find no conveyance of this mosquito by<lb/>
railroad, nor save at Evansville, Ind., by P. A. Surgeon Brown, has he<lb/>
been able to have any sufficient search made for them aboard trains<lb/>
running from towns which harbor <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>. As other mosquitoes,<lb/>
notoriously the culicids, are transported by trains, it is probable that<lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> is also. I have then no direct evidence of this that they<lb/>
are thus transported; but the cases of yellow fever contracted at St.<lb/>
Louis and Louisville toward the close of the epidemic of '78 by <hi rend="italic">local</hi><lb/>
trainmen and residents near the stations of railroads from the south<lb/>
is indirect evidence, which to my mind is convincing. To what extent<lb/>
this occurs should evidently affect our measures of inland quarantine.</p>
<p>(b). Conveyance by vessel.</p>
<p>Conveyance by vessel has been frequently noted. It is fair to say<lb/>
that the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia not</hi> being found aboard a vessel is evidence of its<lb/>
absence, of value only in proportion to the process of search adopted<lb/>
and the care taken in making it; and it seems fair to believe that they<lb/>
are conveyed by vessels, in small number, far oftener than the reports<lb/>
we have would lead us to believe. A negative statement of the crew<lb/>
is of little moment. People used to the fiery bite and myriad numbers<lb/>
of the &ldquo;salt water mosquito&rdquo; (<hi rend="italic">C. Sollicitans?</hi>) which infest the wharves<lb/>
of tropical ports, pay little attention to a moderate number of elusive<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi>. Probably the best way to determine their presence is to<lb/>
<pb n="55" id="f02708055"/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
55<lb/>
put out breeding cups or, which indeed is better, to look for such re-<lb/>
ceptacles as may have served for this purpose aboard. Failing this<lb/>
there seems no better way than direct search. Corput of South Atlan-<lb/>
tic Quarantine Station says: &ldquo;I personally search the cabin and fore-<lb/>
castle; all corners, closets, hangings, and roofs of berths.&rdquo; &ldquo;A fav-<lb/>
orite place is in the corner over the shelf where the water bottle and<lb/>
glasses are kept; also the carpenter's shop on account of the water<lb/>
under the grindstone.&rdquo; In cargo vessels where the cargo is a food<lb/>
for mosquitoes, such as bananas, sugar, etc., they would most prob-<lb/>
ably be found in the hold. There would almost certainly be water<lb/>
enough for their drinking in the hold, if only from condensation on<lb/>
the sides of the vessel, if an iron vessel. It is of course in vain to look<lb/>
for a small number of mosquitoes in the hold of a vessel, except by<lb/>
breeding cans.</p>
<p>Although conveyance by vessel has been frequently noted, yet they<lb/>
have been found aboard but a small <hi rend="italic">proportion</hi> of vessels examined.<lb/>
Souchon's inspectors, in '92 found <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> on only two fruit vessels<lb/>
for New Orleans out of a considerable number examined; the mos-<lb/>
quitoes of this variety constituting two and one-half per cent of the<lb/>
mosquitoes found, while in the houses at the port of departure there<lb/>
were forty per cent of captures. This disproportion is in accordance<lb/>
with what we shall learn of their habits.</p>
<p>They have been found at Ship Island Quarantine aboard three vessels<lb/>
sailing from Vera Cruz, a considerable number of vessels were ex-<lb/>
amined negatively. At Tampa Bay Quarantine Station, aboard one ves-<lb/>
sel sailing from Buenos Ayres. They had bred aboard in the water<lb/>
tanks, as had those in one of the previous cases. At the Savannah Quar-<lb/>
antine they were found aboard two vessels; from Cape Town (direct)<lb/>
and Havana respectively, both sailing vessels, and aboard both &ldquo;water<lb/>
barrels were alive with wrigglers&rdquo; which developed into <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi>.<lb/>
At South Atlantic Quarantine aboard five vessels; three sail, two steam;<lb/>
from Rio, Buenos Ayres, Lorenzo Marquez and West Indian ports;<lb/>
at Brunswick Quarantine Station aboard three sailing vessels all from<lb/>
Havana. Larvae were abundant aboard these three, and aboard four<lb/>
of the five at South Atlantic. Nothing is said of larvae aboard the<lb/>
fifth, a steam ship. Goldberger, at Tampico, found them aboard three<lb/>
steamers, on arrival from Vera Cruz. None on a considerable number<lb/>
from New York.</p>
<p>The writer has found <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> at Baltimore aboard two fruit<lb/>
steamers, from Jamacia and East Cuban ports and, as noted, has bred<lb/>
a few of them from larvae taken from near the fruit wharf, while<lb/>
nowhere else in Baltimore has he been able to find them.</p>
<pb n="56" id="f02708056"/>
<p>56<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;Working Party&rdquo; (Parker, Beyer and Pothier) from observa-<lb/>
tions at Vera Cruz, believe the transfer by iron vessels is rare, while<lb/>
by sailing vessels it is far more common. They base their opinion<lb/>
upon the paucity of suitable breeding places on the iron (steam) ves-<lb/>
sels as compared with wooden (sailing) craft. &ldquo;The iron ship on<lb/>
account of its concealed water tanks acts simply as a mechanical host<lb/>
to those that come aboard, while aboard wooden vessels on account<lb/>
of the loosely covered deck containers, under proper conditions, they<lb/>
propagate.&rdquo; While their observations are not sufficiently numerous to<lb/>
warrant the general deduction that iron (steam?) vessels rarely carry<lb/>
this mosquito, yet their estimate of the comparative frequency with<lb/>
which steam and sail vessels convey <hi rend="italic">numbers</hi> of them is undoubtedly<lb/>
correct. It is in accordance with the few observations given above<lb/>
and also with the indirect evidence (as has been frequently pointed<lb/>
out by the writer) that yellow fever is contracted aboard sailing far<lb/>
more commonly than aboard steam vessels.</p>
<p>There can be no doubt then, but that these mosquitoes are carried<lb/>
from place to place by vessels, especially sailing vessels, for indefinite<lb/>
distances (Cape Town to Savannah) in tropical waters.</p>
<p>This is of interest on two accounts:</p>
<p>(A.) It is a means of conveying the infection of yellow fever to<lb/>
other countries: (a.) by mosquitoes coming board already infected,<lb/>
(b) by mosquitoes becoming infected after coming aboard by feeding<lb/>
on cases of yellow fever developed aboard, but contracted ashore. Of<lb/>
course if there be no <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> aboard, the occurrence of yellow fever<lb/>
among her personnel will not &ldquo;infect&rdquo; the vessel. In the absence of<lb/>
the host yellow fever is not a communicable disease.</p>
<p>(B.) The conveyance of uninfected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> to a country hither-<lb/>
to free from them, where they will propagate is, also a thing to be<lb/>
deprecated as it renders the country in question &ldquo;infectable&rdquo; if cases<lb/>
of yellow fever be subsequently introduced. Conveyance to a place<lb/>
where they will not increase is of little or no importance.</p>
<p>There is evidence, and it is, I think, generally held, that this mosquito<lb/>
is not indigenous to the United States, but was thus introduced from<lb/>
the tropics, and has from this become a permanent inhabitant of the<lb/>
Southern Atlantic Coast and Coast Plain, and the Mississippi Valley<lb/>
north to Cairo, Ill. The writer also holds this as an opinion, but he<lb/>
does not consider it proven for the southern part of this area. It is<lb/>
however, unquestionably true that they were very recently thus in-<lb/>
troduced into Hawaii, these islands having been free from mosquitoes<lb/>
prior to the arrival of a ship from San Blas, in 1826. They are abun-<lb/>
dant and generally distributed in these islands now.</p>
<pb n="57" id="f02708057"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
57</p>
<p>We have said that the introduction of the uninfected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> into<lb/>
an environment where it did not increase was of no moment. This is<lb/>
true, but there is another question. Is this mosquito able so to adapt<lb/>
itself to a somewhat unfavorable environment that it can become, so<lb/>
to speak, acclimated? Can it, after some generations, thrive and in-<lb/>
crease normally in environments in which at first it could do so poorly,<lb/>
or not at all? Can it by a series of generations in environments in-<lb/>
creasingly unfavorable -- all being unfavorable in the same way --<lb/>
finally propagate and thrive in a place where the parent brood would<lb/>
have died without successors? This is certainly true of other forms<lb/>
of animal life, generally in proportion to height in the scale of life.<lb/>
It was, and I believe is still, held true for the &ldquo;Texas tick,&rdquo; also the<lb/>
host of a pathogenic parasite, and certainly has some antecedent prob-<lb/>
ability. The Vera Cruz Working Party believe this to be true, and<lb/>
give reasons for their belief; yet to the writer they seem probable<lb/>
rather than conclusive, and he can only say that further observation<lb/>
is needed to answer the question, and that to answer it merits further<lb/>
observation. It is also conceivable that conditions, climatic and other-<lb/>
wise, may suffice for the host to thrive and yet not be such as to suit<lb/>
its parasite and thus the temperature limits of yellow fever and the<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> not be identical. This is alleged* of <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi> and the<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Plasmodium Malariae</hi>, although I think, not generally accepted.</p>
<p>(3.) Method of propagation.</p>
<p>(a). All observers note that by preference this form elects to breed<lb/>
in clear water, not necessarily clean water (Reed added small amounts<lb/>
of fecal matter to his breeding jars) in artificial containers, cisterns,<lb/>
tubs, barrels, cans, etc. Theobald classes them as &ldquo;almost exclusively<lb/>
a can and pot breeder.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The New Orleans &ldquo;Mosquito Commission&rdquo; of 1902, in the part of<lb/>
the city where the above class of receptacles were available found<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> larvae in 60% of them and in only 10% of gutters. On<lb/>
the outskirts of the city where such receptacles were not available the<lb/>
same commission found them in nearly 80% of the gutters examined.<lb/>
Other observers, however, have found them far less frequently in<lb/>
gutters and pools even when there were no other breeding places.<lb/>
The &ldquo;Working Party&rdquo; in Vera Cruz found <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> larvae seldom in<lb/>
gutters, almost invariably in water cans. Taylor, of Las Animas Hos-<lb/>
pital, Havana, after finding them commonly in artificial containers,<lb/>
notes that they &ldquo;are also found in pools,&rdquo; as if it were rare, and this<lb/>
is the general testimony of my correspondents who have found them<lb/>
breeding in the United States.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>* Note too the very slow development of the infecting power of the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi><lb/>
in Reed's December experiments in Havana.</p>
<pb n="58" id="f02708058"/>
<p>58<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.</p>
<p>Muddying and disturbing the water in the pool causes the death of<lb/>
many of the larvae. Possibly on this account the pools on the out-<lb/>
skirts of New Orleans were more suitable for breeding than those in<lb/>
the more inhabited parts of the city, indeed a still, undisturbed pool<lb/>
of water, cleared by standing, should, for this purpose, differ in no<lb/>
wise from a hard walled receptacle. <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> is not a cess-pool<lb/>
breeder.</p>
<p>(b). The time from egg to fly is from two to four days shorter<lb/>
than others of its general order, <hi rend="italic">Culicidal</hi>.</p>
<p>(c.) Eggs are at times laid above water and, if kept dry, will pre-<lb/>
serve their vitality a long time. Finlay has kept eggs dry six weeks,<lb/>
Theobald (eggs sent by Finlay) over two and one-half months, and<lb/>
Reed ninety days, and then hatched them. The latter states that<lb/>
freezing does not destroy their fertility.</p>
<p>Its choice of breeding places indicates the especial danger of open<lb/>
cisterns; water jars and collections of water in any artificial container;<lb/>
cans, troughs, etc. Thus the measures for their destruction are in<lb/>
contrast with those against <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi>. In Gorgas' work in Havana<lb/>
the <hi rend="italic">&ldquo;Stegomyia Brigade&rdquo;</hi> waged especial war in town and on artificial<lb/>
receptacles about houses. The <hi rend="italic">&ldquo;Anopheles Brigade&rdquo;</hi> drained and kero-<lb/>
sened puddles and pools in the suburbs.</p>
<p>It is well to note that the larvae are not gotten rid of by emptying<lb/>
the water jars, as it is usually done in daily use. The &ldquo;Working Party&rdquo;<lb/>
in Vera Cruz found that when water was poured from a jar the larvae<lb/>
present sought the very bottom and, unless the jars were tipped up so<lb/>
as to empty them completely, which was not usually done, nearly all<lb/>
the larvae remained in the jar.</p>
<p>Obviously then the introduction of water by pipes into all<lb/>
houses, rendering the keeping of water in containers unnecessary,<lb/>
is a most important measure in freeing a town of this mosquito. Nat-<lb/>
ural pools, however, must by no means be neglected and the necessity<lb/>
of drainage, and with drains underground in place of open gutters, is,<lb/>
especially from the observations in New Orleans, equally obvious.</p>
<p>The slightly shortened period in the egg and larval state and that<lb/>
the eggs are occasionally laid above water and may preserve their<lb/>
vitality almost indefinitely, plainly make for the preservation of the<lb/>
insect and this latter may be a means by which it survives the winter<lb/>
in (for it) north latitudes.</p>
<p>(4.) The habits of the adult, female.</p>
<p>In spite of some statements to the contrary, the evidence seems con-<lb/>
clusively that only the female <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> feeds on man, or if the male<lb/>
does so it is extremely rare.</p>
<pb n="59" id="f02708059"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
59</p>
<p>(a.) The female is very long lived. Theobald has kept them alive<lb/>
two months from the larvae without food; these specimens finally dying<lb/>
for want of water. Of eleven mosquitoes, five days old, fed by Guit-<lb/>
eras on a case of yellow fever and hence infected insects, only two had<lb/>
died on the 41st day, five lived over 101 days and one 154 days.</p>
<p>(b.) Having acquired the power of communicating yellow fever<lb/>
they preserve it apparently as long as they live. Reed reports yellow<lb/>
fever transmitted on the 59th day after feeding on a yellow fever<lb/>
patient.</p>
<p>The conveyance by vessels, shown before, together with the long life<lb/>
and persistence of this mosquito in transmitting yellow fever increases<lb/>
the difficulty of protecting the countries of the Old World, where the<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> is found, from yellow fever. Because although so<lb/>
distant that it is not possible for a man contracting the disease in<lb/>
America to contaminate mosquitoes in, say Japan, yet it is perfectly<lb/>
possible for a mosquito contaminated in America to infect a man in<lb/>
Japan, and from him any number of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi>.</p>
<p>Hitherto there has been but little direct communication from the<lb/>
yellow fever ports on the west coast of America with the east (all the<lb/>
coast of America from Payta, south and from Cape St. Lucas north<lb/>
is free from infection); but this may not be the case when the inter-<lb/>
oceanic canal is open. Yellow fever introduced into a country like<lb/>
India or the Straits settlements might well become epidemic and, if<lb/>
so, such countries would in turn be a continual menace to the rest of<lb/>
the (infectable) world, repeating the history of Rio Janiero and, prob-<lb/>
ably that of Havana.</p>
<p>(c.) They are essentially house mosquitoes. Not only do they<lb/>
breed best under the conditions which obtain in and about houses, but<lb/>
having entered a living house and fed, they do not like to leave the<lb/>
premises. Here again their habit is in contrast with that of the <hi rend="italic">Ano-<lb/>
pheles</hi>. It was the almost universal existence of this mosquito in the<lb/>
houses of Havana which first led Finlay to select it as the probable<lb/>
conveyor of yellow fever, an essentially house disease. Indeed his<lb/>
early arguments based on the peculiarities of this insect and the<lb/>
observed phenomena of yellow fever, dove-tailing in with the theory<lb/>
of its conveyance of yellow fever to man is an extremely beautiful<lb/>
piece of deductive reasoning.</p>
<p>The limitation of infection to the neighborhood of houses which con-<lb/>
tain, or have contained yellow fever patients is a marked feature in<lb/>
the early part of an epidemic.</p>
<p>(d.) It requires a considerable interval of time, generally about<lb/>
fourteen days in summer, after feeding on one sick of yellow fever<lb/>
before the mosquito is capable of imparting the disease.</p>
<pb n="60" id="f02708060"/>
<p>60<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.</p>
<p>If then the mosquitoes be destroyed or all people be removed soon<lb/>
after the first case of yellow fever develops in a place, no one will have<lb/>
been exposed to infection and these people need not be regarded as<lb/>
&ldquo;suspects.&rdquo; The minimum limit of this &ldquo;extrinsic incubation&rdquo; of yellow<lb/>
fever is not certainly fixed. Twelve days is the shortest which has<lb/>
been so far found in experimental cases.</p>
<p>(e.) Its time of feeding.</p>
<p>Observers seem to disagree as to its hours of feeding, but the dis-<lb/>
agreement is more apparent than real. All agree that its principal time<lb/>
of flight is in the afternoon. It is &ldquo;essentially crepuscular.&rdquo; Reed<lb/>
says: &ldquo;after four o'clock.&rdquo; The New Orleans Commission: &ldquo;especially<lb/>
in the afternoon hours.&rdquo; The Vera Cruz Working Party states &ldquo;early<lb/>
in the morning and late in the afternoon.&rdquo; It does not feed in the<lb/>
dark nor does it in a strong light, and its feeding seems more dependent<lb/>
on the degree of <hi rend="italic">light</hi> than on the time of day. If the place be fairly<lb/>
light it approaches its victim on the shadow side, thus especially attack-<lb/>
ing the ankles under a writing table, or the hands under the head<lb/>
during siesta. It bites after dark if there be artificial light in the<lb/>
room. It does not bite out of doors in ordinary bright daylight.</p>
<p>The above habits, together with the fact of its being a house mos-<lb/>
quito and the infected insects being mainly confined to dwelling houses,<lb/>
explains the <hi rend="italic">comparative</hi> safety of &ldquo;day-light communication&rdquo; i. e., en-<lb/>
tering a town only after 10 A. M. and leaving by 4 P. M. under pledge<lb/>
to go in only on sunny days and to enter no residence; sometimes not<lb/>
to go into the residence portion of the city. The danger of staying all<lb/>
night was really the danger of the late afternoon, early evening, and<lb/>
morning hours and in residences.</p>
<p>(f.) Hybernation.</p>
<p>Many species of mosquito are known to hybernate, some as adults,<lb/>
some as wrigglers and some doubtless as both. L. O. Howard, as<lb/>
quoted by Ross of the United States Navy states: &ldquo;That the <hi rend="italic">Steg-<lb/>
omyia</hi> hybernates in the adult stage.&rdquo; I have not seen reported the<lb/>
instances on which this statement is based. Guiteras placed thirty-three<lb/>
mosquitoes in an ice box at 46.5&deg; to 50&deg; F. without food or water;<lb/>
three of them survived to the 87th day, when they were eaten by ants.</p>
<p>That the <hi rend="italic">species</hi> habitually hybernates, i. e., exists quiescent through<lb/>
the winter, either as adult, larva or egg, is beyond dispute. Admitting<lb/>
that they hybernate as adults our experience with yellow fever teaches<lb/>
us that either but a small proportion of <hi rend="italic">infected</hi> insects survive, as in-<lb/>
deed the experience of Guiteras would indicate; or else that the power<lb/>
to convey yellow fever is <hi rend="italic">generally</hi> lost after hybernation. For while<lb/>
there is much evidence, and it has generally been accepted, that yellow<lb/>
fever <hi rend="italic">occasionally</hi> recrudesces after a winter of quiescence without re-<lb/>
<pb n="61" id="f02708061"/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
61<lb/>
introduction, yet it is <hi rend="italic">certain</hi> that this is not the rule. In a large<lb/>
majority of places where this species unquestionably hybernates, re-<lb/>
crudescence of yellow fever after an epidemic has not occurred, and,<lb/>
even where it is claimed to have occurred, only a small proportion of<lb/>
the infection that existed when the epidemic ceased is observed in the<lb/>
beginning of the recrudescence. Unquestionably then, <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi><lb/>
capable of conveying infection at the beginning of cold weather are<lb/>
only exceptionally -- and very exceptionally -- capable of conveying it<lb/>
after a winter in the Gulf States. Of course it may be that the para-<lb/>
site dies in the hybernating host which survives.</p>
<p>(g.) Aerial conveyance.</p>
<p>Some mosquitoes are carried occasionally great distances aerially.<lb/>
The writer has personal knowledge of the flights of myriads of mos-<lb/>
quitoes (<hi rend="italic">Culex Sollicitans</hi> as he remembers them) which were car-<lb/>
ried by wind fifteen or eighteen miles from the Louisiana marshes<lb/>
across Chandeleur Sound to vessels in the sound and to Chandeleur<lb/>
Island. In both cases the wind had blown moderately and steadily<lb/>
for two or three days from the marshes. Other instances are reported;<lb/>
and, in spite of the general opinion of men far abler to express an<lb/>
opinion on the subject, the writer thinks from his observation afloat on<lb/>
salt water in the lee of islands and mosquito-infested shores that the<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Culex</hi> of the salt marshes is quite frequently carried considerably over<lb/>
a mile by light, steady breezes, long continued.</p>
<p>Is this true of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>? It is a far lighter insect, more fragile<lb/>
and apparently with very little wing power. It probably never flies<lb/>
high. It is found, by preference, near the ground, in the lower stories<lb/>
of houses and would thus be little liable to conveyance by wind, and<lb/>
its feeble power of flight should prevent its passage over any consider-<lb/>
able distance by its own wing power. Nearly two years ago, the writer<lb/>
suggested that this problem be taken up, it being of importance in<lb/>
determining the anchorage of vessels in yellow fever ports. So far<lb/>
he knows of no direct observations on this subject, except those of<lb/>
Goldberger at Tampico and of Grubbs at Ship Island Quarantine.<lb/>
The latter found <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> aboard three vessels from Vera Cruz,<lb/>
two of which claimed to have laid a half mile from shore. He be-<lb/>
lieved they came aboard at Vera Cruz. The observations of Gold-<lb/>
berger will be given later.</p>
<p>Although direct observations on this problem are few, yet there are<lb/>
certain <hi rend="italic">indirect</hi> ones, bearing, however, entirely on the aerial convey-<lb/>
ance of the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> infected with yellow fever. It is notorious that<lb/>
in town yellow fever is usually conveyed but a short ways aerially<lb/>
&ldquo;across the street,&rdquo; or, more often &ldquo;to the house in the rear,&rdquo; which<lb/>
is about as far as it was expected to be thus conveyed. This represents<lb/>
<pb n="62" id="f02708062"/>
62<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
a maximum distance of about 75 yards. The two longest distances<lb/>
recorded in recent times of aerial conveyance, one of 225 metres<lb/>
(M&egrave;ller) and one of 76 fathoms -- 456 feet -- (the writer) are entirely<lb/>
exceptional. So much for the distance which the (infected) <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi><lb/>
is conveyed -- or rather usually conveyed -- aerially.</p>
<p>On the other hand it is known that vessels moored in certain districts<lb/>
of the Havana harbor did not develop yellow fever aboard, except in<lb/>
those who had been ashore, or unless they lay close to other vessels<lb/>
which were infected. This experiment has been made on so large a<lb/>
scale -- with so many vessels and for so many years -- that we <hi rend="italic">must</hi><lb/>
accept as a fact that infected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi> were <hi rend="italic">not</hi> conveyed aerially<lb/>
from the Havana shore to those vessels, or, allowing for errors, very<lb/>
rarely so conveyed. The distance which had been found safe was some-<lb/>
thing over 250 fathoms -- 1,500 feet. No minimum however had been<lb/>
established. The prevaling wind was generally slightly on shore, but<lb/>
was not constantly blowing. Whether there is any difference in the<lb/>
distance to which infected or non-infected mosquitoes are conveyed is<lb/>
of course entirely a matter of surmise. Yet the infected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi><lb/>
have almost certainly become so in a house; and, with their very domes-<lb/>
tic habits, must be found out of doors, where they would be subject<lb/>
to conveyance by the wind, in much smaller numbers than the unin-<lb/>
fected insects, and consequently a lesser <hi rend="italic">number</hi> of them would be con-<lb/>
veyed aerially. Observation is needed on this subject -- the disance<lb/>
(across water) that <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi> are aerially conveyed.</p>
<p>Goldberger, very ingeniously, suggests that on account of its diurnal<lb/>
flight, the direction of the wind during the <hi rend="italic">day only</hi> need be considered<lb/>
in estimating this factor in their aerial conveyance, and states that at<lb/>
Tampico, he has failed to find <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> aboard vessels lying for ten<lb/>
or fifteen days about half a mile from a shore where they were abun-<lb/>
dant, while numbers of <hi rend="italic">Anopheles albipes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Culex pungens</hi> were<lb/>
found. The wind was on shore during the day and calm or off shore<lb/>
during the night. The importance of this point is obvious, as on the<lb/>
coast, except when overborne by the trades, the direction of the wind<lb/>
is very generally different by day and night.</p>
<p>To sum up.</p>
<p>Among the special characteristics of the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> which affect its<lb/>
role as a carrier of yellow fever are:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Its distribution.<lb/>
This is, generally, between lats. 43 N. and 43 S. on the coasts and<lb/>
low plains of Africa, Asia, and the adjacent islands; Australia and the<lb/>
Mediterranean basin of Europe.<lb/>
It is also general on the eastern coast of America from 38 N. to 35<lb/>
<pb n="63" id="f02708063"/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
63<lb/>
S. Lat. On the west coast it is found at Panama and Guyaquil, and<lb/>
its existence is <hi rend="italic">implied</hi> from Guyaquil to Acapulco.<lb/>
In the United States it is general on the coast and low plains of the<lb/>
southern states, except Maryland.</item>
<item>2. That it is conveyed by vessels indefinite distances (from Cape<lb/>
Town to Savannah Quarantine); in much greater numbers and more<lb/>
often by sail than by steam vessels.</item>
<item>3. That it lives a long time -- 154 days being recorded by Guiteras<lb/>
of an infected insect.</item>
<item>4. That once having acquired the power of transmitting yellow<lb/>
fever it retains it apparently as long as it lives -- 59 days being re-<lb/>
corded.<lb/>
A consideration of the four postulates above will render it advisable<lb/>
to safeguard the tropical countries of the east when communication is<lb/>
opened up between them and American ports infected with yellow fever,<lb/>
preferably by freeing the American ports of yellow fever.</item>
<item>5. That it propagates preferably in artificial containers, but will<lb/>
propagate in pools where such containers are not available.</item>
<item>6. That in America it has been reported only in the vicinity of<lb/>
human dwellings and seems here not to be a sylvan, paludal, or camp-<lb/>
estral mosquito.<lb/>
From 5 and 6 the war against this insect in America should be waged<lb/>
about the houses of men, and especially against water in artificial con-<lb/>
tainers. The introduction of a water supply, piped to every house so<lb/>
as to do away with cisterns and water jars, is the most important meas-<lb/>
ure of sanitary engineering to free a town of this mosquito. Next to<lb/>
this is a system of drainage by covered drains to carry off the rain<lb/>
water and prevent pools. Cess-pools are not objectionable on this<lb/>
score.</item>
<item>7. It unquestionably hybernates in the United States, either as<lb/>
adult larva or egg, but if the <hi rend="italic">infected adult</hi> hybernates, either a very<lb/>
large proportion of them die, or else the infecting parasite must <hi rend="italic">gen-<lb/>
erally</hi> die in the hybernating mosquito. The first seems more probable.</item>
<item>8. It is essentially a house mosquito, and is inclined to stay about<lb/>
the premises where it has fed. Hence the greater safety of the whole-<lb/>
sale district of an infected city as compared with the residence portion.</item>
<item>9. It does not feed in the dark or in bright sunlight. Therefore<lb/>
in bright daylight or at night without artificial light are the safest times<lb/>
to be in an infected place.</item>
<item>10. The cycle of the yellow fever parasite in the mosquito before it<lb/>
can be conveyed to man is generally, in hot weather, about fourteen<lb/>
days or over. Prior to the accomplishment of this cycle (once called<lb/>
<pb n="64" id="f02708064"/>
64<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">CHARACTERISTICS OF THE STEGOMYIA FASCIATA</hi>.<lb/>
the &ldquo;extrinsic incubation of yellow fever&rdquo;) the mosquito cannot con-<lb/>
vey this disease.</item>
<item>11. It is probably usually conveyed aerially less than 100 yards.<lb/>
In Havana the <hi rend="italic">infected</hi> insect is believed not to be aerially conveyed<lb/>
250 fathoms -- 1,500 feet -- from the Havana shore.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The direction of the prevailing wind <hi rend="italic">during the day</hi> influences its<lb/>
aerial conveyance.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="5">
<head>PERIOD OF THE DISEASE IN MAN DURING WHICH<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER CAN BE TRANSMITTED TO THE<lb/>
MOSQUITO.</head>
<pb n="65" id="f02708065"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>COL. W. C. GORGAS</docAuthor>,<lb/>
ASSISTANT SURGEON-GENERAL U. S. ARMY, WASHINGTON, D. C.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub H. A - 31st meet<lb/>
Wash Oct 26-30, 1903</p>
<p>Since the publication of the work of the Army Medical Board, of<lb/>
which Major Reed was Chairman, concerning the etiology of yellow<lb/>
fever, a great deal of work has been done with respect to this disease,<lb/>
and some knowledge added to our present store concerning it. The<lb/>
most important, probably, is the work of the yellow fever board of<lb/>
the Public Health and Marine Hospital Service at Vera Cruz, Mexico,<lb/>
which has recently been published. They give very strong evidence<lb/>
that they have discovered a micro-organism closely related to yellow<lb/>
fever. They find that organism in the salivary glands of infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes, which they do not find in the glands of uninfected mosquitoes<lb/>
of the same species. This, it seems to me, is a very helpful step<lb/>
toward discovering the organism which causes yellow fever, but there<lb/>
is still a wide field for work in clearing up obscure points in the etiology<lb/>
of this disease. One point as to which there seems to be a very gen-<lb/>
eral misconception, is with regard to the period during which a patient<lb/>
suffering from yellow fever can convey the disease to the mosquito.<lb/>
Every writer, in my knowledge, who refers to this subject, states that<lb/>
the mosquito can become contaminated only within the first three<lb/>
days of the disease in the human being. Manson, in his last edition,<lb/>
page 192, states as follows: &ldquo;Duration of the infective period -- This<lb/>
is singularly circumscribed. The American observers have shown that<lb/>
a yellow fever patient is dangerous to his neighbors only during the<lb/>
first three days of the disease. After this he cannot confer infection.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Major R. H. Firth, Royal Army Medical Corps, in the Report of<lb/>
the Army Medical Department for the year 1901, Vol. XLIII, page<lb/>
364, says: &ldquo;A further important fact has been established, namely,<lb/>
as to when a yellow fever patient is infectious, that is, capable of in-<lb/>
fecting mosquitoes. He appears to be infectious only during the first<lb/>
three days of the disease; therefore, if the patient is protected with a<lb/>
fine mesh screen during the first or infectious stage, he ceases there-<lb/>
after to be a source of danger to anyone.&rdquo; And others make this same<lb/>
statement. These statements probably arise from the fact that the<lb/>
conclusions arrived at by the Army Board, conclude that if a female<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> mosquito bites a human being suffering from yellow fever,<lb/>
65<lb/>
<pb n="66" id="f02708066"/>
66<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">TRANSMISSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
within the first three days of the disease, she can transmit it, etc.<lb/>
The Board mean to state by this, the fact that a female <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi><lb/>
mosquito, contaminated within that period, may transmit the disease,<lb/>
but do not mean to assert at all that one infected after the third day<lb/>
will not transmit the disease. While mosquitoes were applied to yel-<lb/>
low fever patients after the third day, and failed to transmit the dis-<lb/>
ease, there were other causes for this failure, and they were unable<lb/>
to make any positive statement with regard to its communicability<lb/>
after that period. Writers on the subject have probably dropped into<lb/>
error, misunderstanding the statement of the Board, concluding from<lb/>
their languge in stating that <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> mosquito biting within the<lb/>
first three days, could transmit the disease, that one biting after that<lb/>
period could not transmit. From conversation with the late Dr. Reed<lb/>
on the subject, I found out that he did not at all hold the view that<lb/>
the disease could not be communicated to the mosquito after this<lb/>
period, and Dr. Carroll also writes me to this effect. All that their<lb/>
conclusions meant to convey was the positive fact that the disease<lb/>
could be communicated within the first three days, and as they made<lb/>
no experiments with mosquitoes infected after that period, they could<lb/>
draw no conclusions. I, myself, though on the ground with the experi-<lb/>
menters and seeing all their work, came to the same conclusion, namely,<lb/>
that the disease could not be communicated after the third day, and<lb/>
have so stated in articles on the subject. My friend, Dr. Ross, of the<lb/>
Navy, the Chairman of the committee, also makes the same statement,<lb/>
and Colonel Havard, of the Army, does the same. Both these gentle-<lb/>
men were on the ground, and in touch with the experiments as they<lb/>
were going along. This is a very important and vital point, and<lb/>
ought to be settled at an early date. If a patient cannot infect the<lb/>
mosquito after the third day of his disease, precautions to prevent his<lb/>
being bitten by the mosquito should be laid aside after that time.<lb/>
This would be of very great assistance to the practical sanitary officer.<lb/>
Everything that minimizes the trouble and inconvenience to the people<lb/>
at large, in enforcing sanitary measures, is a great help in popularizing<lb/>
these measures, and in preventing opposition to their enforcement. If<lb/>
the sanitary officer, at the end of the third day, could withdraw his<lb/>
guard, and leave all isolation of the patient to the family concerned,<lb/>
it would be a great step in the practicability of enforcing sanitary<lb/>
measures against yellow fever. But if this is not so, and a mosquito<lb/>
can become infected at a later period of the disease, a fatal error<lb/>
would have been committed by so doing, and the disease would prob-<lb/>
ably spread, just as if no isolation had been attempted. So far as I<lb/>
know, there is no evidence whatever to show that the disease is not<lb/>
infectious after the third day, except the fact that in all transmitted<lb/>
<pb n="67" id="f02708067"/>
<hi rend="italic">TRANSMISSION OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
67<lb/>
cases, the mosquitoes were infected within the third day of the disease,<lb/>
and no attempts were made to infect mosquitoes after this period.<lb/>
The Board were endeavoring to prove that yellow fever could be trans-<lb/>
mitted by the mosquito. It happened that the mosquitoes at first used<lb/>
were infected within the first three days, and to be sure of transmitting<lb/>
the disease in infecting subsequent mosquitoes, they followed exactly<lb/>
the methods that had been used in the first cases. With our present<lb/>
knowledge on this subject, I think that a yellow fever patient should<lb/>
be carefully protected from mosquitoes until convalescence is well estab-<lb/>
lished, and that the same care should be taken with regard to the<lb/>
bodies of the dead. Whether the mosquito will, or can, feed upon a<lb/>
dead body, I do not know. I think it probable that she will be unable<lb/>
to get blood after circulation has ceased, but until we have more posi-<lb/>
tive knowledge on this subject, sanitarians should guard against the<lb/>
possibility of the spread of the disease from this source.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="6">
<head>NEW ASPECTS OF YELLOW FEVER ETIOLOGY ARISING<lb/>
FROM EXPERIMENTAL FINDINGS OF THE LAST<lb/>
THREE YEARS.</head>
<pb n="68" id="f02708068"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>DR. CARLOS J. FINLAY</docAuthor>, HAVANA, CUBA.</byline>
<p>Proc am Public H. A - 31st meet<lb/>
Wash Oct. 26-30, 1903</p>
<p>In the light of modern research yellow fever must now be con-<lb/>
sidered as a disease produced, in individuals belonging to certain<lb/>
human races, by a two-host, microscopic, perhaps ultra-microscopic<lb/>
germ, endo-parasite of the female of a particular species of mosquito<lb/>
-- the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> (Theobald).</p>
<p>This germ pursues its parasitic existence in the body of the in-<lb/>
fected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> during a period of fifty-nine days, as experiments<lb/>
have proved, and probably, under ordinary circumstances till the death<lb/>
of the mosquito host.</p>
<p>In order, however, that it may complete its life cycle, secure the<lb/>
perpetuation of its species, and find its way into the body of other<lb/>
healthy <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>, it is necessary that it, the aforesaid germ or para-<lb/>
site, should penetrate, through the bit of the infected insect into the<lb/>
body of a person who is liable to undergo an attack of yellow fever.</p>
<p>After parting from its mosquito-host, the germ, apparently, goes<lb/>
through certain evolutions in the body of the non-immune, and, after<lb/>
the lapse of from three to five days, as a rule, brings about the at-<lb/>
tack of yellow fever. What the character of thsee evolutions may be<lb/>
can only be surmised. We do know, however, that while the sojourn<lb/>
of the germ in the body of the infected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> may continue dur-<lb/>
ing at least two months without perceptibly affecting the longevity or<lb/>
the functional activity of its insect-host, its presence in the human-<lb/>
host only reveals itself during a short number of days, disappear-<lb/>
ing, apparently, by the end of the sixth day, without leaving any<lb/>
other trace of its passage through the human-host except the im-<lb/>
munity which a first attack of yellow fever confers. The person thus<lb/>
immunized can, thereafter, receive with impunity the bites of any<lb/>
number of infected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyias</hi>, and become incapacitated from con-<lb/>
tributing again to the perpetuation of the germ.</p>
<p>Since the first day of the attack of yellow fever (as early as the<lb/>
ninth hour in one of Dr. Carroll's cases) any healthy <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> that<lb/>
bites the patient is liable to become infected, so that a new life cycle<lb/>
will be opened for the germ in this fresh <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>. Thus by alter-<lb/>
nately passing from the human to the mosquito-host and vice versa,<lb/>
the yellow fever germ has now lived during several consecutive cen-<lb/>
68<lb/>
<pb n="69" id="f02708069"/>
<hi rend="italic">NEW ASPECTS OF YELLOW FEVER ETIOLOGY</hi>.<lb/>
69<lb/>
turies in tropical America, where both the aborigines and the European<lb/>
invaders belonged to susceptible races.</p>
<p>Now, let us consider the probable character of the evolutions which<lb/>
the yellow fever germ undergoes in the body of the human host.<lb/>
Bearing in mind the fact that other two-host protozoa such as the<lb/>
malaria parasite, lead during several consecutive months a parasitic<lb/>
existence multiplying by schizogonia, forming schizonts, merozoits and<lb/>
after awhile also gametes, in the body of their permanent host, and<lb/>
are unable to accomplish the sexual reproduction indispensable for the<lb/>
perpetuation of their species, unless they pass into the body of a<lb/>
second host -- (the <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi>, in the case of the malaria parasite);<lb/>
bearing all this in mind. I say, are we not justified in supposing that<lb/>
the yellow fever parasite being unable to accomplish this sexual re-<lb/>
production in the body of its permanent mosquito-host, can only suc-<lb/>
ceed in doing so by passing into the body of a non-immune human<lb/>
being after some of its elements have reached a stage of sexual dif-<lb/>
ferentiation corresponding to the gametes of malaria? There is,<lb/>
moreover, another important consideration which may be adduced<lb/>
in support of this interpretation. The large tertian parasite un-<lb/>
treated may continue for many months in the body of infected per-<lb/>
sons without immediate danger to the patient, whereas Grassi, I am<lb/>
informed, has found all the <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi> in the Roman marshes, free<lb/>
from parasites during the winter season, so that all the infected ones<lb/>
must have died in consequence of their infection, and the renewal of<lb/>
the malaria epidemic in the following spring is attributed to the sur-<lb/>
vival of the parasites in the body of the human permanent-host. This<lb/>
shows that the act of sexual reproduction is attended with more<lb/>
dangerous results for the host in which it is accomplished than<lb/>
happens during the various schizogonic phases of the same germ: A<lb/>
result which I had already surmised by reason of the greater meta-<lb/>
bolic changes which must accompany the sexual reproduction as com-<lb/>
pared with the schizogonic multiplication.</p>
<p>If it be admitted, therefore, that the penetration of the germ into<lb/>
the body of the non-immune is intended for the accomplishment of<lb/>
its sexual reproduction, and also that the analogy between it and the<lb/>
malaria parasite holds good, with the difference only that the lat-<lb/>
ter accomplishes this act in the <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi> mosquito while the yellow<lb/>
fever germ does so in the human host, the following important in-<lb/>
ferences may be drawn.</p>
<p>The minimum number of days (estimated at 10 or 12 by the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Army Board) which must elapse after the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> has bitten<lb/>
a yellow fever patient before the infected insect is able to inoculate<lb/>
<pb n="70" id="f02708070"/>
70<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">NEW ASPECTS OF YELLOW FEVER ETIOLOGY</hi>.<lb/>
the disease through its bites, must represent a series of transformations<lb/>
in the body of the contaminated mosquito, including:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The introduction of young sporozoits sucked up with<lb/>
the blood of the patient.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Growth of the sporozoits to adult age.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Formation of schizonts and merozoits.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) Formation of gametes.</item>
</list></p>
<p>While in the body of the non-immune, counting from the moment<lb/>
of his inoculation by the infected <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>, the following stages are<lb/>
likely to take place during the period of incubation:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Localization of the gametes in appropriate sites.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Fecundation of the macro by the micro-gametes of<lb/>
the yellow fever germ.</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Formation of the o&ouml;kinet and the development of the<lb/>
o&ouml;cyst in appropriate cells (enclothelial?)</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) Discharges of the free sporozoits of yellow fever<lb/>
into the circulating blood (perhaps too small to be recog-<lb/>
nized with a microscope).</item>
<item>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) Development of the toxemic symptoms characteristic<lb/>
of the invasion of yellow fever, in the inoculated non-immune.</item>
</list></p>
<p>In calling your attention to this correlation of ideas, my object is<lb/>
not the display of fanciful conceptions, but simply to comply with my<lb/>
belief that unless we map out for ourselves some working hypothesis<lb/>
of this kind, we shall continue groping in the dark with little hope of<lb/>
ever completing our knowledge of the yellow fever eitology.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="7">
<head>CONCERNING THE GEOGRAPHIC DISTRIBUTION OF THE<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER MOSQUITO.</head>
<pb n="71" id="f02708071"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>L. O. HOWARD</docAuthor>, PH. D.,<lb/>
CHIEF ENTOMOLOGIST, U. S. DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE: HON. CURATOR OF<lb/>
INSECTS, U. S. NATIONAL MUSEUM: CONSULTING ENTOMOLOGIST,<lb/>
U. S. PUBLIC HEALTH AND MARINE HOSPITAL SERVICE,<lb/>
WASHINGTON, D. C.</byline>
<p>Proc am Pub H A - 31st meet<lb/>
Wash Oct 26-30, 1903</p>
<p>The proper consideration of this now all-important species must<lb/>
necessarily be divided into two sections; first, the actual present dis-<lb/>
tribution of the species so far as it can be ascertained; second, the<lb/>
exact limitations of the regions in which, if accidentally introduced,<lb/>
it may reasonably be expected to propagate and to become perfectly<lb/>
established. For immediate quarantine purposes the first of these is<lb/>
the most important, but looking to the future, an exact knowledge<lb/>
of the regions which must be included in the second category, is<lb/>
obviously scarcely less important.</p>
<p>1. THE PRESENT KNOWN DISTRIBUTION OF THE SPECIES.</p>
<p>When Mr. F. V. Theobald published his two volumes &ldquo;A Monograph<lb/>
of the Culicid&aelig; of the World,&rdquo; in 1901, he stated roughly that <hi rend="italic">Stego-<lb/>
myia fasciata</hi>, which at that time was not known to him as the &ldquo;yellow<lb/>
fever&rdquo; mosquito, ranged from 38&deg; S. Lat. to 38&deg; N. Lat., and his map<lb/>
upon p. 292, Vol. I, indicated a general distribution throughout east-<lb/>
ern Australia; western Sumatra; all of Java and farther India; south-<lb/>
ern Japan; eastern Hindostan; the Seychelles; southeastern Africa;<lb/>
the African West Coast, including Senegambia; and the District<lb/>
Lagos; all of Spain; southern Italy; the east coast of South America<lb/>
from British Guiana to Rio de la Plata; all of Cuba; Jamaica; Hayti;<lb/>
and all of the southern United States. In volume III of this important<lb/>
monograph, published in 1903, the same author includes the follow-<lb/>
ing under &ldquo;<hi rend="italic">New Localities</hi>&rdquo;: St. Kitts, Nevis, Antigua, Carriacou<lb/>
(Grenadine Islands), Trinidad (Hewlett), Barbadoes, Dominica, Mont-<lb/>
serrat (Low) Luzon, Philippine Islands (Sept. 7. '01, Miss C. S. Lud-<lb/>
low); Port Darwin, South Australia; Para (Durham); Gambia<lb/>
(Burdett); taken in houses, McCarthy Islands, in July; Victoria, Sey-<lb/>
chelles (Denman); Nigeria (Hanley); Fiji (Hewlett). Elsewhere<lb/>
he adds: Tyre and Sidon, Palestine; old Calabar; Mashonaland;<lb/>
Malay Peninsula and Eastern Archipelago; Argentine, South America.</p>
<p>71</p>
<pb n="72" id="f02708072"/>
<p>72<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">DISTRIBUTION OF YELLOW FEVER MOSQUITO</hi>.</p>
<p>In my book on mosquitoes, published in 1901, I gave the then known<lb/>
distribution in the United States as follows: &ldquo;In the United States<lb/>
it is common in most of our Southern States. I have seen specimens<lb/>
from New Orleans, La.; Natchitoches, La.; and Napoleonville, La.;<lb/>
eastern Texas; Hot Springs, Ark.; Pelham, Ga.; Virginia Beach,<lb/>
Va.&rdquo; Since that time many new localities have been discovered, and<lb/>
our present knowledge of the exact localities may be tabulated as<lb/>
follows:</p>
<p>UNITED STATES.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Virginia</hi>, -- Virginia Beach. <hi rend="italic">Kentucky</hi>, -- Lexington. <hi rend="italic">Illinois</hi>, --<lb/>
Cairo. <hi rend="italic">Tennessee</hi>, -- Nashville. <hi rend="italic">Arkansas</hi>, -- Hot Springs. <hi rend="italic">Louisi-<lb/>
ana</hi>, -- Ruddock, New Orleans, Baton Rouge, Napoleonville, Ham-<lb/>
mond, Shreveport, Franklin. <hi rend="italic">Mississippi</hi>, -- Pass Christian, Summit,<lb/>
Quarantine Station, Biloxi. <hi rend="italic">Georgia</hi>, -- Atlanta, Pelham, Augusta,<lb/>
Savannah, Brunswick. <hi rend="italic">Florida</hi>, -- Barrancas, Key West. <hi rend="italic">Texas</hi>, --<lb/>
Galveston, Houston, Victoria, San Diego, Tyler. <hi rend="italic">South Carolina</hi>, --<lb/>
Charleston, Sullivan's Island. <hi rend="italic">Maryland</hi>, -- Baltimore (Carter) --<lb/>
breeding in fresh water on fruit wharf. <hi rend="italic">North Carolina</hi>, -- Beaufort,<lb/>
Winston.</p>
<p>MEXICO.</p>
<p>Tampico, Acapulco, Guanajuato, Frontera, Vera Cruz, La Paz<lb/>
(Lower California), Coatzocoalcos, Pachuco, Tuxpan, Nautla, Tlaco-<lb/>
talpam, Mazatlan, San Blas, Carmen, Cozumel, Champoton, Perihuete,<lb/>
Las Pe&ntilde;as.</p>
<p>They have been received from <hi rend="italic">British Honduras</hi>, -- Belize; <hi rend="italic">Nica-<lb/>
ragua</hi>, -- Blue Fields; <hi rend="italic">Costa Rica</hi>, -- Limon, and Bocas del Toro; and<lb/>
have also been received from one of the low-lying localities not specific-<lb/>
ally designated.</p>
<p>From the <hi rend="italic">Hawaiian Islands</hi> they have been received from Honolulu<lb/>
and Hilo.</p>
<p>They were collected by my assistant, Mr. Marlatt, in <hi rend="italic">Java</hi> at Batavia,<lb/>
Soekaboemi, Garoet and at Singapore, <hi rend="italic">Malay Peninsula</hi>.</p>
<p>From the <hi rend="italic">Philippine Islands</hi> they have been received from Iligan,<lb/>
Mindanao; and from Haganoy and Bulacan, Luzon; also from Iloilo.</p>
<p>In <hi rend="italic">Cuba</hi> they have been received from Columbia Barracks, Havana;<lb/>
from Guantanamo, Daiquiri, Baracoa, San Antonio de los Banos, Caya-<lb/>
mas. &ldquo;Yaquaramoa,&rdquo; and the Isle of Pines.</p>
<p>From the British West Indies they have been received from Jamaica,<lb/>
and Montserrat.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Bahama Islands</hi>: Nassau, Spanish Wells, Harbor Island, Current,<lb/>
Tarpon Bay, San Salvador, Long Island, and Government Harbor.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Brazil</hi>: Campinas.</p>
<pb n="73" id="f02708073"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">DISTRIBUTION OF YELLOW FEVER MOSQUITO</hi>.<lb/>
73</p>
<p>No European specimens have been received, but a very interesting<lb/>
locality has turned up in Ismailia, Egypt, whence specimens were<lb/>
received from Dr. W. C. Gorgas, of the U. S. Army.</p>
<p>From the above it will be seen that although the actual localities<lb/>
which may specifically be designated from the United States, are com-<lb/>
paratively small in number, and that although combining Theobald's<lb/>
list with our own, the actual localities from other parts of the world<lb/>
are equally sparse, we have still sufficient facts to enable, in my opinion,<lb/>
a sound generalization, both as to probable actual occurrence, and as<lb/>
to regions in which the species will readily establish itself if once intro-<lb/>
duced. It will be noticed that all of the occurrences with the United<lb/>
States, except Lexington, fall within the limits of what are known as<lb/>
the tropical and Lower Austral Zones. These life zones include prac-<lb/>
tically all of the southern United States which border on the Atlantic<lb/>
Ocean and the Gulf of Mexico, with the exception of those portions<lb/>
of Virginia, North and South Carolina, Georgia, and Alabama, which<lb/>
constitute practically the foot-hills of the Appalachian chain; in other<lb/>
words, western Virginia and North Carolina, the extreme northwestern<lb/>
corner of South Carolina, the northern part of Georgia and the ex-<lb/>
treme northeastern corner of Alabama. Further than this the Lower<lb/>
Austral Zone includes the western half of Tennessee, the western cor-<lb/>
ner of Kentucky, the extreme southern tip of Illinois, the southeastern<lb/>
corner of Missouri, and all of Arkansas, except the northern portion.<lb/>
It also includes the southern portion of Indian Territory, southern<lb/>
Arizona, and some of northern Arizona; and southern strips in Utah,<lb/>
Nevada, and California.</p>
<p>In the greater part of the territory thus indicated, and <hi rend="italic">where the<lb/>
climate is not too dry, Stegomyia fasciata</hi> will, with little doubt, upon<lb/>
close search, be found.</p>
<p>2. THE EXACT LIMITATIONS OF THE REGIONS IN WHICH, IF ACCIDENT-<lb/>
ALLY INTRODUCED, IT MAY REASONABLY BE EXPECTED TO PROPA-<lb/>
GATE, AND TO BECOME PERFECTLY ESTABLISHED.</p>
<p>All the rest of the Lower Austral Territory just indicated, and<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">where the climate is not too dry</hi>, will constitute a region where the<lb/>
yellow fever mosquito, if once introduced, will undoubtedly flourish.<lb/>
Even in the drier portions of western Texas, southern New Mexico,<lb/>
Arizona, southern California, southern Nevada, and southern and<lb/>
northern Arizona where the climate is exceptionally dry, there is a<lb/>
possibility that this species, if once introduced, will breed in the water<lb/>
supply of ranches, except possibly, where the water is impregnated<lb/>
with alkali.</p>
<pb n="74" id="f02708074"/>
<p>74<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">DISTRIBUTION OF YELLOW FEVER MOSQUITO</hi>.</p>
<p>Having made this generalization for the United States, where<lb/>
through the admirable work of Dr. C. Hart Merriam and his Division<lb/>
of Biological Survey of the United States Department of Agriculture,<lb/>
the subject of the exact limitations of the life zones has been so accu-<lb/>
rately investigated, and where these zones have been so carefully<lb/>
mapped out, we naturally may follow it with a corresponding generali-<lb/>
zation for other countries, where the factors which control the distri-<lb/>
bution of animal and vegetable life are, of course, comparable to<lb/>
those which exist in the United States. We may expect to find this<lb/>
species everywhere in the moist tropics, or at all events, when intro-<lb/>
duced at any point within the moist tropics, it may be expected to<lb/>
establish itself. The conditions which control the distribution of life<lb/>
in the so-called Lower Austral Zone, will naturally hold equally in<lb/>
corresponding sections elsewhere, and it becomes necessary to formu-<lb/>
late as easy a means as possible of ascertaining a region between the<lb/>
parallels of latitude of 38&deg; N. and 38&deg; S., whose condition will cor-<lb/>
respond to those of the Lower Austral Zone in the United States,<lb/>
and which will thus admit of the breeding of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>. It<lb/>
has been determined by Dr. Merriam that the northern limit of the<lb/>
Lower Austral Zone is marked by the isotherm showing a sum of<lb/>
normal, positive temperatures of ten thousand degrees centigrade or<lb/>
eighteen thousand degrees Fahrenheit. The sum of normal positive<lb/>
temperatures, means the sum of normal mean daily temperatures above<lb/>
six degrees centigrade, or forty-three degrees Fahrenheit. With this<lb/>
rule as a basis we may take, for example, on the borders of the plateau<lb/>
region in Mexico, any given locality, or elevation, and may sum up<lb/>
the normal mean daily temperatures above six degrees centigrade, or<lb/>
forty-three degrees Fahrenheit, and if this sum for the year reaches<lb/>
ten thousand degrees centigrade, or eighteen thousand degrees Fahren-<lb/>
heit, it is safe to say that the locality is within the limits of the Upper<lb/>
Austral Life Zone, and that the yellow fever mosquito will breed there.</p>
<p>The minimum temperature of six degrees centigrade, or forty-three<lb/>
degrees Fahrenheit, has been estimated as marking the inception of<lb/>
reproductive activity in animals; in other words, the formula which<lb/>
we have just given means that the physiological constant of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia<lb/>
fasciata</hi> is approximately ten thousand degrees centigrade. I have,<lb/>
in the opening paragraph under this head, italicised the clause &ldquo;where<lb/>
the climate is not too dry,&rdquo; for while the temperature predetermines<lb/>
the possibilities of distribution, and fixes the limits beyond which the<lb/>
species cannot pass, and defines certain broad transcontinental <unclear>belts</unclear><lb/>
within which certain forms may thrive, <hi rend="italic">if other conditions permit</hi>,<lb/>
it is by no means the sole factor which determines distribution. Never-<lb/>
<pb n="75" id="f02708075"/>
<hi rend="italic">DISTRIBUTION OF YELLOW FEVER MOSQUITO</hi>.<lb/>
75<lb/>
theless, other conditions being never so favorable, the species possessing<lb/>
the physiological constant characteristic of this zone, cannot exist<lb/>
outside. With mosquitoes it is obvious that the factor next in im-<lb/>
portance to temperature, will be moisture, and in the arid tropics, and<lb/>
in the very dry portions of the Upper Austral Zone, we will not natur-<lb/>
ally look for an abundance of mosquitoes, except under artificial con-<lb/>
ditions brought about by civilization. <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>, however,<lb/>
being a domestic species, that is to say being practically dependent<lb/>
upon the conditions surrounding human habitations, is less subject to<lb/>
normal conditions of moisture, than are the species of the fields and<lb/>
woods.</p>
<p>It is interesting to note that the geographic distribution of the yel-<lb/>
low fever mosquito corresponds rather well with that of the Texas<lb/>
cattle tick (<hi rend="italic">Boophilus annulatus</hi>) which is instrumental in the carriage<lb/>
of the haematozoan of Texas fever. That too is a creature which<lb/>
seems confined to the tropical and Lower Austral Zones.</p>
<p>The southern border of the Austral Zone has not been expressed<lb/>
in a similar formula, but this is unnecessary for the present considera-<lb/>
tion, since the mosquito breeds readily in both tropical and Upper<lb/>
Austral Zones.</p>
<p>The southern limit of the zone in the southern hemisphere, cor-<lb/>
responding to the northern limits of the Upper Austral Life Zone in<lb/>
the northern hemisphere, can probably be calculated by the use of the<lb/>
same formula, and thus in any given locality in the southern hemi-<lb/>
sphere the probable occurrence, or at all events the proper climatic<lb/>
conditions for the existence of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>, can be ascertained.</p>
<p>I conceive that the facts thus formulated, are, and will be, of great<lb/>
importance in the determination of quarantine measures, and that the<lb/>
careful records which have been urged by the International Congress<lb/>
of Sanitarians of the American Republics will justify these broad<lb/>
conclusions.</p>
<p>In an article published in the Journal of Tropical Medicine, for<lb/>
August 1, 1903, Mr. Theobald gives some further notes concerning<lb/>
the distribution of other species of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>, in which he shows a<lb/>
slightly greater northern and southern distribution, with other forms<lb/>
of the same genus, enlarging the field to from 43&deg; S. to 43&deg; N. latitude.<lb/>
As yet, however, the agency of only a single species, <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>,<lb/>
in the transfer of yellow fever, has been proven. Let us, for the<lb/>
present, await experimentation with other species, -- <hi rend="italic">S. africana, S.<lb/>
argenteopuncta, S. notoscripta, S. sugnes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S. scutellaris</hi>, -- before<lb/>
beginning further attempts at generalization. In fact it may very<lb/>
likely be shown that these species have not so close a relationship to<lb/>
<pb n="76" id="f02708076"/>
76<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">DISTRIBUTION OF YELLOW FEVER MOSQUITO</hi>.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">S. fasciata</hi> as to warrant the belief that they may be instrumental in<lb/>
the carriage of disease. In fact the Australian species <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia<lb/>
notoscripta</hi>, laying its eggs as it does in &ldquo;rafts,&rdquo; and not singly as<lb/>
does <hi rend="italic">S. fasciata</hi> may very likely prove to be a distant, rather than a<lb/>
close, relative of the dangerous form.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="8">
<head><unclear>&check;</unclear> THE MOSQUITOES IN MEXICO CITY.</head>
<pb n="77" id="f02708077"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>DR. LUIS E. RUIZ</docAuthor>, MEXICO, D. F.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub H A - 31 meet<lb/>
Wash Oct 26-30, 1903</p>
<p>I.</p>
<p>THE PROBLEM.</p>
<p>One of the interesting subjects of hygiene and therefore one which<lb/>
has the greatest importance for public health, is that which refers to<lb/>
transmissible diseases.</p>
<p>What is their cause; what is the law that rules them, and what is<lb/>
the mechanism of their transmission? These are the points that it<lb/>
is necessary to resolve for instituting the prophylaxis of these diseases<lb/>
that only then can be entirely efficacious.</p>
<p>That these diseases are caused by micro-organisms is a knowledge<lb/>
completely acquired.</p>
<p>That these pathogenic agents come into our organism with the air<lb/>
we inspire or with the food we take, or, breaking through the surface<lb/>
of the body by breaks in the skin or in the mucous membranes, is<lb/>
another knowledge that we have conquered.</p>
<p>But in this third case the cause is not always the contact of contam-<lb/>
inated objects with the injured skin; many times it is the intermedia-<lb/>
tion of an animal that takes the germ from a sick person and brings<lb/>
it to a healthy one.</p>
<p>Examples: Paludism, yellow fever and the plague, the intermedi-<lb/>
aries being, for the first, the anopheles, for the second, the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>;<lb/>
(both mosquitoes) and for the third, the flea.</p>
<p>From the moment we know that mosquitoes, so abundant and of<lb/>
so many kinds in many places, are the sure vehicle for the trans-<lb/>
mission of certain diseases, we are obliged to study them, to identify<lb/>
them and to scutinize their life in order to put into practice the knowl-<lb/>
edge that we may acquire a complete efficacious prophylaxis for pre-<lb/>
venting these diseases.</p>
<p>In Mexico there are only two classes of mosquitoes, but some other<lb/>
classes either dangerous or contaminated can be brought into the city<lb/>
through the railroads that run from some points of the territory to<lb/>
the capital.</p>
<p>To state which are the former and to identify the latter, giving the<lb/>
watch-word against them, is the object of this imperfect essay.</p>
<p>77</p>
<pb n="80" id="f02708080"/>
<p>80<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">THE MOSQUITOES IN MEXICO CITY</hi>.</p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi>, found in a very small number in the southern part<lb/>
of the valley of Mexico where it has not been possible to find any<lb/>
larvae, was also brought from the southern region through the inter-<lb/>
oceanic railroad.</p>
<p>But up to this day we have not found any mosquitoes from remote<lb/>
places notwithstanding that we have looked for them very closely and<lb/>
that we have put in the freight cars, that come from those regions,<lb/>
capsules with a syrup made of a plant called &ldquo;<hi rend="italic">yerba de la cucaracha</hi>.&rdquo;</p>
<p>IV.</p>
<p>CONCLUSIONS.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. It is proved that the classes of mosquitoes called <hi rend="italic">Culex pungens</hi><lb/>
and <hi rend="italic">Culex impiger</hi>, exist in Mexico city.</item>
<item>2. That in Mexico city there were no <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi>.</item>
<item>3. That in the ports of the Mexican Republic exist the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi><lb/>
and the <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi>.</item>
<item>4. That in the hot land of the south exists the <hi rend="italic">Anopheles</hi>.</item>
<item>5. That in conditions, not well determined yet, the transportation<lb/>
of mosquitoes is possible.</item>
<item>6. From all the preceding conclusions we may infer: &ldquo;that it is<lb/>
absolutely indispensable to proceed methodically to the destruction of<lb/>
the noxious classes of mosquitoes, employing all the means of which<lb/>
the efficiency has been demonstrated by experience.</item>
</list>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="9">
<head>QUARANTINE REGULATIONS SHOULD BE BASED<lb/>
AGAINST YELLOW FEVER UPON THE DOCTRINE<lb/>
THAT IT IS ONLY CONVEYED BY THE<lb/>
MOSQUITO.</head>
<pb n="81" id="f02708081"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>J. M. LINDSLEY</docAuthor>, M. D., HAVANA, CUBA.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub H A - 31 Meet<lb/>
Wash Oct 1903</p>
<p>It is now a fact universally accepted by scientists that the mosquito<lb/>
known as the &ldquo;<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>&rdquo; is the only natural means by<lb/>
which yellow fever is transmitted: In 1881 Dr. Carlos J. Finlay of<lb/>
Havana, Cuba, advanced the theory that yellow fever was not conta-<lb/>
gious or infectious, but was transmitted by the bite of the mosquito.<lb/>
His proof was so plausible in the estimation of the English physicians<lb/>
who had been watching the experiments of Ross and Manson in regard<lb/>
to malarial fever, that as early as 1888 the Finlay theory was laid<lb/>
down in text book.*</p>
<p>After the American occupation of Havana, Cuba, the United<lb/>
States War Department appointed a commission to investigate<lb/>
the mosquito as a carrier of yellow fever. This commission, com-<lb/>
posed of Drs. Reed, Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte, after a series of<lb/>
experiments came to the conclusion that yellow fever was transmitted<lb/>
by the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> and that their experiments with fomites<lb/>
failed to produce a single case.</p>
<p>Before the Pan American Medical Congress held in Havana in<lb/>
February, 1901, a second report was submitted by Major Reed, which<lb/>
follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered"> 
<item>1. &ldquo;The mosquito <hi rend="italic">fasciatus</hi> serves as the intermediate host for the<lb/>
parasite of yellow fever.</item>
<item>2. Yellow fever is transmitted to the non-immune individual by the<lb/>
bite of the mosquito that has previously fed on the blood of those sick<lb/>
with this disease.&rdquo;</item>
<item>3. An interval of about thirteen days or more after contamination<lb/>
appears to be necessary before the mosquito is capable of conveying<lb/>
the infection.</item>
<item>4. The bite of the mosquito at an earlier period after contamina-<lb/>
tion does not appear to confer any immunity against a subsequent<lb/>
attack.</item>
<item>5. Yellow fever can also be experimentally produced by subcutane-<lb/>
ous injection of blood taken from the general circulation during the<lb/>
first and second days of this disease.</item>
</list></p>
<p>---------</p>
<p>*&ldquo;The prevention of disease in tropical campaigns,&rdquo; by Dr. Andrew Duncan<lb/>
and others.<lb/>
81</p>
<pb n="82" id="f02708082"/>
<p>82<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered"> 
<item>6. An attack of yellow fever produced by the bite of the mosquito<lb/>
confers immunity against the subsequent injection of the blood of an<lb/>
individual suffering from the nonexperimental form of this disease.</item>
<item>7. The period of incubation in 13 cases of experimental yellow<lb/>
fever has varied from forty-one hours to five days and seventeen hours.</item>
<item>8. While the mode of propagation of yellow fever has now been<lb/>
definitely determined, the specific cause of this disease remains to be<lb/>
discovered.</item>
<item>9. Yellow fever is not conveyed by fomites, and hence disinfection<lb/>
of articles of clothing, bedding, or merchandise, supposedly contamin-<lb/>
ated by contact with those sick of this disease, is unnecessary.</item>
<item>10. A house may be said to be infected with yellow fever only when<lb/>
there are present within its walls contaminated mosquitoes capable of<lb/>
conveying the parasite of this disease.</item>
<item>11. The spread of yellow fever can be most effectually controlled<lb/>
by measures directed to the destruction of mosquitoes and the protec-<lb/>
tion of the sick against the bites of these insects.</item>
</list></p>
<p>In the Report of the Working Party I, Yellow Fever Institute, &ldquo;&Aacute;<lb/>
Study of the Etiology of Yellow Fever,&rdquo; by Herman B. Parker, Assist-<lb/>
ant Surgeon, Geo. E. Beyer, Acting Assistant Surgeon, O. L. Pothier,<lb/>
Acting Assistant Surgeon, of the Public Health and Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service, was made and published by the Treasury Department, March,<lb/>
1903, from which I quote:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The whole mass of corroborative evidence is that the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia<lb/>
fasciata</hi> is the medium for the transference of the disease. This is<lb/>
looked upon as a definite scientific fact. Is it, or is it not, the only<lb/>
means of transference? To prove a negative assertion conditions must<lb/>
be supplied to produce the disease at will or under constant conditions.<lb/>
In the whole history of the disease such data, to this date, are wanting,<lb/>
When one instance occurs and can be repeated the new factor can then<lb/>
be taken into consideration.&rdquo;</p>
<p>On May 13, 1903, I sent the following letter to physicians in Cuba<lb/>
and the United States:<lb/>
<list type="ordered"> 
<item>1. &ldquo;Do you believe that the mosquito is the only natural means by<lb/>
which yellow fever is conveyed?</item>
<item>2. If not, what other?&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
<p>The following replies were received accepting the mosquito theory<lb/>
as the only means of transmitting yellow fever:</p>
<p>Dr. W. C. Gorgas, Ass't Surgeon Gen., U. S. Army, and who had<lb/>
charge of sanitary work in Havana, 1898 to 1902:</p>
<p>NEW YORK CITY, May 27th, 1903.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I believe that the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> mosquito is the only means in nature<lb/>
by which yellow fever is conveyed from person to person.</p>
<p>I hold that success of our sanitary work in Havana demonstrates<lb/>
this. During our work of eradicating that disease in 1901, we paid<lb/>
no attention to fomites of any kind, not only let the soiled clothing,<lb/>
<pb n="83" id="f02708083"/>
<hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
83<lb/>
etc., go freely to the wash in the case of the sick in the city, but after<lb/>
its disappearance from the city, we placed no prohibition upon baggage<lb/>
and household goods coming in from infected suburbs. The non-<lb/>
immunes from these suburbs were not detained but merely inspected<lb/>
daily for six days. We had during the year 1,200 non-immunes come<lb/>
into the city from infected points, and from these 1,200 our inspectors<lb/>
picked up 26 cases of yellow fever. The conditions at Havana were<lb/>
about as unfavorable as could exist.</p>
<p>You will find an interesting discussion in the report of the seven-<lb/>
teenth annual meeting of the &ldquo;Conference of State and Provincial<lb/>
Boards of Health,&rdquo; which met last year at New Haven. A committee<lb/>
had been appointed the preceding year to report as to whether the dis-<lb/>
infection of baggage was necessary in yellow fever. The report of<lb/>
this committee was that such disinfection was not necessary. I wish<lb/>
you success as it means a great deal in dollars and cents to the business<lb/>
interest of our Southern States.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. V. Havard, Med. Dept., U. S. A.</p>
<p>WEST POINT, N. Y.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In reply to the above would say that I believe the mosquito to be<lb/>
the only natural means by which yellow fever is conveyed. Any one<lb/>
who has read the accounts of our experiments in Havana and still be-<lb/>
lieves in the power of fomites to produce yellow fever, must be deaf,<lb/>
dumb and blind.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. James Carroll, Med. Dept., U. S. A.</p>
<p>WASHINGTON, May 16, 1903.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am thoroughly and firmly convinced that natural yellow fever<lb/>
is conveyed in no other way than through the bite of the mosquito.<lb/>
The transmission by that agent was first proved in my own person,<lb/>
August 31st, 1900, and this observation was subsequently confirmed<lb/>
by ourselves and by Guiteras. Our attempts to infect, by means of<lb/>
fomites, all resulted in failure and the same is true of the attempts<lb/>
made by Havard, Gorgas and Ross in the late summer of 1901.</p>
<p>The agency of the mosquito explains all the hitherto unexplainable<lb/>
facts in connection with the erratic course of the disease and its non-<lb/>
communicability in certain localities as well as the interval of time<lb/>
that must elapse between the appearance of the first and the occurrence<lb/>
of subsequent cases. This interval was seldom observed because the<lb/>
earliest cases of the disease have nearly always been called &ldquo;bilious<lb/>
remittent fever,&rdquo; &ldquo;dengue,&rdquo; or something else, until cases occurred<lb/>
with black vomit. Of our 22 consecutive cases of experimental yellow<lb/>
fever not one had black vomit, though some of them were severe.<lb/>
Guiteras lost three out of eight experimental cases with black vomit,<lb/>
so there is no room for doubt as to the genuine nature of the disease.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. H. R. Carter, Surgeon P. H. and M. H. S.<lb/>
<list type="ordered"> 
<item>1. &ldquo;I believe that the mosquito <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> is the only<lb/>
natural means of conveying yellow fever to man.</item>
<item>2. That this mosquito is infected in nature only by feeding on one<lb/>
sick of yellow fever.&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
<p>Baltimore, May 22, 1903.</p>
<pb n="84" id="f02708084"/>
<p>84<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>Dr. R. D. Murray, Surgeon P. H. and M. H. S.</p>
<p>Answer to first question--&ldquo;Yes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Answer to second question--&ldquo;None.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Key West, Fla., May 23, 1903.</p>
<p>Dr. John W. Ross, Med. Director, U. S. Navy.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do believe that the only way in nature for man to contract yellow<lb/>
fever is from the mosquito (<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>), or, in other words, that the<lb/>
mosquito is the only natural means by which yellow fever is conveyed<lb/>
to men seems absolutely demonstrated.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Washington, D. C., June 6th, 1903.</p>
<p>Carlos J. Finlay, M. D., Chief Sanitary Officer of Cuba, Havana:</p>
<p>In accordance with the request expressed in your circular of May<lb/>
13th, my answers to your two questions are as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered"> 
<item>1. I do firmly believe that the mosquito is the only natural means<lb/>
by which yellow fever is transmitted; my, experience in Havana dur-<lb/>
ing the last months admitting of no other interpretation.</item>
<item>2. During that space of time ten (10) yellow fever patients im-<lb/>
ported from different Mexican ports have been conveyed from the<lb/>
vessels on which they had come or from the observation camp across<lb/>
the bay, through the entire length of the streets of Havana, to Las<lb/>
Animas Hospital, and were there treated during consecutive weeks<lb/>
without the disease having ever been transmitted to the non-immunes<lb/>
who surrounded them. Now, considering that the only barrier which<lb/>
had been interposed between the said patients and the public or the<lb/>
other inmates of the hospital consisted in simple mosquito-bars or<lb/>
wire-netting of fourteen strands to the inch, this simple fact conclu-<lb/>
sively proves that the disease is not transmitted either by air-borne<lb/>
germs or by any blood-sucking insects which can find their way<lb/>
through the meshes of such netting. Indeed, consistently with all the<lb/>
observed facts I cannot think of any other means by which yellow<lb/>
fever may be transmitted except through the yellow fever mosquito.</item>
</list></p>
<p>John Guiteras, M. D., Havana:</p>
<p>The mosquito is the only proven natural means by which yellow<lb/>
fever is conveyed; and as all other means heretofore suggested have<lb/>
been proven not to be means of transmission of this disease, it is<lb/>
highly probable that the mosquito is the only means. I believe that<lb/>
it is the only means.</p>
<p>Aristides Agramonte, M. D., Havana, one of the commissioners ap-<lb/>
pointed by the U.S. Army to investigate the cause of yellow fever:</p>
<p>Your favor of the 19th inst. has come to hand, and in answer, beg to<lb/>
state that I am convinced that the mosquito is the only natural means<lb/>
by which yellow fever is propagated.</p>
<p>There is absolutely no other way; this has been demonstrated in<lb/>
every manner within the power of man.</p>
<pb n="85" id="f02708085"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
85</p>
<p>Extract from a letter from D. T. Lanie, M. D., Havana, Late Colonel<lb/>
U. S. V.:</p>
<p>The first question, I should answer: Yes, the mosquito is the only<lb/>
means by which yellow fever is conveyed.</p>
<p>Hugo Roberts, M. D., Quarantine Officer at the Port of Havana:</p>
<p>I have the honor to inform you that from all the experiments made<lb/>
in Havana, the only means by which we have been able to transmit<lb/>
yellow fever has been through previously infected mosquitoes.</p>
<p>All quarantine regulations against yellow fever in Cuba have been<lb/>
directed against mosquitoes and non-immune passengers from in-<lb/>
fected ports. No restrictions have been placed against fomites. That<lb/>
no case has appeared in this city, in spite of the close communication<lb/>
with infected countries, seems to confirm the theory that the mosquito<lb/>
is the sole agent of yellow fever transmission.</p>
<p>Q. Kohnke, Health Officer of New Orleans, La.:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. I believe that yellow fever is conveyed from person to person<lb/>
by the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> mosquito only.</item>
<item>2. It may be possible, though it is not likely, that yellow fever is<lb/>
imported in some other way than by persons or mosquitoes.</item>
</list></p>
<p>A letter from S. E. Chaille, M. D., New Orleans, La.:</p>
<p>1. Do you believe that the mosquito is the only natural means by<lb/>
which yellow fever is conveyed? Yes, but I do not believe that this<lb/>
has yet been finally and conclusively proved.</p>
<p>From the foregoing evidence it is conclusive that no other means<lb/>
of transmitting yellow fever except the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> has been<lb/>
demonstrated. The question naturally arises, should quarantine regu-<lb/>
lations be based upon this fact. Dr. Havard, Assistant Surgeon Gen-<lb/>
eral, U. S. Army, in command of the Island of Cuba, seeing the un-<lb/>
necessary hardship upon the traveling public and the great injustice<lb/>
of quarantine regulations, introduced the following resoluations at the<lb/>
Pan American Medical Congress held in Havana, Cuba, February,<lb/>
1901:</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. &ldquo;That the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>, is, up to the present time the<lb/>
only means demonstrated for the transmission of yellow fever.</item>
<item>2. In accordance with the above, prophylaxis should consist in<lb/>
the destruction, as far as possible, of this species of mosquito and the<lb/>
best means should be adopted to prevent these mosquitoes from gain-<lb/>
ing access to persons ill of yellow fever.</item>
<item>3. That quarantine measures against yellow fever shall be based<lb/>
thereon.</item>
</list></p>
<p>These resolutions were defeated. Dr. Glennon, Surgeon in com-<lb/>
mand of Cuba, stated very forcibly that &ldquo;We, the representatives<lb/>
<pb n="86" id="f02708086"/>
86<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
of the United States Marine Hospital Service, cannot accept the prop-<lb/>
osition in its present form, that it was necessary to bear in mind<lb/>
that in the reformation of quarantine regulations against yellow fever<lb/>
it is necessary to take into consideration the opinion of the health<lb/>
authorities of the southern United States.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It does not appear that the health officers of the Southern States<lb/>
are convinced that the mosquito is the only natural means by which<lb/>
yellow fever can be conveyed, although they accept, with practical<lb/>
unanimity the demonstrated facts showing that the mosquito does<lb/>
transmit the disease.</p>
<p>We find in report of Dr. Geo. R. Tabor, State Health Officer of<lb/>
Texas, for 1902:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In 1900 the Chief Surgeon of the U.S. Army in Cuba appointed<lb/>
a commission which conducted a series of experiments with the pur-<lb/>
pose of determining the true cause of infection from yellow fever.<lb/>
In 1901 Surgeon Ross, of the U. S. Army, made similar experiments,<lb/>
and the conclusions of both were &lsquo;that yellow fever is not conveyed<lb/>
by fomites, and hence disinfection of articles of clothing, bedding, or<lb/>
merchandise, supposedly contaminated by contact with those sick with<lb/>
this disease is unnecessary.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I cannot accept these conclusions, nor do I believe that they are<lb/>
accepted by any of the health authorities of the Gulf States, who,<lb/>
from long experience, know that yellow fever has been and believe it<lb/>
can now be conveyed by fomites.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am not prepared to give my consent to the introduction into<lb/>
this state, of articles of clothing, bedding, baggage, etc., which have<lb/>
been worn by and exposed to persons having yellow fever until it has<lb/>
been thoroughly disinfected; I agree that the mosquito can convey the<lb/>
disease, but I do not concede that it is the sole distributor thereof.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. Joseph Y. Porter, Sanitary Inspector U. S. Public Health and<lb/>
Marine Hospital Service and State Health Officer of Florida:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. &ldquo;Do you believe that the mosquito is the only natural means<lb/>
by which yellow fever is conveyed?<lb/>
I beg to say that I do not think as yet that question has been<lb/>
satisfactorily and definitely settled. The <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> (female),<lb/>
may, or may not, be the sole and only medium of transmission of yel-<lb/>
low fever to man. We need more time and experiments conducted in<lb/>
other countries except Cuba to determine the supposed or contended<lb/>
fact.<lb/>
To your second query,</item>
<item>2. If not, what other? I answer, I do not know, but the history<lb/>
of many outbreaks of yellow fever in the past seems to point to fomites<lb/>
of various kinds as the conducting media.<lb/>
To your third query,</item>
<item>3. Do you believe that the mosquito does convey yellow fever?<lb/>
Most certainly I believe that the female <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> does convey yellow<lb/>
<pb n="87" id="f02708087"/>
<hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
87<lb/>
fever. I do not think there is any doubt or dispute in the mind of<lb/>
any medical man on that point.&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
<p>J. F. Hunter, M. D., Secretary and Executive Officer of the Missis-<lb/>
sippi State Board of Health, Jackson, Miss.:</p>
<p>Q. Do you believe that the mosquito is the only natural means by<lb/>
which yellow fever is conveyed?</p>
<p>A. I do not.</p>
<p>Q. If not, what other?</p>
<p>A. I believe that it is conveyed by fomites and that we have had<lb/>
several practical illustrations of same in this state.</p>
<p>Q. Do you believe that the mosquito does convey yellow fever?</p>
<p>A. If the experiments made in Havana were correct, I do.</p>
<p>Dr. Edmond Souchon, President of the Louisiana State Board of<lb/>
Health, in speaking of the Army Commission Report, says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The conclusion of the experimenters was, that as they had failed<lb/>
to convey yellow fever by fomites, the latter are no longer to be con-<lb/>
sidered a source of danger.</p>
<p>Naturally, the very greatest importance has been attached to these<lb/>
experiments and to the conclusions based on them, as affecting quar-<lb/>
antine methods.</p>
<p>The popular press especially has dwelt with marked emphasis on<lb/>
this phase of the subject in anticipation of a complete revolution in<lb/>
quarantine practice, with corresponding benefit to commerce.</p>
<p>While admitting that the mosquito has been shown to be a potent<lb/>
factor in conveying the disease, we southern health officers, charged<lb/>
with the grave duty of protecting our people against this most dreaded<lb/>
of all diseases, are unwilling to accept the dictum of the experimenters<lb/>
that yellow fever can be conveyed by no other agency.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Previous to the last meeting of the American Public Health Associa-<lb/>
tion the Havard resolutions were endorsed by twenty-two physicians<lb/>
in Havana and at the last meeting of this Association the same resolu-<lb/>
tions were unanimously endorsed by the delegates from Mexico and<lb/>
South America, and of members from the United States, fifty of those<lb/>
whose opinion were asked endorsed the resolutions, while only four<lb/>
declined to give their endorsements. These resolutions were then<lb/>
sent to the Surgeons General of the Army and Navy.</p>
<p>The Surgeon General of the United States Army endorsed as fol-<lb/>
lows:</p>
<p>FIRST ENDORSEMENT.</p>
<p>War Department, Surgeon General's Office:</p>
<p>January 27, 1903.</p>
<p>Respectfully referred to Captain A. N. Stark, Ass't Surgeon U. S.<lb/>
Army. West Point, N. Y., for remark and recommendation.</p>
<p>R. W. O'REILLY,<lb/>
Surgeon General, U. S. Army.</p>
<pb n="88" id="f02708088"/>
<p>88<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>SECOND ENDORSEMENT.</p>
<p>WEST POINT, N. Y., January 28, 1903.</p>
<p>Respectfully returned with remark that the enclosed resolutions<lb/>
make up the sum total of our contention.</p>
<p>I signed the copy circulated at the meeting of the American Public<lb/>
Health Association as a medical man only. The official signature<lb/>
of the Surgeon General would carry great weight and more or less<lb/>
bind the Medical Department. Our representatives have conducted<lb/>
campaigns against yellow fever on the basis of Colonel Havard's reso-<lb/>
lutions and have striven to maintain the same at medical meetings,<lb/>
and therefore I recommend that the Surgeon General sign this paper.</p>
<p>A. N. STARK,<lb/>
Capt. Ass't Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<p>THIRD ENDORSEMENT.</p>
<p>War Department, Surgeon General's Office:</p>
<p>January 30, 1903.</p>
<p>Respectfully returned to Dr. J. M. Lindsley, President International<lb/>
Quarantine League, Nashville, Tenn. It is believed that resolutions<lb/>
1 and 2 represent the unanimous opinion of the medical officers of<lb/>
the Army, in which the Surgeon General fully concurs. The prac-<lb/>
tical application of this or any other scientific proof in the matter<lb/>
of national quarantine does not come within the Province of the<lb/>
Medical Department of the Army, and the Surgeon General does not<lb/>
therefore feel called upon to express an opinion on resolution No. 3.</p>
<p>R. W. O'REILLY,<lb/>
Surgeon General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>The Surgeon General of the Navy wrote:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Replying to your letter of the 24th inst. I take pleasure in endors-<lb/>
ing the Havard resolutions to the effect that the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi><lb/>
is, up to the present time,the only means <hi rend="italic">demonstrated</hi> for the trans-<lb/>
mission of yellow fever; also the second paragraph of these Resolu-<lb/>
tions, and the third that &ldquo;quarantine measures against yellow fever<lb/>
shall be based thereon,&rdquo; with the qualification &ldquo;until further knowledge<lb/>
is obtained of the means of transmission.&rdquo;</p>
<p>P. M. RIXEY.</p>
<p>It is evident that quarantine regulations should be based on demon-<lb/>
strated facts, and in the Medical Record, of October 26, 1901, Drs.<lb/>
Reed and Carroll, under the heading &ldquo;Measures directed against the<lb/>
importation of yellow fever into the United States,&rdquo; we find the fol-<lb/>
lowing proposed regulations for carrying out scientifically the prop-<lb/>
sitions contained in the Havard resolutions:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. &ldquo;Under the admirable system of inspection and reports, as car-<lb/>
ried out by the Marine Hospital Service, the appearance of yellow fever<lb/>
<pb n="89" id="f02708089"/>
<hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
89<lb/>
at any foreign port is promptly reported for the information of the<lb/>
health authorities of our several Atlantic ports. We may, therefore,<lb/>
divide foreign ports within the so-called epidemic zone into (a) in-<lb/>
fected, and (b) non-infected ports.&rdquo;</item>
<item>2. &ldquo;If the disease has developed en route among the crew or pas-<lb/>
sengers, the sick should be promptly removed; the forecastle, or state-<lb/>
rooms, as the case may be, thoroughly disinfected with sulphur or<lb/>
formaldehyde gas, and the vessel allowed to proceed to her wharf.&rdquo;</item>
<item>3. &ldquo;If more than twenty days have elapsed during the voyage,<lb/>
without the occurrence of yellow fever, we see no good reason why<lb/>
either passengers or vessel should be detained.&rdquo;</item>
<item>4. &ldquo;With our present knowledge of its propagation, personal bag-<lb/>
gage should no longer be subjected to disinfection, and, with our<lb/>
increased ability to prevent its spread by measures of easy application,<lb/>
instances should be few and exceptional when a vessel coming from<lb/>
a yellow fever port should be delayed longer than will be necessary<lb/>
to remove her non-immune passengers who have not yet completed<lb/>
their period of five days since leaving the port of departure.&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
<p>A practical demonstration of the measures necessary for protection<lb/>
against yellow fever when the mosquito theory is accepted, is furnished<lb/>
by Dr. Alvah H. Doty, Health Officer of the Port of New York, who<lb/>
outlines his practice in the Medical Record, October 26th, 1901, as fol-<lb/>
lows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In accordance with the above views, the treatment of incoming<lb/>
vessels from ports infected with yellow fever becomes very simple;<lb/>
if they are five days or more in transit, and all on board are found to<lb/>
be well after a careful inspection and the use of the clinical ther-<lb/>
mometer, the vessel, its passengers and crew, shall be released without<lb/>
further detention or treatment. If the vessel has been less than five<lb/>
days in transit, all on board who cannot present satisfactory evidence<lb/>
of immunity should be removed and held for observation until the<lb/>
completion of a period of five days from the time of depart-<lb/>
ure from the infected port, and then released only after<lb/>
a careful inspection. When yellow fever is found on incoming ves-<lb/>
sels, procedure should differ only so far as it concerns the removal of<lb/>
the patient to a properly constructed hospital or apartment for treat-<lb/>
ment.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Southern States are the ones principally affected by the quar-<lb/>
antine regulations against yellow fever. And the commercial import-<lb/>
ance of a scientific quarantine to them is a matter that the southern<lb/>
health officers cannot afford to ignore. Quarantine regulations based<lb/>
upon the mosquito theory and carried out by Dr. Doty of New York<lb/>
is well illustrated by the case of a steamship from a Mexican port to<lb/>
New York via Havana, eight days en route: Inspected, no sickness on<lb/>
board, allowed to wharf.</p>
<p>If sickness, remove the sick, disinfect mosquitoes, and allowed to<lb/>
wharf.</p>
<pb n="90" id="f02708090"/>
<p>90<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">QUARANTINE REGULATIONS IN YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>Compare with this case of a steamship entering New Orleans from<lb/>
Vera Cruz:</p>
<p>Sailed from Vera Cruz April 22d, arrived at Coatzacoalcos 23d,<lb/>
sailed May 1st, for Cardenas and Matanzas, Cuba, for sugar; arrived<lb/>
at New Orleans May 26th, disinfected and detained in quarantine five<lb/>
days.</p>
<p>This ship had not been in a Mexican port for twenty-five days and yet<lb/>
it was held for five days at New Orleans Quarantine Station after<lb/>
disinfection.</p>
<p>Likewise a steamship from Tampico to Mobile: Sailed from Tam-<lb/>
pico, May 16th, arrived at Havana 21st; disinfected, arrived at Mobile<lb/>
24th -- eight days from Tampico. Disinfected at Mobile and held five<lb/>
days. This vessel being held in Mobile cost in loss to cattle waiting<lb/>
at Tampico for the return of this vessel, sixty-four hundred dollars<lb/>
($6.400.00).</p>
<p>Dr. Juan Guiteras has well said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The measure of success that has been thereby attained is such that<lb/>
we cannot help but regard with apprehension the evidence of unwil-<lb/>
lingness to accept this doctrine as the sole basis upon which the prophy-<lb/>
laxis against yellow fever should rest. We are in possession of a<lb/>
specific treatment for the prevention of this disease. No other epi-<lb/>
demic disease can be so perfectly controlled, and a grave responsibility<lb/>
rests upon the leaders of medical opinion who fail to educate their<lb/>
people and to prepare them in the practice of the new methods.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Scientific quarantine must evidently be uniform, recognizing the<lb/>
conditions under which yellow fever is conveyed. A geographical line,<lb/>
one side of which is &ldquo;infectible&rdquo; and the other side of which is &ldquo;non-<lb/>
infectible&rdquo; cannot be accepted as the basis for different quarantine<lb/>
regulations.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="10">
<head>OFFICIAL REPORT OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE<lb/>
THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN<lb/>
PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION.</head>
<pb n="259" id="f02708259"/>
<p>Oct 1903</p>
<p>MONDAY, OCTOBER 26TH.</p>
<p>The Section of Bacteriology and Chemistry held its meetings in<lb/>
the Medical Department of the Columbian University, under the<lb/>
Chairmanship of Dr. H. L. Russell, of Madison, Wis.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, OCTOBER 27TH -- FIRST DAY -- MORNING SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association met in the Assembly Hall of the New Willard Hotel,<lb/>
and was called to order at 10:20 A. M. by the President, Dr. Walter<lb/>
Wyman, Surgeon-General of the Public Health and Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service, of Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>In calling the convention to order, President Wyman said: It be-<lb/>
comes my pleasant duty to call to order the thirty-first annual meeting<lb/>
of the American Public Health Association.</p>
<p>It gives me great pleasure to present to you a gentleman whom it<lb/>
is not necessary to introduce to the individual members of this Asso-<lb/>
ciation, a former President of the Association, who by his scientific<lb/>
attainments and public service has endeared himself to us all. I have<lb/>
the honor of introducing to you General George M. Sternberg. (Ap-<lb/>
plause.)</p>
<p>General Sternberg then delivered the Opening Address. (See p. 13.)</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT. -- The next order is announcements by the Chairman<lb/>
of the Local Committee of Arrangements, Dr. W. C. Woodward.</p>
<p>DR. W. C. WOODWARD. -- There will be an excursion to the vaccine<lb/>
farm of the National Vaccine Establishment, College Station, Mary-<lb/>
land. Electric cars leave Fifteenth and G. Sts., N. W., at half past<lb/>
twelve o'clock sharp, Wednesday, October 28th. They will return<lb/>
in time to permit members to attend the afternoon session. Luncheon<lb/>
will be served during the excursion.</p>
<p>There will be an excursion to Mount Vernon on Friday afternoon,<lb/>
and tickets will be distributed to those members who have registered.</p>
<p>Wednesday, October 28th, at 8 o'clock P. M., there will be a recep-<lb/>
tion tendered in honor of the Association on behalf of the citizens of<lb/>
the District of Columbia, at the New Willard Hotel.</p>
<p>Thursday evening there will be a reception tendered the Associa-<lb/>
tion by Hon. and Mrs. John B. Henderson at their residence, located<lb/>
at the intersection of Florida Avenue and Sixteenth Street.</p>
<p>259</p>
<pb n="284" id="f02708284"/>
<p>284<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p>not make a nuisance, then that is best. One particular method is not<lb/>
suitable for all cities or towns. In connection with the cost of the<lb/>
disposal of refuse, we must take into consideration the cost of trans-<lb/>
portation from house to dump. If that is left out, we will get an<lb/>
erroneous conclusion. From our experience, we cannot deny the fact<lb/>
that almost every one of the processes mentioned has been successfully<lb/>
adopted in one place or another. Dr. Chapin, of Providence, R. I., is<lb/>
emphatic in his recommendation under certain conditions to feed gar-<lb/>
bage to swine, to which very often strenuous objection has been made.<lb/>
Many sanitarians are opposed to the reduction system, and others are<lb/>
again opposed to the cremation system, as usually practiced. It is the<lb/>
opinion of the members of the Committee that if the subject is con-<lb/>
sidered as suggested in the report, by taking up each case individually<lb/>
a proper system for each city can be readily selected, which will be<lb/>
both effective and economical.</p>
<p>Dr. Gardner T. Swarts, Providence, R. I., Chairman of the Com-<lb/>
mittee on Disposal of Industrial Wastes, stated that the Committee<lb/>
simply desired to report progress. (See page 166.)</p>
<p>Dr. J. C. Perry, Washington, D. C., read a paper entitled &ldquo;Maritime<lb/>
Quarantine in the Management of Cholera at Foreign Ports.&rdquo; (See p.<lb/>
232.)</p>
<p>Mr. Marshall O. Leighton, Montclair, N. J., read the report of the<lb/>
Committee on Purification of Water Supplies. (See p. 91.)</p>
<p>DISCUSSION.</p>
<p>MR. F. H. NEWELL, Chief Engineer of the Reclamation Service,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.--The report read by Mr. Leighton brings out<lb/>
some of the points of interest in connection with a general examina-<lb/>
tion of the character of the water resources of the United States. It<lb/>
is not possible to discuss this matter in the brief time allotted, but at-<lb/>
tention may be called to some of the larger features of the work re-<lb/>
ferred to by Mr. Leighton.</p>
<p>The United States Geological Survey has for many years been<lb/>
studying the resources of the country and collecting facts which will<lb/>
be of value in the utilization of the wealth lying dormant in soils, min-<lb/>
erals and waters. The work has been largely of the nature of field<lb/>
examinations as distinguished from laboratory methods. That is to<lb/>
say, efforts have been concentrated upon the development of methods<lb/>
of investigation applicable in a large way to great extent of country.<lb/>
For example, in topographic mapping the vast extent of the United<lb/>
States has been considered, the amount of money which would prob-<lb/>
ably be available,--and plans have been made for a map which would<lb/>
<pb n="285" id="f02708285"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
285<lb/>
ultimately cover the whole United States in a reasonable time and at<lb/>
moderate cost. The resulting methods and control have been widely<lb/>
different from those, perhaps, where the attempt was made merely to<lb/>
utilize certain available funds in mapping along ordinary methods.<lb/>
The same is true of the geological investigations of the Survey. Many<lb/>
geologists would like to spend years upon an area of a few square<lb/>
miles; they must, however, adapt their methods to conditions where<lb/>
large areas are to be examined, and important generalizations deduced<lb/>
for extensive tracts.</p>
<p>In the study of the water resources similar conceptions have en-<lb/>
tered. It is not practicable to make extensive laboratory investiga-<lb/>
tions of a certain stream at a certain point, but all of the important<lb/>
streams of the country must be considered at all points, and methods<lb/>
devised such as will give general knowledge of the quantity and quality<lb/>
of the water supply of the United States, both above and below ground.</p>
<p>The system for measuring the quantity of water has been brought<lb/>
to a point where satisfactory results are being obtained and made<lb/>
available for the use of engineers, sanitarians, or investors.</p>
<p>The study of the quality of water has just begun, and to Mr. Leigh-<lb/>
ton has been entrusted the problem of developing methods of field ex-<lb/>
aminations of waters, such that tests can be made rapidly, with rea-<lb/>
sonable accuracy, and results obtained which will have scientific value<lb/>
and a practical application to various problems.</p>
<p>In this work aid has been received in the way of suggestions and<lb/>
friendly criticisms from many of the members of this Association, and<lb/>
I merely wish to express to you my appreciation for the encourage-<lb/>
ment received from you individually and collectively.</p>
<p>Dr. John W. Ross, U. S. Navy, Washington, D. C., read the Report &check;<lb/>
of the Committee on the Etiology of Yellow Fever. (See p. 39.)</p>
<p>Dr. L. O. Howard, Washington, D. C., read a paper entitled &ldquo;Con- &check;<lb/>
cerning the Geographic Distribution of the Yellow Fever Mosquito.&rdquo;<lb/>
(See p. 71.)</p>
<p>Dr. Henry R. Carter, Baltimore, Md., read a paper entitled &ldquo;Some &check;<lb/>
of the Characteristics of Stegomyia Fasciata Which Affect its Con-<lb/>
veyance of Yellow Fever.&rdquo; (See p. 50.)</p>
<p>A paper by Dr. W. C. Gorgas, U. S. Army, Washington, D. C., on &check;<lb/>
&ldquo;Period of the Disease in Man During Which Yellow Fever can be<lb/>
Transmitted to the Mosquito,&rdquo; was read by title, <hi>in the absence of</hi><lb/>
the author. (See p. 65.)</p>
<p>A paper by Dr. Luis E. Ruiz, Mexico, Mexico, was also read by title.<lb/>
The title of the paper was &ldquo;Mosquitoes in Mexico City.&rdquo; (See p. 77.)</p>
<pb n="286" id="f02708286"/>
<p>286<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p>Dr. Carlos J. Finlay, Havana, Cuba, read a paper entitled &ldquo;New &check;<lb/>
Aspects of Yellow Fever Etiology Arising From the Experimental<lb/>
Findings of the Last Three Years.&rdquo; (See p. 68:)</p>
<p>Dr. J. M. Lindsley, Havana, Cuba, read a paper entitled &ldquo;Quaran- &check;<lb/>
tine Regulations Should be Based Against Yellow Fever upon the Doc-<lb/>
trine that it is Conveyed only by the Mosquito.&rdquo; (See p. 81.)</p>
<p>Dr. John Guiteras, Havana, Cuba, made a few comments corroborat- &check;<lb/>
ing the statements made in the report of the Committee as to the trans-<lb/>
mission of yellow fever. (See page 47.)</p>
<p>DISCUSSION OF THE SYMPOSIUM ON YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>DR. QUITMAN KOHNKE, New Orleans, La.--It is admitted that rail-<lb/>
way cars can carry mosquitoes, and presumably do carry <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi>;<lb/>
but <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi> are fewer in number than other mosquitoes, and the<lb/>
fact that the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> was not found in certain railway cars is no<lb/>
evidence that it does not travel in this way. In vessels their number<lb/>
is small compared with other mosquitoes, but they are conveyed by<lb/>
vessels, and they are conveyable by railroad cars.</p>
<p>The situation in Texas, I believe, has been described, and the reasons<lb/>
for that situation have been properly given. The mosquito theory<lb/>
that was, and law that is, was not recognized properly or completely<lb/>
in the quarantine regulations of Texas against Mexico, for the reason,<lb/>
probably, that the disinfection, which is effective against mosquitoes,<lb/>
was considered destructive to fabrics and to the interior furnishings of<lb/>
cars. Formaldehyde and pyrethrum powder, I believe, are now used<lb/>
to disinfect railway coaches. Pyrethrum powder will not kill mos-<lb/>
quitoes, nor will formaldehyde do so. Sulphur will, and this can be<lb/>
applied to the disinfection of railway coaches without injury to fabrics,<lb/>
and without tarnishing metals. The amount of sulphur burnt in an<lb/>
infected room, according to the United States Public Health and Ma-<lb/>
rine Hospital Service recommendations, is, I understand, four pounds<lb/>
to every thousand cubic feet of space. Experiments undertaken in<lb/>
New Orleans just prior to my departure show that one-fourth of this<lb/>
amount, namely, one pound of sulphur to the thousand cubic feet of<lb/>
space, is sufficient to kill mosquitoes, and it is not sufficient to injure<lb/>
any fabric by decolorization, or to tarnish any metal.</p>
<p>The objection to sulphur fumigation is that the odor clings to fabrics<lb/>
for a long period. We have experimented with ammonia fumes to<lb/>
obviate this. An enclosure was filled with the proper proportion of<lb/>
sulphur fumes, and then ammonia was vaporized in a generator, six<lb/>
ounces for each pound of sulphur being introduced into the enclosure.<lb/>
This produced immediately a white opaque vapor, by the union of<lb/>
ammonia with sulphur, forming the sulphite of ammonia. After five<lb/>
<pb n="287" id="f02708287"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
287<lb/>
minutes admission of air, all odor was gone. The application of am-<lb/>
monia fumes following sulphur disinfection will render a car, in our<lb/>
opinion, habitable immediately after disinfection, and no longer period<lb/>
than an hour and a half (probably much less) will be required to prop-<lb/>
erly disinfect a sleeping coach for suspected yellow fever. I believe<lb/>
that quarantine regulations by land should be as effective, as reason-<lb/>
able, as scientific, and as complete as maritime quarantine, and I speak<lb/>
as a Louisianian desiring to be protected from Mexico through Texas.</p>
<p>DR. CH. WARDELL STILES, Washington, D. C.--I should like to<lb/>
mention two points, one of a practical, the other of a scientific nature,<lb/>
in connection with the symposium on yellow fever.</p>
<p>Referring to fumigation with sulphur, I would suggest that persons<lb/>
who object to this method might try the method of disinfecting against<lb/>
insects by the use of hydrocyanic acid gas, as recently described by<lb/>
L. O. Howard (1902) in Circular 46, Division of Entomology, U. S.<lb/>
Dept., Agriculture.</p>
<p>From a scientific point of view Dr. Finlay's paper has brought up<lb/>
some very interesting propositions, which must necessarily demand a<lb/>
great deal of attention, not only because of the charming personality<lb/>
of the man who presents them, but because of his great scientific ability.<lb/>
At the same time, I must confess the paper gave me a biologic shock.<lb/>
It is a general proposition that we have two methods of reproduction<lb/>
among animals, one the non-sexual, the other the sexual, reproduc-<lb/>
tion. In the non-sexual reproduction, we have reproduction by geo-<lb/>
metric ratio, as 10; 100; 1,000; 10,000; 100,000; 1,000,000; etc.<lb/>
In the sexual reproduction we have a much less rapid reproduction<lb/>
since a number of the members of each generation are males.</p>
<p>In yellow fever we have a disease with a short period of incubation,<lb/>
which points to a very rapid reproduction of the parasite which causes<lb/>
it. The sexual reproduction would necessarily be so slow that it is<lb/>
difficult to conceive how we could have so many parasites of so minute<lb/>
a form developing in numbers sufficient to overcome the human body<lb/>
in such a short period of time. Just think of the difference! In the<lb/>
seventh generation of a parasite by the sexual method of reproduction,<lb/>
we might have only about 15,000 individuals for every one introduced;<lb/>
by the non-sexual method, in the seventh generation we might have<lb/>
about 1,000,000 parasites. The human body is a large body to over-<lb/>
come. We would therefore naturally assume that the rapid method of<lb/>
reproduction, the non-sexual, would be the first we would naturally<lb/>
take into consideration in connection with yellow fever. Take any<lb/>
of the protozoa, where we have rapid reproduction, it is by the non-<lb/>
sexual method; in the insects, where we have rapid reproduction, it is<lb/>
by the parthenogenetic reproduction (i. e. without addition of males).</p>
<pb n="288" id="f02708288"/>
<p>288<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p>When we consider the interesting idea which Dr. Finlay has brought<lb/>
before us, I think it runs against a rather difficult biologic problem;<lb/>
and I hope he will consider this problem and give us some explana-<lb/>
tion of how he can get around it; otherwise we will have to be a little<lb/>
conservative in accepting his view at present.</p>
<p>DR. CARLOS J. FINLAY, Havana, Cuba.--I am surprised that Dr. &check;<lb/>
Stiles should make a calculation of the number of parasites in connec-<lb/>
tion with the transmission of yellow fever. The position taken by me<lb/>
is this: It is not after the spores have been given off or are produced<lb/>
that the greatest danger from yellow fever occurs, but the danger is<lb/>
from the production of toxins that have been already produced through<lb/>
the sexual act, the process of reproduction, or fecundation. The for-<lb/>
mation of toxins in the system helps to give out sporites. After toxins<lb/>
have been introduced into the system, and an attack of yellow fever<lb/>
follows, then yellow fever is to my mind a toxic disease. Let us take<lb/>
tetanus, for instance, a disease in which the infection is caused in<lb/>
a similar manner to that of yellow fever. I do not see how the number<lb/>
of parasites has anything to do with that disease. In a case of tetanus<lb/>
the number of bacilli is small. I do not think there is any connection<lb/>
between an attack of yellow fever and the number of germs produced<lb/>
in the body.</p>
<p>DR. ARTHUR NOLTE, New Orleans, La.--I wish merely to call the<lb/>
attention of the author of the paper on quarantine based on &ldquo;the<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> theory&rdquo; to the fact that he is in error in regard to doing<lb/>
away with detention. That has nothing to do with the mosquito. The<lb/>
period of detention of five days from the last exposure will have to be<lb/>
carried out; whether a vessel is one day or five days in transit, it<lb/>
makes very little difference, as a vessel is merely a moving house, and<lb/>
if that house is infected with mosquitoes (that is, <hi rend="italic">has infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes</hi>) the mosquitoes can bite at any time, and even at the port of<lb/>
arrival. Quite a number of vessels have carried passengers from Rio<lb/>
Janiero, being thirty days on the trip, and yet yellow fever broke out<lb/>
at Louisiana quarantine station.</p>
<p>I wish to call attention also to the methods of handling yellow fever<lb/>
in Southwestern Texas, and to say that Dr. Guiteras is in error. I<lb/>
was not in Laredo myself when the fever broke out there, but the<lb/>
methods of preventing its propagation were based upon the mosquito<lb/>
theory. Other things besides were done. The methods of prevention<lb/>
of the spread of the disease were in charge of the Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service people, who did their best. They surely teach and practice<lb/>
the doctrine that through the &ldquo;<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>&rdquo; is the sole method<lb/>
of propagating yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="289" id="f02708289"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
289</p>
<p>As to San Antonio, I was in that city myself about three weeks before<lb/>
yellow fever was announced. I arrived there the day yellow fever was<lb/>
announced in Laredo. The health authorities put on rigid quarantine,<lb/>
and took precaution at once to provide themselves with mosquito<lb/>
bars, etc., and to carry out the methods of isolation of patients and<lb/>
destruction of mosquitoes, should they have any yellow fever, thor-<lb/>
oughly. The local health officials were willing to receive instructions<lb/>
from Major Mason of the United States Army, stationed there, and<lb/>
myself, and I think all of the modern methods were carried out. I<lb/>
remained in San Antonio eight or nine days, and I do not think there<lb/>
was any case then known, but as I told them, there were probably a<lb/>
few cases of which nobody knew, and if so, they would know it after<lb/>
the period of &ldquo;outside incubation&rdquo; (as mentioned by the doctor), that<lb/>
is, about two or three weeks.</p>
<p>DR. JOSEPH Y. PORTER, Key West, Florida.--It occurs to me that<lb/>
the practical application of the mosquito theory or the mosquito law,<lb/>
as now understood and accepted, and as stated by my friend, Dr.<lb/>
Kohnke, has only this essential bearing upon the management of mari-<lb/>
time quarantine; it does away with disinfection of fomites or what<lb/>
has been supposed to be fomites, as we do not now recognize fomites<lb/>
in yellow fever. I do not understand that it has any influence over<lb/>
the detention of vessels coming from yellow fever infected ports<lb/>
which have not been fumigated prior to their leaving said ports.</p>
<p>Dr. Nolte has anticipated me a little, as I was to remark that a vessel<lb/>
is a &ldquo;moving house.&rdquo; If mosquitoes on board have not been destroyed<lb/>
at the port of departure, and there are non-immune persons on board,<lb/>
the vessel must be fumigated and detained at quarantine to kill any<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, provided she has been less than five days from<lb/>
the port of departure. That, I think, is the sum and substance of the<lb/>
application of the mosquito law to the management of quarantine on<lb/>
our coasts, and that is the application I have tried to make in my<lb/>
management under your directions (referring to the President) at<lb/>
the ports of Florida during the past summer. It is said that only a<lb/>
woman is allowed to change her mind, and it has been hinted that I<lb/>
am not consistent. I was not convinced, when the Pan-American<lb/>
Medical Congress was held in Havana, some three years ago, that the<lb/>
mosquito was the only and sole means of transmitting yellow fever to<lb/>
the human being, but stated then that I was ready to be convinced;<lb/>
I wanted the proof, and I have had the proof given to me since. I<lb/>
am ready to accept the law, and I wish to commend the efforts and<lb/>
action of the sanitary authorities of Havana in all of the work they<lb/>
have done during the past year previous. I have been in close touch<lb/>
with them during the past summer, and I can personally testify that<lb/>
<pb n="290" id="f02708290"/>
290<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
there is no doubt in my mind that the mosquito is the only means of<lb/>
transmitting yellow fever to the human. (Applause).</p>
<p>DR. HENRY R. CARTER, Baltimore, Md.--Like Dr. Porter, I must &check;<lb/>
take up my testimony against the doctrine that the acceptance of the<lb/>
theory of the mosquito conveyance of yellow fever changes <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of our<lb/>
quarantine practice--maritime quarantine, I mean. Like him, almost<lb/>
the only change I would make in my maritime work is that I would<lb/>
not disinfect fomites--bedding, baggage, freight, etc. There is the<lb/>
same need of providing against men in the active or incubative stage<lb/>
of yellow fever, as there ever was. The risk conveyed by such men,<lb/>
unless provided against, whether by isolation at quarantine station or<lb/>
elsewhere, is as great as ever.</p>
<p>My creed Dr. Lindsley has read: I believe the mosquito is the only<lb/>
conveyor of yellow fever to man, and am perfectly willing--nay, de-<lb/>
sirous--of basing all measures against it on that doctrine; but I do<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">not</hi> agree that this involves, or allows, the radical changes in our mari-<lb/>
time quarantine which have been outlined. Surely Dr. Finlay believes<lb/>
this doctrine, and it is reasonable to believe that his maritime quaran-<lb/>
tine at Havana is based on it; yet it is by no means such a quarantine<lb/>
as Dr. Lindsley has described. Vessels and passengers from yellow<lb/>
fever ports are treated at the Havana station very nearly in the same<lb/>
way as at United States quarantine stations. The vessel is either dis-<lb/>
infected or kept away from the wharves, and the non-immune pas-<lb/>
sengers are detained five days in quarantine dating <hi rend="italic">from the time they<lb/>
leave the vessel</hi>. When the vessel has taken the precaution at the in-<lb/>
fected port of lying too far from shore to allow of the conveyance<lb/>
aboard of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi>, the vessel is not disinfected at Havana, and the<lb/>
quarantine of the passengers dates from leaving the infected port.<lb/>
This is a logical quarantine, (from the mosquito doctrine,) but not<lb/>
such a one as Dr. Lindsley has described.</p>
<p>Reed indeed said that vessels which had been out twenty days with-<lb/>
out infection needed no disinfection, but he wrote me afterwards stat-<lb/>
ing that he was in error in saying that.</p>
<p>I also think it &ldquo;consistent and reasonable&rdquo; to draw a geographical<lb/>
line in yellow fever maritime quarantine,--between places where <hi rend="italic">Stego-<lb/>
myiae</hi> are present and places where they are not. In the latter yellow<lb/>
fever is not an infectious disease, and may be admitted without limit<lb/>
and with no precautions, and there will be no spread. We know only<lb/>
too well that this is not true in our Southern ports. This line, so<lb/>
decried, is intended to mark the northern limit of coast habitually<lb/>
harboring the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>, and it is eminently logical and alto-<lb/>
gether consistent with the mosquito theory, to recognize such a line.<lb/>
<pb n="291" id="f02708291"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
291<lb/>
Moreover, I believe the line hitherto recognized is rightly, or very<lb/>
nearly rightly, placed.</p>
<p>DR. JAMES CARROLL, Washington, D. C.--There is one point in con- &check;<lb/>
nection with the spread of yellow fever that has not been brought out.<lb/>
I was informed on good authority that a number of cases of yellow<lb/>
fever had escaped observation. It brings out the necessity for strict<lb/>
regulations requiring vessels under penalty, where yellow fever is sus-<lb/>
pected to be present, to report to the authorities at once all cases of<lb/>
yellow fever of any kind coming under their control. These cases<lb/>
should be inspected by men of experience or experts, and they should<lb/>
be treated as cases of yellow fever until they are proven beyond a<lb/>
doubt that they are cases of fever of another nature; at the same<lb/>
time, unless measures are instituted, the disease cannot be stamped<lb/>
out with absolute certainty, because some cases of yellow fever are<lb/>
so mild that they escape recognition unless the disease is known to<lb/>
be prevailing, and men who have not had considerable experience are<lb/>
liable to err. The only way to overcome the possibility of mistakes,<lb/>
such as those arising on vessels, is to report every case, no matter<lb/>
what its nature, to the authorities, in order to be properly inspected<lb/>
and taken care of.</p>
<p>DR. J. M. LINDSLEY, Havana, Cuba.--I want to make a practical<lb/>
illustration between the different southern ports and Havana. We have<lb/>
the Ward Line steamer which runs out of New York to Havana into<lb/>
Mexican ports, back to Havana, and into New York. It has carried<lb/>
yellow fever patients this summer and last summer. That steamer is<lb/>
not held in Havana during its voyage; but there are certain regulations<lb/>
governing it. No ship should be held when you know positively that it<lb/>
is not infected, whenever the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> is killed on that ship. If the<lb/>
South should change its regulations, it must be prepared in letting ves-<lb/>
sels go through southern ports and not detain them five days in cases<lb/>
of infection. Let Florida and Mississippi, give us scientific quarantine,<lb/>
and Texas, Louisiana and Alabama will follow. Last year, when I<lb/>
started to agitate this question as an educational feature, the state<lb/>
boards of health (known as the Galveston Conference) had quaran-<lb/>
tined against Cuba, when we had not had a case of yellow fever in two<lb/>
years. Surgeon-General Wyman took quarantine off, so far as the<lb/>
states of Florida and Mississippi were concerned, and the other states<lb/>
could not hold out with these two states open.</p>
<p>A vessel is never infected unless there is one condition, namely, that<lb/>
it has an infective <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> on board. A vessel went from<lb/>
Texas to Mexico into Cuba, came back up to New Orleans, and was 26<lb/>
days out; not a single case of yellow fever developed on that ship,<lb/>
yet the vessel was held five days on arrival at New Orleans.</p>
<pb n="292" id="f02708292"/>
<p>292<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.</p>
<p>We want quarantine regulations for protection of the public. We<lb/>
must not hinder commerce unless it is absolutely necessary.</p>
<p>DR. JOSEPH Y. PORTER, Key West, Florida.--I would like to ask Dr.<lb/>
Lindsley a question, how he would treat a vessel under these conditions:<lb/>
Let us suppose that a vessel has come from Tampico to Pensacola with<lb/>
a non-immune crew, probably infected with <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> at Tam-<lb/>
pico, the vessel not efficiently fumigated before leaving Tampico on<lb/>
account of conditions over which the health officers at Tampico had no<lb/>
control, and that vessel arrives at Pensacola -- suppose he takes off<lb/>
every man of that crew at the quarantine station, what becomes of the<lb/>
vessel? Would he find any captain who would surrender his vessel,<lb/>
to be taken across the bay at the will and pleasure of the consignees?<lb/>
He talks about taking off people and detaining them at quarantine,<lb/>
and letting the vessel go. I agree with the Doctor that it is possible<lb/>
to do this, but what would become of the vessel in the mean time? No<lb/>
captain would surrender his vessel; so the detention will have to be<lb/>
until the vessel is determined to be safe by the quarantine officer at the<lb/>
point of arrival to go to Pensacola or to other ports in the State of<lb/>
Florida.</p>
<p>Practical and rational measures must prevail in quarantine man-<lb/>
agement. To theorize is one thing, but &ldquo;the man behind the gun,&rdquo;<lb/>
the &ldquo;fighter&rdquo; and the man responsible to the people deals with practical<lb/>
and practicable measures,--not theories.</p>
<p>DR. J. M. LINDSLEY, Havana, Cuba.--I will give an illustration of<lb/>
what occurred in Mobile. A steamship came into Mobile bay. It had<lb/>
a yellow fever case on board. How the man became infected I was<lb/>
unable to find out. I have written to the proper authorities, but thus<lb/>
far have not received any reply. What was the condition? They left<lb/>
enough men on board to carry the ship to the wharf. They took the<lb/>
man sick with yellow fever and placed him in quarantine, disinfecting<lb/>
the quarters he had occupied. Then they allowed the vessel to unload<lb/>
its cargo of fruit, because it could not be detained for five days with-<lb/>
out destroying cargo. They killed all <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>, but even<lb/>
had they not done so the vessel would not have been infected, because<lb/>
it would have taken twelve days before the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> could become<lb/>
infective. What became of that steamship? After unloading they<lb/>
sent it to the quarantine station at Mobile; took on the sick man; car-<lb/>
ried him over to Ship Island, removed him again from the ship, and<lb/>
he died from yellow fever, after which the vessel was disinfected and<lb/>
held five days. The steamer was not infected with yellow fever. There-<lb/>
fore it was unnecessary to re-disinfect, send it to Ship Island and hold<lb/>
it five days at a tremendous loss to the steamship line.</p>
<pb n="293" id="f02708293"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
293</p>
<p>As far as the crew is concerned, my remarks had reference to pas-<lb/>
sengers. We want the South open for passengers. The crew of a ves-<lb/>
sel can be handled in one of two ways. Every captain of a steamship<lb/>
should be a part of the quarantine service. Let him give bond to keep<lb/>
the crew on the vessel while it is in port. Let the quarantine officer<lb/>
take the temperature of the crew every twenty-four hours, which will<lb/>
absolutely prevent yellow fever from coming into the United States.</p>
<p>DR. ARTHUR NOLTE, New Orleans, La.--I want to say this, after<lb/>
listening to the remarks of Dr. Lindsley, that we know how best to<lb/>
carry out the quarantine regulations in the southern ports, and those<lb/>
methods are so well known that it is unnecessary and it would take too<lb/>
much time to go into details now. We do not want to interfere with<lb/>
commerce at all; we strive to guard against that at all times.</p>
<p>DR. WILLIAM BAILEY, Louisville, Ky.--I want to speak of a little<lb/>
bit of early history, and to say how much I am pleased with the mos-<lb/>
quito theory to enable me to account for some of the difficulties that<lb/>
presented themselves at that time. Going back to the history of 1878, I<lb/>
lived in one of the few cities in the country where public sentiment<lb/>
had been created that yellow fever was not a contagious disease. In<lb/>
that city we opened our doors and received ten thousand refugees from<lb/>
the South. We built a yellow fever hospital; we treated hundreds of<lb/>
these refugees with yellow fever, everybody in connection with this<lb/>
yellow fever hospital being non-immune, and we made every examina-<lb/>
tion that intelligent observation could do. We had ten or a dozen post-<lb/>
mortem examinations which were closely studied, sections having been<lb/>
made and examined by the microscope, by chemical analysis, etc.<lb/>
Everything was done to determine the character of the disease. With<lb/>
this number of cases, and we physicians who had never seen a single<lb/>
case of yellow fever before, there was not a single case developed in<lb/>
that city from that hospital.</p>
<p>Another circumstance came up that gave me great difficulty, and that<lb/>
was separate and distinct from this hospital, and immediately surroun-<lb/>
ing the L. and N. depot (I refer to the city of Louisville), within one<lb/>
block, we had twenty or thirty of our own people who had yellow fever<lb/>
and who were sent to the hospital. Some of them died under the same<lb/>
circumstances and with the same symptoms as those who had come<lb/>
from the South. Now, I am happy to say that there was no danger<lb/>
to us from contact with yellow fever patients brought to Louisville;<lb/>
but it is my conviction that the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> was brought there<lb/>
in the car, acted upon, and infected the twenty or thirty cases we had<lb/>
among our people.</p>
<p>In the same year we had a vessel. (The John D. Porter) coming up<lb/>
the Ohio above Cincinnati with a case of yellow fever on board, and<lb/>
<pb n="294" id="f02708294"/>
294<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
yet no person in Ohio contracted the disease except those who visited<lb/>
and were on this vessel, where the patient was subjected to the bite<lb/>
of the mosquito. I think the whole history now is confirmatory of<lb/>
and the difficulties explained by the mosquito doctrine which we have<lb/>
heard.</p>
<p>On motion, the Association adjourned until Thursday, at 10 A. M.</p>
<p>THURSDAY, OCTOBER 29, 1903 -- THIRD DAY --<lb/>
MORNING SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association met at 10 A. M., and was called to order by the<lb/>
President.</p>
<p>The first order was the report of the Executive Committee by the<lb/>
Secretary.</p>
<p>THE SECRETARY.--The Executive Committee considered the resolu-<lb/>
tion offered by Dr. Lindsley in regard to the transmission of yellow<lb/>
fever by the mosquito, and reports that it is deemed inexpedient to<lb/>
adopt such a resolution at this time.</p>
<p>The resolution is as follows:</p>
<p>WHEREAS, it is an universally accepted fact by scientists that the only<lb/>
known natural way by which yellow fever is transmitted is by the mos-<lb/>
quito, known as the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>; therefore, be it</p>
<p>RESOLVED, By this Association that all quarantine regulations shall<lb/>
be based thereon.</p>
<p>RESOLVED, That a special committee shall be added to the committees<lb/>
now in existence to be known as the Quarantine Committee.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.--You have heard the report of the Executive Com-<lb/>
mittee. Are there any remarks?</p>
<p>DR. J. M. LINDSLEY, Havana, Cuba.--I would like to make a few<lb/>
remarks on that resolution. Gentlemen, we have been for three or<lb/>
four years trying to get resolutions passed by different bodies on the<lb/>
question of yellow fever, as to whether quarantine regulations should<lb/>
be based on the mosquito and that alone. They tell us that we must<lb/>
educate the people. This Association was organized to educate the<lb/>
people thirty-one years ago, and it came into existence for that very<lb/>
purpose. It was not satisfied with educating the people of the United<lb/>
States, but it took into its fold the people of Canada, the people of<lb/>
Mexico, and last year they received into this organization the little Re-<lb/>
public of Cuba.<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>Dr. Guiteras, who spoke so admirably yesterday afternoon, has been<lb/>
for the last one or two years trying to get the health authorities to<lb/>
adopt the same plan adopted in Havana, by which yellow fever has<lb/>
been absolutely kept out of Cuba for three years. These resolutions<lb/>
<pb n="295" id="f02708295"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-FIRST ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
295<lb/>
were killed at the Pan-American Medical Congress, held in Havana, by<lb/>
the Public Health and Marine Hospital Service. If these resolutions<lb/>
are correct, we want to have them adopted. We have in the chair<lb/>
to-day the President or Surgeon-General of the Public Health and<lb/>
Marine Hospital Service, and we do not see any reason why these reso-<lb/>
lutions should be killed by the Executive Committee. I appeal to<lb/>
this body to adopt them, and if it does not, then epidemics occur in<lb/>
the South because our people are not educated along this line, as<lb/>
they should be by the Public Health and Marine Hospital Service, and<lb/>
this Association.</p>
<p>At the conclusion of Dr. Lindsley's remarks, it was moved that the<lb/>
report of the Executive Committee be adopted. Seconded and car-<lb/>
ried.</p>
<p>The report of the Treasurer was then presented by Dr. Frank W.<lb/>
Wright, New Haven, Conn., as follows:</p>
<p>FRANK W. WRIGHT, TREASURER IN ACCOUNT WITH THE<lb/>
AMERICAN PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION.</p>
<p>RECEIPTS.</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="2">
<row><cell>To Cash on hand at last meeting........................</cell><cell>$579 59</cell></row>
<row><cell>To Cash from dues of members for 1900................</cell><cell>20 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>To Cash from dues of members for 1901................</cell><cell>95 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>To Cash from dues of members for 1902.................</cell><cell>1,825 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>To Cash from dues of members for 1903................</cell><cell>15 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>To Cash for sale of transactions, etc....................</cell><cell>268 63</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell>----------</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell>$2,803 22</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<p>EXPENDITURES.</p>
<p>
<table rows="18" cols="3">
<row><cell>1902.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Dec., 20.</cell><cell>By cash paid C. O. Probst (Order No. 137)......</cell><cell>$110 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>27.</cell><cell>By cash paid G. C. Whipple (Order No. 138)..</cell><cell>23 15</cell></row>
<row><cell>27.</cell><cell>By cash paid H. D. Pease (Order No. 139)....</cell><cell>29 64</cell></row>
<row><cell>27.</cell><cell>By cash paid F. W. Wright (Order No. 140)..</cell><cell>141 50</cell></row>
<row><cell>1903.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Feb., 19.</cell><cell>By cash paid Wm. Whitford (Order No. 141)..</cell><cell>210 51</cell></row>
<row><cell>May, 23.</cell><cell>By cash paid J. Nolty, Mngr. (Order No. 142)..</cell><cell>27 50</cell></row>
<row><cell>Aug., 13.</cell><cell>By cash paid Berlin Ptg. Co. (Order No. 143)..</cell><cell>1,237 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>13.</cell><cell>By cash paid J. E. Bauman (Order No. 144)..</cell><cell>10 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>27.</cell><cell>By cash paid C. O. Probst (Order No. 145)..</cell><cell>251 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Oct., 19.</cell><cell>By cash paid C. O. Probst (Order No. 146)....</cell><cell>50 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>19.</cell><cell>By cash paid U. S. Express Co. (Order No. 147).</cell><cell>3 49</cell></row>
<row><cell>19.</cell><cell>By cash paid F. W. Wright (Order No. 148)..</cell><cell>28 86</cell></row>
<row><cell>19.</cell><cell>By cash paid Berlin Ptg. Co. (Order No. 149)..</cell><cell>57 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Oct.,</cell><cell>24. By cash on hand.............................</cell><cell>623 57</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>----------</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>$2,803 22</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<p>WASHINGTON D. C., October 29, 1903.</p>
<p>The auditing committee has examined the books and vouchers and report<lb/>
of the treasurer and find them correct. We beg leave to express our commenda-<lb/>
tion of the system of accounts and accuracy with which they are kept.</p>
<p>Signed.</p>
<p>GRANVILLE P. CONN,<lb/>
WM. BAILEY,<lb/>
J. N. HURTY,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Committee</hi>.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="11">
<head>THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER.<lb/>
AN ADDENDUM.</head>
<pb n="406" id="f02708406"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>JAMES CARROLL</docAuthor>,<lb/>
FIRST LIEUTENANT AND ASSISTANT SURGEON, U. S. ARMY, WASHINGTON, D. C.</byline>
<p>Proc am Pub H. A - 31 meet<lb/>
Wash Oct 1903</p>
<p>In a paper entitled &ldquo;The Etiology of Yellow Fever, a Supplemental<lb/>
Note,&rdquo;<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> the Army Yellow Fever Board (which was then composed of<lb/>
the late Major Walter Reed, Surgeon, U. S. Army, and the writer,)<lb/>
stated that no results worthy of record had been obtained from the<lb/>
examination of infected mosquitoes either when dissected in the fresh<lb/>
state, or when studied in serial sections after being hardened and em-<lb/>
bedded. They also reported that two out of three non-immunes had been<lb/>
infected with yellow fever by the subcutaneous injection of 1.5 c.c. of</p>
<p><figure entity="t02708406"></figure> Figure 1. This is figure 15 from the report of Working Party No. 1, etc., and shows the fusi-<lb/>
form bodies in the stomach and diverticulum of infected mosquitoes.</p>
<p>blood serum drawn from a yellow fever patient and subsequently passed<lb/>
through a new Berkefeld filter which was afterward found to be im-<lb/>
pervious to the <hi rend="italic">Micrococcus aureus</hi>.</p>
<p>In the latter part of July of the present year there appeared from<lb/>
the government printing office the report of Working Party No. 1<hi rend="superscript">2</hi><lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Institute of the U. S. Public Health and Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service. These observers, after repeating some of our ex-<lb/>
periments, presented additional confirmatory evidence in support of the<lb/>
mosquito theory of the transmission of yellow fever and in that respect</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">1</hi>. Read before the third annual meeting of the Society of American Bacteriologists,<lb/>
Chicago, Ills., December 31, 1901, and published in American Medicine, Philadelphia,<lb/>
February 22, 1902.</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">2</hi>. Report of Working Party No. 1, Yellow Fever Institute. A study of the Etiology of<lb/>
Yellow Fever, by Herman B. Parker, Assistant Surgeon, George E. Beyer, Acting Assist-<lb/>
ant Surgeon, O. L. Pothier, Acting Assistant Surgeon, March, 1903, Washington, Gov-<lb/>
ernment Printing Office.<lb/>
406</p>
<pb n="407" id="f02708407"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
407</p>
<p>as well as in the negative results of their blood examinations their con-<lb/>
clusions agreed with those of the army commission. They reported<lb/>
negative results, however, from two (subcutaneous?) inoculations with<lb/>
fresh yellow fever serum after it had been passed through a Berkefeld<lb/>
filter. The quantity of filtered serum injected in these experiments<lb/>
was in one instance one forty-fifth and in the other one-fifth of that<lb/>
used in our own cases.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
<p>The most interesting and striking feature of the report was the de-<lb/>
scription of a protozoan parasite to which the name <hi rend="italic">Myxococcidium<lb/>
stegomyiae</hi> has been given. This parasite was found with regularity <hi rend="superscript">2</hi><lb/>
in the appropriate mosquitoes that had bitten patients affected with</p>
<p><figure entity="t02708407"></figure> Figure 2. Photomicrograph, showing yeast cells in the diverticulum of a non-infected ba-<lb/>
nana-fed insect from Havana. Spherical cells predominate but fusiform and bud-<lb/>
ding (conjugating (?) cells are also shown. &times; 600.</p>
<p>yellow fever, these mosquitoes after varying periods being killed, sec-<lb/>
tioned and stained. Simple staining with Bismarck brown or hema-<lb/>
toxylin were the methods used by these observers for the demonstration<lb/>
of the parasite. Five forms are described: (a) fusiform bodies found<lb/>
in the stomach and ventral diverticulum<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>; (b) fragmentation bodies<lb/>
lying in an albuminoid mass within the same diverticulum<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>; (c) com-<lb/>
pact aggregations of spores (called o&ouml;cysts) occurring in spherical<lb/>
masses<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> in similar albuminoid material in the same location; (b) spo-<lb/>
roblasts (?) appearing as single or aggregated spherical or ovoid cells<lb/>
in the albuminous material in the diverticulum and in the tissues of</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. Reed and Carroll, American Medicine, February 22, 1902.</p>
<p>2. Report of Working Party No. 1. Conclusion 3, p. 8.</p>
<p>3. Fig. 15 of the Report.</p>
<p>4. Fig. 16 of the Report.</p>
<p>5. Figs. 17 to 24 of the Report.</p>
<pb n="408" id="f02708408"/>
<p>408<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>the thorax<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>; (e) spores (?) containing sporozoites (?) in the sali-<lb/>
vary glands<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>. One or more of these stages were said to have been<lb/>
found in a large proportion of the infected mosquitoes that were killed<lb/>
not earlier than the third day after being fed upon the blood of pa-<lb/>
tients during the second, third and fourth days of the disease. The<lb/>
cycle of development of these so-called animal parasites as given by<lb/>
the authors is about as follows. On the third or fourth day, after the<lb/>
disappearance of the blood, the stomach was found to contain varying<lb/>
numbers of small fusiform-shaped protozoa arranged singly or in groups<lb/>
and containing a central, oval nucleus. Certain of these forms (bud-<lb/>
ding forms) were interpreted as indicating a terminal conjugation;<lb/>
after conjugation the resulting zygotes migrated through the stomach<lb/>
wall into the diverticulum and underwent further development in a</p>
<p><figure entity="t02708408"></figure> Figure 3. Photomicrograph, showing fusiform and budding cells in the diverticulum of an-<lb/>
other non-infected banana-fed insect from Havana. &times; 600. These mos-<lb/>
quitoes were sectioned and examined early in 1901.</p>
<p>mass of albuminoid material in the latter sac. Here were found also<lb/>
the fragmentation bodies and o&ouml;cysts (?), the latter represented by<lb/>
rather compact spherical aggregations of round or ovoid bodies, the<lb/>
sporoblasts (?). After their liberation these sporoblasts wandered<lb/>
into the thoracic end of the diverticulum, passed through its wall and<lb/>
the tissues of the thorax until the salivary gland was reached. After<lb/>
penetration of the gland sporozoites were developed and liberated.</p>
<p>Availing myself of the announcement that type specimens were<lb/>
preserved in the collection of the Hygienic Laboratory of the U. S.<lb/>
Public Health and Marine Hospital Service, I requested permission</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. Figs. 25 to 28 of the Report.</p>
<p>2. Figs. 29 and 30 of the Report.</p>
<pb n="409" id="f02708409"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
409</p>
<p>to examine them and I desire to acknowledge here the great courtesy<lb/>
and kindness extended to me on two such occasions by Dr. Herman B.<lb/>
Parker, the chairman of the Working Party. Upon subsequently re-<lb/>
examining our own sections of infected and non-infected mosquitoes<lb/>
which had already been studied more than two years before in con-<lb/>
junction with my honored colleague, the late Major Walter Reed, Sur-<lb/>
geon, U. S. Army, and Dr. William M. Gray<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, Microscopist to the<lb/>
Army Medical Museum, I was unable to satisfy myself that a single<lb/>
one of our infected mosquitoes contained any of the fusiform, round or<lb/>
oval bodies described in the report of the Working Party of the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Institute, but forms similar in appearance to those shown in Fig.<lb/>
16 of the report were occasionally found in the stomach contents. From<lb/>
their striking inequality in size and the absence of any structural de-<lb/>
tails in these &ldquo;fragmentation&rdquo; forms I regarded them even in the<lb/>
type specimens above referred to as masses of amorphous granular ma-</p>
<p><figure entity="t02708409"></figure> Figure 4. Photomicrograph, showing the ellipsoid yeast obtained from banana.<lb/>
Deep colonies in an agar culture two days old. Stained<lb/>
by Gram's method. &times; 600.</p>
<p>terial. The bodies containing sporozoites<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> (?) which were found in<lb/>
the salivary gland have been abandoned by these investigators because<lb/>
they no longer regard them as of importance.<hi rend="superscript">3</hi></p>
<p>It is noted that in a more recent article by the chairman of the<lb/>
Working Party all mention of these supposed sporozoites is omitted.<hi rend="superscript">4</hi><lb/>
The report does not state in what relative number of insects each of<lb/>
these forms was seen, but I learned from Dr. Parker, upon inquiry,<lb/>
that the forms interpreted by them as fusiform protozoa were the only<lb/>
ones found to be constantly present. These are described as 3 to 4 &micro;</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. Practically all of our insects were embedded, cut and mounted by Dr. Cray.</p>
<p>2. Figs. 29 and 30 of the Report.</p>
<p>3. Dr. Herman B. Parker, Chairman of the Party is my authority for this statement.</p>
<p>4. The Etiology of Yellow Fever by Herman B. Parker, M. D., Journal of the Asso-<lb/>
ciation of Military Surgeons, Vol. XIII, No. 4, October, 1903.</p>
<pb n="410" id="f02708410"/>
<p>410<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>long by 1.5 to 2 &micro; broad, and containing a nucleus.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> Appearances in-<lb/>
terpreted as evidence of conjugation are seen in certain of these forms<lb/>
where two of the ovoid bodies, varying more or less in size, are joined<lb/>
by a slender protoplasmic constriction<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> (see Fig. 1); others show a<lb/>
minute bud projecting from one or both poles. The nucleus appears<lb/>
as a small brightly refractive unstained spot when the bodies are<lb/>
stained with hematoxylin or Bismarck brown, either of which colors<lb/>
the whole cell. The bodies that impressed me as being of the greatest<lb/>
importance, if constantly present, were the o&ouml;cysts (?) in the albu-</p>
<p><figure entity="t02708410"></figure> Figure 5. Photomicrograph, showing masses of yeast cells in the stomach and diverticulum<lb/>
of an insect fed on yeast culture and banana. Gram's method and Bismarck<lb/>
brown. Many of the yeast cells are decolorized and<lb/>
stained with Bismarck brown. &times; 50.</p>
<p>minoid mass (Fig. 23 of the Report) and the sporoblasts (?) (Figs.<lb/>
27 and 28 of the Report) in the connective tissues of the thorax.</p>
<p>With these pictures fresh in mind, upon re-examining our slides<lb/>
prepared from infected mosquitoes I failed to find any of the forms<lb/>
described, excepting, of course, the &ldquo;fragmentation&rdquo; bodies (Fig. 16<lb/>
of the Report) to which I could attach no significance. Upon re-ex-<lb/>
amining sections of normal (non-infected) mosquitoes the result was<lb/>
different, for in one of these cut in cross section the ventral diverti-</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. Report of Working Party No. 1, etc., p. 31.</p>
<p>2. Loc. cit., Fig. 15</p>
<pb n="411" id="f02708411"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
411</p>
<p>culum showed large numbers of spherical and fusiform cells, some of<lb/>
them corresponding in size and form to those described by the Work-<lb/>
ing Party but stained brilliantly with eosin (see Fig. 2). The majority,<lb/>
however, were spherical and a few were elongated into large rod forms<lb/>
resembling detached hyphae. The smallest contained a single refrac-<lb/>
tive spore, of minute size. The larger fusiform or flask-shaped bodies<lb/>
often contained several spores, and in a few instances a single spore<lb/>
was seen to have passed into a projecting bud of protoplasm. A few<lb/>
hyphal filaments about 2 to 3 &micro; broad and 15 to 20 &micro; long exhibited<lb/>
a central row of spores arranged with a fair degree of regularity. The<lb/>
characters described justified the conclusion that these cells were blas-<lb/>
tomycetes that had gained access to the body cavities of the insect<lb/>
with food or water.</p>
<p>In another non-infected insect cut in longitudinal section, fusiform,<lb/>
ovoid and flask-shaped cells (see Fig. 3) corresponding in every way<lb/>
with the fusiform stage of the <hi rend="italic">Myxococcidium stegomyiae</hi> as seen in<lb/>
the type specimens, were found throughout the ventral diverticulum<lb/>
but were present in the upper portion of the stomach only, and away<lb/>
from the blood mass. This insect had been permitted to take a meal<lb/>
of normal blood some hours before it died, and it is of interest to note<lb/>
that the organisms were found not within or near the residual mass<lb/>
of ingested blood but only in the upper third of the stomach and asso-<lb/>
ciated with large numbers of bacteria. Their location suggests that<lb/>
instead of migrating through the wall of the stomach to the diverti-<lb/>
culum<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> they were carried over mechanically from the diverticulum<lb/>
into the stomach.<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> The large majority of these cells showed a single<lb/>
central refractive vacuole (not spores in this instance) of minute size;<lb/>
a few contained two of them. Hyphal forms were not observed. The<lb/>
sections were stained originally with thionin and eosin upon a number<lb/>
of slides, and after decolorization the cells described were found also<lb/>
to stain perfectly with hematoxylin, Bismarck brown, (these two were<lb/>
the methods used by Parker, Beyer and Pothier) and by Gram's method.<lb/>
Similar results were obtained with smears from a culture of a white<lb/>
yeast kept in the laboratory. A week or so later I showed these slides<lb/>
to Drs. Parker and Rosenau of the Marine Hospital Service and ex-<lb/>
pressed the opinion that the fusiform bodies were yeast cells.</p>
<p>In the endeavor to account for the presence of these bodies in our<lb/>
non-infected mosquitoes and their absence from those that had been<lb/>
infected it was recalled that the insects had been reared and kept in<lb/>
different buildings and fed differently for the greater part of the time</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. Report of Working Party No. 1, etc.., p. 29.</p>
<p>2. Accompanying the residual food supply, as indicated by Nuttall and Shipley, Studies<lb/>
in Malaria, Journal of Hygiene, Vol. III, No. 2, April 1903.</p>
<pb n="412" id="f02708412"/>
<p>412<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>at least. The non-infected mosquitoes were supplied with banana;<lb/>
the infected insects referred to in this paper were at no time permitted<lb/>
to feed on fruit but were given only sugar and water in separate ves-<lb/>
sels. Many of the infected insects were reared under these conditions.<lb/>
I can speak positively upon this point because from the establishment<lb/>
of Camp Lazear until its abandonment, the infected mosquitoes kept<lb/>
there were under my exclusive charge and control.</p>
<p>To establish, if possible, the connection between over-ripe fruits and<lb/>
the presence of these bodies in mosquitoes I obtained some<hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi><lb/>
through the courtesy of Dr. Edmond Souchon of New Orleans, and<lb/>
Dr. L. O. Howard of the U. S. Department of Agriculture, the latter<lb/>
kindly supplying me with fifty living insects, a large number of eggs<lb/>
and some insects preserved in alcohol. Fusiform yeast cells were<lb/>
found in the diverticula of a very small proportion of those that were</p>
<p><figure entity="t02708412"></figure> Figure 6. The same. A field from the diverticulum. &times; 600.</p>
<p>received in alcohol. An ellipsoid wild yeast (see Fig. 4) was then<lb/>
isolated from an old banana and insects were subsequently fed upon<lb/>
the fermenting fruit to which this yeast in pure culture had been<lb/>
added. Previous sterilization of the banana was not considered neces-<lb/>
sary. As a result I have brought about the presence of bodies iden-<lb/>
tical in appearance with the fusiform stage of the so-called <hi rend="italic">Myxococ-<lb/>
cidium stegomyiae</hi> in nearly fifty insects that have never been in con-<lb/>
tact with a case of yellow fever and have demonstrated them, in large<lb/>
numbers, in the diverticula of four <hi rend="italic">male</hi> insects that have been hatched<lb/>
and reared in the laboratory of the Surgeon General's Office in Wash-<lb/>
ington. I have been able to demonstrate the passage of these organ-<lb/>
isms from the ventral diverticulum through the natural opening of<lb/>
<pb n="413" id="f02708413"/>
<hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
413<lb/>
communication to the oesophagus and thence to the stomach, where they<lb/>
are found only in the upper part of the organ, and are absent from the<lb/>
blood mass below, which is of large size and recently ingested. I have<lb/>
obtained in one instance as the result of feeding a male insect upon<lb/>
wild yeast and banana, sections which show these organisms among<lb/>
the muscular tissues of the thorax and many of them lie in close prox-<lb/>
imity to the gland. Several insects similarly treated show the same<lb/>
bodies in the stomach and diverticula (see Figs. 5, 6 and 7). They<lb/>
have not been found in fifty-two <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi> fed upon yellow fever<lb/>
patients and kept under my immediate charge, a number of them hav-<lb/>
ing been used in reproducing the disease. Many of these mosquitoes<lb/>
that were kept for inoculation purposes died in the jars and are poorly<lb/>
preserved, but a number were killed and preserved immediately. The<lb/>
state of preservation of the insect, however, does not mater&iacute;ally affect<lb/>
the staining properties of the blastomycetes, for in non-infected insects<lb/>
that have died in the jars and are crowded with bacteria, they color<lb/>
brilliantly and sharply. This would seem to indicate that they still<lb/>
retain their vitality after the death of the mosquito containing them.</p>
<p>Dr. L. O. Howard informs me that Dr. J. W. Dupree of Baton<lb/>
Rouge, La., writes him that he also finds <hi rend="italic">&ldquo;Myxococcidium stegomyiae&rdquo;</hi><lb/>
in non-infected mosquitoes at Baton Rouge.</p>
<p>Indirect confirmation of my results is seen in the Report cited<hi rend="superscript">1</hi><lb/>
where it is stated that the parasite was not found in <hi rend="italic">Stegomyiae</hi> that<lb/>
had been applied to a malignant case of malarial fever and were then<lb/>
fed upon blood, sugar and water. If a sufficient number of insects<lb/>
had been used and they had been fed upon over-ripe banana or other<lb/>
fruit as the Working Party recommends for yellow fever mosqui-<lb/>
toes,<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> the supposed animal parasites would in all probability have been<lb/>
demonstrated.</p>
<p>Upon close examination of the liberated sporoblasts (?) shown in<lb/>
Figs. 25 and 26 of the Report referred to,<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> it will be seen that these<lb/>
bodies show the variations in size and form and the typical budding<lb/>
processes of yeast cells. This is particularly well marked in the left<lb/>
central and lower portions of figure 26.</p>
<p>That ellipsoid wild yeasts may be pathogenic for the lower animals<lb/>
is shown by the researches of Rabinowitch,<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> who states also that these<lb/>
cells are stained by all the usual aniline colors. In the course of my<lb/>
observations it has been found that typical ellipsoid forms in one of</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. Report of Working Party No. 1, etc., p. 30.</p>
<p>2. Report of Working Party No. 1, etc., p. 28.</p>
<p>3. Report of Working Party No. 1, etc.</p>
<p>4. Zeitschrift fur Hygiene etc., Vol. 21, 1896, p. 11.</p>
<pb n="414" id="f02708414"/>
<p>414<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.</p>
<p>the mosquitoes were stained equally well with eosin, Bismarck brown,<lb/>
hematoxylin and by Gram's method.</p>
<p>Similar forms of blastomycetes have already been isolated from the<lb/>
broken down nodules of spurious glanders and the statement is made<lb/>
by Italian investigators that several parasites which are classified under<lb/>
the sarco or micro-spordia belong really to the blastomycetes.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
<p>As the yeasts are universally disseminated in nature (and there are<lb/>
many species of them, only a relatively small number being patho-<lb/>
genic), it is not surprising that experiments with a single species have<lb/>
failed to show positive evidences of invasion of the tissues of the<lb/>
insect. This was obtained by the Working Party of the Marine Hos-<lb/>
pital Service in only a few instances, and is obviously of no importance<lb/>
from the point of view of the etiology of yellow fever. On the other</p>
<p><figure entity="t02708414"></figure> Figure 7. Colonies in the albuminoid mass in the diverticulum of a yeast-fed<lb/>
insect. Bismark brown. &times; 600.</p>
<p>hand it is regarded as of the greatest importance that bodies appar-<lb/>
ently identical with the fusiform stage of this supposed protozoan, the<lb/>
only form found to be constantly present, can be easily reproduced<lb/>
anywhere by feeding to mosquitoes a culture of an ellipsoid yeast.</p>
<p>The results of the observations here recorded are believed to justify<lb/>
the following conclusions:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. The fusiform stage of the so-called <hi rend="italic">Myxococcidium stegomyiae</hi><lb/>
of Parker, Beyer and Pothier, (1903) is not connected in any way<lb/>
with the transmission of yellow fever.</item>
</list></p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. A new pathogenic species of yeast etc., Fermi and Aruch, Centralblatt fur Bakt.,<lb/>
etc., 1st Abt., Vol. XVII, No. 17, May, 1895, p. 593.</p>
<pb n="415" id="f02708415"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
415</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>2. This organism appears to be not a protozoan parasite but a<lb/>
yeast fungus. In its fusiform stage, the only form in which it was con-<lb/>
stantly present, it shows the characteristic budding, staining affinities<lb/>
and vacuolation or spore formation of a blastomycete, and it is found<lb/>
with considerable regularity in both male and female mosquitoes that<lb/>
have purposely been fed upon over-ripe banana to which a pure cul-<lb/>
ture of a wild yeast had been added in the laboratory.</item>
<item>3. The organism has not hitherto been found in repeated examina-<lb/>
tions of mosquitoes of the genus <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi> that have bitten yellow<lb/>
fever patients in the early stages of the disease, such insects having been<lb/>
fed only upon blood, dry sugar and water. This statement applies<lb/>
also to mosquitoes that are known to have reproduced the disease in<lb/>
human beings.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
