<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02719001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Biography of Walter Reed, by Christopher Reed, [1903?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02719001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1903-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Pharaba W.</name>
<name type="person">Blincoe, Laura Reed</name>
<name type="person">Reed, James C.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Thomas</name>
<name type="person">Hutchinson, Joseph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, William Houston</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, </name>
<name type="place">Bellevue Hospital Medical College, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Randall's Island (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="hospital">Brooklyn City Hospital (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1903-00-00">[1903?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02719001</idno>
<title>Biography of Walter Reed, by Christopher Reed, [1903?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Christopher Reed provides a biographical sketch of Walter Reed written.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1903-00-00">
<head>Biography of Walter Reed, by Christopher Reed, [1903?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02719001"/>
<p><unclear>Sketch</unclear> written by Walter Reed's brother - Christopher<unclear>.</unclear> (See p 6)<lb/>
P S H</p>
<p>Walter Reed, M. D., M. A., L. L. D., was born on the 13th day of<lb/>
September A. D. 1851, in Gloucester County, Virginia, and was the son<lb/>
of Lemuel Sutton Reed, a native of North Carolina, who was for forty<lb/>
years or more a leading Methodist Divine of Virginia,. His mother's<lb/>
maiden name was Pharaba White, a native of North Carolina, a woman of<lb/>
charming sweetness of character with a good and creditable ancestry.<lb/>
Five children were the issue of this marriage, here named in the order<lb/>
of their birth: Laura, James, Thomas, Christopher, and Walter, the<lb/>
deceased. He was descended in a direct line on the male side from<lb/>
Sir Christopher Reed of Chipchase Castle on the Tyne, England, and his<lb/>
son Thomas, was in his day, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland. In common with<lb/>
the great statesman Thomas Brackett Reed, of Maine, his lineage, so<lb/>
far as historical data can be relied upon, may be traced back to one<lb/>
Bryanus de Rede, a prominent officer in the army of William, the Norman<lb/>
Conqueror.</p>
<p>In personal appearance the subject of this sketch in his<lb/>
childhood was highly favored, and to this he added the sweetest<lb/>
disposition and most gracious manners. So pleasing was his person,<lb/>
when a child, that our father pointing to him was accustomed to say to<lb/>
our mother: &ldquo;What a choice temple for the Almighty to dwell in<unclear>.</unclear>&rdquo;<lb/>
He was interesting from <unclear>his</unclear> early youth, and the family reluctantly<lb/>
dined without his presence. My father was accustomed to say: &ldquo;Wait<lb/>
children till your youngest brother comes.&rdquo; All of us desired the<lb/>
joy of his conversation and the clear ring of his laughter, which,<lb/>
to me, was as sweet as the &ldquo;Chimes of Normandy&rdquo; or &ldquo;The Bells of<lb/>
Shandon.&rdquo; The tabernacle of the home was never complete until he<lb/>
entered it with his cheery smile. He was of a happy nature. He<lb/>
found &ldquo;tongues in trees, books in running brooks, sermons in stones,<lb/>
and good in everything.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As a boy he was very precocious; he mastered with ease all<lb/>
the little problems that come to youth. At thirteen years of age<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02719002"/>
2.<lb/>
he was a good Greek and Latin scholar, and at fifteen years<lb/>
of age he understood these studies with great accuracy. He<lb/>
was an omnivorous reader in his youth. He was particularly<lb/>
fond of history, literature and philosophy, and from them he<lb/>
had memorized the choicest selections. His favorite poet was<lb/>
Sir Walter Scott, and from this author he selected the finest<lb/>
passages, and would recite them with great beauty. There was<lb/>
no subject which his mind could not grasp and solve even when<lb/>
a boy, and he did it all without pride. Never once after his<lb/>
greatest success was there ever noticed in his face even the<lb/>
semblance of the spirit of the self-congratulatory words:<lb/>
&ldquo;veni, vidi, vici,&rdquo; which more or less always fills the breast<lb/>
of a proud man who has accomplished his task. He was modest<lb/>
at all times; and after all modesty is a safe and reliable<lb/>
evidence of true greatness. Every modest man is not great,<lb/>
but it is equally true that every great man is modest. As<lb/>
&ldquo;Nature abhors a vacuum,&rdquo; so he detested a pretender; naught<lb/>
but a genuine, golden merit could arrest his attention.</p>
<p>By a special dispensation, as I now recall, of the Faculty<lb/>
of the University of Virginia, he was matriculated at the age<lb/>
of sixteen as a student of that great University. He pursued<lb/>
with great success a number of studies during his first year<lb/>
and was always among those who obtained the highest mark in<lb/>
his classes. As my father's means were limited and there<lb/>
were two other sons at the University of Virginia at the same<lb/>
time, the subject of this sketch realized that he would not be<lb/>
able to complete the full course in the Academic departments.<lb/>
He therefore, at the ensuing session, selected the study of<lb/>
medicine and in one session of nine months graduated with the<lb/>
honor and title of M. D. at the age of seventeen years.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02719003"/>
<p>3.</p>
<p>This was an unusual feat, and the first of its character<lb/>
since the immortal Jefferson laid the corner stone of this, one<lb/>
of the greatest American institutions of learning. During<lb/>
the time he was a pupil in the medical class, Doctor Cabell,<lb/>
then a leading member of the medical faculty, told my father<lb/>
that the task undertaken by my brother Walter to graduate at<lb/>
his age in the short space of nine months was too much, and<lb/>
<unclear>that</unclear> he, Walter, should be persuaded to abandon the same. My<lb/>
brother replied to that by saying: &ldquo;I do not fear the result.&rdquo;<lb/>
Ordinarily, students took a course of two or three years to<lb/>
acquire the degree of M. D., but the subject of this sketch<lb/>
attained that honor at the age of seventeen, and in one<lb/>
session of nine months. He was one of nine out of a class<lb/>
of nearly one-hundred, as I remember, that passed the examination<lb/>
and secured the degree. He was an enthusiastic student.<lb/>
I was his room-mate, and I recall very vividly that during this<lb/>
time, in the year 1869, he was accustomed for three or four<lb/>
months in succession to allow himself only three or four hours<lb/>
sleep out of the twenty-four, and I recollect very distinctly<lb/>
that on two or three occasions he studied uninterruptedly for<lb/>
three days and nights without a moment's sleep, and did, as a<lb/>
result of such an effort, suddenly collapse falling upon the<lb/>
floor of his room into the deepest slumber.</p>
<p>3rd of <unclear>f<lb/>
check the<lb/>
47</unclear></p>
<p>don't<lb/>
<unclear>belongs</unclear></p>
<p>In a few months after his graduation, which was in 1869,<lb/>
he left for New York City, and there matriculated as a student<lb/>
of Bellevue Hospital Medical College, and in one session acquired<lb/>
the degree of M. D.. With his former preparation this degree<lb/>
was so easily acquired that he was enabled to give three -<lb/>
fourths of his time to the clinics of the hospitals and to other<lb/>
intellectual persuits; <hi>for if Beecher or Chapin were to preach,<lb/>
Tyndall, Huxley, or Froude to lecture</hi>, <hi>Booth or Neilson to act</hi>,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02719004"/>
4.<lb/>
O'Connor or Evarts to argue in court, he could always be found<lb/>
in the audience.</p>
<p><unclear>W. R. verified in letter<lb/>
from frontier</unclear></p>
<p>After finishing his course at the Bellevue Hospital Medical<lb/>
College he was attached to several of the hospitals of Brooklyn<lb/>
and New York. He was located at the Hospital on Randall's<lb/>
Island in the vicinity of New York, where he went to study the<lb/>
diseases of children. He was for a time House Surgeon of<lb/>
the Brooklyn City Hospital. As I now recollect he had four<lb/>
or five diplomas of the hospitals of Brooklyn and New York,<lb/>
certifying to the fact that he had passed through them and dis-<lb/>
charged his duty faithfully. He was also before he was<lb/>
twenty-one years of age District physician of one of the<lb/>
districts of New York, where it became his duty to administer<lb/>
to the poor; and this duty he discharged with the greatest<lb/>
fidelity. At this time I was his room-mate, having gone to<lb/>
New York to practice law. While acting in this capacity he<lb/>
never failed to respond to every call, however lowly, even<lb/>
though the same should take him into the most dangerous quarters<lb/>
of the city at the most critical hours of the night. On one<lb/>
occasion he returned to his room very late at night from one<lb/>
of these professional calls. He entered the room and I made<lb/>
no manifestation that I was awake. He walked to the window of<lb/>
the room and there remained some time looking into the<lb/>
street, for it was a bright night; after remaining there a while<lb/>
I heard him speak slowly and with a deeply pathetic tone these<lb/>
words: &ldquo;Wo unto thee Chorazin, wo unto thee Bethsaida, for if<lb/>
the mighty works which were done in you had been done in<lb/>
Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago in sackcloth<lb/>
and ashes.&rdquo; I concluded that he was reflecting upon the<lb/>
wickedness of a great city. He afterwards undressed himself<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02719005"/>
5.<lb/>
and kneeling down by the bedside repeated in distinct tones<lb/>
that greatest symphony of the soul, the Lord's Prayer. The<lb/>
whole occasion was so solemn and beautiful, that I never<lb/>
alluded to it; for there are some things too sacred for the<lb/>
invasion of words. I only speak of them now to illustrate the<lb/>
character and trend of his thought while yet a young man.</p>
<p><unclear>when<lb/>
were<lb/>
they</unclear></p>
<p>While at a Brooklyn City Hospital he attracted the atten-<lb/>
tion of one of its visiting surgeons and physicians, Dr.<lb/>
Joseph Hutchinson, who was then regarded as the leading physi-<lb/>
cian and surgeon of Brooklyn. Through the influence of this<lb/>
acquaintance he subsequently acquired the position of one of<lb/>
five Inspectors on the Board of Health of the City of Brooklyn,<lb/>
and was holding this position when only twenty-two years of age.<lb/>
He was regarded universally by those of his profession who<lb/>
knew him while in New York as a young man of the highest talent,<lb/>
and was especially known among his professional acquaintances<lb/>
for his great skill in surgery. Several of them spoke to me<lb/>
on this subject in most laudatory terms. In 1874, he stated<lb/>
to me that there were too many able doctors doing too<lb/>
little in the City of New York; that success in his line seemed<lb/>
to be dependent very largely upon social connection and<lb/>
wealthy, influential friends; that as he was unable to rely upon<lb/>
this source for his success he had determined to go into the<lb/>
army or navy where his future could be secured, and where at<lb/>
the same time he could pursue his researches in medicine. Early<lb/>
in 1875, in compliance with this intention, after a most brilliant<lb/>
examination, he entered the army where his record is known to<lb/>
all his professional brethren. As a boy he possessed the<lb/>
same power he displayed as a man. He had great courage,<lb/>
and under no circumstances would be relinquish the task which<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02719006"/>
6.<lb/>
he had undertaken. When twelve years of age, when the ther-<lb/>
mometer was ten degrees below zero on an occasion of great<lb/>
urgency, accompanied by a man servant, he took a long journey<lb/>
of two or three days over difficult roads into the country.<lb/>
This journey was made on behalf of my father and he accomplished<lb/>
the work for which he had been sent with great success, and I<lb/>
can now see him as he returned; with joy he sprang out of the<lb/>
conveyance which brought him safely back and ran into my father's<lb/>
arms and said: &ldquo;Pa, everything is all right, I have got the money<lb/>
here in my pocket.&rdquo; This only illustrates the character of<lb/>
the man. It was literally true of him that the &ldquo;boy was<lb/>
father to the man.&rdquo; When a young man he was as dignified<lb/>
as Chesterfield and as gracious as a great heart could make<lb/>
him, the knightliest of the knightly, a Cavalier among his<lb/>
fellows. He had a great contempt for ostentation and display.<lb/>
He never &ldquo;blew his own trumpet.&rdquo; With the faith of a strong<lb/>
man he was content to await the rewards which always come from<lb/>
results justly and worthily obtained. He saw the thing to be<lb/>
done and however difficult he did it. His master spirit knew<lb/>
no defeat and his great soul knew no pride. His whole life,<lb/>
however successful, was in harmony with that great line of the<lb/>
poet<unclear>:</unclear>- &ldquo;Oh, why should the spirit of mortal be proud?&rdquo; <hi>The<lb/>
writer of this sketch, his brother Christopher,</hi> received a<lb/>
letter from him some three or four months ago in which he spoke<lb/>
of the interesting work which he had already mapped out to ac-<lb/>
complish. He expressed himself with great satisfaction at the<lb/>
result of his labors in Cuba, in finding the cause and remedy for<lb/>
that most devastating epidemic, yellow fever. He acknowledged<lb/>
in his letter that in conducting the experiments which he conducted<lb/>
in Cuba that he went down into the &ldquo;valley and shadow of death,&rdquo;<lb/>
but he thanked God that he had been enabled to do so with<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02719007"/>
7.<lb/>
the expectation of accomplishing great results for afflicted<lb/>
humanity. And in the same letter he expressed the desire to<lb/>
live until he might set upon foot other investigations that<lb/>
would result in the destruction of many of the epidemics that<lb/>
now prevail, distress and afflict humanity.</p>
<p>He appreciated highly the honor of L.L. D. conferred on<lb/>
him by Ann Arbor University and M. A. by Harvard University.<lb/>
But in a letter to me he said to me that while these honors were<lb/>
pleasing to him, that the chief source of his joy was that he had<lb/>
been able to do something for afflicted humanity, and that his<lb/>
life had not been spent in vain.</p>
<p>He was devoted to his family and always spoke of them<lb/>
with the greatest affection, and undoubtedly was giving his<lb/>
best efforts to make them happy. He was very fond of his<lb/>
son, a lieutenant in the Philippines, and always made reference<lb/>
to him in letters written to myself. I am not familiar with<lb/>
his home life, as we have been living apart since 1875, in<lb/>
extreme sections of the country, but I undertake to say that<lb/>
he entertained the highest ideal of home and that he discharged<lb/>
the relation of husband and father judged by the very strictest<lb/>
and highest standard.</p>
<p>He possessed other powers beside those displayed in his<lb/>
profession. He was a profound thinker on all subjects and<lb/>
cultivated the whole range of thought. At a medical banquet<lb/>
in New York at the age of twenty-two years I heard him make<lb/>
an address which, for sublime and chaste eloquence and a<lb/>
high conception of the relationship of man to man, I have<lb/>
never heard surpassed. If he had taken up the study of law<lb/>
he would have been known as a great lawyer with extraordinary<lb/>
powers of oratory. If he had gone into the ministry, he<lb/>
would have charmed and enchanted his audience by the strength<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02719008"/>
8.<lb/>
and character of his thought and the purity of his style.<lb/>
As it was he selected the field of medicine, and the glory of<lb/>
his record in that line is attested by all of his professional breth-<lb/>
ren. He was intensely spiritual by nature; all of his work<lb/>
was subordinated to that conception of things. He worked wholly<lb/>
in the light of Divine impulses and was in touch with its finest<lb/>
inspiration and worshipped daily at its unseen altars.<lb/>
He was God's child, especially endowed to work in God's vine-<lb/>
yard for God. He was a messenger commissioned to deliver the<lb/>
Divine message, and he delivered it. There is the man and<lb/>
there is his work, and if you would know more of him, I point<lb/>
for an answer to those memorable words engravened upon the<lb/>
memorial tablet of Sir Christopher Wren in the Cathedral of<lb/>
St. Paul in London: &ldquo;Si monumentum quaeris, circumspice.&rdquo;<lb/>
Of him might be justly said as Livy the historian said of Cato<lb/>
the Greater: &ldquo;In illo viro tantum robur corporis et animi fuit<lb/>
ut quocunque loco natus esset, fortunam sibi facturus videretur.&rdquo;</p>
<p><unclear>wow!</unclear></p>
<p>But first and foremost, he was in truth, a good man, right-<lb/>
eous in every thought. He breathed the oxygen of moral alti-<lb/>
tudes; sooner than adandon the cause of truth, he would have,<lb/>
refused like Moses of old, to have been called the son of<lb/>
Pharaoh's daughter. He was as faithful to his convictions<lb/>
as historic John Maynard, the brave pilot on burning ship, was<lb/>
faithful to the commands of his captain; when and wherever duty<lb/>
called his great soul made response with the &ldquo;Aye, aye Sir&rdquo;<lb/>
of midnight watch on tempest tossed sea. With him there was<lb/>
no greatness without goodness. It was not the great Napoleon<lb/>
at Austerlitz, but the great and good Washington at <unclear>Va<del>l</del>ley</unclear> Forge<lb/>
that elicited his admiration and praise.</p>
<p>He believed that the philosophy of the Nazarene alone<lb/>
could unravel the mystery of human life and give to it a meaning.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f02719009"/>
<p>9.</p>
<p>The Sermon on the Mount was his religious chart, &ldquo;A cloud<lb/>
by day and a pillar of fire by night&rdquo; to point the way, which<lb/>
he always found, and in which he walked unerringly. He made<lb/>
love not to the continuance of his days, but to their goodness.<lb/>
The Maccabees in their zeal inscribed upon their banners these<lb/>
words: &ldquo;Moriamur in nostra simplicitate.&rdquo; He inscribed upon<lb/>
his banner these <unclear>better</unclear> words: &ldquo;The world is my parish and to<lb/>
do good is my religion;&rdquo; in his heart, therefore, naturally and<lb/>
continually dwelt the sentiment, which little Paul dying, in<lb/>
&ldquo;Dombey and Son,&rdquo; whispered to his sister Florence, as he saw<lb/>
the beautiful visions of the life to come: &ldquo;Tell them that<lb/>
the face of the picture of Christ on the staircase at school<lb/>
is not divine enough; and the light from it is shining on me now.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Our brother died comparatively young, just as he was<lb/>
ascending the summit of his life's work to catch the light of<lb/>
things more divine. But it has been well said: &ldquo;After all be a<lb/>
course short or long, it is complete in the eyes of the Great<lb/>
Master to whom we reverently commit all our ways. There is no<lb/>
broken column. The Supreme Architect finishes the shaft.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Here we leave our beloved; and as Margarita said to<lb/>
Faust on the eve of their final separation, so now we say to<lb/>
our precious departed: &ldquo;Think of me sometime, for I shall think<lb/>
of you all the time.&rdquo; We do not say good bye, but only, &ldquo;Aufwie-<lb/>
dersehn,&rdquo; for we shall meet again.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
