<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02714001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Senate Document Number 118, 57<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Session, 1903</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02714001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1903-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel Sutton</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert Page</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">North Carolina</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Bellevue Medical College, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Arizona</name>
<name type="place">Dakota</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Michigan</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Brooklyn City Hospital</name>
<name type="hospital">City Hospital on Blackwell Island</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>27 pp.</extent>
<date value="1903-00-00">1903</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02714001</idno>
<title>Senate Document Number 118, 57<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Session, 1903</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This document concerns the work of Walter Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1903-00-00">
<head>Senate Document Number 118, 57<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Session, 1903</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02714001"/>
<opener>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
J. R. Kean<lb/>
57TH CONGRESS,}<lb/>
2d Session.}<lb/>
SENATE.<lb/>
{DOCUMENT<lb/>
{No. 118.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
THE<lb/>
SCIENTIFIC WORK AND DISCOVERIES<lb/>
OF THE LATE<lb/>
MAJ. WALTER REED,<lb/>
SURGEON IN THE ARMY OF THE UNITED STATES.<lb/>
----------<lb/>
PREPARED BY<lb/>
MAJ. JEFFERSON RANDOLPH KEAN,<lb/>
Surgeon in the Army of the United States.<lb/>
----------<lb/>
JANUARY 28, 1903.--Ordered to be printed.<lb/>
----------<lb/>
<dateline>
WASHINGTON:<lb/>
GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE.<lb/>
<date value="1903-00-00">1903.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<pb n="2" id="f02714002"/>
<p>RECOMMENDATION OF SECRETARY OF WAR IN REPORT FOR YEAR 1902.<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></p>
<p>The brilliant character of this scientific achievement, its inestimable<lb/>
value to mankind, the saving of thousands of lives, and the deliverance<lb/>
of the Atlantic seacoast from constant apprehension demand special<lb/>
recognition from the Government of the United States.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed is the ranking major in the Medical Department, and within<lb/>
a few months will, by operation of law, become lieutenant-colonel. I<lb/>
ask that the President be authorized to appoint him assistant surgeon-<lb/>
general with the rank of colonel, and to appoint Major Gorgas deputy<lb/>
surgeon-general with the rank of lieutenant-colonel, and that the respec-<lb/>
tive numbers in those grades in the Medical Department be increased<lb/>
accordingly during the period for which they hold those offices.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Page 10; in print, but not published at the time of Major Reed's death.</p>
<p>3</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02714003"/>
<p>SKETCH OF THE LIFE OF MAJ. WALTER REED, SURGEON, U. S. A.</p>
<p>---------</p>
<p>Walter Reed, M. D., LL. D., M. A., major and surgeon, U. S. Army,<lb/>
was born September 13, 1851, in Gloucester County, Va., and was the<lb/>
son of the Rev. Lemuel Sutton Reed, a leading Methodist divine of<lb/>
that State. His ancestors came from North Carolina, having been<lb/>
among the earliest settlers of that colony. He gave early evidence of<lb/>
the intellectual brilliancy and earnestness of purpose which distin-<lb/>
guished him in later years, and graduated in medicine at the University<lb/>
of Virginia in 1868. He afterwards took the degree of &ldquo;M. D.&rdquo; in<lb/>
Bellevue Medical College, New York City. He served as house sur-<lb/>
geon in the Brooklyn City Hospital and the City Hospital on Black-<lb/>
wells Island, and before the age of 21 was appointed a district physi-<lb/>
cian in New York City. He was also appointed one of the five inspect-<lb/>
ors of the board of health of the city of Brooklyn at the age of 22.<lb/>
In 1875 he entered the Medical Corps of the Army, and for eighteen<lb/>
years thereafter performed the customary duties of a medical officer at<lb/>
various posts in different parts of the United States and in the field.<lb/>
His military service included fifteen changes of station with four years<lb/>
in Arizona, five in the Department of the Platte, two in the Depart-<lb/>
ment of Dakota, three in the South, and three years in the East. He<lb/>
was promoted full surgeon with the rank of major December 4, 1893,<lb/>
and at the time of his death was first on the list of majors in the Medical<lb/>
Department of the Army. In the fall of 1890 he was assigned to duty<lb/>
as attending surgeon in Baltimore, Md., which position he held for a<lb/>
year. He promptly embraced this opportunity to make special studies<lb/>
in bacteriology and pathology, and soon won the attention and esteem<lb/>
of Prof. William H. Welch. This was the beginning of a close friend-<lb/>
ship with that distinguished scientist which lasted until the untimely<lb/>
death of Major Reed, on November 23, 1902.</p>
<p>In 1893 Major Reed was placed on duty in Washington as curator<lb/>
of the Army Medical Museum and appointed the professor of bacte-<lb/>
riology of the newly organized Army Medical School.</p>
<p>In the ten years subsequent to this date, in the intervals of his<lb/>
routine duties and others which came to him as a medical officer, such<lb/>
as member of examining boards, teaching, investigation of numerous<lb/>
sanitary questions, and making sanitary inspections, he was able, by<lb/>
immense industry, to obtain a position in the scientific world such as<lb/>
5<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02714004"/>
6<lb/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
comes to few of those who are able to devote a lifetime exclusively to<lb/>
such pursuits.</p>
<p>Of the numerous monographs which show his scientific work during<lb/>
this time, all are creditable; nor do any show marks of carelessness or<lb/>
haste, in spite of the limited time which he had at his disposal.</p>
<p>In 1898, when typhoid fever prevailed so extensively in the camps<lb/>
of the volunteer armies of the United States, Major Reed was put at<lb/>
the head of a commission--Dr. Victor C. Vaughan, of the University<lb/>
of Michigan, and Dr. E. O. Shakespeare, of Philadelphia, being the<lb/>
other members--to study the causation and methods of spread of that<lb/>
disease. This investigation, which covered a period of more than a<lb/>
year, was remarkable for the patience and skill with which a vast<lb/>
number of details were assembled and studied, and it marks a great<lb/>
advance in our knowledge of this widespread disease. Among the<lb/>
points of great value brought out were the importance of the common<lb/>
fly as a carrier of infection in camps, and the frequency with which<lb/>
the contagion of typhoid fever is in camp life spread from man to<lb/>
man by immediate contact with each other or with bedding, tents,<lb/>
and implements which have become infected. Strangely enough, this<lb/>
report has never been published in full, but only an abstract of<lb/>
it containing some 240 pages, and, on account of the failure to pub-<lb/>
lish and disseminate the full report, its conclusions are but little<lb/>
known abroad or among the members of the medical profession in this<lb/>
country. Many of the facts contained in it were rediscovered by<lb/>
the English during the Boer war, and it is probable that its prompt<lb/>
publication and dissemination would have saved many thousand lives<lb/>
during that war.</p>
<p>The first work by Major Reed bearing on the causation of yellow<lb/>
fever was in 1899-1900, when he overthrew the claim of the dis-<lb/>
tinguished bacteriologist, Sanarelli, to have discovered the bacillus of<lb/>
yellow fever, by his demonstration that the Bacillus icteroides (Sana-<lb/>
relli) was an organism widely disseminated in this country and having<lb/>
no causative relation to that disease. He began the special work with<lb/>
which his name will always be inseparably associated as one of the ben-<lb/>
efactors of mankind in June, 1900, when he went to Cuba as presi-<lb/>
dent of a commission to study the infectious diseases of Cuba, with<lb/>
special reference to yellow fever. The other members of this commis-<lb/>
sion were Acting Asst. Surgs. James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear, and<lb/>
A. Agramonte. The time was most opportune for such investigation,<lb/>
as the disease was at that time prevalent both in Habana and in the<lb/>
little town of Quemados, near the camp of the American troops, and<lb/>
it was plainly evident that the energetic measures of the American<lb/>
military government to clean up the towns, disinfect, and enforce<lb/>
other sanitary measures were without effect in preventing the spread<lb/>
of this particular disease. Major Reed became convinced that proper<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02714005"/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
7<lb/>
sanitation was not all that was needed, and that some other agent than<lb/>
unclean conditions was responsible for the spread of the disease.</p>
<p>The transmission of malaria by a certain species of mosquito had<lb/>
been recently demonstrated by the English military surgeon, Ronald<lb/>
Ross. The theory had also been advanced both by a Mobile physician<lb/>
and by Dr. Finlay, of Habana, that a mosquito was the agent for the<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever; but these theories, being unsupported<lb/>
by scientific demonstration, received no more attention than the vast<lb/>
number of others which had been at one time or another advanced<lb/>
with regard to this mysterious and deadly disease.</p>
<p><unclear>not 23</unclear></p>
<p>Dr. Reed's attention was attracted by a paper on the spread of yellow<lb/>
fever in Ormond, Miss., by Dr. H. R. Carter, of the Marine-Hospital<lb/>
Service, in which it was shown that although the period of incubation<lb/>
of the disease was five days, fifteen or twenty elapsed before a house<lb/>
became infected after a patient sick with yellow fever was carried into<lb/>
it. He inferred that the difference between the time of incubation and<lb/>
the time required to infect a building was due to the fact that the<lb/>
infective agent passed through a stage of development in the body of<lb/>
some biting insect as an intermediate host, and he at once determined<lb/>
to conduct his experiments along that line. It was evident to his mind<lb/>
that the solution of this question, which meant so much for the human<lb/>
race, could never be satisfactorily determined without experiments on<lb/>
human beings, and he went to General Wood, the military governor<lb/>
of Cuba, to ask permission to conduct such experiments, and for a sum<lb/>
of money to liberally reward volunteers who should submit themselves<lb/>
for experiment. General Wood promptly granted both, with a ready<lb/>
appreciation of the importance of the matter and the force of Dr.<lb/>
Reed's arguments, which will entitle him to no small measure of the<lb/>
glory of this discovery.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, during a temporary absence of Dr. Reed in the United<lb/>
States, his assistants, Dr. James Carroll and Dr. Jesse W. Lazear,<lb/>
who had offered themselves as the first volunteers for these experi-<lb/>
ments, had demonstrated that mosquitoes would convey yellow fever.<lb/>
Dr. Carroll, who was the first experimental case, suffered a very severe<lb/>
attack, but recovered. Dr. Lazear was not infected at this time, due<lb/>
to the fact that the conditions necessary to the transmission of the<lb/>
disease by the mosquito were not yet understood, but he was bitten<lb/>
while working in the yellow-fever ward somewhat later, and died a<lb/>
martyr of science, working in behalf of humanity. This was the only<lb/>
fatality which occurred in these experiments. The fourth member of<lb/>
the commission, Dr. Agramonte, did not participate in the mosquito<lb/>
work of the commission until a later date, nor did he share their dan-<lb/>
gers, as he was a Cuban and immune.</p>
<p>Immediately upon Dr. Reed's return arrangements were made, with<lb/>
the assistance of the military governor, as stated above, for a series of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02714006"/>
8<lb/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
experiments which, by precision of detail and rigidness of control,<lb/>
would admit of no uncertainty of interpretation and would be a per-<lb/>
fcet demonstration, carrying conviction to every scientific and unpreju-<lb/>
diced mind. These experiments will, as stated by Prof. William H.<lb/>
Welch, always remain as models in the annals of scientific research,<lb/>
both for the exactness with which they were adapted to the points to<lb/>
be proved and the precautions taken that no experiment should be<lb/>
vitiated by failure to exclude all possible sources of error. They<lb/>
were conducted in a camp especially constructed for the purpose, about<lb/>
4 miles from Habana, and appropriately named &ldquo;Camp Lazear.&rdquo; The<lb/>
history of the work is best given in Dr. Reed's own words, in an article<lb/>
published in the Journal of Hygiene, Cambridge, England. The fol-<lb/>
lowing is the article in a somewhat abridged form:</p>
<pb n="7" id="f02714007"/>
<p>[From the Journal of Hygiene, Vol. II, No. 2, April, 1902.]</p>
<p>RECENT RESEARCHES CONCERNING THE ETIOLOGY, PROPAGA-<lb/>
TION, AND PREVENTION OF YELLOW FEVER BY THE U. S. ARMY<lb/>
COMMISSION.</p>
<p>By WALTER REED, M. D.,<lb/>
Surgeon, U. S. Army, President of the Commission.</p>
<p>(Three charts.)</p>
<p>The efficient control of the spread of yellow fever is a matter of<lb/>
such vast practical importance, both from the hygienic and commercial<lb/>
point of view--not only for the countries where this disease prevails<lb/>
as an epidemic, but also for those in which, after importation, it may<lb/>
assume epidemic proportions--that it has seemed appropriate to bring<lb/>
together in this paper a summary of the work thus far accomplished<lb/>
by the U. S. Army commission<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> on the island of Cuba during the<lb/>
years 1900 and 1901, in order that English and colonial readers who<lb/>
have not, perhaps, had access to the original contributions published<lb/>
in different American journals may be able to form an intelligent<lb/>
opinion concerning the permanent value of this work. It will also<lb/>
afford opportunity for recording the more recent confirmatory obser-<lb/>
vations made by others concerning the mode of transmission of yellow<lb/>
fever discovered by the commission, and for calling attention to the<lb/>
results already obtained by the U. S. Army Medical Department in<lb/>
the suppression of this disease, especially in the city of Habana,<lb/>
through the enforcement of sanitary measures based on these later<lb/>
researches.</p>
<p>The American commission was organized in May, 1900, and began<lb/>
its investigations during the following month (June), being equipped<lb/>
with suitable laboratory facilities for practical work, both at the mili-<lb/>
tary garrison of Columbia Barracks, near Quemados, Cuba, and also<lb/>
in the city of Habana. As yellow fever was already prevailing at the<lb/>
time of our arrival in Cuba, suitable material for the scientific study<lb/>
of this disease was immediately available.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">a</hi> The members of this commission were Maj. Walter Reed, surgeon, U. S. Army,<lb/>
and Drs. James Carroll, A. Agramonte, and the late Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, contract<lb/>
surgeons, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>9</p>
<pb n="8" id="f02714008"/>
<p>10</p>
<p>THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.</p>
<p>THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>Before giving the results of our investigations, it may be well to<lb/>
recall the situation as regards the etiology of yellow fever at that<lb/>
time. Briefly, it may be said that the claims of all investigators for<lb/>
the discovery of the specific agent of yellow fever--since modern bac-<lb/>
teriological methods had come into use--had been disproved by the<lb/>
exhaustive observations of Sternberg, published in 1890, except that<lb/>
made by Sanarelli for a small, motile bacillus isolated by him from the<lb/>
blood drawn during life in two of six cases of yellow fever, and from<lb/>
the blood and organs after death in seven of twelve cases of this dis-<lb/>
ease (58 per cent), studied at Montevideo and Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.<lb/>
The results obtained, however, by those who had promptly undertaken<lb/>
to investigate Sanarelli's claim for the specific character of Bacillus<lb/>
icteroides seemed to show a lack of agreement such as has never been<lb/>
reported, as far as the writer can recall, in connection with the sup-<lb/>
posed specific cause of any of the other acute infections.</p>
<p>Under these circumstances it seemed to the members of the commis-<lb/>
sion of the first importance to give their entire attention to the<lb/>
bacteriological study of the blood of those sick with yellow fever and<lb/>
of the blood and organs of yellow-fever cadavers, having especially in<lb/>
view the isolation of B. icteroides. We were thus able during June,<lb/>
July, and August to take repeated cultures from the blood during life<lb/>
in 18 cases of yellow fever, adopting the usual method employed in<lb/>
withdrawing blood from a vein at the bend of the elbow, and trans-<lb/>
ferring the blood at once in quantities of 0.5 c. c. to each of several<lb/>
tubes containing 10 c. c. of nutritive bouillon, which were afterwards<lb/>
incubated at 37&deg; C. for a period of one week. In seven cases, four of<lb/>
which were designated as &ldquo;mild&rdquo; yellow fever and three as &ldquo;well-<lb/>
marked&rdquo; yellow fever, only one culture was made from the blood in<lb/>
each case, viz, in two cases on the first day, in one case on the second<lb/>
day, in three cases on the third day, and in one case on the fourth day.<lb/>
In the remaining 11 cases diagnosed as &ldquo;severe&rdquo; yellow fever, of<lb/>
whom four died, more frequent cultures were taken from the blood,<lb/>
these varying from two to six cultures on as many different days of<lb/>
the disease. In two of the fatal cases cultures were made each day<lb/>
from the commencement of the attack and including the day on which<lb/>
death occurred.</p>
<p>The negative result of these numerous cultures taken from the blood<lb/>
of cases of yellow fever, as regards the presence of B. icteroides, was<lb/>
reported in a &ldquo;Preliminary note&rdquo; presented at the meeting of the<lb/>
American Public Health Association, held in Indianapolis, Ind., Octo-<lb/>
ber 22-26, 1900. To these 18 cases we can now add 6 other cases, or<lb/>
a total of 24, from which blood cultures have been made during life<lb/>
with negative results.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f02714009"/>
<p>THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.</p>
<p>11</p>
<p>The importance of this negative finding as regards the growth of any<lb/>
specific bacterium will be better appreciated when it is seen, as I shall<lb/>
soon have occasion to point out, that yellow fever may be produced in<lb/>
nonimmune human beings by the subcutaneous injection of a small<lb/>
quantity (0.5-2 c.c.) of blood withdrawn from the venous circulation of<lb/>
a patient suffering with this disease.</p>
<p>In addition to the results above recorded, the careful study of 11<lb/>
autopsies was equally barren as to the presence of any particular micro-<lb/>
organism, although the quantity of material with which our tubes were<lb/>
inoculated was greater than is usually made use of at autopsies.</p>
<p>In a word, then, the careful bacteriological study which the com-<lb/>
mission had made in cases of yellow fever had given no indications as<lb/>
to the presence of the specific agent of this disease. The same may be<lb/>
said concerning the result of numerous microscopic examinations of<lb/>
fresh and stained specimens of blood which he had in the meanwhile<lb/>
studied with the view of finding possibly some intracellular or extra-<lb/>
cellular body. Apparently no body, bacterial or protozoan, which<lb/>
could be brought into view with a one-twelfth Zeiss immersion objec-<lb/>
tive was present in the blood of these cases.</p>
<p>Although displaced from the order in which the following observa-<lb/>
tions were made, it will be best to present at this time the results of<lb/>
the experiments which were later carried out by the commission on<lb/>
nonimmune human beings by means of the subcutaneous injection of<lb/>
blood, withdrawn during the active stage of the disease, as these<lb/>
results bear so directly upon the subject which we are now consider-<lb/>
ing, viz, the etiology of yellow fever.</p>
<p>The only reference that I can find in the literature relative to an<lb/>
attempt to convey yellow fever in this way is cited by Sternberg, who<lb/>
states that at Vera Cruz, Mexico, in 1877, he saw Dr. Ruis inject into<lb/>
a nonimmune individual a hypodermic syringeful of blood drawn<lb/>
from a case of yellow fever on the eighth day of the disease. The<lb/>
result was negative, as was also the result of two other attempts related<lb/>
to him by Ruis.</p>
<p>Our own observations, undertaken for the purpose of ascertaining<lb/>
whether an attack of yellow fever could be induced in a second indi-<lb/>
vidual by the injection of a small quantity of blood, embrace experi-<lb/>
ments made on 12 American soldiers and Spanish immigrants, all<lb/>
nonimmune individuals.</p>
<p>These observations may be divided into the following classes:</p>
<p>(1) Injection of the fresh blood taken from a vein at the bend of the<lb/>
elbow; (2) injection of partially defibrinated blood; (3) injection of<lb/>
partially defibrinated blood heated for ten minutes at 55&deg; C.; (4) injec-<lb/>
tion of blood-serum previously diluted with sterilized water and filtered<lb/>
slowly through a Berkefeld laboratory filter.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f02714010"/>
<p>12</p>
<p>THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.</p>
<p>The following table gives the results of these several inoculations:</p>
<p>TABLE I.</p>
<p>
<table rows="14" cols="6">
<row>
<cell>No. of<lb/>
case.</cell><cell>Quantity and material used.</cell><cell>Day of<lb/>
disease.</cell><cell>Date of<lb/>
inoculation.</cell><cell>Result.</cell><cell>Date of<lb/>
attack.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>I</cell><cell>2 c. c. fresh blood.....................</cell><cell>Second.....</cell><cell>Dec. 26, 1900</cell><cell>Negative ...</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>II</cell><cell>.....do ................................</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>Jan. 4, 1901</cell><cell>Positive ....</cell><cell>Jan. 8, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>III</cell><cell>1.5 c. c. fresh blood ...................</cell><cell>First........</cell><cell>Jan. 8, 1901</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>Jan. 11, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>IV</cell><cell>0.5 c. c. fresh blood ...................</cell><cell>Second .....</cell><cell>Jan. 22, 1901</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>Jan. 24, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>V</cell><cell>1 c. c. fresh blood .....................</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>Jan. 25, 1901</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>Jan. 28, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VI</cell><cell>0.75 c. c. partially defibrinated blood.</cell><cell>Third.......</cell><cell>Oct. 15, 1901</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>Oct. 20, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VII</cell><cell>1.5 c. c. partially defibrinated blood<lb/>
heated for ten minutes at 55&deg; C.</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>.....do .......</cell><cell>Negative ...</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VIII</cell><cell>Same as No. VII......................</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>.....do .......</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>IX</cell><cell>.....do ................................</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>.....do .......</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>X</cell><cell>1.5 c. c. of filtered blood serum .......</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>.....do .......</cell><cell>Positive ....</cell><cell>Oct. 19, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>XI</cell><cell>Same as No. X .......................</cell><cell>.....do .......</cell><cell>.....do .......</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>Do.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell rows="13-14">XII</cell><cell>{....do ................................</cell><cell>.....do ......</cell><cell>.....do .......</cell><cell>Negative ...</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>{2 c. c. fresh blood .....................</cell><cell>Fourth .....</cell><cell>Oct. 22, 1901</cell><cell>Positive ....</cell><cell>Oct. 23, 1901</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>By an examination of this table it will be seen that of the seven<lb/>
individuals who received subcutaneously the fresh or partially defi-<lb/>
brinated blood in quantities of 0.5-2 c. c., six (85.7 per cent) developed<lb/>
an attack of yellow fever within the usual period of incubation of<lb/>
the disease.</p>
<p>These results are of very great interest as demonstrating that the<lb/>
specific agent of yellow fever is present in the blood, at least during<lb/>
the first, second, and third days of the attack.</p>
<p>Another important point brought out by these experiments was that<lb/>
the blood which conveyed the disease did not contain any bacterium<lb/>
which would grow on our usual laboratory media.</p>
<p>In order to establish this fact, as soon as blood had been injected<lb/>
into the nonimmune subject, additional blood was at once withdrawn<lb/>
in considerable quantity and transferred to tubes of nutritive bouillon.<lb/>
In one instance, where 2 c.c. of blood had been drawn into the syringe,<lb/>
0.5 c.c. of this sufficed, when injected, to produce a severe attack of<lb/>
yellow fever, after seventy-three hours' incubation, while the remain-<lb/>
ing 1.5 c.c. transferred immediately to four tubes of bouillon gave no<lb/>
growth, except that from one tube we isolated on the fourth day<lb/>
Staphylococcus pyogenes citreus, found by us to be a common skin-<lb/>
contaminating organism in Cuba.</p>
<p>Table I further shows that the specific agent contained in the blood<lb/>
is destroyed or attenuated by heating the latter at 55&deg; C. for ten minutes,<lb/>
so that the injection of 1.5 c.c. of this heated blood was harmless<lb/>
(Cases VII, VIII, and IX), while the injection of 0.75 c.c. of the same<lb/>
blood unheated sufficed to promptly induce an attack of yellow fever<lb/>
in a &ldquo;control&rdquo; individual (Case VI).</p>
<p>Of not less interest was the fact brought out by these observations<lb/>
that yellow fever can be produced by the injection of a small quantity<lb/>
of bacteria-free serum filtrate, obtained by passing the diluted serum<lb/>
through a Berkefeld laboratory filter (Cases X and XI), and further<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f02714011"/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
13<lb/>
that the blood of a case of yellow fever, thus produced, when injected<lb/>
into a third nonimmune subject will promptly bring about an attack<lb/>
of this disease (Case XII); thus demonstrating that the specific agent<lb/>
of yellow fever can find its way through the pores of a filter which<lb/>
ordinarily serves to prevent the passage of all known bacteria.</p>
<p>I have elsewhere, in conjunction with one of my colleagues (Carroll),<lb/>
discussed the facts here presented more at length, and will limit<lb/>
myself, therefore, to the remark that these experiments appear to<lb/>
indicate that yellow fever, like the foot-and-mouth disease of cattle, is<lb/>
caused by a micro-organism so minute in size that it might be desig-<lb/>
nated as ultra-microscopic.</p>
<p>THE PROPAGATION OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>Prior to the time at which the foregoing observations were made the<lb/>
commission had already turned its entire attention to the possible<lb/>
solution of the problem of the propagation of yellow fever, being<lb/>
induced thereto not only by the fruitlessness of the investigations<lb/>
made thus far along bacteriological lines, but also by reason of certain<lb/>
facts which seemed to call for a better interpretation than had hitherto<lb/>
been accorded them.</p>
<p>Without entering into details, I may say that, in the first place, the<lb/>
commission saw, with some surprise, what had so often been noted in<lb/>
the literature, that patients in all stages of yellow fever could be cared<lb/>
for by nonimmune nurses without danger of contracting the disease.<lb/>
The noncontagious character of yellow fever was, therefore, hardly<lb/>
to be questioned.</p>
<p>In the second place, it had been observed that patients discharged<lb/>
from the wards during early convalesence could be brought into inti-<lb/>
mate association with nonimmune individuals without thereby estab-<lb/>
lishing fresh foci of the disease. This did not seem to indicate that<lb/>
any specific agent was present in the excreta of the sick.</p>
<p>Again, it has been noted that in certain cases of this disease no<lb/>
growth had been obtained on the ordinary laboratory media, either by<lb/>
frequent cultures from the blood during life or from the blood and<lb/>
organs after death.</p>
<p>Further, in the course of an investigation which the commission<lb/>
were able to make during the last week of July, 1900, concerning the<lb/>
origin and spread of a small epidemic of yellow fever that had appeared<lb/>
in a military garrison, numbering about 900 men, at Pinar del Rio,<lb/>
Cuba, they had seen that by reason of the false diagnosis of &ldquo;pernicious<lb/>
malarial fever&rdquo; which had been given to these cases no disinfection of<lb/>
bedding or clothing had been carried out; and yet there was no indica-<lb/>
tion that this neglect had contributed in the least to the spread of the<lb/>
disease; nor had any harm come to those nonimmunes who had slept<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f02714012"/>
14<lb/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
in the beds vacated by the sick or washed the supposedly infected<lb/>
garments of those who had recovered or died of this disease.</p>
<p>Putting these various data together, it seems probable that more<lb/>
progress might be made if attention should be turned to the mode of<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever, especially as our own observations had<lb/>
caused us to seriously doubt the usually accepted belief of the convey-<lb/>
ance of this disease by means of fomites.</p>
<p>Then, too, the endemic curve of yellow fever in the city of Habana,<lb/>
and its well-known epidemic curve in the United States, appeared to<lb/>
be more intimately associated with and more affected by the rise and<lb/>
fall of the annual temperature curve than was to be seen in any of the<lb/>
acute infections except malarial fever. The peculiar behavior of this<lb/>
disease (if I may use the expression) in rapidly spreading in certain<lb/>
localities, when introduced, as contrasted with its failure to propagate<lb/>
itself in other places where the conditions for its increase were appar-<lb/>
ently just as favorable, seemed to point in the strongest manner to<lb/>
the necessity for some special agent or intermediate host in the dis-<lb/>
semination of its specific cause. If malarial fever--a disease so much<lb/>
affected by temperature conditions--required the agency of a special<lb/>
genus of mosquito for its propagation, as had in recent years been so<lb/>
brilliantly worked out by Ross, Grassi, Bastianelli, Bignami, and others,<lb/>
it did not seem unreasonable to suppose that yellow fever--a disease<lb/>
so plainly controlled by seasonal conditions--might also depend on<lb/>
some such agent for its spread. Influenced by this line of reasoning<lb/>
the commission began, during the second week of August, 1900, its<lb/>
observations relative to the propagation of yellow fever by means of<lb/>
the bite of a certain species of mosquito, Stegomyia fasciata.</p>
<p>The work along this line was carried forward so rapidly that within<lb/>
thirty days 11 individuals had been bitten by infected Stegomyia,<lb/>
of whom 2<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> developed well-marked attacks of yellow fever within<lb/>
the usual period of incubation, and under such circumstances as to<lb/>
positively exclude in one case any other possible source of infection.</p>
<p>Appreciating fully the importance of this discovery, and in order to<lb/>
exclude all other possible sources of infection in our future observa-<lb/>
tions, it was now determined to establish a special experimental station<lb/>
where further observations could be made on nonimmune human<lb/>
beings, both as to the propagation of yellow fever by means of the<lb/>
bite of the mosquito as well as by exposure to the most intimate con-<lb/>
tact with infected clothing and bedding, and this under the strictest<lb/>
enforcement of military quarantine. With the approval and assistance<lb/>
of the military governor of the island of Cuba, this experimental sta-<lb/>
tion was ready for occupancy on November 20, 1900, and was contin-<lb/>
uously occupied until March 1, 1901.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">a</hi> One of these cases was that of Dr. James Carroll, contract surgeon, U. S. Army,<lb/>
a member of the commission.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f02714013"/>
<p>THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.</p>
<p>15</p>
<p>As the results obtained at this station have already been published<lb/>
in full elsewhere, I will here only present a brief account, first of the<lb/>
experiments with fomites and afterwards of those made with infected<lb/>
mosquitoes.</p>
<p>ATTEMPTS AT INFECTION BY FOMITES.</p>
<p>I quote from a paper which the writer presented for the commission<lb/>
at the meeting of the Pan-American Medical Congress,<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> held in<lb/>
Habana, Cuba, February 4-7, 1901:</p>
<p>For this purpose there was erected at Camp Lazear a small frame house, consisting<lb/>
of one room, 14 by 20 feet, and known as &ldquo;Building No. 1,&rdquo; or the &ldquo;Infected<lb/>
clothing and bedding building.&rdquo; The cubic capacity of this house was 2,800 feet.<lb/>
It was tightly sealed within with &ldquo;tongued and grooved boards,&rdquo; and was well bat-<lb/>
tened on the outside. It faced the south and was provided with two small windows,<lb/>
each 26 by 34 inches in size. These windows were both placed on the south side of<lb/>
the building, the purpose being to prevent, as much as possible, any thorough circu-<lb/>
lation of the air within the house. They were closed by permanent wire-screens of 0.5<lb/>
mm. mesh. In addition, a sliding glass sash was provided within and heavy wooden<lb/>
shutters without; the latter intended to prevent the entrance of sunlight into the<lb/>
building, as it was not deemed desirable that the disinfecting qualities of sunlight,<lb/>
direct or diffused, should at any time be exerted on the articles of clothing contained<lb/>
within this room. Entrance was effected through a small vestibule, 3 by 5 feet,<lb/>
also placed on the southern side of the house. This vestibule was protected without<lb/>
by a solid door, and was divided in its middle by a wire-screen door swung on<lb/>
spring hinges. The inner entrance was also closed by a second wire-screen door.<lb/>
In this way the passage of mosquitoes into this room was effectually excluded.<lb/>
During the day, and until after sunset, the house was kept securely closed, while by<lb/>
means of a suitable heating apparatus the temperature was raised to 92&deg;-95&deg; F.<lb/>
Precaution was taken at the same time to maintain a sufficient humidity of the<lb/>
atmosphere. The average temperature of this house was thus kept up at 76.2&deg; F.<lb/>
for a period of sixty-three days.</p>
<p>November 30, 1900, the building now being ready for occupancy, three large boxes<lb/>
filled with sheets, pillowcases, blankets, etc., contaminated by contact with cases of<lb/>
yellow fever and their discharges, were received and placed therein. The majority<lb/>
of the articles had been taken from the beds of patients sick with yellow fever at<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital, Habana, or at Columbia Barracks. Many of them had been<lb/>
purposely soiled with a liberal quantity of black vomit, urine, and fecal matter. A<lb/>
dirty &ldquo;comfortable&rdquo; and a much-soiled pair of blankets, removed from the bed of a<lb/>
patient sick with yellow fever in the town of Quemados, were contained in one of<lb/>
these boxes. The same day, at 6 p. m., Dr. R. P. Cooke, acting assistant surgeon,<lb/>
U. S. Army, and two privates of the Hospital Corps, all nonimmune young Ameri-<lb/>
cans, entered this building and deliberately unpacked these boxes, which had been<lb/>
tightly closed and locked for a period of two weeks. They were careful at the same<lb/>
time to give each article a thorough handling and shaking, in order to disseminate<lb/>
through the air of the room the specific agent of yellow fever, if contained in these<lb/>
fomites. These soiled sheets, pillowcases, and blankets were used in preparing the<lb/>
beds in which the members of the Hospital Corps slept. Various soiled articles<lb/>
were hung around the room and placed about the bed occupied by Dr. Cooke.</p>
<p>From this date until December 19, 1900, a period of twenty days, this room was<lb/>
occupied each night by these three nonimmunes. Each morning the various soiled<lb/>
articles were carefully repacked in the aforesaid boxes and at night again unpacked<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Loc. cit.<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f02714014"/>
16<lb/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
and distributed about the room. During the day the residents of this house were<lb/>
permitted to occupy a tent pitched in the immediate vicinity, but were kept in strict<lb/>
quarantine.</p>
<p>* * * * * * *</p>
<p>December 19 these three nonimmunes were placed in quarantine for five days and<lb/>
then given the liberty of the camp. All had remained in perfect health, notwith-<lb/>
standing their stay of twenty nights amid such unwholesome surroundings.</p>
<p>During the week December 20-27 the following articles were also placed in this<lb/>
house, viz, pajamas suits, 1; undershirts, 2; nightshirts, 4; pillow slips, 4; sheets, 6;<lb/>
blankets, 5; pillows, 2; mattresses, 1. These articles had been removed from the<lb/>
persons and beds of four patients sick with yellow fever, and were very much soiled,<lb/>
as any change of clothing or bedlinen during their attacks had been purposely<lb/>
avoided, the object being to obtain articles as thoroughly contaminated as possible.</p>
<p>From December 21, 1900, till January 10, 1901, this building was again occupied<lb/>
by two nonimmune young Americans, under the same conditions as the preceding<lb/>
occupants, except that these men slept every night in the very garments worn by<lb/>
yellow-fever patients throughout their entire attacks, besides making use exclusively<lb/>
of their much-soiled pillow slips, sheets, and blankets. At the end of twenty-one<lb/>
nights of such intimate contact with these fomites they also went into quarantine,<lb/>
from which they were released five days later in perfect health.</p>
<p>From January 11 till January 31, a period of twenty days, &ldquo;Building No. 1&rdquo; con-<lb/>
tinued to be occupied by two other nonimmune Americans, who, like those who pre-<lb/>
ceded them, have slept every night in the beds formerly occupied by yellow-fever<lb/>
patients and in the nightshirts used by these patients throughout the attack without<lb/>
change. In addition, during the last fourteen nights of their occupancy of this<lb/>
house they had slept each night with their pillows covered with towels that had<lb/>
been thoroughly soiled with the blood drawn from both the general and capillary<lb/>
circulation on the first day of the disease in the case of a well-marked attack of yellow<lb/>
fever. Notwithstanding this trying ordeal, these men have continued to remain in<lb/>
perfect health.</p>
<p>The attempt which we have therefore made to infect &ldquo;Building No. 1&rdquo; and its<lb/>
seven nonimmune occupants during a period of sixty-three nights has proved an<lb/>
absolute failure.</p>
<p>INFECTION BY MOSQUITOES.</p>
<p>While the experiments with fomites were being carried out in<lb/>
building No. 1, certain nonimmune individuals who were lodged in<lb/>
tents, in a separate part of the camp, were being subjected, with their<lb/>
full consent, to the bites of mosquitoes which had previously fed on<lb/>
the blood of cases of yellow fever occurring in the city of Habana.<lb/>
Thus, during the period from December 5, 1900, to February 7, 1901,<lb/>
we had subjected to this method of infection twelve nonimmune sub-<lb/>
jects who had previously passed their full record of quarantine in this<lb/>
camp. Of these 10, or 83.3 per cent, experienced attacks of yellow<lb/>
fever and always within the period of incubation of this disease.</p>
<p>The following table gives the necessary data concerning these<lb/>
observations:</p>
<pb n="15" id="f02714015"/>
<p>THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.</p>
<p>17</p>
<p>TABLE II.</p>
<p>
<table rows="14" cols="9">
<row>
<cell rows="1-2">No. of<lb/>
case.</cell><cell rows="1-2">Days in<lb/>
quaran-<lb/>
tine.</cell><cell cols="3-4">Inoculation.</cell><cell rows="1-2">Method of<lb/>
inocula-<lb/>
tion.</cell><cell rows="1-2">Period<lb/>
of incu-<lb/>
bation<lb/>
in<lb/>
hours.</cell><cell rows="1-2">Result.</cell><cell rows="1-2">Order<lb/>
of oc-<lb/>
cur-<lb/>
rence.</cell><cell rows="1-2">Date of<lb/>
occurrence.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hour.</cell><cell>Date.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>I.........</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>2 p.m.......</cell><cell>Dec. 5, 1900</cell><cell>Mosquito</cell><cell>81 <unclear>1/2</unclear></cell><cell>Positive...</cell><cell>I......</cell><cell>Dec. 8, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>II........</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>4 p.m.......</cell><cell>Dec. 8, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>137</cell><cell>.....do.....</cell><cell>III....</cell><cell>Dec. 13, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>III.......</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>10.30 a.m...</cell><cell>Dec. 9, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>83 <unclear>1/2</unclear></cell><cell>.....do.....</cell><cell>II.....</cell><cell>Dec. 12, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>IV.......</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>4.30 p.m....</cell><cell>Dec. 11, 1900</cell><cell>.....do ....</cell><cell>91 <unclear>1/2</unclear></cell><cell>.....do.....</cell><cell>IV....</cell><cell>Dec. 15, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>V........</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>12 noon.....</cell><cell>Dec. 21, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>95</cell><cell>.....do.....</cell><cell>V.....</cell><cell>Dec. 25, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VI.......</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>10 a.m......</cell><cell>Jan. 8, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>Negative..</cell><cell>VI....</cell><cell>..............</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VII......</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>11 a.m......</cell><cell>Dec. 30, 1900</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>94 <unclear>1/2</unclear></cell><cell>Positive...</cell><cell>VII...</cell><cell>Jan. 3, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>VIII.....</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>8.30 p.m....</cell><cell>Jan. 19, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>95 <unclear>1/2</unclear></cell><cell>.....do.....</cell><cell>VIII..</cell><cell>Jan. 23, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>IX.......</cell><cell>74</cell><cell>10.30 a.m...</cell><cell>Jan. 25, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>Negative..</cell><cell>IX....</cell><cell>..............</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>X........</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>9.30 a.m....</cell><cell>Jan. 31, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>74 <unclear>1/2</unclear></cell><cell>Positive...</cell><cell>X.....</cell><cell>Feb. 3, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>XI.......</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>11 a.m......</cell><cell>Feb. 6, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>.....do.....</cell><cell>XI....</cell><cell>Feb. 9, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>XII......</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>2 p.m.......</cell><cell>Feb. 7, 1901</cell><cell>.....do....</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>.....do.....</cell><cell>XII...</cell><cell>Feb. 10, 1901</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>The positive results obtained, therefore, by this mode of infection<lb/>
stand in striking contrast to the negative experiments made with<lb/>
fomites. Indeed, Cases VIII and XI of Table II had each slept<lb/>
twenty-one nights in the garments of yellow-fever patients while<lb/>
occupants of building No. 1. As they had remained in perfect health<lb/>
at Camp Lazear for yet thirty days longer, they were at the expiration<lb/>
of this time bitten by infected mosquitoes solely for the purpose of<lb/>
testing their immunity and with the result that an attack of yellow<lb/>
fever promptly followed in each case.</p>
<p>It should be borne in mind, also, that of the nonimmune residents at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, while all lived under the same hygienic conditions, only<lb/>
those individuals developed yellow fever who were purposely bitten<lb/>
by contaminated mosquitoes, or injected with the blood of those sick<lb/>
with this disease. Moreover, the precision with which the infection<lb/>
of the individual followed the bite of the mosquito left nothing to be<lb/>
desired in order to fulfill the requirements of a scientific experiment.</p>
<p>Case V of Table II is of especial interest, when taken in connection<lb/>
with the failure to induce the disease by contact with fomites.</p>
<p>This individual, having been quarantined for thirty-two days at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, volunteered to enter a newly erected building in which<lb/>
fifteen contaminated mosquitoes had just been freed. His first visit<lb/>
was at noon, December 21, 1901, and the length of his stay thirty<lb/>
minutes. At 4.30 p. m. the same day he again entered this building<lb/>
and remained twenty minutes. The following day at 4.30 p. m. he<unclear>.</unclear><lb/>
for the third time, visited this room and remained twenty minutes.<lb/>
During each of these visits he was bitten by mosquitoes. He did not<lb/>
enter the building again, nor was he exposed to any other source of<lb/>
infection. Nevertheless at the expiration of three days and twenty-<lb/>
three hours, or at 6 a. m. December 25, 1900, he was suddenly seized<lb/>
with an attack of yellow fever, which proved to be severe in charac<lb/>
ter. That the infection was occasioned by the bites of contaminated<lb/>
mosquitoes was plainly shown by the immunity from the disease<lb/>
S. Doc. 118----2<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f02714016"/>
18<lb/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
enjoyed by two nonimmunes &ldquo;controls,&rdquo; who, protected only by a<lb/>
wire-screen partition, had been present at each of the subject's visits<lb/>
and who, under the same conditions of security against the bites of the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, continued to sleep in and breathe the common<lb/>
atmosphere of this room for yet eighteen nights.</p>
<p>To the positive cases contained in Table II, which were produced at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, we are now able to add four other cases of yellow fever<lb/>
occasioned by the bites of infected mosquitoes, thus making a total of<lb/>
14 cases, in each of which happily recovery followed.</p>
<p>A very important point brought out by these observations is that<lb/>
an interval of about twelve days or more after contamination appears to<lb/>
be necessary before the infected Stegomyia is capable of conveying the<lb/>
disease to a susceptible individual. Repeated experiments made with<lb/>
insects which had bitten yellow-fever patients two to ten days<lb/>
previously were always negative, although these same insects were<lb/>
proven capable of conveying the disease after having been kept until<lb/>
seventeen to twenty-four days had elapsed. Our observations further<lb/>
demonstrate that mosquitoes that have been kept for periods varying<lb/>
from thirty-nine to fifty-seven days after contamination are still<lb/>
capable of conveying the disease, and, further, that infected Stegomyia<lb/>
may survive for a period of at least seventy-one days. This will<lb/>
explain how the contagion of yellow fever may cling to a building,<lb/>
although it has been vacated for a period of two or more months.</p>
<p>Bearing in mind that the observations made by means of blood<lb/>
injections (Table I) were only undertaken after we had succeeded in<lb/>
demonstrating that the disease could be conveyed by the bites of<lb/>
infected Stegomyia, it will be seen that our study of the method of<lb/>
propagation of yellow fever at Camp Lazear sufficed to prove very<lb/>
definitely that, while the natural mode of transmission of this disease<lb/>
is through the bites of infected mosquitoes, yellow fever may also be<lb/>
conveyed, like malarial fever, by the injection of a small quantity of<lb/>
blood taken from the veins of an individual suffering with this disease.</p>
<p>Per contra, our observations show that, notwithstanding the com-<lb/>
mon belief in this mode of transmission, yellow fever can not be<lb/>
induced in the nonimmune individual even by the most intimate con-<lb/>
tact with contaminated articles of clothing and bedding.</p>
<p>Although the investigations made at Camp Lazear were only con-<lb/>
cluded one year ago, already confirmatory evidence of the strongest<lb/>
character has been furnished in a series of experiments carried out by<lb/>
Guit&eacute;ras at the inoculation station of the sanitary department of<lb/>
Habana.</p>
<p>I may be pardoned for quoting the paragraph with which Guit&eacute;ras<lb/>
begins his contribution. He says:</p>
<p>The favorable results obtained by the U. S. army commission in their experiments<lb/>
with yellow fever, the continued series of mild cases resulting from these experi-<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f02714017"/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
19<lb/>
ments without a death, suggested very naturally the continuation of their work on a<lb/>
larger scale; not with a view to control or confirm the conclusions of the commission,<lb/>
for anyone who had followed their work with unprejudiced attention must have<lb/>
concluded that their solution of the problem of the etiology of yellow fever was final;<lb/>
but rather in the hope of propagating the disease in a controllable form, and securing<lb/>
among the recently arrived immigrants immunization with the minimum amount<lb/>
of danger to themselves and the community.</p>
<p>Of a total of 42 individuals inoculated by Guit&eacute;ras 25 were rejected<lb/>
by him by reason of having been bitten by insects that had been<lb/>
applied to cases of fever about which the diagnosis was in doubt. The<lb/>
following table, therefore, only includes 17 persons who were bitten by<lb/>
Stegomyia that had previously fed on unmistakable cases of yellow<lb/>
fever at intervals of fourteen to thirty-six days before being applied<lb/>
to the nonimmune subject.</p>
<p>TABLE III.</p>
<p>
<table rows="18" cols="5">
<row>
<cell>No. of case.</cell><cell>Date of inocu-<lb/>
lation.</cell><cell>Mode of inocu-<lb/>
lation.</cell><cell>Result.</cell><cell>Period of incuba-<lb/>
tion.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1.........................</cell><cell>Feb. 23, 1901</cell><cell>Mosquito.........</cell><cell>Positive..........</cell><cell>3 days, 10 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 4, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative.........</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3.........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 7, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 8, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Positive..........</cell><cell>4 days, 5 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6.........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>3 days, 3 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>7.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 7, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative.........</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>8.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 9, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Positive..........</cell><cell>5 days, 3 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>9.........................</cell><cell>Aug. 10, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative.........</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>10........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>11........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>12........................</cell><cell>Aug. 13, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Positive..........</cell><cell>3 days, 19 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>13........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative.........</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>14........................</cell><cell>Aug. 14, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Positive..........</cell><cell>3 days, 21 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>15........................</cell><cell>.....do.......</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>5 days, 21 hours.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>16........................</cell><cell>Aug. 22, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>3 days.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>17........................</cell><cell>Aug. 24, 1901</cell><cell>.....do............</cell><cell>Negative.........</cell><cell></cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>A more complete confirmation of the results obtained by the American<lb/>
commission could not be furnished than the data contained in the fore-<lb/>
going table, since they show that of 17 individuals who were bitten by<lb/>
infected Stegomyia fasciata, 8 (47 per cent) developed the disease.<lb/>
Most unfortunately in three of these cases very grave symptoms ensued,<lb/>
such as black vomit and suppression of the urine, which eventuated in<lb/>
the death of the patients. I may add that in the hands of Guit&eacute;ras<lb/>
fomites failed to exert any effect on nonimmunes.</p>
<p>Whether other species of mosquitoes than Stegomyia are capable of<lb/>
conveying the parasite of yellow fever has not as yet been determined<lb/>
by the commission, nor have we been able to ascertain whether the<lb/>
parasite passes from the mother insect to daughter insects. The<lb/>
experiments which we have thus far been able to make for the purpose<lb/>
of determining these important points, although negative, have been<lb/>
too few in number to warrant any definite expression of opinion.</p>
<p>THE PREVENTION OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>The definite determination of the way in which yellow fever is<lb/>
transmitted from the sick to the well furnishes a solution at last of<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f02714018"/>
20<lb/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
that much-vexed problem of how to prevent the spread of the disease.<lb/>
Even in the absence of more definite knowledge concerning its specific<lb/>
agent--knowledge greatly to be desired from the scientific standpoint--<lb/>
we are now able, as sanitarians, to direct our efforts along certain well-<lb/>
defined lines, with a feeling of security heretofore unknown.</p>
<p>From the point of view of prevention the situation may be briefly<lb/>
summed up in the following conclusion, which was presented by the<lb/>
American army commission to the Pan-American Congress of 1900,<hi rend="superscript">a</hi><lb/>
viz, &ldquo;The spread of yellow fever can be most effectually controlled by<lb/>
measures directed to the destruction of mosquitoes and the protection<lb/>
of the sick against the bites of these insects.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This conclusion was the logical outcome of the observations that<lb/>
had been made by the commission at its experimental station near<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba.</p>
<p>The importance of the discovery that yellow fever is transmitted by<lb/>
the bite of a certain species of mosquito did not fail to attract the<lb/>
prompt attention of the military governor of the island of Cuba, him-<lb/>
self a physician and formerly a distinguished member of the Medical<lb/>
Department of the U. S. Army. By his direction the theory was at<lb/>
once subjected to a practical test in the city of Habana, in which city<lb/>
yellow fever had not failed to make its yearly appearance during the<lb/>
past one hundred and forty years.</p>
<p>Under the efficient management of the chief sanitary officer, Surg.<lb/>
Maj. William C. Gorgas, U. S. Army, the sanitary regulations were<lb/>
so far modified as to require that every patient having yellow fever<lb/>
should not only be quarantined, but that his room should be promptly<lb/>
protected with wire screens, so as to prevent the possibility of mos-<lb/>
quitoes becoming infected by sucking the blood of the patient. As a<lb/>
second important measure, a systematic destruction of all mosquitoes<lb/>
in other rooms of the patient's house, as well as in adjoining houses,<lb/>
was at once begun, the fumes of pyrethrum being relied upon to stupefy<lb/>
the insects, after which they were carefully swept up and burned. In<lb/>
other words, Surgeon-Major Gorgas, relying upon the well-known slow<lb/>
progress of yellow fever, sought to destroy all mosquitoes, infected or<lb/>
noninfected, within a given radius of each case, while at the same<lb/>
time he effectually excluded all mosquitoes from access to the sick.<lb/>
If a secondary case occurred, the same hygienic measures were vigorously<lb/>
enforced along the lines indicated.</p>
<p>As an illustration of what has been accomplished by these newer<lb/>
sanitary regulations, I may state that counting from the date when<lb/>
they were put into force, viz, February 15, 1901--Habana was freed<lb/>
from yellow fever within ninety days; so that from May 7 to July 1--<lb/>
a period of fifty-four days--no cases occurred. Notwithstanding the<lb/>
fact that on the latter date and during the months of July, August, and<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Loc. cit.<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f02714019"/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
21<lb/>
CHART I.--Showing monthly mortality from yellow fever in the city of Habana, for the twenty years<lb/>
1880-1899, and for the years 1900-1901.<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f02714020"/>
22<lb/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
CHART II.--Cases and deaths from yellow fever in the city of Habana, for the epidemic<lb/>
year March 1, 1900, to March 1, 1901 (by month).<lb/>
CHART III.--Cases and deaths from yellow fever in the city of Habana for the epidemic<lb/>
year March 1, 1901, to March 1, 1902 (by month).<lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f02714021"/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
23<lb/>
September the disease was repeatedly reintroduced into Habana from<lb/>
an inland town, no difficulty was encountered in promptly stamping it<lb/>
out by the same measures of sanitation intelligently applied both in<lb/>
the city of Habana as well as in the town of Santiago de las Vegas,<lb/>
whence the disease was being brought into Habana.</p>
<p>As a further illustration of the remarkable sanitary victory accom-<lb/>
plished over a disease whose progress we have heretofore been power-<lb/>
less to arrest, I will close this paper by inviting the reader's attention,<lb/>
first to the accompanying Chart I, which shows the average monthly<lb/>
mortality from yellow fever in Habana for the twenty years 1880-<lb/>
1899, inclusive, and also the mortality by month for the years 1900 and<lb/>
1901. I will then ask him to examine Chart II, which shows the<lb/>
progress of yellow fever in Habana during the epidemic year ending<lb/>
March 1, 1901, when the sanitary authorities were putting forth every<lb/>
effort known at that time to sanitary science in order to control the<lb/>
march of the disease, and when he has satisfied himself that no effect<lb/>
whatever was produced upon the epidemic of that year, I will invite<lb/>
his attention to Chart III, which shows the occurrence of this disease<lb/>
in Habana for the epidemic year March 1, 1901, to March 1, 1902,<lb/>
during which year yellow fever was fought on the theory that the<lb/>
specific agent of this disease is transmitted solely by means of the bites<lb/>
of infected mosquitoes. By carefully comparing the figures both as<lb/>
to deaths and cases in these two charts, and recalling that between the<lb/>
years 1853 and 1900 there have been recorded in the city of Habana<lb/>
35,952 deaths from yellow fever, he will then be able to more clearly<lb/>
appreciate the value of the work accomplished by the American Army<lb/>
commission.<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></p>
<p>------</p>
<p>VALUE OF DR. REED'S WORK.</p>
<p>Popular appreciation of the value of the work of the yellow fever<lb/>
commission has been singularly slow and imperfect. While nearly<lb/>
every educated person in the United States is familiar with the name and<lb/>
work of a distinguished Austrian surgeon who has recently demonstrated<lb/>
in this country an operation for the cure of a rather rare deformity<lb/>
in children, only a small fraction of them know anything of Walter<lb/>
Reed, the conqueror of of the &ldquo;yellow plague.&rdquo; And yet distinguished<lb/>
men have not been silent in regard to him. Gen. Leonard Wood said,<lb/>
in a recent address at a memorial meeting of scientific men held in<lb/>
honor of his memory in Washington:</p>
<p>I know of no other man on this side of the world who has done so much for<lb/>
humanity as Dr. Reed. His discovery results in the saving of more lives annually<lb/>
___________________________________________________<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">a</hi> Not a single case of yellow fever occurred in Habana during the year 1902, nor,<lb/>
so far as known, in the island of Cuba.--J. R. K.<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="f02714022"/>
24<lb/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
than were lost in the Cuban war, and saves the commercial interests of the world a<lb/>
greater financial loss each year than the cost of the Cuban war. He came to Cuba at<lb/>
a time when one-third of the officers of my staff died of yellow fever, and we were<lb/>
discouraged at the failure of our efforts to control the disease. In the months when<lb/>
the disease was ordinarily worst the disease was checked and driven from Habana.<lb/>
That was the first time in nearly two hundred years that the city had been rid of it.<lb/>
The value of his discovery can not be appreciated by persons who are not familiar with<lb/>
the conditions of tropical countries. Hereafter it will never be possible for yellow<lb/>
fever to gain such headway that quarantine will exist from the mouth of the Poto-<lb/>
mac to the mouth of the Rio Grande. Future generations will appreciate fully the<lb/>
value of Dr. Reed's services. His was the originating, directing, and controlling<lb/>
mind in this work, and the others were assistants only.</p>
<p>In a letter dated November 24 General Wood said:</p>
<p>To Major Reed belongs the honor of having led in the greatest medical work of<lb/>
modern times, and the results he accomplished will live for all time.</p>
<p>Prof. William H. Welch, of Johns Hopkins, said in a letter to the<lb/>
Secretary of War:</p>
<p>Dr. Reed's researches in yellow fever are by far the most important contributions<lb/>
to science which have ever come from an army surgeon. In my judgment, they are<lb/>
the most valuable contributions to medicine and public hygiene which have ever<lb/>
been made in this country with the exception of the discovery of an&aelig;sthesia. They<lb/>
have led and will lead to the saving of untold thousands of lives. I am in a position<lb/>
to know that the credit for the original ideas embodied in this work belongs wholly<lb/>
to Major Reed. Such work, if done in Europe, would receive substantial recogni-<lb/>
tion from the Government.</p>
<p>He was last year given the degree of LL. D. by the University of<lb/>
Michigan and the degree of M. A. by Harvard University. In con-<lb/>
ferring, the language used by President Eliot was:</p>
<p><hi>Walter Reed, graduate of medicine of the University of Virginia, the army surgeon<lb/>
who planned and directed in Cuba the experiments which have given man control<lb/>
over that fearful scourge, yellow fever</hi>.</p>
<p>Precedents are abundant for State aid to public benefactors and their<lb/>
families. The English Government a century ago, when the purchas-<lb/>
ing value of money was far greater than at present, gave to Jenner,<lb/>
the discoverer of vaccination, grants amounting to &pound;30,000. He also<lb/>
received &pound;7,383 from a subscription in India.</p>
<p>Pasteur, the founder of the science of bacteriology, besides numer-<lb/>
ous honors and decorations and money donations from other sources,<lb/>
received from the French Government a pension of 12,000 francs.</p>
<p>Lister, the originator of antiseptic surgery, has, besides numerous<lb/>
honors and decorations, been successively knighted and elevated to the<lb/>
peerage.</p>
<p>In this country a bill to donate $100,000 to the discoverer of an&aelig;s-<lb/>
thesia was twice passed by the Senate (in 1853 and 1854), but failed in<lb/>
the House, probably because of the uncertainty as to which of the rival<lb/>
claimants was entitled to the credit of that discovery.</p>
<p>The resolutions of various scientific and professional societies are<lb/>
<pb n="23" id="f02714023"/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
25<lb/>
appended as an indication of the standing which Dr. Reed occupied in<lb/>
the scientific world at the time of his death.</p>
<p>The following editorial from a prominent medical journal, American<lb/>
Medicine, is also quoted on account of its pertinence to the question:</p>
<p>DUE REWARDS FOR SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS.</p>
<p>The recent death of Maj. Walter Reed directs attention to the self-sacrifice of the<lb/>
medical investigator and the inadequacy of the recognition which is attainable in<lb/>
America by these heroes of science. His demise deprives the country of a citizen<lb/>
whose public spirit, devotion to duty, and splendid achievements justly entitle him<lb/>
to an enduring testimonial. His scientific career, strictly speaking, began about<lb/>
1890, when, through the stimulating influence of his illustrious teacher, Dr. Welch,<lb/>
of Johns Hopkins, his interest was awakened in the intimate nature and underlying<lb/>
causes of disease, and he took up the special study of pathology and bacteriology.<lb/>
With rare native intelligence, indefatigable industry, high ideals, broad sympathies,<lb/>
and a personality that attracted all who came in contact with him, he soon distin-<lb/>
guished himself as a trustworthy, independent investigator, and entered upon a work<lb/>
that was to become a triumph for scientific medicine and a blessing to humanity.<lb/>
Notwithstanding his manifold duties as curator of the Army Medical Museum, Reed<lb/>
never lost his love for pure medical investigation, and was a frequent contributor to<lb/>
medical literature. Yet while his contributions in general to scientific medicine are<lb/>
uniformly as good as the best, they are insignificant when compared with the great<lb/>
work upon yellow fever with which his name will ever be inseparably associated.<lb/>
His was the master mind and he the guiding spirit in an investigation whereby mul-<lb/>
titudes of lives have been saved, a pestilential malady robbed of its mysteries and<lb/>
terrors, and an annual expenditure of millions of money shown to be in large part,<lb/>
if not entirely, needless. As has been said, his work &ldquo;means to the United States<lb/>
for the future a saving in life and treasure that is cheaply paid for by the whole cost<lb/>
of the Spanish-American war.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In other countries a man who had done such a work as Reed would at once receive<lb/>
office, honors, and financial security. In ours we leave him unrewarded, to work<lb/>
out his life, to die early, perhaps, and then we offer his family a sum as a pension<lb/>
small beyond ridicule. We appeal to Congress to demonstrate the nation's gratitude<lb/>
in this case. It should act promptly and in a manner commensurate with the mag-<lb/>
nificent public service rendered by our colleague. This, we are sure, is the wish of<lb/>
everyone conversant with what he has done.</p>
<p>RESOLUTIONS OF MEDICAL SOCIETIES AND LEARNED BODIES<lb/>
WITH REFERENCE TO MAJ. WALTER REED, SURGEON, U. S.<lb/>
ARMY.</p>
<p>At a stated meeting of the New York Academy of Medicine, held<lb/>
December 3, 1902, the following resolution was unanimously adopted:</p>
<p>Whereas in the recent death of Dr. Walter Reed, major and surgeon, U. S. Army,<lb/>
the science of medicine has lost the one whose brilliant research led first to the<lb/>
demonstration of the transmission of yellow fever by the mosquito, and later to the<lb/>
practical removal of the disease from a large part of Cuba and the prevention of its<lb/>
transmission to the shores of this country: Be it</p>
<p>Resolved, That the New York Academy of Medicine records its sense of the great-<lb/>
ness of the loss to science and to mankind and its sympathy with the friends and<lb/>
relatives of the deceased.</p>
<pb n="24" id="f02714024"/>
<p>26</p>
<p>THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.</p>
<p>IN MEMORY OF MAJOR REED.</p>
<p>The following minutes and resolutions were adopted at a special<lb/>
meeting of the faculty of the medical department of the Columbian<lb/>
University:</p>
<p>The sudden and unexpected demise of our esteemed friend and colleague, Maj.<lb/>
Walter Reed, U. S. Army, professor of bacteriology and pathology in the medical<lb/>
school of the Columbian University, is an event that brings to us the most acute<lb/>
regret and overwhelming sorrow.</p>
<p>Taken from us in the prime of manhood and in the zenith of his professional use-<lb/>
fulness, at a time when the medical profession and humanity at large were prepared<lb/>
to do him homage for his great work in demonstrating the method of exterminating<lb/>
yellow fever by protection from inoculating mosquitoes and by which that fatal<lb/>
disease has been abolished from some of its most malignant haunts--at a time, too,<lb/>
when his relations with the faculty and students of the Columbian University had<lb/>
become securely united by bonds of mutual affection and esteem--under these cir-<lb/>
cumstances it is with a most earnest and sincere feeling that we, the medical faculty<lb/>
of the Columbian University, hereby desire to express our unreserved admiration for<lb/>
the work, life, and character of Professor Reed, both as a physician, a teacher, a<lb/>
trusted friend, and a man of science. In testimony whereof, it is hereby</p>
<p>Resolved, That the foregoing note be recorded in the permanent archives of the<lb/>
faculty; that a copy of the same be given to the press for publication and also for-<lb/>
warded to the family of Dr. Reed as an evidence of our sympathy for them in their<lb/>
great sorrow.</p>
<p>Resolved, That, as a further mark of respect for our lamented colleague, the exercises<lb/>
of the medical school be suspended and that the students and faculty attend in a<lb/>
body his funeral obsequies.</p>
<p>DR. WALTER REED.</p>
<p>The following resolutions were adopted by the medical faculty of<lb/>
the University of Virginia December 8, 1902, and by them reported to<lb/>
the general faculty, which heartily concurred in this expression of<lb/>
regard for the memory of Dr. Reed, of admiration for his work, and<lb/>
of sympathy for his family:</p>
<p>The medical faculty of the University of Virginia have heard with deep sorrow<lb/>
of the death of Maj. Walter Reed, professor of bacteriology and pathology in the<lb/>
Army Medical School, and distinguished graduate of this medical department.</p>
<p>His masterly investigation of the causes of the outbreaks of typhoid fever in the<lb/>
U. S. Army during the Spanish-American war, and especially his work furnishing<lb/>
conclusive proof of the conveyance of yellow fever by the mosquito, entitle him to a<lb/>
preeminent place amongst scientists and sanitarians and will prove of inestimable<lb/>
service to mankind.</p>
<p>As an alumnus he was true and loyal, manifesting on every appropriate occasion<lb/>
his continued interest in the university, upon which he has reflected great credit.</p>
<p>In testimony of our high appreciation of his character and achievements it is<lb/>
hereby</p>
<p>Resolved, That the foregoing note be spread upon our minutes and a copy be for-<lb/>
warded to the family of Dr. Reed as an evidence of our sympathy for them in their<lb/>
great sorrow.</p>
<p>RESOLUTIONS OF THE AMERICAN ASSOCIATION FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE.</p>
<p>Resolved, That the American Association for the Advancement of Science hereby<lb/>
records its sense of the great loss sustained by science in the death of Maj. Walter<lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f02714025"/>
THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.<lb/>
27<lb/>
Reed, surgeon in the U. S. Army, and its appreciation of the far-reaching and invalu-<lb/>
able services which he has rendered to humanity. By solving the problem of the<lb/>
mode of spread of yellow fever, Major Reed not only made a great contribution to<lb/>
science, but at the same time conferred inestimable benefits upon his country and<lb/>
upon mankind. To have discovered and demonstrated the methods, which have<lb/>
already been successfully tested in Cuba, of eradicating a widespread and terrible<lb/>
pestilence, is a benefaction of imperishable renown, of incalculable value in the sav-<lb/>
ing of human lives, of vast importance to commercial interests, and deserving the<lb/>
highest rewards in the power of his countrymen to bestow. This association earn-<lb/>
estly urges upon the attention of Congress the duty of making full provision for the<lb/>
support of his family.</p>
<p>Resolved, That the President designate a committee of nine members of this associ-<lb/>
ation, with power to increase its number, which shall be authorized and requested<lb/>
to devise and carry out a plan or aid in similar efforts elsewhere instituted, by which<lb/>
a suitable and permanent memorial of this great benefactor of his race may be<lb/>
secured. This committee shall be authorized to prepare and publish a statement of<lb/>
the services of the late Major Reed in discovering the mode by which yellow fever<lb/>
may be exterminated.</p>
<p>IN MEMORIAM--DR. WALTER REED, MAJOR AND SURGEON, U. S. ARMY.</p>
<p>Whereas the Medical Society of the District of Columbia has sustained an irre-<lb/>
trievable loss by the death of Walter Reed, who died at 2 a. m. November 23, 1902,<lb/>
from appendicitis, for which an operation was performed five days before: Be it</p>
<p>Resolved, That in the death of Dr. Reed the Medical Society has lost one of its<lb/>
most distinguished members whose best efforts were always at their disposal, and<lb/>
upon whom they had learned to rely as an able, calm, and accurate exponent of<lb/>
scientific medicine.</p>
<p>Major Reed was born in Gloucester County, Va., September 13, 1851, and was a<lb/>
graduate of the medical department of the University of Virginia, 1869, and Bellevue<lb/>
Hospital Medical College, 1872. He was appointed assistant surgeon, U. S. Army,<lb/>
June 26, 1875, promoted assistant surgeon with the rank of captain, June 26, 1880,<lb/>
surgeon with rank of major, December 4, 1893, and at the time of his death was first<lb/>
on the list of majors in the Medical Department.</p>
<p>He served with distinction as medical officer at various army posts in the &ldquo;far<lb/>
West,&rdquo; and as his skill and devotion extended to both officers and enlisted men alike,<lb/>
he endeared himself to all classes in the command.</p>
<p>During his service at Fort McHenry, Md., in 1881, and again while attending<lb/>
surgeon and examiner of recruits at Baltimore, from October, 1890, to October, 1891,<lb/>
he made special studies in bacteriology and pathology at the Johns Hopkins Hos-<lb/>
pital, and after a tour of service at Fort Snelling and St. Paul, he was selected by the<lb/>
Surgeon-General, in August, 1893, as curator of the Army Medical Museum, where<lb/>
he continued his studies which ultimately secured for him fame and distinction.</p>
<p>During the Spanish-American war he was president of the board of medical officers<lb/>
to investigate and report on the prevalence of typhoid fever in the Army, and the<lb/>
commission, strongly impressed with the agency of flies as carriers of this disease,<lb/>
recommended the collection of excreta in galvanized-iron tanks, which method was<lb/>
adopted and followed by a cessation of the disease.</p>
<p>His greatest achievement for science and humanity was his contribution to the<lb/>
cause, spread, and prevention of yellow fever. Starting from Finlay's theory of the<lb/>
agency of the mosquito in the dissemination of this disease, the commission of which<lb/>
Dr. Reed was the head made a series of painstaking experiments and demonstrated<lb/>
conclusively the causal relation of Stegomya fasciata to yellow-fever epidemics and<lb/>
disproved the theory that the disease could be conveyed by fomites, or that it was<lb/>
contagious in the ordinary acceptation of the term.</p>
<pb n="26" id="f02714026"/>
<p>28</p>
<p>THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.</p>
<p>The practical value of this discovery, which in point of importance and far-reaching<lb/>
beneficence ranks only second with Jenner's discovery of vaccination, has been<lb/>
proved by the complete eradication of this scourge from Habana.</p>
<p>Major Reed has demonstrated how to rid the world of yellow fever, but his studies<lb/>
as to the etiology of the disease were interrupted by his untimely death. He had,<lb/>
however, arrived at the conclusion that the disease was not due to Sanarelli's Bacillus<lb/>
icteroides, but was probably caused by some ultramicroscopic organism. Dr. Reed<lb/>
was a clear, forceful writer and speaker; all of his facts were collected with the<lb/>
utmost care and presented in a concise, logical, and convincing manner, and his<lb/>
crowning work shows the highest degree of scientific accuracy combined with calm<lb/>
judgment and discrimination, qualities which are not only of the utmost importance<lb/>
in the search of causes of epidemic diseases and tracing their progress, but which<lb/>
would have also fitted him for the highest position in his corps.</p>
<p>In every sphere of activity, whether as a medical officer, author, teacher, or inves-<lb/>
tigator, he has acquired a distinction which rightly places him in the first rank of<lb/>
illustrious American physicians. His labors in behalf of science and humanity have<lb/>
been recognized by Harvard, Ann Arbor, and the American Medical Association,<lb/>
and he has borne his honors with accustomed modesty and innate dignity. Dr. Reed<lb/>
was singularly clear from all mean self-interest and ambition, and was ever ready to<lb/>
give full credit to his colleagues for their share of the work which made him famous.<lb/>
We have simply to recall his glowing tribute to that brave young soldier, Kissinger,<lb/>
from Ohio, who on December 5, 1900, was the first to volunteer to be bitten by<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, with the only proviso that he should receive no pecuniary<lb/>
reward, since, as he expressed it, he was actuated &ldquo;solely in the interest of humanity<lb/>
and the cause of science.&rdquo; Such exhibition of moral courage, in the opinion of Dr.<lb/>
Reed, has never been surpassed in the annals of the Army of the United States,<lb/>
and we will add could never have been inspired except by a man of Dr. Reed's<lb/>
greatness.</p>
<p>His lips are silent; no longer will the sound of his musical but decisive voice be<lb/>
heard within these halls, nor his personal magnetism and discerning mind delight,<lb/>
instruct, and charm his listeners, but his deeds will live and his example will be an<lb/>
inspiration to present and future generations.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed's death in the prime of life, in the zenith of his distinguished career, is<lb/>
a severe blow to scientific medicine, his corps, and the medical profession which he<lb/>
adorned. The society, while expressing the sincerest grief at the loss of our dis-<lb/>
tinguished associate, whose personal qualities commanded our highest friendship and<lb/>
respect, is not undmindful of the irreparable loss sustained by his beloved family, to<lb/>
whom we beg to offer our heartfelt sympathy in the hour of their great affliction,<lb/>
united with the fervent hope that a grateful nation will recognize the economic value<lb/>
of Dr. Reed's discovery and make adequate provision for those who were dependent<lb/>
upon him for support.</p>
<p>GEORGE M. KOBER,<lb/>
D. K. SHUTE,<lb/>
FRANCIS S. NASH,<lb/>
Committee.</p>
<p>Your committee recommends, on account of Dr. Reed's distinguished achievements<lb/>
and as a further evidence of respect, that a special memorial meeting be held Decem-<lb/>
ber 31, with the following programme:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Introductory address, by the president of the society, Dr. S. S. Adams.</item>
<item>Biographical sketch, Dr. Robert A. Marmion, of the U. S. Navy.</item>
<item>Dr. Reed as a medical officer, Dr. J. R. Kean, of the U. S. Army.</item>
<item>Dr. Reed as a teacher, Dr. A. F. A. King.</item>
<item>Dr. Reed as an author, Prof. C. W. Stiles, of the Public Health and Marine-<lb/>
Hospital Service.</item>
<pb n="27" id="f02714027"/>
<item>THE LATE MAJ. WALTER REED.</item>
<item>29</item>
<item>Dr. Reed's work in Cuba, Gen. Leonard Wood.</item>
<item>Dr. Reed as a scientist and benefactor to humanity, Dr. William H. Welch.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The following resolution was adopted at the meeting of the Ameri-<lb/>
can Medical Association at Saratoga, N. Y., on June 11, 1902:</p>
<p>Whereas the members of the American Medical Association believe that the<lb/>
recent work of the U. S. Army surgeons in Cuba in relation to the discovery of the<lb/>
method of transmission of yellow fever is of such magnitude and far-reaching benefi-<lb/>
cence as to rank only second with Jenner's discovery of vaccination; and</p>
<p>Whereas the practical value of this discovery has been proven by the complete<lb/>
eradication of this scourge from Habana:</p>
<p>Resolved, That the thanks of this association be tendered the gentlemen who<lb/>
accomplished this brilliant result, and particularly to Drs. Walter Reed, James<lb/>
Carroll, A. Agramonte, W. O. Gorgas, and to Leonard Wood, who recognized the<lb/>
importance of the work and made it possible by his hearty encouragement and<lb/>
assistance.</p>
<p>Resolved, That this association, while deeply deploring the death of Dr. Jesse A.<lb/>
Lazear, who died a martyr to science, admires and gratefully acknowledges the<lb/>
heroic devotion of this physician and some of the members of the Hospital Corps to<lb/>
the cause of humanity.</p>
<p>Resolved, That these resolutions be published in The Journal, and that copies be<lb/>
transmitted to Drs. Reed, Carroll, Agramonte, Wood, Gorgas, and Mrs. Lazear.</p>
<p>RESOLUTIONS TAKEN BY THE INTERNATIONAL CONGRESS OF<lb/>
MEDICINE AT CAIRO, EGYPT, DECEMBER 22, 1902.</p>
<p>Les membres du Premier Congres de Medecine en Egypte apprennant avec le plus<lb/>
profond regret la mort prematur&eacute;e du Maj. Walter Reed du Corps Medical de l'Arm&eacute;e<lb/>
des Etats Unis d'Amerique.</p>
<p>La part brillante et importante qu'il a pris dans la d&eacute;couverte du moustique<lb/>
st&eacute;gomyia comme le seul agent transmitteur du parasite de la fi&egrave;vre jaune, r&eacute;ussessant<lb/>
ainsi a mettre les ravages de cette terrible maladie sous le controle des hygienistes<lb/>
fait de sa mort une perte cruelle pour l'humanit&eacute;.</p>
<p>Le Congr&egrave;s decide en consequence d'exprimer a cette occasion toute sa sympathie<lb/>
au Corps Medical de l'Arm&eacute;e des Etats Unis ainsi qu'a la famille du Major Reed.</p>
<p>Le Congr&egrave;s decide en outre de prier le secretaire du Congres d'envoyer officielle-<lb/>
ment par l'entremise des Autorit&eacute;s comp&eacute;tentes une copie de la presente r&eacute;solution<lb/>
au Chirurgien en Chef de l'Arm&eacute;e des Etats Unis d'Amerique et une autre &eacute;galment<lb/>
a Madame Veuve Reed.</p>
<p>Similar resolutions have been passed by numerous other scientific<lb/>
bodies. They are not given here because it is not desired unduly to<lb/>
lengthen this report.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
