<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02736001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Recollections of Lena A. Warner, December 7, 1904</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02736001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1904-12-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Maury, R.B.</name>
<name type="person">Mitchell, R.W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Grenada (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Tennessee</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Mantanzas (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1904-12-07">December 7, 1904</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02736001</idno>
<title>Recollections of Lena A. Warner, December 7, 1904</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Warner writes about the unreported side of the yellow fever epidemic, including her own experiences during an 1878 outbreak in her hometown.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="Recollection" n="1904-12-07">
<head>Recollections of Lena A. Warner, December 7, 1904</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02736001"/>
<opener>
Received<lb/>
Dec. 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1904.<lb/>
<lb/>
Written by <unclear>Mrs</unclear> Lena A. Warner<lb/>
Kelly quotes much of this<lb/>
in his book p <unclear>227</unclear><lb/>
</opener>
<p>From date of the lecture I heard on Yellow Fever, de-<lb/>
livered by Drs. R. B. Maury and R. W. Mitchell, I was possessed of<lb/>
a great desire to come a second time in contact with this disease,<lb/>
as my first knowledge of sorrow came to me through this terrible<lb/>
scourge in 1876, in the town of Grenada, Miss. a place of 3000 in-<lb/>
habitants.</p>
<p>History records this epidemic as the most terrible death<lb/>
rate known. In my own family eight members were stricken, and myself<lb/>
and a child of nine years were the only one to recover. I can re-<lb/>
call very distinctly the terribly ordeal we had to undergo; while<lb/>
many noble men and women sacrificed their lives in response to the<lb/>
helplessness of these unfortunate people. They came from all sec-<lb/>
tions of the country, and as every occasion of this kind is burdened<lb/>
with human, beasts of prey - robbing, pilfering the living, dying and<lb/>
dead, so was this plague stricken little city. Men sent there by<lb/>
the Howard Benevolent Association, who represented themselves as nurses,<lb/>
were among the worst. My own Father, while ill with the fever, was<lb/>
choked, robbed and left alone to die: I was too ill <del>to</del> even to cry<lb/>
out for help, but witnessed the entire affair. It was twenty hours<lb/>
before we were found in this condition.</p>
<p>Burning tar, bonfires and disinfectants of various kinds<lb/>
were placed on the corners of the streets, and yet, that peculiar o--<lb/>
dor from Yellow Fever could be detected from every direction.</p>
<p>The only signs of traffic, were wagons hauling the dead;<lb/>
few caskets were seen and in their stead plain boxes, and sometimes<lb/>
dry goods boxes were utilized: they were piled one on top of the other<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02736002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
and fastened with ropes to the bed of the wagons. Negroes were se-<lb/>
cured for this work; they were known to rob the dead and vacant res-<lb/>
idences. The following winter several visits were made to the cabins,<lb/>
where clothing, silver and other valuables were found. On one occa-<lb/>
sion like this, I was called by the town Marshall to identify some<lb/>
things supposed to have been taken from our house; while looking<lb/>
down on a crowd of negroes, I called the Marshall's attention to a<lb/>
negro man wearing my father's hat: he proved to be <del>the</del><add>a</add> minister and<lb/>
we found a wagon load of various articles at his house. The negro's<lb/>
work as grave diggers proved to be very poor, as sixteen inches was<lb/>
afterwards found to be the depth of any grave made during that time.</p>
<p>In 1897, we had a few scattered cases of the fever<lb/>
in Mississippi and Tennessee: I was <del>then</del> in the Delta, where I learn-<lb/>
ed that Memphis was in quarantine against Mississippi, and vice versa<lb/>
Mississippi was quarantined against Memphis: at the telegraph office<lb/>
I learned that a freight train from New Orleans, bound for Memphis,<lb/>
would take water about five A. M. and that it would be the last train<lb/>
allowed to stop: I at once planned a trip to Memphis, and<lb/>
when the train came, <add>began</add> climbing up on the engine and holding a ten<lb/>
dollar bill before the engineer, I managed to seat myself near<lb/>
him. I will not go into the details of this most unsafisfactory<lb/>
trip, except to say that everytime we attempted to make a stop at<lb/>
any place for water, that men would mysteriously make their appearance<lb/>
with the biggest shot-guns I had ever seen. About dark the engineer<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02736003"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
began to argue that I could not get into Memphis, as I would certainly<lb/>
be seen on the engine. We were at a small place called Lakeview, a<lb/>
about ten miles from Memphis, it seemed fifty to me: I persuaded him<lb/>
to put me in a box car, which was partially loaded with barrels, and as<lb/>
they were constantly rolling I was compelled to stand all the way to<lb/>
Memphis. I asked the engineer to telephone my brother as soon as he<lb/>
reached Memphis where he could find me.</p>
<p>On reaching Memphis, I was rewarded by getting to see nine<lb/>
cases of the fever with Dr. R. W. Mitchell.</p>
<p>In 1898, at the City Hospital I saw three cases of fever: one<lb/>
a tramp and he told me that he left his partner nearly dead in a country<lb/>
church at Phillips, Miss. affected just as he was - that was every sympton<lb/>
of yellow fever: the next day I read in a paper where a church near Phil-<lb/>
lips, Miss. had been burned because of a tramp dying with yellow fever,<lb/>
and no one would bury him: this case and two others were diagnosed as<lb/>
Malarial Hematuria.</p>
<p>When our Government called for volunteer nurses to go to Cuba,<lb/>
I availed myself of this opportunity.</p>
<p>During August, 1900 I was ordered from Matanzas to Havana.<lb/>
The night before my transfer to Havana, I was entertained at the quarters<lb/>
of the officers of the 2nd Cavalry station<add>ed</add> at Matanzas: there I met a Ma-<lb/>
jor Cartwright, who informed me that he also had been ordered to Havana,<lb/>
as he was an immune, had had the fever in '98 at Santiago. Two weeks af-<lb/>
ter my arrival in yellow fever camps, the ambulance brought a patient from<lb/>
Gen Lee's headquarters: as I stepped forward to give directions in<lb/>
regard to the patient I recognized Major Cartwright:</p>
<pb n="4" id="f02736004"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p><del><unclear>th</unclear></del> after some conversation, he stated that he could not<lb/>
possible have yellow fever, as he certainly had a genuine case in '98.<lb/>
However, on the six<add>th</add> day after his arrival he died of black vomit.</p>
<p>Major Peterson also thought that he had had the fever,<lb/>
but he was taken ill again with it, and his wife hearing of his ill-<lb/>
ness two hours after his death, committed suicide by shooting her-<lb/>
self through the temple in our quarters at Las Animas. The waiter<lb/>
being an eye witness to this dreadful tragedy.</p>
<p>The only nurse with me that had yellow fever, was one<lb/>
who claimed to be an immune: she <add>was</add> sent to Major Edmund's residence at<lb/>
Quemados, the night before his death, she returned to the camp and<lb/>
four days after was taken with a mild case, (we had no mosquitoes in<lb/>
our camp.)</p>
<p>Quarentien was very strict, but we continued to have<lb/>
yellow fever among the soldiers and officers: we were poorly equip-<lb/>
ped at Columbia Barracks Detention Camp and yet the mortality was<lb/>
not as great as in this Country. A few officers and privates from<lb/>
the Palace in Havana were taken to Las Animas, a Cuban Hospital for<lb/>
civilians under Major Gorgas supervision; he called on our chief<lb/>
Surgeon for help: I was ordered there for ten days: at this place<lb/>
they were well equipped, the nurses being well cared for as well as<lb/>
the patients. We lost that week Major Peterson, Captain Page, the<lb/>
Quarter Master Sargent, one soldier, one civilians employee. Major<lb/>
Gorgas was very successful in the treatment of the fever, and upon<lb/>
my return to Camp Columbia, I determined to imitate his directions.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f02736005"/>
<p>- 5 -</p>
<p>In September I nursed Dr. James A. Carroll, a member of Major<lb/>
Reed's Staff of Commissioners, and he told he me that he experiment-<lb/>
ed upon himself with the mosquito: while he had a severe case he<lb/>
did not have hemorrhages: even to the whites of his eyes were as<lb/>
yellow as saffron. A few days after Dr. Carroll's chill, Dr. Jessie<lb/>
Lazear was stricken with the fever: he also was a member of this board<lb/>
and brought on a litter to our <hi>Camp about eleven A.M.</hi> he knew what his<lb/>
illness was, and informed me that he had his chill about six P. M.<lb/>
<hi>had not been in bed all night</hi>, as he was busy writing up on their<lb/>
experiments in regard to yellow fever and the mosquito. His temperature<lb/>
was 103, pulse 80: he lived five days: the black vomit would spurt<lb/>
from his mouth up through the bar over his cot. I had just relieved<lb/>
the day nurse and gone on for the night: my efforts to keep him in<lb/>
bed failed and I called for help, but before assistance reached me<lb/>
we had made several turns around the room in his efforts to get out.<lb/>
All night it took two men to hold him, and he <hi>died the next morning</hi>.</p>
<p>Mrs Warner<lb/>
erred here.<lb/>
Lazear died<lb/>
at 8<hi rend="superscript">45</hi> <hi>PM</hi><lb/>
P.S.H</p>
<p>In December I met Major Reed, and it was at this time<lb/>
that they began in earnest to erect buildings for the special exper-<lb/>
iments to prove that the mosquito was the only source of infection.</p>
<p>Major Reed was an officer whom we were all devoted to: he<lb/>
liked best to be called &ldquo;Doctor&rdquo;, I was always glad on my daily vis-<lb/>
its to Labratory, to catch him there: he had won the friendship and<lb/>
esteem of the entire corps, having the most genial manners and so<lb/>
considerate and kind to every one. I do not feel that I could speak<lb/>
in too high terms of Major Reed. At all times he was so willing to<lb/>
go into detail with <add>any part of</add> the experiment I did not comprehend, and was<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02736006"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
patient enough to give me a peep through the different microscopes and<lb/>
give a full explanation. I told him of our '78 epidemic and he in-<lb/>
formed me that S. <add>Surg</add> Gen. Sternberg was in Memphis at that time. The<lb/>
experimental camp was called after Dr. Lazear: in a statement I heard<lb/>
Major Reed make he said that Dr. Lazear's efforts in this work had<lb/>
been of vast importance. Major Reed was strong in his friendships<lb/>
as Dr. Jas A. Carroll can readily testify. I recall an incident which<lb/>
gives an insight into the kind of man he was - On one occasion he moved<lb/>
his mess quarters because he heard his brother officer use language<lb/>
at the table which was very ungentlemanly. It was due to his inde-<lb/>
fatigable efforts that we owe our success with yellow fever at Camp<lb/>
Lazear., as we never lost a case experimented upon.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Lena A. Warner.<lb/>
Ex. Chief Nurse, U. S. A. N. C.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="letter" n="1904-12-07">
<head>Letter from R.B.M. to Dear D.</head>
<pb n="7" id="f02736007"/>
<opener>
<unclear>Ac</unclear><lb/>
Va<lb/>
<dateline>
Memphis<lb/>
<date value="1904-12-07">Dec 7. 04</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>,</salute>
</opener>
<p>This is a truthful<lb/>
narration of facts, which<lb/>
are witnessed in almost<lb/>
every locality which may<lb/>
be visited by Y. Fever.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yrs &amp; c</salute>
<signed><hi>R.B.M</hi></signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

