<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02748001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter with memorandum from William Crawford Gorgas to Charles A.L. Reed, February 17, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Gorgas, William Crawford</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02748001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-02-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Charles A.L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Ross, John W.</name>
<name type="person">LaGarde, Louis L.</name>
<name type="place">Canal Zone (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Panama City (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-02-17">February 17, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02748001</idno>
<title>Letter with memorandum from William Crawford Gorgas to Charles A.L. Reed, February 17, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gorgas writes to Reed concerning the organization of the Canal Zone Sanitary Department, and details problems in its function. Memorandum details the problems in the Panama Canal.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-02-17">
<head>Letter with memorandum from William Crawford Gorgas to Charles A.L. Reed, February 17, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02748001"/>
<opener>
Memorandum<lb/>
of Col WC Gorgas<lb/>
<unclear>Ch. San.</unclear> Officer<lb/>
<dateline>
Ancon, Isthmian Canal Zone,<lb/>
<date value="1905-02-17">February 17, 1905.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Reed<lb/>
(Dr. C.A.L. Reed of Cincinnati)<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just read the recommendations of the Secretary<lb/>
of War before the Senate Committee, and this gives me a pretty good<lb/>
idea of the character of general organization the Secretary would<lb/>
like to have in Panam&aacute;.</p>
<p>As I understand the Secretary's scheme, it is: that<lb/>
Congress authorize the President to construct the canal, through<lb/>
the Commission,- as a body or individually as he thinks best.<lb/>
That the construction of the canal be placed under the Secretary<lb/>
of War; that an Executive body of three be established on the<lb/>
Isthmus, to consist of the Chief Engineer, the Governor and one<lb/>
other member; that the rest of the Commission be merely advisory.<lb/>
This, for the execution of sanitary work, I can see would be a<lb/>
great improvement over the present arrangement. But my idea would<lb/>
be under this organization, that the Chief Sanitary Officer report<lb/>
directly to the Secretary of War as the highest authority. The<lb/>
Sanitary Department would have no representation on this governing<lb/>
body; and while the Chief Sanitary Officer would be in contact with<lb/>
them and would be able to urge his views personally, there would<lb/>
still be many objections to this form of organization, of much the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02748002"/>
2<lb/>
the same character as exist under the present Commission. That<lb/>
there would be no one on this board who had any special knowledge<lb/>
of sanitary matters. But where the Sanitary Officer reported di-<lb/>
rectly to this board or to the Secretary, I think the other points<lb/>
named in the memoranda just given you, are equally important. If<lb/>
the Sanitary Officer reports to this body he should not do so as a<lb/>
subordinate to the Governor or any other department, but directly,<lb/>
as do now the Chief Engineer, the Chief of Material &amp; Supplies and<lb/>
the Disbursing Officer. The department should have its own chief<lb/>
of material &amp; supplies, who should report direct to the Chief Sani-<lb/>
tary Officer and be under his orders; should have its own construct-<lb/>
ing officer, who should also report direct to the Chief Sanitary<lb/>
Officer and be under his control; and should have its own disburs-<lb/>
ing officer, who should bear the same relation to the Chief Sanitary<lb/>
Officer as the others.</p>
<p>The whole object of the organization is to enable the<lb/>
Sanitary Department rapidly to organize, to get its supplies prompt-<lb/>
ly, to get its constructing done promptly and to have its payments<lb/>
made promptly. The experience of the past nine months shows that<lb/>
this could not be accomplished under the present organization, no<lb/>
matter what efforts and pressure were brought to bear; and it seems<lb/>
to me that there will always be this difficulty as long as the Sani-<lb/>
tary Department has to have the details of its work carried on<lb/>
through the other departments. The wants of the Sanitary Depart-<lb/>
ment are small as compared with the great work going on. It is<lb/>
natural that an ounce of quinine is not very important in the eyes<lb/>
of the Chief of Material &amp; Supplies, as compared with a steam dredge;<lb/>
and the ounce of quinine will be overlooked and the steam dredge<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02748003"/>
3<lb/>
attended to if the work is pressing. And this will be the case all<lb/>
through. If the Sanitary Department has to depend for its executive<lb/>
work upon the other departments, I believe this executive work will<lb/>
always be slow and done under great difficulties. This was our<lb/>
experience in Cuba after over two years of trial; and we finally<lb/>
adopted a general plan, as described above, as the only means of<lb/>
getting our work done effectively.</p>
<closer>
<signed>W. C. Gorgas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1905-02-17">
<head>MEMORANDUM FOR DR REED.</head>
<pb n="4" id="f02748004"/>
<p>Certain serious defects in the Sanitary Organization at present are<lb/>
due to the fact that the Commission originally adopted no general plan covering<lb/>
the whole ground. I proposed to them an organization, which, in my opinion,<lb/>
covered the whole ground in April, 1904: my idea under this plan being to get the<lb/>
department thoroughly organized in, any half a year, and within a year from that<lb/>
time, eighteen months from the date of my appointment, to have the towns of<lb/>
Panama and Colon and the strip between them in a good sanitary condition in every<lb/>
respect. This scheme was considered at their meeting May 8th, 1904, and action<lb/>
was taken as shown by the within quotation, found on page 44. Proceedings, Isthmian<lb/>
Canal Commission, March to September, 1904.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Chairman submitted a report on the sanitation of the Canal<lb/>
Zone and Panama and Colon by Drs. Gorgas, Ross and LaGarde, accompanied by<lb/>
a report to Dr Gorgas by Captain Gillette, of the Engineer Corps, U. S. A.,<lb/>
relating to the condition of hospital buildings and kindred matters.</p>
<p>The general outline for a scheme of sanitation for the Canal<lb/>
Zone, submitted by Colonel W. C. Gorgas, U.S.A.; Medical Director, John W.<lb/>
Ross, U.S.N., and Major Louis A. LaGarde, U.S.A.; was considered and the follow-<lb/>
ing action was taken:</p>
<p>The Chief Sanitary Officer and the Director of Hospitals, in<lb/>
addition to other duties, were designated as the Health Board for Colon and<lb/>
Panama, as well as of the Canal Zone, in lieu of the independent health boards<lb/>
provided for in the scheme of sanitation.</p>
<p>The Chief Sanitary Officer was authorized to proceed with the<lb/>
cleaning, disinfecting and collecting of garbage and nightsoil in Colon and<lb/>
Panama, and to employ staffs for these purposes as may be necessary from time<lb/>
to time, whose wages are to be fixed by the Commission before employment; to<lb/>
make requisition for carts, mules, garbage cans, and so forth, as needed. He<lb/>
was authorized to have plans prepared for a 100-bed hospital, and to employ<lb/>
a physician to take charge of the Colon Hospital and act as sanitary officer,<lb/>
at a salary of $250. per month, if taken from civil life, and to employ what<lb/>
other staff may be necessary from time to time, whose rates of pay will be<lb/>
fixed by the Commission before employment.</p>
<p>The matter of quarantine stations at Colon and Panama was referred<lb/>
back to Colonel Gorgas for further consideration and recommendation.</p>
<p>The employment of a sanitary officer for the Canal Zone, from Colon<lb/>
to Panama, at a salary not exceeding $350. per month if taken from civil life,<lb/>
one clerk at $125. per month, two clerks at $100. per month, two sanitary<lb/>
officers at $100. per month, and other sanitary officers at $50. per month was<lb/>
authorized, such employment to begin from time to time as needed.</p>
<p>A pathologist and clinician for the General Hospital at Ancon Hill<lb/>
at a salary of $333.33 per month was authorized. Also other staff for this<lb/>
hospital as needed from time to time, their pay to be fixed by the Commission<lb/>
before employment.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02748005"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
Staffs for Director of Hospital and Chief Sanitary Officer were also<lb/>
authorized, to be employed as needed from time to time, their salaries<lb/>
to be fixed by the Commission before employment.</p>
<p>The wages of foremen, laborers and other subordinates of like<lb/>
class employed from time to time as needed and not fixed by the<lb/>
Commission, shall be temporarily fixed by the representative of the<lb/>
Commission on the Isthmus.</p>
<p>Action on the matter of taking charge of the City Hospital<lb/>
and Poor House in Panama, Convalescent Hospital at Taboga Island and<lb/>
immigration stations in Panama and Colon was deferred</p>
<p>It was decided that all disbursements should be made through the<lb/>
Disbursing Officer of the Commission, and all purchases should be made by the<lb/>
Purchasing Agent of the Commission, and <hi>independent disbursing officer and<lb/>
purchasing agent</hi> were not allowed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This shows what a very limited Sanitary Department was at that time<lb/>
contemplated by the Commission.</p>
<p>At the direction of the Commission, after I had been on the Isthmus<lb/>
about six weeks and started such organization as had so far been authorized,<lb/>
I again submitted a scheme upon which they noted at their meeting of August 28th.<lb/>
Proceedings will be found on Page 159.</p>
<p>This scheme adopted by them was excellent in many respects and liberal<lb/>
as far as appropriation went, but it left out very important matters, such as<lb/>
the disposal of nightsoil along the Zone and making no provision for the health<lb/>
departments of Panama and Colon and many minor details. But the greatest defect<lb/>
in the organization has been that, we have been entirely unable to carry out many<lb/>
of the provisions made in this scheme. The Supply Department not having been<lb/>
entirely organized, we have been unable to get a great part of our supplies through<lb/>
them. None of the large requisitions made back in July, August and September<lb/>
have <del>not</del> yet been filled, and the same has been the case in regard to<lb/>
construction and repair. We had to do this through another department. Repairs<lb/>
and construction asked for in July remain still unfinished. I think the fact<lb/>
that so incomplete a scheme was adopted in the beginning was due a good deal to<lb/>
the personnel of the Commission. None of the gentlemen deciding this matter<lb/>
had any special sanitary or medical knowledge. It is true that I had a good<lb/>
opportunity of presenting my views and arguments beforehand, but, beyond this<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02748006"/>
-3-<lb/>
sanitation had no representation in their counsels.</p>
<p>After the scheme had been adopted I was removed still further from them,<lb/>
having to communicate with them subject to the control of the Board of Health and<lb/>
through the Governor. At present I am merely sanitary adviser of the Governor,<lb/>
he making recommendation on sanitary matters to the Commission.</p>
<p>With regard to the difficulty in getting supplies and construction<lb/>
work done, I think they are inherit in the organization, and I do not believe<lb/>
the work can ever be carried out promptly under the present plan. I stated this<lb/>
to the Commission at the time of their adoption, pointing out that from my past<lb/>
experience in these matters, I believe supplies for our department could not<lb/>
be obtained in this way, <del><unclear></unclear></del> that construction could not be done in this way,<lb/>
that I would necessarily be hold back until these departments were organized and<lb/>
that other interests would be so great that the smaller demands of my department<lb/>
in these respects would be overlooked. This has been the case to an eminent<lb/>
degree.</p>
<p>The functions of the Sanitary Department here are peculiar. Our<lb/>
reason d' etre is to aid in the construction of the Canal. In this respect we<lb/>
principally come in contact with the laborers of the Engineer Department and<lb/>
probably have more extensive and intimate relations with the Chief of Engineers<lb/>
than with any other official.</p>
<p>As to having charge of the health of the towns of Panama and Colon, we<lb/>
derive our authority exclusively from the Panamaian Government, and as far as<lb/>
authority goes in this respect we are entirely outside of the jurisdiction<lb/>
of the Commission. Along the Zone and as far as any sanitary control of the<lb/>
villages is concerned, we come in contact with the Zone Government. I think,<lb/>
therefore, the Chief Sanitary Officer should report directly to the supreme authority,<lb/>
as do the Chief of Engineers, Chief of Material and Supplies and the Paymaster.</p>
<p>At present we are subordinate, having no direct contact with the Chief<lb/>
Engineer or with the Commission.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f02748007"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>The schemes I formerly submitted to the Commission in April and<lb/>
September were based upon the organization under similar circumstances, which<lb/>
were slowly evolved at Havana, after three years experience, in almost exactly<lb/>
similar work, and this in rough would be my outline.</p>
<p>That the Chief Sanitary Officer should report direct to the supreme<lb/>
authority: that the present scheme for the sanitation of the Zone should be acted<lb/>
upon by this supreme authority and that in considering these matters the supreme<lb/>
authority should have some person of special knowledge in these matters with whom<lb/>
he could consult. If the supreme authority were the Secretary of War, I should<lb/>
think he might call upon the Surgeon General of the Army for recommendation; or,<lb/>
if the supreme authority were the Commission, it might do the same. That such<lb/>
portions of this scheme as finally seem good should be adopted and the Chief<lb/>
Sanitary Officer be directed to make a detailed estimate under this scheme for<lb/>
one year; that for each month he put in an estimate for funds needed for that month<lb/>
a sufficient length of time ahead for the supreme authority to act upon; that the<lb/>
sum allowed by the proper authority be placed to the credit of the Disbursing<lb/>
Officer of the Sanitary Department and disbursed by him, under the orders of the<lb/>
Chief Sanitary Officer, with just the same safe-guards and regulations as apply<lb/>
to any other disbursing officer of the Government; that a Construction Officer be<lb/>
appointed who would be also under the orders of the Chief Sanitary Officer. This<lb/>
would enable him to get his supplies expeditiously and have his building and<lb/>
repairing done rapidly, and, if the scheme were not carried out satisfactorily<lb/>
the Chief Sanitary Officer would alone be responsible and could justly be held<lb/>
accountable. Of course, if I had some idea of the form of organization<lb/>
contemplated by the Secretary of War, I could fit in my scheme more in detail and,<lb/>
if I remain in charge of health matters on the Isthmus I would like very much<lb/>
to lay my scheme of organization before the Secretary of War in person. I think<lb/>
my experience both in Cuba and in Panama would enable me to make many suggestions<lb/>
<unclear>that would</unclear> be useful before a final plan is settled upon</p>
<pb n="8" id="f02748008"/>
<p>Col. W. C. Gorgas<lb/>
<unclear>Nueve</unclear> for Dr. C.A.L.<lb/>
Reed of Cincinnati, <unclear>Q.</unclear></p>
<p>Feb. 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1905-</p>
<p>He was sent to the Canal<lb/>
Zone to inspect and<lb/>
report as to the <unclear>work</unclear><lb/>
of the Sanitary Dept.</p>
<p>His report was a devasta-<lb/>
ting attack on the<lb/>
Panama Commission<lb/>
which caused its<lb/>
dismissal by the<lb/>
President.</p>
<p>Feb. 17, 1905.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
