<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02746001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Sanitary Conditions in Panama, by William Crawford Gorgas, February 10, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02746001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-02-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Panama City (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-02-10">February 10, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02746001</idno>
<title>Report: Sanitary Conditions in Panama, by William Crawford Gorgas, February 10, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report was prepared for the Smithsonian Institution and includes autographed notes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1905-02-10">
<head>Report: Sanitary Conditions in Panama, by William Crawford Gorgas, February 10, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02746001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Ancon, Isthmian Canal Zone,<lb/>
<date value="1905-02-10">February 10th, 1905L</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>From a sanitary point of view the location of the Panam&aacute;<lb/>
Canal is very important. It is within the limits of the Republic<lb/>
of Panam&aacute;, in the tropics, and about nine degrees north of the<lb/>
Equator. For engineering reasons the lowest point in the mountain<lb/>
range, running north and south through the Western Hemisphere,<lb/>
has been selected, the range at this point being about three hun-<lb/>
dred feet high. The Isthmus, in its general direction here, runs<lb/>
east and west; the Canal, therefore, in a general direction, is<lb/>
north and south. The local coast line, at the point where the<lb/>
town of Panam&aacute; is situated, bellies somewhat toward the south, so<lb/>
that when you look to the east you see nothing but the Pacific<lb/>
Ocean as far as the eye can reach. It struck me with surprise<lb/>
and took me some time to get used to the phenomen<del>a</del><add>on</add> of every morning<lb/>
seeing the sun rise out of the Pacific Ocean, and set behind the<lb/>
mountain on which I live. My preconceived ideas were just the<lb/>
opposite; that is, that the sun should rise out of the Atlantic<lb/>
Ocean and set in the Pacific. As a matter of fact the town of<lb/>
Panam&aacute; is some twenty miles east of a line, drawn north and south,<lb/>
from the town of Colon.</p>
<p>Panam&aacute;, or the town of Panam&aacute;, was established early in<lb/>
the 15<del>00</del>s, and was probably selected because the <del>range</del><add>ridge</add> of the<lb/>
hemisphere was lowest at this point and because the Chagres River<lb/>
gave river transportation at this point about two-thirds the dis-<lb/>
tance across the Isthmus. The Isthmus is narrower, considerably,<lb/>
at several other points than at Panam&aacute;; but the <del>range</del><add>ridge</add> at these points<lb/>
is very much higher. The town rapidly grew in importance, and in<lb/>
the first hundred years after its settlement was probably the most<lb/>
important town in Spanish America. Here Pizarro's expedition was<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02746002"/>
2<lb/>
fitted out, and <add>here</add> all the enormous gold and silver treasure from the<lb/>
South American conquests came across the Continent. In 1671 the<lb/>
English buccaneer, Henry Morgan, captured and sacked the city after<lb/>
he had outmanoeuvred and defeated a larger and superior Spanish<lb/>
regular force on the broad savan<add>n</add>as adjacent to the town. After<lb/>
this catastrophe the present location of Panam&aacute; was selected<del>,</del>- a<lb/>
high peninsula<del>r</del> running south into the Pacific, and easy of defense.<lb/>
It was so strongly fortified that no attempts thereafter were made<lb/>
to carry it by storm. It stands about six miles west of the site<lb/>
of the old town, of which abundant ruins are still visible.</p>
<p>In former days a <del>convenient</del><add>good</add> paved highway ran straight<lb/>
north through the mountains, toward the convenient port of Puerto<lb/>
Bello; but when the railroad was constructed the northern terminus<lb/>
was located at the present town of Colon. The line of the Canal,<lb/>
so far as it is at present fixed, runs about fifty miles north and<lb/>
south, between the port of Colon on the north and Panam&aacute; on the<lb/>
south. It follows, in general, beginning from the northern end,<lb/>
the valley of the Chagres River and one of its branches, the Obispo,<lb/>
up to the top of the divide at Culebra, some <del>forty</del><add>thirty</add>-five miles; and<lb/>
then down the valley of the Rio Grande to Panam&aacute;,<del>-</del> some fifteen<lb/>
miles. Contrary to the general impression that I had formed be-<lb/>
fore coming down, the country is rolling and well drained, being<lb/>
essentially a mountainous district. The Chagres of course has<lb/>
marsh and lowlands in its valley, but no more than <del>half</del><add>have</add> the small-<lb/>
er rivers and larger creeks of the mountainous districts of Ala-<lb/>
bama or New York. The country in general is very attractive, high<lb/>
and variegated as it is, with rolling hills and tropical verdure as<lb/>
far as the eye can reach. Insects and reptiles <del>, in general,</del> are<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02746003"/>
3<lb/>
scarce; and our friend, the mosquito, could not be called abundant.<lb/>
I believe any dweller of Staten Island or New Jersey, after a week's<lb/>
residence, would leave with the impression that there were none of<lb/>
the latter.</p>
<p>For purposes of canal building the United States has pur-<lb/>
chased a tract of land extending along the whole length of the<lb/>
line of the Canal, ten miles in width, of which the Canal is in<lb/>
the center. The history of this Zone, with regard to health, has<lb/>
been exceedingly lugubrious<del>;</del>- just as it <add>has</add> occurred everywhere else<lb/>
in the Tropics or wherever a large, unacclimated population has<lb/>
been brought in, either for military or industrial purposes. The<lb/>
railroad was built in the early fifties, and its cost was greatly<lb/>
increased and the work itself several times stopped, on account<lb/>
of the heavy mortality among the unacclimated laborers brought<lb/>
here. Later, between the years 1880 and 1889, the same thing oc-<lb/>
curred, on a much larger scale, in the French attempt to dig a<lb/>
canal under de Lesseps. The diseases causing the most mortality<lb/>
at these times were yellow fever and malaria.</p>
<p>At the present time on the Zone there are 40,000 inhabit-<lb/>
ants; Panam&aacute; containing 20,000, Colon 10,000 and the towns along<lb/>
the Canal between Panam&aacute; and Colon, 10,000. The prevailing dis-<lb/>
ease <add>is</add> malaria. Leprosy also exists. In Panam&aacute; we have at present<lb/>
some yellow fever and a great deal of beri<add>-</add>beri; and of course all<lb/>
other tropical diseases to a limited extent. Eighteen months from<lb/>
the present time, I am informed by the Chief Engineer, we will<lb/>
probably have on the Isthmus a force of some 15,000 men. Estimat-<lb/>
ing from our present ratio, I am inclined to think that not more<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02746004"/>
4<lb/>
than 2,000 of these will be Caucasians and the other 13,000 ne-<lb/>
groes. <del>Now</del><add>But</add>, the sanitary problem will be to protect these 15,000<lb/>
men from malaria and from yellow fever. I will take up first,<lb/>
yellow fever. I assume it as accepted that it is conveyed from<lb/>
man to man only by the female Stegomyia, who has previously bit-<lb/>
ten some human being suffering from yellow fever. Therefore,<lb/>
given a place in which there are no infected Stegomyia, yellow<lb/>
fever cannot originate until a human being, suffering from yel-<lb/>
low fever, has been introduced and infected the local Stegomyia;<lb/>
or, unless the female Stegomyia, infected at some distant point<lb/>
where yellow fever prevails, has been introduced. Practically the<lb/>
first is almost the only method of infecting a locality, namely:-<lb/>
the introduction of a human being suffering from yellow fever.<lb/>
<del><unclear>Lw,</unclear></del> The city of Panam&aacute; has been in the condition for a great many<lb/>
years, of at all times having within her borders some infected<lb/>
<del><unclear>S</unclear></del><add>St</add>egomyia, at all seasons of the year, and the non-immune foreign-<lb/>
er coming within her limits is liable to contract the disease.<lb/>
Yellow fever is at present endemic nowhere on the Zone except in<lb/>
the city of Panam&aacute;. The object of the sanitarian is, therefore,<lb/>
to get rid of the infected Stegomyia at present existing in the<lb/>
city; and this can be done in this way: Establish a system where-<lb/>
by the health authorities will pretty certainly be informed of<lb/>
every case of yellow fever occurring: then take the house in<lb/>
which this case occurs and fumigate it so as to destroy all the<lb/>
mosquitoes within its borders. Do the same with all the contig-<lb/>
uous houses. This, it has been found by experience, kills all the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes at that particular focus. The same thing is<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02746005"/>
5<lb/>
done at every other foc<del>i</del><add>us</add>, as yellow fever occurs. Gradually, in<lb/>
this way, all the foci in the community are destroyed; and when<lb/>
you have destroyed your last focus yellow fever is at an end. Or,<lb/>
if you want to be more expeditious, and the town is not too large,<lb/>
you can systematically fumigate every house in the town and thus<lb/>
pretty certainly destroy all infected mosquitoes and do away with<lb/>
yellow fever much more rapidly. But no system of reporting is<lb/>
ever absolutely certain; and the sanitarian should see that other<lb/>
very important adjuncts to the fumigation work are carried on at<lb/>
the same time. The Stegomyia is a house mosquito and cleanly in<lb/>
her habits,<del>-</del> seeks principally clean rain-water barrels and water<lb/>
containers; and lives very close to her birthplace, not traveling<lb/>
far. Therefore, as an additional sanitary safeguard, every recept-<lb/>
acle for water should be so screened and covered that mosquitoes<lb/>
cannot have access. All yards should be thoroughly cleaned so<lb/>
that there will be no old bottles or cans left around. The water<lb/>
supply should be piped in so that the people will not desire to<lb/>
have water in containers. Sewers should be put in, so that there<lb/>
will be no tendency for people to throw slop water in the yards.<lb/>
All standing puddles should be drained and kept dry. Streets<lb/>
should be paved and kept well swept; and the garbage carefully<lb/>
collected, with a view to decreasing to the minimum all trash<lb/>
capable of retaining fresh water in any way. When Panam&aacute; has been<lb/>
in this <del>condition</del><add>state</add> for a month or two we will be in the same condi-<lb/>
tion that Havana is, as the result of just such operations as I<lb/>
have described above. When Panam&aacute; has thus been freed from yellow<lb/>
fever, we will not have any more until a man, sick from yellow<lb/>
fever, is introduced from some infected point without. This we<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02746006"/>
6<lb/>
will prevent by a proper system of quarantine, just as Havana<lb/>
has done for the past three years.</p>
<p>Thus, I can see the entire possibility of protecting our<lb/>
laborers on the Canal during the whole time of its construction<del>,</del><lb/>
from one of the two greatest causes of former mortality.</p>
<p>But I think that probably a more important problem for<lb/>
the health of our laborers, and certainly a much more difficult<lb/>
one to deal with, is that of malaria along the line of the Canal.<lb/>
The 10,000 natives living along the Canal are distributed in<lb/>
about twenty small villages. These people are very generally<lb/>
infected with malaria. A recent microscopical examination of the<lb/>
blood<del>,</del> of people, taken at random at various points along the line,<lb/>
in several hundred cases, showed parasites in the blood of fifty<lb/>
per cent. of these <del>examinations</del><add>people</add> on the first examination. This<lb/>
means pretty certainly that about eighty per cent. of the natives<lb/>
at the present time have the malarial parasite in their blood.<lb/>
Four times out of five, when a female Anopheles bites one of the<lb/>
natives she becomes infected; and when she in turn bites one of<lb/>
our nearby laborers he becomes infected. It is thus evident that<lb/>
our force will rapidly be used up, just as <del>were</del><add>was</add> the French, un-<lb/>
less our sanitary measures prevent it.</p>
<p>Now, we can approach this problem from two sides; either<lb/>
on the side of doing away with the infected human being so that<lb/>
he cannot infect the mosquito, or doing away with the mosquito<lb/>
so that she cannot transmit the parasite from the diseased to the<lb/>
well. If we could kill these 10,000 natives and keep our labor-<lb/>
ers away for four or five months until all previously infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes had died. the problem would be settled; but our superiors<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02746007"/>
7<lb/>
would ve<add>r</add>y properly not sanction this very drastic measure, even<lb/>
if proposed by us. <del>Now</del><add>But</add>, if we have some substance which could<lb/>
be introduced into the circulation of the infected man, and kill<lb/>
the parasite and at the same time not be injurious to man, we<lb/>
would accomplish the same object just as effectively as if we<lb/>
killed the man, and the measure would not meet with such general<lb/>
opposition as the former proposition would. <del>Now,</del> In quinine we<lb/>
have discovered this poison. This vegetable substance is hrmless<lb/>
to man and fatal to the malarial parasite. The greater number of<lb/>
practical tropical sanitarians, the Germans and the Italians con-<lb/>
spicuously, advocate and have been successful on these lines:-<lb/>
have gotten as large a proportion of the population as possible<lb/>
to take small quantities of quinine with as much regularity as<lb/>
they could; and thus have been successful, without adopting any<lb/>
other measures, in doing away with malaria in the several locali-<lb/>
ties. Or, we can attack it from the side of the mosquito; do<lb/>
just what we intend doing in Panama with regard to the Stegomyia:-<lb/>
cover all water containers, clean up the yards, fix the roads so<lb/>
there will be no puddles, have <add>a</add> regular system in all the towns<lb/>
of collecting garbage and waste so there will be no cans around;<lb/>
and ditching everywhere where there are small breeding places in<lb/>
the neighborhood of dwellings, and oil where ditching is not prac-<lb/>
ticable. This latter method<del>,</del> of killing the mosquito, is the<lb/>
method most in favor by English and American tropical sanitarians.<lb/>
This alone has been successful in eradicating malaria in many lo-<lb/>
calities.</p>
<p>Along the route of the Panama Canal the malaria problem,<lb/>
I think, is more difficult to deal with, and more serious<del>,</del> than<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02746008"/>
8<lb/>
any place where it has previously been tried. We, therefore, ex-<lb/>
pect to adopt both methods; and, I am convinced, that in this way<lb/>
we will be able to protect our laborers from the serious mortal-<lb/>
ity that has undone our predecessors in this important work.</p>
<p>The other diseases to which we are subject, I think, will<lb/>
not give us serious trouble, but will be controlled by the ordi-<lb/>
nary measures usually adopted by a health department.</p>
<p>I could go much more <del>in</del><add>into</add> detail and describe the organiza-<lb/>
tion which we have perfected so far, and what, in addition, we ex-<lb/>
pect to get in operation within the next six months; but I have<lb/>
probably already said all that is pertinent for an article of this<lb/>
kind.</p>
<p>-----------------------</p>
<p>Dear General,</p>
<p>This is an article I have written at the request of the Smith-<lb/>
sonian institute, <unclear>Shuigo</unclear> an <unclear>coming</unclear> our way down here<lb/>
I think,</p>
<p>Sincerely yours,</p>
<p>W. C. Gorgas.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f02746009"/>
<p>Sanitary Conditions<lb/>
in<lb/>
Panama<lb/>
Written for Smithson-<lb/>
ian Institute<lb/>
Feb. 10-<lb/>
1905<lb/>
W.C. Gorgas</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
