<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02749001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Report to the Secretary of War, by Charles F. Mason, February 17, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02749001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-02-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Ross, John W.</name>
<name type="person">La Garde, Louis L.</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cristobal (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>22 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-02-17">February 17, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02749001</idno>
<title>Report to the Secretary of War, by Charles F. Mason, February 17, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Mason reports on the Panama Canal Zone Sanitary Department activities with appendices: A - plan of action; B - departmental organization; C - free distribution of quinine.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-02-17">
<head>Report to the Secretary of War, by Charles F. Mason, February 17, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02749001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1905-02-17">February 17, 1905.</date>
</dateline>
The Honorable Secretary of War,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to report that in compliance with your instruction I sailed<lb/>
from New York for the Isthmus of Panama on January 24th and arrived there Thursday,<lb/>
February 2d; I again left Panama Thursday, February 9th, having carried out the in-<lb/>
structions confided to me.</p>
<p>In making this report I shall endeavor, as far as possible, not to go over<lb/>
again ground which is familiar to you and which is covered by official reports, except<lb/>
when necessary to elucidate my remarks.</p>
<p>The present condition of health of the canal employes is good; with a total<lb/>
of about 5000 employes less than 3% are in hospital.</p>
<p>With regard to the present outbreak of yellow fever the following remarks<lb/>
are submitted:</p>
<p>The statistics regarding yellow fever in the city of Panama prior to Ameri-<lb/>
can occupation show deaths only as other cases were not reported:</p>
<p>1901 1902 1903<lb/>
Deaths from Yellow fever in Panama.......11 ...........182 ........... 48</p>
<p>In the first 6 months of 1904 (before American occupation) there were 6 deaths<lb/>
" " second " " " " (after " " ) " " 13 cases and<lb/>
three deaths.</p>
<p>In January, 1905, there were 18 cases with 6 deaths (including 2 on the <add>U.S.S.</add> Boston<lb/>
and 1 in Colon)</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02749002"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Of the total 33 cases, 30 originated in Panama, 3 in Colon.<lb/>
" " " " " 14 were American, and 11 were Canal employes.</p>
<p>There were no secondary cases, each focus of infection having been promptly<lb/>
stamped out.</p>
<p>The distribution of the Panama cases showed widely scattered infection:<lb/>
all the Colon cases originated at one hotel. The three Colon cases occurred on ship-<lb/>
board, en route to Havana and in the persons of steamer passengers detained at Colon<lb/>
on account of small-pox; had there been proper detention facilities at that point<lb/>
these cases should not have occurred.</p>
<p>The cases on the Boston are believed to have been due to a mild and unrecog-<lb/>
nized case having visited the ship on the occasion of an entertainment given there on<lb/>
the night of December 31st, which was largely attended by non-immunes from Panama.<lb/>
Yellow fever mosquitoes were brooding abundantly on the ship and probably became infec-<lb/>
ted at that time. The fumigation of the ship promptly stopped the outbreak.</p>
<p>While, considering the previous history of Panama in regard to yellow fever,<lb/>
and the large influx of non-immunes since July first, the number of cases and deaths<lb/>
has been small, the outbreak becomes important on account of the effect upon public<lb/>
opinion in relation to the work to be done on the canal.</p>
<p>The sanitary department of the Canal Zone government is subdivided as fol-<lb/>
lows: A department of hospitals, a maritime quarantine service, a sanitary service<lb/>
for the Canal Zone, and the health departments of Panama and Colon.</p>
<p><hi>Department of Hospitals</hi>.</p>
<p>This includes at present actually in operation the hospitals at Ancon and<lb/>
Colon and one emergency hospital at Calebra, the three having a total capacity of<lb/>
254 beds, all of which are occupied. Additional beds are needed, to supply which the<lb/>
chief sanitary officer has asked for a hundred bed Convalescent hospital at Tuboga<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02749003"/>
-3-<lb/>
island, and another hospital of about the same capacity at Miraflorer; the former has<lb/>
been disallowed for the present, the latter was authorized by Governor Davis about<lb/>
December 1st, but, through delay in construction and supplies, it is not yet ready for<lb/>
use. The commission has authorized construction at Ancon and Colon which will give<lb/>
600 beds, but there is no immediate prospect of the work being done nor any material<lb/>
or personnel available for utilizing them.</p>
<p>Along the line of the Canal, at convenient points, are stationed four medi-<lb/>
cal officers with medical supplies, each having charge of a district for emergency<lb/>
work.among Canal employees.</p>
<p>While the hospital department has about reached the limit of its present<lb/>
capacity, the sick are well cared for, though for lack of wire screening they are not<lb/>
adequately protected against malarial infection.</p>
<p><hi>Maritime Quarantine</hi>.</p>
<p>At Panama the arrangements while not all that could be desired, are believed<lb/>
to afford adequate protection against the introduction of quarantinable diseases from<lb/>
without.</p>
<p>At Colon the arrangements are not so far advanced nor so satisfactory.<lb/>
Though plans have been approved for a detention building, construction has not been<lb/>
commenced; the surveillance of detained suspects at hotels, etc., is difficult and<lb/>
somewhat risky. Notwithstanding these shortcomings, which it is hoped to soon remedy,<lb/>
it is believed that the quarantine service to date has been effective and that no in-<lb/>
fectious diseases have been introduced through either port.</p>
<p>Immigration. In this connection the laws of the Canal Zone provide that the<lb/>
chief quarantine officer shall prevent the entrance to the Zone of any person who is<lb/>
likely to prove a menace to the public health or welfare or who is likely to become a<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02749004"/>
-4-<lb/>
charge upon the public. Nothing however has been actually done under this law to res<lb/>
strict undesirable immigration.</p>
<p><hi>Sanitary Service of the Canal Zone</hi>.</p>
<p>This service, under a Chief Sanitary Inspector, employed on January 31st<lb/>
about 275 men.</p>
<p>In general it is charged with the duty of cleaning up the settlements of<lb/>
laborers along the Zone, the removal of night-soil and garbage, surface drainage and<lb/>
other anti-mosquito work. A great deal of valuable work has been done along the line<lb/>
but much remains to be done, especially in the matter of screening the dwellings of the<lb/>
Canal employes and covering their water-barrels with wire gauze. No screening has<lb/>
been done, and while a large number barrels in some localities have been covered, and<lb/>
covers prepared for many more, the work is very far from completion because no more<lb/>
spigots are available to permit the use of the water.</p>
<p><hi>Panama Health Office</hi>.</p>
<p>The Chief Sanitary Officer of the Commission has been appointed by the<lb/>
Republic of Panama, its health officer for the cities of Panama and Colon. In Panama<lb/>
he has taken charge of the matter of street cleaning, removal of garbage and general<lb/>
anti-mosquito work on the lines of that carried out in Havana. Just now the whole<lb/>
city is being fumigated for the destruction of mosquitoes and the work is expected to<lb/>
be completed by the end of the present month. The cleanliness of the streets, yards<lb/>
and interior courts has been greatly improved.</p>
<p><hi>Colon Health Office</hi>.</p>
<p>Here sanitary work has been confined to garbage removal, a small amount of<lb/>
street cleaning, and a little oiling of water tanks; the results thus far are not<lb/>
very apparent, the city being in a very dirty and unsanitary condition.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f02749005"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>In Cristobal, however, where most of the Canal employes live, very much more has been<lb/>
accomplished in the way of surface drainage, removal of garbage and night-soll, anti-<lb/>
mosquito work, etc.</p>
<p>In making a comparison of sanitary accomplishment with that at Havana in<lb/>
1901 the differences in condition must be fully understood. In Havana we had a compact<lb/>
city, with water-works, which had been under American control for more than two years<lb/>
at the time the anti-mosquito work was begun; which had been thoroughly cleaned; in<lb/>
which the health and other departments were efficiently organized, and with the Chief<lb/>
Sanitary Officer possessing complete autonomy in the matter of construction, material<lb/>
and supplies. In Panama everything was different. The sanitary work had to be done<lb/>
in two cities, some 50 miles apart and along the intervening strip containing numbers<lb/>
of native villages. There was no organization anywhere; everything had to be start-<lb/>
ed. The two cities at either end of the strip were without adequate water supply,<lb/>
without sewers, without organization of any sort for municipal sanitation, and in an<lb/>
extremely filthy condition. Being at the very commencement of a vast engineering en-<lb/>
terprise in which sanitation was only one of the features, it was perhaps natural that<lb/>
it should receive only what was considered its due share of attention instead of being<lb/>
the principal feature as at Havana.</p>
<p>Col. Gorgas, the Chief Sanitary Officer, arrived permanently on the Isthmus<lb/>
and began his work about July 1st last. <add>1904</add> The preliminary plan for sanitary work sub-<lb/>
mitted by him was already in operation to a limited extent. In the months which have<lb/>
followed much has been accomplished as pointed out under the separate headings.<lb/>
In Havana in the same period of time yellow fever was wiped out; here it has not been,<lb/>
though I believe that end will soon be accomplished. In my opinion the diseases<lb/>
would have been eradicated before this time had it been found practicable to adopt<lb/>
in its entirety and carry out promptly the scheme proposed by the chief sanitary officer.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02749006"/>
<p>-6-</p>
<p>The two diseases which more than any others threaten the success of the<lb/>
Canal project are malaria and yellow fever. While malaria is far more important in<lb/>
the amount of disease, death and invaliding it is likely to cause on the Isthmus,<lb/>
yellow fever is no less important in its indirect bearing. While 50 deaths from<lb/>
malaria might occur without attracting much attention, one-tenth as many from yellow<lb/>
fever would cause a panicky feeling which would keep any thousands of persons whose<lb/>
services are needed, or cause them to demand much higher pay for their services.</p>
<p>In the preliminary plan of organization of the sanitary department submitted<lb/>
in April by Doctors Gorgas, Ross and La Garde, and which in its general features was<lb/>
approved by the Commission and went into effect in July, 1904, it was proposed to keep<lb/>
out infectious diseases by a quarantine system, to get in touch with all cases of<lb/>
malaria and yellow fever by assuming charge of the sick of Panama and Colon and the<lb/>
Canal strip, to detect them early by a system of inspection, and by screening all acute<lb/>
cases and keeping others under treatment until they were no longer capable of infecting<lb/>
mosquitoes, to prevent the spread of these diseases.</p>
<p>On July 26th <add>1904</add> the chief sanitary officer, after two months experience as<lb/>
such, submitted <add>to</add> the Commission a permanent scheme of sanitary organization and read to<lb/>
the Commission an explanatory statement which I deem of so much importance that it is<lb/>
hereto appended, marked &ldquo;A&rdquo;. In this statement he takes the ground that the cities<lb/>
of Panama and Colon can and should be freed from yellow fever by January, 1905, and<lb/>
the Zone from malarial fever in the same period, and before the arrival of the main force<lb/>
of Canal employes; but that to accomplish such a result he must be able to work <add>more</add> rapid-<lb/>
ly than was possible with the delay in material, construction, etc., which had occurred<lb/>
and must occur under the present organization. He further stated that, while the<lb/>
health conditions on the Isthmus with its present small non-immune population were<lb/>
about normal, the conditions existed which if not radically changed would in time give<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02749007"/>
-7-<lb/>
us the heavy mortality of the French regime. He suggested a remedy in the shape of<lb/>
greater autonomy with a view to more rapid work, his idea being that the great work<lb/>
of the sanitary department should be done before the active work began in digging the<lb/>
Canal. The scheme of organization submitted was an exceedingly able and comprehen-<lb/>
sive one and if carried out in its entirety would no doubt have accomplished all that<lb/>
its author hoped for.</p>
<p>To control malaria and yellow fever, besides the general features already<lb/>
outlined, he provided for treating all the sick of the Canal Zone, and for the admin-<lb/>
istration of quinine to all those infected with malaria, even though not sick, and<lb/>
this for both employes and non-employes. This plan, with the anti-mosquito work<lb/>
would probably have eradicated these diseases. The plan provided for 20 small emer-<lb/>
gency hospitals with dispensaries attached, and 20 sanitary inspectors with the neces-<lb/>
sary subordinates, distributed in the villages along the Canal Zone, -the inhabitants<lb/>
of which were proven to be widely infected with malaria, -and ready to infect, through<lb/>
the mosquito, the employes of the Canal Commission.</p>
<p>The action taken on this proposed plan and the organization finally adopted<lb/>
is shown in the Proceedings of the 42d meeting of the Isthmian Canal Commission, dated<lb/>
August 28, 1904. In a general way the proposed organization was adopted, but<lb/>
the details were modified in certain very important particulars. The idea of the<lb/>
Commission seems to have been that conditions should be met as they arose, while the<lb/>
vital point in the plans of the Chief Sanitary Officer was <hi>prevention</hi> rather than<lb/>
cure.</p>
<p>Instead of 20 emergency hospitals and dispensaries, and 20 hospitals along<lb/>
the Zone, 3 hospitals and dispensaries, 2 additional dispensaries, and 8 Inspectors<lb/>
were allowed with the proviso for extension when deemed necessary by the Commission.<lb/>
No reference was made to the plan of treating with Quinine all the inhabitants of the<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02749008"/>
-8-<lb/>
Zone infected with malaria, and this recommendation was subsequently disapproved by<lb/>
the Commission under date of November 5, 1904. On December 21st the Chief Sanitary<lb/>
Officer explained the importance of this provision in a letter to the Commission in<lb/>
which he stated that if it was not allowed, his ability to combat malaria would be<lb/>
reduced one-half.</p>
<p>In regard to assuming complete sanitary control of the cities of Panama and<lb/>
Colon there were certain legal difficulties of which you know and which were not set-<lb/>
tled until very recently.</p>
<p>Thus the success of the scheme for the prevention of malaria has been seriously<lb/>
endangered by doing away with all of its most important features, that of treating<lb/>
with quinine all persons dangerous to others by harboring the malarial parasites in<lb/>
the blood. <add>(See Appendix &ldquo;C&rdquo;)</add> That part of the scheme which provided for the protection of the canal<lb/>
employee by screening their dwellings appears to have received no definite action;<lb/>
nothing has been done toward carrying it into effect.</p>
<p>The defects in the sanitation of the Isthmus then, are, in my opinion, as<lb/>
follows:-</p>
<p>1. Inadequacy of the scheme for the protection of the Canal employes<lb/>
against malaria. The scheme as submitted by the chief sanitary officer was adequate,<lb/>
but its modification by the Commission in cutting off the free issue of quinine, but<lb/>
authorizing the screening of the dwellings of Canal employes along the strip, and re-<lb/>
ducing the number of physicians, hospitals and dispensaries along the line has dimin-<lb/>
ished its value at least one-half.</p>
<p>2. Defective organization of the sanitary department in the lack of suffi-<lb/>
cient autonomy to carry out its work effectively.</p>
<p>Under the first heading no serious results have followed as yet, but that<lb/>
they will follow all tropical experiences of like undertakings certainly indicates.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f02749009"/>
<p>-9-</p>
<p>Under the second heading the result has been to greatly delay the work of the sanita-<lb/>
ry department. Many instances might be quoted; a few will suffice. The principal<lb/>
large requisition for medicine and medical supplies was made about the first of last<lb/>
<hi>August</hi>; at this date, <hi>February 8th</hi>, <hi>not one item has been received.</hi> Other large<lb/>
requisitions made subsequently to this have met the same fate. The Governor, General<lb/>
Davis, tells me that these requisitions were approved by him and went forward promptly,<lb/>
and that he has done all in his power to get them filled; what the trouble is he does<lb/>
not know. Meantime, he has bought what was most urgently needed through the local<lb/>
markets. Even articles produced in the local market have sometimes required nearly<lb/>
or quite a month for delivery.</p>
<p>The estimates for repairs to Ancon hospital was made in July last; those<lb/>
repairs are not yet completed; today, after seven months, only one ward has been<lb/>
screened. But these points are well covered in the letter of the Chief Sanitary<lb/>
Officer already referred to as appended and marked &ldquo;A&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I think it may be taken <unclear>as</unclear> generally accepted that to dig the Canal quickly,<lb/>
economically and with as little sickness and loss of life as possible it is necessary<lb/>
that the sanitary work shall be thorough and efficient and shall accomplish results.<lb/>
If it fails, if the death-rate becomes high, especially for yellow fever, it will in-<lb/>
crease the cost of the Canal by millions of dollars and delay its completion by years.<lb/>
I have no doubt that the present small outbreak of yellow fever will add many hundreds<lb/>
of thousands to the cost of the work and materially delay its construction because<lb/>
there will be a greater unwillingness to come here, and higher salaries will be de-<lb/>
manded. There is already apparent a panicky feeling widespread among the employes<lb/>
and this will be reflected in an exaggerated form in the States. The work of the<lb/>
Sanitary department is primarily preventive, and only secondarily to meet indications<lb/>
as they arise; the important part of that work should have been done before the arrival<lb/>
* Requisition of Dr. La Garde dated Dec. 12/04.<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f02749010"/>
-10-<lb/>
of the great mass of employes. The defects of the present system and the delays and<lb/>
imperfections of sanitary accomplishment which have resulted therefrom have been<lb/>
pointed out in the foregoing pages.</p>
<p>It seems to me that if the work of the sanitary department is to be success-<lb/>
ful,- and the success of the Canal project depends on it -, the Commission having se-<lb/>
lected a chief sanitary officer in whom they have confidence should accept his plans<lb/>
for sanitation as final, give him a free hand and their earnest support in carrying them<lb/>
out, and hold him strictly responsible for results. What if the chief sanitary of-<lb/>
ficer does spend $56,000. or $100,000. that could have been saved under a slower and<lb/>
more restricted method of procedure: The prevention and suppression of epidemic di-<lb/>
seases often depends upon quick action, and a week's delay may often cost many hun-<lb/>
dreds of thousands and delay the work of the Canal for long periods. While the<lb/>
figures show that the rate of sickness among Canal employes is not excessive at pres-<lb/>
ent, there is no reason to hope that such a condition will continue; on the contrary,<lb/>
unless the plans of the sanitary department are more quickly and completely carried out<lb/>
than at present, there is every reason to believe that sickness and mortality will in-<lb/>
crease as the work goes on and time passes, until health conditions not far different<lb/>
from those under the French regime will obtain.</p>
<p>In view of the President's message on the subject of the Commission, and<lb/>
not knowing what the ultimate plan of reorganization may be, I can only make these<lb/>
broad suggestions as to the work of the sanitary department.</p>
<p>A scheme suggested to the chief sanitary officer and hereto appended, marked<lb/>
&ldquo;B&rdquo; appears to be an excellent one if it can be made to fit into the general plan.<lb/>
In any case the scheme should be such that measures recommended and requisitions made<lb/>
by the chief sanitary officer may be acted on promptly and executed without delay.<lb/>
To effect this it would seem to be necessary that the final authority should reside<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f02749011"/>
-11-<lb/>
on the Isthmus and not in Washington.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Sgd C. F. <unclear>Mason</unclear><lb/>
Major, Surgeon, U. S. Army.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="12" id="f02749012"/>
<opener>
APPENDIX (A)<lb/>
Copy of communication of the Chief Sanitary Officer.<lb/>
Ancon, Isthmian Canal Zone,<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1904-07-26">July 26, 1904.</date>
</dateline>
Rear Admiral John C. Walker, U. S. N.,<lb/>
Chairman, Isthmian Canal Commission.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I desire to submit the following scheme to the Commission for their con-<lb/>
sideration:</p>
<p>I have now been the Chief Sanitary Officer of the Commission for two months,<lb/>
and actively engaged in the organization of my department. In the several informal<lb/>
conversations I have had with the Commission, I have taken the ground that the towns<lb/>
of Panama and Colon could be freed from yellow fever, and the strip practically freed<lb/>
from malarial fever, by July 1905. I had assumed always, in making those statements,<lb/>
that I could organize and get to work just as rapidly as I, myself, could handle my<lb/>
material; but in undertaking my work I find that I have to work through other depart-<lb/>
ments of the Commission, such as the Supply Department, the Engineering Department,<lb/>
and so on. But from the nature of things those departments are large and extensive,<lb/>
and their organization will go on slowly. It is not necessary that they be fully<lb/>
organized until the actual digging of the canal commences. My department is small,<lb/>
could be organized in a few months; and it is necessary that my work shall have been<lb/>
completed before that of the others commences. As an illustration: The present<lb/>
scheme contemplates that the construction of the Sanitary Department be done by the<lb/>
Engineer Department, and the supplies ordered through the Chief of the <hi>Bureau of Ma-<lb/>
terials and Accounts.</hi></p>
<pb n="13" id="f02749013"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>There were certain necessary repairs at Ancon Hospital, that had to be made<lb/>
before the buildings were occupied. To carry out my idea of the proper care of the<lb/>
sick, Ancon Hospital should be treating, by Jan. 1st, within the neighborhood of five<lb/>
hundred patients. The estimates have just been made for these repairs, and the ma-<lb/>
terial ordered; and it will probably be the 1st of January before those repairs are<lb/>
anywhere near completion. I had proposed to the Commission to give the sanitary de-<lb/>
partment a competent engineer. If he had come down with us in April he could have<lb/>
made all these estimates for the whole department. During May he could have returned<lb/>
to the United States, ordered all his material, gotten a sufficient personnel together,<lb/>
and been back on the strip by the 1st of June. By the 1st of July the work could<lb/>
have been well under way, and by the 1st of October the buildings ready for occupancy.<lb/>
<unclear>O</unclear> do not speak of this in criticism at all; but it is impossible for the Chief Engi-<lb/>
neer and the Chief of Department of Materials and Accounts to have organized their big<lb/>
departments so as to meet my emergencies at once; and I have no doubt that two years<lb/>
from now the Chief Engineer can manage such things much more economically and more ex-<lb/>
peditiously than I could through my own department. But this system has certainly<lb/>
up to the present time caused me two months delay; and as I had only about fourteen<lb/>
months in which to do my work, this has been a very serious loss to me.</p>
<p>Or, take another instance; of my having to work through the Chief of De-<lb/>
partment of Materials and Accounts. The material which the Commission had authorized<lb/>
me to buy in New York I was directed, when I arrived, to turn over to the Chief, De-<lb/>
partment of Materials and Accounts. This was done in accordance with the general<lb/>
plan adopted by the governor. I make requisition for the spades, bars and special<lb/>
things which I had bought for special work, in New York. My men are all ready to go<lb/>
to work and are merely waiting for this material. Two weeks after making the requi-<lb/>
sition, the things are supplied; but instead of being the things which I had brought<lb/>
down, they were the old stock of the French company, entirely unsuited for the work;<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f02749014"/>
-3-<lb/>
and still (a month from the time of my arrival) I have not gotten these things. The<lb/>
Chief of Materials and Accounts has a large amount of property to distribute, and a<lb/>
great many regulations, - of which my own is a small part. If I had retained control<lb/>
of my own property, placed it in a store house and issued it myself, I think my men<lb/>
could have been at work, as far as tools are concerned, at the end of a week. As I<lb/>
said before, I have no doubt that two years from now the Chief of this bureau would<lb/>
have gotten thoroughly organized, and my requisitions would be filled very promptly.<lb/>
But what will be too late for me. My work will have been either a success or a fail-<lb/>
ure by that time; and in my opinion some system must be adopted within the next month<lb/>
or two, which will meet my wants.</p>
<p>And again, with regard to my getting authority from the Governor. As an<lb/>
illustration: A case of yellow fever occurs in the town of Panama. I have to ask<lb/>
the Governor's authority for every dollar of expenditures I make. This involves<lb/>
seeing him every day about two or three points, many of them involving only a few dol-<lb/>
lars, and unimportant. I consume the Governor's time, although I know every moment<lb/>
of his time is necessary for important matters of State; and consume my time, which<lb/>
should be occupied with much more important matters pertaining to the practical work<lb/>
of my department.</p>
<p>I write a letter to the Governor on this subject, of which I enclose a copy.<lb/>
The Governor replies, granting the specific things in regard to men, which I ask for.<lb/>
But the gist of my request, which would have granted me some liberty of action, namely;<lb/>
that he authorize my expenditure up to $7000 for this purpose, for the succeeding<lb/>
month, is not granted. I therefore have to go to the Governor in the same way as be-<lb/>
fore. The next day, the amount of expenditure of $30 or $40 for printing a sanitary<lb/>
ordinance in this connection comes up. It was not specifically authorized in the<lb/>
Governor's letter, and I therefore have to go to him about it.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f02749015"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>The instances quoted are merely a few among the daily occurrences, that, it<lb/>
seems to me, are inherent in my position here, namely: being associated with large<lb/>
departments which necessarily have to be organized slowly, my own department being<lb/>
small, and the work having to be accomplished before the others commence.</p>
<p>Now, there is no sense in an executive officer pointing out to his superiors<lb/>
defects, unless he has some suggestion as to remedy. I think it would accomplish my<lb/>
objects and enable me to organize rapidly and effectively if the Commission would<lb/>
grant me, for two years, some such scheme as this: That I propose a general plan of<lb/>
sanitation covering, say, up to July, 1905, going as much as possible into details,<lb/>
and give items, figures, etc. That the Commission consider this, authorize what they<lb/>
deem expedient, and then after that, allow me to act freely under this authorization<lb/>
without further authority from the Governor or Commission. That for every month I<lb/>
submit to the Commission an estimate of the amount of money needed for that month, for<lb/>
the running of the department; of course, being governed by the general estimate al-<lb/>
ready submitted; that this money be placed to the credit of a bonded disbursing offi-<lb/>
cer of the Sanitary Department; establish a purchasing officer in New York; also a<lb/>
storehouse on the strip. In this way I think I could obviate delays in getting ma-<lb/>
terial. As my department expanded, I would want an additional inspector, say.<lb/>
I see that so many inspectors are authorized by the general scheme. I could communi-<lb/>
cate with the man, offer him the salary fixed by the Commission and have him at once<lb/>
placed on my payrolls and put to work; instead of having to go to the Governor, get<lb/>
the Governor to write to the Commission asking the authority at a certain sum; have<lb/>
the letter returned from the Commission for some change in the terms allowed, and<lb/>
finally send to the man to know whether or not he will accept. Or, if it is material<lb/>
wanted, I could see in the general scheme whether I was authorized to make such pur-<lb/>
chase; and if I were, write to the Sanitary Department Purchasing Agent in New York,<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f02749016"/>
-5-<lb/>
have him purchase the goods, ship them at once to the Sanitary Storekeeper and send<lb/>
the bills to the Sanitary Disbursing Officer. Of course, there would always be<lb/>
items which cannot be foreseen in my estimate; and these I would have to bring up to<lb/>
the Governor or to the Commission for authorization; but under my scheme this would<lb/>
only occur occasionally and would not be a daily affair as it is now.</p>
<p>I would not undertake to make an argument for the necessity of sanitation.<lb/>
I presume that the Commission accept this. Personally I am more impressed with its<lb/>
necessity now, than I was two months ago. I see in detail the local causes that<lb/>
will give us the heavy mortality that the French had, or that occurred during the<lb/>
days of the railroad construction, unless they are corrected. The inhabitants of the<lb/>
strip are thoroughly infected with malarial fever, and the conditions of our Marines<lb/>
and of the American engineers who have so far come in, show that they readily become<lb/>
infected from these natives. It is evident to anyone, that if you put 15,000 laborers<lb/>
in the position of these Marines or engineers, they will likewise become infected, and<lb/>
in the course of time will develop a severe form of malarial fever, as did the French.<lb/>
The conditions are now, I believe, about the normal state for this tropical locality;<lb/>
and I have no doubt they were the same a year before the French came here; and our<lb/>
present knowledge of tropical sanitation makes us certain that two years from now our<lb/>
mortality will be as heavy as it was two years after the French commenced work, unless<lb/>
we can radically change conditions.</p>
<p>It is no doubt possible to wait until this mortality begins to show itself,<lb/>
both in yellow fever and malarial fever, and then take the steps that we see are abso-<lb/>
lutely necessary. This was done in Havana, and I think could be done here. But a<lb/>
very much wiser and more economical plan, in my opinion, is to devote the next year to<lb/>
freeing the Strip, as far as possible, from this malarial infection; to get the towns<lb/>
along the strip in such condition that when fresh population comes in they will not<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f02749017"/>
-6-<lb/>
contract malaria from the population already on the ground. Under the present scheme<lb/>
of administration, I think, the probabilities are that I could do the second; that is,-<lb/>
by July 1905, get our department in working order so that I could cope with necessi-<lb/>
ties as they arose; and then, two or three years after that time, get malaria under<lb/>
control, even with a large laboring population on the ground.</p>
<p>If it were arranged so that I could go on with my organization as rapidly as<lb/>
I could use my personnel and material, I think that the first could be accomplished,<lb/>
namely: that by July, 1905, I could get the Strip free from malaria so that the labor-<lb/>
ing population coming in, would not have the mortality that they will necessarily have<lb/>
under present conditions.</p>
<p>I do not ask the Commission to change their scheme. I merely ask that I be<lb/>
temporarily excluded in the points mentioned. As the other departments get organized<lb/>
I can drop into the general scheme. But if I am to accomplish the work proposed, by<lb/>
July, 1905, some change which will enable me to act much more expeditiously than I am<lb/>
at present doing, is absolutely necessary. So far I have carried out, under the di-<lb/>
rection of General Davis, Governor, the scheme proposed to the Commission in April.<lb/>
Dr. Carter, as Chief Quarantine Officer, has inaugurated a system of quarantine whereby<lb/>
infectious and contagious diseases will be kept from coming from the outside. The<lb/>
President of the Republic, under most liberal decrees, has placed me in entire control<lb/>
of the quarantine of Panama and Colon; and by another decree, in entire control of<lb/>
the sanitation of the towns of Panama and Colon. And I would like here to call the<lb/>
attention of the Commission to the very hearty way in which the President of the Re-<lb/>
public has cocinded me in every way, in sanitary matters.</p>
<p>Dr. Balch has begun the organization of the Health Department for the city<lb/>
of Panama; and Dr. Spratling, of the Health Department for the town of Colon.<lb/>
Dr. Ross, Director of Hospitals, has commenced the organization of the hospitals; and<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f02749018"/>
-7-<lb/>
Mr. LePrince, Health Officer of the Strip, has commenced his very important work on<lb/>
the Strip.</p>
<p>I enclose herewith a general estimate of what I think necessary for my de-<lb/>
partment for the next year. I request that the Commission allow me to appear before<lb/>
them for the purpose of explaining in detail, this estimate; and for explaining what<lb/>
to me seems of great importance:- of allowing me greater liberty of action than I at<lb/>
present <unclear>possess</unclear>, and if the necessity of placing my department is such a position that<lb/>
it can push rapidly forward.</p>
<p>I do not think it necessary that I should have such liberty of action as<lb/>
this scheme provides, in all the departments for the whole time; for instance:- I can<lb/>
see very well that the Chief Engineer, from this time on, will do my construction<lb/>
probably more rapidly and economically that I could do it, and I therefore think it<lb/>
would be of advantage to the service to leave such work of my department under the<lb/>
Chief Engineer, as is provided in the present scheme. And so with the other branches.<lb/>
As I find that I can work with rapidly and efficiency through the other departments<lb/>
I am perfectly willing to come into the general scheme from time to time.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Sgd W.C. Gorgas<lb/>
Ch <unclear>san</unclear> Officer</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="19" id="f02749019"/>
<opener>
APPENDIX(B)<lb/>
Scheme of Organization of the Sanitary Department suggested by the<lb/>
Chief Sanitary Officer.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>The ideal of sanitary organization to my mind, and the best adapted for the<lb/>
circumstances, is such as we had at Havana: That the Sanitary Department should be an<lb/>
independent organization just as the Engineers are down here, or the Department of<lb/>
Material &amp; Supplies, or the Pay Department; and that the Chief Sanitary Officer<lb/>
should report direct to the supreme authority, without the interference of the Board<lb/>
of Health, and without the intervention of the Governor. That it should have as-<lb/>
signed to it its own purchasing officer, its own disbursing officer, and own construct-<lb/>
ing officer. That the Chief Sanitary Officer should propose a scheme of organization<lb/>
to this supreme authority, who should adopt such of it as he thought fitted the case:<lb/>
That for every month the Chief Sanitary Officer should submit a detailed estimate of<lb/>
the expenses of his department for that month; that the supreme authority should act<lb/>
upon this estimate; that the sum approved by the supreme authority for that month be<lb/>
placed to the credit of the disbursing officer of the Sanitary Department and dis-<lb/>
bursed under the order of the Chief Sanitary Officer according to the approved esti-<lb/>
mate. With this authority and organization, I am sure I could carry forward the sani-<lb/>
tation just as we did in Havana. I would then be responsible and could control all<lb/>
those delays in getting supplies, construction and personnel that have occurred here<lb/>
and delayed me so much in the sanitation under the Commission. Whatever organization<lb/>
is adopted for the construction of the canal, it seems to me this is the essential,<lb/>
as far as the sanitation is concerned: that the Chief Sanitary Officer be held entire<lb/>
ly responsible for the sanitation, and then be given powers commensurate with this re-<lb/>
sponsibility. Under the present organization I am nominally responsible, but en-<lb/>
tirely unable to control, as I am completely dependent upon other departments which,<lb/>
so far, have been entirely unable to meet my wants.</p>
<pb n="20" id="f02749020"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>If the present organization for constructing the canal is continued, the or-<lb/>
ganization I would urge for the Sanitary Department would be this: That the Chief<lb/>
Sanitary Officer report directly to the Commission; that in matters which he thought<lb/>
sufficiently important he could appeal to the Secretary of War, and that the Secretary<lb/>
of War have the Surgeon General of the Army advise him with regard to such subjects<lb/>
appealed. That the Commission allow the Sanitary Department a chief of material and<lb/>
supplies and that this officer be under the orders of the Chief Sanitary Officer, do<lb/>
all the purchasing and care for all the supplies of the Sanitary Department, just as<lb/>
the quartermaster of an army post is under the orders of the post commander. That<lb/>
the Commission appoint for the Sanitary Department an engineer, who shall have charge<lb/>
and control of all construction under the orders of the Chief Sanitary Officer. That<lb/>
they appoint for the Sanitary Department a paymaster, who shall do all the disbursing<lb/>
for the Sanitary Department/ that the Chief Sanitary Officer make monthly estimates to<lb/>
the Commission, as proposed above. This organization will enable the Chief Sanitary<lb/>
Officer, after an estimate has been approved for the month, to act freely and promptly<lb/>
under that estimate and at the same time give the Commission absolute control of the<lb/>
expenses of the department from the fact that they have to authorize all expenditures.</p>
<pb n="21" id="f02749021"/>
<p>APPENDIX (C)</p>
<p>The rationale of the free issue of quinine to the native population of the<lb/>
Canal Zone is as follows:</p>
<p>The malarial infection is due to a microscopic organism which circulates<lb/>
in the blood of those infected, and when they are bitten by a mosquito of the genus<lb/>
anopheles the mosquito becomes infected and is probably able to transmit the disease<lb/>
during the rest of its life.</p>
<p>It has been found that about 70 per cent. of the apparently healthy popu-<lb/>
lation of the Zone have the malarial infection in their general circulation and so<lb/>
are active agents in its spread. The routine administration of quinine causes the<lb/>
malarial parasite to disappear from the blood and <unclear>no</unclear> breaks the cycle of the infection,<lb/>
and thus prevents the native population from being an active source of infection to<lb/>
the canal employes. It is a preventive measure of primary importance.</p>
<pb n="22" id="f02749022"/>
<p>Mason- Char F<lb/>
Report to Secy<lb/>
of War-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
