<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02743001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Robert M. O'Reilly, January 3, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Gorgas, William Crawford</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02743001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-01-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">O'Reilly, Robert M.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Weyman, Surgeon General</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Panama City (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Ancon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Vera Cruz (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Miraflores (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-01-03">January 3, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02743001</idno>
<title>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Robert M. O'Reilly, January 3, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gorgas writes about his own work with the Canal Zone Sanitary Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-01-03">
<head>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Robert M. O'Reilly, January 3, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02743001"/>
<opener>
<hi>COPY</hi>.<lb/>
<dateline>
ISTHMIAN CANAL COMMISSION.<lb/>
Ancon, C. Z., <date value="1905-01-03">January 3, 1905.</date>
</dateline>
General R. M. O'Reilly,<lb/>
Surgeon-General United States Army,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Kean writes me that you wish him to give you an outline of our<lb/>
conditions down here, and to make this intelligible I will review shortly the<lb/>
history of the facts.</p>
<p>When I first came down with the Commission in April of last year, I<lb/>
made a general plan at their request for what I thought would be the necessary<lb/>
sanitation. The Commission at the time, took no definite action on this plan,<lb/>
but when I came down in June, authorized me in a general way to get it into run-<lb/>
ning order. Before starting down in June they authorized my getting certain<lb/>
personnel and about $50,000.00 worth of sanitary and hospital supplies with which<lb/>
to make a start.</p>
<p>Under this authority I came down and established a Quarantine Depart-<lb/>
ment at the two points of Panama and Colon. While the Commission paid for this,<lb/>
it was done only under the authority of the Panamanian Government. I inclose<lb/>
you copies of decrees issued by the Panamanian Government making me Health Offi-<lb/>
cer for them at the two ports and at the towns of Panama and Colon. I have<lb/>
already sent you copies of the scheme which I proposed to the Commission.<lb/>
I also established Health Departments for the management of the towns of Panama<lb/>
and Colon under this same authority. Also a Health Organization for the Zone<lb/>
between Panama and Colon and a Hospital Department for the management of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02743002"/>
-2-<lb/>
various hospitals.</p>
<p>I foresaw before I left the United States that there would be great<lb/>
difficulty about supplies and construction as the Commission wished me to manage<lb/>
these things through other departments. I pointed out to them that in the<lb/>
question of supplies, if bought by one department for the whole canal, it would<lb/>
take some time for such department to get organized and that I could not get my<lb/>
supplies through them until they had been organized; that if my construction was<lb/>
done by the Engineering Department the same difficulties would arise until the<lb/>
Engineering Department had become fully organized, and this organization for<lb/>
them would take considerable time. Another great objection to such a plan as<lb/>
that proposed, was that in any case where rapid executive work was necessary, as<lb/>
it was in my case, I could not control. For instance, if I asked for ordinary<lb/>
supplies through the ordinary routine and greater pressure was brought to bear<lb/>
by some other department, this other department would be attended to first and<lb/>
I would have to wait. That, if in construction, the Chief Engineer, where he<lb/>
could not do all, he would naturally favor those that were most important to him.</p>
<p>The Commission came down in September, made a formal plan of organiza-<lb/>
tion, organizing the Department as I had already established it and making a fair-<lb/>
ly liberal appropriation of about a million dollars for carrying it on for a<lb/>
year, but did not grant independence of action in getting supplies and doing my<lb/>
own constructing.</p>
<p>I have used my experience in Havana and depended pretty much on the<lb/>
methods down there in making my plan of organization.</p>
<p>We have now been running six months on this scheme and have accom-<lb/>
plished, to my mind, most satisfactory results.</p>
<p>The Quarantine Department is in full swing and is most effectively<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02743003"/>
-3-<lb/>
organized at both ports. No case of any contagion has been admitted to the<lb/>
Zone in this time. I can state this positively as with our control of the situ-<lb/>
ation we would know of any case occurring. I feel entirely confident that our<lb/>
quarantine is as effectively managed as that in the United States.</p>
<p>The Hospital Departments of Panama and Colon are organized and working<lb/>
effectively as far as mosquito work and the control of contagious diseases are<lb/>
concerned. This is all that I am very anxious about and all that the Commis-<lb/>
sion will furnish funds for at present. While I proposed to the Commission a<lb/>
scheme which, if carried out, would have given us a well rounded sanitary organ-<lb/>
ization, such as we had in Havana, I, myself, do not lend such great importance to<lb/>
such matters as street cleaning, collection of garbage, disposal of night-soil,<lb/>
&amp; c, as long as we can do the mosquito work and have an official reporting of<lb/>
contagious diseases. While this is done I am satisfied that we can control the<lb/>
situation. In these two towns the disease of vital importance is Yellow Fever,<lb/>
and this I believe we have under control. In the six months we have had no<lb/>
cases in Colon and but 13 in Panama. No two cases of yellow fever in Panama<lb/>
have occurred in the same house - that is, after fumigating there has been no<lb/>
secondary case, indicating that our fumigation kills all the mosquitos and each<lb/>
focus as it occurs, so that eventually we will get rid of it as we did at Havana.<lb/>
Along the strip we have some three hundred men doing mosquito work and have<lb/>
started a dozen or more dispensaries along the line at the little towns with the<lb/>
object of treating the malarially infected natives.</p>
<p>While it is not so easy to put down the results of this work, I feel<lb/>
confident that it is producing the results. The general opinion at all these<lb/>
little places is that the work has greatly decreased the number of mosquitos.<lb/>
A more important fact, however, is that we have lost from malarial fever, as yet,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02743004"/>
-4-<lb/>
no white American brought from the United States. This, I think, is saying a<lb/>
great deal as compared with the former French and Railroad administrations.<lb/>
To have been on the Canal Zone for six months with a considerable number of un-<lb/>
acclimated Americans and to have lost not a single one from malarial fever and<lb/>
but one from yellow fever is very good I think. Of course I am only speaking<lb/>
of the whites from the United States. We have lost some of our Jamaican negro<lb/>
employes.</p>
<p>In our Hospital Department we have at Ancon a fairly well equipped hos-<lb/>
pital containing two hundred patients. At Miraflores we are organizing a hos-<lb/>
pital for chronic cases, which has just commenced and has at present only the<lb/>
lepers, but which we expect to use for all our chronic cases. We have a small<lb/>
hospital of ten beds at Culebra, another at Gorgona of about the same size and ten<lb/>
dispensaries at other points. At Colon Hospital we have at present forty pa-<lb/>
tients, but this hospital will be brought up eventually to a capacity of three<lb/>
hundred. We are able to take care of, well, all the single employes of the<lb/>
Commission.</p>
<p>I think that we have accomplished everything which could have been ac-<lb/>
complished with what has been allowed by the Commission. I would like to have<lb/>
a very much more perfect organization than I have, but it is not worrying me.<lb/>
I can see that we are going to get, gradually, one thing and another from the<lb/>
Commission as the necessity comes to them and within two or three years will<lb/>
probably have all that I originally asked for, and that we will accomplish the<lb/>
great result for which we came here - to free this Zone from malaria and yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>What I hoped and wanted when I came down here was to bring this result<lb/>
about in six months rather than two or three years, but just exactly what I pre-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02743005"/>
-5-<lb/>
dicted to the Commission has come about. The big supply department has been<lb/>
unable to organize with sufficient rapidity to meet my wants. So far I have<lb/>
only had the supplies which I brought down with me and such things as the Panama<lb/>
market could afford. My first requisition (put in in July) from the United<lb/>
States is as yet unfilled.</p>
<p>The same thing has occurred in the Construction Department. Estimates<lb/>
that were made in July for the repair of Ancon Hospital have just been begun<lb/>
within the last month. The Construction Department has had a very small force<lb/>
of laborers and these are used at other points for which more pressure was brought<lb/>
to bear.</p>
<p>This, I think, will give you a very good idea of our successes and our<lb/>
difficulties. I am satisfied that we have the situation under control. I be-<lb/>
lieve that we have practically wiped out yellow fever and I think I see ahead the<lb/>
control of malarial fever. These two diseases, I am confident, control sanita-<lb/>
tion on the Isthmus.</p>
<p>I inclose you under separate cover, copies of my October and November<lb/>
reports which will also help give an idea of our present conditions.</p>
<p>* * * * *</p>
<p>The Commission do not favor any laboratory down here outside of those in<lb/>
the hospitals - I mean any laboratory for original research. I am inclined to<lb/>
think that Surgeon General Weyman of the Public Health Service has discussed this<lb/>
matter with the Commission and has offered to take the whole matter off their<lb/>
hands and that his Department would assume the expense. Of this I am sorry, but<lb/>
I will raise no objection to the Public Health Service provided we are entirely<lb/>
separate; that is, provided there will be just such a laboratory established<lb/>
here as they had at Vera Cruz and at Havana.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02743006"/>
<p>-6-</p>
<p>La Garde thinks that Carroll would like to do some yellow fever work<lb/>
down here. If such is the case and you want him to come, you know I would sec-<lb/>
ond your views in every possible way. If he wants to come, I think I could<lb/>
have him made head of whatever laboratory we have and furnish him with an unlimit-<lb/>
ed supply of human pathology, but our equipment at present is very small and<lb/>
would come very slowly. But we need some one for pushing our laboratory work.</p>
<p>* * * * *</p>
<p>I will write you from time to time explaining little points that come<lb/>
up. It will give you an idea of how things are going on.</p>
<p>I remain, my dear General.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) W. C. Gorgas</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
