<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02752001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter fragment to Howard A. Kelly, March 4, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02752001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-03-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Selden, W.</name>
<name type="person">Nash, Herbert</name>
<name type="place">Norfolk (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Hampton (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Richmond (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Portsmouth (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-03-04">March 4, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02752001</idno>
<title>Letter fragment to Howard A. Kelly, March 4, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The writer informs Kelly about a yellow fever epidemic in Norfolk, Virginia, in 1855.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-03-04">
<head>Letter fragment to Howard A. Kelly, March 4, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02752001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Norfolk, <date value="1905-03-04">March 4th. 1905.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Howard A. Kelly,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Kelly,</salute>
</opener>
<p>I would have answered your letter sooner, except that<lb/>
I have been trying to get you everything I could on the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Epidemic of 1855. And I have not yet found the medical report<lb/>
written by my grand-father, Dr. Wm. Selden, but I will try again to find<lb/>
a copy, if I cannot find my own. I will however be glad to lend you<lb/>
the books by Forrest and Armstrong, neither of whom were physicians.<lb/>
Consequently some of their conclusions are a little peculiar.</p>
<p>My grand-father, who had seen a good deal of Yellow Fever did<lb/>
not believe it contagious, but thought it due to something which<lb/>
could be carried in the hold of a vessel. This is brought <add>out</add> by Arm<del>e</del>-<del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
strong who considers it due to &ldquo;a Miasma&rdquo;, a theory resembling the<lb/>
old theory for Malaria. Thus on page 26 he says, &ldquo;It was by the<lb/>
breaking out of the hold of that steamer that the fatal miasma was let<lb/>
loose.&rdquo; The fever was also said to be carried by the wind, and only<lb/>
to be caught at night (pp. 187, 8, &amp; 9). I have also frequently heard<lb/>
that the Fever would appear first on the ground floor, and that<lb/>
cases would <add>not</add> appear at the top of the house for some days. Armstrong<lb/>
says further that secluding oneself within the town will not pro-<lb/>
tect from the Fever, and that the only safety is in flight to a<lb/>
distant place. Cases of Yellow Fever appeared in Norfolk people, who<lb/>
had gone to Hampton, Richmond, and Baltimore, where some died, but no<lb/>
infection was spread by them.</p>
<p>The facts just given you can all be explained by Dr. Reed's Mos-<lb/>
quito Theory, for I have found the Stegomyia in Norfolk, where it un-<lb/>
doubtedly was in '55.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02752002"/>
<p>(2)</p>
<p>The infected ship came to the dock on June 19, having had the Fever<lb/>
on board, and the first local <add>case</add> seems to have occured in a workman, who<lb/>
had been aboard of her, and who was attacked about July 2, There is<lb/>
a possible earlier case in a woman who lived <add>near</add> where the ship lay <add>(Armstrong p. 170)</add>, and<lb/>
was seen <add>by a physician</add> on June 30. Both of these cases were probably infected by<lb/>
Stegomyia, imported on the steamer. From these cases the Stegomuia of<lb/>
Portsmouth were probably infected, but no cases originated away from<lb/>
this locality till Aug. 7, <del><unclear></unclear></del>(Forrest p. 28). <hi>The disease then gradually<lb/>
spread in a Northerly direction, the mosquitoes being carried</hi> by<lb/>
<hi>the prevalent South winds</hi>. The appearance of the Fever first on the<lb/>
<hi>ground floor of a house, can</hi> be explained by the mosquito's habit of<lb/>
staying close to the ground, when in the open. Armstrong's observation<lb/>
on the futility of secluding oneself within the infected town, and<lb/>
that no cases resulted from those that developed after they had<lb/>
left Norfolk can also be well understood in the light of Dr. Reed's<lb/>
hypothesis. The observation that the Fever was only caught at night<lb/>
does not seem to accord with what I have read of the habits of the<lb/>
Stegomyia.</p>
<p>Norfolk has in other years repeatedly had Yellow Fever brought to<lb/>
its doors, without having further cases develop. They were frequently<lb/>
treated in the Naval Hospital, just across the river, and Dr. Herbert<lb/>
Nash, who was long our Health Officer <add>tells me</add> that he has often had cases<lb/>
on a barge a few miles down the river, and that he always brought the<lb/>
convalescents to the hospital here, and that contagion never result-<lb/>
ed. This corroborates Dr. Reed's observation <hi>that convalescents<lb/>
are not dangerous</hi>.</p>
<p>There was Yellow Fever at the Soldiers Home, near Hampton after<lb/>
the Spanish War, the original case being imported, and the other</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
