<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02750002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Article: The American Mosquito Extermination Society on Mosquito Work Going on at Panama, February 20, 1909</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02750002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1909-02-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama City (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1909-02-20">February 20, 1909</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02750002</idno>
<title>Article: The American Mosquito Extermination Society on Mosquito Work Going on at Panama, February 20, 1909</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This article discusses mosquito control efforts in Panama around the Canal Zone.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1909-02-20">
<head>Article: The American Mosquito Extermination Society on Mosquito Work Going on at Panama, February 20, 1909</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02750002"/>
<p>As this is a <add>&ldquo;</add>Mosquito Extermination Society<add>&rdquo;</add>, I <del>would</del><add>will</add> confine my remarks<lb/>
to describing the mosquito work we have already done and that which we expect<lb/>
to do.</p>
<p>The American Territory here exten<del>t</del><add>d</add>s north and south for a distance of about<lb/>
fifty miles<add>,</add> <del>and</del> being in width ten miles. The Canal is its centre through its<lb/>
length, with the town of Colon at its northern extremity on the Carribean and<lb/>
Panama its southern extremity on the Pacific. The line of the Canal runs from<lb/>
north to south up the Chagres river and up the Obispo, one of the branches of the<lb/>
Chagres, some thirty-five miles to the continental divide. It then descends<lb/>
to the valley of the Rio Grande, some fifteen miles, to the Pacific. The country<lb/>
is rolling, covered with tropical undergrowth<add>,</add> and very attractive in appearance; no<lb/>
more swamp than we have along one of our small rivers in the hill country of New York.</p>
<p>In the town of Panama our attention is principally turned to the stegomyia<lb/>
work. Our Inspectors go about the city methodically, in districts laid off, noting<lb/>
the number of deposits of each breeding mosquito. At present there is no water<add>-</add><lb/>
supply in Panama and almost everybody has to depend upon collecting rain water.<lb/>
The poor do this principally in barrels and containers of all sorts and descriptions.<lb/>
This makes the town an ideal breeding place for the stegomyia. I recently had<lb/>
examined one hundred mosquitoes, killed in one house, and eighty-one out of the<lb/>
hundred were stegomyia. This is a very much larger <add>pro</add>portion of stegomyia than<lb/>
I ever found in Havana. The largest proportion I think I ever found there was<lb/>
about twenty-fi<del>c</del><add>v</add>e per cent. The town also at this time gets a good part of its <add>water</add><lb/>
supply from surface wells scattered all about the suburbs</p>
<p>Upon the report of these inspectors, tops o<del>r</del><add>f</add> wood and wire gauze are made for<lb/>
all water barrels and cisterns, and wooden spigots put in all barrels. When this<lb/>
has been entirely accomplished the breeding of stegomyia in the city will be<lb/>
greatly decreased. At the present time we have about all the water barrels covered<lb/>
and most of the cisterns oiled. In the suburbs we have most of the <unclear></unclear><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02750003"/>
-2-<lb/>
oiled, and expect, as we are able, to drain many of them. The greater part of<lb/>
our present mosquito work in Panama is devoted to the killing of adults.</p>
<p>During December and January we had some sixteen or seventeen cases of yellow<lb/>
fever in the town. Up to the middle of January, as each case of yellow fever was<lb/>
reported, we had been going to the house, fumigating that house and all contiguous<lb/>
houses, <del>and</del> thus killing all the infected mosquitoes at that particular focus, as<lb/>
had been done in Havana. But<add>,</add> wishing to get rid of yellow fever more expeditiously<lb/>
than we had done there, we have now adopted the plan of going through the town<lb/>
systematically and fumigating every house there. At this work we have at present<lb/>
150 men pasting up houses and burning sulphur and pyrethrum. This mosquito work<lb/>
is done entirely with regard to Yellow Fever. When we have yellow fever in a<lb/>
place we know that we have had some infected adult mosquito. Now if we simply<lb/>
depend upon preventing the development of mosquitoes we know that this yellow<lb/>
fever will continue until the infected mosquitoes die a natural death. This might<lb/>
be four or five months and, therefore, we have to adopt more expeditious methods.</p>
<p>Water is being brought in by pipe line from the head waters of the Rio Grande,<lb/>
some ten miles and at the same time a sewer system is being put in and<add>,</add> when this is<lb/>
do<del>wn</del><add>ne</add><add>,</add> it is probable that the streets will be paved. This will, of course, greatly<lb/>
decrease the necessity for our mosquito work. When we have a plentiful supply of<lb/>
water we can prohibit the collection of rain water and enforce such prohibition.<lb/>
Street paving will do away with most puddles and sewerage help in the <del><unclear>see</unclear></del><add>same</add><lb/>
direction.</p>
<p>At Colon we are trying the same work, but as most of the town is on piles in<lb/>
a swamp, complete eradication is at present impossible, but by the end of another<lb/>
year the town will have been filled in entirely some ten feet, a sewerage system<lb/>
put in, streets paved and a water supply <del><unclear>interest</unclear></del> introduced. This<add>,</add> with very little<lb/>
supervision<add>,</add> will settle the mosquito question there.</p>
<p>Along the line of the Canal is the hardest and most difficult problem we have<lb/>
with regard to anopheles work. We have 300 men along this strip looking after<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02750004"/>
-3-<lb/>
mosquito breeding in some twenty little towns. The water barrels are looked<lb/>
after in the way described, but most of the work is devoted to superficial<lb/>
drainage and ditching. It is hard to describe how much work has been<lb/>
accomplished in the last eight months along these lines, but I think it fair<lb/>
to attribute some of the present good health of our laboring force to these<lb/>
measures, as they certainly did not exist formerly with the laboring force in the<lb/>
same locality.</p>
<p>We had on our rolls on the first of February something over 6,000 men. Of<lb/>
these 6,000 on the same date, 125 were in the hospital, a rate of about 2 per cent.<lb/>
When we compare this with anything we know of in the former construction down here,<lb/>
or even the health conditions at home in our Army and Navy, it <del>would</del><add>will</add> make a very<lb/>
good showing.</p>
<p>With the employees brought from the United States we have been particularly<lb/>
fortunate with regard to malaria, not having had a single death since we came down<lb/>
in July, nearly eight months now, among this class of employees. We probably<lb/>
have in the neighborhood of 700 white men from the United States. Up to the<lb/>
first of this month we could say the same with regard to yellow fever, not a<lb/>
single man of this class having died. So far this month (February)<add>,</add> up to the<lb/>
14th, in the whole Zone we have had only four cases of yellow fever. But one<lb/>
of these was an American employee who died. Considering the circumstances<add>,</add> I<lb/>
think our mosquito work is holding Yellow Fever very well in check, when we<lb/>
consider that we are living with<add>in</add> an old<add>,</add> crowded town of 20,000 inhabitants and in<lb/>
one of the worst months of the year, to have only four cases within two weeks.</p>
<p>I look forward, in a very short time, to having the last infected female<lb/>
stegomyia mosquito safely smothered in pyrathrum funes<add>,</add> and that means the<lb/>
extinction of Yellow Fever on the Zone. Then all we will have to do will be to<lb/>
keep a sharp watch and see that none is introduced from the outside, just as the<lb/>
Cubans have done at Havana for the last three years; and surely we can do as well<lb/>
as they. When that condition is reached Panama will be as safe as Havana, which<lb/>
is all we ask, as far as yellow fever is concerned.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
