<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02753001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Pride Thomas to Howard A. Kelly, March 6, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Thomas, Pride</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02753001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-03-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Thomas, William, George</name>
<name type="person">Wragg, W. T.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">Wilmington (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Charleston (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-03-06">March 6, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02753001</idno>
<title>Letter from Pride Thomas to Howard A. Kelly, March 6, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Thomas writes about a yellow fever epidemic in Wilmington, North Carolina, in 1862.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-03-06">
<head>Letter from Pride Thomas to Howard A. Kelly, March 6, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02753001"/>
<opener>
3/10/05<lb/>
will return Journal<lb/>
<dateline>
DR. PRIDE JONES THOMAS,<lb/>
WILMINGTON, N. C.<lb/>
<date value="1905-03-06">March 6th, 1905.pb</date>
</dateline>
Journal returned &amp; ack.<lb/>
July 8/05. <unclear>Thien</unclear>.<lb/>
Dr. Howard A. Kelly,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am told you are looking up the records of the outbreak of<lb/>
yellow fever in this place, Wilmington, N. C.</p>
<p>I beg leave to say I have what was considered a complete history<lb/>
of the outbreak of the yellow fever in 1862, written by my grand-father,<lb/>
the late Dr. William George Thomas. It is proper to say, in this con-<lb/>
nection, that he was at that time actively engaged in the practice of<lb/>
medicine in Wilmington, and was here from the date of the arrival of<lb/>
the blockade runner &ldquo;Kate&rdquo;, August 6th, 1862, until he was strickened<lb/>
with the fever in the first week of October. You will pardon me for<lb/>
saying he was at that time, and up to the time of his death, in 1890,<lb/>
the leading practitioner of Wilmington. You will note, if you should<lb/>
desire to read this article, that it is written to disprove the asser-<lb/>
tion of Dr. W. T. Wragg of Charleston, S. C., that the whole trouble in the<lb/>
Southern States was of spontaneous origin. Dr. Wragg was a highly es-<lb/>
teemed physician of his native city, and had participated in the care<lb/>
of those sick with the disease in Charleston in quite a number of seri-<lb/>
ous outbreaks. The excellent work of the lamented Walter Reed, which<lb/>
established the fact that the conveyance of yellow fever poison was by<lb/>
means of the stegomyia fasciata, was then not dreamed of. Following the<lb/>
suggestion along this line, made by Dr. Carlos Finlay in the 80s, you<lb/>
will note that among the first cases recorded were persons who visited<lb/>
the steamer &ldquo;Kate&rdquo; or lived so short a distance from the wharf at which<lb/>
the craft was moored as to make an easy flight for the mosquito bearing<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02753002"/>
DR. PRIDE JONES THOMAS,<lb/>
WILMINGTON, N. G.<lb/>
.2<lb/>
the poison. The time occupied by one of the blockade runners between<lb/>
Nassau and Wilmington was between three and four days. You will notice<lb/>
also that the author of this article alludes to the rain fall during the<lb/>
months of August, September and October; this atmospheric condition<lb/>
making many collections of stagnant water in which mosquitoes might breed.<lb/>
There was an outbreak of yellow fever in this town in 1854, but it oc-<lb/>
curred so late in the fall that the appearance of an early frost put a<lb/>
stop to the further progress of the disease. As far as I know, there<lb/>
are no connective histories of previous outbreaks of this disease in<lb/>
this community. It may interest you to know that Dr. John Guiteras,<lb/>
now of Havana, whom you will recollect as the celebrated yellow fever<lb/>
expert, entertained the opinion that many of the cases of so called<lb/>
pernicious malarial fever, so aptly described in Woods' Practice, first<lb/>
and second editions, were really cases of yellow fever in the cities<lb/>
of the seaboard of the South Atlantic States.</p>
<p>I trust I have not trenched upon your time with so long a letter,<lb/>
but you will easily understand my interest in this epidemic of 1862, in<lb/>
which my grand-father bore so conspicuous a part.</p>
<p>I am sending you, under separate cover, a copy of the New York Medi-<lb/>
cal Journal, above alluded to. If there is any other information I can<lb/>
obtain for you regarding the outbreak of yellow fever in this community,<lb/>
I shall be glad for you to indicate what information you desire, and it<lb/>
will give me great pleasure to find it for you, if possible.</p>
<p>My father, Dr. Geo. G. Thomas, wishes to be remembered most kindly<lb/>
to you, and joins me in my efforts to serve you.</p>
<p>As this Journal is one of my file, I would ask you please to return<lb/>
it to me after it has served your purposes.</p>
<p>encl.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very truly,</salute>
<signed>Pride J Thomas</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
