<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02755001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from William C. Borden to Howard A. Kelly, March 16, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Borden, William C.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02755001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-03-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, R.M.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Neff, Wallace</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-03-16">March 16, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02755001</idno>
<title>Letter from William C. Borden to Howard A. Kelly, March 16, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Borden provides details of the surgical operation for appendicitis that immediately preceded Walter Reed's death.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-03-16">
<head>Letter from William C. Borden to Howard A. Kelly, March 16, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02755001"/>
<opener>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
<dateline>
U. S. A. General Hospital,<lb/>
WASHINGTON BARRACKS.<lb/>
Washington, D. C., <date value="1905-03-16">March 16th, 1905.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. HOWARD A. KELLY,<lb/>
1418 Eutaw Place,<lb/>
BALTIMORE, MD.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Kelly:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>In reply to your request for information<lb/>
relative to the operation and death of Dr. Reed, I take pleasure<lb/>
in enclosing you a copy of the report made by me a short time<lb/>
after the operation was done.</p>
<p>In addition to the fact therein set forth, I might say that<lb/>
Dr. Reed had suffered for years with what he considered attacks<lb/>
of acute indigestion, and that he had never suspected that the<lb/>
trouble was appendicitis, although it undoubtedly was. The<lb/>
appendix showed marked evidence of previous inflammatory action,<lb/>
the lumen being nearly obliterated in several places. The o-<lb/>
bliteration was, however, not distal, so that it cannot be con-<lb/>
sidered a case of appendicitis obliterans. As stated in the<lb/>
report, Dr. Reed's symptoms in no way indicated the gravity of<lb/>
the intra-abdominal trouble, and when I started to operate I<lb/>
expected to find a case of ordinary catarrhal appendicitis, an<lb/>
appendix in which the inflammatory action was still limited.<lb/>
At the operation the condition was found as stated in the report.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02755002"/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
The site of operation was carefully walled off, but in manipu-<lb/>
lating the appendix the pus cavity was opened. The pus was all<lb/>
carefully sponged out with gauze sponges and I believe none of<lb/>
it escaped from the gauze crater. The appendix was so necrotic<lb/>
at the base that it was simply ligated off. No invagination of<lb/>
the <del>stomach</del><add>stump</add> could be done owing to the necrotic condition of the<lb/>
caecum in the neighborhood. Gauze drainage was inserted, the<lb/>
lower end of the drain being carefully packed over the <del>stomach</del><add>stump</add><lb/>
and down into the space between the <del>peritoneal</del><add>posterior</add> abdominal wall<lb/>
and lower end of the caecum, where the pus had gravitated. The<lb/>
Surgeon General of the Army--Brigadier General R. M. O'Reilly--<lb/>
Major Jefferson R. Kean, and other medical officers, as well as<lb/>
Dr. Wallace Neff of this city, were present at the operation. The<lb/>
operation was not prolonged, although I have forgotten the exact<lb/>
length of time--probably 1/2 hour. Dr. Reed reacted badly. He<lb/>
was very nervous and was much run down before the operation from<lb/>
overwork. He had been doing a great deal of extra bacteriological<lb/>
work and had been much confined, so that altogether his general<lb/>
condition at the time of operation was very unsatisfactory. This<lb/>
probably accounts, in part, for his reacting so badly. From the<lb/>
subsequent course of the case I am inclined to think that peri-<lb/>
tonitis gradually spread from the vicinity of the stump of the<lb/>
appendix, although he did very well for the first three days after<lb/>
the operation, so well, in fact, that the drain was not removed<lb/>
until the fourth day, being left in with the hope that by that<lb/>
time the infected area would be well walled off. Still there<lb/>
was suspicious evidence of peritoneal involvement in the right<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02755003"/>
3<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
and lower regions of the abdomen. The drain was removed without<lb/>
trouble, and apparently without breaking down any adhesions or<lb/>
interfering with the gut. The next day faecal matter in large<lb/>
quantity came through the wound, snowing that the caecum had<lb/>
broken down at or near the place where the appendix was ligated<lb/>
off. The opening must have been of considerable size as the<lb/>
quantity discharged was large. Shortly after the appearance of<lb/>
the faecal matter <del>the</del> symptoms of extensive peritonitis appeared,<lb/>
<del>proceed</del><add>preceded</add> by symptoms which indicated a rupture into the general<lb/>
peritoneal cavity, and I believe that the necrotic caecum slough-<lb/>
ed through causing general peritoneal infection. From this time<lb/>
forward Dr. Reed rapidly grew worse and died the next day--the<lb/>
sixth day after the operation.</p>
<p>Relative to information regarding his last days, I think<lb/>
there is little which can be said which would be of interest.<lb/>
Dr. Reed, aside from being excessively nervous, in fact unusually<lb/>
nervous, due, as I attribute it, to his mental fatigue from prev-<lb/>
ious overwork and consequent nervous collapse, was generally<lb/>
cheerful and unapprehensive of any ill result. After the appear-<lb/>
ance of the faecal fistula and the probable rupture into the<lb/>
general peritoneal cavity, he suffered from partial collapse and<lb/>
thereafter grew rapidly worse and soon became delirious.</p>
<p>The case was a particularly trying one to me for the reason<lb/>
that I was a great personal friend of Dr. Reed's, had known him<lb/>
for many years, and his family and my own are intimately acquainted.<lb/>
The case was also particularly unfortunate to me professionally,<lb/>
in that it is the only operative case of appendicitis which I<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02755004"/>
have ever lost, although I have operated a large number of times.<lb/>
It seemed particularly unfortunate that of the cases operated<lb/>
upon by me, that Dr. Reed should be the only one to die.</p>
<p>If there are any other particulars which you would like to<lb/>
know, I would be very glad to inform you in regard to them.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed><unclear>W. C. Borden</unclear><lb/>
Major, Surgeon, U. S. Army</signed>.
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
