<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02757001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Transcript of letter from William H. Taft to Theodore Roosevelt, March 30, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Taft, William H.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02757001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-03-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Roosevelt, Theodore</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Wallace, John Findley</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-03-30">March 30, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02757001</idno>
<title>Transcript of letter from William H. Taft to Theodore Roosevelt, March 30, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Taft details the requirements for the completion of the Panama Canal and the need to reorganize the Canal Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-03-30">
<head>Transcript of letter from William H. Taft to Theodore Roosevelt, March 30, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02757001"/>
<opener>
From W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> H. Taft<lb/>
Secy of War<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
<dateline>
Washington, <date value="1905-03-30">March 30, 1905.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Mr. President:</salute>
</opener><lb/>
<p>In the matter of the reorganization of the machine by which<lb/>
the Panama Canal is to be built, I beg first to call your attention<lb/>
to the extreme importance of fixing a definite plan with respect to<lb/>
which you may feel reasonable certainty, first, that it can be prac-<lb/>
tically executed and will result in a navigable canal, and, second,<lb/>
that the navigable canal will be the one best adapted to the demands<lb/>
which may be made upon it by the commerce of the world.</p>
<p>The Act of Congress evidently contemplates a canal with locks,<lb/>
the cost of which shall be in the neighborhood of $200,000,000, in-<lb/>
cluding the money already expended. It is quite within the bounds<lb/>
of possibility that the best form of canal will be a sea-level canal<lb/>
with a tidal lock only, at one end, and that the cost of it may ex-<lb/>
ceed the $200,000,000 in the mind of Congress by at least $100,000,000<lb/>
more.</p>
<p>The work of the engineering department of the present Commission<lb/>
has been largely devoted to obtaining the data upon which the plan<lb/>
of the canal must be determined. These data include topographical<lb/>
measurements, borings, the character of the soil, the flow of water<lb/>
in the rivers - all stated with sufficient exactness to secure the<lb/>
closest calculations by experienced engineers though not on the<lb/>
ground. It is probable that within the next few months, these data<lb/>
will have been so fully ascertained by the Chief Engineer, Mr. Wallace,<lb/>
and his assistants, that they may be submitted to a board of engi-<lb/>
neers of the highest standing for recommendation as to the best plan<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02757002"/>
-2-<lb/>
upon which to proceed with the work.</p>
<p>It also has been made apparent, by the reports of Mr. Wallace<lb/>
and the Commission, that whatever plan is likely to be adopted, work<lb/>
of excavation and construction which would have to be done under any<lb/>
plan may proceed without waste of energy for a period quite long<lb/>
enough to enable you to decide which is the best plan.</p>
<p>I suggest, therefore, that the first work to be done in the ap-<lb/>
pointment of an advisory board of engineers, say seven or nine in<lb/>
number, to be selected from the engineers having especial knowledge<lb/>
of hydraulic engineering and canal construction, to whom shall be<lb/>
submitted all possible information with respect to the projected<lb/>
Panama Canal, both that obtained by the French engineers before our<lb/>
purchase of the plant, and the data obtained by the Chief Engineer<lb/>
of the present Canal Commission, together with all projects suggested<lb/>
for the solution of the problem which the Canal Commission deem rea-<lb/>
sonably possible or practicable; that this advisory board be invited<lb/>
to Washington for the purpose of agreeing upon its recommendations<lb/>
in the promises and that if possible such recommendations be made<lb/>
before the regular meeting of Congress in December; that the recom-<lb/>
mendations be submitted to the Canal Commission as then constituted,<lb/>
for its approval or modification, and with the recommendations of<lb/>
the Canal Commission be submitted to the President for his action<lb/>
and transmission to Congress. As already suggested, this work of<lb/>
securing the best plan and its approval by Congress need not delay<lb/>
in any way the preliminary work adapted to any possible plan, or the<lb/>
highly critical work of sanitation, the extreme importance of which<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02757003"/>
-3-<lb/>
you have already emphasized in your previous instructions to the<lb/>
Canal Commission.</p>
<p>It is conceded, even by its own members, that the present com-<lb/>
mission has not so developed itself into an executive body as to give<lb/>
hope that it may be used successfully as an instrumentality for car-<lb/>
rying on the immense executive burden involved in the construction<lb/>
of the canal, and it remains for the President, in the failure of<lb/>
Congress to act, to reorganize the Commission, both by change in<lb/>
personnel and by certain instructions as to its internal procedure<lb/>
and distribution of powers and authority, to secure greater rapidity<lb/>
and efficiency in the doing of the work.</p>
<p>It is not to be supposed that Congress intended that the Com-<lb/>
mission was personally to do the work, or to come nearer to the di-<lb/>
rect agencies in doing the work than the directory of a railroad<lb/>
comes to the construction of railroad work, and we may assume there-<lb/>
fore that it was quite within the Congressional intention that the<lb/>
Commission might, for convenience and rapidity of action, after<lb/>
formulating the general plan of work, delegate to a committee or<lb/>
committees the doing of the work in detail, the result to be reported<lb/>
subsequently of course to the full Commission. The Commission should<lb/>
therefore appoint an Executive Committee, to be constituted and em-<lb/>
powered as hereafter stated.</p>
<p>The actual executive work must be divided by the Commission into<lb/>
departments. One department would naturally be the Political Depart-<lb/>
ment - that is, the control of the Zone, over which there should be<lb/>
an administrator or governor, and to secure harmony of action the<lb/>
wise policy is that already followed of appointing a member of the<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02757004"/>
-4-<lb/>
commission to be governor. This department should include, as it<lb/>
does now, the Bureau of Sanitation, because the latter involves<lb/>
policing the Zone and the two cities of Colon and Panama. Another<lb/>
department should be the Engineering Department, or Department of<lb/>
construction, under which the work is to be organized and actually<lb/>
don<del>w</del><add>e</add>. It should include the custody of supplies and the care of<lb/>
plant, and the practical operation of the railroad on the Isthmus<lb/>
with the special view to its utilization in canal construction. The<lb/>
Chief Engineer must be the head of this, and is so important a factor<lb/>
in the whole enterprise that he should be given the powers and dig-<lb/>
nity of a member of the commission also. Another, and in many re-<lb/>
spects the most important, department is that which embraces the<lb/>
functions of financing the operations of the Commission, of purchas-<lb/>
ing the supplies, of the accounts and audits, the commercial opera-<lb/>
tions of the Panama Railroad Company and the steamship lines, the<lb/>
general oversight of the work and the duty of reporting the progress<lb/>
of the same through the Secretary of War to the President. The head<lb/>
of this Department should be the Chairman of the Commission. All<lb/>
subordinates in Departments should be appointed by the heads thereof<lb/>
under those provisions of the civil service law which may have been<lb/>
made applicable, and their salaries fixed by same authority, subject<lb/>
to the approval of the Commission, or in the intervals between the<lb/>
meetings of the Commission by the Executive Committee.</p>
<p>An important change from the present condition of affairs should<lb/>
be the transfer of the headquarters of the Commission from Washington<lb/>
to the Isthmus of Panama, where the work is to be done. No meeting<lb/>
of the Commission or executive committee should be held out of the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02757005"/>
-5-<lb/>
Isthmus except by express authority of the Secretary of War. The<lb/>
attention of all engaged in the enterprise will thus be fixed on the<lb/>
work. With the general authority of the executive committee, it will<lb/>
be entirely possible for the work to proceed unhindered without more<lb/>
frequent meetings of the Commission than once a quarter. The Execu-<lb/>
tive Committee should have power to act while the Commission is not<lb/>
in session in the purchase of all supplies, to confirm all officers<lb/>
and employee except heads of departments, and to fix their salaries,<lb/>
and to make contracts for construction. The executive committee thus<lb/>
appointed should keep accurate minutes of its transactions and submit<lb/>
them to the Secretary of War and the Commission, which, having found<lb/>
the same to be within the authority of the committee and executed,<lb/>
shall ratify and confirm them or if unexecuted, may revise them.<lb/>
Contracts for the purchase of supplies or of construction, the esti-<lb/>
mated cost of which may exceed $10,000 should be <del>left</del> let after due<lb/>
public advertisement, upon plans and specifications approved by the<lb/>
executive committee or by the Commission, unless with the approval<lb/>
of the Secretary of War, on grounds of an emergency in a special case,<lb/>
such advertisement be dispensed with. In all other purchases or<lb/>
contracts involving the expenditure of more than $1000, real compe-<lb/>
tition should be invited when practicable. By means of an executive<lb/>
committee constantly in session, the delays incident to awaiting the<lb/>
decision of a large body like the Commission may be avoided, while<lb/>
its examination of the doings of the executive committee every three<lb/>
months and its power to reverse unauthorized acts and to revise every-<lb/>
thing not completely executed, will insure the conservatism sought<lb/>
by the establishment of the larger board.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02757006"/>
<p>-6-</p>
<p>The change of headquarters and power from Washington to the<lb/>
Isthmus will doubtless require a radical change in the office of the<lb/>
Commission in Washington. I am quite sure that greater economy and<lb/>
more satisfactory methods of accounting can be secured than now<lb/>
exist. Machinery for purchase of supplies and a force sufficient<lb/>
to maintain a duplicate set of accounts and the necessary correspond-<lb/>
ence must of course be maintained in Washington, but very little<lb/>
else is needed. But these changes may be safely left to the Commis-<lb/>
sion and executive committee as newly constituted.</p>
<p>I beg to submit herewith the resignations of all the present<lb/>
Canal Commission, to take effect at your pleasure.</p>
<p>I respectfully recommend the appointment of a new Commission and<lb/>
a designation of the Chairman of the Commission, the Governor of the<lb/>
Zone, and the Chief Engineer, and the issuing of an executive order<lb/>
embodying the recommendations herein.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Wm. H. Taft,</signed>
Secretary of War.<lb/>
The President.<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02757007"/>
<seg>Secretary Taft makes the following statement:<lb/>
The President has made an order allowing a salary of $7,500,<lb/>
with travelling expenses, to each member of the Commission, and to<lb/>
the Chairman of the Commission the additional compensation of<lb/>
$22,500; to the Chief Engineer the additional compensation of<lb/>
$17,500, and to the Governor of the Zone the additional compensation<lb/>
of $10,000. The head of each department is allowed the use of a<lb/>
furnished house upon the Isthmus, and his travelling expenses when<lb/>
travelling on the business of the Commission.<lb/>
The total is <unclear>$108,500.</unclear> The salaries and allowances under the<lb/>
former Commission amounted to <unclear>$120,000</unclear>. The total compensation of<lb/>
the Governor of the Zone and the Chief Engineer are in effect un-<lb/>
changed.<lb/>
Professor William H. Burr and Mr. William Barelay Parsons, Civil<lb/>
Engineers, and members of the retiring Commission, will be appointed<lb/>
as members of the Consulting Board of Engineers.</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
