<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02801001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Transcript of letter from Theodore Roosevelt to The White House, April 1, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Roosevelt, Theodore</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02801001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-04-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">The White House</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-04-01">April 1, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02801001</idno>
<title>Transcript of letter from Theodore Roosevelt to The White House, April 1, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Roosevelt reorganizes the Panama Canal Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1905-04-01">
<head>Transcript of letter from Theodore Roosevelt to The White House, April 1, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02801001"/>
<p>THE WHITE HOUSE</p>
<p>Washington, D. C., April 1st, 1905.</p>
<p>The practical result of the operations of the Isthmian Canal<lb/>
Commission appointed and acting under previous executive orders has<lb/>
not been satisfactory and requires a change in the personnel of the<lb/>
Commission and in the instructions for its guidance.</p>
<p>The Commission will held quarterly sessions the first of January,<lb/>
April, July and October of each year at the office of the Governor<lb/>
on the Isthmus of panama, and will continue each session as long as<lb/>
public business may require. Further notice of such meetings shall<lb/>
not be necessary to their regularity. The Commission may hold spe-<lb/>
cial sessions at the call of the Chairman. Four members shall con-<lb/>
stitute a quorum and the action of such majority shall be the action<lb/>
of the Commission.</p>
<p>The Commission, under the supervision and direction of the Sec-<lb/>
retary of War and subject to the approval of the President, is charged<lb/>
with the general duty of the adoption of plans for the construction<lb/>
and maintenance of the canal and with the execution of the work of<lb/>
the same; with the purchase and delivery of supplies; machinery and<lb/>
necessary plant; the employment of the necessary officers, employes<lb/>
and laborers and with the fixing of their salaries and wages; with<lb/>
the commercial operation of the Panama Railroad Company and its<lb/>
steamship lines as common carriers; with the utilization of the rail-<lb/>
road as a means of constructing the canal; with the making of con-<lb/>
tracts for construction and excavation and with all other matters<lb/>
incident and necessary to the building of a waterway aereas the Isth-<lb/>
mus of Panama as provided by the Act of Congress of June 25, 1902.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02801002"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>For convenience, and to secure the uninterrupted course of the<lb/>
work, an Executive Committee of not less than three members of the<lb/>
Commission, shall be appointed by the Commission to act in place of<lb/>
the Commission during the intervals between the meetings of the Com-<lb/>
mission and to report its doings in full to the Commission at the<lb/>
next regular meeting. A minute of every transaction of the Executive<lb/>
Committee shall be made and one copy of the minutes shall be forwarded<lb/>
to the Secretary of War and another transmitted for the consideration<lb/>
of the Commission at its next meeting. Regular meetings of the Exec-<lb/>
utive Committee shall be held at the office of the Governor on the<lb/>
Isthmus of Panama at 10 o'clock in the forenoon on each Monday and<lb/>
Wednesday of every week, and further notice of such meetings shall<lb/>
not be necessary to their legality. A majority of their number shall<lb/>
constitute a quorum for the transaction of business at such meetings.<lb/>
The action of such majority shall be the action of the Executive<lb/>
Committee.</p>
<p>For convenience of executing the work to be done, there shall be<lb/>
constituted three executive departments:</p>
<p>(a) The head of the first department shall be the Chairman of<lb/>
the Commission, who shall have direct and immediate<lb/>
charge of:</p>
<p>1. The fiscal affairs of the Commission;</p>
<p>2. The purchase and delivery of all materials and<lb/>
supplies;</p>
<p>3. The accounts, bookkeeping and audits;</p>
<p>4. the commercial operations in the United States of the<lb/>
Panama Railroad and steamship lines.</p>
<p>5. He shall have charge of the general concerns of the<lb/>
Commission subject to the supervision and direction<lb/>
of the Secretary of War and shall perform such<lb/>
other duties as may be placed upon him from time<lb/>
to time by the Secretary of War.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02801003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>(b) The head of the second department shall be the Governor of<lb/>
the Zone, with the duties and powers indicated in the<lb/>
Executive Order of May 9, 1904, which includes in general:</p>
<p>1. The administration and enforcement of law in the Zone;</p>
<p>2. All matters of sanitation within the Canal Zone and<lb/>
also in the cities of Panama and Colon and the har-<lb/>
bors, etc., so far as authorized by the treaty, the<lb/>
Executive Orders and Decrees of December 3, 1904,<lb/>
between the United States and the Republic of Panama<lb/>
relating thereto;</p>
<p>3. The custody of all supplies needed for sanitary pur-<lb/>
poses, and such construction necessary for sanitary<lb/>
purposes as may be assigned to this Department by<lb/>
the Commission.</p>
<p>4. Such other duties as he may be charged with from time<lb/>
to time by the Secretary of War;</p>
<p>5. He shall reside on the Isthmus and devote his entire<lb/>
time to the service, except <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> when granted leave<lb/>
of absence by the Secretary of War.</p>
<p>(c) The head of the third department shall be the Chief Engi-<lb/>
neer. He shall have full charge on the Isthmus:</p>
<p>1. Of all the actual work of construction carried on by<lb/>
the Commission on the Isthmus;</p>
<p>2. The custody of all the supplies and plant of the<lb/>
Commission upon the Isthmus.</p>
<p>3. The practical operation of the railroad on the Isthmus<lb/>
with the special view to its utilization in canal<lb/>
construction work.</p>
<p>4. He shall reside on the Isthmus and devote his entire<lb/>
time to the service except when granted leave of<lb/>
absence by the Secretary of war.</p>
<p>Appointment of Officers.</p>
<p>All officers and employees shall be appointed and their salaries<lb/>
shall be fixed by the head of the department in which they are engaged.<lb/>
Their appointment and salary shall be subject to the approval either<lb/>
of the Commission, or if the Commission is not in session, of the<lb/>
Executive Committee. The employment of laborers where the contract<lb/>
of employment is made in the United States or outside of the Isthmus<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02801004"/>
-4-<lb/>
shall be negotiated and concluded by the Chairman of the Commission,<lb/>
subject to the approval of the Executive Committee. Where the em-<lb/>
ployment of laborers is effected upon the Isthmus it shall be con-<lb/>
ducted under the supervision of the Chief Engineer, subject to the<lb/>
approval of the Executive Committee.</p>
<p>Contracts.</p>
<p>Contracts for the purchase of supplies or for construction in-<lb/>
volving an estimated expenditure exceeding $10,000 shall only be made<lb/>
after due public advertisement in newspapers of general circulation,<lb/>
and shall be awarded to the lowest responsible bidder, except in case<lb/>
of emergency, when with the approval of the Secretary of War, adver-<lb/>
tising may be dispensed with. In the making of contracts for sup-<lb/>
plies or construction involving an estimated expenditure of more than<lb/>
$1,000 and less than $10,000, competitive bids should be secured by<lb/>
invitation or advertisement whenever practicable.</p>
<p>As soon as practicable after the date of this order, the Isthmian<lb/>
Canal Commission as hereafter constituted shall hold a session in the<lb/>
city of Washington for the general purposes of organization under<lb/>
this order, and for the special purpose of fixing the number and<lb/>
character of officers and employees to serve in the city of Washing-<lb/>
ton in the work of the Commission. The Commission is especially<lb/>
charged with the duty of maintaining a complete system of accounts<lb/>
on the Isthmus, which shall be duplicated in Washington, so that<lb/>
there may always be in Washington the proper means of informing the<lb/>
President, the Secretary of War and the Congress of the amount of<lb/>
work done, the cost of the same, the amount of money available, the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02801005"/>
-5-<lb/>
amount of money expended and the general financial condition of the<lb/>
enterprise.</p>
<p>Board of Consulting Engineers.</p>
<p>There will hereafter be appointed by the President, nine civil<lb/>
engineers of the highest standing, having experience in works of<lb/>
canal construction <add>and</add> hydraulics, to constitute a Board of Consulting<lb/>
Engineers, to which will be submitted by the Isthmian Canal Commis-<lb/>
sion for its consideration and advice the important engineering ques-<lb/>
tions arising in the selection of the best plan for the construction<lb/>
of the canal. The recommendation of the Board of Consulting Engin-<lb/>
eers shall be considered by the Isthmian Canal Commission and with<lb/>
the recommendations of the Commission shall finally be submitted,<lb/>
through the Secretary of War, to the President for his decision.</p>
<p>Reports.</p>
<p>The executive officers of the Commission shall make duplicate<lb/>
reports upon the work and operation of their respective departments<lb/>
to the Secretary of War and the Isthmian Canal Commission from time<lb/>
to time and as often as may he required by the Secretary of War or<lb/>
the Chairman of the Commission.</p>
<p>The Secretary of War will make to the President a report at<lb/>
least annually and as often as he may <unclear>deem</unclear> advisable or the President<lb/>
may require.</p>
<p>All executive orders relating to the subject of the Panama Canal,<lb/>
except so far as they may be inconsistent with the present order,<lb/>
remain in force.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02801006"/>
<p>-6-</p>
<p>Theodore P. Shonts is hereby appointed a member of the Isthmian<lb/>
Canal Commission and its Chairman; Charles E. Magson is hereby ap-<lb/>
pointed a member of the Commission and Governor of the Canal Zone;<lb/>
the appointment as Governor shall take effect upon the date of his<lb/>
arrival on the Isthmus and the resignation of the present incumbent<lb/>
of said office shall thereupon take effect; John F. Wallace is<lb/>
hereby appointed member of the Commission and Chief Engineer; Rear-<lb/>
Admiral Mordecai T. Endicott, U. S. A.; Brigadier-General Peter C.<lb/>
Hains, U. S. A. (Retired); Colonel Oswald H. Ernst, Corps of Engi-<lb/>
neers, U. S. A., and Benjamin M. Harred are hereby appointed members<lb/>
of the Isthmian Canal Commission.</p>
<p>Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
