<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02805001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Rudolph Matas to Howard A. Kelly, April 14, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Matas, Rudolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02805001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-04-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Shannon, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Chaille, S.E.</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Brownsville (Tex.)_</name>
<name type="place">Matamoros (Mexico)_</name>
<name type="place">Mier, Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="publication">The Diary of a Samaritan</name>
<name type="publication">Yellow Fever, Heroes, Honors and Horrors of 1878</name>
<name type="publication">&ldquo;Chita&rdquo; A Memory of the Last Island</name>
<name type="hospital">Charity Hospital [s.l.]</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-04-14">April 14, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02805001</idno>
<title>Letter from Rudolph Matas to Howard A. Kelly, April 14, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Matas provides references on yellow fever, and gives information on his own work and experience with the disease.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-04-14">
<head>Letter from Rudolph Matas to Howard A. Kelly, April 14, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02805001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
DR. RUDOLPH MATAS.<lb/>
2256 ST. CHARLES AVE.<lb/>
TELEPHONE 137.<lb/>
New Orleans, <date value="1908-04-14">April 14th.1905 190___</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Kelly;</salute>
</opener>
<p>While I am looking up some more references to personal<lb/>
letters and other information which may give you the &ldquo;vivid&rdquo;<lb/>
material need for your paper, I would suggest that you look up the<lb/>
following references: &ldquo;1. The diary of a Samaritan by a member of the<lb/>
Howard Association New Orleans, 1878, Published by Harper Bros.<lb/>
2) Yellow Fever, Heroes, Honors and Horrors of 1878 by J.P. Dromgoole,<lb/>
Louisville, Ky. 1879. You might find some suggestive paragraphs in<lb/>
&ldquo;Chita&rdquo; A memory of the last island by Lafcadio Hearn, Harper Bros.<lb/>
New York, 1900, in which you will find something that may interest you<lb/>
on P.162 et seq. This is one of Hearn's most extrordinary books and<lb/>
I am sure you will enjoy reading it any how, for the intense vividness<lb/>
of its portrayal of our Gulf coast and the marsh girt country of the<lb/>
great Delta.</p>
<p>You can, I am sure, find a great many sources of inspiration by<lb/>
looking into the general references on yellow fever epide<del>r</del>miology, etc.,<lb/>
from the from the professional point of view in the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Library; and, on yellow fever bibliography from the laymen's or popular<lb/>
point of view, in the Congressional Library. The majority of the re-<lb/>
ferences that we have in our Howard Library and Fisk Library can be<lb/>
obtained in Washington.</p>
<p>I also enclose a reprint of a paper read at our Parish Society in 1897<lb/>
It simply shows how our eyes were shut to the tr<del>y</del><add>u</add>th even at so late a<lb/>
date as 1897. I reme<add>m</add>ber when I was writing this paper (it was a very<lb/>
hurried affair I assure you) that I thought of embodying a discussion<lb/>
on Finlay's earlier researches on the Mosquito as the agent of trans-<lb/>
mission, which I was the first to translate into English (New Orleans<lb/>
Med'l. &amp; Surg'l. Jn'l.) in 1881 .But in 1897 we were so engrossed with<lb/>
<unclear>San elli</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02805002"/>
DR. RUDOLPH MATAS.<lb/>
2256 ST. CHARLES AVE.<lb/>
TELEPHONE 137.<lb/>
New Orleans,_______________190___<lb/>
Sanarelli and his fascinating paper that we forgot almost evrything<lb/>
else. Of course, the mode of transmission <add>by</add> fomites and atmospheric<lb/>
contamination, referred to so graphically and vividly by Dr. Shannon<lb/>
in his letter to Dr. Bemiss, and which we still believed in in 1897,<lb/>
is curious and not easily explained in the light of past evidence. I<lb/>
have no doubt, however, that the case of Dr. Shannon would have been<lb/>
easily accounted for if the attention of the observers at that time,<lb/>
had been directed to the possibilities of mosquito innoculation. I<lb/>
am now very sorry indeed that my interest in Sanarelli's work in 1897<lb/>
and the brief time at my disposal made me oblivious of Finl<del>e</del><add>a</add>y's great<lb/>
and fundamental work on the mosquito transmission of yellow fever<lb/>
previously referred to. Before closing, I must correct the impression<lb/>
conveyed in your letter that I had any experience in Memphis in 1878<lb/>
I have never visited Memphis except as a transie<add>n</add>t traveller, en<lb/>
route to some other place. My first professional experience with<lb/>
yellow fever in 1878 when I was still an interne in the Charity Hospi-<lb/>
tal where I contracted my second attack of the disease. I again saw<lb/>
yellow fever in Havana in 1879 as an undergraduate and medical clerk<lb/>
of the U.S. Yellow Fever commission (by the bye the report of our<lb/>
Chairman, DR. S. E. Chaille, published by the National Board of Health<lb/>
is a perfect mine of information on all the phases of yellow fever and<lb/>
is, in every sense, a masterful document. I saw the yellow fever for<lb/>
the first time as a graduate of medecine in 1882, during the epidemics<lb/>
which ravaged the Texan frontier on the Rio Grande <del>in 1882</del><add>that were</add> especially<lb/>
attacking Brownsville, Matamoros, and Mier and subsequently had occasion<lb/>
to observe the milder epidemics in New Orleans of 1897-98. The paper<lb/>
which I enclose is an introduction to the symposium on yellow fever<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02805003"/>
AC<lb/>
In to L<lb/>
which was presented to the society in anticipation of the epidemic<lb/>
which soon followed.  When I look at this paper and others and the<lb/>
discussions at that time, I feel like exclaiming &ldquo;Tempora Mutantur,<lb/>
etc&rdquo;. Indeed how the times change!</p>
<p>With best wishes, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very Truly Yours.</salute>
<signed><hi>R.Matas</hi></signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
