<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02821001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Public Health Papers and Reports Volume XXXI Part 1 Presented at the Thirty-third Annual Meeting of the American Public Health Association, Boston, Massachusetts, September 25-29, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02821001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-09-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Liceaga, Eduardo</name>
<name type="place">Boston (Mass.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>23 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-09-25">September 25, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02821001</idno>
<title>Public Health Papers and Reports Volume XXXI Part 1 Presented at the Thirty-third Annual Meeting of the American Public Health Association, Boston, Massachusetts, September 25-29, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Proceedings of the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> meeting of the American Public Health Association, including &ldquo;Lessons to be Learned from the Present Outbreak of Yellow Fever in Louisiana&rdquo; by James Carroll, &ldquo;Some New Points in the Etiology and Symptomatology of Yellow Fever&rdquo; by Juan Guiteras, &ldquo;Yellow Fever in Mexico&rdquo; by Eduardo Liceaga, and the &ldquo;Official Report of the Proceedings....&rdquo;.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="book">
<p></p>
</div1>
<pb n="i" id="f02821001"/>
<titlePage> 
<docTitle> 
<titlePart>PUBLIC HEALTH<lb/>
PAPERS AND REPORTS<lb/>
VOLUME XXXI<lb/>
PART I<lb/>
LIBRARY<lb/>
<unclear>Indexed</unclear><lb/>
S. G. O.</titlePart> 
</docTitle> 
<byline>PRESENTED AT THE THIRTY-THIRD ANNUAL MEETING OF THE<lb/>
American<lb/>
Public Health Association<lb/>
BOSTON, MASSACHUSETTS</byline>
<docDate>SEPTEMBER 25, 26, 27, 28, 29<lb/>
1905<lb/>
LIBRARY<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE<lb/>
MAY-31-<unclear>1905.</unclear><lb/>
-----------<lb/>
193138.</docDate>
<docImprint>COLUMBUS, OHIO:<lb/>
PRESS OF F. J. HEER<lb/>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="chapter" n="1">
<head>LESSONS TO BE LEARNED FROM THE PRESENT OUT-<lb/>
BREAK OF YELLOW FEVER IN LOUISIANA.</head>
<pb n="272" id="f02821002"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>JAMES CARROLL</docAuthor>, ASSISTANT SURGEON, U. S. ARMY, WASHINGTON, D. C.</byline>
<p>&check;</p>
<p>The present seems to be a suitable occasion to invite attention to<lb/>
several points in connection with the epidemic occurrence of yellow<lb/>
fever in the United States at the present as well as at other times. In<lb/>
the discussion of the symposium on yellow fever at the meeting of the<lb/>
Association in Washington, in 1903, the writer called attention<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> to the<lb/>
necessity during the epidemic season for requiring physicians, in cities<lb/>
where yellow fever is prevailing or likely to prevail, to report promptly<lb/>
to the authorities all cases of fever of any kind, coming to their notice.<lb/>
This is necessary in order that there may be no delay in the institution<lb/>
of proper measures to protect the community against extension of the<lb/>
disease if it be yellow fever, for this extension will almost surely take<lb/>
place in the more southern latitudes if the patients are not protected<lb/>
from mosquitoes at the outset. If all cases of undetermined fever were<lb/>
promptly reported and at once protected from mosquitoes<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> it would<lb/>
hardly be possible for the disease to spread if it were yellow fever; on<lb/>
the other hand, where the physician waits for the appearance of black<lb/>
vomit the golden opportunity passes by, for it has been shown that in<lb/>
practically all cases the disease cannot be communicated after the fourth<lb/>
day of the fever. For this reason the diagnosis should be anticipated,<lb/>
and all febrile patients should be immediately protected from mosqui-<lb/>
toes until it is shown by actual demonstration that they are not cases<lb/>
of this disease. Epidemics do not follow every introduction of yellow<lb/>
fever; mosquitoes becoming infected may die before they bite a non-<lb/>
immune, or the patients may happen to be treated in a locality free<lb/>
from <hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>. A group of cases of yellow fever occurring without<lb/>
black vomit usually receives the designation <hi rend="italic">bilious remittent fever</hi>, a<lb/>
diagnosis that should be erased from our text books. Bilious remit-<lb/>
tent fever, acute in type and of short duration, appearing in the United<lb/>
States, is yellow fever, and it should be so regarded. Bilious remittent<lb/>
fever was formerly regarded as a type of malarial remittent, but that</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Report of the Proceedings of the American Public Health Association,<lb/>
Vol. XXIX, p. 291.</p>
<p>Since this paper was read, I have been informed by Dr. E. Liceaga, presi-<lb/>
dent of the Superior Board of Health of Mexico, that the line of procedure<lb/>
indicated is now being followed in his country.</p>
<p>272</p>
<pb n="273" id="f02821003"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN LOUISIANA</hi>.<lb/>
273</p>
<p>was before the use of the microscope was found to be necessary for a<lb/>
positive diagnosis of malarial infection. We know now that malarial<lb/>
fever is not a disease of cities, but of outlying districts, while the<lb/>
bilious remittent fever, so-called, has been recorded in the cities, in<lb/>
epidemic form, and in such intimate association with yellow fever that<lb/>
by some, the diseases were declared identical, and by others, the latter<lb/>
was said to be only a modification of the former. Most interesting<lb/>
and important in this connection is the statement cited by La Roche<hi rend="superscript">3</hi><lb/>
in his chapter on bilious remittent fever, that &ldquo;The morbid appearances<lb/>
revealed on dissection are the same in remittent as in yellow fevers.&rdquo;<lb/>
This statement, however, was not wholly accepted by him, for he calls<lb/>
attention to the bronzed appearance of the liver in certain remittents,<lb/>
a condition that we know results only from malarial pigmentation.<lb/>
Now that we can so easily differentiate malarial remittent and typhoid<lb/>
fevers from yellow fever the diagnosis is much less difficult, except<lb/>
where yellow fever occurs as a complicating infection.</p>
<p>Our confreres in Havana have demonstrated to us that it is possible<lb/>
to prevent the epidemic occurrence of yellow fever, even while occa-<lb/>
sionally admitting cases of the disease into the heart of a city in which<lb/>
the climatic and other conditions are known to be most favorable for<lb/>
its extension in epidemic form, and in which there are more susceptible<lb/>
persons now than ever before. The method suggested here is in many<lb/>
respects similar to, and is based upon, the one adopted during the<lb/>
American occupation of Havana.</p>
<p>Since then it has been sufficiently demonstrated in 1903 and again in<lb/>
1905, that under the lax system heretofore and now in vogue, yellow<lb/>
fever can easily secure a firm foothold in certain of the southern states<lb/>
and escape recognition until it has passed almost completely beyond<lb/>
control. On both the occasions cited the outbreak was suppressed or<lb/>
limited only by the intervention of the general government, which<lb/>
through the energetic action of the United States Public Health and<lb/>
Marine Hospital Service, finally succeeded in checking two epidemics<lb/>
that threatened to become little less than national calamities. Great<lb/>
credit is due to those officials for the success that was attained in spite<lb/>
of the extreme delicacy of the situation and the passive opposition<lb/>
encountered from many quarters.</p>
<p>Our experiences in Cuba have shown that for the exclusion and sup-<lb/>
pression of yellow fever absolute hygienic control is necessary, not<lb/>
only of the people at large but of the patients as well, and especially<lb/>
of the practicing physicians. The aim of modern medicine is the pre-</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">3</hi> Yellow Fever, La Roche, Philadelphia, 1855, Vol. 1, p. 590.</p>
<p>18</p>
<pb n="274" id="f02821004"/>
<p>274<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN LOUISIANA</hi>.</p>
<p>vention of disease rather than its cure, and the safety and welfare of<lb/>
the thousands of persons exposed demand that the proper measures be<lb/>
instituted and rigidly enforced. No valid argument can be brought<lb/>
forward to show why the United States should not be kept as free from<lb/>
outbreaks of yellow fever as the city of Havana, its former endemic<lb/>
home, has been, during the past four years.</p>
<p>To attain this result the following requirements seem to be essential:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Our physicians, or at least those who are in control, must disa-<lb/>
buse their minds of the impression that black vomit necessarily occurs<lb/>
in the majority of cases of yellow fever.</item>
<item>2. During the epidemic season, viz.: from May 1 to October 31, and<lb/>
in the epidemic zone, physicians should be required to report to the<lb/>
health authorities, immediately, all cases of fever of any kind that<lb/>
come under their observation, whether among their patients or not, and<lb/>
failure to do so should be made punishable under the law.</item>
<item>3. The board of health should be authorized to appoint, with proper<lb/>
compensation, a commission of three experts, all of whom should be<lb/>
men of high reputation as diagnosticians. It should be the duty of this<lb/>
commission to visit without delay all cases of fever reported to the<lb/>
health authorities, and the onus of diagnosis should rest upon the com-<lb/>
mission and not upon the attending physicians. They (the commis-<lb/>
sion) should visit each patient daily until the diagnosis is established<lb/>
or the patient sent to a hospital, and they should forward promptly<lb/>
to the health department a written report at each visit. The commission<lb/>
should determine whether or not the patient shall be treated as a possi-<lb/>
ble case of yellow fever and their decision should be final and obligatory<lb/>
upon all concerned.</item>
<item>4. All patients presenting the symptoms of yellow fever, and all<lb/>
cases not diagnosed but remaining under suspicion, should be promptly<lb/>
removed for treatment to a hospital especially located and provided<lb/>
with wire screens and mosquito nets, and the whole or a portion of<lb/>
which has been set apart for that purpose. The yellow fever wards<lb/>
or hospital should be under the direct control of the senior diagnosis<lb/>
commission and the patients should be treated by physicians appointed<lb/>
only on their recommendation and acting under their direction.</item>
<item>5. In exceptional cases, to be determined by the commission, patients<lb/>
under observation awaiting diagnosis could be treated in their homes<lb/>
beneath mosquito netting, and in rooms properly protected with wire<lb/>
screens, until the nature of the case had been finally settled to the sat-<lb/>
isfaction of the commission.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The commission and not the attending physician should be held re-<lb/>
sponsible for the enforcement of all clinical measures necessary for the<lb/>
<pb n="275" id="f02821005"/>
<hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN LOUISIANA</hi>.<lb/>
275<lb/>
protection of the community, and they should be empowered to employ<lb/>
such help as seemed in their judgment to be required. They should<lb/>
also be assisted at times by sub-commissions appointed on their rec-<lb/>
ommendation.</p>
<p>Under such a system, conscientiously carried out, the occurrence of<lb/>
an epidemic of yellow fever in any city would become an impossibility.<lb/>
Objection cannot be made on the ground of expense if the members of<lb/>
the diagnosis commission are paid only for every visit to a patient;<lb/>
under such an arrangement the cost to the city would be trifling when<lb/>
compared with the losses now sustained by individuals and the whole<lb/>
community through the failure of practicing physicians to recognize<lb/>
and report mild cases of the disease. And herein lies the crucial point.<lb/>
The diagnosis must be anticipated and the proper precautionary meas-<lb/>
ures be taken before the disease has fully declared itself. Diagno-<lb/>
ses of malarial remittent, and above all of bilious remittent fever,<lb/>
must not be accepted as conclusive until the presence of malarial<lb/>
or other parasites has been demonstrated to the satisfaction of the<lb/>
members of the diagnosis commission. Attention was called two<lb/>
years ago<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> to the fact that over and over again, since the time of<lb/>
Benjamin Rush, yellow fever has stalked abroad in our cities, un-<lb/>
recognized, under the guise of bilious remittent fever. The time<lb/>
has come when a diagnosis of bilious remittent fever should no longer<lb/>
be accepted for there is no such disease <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>. We may have mala-<lb/>
rial fever complicated with jaundice, but this should not change<lb/>
the diagnosis of malaria any more than an accompanying icterus would<lb/>
change a diagnosis of typhiod fever. Similarly, a complication of mala-<lb/>
ria no longer justifies the diagnosis of typho-malarial fever, and that<lb/>
term has properly been discarded. In numerous instances it is stated in<lb/>
the records of the older epidemics of yellow fever that the disease was<lb/>
preceded by, or began as, a bilious remittent fever, just as in more<lb/>
recent times physicians have believed that typhoid fever began as<lb/>
malarial fever. The conclusion is equally untenable in both cases, and<lb/>
the deduction is obvious that cases of so-called bilious remittent fever<lb/>
must be regarded and treated as cases of yellow fever, unless a satis-<lb/>
factory specific cause for the condition can be demonstrated beyond a<lb/>
doubt. It is proper to mention here, that in every one of the twenty-<lb/>
two cases of yellow fever purposely inoculated by the Army Board in<lb/>
Cuba, a diagnosis of bilious remittent fever would have been justified<lb/>
if it had not been known that they were produced from true cases of</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">4</hi> Journal of the Association of Military Surgeons, 1903, (No. 4), Vol. XIII,<lb/>
pp. 193, 199 and 200.</p>
<pb n="276" id="f02821006"/>
<p>276<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN LOUISIANA</hi>.</p>
<p>yellow fever, for, although some of them were severe, black vomit was<lb/>
absent from all.</p>
<p>It may seem unnecessarily severe to require physicians, under pen-<lb/>
alty, to report all cases of fever coming under their observation, but no<lb/>
other means will attain the desired results, and the enormous interests<lb/>
at stake demand that the methods instituted be thorough and that they<lb/>
be rigidly carried out. The appointment of a board of diagnosis as has<lb/>
been suggested will relieve the attending physician from the odium that<lb/>
accompanies a diagnosis of yellow fever in a doubtful case, and the<lb/>
board, fully appreciating the responsibility that rests upon them, may<lb/>
be relied upon to do their duty. During the discussion upon yellow<lb/>
fever before this Association at its meeting in Washington, two years<lb/>
ago, already referred to, in my remarks, which were badly misquoted,<hi rend="superscript">5</hi><lb/>
I urged the necessity for requiring physicians, under a penalty, to re-<lb/>
port all cases of fever in order that they might be examined by a board<lb/>
of experts (as was done in Cuba), and treated as cases of yellow fever<lb/>
until the diagnosis was established. Only last month in a conversa-<lb/>
tion upon this subject with a physician from a large city in Texas, he<lb/>
laughingly remarked. &ldquo;We never report our cases of yellow fever until<lb/>
we have about a dozen of them!&rdquo;</p>
<p>The present epidemic in and about New Orleans only serves to em-<lb/>
phasize the necessity for such regulations as are here suggested, and<lb/>
this necessity is further emphasized by the statement in the public press<lb/>
of September 5, that &ldquo;Inspector Brady attributed the continued spread<lb/>
of the disease to the unwillingness or inability of physicians to diagnose<lb/>
mild cases of yellow fever, and that physicians of standing and ability<lb/>
look for black vomit before making a diagnosis.&rdquo; I have elsewhere<hi rend="superscript">6</hi><lb/>
cited the occurrence of the same difficulty at Key West in 1899, and<lb/>
I again assert that these physicians may be thoroughly conscientious<lb/>
and able men, but they are baffled by the differences between the aspects<lb/>
of the disease as they actually find it and as they have been taught by<lb/>
the best authorities to expect to find it. It is the manifest duty of local<lb/>
health authorities therefore to relieve the physician of the burden of<lb/>
diagnosis and to leave that and the adoption of protective measures<lb/>
to the board of expert diagnosticians.</p>
<p>In this connection I beg to be permitted to call attention to the pres-<lb/>
ent situation at Jackson Barracks, a station of two batteries of coast<lb/>
artillery, in New Orleans. By the 7th day of the present month a</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">5</hi> Reports of the Proceedings of American Public Health Association, Vol.<lb/>
XXIX, 1904, p. 291.</p>
<p><hi rend="superscript">6</hi> Journal of the Association of Military Surgeons, 1903, Vol. XIII, No.<lb/>
4, p. 201.</p>
<pb n="277" id="f02821007"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN LOUISIANA</hi>.<lb/>
277</p>
<p>number of cases of yellow fever had appeared in the neighborhood and<lb/>
seven of them in a block that approached within one hundred feet of<lb/>
the officers' quarters. Still the garrison has not been removed and up<lb/>
to the present time no single case has occurred among them; even<lb/>
should a case or two appear an epidemic is not feared. The reason<lb/>
for this is simply that the medical officers know that it is absolutely<lb/>
within their power to prevent any epidemic extension of the disease;<lb/>
they are constantly on the alert and all cases of fever are handled in<lb/>
the beginning as though they might be yellow fever.</p>
<p>Again at Fort McIntosh, in Laredo, Texas, in 1903 there were only<lb/>
five cases of yellow fever in a command of one hundred and eleven<lb/>
officers and men, while in the town along side them over one thou-<lb/>
sand cases and more than one hundred deaths occurred. It was found<lb/>
that the five men who became infected had violated orders by visiting<lb/>
the town at night without wearing the prescribed mosquito head-nets,<lb/>
leather gauntlets and leggings.</p>
<p>If, in the presence of cases of yellow fever among and around them,<lb/>
garrisons of soldiers can be protected from the infection in anything<lb/>
like epidemic form, it necessarily follows that the same measures and<lb/>
the same degree of vigilance will protect a community, provided the<lb/>
physicians do their full duty, and they are properly assisted by the<lb/>
authorities. The subject is one involving the lives and interests of<lb/>
thousands of innocent persons and the secret of success lies in eternal<lb/>
vigilance with the determination to allow no case, however mild and<lb/>
doubtful, to escape the fullest precautions.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="2">
<head>SOME NEW POINTS IN THE ETIOLOGY AND SYMPTOM-<lb/>
ATOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER.</head>
<pb n="278" id="f02821008"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>JUAN GUITERAS</docAuthor>, M. D., HAVANA, CUBA.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub H. A 33 meet<lb/>
Boston Sept 1905</p>
<p>&check;</p>
<p>MR. PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF THE ASSOCIATION: -- I am very<lb/>
sorry that I have not a carefully prepared paper to present to the Asso-<lb/>
ciation; but my duties in New Orleans, Pensacola, and through the<lb/>
South, have prevented me. I can therefore only put together some<lb/>
rather desultory remarks concerning new points that have been brought<lb/>
out in the struggle with yellow fever during the present year or by<lb/>
investigators in distant parts.</p>
<p>The French Commission from the Pasteur Institute, working in Rio<lb/>
Janeiro, report that they have produced a case of yellow fever by<lb/>
applying to a non-immune a mosquito that had been raised from eggs<lb/>
laid by an infected mosquito. This brings up the question of the<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever by the progeny of infected mosquitoes.<lb/>
This is entirely a new point and of great interest, as you may well<lb/>
imagine. We thought that we had settled this matter in Havana in<lb/>
the negative. Dr. Carroll, speaking for the American Commission,<lb/>
and myself, speaking for the work I did at Las Animas Hospital, came<lb/>
to the conclusion that this was not so, that is, that an infected mosquito<lb/>
did not transmit infection to its progeny through the eggs. Though<lb/>
neither the American Commission nor myself carried out any special<lb/>
experiments in this direction, our experience, however, in the course<lb/>
of other experiments shows that the mosquitoes raised from infected<lb/>
insects were inoffensive. As a matter of fact, the majority of the<lb/>
mosquitoes we had to deal with, all the <hi rend="italic">Stegomyias</hi> which we worked<lb/>
with in the laboratory at Las Animas Hospital were the progeny of<lb/>
infected mosquitoes. We started with infected mosquitoes and raised<lb/>
generation after generation from them. These were constantly fed by<lb/>
non-immune persons, by assistants in the laboratory, and by several<lb/>
men I had there ready to be bitten by mosquitoes. They were all non-<lb/>
immunes. We did not take any special note of this fact, but, in a<lb/>
general way, we were impressed with the non-transmissibility of the<lb/>
disease through the eggs to the progeny. There is, then, experimental<lb/>
proof of some value against the views of Marchoux and Simond, of<lb/>
the French Commission. Furthermore, these gentlemen have had<lb/>
positive results in one case alone, and, as they were working in infected<lb/>
278<lb/>
<pb n="279" id="f02821009"/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY AND SYMPTOMATOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
279<lb/>
territory, it is quite possible that this man was bitten accidentally by an<lb/>
infected mosquito. There is another argument which I believe is of<lb/>
great importance against the transmission of the disease by the pro-<lb/>
geny. It seems to me it would have been really impossible for us to<lb/>
have eradicated yellow fever as we did in Havana if the views of<lb/>
Marchoux were correct. During the memorable campaign in that<lb/>
city the cases were quite often not seen until the second or third day of<lb/>
the disease, so that they surely had the opportunity of laying eggs<lb/>
before being killed; and the infected mosquitoes that were actually<lb/>
producing infections, they were laying eggs with but little hindrance,<lb/>
for, it must be remembered, that during that campaign the reduction<lb/>
in the number of <hi rend="italic">Stegomyias</hi> in the city was scarcely appreciable.<lb/>
Really, if the French Commission be right, the problem becomes appall-<lb/>
ing, impossible of solution. We got rid of yellow fever in Havana<lb/>
very easily, and at little expense comparatively; this would have been,<lb/>
it appears to me, impossible if the progeny of infected mosquitoes had<lb/>
been also infected.</p>
<p>Another interesting point to which Marchoux and Simond, of the<lb/>
Pasteur Institute, called attention is one that has already been studied<lb/>
in this country. They seem to have ignored our work, or they are not<lb/>
familiar with it. They believe they have discovered a new source of<lb/>
infection of yellow fever in young children affected with mild forms of<lb/>
the disease. This is old. Dr. Blair, of Guiana, a great student of yel-<lb/>
low fever; Dr. Chaill&eacute;, of New Orleans, and myself, in Key West<lb/>
and Havana, have shown previously that this was an important source<lb/>
of infection of yellow fever; that there were a great many cases of<lb/>
mild, unrecognized yellow fever amongst children; and that these were<lb/>
frequently unsuspected sources of infection. In fact, it was a study of<lb/>
this problem of yellow fever in young children in the yellow fever zone<lb/>
that led me to call attention to and to insist upon the fact of the great<lb/>
danger of mild cases of yellow fever. I have been insisting upon this<lb/>
point for many years, not only in the case of young children but also in<lb/>
adults, especially the colored population, who are apt to have mild<lb/>
cases of the disease. These I have always considered as the most dan-<lb/>
gerous transmitters of the infection.</p>
<p>I shall now take up some new diagnostic signs of yellow fever.<lb/>
We are all convinced of the importance of an early diagnosis of<lb/>
yellow fever, and I wish briefly to call attention to points of interest<lb/>
and of importance in enabling us to make an early diagnosis even in<lb/>
mild cases of the disease; of course, acknowledging that there are<lb/>
some cases in which an exact diagnosis is not possible, with our pres-<lb/>
ent means, and without our knowledge of the parasite of the disease.<lb/>
<pb n="280" id="f02821010"/>
280<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY AND SYMPTOMATOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
These special symptoms we have brought out in recent work on yellow<lb/>
fever in Cuba, and which have been confirmed in New Orleans, are:<lb/>
In the first place, a high percentage of hemoglobin in the blood of yel-<lb/>
low fever patients. That is a very important diagnostic sign of the<lb/>
disease, especially as distinguishing it from typhoid fever, malaria and<lb/>
influenza, three diseases that are frequently confounded with yellow<lb/>
fever. In influenza, typhoid fever and malaria, the percentage of hem-<lb/>
oglobin is low -- 70, 75, 80 perhaps. In yellow fever we have a high<lb/>
percentage of hemoglobin, very often 100, sometimes above 100, during<lb/>
the first three, four and five days of the disease, and rarely below 90.<lb/>
If the percentage of hemoglobin should go below 80, and the case<lb/>
should turn out to be one of yellow fever, we find almost always<lb/>
some complication or the patient has been suffering previously from<lb/>
malaria.</p>
<p>Another diagnostic point has been of considerable help to me during<lb/>
the present epidemic, especially in Florida, where we were confronted<lb/>
with the existence of an epidemic of dengue, and where the question<lb/>
came up quite frequently as to whether yellow fever was or was not<lb/>
present. I refer to the diazo-reaction of Ehrlich. The diazo-reaction of<lb/>
Ehrlich is an important diagnostic sign in typhoid fever in the first<lb/>
days of the disease. It may be present in other infectious diseases,<lb/>
but I doubt if it be ever present in uncomplicated yellow fever. On<lb/>
two occasions my mind has been completely relieved as to the exis-<lb/>
tence of yellow fever during the past summer in the South by find-<lb/>
ing the Ehrlich diazo-reaction in the urine. I was able from my ex-<lb/>
perience in Havana to exclude at once yellow fever. The Ehrlich<lb/>
reaction was found occasionally in severe cases of dengue.</p>
<p>Another diagnostic point that I wish to refer to is the albuminuria.<lb/>
We all know that albumin in the urine is a very characteristic symptom<lb/>
of yellow fever, but our judgment should be careful as to the interpre-<lb/>
tation that is to be given to the presence of albumin in the urine. After<lb/>
a careful study in Havana of many kinds of fever, we have found that<lb/>
albumin in the urine is more common in other acute infectious diseases<lb/>
than we thought. Albumin in the urine is common in influenza; it is<lb/>
quite common in typhoid fever; it is not so common, but is occasionally<lb/>
found, in cases of malaria. Albumin is found in the urine in cases of<lb/>
dengue. That is an important point. Some have been inclined to<lb/>
think that as long as we find albumin in the urine we have yellow fever,<lb/>
and not dengue.</p>
<p>The special point I wish to bring out is that the quantity of albumin<lb/>
in yellow fever is entirely out of proportion to the other symptoms<lb/>
present.</p>
<pb n="281" id="f02821011"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY AND SYMPTOMATOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
281</p>
<p>Let us take up the question from the point of view of dengue, which<lb/>
is perhaps the most interesting. If you have a patient taken sick, with<lb/>
a temperature of 104 degrees or more, and if the high temperature<lb/>
should persist for forty-eight hours or longer, you are very apt to find<lb/>
some albumin in the urine in dengue. But in yellow fever such tem-<lb/>
perature is indicative of severe infection. A temperature of 104<lb/>
degrees, lasting over forty-eight hours, in yellow fever, means a very<lb/>
grave case, perhaps a fatal case, and such a patient is sure to have a<lb/>
large quantity of albumin in the urine and to be in a very critical con-<lb/>
dition about the sixth day, when the case of dengue will be getting<lb/>
well. A case of yellow fever beginning with such high temperatures<lb/>
will present the characteristic symptoms in a pronounced manner.</p>
<p>Let me say a few words in connection with the methods of disinfec-<lb/>
tion that are being employed in New Orleans. From the beginning,<lb/>
understand clearly that there is a fundamental distinction to be drawn<lb/>
between the battle that is being fought in New Orleans and the battle<lb/>
that was fought in Havana. There is a fundamental difference between<lb/>
the two problems, and it is this: In Havana we attacked yellow fever<lb/>
at the beginning of the epidemic, a time when it should be attacked<lb/>
always. We began our operations in February. In Havana we had<lb/>
an epidemic of yellow fever, beginning every year in February and<lb/>
increasing in March, April and May, to the full development in August<lb/>
and September. In 1901 we began to attack this epidemic at the begin-<lb/>
ning of February, when there were only two or three cases. On the<lb/>
other hand, in New Orleans they began to attack the disease in the<lb/>
midst of the epidemic. This has never been done successfully, namely,<lb/>
to attack yellow fever and try to stop it in the midst of a great epidemic.<lb/>
This has been done this year in New Orleans, and with wonderful suc-<lb/>
cess. The epidemic has been checked; it has been brought to a stand-<lb/>
still, although the authorities had to attack the epidemic under such<lb/>
unfavorable conditions in the midst of a very large non-immune popu-<lb/>
lation; probably the largest that was ever exposed to yellow fever<lb/>
within the limits of a city. New measures were, therefore, necessary<lb/>
to meet the circumstances and exigencies of the epidemic. In New<lb/>
Orleans they have attempted to destroy all mosquitoes in the city.<lb/>
They are fumigating all houses, whether they contain infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes or not. Housewives have taken charge of this. It is perhaps<lb/>
the only way to deal with the disease under the conditions prevailing<lb/>
in New Orleans.</p>
<p>In Havana, on the other hand, we did not fumigate any houses except<lb/>
those that were infected, and those immediately adjoining. We ap-<lb/>
plied the specific measures for the treatment of epidemics of yellow<lb/>
<pb n="282" id="f02821012"/>
282<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY AND SYMPTOMATOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
fever; we killed the infected mosquitoes, and no others; that is, mos-<lb/>
quitoes about the patients and those which were supposed to have<lb/>
bitten patients.</p>
<p>Now, is it necessary to follow the example of New Orleans? I am<lb/>
a little doubtful. I know that we are not able as yet to draw conclu-<lb/>
sions, but I was rather impressed with the fact that the attempt to do<lb/>
this great thing of disinfection of a city, of killing mosquitoes every-<lb/>
where, rather weakened action against infected mosquitoes. A great<lb/>
deal of energy was spent in fumigating the whole city that perhaps<lb/>
might have been better employed if concentrated upon the infected<lb/>
mosquitoes only.</p>
<p>Another thing noticeable was that, after this great display of energy<lb/>
it was rather discouraging to find that no immediate results followed.<lb/>
The fever did not disappear rapidly. It was very discouraging, and<lb/>
there was an inclination to cast some doubt on the efficacy of the mos-<lb/>
quito doctrine. The final success, however, may justify the process.</p>
<p>Another point to which I desire to call attention as new in the strug-<lb/>
gle against yellow fever is the use of steam under high pressure for the<lb/>
destruction of mosquitoes. That has not been used heretofore. The<lb/>
method was suggested and carried out by Dr. Berry, of the Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service. A fire engine was brought to the houses to be dis-<lb/>
infected, and in certain places which were difficult to seal, as in court-<lb/>
yards and in stairways, a jet of steam was thrown against the walls<lb/>
and about the locality. In this way many insects were destroyed by<lb/>
the direct action of the superheated steam and by the force of the<lb/>
stream mechanically. That is an interesting departure.</p>
<p>Coming to one of the suggestions that was made by Dr. Carroll, as<lb/>
to the existence or appointment of a commission to make a diagnosis<lb/>
of yellow fever, no more important suggestion can be made, and I<lb/>
wish to speak decidedly in favor of it. It is the plan I adopted in<lb/>
Havana during the American intervention. We had such a com-<lb/>
mission then, and it is still in existence. This commission visits<lb/>
all cases of suspicious disease, and the opinion of the commis-<lb/>
sion is final as to whether a case is one of yellow fever or not.<lb/>
There is, however, something more important than this commis-<lb/>
sion, and that is the general education of the people. Take, for<lb/>
instance, such a commission as Dr. Carroll wishes to have ap-<lb/>
pointed. Do you know what would have happened in New Orleans<lb/>
early this spring or this summer if there had been such a commission?<lb/>
The commission would not have been called in to see the suspicious<lb/>
cases. They would have been afraid to call it, because the people were<lb/>
not properly educated. It is necessary to educate the people, so that<lb/>
<pb n="283" id="f02821013"/>
<hi rend="italic">ETIOLOGY AND SYMPTOMATOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</hi>.<lb/>
283<lb/>
the appearance of the first case of yellow fever may be reported at<lb/>
once without causing any excitement. Then, and only then, will capital<lb/>
cease to object to the timely reporting of cases of yellow fever.</p>
<p>It is to be regretted that some commercial interests in the South have<lb/>
thought that it was to their advantage to create the impression that<lb/>
yellow fever had made its appearance in Havana. For a while they<lb/>
succeeded in frightening Galveston and Mobile into quarantining<lb/>
against Havana. It is a pity, because Havana stood as a great object<lb/>
lesson to the South, and just when the South was beginning to believe<lb/>
in and profit from this lesson these foolish people have raised a cloud<lb/>
of doubt around the brilliant results that have been obtained, and are<lb/>
obtaining, in Havana.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1905-09-25">
<head>YELLOW FEVER IN MEXICO.</head>
<pb n="284" id="f02821014"/>
<byline>BY <docAuthor>DR. EDUARDO LICEAGA</docAuthor>, MEXICO CITY, MEXICO.</byline>
<p>Proc Am Pub H. A. - 33 meet<lb/>
Boston Sept 1905</p>
<p>&check;</p>
<p>As in former years, I come to give the Association an account of the<lb/>
course which the yellow fever has taken in the Republic of Mexico<lb/>
from the beginning of the year until the 31st of August, in order to<lb/>
continue thus the report which I brought to the meeting which took<lb/>
place in Havana in the month of January of the present year.</p>
<p>Although at first sight it would seem useless to again present the<lb/>
doctrine of the transmission of yellow fever, which has been accepted<lb/>
by the scientific world, I believe myself obliged to do so, for upon that<lb/>
doctrine is founded the procedure which we are following in Mexico<lb/>
in order to do away with the disease.</p>
<p>In order to transmit the yellow fever the concurrence of these three<lb/>
elements is needed: a yellow fever patient; a mosquito of the genus<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia</hi>, which bites the patient, and a person not immune to receive<lb/>
the bite of the mosquito.</p>
<p>The problem of fighting the yellow fever consist then, in separating<lb/>
these three elements, and I am going to demonstrate the way in which<lb/>
these problems are solved in Mexico.</p>
<p>ISOLATION OF THE PATIENTS.</p>
<p>In order to separate a patient, the first thing to know is that the<lb/>
patient exists, and in order to find him we proceed in the following<lb/>
manner: In each village where there is yellow fever or it is feared<lb/>
that it will develop, we organize a <hi rend="italic">Sanitary Brigade</hi>. Some of its<lb/>
members busy themselves in making a register of all the people who<lb/>
are not immune and who live in the locality. In this register a note<lb/>
is made of the age, sex, and nationality of each person and the place<lb/>
of his residence. The Sanitary Agents who form part of this brigade,<lb/>
divide the city or town, in which the fight is waged against yellow<lb/>
fever in such a way as to be able to visit the non-immunes daily. When<lb/>
one of these is found to have fever, whatever its origin may be, the<lb/>
patient is separated immediately, being put in a room whose windows<lb/>
have been provided with fine wire screens which will prevent the en-<lb/>
trance of the mosquitoes, and a double door also of wire is provided,<lb/>
and so arranged that when the outside door is opened the inside one<lb/>
will automatically close and vice-versa. This can be done by means<lb/>
284<lb/>
<pb n="285" id="f02821015"/>
<hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN MEXICO</hi>.<lb/>
285<lb/>
of a chain of a certain length which unites the two doors. This is<lb/>
much more satisfactory than covering of the beds with mosquito net-<lb/>
ting, for the latter has to be opened frequently in order to observe the<lb/>
patient, to give him medicine, food, etc., and each time the curtain is<lb/>
opened you run the risk of letting a mosquito in, or should the curtain<lb/>
accidentally come in contact with the patient's body the mosquito can<lb/>
bite the patient from the outside of the curtain; whereas if the patient<lb/>
is in a room from which the mosquitoes have been previously driven<lb/>
out, and where they cannot come in again, the contact with the patient<lb/>
is impossible. This means of separation has another advantage, that<lb/>
is, that you may put in the same room a patient who has already been<lb/>
proved to have yellow fever and another whom they only suspect of<lb/>
having it, without the latter being liable to catch the disease.</p>
<p>As we have just seen, in our plan of campaign we do not wait until<lb/>
we are satisfied of the existence of yellow fever, but we isolate the<lb/>
patient from the first day that any fever appears, and consequently we<lb/>
isolate him during the first three days, which are the dangerous ones,<lb/>
and those in which the mosquitoes become infected. Experience has<lb/>
demonstrated the sufficiency of the methods we have adopted for the<lb/>
isolation of the sick.</p>
<p>DISINFECTION OF THE HOME OCCUPIED BY THE PATIENT.</p>
<p>During the time which elapses between the moment in which a<lb/>
person takes the yellow fever and that in which it is discovered by our<lb/>
agent, he may have been bitten by the mosquitoes and infected them,<lb/>
so that they are ready to spread the disease. In order to prevent this<lb/>
danger we proceed to disinfect the house as soon as it is left empty<lb/>
by the patient. The disinfection in this case has for its only object the<lb/>
destruction of the mosquitoes. In order to accomplish this we close<lb/>
the room as it is ordinarily closed, pasting manila paper over all cracks,<lb/>
and after this has been done we proceed to burn sulphur in the pro-<lb/>
portion of twenty grams per the cubic meter of capacity. The sulphur<lb/>
must be spread in a thin layer so that all will be burned. In this prac-<lb/>
tice, which is so common and known to all, we have introduced another<lb/>
innovation which seems to me of great importance, and it is this: As<lb/>
it is very difficult to know whether the disinfection has been complete<lb/>
or not, we take some mosquitoes which have not been infected and<lb/>
which have been taken from the exterior of the room and put them in<lb/>
the farthest room from the one in which the sulphur is burned. These<lb/>
mosquitoes are put in open vessels, or which are only closed with a<lb/>
coarse cloth, so that it will allow the sulphurous acid to penetrate into<lb/>
<pb n="286" id="f02821016"/>
286<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN MEXICO</hi>.<lb/>
the vessel and prevent the mosquito from getting out. These mosqui-<lb/>
toes serve us as witnesses. If, at the close of the disinfection, these<lb/>
mosquitoes which were in unfavorable conditions to suffer from the<lb/>
action of the sulphurous acid are found dead, we have proof that all<lb/>
the others in the same room and under more favorable conditions for<lb/>
receiving the sulphurous acid are dead also. If, on the contrary, we<lb/>
find them alive, it is a proof that the disinfection was not well done<lb/>
and that it will have to be repeated.</p>
<p>Already in the last meeting, I explained the way in which the huts,<lb/>
which in our country are called &ldquo;jacales,&rdquo; are disinfected. I will there-<lb/>
fore not have to repeat it now, and it will be all sufficient to state this<lb/>
fact, that there is not a house which cannot be made perfectly free of<lb/>
the mosquito.</p>
<p>In disinfecting Pullman cars, other railroad cars or any limited space<lb/>
where there are delicate objects which can be damaged we used for-<lb/>
maldehyde.</p>
<p>In dry goods stores, where the sulphur, the pyrethrum and even the<lb/>
formaldehyde might alter the color of the merchandise we have used<lb/>
hydrocyanic acid, the result of which is as satisfactory as that of the<lb/>
sulphur and has not the objectionable effect that this presents of injur-<lb/>
ing the merchandise, but on the other hand it cannot be used except by<lb/>
a person who is very skillful in its use.</p>
<p>DESTRUCTION OF THE MOSQUITO LARVAE.</p>
<p>Another group of the sanitary agents is employed in making a daily<lb/>
house to house inspection of the cisterns which supply the families with<lb/>
water. If the deposit is found to contain larvae it is emptied and the<lb/>
place in which the water flows is covered with petroleum; the deposit<lb/>
is washed and the inside surface is searched in such a way that not a<lb/>
larvae is left alive, then it is filled with pure water and is covered with<lb/>
a close fitting lid, with a wire netting, or with a layer of petroleum.<lb/>
All the other deposits of water are covered with petroleum whatever<lb/>
their size, even when they are very small.</p>
<p>As you have just heard, those methods in which we have introduced<lb/>
innovations over those adopted in other countries are the following:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>I. Making a register of the persons not immune.</item>
<item>II. Visiting the houses daily so that the patient can be discovered<lb/>
the same day that the disease begins.</item>
<item>III. The disuse of the mosquito curtains, because their use is insuf-<lb/>
ficient to isolate the patient and the placing of patients in rooms whose<lb/>
windows are screened and which have double doors of wire netting.<lb/>
<pb n="287" id="f02821017"/>
<hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN MEXICO</hi>.<lb/>
287</item>
<item>IV. In order to convince ourselves that the disinfection has been<lb/>
complete we put mosquitoes in the house under favorable conditions<lb/>
so that they can be reached by the action of the disinfectant. If, at<lb/>
the close of the disinfection the test mosquitoes are dead, we can be<lb/>
sure that the disinfection was well done.</item>
<item>V. We have the means of making impossible the escape of the mos-<lb/>
quito from the disinfected houses even if these are only huts whose<lb/>
walls and roofs are made of grass, or of branches or of any other pen-<lb/>
etrable material.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>To prevent the disease from attacking a place where there are <hi rend="italic">Ste-<lb/>
gomyia</hi>, we have proceeded in the following manner:</p>
<p>In all towns of this class we establish an inspection upon the arrival<lb/>
of the trains, and in other places where passengers reach the town on<lb/>
horseback, on foot or in carriages. Each passenger who is to remain<lb/>
in the locality is examined and is kept under watch by our sanitary<lb/>
agents, or by the police for five days after his arrival. In the places<lb/>
already invaded by the yellow fever, the same inspection is made of all<lb/>
the passengers who take the trains and they are prevented from leaving<lb/>
if they are ill and if they are not immune and have fever. Could not<lb/>
the passengers take the trains between the points where the inspections<lb/>
are made? The sanitary agent travels continually on the trains which<lb/>
traverse the infected districts, which are at present the small towns in<lb/>
the state of Veracruz and the towns traversed by the Tehuantepec<lb/>
Railroad, so that agents travel between Veracruz and Tierra Blanca;<lb/>
from Cordova to Tierra Blanca; from Tierra Blanca to Santa Lucre-<lb/>
cia; from Coatzacoalcos to Santa Lucrecia; from Santa Lucrecia to<lb/>
Tehuantepec and Salina Cruz. If a patient is found on any of these<lb/>
routes he is taken to the nearest hospital and at night the Pullman or<lb/>
railroad car in which the patient traveled is disinfected.</p>
<p>Having thus organized our system of inspection we have followed<lb/>
it in Yucatan, notwithstanding the fact that since the 27th day of the<lb/>
month of November last not a single case of yellow fever has been<lb/>
found either in Merida, in Progreso or in any of the other towns of the<lb/>
state above mentioned. There has not been a single case of yellow<lb/>
fever in Veracruz since December 29th, 1904, up to July 4th of this<lb/>
year. In spite of the vigilance which we have exercised it is possible<lb/>
that a patient who did not arrive by the railroad nor by the most fre-<lb/>
quented roads has clandestinely entered the town and was able to re-<lb/>
main hidden; and as he was not on the <hi rend="italic">Register</hi> he was not visited by<lb/>
the sanitary agent. This is the only explanation which we can give of<lb/>
the appearance of this disease in the harbor of Veracruz. We have es-<lb/>
tablished a sanitary brigade and a lazaret in Tehuantepec, notwithstand-<lb/>
<pb n="288" id="f02821018"/>
288<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">YELLOW FEVER IN MEXICO</hi>.<lb/>
ing the fact that the last case that originated in the town was observed<lb/>
on the 5th of December last, since another case which was found in<lb/>
April 26, was imported from Santa Lucrecia. Another service is estab-<lb/>
lished in Salina Cruz where the last case registered was on October<lb/>
27, 1904. Lastly, in Tierra Blanca where a small focus was formed.<lb/>
Tierra Blanca is a village at the junction of the three branches of the<lb/>
Veracruz and Pacific Railroad. The village is composed of persons<lb/>
not immune who are employes and workmen on the railroad. As the<lb/>
village is cosmopolitan, and very poor and dirty, it has been truly diffi-<lb/>
cult to completely extinguish the disease, and for that reason a brigade<lb/>
has been established there.</p>
<p>In the other places of the small infected zone, when isolated cases<lb/>
appear a physician and sanitary agents of some experience are sent<lb/>
immediately to proceed with the house to house inspection and to dis-<lb/>
infect wherever it is necessary and to destroy the mosquito larvae.</p>
<p>There were 635 cases and 197 deaths registered in the Republic from<lb/>
January 1 to August 31, 1905.</p>
<p>The success which has been reached in Mexico in the struggle against<lb/>
yellow fever and the certainty that in a not far distant future the dis-<lb/>
ease will be completely extinguished as has been done in the island of<lb/>
Cuba, can be easily seen from the statements already made.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="3">
<head>OFFICIAL REPORT OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE THIR-<lb/>
TY-THIRD ANNUAL MEETING OF THE AMERICAN PUB-<lb/>
LIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION.</head>
<pb n="373" id="f02821019"/>
<p>&check;</p>
<p>MONDAY, SEPTEMBER 25, 1905.</p>
<p>The Laboratory Section held its meetings at the Fenway, under the<lb/>
Chairmanship of Dr. Wm. H. Park, of New York.</p>
<p>TUESDAY, SEPTEMBER 26, 1905 -- FIRST DAY.</p>
<p>MORNING SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association met at the Young Men's Christian Association Hall,<lb/>
and was called to order at 10 A. M. by the President, Dr. F. F. Wes-<lb/>
brook, of Minneapolis, Minnesota.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.-- The first order of business is the reading of the<lb/>
minutes of the last meeting.</p>
<p>DR. HENRY D. HOLTON, of Vermont.-- Inasmuch, Mr. President,<lb/>
as these minutes have been printed and probably read by all of the<lb/>
members, I move that the reading of them be dispensed with. Sec-<lb/>
onded by Dr. Montizambert, and carried.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.-- We will now listen to a report of the Executive<lb/>
Committee by the Secretary.</p>
<p>THE SECRETARY.-- The Executive Committee has only to report<lb/>
this morning a list of applicants for membership which has been<lb/>
acted upon by the Executive Committee favorably and recommended<lb/>
to the Association for election.</p>
<p>The Secretary then read a list of the applications for membership<lb/>
which were recommended by the Executive Committee to the Associa-<lb/>
tion for election, and, on motion of Dr. John Guiteras, the Secretary<lb/>
was instructed to cast the unanimous ballot of the Association for the<lb/>
names mentioned, which he did, and they were declared duly elected.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.-- We will now listen to a report by the Chairman<lb/>
of the Local Committee of Arrangements, Dr. Durgin, of Boston.</p>
<p>REPORT OF THE LOCAL COMMITTEE OF ARRANGEMENTS.</p>
<p>DR. SAMUEL H. DURGIN, of Boston.-- Your Local Committee wishes<lb/>
to announce, that on Wednesday morning we had an invitation from<lb/>
373<lb/>
<pb n="444" id="f02821020"/>
444<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-THIRD ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
a very important subject, and we are supposed to take interest in every<lb/>
line of sanitary work, it would seem appropriate to take some action<lb/>
which will go before the public in proper form. I would move, there-<lb/>
fore, Mr. President, that a committee be appointed to present at the<lb/>
next session a resolution expressing the feelings of this Association to<lb/>
the effect that the bill now pending before Congress, and which has been<lb/>
referred to by General Woodhull, be approved by the Association.</p>
<p>The American Medical Association is endeavoring to make itself felt,<lb/>
politically and otherwise, and while perhaps we cannot always agree<lb/>
as to certain things or methods, at the same time, we should express<lb/>
ourselves as a strong body of sanitarians. Perhaps by expressing our-<lb/>
selves in the form of a resolution regarding the bill to which General<lb/>
Woodhull has referred, and which we would all like to see passed, we<lb/>
may gain some advantages in the next ten years.</p>
<p>The resolution was seconded by Dr. Liston H. Montgomery, and was<lb/>
referred to the Executive Committee.</p>
<p>The President appointed on this Committee General Alfred A. Wood-<lb/>
hull, Dr. H. M. Bracken, and Dr. Gardner T. Swarts.</p>
<p>Dr. James Carroll, of Washington, D. C., then read a paper entitled<lb/>
&ldquo;The Lessons to be Learned from the Present Outbreak of Yellow<lb/>
Fever in Louisiana.&rdquo; (See paper, page 272.)<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>Dr. Eduardo Liceaga, of Mexico, read a paper on &ldquo;Yellow Fever in<lb/>
Mexico.&rdquo; (See paper, page 284.)</p>
<p>Dr. Juan Guiteras, of Havana, Cuba, followed with &ldquo;Remarks on<lb/>
Some New Points in the Etiology and Prevention of Yellow Fever.&rdquo;<lb/>
(See paper, page 278.)<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>At the conclusion of the reading of the papers on yellow fever, the<lb/>
Committee, appointed to draft resolutions in connection with yellow<lb/>
fever in the South, presented the following report, which was referred<lb/>
to the Executive Committee:</p>
<p>WHEREAS, The results obtained during the present epidemic of yel-<lb/>
low fever in New Orleans, by the methods of mosquito extermination<lb/>
and by the prevention of the access of the mosquito to the patients,<lb/>
have been far in advance of the results obtained by the older methods;</p>
<p>WHEREAS, It has been possible by the new methods to hold in check<lb/>
and to gradually reduce an epidemic that has taken a firm foothold in<lb/>
the midst of the largest non-immune population that was ever exposed<lb/>
to yellow fever; therefore, be it</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, (1) That the Association sees in these results a further<lb/>
confirmation of the view that yellow fever is naturally transmitted<lb/>
only by the bite of an infected mosquito.</p>
<p>(2) That the Association is of opinion that an efficient plan of<lb/>
<pb n="445" id="f02821021"/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-THIRD ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
445<lb/>
defense against the propagation of yellow fever, at the beginning of<lb/>
an epidemic, can be easily established upon the basis of this doctrine.</p>
<p>(3) That the successful carrying out of such plans depends upon<lb/>
a thorough understanding of the mosquito doctrine by the people, and<lb/>
the support that they may give to the prompt and frank reporting and<lb/>
to the proper handling of the first cases and of all suspicious cases.</p>
<p>(4) The Association wishes further to congratulate the Public<lb/>
Health and Marine Hospital Service for the brilliant work done by<lb/>
Dr. Joseph H. White and his colleagues in New Orleans, and to urge<lb/>
upon all concerned that the said service be called upon to take charge<lb/>
permanently of maritime quarantine along the Gulf Coast.</p>
<p>Regarding the visit of the President to New Orleans, the Associa-<lb/>
tion would urge that the contemplated trip be postponed.</p>
<p>Whilst it is true that the epidemic will be very much under control<lb/>
by the 24th of October, so that there will be but little danger of infec-<lb/>
tion, this danger would certainly be enhanced by the public life and<lb/>
inability to surround themselves with proper safeguards that would<lb/>
prevail in the case of the President. If the President were called to<lb/>
New Orleans by some public duty connected with the epidemic -- if<lb/>
he were, for instance, to reside in the yellow fever hospital and have<lb/>
some special duty to perform in visiting the sick -- it would be very<lb/>
easy to guarantee his safety from infection; but with a number of<lb/>
public functions to perform, entertainments to receive, and numerous<lb/>
places to visit, the Association does not believe that an absolute secu-<lb/>
rity can be promised at a time when there may still be in existence a<lb/>
number of active, infected mosquitoes.</p>
<p>The Association is also of opinion that the large influx of strangers<lb/>
that would attend the visit of the President would result in a tem-<lb/>
porary increase of the number of cases.</p>
<p>(Signed) JOHN GUITERAS, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>,</p>
<p>PRESTON H. BAILHACHE,</p>
<p>JAMES CARROLL,</p>
<p>E. LICEAGA,</p>
<p>WM. BAILEY.</p>
<p>DISCUSSION OF THE PAPERS ON YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>DR. LISTON H. MONTGOMERY, of Chicago.-- Dr. Guiteras in his re-<lb/>
marks spoke of the authorities in New Orleans trying to exterminate<lb/>
every mosquito, but he thought, if I understood him correctly, that this<lb/>
detracted considerably from their work, and that they should concen-<lb/>
trate their action or attack upon the infected mosquito. How can that<lb/>
be determined? Would it not be better to exterminate all mosquitoes,<lb/>
whether they are the harmless or infected ones?<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>DR. JOHN GUITERAS, of Havana, Cuba.-- I expressed the idea that<lb/>
considerable energy was being diverted from the proper and best chan-<lb/>
nels. In answer to the question of Dr. Montgomery, I will say that it<lb/>
<pb n="446" id="f02821022"/>
446<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-THIRD ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
is easy to determine which are infected mosquitoes from those that are<lb/>
not. Infected mosquitoes are those found in the houses of patients, and<lb/>
we should kill them. The yellow fever mosquito is a weak mosquito; it<lb/>
is apt to stay in the same room, and certainly in the same house.</p>
<p>DR. JAMES CARROLL, of Washington, D. C.-- Dr. Guiteras has taken<lb/>
it for granted, without full justification, it seems to me, that my idea<lb/>
was that this commission I have suggested should go down and stamp<lb/>
out such an epidemic as prevails in New Orleans at present. I intended<lb/>
nothing of the kind. I spoke of preventive rather than curative meas-<lb/>
ures, and the idea I had in my mind was that if a commission, appointed<lb/>
at the proper time, could take up the work in a proper way and prevent<lb/>
or control the extension of the disease, at the season when the cases<lb/>
were fewest, it would accomplish a great deal. This measure was sug-<lb/>
gested by me upon the ground that if such a commission were in exist-<lb/>
ence, and the proper laws were enacted, it would require physicians to<lb/>
report their cases of yellow fever early, so that the disease could be<lb/>
readily controlled, and then there would be no possibility of its further<lb/>
extension.</p>
<p>In regard to educating the people, did we wait for their education<lb/>
before laws were enacted requiring proper disinfection to prevent the<lb/>
extension of diphtheria? It has taken five years, and that has not been<lb/>
sufficiently long to educate the physicians in some of our states up to the<lb/>
point of believing in the mosquito theory fully, and it seems to me it<lb/>
would be much less important to wait for the education of the people<lb/>
when it takes some physicians more than five years to accept the mos-<lb/>
quito theory. Reasoning on this basis, how many more years will it<lb/>
require to educate the people up to that point? This is a matter of<lb/>
protection of the lives and welfare of the people, and their personal ideas<lb/>
and idiosyncrasies are not to be considered. We know absolutely that<lb/>
if these measures are taken in proper time, any extension of the disease<lb/>
can be prevented, and the only thing to do, in my opinion, is to take<lb/>
such measures and thereby see to it, when the disease is found to exist,<lb/>
or when the cases are at a low ebb, that proper measures are taken, and<lb/>
that the possibility of any further extension of the disease be removed.<lb/>
In this way the disease can be eventually stamped out, and once it is<lb/>
stamped out, it is done with forever unless there is a fresh importation.</p>
<p>On motion, the Association adjourned until 10 A. M., Friday.</p>
<pb n="447" id="f02821023"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">PROCEEDINGS -- THIRTY-THIRD ANNUAL MEETING</hi>.<lb/>
447</p>
<p>SEPTEMBER 29 -- FOURTH DAY.</p>
<p>MORNING SESSION.</p>
<p>The Association met at 10:10 A. M., and was called to order by the<lb/>
President.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.-- We will listen to the Report of the Executive<lb/>
Committee by the Secretary.</p>
<p>THE<unclear>.</unclear> SECRETARY.-- The Executive Committee has acted favorably<lb/>
upon the resolutions in regard to yellow fever in New Orleans, except<lb/>
as regards advising the President not to visit that city, and recommends<lb/>
their adoption by the Association A sub-committee will report upon<lb/>
this part of the resolutions. (See resolutions on page 444.)</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.-- You have heard the recommendations of the Ex-<lb/>
ecutive Committee concerning these resolutions on yellow fever. What<lb/>
is your pleasure?</p>
<p>DR. WILLIAM BAILEY, of Louisville, Kentucky.-- I move that the<lb/>
resolutions be adopted. Seconded and carried.</p>
<p>The Secretary read a resolution offered by Dr. J. Ewing Mears (see<lb/>
resolution, page 424), and said: The Executive Committee finds that a<lb/>
similar resolution was recently adopted by the Association, and there-<lb/>
fore it deems it unnecessary to take further action at this time.</p>
<p>THE PRESIDENT.-- Will you confirm the action of the Executive<lb/>
Committee, or do you wish to adopt this resolution?</p>
<p>DR. HENRY D. HOLTON.-- I move that the action of the Executive<lb/>
Committee be concurred in.</p>
<p>Seconded by Professor Brewer, and carried.</p>
<p>THE SECRETARY.-- The following resolution are offered as repre-<lb/>
senting the sense of the American Public Health Association:</p>
<p>RESOLVED, That this Association, recognizing the extreme value of<lb/>
a properly organized and efficiently administered medical department<lb/>
as an essential part of any army, cordially approves the proposal for<lb/>
the greater efficiency of that department in the army of the United<lb/>
States, as embodied in a bill brought before the fifty-eighth Congress<lb/>
(Senate, 4838; H. R., 13998, fifty-eighth Congress, second session),<lb/>
and earnestly recommends favorable action upon such a measure when<lb/>
it may again be brought up for consideration;</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That an official copy of these resolutions be transmitted<lb/>
to the committees on military affairs of the Senate and of the House<lb/>
of Representatives of the United States, and to the surgeon-general,<lb/>
United States army.</p>
<p>(Signed) ALFRED A. WOODHULL,<lb/>
H. M. BRACKEN,<lb/>
GARDNER T. SWARTS,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Committee</hi>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
