<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02824001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry M. Hurd to Howard A. Kelly, November 13, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hurd, Henry M.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02824001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-11-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="place">Minnesota</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">North East Harbor (Wash.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-11-13">November 13, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02824001</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry M. Hurd to Howard A. Kelly, November 13, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hurd writes with suggestions for changes to Kelly's manuscript on the life of Walter Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-11-13">
<head>Letter from Henry M. Hurd to Howard A. Kelly, November 13, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02824001"/>
<opener>
Form 135-10,000-5-31-1905.<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
<dateline>
THE JOHNS HOPKINS HOSPITAL,<lb/>
NORTH BROADWAY.<lb/>
Baltimore, <date value="1905-11-13">November, 13th, 1905 190</date>
</dateline>
HENRY M. HURD, M. D.<lb/>
Superintendent.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Kelly:--</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have gone over the Reed manuscript very care-<lb/>
fully, and find it admirable even in its present imperfect form. When<lb/>
it is fully prepared for the press, I should like to look over it again,<lb/>
not with the idea of making corrections as to form and style (I think<lb/>
too much of that has already been done by Miss Scott), but with the<lb/>
idea of making certain suggestions as to omissions and additions. I<lb/>
would now make the following suggestions:</p>
<p>1. Omit all names where Reed in private letters speaks dis-<lb/>
paragingly, critically or freely of other physicians. To<lb/>
publish the names of Sternberg, Guiteras and others can<lb/>
only wound and injure his memory without doing any good.</p>
<p>2. I think it should be noted that Dr. Reed left his work in<lb/>
Dr. Welch's laboratory to go west to Minnesota, and was<lb/>
present at the Battle of Wounded Knee, where the Ghost<lb/>
Dancers had stirred up a serious rebellion. I am sure<lb/>
that he wrote some graphic account of his experiences then.<lb/>
I know that he told of them in a most interesting way.<lb/>
The spirit and energy which he displayed at that time show-<lb/>
ed that laboratory work did not unfit a man for the active<lb/>
duties of an army surgeon.</p>
<p>3. I would mention Reed's great anxiety at the outbreak of<lb/>
the Spanish-American War to hold some responsible position<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02824002"/>
Form 135-10,000-5-31-1905.<lb/>
THE JOHNS HOPKINS HOSPITAL,<lb/>
NORTH BROADWAY.<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
HENRY M. HURD, M.D.<lb/>
Superintendent.<lb/>
Baltimore,____________________190<lb/>
#2.<lb/>
in charge of sick soldiers. He knew that his experience<lb/>
had fitted him to undertake this work, and was familiar<lb/>
with the conditions of the army, the routine of getting<lb/>
supplies, the manner of preserving the health of soldiers,<lb/>
and general management, practical matters which were un-<lb/>
known to civilian physicians and political doctors who<lb/>
were appointed to responsible positions over him. He made<lb/>
a strong effort to secure some responsible position, for<lb/>
which years of army work had admirably fitted him, and<lb/>
was chagrined and distressed that men with political pull<lb/>
were preferred, while he and other practical army surgeons<lb/>
were relegated to other unimportant positions.</p>
<p>4. In a conversation with me after the War was over, he spoke<lb/>
with extreme sadness of the fact that, by such mismanagement<lb/>
on the part of the Secretary of War and others who should<lb/>
have known better, the Army Medical Corps had been subjected<lb/>
to a censure which it did not deserve. To use his own<lb/>
words, &ldquo;the Army Medical Corps received a &ldquo;black eye&rdquo; be-<lb/>
cause of the neglect and incompetence of men who really<lb/>
did not belong to it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>5. In the Yellow Fever chapter I would add a full account of<lb/>
the late epidemic at New Orleans, in order to complete the<lb/>
yellow fever history and as an illustration of the way in<lb/>
which the epidemic was controlled by due attention to the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02824003"/>
Form 135-10,000-5-31-1905.<lb/>
THE JOHNS HOPKINS HOSPITAL,<lb/>
NORTH BROADWAY.<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
HENRY M. HURD, M. D.<lb/>
Superintendent.<lb/>
Baltimore,____________________190<lb/>
#3.<lb/>
facts brought out by Reed's &ldquo;mosquito theory&rdquo;.</p>
<p>6. I think also I would give a full account of the methods em-<lb/>
ployed in New Orleans to destroy mosquitoes and to screen<lb/>
cisterns, and for historical completeness I would add some<lb/>
account of the present method of treating the disease.<lb/>
There is every reason to think that the epidemic was more<lb/>
successfully treated in New Orleans during the past summer<lb/>
than any previous epidemic. The mortality was smaller and<lb/>
the convalescence of patients who survived was more speedy.<lb/>
Local physicians insisted that these improved conditions<lb/>
were due to improved methods of treatment.</p>
<p>7. I would give an account of the work of the Typhoid Commiss-<lb/>
ion composed of Reed, as Chairman, Shakespeare and Vaughan.<lb/>
Upon this Commission Reed did most important work, as shown<lb/>
by the late elaborate report which has appeared under the<lb/>
names of Reed, Shakespeare and Vaughan, although finally<lb/>
written by Vaughan. There must be some record in the Army<lb/>
Reports of the amount of preliminary work which Reed did. I<lb/>
know he went about extensively, visiting camps and also col-<lb/>
lected a large amount of material.</p>
<p>8. I think also there should be in the volume somewhere, prob-<lb/>
ably at the end, a strong appeal for the reorganization of<lb/>
the Army Medical Corps, in the light of experiences in Cuba.<lb/>
In Cuba, it will be remembered, the Army Medical Corps in<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02824004"/>
Form 135-10,000-5-31-1905.<lb/>
THE JOHNS HOPKINS HOSPITAL,<lb/>
NORTH BROADWAY.<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
HENRY M. HURD, M.D.<lb/>
Superintendent.<lb/>
Baltimore,____________________190<lb/>
#4.<lb/>
hygienic and sanitary matters was entirely subordinated to<lb/>
the will of ignorant, incompetent or indifferent military<lb/>
officers. The Army Surgeon could recommend, but he had<lb/>
no authority to carry out his recommendations. This, in<lb/>
fact, was General Sternberg's excuse for permitting disease<lb/>
to ravage the camps -- that he was powerless to enforce clean<lb/>
camps, good drinking water and adequate sanitary arrangements<lb/>
because of the lack of co-operation on the part of the mili-<lb/>
tary men. These things could only be secured when the mili-<lb/>
tary commander was willing to order the work to be done. If<lb/>
he was not willing, the surgeon had no power.</p>
<p>9. I think it would be well to publish a chapter containing an<lb/>
account of the meetings held at North East Harbor, Washing-<lb/>
ton and elsewhere to raise funds for a statue and for the<lb/>
family of Dr. Reed. Some of the best men of the nation<lb/>
spoke and co-operated in the movement, and I think it would<lb/>
be of great interest to have a statement of the fact.</p>
<p>In conclusion, I would add that I have been much interested<lb/>
in your book, and I congratulate you upon its success in its present<lb/>
form. I believe that the book will do a lot of good.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry M. Hurd</signed>
add ref to <unclear>Nuttalls</unclear> appreciation in Jour. Hygiene
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
