<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02841005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report to the Surgeon General, by James Carroll, August 18, 1906</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carroll, James</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02841005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1906-08-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Surgeon General</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="person">Havard, Valery</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Wasdin, Eugene</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Ross, John W.</name>
<name type="person">Rosenau, M. J.</name>
<name type="person">Geddings, Henry Downes</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Havana)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1906-08-18">August 18, 1906</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02841005</idno>
<title>Report to the Surgeon General, by James Carroll, August 18, 1906</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carroll gives a detailed report about his involvement with the yellow fever project in Cuba and the necessity of having human volunteers. He also provides a listing of his publications. Included are notes by Truby. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1906-08-18">
<head>Report to the Surgeon General, by James Carroll, August 18, 1906</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02841005"/>
<opener>
OFFICE OF SURGEON GENERAL<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear><lb/>
No.1<lb/>
Z<lb/>
19928<lb/>
<unclear>1906</unclear><lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT<lb/>
Army Medical Museum,<lb/>
Washington,<lb/>
August 18, 1906.<lb/>
<lb/>
1 Lieut. James Carroll,<lb/>
Asst Surgeon, U. S. A.,<lb/>
Curator.<lb/>
<lb/>
Makes detailed report<lb/>
of his connection with<lb/>
the board convened on the<lb/>
Island of Cuba for the in-<lb/>
vestigation of yellow fever.<lb/>
(17 enclosures)<lb/>
<lb/>
File with<lb/>
memo for the Presi-<lb/>
dent-<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear><lb/>
1-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02841006"/>
WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON GENERAL,<lb/>
ARMY MEDICAL MUSEUM AND LIBRARY,<lb/>
WASHINGTON.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1906-08-18">August 18, 1906.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
To the<lb/>
Surgeon General, U. S. Army.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>In accordance with the desire of the Surgeon General,<lb/>
expressed in letter of August 17, 1906, I have the honor to submit<lb/>
the following statement:</p>
<p>In July, 1897, I was assigned with Major Reed to the work<lb/>
of studying and reporting upon Sternberg's Bacillus X, and in Sept-<lb/>
ember we were given a culture of Sanarelli's Bacillus icteroides which<lb/>
he had reported to be the cause of yellow fever. At this time I was<lb/>
on duty at the Army Medical School, assisting Major Reed. I held the<lb/>
grade of Hospital Steward, was a graduate in medicine and had spent<lb/>
about five years in bacteriological and pathological work exclusively<lb/>
after having taken special post graduate courses in those subjects at<lb/>
the Johns Hopkins.</p>
<p>Our first publication was A Preliminary Note (see enclosure<lb/>
A, from The Medical News, New York, April 20, 1899) in which the striking<lb/>
resemblances between Bacillus icteroides of Sanarelli and the Bog Cholera<lb/>
bacillus were brought out. This called forth contradiction from Prof.<lb/>
Sanarelli (Medical News, N. Y., August 12, 1899), to which a reply was<lb/>
made after additional work confirming our first opinion (see enclosure<lb/>
B, A Reply to Dr. G. Sanarelli, Medical News, N. Y., Sept. 9, 1899.).<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02841007"/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
The work was continued, with many interruptions incident to the<lb/>
Spanish American War, and the final and decisive report was com-<lb/>
pleted in February, 1900, and published in the Journal of Experi-<lb/>
mental Medicine in December of that year. (Copy marked enclosure C).<lb/>
In the mean time the claims of Sanarelli for Bacillus icteroides as<lb/>
the specific cause of yellow fever were sustained by several inves-<lb/>
tigators, among the most important of whom were Drs. Wasdin and Ged-<lb/>
dings of the Marine Hospital Service, who, in an elaborate and sensa-<lb/>
tional report of almost 100 pages, pronounced B. icteroides the cause<lb/>
of yellow fever and claimed to be able to infect dogs, monkeys, rabbits,<lb/>
mice and other animals with yellow fever by inoculations with it.</p>
<p>Such was the status of the question when, in May, 1900, on the<lb/>
recommendation of Surgeon General Sternberg, an order was issued con-<lb/>
vening a board of Army Medical Officers on the Island of Cuba for the<lb/>
investigation of yellow fever, which was at that time epidemic in<lb/>
Havana. Major Reed and the undersigned sailed from the United States,<lb/>
reaching Havana June 25, 1900, and the board, which consisted of Major<lb/>
Walter Reed, Surgeon, Drs. James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear and Aristides<lb/>
Agramonte, was convened on the following day in obedience to Par. 34,<lb/>
S. O. 22, A. G. O., May 24, 1900. Work was begun immediately and<lb/>
after a careful study of 18 cases of yellow fever with failure to dis-<lb/>
cover a single specimen of Bacillus icteroides the result was regarded<lb/>
as conclusive evidence that B. icteroides was <hi>not</hi> the cause of yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f02841008"/>
<p>-- 3 --</p>
<p>Early in the month of August it was decided to test the mosquito<lb/>
theory advanced by Dr. Finlay, and since man is the only animal known<lb/>
to suffer from yellow fever, there was no alternative but to make the<lb/>
tests upon human beings. The question arose of the tremendous respons-<lb/>
ibility of such an undertaking which could only be justified by the<lb/>
enormous saving of life that would follow the establishment of the theory,<lb/>
even should one or several lives be sacrificed in the course of the work.<lb/>
The best atonement we could offer for endangering the lives of others was<lb/>
to take the same chances ourselves, and it was agreed by Dr. Reed, Dr.<lb/>
Lazear and myself that experiments should be undertaken and that we would<lb/>
all be bitten by contaminated mosquitoes. <hi>Dr. Agramonte was kept in en-<lb/>
tire ignorance of this part of the work by direction of Major Reed, as I<lb/>
have written evidence to show, until after the first set of experiments<lb/>
was completed and the report of them compiled for publication</hi>. Dr. Reed<lb/>
left for the United States about August <hi>fourth</hi><unclear><add>2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></add></unclear>, 1900, and the experiments<lb/>
were begun by Dr. Lazear, the only member of the board who had had any<lb/>
previous experience with mosquitoes. It was my part to continue the<lb/>
bacteriological investigations as before. After nine unsuccessful at-<lb/>
tempts to inoculate persons, including himself and one other medical of-<lb/>
ficer, Acting Assistant Surgeon Pinto, <hi>Dr. Lazear</hi> succeeded in infecting<lb/>
me with a single mosquito applied <hi>July</hi><add>August</add> 27th, 1900, and upon the day that<lb/>
I was taken sick, <hi>July</hi><add>August</add> 31st, <hi>he</hi> applied the same insect, with others, to<lb/>
a soldier, who after six days was down with yellow fever. On Sept. 13th<lb/>
Dr. Lazear himself was bitten by a stray mosquito in Las Animas Hospital;<lb/>
AET<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02841009"/>
- 4 --<lb/>
he sickened Sept. 18th and died Sept. 25th, 1900, a martyr to the cause.<lb/>
<hi>Major Reed returned Oct. 1st<add> 4</add>, 1900, wrote the report</hi> and presented it<lb/>
at Indianapolis Oct. 22-26, 1900. (See The Etiology of Yellow Fever, A<lb/>
Preliminary Note, Proceedings of The American Public Health Association,<lb/>
meeting held in October 1900, copy marked D enclosed). I left Cuba for<lb/>
the United States about October 11th, 1900, on sick leave for one month,<lb/>
to recuperate, and returning about Nov. 11th took charge of the infected<lb/>
mosquitoes used in subsequent experiments, participating in the general<lb/>
work and devoting special attention to the microscopic study of the blood<lb/>
of cases of yellow fever. The results obtained at Havana up to March<lb/>
1st, 1901, were reported in the Journal of the American Medical Associa-<lb/>
tion, Feb. 16, 1901 (enclosure E) and in American Medicine July 6, 1901<lb/>
enclosure F). Dr. Agramonte was relieved from the board early in the<lb/>
summer of 1901.</p>
<p>In the beginning of August, 1901, the undersigned returned<lb/>
to Cuba, under orders, alone, for the purpose of making certain experi-<lb/>
ments bearing upon the causative agent of yellow fever. Dr. John<lb/>
Guiteras, of Havana, had made unsuccessful attempts at inoculation<lb/>
throughout the summer and his first case was taken sick on the day<lb/>
of my arrival. This was followed by six other experimental cases,<lb/>
among them Miss Maas, an American woman nurse, who, with two others<lb/>
of the seven, died. Dr. Guiteras declined to permit me to use his<lb/>
cases for my work, and after the conclusion of his work I obtained<lb/>
some of his infected mosquitoes through the courtesy of Col. Havard,<lb/>
Chief Surgeon, and proceeded to inoculate. The experiments were<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02841010"/>
-- 5 --<lb/>
brought to a successful conclusion after the inoculation of six per-<lb/>
sons with yellow fever, all of whom recovered. In this work it was<lb/>
shown for the first time that the specific cause of yellow fever was<lb/>
sufficiently minute to pass through a new Barkefeld filter capable of<lb/>
holding back the smallest of the ordinary known bacteria, and it was<lb/>
further shown, for the first time, that the infectious power of yellow<lb/>
fever blood was completely destroyed by a temperature of 55&deg;C. (See<lb/>
enclosure G, from American Medicine, Feb. 22, 1902.). These results,<lb/>
as well as the other findings of the board, were all confirmed in the<lb/>
following year by Messrs. Marchoux, Salimbeni and Simond, a commission<lb/>
from the Pasteur Institute at Paris, who were working in Brazil. The<lb/>
accompanying photograph of a cartoon, <add>(Enclosure J)</add> with Dr. Ross as the central figure,<lb/>
taken from a daily paper, shows the state of public feeling in Havana<lb/>
after the death of Dr. Guiteras' cases and before my first case was in-<lb/>
oculated. It is worthy of note that this work was begun by me against<lb/>
the protests of Dr. John Guiteras and Dr. Charles Finlay of Havana, and<lb/>
of Dr. Ross, U. S. Navy, retired, then Director of Las Animas Hospital,<lb/>
where I was quartered. I was convinced that with selected individuals,<lb/>
properly treated, the work could be done with comparative safety. I wish<lb/>
to make acknowledgment here of the strong and cordial support accorded<lb/>
me by Col. Valery Havard, the Chief Surgeon, and without which the re-<lb/>
sults could not have been accomplished.</p>
<p>Through the courtesy of Dr. Gorgas I enjoyed the privilege<lb/>
on this occasion of making a post mortem examination of the first fatal<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02841011"/>
-- 6 --<lb/>
case of Dr. Guiteras' series, and was thus able to show that the<lb/>
lesions present in the experimental cases were identical with those<lb/>
found in naturally infected cases of yellow fever.</p>
<p>In March, 1903, there was issued from the Yellow Fever In-<lb/>
stitute of the U. S. Public Health and Marine Hospital Service the<lb/>
report of a commission of medical officers entitled Working Party<lb/>
No. 1, who described a protozoanparasite found in infected yellow<lb/>
fever mosquitoes and which they regarded as of importance in connec-<lb/>
tion with the disease (see page 31 of the report). In October of<lb/>
the same year the undersigned reported before the meeting of the<lb/>
American Public Health Association at Washington, D. C., that the<lb/>
supposed protozoan parasites were yeast cells derived from the bananas<lb/>
upon which they had been fed and proved it by demonstrating these bodies<lb/>
in a number of mosquitoes by feeding to them pure cultures of yeast<lb/>
isolated from bananas. <add>(See enclosure <unclear>H</unclear> and enclosure M.)</add> These results were gracefully and frankly<lb/>
acknowledged by Dr. M. J. Rosenan, of the same service, in 1904. (See<lb/>
page 1 of Bulletin No. 14 of the Yellow Fever Institute, the report<lb/>
of Working Party No. 2, U. S. Public Health and Marine Hospital Service,<lb/>
Washington, May 1904, enclosure I.).</p>
<p>The following publications on the subject of yellow fever have<lb/>
been written by me apart from the conjoint publications of the Army<lb/>
Board, viz:-</p>
<p>1. The Treatment of Yellow Fever, Journal of the American<lb/>
Medical Association, July 19, 1902, enclosure K.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f02841012"/>
<p>-- 7 --</p>
<p>2. The Transmission of Yellow Fever, - ibid May 23, 1903, encl. L.</p>
<p>3. The Etiology of Yellow Fever, an addendum, - ibid November 28,<lb/>
1903, enclosure M.</p>
<p>4. Yellow Fever, A Popular Lecture, American Medicine, June 3,<lb/>
1905, enclosure N.</p>
<p>5. Lessons to be Learned from the Present Outbreak of Yellow Fever.<lb/>
Journal of The American Medical Association, Oct. 7, 1905.<lb/>
enclosure O.</p>
<p>6. Without Mosquitoes there can be no Yellow Fever. American<lb/>
Medicine, March 17, 1906. Enclosure P.</p>
<p>7. Article on Yellow Fever. Mense's Handbuch der Tropenkrankheiten,<lb/>
Vol. II, Leipzig, 1905.</p>
<p>8. Article on Yellow Fever. System of Medicine, Wm. Osler, Not yet<lb/>
published.</p>
<p>I may be pardoned if I refer with pride to the following com-<lb/>
ments of eminent professional men:-</p>
<p>President's address before the American Public Health Association<lb/>
at New Orleans, La., 1902. Proceedings Amer. Pub. Health Ass'n., Vol. XXVIII,<lb/>
Columbus, Ohio, 1903, pages 2 and 3.</p>
<p>President's address before the same association in 1905. See Pro-<lb/>
ceedings of the American Public Health Association at the meeting at Havana,<lb/>
Vol. XXX, 1905, page 1.</p>
<p>Report of Proceedings of the National Legislative Council of the<lb/>
American Medical Association at the meeting held in Washington January<lb/>
9-11, 1906. Journal of the American Medical Association, Jan. 20, 1906,<lb/>
page 216, copy enclosed marked enclosure Q.</p>
<p>Attention is respectfully invited to my description in the first<lb/>
paragraph on page 18 of the paper on The Treatment of Yellow Fever, in<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02841013"/>
-- 8 --<lb/>
which I described a paroxysm suffered during the course of my<lb/>
attack of yellow fever, and which I now believe to have been one<lb/>
of acute cardiac dilatation. As a matter of fact I am now hampered<lb/>
by a pronounced mitral regurgitation, on account of which I have been<lb/>
cautioned by several physicians, including Dr. Thayer of Baltimore,<lb/>
to go slow and be careful.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,<lb/>
Your obedient servant,</salute>
<signed>James Carroll</signed>
1st Lieut. &amp; Asst. Surgeon, U. S. Army.<lb/>
Curator, Army Medical Museum.<lb/>
(17 enclosures.)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
