<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02851001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Book Review: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, October 1906</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02851001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1906-10-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Bellevue Hospital Medical College, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Arizona</name>
<name type="place">Fort McHenry, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Mount Vernon Barracks (Alabama)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1906-10-00">October 1906</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02851001</idno>
<title>Book Review: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, October 1906</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This review, which appeared in "The Journal of Insanity," praises Kelly's biography of Walter Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1906-10-00">
<head>Book Review: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, October 1906</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02851001"/>
<opener>
Ac<lb/>
<unclear>In</unclear> to <unclear>L</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
Journal of Insanity<lb/>
<date value="1906-10-00">Oct. 1906</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Book Reviews.</p>
<p>Ac<lb/>
<unclear>In</unclear> to L</p>
<p>----------------</p>
<p>Walter Reed and Yellow Fever. By HOWARD A. KELLY, Professor of<lb/>
Gynecological Surgery. Johns Hopkins University. (New York:<lb/>
McClure, Phillips &amp; Co., 1906.)</p>
<p>Although the author expresses his disappointment that he has been<lb/>
unable &ldquo;to catch enough of that evanescent aura which we call a person-<lb/>
ality to convey in written words some clear notion of the man to whom<lb/>
it was given to make the greatest American medical discovery,&rdquo; the<lb/>
reader feels that his success has been great and that the scanty material<lb/>
at his hand has grown into a stimulating and interesting book.</p>
<p>Walter Reed was born in Gloucester County, Virginia, in 1851, the son<lb/>
of a clergyman, and on his father's and mother's side came of good English<lb/>
stock. He received his education in a private school and at the Uni-<lb/>
versity of Virginia, where he graduated in medicine in 1869. He then<lb/>
went to New York and received the degree of M. D. a year later from<lb/>
Bellevue Hospital Medical College. He afterwards served as an interne<lb/>
in several hospitals in New York and Brooklyn, and at the age of 22<lb/>
years was appointed one of the inspectors of the Brooklyn Board of Health.<lb/>
In 1875 he passed the required examination to enter the United States<lb/>
Army Medical Corps and was commissioned an Assistant Surgeon with<lb/>
the rank of First Lieutenant. In 1876, soon after his marriage, he was<lb/>
ordered to join his command in Arizona. At the end of four years he<lb/>
was ordered East for examination and promotion to the rank of Captain.<lb/>
In 1881 he was stationed for a short time at Fort McHenry, and there im-<lb/>
proved the opportunity to study physiology at the Johns Hopkins Uni-<lb/>
versity (his first introduction to the methods of scientific research),<lb/>
where he familiarized himself with laboratory work under Martin, who<lb/>
had but recently come to the University from Cambridge, England. In<lb/>
1882 he was transferred to the Department of the Platte in Nebraska.<lb/>
In 1887 he was ordered to Mt. Vernon Barracks in Alabama. In 1889 he<lb/>
was sent to Baltimore to take medical studies to fit himself for promotion<lb/>
to the rank of Major and there he began the study of pathology and<lb/>
bacteriology under Welch, and immediately took high rank as a student<lb/>
and an investigator. In 1891 he was sent to Dakota, where he remained<lb/>
until 1893 when he returned to Washington to become curator of the<lb/>
Army Medical Museum and professor of bacteriology and clinical micro-<lb/>
scopy in the Army Medical School recently organized by Surgeon-General<lb/>
Sternberg. His varied experience in the Army made him an excellent<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02851002"/>
I42<lb/>
BOOK REVIEWS<lb/>
[July<lb/>
diagnostician and gave him a courage of conviction and a fixedness of<lb/>
purpose which proved of great value in his subsequent scientific labors.</p>
<p>In 1898 when the Spanish-American War broke out Dr. Reed was<lb/>
anxious to fill a responsible position in the care of the sick, for which his<lb/>
experience had fitted him. He was familiar with the conditions of army<lb/>
life and knew how to preserve the health of troops under his charge, vital<lb/>
matters concerning which the civilian physicians and political doctors who<lb/>
were appointed were lamentably ignorant. He was chagrined and dis-<lb/>
tressed to find that men without army experience but with political influ-<lb/>
ence were preferred, while he and other surgeons of the army were<lb/>
relegated to comparatively unimportant positions. At the close of the<lb/>
war he was appointed upon a Commission to visit Cuba to investigate the<lb/>
cause of yellow fever. The story of his work in this Commission is told<lb/>
clearly and yet succinctly and the details of his investigations are given<lb/>
in successive chapters. When the Commission had failed to discover any<lb/>
bacterial cause for the disease, the attention of its members was directed<lb/>
to the death of a prisoner under strict guard and isolation in the Bar-<lb/>
racks at Pinar del Rio, Cuba. This suggested a special infection due<lb/>
probably to some insect and discredited the old doctrine of fomites which<lb/>
had given rise to many barbarities in an effort to quarantine non-infected<lb/>
communities against persons and their effects coming from infected<lb/>
regions.</p>
<p>There is not space to enter upon the remarkable series of experiments<lb/>
carried on under Dr. Reed's supervision, by which it was ultimately<lb/>
demonstrated that a form of mosquito known as Stegomyia fasciata was<lb/>
the carrier of the infection of yellow fever. The account given in the<lb/>
volume is complete and full of interest, and deserves careful reading.<lb/>
Chapters IV, V, VI, VII, and VIII are entitled in succession &ldquo;History of<lb/>
Yellow Fever in the Past,&rdquo; &ldquo;Insects and Diseases,&rdquo; &ldquo;Work in Yellow<lb/>
Fever,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Practical Application of the Mosquito Theory.&rdquo; Chapter<lb/>
IX treats generally of the value of the work of Walter Reed. Chapter X<lb/>
gives an account of his sudden illness and untimely death in November,<lb/>
1902. Dr. Kelly gives due credit to the work of King, Finlay, Carter,<lb/>
Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte, and presents a charming narrative of<lb/>
the successive steps in the discovery. In concluding his work, the author<lb/>
remarks:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The annals of Walter Reed's early years are refreshing in their sim-<lb/>
plicity. They record a natural, healthful life, with habits and interests<lb/>
in no wise different from those of thousands of American boys. Nothing<lb/>
in its circumstances or pursuits marked him as different from his fellows,<lb/>
and his character was distinguished from theirs, not by flashes and<lb/>
premonitions of genius, but by a remarkable uprightness, earnestness of<lb/>
purpose, and tenderness of heart. Neither his youth nor his mature<lb/>
years were characterized by any of those eccentricities which it is often<lb/>
the fashion to consider inseparably associated with genius; indeed, his<lb/>
whole life is a consistent witness to the falsity of the theory which ex-<lb/>
empts a man of unusual abilities from the laws governing mankind in<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02851003"/>
1906]<lb/>
BOOK REVIEWS<lb/>
143<lb/>
general, on the ground that exceptional talent is in itself abnormal. The<lb/>
popular idea that the gifted few are not responsible for their actions,<lb/>
because they are themselves a deviation from the normal, and that what<lb/>
are vices in their fellow-men are venial errors in them, finds no support<lb/>
in Walter Reed's life. Sanity, next to earnest Christian principle, was his<lb/>
distinguishing trait.</p>
<p>Again, let those who complain of the cramping influence of uncongenial<lb/>
environment, and insist upon the necessity of opportunity and sympa-<lb/>
thetic surroundings to a full intellectual development, review the record<lb/>
of the forty years spent by Reed, first in his quiet Virginia home, and<lb/>
then on the far Western frontier. The foundations of his achievements<lb/>
were not laid amidst a stimulating mental atmosphere, nor did he make<lb/>
success the one object in life to which all other aims were subordinated;<lb/>
on the contrary, the training which prepared him, quite unconsciously, to<lb/>
enter, fully equipped, upon the great work in store for him, was a con-<lb/>
stant, daily, unselfish devotion to the needs of others, often amid most<lb/>
uncongenial surroundings.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The volume is of absorbing interest and should be read by every physi-<lb/>
cian. The simple story is charmingly told.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
