<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02866004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Book Review: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, September 1906</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02866004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1906-09-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins University Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1906-09-00">September 1906</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02866004</idno>
<title>Book Review: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, September 1906</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This review, which appeared in the "St. Louis Medical Review," praises Kelly's biography of Walter Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1906-09-00">
<head>Book Review: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, September 1906</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02866004"/>
<opener>
St Louis Med. Review<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1906-09-00">Sept. 1906</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Walter Reed and Yellow Fever. By Howard A.<lb/>
Kelly, Professor of Gynaecological Surgery,<lb/>
Johns Hopkins University. Pp. xvi--293. New<lb/>
York: McClure, Phillips &amp; Co. 1906.</p>
<p>A delightful and timely book. We say timely,<lb/>
particularly, because it seems to us that by popular-<lb/>
izing the knowledge of Reed's great achievement in<lb/>
identifying the stegomyia fasciata as the carrier of<lb/>
the infection of yellow fever, whereby a great ad-<lb/>
vance has been made towards the entire eradication<lb/>
of the scourge, the public which has benefited so<lb/>
largely and will benefit so much more largely, from<lb/>
this work, ought to be stimulated to do its share<lb/>
in raising the necessary funds for the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial, which, as we understand from the report<lb/>
of the committee recently issued, still lacks some<lb/>
$5,000. It can only be attributed to lack of infor-<lb/>
mation that the great lay public leaves the major<lb/>
portion of a fund raised to honor the memory of a<lb/>
man who has conferred an everlasting benefit on it,<lb/>
and to assist those he has left behind, to be pro-<lb/>
vided by the medical profession to which he be-<lb/>
longed. It is to be hoped that this work, therefore,<lb/>
will reach a large number of lay readers and will<lb/>
have a due effect.</p>
<p>Dr. Kelly has executed his self-imposed task with<lb/>
that conscientious thoroughness that characterizes<lb/>
his work of whatever kind. He introduces us to<lb/>
Reed's early life and training, from which we may<lb/>
learn the lesson that, however advantageous they<lb/>
may be, congenial and contributory surroundings in<lb/>
early life are by no means essential for the produc-<lb/>
tion later of scientific researches of the highest<lb/>
character. The beginning of his career as a scien-<lb/>
tist--his earlier years were spent as a military med-<lb/>
ical officer living a frontier life which is scarcely<lb/>
conducive to the pursuit of scientific reasearch--<lb/>
dates from his assignment to duty at Baltimore in<lb/>
1890. Dr. William Welch has provided Dr. Kelly<lb/>
with an account of his work at the Johns Hopkins<lb/>
University and Hospital.</p>
<p>We cannot refrain from quoting the following<lb/>
passage concerning the necessity for adequate spec-<lb/>
ialized training for Army Medical officers in time of<lb/>
war. The evil of supposing that the best profes-<lb/>
sional man necessarily makes the best army medical<lb/>
officer, and the still greater evil of considering any<lb/>
professional man, who can obtain sufficient influence<lb/>
good enough to hold a medico-military position are<lb/>
well illustrated in the following passage:</p>
<p>In 1898, when the Spanish-American war broke<lb/>
out, Dr. Reed became extremely anxious to hold<lb/>
some responsible position in charge of sick soldiers.<lb/>
He knew that his experience peculiarly fitted him to<lb/>
do this work, since he was familiar with practical<lb/>
matters, such as the condition of the army, the rou-<lb/>
tine of getting supplies, the manner of preserving<lb/>
the health of the soldiers, and all questions of gen-<lb/>
eral management, which were unknown to the ci-<lb/>
vilian physicians and political doctors appointed to<lb/>
hold responsible positions over him. He made a<lb/>
strong effort to secure some such appointment, for<lb/>
which years of army work had so admirably fitted<lb/>
him, only to be chagrined and distressed when men<lb/>
with political influence were preferred, while he<lb/>
and other army surgeons were relegated to other<lb/>
unimportant positions. The records of our camps<lb/>
during the Spanish-American war afford, indeed, a<lb/>
valuable object lesson on the evils of allowing mat-<lb/>
ters in which human safety depends upon technical<lb/>
knowledge and specialized training to be governed<lb/>
by political interest. For, not only is human life,<lb/>
under such conditions, at the mercy of ignorance,<lb/>
indifference, and greed, but the very men whose<lb/>
hands are tied by political usurpation of authority<lb/>
which should be theirs, are liable to undeserved<lb/>
blame for the evils they have striven to prevent,<lb/>
and our credit as a nation suffers in consequence.</p>
<p>No one felt this injustice more keenly than Dr.<lb/>
Reed; and in a conversation with a friend soon after<lb/>
the war was over, he spoke with extreme sadness of<lb/>
the fact that by such mismanagement on the part of<lb/>
the Secretary of War and others who should know<lb/>
better, the Army Medical Corps had been subjected<lb/>
to censure which it did not deserve. To use his own<lb/>
words, &ldquo;The Army Medical Corps has received a<lb/>
black eye because of the neglect and incompetence<lb/>
of men who did not really belong to it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The civilian has to deal with disease and injury<lb/>
from a purely individualistic standpoint. That very<lb/>
training unfits him for the special requirements of<lb/>
the army medical service. As a matter of fact, an<lb/>
average professional man of long military experience<lb/>
is far more efficient as a military medical officer in<lb/>
time of war than the best civilian that the profes-<lb/>
sion can offer. Expert clinicians, expert surgeons,<lb/>
expert sanitarians may with advantage be attached<lb/>
to the forces to give their special aid in individual<lb/>
cases; but to preserve the efficiency of the fighting<lb/>
machine en bloc, the specialized training of the<lb/>
army medical officer is absolutely essential.</p>
<p>We have already devoted more space to this re-<lb/>
view than we are justified in doing, so we can but<lb/>
briefly enumerate the other topics dealt with: The<lb/>
History of Yellow Fever in the Past; Insects and<lb/>
Diseases; Work in Yellow Fever; Practical applica-<lb/>
tion of the Mosquito Theory; Value of Reed's<lb/>
Work to the World; Life after Return from Cuba,<lb/>
and Death, 1901-1902; and finally, Other Members<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Commission in which Carroll,<lb/>
Lazear, and Agramonte receive recognition. It is<lb/>
satisfactory to note also that due credit is given<lb/>
(pp. 113-119) to the initial work of Dr. Carlos J.<lb/>
Finlay, of Havana, whose hypothetical suggestion<lb/>
of the mosquito as the agent of transmission of<lb/>
yellow fever (1881) is too apt to be overlooked, as<lb/>
is often the case with valuable suggestive working<lb/>
hypotheses suggested by thinkers which serve as<lb/>
ladders whereby the practical experimentalists<lb/>
climb.</p>
<p>The book is well got up and is illustrated by por-<lb/>
traits of Reed (at various ages), Finlay, Carroll, La-<lb/>
zear, Agramonte, etc.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
