<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02878002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Editorial: The Promotion of James Carroll, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02878002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="publication">Maryland Medical Journal</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02878002</idno>
<title>Editorial: The Promotion of James Carroll, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This editorial lauds Carroll's achievements and supports the funding of a pension for his widow.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Editorial: The Promotion of James Carroll, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02878002"/>
<p>FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY</p>
<p>THE PROMOTION OF JAMES CARROLL</p>
<p>LIEUTENANT JAMES CARROLL of the Army Medical Corps will soon be<lb/>
promoted to be a Major, if the bill reported by the Senate Committee on<lb/>
Military Affairs becomes a law. The promotion is offered in recognition of<lb/>
distinguished services to science and to his country as a member of the Yel-<lb/>
low Fever Commission, and the first volunteer in the experimental produc-<lb/>
tion of yellow fever by the bite of an infected Stegomyia. It is not pretended<lb/>
that the promotion is an adequate reward. It is simply the measured remu-<lb/>
neration which the country can offer for services which are invaluable -- an<lb/>
outward and visible sign, denoting, not the limits of the country's gratitude,<lb/>
but a government's mode of expression. That Dr. Carroll will be more than<lb/>
satisfied goes without saying. His sense of equivalence is not very delicate,<lb/>
and he probably believes that the debt of the country to a citizen can never<lb/>
be greater than the debt of a citizen to his country. At all events, Carroll<lb/>
is tall enough to know whether any of Columbia's sons are as tall as their<lb/>
mother.</p>
<p>Republics, it is said, are subject to certain disabilities. By being, for a<lb/>
moment, insensitive to the tone and rhythm of national life, and at the same<lb/>
time oversensitive to the distribution of medals and epaulettes, one may<lb/>
entertain the transient notion that republics are ungrateful. But most of<lb/>
us are not great enough, nor small enough, to discuss the disabilities of<lb/>
republics. The disabilities of heroes are within our range, and far more<lb/>
interesting. Let us go down to Olympia and visit the athletes. Here is one<lb/>
who has recently won his event. He is to be made a major. He cannot be<lb/>
very fast, for any man who keeps the course can be a major at fifty. He is<lb/>
well past fifty, and only a lieutenant. At fifty no one looks good enough for<lb/>
any of the five exercises. Carroll won his fifth in 1902, when, as a member of<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Commission and its technical right hand, he gave his body<lb/>
to the proof that yellow fever is carried by the Stegomyia mosquito. He<lb/>
made the proof, and escaped, as a soldier should, with his life -- somewhat<lb/>
impaired, but still able to jog on to his majority. He is to skip the captain's<lb/>
grade. Four or five years earlier Major Walter Reed wanted Carroll as his<lb/>
associate, but Carroll was too old. Reed persuaded the objectors that the<lb/>
disability of age ought not to prevail over Carroll's remarkable technical<lb/>
efficiency. The lesser consideration gave way to the greater, and Carroll<lb/>
was promoted from hospital steward to assistant surgeon. Though serving<lb/>
as a hospital steward, he had been a physician since 1891, when he graduated<lb/>
at the University of Maryland. A good many years earlier another army<lb/>
surgeon, not Dr. Reed, had discovered unusual aptitude in his hospital stew-<lb/>
ard, James Carroll, and had asked that he be given leave to study medicine.<lb/>
Leave was refused at first, but persistent effort secured the permission, and<lb/>
the medical course was finished after much delay and interruption. Before<lb/>
he became a hospital steward, Carroll was a sergeant; before that, a corporal,<lb/>
and before that, a private in the army of the United States since 1874. To<lb/>
one who wishes to become a physician these things are serious stumbling-<lb/>
blocks, especially if one has been a good trooper, a good corporal, a good<lb/>
sergeant and a good hospital steward, and more especially if one desires to<lb/>
belong to the medical corps of the army.</p>
<p>Before 1874 Carroll was a lad in his teens, chasing a vague future in<lb/>
the wilds of Canada. His roof tree is at Woolwich, England, where he was<lb/>
born of English parents in 1854. This, that he was born in England, is the<lb/>
initial disability of our athlete. Truly the Fates are severe handicappers.<lb/>
&ldquo;A <unclear>Aqua</unclear>, <unclear>Sioros</unclear>, <unclear>Spoiuos, waxy, wuypui</unclear>, all the honors of the pentathlon belong<lb/>
to Carroll, and Columbia surely must confer some mark of special favor on<lb/>
so devoted a foster son.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
