<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02877001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from N.P. Stewart to Howard A. Kelly, February 20, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Stewart, N.P.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02877001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-02-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Wyman, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Von Ezdorf, Rudolph H.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="publication">Walter Reed and Yellow Fever (Kelly, author)</name>
<name type="publication">Journal of the American Medical Association</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-02-20">February 20, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02877001</idno>
<title>Letter from N.P. Stewart to Howard A. Kelly, February 20, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Stewart praises Kelly's book. He suggests corrections for clarification, and notes that he would emphasize the role of the Public Health Service.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1907-02-20">
<head>Letter from N.P. Stewart to Howard A. Kelly, February 20, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02877001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
AMERICAN CONSULAR SERVICE.<lb/>
Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, S.A.<lb/>
<date value="1907-02-20">February 20, 1907.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr. Kelly:----</salute>
</opener>
<p>Please do not think that I am very presump-<lb/>
tious in writing to you. I once did meet you, having<lb/>
been given a letter of introduction to you, some thirteen<lb/>
years ago, but I have heard of you so often in a friendly<lb/>
way from Dr. Fry in Washington, that as -at my request --<lb/>
he sent me the last edition of your book, &ldquo;Walter Reed<lb/>
and Yellow Fever&rdquo; I want to suggest one or two very small<lb/>
amendments in the book, when it appears in it's third and<lb/>
fourth, and &ldquo;Xth.&rdquo; editions. For, that the book will be<lb/>
called for to more editions, I cannot doubt. It is the<lb/>
clearest exposition, both of the mosquito theory (please<lb/>
excuse the use of the word theory, I should say causation)<lb/>
od both Malarial infection, and Yellow Fever infection,<lb/>
i.e. the clearest exposition, written in popular terms,<lb/>
and capable of being understood by those who are not &ldquo;Med-<lb/>
icos&rdquo; -- that I, or, probably- anyone else has ever had the<lb/>
pleasure of reading. And, the tribute that you pay to<lb/>
Dr. Reed, although no one could ask for any kinder terms<lb/>
than those in which you have expressed yourself, or any<lb/>
expressions of more lasting and reasonable appreciation<lb/>
of the wonderful addition to medical knowledge which were<lb/>
initiated and developed to full perfection by him, still,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02877002"/>
<hi>Dr. <del>Reed</del><add>Kelly</add> Page</hi> 2.<lb/>
still, although you write to well, and appreciativly, there<lb/>
is no one who could in mere words show just what a bene-<lb/>
fit he has given freely to the world. It will take ages<lb/>
of time to understand this, and even <add>then</add> when it <hi>might</hi> be un-<lb/>
derstood, it will fail to be appreciated, because all the<lb/>
old works speaking of the havoc to life, health, commerce<lb/>
and fellow feeling caused by epidemics of yellow fever,<lb/>
will be so hard to understand, in the light of the knowledge<lb/>
given to the world by Reed, that people will imagine all the<lb/>
old works on this subject, and the many press articles, etc.<lb/>
to be gross exaggerations, etc. etc., caused no doubt by<lb/>
fear of a disease <hi>not understood</hi>, and for the non-under9<lb/>
standing of whch, they, in the light inherited by them from<lb/>
one who hs left us but recently, <del>they</del> themselves will not<lb/>
be able to see any reason for.</p>
<p>But, I would suggest in fairness <hi>to a Government<lb/>
Service, whose</hi> personnel has suffered death from this<lb/>
disease in persuance of their duties in <add>epidemic work and, in</add> disinfecting and<lb/>
cleaning ships -- although much of this disinfection is now<lb/>
sown to have been unnecessary -- (but this fact was not<lb/>
appreciated at the period when these deaths occurred)<lb/>
that a few changes be made in your next edition of your<lb/>
book.</p>
<p>These are really so very small that it may seem to<lb/>
you hardly worth while to make them. However they are as<lb/>
follows.</p>
<p>On page 188, 5th line from the top of page you say that<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02877003"/>
<hi>Dr. Kelly, Page 3</hi>.<lb/>
&ldquo;In 1903, Dr. Guiteras was appointed by the Surgeon General<lb/>
to investigate&rdquo; etc. etc. Now, the Surgeon General, was<lb/>
<hi>Walter Wyman, of the U.S. Public Health and Marine Hospital</hi><lb/>
Service, not of the U.S. Army, as would naturally be un-<lb/>
derstood by inference from the frequent mention of the<lb/>
Surgeons General of the Army in service during the periods<lb/>
which your review of Dr. Reed's life covers.</p>
<p>Again, on the next page but one, you mention &ldquo;Past<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon Von Ezdorf&rdquo; but there <hi>is no mention of<lb/>
the Service to which he belongs.</hi> The Army has no such rank<lb/>
but the Navy has, and unless the Service to which the writer<lb/>
of the article <add>(Dr Guiteras)</add> belonged is clear, there might be some con-<lb/>
fusion. The article in question you show is taken from<lb/>
the Journal of the American Medical Association, but I<lb/>
think, that it might be clearer if the writer's Gocern-<lb/>
ment position were cleary stated.</p>
<p>sic</p>
<p>Now, Dr. Kelly, do not think that I am writing in any<lb/>
spirit of cavil. I was a Commissioned Officer of the Ma-<lb/>
rine Hospital Service, from 1892 to 1899, and then I went to<lb/>
the Phillipines with the Army, first as an Acting Assistant<lb/>
Surgeon, later as a Captain and Assistant Surgeon, of Vol-<lb/>
unteers, and then again as a Contract Surgeon, and resign-<lb/>
ing in 1903, came down here as the representative -- a non<lb/>
commissioned officer -- of the U.S. Public Health and Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service. I am in no way biased, I mean as re-<lb/>
gards any love for either the Army or the M.H.S., but I<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02877004"/>
<hi>Dr. Kelly/ Page 4.</hi><lb/>
<del>words and now,</del> do think this. The U.S. Public Health and Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service, has had more or less <add>for</add> (<add>the past 15 years,</add> always increasing however --<lb/>
I am glad to say --) jurisdiction of the quarantine affairs<lb/>
of the United States, and during this time, to my knowl-<lb/>
edge <hi>four of their personnel have died from yellow fever</hi>,<lb/>
at quarantines, and during epidemics,<lb/>
and of course others have had the disease and recovered.<lb/>
Although their efforts were in certain ways misdirected, at<lb/>
all events <hi>unnecessary in</hi> the light of knowledge given to<lb/>
the world by Dr. Reed and his brave associates, still the<lb/>
work of the Service was given in quite as sincere a way,<lb/>
with just as much indifference to risk of life and health<lb/>
and with quite as sincere a desire to serve mankind, as<lb/>
was the successful work of Dr. Reed, and his Commission.</p>
<p>That is a point that so mny people would naturally<lb/>
lose sight of. The successful people get all the credit<lb/>
(And that is correct)<lb/>
for a work successfully accomplished. But, in making any<lb/>
estimate of Government work of this character, one must<lb/>
remember that the U.S.P.H.M.H.S. did all they could-accor-<lb/>
ding to knowledge at that time -- to prevent the introduc-<lb/>
tion and spread (when introduced) of yellow fever. And,<lb/>
their work has in the main been good and praiseworthy.</p>
<p>Thousands of Southern citizens of the United States<lb/>
will bear witness to that fact, to-day, and at any time<lb/>
during the past twenty years.</p>
<p>Your conclusions on the lower half of page<lb/>
240 every one, who stops to think and who knows anything<lb/>
at all, will without reservation assent to, and hold up.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02877005"/>
<hi>Dr. Kelly. Page 5.</hi><lb/>
Do not think that what is known as &ldquo;Esprit de Corps&rdquo;<lb/>
makes me write as I do about these small matters. I have<lb/>
this feeling both for the P.H.M.H.S., and for the Army, but<lb/>
it is a simple feeling that where any credit could be given<lb/>
to the M.H.S. <add>or to the Army</add>, it should be done. At the same time<lb/>
I can fully appreciate such words as &ldquo;even Wasdin&rdquo; and one<lb/>
or two others wich appear in the book. And, also I can<lb/>
appreciate the remarks of the Dean of the Liverpool School<lb/>
of Tropical Medicine, on page 202 and 203, where the P.H.M.<lb/>
H.S. is given credit for work performed.</p>
<p>You certainly know that to admit oneself in<lb/>
the wrong theoretically, as the PH. M.H.S. has had to do,<lb/>
even although no blame can really be said to be laid to<lb/>
their charge -- <hi>except perhaps slowness of conviction</hi> -- is<lb/>
hard for any person or any Service to do, but the Public<lb/>
Health Service did it, and have certainly helped to prove<lb/>
the truth of Dr. Reed's findings in regard to yellow fe-<lb/>
ver, as your own book clearly shows.</p>
<p>But, all this kind of talk aside, I can only most<lb/>
heartily congratulate you on your book. Anyone would be<lb/>
proud to think, that after their demise, some friend would<lb/>
write of them as you do of Dr. Reed. I have known hun-<lb/>
dreds of his friends and students, and everyone has spo-<lb/>

ken of him personally as you do in your review of his life.</p>
<p>I only met him once myself, and then only for a few mo-<lb/>
ments, and therefor I can not speak of my own impressions<lb/>
of him, for I had no real ones, but, your book is as I say<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02877006"/>
<hi>Dr. Kelly. Page 6</hi>.<lb/>
a lasting memorial to his character and to his work.</p>
<p>I can only congratulate you again on being its writer.<lb/>
Hoping that you will pardon me for writing as I do, and<lb/>
only wishing that the Public Health Service figured a little<lb/>
more prominently as having worked faithfully and well-all<lb/>
things considered -- for so many years as regards Yellow<lb/>
Fever, (for if one does not know the real cause of a dis-<lb/>
ease, one is after all rather fighting in the dark, and<lb/>
can only for the time being, do the best that one knows<lb/>
how, or can learn how)--- (and this the Service certainly<lb/>
did, although there were of course thousands of needless<lb/>
restrictions viewed in the light of our present knowledge)<lb/>
---</p>
<p>I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>very truly yours, with many apologies,</salute>
<signed><hi><unclear>N P Stewart</unclear></hi> M.D.<lb/>
A A.Surgeon, U.S. Public Health and M.H. Service</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
