<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02871001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Minutes from the Conference of the Committee on Medical Legislation, January 12, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02871001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-01-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-01-12">January 12, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02871001</idno>
<title>Minutes from the Conference of the Committee on Medical Legislation, January 12, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>These minutes include a discussion of the failure of Congress to pass a bill to provide financial relief to James Carroll's family.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1907-01-12">
<head>Minutes from the Conference of the Committee on Medical Legislation, January 12, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02871001"/>
<opener>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
<unclear>EGISLATION</unclear>.<lb/>
<dateline>
JOUR. A. M. A.<lb/>
<date value="1907-01-12">JAN. 12, 1907.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Medical Legislation</p>
<p>------</p>
<p>CONFERENCE OF THE COMMITTEE ON MEDICAL LEGIS-<lb/>
LATION AND THE NATIONAL LEGISLATIVE<lb/>
COUNCIL.</p>
<p>Annual Meeting, held in Washington, D. C., Dec. 13-15, 1906.</p>
<p>The Chairman, DR. CHARLES A. L. REED, Cincinnati, presiding.</p>
<p>The Conference of the Committee on Medical Legislation<lb/>
with the National Legislative Council of the American Medi-<lb/>
cal Association, for the Fifty-ninth Congress, second session,<lb/>
was held at the New Willard Hotel, Washington, D. C., Dec.<lb/>
13-15, 1906. The attendance was as follows:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<head>COMMITTEE ON MEDICAL LEGISLATION.</head>
<item>CHARLES A. L. REED, CHAIRMAN, CINCINNATI.</item>
<item>WILLIAM L. RODMAN, PHILADELPHIA.</item>
<item>WILLIAM H. WELCH, BALTIMORE.</item>
</list></p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head>NATIONAL LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL.</head>
<item>NAME. RESIDENCE.</item>
<item>Dr. S. D. Van Meter..........1723 Tremont Street, Denver, Colo.</item>
<item>Dr. H. R. Burton, M.C...............................Delaware.</item>
<item>Dr. George N. Acker......913 Sixteenth Street, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Dr. W. A. Spurgeon...............................Marion, Ind.</item>
<item>Dr. J. T. Percy.................................Galesburg, Ill.</item>
<item>Dr. E. J. Lutz...............................Kansas City, Kan.</item>
<item>Dr. C. Z. Aude...................................Cecilian, Ky.</item>
<item>Dr. W. L. Cousins.............................Portland, Maine.</item>
<item>Dr. John S. Fulton..........1925 St. Paul Street, Baltimore, Md.</item>
<item>Dr. S. D. Presbrey..............................Taunton, Mass.</item>
<item>Dr. A. S. von Mansfelde..........................Ashland, Neb.</item>
<item>Dr. L. M. Halsey.........................Williamstown, N. J.</item>
<item>Dr. Charles A. L. Reed........60 &ldquo;The Groton,&rdquo; Cincinnati, Ohio.</item>
<item>Dr. A. J. Barchfeld..............................Pittsburg, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. W. P. Goff..............................Clarksburg, W. Va.</item>
<item>Surg.-Gen. Walter Wyman, U. S. M.-H. Service, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Surg.-Gen. R. A. Marmion, U. S. N. Med. Service, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Surg.-Gen. R. M. O'Reilly, U. S. A., Med Service, Washington, D. C.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Dr. E. W. Samuel, member of Congress for the Sixteenth Penn-<lb/>
sylvania District, was requested to consider himself a member by<lb/>
courtesy.</p>
<p>Dr. H. L. E. Johnson, special committeeman, by request in the<lb/>
Hammond and Canteen bills, was extended a similar courtesy.</p>
<p>OPEN SESSION.</p>
<p>NEW WILLARD HOTEL, WASHINGTON, D. C., DEC. 13, 10 O'CLOCK,<lb/>
A. M.</p>
<p>Dr. Charles A. L. Reed, chairman, on calling the Conference<lb/>
to order, spoke in part as follows:</p>
<p>Change of Policy.</p>
<p>It has seemed wise to the Committee on Medical Legislation<lb/>
to suggest a departure from the usual custom of considering<lb/>
all of these questions practically in executive session. We<lb/>
have accordingly, arranged to have several of the most im-<lb/>
portant questions discussed by prominent members of Congress,<lb/>
by distinguished scientists and publicists and by the repre-<lb/>
sentatives of the profession and the public, all of whom are<lb/>
invited to participate in the series of public meetings. In<lb/>
this way we ought to be able to arrive at a conclusion from<lb/>
all of the various standpoints concerned, and therefore place<lb/>
ourselves in position to act with more wisdom on the ques-<lb/>
tions which naturally come before this conference.</p>
<p>A DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH.</p>
<p>It is a hopeful sign of the times that the general public,<lb/>
through a great national scientific organization is demanding<lb/>
the organization of a National Department of Public Health,<lb/>
with representation in the Cabinet of the President. I will<lb/>
not go into the details of this movement, which will be fully<lb/>
discussed by several distinguished speakers. It is equally<lb/>
gratifying to be able to state that this great movement has<lb/>
staunch friends in both branches of Congress. The general<lb/>
provisions of a bill creating such a department were discussed<lb/>
and tentatively agreed on at our last conference. It is hoped<lb/>
that our special committee then appointed to consider this<lb/>
subject will be able to avail themselves of the counsel and<lb/>
advice of the distinguished legislators and publicists who are<lb/>
interested in the question, with the result that a bill will be<lb/>
formulated for presentation to Congress. Whether it will be<lb/>
wise or expedient to present the bill to the present short<lb/>
session, crowded as is the calendar with important bills of an<lb/>
emergency character, is a question to be determined in con-<lb/>
ference.</p>
<p>MEASURE FOR THE RELIEF OF DR. JAMES CARROLL.</p>
<p>The ultimate completion of the Panama Canal, the present<lb/>
salubrity of Cuba, the safety of our southern seaboard against<lb/>
periodic invasion by epidemics, the maintenance of life and<lb/>
health of our citizens in that great section, and the stability<lb/>
<unclear></unclear><lb/>
of our national commerce against disturbance from the same<lb/>
cause, all are made possible by the discovery that the mos-<lb/>
quito is the carrier of the contagion of yellow fever. That<lb/>
fact was established by the labors of three men, two of whom<lb/>
in the interests of humanity and science subjected themselves<lb/>
to inoculation by infected mosquitoes. As a result of that<lb/>
experiment, one of them, Mr. Jesse W. Lazear, within the next<lb/>
few days, died a martyr's death, the other, Dr. James Carroll,<lb/>
survived to live a martyr's life. The only reward that he has<lb/>
thus far received is a disease of the heart that occurred as a<lb/>

result of the yellow fever, that he voluntarily contracted for<lb/>
the welfare of his race. This man, this hero, after risking<lb/>
his life to give this priceless boon to the world, after incurring<lb/>
a permanent invalidism in that cause, after having spent 34<lb/>
years in the faithful service of his country is permitted to<lb/>
remain only an assistant surgeon with the rank of first lieu-<lb/>
tenant in the United States army, with the paltry salary of an<lb/>
officer of this grade. And with broken health this man far past<lb/>
the meridian of life is supposed to meet the obligations resting<lb/>
upon a husband, the father of seven children, and to provide<lb/>
against the requirements of old age. A bill for his relief,<lb/>
endorsed by this council at its last conference, was intro-<lb/>
duced in the Senate but has never been reported out of com-<lb/>
mittee. This is a shame. Surely if Congress understood the<lb/>
facts of the case the bill would pass within an hour by con-<lb/>
current action of both houses. To permit it longer to slumber<lb/>
will be to bring the blush of humiliation to the cheek of every<lb/>
intelligent and grateful citizen of the Republic.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
