<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02876001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Howard A. Kelly, February 15, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02876001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-02-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Quemados, Cuba</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</name>
<name type="hospital">Yellow Fever Hospital, Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-02-15">February 15, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02876001</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Howard A. Kelly, February 15, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran provides his autobiography, including his experiences as a participant in the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1907-02-15">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Howard A. Kelly, February 15, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02876001"/>
<opener>
L<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
<dateline>
Panama, <date value="1907-02-15">February 15, 1907.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Howard A. Kelly,<lb/>
1418 Eutaw Place,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Kelly:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Yours of the 4th instant to hand. Agreeable to your wish<lb/>
that I write you something of my life prior to submitting to the experiments<lb/>
at Camp Lazear, etc., I beg to state that the task becomes an easy one<lb/>
since there is so little to tell of interest or worthy of special record.<lb/>
However, what little there is may be summed up as follows:</p>
<p>Age at present thirty-one. Born in Ireland. Came to the United States<lb/>
when but a small chap and made the voyage alone. Parents lived out their<lb/>
lives in Ireland. Knew the English alphabet at the age of three. At the<lb/>
age of eight had absorbed and was saturated with the biographies of<lb/>
George Washington and Robert Emmett, hence my desire to come to the United<lb/>
States. On arrival in the States went to Ohio and was raised there under my<lb/>
brother's care. Education: High School, supplemented by a special course in<lb/>
Book-keeping, Accounting, Commercial Law, and penmanship, receiving, on<lb/>
completion of the Course, the imposing title of &ldquo;Bachelor of Commercial<lb/>
Science&rdquo;. First regular employment was that of Hotel Clerk at the Central<lb/>
Hotel, Beaver Falls, Penna. In 1897 enlisted in the U. S. Army Hospital<lb/>
Corps as a Private, at Washington Barracks, D. C. First six months of my<lb/>
term of enlistment was served at the Hospital School of Instruction,<lb/>
Washington Barracks. (At this period I made up my mind I was one of the<lb/>
men set aside by Providence to practice Medicine and I promised myself that,<lb/>
at the expiration of my term of enlistment, I would take up the study of<lb/>
Medicine, a promise which I kept although I have never been able to complete<lb/>
the Course.) Transferred to Fort Mott, N. J. in 1898. Tried to be sent<lb/>
to Cuba, but failed. Transferred to Fort Delaware, Del., same year, and<lb/>
later transferred to Bedloes Island (Liberty Island), New York Harbor and<lb/>
promoted from Private to the grade of Acting Hospital Steward. Early in<lb/>
1899 transferred to Cuba with the Army of Occupation. Assigned to duty at<lb/>
Military Hospital No. 1, Havana (Under Spanish rule known as Hospital<lb/>
Alfonso XIII). Same year transferred to Guanajay Barracks, Cuba and later<lb/>
in same year transferred to Columbia Barracks, Quemados, Cuba, for duty at<lb/>
the hospital for the Seventh Cavalry and other troops stationed at that<lb/>
Post. Honorably discharged from the U. S. Army with &ldquo;Character: EXCELLENT&rdquo;<lb/>
on July 3, 1900. Was appointed Clerk at Headquarters of General Fitzhugh<lb/>
Lee which position I held until the Department of Western Cuba was dis-<lb/>
continued. About this time was approached by Dr. Roger Post Ames, an Army<lb/>
Surgeon, who told me he was authorized to offer volunteers for experiments<lb/>
at Camp Lazear $500. Doctor Ames being a friend of mine and interested in<lb/>
my plans to study medicine advised me to accept the proposition, using the<lb/>
money thus obtained to help defray my expenses at College. Told him I would<lb/>
$100<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02876002"/>
Dr. H. A. K.<lb/>
(2)<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
sleep over it and let him have an answer in the morning, which I did, to the<lb/>
effect that I would undergo experiments but without compensation. Entered<lb/>
Camp Lazear as an experimental patient and got good and tired of the proposit<lb/>
-ion before I had had my case. Was not allowed to leave Camp. Honor system<lb/>
was in vogue among us. Doctor Reed was wont to tell me, when I complained<lb/>
of the tiresome camp life, that he would give me my dose next day but it<lb/>
was two months from the date on which I entered Camp until I was sent to the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Hospital as a pet patient. The Major kept me busy with Reports<lb/>
and other clerical work part of the time while I was in Camp. Was bitten<lb/>
once by a mosquito confined in a test tube. This was about two weeks after<lb/>
I entered the Camp. No results. Was the &ldquo;Star&rdquo; patient and the first to<lb/>
enter the &ldquo;Mosquito House&rdquo;, triple-doored and muslin-lined for this special<lb/>
purpose. Audience on the other side of the wire screen: Doctors Reed and<lb/>
Carrol and one or two others whom I do not now remember. Bitten by seven<lb/>
mosquitoes in the morning and by five or six in the afternoon, all taking<lb/>
their fill of good Irish-American blood. On December 24th I bet five dollars<lb/>
with one of the boys who was taking the experiments in the &ldquo;Infected Bedding<lb/>
and Clothing Building&rdquo; that I would eat Christmas Dinner with them in Camp.<lb/>
Christmas Day about 11 A. M. I took my own temperature and I found it to be<lb/>
101 F. By noon it was 102 F. but as I did not want the &ldquo;Boys&rdquo; to have the<lb/>
laugh at my expense I ate as much dinner as the circumstances and prudence<lb/>
would admit. None of them suspected that I had fever. Sent to Yellow<lb/>
Fever Ward Christmas afternoon. First three days could not locate my pains-<lb/>
 - they were all through my body. Did not yell or make any fuss. Made up<lb/>
my mind I was not going to act the baby and stuck to it. Out of Hospital in<lb/>
fourteen days. Two weeks convalescing. Meantime, to make sure that I<lb/>
really had had yellow fever they injected the blood of another man into my<lb/>
circulatory apparatus. This man had a good straight attack of Y. F. No<lb/>
results, as expected. After leaving Cuba commenced the study of Medicine<lb/>
in the University of Virginia but was never able to complete the Course.<lb/>
Foolish and ill-advised investments caused me to give up.</p>
<p>Trusting this will prove of some use to you and hoping you will<lb/>
pardon its disconnected makeup, it being the best of which I am capable,<lb/>
I am, with very kindest regards to you and yours,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>John J Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

