<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02875001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Senate Report No. 6009, 59<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 2d Session, February 2, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02875001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-02-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Cuba Libre, Jacksonville (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbian University, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-02-02">February 2, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02875001</idno>
<title>Senate Report No. 6009, 59<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 2d Session, February 2, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report concerns James Carroll.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1907-02-02">
<head>Senate Report No. 6009, 59<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 2d Session, February 2, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02875001"/>
<p>59TH CONGRESS,}<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">2d Session.</hi>}</p>
<p>SENATE.</p>
<p>{REPORT<lb/>
{No. 6009.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>JAMES CARROLL.</p>
<p>--------------------<lb/>
<date value="1907-02-02">FEBRUARY 2, 1907.</date>
--Ordered to be printed.<lb/>
--------------------</p>
<p>Mr. WARREN, from the Committee on Military Affairs, submitted the<lb/>
following</p>
<p>REPORT.</p>
<p>[To accompany S. 5888.]</p>
<p>The Committee on Military Affairs, having had under careful consid-<lb/>
eration the bill (S. 5888) authorizing the President to place James Car-<lb/>
roll on the retired list with the rank of major, reports the bill<lb/>
favorably and recommends the following amendment:</p>
<p>Strike out all after the article &ldquo;a&rdquo; in line 6, and insert in lieu thereof<lb/>
the following: &ldquo;surgeon with the rank of major in the Medical Corps<lb/>
of the Army, and that the number of officers in the Medical Corps be<lb/>
increased by one, with the rank of major, for this purpose.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Amend the title so as to read: &ldquo;A bill authorizing the President to<lb/>
appoint James Carroll a surgeon with the rank of major in the United<lb/>
States Army.&rdquo;</p>
<p>And your committee further recommends that, when so amended, the<lb/>
bill be passed.</p>
<p>This action is taken in appreciation and because of the exceptionally<lb/>
heroic service performed by James Carroll in the interest of his country<lb/>
and of science in submitting himself for experiment during the investi-<lb/>
gation in Cuba as to the causes and best mode of eradication of yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>-----------</p>
<p>THE WAR DEPARTMENT'S OPINION OF JAMES CARROLL'S SERVICE.</p>
<p>[First indorsement.]</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
THE MILITARY SECRETARY'S OFFICE,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Washington, April 28, 1906.</hi></p>
<p>Respectfully referred to the Surgeon-General of the Army for remark.<lb/>
By order of the Acting Secretary of War:</p>
<p>F. C. AINSWORTH,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Military Secretary.</hi></p>
<pb n="2" id="f02875002"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>JAMES CARROLL.</p>
<p>[Second indorsement.]</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON-GENERAL,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">April 30, 1906.</hi></p>
<p>Respectfully returned to The Military Secretary.</p>
<p>Lieut. James Carroll, assistant surgeon, entered the service January 9, 1874, and<lb/>
had nine years' service as private, sergeant, and first sergeant of infantry, followed by<lb/>
sixteen years as hospital steward. Having shown ability for <unclear>laboratory</unclear> work and<lb/>
having graduated in medicine, he was appointed contract surgeon May 23, 1898, and<lb/>
afterwards first lieutenant and assistant surgeon October 27, 1902.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll went to Cuba as a member of the commission to investigate yellow<lb/>
fever in June, 1900, and distinguished himself as a member of that board, not only<lb/>
by his scientific work as a member of the commission, but also for having offered<lb/>
himself for experiment to demonstrate the transmission of yellow fever by the<lb/>
mosquito. He suffered in this way a very severe attack of the disease, being the<lb/>
first case of experimental yellow fever. He was commended by the Hon. Elihu<lb/>
Root, Secretary of War, in his report for the year 1902, for his share in connection<lb/>
with the great scientific achievement of that commission.</p>
<p>He is at present curator of the Army Medical Museum and in charge of the labora-<lb/>
tory of the Surgeon-General's office.</p>
<p>He is, in my opinion, far too valuable a man to be placed on the retired list as<lb/>
provided by this bill. I recommend, therefore, that this bill be passed, so amended<lb/>
as to give Doctor Carroll the grade of major on the active list, the number of majors<lb/>
in the Medical Corps being increased by one for this purpose.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll will be 52<unclear>,</unclear> years old in June, and stands 162 on the list of assistant<lb/>
surgeons. There is thus but little prospect under present conditions of his reaching<lb/>
the grade of major before his retirement in any other way than by a special act of<lb/>
Congress.</p>
<p>R. M. O'RIELLY,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Surgeon-General U. S. Army.</hi></p>
<p>{Third indorsement.]</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
THE MILITARY SECRETARY'S OFFICE,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Washington, May 1, 1906.</hi></p>
<p>Respectfully returned to the Secretary of War, inviting attention to the remarks<lb/>
and recommendation of the Surgeon-General in his foregoing indorsement hereon.</p>
<p>F. C. AINSWORTH,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">The Military Secretary.</hi></p>
<p>[Fourth indorsement.]</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT, <hi rend="italic">May 9, 1906.</hi></p>
<p>Respectfully returned to the chairman Committee on Military Affairs, United<lb/>
States Senate, inviting attention to the foregoing report of the Surgeon-General of<lb/>
the Army, in whose views the Department concurs.</p>
<p>This case is one of exceptional merit, and it is thought fully justifies the unusual<lb/>
action here proposed.</p>
<p>WM. H. TAFT,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Secretary of War.</hi></p>
<p>------</p>
<p>PROCEEDINGS IN THE NATIONAL LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL OF THE AMERICAN MEDICAL<lb/>
ASSOCIATION, WASHINGTON, D. C., DECEMBER, 1906.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">December 13.</hi>--The case of Dr. James Carroll and the bill for his relief introduced<lb/>
by Hon. Charles Dick, of Ohio, and now pending in the United States Senate, having<lb/>
been formally brought to the attention of the council by the chairman, Dr. A. S.<lb/>
von Mansfelde, representative from the Medical Association of the State of Nebraska,<lb/>
moved to refer the subject to a special committee, with instruction to report at the<lb/>
present meeting of the council.</p>
<p>The motion, having been duly seconded, was formally put and unanimously carried<lb/>
by a standing vote.</p>
<p>The chairman thereupon appointed A. S. von Mansfelde (Nebraska), C. Z. Aude<lb/>
(Kentucky), and S. D. Van Meter (Colorado) as such committee.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02875003"/>
<p>JAMES CARROLL.</p>
<p>3</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">December 14.</hi>--On call, the special committee, to which was referred the chairman's<lb/>
remarks relative to Dr. James Carroll, reported as follows:</p>
<p>"Whereas the chairman of this council, Dr. Charles A. L. Reed, in his address to<lb/>
this body uses this language:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The ultimate completion of the Panama Canal, the present salubrity of Cuba, the<lb/>
safety of our southern seaboard against periodic invasion by epidemics, the main-<lb/>
tenance of life and health of our citizens in that great section, and the stability of<lb/>
our national commerce against disturbance from the same cause are all made possible<lb/>
by the discovery that the mosquito is the carrier of the contagion of yellow fever.<lb/>
That fact was established by the labors of three men, two of whom, in the interests of<lb/>
humanity and science, subjected themselves to inoculation by infected mosquitoes.<lb/>
As a result of that experiment, one of them, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, within the next<lb/>
few days, died a martyr's death; the other, Dr. James Carroll, survived to live a<lb/>
martyr's life. The only reward that he has so far received is a disease of the heart<lb/>
that occurred as the result of the yellow fever that he voluntarily contracted for the<lb/>
welfare of his race. This man, this hero, after risking his life to give this priceless<lb/>
boon to the world, after incurring a permanent invalidism in that cause, after having<lb/>
spent thirty-four years in the faithful service of his country, is permitted to remain<lb/>
only an assistant surgeon with the rank of first lieutenant in the United States Army,<lb/>
with the paltry salary of an officer of this grade, and with broken health this man,<lb/>
far past the meridian of life, is supposed to meet the obligations resting upon a hus-<lb/>
band, the father of seven children, and to provide against the requirements of old<lb/>
age.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(This is about both of <unclear>them</unclear>)</p>
<p>* * * * * * *</p>
<p>The special committee appointed to pass upon said remarks of the chairman do<lb/>
most emphatically approve the same and recommend that this council, as the repre-<lb/>
sentative body of the medical profession of America, urge upon the President and<lb/>
Congress to make such investigation and take such action as will mete out a full<lb/>
measure of justice to Dr. James Carroll and to the <hi>family of the late Dr. Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear.</hi></p>
<p>It is further recommended that the medical members of Congress be respectfully<lb/>
requested to use their utmost power to accomplish this end.</p>
<p>A. S. v. MANSFELDE, <hi rend="italic">Chairman.</hi><lb/>
C. Z. AUDE,<lb/>
S. D. VAN METER.</p>
<p>-------</p>
<p>MILITARY RECORD OF JAMES CARROLL.</p>
<p>Born in England June 5, 1854. Enlisted in Company E, First Infantry, January<lb/>
9, 1874. Promoted corporal May 1, 1874. Sergeant January 1, 1875, until discharged<lb/>
sergeant January 9, 1879.</p>
<p>Reenlisted as private in Company C, Seventh Infantry, January 22, 1879. Pro-<lb/>
moted sergeant from private February 1, 1879.</p>
<p>Appointed first sergeant June 20, 1879.</p>
<p>Served in campaign against Ute Indians October, 1879, to June, 1880.</p>
<p>Resigned as sergeant to take furlough November 14, 1882.</p>
<p>Reappointed first sergeant and detailed as second-class hospital steward April 7, 1883.</p>
<p>Appointed hospital steward from sergeant September 15, 1883.</p>
<p>Detailed for duty at Columbia Exposition, Chicago, about May 1, 1893.</p>
<p>Detailed for duty at the Army Medical Museum about November 1, 1893.</p>
<p>Service continuous as hospital steward until discharged on May 21, 1898. Appointed<lb/>
contract (A. A. Asst.) surgeon May 22, 1898, and assigned to duty in the laboratory of<lb/>
the Surgeon-General's Office by an order dated Surgeon-General's Office, May 22, 1898.</p>
<p>Detailed as a member of the army board for the study of infectious diseases in the<lb/>
island of Cuba, in association with Maj. Walter Reed and Acting Assistant Surgeons<lb/>
Anstides, Agramonte, and Jesse W. Lazear, per paragraphs 33 and 34, Special Orders,<lb/>
No. 122, Adjutant-General's <unclear>Office</unclear>, May 24, 1900. In the course of their experiments<lb/>
he voluntarily submitted to the bite of an infected mosquito August 27, 1900, and<lb/>
was taken sick with yellow fever August 31, 1900, suffering a severe attack. His was<lb/>
the first case of experimental yellow fever. He was confined strictly to bed until<lb/>
September 13, and, convalescence being slow, he left Cuba October 9, 1900, on sick<lb/>
leave, returning for duty November 11, 1900. He took part in all the experimental<lb/>
work of the board, made nearly all of the experimental inoculations, and had charge<lb/>
of the infected mosquitoes until March 4, 1904, one month after the departure of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02875004"/>
4<lb/>
JAMES CARROLL.<lb/>
Major Reed. At this time he had been recommended for appointment to a volunteer<lb/>
majority by Gen. Leonard Wood and Surgeon-General Sternberg, but Secretary<lb/>
Root decided that no more appointments would be made. After returning from<lb/>
Cuba his time was devoted to the study of mosquitoes that had been infected and<lb/>
preserved for the purpose. In August he again proceeded to Cuba, under orders,<lb/>
alone, for the purpose of performing additional experimental work, in which he pro-<lb/>
duced six more experimental cases of yellow fever, all of which ended in recovery.<lb/>
In 1903 he showed by experimental demonstration that the supposed protozoon<lb/>
parasites reported to have been found in yellow fever infected mosquitoes were ordi<lb/>
nary yeast cells.</p>
<p>He was assigned by General Sternberg in 1897 to the work of studying the sup-<lb/>
posed cause of yellow fever, in association with Maj. Walter Reed, and in this work<lb/>
it was shown that the supposed cause of yellow fever described by Professor Sanarelli<lb/>
was closely related to the hog cholera bacillus.</p>
<p>In 1898 he was sent to Camp Alger to study the blood of the fever patients, and<lb/>
he was the first to show and reported to General Sternberg that the prevailing illness<lb/>
among the troops was typhoid and not malarial fever. He was then ordered to<lb/>
Camp Cuba Libra, Jacksonville, Fla., for similar work, and his results were included<lb/>
in the report of the typhoid fever board. He was subsequently ordered to Camp<lb/>
Chickamauga to obtain samples of the waters in use and to examine them<lb/>
bacteriologically.</p>
<p>His service as contract surgeon continued until October 26, 1902, and on October<lb/>
27, 1902, he was appointed first lieutenant and assistant surgeon in the Medical Corps,<lb/>
the age limit having been waived to permit him to appear for examination. He was<lb/>
assigned to duty as assistant curator of the Army Medical Museum by paragraph 20,<lb/>
Special Orders, No. 257, dated Adjutant-General's Office, November 1, 1902, and as<lb/>
professor of bacteriology and clinical microscopy at the Army Medical School by an<lb/>
order dated Surgeon-General's Office, November 20, 1902, having previously served as<lb/>
assistant during every session of the school. Was appointed curator of the Army<lb/>
Medical Museum by an order of the Surgeon-General, dated July 3, 1903. He has<lb/>
performed the above duties continuously since appointment to them and will have<lb/>
completed thirty-three years' continuous service in the Army on January 21, 1907.</p>
<p>He studied medicine at the University of the City of New York during the session<lb/>
of 1886-87 and at the University of Maryland in the sessions of 1889-90 and 1890-91,<lb/>
graduating in the latter year. He took a post-graduate course in pathology under<lb/>
Professor Welch at the Johns Hopkins Hospital in 1891-92 and in bacteriology in the<lb/>
winter of 1892-93.</p>
<p>He assisted Major Reed in the department of bacteriology and pathology of the<lb/>
Columbian (now George Washington) University from the session of 1895-96 until<lb/>
the death of Major Reed, whom he has now succeeded as professor of those subjects,<lb/>
which he teaches to evening classes.</p>
<p>He was suggested for a share of the Nobel prize by an editorial in the British<lb/>
Medical Journal for September 8, 1906.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Membership in societies.</hi>--Society of American Bacteriologists, ex-vice-president;<lb/>
American Society of Pathologists and Bacteriologists; Washington Academy of Sci-<lb/>
ences; American Public Health Association; honorary member of the Medical<lb/>
Society of Manila; Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Sci-<lb/>
ence; member of the Society of American Naturalists; member of the Washington<lb/>
Biological Society.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi rend="italic">List of publications by Dr. Carroll.</hi></head>
<item>1. The Treatment of Yellow Fever. Journal A. M. A., 1902, xxxiv, 117-124.</item>
<item>2. The Etiology of Yellow Fever--an addendum. Journal A. M. A., 1903, xli,<lb/>
1341-1344.</item>
<item>3. The Transmission of Yellow Fever. Journal A. M. A., 1903, xli, 43.</item>
<item>4. The Alleged Parasite of Yellow Fever. Med. Record, N. Y., 1903, lxiii, 25.</item>
<item>5. Remarks on the History, Cause, and Mode of Transmission of Yellow Fever<lb/>
and the Occurrence of Similar Types of Fatal Fevers in Places where Yellow Fever<lb/>
is not Known to Have Existed. Journ. Assn. of Mil. Surg. U. S., Carlisle, Pa., 1903,<lb/>
xiii, 177-210.</item>
<item>6. A Brief Review of the Etiology of Yellow Fever. N. Y. Med. Jour., 1904,<lb/>
lxxix, 241-245.</item>
<item>7. The Discovery of the Transmission of Yellow Fever by the Mosquito. Ameri-<lb/>
can Med., Phila., 1904, viii, 583.</item>
<item>8. Yellow Fever: A Popular Lecture. Forms No. 62, of Bull. Univ. of Texas,<lb/>
Med. Series No. 1. Also Amer. Med., Phila., 1905, ix, 907-915.</item>
<pb n="5" id="f02875005"/>
<item>JAMES CARROLL.</item>
<item>5</item>
<item>9. Lessons to be Learned from the Present Outbreak of Yellow Fever in Louisiana.<lb/>
Journal A. M. A., 1905, xlv, 1079-1081.</item>
<item>10. Remarks on the Epidemics of Yellow Fever in Baltimore. Old Maryland,<lb/>
Balt., 1906, ii, 17-23.</item>
<item>11. Without Mosquitoes There Can Be no Yellow Fever. Science, N. Y., and Lan-<lb/>
caster, Pa., 1905, N. S. xxiii, 401-407. Also Amer. Med., Phila., 1906, xii, 383-386.</item>
<item>12. The Microscope in Its Relation to Medicine. The Bulletin of the University<lb/>
of Nebraska, College of Medicine, vol. xxi, No. 3, 1906.</item>
<item>13. Yellow Fever in New Orleans and its Bearing on the Health of the State.<lb/>
New Orleans Med. and Surg. Jour., September, 1906, 180-195.</item>
<item>14. Text-book Article on Yellow Fever. Dr. C. Mense's Handb. de Tropenkrank.,<lb/>
Leipzig, 1905, ii, pp. 108-139.</item>
<item>15. Notis. Gelt fieber betreffend. Centrlbl. f. Bact., Jena, 1904, xxxvii, 666-668.</item>
<item>16. Yellow Fever, Osler's Text-book on Medicine. Now in the hands of the<lb/>
publishers.</item>
<item>17. Pathological Report and Histological Study of an Endothelioma of the Cere-<lb/>
bellum, with some General Remarks on the Difference between the Cells of Endo-<lb/>
thelium and of Epithelium. George Washington University Bulletin.</item>
</list></p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi rend="italic">List of publications by Carroll and others.</hi></head>
<item>18. Bacillus Icteroides and Bacillus Choler&aelig; Suis. A Preliminary Note. By Reed<lb/>
and Carroll. Med. News, N. Y., 1899, 513.</item>
<item>19. The Specific Cause of Yellow Fever. A Reply to Dr. G. Sanarelli. By Reed<lb/>
and Carroll. Med. News, N. Y., Sept. 9, 1899.</item>
<item>20. The Etiology of Yellow Fever. A Preliminary Note. By Reed, Carroll,<lb/>
Agramonte and Lazear. Phila. Med. Jour., 1900, vi, 790-796.</item>
<item>21. A Comparative Study of the Biological Characters and Pathogenesis of Bacillus<lb/>
X (Sternberg), Bacillus Icteroides (Sanarelli) and the Hog Cholera Bacillus (Salmon<lb/>
and Smith). By Reed and Carroll. Jour. Exper. Med., vol. v, No. 3, 215-270.</item>
<item>22. The Etiology of Yellow Fever: An Additional Note. By Reed, Carroll, and<lb/>
Agramonte. Journal A. M. A., 1901, xxxvi, 431-440.</item>
<item>23. Experimental Yellow Fever. By Reed, Carroll, and Agramonte. Tran. Amer.<lb/>
Phys., vol. xvi, 1901. Also Amer. Med., Phila., July, 1901.</item>
<item>24. The Prevention of Yellow Fever. By Reed and Carroll. Med. Record, Oct.<lb/>
26, 1901.</item>
<item>25. The Etiology of Yellow Fever (a Supplemental Note). By Reed and Carroll.<lb/>
Amer. Med., Feb. 22, 1902.</item>
<item>26. Leprosy. Report of Surgeon-General U. S. Army, Washington, 1902-3, pp.<lb/>
65-69. By Carroll and Gilchrist.</item>
<item>27. Microscopical Report of a Case of Fungus Foot. Amer. Jour. Med. Sci.,<lb/>
Philadelphia, 1899, N. S. cxviii, 394-399.</item>
</list></p>
<p><unclear>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></unclear> Carroll elected honorary member of the<lb/>
Nebraska Academy of Science. (I am an <unclear>ex president</unclear>)<lb/>
in January 1907, last month.</p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Carroll <hi>elected</hi> by the Board of Regints to<lb/>
receive the degree of L. L. D. from the University<lb/>
<del>at the</del> of Nebraska at the June 1907 <unclear>commencement</unclear>.</p>
<p>----------------------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
