<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02880001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Telegram from James Carroll to Howard A. Kelly [telegram; article fragment], March 11, [1907]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carroll, James</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02880001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-03-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<idno rend="suppress">02880001</idno>
<date value="1907-03-11">March 11, [1907]</date>
<title>Telegram from James Carroll to Howard A. Kelly [telegram; article fragment], March 11, [1907]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The telegram deals with the James Carroll's promotion to Major, and is then followed by a biographical article about him. [missing pages 1 - 3 of 5].</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1907-03-11">
<head>Telegram from James Carroll to Howard A. Kelly [telegram; article fragment], March 11, [1907]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02880001"/>
<opener>
form No. 668<lb/>
THE WESTERN UNION <hi>TELEGRAPH COMPANY</hi>, OF BALTIMORE CITY.<lb/>
CABLE SERVICE TO ALL THE WORLD.<lb/>
This Company TRANSMITS and DELIVERS messages only on conditions limiting its liability, which have been assented to by the sender of the following message<lb/>
Errors can be guarded against only by repeating a message back to the sending station for comparison, and the Company will not hold itself liable for errors or delays<lb/>
in transmission or delivery of Unrepeated Messages, beyond the amount of tolls paid thereon, nor in any case where the claim is not presented in writing within sixty<lb/>
days after the message is filed with the Company for transmission.<lb/>
This is an UNREPEATED MESSAGE, and is delivered by request of the sender, under the conditions named above.<lb/>
RECEIVED at Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
WESTERN UNION TEL. CO.,<lb/>
332 <unclear>McMEGNEN</unclear> ST.<lb/>
<dateline>
28 CG HN Mch 11th 10 Collect.<lb/>
Washn Dc Mch 11th .<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Dr H A Kelly.</salute>
</opener>
<p>1418 Eutaw Place Balto Md.<lb/>
Commission received saturday sick in Bed three weeks Influenza.</p>
<p>Jas Carroll.</p>
<p>1225pm.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1907-03-11">
<pb n="2" id="f02880002"/>
<p>From what? Where are pp 1-3</p>
<p>4</p>
<p>Walter <unclear>apparent</unclear><lb/>
mid - March 1907</p>
<p>FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY.</p>
<p>Shortly after Carroll recovered from his attack of yellow fever, he<lb/>
was recommended for promotion to a volunteer majority by General Leonard<lb/>
Wood, the military governor of Cuba, and by Surgeon-General Sternberg, but<lb/>
Secretary Root refused to make any more volunteer appointments except to<lb/>
the Philippines. In a letter to Dr. Carroll, written after Reed had re-<lb/>
turned to this country and dated February 16, Reed says: &ldquo;I am sorry to<lb/>
tell you that you need not look for any promotion, as the secretary re-<lb/>
fuses to fill any vacancies caused by Major Kean's resignation or any other<lb/>
vacancies under that particular act -- appointments will be made <add>only</add> for the<lb/>
Philippine service. It would be folly for you to go there. The gener-<lb/>
al recommended you to fill Kean's vacancy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>From this time on promises <del>have b were wa</del> of promotion were<lb/>
made to Dr. Carroll again and again, but without success. About a year<lb/>
ago, however, the matter was taken up by some of his friends and some months<lb/>
ago a bill was introduced before the Senate to retire Lieutenant <add>'Carroll</add> with the<lb/>
rank of Major. The matter was backed by the personal interest of the Pres-<lb/>
ident, and has received much support from the medical profession, mani-<lb/>
fested through the medical press, several leading articles having appear-<lb/>
ed in the principal journals. For some time; however, the matter hung<lb/>
fire, but I am glad to say the inaction is at an end and Major Carroll<lb/>
received his commission last Saturday. [Telegram]</p>
<p>This is the only reward which has as yet been accorded to Dr.<lb/>
Carroll for his services; his name has recently been mentioned however,<lb/>
in connection with one of the greatest honors which can be bestowed upon<lb/>
a man of science. An editorial in the British Medical Journal for Septem-<lb/>
ber 8, 1906, suggested that the Nobel prize, which is given in Sweden<lb/>
every year, should next time be awarded for the yellow fever discoveries,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02880003"/>
5<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY.<lb/>
and that as Dr. Reed could not receive it, it should be divided between<lb/>
Dr. Carroll and others who have labored in the matter. It would seem that<lb/>
its division between Dr. Carroll and Dr. <add>Carlos</add> Finaly, who first suggested the<lb/>
mosquito theory of yellow fever, would be a most right and proper recogni-<lb/>
tion of merit. The Nobel prize, I need hardly say, is <del>wa</del> awarded every<lb/>
year, on December 10, at Stockholm. There are three prizes, to be bestow-<lb/>
ed for original work done in the medical sciences, physics, chemistry,<lb/>
literature, and the peace propaganda. Each is worth eight thousand pounds,<lb/>
and their value is greatly enhanced by the extreme care <del>which is</del> exercised<lb/>
as to the selection of the recipients. The Nobel prize represents the<lb/>
first organized effort yet made to discharge something of the debt which<lb/>
humanity owes to those who have given their life-wo<del></del><add>r</add>k in its service, and<lb/>
surely, there have been few greater benefits than the control of yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>I must not cease speaking of Dr. Carroll without mention<add>ing</add> <del>of</del> the<lb/>
work which he has accomplished by his pen since his return from Cuba.<lb/>
In addition to his share in the preparation<del>s</del> of the official reports of<lb/>
the Commission, which all bear his name, he has made a number of independent<lb/>
contributions on the subject in the various medical journals, during the<lb/>
last five years. The most valuable of these perhaps, is that on the<lb/>
&ldquo;Treatment of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, in the Journal of the American Sciences for<lb/>
1902, (vol. 34, p. 117). This is the first contribition to the treatment<lb/>
of the disease since its nature and etiology have been understood.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
