<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02913001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Marshall L. Price to Howard A. Kelly, October 19, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Price, Marshall L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02913001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-10-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Pilcher, James</name>
<name type="person">Price, Curtis E.</name>
<name type="place">Fort Custer (Mont.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-10-19">October 19, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02913001</idno>
<title>Letter from Marshall L. Price to Howard A. Kelly, October 19, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Price writes about Carroll's experience in the military, particularly under the command of his father. He corrects misconceptions regarding his father's role in Carroll's career.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1907-10-19">
<head>Letter from Marshall L. Price to Howard A. Kelly, October 19, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02913001"/>
<opener>
<unclear>V</unclear><lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
<dateline>
State Board of Health<lb/>
OF MARYLAND<lb/>
8 AND 10 SOUTH STREET<lb/>
BALTIMORE, <date value="1907-10-19">October 19th.1907</date>
</dateline>
WM. H. WELCH, M. D., PRESIDENT<lb/>
DR. EUGENE JONES<lb/>
DR. LOUIS A. GRIFFITH<lb/>
DR. JAMES BOSLEY<lb/>
MR. DOUGLAS H. THOMAS, JR.<lb/>
HON. WM. S. BRYAN, JR.<lb/>
John H. FULTON, M.D., SECRETARY<lb/>
MARSHALL LANGTON PRICE M.D. Secretary.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Kelly;-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have taken advantage of your note of October 15th.<lb/>
which I found awaiting me on my return from Cambridge to make you a<lb/>
rather voluminous reply. I had personally no share in Carroll's early<lb/>
work though I have aided in every way which I could in the work of<lb/>
his professional and other friends to secure recognition of his ser-<lb/>
vices,-as much through a sense of justice as on account of my person-<lb/>
al friendship for him.</p>
<p>My only reason for referring to the statements of Dr. Jas. Pilcher was<lb/>
to give you my reasons for believing them in the main untrue, though I may<lb/>
have attached undue importance to them at the time. I believe that<lb/>
Carroll referred to Pilchers remarks at the time they were made but<lb/>
neither of us th<del>a</del><add>e</add>n attached any importance to them. I feel however<lb/>
that Carroll's death has placed them in a new aspect, first because I<lb/>
belive that Carroll will occupy a high place in future medical history<lb/>
and second I have a strong objection to what appears to me to be an<lb/>
attempt to exploit a dead man for personal advancement.</p>
<p>My own acquaintance with Carroll began at Fort Custer Montana in about<lb/>
1884 or 1885. At that time my father Curtis E. Price was surgeon of the<lb/>
Post and Drs. Pilcher and Beach were his assistants. I saw Carroll<lb/>
in the Laboratory of Dr. LaGarde of the Army again in 1893 at the Col-<lb/>
umbian Exposition at Chicago but did not recognize him. The first<lb/>
time I renewed my acquaintance with him from the time he left Ft.<lb/>
Custer was at the New Orleans meeting of the AM.M.A. where he and I<lb/>
read papers the same day, this was in 1903. Dr. Pilcher did not meet<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02913002"/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY.<lb/>
2.<lb/>
him or <unclear>avery</unclear> see him again as far as I know subsequent to 1884.<lb/>
Dr. Carroll at that time was my father's Hospital Steward. I believe<lb/>
that it was while stationed at Ft. Custer that Carroll decided to study<lb/>
medecine though while I remember Carroll well I of course had no re-<lb/>
collection of this plan then and did not have until Carroll told me<lb/>
in recent years. According to what Carroll told me he stated his de-<lb/>
sire to my father and requested a detail at St. Paul Minn. so that he<lb/>
could attend the medical lectures there. His application was approv-<lb/>
ed and forewarded in accordance with the military regulations to Col.<lb/>
N.A.M. Dudley, Bvt. Brig. Gen. Commanding Officer of the Post who dis-<lb/>
proved it and returned the papers to the Post Surgeon, with an endorse-<lb/>
ment reading about as follows,-&ldquo;this man desires to educate himself<lb/>
with the object of leaving the service, his application is disapproved&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The reason for Gen. Dudley's unfavorable endorsement was one of the<lb/>
petty affairs which persons not born in the Army would hardly apprec-<lb/>
iate and which those of us not acquainted with Army tradition and feeling<lb/>
are apt to condemn too severely. My recollection is that my father<lb/>
secured the detail over the head of the Commanding Officer, not as I<lb/>
believe through any special recognition of Carroll's ability and char-<lb/>
acter but because he would have made the same fight with pleasure and<lb/>
enthusiasm for any of the men of ability, ambition and good character<lb/>
of his command. Doubtless he also was in part determined to press the<lb/>
matter through resentment of what he must have considered an unwarrented<lb/>
interference with the affairs of his department. In the matter of<lb/>
Carroll's departure from Ft. Custer Mont. to Ft. Snelling Minn., Dr. Pilcher<lb/>
did not have and could not have any part, as he remained my father's ass<del>t</del>-<lb/>
istant at the Post until he was ordered away, and Carroll left imediately<lb/>
upon receipt of his orders to go to Fort Snelling at St. Paul where he<lb/>
began his medical education which was to continue with many interrupt-<lb/>
ions for about ten years of life in the ranks of the Army, at Omaha,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02913003"/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
3.<lb/>
at New York, and at Baltimore. I fail to see how Dr. Pilcher could if<lb/>
he would, have been of any material assistance to Carroll during this<lb/>
time and my knowledge of Pilcher (all hearsay, and dating twenty years<lb/>
back) does not incline me to put great faith in his absolute veracity.</p>
<p>If you consider this an important part of Carroll's rise the facts<lb/>
could no doubt be ascertained at first hand from the Army records and the<lb/>
surviving officers of the 1st. and 2nd. Cavalry and 17th., 3rd. and 5th.<lb/>
Infantry stationed at Ft? Custer in the early eighties. I believe<lb/>
moreover from the few words Carroll and myself exchanged on the subject<lb/>
of Dr. Pilcher indifference if not dislike was the only feeling existing<lb/>
between them.</p>
<p>You are at liberty to make use of this letter in any way you think proper<lb/>
but I would prefer that my father's name would not appear in the light<lb/>
of a benefactor to Carroll. I am as unwilling as he would be to have<lb/>
him credited with results for which he was in no way responsible, and<lb/>
I am sure that if he were living and were credited with the &ldquo;discovery&rdquo;<lb/>
of Carroll he would be both surprised and amused. I feel strongly<lb/>
that one man was responsible for Carroll's rise and that was James<lb/>
Carroll, and that his rise after a life of fifty years of not alone ob-<lb/>
scurity, but submersion shows the remarkable material of which the man<lb/>
was made whom I shall always be glad to count as a friend.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely Yours</salute>
<signed>Marshall Langton Price</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
