<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02929001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from W.F. Arnold to Howard A. Kelly, October 14, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Arnold, W.F.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02929001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-10-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Ross, John W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Grenada (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Pensacola (Fla.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-10-14">October 14, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02929001</idno>
<title>Letter from W.F. Arnold to Howard A. Kelly, October 14, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Arnold defends the reputation of Ross.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1907-10-14">
<head>Letter from W.F. Arnold to Howard A. Kelly, October 14, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02929001"/>
<opener>
<unclear>V</unclear><lb/>
not ans.<lb/>
<dateline>
W. F. ARNOLD, M.D.<lb/>
Hotel Stafford, City,<lb/>
<date value="1907-10-14">October fourteenth, MVMVII.</date>
</dateline>
(Dictated.)<lb/>
Prof. Howard A. Kelly,<lb/>
1418 Eutaw Place,<lb/>
City,<lb/>
<salute>Dear Prof. Kelly:</salute>
</opener>
<p>To-night in your address at the Johns Hopkins Hospital<lb/>
History Club you mentioned unfavorably by name and as obstructionists to<lb/>
the late Dr. James Carroll's work only two persons, to-wit: Dr. John<lb/>
Guiteras and &ldquo;Major&rdquo; Ross, the comdg. officer of the Las Animas Hospital.</p>
<p>With the former, I have no concern; but Dr. John W. Ross, then Surgeon<lb/>
and Lt.-Comdr. U. S. Navy, Retired, I feel quite sure is quite undeser-<lb/>
ving - even if we admit that he did in the instance you quoted interfere<lb/>
as you stated that he did - of this invidious distinction.</p>
<p><del>Judging</del> Guided by my memory alone, I can be sufficiently positive to<lb/>
assert that Dr. Ross was there merely because he was a yellow fever im-<lb/>
mune and because in his own and Dr. W. C. Gorgas's opinion, he could be<lb/>
of service in the yellow fever epidemic that everyone without exception<lb/>
expected to devastate Americans in Cuba. An older b<add>r</add>other of his had died<lb/>
of it in Havana years before while a consular clerk there; but Ross had<lb/>
acquired immunity through a severe attack of yellow fever at Grenada, Mis-<lb/>
sissippi, whither he went as a volunteer very soon after he had entered<lb/>
the Navy Medical Corps. He served there most gallantly both before and<lb/>
after the attack mentioned, as you doubtless can learn, along with many<lb/>
enconiums upon the man's lovable personal attributes, from Dr. Carroll's<lb/>
nurse whom you quoted to-night. For this service, he was rewarded by<lb/>
Congress by advancement in his grade; but he did not accept the full<lb/>
measure of the distinction offered him, <add>and</add> <del><unclear>are</unclear></del> elected instead merely to<lb/>
regain the place wh<del>ich</del><add>ence</add> a new construction of Navy laws had, as he felt,<lb/>
degraded him. Personally, I do not know another man that would have done<lb/>
this. Recently, he was promoted to the rank of Medical Director along<lb/>
with Col. Gorgas's advancement to this rank, the grades being correlative.</p>
<p>Being a much older man than any of those that I have mentioned, I be-<lb/>
lieve, he had not their advantages; hence, he cannot be called a modern<lb/>
doctor. But he is a man of an open mind, and he is quite as incapable<lb/>
as anyone that I know of feeling, much the less of exhibiting, jealousy<lb/>
towards any colleague or obstructing his work. As an evidence of his in-<lb/>
dustry, I shall cite the fact that when he was stationed on a Navy supply<lb/>
ship in Callao, Peru, he secured by passing the rigid examinations (such<lb/>
as the jealous and unprogressive South Americans submit all in-comers to)<lb/>
of the University of Lima; and it was admitted throughout the Navy that<lb/>
he not only did a most unusual amount of good work there, but it was e-<lb/>
qually well known that he exacted almost no pecuniary profit for himself<lb/>
from it. Similarly, in the many years that he spent at Pensacola, Flor-<lb/>
ida, he was the best known medical man probably along the entire Gulf<lb/>
Coast; and I happen to know that he spent more on his patients than they<lb/>
paid, at least in money, to him. - Hence, I hope you will consent to ex-<lb/>
clude the unfavorable reference to him from your paper, or, at least, pub-<lb/>
lish the incident in full, as it doubtless may be secured in its entirety.</p>
<p>I have the honor to be, Sir,</p>
<closer>
<salute>yours very sincerely:</salute>
<signed>W.F. Arnold</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
