<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02936001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Method of the Spread of Yellow Fever, by William Crawford Gorgas, April 15, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02936001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-04-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Chaille, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Ancon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Boston (Mass.)</name>
<name type="place">Quebec (Canada)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-04-15">April 15, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02936001</idno>
<title>Report: Method of the Spread of Yellow Fever, by William Crawford Gorgas, April 15, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gorgas reports on work done in Cuba and Panama to eradicate yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-04-15">
<head>Report: Method of the Spread of Yellow Fever, by William Crawford Gorgas, April 15, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02936001"/>
<opener>
<hi>Gorgas</hi><lb/>
FROM GEN, J. R. KEAN<lb/>
ARTICLE READ BEFORE THE CANAL ZONE<lb/>
<dateline>
MEDICAL ASSOCIATION,<lb/>
Wednesday, <date value="1908-04-15">April 15, 1908.</date>
</dateline>
-------ooo---------<lb/>
&ldquo;Method of the Spread of Yellow Fever.&rdquo;<lb/>
</opener>
<p>I believe that, in nature, yellow fever is entirely trans-<lb/>
mitted from human being to another by the bite of a female stegomyia<lb/>
mosquito, which has previously bitten another human being suffer-<lb/>
ing from yellow fever. Since the epoch-making work of the Army<lb/>
Board, of which Reed was President, this has come to be universally<lb/>
accepted, and I do not intend tonight to discuss this phase of the<lb/>
question.</p>
<p>In Havana, Cuba, we had a large city - 250,000 people, with<lb/>
a considerable non-immune population, and fresh non-immunes coming<lb/>
in at the rate of 20,000 a year, and children being born at the<lb/>
rate of 6000 a year. The city had been infected continuously<lb/>
for 130 years and seemed to have the infecting material in every<lb/>
nook and corner.</p>
<p>We commenced work against yellow fever, along mosquito<lb/>
lines, in February, 1901, and the last case of yellow fever oc-<lb/>
curred in the city in September of that year; that is, it took us<lb/>
about eight months to get rid of fever in the city.</p>
<p>The general plan of our mosquito anti-yellow fever work was<lb/>
arranged under three general heads: We endeavored in every possi-<lb/>
ble way to prevent the breeding of stegomyia mosquitoes. Secondly,<lb/>
in every possible way to destroy the stegomyia mosquitoes that had<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02936002"/>
-2-<lb/>
become infected. Third, we tried in every possible way to prevent<lb/>
mosquitoes becoming infected by protecting and caring for the sick<lb/>
so that they could not be bitten by mosquitoes.</p>
<p>To prevent the breeding of mosquitoes, we divided the city<lb/>
into districts, put each district under the charge of an in-<lb/>
spector who got around to every house in his district once a<lb/>
month, and saw that all breeding places were destroyed.</p>
<p>To destroy infected mosquitoes, we fumigated with pyrethrum<lb/>
or sulphur, every house in which a case of yellow fever was re-<lb/>
ported, and also fumigated all the contiguous houses to the in-<lb/>
fected one.</p>
<p>To prevent the infection of fresh mosquitoes we moved all<lb/>
the yellow fever patients so screened hospital wards, or, if they<lb/>
preferred, screened the house in which they were sick.</p>
<p>The prompt success with which these measures was met I,<lb/>
at the time, attributed principally to the measures taken to des-<lb/>
troy infected mosquitoes, and to the measure to prevent fresh<lb/>
mosquitoes from becoming infected. And this seemed to be the<lb/>
general belief, also, of most of those engaged in the work.</p>
<p>I conceived that necessarily a considerable number of in-<lb/>
fected mosquitoes must escape from every fumigation, and it was<lb/>
always more or less a mystery to me, why, with some infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes in all parts of the city, and non-immune adults and chil-<lb/>
dren coming in at the rate of 25,000 a year, we did not continue<lb/>
to have yellow fever. Dr. Chaille and his followers - Guiteras<lb/>
and others - explained the immunity of natives in an infected<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02936003"/>
-3-<lb/>
locality as due to the fact that they have yellow fever in a mild<lb/>
form while infants and children. It seemed that if this were the<lb/>
case we should be having yellow fever at the rate of 6000 cases<lb/>
yearly in Havana; that these cases would all be infecting mosqui-<lb/>
toes; and we had taken no measures whatever toward destroying the<lb/>
mosquitoes that had been infected by these 6000 yellow fever chil-<lb/>
dren. I thought that the results we obtained in Havana were due<lb/>
to the destruction of the infected mosquitoes, and to the prevent-<lb/>
ing fresh mosquitoes from becoming infected. If 6000 children<lb/>
were having the fever every year in Havana I could see that our<lb/>
methods destroyed none of the mosquitoes that were infected by<lb/>
these children, nor did they prevent fresh mosquitoes from be-<lb/>
coming infected by these children. I, therefore, did not accept<lb/>
Dr. Chaille's explanation of native immunity, though I could see<lb/>
that it was a fact that the native Havanese was immune to yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>In 1904 I was sent to the Isthmus of Panama to take charge<lb/>
of the sanitary work there. The principal sanitary work at that<lb/>
time was to get rid of yellow fever. We put the same methods in<lb/>
operation which we had done in Havana. But we were on the Isthmus<lb/>
sixteen months before the last case of yellow fever occurred here.<lb/>
Now what makes the difference? Why did we get rid of yellow fever<lb/>
so much more promptly in Havana than in Panama? As far as yellow<lb/>
fever was concerned, it seemed to me that it should have been ac-<lb/>
complished certainly as promptly at Panama as it was at Havana.<lb/>
I was very much surprised at our want of prompt results at Panama,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02936004"/>
-4-<lb/>
and have thought over the matter a great deal, and have satisfied<lb/>
myself that I understand the reason why one was apparently accom-<lb/>
plished more quickly than the other - for after all the difference<lb/>
is only apparent, not real. We had been doing sanitary work in<lb/>
Havana for two years and a half before yellow fever disappeared,<lb/>
and while for the first two years this work was not being done<lb/>
on mosquito lines, a most excellent machine was being organized<lb/>
and perfected, wherewith to carry through the work when the real<lb/>
cause of yellow fever was discovered.</p>
<p>In February, 1901, in Havana the machine was all perfected,<lb/>
and everything ready, and all that I had to do was to give the<lb/>
necessary orders. In Panama the machine had to be built up from<lb/>
the bottom, and for the first year giving orders was of no more<lb/>
use than whistling.</p>
<p>Take a city such as Panama in which normally all the condi-<lb/>
tions are perfect for the perpetuation of yellow fever. Under<lb/>
these conditions, we will say we have 100 stegomyia to the square<lb/>
yard. When a case of yellow fever occurs it is always bitten by<lb/>
mosquitoes during the infective period and therefore always leaves<lb/>
a number of infected stegomyia mosquitoes who can convey the disease<lb/>
to non-immunes present. This has been the mosquito condition of<lb/>
Panama since the world began. Now if we reduce those mosquitoes<lb/>
to 50 to the square yard, the yellow fever case will still be<lb/>
bitten, but not by so many mosquitoes, and there, therefore, will<lb/>
not be so many infected mosquitoes left. We would still have<lb/>
yellow fever if non-immunes were present, but not so extensively.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02936005"/>
-5-<lb/>
We reduce them still further to 25. A smaller number of stegomyia<lb/>
bite the yellow fever patient, and we have fewer infected stegomyia<lb/>
mosquitoes but still some, and if non-immunes are present we have<lb/>
a slight epidemic. We go on still further with our work and re-<lb/>
duce them to 15. The same results follow, only the epidemic is<lb/>
still milder as to numbers. We go on with our work and reduce them<lb/>
to 10 per cent. The probabilities are at this stage if we intro-<lb/>
duce the yellow fever patient the patient is not bitten, we get no<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, and yellow fever abruptly disappears.</p>
<p>While it is possible with 10 mosquitoes to the square yard<lb/>
for one mosquito to become infected and give yellow fever to some<lb/>
other non-immune in the house, it isn't probable that this second<lb/>
yellow fever case will infect a second stegomyia. I am inclined<lb/>
to believe that a certain number of stegomyia mosquitoes are necess-<lb/>
ary for the propogation of yellow fever, and ordinarily in yellow<lb/>
fever countries this number is largely exceeded; that your work<lb/>
goes on reducing the number without showing much results; and<lb/>
after awhile your work reduces the number below this spreading<lb/>
point whenbyellow fever abruptly ceases. Now keep your number<lb/>
of mosquitoes below this number, which we will call the yellow<lb/>
fever point, and no matter how many non-immunes or how many cases<lb/>
of yellow fever you introduce, yellow fever cannot spread.</p>
<p>Take Havana in September, 1901. There were still stegomyia<lb/>
mosquitoes in the city - the inspectors showed them as being pres-<lb/>
ent in considerable numbers every day. There were a large number<lb/>
of non-immunes - over 50,000 at least - and in the preceding months<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02936006"/>
-6-<lb/>
quite a number of known cases of yellow fever; if Chaille's theory<lb/>
is true, there were a still large number of Cuban children having<lb/>
yellow fever. Yet yellow fever not only did not spread but dis-<lb/>
appeared.</p>
<p>Take Panama in December, 1905. There were stegomyia mos-<lb/>
quitoes, non-immunes, and yellow fever sick all present, yet the<lb/>
same results came about; yellow fever not only did not spread but<lb/>
disappeared. I think the reason is that while stegomyia were pres-<lb/>
ent they had fallen below the yellow fever point.</p>
<p>This theory, it seems to me, accords more with the facts as<lb/>
you meet them. The destruction of infected mosquitoes and isolation<lb/>
of the sick, if carried out to theoretical perfection, might get<lb/>
rid of yellow fever, if the adult non-immune population were the<lb/>
only people concerned, but if at the same time we have 5,000 chil-<lb/>
dren yearly having yellow fever, who are never reported, and not<lb/>
looked after in any way, the work among the adult non-immunes<lb/>
would not be enought to affect the epidemic in any way. On the<lb/>
other hand, if the stegomyia mosquito is reduced below the yellow<lb/>
fever point, it would not make any difference how many cases of<lb/>
yellow fever we introduced or how many non-immunes as had present,<lb/>
the disease would not spread.</p>
<p>When we came to Panama we had to build up a sanitary organi-<lb/>
zation, and had great difficulty in getting supplies and the necess-<lb/>
ary quthority for doing yellow fever work. But believing that the<lb/>
destruction of infected mosquitoes, and the prevention of mosquitoes<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02936007"/>
-7-<lb/>
becoming infected were the essentials in yellow fever work, we<lb/>
concentrated all our energies on this phase of the work, and car-<lb/>
ried out this part of the mosquito work during the year 1904 just<lb/>
about as thoroughly as we had in Havana, but with no results what-<lb/>
ever. As our non-immunes increased yellow fever increased, and<lb/>
by the spring of 1905 we were having a good deal of yellow fever.<lb/>
But our organization became gradually perfected, supplies came in,<lb/>
the authority of the sanitary department was increased, and the<lb/>
stegomyia work was pushed, and by September, 1905, the stegomyia<lb/>
had been reduced below the yellow fever point and yellow fever<lb/>
disappeared.</p>
<p>The fumigations in Panama were much more extensive than<lb/>
they had been in Havana. In addition to fumigating the infected<lb/>
houses and all contiguous houses, we went over the city three<lb/>
different times during the spring and summer of 1905, fumigating<lb/>
every house within its limits, yet yellow fever continued to in-<lb/>
crease.</p>
<p>I doubt if it is possible under any sanitary organization<lb/>
to do away with the stegomyia mosquito altogether, but it is very<lb/>
obvious, as shown by the results of sanitary work, to reduce them<lb/>
below the yellow fever point. If your sanitary work is so organ-<lb/>
ized that you can feel reasonably sure of keeping your stegomyia<lb/>
below this point, then you need have no fear of letting yellow<lb/>
fever cases come in, because even when they are admitted, the<lb/>
disease cannot spread. Get your locality in this condition, and<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02936008"/>
-8-<lb/>
you could then do away with your quarantine, and thus grant great<lb/>
freedom to commerce.</p>
<p>I am inclined to think that now at Panama all that is necess-<lb/>
ary, as far as yellow fever is concerned, is to keep the stegomyia<lb/>
work so organized that we are sure in Panama and Colon of keeping<lb/>
stegomyia below the yellow fever point. In combating the disease<lb/>
I would not advocate doing away with the other methods. It is<lb/>
very evident theoretically, and Reed shows in his work practical,<lb/>
that you could put half a dozen infected stegomyia in a room, and<lb/>
every non-immune who slept in that room afterwards would develop<lb/>
yellow fever. You could fumigate that room with sulphur, kill the<lb/>
infected stegomyia mosquitoes, and non-immunes could afterwards<lb/>
sleep there with perfect safety. This is an illustration of what<lb/>
fumigation can do under certain peculiarly favorable conditions.</p>
<p>In the yellow fever wards at Ancon during 1905 all the<lb/>
doctors and nurses were non-immunes. They were in the wards day<lb/>
and night where there were always some yellow fever cases, yet<lb/>
none of them contracted the disease. These wards were so screened<lb/>
and cared for that no stegomyia mosquitoes could get at the patients<lb/>
so as to become infected.</p>
<p>But what I wish to emphasize in this paper is the fact that<lb/>
there are a certain proportion of stegomyia mosquitoes in a locality<lb/>
necessary for the spread of yellow fever; that if the number of<lb/>
stegomyia mosquitoes remain above this yellow fever point, we will<lb/>
continue to have yellow fever as long as we have non-immunes present,<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02936009"/>
-9-<lb/>
no matter how much we fumigate or how carefully we isolate the<lb/>
sick, and I advance Panama in 1905 as an illustration of this<lb/>
phase of the proposition. I think it is impossible to fumigate<lb/>
and isolate the sick more extensively or carefully than was done<lb/>
in Panama in 1905. If stegomyia are reduced below the yellow fever<lb/>
point we can introduce yellow fever to any extent and non-immunes<lb/>
in any number and yellow fever will not spread. In proof of this<lb/>
phase of the proposition I advance Havana in 1901 and Panama in<lb/>
1905 as x illustrations.</p>
<p>This, it seems to me, gives a reasonable explanation for<lb/>
the disappearance of yellow fever from Philadelphia, New York,<lb/>
Boston and Quebec before we knew of its propogation by mosquito.<lb/>
Take a city such as Philadelphia. The stegomyia is not found<lb/>
there normally, but 100 years ago when Philadelphia was subject<lb/>
to yellow fever, we had numerous wells and cisterns as receptacles<lb/>
for storing water. Shipsmwere constantly coming in from stegomyia<lb/>
regions and introducing the mosquito. Nearly every summer, no<lb/>
doubt, they were brought in and propagated there. When they had<lb/>
sufficiently to be above the yellow fever point over any considerable<lb/>
area and yellow fever was introduced, we had an epidemic. Nowadays<lb/>
they have a piped water supply and there are very few breeding<lb/>
places. The communication with stegomyia regions is almost entire-<lb/>
ly by steamer and few mosquitoes are carried by steamers as compared<lb/>
with the old sailing vessels, and now there are no means of propagat-<lb/>
ing mosquitoes, so that when a case is introduced, even if there<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f02936010"/>
-10-<lb/>
should happen to be a few stegomyia around, they are not in<lb/>
sufficient numbers to be above the yellow fever point.</p>
<closer>
<signed>W.C. Gorgas</signed>--
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
