<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02940001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Extracts from An Account of Dr. Louis-Daniel Beauperthuy: A Pioneer in Yellow Fever Research, by Aristides Agramonte, and Mosquito or Man, by Sir Rubert Boyce, June 11, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02940001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-06-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Beauperthuy, Louis-Daniel</name>
<name type="place">Paris (France)</name>
<name type="place">Basse Terre (West Indies)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-06-11">June 11, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02940001</idno>
<title>Report: Extracts from An Account of Dr. Louis-Daniel Beauperthuy: A Pioneer in Yellow Fever Research, by Aristides Agramonte, and Mosquito or Man, by Sir Rubert Boyce, June 11, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The extracts from Agramonte's report detail Beauperthuy's work with mosquitos as disease vectors.  The extracts from Boyce's report [in French] also deal with mosquitos and their connections to yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-06-11">
<head>Report: Extracts from An Account of Dr. Louis-Daniel Beauperthuy: A Pioneer in Yellow Fever Research, by Aristides Agramonte, and Mosquito or Man, by Sir Rubert Boyce, June 11, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02940001"/>
<p><hi>Book</hi><lb/>
Beauperthuy</p>
<p>1/<lb/>
Extracts from Agramonte's Piece on Beauperthuy.<lb/>
2/ Sir Rubert Boyce " " in &ldquo;Mosquito or Man?&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02940002"/>
<p>Extract: An Account of Dr. Louis-Daniel Beauperthuy.<lb/>
A Pioneer in Yellow Fever Research.<lb/>
By Aristides Agramonte,<lb/>
Boston Medical &amp; Surgical Journal.<lb/>
June 11, 1908. Vol. CLV111, No. 25.</p>
<p>Page 928-929</p>
<p>&ldquo;These observations, made in the equinoctial and tropical regions,<lb/>
were of great aid to me in recognizing the causes of yellow fever and the<lb/>
appropriate means of combating this terrible disease. As to my work re-<lb/>
garding the etiology of yellow fever, I shall abstain from making it pub-<lb/>
lic just at present. My investigations in this direction are part of an<lb/>
extensive work in which the results present facts, so new and so different<lb/>
from the accepted views, that I must not publish them without (bringing to<lb/>
<add>(advancing <unclear>full view decision</unclear> support oz.)</add><lb/>
their support the most evident demonstrations). On the other hand, I am send-<lb/>
ing to the Academy at Paris a sealed letter which contains a resum&eacute; of the<lb/>
observations which I have collected up to date (1854), and the object of<lb/>
<add><unclear>(proprity B)</unclear></add><lb/>
which is to insure against all events the (propriety) of my discoveries re-<lb/>
garding the causes of fever in general.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is my intention to obtain from the legal heirs of Dr. Beauperthuy<lb/>
authority to open the letter to which he refers; it is no doubt fraught<lb/>
with interesting data and thus we shall rescue one more document from un-<lb/>
deserved obscurity.</p>
<p>Further on he says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The disease known as yellow-typhus, black-vomit, etc., is (produced<lb/>
<add>(due to &amp;)</add><lb/>
by) the same causes which induce the intermittent fevers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yellow fever cannot be considered as a contagious disease. The<lb/>
<add>(The disease develops itself under conditioned which favor the development of mosquitoes&rdquo;</add><lb/>
cause of this disease develops under <hi>climacteric</hi> conditions which allow<lb/>
it to spread at once or successively; these conditions are those which<lb/>
favor the development of mosquitoes (insectes tipulaires, maringoines, etc.)&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The mosquitoes introduce into the skin their <hi>sucker</hi>, composed of a<lb/>
grooved sting or spur with two lateral saws; they instil into the skin a<lb/>
<add>(<unclear></unclear> to that)</add><lb/>
venomous fluid, which has the property of snake poisons. It softens the<lb/>
blood cells, produces a rupture of their tegumentary membranes, dissolves<lb/>
the parenchymatous portion and facilitates the solution of the coloring<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02940003"/>
coloring 2<lb/>
matter in the blood plasma. This dissolvent action seems to facilitate<lb/>
the flow of the blood through the capillary duct of the mosquito's &ldquo;sucker.&rdquo;</p>
<p><add>are of a considerable number of <unclear>stead</unclear></add></p>
<p>&ldquo;The agents of this infection (yellow fever) (present great number of<lb/>
varieties,) not all of them being equally harmful. The variety known as<lb/>
&ldquo;Zancudo bobo,&rdquo; which has <hi>white-striped legs</hi>. is to a certain extent the<lb/>
X <hi>domestic species</hi>. It is not the most common, and its sting is compara-<lb/>
tively less painful than that of the other species.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The following is an interesting statement, which shows Beauperthuy's<lb/>
power of observation and his good judgment:</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is not necessary to search very far in order to find why typhus<lb/>
icteroides is so common along the seacoast and so rare in the interior of<lb/>
the country and in localities little frequented by mosquitoes. In Basse<lb/>
Terre, capital of one of the West Indies, it has been observed that the epi-<lb/>
demics of yellow fever do not extend their harmful influences as far as the<lb/>
? town of Matouba, situated barely three miles from said city. It must be ad-<lb/>
mitted that this distance is entirely too short to preserve, by itself, the<lb/>
? town of Mantouba against the supposed noxious effluvia exhaled by the coast<lb/>
and which the winds, when blowing from the east, would transport within a<lb/>
few minutes; on the other hand, this distance from the sea. that is, from<lb/>
the locality inhabited by mosquitoes, is more than sufficient to preserve<lb/>
against their action and the serious inconveniences which they produce.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Beauperthuy thought that mosquitoes obtained the yellow fever poison<lb/>
X from the putrefying organic matter in the stagnant waters in which they<lb/>
breed; this grave error is quite excusable when we consider the meager medi-<lb/>
cal attainments of his day.</p>
<p>Speaking of malaria fever, he says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The intermittent fevers are severe in proportion with the abundance<lb/>
of mosquitoes, and these fevers disappear or lose much of their intensity<lb/>
(in the woods which,) on account of their altitude, contain but few of these<lb/>
<add><unclear>Omi A Bayce</unclear></add><lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02940004"/>
these 3<lb/>
insects.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The marshy emanations are reputed as more energetic during the night<lb/>
than in the rest of the day. These are the hours in which mosquitoes are<lb/>
most active.</p>
<p>&ldquo;To protect themselves against the fevers, the Indians employ certain<lb/>
preservatives, and those who inhabit the unhealthy valleys place burning<lb/>
coals (a brazier) at the entrance of their huts. This method is very ef-<lb/>
fective for barring mosquitoes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of all means employed to protect themselves from the action of mos-<lb/>
quito bites, the most efficient is that followed by some Indians, which<lb/>
consists in rubbing the skin with oleaginous substances.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Upon acclimatization, he says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Perhaps we ought to look upon acclimatization only as an inocula-<lb/>
tion. It is not that the febrile virus introduced under the skin of man<lb/>
preserves him from the fevers, but that it diminishes the harmful action<lb/>
of these diseases and makes them lose a great part of their gravity. It<lb/>
acts as the variola inoculation, although the latter does not always pre-<lb/>
serve from pustulous infections. This analogy is still more evident in<lb/>
yellow fever. which generally affects the individual only once.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Further on we find:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Contagious diseases are transmitted by inoculation. A certain period<lb/>
must elapse between the action of an infecting cause and the start of a<lb/>
visible lesion.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The expression 'winged serpents,&rdquo; used by Herodotus, is well ap-<lb/>
plicable to the tipulary insects and the action of their bites upon the<lb/>
human economy. -- (additional in Boyces &rdquo;Mosquito or Man&rdquo; Page 103) So true<lb/>
it is that truth appeared to the ancients even in fables.&rdquo;<lb/>
(only as)<lb/>
(jusque dans les fables)</p>
<pb n="5" id="f02940005"/>
<p>Extracts from: &ldquo;Mosquito or Man?&rdquo;<lb/>
Sir Rubert Boyce.</p>
<p>Chapter X. Dr. Beauperthuy on Tradition in Medicine, etc.<lb/>
<hi>Page 99-100:</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;L'absence d'insectes tipulaires pendant L'hiver explique pour-<lb/>
quoi dans cette saison le voisinage des marais cesse d'&ecirc;tre dangereux.<lb/>
Les marais immenses du Nord de l'Europe ne sont point malsains par la<lb/>
m&ecirc;me raison. Les marais ne communiquent &agrave; l'atmosph&egrave;re que de l'humi-<lb/>
dit&eacute;, et la faible quantit&eacute; de gaz hydrog&egrave;ne carbon&eacute; qu'ils exhelent ne<lb/>
produit chez l'homme aucune indisposition dans les re&eacute;gions equatoriales<lb/>
et intertropicales r&eacute;put&eacute;es pour leur insalubrit&eacute;. Ce n'est pas seule-<lb/>
ment la corruption des eaux qui les rend insalubres, mais la pr&eacute;sence<lb/>
des tipulaires!&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 104</hi>.</p>
<p>&ldquo;On ne peut consid&eacute;rer la fi&egrave;vre jaune comme une affection conta-<lb/>
gieuse. Les causes de cette maladie so d&eacute;veloppent dans des conditions<lb/>
climat&eacute;riques leur permettant de s'&eacute;tendre &agrave; la fois ou successivement<lb/>
sur plusieurs localit&eacute;s. Ces conditions sont: l'&eacute;l&eacute;vation de la tem-<lb/>
p&eacute;rature, l'humidit&eacute;, le voisinage des cours d'eau, les lagunes, le<lb/>
peu d'&eacute;l&eacute;vation du sol au-desaus du niveau de la mer. Ces conditions<lb/>
sont celles qui favorisent le d&eacute;veloppement des insectes tipulaires.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Page 106:</hi></p>
<p>&ldquo;Que sont les mati&egrave;res p&eacute;lagiques dont les tipulaires se nour-<lb/>
rissent, sinon des substances animales phosphorescentes comme la chair<lb/>
des poissons? Qu'y a-t-il d'&eacute;trange que l'instillation dans le corps de<lb/>
l'homme de ces substances a l'&eacute;tat putride produise des d&eacute;sordres tr&egrave;s<lb/>
graves? M. Magendie n'a-t-il pas prouv&eacute; que quelques gouttes d'eau de<lb/>
poisson pourri, introduites dans le sang des animaux, d&eacute;terminaient en<lb/>
peu d'heures des sympt&ocirc;mes analogues &agrave; ce<del><unclear></unclear></del>x du typhus et la fi&egrave;vre jaune?<lb/>
N'est-ce pas, en effet, une instillation de poisson en putr&eacute;faction que<lb/>
versent ces insectes sous la peau et dans le tissu cellulaire de l'homme?&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
