<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02946001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from the Jef&eacute; de Sanidad to the Local Sanitary Officers, July 20, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02946001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-07-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Santiago (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Daiquiri (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Santa Clara (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-07-20">July 20, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02946001</idno>
<title>Letter from the Jef&eacute; de Sanidad to the Local Sanitary Officers, July 20, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Chief Sanitary Officer details actions taken to prevent yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1908-07-20">
<head>Letter from the Jef&eacute; de Sanidad to the Local Sanitary Officers, July 20, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02946001"/>
<opener>
xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx<lb/>
xxxx<lb/>
<dateline>
CHIEF SANITARY OFFICER.<lb/>
Jefetura.<lb/>
Havana, <date value="1908-07-20">July 20, 1908.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>To Local Sanitary Officers:</salute>
</opener>
<p>As many exaggerated and erroneous accounts have been circu-<lb/>
lated <del>in the newspapers</del> about the occurrence of yellow fever in<lb/>
Santiago and Daiquir&iacute;, it is thought that an exact statement of the<lb/>
cases which have occurred since the first of April, the beginning of<lb/>
the present epidemic year, will be of interest. No case of this<lb/>
disease has occurred in Havana or in any of the six provinces of the<lb/>
island except Oriente during that time, the last occurrence, with the<lb/>
exceptions noted below, having been the brief and promptly extin-<lb/>
guished outbreak among the American troops stationed in the city of<lb/>
Santa Clara, of which the first case occurred on February 9th and<lb/>
the last on February 18th. The history of the outbreak in Oriente<lb/>
is as follows:</p>
<p>On April 21st Fructuoso Valverde, a Spaniard, was taken sick<lb/>
at Daiquir&iacute; and came on the 22d to Santiago and was admitted for<lb/>
treatment at the hospital of the Colonia Espa&ntilde;ola, where he was dis-<lb/>
covered by the sanitary authorities and the case put under observa-<lb/>
tion. This man had come from Daiquir&iacute; to Santiago on April 15th<lb/>
and had stayed two days in a hotel within 200 meters of the spot<lb/>
where the preceeding case of Feb. 11th occurred, returning to Daiquir&iacute;<lb/>
on the 17th. His infection is therefore credited to Santiago. The<lb/>
symptoms being mild, the diagnosis was so much in doubt, that Dr.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02946002"/>
2-<lb/>
Juan Guiteras, president of the Board of Diagnosis of Contagious<lb/>
Diseases, was sent to Santiago, and pronounced it yellow fever on<lb/>
May 1st. Measures were promptly taken to disinfect the buildings<lb/>
in which the patient lived at Daiquir&iacute;, and the boat in which he had<lb/>
come to Santiago, as well as all buildings entered by him in San-<lb/>
tiago after the beginning of his sickness. Subsequent events, how-<lb/>
ever, have demonstrated that owing probably to the delay in arriving<lb/>
at a diagnosis, the measures of fumigation taken at Daiquir&iacute; were<lb/>
not successful in destroying all infected mosquitoes, and the focus<lb/>
now existing at that place, as well as the two subsequent cases occur-<lb/>
ring in Santiago on May 13th and June 4th, must be ascribed to the<lb/>
failure of the fumigation there and in Santiago.</p>
<p>An elaborate system of medical inspections, together with an<lb/>
efficient organization for mosquito work were instituted at Santiago,<lb/>
and as no case has occurred in that city in more than six weeks, it<lb/>
is believed that the infection is extinguished there. Mosquito work<lb/>
was begun in Daiquir&iacute; and a medical inspector sent there, but he<lb/>
abandoned his post after a few days stay, and a second inspector<lb/>
sent to this position remained less than a month. In order to keep<lb/>
this point under observation, inspectors were sent there at intervals,<lb/>
and in the case histories sent by the Special Medical inspector,<lb/>
Dr. Agostini, about the 20th of June to this office, a case was<lb/>
found which excited the suspicion of the Chief Sanitary Officer.<lb/>
A second inspection was then ordered, Dr. Cartaya, the medical scout<lb/>
on duty in Santiago, being sent to Daiquir&iacute; where he arrived on<lb/>
July 1st and found a case of yellow fever, the diagnosis of which<lb/>
was confirmed by autopso the next day. Ten other cases have been<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02946003"/>
3-<lb/>
confirmed, and it is probable from the investigations of Dr. Aris-<lb/>
tides Agramonte who was sent from Havana to make further investiga-<lb/>
tions, there have been several unrecognized cases antecedent to it.<lb/>
Active measures of fumigation and mosquito destruction were at once<lb/>
instituted upon the recognition of this focus, first under the super-<lb/>
vision of Special Commissioner, Captain H. D. Thomason, Medical Corps,<lb/>
U. S. Army, and later under Major P. C. Fauntleroy, Medical Corps,<lb/>
U. S. Army, who has been sent from this office to take charge at<lb/>
Daiquir&iacute; as a Special Commissioner.</p>
<p>Owing to the isolated position of the iron mines at Daiquir&iacute;<lb/>
and the fact that the population is composed almost entirely of em-<lb/>
ployees of the Spanish-American Iron Company, while communication with<lb/>
the outside world is limited to a few difficult trails leading to<lb/>
Santiago and by a boat belonging to the company, the circumstances<lb/>
seemed peculiarly favorable for the application of a local quarantine<lb/>
by land as well as sea. This was ordered by the National Sanitary<lb/>
Board with the approval of the Provisional Governor on July 7th, and<lb/>
it is believed to be entirely efficient in securing the observation<lb/>
for the necessary period of all non-immunes leaving the infected focus.<lb/>
At the same time a stop has been put to the admission of non-immunes<lb/>
to the infected locality. There is every evidence that these steps<lb/>
will be promptly successful, and it is hoped by the end of the current<lb/>
month that the infection of yellow fever which lingers in only one<lb/>
exttemity of the republic, will be extinguished throughout its terri-<lb/>
tory.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f02946004"/>
<p>4-</p>
<p><hi>DATE OF LAST OCCURRENCE BY PROVINCES.</hi></p>
<list type="simple">
<item>In Pinar del Rio Province, eight years ago;</item>
<item>In Havana City, ---------- January 31, 1908;</item>
<item>In Havana province, ------- " 10, "</item>
<item>In Matanzas province, ----- December 24, 1907;</item>
<item>In Santa Clara province, -- February 18, 1908;</item>
<item>In Camaguey province, ----- November 12, 1907;</item>
<item>In Oriente province, ------ July 13, 1908.</item>
</list>
<p><hi>LIST OF CASES IN ORIENTE - (Santiago-Daiquir&iacute; focus.)</hi></p>
<list type="simple">
<item>Fructuoso Valverde, Daiquir&iacute; April 21, 1908, (probably in-fected in Santiago).</item>
<item>Jos&eacute; Diaz, Santiago, ------------------- May 13, 1908; Discharged</item>
<item>Bartolime Vales Pons, Santiago, -------- June 4, " Died</item>
<item>Juan Salgado Cantelo, Daiquir&iacute;, -------- " 26- " "</item>
<item>Jos&eacute; Alvarez Vasques, " ---------- " 29, " Discharged</item>
<item>Dositeo Alvarez, " -------- July 1, " "</item>
<item>Jose Gomez, " --------- " 4, " "</item>
<item>Ram&oacute;n Randino, " --------- " 5, " "</item>
<item>Juan Longarela, " --------- " 5, " "</item>
<item>Miceno Cameno, " --------- " 6, " "</item>
<item>Juan Alvarez, " --------- " 7, " "</item>
<item>Jaime Stone, " --------- " 8, " "</item>
<item>Jos&eacute; Fernandez, " --------- " " Remaining</item>
<item>Manuel Sabin, " --------- " 14, " (<unclear>Justed.</unclear>) "</item>
<item>Jos&eacute; Villar Maurillo "</item>
</list>
<closer>
<signed>Jef&eacute; de Sanidad</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
