<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02959001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Documents in matter of Quarantine Against Yellow Fever in Cuba, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02959001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, R.M.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Santiago de Cuba (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>44 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-00-00">1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02959001</idno>
<title>Documents in matter of Quarantine Against Yellow Fever in Cuba, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This pamphlet contains letters bearing on yellow fever conditions in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-00-00">
<head>Documents in matter of Quarantine Against Yellow Fever in Cuba, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02959001"/>
<p>(yellow Fever)</p>
<p>DOCUMENTS<lb/>
IN MATTER OF<lb/>
QUARANTINE<lb/>
AGAINST YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
IN CUBA</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02959002"/>
<p>PREFACE</p>
<p>The gravity of a quarantine and the fact that the feeling in<lb/>
favor thereof can only be removed by an intelligent under-<lb/>
standing of the conditions existing has caused the Bureau of<lb/>
Insular Affairs of the War Department to deviate from the<lb/>
usual Governmental custom and publish a number of confiden-<lb/>
tial and simi-confidential letters bearing on yellow fever condi-<lb/>
tions in Cuba.</p>
<p>The confidence of the Government in the Provisional Gover-<lb/>
nor of Cuba, and in Major Kean, of the Army Medical Corps,<lb/>
the advisor of the sanitary department of Cuba, is such that<lb/>
the bureau feels that without the slightest American repre-<lb/>
sentation this question would be handled in Cuba in a man-<lb/>
ner satisfactory to the American people.</p>
<p>-----------</p>
<p>HAVANA, March 23, 1908.</p>
<p>MY DEAR GENERAL: I enclose you herewith copy of a di-<lb/>
rection which has been given to the Foreign Office of the Re-<lb/>
public of Cuba, and invite your careful perusal of it.</p>
<p>The unjustifiable action of the quarantine officials of the<lb/>
United States is a clear violation of the terms of a convention<lb/>
existing between the Republic of Cuba and the Government of<lb/>
the United States, and therefore it was necessary and, I be-<lb/>
lieve, desirable, to take the matter up through the Department<lb/>
of State. I am writing a personal letter to Minister Quesada<lb/>
requesting him to call on you and secure your valuable assist-<lb/>
ance in seeking to prevent the carrying out of the unjust order<lb/>
of quarantine, and I feel sure that you will aid him in every<lb/>
way possible.</p>
<p>There may have been a time when it was necessary to estab-<lb/>
lish quarantines because a fear existed that something might<lb/>
happen, especially when that something was yellow fever; that<lb/>
was a time when medical science was ignorant of the means<lb/>
1<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02959003"/>
2<lb/>
by which yellow fever is communicated, and therefore, the dis-<lb/>
ease spread very rapidly and could not be checked easily, if at<lb/>
all. The great horror of yellow fever arose from the fact that<lb/>
it spread so rapidly and that there was no specific for its<lb/>
cure, but in these days such fear is well-nigh absurd. Since<lb/>
August, 1904, I have been living in yellow fever-infected coun-<lb/>
tries and actively engaged in combating the disease, and there-<lb/>
fore I am not talking at random. I no more doubt the ability<lb/>
of a government which is fairly efficient, to check yellow fever,<lb/>
or to prevent an epidemic of that disease, than I doubt its ability<lb/>
to prevent an epidemic of broken legs. The stegomyia remains<lb/>
in the house and can, therefore, be destroyed by fumigation;<lb/>
and a fairly careful inspection and fairly effective fumiga-<lb/>
tion is all that is necessary to prevent an epidemic. Take<lb/>
Havana, for instance--when I arrived in October, 1906, there<lb/>
were, I think, fourteen cases in the city. There are more than<lb/>
100,000 non-immunes in the city. If nothing had been done,<lb/>
or if the disease had been fought in the way it used to be,<lb/>
twenty years ago, undoubtedly there would have been a yellow<lb/>
fever epidemic in the city; but by fumigating the house in<lb/>
which the disease appeared and adjacent houses the disease was<lb/>
kept down to a very few cases and eventually eliminated. I<lb/>
am quite sure there have been more serious accidents on the<lb/>
street railway or in or about the shipping in the harbor, than<lb/>
there have been cases of yellow fever. The point I want to<lb/>
make is that medical science knows how to and does control the<lb/>
spread of yellow fever.</p>
<p>We have an excellent system of medical inspection through-<lb/>
out the Island. Passengers and crews on board shipping leav-<lb/>
ing any port of the Island are subjected to medical examination,<lb/>
and examination is also made when the vessel arrives in the<lb/>
ports of the United States. If a case should escape our vigil-<lb/>
ance or the vigilance of the health authorities of a United States<lb/>
port, the danger is very slight, assuming, of course, that the<lb/>
health officers and physicians of the United States are fairly<lb/>
vigilant. This induced the fixing of the limit of eighteen<lb/>
days in the Sanitary Convention between the several countries<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02959004"/>
3<lb/>
parties thereto. It is entirely safe for the United States to<lb/>
carry out the terms of that Convention, and at least wait until<lb/>
a case exists in some seaport of Cuba before establishing a<lb/>
quarantine, and when such case does exist the quarantine<lb/>
should be against the port where the case appeared.</p>
<p>We are very careful about people leaving a city where there<lb/>
is yellow fever and going to some other town in the Island;<lb/>
they are kept under observation in the town to which they go.<lb/>
We have the co-operation of all health and sanitary officials<lb/>
--in fact, of everybody--and are expending vast sums of<lb/>
money in carrying out precautionary measures, and we should<lb/>
be helped and not hindered by the United States sanitary<lb/>
officials.</p>
<p>Havana is filled with tourists, and among them are many<lb/>
of my dearest friends, who have come here upon my invitation<lb/>
or by my urging. I am non-immune, and I think my experience<lb/>
in the past four years justifies me in saying that my opinions<lb/>
are not conceived in ignorance.</p>
<p>I am quite surprised that the sanitary officials of the United<lb/>
States should take a step which must necessarily be held as dis-<lb/>
crediting the mosquito theory of yellow fever transmission. If<lb/>
that theory is correct, and few intelligent men now combat it,<lb/>
then yellow fever must take its place among diseases the spread<lb/>
of which can be controlled; and when all possible effort is made<lb/>
to control it in accordance with that theory the result should be<lb/>
accepted and upheld, not allowed to go for naught.</p>
<p>Yours very truly,<lb/>
CHARLES E. MAGOON.<lb/>
BRIGADIER-GENERAL CLARENCE R. EDWARDS,<lb/>
Chief of the Bureau of Insular Affairs,<lb/>
Washington.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f02959005"/>
<p>4</p>
<p>HAVANA, March 19, 1908.</p>
<p>MY DEAR MR. SECRETARY: You are directed to advise<lb/>
Se&ntilde;or Gonzalo de Quesada, Envoy Extraordinary and Min-<lb/>
ister Plenipotentiary of the Republic of Cuba, in Washington,<lb/>
to inform the American Department of State that the Gov-<lb/>
ernment of Cuba has received, with regret and surprise, official<lb/>
notice that the Government of the United States proposes to<lb/>
establish a quarantine of the ports of that country against<lb/>
Cuba, beginning on April 1, 1908, and that the order of quar-<lb/>
antine makes no distinction between the Cuban ports; all are<lb/>
to be included.</p>
<p>The Cuban Minister will further advise the American De-<lb/>
partment of State that the last case of yellow fever in the<lb/>
City of Havana was discharged on January 31, 1908, and the<lb/>
last case in Havana before that on December 4, 1907; that the<lb/>
last case in Santiago de Cuba was discharged February 11,<lb/>
1908; and that the last case at Matanzas was discharged on<lb/>
October 26, 1907. These cities are the only seaports of the<lb/>
Island in which yellow fever has appeared during the past<lb/>
twelve months. During the past one hundred and twenty<lb/>
days there have been, in the whole Island, but twenty-eight<lb/>
cases of yellow fever.</p>
<p>The Cuban Minister will further advise the American De-<lb/>
partment of State that this Government believes and must insist<lb/>
that the establishment of the proposed quarantine on April<lb/>
first violates the spirit, if not the letter, of Section 2, Chapter<lb/>
<unclear>I</unclear>, of the International Sanitary Convention, signed ad referen-<lb/>
dum at Washington on October 14, 1905, which signing has<lb/>
been formally and duly ratified by both Cuba and the United<lb/>
States. The intention of Article VIII of this Section is to<lb/>
limit the measures to the infected region alone, and it would<lb/>
seem to forbid the application of a blanket quarantine, which<lb/>
would apply to the ports of one end of the Island when an in-<lb/>
fection existed only at the other, as was applied last year.<lb/>
Article IX provides as follows:</p>
<p>* * * "That an area should no longer be considered as in-<lb/>
fected, official proof must be furnished: * * * First that there<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02959006"/>
5<lb/>
has neither been a death nor a new case of plague or cholera for<lb/>
five days after isolation (I) death, or cure of the last plague or<lb/>
cholera case. In case of yellow fever the period shall be eighteen<lb/>
days, but each government may reserve the right to extend that<lb/>
period.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Second: That all the measures of disinfection have been ap-<lb/>
plied; in the case of plague, that the precautions against rats have<lb/>
been observed, and in the case of yellow fever that the measures<lb/>
against mosquitos have been executed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It will be observed that this Article limits the application<lb/>
of quarantine to the period of eighteen days after the occur-<lb/>
rence of the last case or the last death from yellow fever, with<lb/>
the proviso that either Government may reserve the right to<lb/>
extend this period.</p>
<p>As the last case of yellow fever in Cuba occurred in the city<lb/>
of Santa Clara, 150 miles east of Havana, on February 18,<lb/>
1908, and the last case in the city of Havana occurred on<lb/>
January 31, 1908, it is presumed that a declaration of quaran-<lb/>
tine is justified only by the proviso in Article IX.--&ldquo;but each<lb/>
Government may reserve the right to extend this period.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This proviso, following the statement of a definite limit<lb/>
of time, may fairly be assumed to be intended to give a means<lb/>
of self-defense to any nation against another as to which it<lb/>
may doubt the willingness or ability to carry out thoroughly or<lb/>
conscientiously the prescribed measures of disinfection and the<lb/>
prompt reporting of all cases.</p>
<p>It is believed that no such doubt can exist in Washington<lb/>
either with regard to the promptness and vigor with which<lb/>
all known measures to combat yellow fever are applied, or the<lb/>
candor and promptness with which all information accessible to<lb/>
the Cuban Sanitary Department has been at once placed at the<lb/>
disposal of the sanitary authorities of the United States by the<lb/>
Cuban Government.</p>
<p>The fact that the Government of Cuba is at present being<lb/>
provisionally administered by the United States should make<lb/>
such a suspicion untenable. If in the opinion of the sanitary<lb/>
authorities at Washington the time set by the International<lb/>
Sanitary Convention (eighteen days), which is the average<lb/>
time for the appearance of secondary cases from an infected<lb/>
one, is too short, double that time can be required, and still the<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02959007"/>
6<lb/>
conditions would not justify a quarantine. With regard to<lb/>
Havana, the interval might be multiplied by three and still the<lb/>
conditions would not justify a quarantine against this port,<lb/>
it being assumed that no new cases occur between this date<lb/>
and the first of April.</p>
<p>It is submitted that the occurrence of new cases of yellow<lb/>
fever in the interior of the Island does not make it necessary<lb/>
to quarantine the ports of Havana and Santiago de Cuba. It<lb/>
is true that passengers can reach these ports from the interior<lb/>
of the Island in a period varying from a few hours to a day,<lb/>
but these ports being free from yellow fever, nothing is easier<lb/>
than to enforce the requirement that passengers shall remain<lb/>
five days in the port city before embarking. This may be done<lb/>
by requiring passengers to report daily to a health officer of<lb/>
either the Department of Sanitation of the Republic of Cuba<lb/>
or the United States Public Health and Marine Hospital Ser-<lb/>
vice; and it will be as efficient a precaution as the inconvenient<lb/>
and tedious internment at the quarantine camp at Triscornia<lb/>
which was resorted to last year.</p>
<p>In 1900, when there were 310 deaths from yellow fever in<lb/>
Havana, passengers from Camp Columbia were not subjected<lb/>
to disinfection or treated as coming from an infected locality.<lb/>
Last year, however, when only one death from yellow fever<lb/>
occurred in Havana during the whole year, no exception was<lb/>
made for passengers coming from Columbia Barracks and other<lb/>
points equally free from yellow fever infection.</p>
<p>There are a number of thousands of American residents<lb/>
in Havana, who remain here throughout the summer with their<lb/>
families; yet no case of yellow fever in an American occurred<lb/>
last year. It seems that it would be difficult to bring forward<lb/>
a better evidence of the fact that Havana is not an infected<lb/>
city and should not be so treated.</p>
<p>It is the belief of the Cuban Government that the stegomyia<lb/>
mosquitos in Havana have been reduced below what is known<lb/>
as &ldquo;the yellow fever point,&rdquo; and hence that it is impossible for<lb/>
Havana to become infected unless, by the relaxation in the<lb/>
work of preventing the breeding of mosquitos, the number of<lb/>
stegomyia mosquitos is allowed to rise above this point.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f02959008"/>
<p>7</p>
<p>It is clear that the United States and the other parties to the<lb/>
agreement had certain objects in view in entering into the<lb/>
International Sanitary Convention above referred to; and that<lb/>
an important one of these objects was to make the precautions<lb/>
against the spread of the quarantinable diseases as little burden-<lb/>
some as possible, especially by limiting the application, the<lb/>
duration and the area of the quarantines.</p>
<p>The Cuban Minister will also bring to the attention of<lb/>
the American Department of State that upon the estab-<lb/>
lishment of the existing provisional Administration, in October,<lb/>
1906, yellow fever was found to exist in the Island, and that<lb/>
the Government at once proceeded to take energetic measures<lb/>
for its suppression. In the city of Havana, which was the<lb/>
most serious problem, there was a thorough reorganization of<lb/>
the existing methods. The city was divided into forty-two<lb/>
districts for the purposes of house-to-house inspection; and<lb/>
over each district was placed a carefully selected district in-<lb/>
spector who was made personally responsible for conditions<lb/>
in his district.</p>
<p>These methods were so effective that between the twenty-<lb/>
fifth of December, 1906, and the twenty-seventh of August,<lb/>
1907, not a single case of yellow fever appeared in the city of<lb/>
Havana, and only nine cases have occurred in Havana since<lb/>
that date.</p>
<p>It was found, however, that, owing to the ineffective char-<lb/>
acter of the municipal sanitary work in the eight-one muni-<lb/>
cipalities outside of Havana, which were not, like Havana, un-<lb/>
der direct Government control, the spread of yellow fever<lb/>
could not be checked, or effective methods taken to maintain<lb/>
conditions which would prevent its appearance; and it had<lb/>
therefore spread to several of the small municipalities of the<lb/>
interior.</p>
<p>To meet these new conditions the Government has made a<lb/>
sweeping and radical reorganization of the sanitary system of<lb/>
the Republic, and has assumed direct control of municipal sani-<lb/>
tary work throughout the Island. So great and elaborate a<lb/>
measure could not be at once installed and set in motion, but<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02959009"/>
8<lb/>
the organization is now complete and the Central Government<lb/>
is now prepared to do effective sanitary work throughout the<lb/>
Island at a cost to the Government treasury of not less than<lb/>
$150,000 a month outside of the exclusive sanitary services of<lb/>
the city of Havana.</p>
<p>In the meanwhile, local foci of infection have been attacked<lb/>
wherever they have appeared, with sweeping and thorough<lb/>
methods of disinfection. A new system of disinfection has been<lb/>
developed by which entire city blocks are covered with great<lb/>
sheets of canvas and all the houses in a block fumigated simul-<lb/>
taneously.</p>
<p>To show the sweeping character of these measures, three<lb/>
cases of yellow fever appeared in Santiago de Cuba, one in<lb/>
each of the months of December, January, and February, just<lb/>
passed, being the only cases that have occurred there in a num-<lb/>
ber of years. The special sanitary measures carried out on<lb/>
account of these three cases have cost the Cuban Government<lb/>
more than $30,000 or at a rate of $10,000 for each case, in ad-<lb/>
dition to the routine sanitary work of that city.</p>
<p>The total amount of money spent for yellow fever works,<lb/>
and works of municipal sanitation under the reorganization<lb/>
above referred to, since the establishment of the Provisional<lb/>
Government, has been $1,566,085. This does not include the<lb/>
cost of the sanitary service in Havana, which would be up-<lb/>
wards of $2,000,000 more.</p>
<p>During the last fifteen months, 188 cases of yellow fever<lb/>
have occurred within the limits of the Republic, of which<lb/>
twenty-nine have occurred during the last three and a half<lb/>
months (since November 30th). During the month of Febru-<lb/>
ary, 1908, yellow fever appeared in two localities in the Island:<lb/>
viz., Santiago de Cuba and Santa Clara; in both of which places<lb/>
it is believed to be now extinguished. No cases have occurred<lb/>
during the month of March, up to this date; and with the pres-<lb/>
ent measures at the command of this Government, it is believed<lb/>
that any smouldering foci which may develop hereafter can<lb/>
be promptly extinguished.</p>
<p>Work to prevent the breeding of mosquitos is going on<lb/>
throughout the infected zones, and it is improving in efficiency.<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f02959010"/>
9<lb/>
With these services it is difficult to see any reason for the<lb/>
assumption that Cuba will hereafter be a dangerous neighbor,<lb/>
against which the most severe measures must be taken.</p>
<p>This Government insists that quarantine against all Cuban<lb/>
ports is not justified by the sanitary conditions existing in the<lb/>
Island, and that any uneasiness which exists in the American<lb/>
Southern States can be satisfied by less radical measures, which<lb/>
will give complete security to the United States with less<lb/>
damage and inconvenience to the Republic of Cuba.</p>
<p>The attention of the American Department of State should<lb/>
also be directed to the necessity of recognition and consider-<lb/>
ation by the United States of the efforts of the Republic of<lb/>
Cuba to discharge the obligations of the International Sani-<lb/>
tary Convention resting upon said Republic. It would be<lb/>
exceedingly discouraging if, after the expenditure of so much<lb/>
money and effort and the accomplishment of such great im-<lb/>
provement in the matter of sanitation, the Republic received no<lb/>
other or different treatment than would have been accorded in<lb/>
the absence of such effort. The Cubans believe themselves to<lb/>
be exempt from yellow fever, but they cheerfully expend pub-<lb/>
lic moneys and make extensive effort to eradicate yellow fever;<lb/>
first, because they desire to promote friendship and good will<lb/>
with the United States, and, second, because of the commer-<lb/>
cial advantages to the Island.</p>
<p>The action now contemplated by the United States will de-<lb/>
prive them of the commercial advantages; for instance, many<lb/>
tourists now in Cuba who expected to remain several weeks<lb/>
longer are preparing to leave the Island prior to April first,<lb/>
and others who contemplated coming will abandon their trip;<lb/>
and there are, of course, many and more important injuries to<lb/>
trade which invariably result from a quarantine against the<lb/>
ports of an island.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
CHARLES E. MAGOON,<lb/>
Provisional Governor.<lb/>
The Acting Secretary, Department of State.<lb/>
Havana,</p>
<pb n="11" id="f02959011"/>
<p>10</p>
<p>REPUBLIC OF CUBA.<lb/>
UNDER PROVISIONAL ADMINISTRATION OF THE UNITED STATES.</p>
<p>HAVANA, CUBA, March 29, 1908.</p>
<p>MY DEAR GENERAL: Enclosed please find copy of a letter<lb/>
written by my direction, by Major J. R. Kean, Adviser to the<lb/>
Department of Sanitation of the Government of Cuba, to Dr.<lb/>
John N. Thomas, Acting Assistant Surgeon, U. S. P. H. &amp; M.<lb/>
H. S., Havana, Cuba. The letter refers to the sanitary condi-<lb/>
tions in Cuba and the quarantine about to be established by the<lb/>
United States against Cuba.</p>
<p>I think this letter will be of assistance to you in securing the<lb/>
abandonment, or modification, of the proposed order of quar-<lb/>
antine. My own view continues to be that the United States<lb/>
is bound to withhold establishing a quarantine until there is a<lb/>
case of yellow fever in the Island. You will observe Kean sug-<lb/>
gests that Havana be dealt with as though it were an isola-<lb/>
tion camp, and therefore living in Havana for the five days im-<lb/>
mediately preceding sailing should entitle the person to admis-<lb/>
sion into the ports of the United States. If this is the best<lb/>
that can be done, then the order should include Camp Colum-<lb/>
bia and Marianao: inclusion of these two localities is quite im-<lb/>
portant.</p>
<p>Sincerely yours,<lb/>
CHARLES E. MAGOON,<lb/>
BRIG.-GEN. CLARENCE R. EDWARDS,<lb/>
Chief, Bureau of Insular Affairs,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>HAVANA, CUBA, March 26, 1908.</p>
<p>DR. JOHN N. THOMAS,<lb/>
Acting Assistant Surgeon, U. S. P. H. &amp; M. H. S.,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba.</p>
<p>MY DEAR DR. THOMAS: With reference to our conversa-<lb/>
tion as to sanitary conditions in Cuba, and especially in Havana,<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f02959012"/>
11<lb/>
I desire to suggest for your consideration and for your sub-<lb/>
mission to the head of your Department, if you are willing to<lb/>
do so, the substitution of less burdensome and restrictive meas-<lb/>
ures for the quarantine which it is proposed to establish against<lb/>
the whole Island of Cuba on the first of April.</p>
<p>It is my belief that none of the Cuban ports is infected with<lb/>
yellow fever at the present time. I believe that in Havana the<lb/>
warfare against stegomyia mosquitos has been so successful<lb/>
that it is impossible to infect it; and the other important ports,<lb/>
Matanzas, Cienfuegos and Santiago de Cuba, are rapidly ap-<lb/>
proaching this condition.</p>
<p>In Matanzas there has been no case of yellow fever since<lb/>
the 27th of October, 1907, and this was the only case which oc-<lb/>
curred in that city in over a year, although during the summer,<lb/>
three cases occurred at the village of Ceiba Mocha, in the mu-<lb/>
nicipality of Matanzas, about ten miles distant from the city,<lb/>
the infection having come from Union de Reyes.</p>
<p>Sanitary matters in Santiago de Cuba and Cienfuegos are at<lb/>
present under the immediate supervision of Medical Officers of<lb/>
the Army, detailed as Special Commissioners for that work,<lb/>
who are conducting the service of inspection of non-immunes<lb/>
with fever and the work of mosquito prevention with energy<lb/>
and ability. Under these circumstances it is difficult to see why<lb/>
these ports should be treated as infected.</p>
<p>In Havana, I do not hesitate to claim that the facilities for<lb/>
the detection of yellow fever are superior to those of any<lb/>
other large city in the world owing to the following condi-<lb/>
tions:</p>
<p>The non-immune population is almost entirely Spanish and<lb/>
American, of which the Spanish element is by far the largest.<lb/>
It is the custom of the Spanish immigrants on arriving in<lb/>
Havana to join one of a half dozen great Spanish societies,<lb/>
which are in reality co-operative associations and which furnish,<lb/>
among other things, medical attendance to sick members, and<lb/>
which have large and well-appointed hospitals in this city.<lb/>
The membership of these clubs is as follows:<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f02959013"/>
12<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Centro Dependientes.................. 27,494</item>
<item>" Asturiano ..................... 27,627</item>
<item>" Gallego ...................... 25,060</item>
<item>Asociacion Canaria .................. 15,329</item>
<item>" Balear ..................... 4,000</item>
<item>---------</item>
<item>Total.......................... 99,510</item>
</list></p>
<p>Though the members are not all in Havana, almost every<lb/>
Spaniard in the city is a member of one of them.</p>
<p>The great majority of the Spanish immigrants are unmar-<lb/>
ried, the wives of those who are married being almost <unclear>invar-<lb/>
iably</unclear> immune Cuban women. As the members universally go<lb/>
to the hospital of their clubs for medical advice, and when<lb/>
necessary, for hospital treatment, the Sanitary Department by<lb/>
a daily inspection of the hospitals is able to see practically all<lb/>
the cases of sickness in this class of non-immunes.</p>
<p>These hospitals are required to have their fever wards and<lb/>
even their consulting rooms thoroughly screened, and to re-<lb/>
port to the Medical Inspector of the Sanitary Department each<lb/>
case of a non-immune having fever.</p>
<p>The American population are practically all treated by two<lb/>
or three American Physicians; and suspicious cases among<lb/>
them are quite certain to come to the notice of the Sanitary De-<lb/>
partment.</p>
<p>The practice of the Cuban physicians is practically confined<lb/>
to Cuban immune population; and thus it will be seen that the<lb/>
Sanitary Department is far less dependent upon the report-<lb/>
ing of cases by general practitioners in Havana than in other<lb/>
cities.</p>
<p>For the study of suspicious cases there has been since 1899<lb/>
an official Board, known as the Board of Diagnosis of Con-<lb/>
tagious Diseases, of which Dr. Carlos J. Finlay, Dr. Juan<lb/>
Guiteras and Dr. Aristides Agramonte are members; men<lb/>
whose reputation as experts in yellow fever will be admitted to<lb/>
be equal to that of any three physicians in the world.</p>
<p>With such extraordinary facilities for the detection and<lb/>
diagnosis of cases of yellow fever, and with the excellent record<lb/>
which Havana has recently had with regard to its occurrence,<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f02959014"/>
13<lb/>
it seems perfectly safe to treat it as a non-infected city. To<lb/>
do otherwise is to ignore scientific facts, treaty right and the<lb/>
interests and convenience of American citizens.</p>
<p>Havana being admitted to be a clean city, the application of<lb/>
a quarantine to it on account of the occurrence of cases in the<lb/>
<unclear>interior</unclear> is entirely unnecessary. Nothing is easier than to re-<lb/>
quire evidence that all persons taking passage for the United<lb/>
States shall reside in Havana a sufficient time before embarka-<lb/>
tion to make up six days before they reach their destination in<lb/>
the United States. This furnishes a guaranty as complete as<lb/>
the quarantine and as the majority of passengers do not come<lb/>
from the interior, it is far less disturbing to travelers, and in<lb/>
fact would inconvenience the majority of persons coming to<lb/>
Havana for pleasure and health very slightly. In the absence<lb/>
of cases in the interior even this precaution would be un-<lb/>
necessary.</p>
<p>While it is admitted that there are difficulties in the way of<lb/>
prompt recognition and reporting of cases of fever in the small<lb/>
interior towns, these difficulties have been to a large extent<lb/>
overcome by the creation of zones of observation embracing the<lb/>
localities where cases of yellow fever have occurred within six<lb/>
months. These zones are under the constant observation of<lb/>
Special Inspectors of this Department; and as a still further<lb/>
safeguard, skilled microscopists with a good clinical knowledge<lb/>
of yellow fever have been appointed Medical Scouts and con-<lb/>
stantly patrol these zones, making blood examinations and<lb/>
urinalyses and critically investigating cases which are in any<lb/>
way suspicous. There is an additional service of train in-<lb/>
spectors, keeping track of the movement of <unclear>non-immunes</unclear> from<lb/>
the Guines-Uni&oacute;n zone and train inspector at Santo Domingo<lb/>
who keeps track of the traffic going east and west in the Island.<lb/>
This train service could be increased, if necessary, but I do not<lb/>
believe it desirable to do so.</p>
<p>If the United States Sanitary authorities desire any additional<lb/>
precautions taken, they have only to suggest them.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
J. R. KEAN,<lb/>
Advisor to Sanitary Department.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f02959015"/>
<p>14</p>
<p>[Copy of Cablegram Received.]</p>
<p>HAVANA, March 27, 1908.</p>
<p>EDWARDS, WASHINGTON.</p>
<p>Quarantine against Cuba serious matter, as it works great<lb/>
injury to commercial interests. All tourists are cutting short<lb/>
their stay although weather here cool and health conditions<lb/>
superb. Large number of tourists have arranged to remain if<lb/>
any assurances are given that quarantine will not be established<lb/>
on April first. Tuesday last date they can leave and get in<lb/>
United States before April first. Am anxious to get notice of<lb/>
suspension at once. It is certainly safe beyond question to ex-<lb/>
tend limit until April fifteenth. The order should be suspended<lb/>
at least until a case of yellow fever exists in Cuba.</p>
<p>MAGOON.</p>
<p>------</p>
<p>On the receipt of this telegram from Governor Magoon the<lb/>
Secretary of War called on General Robert M. O'Reilly, Sur-<lb/>
geon-General of the Army, for a confidential report.</p>
<p>General O'Reilly is himself an expert on yellow fever, hav-<lb/>
ing served as chief surgeon of the Military Division of Cuba<lb/>
during the former American occupation, when yellow fever<lb/>
was prevalent, and having had the disease himself. Moreover,<lb/>
he has at his service a corps of officers who certainly represent<lb/>
in the highest degree, not only in the eyes of the United States,<lb/>
but in the eyes of the world, expert knowledge of tropical<lb/>
medicine.</p>
<p>------</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON-GENERAL<lb/>
WASHINGTON</p>
<p>March 30, 1908.</p>
<p>Memorandum for the Secretary of War:</p>
<p>I assume that the Surgeon-General of the Public Health<lb/>
and Marine Hospital Service would not desire to impose quar-<lb/>
antine restrictions against the Island of Cuba if he were satis-<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f02959016"/>
15<lb/>
fied that yellow fever does not exist in the Island. He seems<lb/>
to consider that there may be a number of mild cases there,<lb/>
but there is also a large number of non-immunes--Spanish<lb/>
immigrants, Americans, soldiers and civilians and Cuban chil-<lb/>
dren who have been born during the period when the Island<lb/>
was free from the fever, so that there must be a large non-<lb/>
immune population, and among these it is reasonably certain<lb/>
that a mild form of the disease could not exist for any length<lb/>
of time without the occurrence of some severe cases.</p>
<p>The Advisor to the Department of Sanitation of the Cuban<lb/>
Government is a very efficient medical officer who possesses the<lb/>
entire confidence of this Department, and who, although not<lb/>
formally a part of the Reed Commission, really took part in<lb/>
its debates and proceedings, and was also in consultation with<lb/>
Colonel Gorgas at the time the latter officer cleaned yellow<lb/>
fever out of Havana. He has at present a Sanitary Organiza-<lb/>
tion which I think would keep him advised of any yellow fever<lb/>
in the Island.</p>
<p>I do not think any great harm would or could result from<lb/>
delaying the date of the imposition of quarantine against Cuba<lb/>
until the Government of Cuba was given an opportunity to<lb/>
satisfy the President of the freedom of the Island from yellow<lb/>
fever. This should not be a matter of more than four or five<lb/>
days.</p>
<p>R. M. O'REILLY,<lb/>
Surgeon-General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>[Cablegram]<lb/>
BUREAU OF INSULAR AFFAIRS<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT</p>
<p>WASHINGTON, March 30, 1908.</p>
<p>MAGOON, Havana:</p>
<p>Following memorandum comes to War Department from<lb/>
White House, evidently there submitted by Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service. First under head of legality quote provision of sec-<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f02959017"/>
16<lb/>
tion nine of convention adopted at Second International Sani-<lb/>
tary Convention of American Republics ratified by President<lb/>
May twenty-ninth ninteen hunderd six. Then follows quota-<lb/>
tion from remarks of Doctor Guiteras, Cuban represntative,<lb/>
in proceedings of this convention and then goes on as follows:</p>
<p>There is no doubt, therefore, of the authority of the United<lb/>
States to extend the period of quarantine, and it will be seen<lb/>
from Dr. Guiteras' statement that such action was fully con-<lb/>
templated in adopting the article.</p>
<p>PRACTICE.</p>
<p>Vessels bound from Cuba to southern ports of the United<lb/>
States, which lie at approved moorings prior to taking on<lb/>
cargo or receiving passengers, are not required to be disinfected<lb/>
either at the point of departure or at the port of arrival in the<lb/>
United States. Immune passengers, namely, those who pre-<lb/>
sent satisfactory evidence of having had an attack of yellow<lb/>
fever, or of having resided in an endemic focus of the disease<lb/>
for ten years, are permitted to embark and disembark without<lb/>
hindrance, upon being furnished a certificate by the Public<lb/>
Health and Marine Hospital officer at Havana, setting forth<lb/>
such immunity. Passengers who are not immune, are required<lb/>
to reside at the detention camp in Triscornia for five days, if<lb/>
going to New Orleans or Mobile, or six days if going to a<lb/>
Florida port, prior to sailing. At the port in the United States,<lb/>
there is no detention, other than the usual inspection which<lb/>
takes place at the same time as the examination of the baggage<lb/>
by the customs officials. No vessels engaged in passenger traf-<lb/>
fic with the southern ports of the United States are allowed to<lb/>
land at wharves in Havana. Vessels which land at wharves<lb/>
are usually fruit vessels which, upon arriving in the United<lb/>
States, are detained to complete a period of five days from the<lb/>
time of departure, and are fumigated.</p>
<p>Vessels for northern ports, carrying passengers, also lie at<lb/>
moorings in the open bay beyond the flight of the stegomyia<lb/>
mosquito. They are inspected prior to taking on freight and<lb/>
passengers. Certificates of immunity are not required for pas-<lb/>
sengers embarking on these steamers, nor is there the prelimin-<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f02959018"/>
17<lb/>
ary detention at Triscornia. The vessels occupy generally<lb/>
three and one-half days in the trip to New York. On arrival<lb/>
at New York, the vessels are inspected at the State quarantine<lb/>
station on Staten Island and those passengers who do not<lb/>
give an authenticated residential address in Greater New York,<lb/>
are detained at the detention station, Hoffman Island, New<lb/>
York Harbor, for a sufficient length of time to complete five<lb/>
days from time of departure from Havana. This detention<lb/>
seldom amounts to more than one and one-half days.</p>
<p>ADVISABILITY.</p>
<p>The Public Health and Marine Hospital officers are decided<lb/>
in their views of the necessity of maintaining the present ar-<lb/>
rangements. Last year the close season began on the 15th of<lb/>
March, but this year, the time was extended to the 1st of<lb/>
April. From January to March is the period when there is<lb/>
the smallest amount of yellow fever in Cuba. From January<lb/>
to March, 1907, there were two cases reported in Cuba; for<lb/>
the same period this year there were 28. From April to June,<lb/>
1907, there were eleven cases, and from July to December,<lb/>
1907, there were 148 cases. During the past nine months,<lb/>
there have been 176 cases of yellow fever reported on the Island<lb/>
of Cuba, as compared with ninty-five for the corresponding<lb/>
period of the year before. The representative of the Public<lb/>
Health and Marine Hospital Service in Havana reports that<lb/>
from January 1 to February 26, 1907, there was one focus of<lb/>
infection in the Island of Cuba; for the same period this year,<lb/>
the number of foci reported was approximately nineteen.</p>
<p>Although in the past three months there have been only<lb/>
two cases of yellow fever in Havana, and in the past two<lb/>
months only ten cases in the Island of Cuba, reported, the<lb/>
officers of the Public Health and Marine Hospital Service be-<lb/>
lieve that yellow fever probably exists, although possibly but<lb/>
in a mild form, at the present time. This view is based on the<lb/>
fact that a considerable percentage of persons with yellow fever<lb/>
are not sufficiently ill to prevent their being up and about,<lb/>
and yet the infection from these persons is just as severe as<lb/>
from others affected with a more serious form of the disease.<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f02959019"/>
18<lb/>
The experience of the officials at the head of the Public Health<lb/>
and Marine Hospital Service who have been in Cuba has been<lb/>
that Cuban doctors are accustomed to disregard and not to<lb/>
diagnose as yellow fever mild cases which are clinically proven<lb/>
to be yellow fever.</p>
<p>Mosquitos can be infected from a person during the first<lb/>
three days of illness. After twelve days, a mosquito is capable<lb/>
of communicating the disease, and this power of infection lasts<lb/>
during the life of the mosquito which has been known, in<lb/>
some cases, to be 180 days. A person infected by the bite<lb/>
of a mosquito develops the disease usually between three or<lb/>
four days. In some cases the period of incubation has been<lb/>
as much as five days and seventeen hours, and in some cases<lb/>
as little as sixteen hours.</p>
<p>The stegomyia, or yellow fever mosquito, does not exist<lb/>
north of a line drawn through the southern boundary of Mary-<lb/>
land. Consequently, a patient affected with yellow fever in<lb/>
localities north of this line would not be a menace to the com-<lb/>
munity. If the quarantine regulations were abolished, and ves-<lb/>
sels coming from Cuba were not detained, it would be possible<lb/>
for a person infected in Cuba by the bite of a mosquito to ar-<lb/>
rive in New York and to proceed to some place south of the<lb/>
southern boundary of Maryland before developing yellow<lb/>
fever. If this locality should be a place where yellow fever<lb/>
is not well known, and there the stegomyia exists, the spread<lb/>
would probably be rapid and extensive. This has indeed oc-<lb/>
curred. In 1890, for example, Mr. Ellinger, coming from<lb/>
Havana, arrived at the port of New York, and at once pro-<lb/>
ceeded to his home in Key West, there being no quarantine<lb/>
restrictions at that time in New York. Shortly after his ar-<lb/>
rival in Key West, he developed yellow fever.</p>
<p>In view of the possibility of yellow fever in a mild form<lb/>
existing at present in certain parts of Cuba and the fact that<lb/>
the stegomyia mosquito exists in the southern portions of the<lb/>
United States, it would seem unsafe to remove the quarantine<lb/>
regulations for vessels arriving at one of the southern ports.</p>
<p>If the quarantine restrictions were removed at the northern<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f02959020"/>
19<lb/>
ports, the chances of a person infected with yellow fever in<lb/>
Cuba, proceeding to New York, not developing the disease<lb/>
before arrival, thence proceeding to a point south of the south-<lb/>
ern boundary of Maryland, and there developing, the disease<lb/>
is slight. On the other hand, should this occur, the chances of<lb/>
infecting a large area with yellow fever would be great.</p>
<p>Have taken matter up with Medical Department, and<lb/>
O'Reilly makes following memorandum: (quote) "I assume<lb/>
that the Surgeon General of the Public Health and Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service would not desire to impose quarantine re-<lb/>
strictions against the Island of Cuba if he were satisfied that<lb/>
yellow fever does not exist in the Island. He seems to consider<lb/>
that there may be a number of mild cases there, but there is<lb/>
also a large number of non-immunes--Spanish immigrants,<lb/>
Americans, soldiers and civilians and Cuban children--who<lb/>
have been born during the period when the Island was free<lb/>
from the fever, so that there must be a large non-immune<lb/>
population, and among these it is reasonably certain that a mild<lb/>
form the disease cauld not exist for any length of time without<lb/>
the occurrence of some severe cases.</p>
<p>"The Advisor to the Department of Sanitation of the Cuban<lb/>
Government is a very efficient medical officer who possesses<lb/>
the entire confidence of this Department, and who, although<lb/>
not formally a part of the Reed Commission, really took part<lb/>
in its debates and proceedings, and was also in consultation<lb/>
with Colonel Gorgas at the time the latter officer cleaned yel-<lb/>
low fever out of Havana. He has at present a sanitary or-<lb/>
ganization which I think would keep him advised of any yellow<lb/>
fever in the Island.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I do not think any great harm would or could result from<lb/>
delaying the date of the imposition of quarantine against Cuba<lb/>
until the Government of Cuba was given an opportunity to<lb/>
satisfy the President of the freedom of the Island from yellow<lb/>
fever. This should not be a matter of more than four or five<lb/>
days.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Let's hear from you on this matter immediately. Will<lb/>
advise you of action of White House.</p>
<p>EDWARDS.</p>
<pb n="21" id="f02959021"/>
<p>20</p>
<p>[Translation of cablegram received at 6:05 p.m. April 2, 1908.]</p>
<p>HAVANA.</p>
<p>EDWARDS, Washington.</p>
<p>Regret change of date from that announced in press dis-<lb/>
patches, but feel confident showing made will cause indefinite<lb/>
suspension quarantine. Feeling here intensely resentful. See<lb/>
article La Lucha English page, March 31st. Article in Span-<lb/>
ish few days prior said useless for Cuba to spend money on<lb/>
sanitation for which no benefit is received; that evidently<lb/>
United States had determined to trade with Cuba only when<lb/>
winter weather permitted; that sanitation in Cuba did not effect<lb/>
temperature in United States Verb Sap.</p>
<p>MAGOON.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>[Copy of Cablegram received 5.40 p. m., April 2, 1908.]</p>
<p>HAVANA.</p>
<p>SECRETARY OF WAR, WASHINGTON: I desire to state as<lb/>
follows, as to memorandum in your cable of March 30th:</p>
<p>Attention is invited to the fact that although Section<lb/>
ninth of sanitary convention provides for extension of quaran-<lb/>
tine beyond specified time of eighteen days, it does not recog-<lb/>
nize right to impose quarantine in the absence of evidence of<lb/>
existing quarantinable disease. There is no evidence known to<lb/>
Cuban sanitary authorities of existence of yellow fever<lb/>
in Cuba to-day. With regard statement of occurrence<lb/>
of yellow fever in Cuba this winter as compared with<lb/>
last, it is admitted that there have been more cases dur-<lb/>
ing the past winter due to several factors, prominent among<lb/>
which must be considered the increased facility given by new<lb/>
national sanitary organization for detection of cases. In ad-<lb/>
dition to personal responsibility of local sanitary officers under<lb/>
the new organization, all places where cases have occurred<lb/>
within six months are included in three zones under direct<lb/>
charge of special commissioners, who visit frequently all<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="f02959022"/>
21<lb/>
points under observation and observe mosquito work and cases<lb/>
of fever. In addition each zone has a medical scout who is<lb/>
clinically experienced in yellow fever and is a competent micro-<lb/>
scopist, who travels continually through the zone, examining<lb/>
cases of fever in non-immunes and making blood examinations<lb/>
and urinalyses. The number of cases in Cuba since January<lb/>
first is twenty, of which one is doubtful instead of twenty-<lb/>
eight, as stated by the Marine Hospital Service. They<lb/>
state number of foci in this period is nineteen,<lb/>
whereas fever has appeared in only nine localities counting<lb/>
separately different places in same municipality. Statement<lb/>
that &ldquo;last year the close season began on the fifteenth of<lb/>
March, but this year the time was extended to the first of<lb/>
April,&rdquo; is erroneous. Last year quarantine against Cuba was<lb/>
declared May twenty-eighth, after occurrence of three cases<lb/>
in May, and five since first of January. Yellow fever experts<lb/>
count the yellow fever year to begin April first, regarding cases<lb/>
prior to that date as aftermath of preceding epidemic year.<lb/>
This clearly applies to the thirteen cases in seven localities oc-<lb/>
curring in January, and seven cases in two localities occurring<lb/>
in February of this year. Taking the epidemic year instead of<lb/>
the calendar year, quarantine was imposed last year after<lb/>
occurrence of three cases, but it is proposed this year before<lb/>
the occurrence of any case. It will be difficult to explain at<lb/>
next meeting of International Sanitary Congress this action<lb/>
if no case has occurred in whole Island since February eigh-<lb/>
teenth. United States sanitary authorities do not count residence<lb/>
in Havana since year nineteen hundred in granting immunity<lb/>
certificates. This seems inconsistent with present disposition<lb/>
to regard it as an epidemic focus. Cuban Government claims<lb/>
that Havana is and should be regarded a non-infected city.</p>
<p>Attention invited to fact that facilities for recognizing and<lb/>
reporting mild cases in Havana are unrivalled by any city of<lb/>
its size, due to fact that all suspicious cases are seen by most<lb/>
skillful expert board in the world also that recognition of cases<lb/>
does not depend upon report of suspicious cases by Cuban<lb/>
physicians because a vast majority of non-immunes are not<lb/>
<pb n="23" id="f02959023"/>
22<lb/>
treated by them. Americans, treated by American physi-<lb/>
cians, while Spaniards, who make up great bulk of non-<lb/>
immunes in Havana, are members of benevolent associations<lb/>
which maintain hospitals, to which members go for free medi-<lb/>
cal treatment; membership of these associations is over<lb/>
ninety-nine thousand. These hospitals are under rigid<lb/>
daily inspection, by experts of sanitary department, who<lb/>
report all suspicious cases to the board of diagnosis.<lb/>
In addition, there are stringent and successful measures taken<lb/>
to exterminate stegomyia, which have almost disappeared from<lb/>
Havana. For a year past the city of Havana divided into<lb/>
forty-two districts, for house to house inspections, of which<lb/>
more than two thousand are made daily, and occupants of<lb/>
<unclear>houses</unclear> fined whenever mosquito larva are found on premises.<lb/>
For example, number of houses inspected in Havana, March<lb/>
thirtieth, was two thousand twenty-nine, number of places<lb/>
where mosquito larva were found was one, which, on examina-<lb/>
tion proved not to be stegomyia. On March thirty-first, two<lb/>
thousand thirty-nine houses, including premises, were inspected,<lb/>
and no deposit of larva found. Work of these district inspec-<lb/>
tors is rigidly followed up by re-inspections, made by special<lb/>
inspectors. The fact that no case of yellow fever has ap-<lb/>
peared in Havana in two months, with its large non-immune<lb/>
population, in spite of the warm weather of March of this<lb/>
year, shows Havana to be not infected. For the past six weeks<lb/>
Havana has been filled with American tourists all of whom<lb/>
have loudly praised the cleanliness of the city. With full ap-<lb/>
preciation of the magnitude of the claim, I assert that Havana<lb/>
is to-day the cleanest city of its size in the world. The sanitary<lb/>
authorities here concur fully in the opinion of Surgeon-General<lb/>
O'Reilly that although mild cases of yellow fever may go un-<lb/>
recognized, it is not possible that a mild form of the disease<lb/>
could exist any length of time without the occurrence of severe<lb/>
cases and deaths. The fact that there has been, since Novem-<lb/>
ber, nineteen hundred six, only one death from yellow<lb/>
fever, contracted in Havana, is considered a demonstration that<lb/>
the disease is not existing in a mild form in this city.</p>
<pb n="24" id="f02959024"/>
<p>23</p>
<p>I have consulted the National Sanitary Board and also the Board<lb/>
of Diagnosis of Contagious Diseases with regard to the question<lb/>
of quarantine, and both boards are unanimous in their expres-<lb/>
sion of opinion, first, that such a measure is not necessary for<lb/>
the protection of the United States against infection from<lb/>
Cuba; second, that Havana should not be considered an in-<lb/>
fected city or suspected of being infected, and third, that in the<lb/>
event of occurrence of new cases of yellow fever in other parts<lb/>
of the Island the safety of the United States can be abundantly<lb/>
guaranteed by substituting for detention at Triscornia a period<lb/>
of residence in Havana and its suburbs. The Board of Diag-<lb/>
nosis of Contagious Diseases adds the following remarks, with<lb/>
reference to the statement of the Marine Hospital Service, giv-<lb/>
en in cable, that the life of a mosquito has been known, in some<lb/>
cases, to be one hundred and eighty days: &ldquo;With respect to<lb/>
the assertion made in the statement presented to the President<lb/>
of the United States to the effect that the duration of the life<lb/>
of a mosquito may extend to a period of one hundred and<lb/>
eighty days, this commission wishes to state that in the experi-<lb/>
ence of some of its members, who have made experiments in<lb/>
this direction, the duration of life has reached one hundred and<lb/>
<unclear>fifty</unclear>-four days, in one single instance, which was one of a con-<lb/>
siderable number in which the insect was afforded every pro-<lb/>
tection against its natural enemies. During the experiments of<lb/>
the U. S. A. Commission, in Havana, the insects that were left<lb/>
free in the house for experimental purposes were all destroyed<lb/>
by other insects within a period of a very few days. We be-<lb/>
lieve that this latter experiment represents more accurately the<lb/>
normal expectation of life of free mosquitoes than the very<lb/>
special conditions of laboratory life, where the insects are <unclear>pro-<lb/>
tected</unclear> from all accidents and enemies.&rdquo; Attention is called to<lb/>
the fact that the stegomyia is parasitic in its habits and being<lb/>
also of delicate organism seeks shelter in human habitations,<lb/>
where it is exposed to its enemies, of which there are a large<lb/>
number, such as spiders, ants, beetles, house lizards, etc. The<lb/>
stegomyia is more easily affected by moderately cold weather<lb/>
than its enemies and becoming torpid is easy prey. In the win-<lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f02959025"/>
24<lb/>
ter months this takes place in Cuba. The contention of the<lb/>
Cuban Government is that, between the efforts of its sanitary<lb/>
department, and the beneficial effects of the climate, during<lb/>
the winter months, the slate has been cleaned, certainly with<lb/>
regard Havana and its environments, and probably with regard<lb/>
the rest of the Island, and that the United States should with-<lb/>
hold action until yellow fever again appears in the Island;<lb/>
that withholding until a new case appears is a moral obligation<lb/>
arising from the comity of nations in the absence of all treaty<lb/>
stipulations and the existence of the sanitary convention of<lb/>
1905, makes such obligation positive and certain.</p>
<p>Object of the Sanitary Convention between the United States<lb/>
and Cuba is to limit the geographical area and duration of<lb/>
quarantines. As regards area it is urged that Cuba is over seven<lb/>
hundred miles long, and the occurrence of a quarantinable dis-<lb/>
ease in part one should not cause quarantine of the entire Island<lb/>
any more than occurrence at Norfolk should cause quarantine<lb/>
against Jacksonville. Occurrence of yellow fever outside of<lb/>
the province of Havana should not cause quarantine of<lb/>
Havana, but in substitution thereof observation of passengers<lb/>
in Havana for the requisite number of days. Details of such<lb/>
observation for interior towns situated beyond the zone of<lb/>
electric trolley communication with Havana, can be easily ar-<lb/>
ranged by agreement with local representatives of the United<lb/>
States quarantine service. In other words, it is proposed to<lb/>
substitute observation in Havana and its suburbs, Marianao,<lb/>
and Camp Columbia, for observation at quarantine camp at<lb/>
Triscornia. Applicants for passage on steamships to the United<lb/>
States can be examined daily, about the middle of the day, or,<lb/>
<unclear>if</unclear> necessary, twice daily, and if necessary, lists of passengers,<lb/>
on all roads leaving Havana, on afternoon trains, can be kept<lb/>
to insure applicants not leaving Havana. Other precautions,<lb/>
thought necessary by local representatives of the United States<lb/>
quarantine service can be taken.</p>
<p>It is requested, therefore, first, that no steps be<lb/>
taken to restrict travel until a case of yellow fever occurs in<lb/>
Cuba; second, that upon the occurrence of such case the<lb/>
<pb n="26" id="f02959026"/>
25<lb/>
measures taken in accordance with the spirit of Sanitary<lb/>
Convention of October fourteenth, nineteen hundred<lb/>
five, be localized so as to prevent travel of passengers from such<lb/>
locality or province, to the United States, by observation of<lb/>
passengers in clean ports, in place of blanket quarantine, em-<lb/>
bracing the whole Island; third, that Commission of Sanitary<lb/>
Experts from the Southern States be sent to Cuba to examine<lb/>
sanitary conditions and measures taken to control yellow fever,<lb/>
in order to quiet apprehension in Southern States. During<lb/>
this intervention the Government has expended millions of<lb/>
dollars in the sanitary works and services of the Island, in com-<lb/>
pliance with the existing treaty between the United States and<lb/>
Cuba and the Sanitary Convention of nineteen hundred and<lb/>
five. The Cubans, although themselves immune and having no<lb/>
fear of yellow fever, have accepted these expenditures com-<lb/>
placently, anticipating that the effort would be appreciated and<lb/>
the Island secure immunity from travel restrictions. If, in-<lb/>
stead of immunity, these restrictions are imposed with greater<lb/>
vigor than before such expenditures and improvements were<lb/>
made, it will be impossible to induce the Cubans who believe<lb/>
themselves immune from birth, to continue these expenditures<lb/>
and precautionary measures when the administration of the<lb/>
Government passes into their hands. The United States Gov-<lb/>
ernment has recently taken action with reference to certain<lb/>
great sanitary works in the cities of Havana and Cienfuegos,<lb/>
involving an expenditure of fifteen millions of dollars. Both<lb/>
cities have under the provisional government suffered the in-<lb/>
conveniences of extensive fumigations and continual and vig-<lb/>
orous house inspections, with fines for failure to comply with<lb/>
an elaborate code of sanitary ordinances. If, now, they suffer<lb/>
the imposition of a quarantine which they regard as a stigma<lb/>
and believe to be unnecessary, a belief which is shared by all<lb/>
the American residents of the Island, it is doubtful if the forth-<lb/>
coming independent administration will keep up the present<lb/>
expensive and efficient sanitary service.</p>
<p>I requested General Barry to secure reports from<lb/>
all Army and Navy medical officers of his command<lb/>
<pb n="27" id="f02959027"/>
26<lb/>
as to the necessity of the United States quarantining<lb/>
against Cuba and the present absence of yellow fever<lb/>
in the districts where they are stationed. At this hour<lb/>
reports have been received from twenty-six such officers, seven<lb/>
of whom are Naval Surgeons on duty with the Marines. The<lb/>
character of all these reports is well shown by that of the post<lb/>
surgeon at Camp Columbia: &ldquo;Under existing conditions a<lb/>
quarantine, in my opinion, is not only unnecessary, but un-<lb/>
reasonable and unjust to Cuba. If yellow fever appears it will<lb/>
allow ample time to begin a quarantine.&rdquo; In transmitting these<lb/>
reports, Major Birmingham, Chief Surgeon, Army of Cuban<lb/>
Pacification, says: &ldquo;I enclose telegrams received from all the<lb/>
medical officers with the Army of Cuban Pacification. In ac-<lb/>
cordance with existing orders these Medical Officers co-operate<lb/>
with the Boards of Health of the respective towns in or near<lb/>
which they are stationed and make sanitary inspections from<lb/>
time to time, accompanied by the local Sanitary Inspector,<lb/>
under instruction from the Chief Sanitary Adviser of the<lb/>
civil government, so that they are in a position to know of any<lb/>
contagious or other disease that may exist in or near their re-<lb/>
spective vicinities. As former Medical Inspector of the Army<lb/>
of Cuban Pacification, I personally investigated all outbreaks of<lb/>
yellow fever or other contagious diseases occurring among the<lb/>
troops of the Army and the causes leading thereto, and so I<lb/>
am familiar to that extent with the yellow fever situation in<lb/>
Cuba since the arrival of the Army. The health conditions in<lb/>
Cuba are at this time in all respects most excellent. To estab-<lb/>
lish a quarantine against a disease which is conclusively shown<lb/>
by the best obtainable medical evidence to be at the present time<lb/>
non-existent seems to me to be a grave injustice, as the hard-<lb/>
ships both personal and pecuniary, of even the most reasonably<lb/>
administered quarantines are extremely oppressive.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Foregoing letter endorsed by Brigadier-General Barry, com-<lb/>
manding Army of Cuban Pacification. &ldquo;I concur in the opinion<lb/>
of the medical officers and the Chief Surgeon of this Army, that<lb/>
there is no necessity at the present time to establish a quarantine<lb/>
against the Island of Cuba on account of yellow fever, as none<lb/>
<pb n="28" id="f02959028"/>
27<lb/>
so far as is shown by these reports exists. Should there be a<lb/>
recurrence of yellow fever at any point in this Island, the<lb/>
United States authorities could be informed thereof in ample<lb/>
time to protect the United States in the premises.&rdquo; Attention<lb/>
is called to the fact that the Army and Navy surgeons are<lb/>
stationed in various localities and cover the entire Island.<lb/>
Attention is called to the statement, in re sanitary conditions,<lb/>
Cuba, by Dr. Darlington, Health Commissioner, New York<lb/>
City, published in the New York Tribune, Sunday, March 29,<lb/>
page six. Clip statement and file as part of this report.</p>
<p>MAGOON.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>(Copy of Cablegram Received at 1.15 p.m. April 3, 1908.)</p>
<p>HAVANA.</p>
<p>TAFT, Washington.</p>
<p>The National Board of Health and the Commission of In-<lb/>
fectious Diseases submit combined report on quarantine matter.<lb/>
Included in membership of these boards are Drs. Finley, Gui-<lb/>
teras and Agramonte, famous yellow fever experts. Report as<lb/>
follows:</p>
<p>"In reply to your communication of yesterday I have<lb/>
the honor to inform you that a meeting of the National<lb/>
Board was called at which the members of the Commission<lb/>
of Infectious Diseases were invited for the purpose of discus-<lb/>
sing the questions submitted in your letter, namely as to the<lb/>
necessity on the part of the United States to establish quaran-<lb/>
tine against Cuba for yellow fever.</p>
<p>"The Commission of Infectious Diseases due de-<lb/>
liberation presented to the National Board the following<lb/>
report: The Commission of Infectious Diseases is of the<lb/>
opinion that there is no evidence at the present time of<lb/>
the existence of yellow fever within the territory of the Repub-<lb/>
lic. The period of time that has elapsed since the development<lb/>
of the last cases in Santiago February eleventh and Santa Clara<lb/>
February eighteenth, is sufficiently long to have given an oppor-<lb/>
<pb n="29" id="f02959029"/>
28<lb/>
tunity for secondary cases to develop. During this time the<lb/>
conditions have been particularly favorable for the outcrop-<lb/>
ping of the disease, first, because the said cases occurred in the<lb/>
very midst of a large non-immune population, and second, be-<lb/>
cause the weather has been unusually warm for the season.</p>
<p>"We feel very hopeful that the disease has been once more<lb/>
eradicated but if it has not we are absolutely sure that the ex-<lb/>
pert vigilance that is kept up by the sanitary authorities would<lb/>
insure the prompt recognition and declaration of the existence<lb/>
of the disease. The Commission therefore answers the ques-<lb/>
tions of the provisional governor as follows: First, Havana<lb/>
should not be considered at the present time as an infected<lb/>
city or as suspected of being infected; second, in the event of the<lb/>
occurrence of new cases of yellow fever in other parts of the<lb/>
Island outside of Havana Province the requirement of a period<lb/>
of residence in Havana including its suburbs may be substi-<lb/>
tuted for the detention at Triscornia and the United States<lb/>
will be thereby perfectly guaranteed against infection as with a<lb/>
quarantine; third, with respect to the assertion made in the<lb/>
statement presented to the President of the United States to<lb/>
the effect that the duration of life of a mosquito may extend<lb/>
to a period of 180 days, this Commission wishes to state that<lb/>
in the experience of some of its members who have made ex-<lb/>
periments in this dircetion the duration of life has reached<lb/>
154 days in one single instance in which the insect was afforded<lb/>
every protection against its natural enemies. During the exper-<lb/>
iments of the U. S. A. Commission in Havana the insects that<lb/>
were left free in the house for experimental purposes were<lb/>
destroyed by other insects within a period of a very few days.<lb/>
(Signed,) Dr. Juan Guiteras, President; Dr. Aristides Agra-<lb/>
monte, Secretary.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The National Board after ample discussion and fully<lb/>
aware of the responsibilities involved in their decision<lb/>
unanimously approve the said report of the Commission of<lb/>
Infectious Diseases and resolve that the following conclusions<lb/>
be submitted to you, that there is no reasonable motive for es-<lb/>
tablishing quarantine against Cuba. That in the event that its<lb/>
<pb n="30" id="f02959030"/>
29<lb/>
establishment be the nevertheless insisted upon, it would be<lb/>
under the following conditions: Havana being considered as<lb/>
free from yellow fever as from any suspicious case, will be<lb/>
used as quarantine station not only for its own inhabitants<lb/>
but also for those coming from the interior of the Island with<lb/>
the intention of embarking for the United States any person<lb/>
intending to embark will notify the sanitary department in<lb/>
order to be submitted to a proper inspection during a period<lb/>
of six days previous to his embarkation he will be visited twice<lb/>
or thrice a day by the inspector and his temperature taken in<lb/>
order that he may be furnished a certificate stating that the<lb/>
person concerned has not left this city during the aforesaid<lb/>
period of observation, and that he is in good health; only such<lb/>
persons as can furnish clear evidence of their immunity will<lb/>
be exempted from the aforesaid inspection; these measures if<lb/>
agreed upon will be published in the principle newspapers so<lb/>
that they be made known to the public at large. (Signed,)<lb/>
Carlos J. Finlay, President.&rdquo;</p>
<p>MAGOON.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>OFFICE OF THE SECRETARY</p>
<p>TREASUARY DEPARTMENT</p>
<p>WASHINGTON, April 4, 1908.</p>
<p>My dear Mr. President: With regard to the quarantine<lb/>
restraints in Cuba, in view of all the facts elicited, there having<lb/>
been no yellow fever reported in Havana since February 6,<lb/>
1908, and provided that the case now under examination is<lb/>
proven to be not yellow fever, the Surgeon-General of the Pub-<lb/>
lic Health and Marine Hospital Service believes that at the<lb/>
present time it would be practicable to regard the city of Ha-<lb/>
vana, including the base Camp Columbia and the suburb of<lb/>
Marianao as localities from which persons with proved resi-<lb/>
dence therein for a period of <unclear>six</unclear> days, and after inspection by<lb/>
the service officer, could be allowed to take passage for ports<lb/>
of the United States, the details to carry out this matter to<lb/>
<pb n="31" id="f02959031"/>
30<lb/>
be subsequently arranged. These details would relate to cer-<lb/>
tificates of inspection during the six days, etc. This plan has<lb/>
been under consideration for some time, and the fact that the<lb/>
Department Circular of March 4th was prepared a month ago,<lb/>
and that no serious conditions have been reported in Havana<lb/>
since that date, makes this plan more readily feasible at the pres-<lb/>
ent time. It should be understood that if present apparent con-<lb/>
ditions become changed, or that yellow fever is known to exist<lb/>
in Havana, the provisions regarding passenger traffic made as<lb/>
above would be subject to change. This is virtually what is<lb/>
proposed by the National Board of Health in Cuba as wired<lb/>
by Governor Magoon yesterday. All that will be required is<lb/>
for an order to be sent by the Surgeon-General to the service<lb/>
officer in Cuba to put this plan into effect. The regulations<lb/>
and Department Circulars of the Secretary of the Treasury<lb/>
will not need alteration.</p>
<p>If the above meets with your approval, I shall give orders<lb/>
for carrying the above provisions into effect, and shall also<lb/>
notify the Secretary of State.</p>
<p>Respectfully,<lb/>
GEO. B. CORTELYOU.</p>
<p>The President,<lb/>
The White House.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>REPUBLIC OF CUBA<lb/>
UNDER THE PROVISIONAL ADMINISTRATION<lb/>
OF THE UNITED STATES</p>
<p>HAVANA, CUBA, April 3, 1908.</p>
<p>MY DEAR MR. SECRETARY: For your further information I<lb/>
have the honor to enclose herewith copy of my letter to Brig-<lb/>
adier General Thomas H. Barry, Commanding the Army of<lb/>
Cuban Pacification, requesting him to secure reports from the<lb/>
Army Surgeons attached to his Command as to health con-<lb/>
ditions and the necessity of establishing a quarantine against<lb/>
<pb n="32" id="f02959032"/>
31<lb/>
the Island of Cuba in the ports of the United States; also copy<lb/>
of General Barry's reply, and of the telegrams received from<lb/>
the Medical Officers of his Command.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
CHARLES E. MAGOON,<lb/>
Provisional Governor.</p>
<p>The Honorable,<lb/>
The Secretary of War,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>HAVANA, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>MY DEAR GENERAL: The War Department advises me by<lb/>
cable that the President and the Secretary of War desire that<lb/>
a report be made to them as to health conditions on the Island<lb/>
of Cuba, especially as to the absence of yellow fever from the<lb/>
Island. This information is needed in Washington for con-<lb/>
sideration in connection with the question as to whether or not<lb/>
a quarantine shall be established at the ports of the United<lb/>
States against Cuba. I believe that rumors and unfounded<lb/>
reports have reached Washington and caused undue alarm<lb/>
which has induced unjustifiable action on the part of the<lb/>
quarantine authorities, to the great injury of Cuban interests.</p>
<p>There are attached to your command a number of officers of<lb/>
the Medical Corps of the United States Army; these officers<lb/>
are stationed at different localities throughout the Island and<lb/>
have been at said stations for a year or more. Their opinion<lb/>
as to health conditions and the necessity of establishing a quar-<lb/>
antine against the Island in the ports of the United States is of<lb/>
great value, and undoubtedly would be given great weight by<lb/>
the Washington authorities--in fact, I think will control the<lb/>
final determination--and I greatly desire to hear from them.</p>
<p>I therefore have the honor to request that you telegraph each<lb/>
of the Medical Officers of your command, outside of Camp<lb/>
Columbia, substantially as follows:</p>
<pb n="33" id="f02959033"/>
<p>32</p>
<p>&ldquo;Inform me by telegraph if you have any reason to believe that<lb/>
yellow fever exists or has existed within six weeks in town where<lb/>
you are stationed or its vicinity. If so, state reasons for such belief.<lb/>
State whether, in your opinion, under present conditions quarantine<lb/>
against Cuba is necessary to protect the United States from yellow<lb/>
fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Also that a similar request be made to the Medical Officers,<lb/>
United States Army, stationed at Camp Columbia, to be an-<lb/>
swered in writing.</p>
<p>The President has suspended the order of quarantine until<lb/>
April 8th, for the purpose of securing this information, and,<lb/>
therefore, it is necessary that your inquiries and the responses<lb/>
be by telegraph.</p>
<p>Very sincerely yours,<lb/>
CHARLES E. MAGOON,<lb/>
Provisional Governor.</p>
<p>BRIGADIER-GENERAL THOMAS H. BARRY, U. S. A.,<lb/>
Commanding Army of Cuban Pacification,<lb/>
Marianao, Havana, Cuba.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS, ARMY OF CUBAN PACIFICATION,<lb/>
CHIEF SURGEON'S OFFICE.<lb/>
MARIANAO, HAVANA, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>THE ADJUTANT GENERAL,<lb/>
Army of Cuban Pacification.</p>
<p>SIR: I enclose telegrams received from all the Medical Offi-<lb/>
cers with the Army of Cuban Pacification.</p>
<p>In accordance with existing orders these Medical Officers co-<lb/>
operate with the Boards of Health of the respective towns in,<lb/>
or near which they are stationed, and make sanitary inspec-<lb/>
tions from time to time accompanied by the local sanitary in-<lb/>
spector, under instructions from the Chief Sanitary Adviser of<lb/>
the Civil Government, so that they are in a position to know of<lb/>
any contagious or other disease that may exist in or near<lb/>
their respective vicinities.</p>
<pb n="34" id="f02959034"/>
<p>33</p>
<p>As former Medical Inspector of the Army of Cuban Pacifi-<lb/>
cation, I personally investigated all outbreaks of yellow fever<lb/>
or other contagious diseases occurring among the troops of this<lb/>
Army, and the causes leading thereto, and so I am familiar to<lb/>
that extent with the yellow fever situation in Cuba, since the ar-<lb/>
rival of the Army.</p>
<p>The health conditions in Cuba are at this time, in all re-<lb/>
spects, most excellent.</p>
<p>To establish a quarantine against a disease which is conclu-<lb/>
sively shown by the best obtainable medical evidence to be,<lb/>
at the present time, non-existent, seems to me to be a grave in-<lb/>
justice, as the hardships both personal and pecuniary of even<lb/>
the most reasonably administered quarantine are extremely<lb/>
oppressive.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
H. P. BIRMINGHAM,<lb/>
Major, Surgeon, U. S. Army, Chief Surgeon.</p>
<p>21 enclosures.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>[First Endorsement.]</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS, ARMY OF CUBAN PACIFICATION,<lb/>
MARIANAO, HAVANA, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>Respectfully referred to the Provisional Governor, The Palace,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba, as reply to his communication of April<lb/>
1, 1908.</p>
<p>I concur in the opinion of the Medical Officers and the Chief<lb/>
Surgeon of this Army, that there is no necessity at the present<lb/>
time to establish a quarantine against the Island of Cuba on<lb/>
account of yellow fever, as none, so far as is shown by these<lb/>
reports, exists.</p>
<p>Should there be a recurrence of yellow fever at any point in<lb/>
this Island, the United States authorities could be informed<lb/>
thereof in ample time to protect the United States in the prem-<lb/>
ises.</p>
<p>THOMAS H. BARRY,<lb/>
Brigadier-General, U. S. Army, Commanding.</p>
<pb n="35" id="f02959035"/>
<p>34</p>
<p>INFORMATION SLIP</p>
<p>FOR THE SURGEON, POST HOSPITAL.</p>
<p>MARIANAO, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Report as early as practicable if you have any reason to<lb/>
believe that yellow fever exists or has existed within six weeks<lb/>
at your station or vicinity. If so, state fully reasons for such<lb/>
belief. In your opinion, under present conditions, is quarantine<lb/>
against Cuba necessary to protect United States from yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>H. P. BIRMINGHAM,<lb/>
Major, Surgeon, U. S. Army,<lb/>
Chief Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>[First Endorsement.]</p>
<p>HOSPITAL</p>
<p>CAMP COLUMBIA, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Respectfully returned to the Chief Surgeon, AOCP. No<lb/>
case of yellow fever has been at this post since it was occupied<lb/>
by troops in October, 1906. I have heard of no case in the<lb/>
vicinity during this period, and am sure beyond any reason-<lb/>
able doubt that none exists in the vicinity. Under existing<lb/>
conditions a quarantine is in my opinion not only unnecessary<lb/>
but unreasonable and unjust to Cuba. If yellow fever appears<lb/>
it will allow ample time to begin a quarantine.</p>
<p>CHARLES WILLCOX,<lb/>
Major, Surgeon. U. S. A.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>TELEGRAMS.</p>
<p>TRINIDAD, CUBA, April 1, 1907.</p>
<p>Birmingham, Chief Surgeon, Marianao, Havana, Cuba.</p>
<p>Have no reason to believe that yellow fever exists or has<lb/>
existed within six weeks at this station or vicinity. In my opin-<lb/>
<pb n="36" id="f02959036"/>
35<lb/>
ion under present conditions quarantine against Cuba is not<lb/>
necessary to protect United States from yellow fever.</p>
<p>TAYLOR, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>CAMAGUEY, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao.</p>
<p>Do not believe there has been a case of yellow fever here<lb/>
since American intervention. Do not consider quarantine nec-<lb/>
essary under the present conditions.</p>
<p>MILLER, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>PALMIRA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao.</p>
<p>No yellow fever here or in vicinity past six weeks to my<lb/>
knowledge if no fever existed midland do not believe it neces-<lb/>
sary to quarantine against it at present.</p>
<p>W. N. HOLLOWAY, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>GUINES, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>I have no reason to believe that yellow fever exists or has<lb/>
existed within six weeks at my station or vicinity. Under<lb/>
present conditions so far as I am informed I do not consider<lb/>
quarantine against Cuba necessary to protect Uuited States<lb/>
from yellow fever.</p>
<p>MANLEY, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>SPIRITUS, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao.</p>
<p>No yellow fever exists or has existed in this vicinity within<lb/>
six weeks. Do not think quarantine against Cuba necessary.</p>
<p>WHITE, Surgeon.</p>
<pb n="37" id="f02959037"/>
<p>36</p>
<p>GUANAJAY, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>The Chief Surgeon, Marianao.</p>
<p>No yellow fever has occurred at or in the vicinity of this<lb/>
post within last six weeks. In my opinion quarantine is not<lb/>
necessary to protect the United States.</p>
<p>BAKER, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>CARDENAS, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>Case yellow fever here February 8, 1908. None since.<lb/>
From conditions quarantine unnecessary.</p>
<p>GILCHRIST, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>BARACOA, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>There is no reason to believe that yellow fever exists or has<lb/>
existed within six weeks at this station, or vicinity. Under<lb/>
present conditions at this post there seems to be no indication<lb/>
for quarantine against Cuba to protect United States from<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<p>MERAS, Post Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>HOLGUIN, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>Reference your telegram this date have no reason to believe<lb/>
that yellow fever exists or has existed in this vicinity for the<lb/>
last eighteen months. So far as this vicinity is concerned do<lb/>
not believe the United States is warranted in re-establishing<lb/>
quarantine against Cuba, under present conditions. Attention<lb/>
is invited to the fact that no health bulletin or other communi-<lb/>
cations are received by me which would inform me of health<lb/>
conditions in Cuba as a whole, and therefore cannot intelli-<lb/>
gently answer your last question, except so far as it relates to<lb/>
Holguin and the immediate vicinity.</p>
<p>KOERPER, Surgeon.</p>
<pb n="38" id="f02959038"/>
<p>37</p>
<p>CAIBARIEN, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>As far as know no yellow fever exists or has existed at this<lb/>
station or vicinity within six weeks. The nearest point known<lb/>
where yellow fever has existed is Santa Clara. Under present<lb/>
conditions here quarantine against Cuba is not necessary to pro-<lb/>
tect the United States from yellow fever.</p>
<p>HESS, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>SANTO DOMINGO, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>To the best of my knowledge and belief no yellow fever<lb/>
exists now or has existed within six weeks at or in vicinity of<lb/>
this post. In my opinion, under present conditions as reported<lb/>
throughout Cuba, close quarantine against Cuba to protect Uni-<lb/>
ted States against yellow fever is not more necessary now than<lb/>
during any winter month past, when sporadic cases occurred<lb/>
here and there without such quarantine. This, in view of well<lb/>
known activity of stegomyia in southern and Gulf States the<lb/>
year round.</p>
<p>H. D. RIGGS.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>NUEVA GERONA, ISLE OF PINES, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>I have no reason to believe yellow fever has existed at this<lb/>
station or on the Isle of Pines for more than six weeks past.</p>
<p>A. H. ROBLETT, Post Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>MORRO BARRACKS, SANTIAGO DE CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>No cases of yellow fever in his vicinity in the last six weeks.<lb/>
In my opinion quarantine against Cuba could be omitted with-<lb/>
out risk of introduction of yellow fever into the United<lb/>
States.</p>
<p>FRICK, Surgeon.</p>
<pb n="39" id="f02959039"/>
<p>38</p>
<p>SAGUA LA GRANDE, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao:</p>
<p>Report that there has been no yellow fever at Sagua la<lb/>
Grande within the past six weeks, nor any in this vicinity. Am<lb/>
associated with the health authorities and would see any sus-<lb/>
picious cases. My opinion is most positive that quarantine<lb/>
against Cuba by the United States is not necessary.</p>
<p>LITTLE, A. S.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>CIENFUEGOS, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, Marianao, Cuba:</p>
<p>No yellow fever here for over two months. In my opinion<lb/>
no quarantine is necessary to protect United States.</p>
<p>QUINTON, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>PLACETAS, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, A. O. C. P., Marianao, Cuba:</p>
<p>No case of yellow fever in this territory. No need of quar-<lb/>
antine as far as this locality is concerned.</p>
<p>RICHARDS, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>MATANZAS, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, A. O. C. P.,<lb/>
Marianao, Cuba.</p>
<p>Have no reason to believe that yellow fever exists or has<lb/>
existed within six weeks at or near this station. Have full<lb/>
confidence in local health department. In my opinion quaran-<lb/>
tine against Cuba is not necessary at the present time to protect<lb/>
United States from yellow fever.</p>
<p>STONE, Surgeon.</p>
<pb n="40" id="f02959040"/>
<p>39</p>
<p>SANTA CLARA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, A. O. C. P.,<lb/>
Marianao, Havana, Cuba.</p>
<p>There is no reason to believe that yellow fever exists or has<lb/>
existed in Santa Clara or vicinity since Private Travers &ldquo;K&rdquo;<lb/>
troop had the disease. He entered hospital February 19.<lb/>
Quarantine against Cuba is not believed necessary at the pres-<lb/>
ent time to protect the United States from yellow fever.</p>
<p>WHITCOMB, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>MANZANILLO, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>Birmingham, Chief Surgeon,<lb/>
Camp Columbia, Marianao, Cuba.</p>
<p>Have no reason to believe that yellow fever exists or has<lb/>
existed at this station within the past year. Quarantine to<lb/>
protect United States not necessary as far as this station is<lb/>
concerned.</p>
<p>IDEN.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>[Telegram.]</p>
<p>PINAR DEL RIO, CUBA, April 1, 1908.</p>
<p>Chief Surgeon, A. O. C. P., Marianao:</p>
<p>No reason to believe yellow fever exists or has existed within<lb/>
six weeks at this station or vicinity. Health officer says not a<lb/>
single case has occurred or has been reported during the inter-<lb/>
vention, nor for years before, and that there never has been<lb/>
an epidemic here. Spanish troops were at times sent here to<lb/>
acclimatize them against yellow fever. Sanitary inspectors<lb/>
meet all trains and all incoming sick by train, or otherwise, are<lb/>
placed under surveillance until known to be suffering from non-<lb/>
infectious diseases. I have not been able to demonstrate the<lb/>
stegomyia and believe they are few in numbers. There are<lb/>
sanitary officers for all roads being constructed here. The<lb/>
<pb n="41" id="f02959041"/>
40<lb/>
working parties contain many non-immunes and no suspected<lb/>
cases have ever been reported. For these reasons and because<lb/>
this place is inland I believe yellow fever is not apt to occur<lb/>
and as far as this section is concerned quarantine is not neces-<lb/>
sary to protect United States from yellow fever.</p>
<p>SHOOK, Surgeon.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>POST HOSPITAL, CAMP COLUMBIA, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>To the Commanding Officer, Post Hospital, Camp Columbia,<lb/>
Cuba:</p>
<p>SIR: In compliance with letter from Adjutant General,<lb/>
Army of Cuban Pacification, this date, I have the honor to<lb/>
make the following reply:</p>
<p>I do not know of any cases of yellow fever in this vicinity<lb/>
and have no reason to suspect any.</p>
<p>As the undersigned has not been in Cuba very long, having<lb/>
arrived March 20, 1908, he does not know much about the<lb/>
existing conditions; however, from the information he can<lb/>
obtain, a quarantine seems unnecessary.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
E. M. TALBOTT.<lb/>
Captain, Asst. Surg., U. S. A.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted:</p>
<p>I agree with the opinions expressed herein.</p>
<p>CHARLES WILLCOX,<lb/>
Major and Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>CAMP COLUMBIA, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>The Adjutant General, A. O. C. P.</p>
<p>Sir: In reply to your telephonic message just rec'd, I have<lb/>
the honor to state that I made a report to the Chief Surgeon,<lb/>
yesterday, on the subject of the proposed quarantine against<lb/>
Cuba. I stated in substance as follows:</p>
<pb n="42" id="f02959042"/>
<p>41</p>
<p>No case of yellow fever has appeared in Camp Columbia<lb/>
since the U. S. Troops reached the Camp in Oct., 1906, and I<lb/>
am sure beyond any reasonable doubt that no case existed in<lb/>
the vicinity during that time. Under the present conditions<lb/>
in the Island I consider a quarantine unnecessary, unreason-<lb/>
able, and unjust to Cuba.</p>
<p>Reports from other medical officers are submitted. Capt.<lb/>
Webber could not be found this morning, but his report will<lb/>
be forwarded as soon as it can be procured. The others are<lb/>
sent at once to avoid delay. Report from Capt. Bartlett not<lb/>
yet received. Will be forwarded later.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
CHARLES WILLCOX,<lb/>
Major &amp; Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<p>(4 enclosures.)</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>CAMP COLUMBIA, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>The Adjutant General, A. O. C. P. desires immediately<lb/>
the report of all Medical Officers on the following subject:<lb/>
Quarantine against Cuba.</p>
<p>1. Do you know of any case of yellow fever in or in the<lb/>
vicinity of Camp Columbia? Have you any reason to believe<lb/>
any case has existed recently; if so when and where? (This<lb/>
in regard only to Camp Columbia and the neighborhood.)</p>
<p>Do you think that under the present conditions it is neces-<lb/>
sary or advisable to establish a quarantine against Cuba? An<lb/>
immediate reply is desired on this paper and following sheets,<lb/>
report to be signed in each case.</p>
<p>CHARLES WILLCOX.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>I know of no case of yellow fever in vicinity of Camp Col-<lb/>
umbia, nor has such existed to my knowledge since Feb. 19,<lb/>
<pb n="43" id="f02959043"/>
42<lb/>
1908. It is thought unnecessary and decidedly unadvisable to<lb/>
establish quarantine under the present healthy conditions.</p>
<p>WM. F. DAVIS,<lb/>
Capt, &amp; Surgeon.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted:</p>
<p>I agree with opinions expressed herein.</p>
<p>CHARLES WILLCOX,<lb/>
Major &amp; Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>POST HOSPITAL, CAMP COLUMBIA, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>The Commanding Officer, Post Hospital.</p>
<p>SIR: In reply to note regarding the presence of yellow fever<lb/>
in this vicinity and the advisability of quarantine, I have the<lb/>
honor to report concisely as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. No case of yellow fever has come to my notice in this<lb/>
camp or the immediate vicinity since the occupation of Cuba,<lb/>
in October, '06.</item>
<item>2. No recent cases of yellow fever have, to my knowledge.<lb/>
been reported in this province for several months.</item>
<item>3. Judging from previous conditions and the history of<lb/>
epidemics of former times, I think the quarantine of this Island<lb/>
at present inadvisable.</item></list></p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
J. M. HANSON,<lb/>
Captain and Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted:<lb/>
I agree with the ideas expressed in this report.</p>
<p>CHARLES WILLCOX,<lb/>
Major and Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<pb n="44" id="f02959044"/>
<p>43</p>
<p>POST HOSPITAL, CAMP COLUMBIA, CUBA, April 2, 1908.</p>
<p>The Commanding Officer, Post Hospital Camp Columbia,<lb/>
Cuba.</p>
<p>SIR: In compliance with your instructions, I have the honor<lb/>
to report I have no knowledge of any yellow fever cases hav-<lb/>
ing occurred in Camp Columbia, or its vicinity, since arriving<lb/>
in Cuba, October 12, 1906.</p>
<p>I have no knowledge of any cases of yellow fever on the<lb/>
Island at present, and therefore deem quarantine unnecessary,<lb/>
unless another outbreak occurs on this Island.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
ROBERT U. PATTERSON,<lb/>
Captain and Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted:<lb/>
I agree with the opinions expressed herein.</p>
<p>CHARLES WILLCOX,<lb/>
Major and Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
