<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02957003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Obituary fragment of James Carroll, by Howard A. Kelly, [1908]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02957003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">St. Paul (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="publication">The Treatment of Yellow Fever by Carroll</name>
<name type="publication">System of Medicine by Osler</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-00-00">[1908]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02957003</idno>
<title>Obituary fragment of James Carroll, by Howard A. Kelly, [1908]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is an incomplete, hand-corrected draft of an obituary of James Carroll, written for the Washington Academy of Sciences.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-00-00">
<head>Obituary fragment of James Carroll, by Howard A. Kelly, [1908]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02957003"/>
<opener>
1<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
JAMES CARROLL<lb/>
</opener>
<p>James Carroll, the second in command on the United States<lb/>
Army Yellow Fever Commission, was an Englishman, born at Woolwich, on June<lb/>
5, 1854. His early years, like those of <del>all</del><add>many</add> men whose maturity is spent<lb/>
in a country not their<del>s</del> <add>own</add> by birth, are little known, especially as his <del><unclear>own</unclear></del><lb/>
<add>entire</add> lack of egotism prevented his dwelling upon them. He was educated <add>a- Albion House</add> with a<lb/>
view to entering the British Army as an engineer student, but shortly be-<lb/>
<add>?</add> fore the time came <del>for him to do so</del>, he emigrated to Canada, in consequence,<lb/>
as he once told me, of <del>us</del> disappointment in an youthful love affair. For<lb/>
some time after he reached Canada, his life was that of a farmer in the back-<lb/>
woods, <del>but</del><add>until</add> <del>in 1874 he is the</del> <add>in</add> course of time he came to the <del>United</del> States<lb/>
and in <add>January</add> 1874 entered the United States Army.</p>
<p><del>After</del><add>Upon</add> enlisting he was ordered to the Far West and while serving<lb/>
<del>there</del> in Montana<del>,</del> as a hospital steward, he became interested in the study<lb/>
of medicine. After some difficulty- he obtained permission to attend <add>medical</add> lec-<lb/>
<add>lec</add> tures <del><unclear>a became</unclear></del> at St. Paul, Minnesota, and from this time on he pursued his<lb/>
medical education as he could and where he could, until, on his return to the<lb/>
East, he finally completed it at the University of the City of New York and<lb/>
the University of Maryland, receiving his degree <del>as</del><add>of</add> M. D. from the latter in-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02957004"/>
2<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
stitution in 1891. He <del>had</del> bec<del>o</del><add>a</add>me intensely interested in the new science<lb/>
of bacteriology, which was then <del>just</del> beginning to develop <add>in this country</add>, and availed him-<lb/>
self of the graduate classes just opened at the Johns Hopkins Hospital to<lb/>
<del>take up</del><add>prosecute</add> this line of work. In 1895 he was assigned to duty in the Army<lb/>
Medical Museum at Washington, where Walter Reed was Curator, and from this<lb/>
time <add>on</add> the<del>ir</del> names <add>of these two eminent colaborers</add> were constantly associated. In 1899 <del>they</del> <add>Reed &amp; Carroll</add> were <del>both</del> appoint-<lb/>
ed by Surgeon-General Sternberg to investigate <del>into</del> the true nature of the<lb/>
<hi>bacillus icteroides</hi> which Sanarelli had just declared <del>to be</del><add>was</add> the specific<lb/>
agent in yellow fever. Their work on this subject naturally associated<lb/>
their names <add>prominently</add> with <add>the great</add> yellow fever <add>question &amp;, so it came about that</add> <del>and</del> in 1900, when an Army Medical Commission<lb/>
was appointed to <add>go to Cuba and</add> investigate into the nature and transmission of thi<add>s</add> <del>disease</del> <add>scourge of the centuries</add><lb/>
<del>in Cuba</del>. Reed was made Chairman with Carroll <del>as</del><add>placed</add> second in command.</p>
<p>Carroll arrived in Cuba on June 25, 1900, and shortly afterwards<lb/>
the preliminary experiments were begun. Early in the course of the work<lb/>
it became apparent to the members of the Commission that the proposed line<lb/>
of work could not be carried on without experiments upon human beings and<lb/>
they agreed that the initial experiment must be <add>made</add> upon one of themselves.<lb/>
Carroll volunteered for this service, and he always said that the proudest<lb/>
circumstances of his life was that he was the first person to <unclear>succumb</unclear> to<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02957005"/>
-3-<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
to mosquito inoculation. He had a <del>most</del> severe attack of the disease, du-<lb/>
ring which his life was despaired of, and although he recovered, <del>as <add>it</add> seemed<lb/>
completely</del>, <del>he did so</del><add>it was</add> with an organic heart lesion which ultimately caused<lb/>
his death.</p>
<p>Carroll's services upon the Yellow Fever Commission, apart from<lb/>
the inestimable <del>one</del> <add>act of self sacrifice</add> just mentioned, were of the most essential <del>kind</del><add>character</add>, and<lb/>
it is not at all too much to say that without his <add>native</add> force <del>of character</del> and<lb/>
perseverance, <del>in addition to</del><add>guided by</add> his scientific knowledge and training, the<lb/>
work of the Commission could <del>not</del><add>scarcely</add> have been carried to a conclusion. Cir-<lb/>
cumstances obliged Dr. Reed to leave Carroll in charge of the preliminary<lb/>
experiments while he himself returned to the United States on business<lb/>
connected with them, and it was entirely through Carroll's exertions <add>at this time</add> that<lb/>
they were brought to a satisfactory conclusion <add>&amp; the demonstration was completed</add> by the time Reed was again<lb/>
in Cuba. Again, in February 1901, when the fact that yellow fever is<lb/>
transmitted by the <hi>stegomyia calopus</hi> was finally prove<del>d</del><add>n</add> and Reed went<lb/>
home, Carroll remained behind for several weeks to determine one or<lb/>
two <add><del>minor</del> added</add> points necessary to the perfect completion of the experiments.<lb/>
<del>But</del> His most valuable, as well as most independent service to the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Commission was rendered in the following summer, when he returned<lb/>
(where - p 4 - <unclear>p 815</unclear> ?)<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02957006"/>
-5-<lb/>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
on the subject of yellow fever through the medium of the medical press.<lb/>
The first paper which he published independently, <del><unclear>was</unclear></del> on the &ldquo;The Treatment<lb/>
of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, is the first contribution to the therapeutics of the dis-<lb/>
ease after its mode of transmission became known; <del>and the</del><add>his</add> last is the sec-<lb/>
tion on yellow fever in Osler's &ldquo;System of Medicine&rdquo;.</p>
<p>For some years Carroll services received no official recognition,<lb/>
but during the last year of his life honors began to accrue to him, in which<lb/>
he took an <del>straightforward and</del><add>mainly</add> honorable <add>&amp; justifiable</add> pleasure. He was promoted from<lb/>
<add>?</add> the rank of Lieut<del>a</del><add>e</add>nant to that of Major and two universities <add>the U. of N. &amp; the U. of Md.</add> conferred upon<lb/>
him the honorary degree of L L. D. In the summer of 1897 the heart lesion,<lb/>
which originated during the attack of yellow fever., asserted itself and his<lb/>
health began to fail. He died at his home in Washington <del>in October</del><add>on September .16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></add><lb/>
1907.</p>
<p>In reviewing the facts of Carroll<unclear>',</unclear>s life it is plain<lb/>
that he had the elements of success <add>with</add> in him from the first. He was the typ-<lb/>
ical <hi>vir teuax propositi</hi> and this quality in his nature enabled him to<lb/>
show a persistence which, if not a necessary element of genius is at least<lb/>
<del>an essential part of</del> its closest ally, and is often, pardonably, mistaken<lb/>
for it. His personal character was one which commanded respect and in-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
