<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02961018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from the Surgeon General's Office to Aristides Agramonte, October 10, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02961018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-10-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Agramonte, Aristides</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Torney, George H.</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Stone, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Beauperthuy, Louis-Daniel</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Santa Clara (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio Barracks (Cuba) </name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-10-10">October 10, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02961018</idno>
<title>Letter from the Surgeon General's Office to Aristides Agramonte, October 10, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Agramonte is notified that his letter has been received and filed for future reference. Agramonte's letter of August 31, 1908, is included, testifying to the sequence of events in the work carried out by the Army Board on Yellow Fever. Included are two notes by Truby. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-10-10">
<head>Notes by Albert E. Truby, [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02961018"/>
<p><hi>Oct 10, 1908</hi></p>
<p>O'Reilly was the S.G. and know<lb/>
all about Reed's work as well<lb/>
as what the other members of the<lb/>
Board had done, He &amp; Kean<lb/>
then wrote this conciliatory letter.<lb/>
The S G O was so disgusted with<lb/>
Carroll's claim that they probably<lb/>
felt it unwise to air the claims<lb/>
of Carroll &amp; Agramonte and therefore<lb/>
<del><unclear>try</unclear></del><add>tried to</add> <del><unclear>at</unclear></del> stave<unclear><del>ing</del></unclear> off action.</p>
<p>Then Torney became S.G and<lb/>
it was than that Agramonte's letter<lb/>
was published in the Sen. Doc. with<lb/>
remarks by Kean who probably felt<lb/>
that after Carroll's statements the<lb/>
whole thing would cause a real<lb/>
mess if published in all details.<lb/>
Of course this is just a surmise<lb/>
on my part. I have never seen<lb/>
the most of the correspondence between<lb/>
the S.G.O &amp; Agramonte,<lb/>
aet</p>
<pb n="2" id="f02961019"/>
<p>Dr Carroll died in 1907. This letter<lb/>
was written a year later. But<lb/>
its claims are mild to those<lb/>
written later. I have made<lb/>
a few notes on this and<lb/>
underlined a few important<lb/>
things.</p>
<p>Lazear's mosquitoes were<lb/>
all kept at his laboratory at<lb/>
Col. Bks Hosp. I saw them there<lb/>
in July and I saw them again<lb/>
after Lazear's death when Neate<lb/>
was in charge, but I was responsible<lb/>
aet<lb/>
as C.O.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="letter" n="1908-10-10">
<head>Letter from the Surgeon General's Office to Aristides Agramonte, October 10, 1908</head>
<pb n="3" id="f02961020"/>
<opener>
File<lb/>
FROM THE NATIONAL ARCHIVE<lb/>
I&sol;H<lb/>
OFFICE OF SURGEON GENERAL<lb/>
OCT 10<lb/>
6<lb/>
71980<lb/>
1908<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON GENERAL,<lb/>
WASHINGTON<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1908-10-10">October 10, 1908.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Aristides Agramonte,<lb/>
Profesor de Bacteriologia y Patologia Experimental,<lb/>
Universidad de la Habana, Habana, Cuba.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Agramonte:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The Surgeon General directs me to say that he has<lb/>
carefully considered your statements inclosed in your<lb/>
letter of August 31, 1908, regarding the work carried<lb/>
out by the Army Board appointed by paragraph 34, Special<lb/>
Order Bo. 122, series of 1900, and to inform you that<lb/>
the same has been placed in the files of this office,<lb/>
so that it will be considered whenever the question of<lb/>
the discovery that yellow fever was transmitted by<lb/>
the mosquito is discussed in the future.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,</salute>
<signed><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></signed>
Major, Medical Corps, U. S. Army.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-10-10">
<head>Letter from the Surgeon General's Office to Aristides Agramonte, August 31, 1908</head>
<pb n="4" id="f02961021"/>
<p>OFFICE OF SURGEON GENERAL<lb/>
OCT 12<lb/>
6<lb/>
71980<lb/>
1908<lb/>
<unclear>WAR DEPARTMENT</unclear></p>
<p>Vedado, Havana, Cuba<lb/>
Aug. 31, 1908.</p>
<p>Aristides Agramonte<lb/>
M.D.</p>
<p>Encloses general statement<lb/>
of the manner in which<lb/>
the work was carried out<lb/>
by the Army Medical Board<lb/>
which demonstrated the<lb/>
mosquito transmission<lb/>
in yellow fever.</p>
<p>(1 enclosure)</p>
<p>File</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="letter" n="1908-08-31">
<head>Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Robert M. O'Reilly, August 31, 1908</head>
<pb n="5" id="f02961022"/>
<opener>
Doc File 71980 War Dept.<lb/>
Records, of the War Dept, S G O<lb/>
File No 71980<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Dr. Aristides Agramonte<lb/>
Profesor de Bacteriologia y Patologia Experimental<lb/>
Facultad de Medicina,<lb/>
Universidad de la Habana, Cuba</hi>.<lb/>
-----<lb/>
<dateline>
Vedado, Havana, Cuba, <date value="1908-08-31">August 31, 1908.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Gen. R. M. O'Reilly, U. S. Army,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In compliance with your request, when I had<lb/>
the pleasure to see you in Havana, I have the honor to hand you<lb/>
herein enclosed, a general statement of the manner in which the<lb/>
work was carried out by the Army Board which demonstrated the<lb/>
mosquito transmission in yellow fever.</p>
<p>I have never, directly or indirectly, received any <add>material</add> reward for<lb/>
my share in said researches.</p>
<p>With the hope that it may meet with your approval and best<lb/>
wishes for yourself, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Aristides Agramonte</signed>
Aug. 10&sol;10&sol;08<lb/>
M <unclear>to</unclear> H<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-08-31">
<head>Statement by Aristides Agramonte, August 31, 1908</head>
<pb n="6" id="f02961023"/>
<p>STATEMENT by Aristides Agramonte, M. D. of Havana, Cuba,<lb/>
regarding the work carried out by the Army Board, appointed by<lb/>
paragraph 34, Special Orders No. 122, series of 1900, Headquarters<lb/>
of the Army. ----------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>----::::(0)::::----</p>
<p>The detail for the Board consisted of,<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Major Walter Reed, Surgeon, U. S. Army;
</item><lb/>
<item>Acting Assistant Surgeon James Carroll, U. S. Army;</item><lb/>
<item>Acting Assistant Surgeon Aristides Agramonte, U. S. Army;</item><lb/>
<item>Acting Assistant Surgeon Jesse W. Lazear, U. S. Army.</item><lb/>
</list></p>
<p>This Board was to act under <hi>general instructions</hi> to be commu-<lb/>
nicated to Major Reed by the Surgeon General of the Army.</p>
<p>-----------------------</p>
<p>Soon after its appointment, the Board met at Camp Columbia, <del>XX</del><lb/>
near the town of Quemados, Cuba.</p>
<p>A mild epidemic of yellow fever was in cou<add>r</add>se of development<lb/>
in the above mentionned town, so that work was commenced at once.</p>
<p><hi>By tacit consent of all concerned, Maj. Reed was to be the<lb/>
director</hi> of the work which the Board might undertake and which was<lb/>
devided at the time as follows;<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Carroll, bacteriological work,</item><lb/>
<item>Dr. Agramonte, auto<add>p</add>sies and gross pathology,</item><lb/>
<item>Dr. Lazear, microscopical pathology.</item><lb/>
</list></p>
<p><hi>As may be seen, no mosquito investigation was thought of at<lb/>
that time</hi>.</p>
<p>Besides his duties as a member of the Board, Dr. Agramonte had<lb/>
charge of the Division Laboratory, located in Havana, at the U. S.<lb/>
Military Hospital No. 1, as per paragraph 3, Special Orders No. 74,<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02961024"/>
See Agramonte letter to Kean July 3, 1908<lb/>
============<lb/>
(2)<lb/>
from Headquarters Division of Cuba, May 23, 1900.</p>
<p><hi>In June of the same year</hi>, an epidemic of yellow fever develop-<lb/>
ed in the city of Santa Clara and Dr. Agramonte was ordered to in-<lb/>
vestigate its origin, as per paragraph 3, Special Orders No. 97,<lb/>
Headquarters Division of Cuba, June 27, 1900.</p>
<p><hi>While examining into the epidemiology of this outburst, the<lb/>
question of mosquito transmission was fir<del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>st</add> discussed by Dr.</hi> Agra-<lb/>
monte and he remembers having talked upon the subject with Capt.<lb/>
Stone, Post Surgeon, at Santa Clara, who was also inclined to be-<lb/>
lieve in its probability.</p>
<p>Dr. Agramonte returned to his post and the routine work of the<lb/>
Board was continued, <hi>no mosquito work being yet undertaken</hi>.</p>
<p>A month after, Dr. Agramonte was ordered to Pinar del Rio &ldquo;for<lb/>
the purpose of examining into the exact nature of certain cases of<lb/>
&ldquo;pernicious fever reported to have occurred at said post&rdquo;, as per<lb/>
paragraph 1, Special Orders No. 112, Headquarters Division of Cuba,<lb/>
July 17, 1900. He found an epidemic of yellow fever among the troo<add>ps,</add><lb/>
which was not only unrecognized by the Surgeon in charge but actual-<lb/>
ly denied by him and three other contract surgeons on duty at said<lb/>
post. In face of this oposition, Dr. Agramonte telegraphed his<lb/>
opinion to Headquarters within 24 hours after his arrival, assum-<lb/>
ing all responsibility for his action. An immune surgeon was sent<lb/>
to look after the sick, Camp was moved to the country and Major<lb/>
Read came, two days later, to study the possible origin of the infect-<lb/>
ion. <hi>It was there on the ground, that for the first time the proba-<lb/>
bility of mosquito agency was seriously discussed by</hi> members of the<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02961025"/>
(3)<lb/>
Board and it was decided to carry out some research in this direct-<lb/>
ion.</p>
<p>As Dr. Lazear had obtained <hi>considerable training in mosquito<lb/>
work, while in Italy, and</hi> none of the other members of the Board had<lb/>
<add>not true</add><lb/>
any, it was agreed that he take up this part of the work in the<lb/>
beginning. Dr. Carroll continued to investigate the bacteria and<lb/>
Dr. Agramonte the Pathological anatomy of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Major <add>R</add>eed at this time returned to Washington, for the purpose<lb/>
of completing the Report upon &ldquo;Typhoid fever in the Army&rdquo; in col-<lb/>
laboration with Drs. Shakespear and Vaughn.</p>
<p><hi>Lazear began to breed, dissect, classify and infect mosquitoes,<lb/>
in which work, <del>c</del><add>C</add>arroll and Agramonte took little or no part</hi>. Now and<lb/>
then, Lazear would apply them to whoever allowed it. Most of the<del>m</del><add> mosquitoes</add><lb/>
died early in captivity; <hi>Lazear, Carroll and several other persons<lb/>
had been bitten several times</hi> by mosquitoes which previously had<lb/>
fed on yellow fever bl<add>oo</add>d, without result, so that the theory of<lb/>
mosquito transmission was gradually being discredited, until Carroll<lb/>
fell sick, on the 30th of August, (1900) entirely innocent of <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><lb/>
the real nature of his illness.</p>
<p>Suspecting the origin of his infection and its real gravity,<lb/>
Drs. Lazear and <hi>Agramonte</hi> decided to test the mosquito which pre-<lb/>
sumably had caused Carroll's attack by applying it to the first non-<lb/>
immune individual who might allow it.</p>
<p>Therefor on the afternoon of August 31st, the same mosquito<lb/>
and three others, were applied to an American soldier who had not<lb/>
left Columbia Barracks, (which was free from yellow fever,) for 57<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02961026"/>
(4)<lb/>
days prior to his inoculation; nor did he go out of <del>a</del> said reservat-<lb/>
ion before he fell sick with yellow fever, five days afterwards,<lb/>
thus confirming in our mind<unclear>s</unclear> the fact that he had been infected by<lb/>
the mosquito bites.</p>
<p>Dr. Carroll being at this time still suffering from a severe<lb/>
attack of the disease, <hi>Drs. Lazear and Agramonte decided to com-<lb/>
municate these results to Major Reed who was yet in Washington</hi>.</p>
<p>Before Major Reed's arrival in Havana, Dr. Lazear became infec<add>t-</add><lb/>
ed with yellow fever, his death taking place on the 25th of Sept.</p>
<p><hi>During Carroll's convalescence, the Board decided</hi> that the<lb/>
results of the investigation were so far sufficiently convincing to<lb/>
justify their presentation, in the shape of a Preliminary Note, be-<lb/>
fore the coming meeting of the American Public Health Association,<lb/>
at Indiannapolis, Ind. (Oct. 1900).</p>
<p>Major Reed went North for this purpose, and while Carroll took<lb/>
a short vacation, to recuperate from his recent attack, Dr. Agra-<lb/>
monte was charged with breeding and infecting mosquitoes, keeping<lb/>
them at the Division Laboratory, which was under his care in Havana,<lb/>
in preparation for the work which the Board intended to carry out<lb/>
after the Indiannapolis meeting.</p>
<p>When Major Reed returned from the States, moral and material<lb/>
aid was obtained from Gen. Leonard Wood, commanding the Division,<lb/>
and we determined to carry out an investigation exclusively based<lb/>
upon the mosquito theory sustained by Finlay: we knew nothing of<lb/>
Beauperthuy, then, who in 1853 had defended practically the same<lb/>
theory.</p>
<p>While the experimental station, afterwards named Camp Lazear,<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f02961027"/>
(5)<lb/>
in honor to the memory of our deceased colleague, was being establi<add>sh-</add><lb/>
ed, the care of the mosquitoes and their infection by applying them<lb/>
to yellow fever cases, was in the hands of Dr. Agramonte, at the<lb/>
Division Laboratory; when the permanent &ldquo;mosquito building&rdquo; was<lb/>
erected at Camp Lazear, (Dec. 1, 1900), these mosquitoes were turn-<lb/>
ed over to Dr. Carroll for his care. It devolved then <del>to</del><add> upon</add> Dr. Agra-<lb/>
monte to select the mosquitoes from those kept by Dr. Carroll and<lb/>
to apply them to non-immunes, as well as to make all subsequent<lb/>
direct <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> inoculations and to obtain the non-immunes, (Spaniards,)<lb/>
for the purpose, until the end of the work in Cuba.</p>
<p>Let me add, that the best fr<unclear><add>ie</add></unclear>ndship existed between all the<lb/>
members of the Board and from the beginning of their work it was<lb/>
agreed that the honor of the results was to be shared by all alike<lb/>
as the labor was so evenly shared. Unfortunately this has not been<lb/>
the case, let us hope through no fault of the Members themselves.<lb/>
Drs. Reed and Carroll had been connected in laboratory work for<lb/>
several years and Dr. Agramonte had also w<add>o</add>rked at the Army Medical<lb/>
Museum Laborat<del>i</del><add>o</add>ry: Drs. Lazear and Agramonte were classmates, hav-<lb/>
ing graduated from the College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York<lb/>
in June 1892.</p>
<p>I certify to the absolute truth of the above STATEMENT:</p>
<p>In testimony whereof, I affix my signature, in the City of<lb/>
Havana, August 31, 1908.</p>
<p>Aristides Agramonte<lb/>
<hi>M.D.</hi></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
