<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02961004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Jefferson Randolph Kean, July 3, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author>Agramonte, Aristides</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02961004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-07-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Cuba, Washington D.C.</name>
<name type="place">Santa Clara (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Italy</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-07-03">July 3, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02961004</idno>
<title>Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Jefferson Randolph Kean, July 3, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Agramonte describes his role with the Yellow Fever Commission. Included are autograph notes by Truby and Hench.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1908-07-03">
<head>Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Jefferson Randolph Kean, July 3, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02961004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1908-07-03">July 3, 1908.</date>
</dateline>
Maj. Jefferson R. Kean, U. S. Army,<lb/>
Havana.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Major Kean;</salute>
</opener>
<p>I beg to return to you, herein enclosed, the<lb/>
Senate Report which you kindly allowed me to examine. At the same<lb/>
time, I desire to make a few remarks in answer to your question, as<lb/>
to whether I thought that justice had been done to me for the part<lb/>
which I took in the demonstration of the mosquito-transmission-<lb/>
theory in yellow fever.</p>
<p>Speaking sincerely, I must say, that had I not read the docu-<lb/>
ment above referred to, I would not have believed that such flagrant<lb/>
injustice could have been committed by parties who, because of their<lb/>
official positions, if for no other reason, ought to have <add>been</add> incapable<lb/>
of such an act.</p>
<p>The Report which I return herewith, contains numerous mis-<lb/>
statements, unpardonable misrepresentations, inexplicable omissions<lb/>
and absolutely fails to give me credit for my share in the work<lb/>
which resulted in a manner so brilliant and far-reaching, for the<lb/>
sole purpose of enhancing the value of the services rendered by my<lb/>
colleagues in the same work.</p>
<p>The Report truthfully states that Major Reed's &ldquo;duties re-<lb/>
quired him to be in Washington the greater part of the time; but<lb/>
falls far short of the truth when it adds that &ldquo;the actual work...<lb/>
......was carried on in Cuba by Major Carroll and Doctor Lazear&rdquo;.</p>
<p>No indeed; I was there on the spot all the time. Carroll heard<lb/>
about the result of the mosquito w<del>a</del>ork only after he recovered from<lb/>
his attack of yellow fever, which latter was the outcome, <unclear></unclear> not of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02961005"/>
a definite purpose to become infected, on his part but of a mosquito<lb/>
bite received by him when he was confident of its innocuousness.</p>
<p>It was on the day that Carroll fell sick that Lazear and I be-<lb/>
came convinced that his mosquito bite had done its work and im-<lb/>
mediately decided, unknown to Carroll, of course, to apply the same<lb/>
mosquito, together with others, to the first man who presented him-<lb/>
self and furnished sufficient evidence that he had not been within<lb/>
the infected zone for several days. This man happened to be Ser-<lb/>
geant Dean, who also unknown to Carroll, came down with yellow<lb/>
fever while C. was in the <hi>acme</hi> of his attack. When Dr. Ames, great-<lb/>
ly mystified, admitted that Dean's case was yellow fever, Lazear and<lb/>
I decided to communicate with Major Reed who was then in Washington.</p>
<p>It is very easy to prove these facts by referring to the dates<lb/>
on the official records.</p>
<p>Before Carroll's case, we had little confidence in the mosquito<lb/>
theory. Carroll had absolutely none; he was thinking all the time<lb/>
of an anaerobic organism as the etiologic agent of the disease,<lb/>
which, he thought, presented great difficulties for its cultivation.<lb/>
Reed and I were slightly inclined to the belief in some insect<lb/>
agency, but Lazear was a convert from the early part of our work <del>and</del><lb/>
so soon as it became evident that the tissues in our autopsies were<lb/>
practically sterile and contained no organisms. What inclined Reed<lb/>
and myself to the insect theory were probably the following facts.</p>
<p>On the 27th of June 1900 I was ordered to Santa Clara, to in-<lb/>
vestigate an epidemic of yellow fever which had been active in said<lb/>
city; my inability to place the blame, the manner in which the epi-<lb/>
demic extended and <add>that</add> in which cases developed in the Post Hospital,<lb/>
led me to think of insect agency in the transmission of the dis-<lb/>
ease. I remember having discussed the question with Capt. Stone,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02961006"/>
(3)<lb/>
Post Surgeon, at the time; Dr. Stone may remember the circumstance;<lb/>
if not a convert, at least he was also inclined to believe in mos-<lb/>
quitoes. After my return from this duty, the Board discussed for<lb/>
the first time the possibility of mosquito infection.</p>
<p>During the month of July 1900, several suspicious cases oc-<lb/>
curred at Pinar del Rio Barracks which were being diagnosed as per-<lb/>
nicious malaria by the post surgeons. I was ordered, (July 27th,) <lb/>
to investigate them and the same day of my arrival I reported an<lb/>
epidemic of yellow fever at said station, against the opinion of the<lb/>
Post Commander and four medical officers, who were there in charge<lb/>
of the sick. Major Reed came to Pinar del Rio two days after and<lb/>
there, on the ground, we studied together the possibility of all<lb/>
methods of infection, we visited the sleeping quarters, an old<lb/>
Spanish barrack, and endeavored to trace the facts which might ac-<lb/>
cord with the mosquito theory sustained by Finlay. We knew nothing<lb/>
of the writings of Beauperthuy at that time.</p>
<p>As I say above, Lazear was the only member of the Board who had<lb/>
complete faith in the mosquito transmission of the disease; he had<lb/>
obtained considerable experience while in Italy, <del>with</del><add>in</add> the study of<lb/>
this insect, particularly in <del>their</del><add>its</add> breeding and microscopical ex-<lb/>
amination. Neither Reed, Carroll or myself, at the time, could tell<lb/>
the difference between Culex fasciatus and any other culex. For this<lb/>
reason, Lazear undertook to make a study of mosquitoes, to breed<del>,</del><lb/>
them and if possible to infect them for microscopical investigation.</p>
<p>You know the consequences in the latter part of August. The<lb/>
fortunate results in Carroll's and Dean's cases led Dr. Lazear to<lb/>
believe that experimental yellow fever was absolutely safe: this<lb/>
idea I combatted upon every opportunity, even as we stood by Carroll's<lb/>
bed and watched him, in what seemed the agony of death. Lazear was<lb/>
very fixed in his opinions and <del><unclear></unclear></del> once having formed one, it was<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02961007"/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
(4)<lb/>
very difficult to make him change it; as we know, a few days after<lb/>
the recovery of Dean, he allowed himself to be bitten by a mosquito<lb/>
which escaped him, undoubtedly causing his infection and subsequent<lb/>
death.</p>
<p>When at Lazear's call, <del><unclear></unclear></del> Major Reed came and saw what had<lb/>
been accomplished, we decided to prepare the &ldquo;Preliminary Note&rdquo;<lb/>
which he rushed away to Indiannapolis, to read, before the American<lb/>
Medical Association, (Oct. 22-26, 1900.)</p>
<p>It was decided that Carroll should take a short rest after his<lb/>
attack of yellow fever and as it was considered unsafe to keep in-<lb/>
fected mosquitoes at Camp Columbia, the duty of infecting and keep-<lb/>
ing them fell to me, who was at the same time in charge of the De-<lb/>
partment Laboratory at Hospital No. 1, from where 1 carried them to<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital<del>s</del> for infection and later to Camp Lazear for<lb/>
inoculation. I have copy of the military orders pertaining to these<lb/>
data.</p>
<p>It was at the Department Laboratory that the real mosquito work<lb/>
was initiated; while breeding and studying the various varieties, I<lb/>
found the first anopheles described in Cuba, which to-day appears<lb/>
under the name of <hi>Nyssorhyneus cubensis, (Agramonte 1900,)</hi> in Prof.<lb/>
Blanchard's latest work &ldquo;Les Moustiques&rdquo;. I also found out the<lb/>
valuable work of the common Cuban fresh water fish &ldquo;<hi>Gambusiae</hi>,&rdquo; in<lb/>
devouring the larvae of mosquitoes, etc. etc.</p>
<p>I have in my possession a complete record of the mosquitoes<lb/>
bred, infected and applied by me from the 6th of October <add>1900,</add> to January 1901,<lb/>
in which record appear<del>s</del> numerous notes made by Maj. Reed during<lb/>
said period and which testify to my active part in the work of the<lb/>
Board.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f02961008"/>
<p><hi>P5</hi> Agramontes letter<lb/>
<hi>K Kean July 3,</hi> 1908<lb/>
&ldquo;Where was I -- (ref to<lb/>
4th note <unclear>s s did not<lb/>
report --- what a<lb/>
late date --- &rdquo;</unclear></p>
<p>But <unclear></unclear> admitted the<lb/>
part at least <unclear>in</unclear> the<lb/>
<unclear>What Sternberg</unclear> (p3)<lb/>
of Aug 31, 1908<lb/>
to S.G. (<unclear>O'Ralf</unclear>)</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02961009"/>
<p>The enclosed Report, in that part cited from Senate Document<lb/>
No. 118, Fifty Seventh Congress, second session, goes on to say<lb/>
that Reed's attention was called to Carter's report of the Ormond,<lb/>
Miss. cases before the first cases of the Board; the fact is that<lb/>
Reed's and the Board's attention was attracted to Carter's paper<lb/>
at the time we were preparing the Preliminary Note and not before.<lb/>
At that time, the Board did not ask any support from General Wood,<lb/>
as it is further misstated; this was done later, after Major Reed<lb/>
returned from Indiannapolis and we felt the necessity of establish-<lb/>
ing an experimental camp.</p>
<p>But the grossest injustice and misrepresentation is found in<lb/>
that paragraph where it says &ldquo;The fourth member of the <del><unclear>Boards</unclear></del> Com-<lb/>
mission, Dr. Agramonte, did not participate in the mosquito work<lb/>
of the commission until a later date, nor did he share their danger,<lb/>
as he was a Cuban and a non-immune&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I would like to know where was I all the time?</p>
<p>It would be highly improper to refer in these lines to petty<lb/>
differences which might have existed between some of the members of<lb/>
the Board, but in my own defence I may be allowed to state that Dr.<lb/>
Lazear and I were upon particularly intimate terms; we were class-<lb/>
mates, having graduated at the same time from the College of Physic-<lb/>
ians and Surgeons, New York, in 1892. Take note, that he it was who<lb/>
made the inoculations upon Carroll and Dean, that Carroll did not<lb/>
know, until his convalescence, where he obtained his infection and<lb/>
further, that Reed was in Washington at the time, so that Lazear and<lb/>
I w<add>e</add>re the only members of the Board present at the first demonstrat-<lb/>
ion. Can any one believe, under the circumstances, that I took no<lb/>
part in the mosquito work of the commission until a later date? If<lb/>
any attempt had been made, and surely Lazear would not have made it<lb/>
to exclude me from participating in the work, we, (you and I,) are <del>kno</del><lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02961010"/>
sufficiently acquainted with Major Reed's character to know that<lb/>
he would have never consented it.</p>
<p>When the Board first met in Cuba, the work was distributed so<lb/>
that Lazear attended to the pathological work, Carroll the bacterio-<lb/>
logical and I performed all the autopsies. Maj. Reed remained as<lb/>
Director. When Reed returned, the experimental camp was established<lb/>
and the &ldquo;mosquito house&rdquo; was built, I brought all my mosquitoes from<lb/>
the Department Laboratory and turned them over to Carroll for their<lb/>
care. It became my duty then to obtain the Spaniards for the ino-<lb/>
culations and to perform these, both by mosquito bite and blood in-<lb/>
jection, until the breaking up of the Camp, after the meeting of<lb/>
the Third Pan-American Medical Congress in February 1901.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;memorandum&rdquo; prepared by Surgeon General O'Reilly and<lb/>
which appears in the Report, comes nearer to the truth, yet in his<lb/>
evident desire to favor Carroll and Lazear for the very laudable<lb/>
purpose of securing a pension for their widows, he forgets the<lb/>
&ldquo;fourth&rdquo; member of the Board, which was &ldquo;third&rdquo;, by the way, and<lb/>
not fourth, in the order of their appointment. Referring to the<lb/>
demonstration on the first cases, it says, &ldquo;these three cases es-<lb/>
tablished in the minds of Reed and Carroll the proof of the mosquito<lb/>
theory and formed the basis of their paper, &ldquo;The Etiology of Yellow<lb/>
fever, (Preliminary Note.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I would ask Gen. O'Reilly whether my name does not appear as<lb/>
part author of that paper? Or was I to be considered as dead as<lb/>
our colleague Lazear, whose <del><unclear>a</unclear></del> name by the way, was added at my per-<lb/>
sistent indication? Do you think this fair justice on the part of<lb/>
your Surgeon General? Can he claim ignorance, do you think?</p>
<p>In the same vein run the final paragraphs of this memorandum,<lb/>
in which the Surgeon General forgets to write my name in connection<lb/>
with the Board of which no one can deny I was an integral part,<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f02961011"/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
(7)<lb/>
much as they may be little, for their own purpose, the share I am<lb/>
entitled to in the honor of its acchievements.</p>
<p>I am striving by dint of constant work, study and unswerving<lb/>
devotion to duty as I see it, that when the time comes for me to<lb/>
take the welcome leap into the Great Unknown, my wife and child<lb/>
may need no pension from the political powers that may be; but if<lb/>
I am so unfortunate as to fail in this undertaking and they be com-<lb/>
pelled to resort to the Government in quest of the means wherewith<lb/>
to support life, it is my wish that they claim for the purpose the<lb/>
glory and honor that may be actually due to me for the work that I<lb/>
may have accomplished, and to refrain from decrying that performed<lb/>
by my colleagues, as it has been done by their friends in may case.</p>
<p>I thank you again for the opportunity afforded to read the Re-<lb/>
port and remain</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very faithfully,<lb/>
Yours,</salute>
<signed>Aristides Agramonte</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
