<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t02962001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report, by Juan Guiteras, [1907?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Guiteras, Juan</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02962001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Menocal, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Ortega, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-00-00">1907?</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02962001</idno>
<title>Report, by Juan Guiteras, [1907?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The report argues in support of nominating Finlay and Agramonte for the Nobel Prize in Medicine. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1907-00-00">
<head>Report, by Juan Guiteras, [1907?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02962001"/>
<p><hi>Guiteras</hi> re Nobel prize for Finlay &amp;<lb/>
Agramonte</p>
<p>The Faculty of Medicine and Pharmacy of the University of Habana<lb/>
approved unanimously the following argument presented by a committee of<lb/>
the Faculty, composed of Drs. Guiteras, Menocal and Ortega, in support<lb/>
of a motion to present the claims of Drs. C.J. Finlay and Aristides Agra-<lb/>
monte for the Nobel prize in Medicine.</p>
<p>The benefits secured to humanity by the discovery of the transmis-<lb/>
sion of yellow fever by the mosquito can be equalled only by those deriv-<lb/>
ed from the discovery of vaccination by Jenner, the production of anti-<lb/>
diphtheric serum by Behring, the demonstration of the nature of surgical<lb/>
infections by Pasteur and Koch, and of the anopheline transmission of<lb/>
malaria, by Grassi and Ross.</p>
<p>If all these discoveries be comparable with that relating to yellow<lb/>
fever from the viewpoint of the number of lives saved; the discovery of<lb/>
Jenner is the only one comparable with it, in that they both tend very<lb/>
decidedly, if not surely, to bring about the complete extinction of two<lb/>
grave epidemic diseases; the yellow fever has disappeared from the great<lb/>
foci of its perennial incidence, Habana, Vera Crus, Panama, Rio.</p>
<p>The participation of our two candidates in this great work may be<lb/>
expressed as follows:</p>
<p>The happy conception, never before imagined by another mind of<lb/>
the transmission of yellow fever from the sick to the well through the<lb/>
mosquito, belongs to Dr. Finlay. This idea, together with that of Dr.<lb/>
Manson concerning the transmission of the filaria by the mosquito, are<lb/>
the foundations upon which rest the new doctrine and the discoveries of<lb/>
the transmission of diseases by blood-sucking insects.</p>
<p>Dr. Finlay was not satisfied with the simple enunciation of a theory.<lb/>
He dedicated his energies to the demonstration and the promulgation of<lb/>
the same, as may be seen in the long series of papers published by him<lb/>
Date? Sometime after 1907 - See p 6<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02962002"/>
2.<lb/>
since the first announcement of his views in 1881. Many of these papers<lb/>
will appear in the volume of his works, which, edited by the Cuban Govern-<lb/>
ment, is to accompany these claims.</p>
<p>The following publications may be here mentioned:</p>
<p>Actas de la Conferencia sanitaria de Washington, 1881, Anales de la<lb/>
Academia de Ciencias de la Habana, t. XVII, p. 449.</p>
<p>El mosquito hipoteticamente considerado como agente de transmission<lb/>
de la fiebre smarilla. Anales de la Acad. de Ciencias de la Hab. t. XVIII<lb/>
p. 147, Agosto de 1881.</p>
<p>Patogenia de la fiebre amarilla, Anal. de la Acad. de Ciencias de la<lb/>
Hab. t. XIX p. 160. Agosto de 1882.</p>
<p>Sur une nouvelle theorie de la fievre jauns. Arch. de Med. Navale t.<lb/>
XXXIX pp. 67, 90 y 307.</p>
<p>Nuevos datos acarca de la relacion entre la fiebre amarilla y el mos-<lb/>
quito. Anal. de la Acad. de Ciencias de la Hab. t. XIX, p. 445.</p>
<p>Fiebre amarilla experimental comparada con la natural en sus formas<lb/>
bomignas. Cron. Med. quir. de la Hab. t. X, pp. 51 y 91, 1884.</p>
<p>Apuntes sobre la historia primitiva de la fiebre amarilla, 1884, y 1885.</p>
<p>Yellow fever, its transmission by the Culex mosquito, Amer. Jour. of the<lb/>
Med. Sciences, Oct., 1886.</p>
<p>Estadiatica de las inoculaciones con mosquitos contaminados en enfer-<lb/>
mos de fiebre amarilla, Anal. de la Acad. de Ciencias de la Hab. t. XXVII,<lb/>
p. 501, 1890.</p>
<p>Inoculations of yellow fever by means of contaminated mosquitos, Amer.<lb/>
Jour. of the Med. Sciences, Sept., 1891.</p>
<p>Yellow fever immunity; modes of propagation by mosquito theory. Comptes<lb/>
rend- du 8 me. Cong. Intern. d'Hyg. et Demogr. Budapest, 1894.</p>
<p>Celbos Fieber, Handb. der prakt. Med. Ebstein u. Schwalbe, 1900.</p>
<p>Is the mosquito the only agent through which yellow fever is transmit-<lb/>
ted! Trans. of the First Intern. Sun. Cong. Of the Amer. Republics, Washington,<lb/>
Dec., 1902.</p>
<p>Method of stamping out yellow fever suggested since 1899. Conf. of<lb/>
State and Prov. Boards of Health, Oct., 1902.</p>
<p>Dr. Finlay's demonstration consisted in a profound study of bionomy<lb/>
of the insect, with a series of experiments showing the influence upon the<lb/>
Stegomyia of meteorologic and telluric phenomena which were proven to be<lb/>
incompatible with the propagation and activities of the insect. These<lb/>
conditions, Dr. Finlay showed, were the same that were incompatible with the<lb/>
propagation of yellow fever. He subjected the insects, their larvae and<lb/>
their eggs, to alterations of the temperature, the atmospheric pressure,<lb/>
the conditions of the environment with respect to the presence or absence<lb/>
of water, and to the operation of accidents from transportation in artifi-<lb/>
cial conditions. He demonstrated that all these agencies coincided with<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02962003"/>
3.<lb/>
conditions that affected the propagation of the disease, and he determined<lb/>
with precision the point where the adverse conditions ended and the favorable<lb/>
ones began.</p>
<p>The only mosquito which adjusted itself to these and other conditions,<lb/>
was the Stegomyia calopus, an insect which was also, as he pointed out, es-<lb/>
sentially a domestic mosquito and a weak flyer. He also showed that the same<lb/>
insect could be easily made to bite at regular intervals different persons,<lb/>
whether sick or well, which was not the case with other mosquitos.</p>
<p>From these data Dr. Finlay logically derived the conclusions which he<lb/>
tenaciously maintained during the 20 years preceding the labors of the Ameri-<lb/>
can Commission; conclusions that may be formulated in the statement that the<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever from the sick to the well through the instru-<lb/>
mentality of the mosquito was the only viable explanation of the epidemiolo-<lb/>
gic phenomena of that disease.</p>
<p>Dr. Finlay endeavored also to demonstrate the truth of his conclusions<lb/>
by other means, namely, by the direct experimentation. This endeavor marks<lb/>
him as the first to apply infected insects experimentally with a view to pro-<lb/>
duce pathologic phenomena of the same kind, and gave the opportunity to in-<lb/>
vent the technique of this method of inoculations.</p>
<p>Convinced of the truth of his discovery, he invented and proposed a<lb/>
complete plan of a prophylactic campaign against yellow fever, the same plan<lb/>
which, accepted later on, has produced the wonderful results that we are all<lb/>
familiar with.</p>
<p>Though it might be maintained, from our viewpoint of today, that the<lb/>
epidemiologic and bionomic demonstrations of Dr. Finlay should have been<lb/>
sufficient, and that our non-acceptance of them was more due to our lack of<lb/>
attention and of complete knowledge than to defects in the proofs themselves,<lb/>
yet it is a fact that the said proofs did not carry conviction to the scien-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02962004"/>
4.<lb/>
tific world, and nothing practical came from the vigorous discussions sustain-<lb/>
ed by our clearsighted compatriot. This was due, more than to anything else,<lb/>
to the negative results obtained in his ingenious and original experiments of<lb/>
inoculation by the mosquito.</p>
<p>The practical acceptance of the mosquito doctrine was due to the conclu-<lb/>
sive demonstration produced by the Commission of medical officers of the United<lb/>
States Army, Drs. Walter Reed, James Carroll, Aristides Agramonte and Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear.</p>
<p>In the year 1900 the said commission established its laboratories and<lb/>
experimental camp in a secluded spot of the military reservation at Camp Co-<lb/>
lumbia, near Habana; a place where the presence of a large body of non-immunes<lb/>
without manifestations of the disease proved the absence of the yellow fever<lb/>
infection. Here, the undisputed demonstration of the transmission of yellow<lb/>
fever by the Stegomyio mosquito was obtained in a series of most brilliant<lb/>
experiments.</p>
<p>The direct experimentation in the human being was employed, adapting<lb/>
the recently acquired knowledge of the transmission of malaria to the pro-<lb/>
cess of experimentation initiated by Finlay.</p>
<p>Non-immune men were subjected to all the agencies of contagion that<lb/>
the most ingenious investigation could suggest, without producing a single<lb/>
case; the application, on the other hand, of infected mosquitos under cer-<lb/>
tain conditions produced the amarillic infection.</p>
<p>Within a building divided in two by a partition of wire gauze men<lb/>
were placed, on the one side of the partition, exposed to all sorts of<lb/>
fomites, bed clothing, etc., contaminated with all kinds of discharges<lb/>
from yellow fever patients, but with the exclusion of mosquitos. On the<lb/>
other side of the partition men were placed with infected mosquitos. Yel-<lb/>
low fever was produced only in this second group. Numbers of cases were<lb/>
produced among the men isolated in that camp by the application of mosquitos,<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02962005"/>
5.<lb/>
without the disease propagating to anyone of the other men who were kept in<lb/>
the same camp. It was proven that the yellow fever patient was infective<lb/>
during the first days of the disease solely, and that the mosquito became<lb/>
infective only after the expiration of 12 days since drawing the infected<lb/>
blood. The period of the incubation of the disease was established. It<lb/>
was proven that yellow fever, like malaria, could be transmitted by the<lb/>
direct inoculation of blood hypodermically. It was proven that patients<lb/>
infected in either one of these two ways, were capable of transferring the<lb/>
disease to others, so that the virus was something living, capable of mul-<lb/>
tiplication in the blood.</p>
<p>These experiments were subsequently repeated by Guiteras in the Las<lb/>
Animas Hospital, and later on by national and foreign commissions in Bra-<lb/>
zil and Mexico, thus fulfilling the provision of experimental comprobation<lb/>
by other authors, as required by the Nobel foundation.</p>
<p>Based on the conclusive demonstration of the American Commission, the<lb/>
sanitary authorities in Cuba established the <unclear>prophylactic</unclear> plan proposed by<lb/>
Finlay. This plan has been copied by other infected regions. The result<lb/>
has been most extraordinary; to wit: the progressive reduction of the zone<lb/>
of distribution of yellow fever, the reduction to insignificant proportions<lb/>
of the remaining foci, the saving of hundreds of thousands of lives, the<lb/>
opening to immigration of the sparsely peopled tropical regions of America,<lb/>
and the possibility to forecast that yellow fever may perish from the earth.</p>
<p>The acceptance of the mosquito doctrine as to yellow fever, and the<lb/>
practical application of the doctrine, was the result of the work of the<lb/>
American Commission. In the bases of its constitution this Commission es-<lb/>
tablished that the results of their labors should be held as common to all<lb/>
the members. The only living member of the said Commission is Dr. Agramonte,<lb/>
an exiled Cuban who, because of distinguished merits, had been honored by a<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f02962006"/>
6.<lb/>
foreign Government with this important and delicate mission. He alone re-<lb/>
presents today the part that the Commission took in the solution of the<lb/>
problem, and to him alone corresponds the reward that attaches to that part<lb/>
of the work.</p>
<p>The following publications of Dr. Agramonte may be here mentioned:</p>
<p>The etiology of yellow fever (preliminary note) in colaboration with<lb/>
Drs. Reed, Carroll and Lazear, Phila. Med. Jour., Oct. 27, 1900.</p>
<p>The etiology of yellow fever (additional note) in colaboration with<lb/>
Drs. Reed, and Carroll, - Third Pan-Amer. Med. Cong., Feb., 1901.</p>
<p>Experimental yellow fever, in colaboration with Drs. Reed and Carroll,<lb/>
American Medicine, July, 1901.</p>
<p>Anotaciones acerca de la etiologia de la fiebre amarilla, - Rev. de<lb/>
Med. y Cir. Habans, <unclear>Aguste</unclear> de 1901.</p>
<p>Mosquitos and yellow fever. Illustrated chapter with eight drawings<lb/>
in &ldquo;Laboratory work with mosquitos&rdquo;, by W. N. Berkeley, New York, 1902.</p>
<p>Epidemiology of yellow fever. Read before the XIV Intern. Cong. of<lb/>
Hygiene and Demogr. Berlin, Sept., 1907.</p>
<p>If we consider fairly the two names mentioned in the motion before the<lb/>
Faculty, Dr. Finlay and Dr. Agramonte, who represent two distinct phases of<lb/>
this glorious evolution, it appears to us that neither one of the two scien-<lb/>
tists could have attained final success without the labors of the other; the<lb/>
teachings of Finlay would have continued in the void that was created about<lb/>
them, and the American Commission would have commenced their labors without<lb/>
the solid foundation upon which the superstructure of success was builded.</p>
<p>So evidently do these two endeavors complete each other, so intimate is<lb/>
the connection between the claims of these two exponents of the several as-<lb/>
pects of the problem, that we are forced to confess that the cause of the<lb/>
delay in presenting their titles for the proper reward is the very fact they<lb/>
had not earlier joined their interests in this most just demand.</p>
<p>The glory is sufficiently great to crown both endeavors, and the reward<lb/>
should be equally divided between the two survivors.</p>
<p>(Signed) Juan Guiteras.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
