<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02960014">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench, February 24, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02960014</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-02-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Mrs. George</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Nadine</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Atcheson Laughlin</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Arlington (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Alexandria (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-02-24">February 24, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02960014</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench, February 24, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench details his efforts to review Carroll's papers, held by George S.H. Carroll.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1954-02-24">
<head>Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench, February 24, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02960014"/>
<p>Please return to <hi>PSH</hi></p>
<p><hi><unclear>Sron</unclear></hi></p>
<p><hi>CONFIDENTIAL MEMORANDUM</hi><lb/>
(Dictated Feb. 24, 1954)<lb/>
Philip S. Hench M.D.</p>
<p>Visits with Mr. and Mrs. George S. H. Carroll, Washington D.C.<lb/>
(With special reference to my visits with Mrs. Carroll, Thurs-<lb/>
day and Friday, February 18 and 19, 1954.)</p>
<p><hi>INTRODUCTION</hi>:</p>
<p>I record these data because of the generally uncooperative, suspicious or even<lb/>
antagonistic attitude on the part of Mr. and Mrs. George Carroll, especially the<lb/>
former. It is likely that no account of the conquest of yellow fever, which is<lb/>
not biased or strongly &ldquo;corrected&rdquo; in the behalf of Dr. James Carroll, will ever<lb/>
satisfy his relatives. It is even possible that one or two of them might write<lb/>
unhappily or criticize severely, or even threaten action, legal or otherwise,<lb/>
against me or anyone who writes of this matter. As a prelude to my recent visit<lb/>
of February 18 and 19 with Mrs. Carroll, I will recall previous difficulties.</p>
<p><hi>PREVIOUS EXPERIENCES</hi>.</p>
<p>On several occasions since 1941, I have visited, or tried to visit, George S.H.<lb/>
Carroll, son of Dr. James Carroll. Before each of these early visits I usually<lb/>
tried to correspond with Mr. Carroll to make an appointment to see him on my next<lb/>
trip to Washington but I never received an answer. Despite this, on my arrival<lb/>
in Washington and before going to his home, I would telephone Mr. Carroll or his<lb/>
wife to see when it might be convenient for me to call. Mr. Carroll's response<lb/>
to these telephonic requests was almost always a refusal to see me. Hence on<lb/>
later visits I neither wrote nor telephoned ahead of time but I just appeared<lb/>
at one or the other of their two houses and asked to be received. Even so, I<lb/>
was not always successful. On certain occasions, Mr. Carroll refused to see me<lb/>
and shut the door in my face or would see me only standing in the outer hall.<lb/>
On one or two later visits I got as far as the parlor but had no cooperation<lb/>
with respect to my requests for data concerning his father.</p>
<p>His stated reasons for this attitude can be summarized, in effect, thus: Reed<lb/>
got all the credit. Mrs. Reed was given a pension (actually she did get a<lb/>
pension earlier than Mrs. Carroll). When his father died in 1907, his mother<lb/>
was left with seven young children and practically no money. Some of the<lb/>
children had to fend for themselves. He, George, missed out on an education<lb/>
and hence was never able to &ldquo;get anywhere.&rdquo; &ldquo;The Government never did anything<lb/>
for my mother; they have never done anything for me. What papers of my father's<lb/>
I have the Government should buy if they want them bad enough. Nobody has told<lb/>
the truth about my father and I am going to write my own book and tell the real<lb/>
story.&rdquo; His belief was that Reed and the world cheated his father of his due<lb/>
honors and cheated his mother and his family of what they should have had. &ldquo;You<lb/>
can't have anything and I won't even show you anything.&rdquo; He spoke bitterly of<lb/>
the &ldquo;high-toned Reeds&rdquo;, etc. etc.</p>
<p>(<hi>Comment</hi>: Why the Government should do anything for George Carroll I do not<lb/>
know as he had nothing whatever to do with his father's work on yellow fever.)</p>
<p>My response to George's argument was always thus: Granted that the world knows<lb/>
much more about Reed than about your father. Reed had nothing to do with that<lb/>
since he died in 1902, five years before your father died, and Doctor Reed always<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02960015"/>
Carroll<lb/>
Confidential Memo - 2 -<lb/>
trusted and wrote of your father with great respect, admiration and even affection;<lb/>
nor, I am sure, did the Reed family have anything to do with the world's acclaim<lb/>
of Reed in contrast to your father, but regardless of all this, how can the world<lb/>
know more about your father unless somebody writes about him and tries to show<lb/>
exactly what he did do? My purpose is identical with yours - I want to show<lb/>
exactly what each member of the Yellow Fever Board did and since the papers and<lb/>
records about your father at the National Archives and elsewhere are few (and<lb/>
this is certainly true). I must find data wherever I can. I would not wish to<lb/>
interfere with your own plans to write a book or story about your father but I<lb/>
doubt if the world wants the story of just one of these men. They want the whole<lb/>
story. Do what you want, but won't you help me to complete the book which I shall<lb/>
write, with or without your help, and if I do it without your help, you will think<lb/>
it biased and incomplete, which it may well be unless you tell me &ldquo;your father's<lb/>
side.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(<hi>Comment</hi>: Since George Carroll had had this material for thirty years and had<lb/>
never done anything about it, I never anticipated that he would ever write any<lb/>
book or paper, nor indeed was he literate enough to do so.)</p>
<p>I never got anywhere. In my opinion, the man had at least a psychopathic per-<lb/>
sonality with definite paranoid trends. Nevertheless, I persisted over the<lb/>
years for the following very important reason:</p>
<p><hi>VITAL MISSING MATERIAL</hi></p>
<p>There are many missing data of vital importance that cannot be found anywhere to<lb/>
date after prolonged search by myself and others. I have turned upside down the<lb/>
Surgeon General's Library, the Army Medical Museum, the Library of Walter Reed<lb/>
Hospital and the various files of the National Archives. Among the missing data<lb/>
are many letters and telegrams between Carroll and Reed, Lazear in Cuba and Reed<lb/>
in Washington; Reed in Cuba and Sternberg in Washington - letters and telegrams<lb/>
which we know existed because they are referred to in the correspondence and<lb/>
records which I and others have collected. Most important of all, perhaps, are<lb/>
two missing items: Lazear's pocket notebook which Lt. Truby found in Lazear's<lb/>
clothing after his death and which was handed to Reed and which served as the<lb/>
basis for all the work which followed, and (2) the correspondence between Reed<lb/>
and Sternberg which resulted in Reed being called back to Washington late in<lb/>
June 1900, to finish the typhoid fever report. Since, strange to say, I have<lb/>
found no military orders regarding the important move of Reed from Cuba to<lb/>
Washington, I assume there must have been correspondence regarding it. Its dis-<lb/>
covery is vital to silence the attitude of some Cubans and that of George Carroll<lb/>
to the effect that &ldquo;Reed wasn't even in Cuba when the other Board members began to<lb/>
produce experimental yellow fever.&rdquo; An occasional strong anti-Reed (that is, a<lb/>
pro-Finlay) Cuban and also Mrs. George Carroll, has told me &ldquo;Why, Reed was a<lb/>
coward, afraid of yellow fever. He left Cuba before the real work began and never<lb/>
was willing to be bitten himself.&rdquo; This attitude is widely prevalent even now<lb/>
in Cuba. Another missing item of lesser importance concerns any correspondence<lb/>
or memoranda between Reed and Sternberg regarding the formation of the Board.</p>
<p>Where are these data? They are not, and, so far as I have been able to find, never<lb/>
have been in the hands of any of the other survivors or their families. General<lb/>
Kean told me the following on several occasions and dictated it to me once or<lb/>
twice in transcribed conversations between us in his home.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02960016"/>
<p>Carroll<lb/>
Confidential Memo - 3 -</p>
<p>Kean, a pallbearer at Reed's funeral, was on the way back from Arlington when the<lb/>
thought occurred, &ldquo;We must secure all of Reed's papers and notes right away.&rdquo; Next<lb/>
morning he went to the Army Medical Museum and Reed's office, and found that it had<lb/>
already been cleaned out. Worried, he inquired discretely among those who might have<lb/>
had authority to do this but no one, presumably, know anything about it. By process<lb/>
of elimination he decided that Dr. James Carroll had done it and was of a mind to<lb/>
speak critically to him about this but then he reflected that Carroll, having been<lb/>
Reed's long-time assistant and associate, might have naturally assumed that Reed's<lb/>
papers now belonged to him or that he needed them for his own later yellow fever<lb/>
papers and had a right to them. So Kean approached Carroll obliquely, told him he<lb/>
had been trying to find the missing data and thereby gave Carroll a chance to ad-<lb/>
mit that he had then but Carroll's reply was apparently evasive and non-informative.<lb/>
Kean always felt sure that Doctor Carroll had taken all the data from Reed's office<lb/>
and has encouraged me through the years to &ldquo;keep after the Carrolls.&rdquo; Indeed,<lb/>
hearing of my early rebuffs at the hands of George Carroll, General Kean on one oc-<lb/>
casion, talked the matter over with General Ireland, and was in the mood to &ldquo;go to<lb/>
the Surgeon General and visit Carroll with him and demand the return of Reed's<lb/>
papers for they never belonged to Dr. James Carroll and certainly don't belong to<lb/>
his son!&rdquo; It is my recollection that General Kean or General Ireland or both<lb/>
did once visit or telephone Carroll's son but to no avail.</p>
<p>For the above reasons, I have endured the many rebuffs, embarrassments and the<lb/>
impolite and almost insulting actions of George Carroll. On early visits he would<lb/>
occasionally talk to me only through a closed door or through a niche in the door.<lb/>
Therefore I learned, on later visits, the technique of getting through the door<lb/>
quickly and into the hall or at least putting my foot into the door so as to insure<lb/>
at least a crack. These activities have been in amazing contrast to the extremely<lb/>
generous and sympathetic and even grateful attitude on the part of all the other<lb/>
relatives who have put practically everything at my disposal and have expressed,<lb/>
on numerous occasions, <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>pleasure</add> that I am interested in their relatives. I re-<lb/>
fer particularly to the Reed, Lazear and Agramonte families.</p>
<p>For the sake of the historical preservation of the invaluable documents which were<lb/>
presumably in the hands of George Carroll, and apparently illegally so, I persisted.<lb/>
I always tried to be polite, despite my inner feelings but I did have to adopt<lb/>
various attitudes, - eagerness, which I had hoped would be catching, or relative<lb/>
indifference, etc. Over the years, I made every kind of an appeal -- to their<lb/>
family pride, to their sense of fairness, to their selfish interests, etc. Once<lb/>
I tried another approach, that of ridicule: &ldquo;Mr. Carroll, for years you have been<lb/>
telling me of the material you have, but you have never identified any of it. I<lb/>
am fed up; if you don't want anyone but yourself to honor your father, so be it.<lb/>
Actually, I don't think you have got a thing. I have tried to cooperate, to<lb/>
demonstrate my sincerity, to show you that I do hope to honor your father but in<lb/>
my opinion you are bluffing and all of this is a waste of time!&rdquo; This attitude<lb/>
got better results than any previous one, and he said, &ldquo;I'll show you who's<lb/>
bluffing.&rdquo; Whereupon he went upstairs and in a few minutes brought down two letters<lb/>
from Walter Reed to his father. I promptly recognized Reed's handwriting on the<lb/>
envelope but George Carroll held his hand over the body of each letter and only<lb/>
let me see the signatures, an incredible performance. Seeing that bluffing and<lb/>
appealing to his selfish nature apparently worked better than anything else, I offered<lb/>
him any one of several propositions: (1) I said I would give him a reasonable or<lb/>
fair amount of money (sums never specified) if he wanted to sell the material, or<lb/>
(2) an appropriate sum if he would let me copy or photostat the material, he to<lb/>

keep the originals. When he refused, I made two more offers: (a) so much if he<lb/>
would just let me see the data without copying any of it, or (b) if he would provide<lb/>
me with a certified listing of what he had. He would often dismiss me by saying<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02960017"/>
Carroll<lb/>
Confidential Memo - 4 -<lb/>
that he couldn't do anything until he saw his lawyer when it was convenient. He<lb/>
also kept referring vaguely to his safe deposit box where he had some of his<lb/>
father's material. Even a listing would have been worthwhile and then I would<lb/>
have known whether or not he had the missing data and if he had, I could have saved<lb/>
many hours and much travel on my vacations and so on, hunting for the missing<lb/>
material, but he accepted none of these offers.</p>
<p>Between these highly unsatisfactory visits, I preserved the amenities and from<lb/>
time to time, sent him and his wife the same data I sent the other relatives of<lb/>
the yellow fever personalities, such as copies of the Cornwell painting of the<lb/>
conquest of yellow fever, or my reprints regarding the discovery of Camp Lazear<lb/>
and the articles and photographs concerning its dedication in 1952. I never had<lb/>
a single acknowledgment of any of these or the letters accompanying them.</p>
<p>I decided therefore that my only hope lay in his wife, Mrs. Carroll, a rather drab<lb/>
and seemingly unhappy woman of limited education who might have just one interest<lb/>
in me, because she has had rheumatoid arthritis for years. Occasionally, I would<lb/>
find her alone and talk to her while waiting for her husband. She would talk to me<lb/>
about her condition. She would say, &ldquo;My husband is a very secretive man, especially<lb/>
about this yellow fever business. He runs his own business and never confides in<lb/>
me. I never interfere. I have no idea what he has, if anything. If he has a safe<lb/>
deposit box, I don't even know what bank it is in, much less what's in it. If he<lb/>
has material in the house, I don't know what he has or where it is. I have never<lb/>
seen any of the stuff he speaks of. Remember that both he and I came from large,<lb/>
poor families. George went to work as a boy and had little education. His mother<lb/>
was very bitter about the way Doctor Carroll was neglected by the Army, by the<lb/>
medical profession and by the country. She resented the Reeds very much and there<lb/>
has been bitter feeling between the Carrolls and the Reeds (I am sure this is en-<lb/>
tirely one <unclear>sided</unclear>. I doubt if the Reeds have had more than passing contact with the<lb/>
Carrolls, if that). Mother Carroll taught all her children that Doctor Carroll had<lb/>
been robbed of his rights. Perhaps she was biased. I know nothing about it and I<lb/>
kept my nose out of their affairs. I can't help you, although I can understand<lb/>
your interest, perhaps better than George.&rdquo;</p>
<p>What little I saw of the relationship between George and his wife led me to con-<lb/>
clude, perhaps erroneously, that their marriage was a pretty dull affair since<lb/>
there was apparently so little confidence and trust. She seemed to have little<lb/>
or no influence on him. He paid little attention to her in my presence and there<lb/>
was no evidences of affection on his arrival home. Indeed he seemed to be hostile<lb/>
to the world in general. I believe he had a minor job in the government for a<lb/>
while and in later years was collector of money for a public utilities. He had a<lb/>
rather drab three-story stone house just off the business district down town<lb/>
(Address: 1309 - 13th Street N. W.) where they would live in hard times<lb/>
when they couldn't rent it. In better times they lived way out at 2814 Rhode<lb/>
Island Avenue N.E. and he would drive around in his car. Through the years, I<lb/>
visited them in either place, but never knew ahead of time where I should ad-<lb/>
dress my letters to them or where I should call on them.</p>
<p>Because I am truly sincere in my desire to give each man, including Doctor Carroll,<lb/>
his full credit, I tried not to let my impatience with Doctor Carroll's unfortunate<lb/>
offspring influence my conduct. Except for the one episode mentioned above when,<lb/>
as a deliberate tactic and change of pace, I spoke sharply to George, I have tried<lb/>
to be friendly and sympathetic, to understand their difficult situation and dif-<lb/>
fering moods. During the War, George was very ill in a Veterans Hospital, Mt. Alto<lb/>
I believe, in Washington. Reputedly, according to his wife, he was &ldquo;dying of a<lb/>
heart attack.&rdquo; I visited his wife and, at considerable expense of time, I visited<lb/>
George. We had a very pleasant hour's visit. I tried to cheer him up. According<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02960018"/>
Carroll<lb/>
Confidential Memo - 5 -<lb/>
to his Veterans Hospital physician whom I saw, he presumably had cholecystitis,<lb/>
not heart trouble. As I recall it, I sent him flowers, a book and a follow-up<lb/>
note.</p>
<p>Obviously I would get no where unless George died before his wife and so about<lb/>
1944 I asked my cousin in Washington, Nadine Hench, to watch the obituary columns<lb/>
and to let me know at once if George should die. Nadine has faithfully examined<lb/>
the obituary columns practically daily ever since and recently remarked, &ldquo;Thousands<lb/>
of Carrolls have died in Washington, even a George Carroll or two, but no George<lb/>
S. H. Carroll. He is immortal.&rdquo; (There were more than one George Carroll in the<lb/>
Washington phone book.) But last October, 1953, at my niece's wedding in Char-<lb/>
lottesville, Nadine told me excitedly, &ldquo;George Carroll just died. The funeral is<lb/>
today.&rdquo; I sent Mrs. Carroll a wire and later a letter of sympathy. The fact that<lb/>
in time I had a reply was hopeful. Anticipating a trip to Washington in February,<lb/>
1954, I wrote her expressing the hope that on my next visit I could call on her and<lb/>
perhaps see the Carroll data. She wrote me in such a way that I was optimistic,<lb/>
but she also asked advice about her arthritis. I replied that I would do whatever<lb/>
I could within the confines of medical ethics, considering that she was actually<lb/>
a patient of a Washington physician and orthopedist. Until I set the time for my<lb/>
Washington visit and asked for a specific appointment, her letters were friendly<lb/>
and hopeful. But, as I feared, at the last minute she wrote saying that she was<lb/>
too lonesome and desolate to be of use to me now, that she couldn't face the<lb/>
prospect of opening her husband's possessions and, in any event, she hardly ex-<lb/>
pected to be in Washington while I was there. In other words, once more she was<lb/>
putting me off and I was again experiencing frustration at the last minute.</p>
<p><hi>PRESENT VISIT</hi></p>
<p>Last Thursday morning, I decided to take another chance and took with me my brother<lb/>
Atch, (Professor of English literature at the University of Virginia, who happened<lb/>
to run up to see me while in Washington). Hiring a taxi by the hour because we<lb/>
didn't expect to be allowed to see the data and expected to be with Mrs. Carroll<lb/>
for not more than five or ten minutes, if she was there, we made the rather long<lb/>
trip to the Rhode Island Avenue home. Our arrival surprised her. At 10 a.m., she<lb/>
was in a dressing gown, talking to a painter. Obviously she wasn't too happy to see<lb/>
us but apparently hesitated to dismiss us in the presence of the painter. So she<lb/>
invited us in and went upstairs to dress.</p>
<p>The house was untidy and gloomy. Most of the window blinds were down and the<lb/>
remnants of a meager breakfast or lunch were on a small table beside an untidy<lb/>
lounge in the living room, a most depressing atmosphere. After Mrs. Carroll dis-<lb/>
missed the painter, we began what we believed would be merely a brief general con-<lb/>
versation. We offered her our condolences, urged her to try to develop new in-<lb/>
terests, etc. Hesitatingly, I told her I was so sorry not to be able to see the<lb/>
Carroll data. My brother joined in and told her how important it was for the<lb/>
whole story to be told and for Doctor Carroll's material to be made available to<lb/>
scholars, whether or not it was sent to join my material or to the National Archives<lb/>
or somewhere else. But she showed little interest in this and merely told us over<lb/>
and over of her own troubles. &ldquo;I have no future. I don't want to live. I would<lb/>
just as soon commit suicide, etc., Etc.&rdquo;.</p>
<p>When we finally got back on the subject of the Carroll papers, at first we got the<lb/>
usual reaction: She didn't know whether she had anything after all. If she did,<lb/>
she couldn't stand the sorrow of reviewing her husband's papers and anyhow, they<lb/>
were locked up in trunks in a cold basement and her arthritis wouldn't permit her</p>
<pb n="6" id="f02960019"/>
<p>Carroll<lb/>
Confidential Memo - 6 -<lb/>
to stay there long enough to examine them. Besides she had no idea which keys<lb/>
would open the locks. My brother asked her. &ldquo;What kind of trunks are they?&rdquo; She<lb/>
suddenly replied, &ldquo;They are those old-fashioned trunks with the round or flat<lb/>
tops, but all of George's keys are mixed up on four rings and I have no idea which<lb/>
key fits what.&rdquo; &ldquo;Couldn't we just try to see if we can find for you the right key?&rdquo;<lb/>
said my brother. To our amazement, she went upstairs and got the four bunches of<lb/>
keys and took us to the basement. There were three ancient trunks - a low, oblong<lb/>
one, a high one with a rounded top, and a high one with a flat top. Within ten<lb/>
minutes, Atch and I had found the keys and opened all three.</p>
<p>What a mass of junk. Hundreds of reprints, hundreds of old letters, negatives and<lb/>
family snapshots jumbled together, a few bound books, a few large and small note-<lb/>
books, Doctor Carroll's old uniforms, canes, etc. After 13 or more years of effort,<lb/>
here we were with this jumbled mass before our eyes and no time to examine them,<lb/>
as my brother had to catch a train and I had to get back to my hotel, go over my<lb/>
lecture carefully to shorten it and then prepare for my lecture and dinner at<lb/>
Walter Reed Hospital. When I suggested that I would stay over an extra day and<lb/>
come out and &ldquo;just sort out the piles,&rdquo; she raised the usual objections. She<lb/>
felt unfair to George for even letting us see the material in the trunks; her<lb/>
two sisters-in law would be mad if she let us go through the material as they had<lb/>
long been desiring their share, etc. We expressed the opinion that the material<lb/>
was here to do with what she wanted and that at any rate she, her sisters-in-law,<lb/>
and the lawyer would want to know something about what was in the trunks before<lb/>
any rational discussion about the material could be held. Finally, she said I<lb/>
could come out the next morning at 9, just to see what was there. I purposely<lb/>
did not give her my Washington address, feeling sure that if she had it, she would<lb/>
merely phone and cancel the appointment. We got in a taxi which had waited an hour<lb/>
and a half for us and drove off to our appointments. Retaining a glimmer of hope.<lb/>
I cancelled my plane reservations and made new ones for the next day.</p>
<p><hi>VISIT OF FRIDAY MORNING, FEBRUARY 19</hi><lb/>
I arrived at Mrs. Carroll's house promptly at 9 a.m. From the curb I saw that all<lb/>
the blinds were down, even on the front door, and an envelope was stuck to the front<lb/>
door. My heart sank as I knew once more the appointment was off. According to the<lb/>
note, apparently written earlier that morning (since she spoke of &ldquo;yesterday&rdquo;),<lb/>
she had called her lawyer yesterday and presumably he had advised her not to let me<lb/>
see any of the material. I refused to give in. I rang the bell for minutes at a<lb/>
time, pounded on various windows and called out to her through the door and dif-<lb/>
ferent windows, &ldquo;Mrs. Carroll, won't you let me talk to you, at least a minute.&rdquo;<lb/>
She had casually mentioned the name of her lawyer the day before but I had for-<lb/>
gotten to write it down and it was my intention not to bother her at all but to<lb/>
visit her lawyer and explain my position. After 20 minutes of the above, I went to<lb/>
a nearby restaurant and phoned her. No reply. Then back to the house where I examined<lb/>
every door, including the side door and back basement door. They were all locked<lb/>
and she did not respond to my calls and knocks. Back to the restaurant; I phoned<lb/>
again and the line was busy. I hoped that this meant that she was at least home<lb/>
but if it was a party line, it might have meant otherwise. I returned to the house<lb/>
for the third time, knocked loudly and then purposely left the outer screen door<lb/>
slam so as to make the decided impression of a definite and final departure. I<lb/>
then walked down the street toward the street-car stop but cut across the street<lb/>
and cut back, walking along a road in a deep ravine and then scrambled up a deep<lb/>
embankment and ending behind a service station, diagonally across the street from<lb/>
the Carroll home. I was hoping that if she was in the house and assumed that I<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f02960020"/>
Carroll<lb/>
Confidential Memo - 7 -<lb/>
had left, she might open the door to a mailman or some delivery man, whereupon<lb/>
I would walk hastily across the street, but no luck. After waiting at the ser-<lb/>
vice station for a half hour, I crossed the street to the restaurant and made two<lb/>
more phone calls. Once the line was busy, the second time there was no answer.<lb/>
For the fourth time, I went to the house and when there was no response to my<lb/>
knocking, I walked to the middle of the street in front of the house so that if<lb/>
she was peeping, she could see me taking a taxi. I got back to the Mayflower<lb/>
about 11 a.m., quickly signed out, picked up my plane reservation, closed my<lb/>
bags and was about to leave the room at 11:40 to catch the 12:30 plane, when I<lb/>
decided to make one last phone call.</p>
<p>To my amazement she answered and chose to tell me the following: &ldquo;Last night I<lb/>
took a sleeping pill and I just woke up. I assume you came to the house. I am sorry<lb/>
that my lawyer does not want me to show you anything.&rdquo; Despite these remarks,<lb/>
she seemed to be not unfriendly and when I asked her if she was making her own<lb/>
breakfast and she said she was just starting it, I said. &ldquo;Hold everything. Would<lb/>
you get dressed and have breakfast with me at the nearby restaurant? That will<lb/>
save you the trouble. Please let me talk to you just a little.&rdquo; Shen she agreed,<lb/>
I quickly hung up lest she change her mind, cancelled the new plane reservations,<lb/>
had difficulty retrieving my room which was already sold to a conventioner, and<lb/>
taxied back to her home, arriving at 12 o'clock. I took her to a nearby restaurant<lb/>
for &ldquo;brunch.&rdquo; I really felt sorry for her. She was all broken up and obviously<lb/>
anxious to talk to someone, anyone, even Hench. She told me at length of her<lb/>
troubles, her abject misery at being alone without her husband, her misunder-<lb/>
standings with Carroll's sisters, her futility and desire to die and so on. Despite<lb/>
a lack of the usual family harmony, apparently there had been a certain closeness<lb/>
and mutual interdependence between her and her husband so that she missed him<lb/>
terribly, even though he was not ordinarily affectionate. The poor woman showed<lb/>
suspicion of everything and everybody. She told me all about her husband's final<lb/>
illness, his mental confusion toward the end, his unauthorized departure from the<lb/>
hospital two or three days before he died, the hospital's preliminary refusal to<lb/>
readmit him, her efforts to get him back in and her unhappy conversations with the<lb/>
doctors who scolded her and her husband. Apparently he died in coma from heart<lb/>
failure the next day. &ldquo;I wouldn't be surprised if the doctors didn't actually kill<lb/>
him. For all I know they might have decided he was no good to anybody and slipped<lb/>
him some medicine. They were certainly mad at him and I wouldn't be surprised if<lb/>
they hadn't done away with him.&rdquo; She had feelings of guilt because she hadn't<lb/>
been with her husband at the moment of death, also because she had no children.<lb/>
&ldquo;When we should have had them, we kept putting it off. Then I got arthritis<lb/>
and it seemed impossible. Later apparently we couldn't have any. I feel as if<lb/>
I had defied God and that is why I am so lonesome.&rdquo; Again she told me of the<lb/>
seconal dosage which she took nightly and on more than one occasion said, &ldquo;Doctor<lb/>
Hench, how many of these will put me out permanently?&rdquo; She has no interests and<lb/>
although her mother, still living, is about 80, her brother and I think a sister<lb/>
live in the District, they live rather far away (one in Alexandria, one in Arling-<lb/>
ton). She cried much of the time. &ldquo;I never leave the house. I just put myself asleep<lb/>
at night, try to sleep as long as possible, wake up and try to distract myself<lb/>
with TV.&rdquo;</p>
<p>She asked for help with respect to her arthritis. Her hands are rather badly<lb/>
deformed but apparently there is little or no activity of the disease. She has<lb/>
badly displaced metatarsal hands and can walk with difficulty. Her orthopedist<lb/>
has advised resection of the heads but her general practitioner says she is too<lb/>
old to risk it. I merely made general comments and told her that she would have<lb/>
to decide that on the basis of how much pain and disability she developed. Toward<lb/>
the end of a long lunch I dared to return to the matter of the Carroll papers.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f02960021"/>
<p>Carroll</p>
<p>Confidential Memo - 8 -</p>
<p>She was a little more friendly but insisted that she really had called her lawyer<lb/>
who had told her not to let me see anything for the following reasons: Although<lb/>
everything she has of her husband's was left to her by her husband's will, the<lb/>
lawyer takes the position that Dr. James Carroll's material was owned after 1907<lb/>
by his widow, George's mother, who died without a will and therefore, technically,<lb/>
his two sisters have a right to an equal share in this material. Presumably, they<lb/>
were supposed to get together sometime between 1930, when Mrs. Carroll died, and<lb/>
the present for an <unclear>amicable</unclear> division but since each suspected the other, they<lb/>
never did. However after George's funeral, one of the sisters went to the safe<lb/>
deposit box which apparently was in the joint name of George and this sister and,<lb/>
without Mrs. George Carroll's permission, she took home Doctor Carroll's Congres-<lb/>
sional medal.</p>
<p>I proposed that since none of them (her lawyer, the sisters and she) knew actually<lb/>
what was in these trunks, her lawyer could at least give her no suggestions without<lb/>
a preliminary listing, but before she would let me make it, she did phone the lawyer.<lb/>
To my pleasant surprise, he told me that he had advised her to let me see and copy<lb/>
anything she had, that he felt my purpose was entirely proper and in the family<lb/>
interest, and that his only recommendation to her had been that although she could<lb/>
lend me material, she should not give it to me, certainly anything of any possible<lb/>
interest to the sisters, in the hopes that eventually a proper division or arrange-<lb/>
ment might be made by the sisters and Mrs. Carroll together. Mrs. Carroll let on<lb/>
she was surprised and insisted again &ldquo;He certainly changed his mind. That isn't what<lb/>
he told me yesterday.&rdquo; But I am quite sure that she had misinterpreted the lawyer's<lb/>
advice, based on her general suspicion and fears.</p>
<p>Finally, at 2:30 p.m., we went to the basement and <unclear>captied</unclear> the three trunks, piling<lb/>
everything on the floor. To make a long story short, we spent the next six hours<lb/>
rearranging, identifying and repacking the trunks. We sorted the reprints and<lb/>
put them all together. One box contained about 50 or 75 letters addressed to Mrs.<lb/>
James Carroll. I examined a few and some would be of interest to save as some of<lb/>
them are letters of condolence and praise from well-known people such as Gorgas,<lb/>
Sternberg, etc. I think a few of these letters are from Doctor Carroll to his wife<lb/>
but only a very few. In another box we put perhaps 75 letters to Doctor Carroll,<lb/>
a miscellaneous assortment, again some from important people. In another box we<lb/>
put hundreds of negatives and prints of Mrs. James Carroll's children and possibly<lb/>
grandchildren, some of which were also in two or three albums. Although I could<lb/>
not examine them in detail, I doubt if there is anything of significance among<lb/>
them. We found perhaps a half dozen interesting old pictures from Cuba. We re-<lb/>
packed considerable clothing of Doctor Carroll, including at least two lieutenant's<lb/>
uniforms and one sergeant's dress uniform. We even repacked a gruesome funeral<lb/>
wreath. In separate boxes, I repacked in one many typed manuscripts of Doctor<lb/>
Carroll's of papers already published but with hand-written corrections, and in<lb/>
the most important box, we put the following: Any hand-written notes by Doctor<lb/>
Carroll we could find, including several letters of Carroll to Reed (which shows<lb/>
that Carroll did have at least some of Reed's material, however come by), a few<lb/>
letters of Reed to Carroll, two or three small and large hand-written notebooks of<lb/>
Carroll's containing pathological studies made between 1895 and 1907, and the<lb/>
original fever and nurses charts of the last 1901 series of experimental cases of<lb/>
yellow fever, including Miss Maasa, Bullard and the several Spaniards, but there<lb/>
was no Lazear notebook. I examined everything carefully and am absolutely certain<lb/>
of that.</p>
<p>In summary, although Doctor Carroll did have some material which at one time be-<lb/>
longed to Reed, this material is quite limited and 95% of the material was of Doctor<lb/>
Carroll. Nevertheless, some of it, that separated into the one box, is of considerable<lb/>
historic importance but of probably little or no commercial value. It is this which<lb/>
I must get copied as soon as possible.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f02960022"/>
<p>Carroll</p>
<p>Confidential Memo - 9 -</p>
<p>While I was going over all this and making a preliminary listing, Mrs. Carroll<lb/>
showed a surprising agility and tolerance to the cold basement. She got around<lb/>
on her hands and knees and sorted reprints, examined most of the material, at<lb/>
least casually enough to convince her that there was nothing of obvious commercial<lb/>
value. Indeed as the afternoon wore on, she lost interest and talked of it as &ldquo;junk.&rdquo;<lb/>
I told her that the uniforms were of no commercial value but that either I or the<lb/>
Army Medical Museum would be delighted to have one or more; however there are<lb/>
enough to go around. During the early evening she made contradictory comments:<lb/>
&ldquo;I am going to get rid of this stuff right away. There is nothing worthwhile<lb/>
here and even though some of it may be of interest, it is painful for me to have<lb/>
it around. I am going to get rid of it.&rdquo; Or &ldquo;I think I will ship these trunks<lb/>
right away to one of George's sisters, but they will probably throw it away.&rdquo; Or<lb/>
&ldquo;I don't believe I want this stuff; I will send it to the sisters but they will<lb/>
either throw it away or, if they keep it, they will never let anyone see it. They<lb/>
are more secretive than George.&rdquo; Or &ldquo;I doubt if these trunks could be shipped by<lb/>
an express company. I am of a mind to get rid of it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My feelings can be imagined. Granted that 90% of the material is useless except<lb/>
as family junk, the few letters of Reed to Carroll and the several letters of<lb/>
Carroll to Reed, the box of Carroll's manuscripts, the notebooks and the reprints<lb/>
of the yellow fever papers and the old photographs and charts of the 1901 series -<lb/>
these certainly must be kept.</p>
<p>Seeing that she was losing interest in the material (I suspect that she and George's<lb/>
sisters had thought there might be something of immediate monetary value therein),<lb/>
and hearing her talk of either suicide or getting rid of the trunks or both, I<lb/>
finally ventured to ask if she would let me have one of each reprint and let me<lb/>
borrow a few items to copy. She first let me take one of each reprint and then,<lb/>
as we were repacking dozens and dozens of them, she said, &ldquo;After all, this stuff<lb/>
has already been published. George's sisters won't want them but will probably<lb/>
throw them away. Take what you want. But don't tell my lawyer or George's sisters.<lb/>
This is my business. I am not doing anything wrong. If you tell my lawyer, he<lb/>
will only call me in for another conference and send me another bill. He charges<lb/>
me too much anyhow. If you tell the sisters they will think I am giving you some-<lb/>
thing they might want.&rdquo;</p>
<p>About 8:30 or 9 p.m., we had everything identified, rearranged and repacked. I<lb/>
proposed that I take her down town for dinner and a movie, an evening of pleasant<lb/>
distraction. I was not surprised when she accepted eagerly because she was so<lb/>
desperately lonely but we couldn't get a taxi and finally went to a nearby restaurant<lb/>
where, despite her supposed &ldquo;complete lack of appetite&rdquo; she ate a hearty meal,<lb/>
bigger than mine. Again she seemed delighted with the opportunity of unburdening<lb/>
herself and once more we went over all her problems. I inquired as to her relation-<lb/>
ships with her minister but unfortunately he is a new one with whom she has little<lb/>
contact. I do want to write to him however and see if he can't help her. It would<lb/>
be fine if she could get a part-time job, perhaps three hours or so a day, not<lb/>
particularly for the income but to get her out of her desperate depression. On<lb/>
the way driving back to her home, she said that she had been glad to talk to me<lb/>
and had after all had an interesting day and &ldquo;I am not very free with people and<lb/>
have few friends but you have been helpful and I enjoyed the day but I dread the<lb/>
night and tomorrow.&rdquo; I had a bright thought - since she was not tired (it was then<lb/>
10:30), I asked her if she would mind if I stayed longer and made copies of at<lb/>
least the Reed letters and such others as I might have time for while she was watching<lb/>
TV. She unhesitatingly agreed as she seemed not to want to be left alone and so<lb/>
I spent two hours copying hastily as many letters as I could. Some of these have<lb/>
already been published by Kelly or Hommeter since Doctor Carroll had loaned them<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f02960023"/>
Carroll<lb/>
Confidential Memo - 10 -<lb/>
material and had given Doctor Kelly certain material which later Doctor Kelly gave<lb/>
me. About 11 p.m. her mother and then another relative phoned. Mrs. Carroll told<lb/>
me they had apparently phoned while we were out. &ldquo;They phone me every day and if I<lb/>
don't answer they are afraid I <hi>have</hi> finally committed suicide.&rdquo; She told them she<lb/>
had been with me and that I was examining the material. Her own relatives ap-<lb/>
parently had no objection whatever. I left at 1:15 a.m. because she said &ldquo;Stay<lb/>
as long as you want. I go to sleep when I want and sleep as long as I want. What<lb/>
difference is there to me.&rdquo; During the evening she interrupted my copying to show<lb/>
me proudly a picture of her christening the U. S. liberty ship, &ldquo;James Carroll,&rdquo;<lb/>
and she spoke of George's feelings on that occasion. &ldquo;During the entire ceremony<lb/>
George said not a word. There were tears in his eyes and later he said to me,<lb/>
'Why couldn't I be somebody like my father?'&rdquo;</p>
<p>Before leaving, I explained again my whole project, told her of the new Reed<lb/>
Museum here and of the one to be set up at Camp Lazear and expressed my hope that<lb/>
I would be permitted to have at least copies and perhaps some of the originals in<lb/>
time. She agreed, for the moment at least, that I could come back and that she<lb/>
would go with me to have the special material, separated in the one box, and the<lb/>
other material for that matter, copied or photostated at our mutual convenience.<lb/>
But I have learned by previous experience that a promise of one day is easily<lb/>
cancelled. It is my great fear that she may actually throw everything away as it<lb/>
is painful to her.</p>
<p><hi>SUMMARY OF UNFINISHED BUSINESS</hi><lb/>
I want to do the following for this unfortunate, miserable woman who is badly<lb/>
in need of friends and of spiritual help.<lb/>
1. Write to her minister.<lb/>
2. Write to her two doctors if that seems appropriate. One of them seems to<lb/>
know me well.<lb/>
3. Send her Kelly's book. She has none and expressed the desire to have one.<lb/>
4. Send Mrs. Carroll copies of my preliminary listing of the material in the trunks.<lb/>
5. As soon as possible, make photostats, either with the help of Miss Schnurr and<lb/>
a professional photographer or with the help of the Army Medical Museum.<lb/>
6. Sometime soon send my reprints to the lawyer and the two sisters to show<lb/>
them of my special interest and, in due time, I must write or visit the two<lb/>
sisters who may well have the missing data as Mrs. Carroll insists that when<lb/>
Mrs. James Carroll died the sisters did take with them a certain amount of<lb/>
Doctor Carroll's material. They may well have the missing data and we may be<lb/>
near to it after all.</p>
<p><hi>ADDENDUM</hi>:<lb/>
Sisters of Mr. George S. H. CARROLL:<lb/>
Mrs. Lyle McClung. Albany Georgia<lb/>
Mrs. Frank Beuhler, 2221 Wrooklage Avenue, Louisville, Kentucky</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
