<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02966001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Article: The Relief of Dr. Carroll's Widow, April 3, 1909</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02966001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1909-04-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Isthmus of Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1909-04-03">April 3, 1909</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02966001</idno>
<title>Article: The Relief of Dr. Carroll's Widow, April 3, 1909</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This article, appearing in the "Journal of the American Medical Association," makes an appeal for monetary contributions to James Carroll's surviving family.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1909-04-03">
<head>Article: The Relief of Dr. Carroll's Widow, April 3, 1909</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02966001"/>
<opener>
Jour. Am. Med. Assn.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1909-04-03">April 3, 1909.</date>
</dateline>
FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY<lb/>
</opener>
<p>THE RELIEF OF DR. CARROLL'S WIDOW</p>
<p>In Dr. Goldberger's excellent monograph on yellow<lb/>
fever the work of the Army board in Cuba, headed by<lb/>
Major Walter Reed, is summarized in a single pithy<lb/>
sentence. Referring to the demonstration of the trans-<lb/>
mission of yellow fever infection by mosquitoes, he says<lb/>
that it &ldquo;converted a discredited hypothesis into an es-<lb/>
tablished doctrine.&rdquo; The positive demonstration of this<lb/>
fact has opened up a wide field of sanitary accomplish-<lb/>
ment. The epoch-making victory over yellow fever of<lb/>
Gorgas in Havana, his sanitary regeneration of the<lb/>
Isthmus of Panama, White's brilliant results in the<lb/>
New Orleans epidemic of 1905, and Kean's recent ex-<lb/>
tensive campaign in Cuba are all the direct results of<lb/>
the confirmation of Finlay's theory by the work of<lb/>
Reed, Lazear, Carroll and Agramonte in 1900. With<lb/>
a single exception, the members of this gallant band<lb/>
have all perished in the prime of their vigor and use-<lb/>
fulness. Dr. Agramonte, the sole survivor, is a distin-<lb/>
guished member of the faculty of the ancient Uni-<lb/>
versity of Havana and a valued adviser of the sanitary<lb/>
department of Cuba.</p>
<p>The rewards which these soldiers of science received<lb/>
for their work during their lives amounted to little or<lb/>
nothing. The value of their work to humanity and<lb/>
civilization is beyond estimate. Yet all of them, owing<lb/>
to the meager pay of the army officer, left their fami-<lb/>
lies without adequate means of support, although their<lb/>
widows are now in receipt of pensions which keep the<lb/>
wolf from the door, but which leave no margin even<lb/>
for Spartan luxuries. On one family in particular the<lb/>
burden has been heavy. Major James Carroll was the<lb/>
first volunteer to submit to an experimental inocula-<lb/>
tion from an infected mosquito and to suffer an attack<lb/>
of yellow fever. This illness was so severe as to en-<lb/>
danger his life. As a result of it he developed a dilated<lb/>
heart, which was the ultimate cause of his death. He<lb/>
died a martyr to science for the benefit of humanity,<lb/>
leaving a widow, an aged mother and seven small chil-<lb/>
dren practically unprovided for. His widow is now<lb/>
threatened with the loss of her home by the foreclosure<lb/>
of a mortgage and is in need of immediate assistance.<lb/>
Attention is called to an appeal on page 1122 of this<lb/>
number of THE JOURNAL setting forth the facts in<lb/>
detail and asking for contributions for the relief of<lb/>
this deserving family.</p>
<p>The experimental work of Carroll and his associates<lb/>
has forever banished yellow fever epidemics from civ-<lb/>
ilized countries. The saving in lives and treasure for<lb/>
present and future generations is beyond all calcula-<lb/>
tions, yet the widow and children of one of the men<lb/>
who made this possible are in danger of losing their<lb/>
home. Surely, if the American public does not realize<lb/>
its enormous debt to this man and his offspring, the<lb/>
medical profession will not turn a deaf ear to the plea<lb/>
for assistance made in behalf of his helpless and de-<lb/>
pendent family.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
