<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02966002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Editorial from the Military Surgeon, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02966002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans, Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Havana, Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02966002</idno>
<title>Editorial from the Military Surgeon, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The editor praises the work of Reed, Lazear, Carroll and Agramonte as having laid the foundation for all future efforts against yellow fever and malaria. Carroll is singled out for commendation and called a martyr.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Editorial from the Military Surgeon, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02966002"/>
<p>Editorial in the Military Surgeon-<lb/>
Appeal for Major James Carroll's Family</p>
<p>FROM <unclear>GEN. J. R. KEAN</unclear></p>
<p>In Dr. Goldberger's excellent monograph on Yellow Fever the work of the<lb/>
Army Board in Cuba, headed by Major Walter Reed, is stated in a single pithy<lb/>
sentence. Referring to the conveyance of the yellow fever infection by mos-<lb/>
quitos he says that <hi>it converted a discredited hypothesis into an established<lb/>
doctrine</hi>. This key unlocked the gate which has lead us into a wide field of<lb/>
sanitary accomplishment. The epoch-making victory over yellow fever of Gorgas<lb/>
in Havana; his sanitary regeneration of the Isthmus, White's brilliant results<lb/>
in the New Orleans epidemic of 1905, and Kean's recent extensive campaign in<lb/>
Cuba are all the direct fruits of the demonstration of Finlay's theory by the<lb/>
work of Reed, Lazear, Carroll and Agramonte in 1900. By a singular fatality<lb/>
this gallant band have, with a single exception, all perished in the prime of<lb/>
their vigor and usefulness. Dr. Agramonte, the sole survivor, is a disting-<lb/>
uished member of the faculty of the ancient University of Havana and a valued<lb/>
adviser of the Sanitary Department of Cuba. The rewards which these soldiers<lb/>
of science received during their lives was little or nothing. All left<lb/>
families without adequate means of support, altho their widows are now in re-<lb/>
ceipt of pensions which keep the wolf from the door indeed, but without any<lb/>
broad margin for even Spartan luxuries. The attention of our readers is<lb/>
called to an appeal on page of this number of the Journal which calls<lb/>
attention to the necessities of the family of Major James Carroll, who are<lb/>
threatened with the loss of their home by the foreclosure of a mortgage and<lb/>
are in need of immediate assistance. Major Carroll, it will be recalled,<lb/>
was the first volunteer to suffer an experimental attack of yellow fever by<lb/>
having submitted to the bite of an infected mosquito. This attack was so<lb/>
severe as to very seriously endanger his life and left him with a dilated<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02966003"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
heart which was the ultimate cause of his death. He thus died a martyr of<lb/>
science, and the medical profession of America will surely not turn a deaf<lb/>
ear to the plea for assistance in the effort to secure a roof over the heads<lb/>
of the large and dependent family which he left behind him.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
