<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02971001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Article Extract: Dr. Osler's Address on "The Nation and the Tropics" and Dr. Finlay, April 1910</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02971001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1910-04-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1910-04-00">April 1910</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02971001</idno>
<title>Article Extract: Dr. Osler's Address on "The Nation and the Tropics" and Dr. Finlay, April 1910</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This extract, by Guiteras, discusses Finlay's work on yellow fever and his association with the U.S. Yellow Fever Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1910-04-00">
<head>Article Extract: Dr. Osler's Address on "The Nation and the Tropics" and Dr. Finlay, April 1910</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02971001"/>
<opener>
Extract<lb/>
from<lb/>
Guiteras' Article on &ldquo;Dr. Osler's Address on &ldquo;The Nation and the Tropics&rdquo;<lb/>
And Dr. Finlay.&rdquo;<lb/>
Carbon copy<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02971002"/>
Extract from: &ldquo;Dr. Osler's Address on &ldquo;The Nation and the Tropics&rdquo;<lb/>
and Dr. Finlay.&rdquo;<lb/>
By Dr. Juan Guiteras,<lb/>
Director of Public Health.<lb/>
Habana, Cuba.<lb/>
<dateline>
Sanidad y Beneficencia, <date value="1910-04-00">1910 (April)</date>
</dateline>
Vol. 3.<lb/>
</opener>
<p><hi>Page 319-321</hi>.</p>
<p>There is no difference whatever between the popular credence of the<lb/>
negroes of Africa and the Italian peasants who believed that fevers<lb/>
were produced by the bites of mosquitoes, and the writings of Nott,<lb/>
Beauperthuy and King. He who follows these authors chronologically,<lb/>
may imagine from the outward show of scientific apparel, that he is pro-<lb/>
gressing in a process of evolution of a great doctrine, but he soon<lb/>
finds that he is follwoing a vicious circle that brings him back to the<lb/>
negroes of Africa, and to nothing practical. It may appear for a mo-<lb/>
ment that Dr. Beauperthuy strikes out of the circle, and that he brings<lb/>
forward, out of the gossamer of his extraordinary and wild fancies, a<lb/>
fact, when he speaks of the mosquito a pattes rayees de blanc, the zan-<lb/>
cudo bobo. This mention, frequently repeated, twisting it out of the<lb/>
original sentence in which it is places, is made to serve as proof that<lb/>
Dr. Beauperthuy had fixed accurately upon the actual transmitter of yel-<lb/>
low fever, the Stegomyia calopus, characterized by white ringed joints<lb/>
in the six legs. But this is not true.</p>
<p><del>"</del>In the first place, Dr. Beauperthuy does not speak of the trans-<lb/>
mission of yellow fever from man to man by the mosquito, but of the pro-<lb/>
duction of ywllow fever and a host of other diseases by the bites of<lb/>
mosquitoes contaminated by feeding on putrid substances, specially in<lb/>
swamps. In the second place, the zancudo bobo is not the Stegomyia.<lb/>
Bobo means silly, dull, and the Stegomyia is one of the most alert of<lb/>
mosquitoes. The term mosquito bobo is applied by us to the Culex sol-<lb/>
licitans, also a striped mosquito that breeds along the sea shore in<lb/>
salt and brackish water, that invades human habitations in enormous<lb/>
swarms, and that might have fitted into Beauperthuy's theory of the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f02971003"/>
the<lb/>
2.<lb/>
origen of yellow fever in decomposing swamp plants from whence he be-<lb/>
lieved it was brought by mosquitoes to man. It is called bobo, because<lb/>
it is the dullest of mosquitoes, being easily killed by gentle applica-<lb/>
tion of the hand when the insect is in the act of feeding. To kill the<lb/>
Stegomyia or the pipiens, under the same circumstances you have to give<lb/>
a quick slap.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The twisting of Dr. Beauperthuy's statement into service consists<lb/>
in ignoring that he singles out this particular mosquito precisely to<lb/>
say that it is not the producer of yellow and malarial fevers. &ldquo;Elle<lb/>
est la plus commune et sa piq&ucirc;re est inoffensive comparativement &agrave; celle<lb/>
des autres esp&egrave;ces.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I wish to leave on record what Dr. Finlay said and did precisely<lb/>
at the time that the American Commissioners were about to commence their<lb/>
epoch making investigation. The African negroes who designate the mos-<lb/>
quito by the same name that they apply to their fevers, the Italian peas-<lb/>
ants<unclear>,</unclear> and Drs. Nott, Beauperthuy and King were equally removed from the<lb/>
possibility of doing what Dr. Finlay did.</p>
<p>This extraordinary man had sutdied very carefully the habits and<lb/>
geographical distribution of the stegomyia, or culex mosquito, De s v.,<lb/>
as it was then called. He had studied the anatomy of the insect, he had<lb/>
determined its manner of feeding and breeding, he had studied its be-<lb/>
haviour under varying influences of temperature and atmospheric pressure,<lb/>
and upon these facts, discovered and analysed by him, he explained with<lb/>
mathematical presision, as we do now, all the phenomena of the epidemio-<lb/>
logy of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Dr. Finlay met the American Commission with this mosquito in his<lb/>
hands. During twenty years he had been breeding it in test tubes and<lb/>
jars, in the manner which was afterwards employed by Ross and Grassi and<lb/>
others, and had been subjecting it to a series of most ingenious experi-<lb/>
ments<unclear>,</unclear> all carefully recorded. In presenting his mosquitoes he said:<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02971004"/>
said:<lb/>
3.<lb/>
if you take this mosquito and apply it to a yellow fever patient and al-<lb/>
low it to feed on his blood you will have an infected insect, capable of<lb/>
producing immunity (here he was mistaken) if you apply it withing two or<lb/>
three days after the bite, to a well man; and capable of producing a se-<lb/>
vere form of the disease, if you apply it later.</p>
<p>This statement he had made in writing in 1891, as follows: &ldquo;By the<lb/>
term &ldquo;contaminated mosquitoes&rdquo; I understand such as have stung a yellow<lb/>
fever patient during the first six days of the disease, and it is my be-<lb/>
lief that whereas one or two stings from mosquitoes recently contaminated<lb/>
may either occasion in susceptible persons a mild attack, or simply con-<lb/>
fer immunity without any pathogenic manifestations, a severe attack would<lb/>
result from a greater number of such stings, and the same might also oc-<lb/>
cur in consequence of a single sting from a mosquito that should have<lb/>
been fed exclusively on sweet joices during several days or weeks, after<lb/>
its contamination, before it is allowed to sting another non-immune sub-<lb/>
ject.&rdquo; (See Revista de Medicina Tropical, Havana, 1903. Vol. IV, Page 136).</p>
<p>Now, these insects, actually received from the hands of Dr. Finlay,<lb/>
were the ones employed by the American Commission to bring about the de-<lb/>
monstration of the new doctrine.</p>
<p>This presentation of his mosquitoes to the United States Army Com-<lb/>
mission was made in 1900.</p>
<p>In 1899 he had written the following statements, which are taken<lb/>
from his address &ldquo;On the Methods of Stamping out Yellow Fever, suggested<lb/>
since 1899&rdquo;, read before the Conference of State and Provincial Boards<lb/>
of Health of North America, in October, 1902.:</p>
<p>"I <unclear>expressed</unclear> my ideas on these points in a paper which I contribut-<lb/>
ed to the World's Congress Auxiliary of Chicago in 1893. &ldquo;On Etiological<lb/>
Factors Concerned in the Propagation of Yellow Fever&rdquo;; and also in an-<lb/>
other paper which I wrote for the Eighth International Congress of Hy-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02971005"/>
Hy-<lb/>
4.<lb/>
giene and Demography held at Budapest in 1894 (see Comptes Rendus of<lb/>
the latter. vol. 11, p. 702). the conclusion of which was as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The special measures which might be adopted against the propaga-<lb/>
tion of yellow fever through mosquitoes must be left to the criterion<lb/>
of those who accept my theory, but the principal indications must be:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>"1. To prevent these insects from stinging yellow fever patients.</item>
<item>"2. To destroy, as far as possible, the mosquitoes which have<lb/>
been infected, bearing in mind that in close spaces a temperature of<lb/>
50&deg; C. is sufficient for that purpose.</item>
<item>&ldquo;3. Finally, to consider any place unsafe so long as the last mos-<lb/>
quitoes which have stung yellow fever patients may be alive in it; from<lb/>
thirty-five to forty days being the term of their existence under the<lb/>
most favorable circumstances.&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
