<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t02973001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Senate Document No. 520, 61<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Congress, 2d Session, April 29, 1910</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>02973001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1910-04-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mable H.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Hamann, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert Page</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, R.M.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Brazil</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Italy</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>23 pp.</extent>
<date value="1910-04-29">April 29, 1910</date>
<idno rend="suppress">02973001</idno>
<title>Senate Document No. 520, 61<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Congress, 2d Session, April 29, 1910</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This document describes in detail the appointment and work of the Yellow Fever Commission and includes an autographed note by Kean.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1910-04-29">
<head>Senate Document No. 520, 61<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Congress, 2d Session, April 29, 1910</head>
<pb n="1" id="f02973001"/>
<opener>
<unclear>This</unclear> never passed<lb/>
J R Kean<lb/>
61ST CONGRESS,}<lb/>
2d Session.}<lb/>
SENATE.<lb/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
{DOCUMENT<lb/>
{No. 520.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Full List of Inoculated-</p>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>------------</p>
<p>Mr. OWEN presented the following</p>
<p>LETTER FROM THE SURGEON-GENERAL OF THE UNITED STATES<lb/>
ARMY RELATIVE TO THE APPOINTMENT OF THE YELLOW-FEVER<lb/>
COMMISSION; SENATE REPORT NO. 574, SIXTY-FIRST CONGRESS,<lb/>
SECOND SESSION, RELATIVE TO THE CASE OF JOHN R. KISSIN-<lb/>
GER; AND THE MESSAGE FROM THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED<lb/>
STATES OF DECEMBER 5, 1906 (S. DOC. 10, 59TH CONG., 2D SESS.),<lb/>
DEALING WITH EXPERIMENTS CONDUCTED FOR THE PURPOSE<lb/>
OF COPING WITH YELLOW FEVER, IN SUPPORT OF SENATE BILL<lb/>
8024, &ldquo;A BILL PROVIDING A MEMORIAL STATUE AND TABLET IN<lb/>
HONOR OF THE YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION, AND FOR OTHER<lb/>
PURPOSES.&rdquo;</p>
<p>------------</p>
<p>May 3, 1910.--Referred to the Committee on Public Health and National Quarantine<lb/>
and ordered to be printed.</p>
<p>------------</p>
<p>By J. R. K-</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON-GENERAL,<lb/>
Washington, <date value="1910-04-29">April 29, 1910.</date></p>
<p>MY DEAR SENATOR: It gives me great pleasure to comply with<lb/>
the request contained in your letter of April 20, to furnish you with a<lb/>
report of the occurrences which led to the appointment of the yellow-<lb/>
fever commission, of which Maj. Walter Reed was president, and the<lb/>
names of the persons connected with the experiments of the com-<lb/>
mission, together with other data which is available concerning them.</p>
<p>Surgeon-General Sternberg was for many years one of the leading<lb/>
authorities in the world on the subject of yellow fever, and had made,<lb/>
under the direction of the President of the United States, very<lb/>
laborious investigations as to its cause in Habana, Brazil, and Mexico.<lb/>
These investigations were unsuccessful because, as we now know, the<lb/>
organism of yellow fever is invisible to the microscope, but they<lb/>
served a valuable purpose in enabling Doctor Sternberg to disprove<lb/>
the claims of other investigators to have discovered the causative<lb/>
organism and to have prepared protective inoculations against the<lb/>
disease. His attention having been attracted by the claim of Sana-<lb/>
relli, of Buenos Aires, to have discovered the cause of yellow fever<lb/>
in the bacillus icteroides, he ordered Major Reed, at that time pro-<lb/>
fessor of bacteriology in the Army Medical School, to study this<lb/>
organism in connection with an organism discovered by Sternberg<lb/>
in the bodies of yellow-fever patients in Habana, and named by him<lb/>
bacillus X. This investigation was continued by a board consisting<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f02973002"/>
2<lb/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
of Maj. Walter Reed, surgeon, U. S. Army, and Acting Asst. Surgs.<lb/>
James Carroll, Aristides Agramonte, and Jesse W. Lazear, U. S. Army,<lb/>
which was appointed to meet at Camp Columbia, near Habana, Cuba,<lb/>
in May, 1900. The instructions to Major Reed, president of this<lb/>
board, included the following:</p>
<p>You will naturally give special attention to questions relating to the etiology and<lb/>
prevention of yellow fever. As you are familiar with what has already been done by<lb/>
other bacteriologists in this field of investigation, I do not consider it necessary to give<lb/>
you any suggestions or detailed instructions. But it is evident that the most important<lb/>
question which will occupy your attention is that which relates to the etiology of this<lb/>
disease.</p>
<p>You will also take advantage of such opportunities as may offer for the study of other<lb/>
infectious diseases, and especially of the malarial fevers prevailing in the island of<lb/>
Cuba. An important question in connection with the diseases of tropical and semi-<lb/>
tropical countries relates to the etiology of febrile attacks of short duration, to which<lb/>
strangers are especially subject. Should you have time, there will be ample oppor-<lb/>
tunity for the study of leprosy in the lepers' hospital in the city of Habana. Attention<lb/>
should also be given to the infectious disease of the lower animals, in case any such<lb/>
prevail, the etiology of which has not been definitely determined.</p>
<p>One member of the board, Dr. Aristides Agramonte, lived in Habana,<lb/>
and another, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, was already stationed at Columbia<lb/>
Barracks, having joined there on February 13, 1900. The remaining<lb/>
members of the board arrived in Cuba June 25, 1900. They were<lb/>
able to prove conclusively that in 18 cases of unmistakable yellow<lb/>
fever investigated from beginning to end bacillus icteroides was not<lb/>
present and that this organism could not be the cause of the disease.<lb/>
These conclusions were diametrically opposite to those of Doctors<lb/>
Wasdin and Geddings, of the Marine-Hospital Service, who likewise<lb/>
at that time were studying yellow fever in Habana, and who con-<lb/>
firmed the findings of Sanarelli. The board then proceeded to inves-<lb/>
tigate the theory advanced by Finlay, that yellow fever was con-<lb/>
veyed by mosquitoes. A full history of these experiments has been<lb/>
published in the reports of the board, and a brief account of it,<lb/>
together with a list of the persons who submitted to experimental<lb/>
inoculation was given in a memorandum prepared for the President<lb/>
by this office on August 30, 1906, and transmitted as a special mes-<lb/>
sage to Congress on December 5, 1906. It was published as Senate<lb/>
Document No. 10, Fifty-ninth Congress, second session, a copy being<lb/>
inclosed.</p>
<p>Before taking up individually the men concerned in these experi-<lb/>
ments, in order to state what is known about them at the present<lb/>
time, it may be mentioned that the Spaniards who were inoculated<lb/>
did so for the pecuniary inducement offered them. After receiving<lb/>
the reward offered them by the liberality of the military government<lb/>
of Cuba, $200 for each person successfully inoculated, they passed<lb/>
from the scene and nothing further is known concerning them.<lb/>
While their names should be preserved as a matter of historical<lb/>
interest, it is considered that they have been well rewarded for their<lb/>
share in the matter, especially as the idea of assisting in the advance-<lb/>
ment of science was not a controlling motive for their action. Also<lb/>
it should be stated that it can not be demonstrated that these exper-<lb/>
iments caused the death or subsequent ill health of any of the par-<lb/>
ticipants, with the exception of Doctor Lazear and of three individ-<lb/>
uals who died in the course of the experiments which were conducted<lb/>
by Major Gorgas and Dr. John Guiteras, at Las Animas Hospital,<lb/>
Habana, between February and December, 1901, which will be referred<lb/>
to later.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f02973003"/>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>3</p>
<p>In view of the facts which have come to the attention of this office<lb/>
since the preparation of the memorandum for the President, it is<lb/>
believed that that memorandum does not do justice to the importance<lb/>
of the part which Doctor Agramonte took in these investigations.<lb/>
Doctor Agramonte has made the following statement with regard to<lb/>
the work of the board:</p>
<p>In the investigations of the board with reference to bacillus icteroides, Doctor<lb/>
Carroll had the bacteriological work, Doctor Agramonte the autopsy and gross<lb/>
pathology, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear the microscopical pathology.</p>
<p>In June, 1900, Doctor Agramonte was sent to the city of Santa Clara to investigate<lb/>
the outbreak of yellow fever in that city, and in July he was sent to the city of Pinar<lb/>
del Rio to investigate the outbreak of yellow fever among the American troops, which<lb/>
the surgeons stationed there had failed to recognize as such. Doctor Agramonte<lb/>
promptly recognized the true character of the disease and was joined there by Major<lb/>
Reed a couple of days later. It was there that for the first time the probability of<lb/>
mosquito agency in transmitting the disease was seriously discussed by members of<lb/>
the board, and it was decided to carry out some research in this direction.</p>
<p>As Doctor Lazear had obtained considerable training in mosquito work while in<lb/>
Italy, and none of the other members of the board had any, it was agreed that he take<lb/>
up this part of the work in the beginning. Doctor Carroll continued to investigate<lb/>
the bacteria and Doctor Agramonte the pathological anatomy of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Major Reed at this time returned to Washington for the purpose of completing the<lb/>
report upon &ldquo;Typhoid Fever in the Army,&rdquo; in collaboration with Doctors Shakespeare<lb/>
and Vaughan.</p>
<p>Lazear began to breed, dissect, classify, and infect mosquitoes, in which work Carroll<lb/>
and Agramonte took little or no part. Now and then Lazear would apply them to<lb/>
whoever allowed it. Most of the mosquitoes died early in captivity. Lazear, Carroll,<lb/>
and several other persons had been bitten several times by mosquitoes which pre-<lb/>
viously had fed on yellow fever blood, without result, so that the theory of mosquito<lb/>
transmission was gradually being discredited, until Carroll fell sick, on the 30th of<lb/>
August (1900), entirely innocent of the real nature of his illness.</p>
<p>Suspecting the origin of his infection and its real gravity, Doctors Lazear and Agra-<lb/>
monte decided to test the mosquito which presumably had caused Carroll's attack by<lb/>
applying it to the first nonimmune individual who might allow it.</p>
<p>Therefore, on the afternoon of August 31, the same mosquito and three others, were<lb/>
applied to an American soldier who had not left Columbia Barracks (which was free<lb/>
from yellow fever) for fifty-seven days prior to his inoculation; nor did he go out of said<lb/>
reservation before he fell sick with yellow fever, five days afterwards, thus confirming<lb/>
in our minds the fact that he had been infected by the mosquito bites.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll being at this time still suffering from a severe attack of the disease,<lb/>
Doctors Lazear and Agramonte decided to communicate these results to Major Reed,<lb/>
who was yet in Washington.</p>
<p>Before Major Reed's arrival in Habana, Doctor Lazear became infected with yellow<lb/>
fever, his death taking place on the 25th of September.</p>
<p>During Carroll's convalescence, the board decided that the results of the investigation<lb/>
were so far sufficiently convincing to justify their presentation, in the shape of a pre-<lb/>
liminary note, before the coming meeting of the American Public Health Association,<lb/>
at Indianapolis, Ind. (October, 1900).</p>
<p>Major Reed went north for this purpose, and while Carroll took a short vacation, to<lb/>
recuperate from his recent attack, Doctor Agramonte was charged with breeding and<lb/>
infecting mosquitoes, keeping them at the division laboratory, which was under his<lb/>
care in Habana, in preparation for the work which the board intended to carry out after<lb/>
the Indianapolis meeting.</p>
<p>When Major Reed returned from the States, moral and material aid was obtained<lb/>
rom Gen. Leonard Wood, commanding the division, and we determined to carry<lb/>
out an investigation exclusively based upon the mosquito theory sustained by Finlay;<lb/>
we knew nothing of Beauperthuy then, who in 1853 had defended practically the<lb/>
same theory.</p>
<p>While the experimental station, afterwards named Camp Lazear, in honor to the<lb/>
memory of our deceased colleague, was being established, the care of the mosquitoes<lb/>
and their infection by applying them to yellow-fever cases, was in the hands of Doctor<lb/>
Agramonte, at the division laboratory; when the permanent &ldquo;mosquito building&rdquo; was<lb/>
erected at Camp Lazear (Dec. 1, 1900), these mosquitoes were turned over to Doctor<lb/>
Carroll for his care. It devolved then upon Doctor Agramonte to select the mosquitoes<lb/>
from those kept by Doctor Carroll and to apply them to nonimmunes, as well as to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f02973004"/>
4<lb/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
make all subsequent direct inoculations and to obtain the nonimmunes (Spaniards)<lb/>
for the purpose, until the end of the work in Cuba.</p>
<p>Let me add that the best friendship existed between all the members of the board,<lb/>
and from the beginning of their work it was agreed that the honor of the results was<lb/>
to be shared by all alike, as the labor was so evenly shared. Unfortunately this has<lb/>
not been the case, let us hope through no fault of the members themselves. Doctors<lb/>
Reed and Carroll had been connected in laboratory work for several years and Doctor<lb/>
Agramonte had also worked at the Army Medical Museum Laboratory; Doctors Lazear<lb/>
and Agramonte were classmates, having graduated from the College of Physicians and<lb/>
Surgeons, New York, in June, 1892.</p>
<p>I certify to the absolute truth of the above statement.</p>
<p>In testimony whereof I affix my signature in the city of Habana, August 31, 1908.</p>
<p>ARISTIDES AGRAMONTE, M. D.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Maj. Walter Reed, surgeon, U. S. Army, died in Washington,<lb/>
D. C., from appendicitis November 23, 1902, aged 51. His widow,<lb/>
Emilie Lawrence Reed, is receiving a pension of $125 a month.</item>
<item>2. Maj. James Carroll was promoted from first lieutenant to major<lb/>
by special act of Congress March 9, 1907. He died in Washington,<lb/>
D. C., of myocarditis, September 16, 1907. His widow, Jennie H.<lb/>
Carroll, since his death has received an annuity of $125 a month,<lb/>
appropriated from year to year in the army appropriation bill.</item>
<item>3. Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, contract surgeon, U. S. Army, died at<lb/>
Camp Columbia, Cuba, of yellow fever September 25, 1900. His<lb/>
widow, Mabel M. Lazear, since his death has received an annuity of<lb/>
$125 a month, appropriated from year to year in the army appropria-<lb/>
tion bill.</item>
<item>4. Dr. Aristides Agramonte is the only living member of the board.<lb/>
He is professor of bacteriology and experimental pathology in the<lb/>
University of Habana and has never received, either directly or indi-<lb/>
rectly, any material reward for his share in the work of the board.</item>
<item>5. The name of the American soldier, XY, who was the subject of<lb/>
the second experiment, was concealed at the time, because the experi-<lb/>
ment was made without military authorization. It has been recently<lb/>
ascertained to be William H. Dean, private, Troop B, Seventh Cav-<lb/>
alry. He has never received any reward. He was discharged August<lb/>
17, 1902, by reason of expiration of term of service, and there is no<lb/>
further record of him at the War Department. His residence at<lb/>
enlistment was given as Grand Rapids, Mich. His case has special<lb/>
importance as having been the first experimental case which was com-<lb/>
plete in the matter of control, for Doctor Carroll's, which came four<lb/>
days earlier, was defective, by reason of his going into the infected<lb/>
zone during the period of incubation.</item>
<item>6. John R. Kissinger, private, Hospital Corps (see p. 6, President's<lb/>
message). Kissinger volunteered for service at the beginning of the<lb/>
Spanish war in Company D, One hundred and fifty-seventh Indiana<lb/>
Volunteers, and after his discharge enlisted in the Hospital Corps.<lb/>
After the first secret experiments of the board, which included the<lb/>
cases of Doctor Carroll and Private Dean, became known and the<lb/>
experimental camp was established and named Camp Lazear, Kis-<lb/>
singer and Moran were the first to volunteer as subjects for experi-<lb/>
ment. Moran was first bitten, but Kissinger was the first to be<lb/>
attacked, on December 8, 1900. He recovered and was afterwards<lb/>
promoted to be acting hospital steward, and discharged November<lb/>
14, 1901, at Columbia Barracks, Cuba. It is understood that his<lb/>
health afterwards failed so that he became entirely dependent upon<lb/>
the labor of his wife for support. He was pensioned at the rate of<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f02973005"/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
5<lb/>
$12 per month, by the act of March 2, 1907. This amount is consid-<lb/>
ered quite inadequate either for his support or as a recognition of his<lb/>
services. A bill granting an increase to $125 per month was favor-<lb/>
ably reported and incorporated in Senate bill 6272 and passed the<lb/>
Senate February 15, 1910, but was objected to by the Committee on<lb/>
Pensions of the House of Representatives. The report of the Senate<lb/>
committee (No. 574) is inclosed.</item>
<item>7. John J. Moran (see p. 6, President's message). Mr. Moran has<lb/>
never received any material reward for his most creditable services.<lb/>
After leaving Cuba he completed his education by a course of study<lb/>
at the University of Virginia, and is at present living at Panama, in<lb/>
the employ of the Isthmian Canal Commission. He is at present an<lb/>
applicant for appointment in the consular service for which, by reason<lb/>
of his excellent knowledge of Spanish and other qualifications, he is well<lb/>
fitted.</item>
<item>8. Levi E. Folk, private, Hospital Corps, volunteered to be bitten<lb/>
by infected mosquitoes and was taken with yellow fever January 23,<lb/>
1901. He is still in the military service, and is a sergeant, Hospital<lb/>
Corps, stationed at the recruit depot, Columbus Barracks, Ohio.<lb/>
He received a donation of $300 from the appropriation made by Gen.<lb/>
Leonard Wood for these experiments.</item>
<item>9. Clyde L. West, private, Hospital Corps, volunteered to be bitten<lb/>
by infected mosquitoes at Camp Lazear, and was taken sick with yellow<lb/>
fever February 3, 1901. He was discharged from the service July<lb/>
10, 1902, at Fort Myer, Va., and his subsequent address is unknown.<lb/>
He received a donation of $200 from the appropriation made by Gen.<lb/>
Leonard Wood for these experiments.</item>
<item>10. James L. Hanberry, private, Hospital Corps, volunteered to<lb/>
be bitten by infected mosquitoes, and in consequence, was taken sick<lb/>
with yellow fever at Camp Lazear February 9, 1901. He deserted<lb/>
the service April 4, 1902, at the general hospital, Washington Bar-<lb/>
racks, D. C. His subsequent address is unknown. He received a<lb/>
donation of $300 from the appropriation made by General Wood for<lb/>
these experiments.</item>
<item>11. Charles G. Sontag, private, Hospital Corps, volunteered to be<lb/>
bitten by infected mosquitoes, and was in consequence taken sick<lb/>
with yellow fever at Camp Lazear February 10, 1901. He was dis-<lb/>
charged from the service December 12, 1901, at Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
Cuba, and his subsequent address is unknown. He received a dona-<lb/>
tion of $200 from the appropriation made by Gen. Leonard Wood for<lb/>
these experiments.</item>
<item>12. Warren Gadsden Jernegan, private, Hospital Corps, was<lb/>
infected with yellow fever by the injection of blood, and taken sick<lb/>
January 8, 1901. He was discharged November 16, 1901, at Colum-<lb/>
bia Barracks, Cuba. Address given, care of M. A. Fowler, McMeekin,<lb/>
Fla. He received a donation of $300 from appropriation made by<lb/>
General Wood for these experiments.</item>
<item>13. William Olsen, private, Hospital Corps, was infected with<lb/>
yellow fever by injection of blood, at Camp Lazear, and taken sick<lb/>
January 11, 1901. He was discharged November 15, 1901, at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks, Cuba. Address given, care of C. Olsen, Plum<lb/>
City, Wis. He received a donation of $200 from the appropriation<lb/>
made by General Wood for these experiments.</item>
<pb n="6" id="f02973006"/>
<item>6</item>
<item>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</item>
<item>14. Wallace W. Forbes, private, Hospital Corps, volunteered to be<lb/>
infected with yellow fever by the injection of blood, at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
and became sick January 24, 1901. He was discharged March 1,<lb/>
1905, at Fort Hancock, N. J. Address given, care of J. W. Forbes,<lb/>
Minneapolis, Minn. This soldier received a donation of $200 from<lb/>
the appropriation made by General Wood.</item>
<item>15. John H. Andrus, private, Hospital Corps, volunteered and was<lb/>
infected with yellow fever by injection of blood, at Camp Lazear, and<lb/>
became sick January 28, 1901. He was discharged April 24, 1902,<lb/>
at Camp Geo. H. Thomas, Chickamauga, Tenn. His subsequent<lb/>
address is not known. He received a donation of $200 from the<lb/>
appropriation made by General Wood.</item>
<item>16. John R. Bullard, native of Massachusetts, a graduate of<lb/>
Harvard University, where he was a distinguished athelete, and<lb/>
engaged in farming in Cuba, volunteered and was infected with<lb/>
yellow fever by the injection of blood. He became sick October 23,<lb/>
1901.</item>
<item>17. Paul Hamann, private, Twenty-third Company, Coast Artillery,<lb/>
volunteered and was infected with yellow fever by injection of filtered<lb/>
blood serum and became sick October 19, 1901. He was discharged<lb/>
July 19, 1902, by reason of expiration of term of service. His address<lb/>
given at time of enlistment was care of August Hamann, Moline, Ill.<lb/>
Present address not known. This soldier received a donation from<lb/>
the appropriation made by General Wood for these experiments.</item>
<item>18. Albert W. Covington, private, Twenty-third Company, Coast<lb/>
Artillery, volunteered and was infected with yellow fever by injection<lb/>
with filtered blood serum and became sick October 19, 1901. He is<lb/>
still in the service, and is serving as sergeant, Twenty-third Company,<lb/>
Coast Artillery Corps, at Fort McKinley, Portland, Me. He received<lb/>
a donation from the appropriation made by General Wood for these<lb/>
experiments.</item>
<item><p>19. Dr. Robert P. Cook (see President's message, p. 7). Doctor<lb/>
Cook entered the medical service June 9, 1900, as contract surgeon,<lb/>
from the State of Virginia. He left the service at his own request,<lb/>
December 22, 1904. His present address is Winchester, Va.</p>
<p>The demonstration made by Doctor Cook and the men with him<lb/>
that yellow fever could not be transmitted by infected clothing and<lb/>
other inanimate objects was of the utmost importance to commerce<lb/>
and has immensely simplified the preventive measures to be taken<lb/>
against this disease. He was shut up in a house with infected bedding<lb/>
for twenty days, together with the following privates of the Hospital<lb/>
Corps, who received a donation of $100 each from the appropriation<lb/>
given by General Wood for these experiments:</p></item>
<item>20. Edward Weatherwalk. Discharged the service December 12,<lb/>
1901, at Columbia Barracks, Cuba. Subsequent address not<lb/>
known. He received a donation of $200.</item>
<item>21. James Hildebrand. Still in service as private, first class,<lb/>
Hospital Corps; stationed at the recruit depot, Columbus Barracks,<lb/>
Ohio. He received a donation of $100.</item>
<item>22. Thomas M. England. Still in service as sergeant, first class,<lb/>
Hospital Corps; stationed at Fort Ward, Wash. He received a<lb/>
donation of $100.</item>
</list></p>
<p>In addition to these, Privates Folk, Jernegan, and Hanberry under-<lb/>
went the exposure to infected bedding prior to being bitten by the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f02973007"/>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>7</p>
<p>Additional experiments by Maj. W. C. Gorgas and Dr. John<lb/>
Guiteras, at Las Animas Hospital, Cuba (see Vol. 111, p. 386, civil<lb/>
report of General Wood, 1901):<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Vergara; Spaniard. Infected by mosquitoes February 23,<lb/>
1901; recovered.</item>
<item>(2) Carro; Spaniard. Inoculated by infected mosquitoes August 8,<lb/>
1901; died.</item>
<item>(3) Represas; Spaniard. Infected by mosquitoes August 8, 1901;<lb/>
recovered.</item>
<item>(4) Campa; Spaniard. Infected by mosquitoes August 9, 1901;<lb/>
died.</item>
<item>(5) Taylor, John R.; <del>Englishman</del><add>American</add>. Infected by mosquitoes Au-<lb/>
gust 13, 1901; recovered.</item>
<item>(6) Miss Clara Louise Maass, of East Orange, N. J., aged 25.<lb/>
Trained nurse in Las Animas Hospital. She served as trained nurse<lb/>
in Medical Department of the Army during the Spanish war. She<lb/>
volunteered and was bitten by infected mosquitoes August 14, and<lb/>
died of yellow fever August 18, 1901.</item>
<item>(7) Varela; Spaniard. Infected by mosquitoes August 14, 1901;<lb/>
recovered.</item>
<item>(8) Alonso; Spaniard. Infected by mosquitoes August 22, 1901;<lb/>
recovered.</item>
<item>(9) Castillo; Spaniard. Infected by mosquitoes September 16,<lb/>
1901, by Doctor Carroll; recovered.</item>
<item>(10) Semil; Spaniard. Infected by mosquitoes November 17, 1901;<lb/>
recovered.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The amount of the donations received by these volunteers is not<lb/>
known.</p>
<p>There were 22 cases of experimental yellow fever produced by Reed,<lb/>
Carroll, and Lazear, and 10 in the experiments carried on in Habana<lb/>
by Gorgas and Guiteras. There were also 7 persons who underwent<lb/>
the very trying experiment of sleeping in infected bedding.</p>
<p>It has been impracticable to make a complete list of the persons<lb/>
who submitted to the bites of mosquitoes but who failed to become<lb/>
infected, although it must be recognized that in many cases these<lb/>
exhibited as high a degree of courage as those who suffered an attack<lb/>
of yellow fever.</p>
<p>It is hoped that the Senator will be able to obtain the consent of<lb/>
Congress to the erection of a monument which will be worthy of<lb/>
Major Reed, who conceived and carried out in so admirable a manner<lb/>
these epoch-making experiments, and to the assistants who shared in<lb/>
his labors and to the persons who offered their bodies for these dan-<lb/>
gerous experiments.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
GEO. H. TORNEY,<lb/>
Surgeon-General, U. S. Army.<lb/>
Hon. ROBERT L. OWEN,<lb/>
United States Senator, Washington, D. C.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f02973008"/>
<p>8</p>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>[Senate Report No. 574, Sixty-first Congress, second session.]</p>
<p>The Committtee on Pensions, to whom was referred the bill (S. 7252)<lb/>
granting an annuity to John R. Kissinger, have examined the same,<lb/>
and report:</p>
<p>A bill granting an increase of $125 per month to John R. Kissinger,<lb/>
the applicant herein, was favorably reported by your committee and<lb/>
incorporated in Senate bill 6272 at this session and passed the Senate<lb/>
on February 15, 1910.</p>
<p>The Senate report No. 210, which contains a very full statement of<lb/>
the services of this soldier, and the grounds upon which his right to<lb/>
increase of pension is recognized, is at follows:</p>
<p>S. 4479. John Kissinger, the claimant, was one of the bravest of soldiers who<lb/>
served in the Spanish-American war. For exhibition of moral courage his submis-<lb/>
sion to inoculation of yellow fever seems unsurpassed. He is now a helpless paralytic,<lb/>
unable to walk, and he is totally disabled for any kind of employment, his ailment<lb/>
being myelitis, or disease of spine, and is the result of experiments made upon him<lb/>
when he volunteered to become a subject for experimental purposes in the yellow-<lb/>
fever hospital in Cuba. At the time he made the sacrifice he was a private in the<lb/>
Hospital Corps of the Army, in which he enlisted November 15, 1898. When he was<lb/>
finally discharged from the hospital, he was appointed an acting hospital steward and<lb/>
served as such until the date of his discharge, November 14, 1901. Previous to his<lb/>
enlistment he served in Company D, One hundred and fifty-seventh Indiana Volun-<lb/>
teer Infantry, from April 28, 1898, to November 1, 1898, having enlisted immediately<lb/>
at the breaking out of the war with Spain, and in response to President McKinley's<lb/>
call for troops.</p>
<p>The commission that investigated the mosquito theory of transmission of yellow<lb/>
fever in the fall of 1900 was composed of Drs. Walter Reed, James Carroll, and Jesse<lb/>
W. Lazear. From a book entitled &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever,&rdquo; by Howard<lb/>
A. Kelly, professor of surgery of the Johns Hopkins University, published in New<lb/>
York by McClure, Phillips &amp; Co., on page 139, is the following paragraph in regard<lb/>
to this soldier:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The subject of the first experiment was a young private from Ohio, named John<lb/>
R. Kissinger, who volunteered for the service, to use his own words, &lsquo;solely in the<lb/>
interest of humanity and the cause of science.&rsquo; When it became known among the<lb/>
troops that subjects were needed for experimental purposes, Kissinger, in company<lb/>
with another young private named John J. Moran, also from Ohio, volunteered their<lb/>
services. Doctor Reed talked the matter over with them, explaining fully the danger<lb/>
and suffering involved in the experiment should it be successful, and then, seeing they<lb/>
were determined, he stated that a definite money compensation would be made them.<lb/>
Both young men declined to accept it, making it, indeed, their sole stipulation that<lb/>
they should receive no pecuniary reward, whereupon Major Reed touched his cap,<lb/>
saying respectfully, &lsquo;Gentlemen, I salute you.&rsquo; Reed's own words in his published<lb/>
account of the experiment on Kissinger are: &lsquo;In my opinion this exhibition of moral<lb/>
courage has never been surpassed in the annals of the Army of the United States.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear died of yellow fever in Cuba at that time. Doctor Carroll died later<lb/>
of disease resulting from yellow fever contracted during his experiments with that<lb/>
trouble. Dr. Walter Reed is also dead, and the widows of these three men have all<lb/>
been remembered by the Government in an annuity of $125 per month. On account<lb/>
of the death of these doctors, soldier is unable, of course, to furnish any further evi-<lb/>
dence from them, but his volunteer submission to inoculation from infected mosqui-<lb/>
toes is a matter of record in the archives of the War Department.</p>
<p>He is now receiving a pension of but $12 per month, and he can obtain no further<lb/>
relief because he is unable to furnish direct testimony tracing his present grievous<lb/>
condition back to yellow fever in the army, although there is but little doubt that<lb/>
the relation of the cause and effect exists. Since his discharge he has never been in<lb/>
good health, which he at first attributed to slow recovery from that disease, thinking<lb/>
that with the passing of time his constitution would enable him to throw it off. He<lb/>
continued to fail, however, and is now a helpless paralytic. In the meantime he<lb/>
had married, and is now supported by his small pension and laundry work done by<lb/>
his wife and contributions to his support by a few people who appreciated his serv-<lb/>
ices to humanity.</p>
<p>A bill to grant him a pension of $30 per month passed the House during the session<lb/>
of the Fifty-ninth Congress, but by mistake the rate was cut to $12 per month, at<lb/>
which amount it was finally approved. In his present helpless condition it is believed<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f02973009"/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
9<lb/>
that he is entitled to a highly substantial measure of relief, his disability seemingly<lb/>
being due to causes of service origin.</p>
<p>In view of the fact that a pension or annuity of $125 per month was granted to the<lb/>
widows of Doctors Lazear and Carroll, who conducted these experiments with yel-<lb/>
low-fever infected mosquitoes, and who died as a result of being infected by mosqui-<lb/>
toes, your committee are of the opinion that as great consideration should be given<lb/>
to the man who braved the danger and who, while he escaped with his life, is so<lb/>
helplessly crippled that he is unable to do anything to care for himself, as to the<lb/>
widows of Doctors Lazear and Carroll. Your committee therefore recommend in<lb/>
this case a pension or annuity of $125 per month.</p>
<p>The bill went to the House and was referred to the Committee on<lb/>
Pensions. There the paragraph increasing the pension to the appli-<lb/>
cant herein was objected to as carrying a rate in excess of that allowed<lb/>
to any other private soldier and, regarded simply as a pension and<lb/>
without distinguishing language, establishing a vexing precedent.</p>
<p>The facts in this case are exceptional and extraordinary. To meet<lb/>
the exceptional case and obviate the objections the pending bill recites<lb/>
the peculiar circumstances that distinguish the case and proposes an<lb/>
annuity of $125 per month, payable by the Secretary of War in the<lb/>
same manner as the same allowances are now paid to the widows of<lb/>
Doctors Carroll and Lazear. In view of the unprecedented facts in<lb/>
the case and the extraordinary services rendered by the soldier, your<lb/>
committee believe he should receive the same recognition accorded the<lb/>
widows heretofore mentioned. The bill is therefore reported back<lb/>
favorably with a recommendation that it pass.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>[Senate Document No. 10, Fifty-ninth Congress, second session.]<lb/>
To the Senate and House of Representatives:</p>
<p>The inclosed papers are transmitted to the Congress in the earnest<lb/>
hope that it will take suitable action in the matter. Major Reed's<lb/>
part in the experiments which resulted in teaching us how to cope<lb/>
with yellow fever was such as to render mankind his debtor, and this<lb/>
nation should in some proper fashion bear witness to this fact.</p>
<p>THEODORE ROOSEVELT<lb/>
THE WHITE HOUSE, December 5, 1906.</p>
<p>[Inclosure 1.]<lb/>
[Memorandum for the President, through The Military Secretary of the Army.]</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON-GENERAL,<lb/>
Washington, August 30, 1906.</p>
<p>The persons taking an important part in the investigations in<lb/>
Cuba, which resulted in the demonstration of the fact that yellow<lb/>
fever is transmitted by a species of mosquito, were three members of<lb/>
the board appointed to investigate epidemic diseases in Cuba--<lb/>
Walter Reed, James Carroll, and Jesse W. Lazear--and the indi-<lb/>
viduals who submitted themselves for experimentation by receiving<lb/>
the bites of infected mosquitoes, by receiving injections of blood from<lb/>
yellow-fever patients, and by sleeping in bedding which had been<lb/>
used by yellow-fever patients.</p>
<p>When the yellow-fever commission, composed of Walter Reed,<lb/>
James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear, and A. Agramonte, assembled in<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f02973010"/>
10<lb/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
Habana they had no thought of investigating the connection of the<lb/>
mosquito with the spread of yellow fever. This idea came to Doctor<lb/>
Reed after the board had demonstrated that the claim of Sanarelli,<lb/>
concurred in by Wasdin and Geddins, that the Baccillus icteroides<lb/>
was the cause of yellow fever was without foundation. Doctor Reed<lb/>
then determined to investigate the theory of Dr. Carlos Finlay,<lb/>
that the mosquito was instrumental in conveying yellow fever, which<lb/>
theory Finlay had failed to demonstrate, and which was not then<lb/>
accepted by scientific men. This determination was reached for the<lb/>
reasons which are well stated in Doctor Kelly's biography, and was<lb/>
original with Reed, not being suggested to him by anyone. The<lb/>
final determination to investigate the mosquito theory was arrived at<lb/>
during an informal meeting of the board (Doctor Agramonte being<lb/>
absent) at Columbia Barracks on the evening before Doctor Reed's<lb/>
departure for the United States, early in August, 1901. It was<lb/>
agreed by these members of the board that in making the experi-<lb/>
ments on human beings, by which alone the demonstration could be<lb/>
made, that they should submit themselves as subjects for experimen-<lb/>
tation. To Doctor Lazear, who was familiar with mosquito work,<lb/>
was assigned the duty of breeding and infecting the mosquitoes,<lb/>
while Doctor Carroll was to continue the bacteriological work on<lb/>
which the board had been engaged.</p>
<p>On August 2, 1900, before the mosquitoes were ready for the<lb/>
experiment, Doctor Reed was called back to Washington to prepare<lb/>
for publication the abstract of the report of the board appointed in<lb/>
1898 to investigate the spread of typhoid fever in the volunteer camps<lb/>
in the United States, of which board he was president. This vast<lb/>
work, of which the full report was published by special authority of<lb/>
Congress about a year after Reed's death, by the only surviving mem-<lb/>
ber of the board, Prof. Victor C. Vaughan, of the University of<lb/>
Michigan, was one of the most valuable contributions to science<lb/>
which has been made by the Surgeon-General's Office. The work of<lb/>
preparation of the abstract report had been brought to a standstill<lb/>
by the sudden death of the third member of the board, Dr. Edward<lb/>
O. Shakespeare, of Philadelphia, and Doctor Reed's presence at this<lb/>
time was essential for its completion.</p>
<p>During Doctor Reed's absence the inoculations by means of the<lb/>
mosquito were begun. On August 11, Doctor Lazear made the first<lb/>
experiment, but nine distinct inoculations on persons including him-<lb/>
self and Acting Asst. Surg. A. S. Pinto were unsuccessful. We<lb/>
know now that these failures were due to two facts--first, that<lb/>
patients after the third day of the disease can not convey the infec-<lb/>
tion to the mosquito, and second, that after having bitten a yellow-<lb/>
fever case the mosquito can not transmit the disease until after an<lb/>
interval of at least twelve days. On August 27 one mosquito was<lb/>
applied to Doctor Carroll, one which happened to fulfil both of these<lb/>
conditions. The result was a very severe attack of yellow fever in<lb/>
which for a time his life hung in the balance. This was thus the<lb/>
first experimental case. The fever developed on the 31st of August,<lb/>
on which day Doctor Lazear applied the same mosquito which bit<lb/>
Doctor Carroll with three others to another person. This man came<lb/>
down with a mild but well-marked case.</p>
<p>On September 13 Doctor Lazear, while on a visit to Las Animas<lb/>
Hospital (for the purpose of collecting blood from yellow-fever<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f02973011"/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
11<lb/>
patients for study) was bitten by a mosquito of undetermined species,<lb/>
which he deliberately allowed to remain on the back of his hand until<lb/>
it had satisfied its hunger. Five days thereafter he came down,<lb/>
without other exposure, with yellow fever, which progressed steadily<lb/>
to a fatal termination. These three cases established in Reed's mind<lb/>
the proof of the mosquito theory and made it, in the opinion of his<lb/>
friends, an unnecessary and foolish risk for him, at his age, to submit<lb/>
himself to inoculation. These cases, with his deductions therefrom,<lb/>
were reported by the board in a paper called &ldquo;The Etiology of<lb/>
Yellow Fever--A Preliminary Note,&rdquo; read before the American<lb/>
Public Health Association at Buffalo, N. Y., October 22-26, 1900.<lb/>
He then immediately returned to Cuba to undertake a second and<lb/>
more elaborate series of experiments which were made possible by<lb/>
the promise made to him by General Wood on October 12, when told<lb/>
by Reed of the experiments already made, to assist him with what-<lb/>
ever money was necessary. This, the second series of experiments,<lb/>
began November 20 at an experimental camp near Quemados, called<lb/>
Camp Lazear, and embraced 14 cases, of which the last was taken<lb/>
sick February 10, 1901. Of these, 10 were mosquito infections and<lb/>
4 were infected by injection of the blood of yellow-fever patients.<lb/>
All of these cases recovered.</p>
<p>A third series of six cases was produced by Dr. James Carroll<lb/>
the next fall to settle certain undetermined facts as regards the<lb/>
etiology of the disease. The first of these cases came down with<lb/>
the fever September 19, 1901, and the last on October 23, 1901. Of<lb/>
these cases two were caused by mosquitoes and four by blood injec-<lb/>
tions. None of them resulted fatally. The highly dangerous char-<lb/>
acter of these experiments and the good fortune of the board in its<lb/>
second and third series of cases is shown by the fact that Doctor<lb/>
Guiteras, of Habana, in a series of seven cases inoculated in Habana<lb/>
lost three, bringing his experiments abruptly to an end.</p>
<p>No enumeration of unsuccessful cases--namely, those which failed<lb/>
to cause the disease--has been made, although it is obvious that the<lb/>
persons undergoing such experiments exhibited as much courage as<lb/>
those in which the disease was transmitted. This is especially true<lb/>
of the cases occurring after the severe case of Doctor Carroll and the<lb/>
fatal case of Doctor Lazear. Certain ones of these unsuccessful<lb/>
cases deserve special mention, being those made with infected bed-<lb/>
ding at Camp Lazear. In a specially constructed house at that camp,<lb/>
which was intentionally ill ventilated and kept continually at a<lb/>
summer temperature, was placed a large quantity of bedding taken<lb/>
from the beds of patients sick with yellow fever in Habana and<lb/>
soiled with their discharges. In this house Acting Asst. Surg. R. P.<lb/>
Cook and two privates of the Hospital Corps slept continuously<lb/>
from November 30 to December 19. Each morning they packed the<lb/>
various soiled articles of bedding in boxes and unpacked them at<lb/>
night when they were used to sleep on.</p>
<p>See<lb/>
p 21</p>
<p>From December 21, 1900, to January 10, 1901, the building was<lb/>
again occupied by two nonimmune Americans under the same cir-<lb/>
cumstances, except that an additional stock of very much fouled<lb/>
bedding and clothing had been added to the collection, and these<lb/>
men slept every night in the very garments worn by yellow-fever<lb/>
patients throughout their entire attacks, besides making use of their<lb/>
much soiled pillow slips, sheets, and blankets. A third couple of<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f02973012"/>
12<lb/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
hospital corps men succeeded these for an equal length of time.<lb/>
None of these seven individuals contracted yellow fever, but the<lb/>
courage and fortitude shown by them certainly equal that of those<lb/>
who submitted to the bites of the mosquitoes, it being borne in mind<lb/>
that belief in the transmission of yellow fever by infected bedding<lb/>
and clothing was at that time practically universal, whereas the<lb/>
mosquito theory had still very few converts.</p>
<p>After this brief history of this great discovery a statement of the<lb/>
part borne by each of the more important participators in it is<lb/>
necessary to a determination of the reward which would be appro-<lb/>
priate to each.</p>
<p>Maj. Walter Reed, surgeon, U. S. Army, president of the commis-<lb/>
sion to investigate and study the epidemic diseases in Cuba, died in<lb/>
Washington from appendicitis, November 23, 1902, at the age of 51.<lb/>
At the time of his death the Secretary of War had said in his report,<lb/>
which was then in press, but not yet given out:</p>
<p>The brilliant character of this scientific achievement, its inestimable value to<lb/>
mankind, the saving of thousands of lives, and the deliverance of the Atlantic sea-<lb/>
coast from constant apprehension, demand special recognition from the Government<lb/>
of the United States.</p>
<p>Doctor Reed is the ranking major in the Medical Department, and within a few<lb/>
months will, by operation of law, become lieutenant-colonel. I ask that the Presi-<lb/>
dent be authorized to appoint him Assistant Surgeon-General with the rank of colonel.</p>
<p>Gen. Leonard Wood said of him, in an address delivered at a<lb/>
memorial meeting of scientific men in Washington, D. C., shortly<lb/>
after his death:</p>
<p>I know of no other man on this side of the world who has done so much for humanity<lb/>
as Doctor Reed. His discovery results in the saving of more lives annually than<lb/>
were lost in the Cuban war, and saves the commercial interests of the world a greater<lb/>
financial loss each year than the cost of the Cuban war. He came to Cuba at a time<lb/>
when one-third of the officers of my staff died of yellow fever, and we were discour-<lb/>
aged at the failure of our efforts to control the disease.</p>
<p>In the months when the disease was ordinarily worst the disease was checked and<lb/>
driven from Habana. That was the first time in nearly two hundred years that the<lb/>
city had been rid of it. The value of his discovery can not be appreciated by per-<lb/>
sons who are not familiar with the conditions of tropical countries. Hereafter it<lb/>
will never be possible for yellow fever to gain such headway that quarantine will<lb/>
exist from the mouth of the Potomac to the mouth of the Rio Grande. Future gen-<lb/>
erations will appreciate fully the value of Doctor Reed's services. His was the origi-<lb/>
nating, directing, and controlling mind in this work, and the others were assistants<lb/>
only.</p>
<p>In a letter from Professor Welch to the Secretary of War he said:</p>
<p>Doctor Reed's researches in yellow fever are by far the most important contribu-<lb/>
tions to science which have ever come from any army surgeon. In my judgment<lb/>
they are the most valuable contributions to medicine and public hygiene which<lb/>
have ever been made in this country with the exception of the discovery of an&aelig;sthesia.<lb/>
They have led and will lead to the saving of thousands of lives. I am in a position<lb/>
to know that the credit for the original ideas embodied in this work belongs wholly<lb/>
to Major Reed.</p>
<p>Professor Welch was Doctor Reed's teacher in bacteriology and<lb/>
was his intimate and confidential friend, with whom he consulted<lb/>
about the details of the work in Cuba.</p>
<p>A bill prepared in this office for a pension for his widow, equal in<lb/>
amount to his monthly pay, was passed, but the amount was so cut<lb/>
down that while it keeps the wolf from the door it does not pro-<lb/>
vide an adequate and comfortable income. It is not probable, how-<lb/>
ever, that Congress would increase this pension, and an effort has<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f02973013"/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
13<lb/>
been made to supplement it by the raising of a fund of $25,000 by the<lb/>
Walter Reed Memorial Association, incorporated for this purpose<lb/>
in the District of Columbia. The interest on this fund will be given<lb/>
Mrs. Reed during her lifetime, and the principal, after her death, will<lb/>
be devoted to some form of memorial. This fund lacks at present<lb/>
about $6,000 of completion. The existence of this association, should<lb/>
its hopes be attained, does not, however, absolve the nation from the<lb/>
obligation of a fitting recognition for this great work, and it is the<lb/>
opinion of the undersigned, which, it is believed, is shared by the<lb/>
vast majority of physicians in the United States, that Congress<lb/>
should erect a statue to Walter Reed in Washington. The assistance<lb/>
of the President in inducing Congress to do so is requested.</p>
<p>The second member of the commission was Dr. James Carroll, at<lb/>
that time acting assistant surgeon, United States Army.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll is now 52 years old. He entered the military serv-<lb/>
ice June 9, 1874, and served as private, corporal, sergeant, and hos-<lb/>
pital steward from that date to May 21, 1898, when he was appointed<lb/>
acting assistant surgeon. He was appointed first lieutenant and<lb/>
assistant surgeon in the Medical Corps October 27, 1902, which rank<lb/>
he still holds.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll was Doctor Reed's truest assistant and coadjutor<lb/>
from the inception of the work which resulted in the discovery of the<lb/>
method of propagation of yellow fever. As stated above, the third<lb/>
series of experiments were performed by Doctor Carroll alone, Doc-<lb/>
tor Reed having been refused permission to return to Cuba to com-<lb/>
plete his work.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll was the first experimental case of yellow fever,<lb/>
and he suffered a very severe attack, to which he attributes a heart<lb/>
trouble from which he now suffers. At the time of undergoing this<lb/>
experiment he was 46 years old, an age at which the risk from this<lb/>
disease is very great, as its mortality rapidly increases with age of<lb/>
patient. He had at that time a wife and five children who had no<lb/>
other means of support except his pay as an acting assistant surgeon.</p>
<p>It is recommended that Congress be asked to pass a special act<lb/>
promoting Doctor Carroll, on account of his services in connection<lb/>
with this discovery and the courage shown by him in subjecting him-<lb/>
self to experiment, to the rank of lieutenant-colonel, the number of<lb/>
medical officers in that grade being increased by one for that purpose;<lb/>
also his name and effigy should appear on the monument to Walter<lb/>
Reed.</p>
<p>Dr. Jesse W. Lazear was the third member of the commission.</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear was a native of Baltimore and a graduate of Johns<lb/>
Hopkins University, afterwards getting his professional degree at<lb/>
Columbia University and Bellevue. At the time he incurred his<lb/>
death in the course of these experiments, as above mentioned, he was<lb/>
34 years old. He left a wife and two young children, the younger,<lb/>
a little son born a few months before his death, whom he never saw.<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear received from Congress a pension of $17 a month with<lb/>
$2 additional for each of two minor children until they reach the age<lb/>
of 16. Also a battery in Baltimore Harbor was, by direction of the<lb/>
Secretary of War, named in his honor. It is believed that this recog-<lb/>
nition on the part of the nation for his services is utterly inadequate.<lb/>
His widow's pension should be increased to $100 a month, and steps<lb/>
should be taken to perpetuate his name in connection with the<lb/>
Walter Reed monument above suggested.</p>
<pb n="14" id="f02973014"/>
<p>14</p>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>Dr. A. Agramonte was the fourth member of the yellow-fever<lb/>
commission. He was a Cuban by birth, an immune to yellow fever,<lb/>
and having been assigned other work, took no part in the first<lb/>
series of experiments with regard to the conveyance of the disease<lb/>
by the mosquito, of which, in fact, he was not at the time cognizant.<lb/>
Being an immune, he ran no risk in connection with this work, and<lb/>
it is believed that his contributions to it have been sufficiently recog-<lb/>
nized in the association of his name with the other members of the<lb/>
commission who brought about this great discovery.</p>
<p>Twenty-three of the men who submitted themselves for experiment<lb/>
by the board contracted yellow fever, beginning with Dr. James Car-<lb/>
roll, who was taken sick August 31, 1900, and ending with John R.<lb/>
Bullard, who was taken sick October 23, 1901.</p>
<p>Conspicuous among them was John J. Moran, a civilian clerk<lb/>
employed at the headquarters of General Fitzhugh Lee, at Quema-<lb/>
dos, who was one of the earliest volunteers for the second set of<lb/>
experiments, and whose action was dictated by the purest motives<lb/>
of altruism and self-devotion. Mr. Moran disclaimed, before sub-<lb/>
mitting to the experiments, any desire for reward, and has never<lb/>
accepted any since, although he was offered the $200, which the<lb/>
liberality of the military governor enabled the commission to give<lb/>
to each experimental patient, the members of the board excepted.<lb/>
Such was his modesty that he has made no effort, so far as known to<lb/>
this office, to make known his connection with these experiments<lb/>
and reap the credit which is so justly due him. Mr. Moran was a<lb/>
native of Ohio. His present address is not known to this office.<lb/>
The first inoculations in the case of Mr. Moran were for some reason<lb/>
unsuccessful, on November 26 and 29. He did not suffer an attack<lb/>
until after the third inoculation on December 21.</p>
<p>The same remarks apply to the first experimental case of the<lb/>
second set, Private John R. Kissinger, Hospital Corps, who volun-<lb/>
teered at the same time with Moran and equally disclaimed any<lb/>
desire for reward.</p>
<p>Private Kissinger did not leave Cuba immediately after the ex-<lb/>
periments, as did Mr. Moran, and therefore the military authorities<lb/>
were able to reward him in some measure along with other enlisted<lb/>
men who volunteered for these experiments. He was promoted<lb/>
acting hospital steward, presented with a gold watch by the chief<lb/>
surgeon of the department in the presence of all the medical officers<lb/>
and hospital corps men on duty at Columbia Barracks, and also<lb/>
received a present of $115 in cash. He took his discharge Novem-<lb/>
ber 14, 1901, and has since (on December 17, 1903) made application<lb/>
for pension. This was refused for lack of evidence that his ill health<lb/>
was incident to the service.</p>
<p>Of the other experimental cases, seven were Spanish immigrants<lb/>
who submitted to experiments purely for the money which they<lb/>
were promised. With regard to those who were American soldiers,<lb/>
however, ten in number, in addition to those already mentioned,<lb/>
it can not be doubted that, although they received pecuniary rewards,<lb/>
a desire to assist in what they appreciated was a great and glorious<lb/>
work, together with a spirit of adventure, was the most powerful<lb/>
motive. The same is true of the last experimental case, Mr. John<lb/>
R. Bullard, a graduate of Harvard, where he was a distinguished<lb/>
athlete and captain of the university crew. The names of these<lb/>
men, with the dates of their attack, is appended with this report.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f02973015"/>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>15</p>
<p>It remains to mention Dr. Robert P. Cook, acting assistant surgeon,<lb/>
and the six privates of the Hospital Corps, who were for twenty nights<lb/>
shut up in the infected bedding house at Camp Lazear. These<lb/>
experiments, which were absolutely necessary to demonstrate that<lb/>
yellow fever could not be carried otherwise than by the mosquito,<lb/>
had for these men, so far as they knew, an equal element of danger<lb/>
with the other experiments and had in addition such repulsive and<lb/>
disagreeable features as to test to the full their hardihood and patience.<lb/>
Much of the bedding upon which they slept and which they were<lb/>
required daily to handle was so soiled with the discharges of the sick<lb/>
as to be very repulsive to the nose and eye, and the last experimenters<lb/>
actually slept in the pajamas and sheets which had been worn by<lb/>
severe cases of yellow fever. The names of these men are appended<lb/>
to the list given below of experimental cases of yellow fever.</p>
<p>It will be observed that three of these men--Folk, Jernegan, and<lb/>
Hanberry--afterwards submitted to the mosquito inoculation or<lb/>
blood injection in order to demonstrate their nonimmunity at the<lb/>
time of the first experiment.</p>
<p>It is believed that the names of all the Americans on this list<lb/>
should be placed on a tablet in connection with the monument to<lb/>
Walter Reed.</p>
<p>From the foregoing it will be seen that the total disbursements of<lb/>
this great nation in the way of rewards for those who made possible<lb/>
this discovery, and their families, amounts to $146 a month. As to<lb/>
its value to the American people, attention is invited to the quota-<lb/>
tions from General Wood and Professor Welch given above, and<lb/>
others given in the inclosed circulars published by the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association.</p>
<p>How discreditable appears this niggardly provision when com-<lb/>
pared with the action of the English Government, which, more than<lb/>
a century ago, when the purchasing power of money was far greater<lb/>
than at present, gave to Jenner, the discoverer of vaccination, grants<lb/>
amounting to 30,000 pounds sterling. He also received from a sub-<lb/>
scription in India 7,383 pounds sterling, while the Reed Memorial<lb/>
has so far succeeded in raising only a little over half that sum.</p>
<p>It is believed that if the President would exert his great personal<lb/>
influence in furtherance of the aims of that association its task<lb/>
would be soon completed.</p>
<p>R. M. O'REILLY,<lb/>
Surgeon-General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>Names of persons who submitted to experimental inoculation of yellow fever, Cuba,<lb/>
1900-1901.</p>
<p>
<table rows="16" cols="3">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Taken sick.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>Infected by mosquitoes.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>James Carroll.......................................................................</cell><cell>Aug. 31, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>X. Y. (American soldier)...........................................................</cell><cell>Sept. 6, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>John R. Kissinger...................................................................</cell><cell>Dec. 8, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4</cell><cell>Nicanor Fernandez..................................................................</cell><cell>Dec. 13, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5</cell><cell>Antonio Benigno..................................................................</cell><cell>Do.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6</cell><cell>Becente Presedo........................................................................</cell><cell>Dec. 15, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>7</cell><cell>John J. Moran.................................................................</cell><cell>Dec. 25, 1900</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>8</cell><cell>Jose Martinez.......................................................................</cell><cell>Jan. 3, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>9</cell><cell>Levi E. Folk........................................................................</cell><cell>Jan. 23, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>10</cell><cell>Clyde L. West........................................................................</cell><cell>Feb. 3, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>11</cell><cell>James L. Hanberry..................................................................</cell><cell>Feb. 9, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>12</cell><cell>Charles G. Sonntag....................................................................</cell><cell>Feb. 10, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>13</cell><cell>Pablo Ruiz Castillo................................................................</cell><cell>Sept. 19, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>14</cell><cell>Jacinto Mendez Alvarez..........................................................</cell><cell>Oct. 13, 1901</cell></row></table></p>
<pb n="16" id="f02973016"/>
<p>16</p>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>Names of persons who submitted to experimental inoculation of yellow fever, Cuba,<lb/>
1900-1901--Contined.</p>
<p>
<table rows="19" cols="3">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Taken sick.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>Infected by injection of blood.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>Warren G. Jernegan...............................................................</cell><cell>Jan. 8, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>William Olson.......................................................................</cell><cell>Jan. 11, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>Wallace Forbes.................................................................</cell><cell>Jan. 24, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4</cell><cell>John H. Andrus................................................................</cell><cell>Jan. 28, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5</cell><cell>Manuel Gutierrez Moran...................................................................</cell><cell>Oct. 20, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6</cell><cell>John R. Bullard....................................................................</cell><cell>Oct. 23, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>Infected by injections of filtered blood serum.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>P. Hamann, Twenty-third Battery Coast Artillery....................................</cell><cell>Oct. 19, 1901</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>A. W. Covington, Twenty-third Battery Coast Artillery.............................</cell><cell>Do.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>Exposed to fomites.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>Dr. R. P. Cooke, acting assistant surgeon............................................</cell><cell>..............</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>Levi E. Folk.......................................................................</cell><cell>..............</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>Warren G. Jernegan........................................................................</cell><cell>................</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4</cell><cell>James L. Hanberry..............................................................</cell><cell>...............</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5</cell><cell>Edward Weatherwalks (bitten once, negative; refused after Hanberry came down)...</cell><cell>................</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6</cell><cell>James Hildebrand (offered himself, but was declined on account of age)..............</cell><cell>................</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>7</cell><cell>Thomas M. England..................................................................</cell><cell>................</cell></row></table></p>
<p>[Inclosure 2.]</p>
<p>WALTER REED MEMORIAL ASSOCIATION, WASHINGTON, D. C.</p>
<p>[Extract from the Report of the Secretary of War, 1901.]</p>
<p>The control of yellow fever, acting upon the results of investigations as to its causes,<lb/>
prosecuted under the direction of the military government, appears to be now prac-<lb/>
tically absolute.</p>
<p>The Surgeon-General of the Army furnishes the following condensed statement<lb/>
concerning the investigation and its result:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The importance and far-reaching consequences of the observations made by Major<lb/>
Reed and his associates at Quemados, Cuba, can hardly be overestimated. For the<lb/>
first time in the history of this widely prevalent tropical disease we are in possession<lb/>
of knowledge in regard to the manner of its propagation which will enable us, I believe,<lb/>
not only to check its ravages, but to effectually stamp it out whenever it may appear<lb/>
in any of our garrisons or cities.&rdquo;</p>
<p>[From the Report of the Secretary of War, 1902.]</p>
<p>The brilliant character of this scientific achievement, its inestimable value to man-<lb/>
kind, the saving of thousands of lives, and the deliverance of the Atlantic seacoast<lb/>
from constant apprehension, demand special recognition from the Government of the<lb/>
United States.</p>
<p>Doctor Reed is the ranking major in the Medical Department, and within a few<lb/>
months will, by operation of law, become lieutenant-colonel. I ask that the President<lb/>
be authorized to appoint him Assistant Surgeon-General with the rank of colonel.</p>
<p>From Maj. Gen. Leonard Wood's address at a memorial meeting of scientific men in Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>I know of no other man on this side of the world who has done so much for humanity<lb/>
as Doctor Reed. His discovery results in the saving of more lives annually than were<lb/>
lost in the Cuban war, and saves the commercial interests of the world a greater finan-<lb/>
cial loss each year than the cost of the Cuban war. He came to Cuba at a time when<lb/>
one-third of the officers of my staff died of yellow fever, and we were discouraged at<lb/>
the failure of our efforts to control the disease.</p>
<p>In the months when the disease was ordinarily worst the disease was checked and<lb/>
driven from Habana. That was the first time in nearly two hundred years that the<lb/>
city had been rid of it. The value of his discovery can not be appreciated by persons<lb/>
who are not familiar with the conditions of tropical countries. Hereafter it will<lb/>
never be possible for yellow fever to gain such headway that quarantine will exist<lb/>
from the mouth of the Potomac to the mouth of the Rio Grande. Future generations<lb/>
will appreciate fully the value of Doctor Reed's services. His was the originating,<lb/>
directing, and controlling mind in this work, and the others were assistants only.</p>
<pb n="17" id="f02973017"/>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>17</p>
<p>[Extract from a letter of General Wood.]</p>
<p>To Major Reed belongs the honor of having led in the greatest medical work of<lb/>
modern times, and the results he accomplished will live for all time.</p>
<p>[Extract from a letter of Prof. William Welch, of Johns Hopkins University, to the Secretary of War.]</p>
<p>Doctor Reed's researches in yellow fever are by far the most important contribu-<lb/>
tions to science which have ever come from any army surgeon. In my judgment<lb/>
they are the most valuable contributions to medicine and public hygiene which have<lb/>
ever been made in this country with the exception of the discovery of an&aelig;sthesia.<lb/>
They have led and will lead to the saving of thousands of lives. I am in a position<lb/>
to know that the credit for the original ideas embodied in this work belongs wholly<lb/>
to Major Reed.</p>
<p>When conferring the degree of M. A., President Eliot, of Harvard University, said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Walter Reed, graduate of medicine of the University of Virginia, the army surgeon<lb/>
who planned and directed in Cuba the experiments which have given man control<lb/>
over that fearful scourge, yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>[From an editorial in American Medicine (referring to Major Reed).]</p>
<p>His was the master mind and he the guiding spirit in an investigation whereby<lb/>
multitudes of lives have been saved, a pestilential malady robbed of its mysteries<lb/>
and terrors, and an annual expenditure of millions of money shown to be in large<lb/>
part, if not entirely, needless.</p>
<p>[From the resolution adopted by the medical faculty of the University of Virginia.]</p>
<p>His masterly investigation of the causes of the outbreaks of typhoid fever in the<lb/>
United States Army during the Spanish-American war, and especially his work<lb/>
furnishing conclusive proof of the conveyance of yellow fever by the mosquito, entitle<lb/>
him to a preeminent place among scientists and sanitarians and will prove of in-<lb/>
estimable service to mankind.</p>
<p>[From the resolutions of the American Association for the Advancement of Science.]</p>
<p>By solving the problem of the mode of spread of yellow fever Major Reed not only<lb/>
made a great contribution to science, but at the same time conferred inestimable<lb/>
benefits upon his country and upon mankind. To have discovered and demonstrated<lb/>
the methods, which have already been successfully tested in Cuba, of eradicating a<lb/>
widespread and terrible pestilence is a benefaction of imperishable renown, of in-<lb/>
calculable value in the saving of human lives, of vast importance to commercial<lb/>
interests, and deserving the highest rewards in the power of his countrymen to<lb/>
bestow.</p>
<p>[From resolutions of the Medical Society of the District of Columbia, December 3, 1902.]</p>
<p>His greatest achievement for science and humanity was his contribution to the<lb/>
cause, spread, and prevention of yellow fever.</p>
<p>The practical value of this discovery, which in point of importance and far-reaching<lb/>
beneficence ranks only second with Jenner's discovery of vaccination, has been<lb/>
proved by the complete eradication of this scourge from Habana.</p>
<p>[From resolutions of the American Medical Association, June 11, 1902.]</p>
<p>The members of the American Medical Association believe that the recent work of<lb/>
the United States Army surgeon in Cuba in relation to the discovery of the method of<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever is of such magnitude and far-reaching beneficence as to<lb/>
rank only second with Jenner's discovery of vaccination.</p>
<p>[From lecture of Sir Patrick Manson, M. D., medical adviser of the British Colonial Office.]</p>
<p>Dr. Walter Reed did a great and beneficent work. We in England thoroughly appre-<lb/>
ciate this, and heartily sympathize with America in the loss she and the world has<lb/>
sustained by his premature death. The best tribute we can pay to his memory is at<lb/>
once to apply his discovery. Let us hope that the good he has done will not be interred<lb/>
with his bones, and that his countrymen and the rest of us will take care to push for-<lb/>
ward the great and beneficent measures his brilliant labors so clearly indicate.</p>
<p>S. Doc. 520, 61-2-----2</p>
<pb n="18" id="f02973018"/>
<p>18</p>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>[Resolutions taken by the International Congress of Medicine at Cairo, Egypt, December 22, 1902.]</p>
<p>Les membres du Premier Congr&egrave;s de M&eacute;decine en &Eacute;gypte apprennent avec le plus<lb/>
profond r&eacute;gret la mort pr&eacute;matur&eacute;e du Major Walter Reed du Corps M&eacute;dical de l'Arm&eacute;e<lb/>
des Etats Unis d'Am&eacute;rique.</p>
<p>La part brillante et importante qu'il a pris dans la d&eacute;couverte du moustique st&eacute;gom-<lb/>
yia comme le seul agent transmitteur du parasite de la fi&egrave;vre jaune, r&eacute;ussissant ainsi<lb/>
&agrave; mettre les ravages de cette terrible maladie sous le controle des hygi&eacute;nistes, fait de<lb/>
sa mort une perte cruelle pour l'humanit&eacute;.</p>
<p>[Extracts from paper by Major Reed and Doctor Carroll, U. S. Army, entitled &ldquo;The Prevention of Yellow<lb/>
Fever.&rdquo;]</p>
<p>If we confine ourselves to the epidemics which have occurred since 1793 we find<lb/>
that there have not been less than 100,000 deaths from this cause.</p>
<p>If we reckon the average mortality at 20 per cent, there have not been less than<lb/>
500,000 cases of yellow fever in the United States during the period from 1793 to 1900.</p>
<p>At the sixth annual meeting of the Public Health Association, held in Richmond,<lb/>
Va., in 1878, Dr. Samuel Choppin, president of the state board of health of Louisiana,<lb/>
estimated the actual cost of the epidemic of that year to the material resources of<lb/>
the city of New Orleans at $10,752,500.</p>
<p>In addressing President McKinley, the chairman of the committee of the Public<lb/>
Health Association, 1897 (Doctor Horlbeck, of Charleston, S. C.), said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is hardly necessary to call your attention to the serious results of the recent<lb/>
epidemic of yellow fever in the States of Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama, but<lb/>
we may be permitted to mention the fact that the great epidemic of 1878 resulted in<lb/>
the loss of nearly 16,000 lives, and that it has been estimated that the total loss to the<lb/>
country resulting from this epidemic was not less than $100,000,000.&rdquo;</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>&ldquo;THE WALTER REED MEMORIAL ASSOCIATION,&rdquo; WASHINGTON, D. C.</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head>INCORPORATORS.</head>
<item>R. M. O'Reilly, Surgeon-General, U. S. Army, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>P. M. Rixey, Surgeon-General, U. S. Navy, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Walter Wyman, LL. D., Surgeon-General, United States Public Health and<lb/>
Marine-Hospital Service, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>George M. Sternberg, LL. D., brigadier-general, U. S. Army (retired), Wash-<lb/>
ington, D. C.</item>
<item>Calvin De Witt, brigadier-general, U. S. Army (retired), Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Daniel C. Gilman, LL. D., president of Carnegie Institution, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Chas. W. Needham, LL. D., president of Columbian University, Washington,<lb/>
D. C.</item>
<item>Carroll D. Wright, LL. D., Commissioner of Labor, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Henry B. F. Macfarland, president Board of Commissioners, District of Columbia.</item>
<item>H. St. George Tucker, LL. D., dean of school of law and diplomacy, Columbian<lb/>
University, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Alexander Graham Bell, LL. D., Columbian University, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>G. Wythe Cook, M. D., LL. D., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>A. F. A. King, M. D., dean emeritus medical school, Columbian University, Wash-<lb/>
ington, D. C.</item>
<item>Chas. Wardell Styles, M. D., Chief of Division of Zoology, Hygienic Laboratory,<lb/>
United States Public Health and Marine-Hospital Service, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>W. J. Boardman, Washington, D. C</item>
<item>William A. Gordon, lawyer, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Maj. J. R. Kean, surgeon, U. S. Army, War Department, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Maj. W. D. McCaw, surgeon, U. S. Army, War Department, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Capt. C. R. Darnall, assistant surgeon, U. S. Army, War Department, Washington,<lb/>
D. C.</item>
<item>First Lieut. Jas. Carroll, assistant surgeon, U. S. Army, War Department, Wash-<lb/>
ington, D. C.</item>
<item>F. S. Nash, M. D., Washington, D. C.</item>
</list></p>
<pb n="19" id="f02973019"/>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>19</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head>OFFICERS OF THE ASSOCIATION.</head>
<item>President, Daniel C. Gilman, LL. D., president Carnegie Institution.</item>
<item>Vice-President, Gen. Geo. M. Sternberg, LL. D., U. S. Army, former Surgeon-<lb/>
General, U. S. Army.</item>
<item>Treasurer, Mr. Chas. J. Bell, president American Security and Trust Company,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Secretary, Gen. Calvin De Witt, U. S. Army, 1707 Twenty-first street NW., Wash-<lb/>
ington, D. C.</item>
</list></p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head>EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE.<lb/>
The officers of the association.</head>
<item>A. F. A. King, M. D., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Maj. J. R. Kean, surgeon, U. S. Army.</item>
<item>Maj. W. D. McCaw, surgeon, U. S. Army.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Contributions to the &ldquo;Memorial Fund&rdquo; should be sent to the treasurer.</p>
<p>Correspondence should be addressed to the secretary.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>[Inclosure 3.]</p>
<p>WALTER REED--A MEMOIR.</p>
<p>It is given to but few scientific men to lay bare a secret of nature materially affecting<lb/>
the prosperity of nations and the lives, fortunes, and happiness of thousands. Fewer<lb/>
still succeed in so quickly convincing brother scientists and men in authority of the<lb/>
truth of their discoveries that their own eyes behold the glorious result of their labor.</p>
<p>Of the fifty-one years of Walter Reed's industrious, blameless life, twelve only<lb/>
were spent in the study of the special branch of science in which he became famous,<lb/>
but his name now stands with those of Jenner, Lister, and Morton as among the bene-<lb/>
factors of humanity.</p>
<p>Walter Reed was born in Gloucester County, Va., September 13, 1851, the son of<lb/>
the Rev. Lemuel Sutton Reed and Pharaba White, his wife.</p>
<p>The circumstances of his family were modest, and some of the years of his boyhood<lb/>
were spent in a much troubled section of the South during the great civil war. He<lb/>
acquired, however, a good preliminary education, and at an age when most boys are<lb/>
still in the schoolroom he began the study of medicine at the University of Virginia,<lb/>
graduating as M. D. in 1868, when only 17 years old.</p>
<p>A second medical degree was received later from Bellevue Medical College, New<lb/>
York, and then came terms of service in the Brooklyn City Hospital and the City<lb/>
Hospital, Blackwells Island.</p>
<p>Before the age of 21 Reed was a district physician in New York City, and at 22 one<lb/>
of the five inspectors of the board of health of Brooklyn.</p>
<p>He entered the Army of the United States as assistant surgeon with the rank of first<lb/>
lieutenant in 1875, and for the next eighteen years, with the usual varying fortunes of<lb/>
a young medical officer in the army, he served in Arizona, Nebraska, Dakota, and in<lb/>
the Southern and Eastern States.</p>
<p>According to the exigencies of the service he was moved frequently from station to<lb/>
station, everywhere recognized by men of his own age as a charming and sympathetic<lb/>
companion and by older officers as an earnest and intelligent physician, whose indus-<lb/>
try, fidelity to duty, and singularly clear judgment gave brilliant promise for the<lb/>
future. In the poor cabins and dugouts of the pioneers in the sparsely settled districts<lb/>
where he served his flag Reed was ever a messenger of healing and comfort. At that<lb/>
time army posts on the frontier were usually remote and with small garrisons. The<lb/>
young medical officer, generally the only one at the station, was called upon by the<lb/>
settlers for miles around. Without help and with only such instruments and medicines<lb/>
as could be hastily stuffed in his saddlebag he was summoned to attend a fractured<lb/>
thigh, a child choking with diphtheria, or, most trying of all, a complicated childbirth.</p>
<p>Such experience schools well in self-reliance and in the formation of quick and<lb/>
accurate observation.</p>
<p>For a man like Reed, already an earnest student, no better preparation could per-<lb/>
haps have been had. His earlier army service must have singularly tended to develop<lb/>
in him the very qualities most necessary to his final success. To the end of his life<lb/>
it was noticeable that even when he had long given up the practice of medicine for<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f02973020"/>
20<lb/>
YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.<lb/>
the work of the laboratory he was nevertheless unexcelled at the bedside for rapid,<lb/>
unerring diagnosis and sound judgment in treatment. So, also, were the series of<lb/>
experiments which robbed yellow fever of its terrors especially remarkable for sim-<lb/>
plicity, accuracy, and completeness, or they never would have so quickly convinced<lb/>
the world of their truth. Too much reverence for accepted teachings and too little<lb/>
experience in grappling with difficulties unassisted and they might never have been<lb/>
conceived or carried out.</p>
<p>In 1890 he was assigned to duty in Baltimore, and remained there over a year.<lb/>
Here he had the great advantage of working in the laboratories of Johns Hopkins Uni-<lb/>
versity and the happiness of winning the close friendship of his distinguished teacher,<lb/>
Prof. William H. Welch.</p>
<p>In 1893 Reed was promoted surgeon with the rank of major, and in the same year<lb/>
was detailed in Washington as curator of the Army Medical Museum and professor<lb/>
of bacteriology at the newly organized Army Medical School. Here he worked in-<lb/>
dustriously at his specialty and wrote many valuable monographs, all characterized<lb/>
by accuracy and originality. His excellent judgment made him especially valuable<lb/>
in investigating the causes of epidemic diseases at military posts and in making sani-<lb/>
tary inspections. He was, therefore, frequently selected for such work, which with<lb/>
his duties as teacher and member of examining boards, occupied much of the time<lb/>
that he would otherwise have spent in his laboratory. Here again it seems that duties<lb/>
which must often have been irksome were specially fitting him for his culminating<lb/>
work.</p>
<p>During the Spanish-American war the camps of the volunteer troops in the United<lb/>
States were devastated by typhoid fever, and Major Reed was selected as the head of<lb/>
a board to study the causation and spread of the disease. This immense task occupied<lb/>
more than a year's time. With the utmost patience and accuracy the details of hun-<lb/>
dreds of individual cases were grouped and studied. The report of the commission,<lb/>
now in course of publication by the Government, is a monumental work which must<lb/>
always serve as a basis for future study of the epidemiology of typhoid fever.</p>
<p>The most original and valuable work of the board is the proof that the infection of<lb/>
typhoid fever is spread in camps by the common fly and by contact with patients<lb/>
and infected articles--clothing, tentage, and utensils--as well as by contaminated<lb/>
drinking water.</p>
<p>In June, 1900, Major Reed was sent to Cuba as president of a board to study the<lb/>
infectious diseases of the country, but more especially yellow fever. Associated with<lb/>
him were Acting Assistant Surgeons James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear, and A. Agramonte.</p>
<p>At this time the American authorities in Cuba had for a year and a half endeavored<lb/>
to diminish the disease and mortality of the Cuban towns by general sanitary work,<lb/>
but while the health of the population showed distinct improvement and the mortality<lb/>
had greatly diminished, yellow fever apparently had been entirely unaffected by<lb/>
these measures. In fact, owing to the large number of nonimmune foreigners, the<lb/>
disease was more frequent than usual in Habana and in Quemados near the camp of<lb/>
American troops, and many valuable lives of American officers and soldiers had been<lb/>
lost.</p>
<p>Reed was convinced from the first that general sanitary measures alone would not<lb/>
check the disease, but that its transmission was probably due to an insect.</p>
<p>The fact that malarial fever, caused by an animal parasite in the blood, is trans-<lb/>
mitted from man to man through the agency of certain mosquitoes had been recently<lb/>
accepted by the scientific world; also, several years before, Dr. Carlos Finlay, of<lb/>
Habana, had advanced the theory that the mosquito conveyed the unknown cause<lb/>
of yellow fever, but did not succeed in demonstrating the truth of his theory.</p>
<p>Dr. H. R. Carter, of the Marine-Hospital Service, had written a paper showing that<lb/>
although the period of incubation of yellow fever was only five days, yet a house to<lb/>
which a patient was carried did not become infected for from fifteen to twenty days.</p>
<p>To Reed's mind this indicated that the unknown infective agent has to undergo a<lb/>
period of incubation of from ten to fifteen days, and probably in the body of a biting<lb/>
insect.</p>
<p>Up to this time the most generally accepted theory as to the causation of yellow<lb/>
fever was that of Sanarelli, who claimed that the bacillus icteroides discovered by<lb/>
him was the specific agent of the disease. Major Reed, in association with Doctor<lb/>
Carroll, had, however, already demonstrated that this bacillus was one widely dissemi-<lb/>
nated in the United States, and bore no special relation to yellow fever.</p>
<p>In June, July, and August, 1900, the commission gave their entire attention to the<lb/>
bacteriological study of the blood of yellow-fever patients and the post-mortem<lb/>
examination of the organs of those dying with the disease. In 24 cases where the<lb/>
blood was repeatedly examined, as well as in 11 carefully studied autopsies, bacillus<lb/>
icteroides was not discovered, nor was there any indication of the presence in the<lb/>
blood of a specific cause of the disease.</p>
<pb n="21" id="f02973021"/>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>21</p>
<p>Application was made to Gen. Leonard Wood, the military governor of Cuba, for<lb/>
permission to conduct experiments on nonimmune persons, and a liberal sum of<lb/>
money requested for the purpose of rewarding volunteers who would submit them-<lb/>
selves to experiment.</p>
<p>It was indeed fortunate that the military governor of Cuba was a man who by his<lb/>
breadth of mind and special scientific training could readily appreciate the argu-<lb/>
ments of Major Reed as to the value of the proposed work.</p>
<p>Money and full authority to proceed were promptly granted, and to the everlasting<lb/>
glory of the American soldier, volunteers from the Army offered themselves for experi-<lb/>
ment in plenty, and with the utmost fearlessness.</p>
<p>Before the arrangements were entirely completed, Doctor Carroll, a member of the<lb/>
commission, allowed himself to be bitten by a mosquito that twelve days previously<lb/>
had filled itself with the blood of a yellow-fever patient. He suffered from a very<lb/>
severe attack, and his was the first experimental case. Doctor Lazear also experi-<lb/>
mented on himself at the same time, but was not infected. Some days later, while<lb/>
in the yellow-fever ward, he was bitten by a mosquito and noted the fact carefully.<lb/>
He acquired the disease in the most terrible form and died a martyr to science, and a<lb/>
true hero.</p>
<p>No other fatality occurred among the brave men who, in the course of the experi-<lb/>
ments, willingly exposed themselves to the infection of the dreaded disease.</p>
<p>A camp was especially constructed for the experiments about 4 miles from Habana,<lb/>
christened Camp Lazear in honor of the dead comrade. The inmates of the camp<lb/>
were put into most rigid quarantine and ample time was allowed to eliminate any<lb/>
possibility of the disease being brought in from Habana.</p>
<p>The personnel consisted of three nurses and nine nonimmunes, all in the military<lb/>
service, and included two physicians.</p>
<p>From time to time Spanish immigrants, newly arrived, were brought in directly<lb/>
from the immigrant station; a person not known to be immune was not allowed to<lb/>
leave camp, or if he did was forbidden to return.</p>
<p>The most complete record was kept of the health of every man to be experimented<lb/>
upon, thus eliminating the possibility of any other disease than yellow fever com-<lb/>
plicating the case.</p>
<p>The mosquitoes used were specially bred from the eggs and kept in a building<lb/>
screened by wire netting. When an insect was wanted for an experiment, it was<lb/>
taken into a yellow-fever hospital and allowed to fill itself with the blood of a patient;<lb/>
afterwards at varying intervals from the time of this meal of blood it was purposely<lb/>
applied to nonimmunes in camp.</p>
<p>In December five cases of the disease were developed as the result of such appli-<lb/>
cations; in January, three, and in February, two, making in all ten, exclusive of<lb/>
the cases of Doctors Carroll and Lazear. Immediately upon the appearance of the<lb/>
first recognized symptoms of the disease, in any one of these experimental cases, the<lb/>
patient was taken from Camp Lazear to a yellow-fever hospital, 1 mile distant. Every<lb/>
person in camp was rigidly protected from accidental mosquito bites, and not in a<lb/>
single instance did yellow fever develop in the camp, except at the will of the<lb/>
experimenters.</p>
<p>The experiments were conducted at a season when there was the least chance of<lb/>
naturally acquiring the disease, and the mosquitoes used were kept active by main-<lb/>
taining them at a summer temperature.</p>
<p>A completely mosquito-proof building was divided into two compartments by a<lb/>
wire-screen partition; infected insects were liberated on one side only. A brave<lb/>
nonimmune entered and remained long enough to allow himself to be bitten several<lb/>
times. He was attacked by yellow fever, while two susceptible men in the other<lb/>
compartment did not acquire the disease, although sleeping there 13 nights. This<lb/>
demonstrates in the simplest and most certain manner that the infectiousness of the<lb/>
building was due only to the presence of the insects.</p>
<p>Every attempt was made to infect individuals by means of bedding, clothes, and<lb/>
other articles that had been used and soiled by patients suffering with virulent yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>Volunteers slept in the room with and handled the most filthy articles for twenty<lb/>
nights, but not a symptom of yellow fever was noted among them, nor was their<lb/>
health in the slightest degree affected. Nevertheless they were not immune to the<lb/>
disease, for some of them were afterwards purposely infected by mosquito bites.<lb/>
This experiment indicates at once the uselessness of destroying valuable property<lb/>
for fear of infection. Had the people of the United States known this one fact a<lb/>
hundred years ago, an enormous amount of money would have been saved to house<unclear>-</unclear><lb/>
holders.</p>
<pb n="22" id="f02973022"/>
<p>22</p>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>Besides the experimental cases caused by mosquito bite, four nonimmunes were<lb/>
infected by injecting blood drawn directly from the veins of yellow fever patients<lb/>
in the first two days of the disease, thus demonstrating the presence of an infectious<lb/>
agent in the blood at this early period of the attack.</p>
<p>Even the blood serum of a patient, passed through a bacteria-proof filter, was found<lb/>
to be capable of causing yellow fever in another person.</p>
<p>The details of the experiments are most interesting, but it must here suffice to briefly<lb/>
sum up the principal conclusions of this admirable board of investigators of which Reed<lb/>
was the master mind:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>"1. The specific agent in the causation of yellow fever exists in the blood of a patient<lb/>
for the first three days of his attack, after which time he ceases to be a menace to the<lb/>
health of others.</item>
<item>"2. A mosquito of a single species, Stegomyia fasciata, ingesting the blood of a<lb/>
patient during this infective period is powerless to convey the disease to another<lb/>
person by its bite until about twelve days have elapsed, but can do so thereafter<lb/>
for an indefinite period, probably during the remainder of its life.</item>
<item>&ldquo;3. The disease can not in nature be spread in any other way than by the bite of<lb/>
the previously infected Stegomyia. Articles used and soiled by patients do not carry<lb/>
infection.&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
<p>These conclusions pointed so clearly to the practical method of exterminating the<lb/>
disease that they were at once accepted by the sanitary authorities in Cuba, and put<lb/>
to the test in Habana, where for nearly a century and a half, by actual record, the<lb/>
disease had never failed to appear annually.</p>
<p>In February, 1901, the chief sanitary officer in Habana, Maj. W. C. Gorgas, Medical<lb/>
Department U. S. Army, instituted measures to eradicate the disease, based entirely<lb/>
on the conclusions of the commission. Cases of yellow fever were required to be<lb/>
reported as promptly as possible, the patient was at first rigidly isolated, and imme-<lb/>
diately upon the report a force of men from the sanitary department visited the house.<lb/>
All the rooms of the building and of the neighboring houses were sealed and fumigated<lb/>
to destroy the mosquitoes present. Window and door screens were put up, and after<lb/>
the death or recovery of the patient, his room was fumigated and every mosquito<lb/>
destroyed. A war of extermination was also waged against mosquitoes in general, and<lb/>
an energetic effort was made to diminish the number bred by draining standing water,<lb/>
screening tanks and vessels, using petroleum on water that could not be drained, and<lb/>
in the most systematic manner destroying the breeding places of the insects.</p>
<p>When the warm season returned a few cases occurred, but by September, 1901,<lb/>
the last case of yellow fever originated in Habana, since which time the city has been<lb/>
entirely exempt from the terrible disease that had there kept stronghold for a hundred<lb/>
and fifty years. Cases are now admitted into Habana from Mexican ports, but are<lb/>
treated under screens with perfect impunity in the ordinary city hospitals. The<lb/>
crusade against the insects also caused a very large decrease in malarial fevers.</p>
<p>The destruction of the most fatal epidemic disease of the western hemisphere, in<lb/>
its favorite home city, is but the beginning of the benefit to mankind that may be<lb/>
expected to follow the work of Reed and his associates. There can be no manner of<lb/>
doubt should Mexico, Brazil, and the Central American Republics, where the disease<lb/>
still exists, follow strictly the example set by Habana, that yellow fever will become<lb/>
extinct and the United States forever freed from the scourge that has in the past slain<lb/>
thousands of our citizens and caused the loss of untold treasure.</p>
<p>More recent investigations into the cause and spread of yellow fever have only suc-<lb/>
ceeded in verifying the work of Reed and his commission in every particular, and in<lb/>
adding very little to our knowledge of the disease.</p>
<p>Later researches by Guiteras in Habana, by the Public Health and Marine-Hospital<lb/>
Service in Vera Cruz, and lastly by a delegation from the Pasteur Institute of Paris<lb/>
in Rio de Janeiro, all confirm in the most convincing manner both the accuracy and<lb/>
comprehensiveness of the conclusions of the American commission. It has been well<lb/>
said that Reed's experiments &ldquo;will always remain as models in the annals of scientific<lb/>
research, both for the exactness with which they were adapted to the points to be<lb/>
proved and the precautions taken that no experiment should be vitiated by failure<lb/>
to exclude all possible sources of error.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Appreciation of Reed's work was instant in the scientific world. Honorary degrees<lb/>
from Harvard University and the University of Michigan were conferred upon him,<lb/>
learned societies and distinguished men delighted to honor him, and after his death<lb/>
Congress voted a special pension to his widow.</p>
<p>To the United States the value of his services can not be estimated. Ninety times<lb/>
has yellow fever invaded the country, carrying death and destruction, leaving poverty<lb/>
and grief.</p>
<p>New Orleans, Memphis, Charleston, Galveston, Portsmouth, Baltimore, Phila-<lb/>
delphia, New York, and many smaller towns have been swept by the disease.</p>
<pb n="23" id="f02973023"/>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER COMMISSION.</p>
<p>23</p>
<p>The epidemic of 1853 cost New Orleans 8,000 lives; that of 1793 wiped out 10 per<lb/>
cent of Philadelphia's population.</p>
<p>The financial loss to the United States in the one epidemic of 1878 was estimated<lb/>
as amounting to $15,335,000, but suffering, panic, fear, and the tears of widows and<lb/>
orphans can never be estimated. Now, however, if yellow fever should again cross<lb/>
our southern border, there need be no disturbance of commerce or loss of property<lb/>
in the slightest degree comparable with that which epidemics in the past have caused.</p>
<p>The death of Major Reed took place November 23, 1902, in Washington, from<lb/>
appendicitis. It is gratifying to think that, although his country and the scientific<lb/>
world were deprived of one from whose future services more benefit to humanity<lb/>
might reasonably be expected, nevertheless he was privileged before his life's close<lb/>
to know that his discovery had been tested, and that a great city was freed from her<lb/>
ancient foe; to know that his conscientious work had contributed immeasurably<lb/>
toward the future prospects of an infant republic, and even more to the welfare of his<lb/>
own beloved country, whose flag he had served so faithfully.</p>
<p>In the national capital and in the great cities of the United States there are stately<lb/>
monuments to the country's great ones. Statues of warriors, statesmen, and patriots<lb/>
stand as silent witnesses of a people's gratitude. Is there not room for the effigy of<lb/>
Walter Reed, who so clearly pointed out to his fellow-man the way to conquer America's<lb/>
worst plague?</p>
<p>WALTER D. McCAW.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
