<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03019001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum of interview with William Crawford Gorgas, by Wickliffe Rose, July 14, 1914</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03019001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1914-07-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Heiser, Victor G.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">South Vietnam</name>
<name type="place">Thailand</name>
<name type="place">Malaya</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1914-07-14">[July 14, 1914]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03019001</idno>
<title>Memorandum of interview with William Crawford Gorgas, by Wickliffe Rose, July 14, 1914</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Rose and Gorgas discuss the relative severity of ankylostomiasis and malaria in Malaya, as well as plans to eradicate yellow fever worldwide.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1914-07-14">
<head>Memorandum of interview with William Crawford Gorgas, by Wickliffe Rose, July 14, 1914</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03019001"/>
<opener>
Copy<lb/>
Book<lb/>
Gorgas<lb/>
</opener>
<p><hi>Memorandum of Interview with General Gorgas</hi></p>
<p>Tuesday, July 14, 1914, General Gorgas called at my office by<lb/>
appointment for conference on two matters which I wanted to talk over with<lb/>
him. The following are the chief points covered in our discussion:</p>
<p>1. I outlined my findings as to ankylostomiasis in Malay States,<lb/>
stating that I had found there a widespread infection among the coolies on<lb/>
the rubber estates throughout the Peninsula; that the infection seems to<lb/>
range from a very light degree in some communities where estate physicians<lb/>
have been alert in detecting and treating it up to 60% and more on many<lb/>
groups of estates; that this infection is recognized by the medical profes-<lb/>
sion and the planters. But that as to what the infection represents as a<lb/>
menace to health and working efficiency the medical profession is divided<lb/>
into two opposing camps. One group of doctors maintains that the infection<lb/>
is a serious handicap; that it lowers the vitality of the coolies and thereby<lb/>
makes them more susceptible to malaria; that this lowered vitality greatly<lb/>
increases the death rate attributed to malaria; and that it has a considera-<lb/>
ble death rate of its own. The other physicians hold that the real scourge<lb/>
of the country is malaria; that ankylostomiasis as a handicapping disease is<lb/>
practically negligible; that the anaemia which one sees among the coolies is<lb/>
due to malaria; that the very high death rate is caused by malaria; that when<lb/>
the malaria is controlled the death rate falls; and that therefore nothing<lb/>
more is needed for ankylostomiasis than to treat the cases which come to the<lb/>
hospitals. After seeing something of conditions from Pinang to Singapore,<lb/>
and examining clinically about 2,000 coolies on the estates and in the hospi-<lb/>
tals, I was not prepared to recommend the expenditure of funds either by the<lb/>
Commission or by the Government in a systematic effort for the relief and<lb/>
control of the disease on the basis of our present knowledge of the facts.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03019002"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>2. In view of this situation I raised the question as to the<lb/>
advisability of appointing a commission of experts to settle this question<lb/>
as to what the ankylostome infection in Malaya represents as a menace to<lb/>
health and working efficiency. If such commission could determine this ques-<lb/>
tion for Malaya it could readily do the same thing for any other countries in<lb/>
the far East where this question has been raised or is likely to come up.<lb/>
Dr. Heiser advises that just this bit of work needs to be done for the Philip-<lb/>
pines. He says that he thinks we shall find it necessary to do a similar work<lb/>
for Cochin China, and probably for Siam. General Gorgas, after hearing the<lb/>
statement of the case, stated that he saw no grave difficulties in the way of<lb/>
making a definite determination of the question, and in view of the situation<lb/>
as outlined, he regarded the appointment of a commission of experts as the<lb/>
best way to accomplish our purpose.</p>
<p>3. As to the constitution of the commission, he favored the sug-<lb/>
gestion of having on it one American, one Englishman, and if possible one<lb/>
local man.</p>
<p>4. I then asked him if in his judgment the prevalence of malaria<lb/>
in tropical countries offers a fruitful field of service for our Commission.<lb/>
Malaria, he said, is the scourge of the tropics. It has been demonstrated<lb/>
that intelligently directed effort for its control gets definite results.<lb/>
This field, he said, offers the Commission opportunity for large service. But<lb/>
the work, he reminded me, is expensive and the fight against mosquitoes is a<lb/>
long one.</p>
<p>I asked him how, in his judgment, the Commission could render most<lb/>
effective service in this field. He replied, &ldquo;By making demonstrations in<lb/>
selected areas.&rdquo; He said we should select our points with care, get the co-<lb/>
operation of the communities selected, place at the head of the work a well<lb/>
trained man, such as La Prince, supply him with a sanitary force, carry the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03019003"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
work as far as possible in the direction of complete control of the disease.<lb/>
These demonstrations at selected points would teach other communities how to<lb/>
do the work. The communitirs themselves must in the end assume all the re-<lb/>
sponsibility for the work.</p>
<p>5. This discussion of malaria suggested the subject of yellow fever.<lb/>
In this General Gorgas showed the keenest interest. I told him I had found<lb/>
the people in the far East entertaining considerable anxiety on the subject<lb/>
of yellow fever as a possibility in those countries as a result of the open-<lb/>
ing of the Panama Canal. He referred to what Sir Patrick Manson had said<lb/>
on that subject, and then proceeded to discuss at length the possibility of<lb/>
eradicating yellow fever from the face of the earth. This, he said, is a<lb/>
perfectly feasible undertaking; a thing that can be definitely accomplished<lb/>
within reasonable time and within the limits of a reasonable expenditure.<lb/>
The Commission, he said, could not undertake a better piece of work than<lb/>
this. Here is a disease that has commanded an unusual amount of attention,<lb/>
one in which all tropical and semitropical countries are now keenly interested.<lb/>
Its eradication would command the attention and the gratitude of the world.<lb/>
And the thing can be done.</p>
<p>I suggested that we mature a plan for attacking it, he agreed. He<lb/>
thought it best that we discuss it further before committing any thing to<lb/>
paper. He left with the understanding that we are to continue our discussion<lb/>
of this subject with a view to maturing a plan of organization and of work<lb/>
for the accomplishment of this end.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) Wickliffe Rose</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
