<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03020001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Union Calendar No. 297, House of Representatives 16510, May 13, 1914</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03020001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1914-05-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Goethals, George W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Hodges, H.F.</name>
<name type="person">Sibert, William L.</name>
<name type="person">Rousseau, H.H.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1914-05-13">May 13, 1914</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03020001</idno>
<title>Union Calendar No. 297, House of Representatives 16510, May 13, 1914</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This bill recognizes the services of certain military officers of the Isthmian Canal Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1914-05-13">
<head>Union Calendar No. 297, House of Representatives 16510, May 13, 1914</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03020001"/>
<opener>
Union Calendar No. 297<lb/>
H. R. 16510.<lb/>
63D CONGRESS,<lb/>
2D SESSION.<lb/>
--------------<lb/>
[Report No. 1022.]<lb/>
--------------------<lb/>
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1914-05-13">MAY 13, 1914.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Mr. ADAMSON introduced the following bill; which was referred to the Com-<lb/>
mittee on Military Affairs and ordered to be printed.</p>
<p>JULY 27, 1914.</p>
<p>Committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the state of the Union<lb/>
and ordered to be printed.</p>
<p>--------------------------------</p>
<p>A BILL</p>
<p>To provide for recognizing the services of certain officers of the<lb/>
Army and Navy, late members of the Isthmian Canal Com-<lb/>
mission, to extend to them the thanks of Congress, to author-<lb/>
ize their promotion, and for other purposes.</p>
<p>1 <hi rend="italic">Be it enacted by the Senate and House of Representa-</hi><lb/>
2 <hi rend="italic">tives of the United States of America in Congress assembled,</hi><lb/>
3 That the thanks of Congress are hereby extended to the<lb/>
4 following officers of the Army and Navy of the United<lb/>
5 States who, as members of the late Isthmian Canal Com-<lb/>
6 mission, have rendered distinguished service in construct-<lb/>
7 ing the Panama Canal, to wit: Colonel George W. Goethals,<lb/>
8 chairman and chief engineer; Brigadier General William C.<lb/>
9 Gorgas, sanitary expert; Colonel H. F. Hodges, Lieutenant<lb/>
10 Colonel William L. Sibert, and Commander H. H. Rousseau.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03020002"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>1 SEC. 2. That the President is hereby authorized, by<lb/>
2 and with the advice and consent of the Senate, to advance<lb/>
3 in rank one officer of the Corps of Engineers, United States<lb/>
4 Army, named in section one of this Act, to the grade of<lb/>
5 major general of the line, United States Army, and one<lb/>
6 officer of the Medical Department, United States Army,<lb/>
7 named in same section to the rank of major general in said<lb/>
8 department: <hi rend="italic">Provided,</hi> That no officers now belonging to<lb/>
9 said corps or said department shall be deprived of or preju-<lb/>
10 diced in his regular promotion.</p>
<p>11 SEC. 3. That for the purposes of this Act the number<lb/>
12 of major generals of the line, United States Army, is in-<lb/>
13 creased by one and the rank of the head of the Medical<lb/>
14 Department, United States Army, is made that of a major<lb/>
15 general: <hi rend="italic">Provided,</hi> That the officer who may be advanced<lb/>
16 and appointed major general in the Medical Department,<lb/>
17 United States Army, shall thereupon become the head of<lb/>
18 such department, and the operation of so much of section<lb/>
19 twenty-six of the Act of February second, nineteen hundred<lb/>
20 and one, as limits the term of office of the head of the Med-<lb/>
21 ical Department, United States Army, shall be suspended<lb/>
22 during the incumbency of the head of the department who<lb/>
23 may be appointed under this Act: <hi rend="italic">Provided further,</hi> That<lb/>
24 whenever any officer advanced under the provisions of this<lb/>
25 Act to the grade of major general, United States Army,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03020003"/>
3<lb/>
1 shall become separated from the active list of the Army<lb/>
2 by retirement or otherwise, the extra office or grade to<lb/>
3 which he shall have been so advanced or appointed shall<lb/>
4 cease and determine, and thereafter the rank of the head<lb/>
5 of the Medical Department<unclear>.</unclear> United States Army, shall be<lb/>
6 that of a brigadier general: <hi rend="italic">Provided also,</hi> That the Presi-<lb/>
7 dent, upon the retirement of the officers of the United States<lb/>
8 Army and Navy named in section one of this Act and not<lb/>
9 advanced in rank in accordance with section two, is hereby<lb/>
10 authorized, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate,<lb/>
11 to advance said officers one grade on the retired list.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03020004"/>
<p>63D CONGRESS,}<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">2D Session.</hi>}<lb/>
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES.<lb/>
{REPORT<lb/>
{No. 1022.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>RECOGNITION OF SERVICES OF CERTAIN OFFICERS OF<lb/>
THE ARMY AND NAVY.</p>
<p>----------------------</p>
<p>JULY 27, 1914.--Committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the state of the<lb/>
Union and ordered to be printed.</p>
<p>----------------------</p>
<p>Mr. DENT, from the Committee on Military Affairs, submitted the<lb/>
following<lb/>
R E P O R T.</p>
<p>[To accompany H. R. 16510.]</p>
<p>The Committee on Military Affairs, to whom was referred the bill<lb/>
(H. R. 16510) to provide for recognizing the services of certain officers<lb/>
of the Army and Navy, late members of the Isthmian Canal Commis-<lb/>
sion, to extend to them the thanks of Congress, to authorize their<lb/>
promotion, and for other purposes, having considered the same, report<lb/>
thereon with a recommendation that it do pass, and submit in support<lb/>
thereof the following:</p>
<p>The first section of the bill extends the thanks of Congress to each<lb/>
of the engineer members of the commission under whose direction<lb/>
the Panama Canal was constructed, with the exception of Col. D. D.<lb/>
Gaillard, who gave up his life to the work and whose death was all<lb/>
the more pitiful by reason of the fact that it occurred just as the work<lb/>
was about completed.</p>
<p>Col. George W. Goethals, chairman of the commission, &ldquo;the man<lb/>
who turned white&rdquo; in the service, of course, the country recognizes<lb/>
as the head of the entire work. His executive and administrative<lb/>
abilities, added to his skill as an engineer, constituted one of the most<lb/>
important factors in the success of the enterprise.</p>
<p>To Col. William C. Gorgas there can not be given too large a measure<lb/>
of praise. It is generally agreed that the failure of the French was<lb/>
due primarily to disease and a large death rate, which finally demoral-<lb/>
ized the entire force. This Col. Gorgas overcame, making the<lb/>
Isthmus sanitary and habitable. Without this it is doubtful if the<lb/>
canal would have ever been constructed, and certainly not without<lb/>
great loss of life and additional expense. The world recognizes that<lb/>
Col. Gorgas has made life in the Tropics not only possible but com-<lb/>
fortable for the inhabitants of the Temperate Zones.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
