<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03026001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from the Chief Quarantine Officer to [Rupert Blue], February 13, 1916</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03026001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-02-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Croll, J.M.</name>
<name type="person">Dutcher, Maj.</name>
<name type="person">del Valle, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Lippitt, W.F.</name>
<name type="place">Scotland</name>
<name type="place">Port Arthur (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital, San Juan (P.R.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-02-13">February 13, 1916</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03026001</idno>
<title>Letter from the Chief Quarantine Officer to [Rupert Blue], February 13, 1916</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Chief Quarantine Officer relates information on a case of yellow fever and notes disagreement over the diagnosis.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1916-02-13">
<head>Letter from the Chief Quarantine Officer to [Rupert Blue], February 13, 1916</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03026001"/>
<opener>
Reporting facts regarding illness and<lb/>
death of Service patient.<lb/>
SAN JUAN, P. R., Q. S.<lb/>
<dateline>
San Juan, Porto Rico, <date value="1916-02-13">February 13, 1916.</date>
</dateline>
The Surgeon-General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have the honor to report the following facts in<lb/>
the case of J. M. Croll, a patient of the Public Health<lb/>
Service, at the Military Hospital, San Juan, Porto Rico,<lb/>
and certified by Major Dutcher, M. C., U. S. A., to have died<lb/>
from yellow fever.</p>
<p>J. M. Croll, aged 58, native of Scotland, purser<lb/>
on S/S. &ldquo;Mariana.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Previous history:- Had been in Scotland some months<lb/>
during which time he had suffered from an attack of asthma<lb/>
or pneumonia. Returning to New York, he shipped in a few<lb/>
days as purser on the S/S. &ldquo;Mariana.&rdquo; His health at that<lb/>
time was not good but improved during the voyage to Galves-<lb/>
ton and Port Arthur, Texas. Three days after leaving Port<lb/>
Arthur and four days before arriving at San Juan, he became<lb/>
worse complaining of dyspnea, vomiting, precardial pain and<lb/>
diarrhea.</p>
<p>On arrival at San Juan he was immediately seen by<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03026002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
Acting Assistant Surgeon del Valle, who examined hin on board.<lb/>
The examination was unsatisfactory owing to the noise and<lb/>
confusion of unloading cargo, but Dr. del Valle made a ten-<lb/>
tative diagnosis of Bright's disease with dilatation of the<lb/>
heart and symptomatic asthma. The man was evidently very<lb/>
sick and was sent at once to the Military Hospital where he<lb/>
was attended by the medical officers of that hospital.</p>
<p>The principal symptoms noted on the clinical history<lb/>
furnished me by Major Dutcher, word:- Dyspnea, vomiting of<lb/>
clear fluid, weak pulse. Heart sounds weak and distant. Signs<lb/>
of fluid in lungs. Pain and tenderness in upper abdomen.<lb/>
Collapse two or three times daily while under treatment.<lb/>
Temperature subnormal between 98. and 94. F until two days<lb/>
before death when it rose to 99. F, and remained about that<lb/>
degree. Pulse averaged between 80 and 90 until three days<lb/>
before death, when it dropped to an average of 70 for two days,<lb/>
rising again to 90 the day before death. During the last two days<lb/>
of illness he vomited sanguinous and tarry appearing vomit.<lb/>
Urine was examined twice. On February 3rd, it showed a trace of<lb/>
albumin and a slightly larger amount on February 4th. On Feb-<lb/>
ruary 4th, the sclera showed jaundice which became noticeable<lb/>
on the skin before death.</p>
<p>He died at 3.45 A.M., February 8, 1916, with symptoms<lb/>
indicating excessive edema of the lung. A copy of the report<lb/>
of autopsy is herewith enclosed.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03026003"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>In blood smears taken before death, and in smears from<lb/>
various organs, taken at autopsy, were certain bodies which<lb/>
Major Dutcher stated were paraplasma flavigenum, or a similar<lb/>
parasite, and which he showed me stating that it was the cause<lb/>
of yellow fever. These bodies were elongated, slightly oval,<lb/>
with roundish or squarish ends from about five to fifteen<lb/>
microns in length, and from approximately two to three microns<lb/>
in width. These measurements I estimated roughly by comparison<lb/>
with the red corpustles from the same specimen. These bodies<lb/>
were transversely segmented, usually into four parts. They<lb/>
did not correspond, except very remotely to descriptions and<lb/>
illustrations that I have seen of Seidelin's paraplasma<lb/>
flavigenum, but I have not at my command a complete literature<lb/>
on this organism.</p>
<p>The New York &amp; Porto Rico Steamship Co., claimed the<lb/>
body and had it prepared for shipment to the United States.<lb/>
The death certificate signed by Major Dutcher gave yellow<lb/>
fever as the cause of death, the only diagnosis which Major<lb/>
Dutcher stated he could concientiously give.</p>
<p>In issuing the shipping permit Dr. W. F. Lippitt,<lb/>
Director of Sanitation, stated that he had investigated the<lb/>
case and did not agree to the diagnosis of yellow fever. It<lb/>
is customary when a body is to be shipped from this port,<lb/>
for this office to issue a similar certificate certifying that<lb/>
it had been properly embalmed and shipped in accordance with<lb/>
the U. S. Quarantine Regulations. In issuing this certificate<lb/>
I also stated that I disagreed with the diagnosis of yellow<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03026004"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>Inasmuch as the death certificate accompanied the<lb/>
body to New York it was <del><unclear>thoughed</unclear></del> <add>thought</add> advisable by both Dr. Lippitt<lb/>
and myself to state our disagreement with the diagnosis in<lb/>
order that the quarantine officer at New York should under-<lb/>
stand the character of the case, and because we did not feel<lb/>
justified in altering the diagnosis on an official death<lb/>
certificate, over the signature of another physician. The body<lb/>
was shipped on the S/S. &ldquo;Carolina&rdquo; on February 9, 1916,</p>
<p>I had heard nothing about this case until the under-<lb/>
taker came to the office for the shipping permit, and was<lb/>
unable to get the above facts in time to make a report of the<lb/>
case in the mail of February 9th.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Surgeon, Chief Quarantine Officer</signed>.
WWK/CVFD.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
