<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03020005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report No. 1022, 63rd Congress: Services of Certain Officers of the Army and Navy, July 27, 1914</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03020005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1914-07-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Gaillard, D.D.</name>
<name type="person">Goethals, George W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Sibert, W.L.</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
<name type="place">Spain</name>
<name type="place">Portugal</name>
<name type="place">Great Britain</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1914-07-27">July 27, 1914</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03020005</idno>
<title>Report No. 1022, 63rd Congress: Services of Certain Officers of the Army and Navy, July 27, 1914</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report recognizes officers whose work was instrumental in the construction of the Panama Canal.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1914-07-27">
<head>Report No. 1022, 63rd Congress: Services of Certain Officers of the Army and Navy, July 27, 1914</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03020005"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>SERVICES OF CERTAIN OFFICERS OF THE ARMY AND NAVY.</p>
<p>The other engineer members of the commission, with the exception<lb/>
of Col. Gaillard, under whose supervision the cut was made at Culebra,<lb/>
and whose untimely death has hereinbefore been referred to, were<lb/>
Col. W. L. Sibert and Col. H. F. Hodges, of the Army, and Com-<lb/>
mander H. H. Rousseau of the Navy. The last two named were<lb/>
special assistants to the chief engineer, Col. Goethals, and in that<lb/>
capacity rendered valuable services in conferring with the members<lb/>
who had special supervision of certain portions of the work, as well<lb/>
as in carrying out the general plan adopted by the commission. In<lb/>
fact, these men kept at all times in touch with each feature of the<lb/>
canal work.</p>
<p>Col. William L. Sibert was especially designated to superintend<lb/>
the construction of the dam across the Chagres River and the three<lb/>
locks connected therewith on the Atlantic side. Perhaps the construc-<lb/>
tion of the dam over this river was the most serious part of the entire<lb/>
work. It is a remarkable coincidence that the late Senator John T.<lb/>
Morgan, of Alabama, who may very properly be called the father of<lb/>
the Isthmian Canal, although he did not get the route he preferred,<lb/>
should have given as his principal objection to the Panama route the<lb/>
fact that the Chagres River could not be successfully dammed, when,<lb/>
as a matter of fact, it was dammed under the supervision of this other<lb/>
Alabamian, Col. Sibert.</p>
<p>The second section of the bill authorizes the President, by and with<lb/>
the advice and consent of the Senate, in effect, to advance Col.<lb/>
Goethals and Gen. Gorgas to the rank of major general, the former of<lb/>
the line and the latter of the Medical Department of the Army, and<lb/>
provides that no officer belonging to said department or corps shall<lb/>
be deprived of or prejudiced in his regular promotion.</p>
<p>The third section of the bill increases the number of major generals<lb/>
of the line by one, and gives to the head of the Medical Department<lb/>
the rank of major general. It also provides that section 26, of the act<lb/>
of February 2, 1901, which limits the term of office of the head of the<lb/>
Medical Department, shall be suspended during the incumbency of<lb/>
the present head. The effect of this would be to continue Gen. Gorgas<lb/>
as the medical head of the Army for about six months beyond the<lb/>
regular term of service and thus prevent the appointment of his suc-<lb/>
cessor as surgeon general with the rank of brigadier general while<lb/>
Gen. Gorgas as a major general would still be in active service. This<lb/>
section also provides that when the officer advanced to the grade of<lb/>
major general by this act shall be separated from the active list by<lb/>
retirement or otherwise, such extra office or grade shall cease, and<lb/>
that the rank of the head of the Medical Department of the Army<lb/>
thereafter shall be brigadier general. It is further provided that,<lb/>
upon the retirement of the other officers mentioned in the first section<lb/>
of this act, to wit, Col. Hodges, Lieut. Col. Sibert, and Commander<lb/>
Rousseau, the President, by and with the advice and consent of the<lb/>
Senate, may advance them one grade on the retired list.</p>
<p>That the construction of the Panama Canal is one of the greatest<lb/>
engineering feats in the history of the world, and that its sanitation<lb/>
is one of the most remarkable achievements in medical history will<lb/>
not be denied. It brings the Atlantic and Pacific coasts of this great<lb/>
country into much closer communication by water, and it will<lb/>
unquestionably revolutionize, to a large extent, the commerce of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03020006"/>
SERVICES OF CERTAIN OFFICERS OF THE ARMY AND NAVY.<lb/>
3<lb/>
world upon the high seas. It has been the dream of many centuries.<lb/>
Spain, Portugal, and Great Britain seriously contemplated it, while<lb/>
France actually undertook it. But it was American genius that<lb/>
finally made the dream a realization in fact.</p>
<p>Had this great work been accomplished by any European nation,<lb/>
the men at the head of it would long since have been knighted, or<lb/>
<unclear>some</unclear> other mark of special recognition and distinction would have<lb/>
been bestowed upon them. The bill proposes practically the only<lb/>
way, under our form of government, that their merits can be recog-<lb/>
nized.</p>
<p>From the days of the Continental Army under George Washington<lb/>
it has been the practice of this country, in one form or another, to<lb/>
recognize unusually meritorious service. It is needless to relate the<lb/>
list. Only a few years ago Congress advanced Peary to the position of<lb/>
rear admiral in the Navy because the scientific world agreed that he<lb/>
had discovered the North Pole. The canal will bring practical good by<lb/>
shortening distances, saving time (and therefore money), and enabling<lb/>
our Navy to better guard the broad expanse of our Atlantic and<lb/>
Pacific coasts. A remarkable illustration of its importance is fur-<lb/>
nished by the record-breaking run around South America made by<lb/>
our battleship Oregon at the outbreak of the Spanish-American War.</p>
<p>The construction of the Panama Canal, all things considered, is<lb/>
without precedent in history.</p>
<p>It is respectfully submitted to the House, therefore, that this is a<lb/>
small but just recognition of American genius, American ability, and<lb/>
American enterprise.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
