<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03029001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Article from Diario Illustrado regarding the American Sanitary Commission, translated from the Spanish by Juan Guiteras, June 26, 1916</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03029001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-06-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Haiti</name>
<name type="place">Santo Domingo</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Colombia</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
<name type="place">Quito, Ecuador</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-06-26">June 26, 1916</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03029001</idno>
<title>Article from Diario Illustrado regarding the American Sanitary Commission, translated from the Spanish by Juan Guiteras, June 26, 1916</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p> This article, translated into English, addresses the involvement of the American Sanitary Commission in Central and South America, and the political ramifications of its actions.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1916-06-26">
<head>Article from Diario Illustrado regarding the American Sanitary Commission, translated from the Spanish by Juan Guiteras, June 26, 1916</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03029001"/>
<opener>
Translation from the Spanish. (By Dr. Guiteras)<lb/>
&ldquo;DIARIO ILUSTRADO&rdquo;,<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1916-06-26">Junio 26, 1916.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>The American Sanitary Commission:-</p>
<p>The International Sanitary Commission could not have arrived<lb/>
in South America under more unfavorable circumstances. The  conti-<lb/>
nental Press which had not taken into consideration the declaration<lb/>
which is attributed to the Government in Washington, to the effect<lb/>
that &ldquo;The United States have decided to bring healthy conditions in<lb/>
all the litoral of the Pacific&rdquo;, a declaration which it is supposed<lb/>
had been made counting with the acquiescence of interested parties;<lb/>
that Press, we say, which in normal conditions would have received<lb/>
with enthusiasm the mentioned Commission, will limit itself today to<lb/>
give the news, without attributing great importance to a commission<lb/>
arriving in the least opportune moment to offer, doubtless, American<lb/>
money to carry into effect improvements that we are the first to wish<lb/>
for most decidedly.</p>
<p>And we say that the moments are not opportune because all our<lb/>
attention is attracted today by the Mexican events in the exterior<lb/>
and by the approaching change of Government in the interior.</p>
<p>The Mexican affairs concern deeply all America. America has<lb/>
seen planted in that country the policy of the &ldquo;big stick&rdquo; advanced<lb/>
by Mr. Roosevelt and we suppose that the so-called Sanitary Commission<lb/>
has no other purpose than to put into effect the policy of the dollar.</p>
<p>When the United States shall show that they wish to preserve an<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03029002"/>
Article from &ldquo;Diario Ilustrado&rdquo;, concluded.<lb/>
2.<lb/>
attitude of non-interference in affairs that interest ourselves<lb/>
alone; when they shall withdraw their troops from Mexico, Haiti<lb/>
and Santo Domingo; when they cease bringing pressue on the Panama<lb/>
Government and when they fulfill loyally their obligations towards<lb/>
Colombia and Ecuador, not only shall we accept, but even solicit<lb/>
the support of that great nation for the development of our in-<lb/>
dustries and for the promotion of our general progress. But let it<lb/>
be understood that it must be under conditions less onerous than<lb/>
those that they have heretofore offered and with sufficient guarantee<lb/>
that there shall be perfect equality in the contracts and in the<lb/>
manner of carrying them out.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the visit of the International Sanitary Commission<lb/>
cannot have practical results, since it is not to be supposed that<lb/>
the said Commission brings unacceptable instructions, or that it<lb/>
comes with the idea of imposing benefits that we could not be grate-<lb/>
ful for, nor would we accept them when offered in that manner.</p>
<p>The members of the Commission have gone to Quito where they<lb/>
will make known their purposes.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, we shall wait and maintain the attitude of reserve<lb/>
that we have taken.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
