<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03039001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Anopheles and Malarial Fever Survey on and within (3) Miles of the Pond of Stevens Creek Dam on Savannah River, Columbia County, Georgia, by T.H.D. Griffitts, [1916]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03039001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Washington (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Kiokee Creek (Ga.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>12 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-00-00">[1916]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03039001</idno>
<title>Report: Anopheles and Malarial Fever Survey on and within (3) Miles of the Pond of Stevens Creek Dam on Savannah River, Columbia County, Georgia, by T.H.D. Griffitts, [1916]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Griffitts describes a house-to-house search to determine the number and type of mosquitoes, as well as the number of people stricken with malaria.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1916-00-00">
<head>Report: Anopheles and Malarial Fever Survey on and within (3) Miles of the Pond of Stevens Creek Dam on Savannah River, Columbia County, Georgia, by T.H.D. Griffitts, [1916]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03039001"/>
<p>Jm. Water<lb/>
S. Creek</p>
<p>REPORT ON ANOPHELES AND MALARIAL FEVER<lb/>
SURVEY ON AND WITHIN (3) MILES OF THE POND OF STEVENS<lb/>
CREEK DAM ON SAVANNAH RIVER, COLUMBIA COUNTY, GEORGIA.<lb/>
BY<lb/>
T. H. D. GRIFFITTS, M.D.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03039002"/>
<p><hi>C.W. Davidson</hi>.</p>
<p>September 21, 1916, made survey on property of Mr. C.W.<lb/>
Davidson, located on Washington road and approximately, it is<lb/>
estimated, two miles from the nearest point of back water on<lb/>
the Savannah River pond or of its afluent streams. Mrs. David-<lb/>
son stated that the family (12 members now) has lived here for<lb/>
13 years; three members (children) have had chills this year.<lb/>
Beginning at 8:50 A.M. and spending 15 minutes (two persons)<lb/>
in a search for Anopheles (a) <hi>in the house occupied</hi> by the<lb/>
Davidson family (nearly all the time spent in the three bed-<lb/>
rooms - these the most favorable places), no Anopheles mosqui-<lb/>
toes were found. (b) <hi>Under the house</hi>, where physical conditions<lb/>
were favorable, <hi>no Anopheles</hi> were found. (c) The <hi>horse and mule<lb/>
barn</hi> (log 14 stalls), no Anopheles, (d) another <hi>mule and calf<lb/>
stable</hi>, negative for Anopheles. (e) In a <hi>shed</hi> where chickens<lb/>
stay, caught five <hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi>; (f) in the <hi>feed room</hi><lb/>
adjoining the chicken shed, caught four (4) <hi>Anopheles puncti-<lb/>
pennis</hi>; (g) in the privy caught two (2) <hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi>.<lb/>
An examination of the other houses or buildings on the premises<lb/>
of Mr. Davidson showed them to be negative as to Anopheles in-<lb/>
festation. These were:</p>
<p>1.- Cotton house, negative.<lb/>
2.- Chicken house, "<lb/>
3.- Pea house, "</p>
<p>The time spent in the examination of Mr. Davidson's res-<lb/>
idence and out-buildings to determine the presence or absence of<lb/>
malaria bearing mosquitoes was one (1) hour for two persons. The<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03039003"/>
(2)<lb/>
foregoing record shows, no Anopheles in the house and eleven (11)<lb/>
-<hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi>-in or about the rest of the premises. No<lb/>
other species of Anopheles found here. It <hi>was</hi> stated by Mrs. David-<lb/>
son that mosquitoes at night were more &ldquo;troublesome&rdquo; on the porches<lb/>
than in the house.</p>
<p><hi>Breeding Places</hi>.</p>
<p>(a) There is a <hi>series</hi> of woodside pools (more or less tempo-<lb/>
rary in character), approximately 250 yards towards Augusta from<lb/>
Mr. Davidson's house, that I examined and found to be breeding both<lb/>
Culex and Anopheles. The Anopheles larvae found here were mostly<lb/>
small, although there were a few of about full size- almost to the<lb/>
stage of becoming pupae. (b) The branch crossing the Washington<lb/>
road near Mt. Enon Colored Church (Augusta side) was examined North<lb/>
of the road where it runs through the pasture fields, and Anopheles<lb/>
larvae of all sizes were found in the portions where current was<lb/>
slight and there was overhanging grass and other protection for lar-<lb/>
vae and pupae. (c) In a marshy area, covering in all about 1/4 acre,<lb/>
and located about 150 yards Southwest of Mt. Enon Church, Anopheles<lb/>
larvae (all sizes) and pupae were found. This is an out crop of<lb/>
water at the toe of the hill, and from appearances is never dry,<lb/>
but a constant Anopheles breeding place throughout the season.<lb/>
Washing rains would not cause an overflow or scouring of area. From<lb/>
an old hollow gum tree, five (5) feet from small collections of<lb/>
water, from which Anopheles larvae were dipped, I caught twelve (12)<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi> and <hi>one (1) Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi>. <del>The</del> <add>X</add><lb/>
(d) The Baptismal pool and adjacent branch, 150 feet from the Mt.<lb/>
Enon Church is breeding Anopheles mosquitoes. From these places<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03039004"/>
(3)<lb/>
I dipped Anopheles larvae of all sizes and pupae. In a privy close<lb/>
by I caught <hi>two (2) Anopheles punctipennis</hi>.<lb/>
<hi>L.A. Kelley</hi>.</p>
<p>(On Mrs. Georgia Kelley's Place) North side of <del><unclear>Wood</unclear></del> <add>road</add> from<lb/>
Davidson's); six members of the family stated they &ldquo;have had<lb/>
chills since the dam was made.&rdquo; Here nine years and &ldquo;most of us<lb/>
had chills.&rdquo; (a) I made a thorough search of the house (2 P.M.)<lb/>
and found <hi>no Anopheles</hi>. It was stated that &ldquo;mosquitoes are espec-<lb/>
ially bad about the cow lot at milking time in evenings&rdquo; and &ldquo;a-<lb/>
round the house after dark.&rdquo; (b) An examination of the barn (used<lb/>
jointly by L.A. and John Kelley and about half way between the two<lb/>
houses) gave negative results for presence of <hi>Anopheles</hi>. (c) In bed<lb/>
rooms of John Kelley's (Mrs. Georgia Kelley) house, caught two (2)<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi>; (d) Chicken house, negative; (e) under crib<lb/>
caught twenty-one (21) <hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi> and <hi>one</hi> (1) <hi>Anopheles<lb/>
quadrimaculatus</hi>. One hour's time was spent at the Kelley places.<lb/>
No search was made for breeding places near the premises.</p>
<p><hi>Lucy Hampton</hi>.</p>
<p>Colored, on Phoebia Porter Place. (a) This woman stated that<lb/>
mosquitoes were very annoying, or &ldquo;bad&rdquo; about the house. Fifteen min-<lb/>
utes'time (2 persons) were spent on inspection in this small house,<lb/>
and <hi>no Anopheles</hi> were found. Caught two (2) Culex. I asked to see<lb/>
the water barrel. It was at the side of the house and within three<lb/>
feet of the door and was &ldquo;teeming&rdquo; with Culex larvae and pupae and<lb/>
rafts of Culex eggs. I called the woman's attention to this and<lb/>
demonstrated the use of kerosene to prevent mosquito development.<lb/>
The Culex breeding barrel, in all probability, is the source of the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03039005"/>
(4)<lb/>
mosquito pest at this house. I judge that Lucy Hampton's house<lb/>
is about 3/4 mile from back water of Betty's Branch (said to be<lb/>
the nearest point of back water) (b) <hi>Breeding</hi>: In swampy area<lb/>
about spring near Lucy Hampton's cabin, I dipped several <hi>Anopheles<lb/>
larvae</hi>. These were small to three quarter grown and none kept for<lb/>
further development. This area is said to be on the Dr. Phinizy<lb/>
plantation.</p>
<p><hi>Impounded Water</hi>-</p>
<p><hi>Betty's Branch</hi>: This was the first place examined on the pond<lb/>
of the Steven's Creek dam. The physical conditions appeared good<lb/>
for Anopheles breeding. At the point touched*, the water was shallow,<lb/>
varying from six inches to practically nothing, the bottom muddy,<lb/>
<unclear></unclear> Cat-tails, growing and dead, overfallen bulrushes and, generally,<lb/>
collections of fine floatage against them. In the area examined-<lb/>
about 20 square feet- there were collected in one-half hour's time<lb/>
(two persons dipping) about one hundred (100) large <hi>Anopheles</hi> lar-<lb/>
vae and twelve (12) to fifteen (15) pupae. There were <hi>Anopheles<lb/>
larvae</hi> here of all sizes. Apparently there were no top feeding min-<lb/>
nows here, although they were acting in fair numbers two hundred<lb/>
yards higher up in Betty's branch. (The breeding place above re-<lb/>
ferred to is 40 minutes' walk from L.A. Kelley's house, and 50<lb/>
- 2 miles!<lb/>
minutes from C.W. Davidson's.) - 2+ miles!</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi>Willie&rdquo; Seymour</hi>-</p>
<p>Colored - Old Sneed place; seven in the family; here two<lb/>
years and they say all had &ldquo;chills&rdquo; last year, and all again this<lb/>
year. This house is located approximately 1/3 of a mile S.W. of<lb/>
the place mentioned in Paragraph 4*. Spent fifteen minutes (2 per-<lb/>
sons) in examining the house. In the house, caught thirteen (13)<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03039006"/>
(5)<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi> and one (1) <hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi>. It was<lb/>
late in the evening and lack of time prevented examination of the<lb/>
entire premises.</p>
<p><hi>M. I. Gray</hi>:</p>
<p>(On Washington road, Sept. 22) There are 10 persons living at<lb/>
this house and three have had &ldquo;chills&rdquo; this year, it is said. (a)<lb/>
The four bed rooms were thoroughly examined for <hi>Anopheles</hi>. In the<lb/>
N.E. room, caught three (3) <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi>. These were all<lb/>
that were found in the house. (b) Barn with six horse stalls (appar-<lb/>
ently good resting place for mosquitoes), caught one (1) <hi>Anopheles<lb/>
punctipennis</hi>; (c) <hi>wagon shed and cow stalls</hi> - 50 feet from horse barn<lb/>
caught twelve (12) <hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi>; (d) chicken house, cotton<lb/>
and carriage houses, all negative; (e) buggy shed. one (1) <hi>Anopheles<lb/>
punctipennis</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Breeding Places</hi>:</p>
<p>(a) Southwest of M.I. Gray's house, 1400 feet and 225 to 500<lb/>
feet from Gray's S. line in a pasture field, is a series of wet areas,<lb/>
hoof prints, small pools and ditches, most of which contained <hi>Anophe-<lb/>
les larvae</hi>. In some they were numerous, particularly small ones. These<lb/>
out-croppings from the hill are more or less permanent and continuous<lb/>
breeding places, judging from the physical appearances. They are on<lb/>
the water shed of Betty's Branch. A good collection of <hi>Anopheles</hi> lar-<lb/>
vae was made here. (b) From this point, I followed the course of<lb/>
Betty's Branch down to the Washington road and no places physically<lb/>
suited for breeding was <del><unclear></unclear></del> encountered, although minute examination<lb/>
was not made, for lack of time. (c) A marshy area 200 yards, South of<lb/>
the store at Gray's. The water in most of this wet area is covered at<lb/>
this time with &ldquo;ground oil&rdquo;, but in three or four hoof prints <hi>Anopheles</hi><lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03039007"/>
(6)<lb/>
larvae were found. This, I think, would become an important<lb/>
breeding place in a wet season.</p>
<p><hi>Earl Jackson</hi>.-</p>
<p>Colored, living in old Stein house N.E.(?) of Gray's and a few<lb/>
hundred feet from the breeding place noted above. Careful search made<lb/>
in the (a) bedrooms and <hi>one</hi> (1) <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi> found; (b)<lb/>
under house, negative.</p>
<p><hi>Ishman Williams</hi>-</p>
<p>Colored, three in family, near Earl Jackson's and on the old<lb/>
Stein place, negative.</p>
<p><hi>Henry Williams</hi>-</p>
<p>Colored, (on Mrs. Sarah Griffins place, 1st cabin West of<lb/>
gin) There are eight in the family, have lived here one year, no<lb/>
history of malaria - mosquitoes do not trouble them (a) No <hi>Anophe-<lb/>
les</hi> found in house; (b) none in barn, cotton house, sheds, etc.</p>
<p><hi>Jims Holmes</hi>-</p>
<p>Colored, (Capt. <del>(</del>Armstrong's place) There are three in the<lb/>
family; have lived in this <add>immediate</add> vicinity for five years; no history of<lb/>
malaria. The woman said mosquitoes were bad in the house at nights-<lb/>
&ldquo;smudged&rdquo; them out. <hi>No Anopheles</hi> were found in the house, found two<lb/>
dead Culex in cob-webs.</p>
<p><hi>John Thompkins</hi>-</p>
<p>Mrs. Sarah Griffin's place. Nine in family, moved here Dec-<lb/>
ember 1915, coming here from near Mt. Hope. Had chills last year,<lb/>
but none this year, (a) In the house I caught one (1) <hi>Anopheles</hi><lb/>
punctipennis; (b) barn, negative.</p>
<p><hi>Andrew Vincent</hi>-</p>
<p>Colored, (Old Stein place) Reported mosquitoes are bad- No<lb/>
history of chills. House not examined.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f03039008"/>
<p>(7)</p>
<p><hi>Louis Gibert</hi>-</p>
<p>Old Sneed place. Here one year, last year at Mrs. Sarah<lb/>
Griffin's old home place. History of chills this year and last<lb/>
year. (a) In the house found three (3) <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi><lb/>
and one (1) <hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Joe Jones</hi>-</p>
<p>Colored - Old Sneed place; two in family, here four months,<lb/>
had first chill (wife) two weeks ago; the husband had &ldquo;chill&rdquo; in<lb/>
August. (a) House, negative for <hi>Anopheles</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Evans Johnson</hi>-</p>
<p>Colored, Old Sneed place; nine in family, here one year;<lb/>
&ldquo;seven have had chills this year&rdquo; and "three or four had chills<lb/>
last year at Allen's station. In the house, caught five (5)<lb/>
<hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi> and one (1) <hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi></p>
<p><hi>James L. Johnson</hi>-</p>
<p>Sept. 23. Colored, one-half mile West of Walton's Island and<lb/>
the same distance South of Little Kiokee Creek. The Johnson's have<lb/>
lived here twenty years; six in the family and he (Johnson) had<lb/>
&ldquo;chills&rdquo; here in 1903. Doesn't &ldquo;remember having chills since that<lb/>
time.&rdquo; (a) In the house (one person collecting for fifteen minutes)<lb/>
caught eleven (11) <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi> and two (2) <hi>Anopheles<lb/>
punctipennis</hi>; (b) Barn, four (4) <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi>; (c)<lb/>
Colt stable, fourteen (14) <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi> and two <hi>Anophe-<lb/>
<unclear></unclear></hi>; (1) <unclear>(d) <hi>Anopheles punctipennis</hi></unclear> (2) <hi><unclear></unclear></hi>-<lb/>
In a marshy area and small pools about 300 yards S.W. of James L.<lb/>
Johnson's house Anopheles are breeding freely - rather profusely.<lb/>
Collected here in about fifteen minutes time (2 personel about<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f03039009"/>
(8)<lb/>
fifty (50) largen <hi>Anopheles</hi> larvae and a dozen pupae. This place<lb/>
is about 100 feet from &ldquo;old gum spring&rdquo; on Mrs. Clanton's (?) prop-<lb/>
erty. Below the gum spring and among water lillies, dipped from one-<lb/>
half dozen to two dozen <hi>Anopheles larvae</hi> a dip. Owing to lack of<lb/>
time this area was not examined further.</p>
<p><hi>Little Kiokee Creek</hi>:</p>
<p>Three-fourth mile N. of James L. Johnson's. There are flat<lb/>
mud banks, much overfallen trees and loge, no green vegetation along<lb/>
water line. Examining for a distance of 100 yards, found <hi>no Anophe-<lb/>
les larvae</hi>, but many top feeding minnows (Gambusia affinis) At this<lb/>
place there is no floatage or debris for larvae protection and the<lb/>
top minnows are apparently controlling. (On September 25; this por-<lb/>
tion of the creek, as well as the part below to the mouth, was exam-<lb/>
ined from a row boat and away from the banks. Here, breeding <del><unclear></unclear></del> of<lb/>
sanitary importance is taking place. A rather large amount of small<lb/>
drift (also logs) and fine and leaf floatage was found and larvae<lb/>
could be taken at each dip. Here they were protected from the attacks<lb/>
of minnows.</p>
<p><hi>Big Kiokee Creek</hi>;</p>
<p>September 25. For a distance of about 3/4 mile up from the<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> former mouth of this creek, examined from a rowboat, <hi>Anopheles</hi><lb/>
are breeding, here profusely. There is a great deal of fine float-<lb/>
age and leaf floatage collected against small branches, overhanging<lb/>
canes, fallen dead vegetation, logs, etc., and every dip made about<lb/>
such places collected <hi>Anopheles larvae</hi> - all sizes - and pupae.<lb/>
some dips brought as many as two dozen <hi>Anopheles</hi> larvae and pupae.<lb/>
This body of water for the 3/4 (lower) mile examined is breeding<lb/>
Anopheles profusely. The back water in this creek is said to extend<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f03039010"/>
(<del>10</del><add>9</add>)<lb/>
for a distance of two miles from its former mouth, but time did<lb/>
not permit of more extended survey</p>
<p><hi>Shore on Main Pond-</hi></p>
<p><hi>Raft of logs 1/4 mile below upper point of Walton Island</hi>,<lb/>
forming the beginning of a floating island, found no <hi>Anopheles<lb/>
larvae</hi>. (b) Raft in little river 100 yards above the lower point<lb/>
of Walton Island - no <hi>Anopheles larvae</hi> found. (c) <hi>Raft below old<lb/>
sawmill</hi> and shore line to Fury's ferry, only about 1/2 dozen<lb/>
(small) <hi>Anopheles larvae</hi> found. Top feeding minnows noted. (d)<lb/>
<hi>Shore Line of Kent Philpot's</hi> place. The banks are flat and clean<lb/>
(bare) except for a very few leafless tree tops; Gambusia affinis<lb/>
(minnows) are numerous, and seem to be controlling, Only about<lb/>
1/2 dozen <hi>Anopheles larvae</hi> dipped and half of these came from an<lb/>
area of seepage outcrop near the lake but not dependent upon it.<lb/>
(Here I would direct your attention to the growth of so-called<lb/>
&ldquo;silver grass&rdquo; growing in the marshy area. This grass gaining a<lb/>
foot-hold in a pond becomes an important factor in mosquito <del><unclear></unclear></del> breed-<lb/>
ing, furnishing protection from the fish that are destructive to<lb/>
larvae) (So far none seems to have extended to the pond). (e) The<lb/>
shore from the Philpot place to within one mile of the dam was<lb/>
examined at intervals and no Anopheles breeding of sanitary importance<lb/>
was noted.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f03039011"/>
<p>(10)</p>
<p><hi>Appendix</hi></p>
<p>Record of development of mosquitoes from the larvae<lb/>
collected.</p>
<p>1. Roadside pools, and other places (near Mt. Enon<lb/>
Church, on Davidson property-<lb/>
Anopheles punctipennis.......8<lb/>
" quadrimaculatus....0<lb/>
2. Baptismal Pool (at Mt. Enon Church) -<lb/>
Anopheles punctipennis......13<lb/>
" quadrimaculatus .. 0<lb/>
3. About mouth Betty's Branch- Water of Savannah Pond.<lb/>
Anopheles punctipennis.......1<lb/>
" quadrimaculatus...16<lb/>
4. Pasture Pools and Seepage out-crops Gray's pasture.<lb/>
Anopheles punctipennis...... 5<lb/>
" quadrimaculatus... 0<lb/>
5. Pools and marsh near James L. Johnson-<lb/>
Anopheles punctipennis......15<lb/>
" quadrimaculatus... 0<lb/>
6. Main Pond the Kiokee Creeks-<lb/>
Anopheles punctiennis........4<lb/>
" quadrimaculatus ...0</p>
<pb n="12" id="f03039012"/>
<p>Griffitts<lb/>
x<lb/>
Columbia a Co. Ga<lb/>
(Stevens Creek Pond</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
