<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03033001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Joseph A. LePrince to J.E.S. Thorpe, September 13, 1916</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>LePrince, Joseph A.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03033001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1916-09-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Thorpe, J.E.S.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Marshall [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Badin (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1916-09-13">September 13, 1916</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03033001</idno>
<title>Letter from Joseph A. LePrince to J.E.S. Thorpe, September 13, 1916</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Le Prince discusses the treatment of a lake shore, in North Carolina, in order to reduce the number of anopheles mosquitos.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1916-09-13">
<head>Letter from Joseph A. LePrince to J.E.S. Thorpe, September 13, 1916</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03033001"/>
<opener>
<hi><unclear>lamp.</unclear> Waters</hi><lb/>
Baden<lb/>
<dateline>
TREASURY DEPARTMENT<lb/>
U.S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
U.S. Marine Hospital,<lb/>
New Orleans, La.<lb/>
Fort Lawn, S. C.<lb/>
<date value="1916-09-13">Sept. 13, 1916</date>
</dateline>
<hi>Please return</hi> Badin<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mr. Thorpe:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You requested me to write you regarding such measures as I<lb/>
thought might be of assistance in preventing the production of<lb/>
anopheles and spread of malaria in the vicinity of the lake at<lb/>
Badin N. C.</p>
<p>The surveys made during July and August 1916 showed the<lb/>




presence of adult anopheles in houses in the area to be flooded<lb/>
as well as in houses a mile distant. The flooding will eradicate<lb/>
the productive areas now in the basin, but we expect a much larger<lb/>
number of anopheles to be produced by the lake next summer and<lb/>
afterwards.</p>
<p>It is advisable to consider the upper half of all bights<lb/>
as being the most probable and important sources of the mosquitoes<lb/>
next summer and particular attention should be given to them when<lb/>
within 1-1/4 miles of occupied residences. Their shore lines between<lb/>
high and low water lines should be <hi>well</hi> cleared, so that no tall<lb/>
grass, weeds, brush, brambles, etc., or other obstructions, will<lb/>
collect floatage or act as hiding places or protection for mosquito<lb/>
lavae. The cleaner or closer it be cut the better.</p>
<p>COPY</p>
<p>In the spring, about April or May, the debris that has<lb/>
collected in the bights should be all removed. There is<lb/>
no particular reason for close clearing, similar to that mentioned<lb/>
above, along the main shore line of the lake where strong wave action<lb/>
will occur, but wherever the wave action is limited and debris and<lb/>
other protection, such as tall clumps of grass, brembles, tall<lb/>
weeds, etc., remain anopheles may develop unless top feeding minnows<lb/>
are very numerous in all parts of the lake. Incidentally these<lb/>
minnows may concentrate in the arm of the lake that is not cleared<lb/>
and be scarce in other parts. They know where food is most plentiful.</p>
<p>Mr. Marshall asked me regarding leasing of houses within<lb/>
flight range of the lake. It would be fair to the tenant as well as<lb/>
the lessor to include a clause in the lease relieving the lessor from<lb/>
all responsibility regarding danger to health or illness that may<lb/>
occur. It will prevent future misunderstanding.</p>
<p>I would recommend that-</p>
<p>(1) The upper half of all bights be cleared of <hi>all</hi> vegetation<lb/>
close to the ground from above the high water line to below the low<lb/>
water line, where such areas are within 11/4 miles of habitations.</p>
<p>(2) That floating debris abd floatage be not left in bights or<lb/>
places having but little wave action (after the breeding season<lb/>
begins). Wherever debris collects on the water surface anopheles<lb/>
may be expected to propagate unless prevented by fish or wave action.<lb/>
The more prolific the breeding the greater will be the flight range<lb/>
of the malaria conveying mosquito.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03033002"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>(3) More care should be given to close cutting of stumps.<lb/>
The trees and saplings have been cut high and not close to the ground<lb/>
as was recommended. This will probably interfere with the stranding<lb/>
of debris and floatage and in some places will assist in collecting<lb/>
it and in the increased production of anopheles.</p>
<p>(4) The following sections of the February survey are considered<lb/>
important.</p>
<p>No.3<lb/>
4 on page 3<lb/>
5 " 5<lb/>
7 " 4<lb/>
10 " 5</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) J. A. Le Prince</signed>
COPY<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
