<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03048001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from H.J. Nichols to the Members of the American Society of Tropical Medicine, July 4, 1919</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03048001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1919-07-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1919-07-04">July 4, 1919</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03048001</idno>
<title>Letter from H.J. Nichols to the Members of the American Society of Tropical Medicine, July 4, 1919</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Nichols encourages members to support the Society, which lapsed during the World War I.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1919-07-04">
<head>Letter from H.J. Nichols to the Members of the American Society of Tropical Medicine, July 4, 1919</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03048001"/>
<opener>
Miscel,<lb/>
<unclear>Trop</unclear> Society<lb/>
<salute>To The Members of the American Society of Tropical Medicine.</salute>
</opener>
<p>During the war the work of the Society, like many other activities, has been<lb/>
disorganized. No annual meeting was held in 1918, the publications of the Society<lb/>
have not been altogether satisfactory, dues have remained unpaid, and we are some-<lb/>
what in debt. There is now need for reorganization and it becomes my duty as presi-<lb/>
dent to call on all members for assistance in making the Society the rallying point<lb/>
for Americans who are interested in Tropical Medicine. It is hardly necessary to<lb/>
say that there is a definite place for the Society to fill. The history of our<lb/>
country shows that many of our citizens have been and are being subjected to dis-<lb/>
eases of warm climates and the future will no doubt bring more responsibilities of<lb/>
the same kind. Many of the problems of tropical medicine have been successfully<lb/>
met by American medical men. There is a distinct need for a representative nation-<lb/>
al organization with all its advantages of mutual stimulus and concerted action.<lb/>
The Society, which has already worked 15 years in this field, is the logical means<lb/>
to this end.</p>
<p>The main functions of the Society have been and should be (1) to provide for<lb/>
an annual professional meeting for benefit of those who can attend, (2) to provide<lb/>
for publications to keep all members in touch with each other's work. In order to<lb/>
accomplish this work, a certain amount of money is of course necessary, which must<lb/>
be made up from dues. During the changes of the war many members have probably<lb/>
failed to receive notices of their dues or at least have not paid them. At the<lb/>
last meeting in June at Atlantic City, the dues were fixed at $5.00, and the<lb/>
Treasurer was instructed to drop the names of members who after notice remained<lb/>
more than three years in arrears. It was also voted that the dues of those who<lb/>
entered the Service from civil life should be remitted on request. Arrangments<lb/>
were also made looking to a satisfactory form of publication. The Society is un-<lb/>
der financial and moral obligations to the New Orleans Medical and Surgical Jour-<lb/>
nal for the present year, but a change will be made in 1920, to annual transactions<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03048002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
or to occasional bulletins or to a special Journal. The consensus of the opinion<lb/>
of the Council was that it would be better to have a smaller number of really<lb/>
active workers as members rather than a large membership with only remote interest.</p>
<p>Under these circumstances I ask each member to reconsider his connection with<lb/>
the Society. Those who have supported it in the past I ask to take a fresh hold;<lb/>
those who wish to make it a useful and active society I ask to contribute to the<lb/>
program and to meet at New Orleans next year if possible; those who for any reason<lb/>
wish to withdraw, I ask to do so now, that we may know whom to count on for sup-<lb/>
port. My policy will be to develop the national spirit in the Society, to culti-<lb/>
vate cordial relation with workers of other nations through corresponding member-<lb/>
ship and to include the results both of investigation and of application in the<lb/>
program of the annual meeting and in the publications of the Society.</p>
<p>Any suggestions and criticisms looking to the improvement of the Society will<lb/>
be welcome.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Take up the white man's burden&rdquo;,</p>
<closer>
<signed>H.J. Nichols.<lb/>
H. J. Nichols</signed>,
Army Medical School,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
July 4, 1919.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
