<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03040001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Malaria Investigations Made during November 1916 and Subsequent Anti-Malaria Campaign, Kress, Va., April 1st, - June 30th, 1917, by Herman W. Snidow, December 15, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03040001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-12-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Cunningham, A.B.</name>
<name type="person">Manson, R.H.</name>
<name type="person">Brumfield, W.A.</name>
<name type="person">Flannagan, Roy K.</name>
<name type="person">McNeill, A.P.</name>
<name type="person">Cline, W.G.</name>
<name type="place">Kress (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>25 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-12-15">December 15, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03040001</idno>
<title>Report: Malaria Investigations Made during November 1916 and Subsequent Anti-Malaria Campaign, Kress, Va., April 1st, - June 30th, 1917, by Herman W. Snidow, December 15, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Snidow details malaria investigations in Virginia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1917-12-15">
<head>Report: Malaria Investigations Made during November 1916 and Subsequent Anti-Malaria Campaign, Kress, Va., April 1st, - June 30th, 1917, by Herman W. Snidow, December 15, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03040001"/>
<opener>
REPORT OF<lb/>
MALARIA INVESTIGATIONS<lb/>
Made during <dateline><date value="1916-11-00">November 1916</date>
</dateline>
And Subsequent<lb/>
ANTI- MALARIA CAMPAIGN<lb/>
Kress, Va.<lb/>
April 1st, - June 30th, 1917.<lb/>
Herman W. Snidow,<lb/>
Director.<lb/>
W. C. Cline,<lb/>
Assistant.<lb/>
</opener>
<pb n="2" id="f03040002"/>
<p><hi>INTRODUCTION</hi></p>
<p>KRESS COMMUNITY, the scene of the anti-malaria campaign of<lb/>
which the following is a report, represents the area immediately<lb/>
surrounding Kress, a small mill town or village of about 150 inhab-<lb/>
itants located on the Seaboard Air Line Railway in the northern end<lb/>
of Brunswick County Virginia.</p>
<p>The town proper is owned entirely by the F. J. Kress Box Co.,<lb/>
of Pittsburg, Pa., and comprises thirty homes, two stores, one church<lb/>
and schools for both white and colored children together with the mills,<lb/>
depot, warehouses and other connections comprising the Company's Vir-<lb/>
ginia Plant for the manufacture of wooden box shooks. Immediately<lb/>
around this settlement but not on the Company's premises are a number<lb/>
of small houses occupied for the most part by negroes, and belonging<lb/>
to A. B. Cunningham from whom the mill site was originally leased.</p>
<p>The plant employes about two hundred men and of these the super-<lb/>
intendent, foreman, assistants and more responsible machine operators<lb/>
with their families, occupy the houses in the village while the remain-<lb/>
<del>ing</del> der of the working force, mostly laborers, are obtained from the<lb/>
country around and from two other villages near by.</p>
<p>The settlement is of comparative recent origin having had its<lb/>
beginning with the location of the box mill some ten years ago. The site<lb/>
chosen was then a part of the large farming estate of A.B. Cunningham and<lb/>
with the exception of perhaps one or two small tenant houses was unsettled.<lb/>
Following the location of the box-mill, the depot, siding, one store and<lb/>
a number of the houses were built. Later the plant was enlarged, a com-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03040003"/>
-2-<lb/>
plete band saw mill was installed and the remainder of the houses and<lb/>
connections necessary for the accommodation of the increased industry<lb/>
were constructed.</p>
<p>Owing to its prevalence in the general section of the state, and<lb/>
the unusual facilities for its spread with the settlement of this par-<lb/>
ticular locality, malaria began to play its inevitable part in the his-<lb/>
tory of the place within a few years after its settlement. At first the<lb/>
cases were few and mild in type but each year the number and severity<lb/>
increased until during the summer of 1915 the out-put of the plant<lb/>
was materially decreased owing to the number of cases among the more<lb/>
responsible employees living in the town. The following summer of 1916<lb/>
the spread of malaria reached its height. Fully seventy percent of the<lb/>
people living in the place were infected. To see a man leave his machine<lb/>
idle and go home shaking with a chill was a common occurrence. During<lb/>
August and September of this year the business of the company was so<lb/>
seriously handicapped by the prevalence of the disease that the absolute<lb/>
necessity of some action to combat the menace became evident.</p>
<p>In September of this year it became the policy of the Company<lb/>
to place a new superintendent in charge of their plant and one of the<lb/>
first actions taken under the new management was a communication with the<lb/>
State Board of Health at Richmond with reference to advice and help in<lb/>
getting rid of the malaria trouble. As a result of this a hurried survey<lb/>
was made in November 1916. This included an examination of the country<lb/>
for about three quarters of a mile in each direction from the town for<lb/>
the character and area of possible breeding placed of anopheles, an exam-<lb/>
ination of the houses with reference to screening and interviews with the<lb/>
resident physician Dr. Manson, the superintendent and others with reference<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03040004"/>
-3-<lb/>
to the number and character of malaria cases. Following the survey<lb/>
recommendations were made that the Company furnish a supply of quinine<lb/>
for a systematic treatment throughout the winter of all the malaria<lb/>
cases, and that all houses in the village be thoroughly screened the fol-<lb/>
lowing spring. Owing to the extensive areas found around the community<lb/>
physically adapted to anopheles production and the probable difficulties<lb/>
of drainage no extensive measures in this line were recommended at the<lb/>
time, however the superintendent was advised to fill or drain certain<lb/>
small pools and marshes nearest the town and particularly to clean the<lb/>
shore lines of two ponds which were being utilized by the mills. A fur-<lb/>
ther arrangement for an educational lecture on the causes of malaria<lb/>
was also made.</p>
<p>In January 1917 the State Board of Health was advised by the super-<lb/>
intendent at Kress that the recommendations with reference to quinine<lb/>
treatment were being fully carried out, and further that his Company was<lb/>
anxious to execute a complete campaign for the control of malaria in<lb/>
the vicinity of the mills, adequate funds for the purpose to be furnished<lb/>
provided the State Board of Health would undertakt the management of the<lb/>
work. A satisfactory arrangement was made and the first steps taken Feb 1<lb/>
when an estimate was made of <del>in</del> the <del><unclear></unclear></del> quantities of screening<lb/>
materials necessary for the entire work and this quantity was ordered<lb/>
in bulk to be delivered ready for use by April 1st.</p>
<p>The actual work of malaria control was begun on April 2nd, 1917.<lb/>
A re-survey of the drainage possibilities developed that fair drainage<lb/>
of the breeding areas within the field considered might be accomplished<lb/>
through cleaning the channel and thereby lowering the water level in<lb/>
Waqua Creek which flows around two sides of the town and along which<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03040005"/>
-4-<lb/>
the greater part of the breeding areas were to be found. This was<lb/>
done along with the screening and other activities and the hoped for<lb/>
result accomplished. On account of the more than ordinary facilities<lb/>
and the unusual co-operation of the management and residents of the<lb/>
community a more complete campaign was accomplished than was at first<lb/>
expected and the undertaking completed on June 30th 1917.</p>
<p><hi>TOPOGRAPHY.</hi></p>
<p>Considering Kress Community as covering a square with an area<lb/>
of about two and a quarter square miles surrounding the town, the to-<lb/>
pography is rather peculiar and yet characteristic of the general sec-<lb/>
tion of the state. Waqua Creek enters the community near the northwest<lb/>
corner flowing in a general southeasterly direction for about one half<lb/>
mile then curves to a course almost due east through the southern half<lb/>
of the community and within a quarter of a mile of the town on its south-<lb/>
ern side. After following this course for nearly a mile it curves<lb/>
again in a southeasterly direction and passes out of the area at almost<lb/>
the opposite corner from that at which it enters. Following the general<lb/>
trend of the creek is the main valley. This varies in width from fifty<lb/>
to a thousand feet. At the north west corner of the community this val-<lb/>
ley is narrow and the banks of the creek are high and well defined, but<lb/>
just before it bends to its easterly course the valley broadens to<lb/>
about five hundred feet and for an equal distance along its course the<lb/>
greater portion of the bottom was found to be marshy. Just at the bend<lb/>
the valley is narrowed by the first of a series of low ridges or eleva-<lb/>
tions <del><unclear></unclear></del> projecting into it but a little further down and just opposite<lb/>
the western edge of the town it broadens again to about eight hundred feet<lb/>
with the bottom lands almost entirely on the side next to the town.<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03040006"/>
-5-<lb/>
Some two thousand feet further down and opposite the eastern edge of<lb/>
the town the valley reaches its maximum width of about one thousand feet.<lb/>
The greater portion or about twenty five acres of the bottom<lb/>
land along this length was found to be marshy. At the lower end of this<lb/>
bottom another of the parallel ridges projects almost to the creek<lb/>
causing the valley to narrow again to about one hundred feet. From this<lb/>
point on through the remainder of the community the width varies from<lb/>
fifty to one hundred and fifty feet with some few smaller marshes in the<lb/>
broader portions. From the first bend in the creek eastw<del>e</del>ard a series<lb/>
of low parallel ridges project from the higher land to the north<lb/>
into and perpendicular with the main creek valley and between these<lb/>
elevations there are a number of minor valleys with small streams or<lb/>
spring branches flowing through them and emptying into Waqua Creek.<lb/>
The northern portion of the community is generally high and well drained<lb/>
into the various depressions extending down into the main creek valley.<lb/>
The area south of Waqua Creek is also high and well drained naturally.</p>
<p><hi>LOCATION OF CONSTRUCTIONS</hi></p>
<p>The Seaboard Air Line Railway passes through the community in a<lb/>
generally southwesterly direction. Entering the community from the east<lb/>
it follows a course parallel to the creek cutting across the ends of the<lb/>
series of low ridge and crossing the mouths of the minor valleys on<lb/>
fills. At the point where the creek valley curves toward the north the<lb/>
railroad curves slightly in the opposite direction crossing the lower<lb/>
end of the upper marsh on a long fill and the creek on a wooden trestle.<lb/>
The two mills comprising the manufacturing plant are located respective-<lb/>
ly in the mouths of two of the shallow parallel valleys withle the great-<lb/>
er portion of the houses making up the town are located on the flat top<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03040007"/>
-6-<lb/>
of the larger of the elevations which lies between the two mills. The<lb/>
houses occupied by colored people are located on the top of another<lb/>
parallel ridge just east of the other section. This site for the loca-<lb/>
tion of the box plant was doubtless chosen on account of the unusual<lb/>
natural advantages for the formation of ponds necessary to the mills.<lb/>
The valley on the western side being larger and also having a stronger<lb/>
stream flowing through it than the others, was chosen for the location<lb/>
of the saw-mill. The log pond covering about one and a half acres was<lb/>
formed by constructing a dam across the valley parallel to and about<lb/>
two hundred feet above the railroad fill. A spur siding was extended<lb/>
from the main line of the railroad upto and along the side of this<lb/>
pond so that the logs from the cars might be unloaded directly into it.<lb/>
The box-mill occupies the eastern side of the next depression. This<lb/>
valley is very short extending only about five hundred feet from its<lb/>
mouth back to a spring the overflow of which drains through it. In the<lb/>
mouth of this valley <del><unclear></unclear></del> close to the box-mill is another small pond or<lb/>
reservoir maintained for fire protection under the <del><unclear>x</unclear></del> insurance regulations<lb/>
covering the plant.</p>
<p><hi>Location and theory of formation of Marshes</hi>.</p>
<p>The formation of the marshes along Waqua Creek is of comparative-<lb/>
ly recent origin and the causes are identical with numerous other cases<lb/>
in Eastern Virginia. The small streams in this section of the state have<lb/>
as a rule very little fall and the grades are very irregular. They may<lb/>
be characterized as flowing down by steps with alternating broad and<lb/>
narrow valleys and with plenty of fall in the narrower sections but al-<lb/>
most none at all through the broader valleys. During the continual pro-<lb/>
cesses of erosion and carriage of sediment from the higher elevations<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f03040008"/>
-7-<lb/>
to the lower the natural tendency is to deposit it in the beds of the<lb/>
streams along the courses where the fall is least. As a result of this<lb/>
bottom lands or &ldquo;creek bottoms&rdquo; as they are commonly called which have<lb/>
at some time in the past constituted some of the best farming lands in<lb/>
the section of the state have been transformed gradually into almost<lb/>
worthless marshes. The rapidity of action from naturaa causes is almost<lb/>
always very materially increased by the carelessness and neglect of man.<lb/>
The channels of the streams are allowed to become and remain blocked by<lb/>
all kinds of debris brought down and lodged during floods. Trees and<lb/>
smaller brush are very often cut and allowed to fall and remain in the<lb/>
water. All of these artificial obstructions cause a much more rapid<lb/>
deposit of sediment and consequently increase the rapidity of marsh<lb/>
formation. Such has been the case with the bottom lands at Kress. Less<lb/>
than fifty years ago the two larger flat areas now marshes described<lb/>
previously were cultivated creek bottoms. Through their entire lengths<lb/>
Waqua Creek has very little fall and the natural filling of the channel<lb/>
has evidently been very materially aided by numerous accumulations of<lb/>
debris which were never removed. Another agent which evidently played<lb/>
its part in the destruction of the farming lands above was an old stone<lb/>
dam in the creek about one half mile below the southeast corner of the<lb/>
community. Only the base of this dam remains, the greater portion of it<lb/>
having been destroyed years ago, and no one seems to remember just when<lb/>
it stood or to what depth the water was impounded behind it. The base<lb/>
of the structure is on a grade some seven feet below the level of the<lb/>
bottoms above and the efidences remaining would suggest that it was orig-<lb/>
inally about six feet in height and that the water had been backed al-<lb/>
most to the bottoms. The size and conditions of the marsh near the western<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f03040009"/>
-8-<lb/>
boundry of the community were dubtless aggravated after the construc-<lb/>
tion of the Seaboard Air Line Railway. Since the greater part of this<lb/>
bottom occupies a level a little above that of the creek after it<lb/>
curves around and across the lower end of it, the evidences are that<lb/>
prior to the construction of the railroad fill it would drain gradually<lb/>
after each overflow. When the railroad fill was constructed a culvert<lb/>
was provided at the proper position and grade to allow a continuation<lb/>
of the natural drainage but after a time this culvert became clogged<lb/>
and then filled with sediment and in the absence of other adequate<lb/>
channels the water collected during overflows could only drain insuffi-<lb/>
ciently and consequently a year around marsh resulted. Through the re-<lb/>
mainder of the community three out of the five culverts constructed<lb/>
under fills were found to be almost completely choked with debris and<lb/>
as a consequence three other small marshes had been formed on the right<lb/>
of way just above the fills. Two of these were in the mouth of the<lb/>
&ldquo;saw-mill valley&rdquo; and one in the valley just east of the box-mill. Some<lb/>
few other very small marshes caused by the ordinary impediments in the<lb/>
channels were found in the neighborhood of some of the small latteral<lb/>
spring branches near the head of the sawmill pond, but for the most<lb/>
part the foregoing constituted the important areas found within the<lb/>
limits of the community.</p>
<p><hi>ANOPHELES BREEDING</hi></p>
<p>As the survey for anopheles breeding was made in November after the<lb/>
active season of production was over only a few larvae were found. The<lb/>
extent of production was judged <del><unclear></unclear></del> princiaplly by the extent of<lb/>
the areas physically adapted and these were noted more on account of their<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> potentiality or adaptability than for any direct evidences of such<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f03040010"/>
-9-<lb/>
propagation. Practically all the areas have been mentioned under previous<lb/>
headings but in order to emphasize them they are listed again as follows<lb/>
and indicated on the accompanying map by corresponding numbers:<lb/>
1. The large marsh between the railroad and the creek and on the south<lb/>
side of the town. The area originally covered by this marsh is approx-<lb/>
imately twenty acres and any portion of it might have been considered<lb/>
as favorable <del><unclear>x</unclear></del> for anopheles production.<lb/>
(2). The smaller marsh on the western side. This covered about four<lb/>
acres and possessed characteristics identical with No. 1.<lb/>
(3). Small marsh about one quarter of an acre in extent just south of<lb/>
the railroad and near the southwest corner of the community.<lb/>
(4). Rob-pond or borrow pit on the railroad right of way south of the<lb/>
track and in the southwest corner of the community. This pond covered<lb/>
about a quarter acre and its banks were overgrown with a thick tangle<lb/>
of vegetation making of it a highly favorable factor.<lb/>
(5). Rob-pond on the north side of the track just opposite No. 4. This<lb/>
was of about the same size as the other and possessed similar character-<lb/>
istics.<lb/>
(6). Small marshy area just above the railroad fill in the mouth of the<lb/>
saw-mill valley.<lb/>
(7). Cat-tail marsh with a small pool in the center also just above<lb/>
the railroad fill and near No. 6. This in particular possessed <del><unclear></unclear></del> highly<lb/>
favorable characteristics.<lb/>
(8). Small cat-tail marsh just south of the railroad and opposite No.7.<lb/>
(9). Upper end of the saw-mill pond. The entire pond covers about one<lb/>
and a half acres and all of the upper end or about one half acre was<lb/>
covered by an almost impenetrable mass of brush and other vegetation<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f03040011"/>
-10-<lb/>
growing in the water and with a fringe of cat-tails in the shallower<lb/>
portions. This was regarded as one of the most favorable breeding<lb/>
places in the community.<lb/>
(10), (11) and (12). Three small and sluggish spring branches emptying<lb/>
into the mill pond near its head.<lb/>
(13). Small pond near the box-mill. This pond covers a little more than<lb/>
a quarter of an acre and was characterized by the quantity of cat-tails<lb/>
growing in the shallower portions at the upper end and also around the<lb/>
edges. At the time of the survey it was given more particular attention<lb/>
than any of the other breeding places and even at the late season anoph-<lb/>
eles larvae were found.<lb/>
(14). Spring branch feeding the box-mill pond. This was included on<lb/>
account of the number of shallow pools along the channel.<lb/>
(15). Small cat-tail marsh just above the railroad and east of the<lb/>
box-mill.<lb/>
(16). Small spring branch above No. 15 and in the valley back of the<lb/>
negro quarters.</p>
<p>CONDITION OF HOUSES.</p>
<p>Identical with the first malaria survey investigation was<lb/>
made of the houses in the community with reference to their structure<lb/>
and condition for future screening against mosquitoes. These were found<lb/>
to be all wooden structures, the majority in very good condition but<lb/>
in need of some repairs. None were equipped with the modern conven-<lb/>
iences of lighting and heating, kerosine lamps and wood stoves being<lb/>
used instead. The houses owned by the Company were found to conform to<lb/>
four types as follows. Two story double houses weatherboarded and plas-<lb/>
tered with tight floors and free from cracks due to faulty construction.<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f03040012"/>
-11-<lb/>
Each of these had two small front porches ceiled and carefully joined<lb/>
to the body of the building but with loosely joined floors with cracks<lb/>
between the boards. (2). Two story single houses with characteristics<lb/>
identical with No. 1, with the exception that in each of these cases<lb/>
there is one front and one back porch and these are about double the<lb/>
size of the others. (3). One story cottages weatherboarded with tight<lb/>
floors but finished with wall-board on the inside. Each of these have<lb/>
still larger front and back porches which were unceiled and loosely<lb/>
joined to the bodies and which also had very loosely joined floors. (4)<lb/>
Small story and a half houses occupied by the colored people. These were<lb/>
rather carelessly constructed inclosed with rough weatherboarding and<lb/>
cardboarded inside. The floors were very good but quite a number of<lb/>
cracks were to be found around the doors windows and eaves of the<lb/>
buildings. Of the four houses outside the Company's premises two were<lb/>
built of logs and two with perpendicular sheeting and all were of very<lb/>
poor construction. Following this investigation recommendations were<lb/>
made to the superintendent for the necessary repairs and screening<lb/>
of all the houses owned by the Company.</p>
<p><hi>SANITARY CONDITIONS</hi>.</p>
<p>The general sanitary appearance of Kress is much above the<lb/>
average. When this survey was made, general cleanliness, care of prem-<lb/>
ises and satisfactory disposal of garbage was evident. The toilets<lb/>
were all of the open back surface type but the majority had the appear-<lb/>
ance of being well kept, limed and cleaned frequently. The domestic<lb/>
water supply is obtained from three wells, two located in the white<lb/>
settlement and one in the colored. All of these are on elevations well<lb/>
above any of the toilets with the natural surface drainage away from them.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f03040013"/>
<p>-12-</p>
<p><hi>MALARIA CONTROL MEASURES</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Drainage Survey</hi></p>
<p>During the November investigation of possible breeding areas<lb/>
in the vicinity of Kress, efficient drainage of the marshes in the<lb/>
Waqua Creek bottoms assumed the appearance of a possibly wholly im-<lb/>
practicable undertaking. This was due to the probable high per capita<lb/>
cost of the undertaking. However, at the beginning of the actual con-<lb/>
trol campaign in April 1917, acting upon the mutual desire of all par-<lb/>
ties concerned for the drainage of this area if at all economically<lb/>
possible, another and more careful survey, with instruments, was made<lb/>
April 2nd to 7th, 1917. A level line was run from a point at water<lb/>
level on Waqua Creek just below the base of the old stone dam men-<lb/>
tioned in the report of &ldquo;Topography&rdquo; to a similar point on the creek<lb/>
at the upper end of the marsh on the western side. Elevations were<lb/>
taken in this profile of water level at different points along the<lb/>
creek particularly the lower and upper ends of the two principal<lb/>
marshes together with their <del>relative</del> relations to different other<lb/>
intermediate elevations taken at different points over the marsh bot-<lb/>
toms. The results of this investigation showed the creek to have very<lb/>
little fall through the bottoms just adjacent to the town but consid-<lb/>
erable grade just below which increased in that direction. Through the<lb/>
length of the upper marsh to the pond in the creek at the railroad<lb/>
bridge the fall was about four inches and from the bridge to the lower<lb/>
corner of the marsh below the railroad fill it was about three inches.<lb/>
The difference in level between the average bottom of the marsh above<lb/>
the fill and the water level of the creek at the lower corner was found<lb/>
to be about ten inches but the level of the bottom of the culvert under<lb/>
the railroad fill was then about five inches below the level of the<lb/>
creek at the last named point. The evidences then were that the con-<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f03040014"/>
- 13 -<lb/>
tinued year around marshy condition of the area above the railroad fill<lb/>
was due to the culverts being filled with sediment and the absence of<lb/>
ditches leading to and from it. The average elevation of the bottom of<lb/>
the lower and larger marsh was found to be about six inches above the<lb/>
level of the creek at the lower end. The reasons for its perpetuality<lb/>
were two-fold; First, continued deposits of sediment during previous<lb/>
overflows had raised the banks of the creek for the greater part of the<lb/>
length of the marsh, to a higher level than the bottom just adjacent. <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
Consequently overflow water in order to reach the channel again had to<lb/>
drain gradually from the upper end to the lower and through a rank<lb/>
growth of vegetation which would very much impede its progress. The<lb/>
second and more vital reason was due to the three small tributary<lb/>
branches from the higher lands above the waters of which reached the<lb/>
main creek through this marsh. After discharging through the railroad<lb/>
culverts they had no particular channels but all finally reached the<lb/>
main creek at the lower end of the marsh after spreading out fan-like<lb/>
over the entire bottom. Levels taken of the bottoms of the other small<lb/>
marshes showed them all possible of drainage through proper ditching.<lb/>
The bottom of the rob-pond below the railroad was found to be about<lb/>
sixteen inches below the level of the creek at the nearest point, and<lb/>
the one above about eight. Since the success of the greater part of<lb/>
the drainage undertaking would be dependent upon lowering the level of<lb/>
the water in Waqua Creek a particular investigation was made of its<lb/>
channel for some distance through the community. This was found to be<lb/>
very much obstructed with numerous collections of logs and other foreign<lb/>
matter also by trees and brush growing in the edges of the water. Fre-<lb/>
quent soundings were made of the depth of the water and also of the<lb/>
loose sediment in the bottom of the channel. This developed: (a) that<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f03040015"/>
- 14 -<lb/>
the level of the water in Waqua Creek through the bottoms adjacent to<lb/>
Kress had doubtless been raised more from artificial than from natu-<lb/>
ral causes; (b) that provided the obstructions could be removed the<lb/>
channel would doubtless scour clean either gradually or under the<lb/>
first influx of flood water; and (c) that consequently the level might<lb/>
be lowered sufficiently, at a small cost, to make the entire drainage<lb/>
undertaking an economic possibility.</p>
<p>Comparative Elevations of Water Level (W.L.) Waqua Creek.</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="6">
<row>
<cell>Sta.</cell><cell>Location</cell><cell>Elev.</cell><cell>Dis.</cell><cell>Fall</cell><cell>Grade</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>A</cell><cell>W.L.-Upper end of Marsh#2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>B</cell><cell>W.L.-Bend at R. R. Bridge</cell><cell>-.4</cell><cell>600</cell><cell>.4</cell><cell>.66%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>C</cell><cell>W.L.-Lower end of Marsh#2</cell><cell>-.7</cell><cell>375</cell><cell>.3</cell><cell>.8%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>D</cell><cell>W.L.-Upper end of Marsh#1</cell><cell>-.8</cell><cell>600</cell><cell>.1</cell><cell>.16+%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>E</cell><cell>W.L.-Lower end of Marsh#1</cell><cell>-1.2</cell><cell>1350</cell><cell>.4</cell><cell>.3%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>F</cell><cell>W.L.-Road Crossing (Bridge)</cell><cell>-2.</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>.8</cell><cell>.6+%</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>G</cell><cell>W.L.-Rock Ledge</cell><cell>-4.1</cell><cell>2000</cell><cell>2.1</cell><cell>1.+%</cell></row></table></p>
<p><hi>Drainage Operations</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Cleaning and Training of Creek Channels and New Ditching</hi></p>
<p>Actual drainage work was started on April 23rd when a force of<lb/>
men were put at cleaning the onstructions from the channel of Waqua<lb/>
Creek. The remains of the old dam were removed and the work continued<lb/>
from that point on to beyond the upper end of the upper marsh. In addi-<lb/>
tion to removing the logs and other foreign matter from the channel the<lb/>
trees and brush were cut away from either side and in a few instances<lb/>
extra accumulations of sediment were shoveled out. Almost before this<lb/>
work was completed the hoped for result was accomplished through the<lb/>
agency of an opportune freshet. After the flood had subsided it was<lb/>
found that the normal level of the creek water through the bottoms<lb/>
had been lowered an average of about twelve inches or eight inches<lb/>
through the upper bottom and sixteen through the lower.</p>
<pb n="16" id="f03040016"/>
<p>- 15 -</p>
<p>For the drainage of the upper marsh two ditches were dug. One,<lb/>
the main ditch, was made to extend from the creek above the railroad<lb/>
bridge parallel with the fill and about fifty feet from it, around to<lb/>
the culvert, which was then cleaned out and the old ditch opened from<lb/>
it to the creek at the lower corner of the bottom. This ditch which<lb/>
was made about fourteen inches deep passes through the rob-pond on the<lb/>
upper side of the fill and drains it almost dry. One lateral was ex-<lb/>
tended from the main ditch for about one hundred feet into the marsh,<lb/>
Below the fill another short lateral was cut to drain the small marsh<lb/>
No. 3.</p>
<p>The bottom of the rob-pond below the fill was still some eight<lb/>
inches below the reduced level of the creek, however, a ditch was opened<lb/>
from it to the channel at the nearest point and about twelve inches of<lb/>
the water drawn off.</p>
<p>For the drainage of the upper end of the large marsh (No. 1) and<lb/>
also to carry the water from the overflow of the saw-mill pond above<lb/>
and prevent its continued activity, a main ditch was cut from the cul-<lb/>
vert under the railroad at No. 7 direct to the creek a distance of<lb/>
630 feet. Areas #6, #7 and #8 were all drained by laterals to this main<lb/>
ditch. Near the lower end of the large marsh another main ditch about<lb/>
400 feet long was cut across the bottom to the creek and into it at the<lb/>
upper end, by a &ldquo;Y&rdquo; system of smaller ditches, was collected the water<lb/>
coming from the overflow of the box-mill pond and the small stream<lb/>
back of the negro quarters. In this manner the tributary streams were<lb/>
carried through to the creek and their continued activity in the main-<lb/>
tenance of the large marsh stopped.</p>
<p>Above the railroad the channel of the small stream feeding the<lb/>
saw-mill pond was cleaned and trained both below the dam and for some<lb/>
two hundred feet above the head of the pond. The three lateral spring<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f03040017"/>
- 16 -<lb/>
branches emptying near the head of the pond were also re-ditched to<lb/>
their heads and the breeding places in their vicinities destroyed. The<lb/>
spring branch feeding the box-mill pond was collected into a <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
practically straight ditch leading from the spring at its head to the<lb/>
head of the pond and from the overflow to the railroad culvert below.<lb/>
The channel of the branch behind the negro quarters was also ditched<lb/>
from the spring down and the remaining small marsh just above the<lb/>
railroad drained.</p>
<p><hi>Treatment of Ponds</hi>.</p>
<p>Since the two ponds located respectively near the two mills could<lb/>
not be destroyed on account of their economic connections with the<lb/>
plant and the remainder of the rob-pond below the railroad could not be<lb/>
drained it became necessary to treat them by a different method in<lb/>
order to render them possible non-factors in mosquito production. Tak-<lb/>
ing advantage of a time when the saw-mill was idle owing to a shortage<lb/>
of logs the saw-mill pond was lowered two feet over night and the next day<lb/>
the entire force working completed the job of cutting out and removing<lb/>
the thick tangle of brush and undergrowth from the upper end. To allow<lb/>
for a coontemplated elevation of the water level of the pond, the shore<lb/>
lines were also thoroughly cleaned of vegetation for a distance of about<lb/>
eight feet back <del><unclear>with</unclear></del> from the normal water line. Following this the<lb/>
dam was reconstructed with a flood-gate which provided for the water<lb/>
level being raised and lowered from time to time in order to prevent<lb/>
the subsequent growth of vegetation around the edges.</p>
<p>The water in the box-mill was also lowered and the <del><unclear>ranks</unclear></del> rank<lb/>
growths of cat-tails and other vegetation completely removed from the<lb/>
body of the pond and around the edges. In order to protect the edges<lb/>
and prevent the growth of vegetation a board wall was constructed around<lb/>
a considerable portion of this pond and dirt fills made behind. The<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f03040018"/>
- 17 -<lb/>
remainder of the rob-pond was cleaned in a similar manner but noth-<lb/>
ing was done to maintain the improvement since the Railroad Company<lb/>
contemplated filling it in the near future. By this system of clean-<lb/>
ing so as to give the small fish free access to any parts of the<lb/>
ponds and by providing for unobstructed wave action on the surface it<lb/>
is hoped anopheles production may be controlled.</p>
<p>For more detailed information as to the extent and cost of<lb/>
the drainage operations at Kress the following tables are appended:</p>
<p>Cleaning and Training of Creek Channels.</p>
<p>
<table rows="9" cols="6">
<row>
<cell>Name of stream</cell><cell>Av.<lb/>
width</cell><cell>Av.<lb/>
depth</cell><cell>Dis.<lb/>
worked</cell><cell>Av. cost<lb/>
per ft.</cell><cell>Total</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Waqua Creek</cell><cell>10 ft.</cell><cell>2 ft.</cell><cell>6650</cell><cell>$0.0108</cell><cell>$72.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Saw-Mill Branch (Below)</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>225</cell><cell>.0266</cell><cell>6.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Saw-Mill Branch (Above)</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>4.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Box-Mill Branch (Below)</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6 in.</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>2.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Box-Mill Branch (Above)</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>300</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>6.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Branch behind N.Quarters</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>350</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>7.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Totals</cell><cell>7825</cell><cell>$97.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></p>
<p>Treatment of Ponds</p>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="5">
<row>
<cell>Name of pond</cell><cell>No. acres<lb/>
covered</cell><cell>sq.yds.veg.<lb/>
removed</cell><cell>No.ft.shore<lb/>
cleaned</cell><cell>Total<lb/>
cost.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Saw Mill</cell><cell>1 - 1/2</cell><cell>2400</cell><cell>700</cell><cell>$45.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Box-Mill</cell><cell>1/2</cell><cell>250</cell><cell>225</cell><cell>25.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Rob-Pond</cell><cell>1/4</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>9.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>---------</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>------</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Totals</cell><cell>2 - 1/4</cell><cell>2750</cell><cell>1075</cell><cell>$79.00</cell></row></table></p>
<pb n="19" id="f03040019"/>
<p>- 18 -</p>
<p>New Ditches.</p>
<p>
<table rows="20" cols="7">
<row>
<cell>From</cell><cell>To</cell><cell>Length</cell><cell>Av.<lb/>
width</cell><cell>Av.<lb/>
depth</cell><cell>Av.cost<lb/>
per ft.</cell><cell>Total<lb/>
cost.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Creek Above</cell><cell>Culvert</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>R.R.Bridge</cell><cell>under R.R.</cell><cell>350 ft.</cell><cell>2 ft.</cell><cell>14 in.</cell><cell>$0.055</cell><cell>$19.25</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Marsh#2</cell><cell>Main ditch</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>1-1/2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>.0375</cell><cell>3.75</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Rob-pond#4</cell><cell>Creek</cell><cell>75</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>.06</cell><cell>4.50</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Marsh#3</cell><cell>Main Ditch</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1-1/2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>.0375</cell><cell>1.87</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Culvert</cell><cell>Creek</cell><cell>250</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>.0575</cell><cell>14.37</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Seepage outcrop</cell><cell>Creek</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>1-1/2</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>.055</cell><cell>11.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Culvert(#7)</cell><cell>Creek</cell><cell>630</cell><cell>2-1/2</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>.065</cell><cell>40.95</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Marsh #6</cell><cell>Main ditch</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>2.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Marsh #7</cell><cell>Main ditch</cell><cell>300</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>.0225</cell><cell>6.75</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Culvert (#8)</cell><cell>Main ditch</cell><cell>225</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>.0575</cell><cell>12.93</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Spring (#10)</cell><cell>Pond</cell><cell>250</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>5.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Spring (#11)</cell><cell>Pond</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>2.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Spring (#12)</cell><cell>Pond</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>.02</cell><cell>4.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Edge Marsh #1</cell><cell>Creek</cell><cell>400</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>.055</cell><cell>22.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Culvert (#13)</cell><cell>Main ditch</cell><cell>250</cell><cell>1-1/2</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>.05</cell><cell>12.50</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Culvert (#15)</cell><cell>Main ditch</cell><cell>250</cell><cell>1-12</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>.05</cell><cell>12.50</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>----</cell><cell>------------</cell><cell>--------------------</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Totals</cell><cell>3630</cell><cell>1-9/16</cell><cell>16-3/4</cell><cell>.0483+$175.37</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></p>
<p>Oiling</p>
<p>Five oil drip-cans were installed on frames over streams and ditches<lb/>
nearer the village as follows:</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="6">
<row>
<cell>Location</cell><cell>First<lb/>
cost</cell><cell>No.gal.oil<lb/>
per week.</cell><cell>No.ft.stream<lb/>
oiled</cell><cell>No. weeks<lb/>
operated.</cell><cell>Total<lb/>
cost.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Spring B #10</cell><cell>$1.50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>$2.82</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Spring B #11</cell><cell>1.50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2.82</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Spring B #12</cell><cell>1.50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2.82</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Spring B #14</cell><cell>1.50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>300</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2.82</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Spring B #16</cell><cell>1.50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>350</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2.82</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>---------</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-----</cell><cell>-------</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Totals</cell><cell>$7.60</cell><cell>1150</cell><cell>$14.10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></p>
<p>Note: The oil drip-cans were installed near the completion of the work<lb/>
the latter part of June and the above estimates are based upon the re-<lb/>
commendations made to the management for their maintenance.</p>
<pb n="20" id="f03040020"/>
<p>- 19 -</p>
<p><del><unclear>screen</unclear></del></p>
<p><hi>Screening of Houses</hi>.</p>
<p>Owing to the uncertainty of any future effective drainage, apparent<lb/>
at the time of the malaria survey, thorough screening of all houses was<lb/>
made the chief recommendation for malaria control in Kress Community.</p>
<p>Consequently, prior to the beginning of constructive work April 2nd,<lb/>
1917, sufficient quantities of all materials had already been procured.<lb/>
These included only the best grades of #16 Galvanoid Screen Wire Cloth<lb/>
and hardware comprising door and window brackets, door fixtures, tacks,<lb/>
nails, etc., and lumber for framing and moulding. With the beginning<lb/>
of the actual campaign this branch of the work was places under the direct<lb/>
supervision of Mr. W. G. Cline who had had previous experience in the<lb/>
supervision of similar work at Wilson, Va. For practically all the<lb/>
houses one general type of construction was applied and is as follows:</p>
<p><hi>Windows</hi>: The screen frames were made to cover the entire opening<lb/>
of the windows fitting perfectly in the window frames just outside the<lb/>
sash. These were made of selected and thoroughly seasoned one by two<lb/>
inch pine strips and were strengthened at the four corners by iron<lb/>
bracketts attached with screws. After the frame had been fitted to the<lb/>
window it was taken out and a sheet of the screen wire out to the proper<lb/>
size was stretched and tacked securely over it after which the raw edges<lb/>
of the wire and tack heads all the way around were covered with strips<lb/>
of 3/4 in. half round moulding. When completed these frames were in-<lb/>
serted in the windows and held in position by nails or screws. For the<lb/>
colored homes and one white home in the community no frames were used<lb/>
the wire being tacked to the outside of the window frames and after-<lb/>
wards covered with moulding strips.</p>
<pb n="21" id="f03040021"/>
<p>- 20 -</p>
<p><hi>Doors</hi>: Owing to the general inferiority of the machine made types<lb/>
for mosquito protection, all doors for this work were made by hand. For<lb/>
the upright sides of the frames carefully selected and thoroughly sea-<lb/>
soned one by four inch pine pieces were used. The pieces across the top<lb/>
bottom and middle portion were made <del>by</del><add>of</add> one by fives. After the different<lb/>
pieces were fitted and nailed in the proper position four heavy iron<lb/>
brackets were attached at the corners and two iron braces at the ends<lb/>
of the middle support. The screen wire was then attached in the same<lb/>
manner as described for the windows. In fitting the doors in the door<lb/>
frames they were made to fit snugly against stops all the way around<lb/>
on the inside so that about a quarter inch space could be allowed around<lb/>
between the edges of the door and the frame for swelling in wet weather.<lb/>
To insure the doors closing the long coiled springs were used instead<lb/>
of springs in the hinges.</p>
<p><hi>Porches</hi>: The frames for these were made of one by two inch pine<lb/>
strips run horizontally around the exposed sides a sufficient distance<lb/>
apart to fit for supports of the edges of whatever width of wire was<lb/>
used. Ordinarily these were three strips of 30 in. stretched horizon-<lb/>
tally. The frames for the doors in the front walls were made of one by<lb/>
three inch pieces, two placed upright <del><unclear>on</unclear></del> the proper distance apart for<lb/>
the width of the door and a short piece across between the two to fit<lb/>
for the top of the door. The strips of wire were stretched ordinarily<lb/>
from the back walls at either end of the porch around to the sides of<lb/>
the door frame in the front wall, drawn as tight as possible and nailed<lb/>
securely at the ends and along the edges with tacks placed about every<lb/>
three inches. The strips of wire were always cut a few inches longer than<lb/>
the distance measured in order to allow for a hand hold for stretching<lb/>
while the last end was being nailed. After the screen wire was all<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="f03040022"/>
- 21 -<lb/>
attached, all the edges, seams and ends were covered on the outside with<lb/>
moulding strips as in the doors and windows, except at the bottom where<lb/>
a one by six inch base-board was provided. When completed the cracks be-<lb/>
tween the weather boarding and the screen frames and others were filled<lb/>
with paper pulp made from old newspapers. Of the thirty two homes twenty<lb/>
nine were screened. In addition to the doors and windows fourteen of<lb/>
these included front porches and three both front and back porches, as<lb/>
follows:</p>
<p><hi>Itemized Table of Screening Expenditures.</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="35" cols="9">
<row>
<cell>House<lb/>
No.</cell><cell>No.<lb/>
porches</cell><cell>No.<lb/>
windows</cell><cell>No.<lb/>
doors</cell><cell>Cost of<lb/>
wire</cell><cell>Cost of<lb/>
lumber</cell><cell>Cost of<lb/>
hardware</cell><cell>Cost of<lb/>
labor</cell><cell>Total<lb/>
costa.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>$15.26</cell><cell>$6.00</cell><cell>$2.54</cell><cell>$8.40</cell><cell>$32.20</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>17.22</cell><cell>6.50</cell><cell>2.64</cell><cell>8.40</cell><cell>34.76</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15.40</cell><cell>5.75</cell><cell>2.29</cell><cell>8.40</cell><cell>31.84</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>16.34</cell><cell>5.80</cell><cell>2.14</cell><cell>11.20</cell><cell>35.48</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15.89</cell><cell>4.50</cell><cell>2.64</cell><cell>11.20</cell><cell>34.23</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4.83</cell><cell>3.00</cell><cell>2.46</cell><cell>5.60</cell><cell>15.89</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>7</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4.34</cell><cell>2.70</cell><cell>2.26</cell><cell>5.60</cell><cell>14.90</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>8</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4.34</cell><cell>2.70</cell><cell>2.26</cell><cell>5.60</cell><cell>14.90</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4.83</cell><cell>3.00</cell><cell>2.46</cell><cell>5.60</cell><cell>15.89</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>10</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>11.13</cell><cell>3.95</cell><cell>2.21</cell><cell>7.00</cell><cell>24.29</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>11</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10.57</cell><cell>4.10</cell><cell>2.31</cell><cell>7.00</cell><cell>23.98</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>12</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9.62</cell><cell>3.85</cell><cell>1.99</cell><cell>7.00</cell><cell>22.46</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>13</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9.62</cell><cell>3.85</cell><cell>1.99</cell><cell>7.00</cell><cell>22.46</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>14</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>9.62</cell><cell>3.85</cell><cell>1.99</cell><cell>7.00</cell><cell>22.46</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>15</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>22.22</cell><cell>6.90</cell><cell>2.69</cell><cell>14.00</cell><cell>45.81</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>16</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>16.34</cell><cell>6.00</cell><cell>2.44</cell><cell>8.40</cell><cell>33.18</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>17</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>21.17</cell><cell>5.85</cell><cell>1.59</cell><cell>11.20</cell><cell>39.81</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>18</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>15.40</cell><cell>4.35</cell><cell>2.46</cell><cell>7.00</cell><cell>29.21</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>19</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>15.40</cell><cell>4.35</cell><cell>2.46</cell><cell>7.00</cell><cell>29.21</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>20</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>15.40</cell><cell>4.35</cell><cell>2.46</cell><cell>7.00</cell><cell>29.21</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>21</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>17.64</cell><cell>6.80</cell><cell>3.01</cell><cell>11.20</cell><cell>38.65</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>22</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3.85</cell><cell>1.95</cell><cell>2.21</cell><cell>2.80</cell><cell>10.81</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>23 (Store)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>.60</cell><cell>.75</cell><cell>1.81</cell><cell>2.80</cell><cell>5.96</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>24</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4.41</cell><cell>2.75</cell><cell>2.27</cell><cell>4.20</cell><cell>13.63</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>25</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2.97</cell><cell>1.40</cell><cell>1.27</cell><cell>2.80</cell><cell>8.44</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>26</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3.95</cell><cell>1.30</cell><cell>1.91</cell><cell>2.80</cell><cell>9.96</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>27</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3.95</cell><cell>1.30</cell><cell>1.71</cell><cell>2.80</cell><cell>9.76</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>28</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3.95</cell><cell>1.30</cell><cell>1.71</cell><cell>2.80</cell><cell>9.76</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>29</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1.57</cell><cell>.45</cell><cell>.67</cell><cell>1.40</cell><cell>4.09</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1.57</cell><cell>.45</cell><cell>.67</cell><cell>1.40</cell><cell>4.09</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>31 (Church)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4.93</cell><cell><unclear>2</unclear>.20</cell><cell>1.59</cell><cell>5.60</cell><cell>14.32</cell></row>
<row><cell>------------------------------------------------------------------------</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Totals</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>186</cell><cell>73</cell><cell>$304.33</cell><cell>$112.00</cell><cell>$65.11</cell><cell>$200.20</cell><cell>$681.64</cell></row></table></p>
<p>Note: The cost of screen wire was $3.50 per 100 sq. ft.</p>
<pb n="23" id="f03040023"/>
<p>- 22 -</p>
<p><hi>Quinine Treatment</hi>.</p>
<p>During the winter of 1916-17 supplies of quinine were procured by<lb/>
the F. J. Kress Company for all of their employees at Kress who had suffered<lb/>
with malaria during the previous season. These treatments were pretty<lb/>
generally taken and continued throughout the greater part <del><unclear>of</unclear></del> of the winter<lb/>
especially by the infected persons living in the town. All of this was<lb/>
under the direction of Dr. R. H. Manson, resident physician.</p>
<p><hi>Educational Measures</hi>.</p>
<p>Prior to <del><unclear>in</unclear></del> and during the course of the campaign a number of<lb/>
educational lectures were given in the community. Two, in particular<lb/>
on the causes and methods of prevention of malaria, were given by<lb/>
Dr. W. A. Brumfield and one on general sanitation by Dr. Roy K. Flannagan<lb/>
both of the State Board of Health. Bulletins on Malaria and other pub-<lb/>
lic health topics were also distributed.</p>
<p><hi>Sanitary Improvements</hi>.</p>
<p>In addition to the malaria control work other sanitary im-<lb/>
provements were made in the community. Sanitary pit privies were in-<lb/>
stalled at each of the homes and mills and certain improvements were<lb/>
made to the wells to protect them from possible contamination. Also<lb/>
in this connection free examination was made by the State Board of Health<lb/>
of all persons in the community for intestinal parasites, and free treat-<lb/>
ment given to all positive cases.</p>
<p><hi>SUMMARY</hi>.</p>
<p>A complete campaign for the control of malaria together with<lb/>
some additional sanitary improvements was executed at Kewss, Va., from<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f03040024"/>
-23-<lb/>
April first to June thirtieth 1917. The measures applied comprised the<lb/>
elimination of breeding places of mosquitoes through drainage and oiling;<lb/>
the protection of homes through screening; and, treatment of &ldquo;carriers&rdquo;<lb/>
and general immunization with quinine. The total expenditures made  in<lb/>
the different branches of the work are as follows:</p>
<p>Drainage Operations</p>
<p>
<table rows="13" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>1 - Cleaning and Training of Creek Channels</cell><cell>$97.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2 - Tratment of Ponds</cell><cell>79.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3 - New Ditches</cell><cell>175.37</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>------------</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>$351.37</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Oiling</cell><cell>$14.10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>$14.10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Screening</cell><cell>681.84</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>681.84</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Direction of Campaign</cell><cell>400.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>400.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>---------------------------------------------------------------</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total Expenditures for entire Campaign</cell><cell>$1,447.11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></p>
<p><hi>RESULTS</hi></p>
<p>Based upon a recent letter received from Supt. A. B. McNeill at<lb/>
Kress, it is with pleasure that report can be made that for the past<lb/>
sason the results of the anti-malaria campaign at Kress have been very<lb/>
satisfactory. Mr. McNeill writes as follows: &ldquo;We have had no further<lb/>
chills in Kress since the completion of the work. Last year labor was<lb/>
plentiful but in spite of that we lost considerable time and during<lb/>
August and September some of our machines were almost always idle due<lb/>
to malaria. This year, in spite of the scarcity of labor, we have been<lb/>
running full force and no machines have been idle and no time has been<lb/>
lost <unclear>#######</unclear> &ldquo;It all goes to show what may be accomplished by the appli-<lb/>
cation of some well directed energy and well invested dollars&rdquo;.</p>
<pb n="25" id="f03040025"/>
<p>-24-</p>
<p>Comparison of Actieve Malaria Cases 1916 and 1917.</p>
<p>No. Cases.</p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="6">
<row>
<cell>Year</cell><cell>June</cell><cell>July</cell><cell>August</cell><cell>September</cell><cell>October</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1916</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>3</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1917</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table></p>
<p><hi>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</hi>.</p>
<p>As a conclusion of this report the author wishes to make the<lb/>
following acknowledgements:</p>
<p>To the F. J. Kress Box Co., for their expressed confidence in the<lb/>
direction of the work.</p>
<p>To the Seaboard Air Line Railway Company for their active<lb/>
cooperation.</p>
<p>To Supt. A. P. McNeill for his most indispensable interest and<lb/>
active cooperation, through the exertion of which much more effective<lb/>
measures were attained than could have otherwise been accomplished.</p>
<p>To Dr. R. H. Manson for his active participation in the campaign,<lb/>
and invaluable influence exerted for the best interests of its success.</p>
<p>To the people of Kress for the unusual and highly satisfactory<lb/>
degree of personal interest and co-operation extended, and the confi-<lb/>
dence expressed by the unqualified application of the measures recom-<lb/>
mended. To such is due the success of any measures for Public Health.</p>
<p>Submitted December 15th, 1917,<lb/>
to the State Board of Health.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(signed) Herman W. Snidow,<lb/>
Director</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
