<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03059045">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, November 2, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03059045</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-11-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-11-02">November 2, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03059045</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, November 2, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses funding and the use of fish in breeding areas. He lists the people in charge of various locations, and has hopes of soon eliminating yellow fever on the coast.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-11-02">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, November 2, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03059045"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
---<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
----<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.<lb/>
<date value="1921-11-02">November 2, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Wicliffe Rose, General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York City.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you for your letter of September 30th, in regard to<lb/>
large chart on the &ldquo;Campana Sanitaria contra la Fiebre Amarill en el Peru&rdquo;.<lb/>
Sr. Burga Cianeros was very much pleased at receiving this evidence of your<lb/>
approval, and remarked that in as much as you liked that &ldquo;we would get up<lb/>
something really good for final report of the year&rdquo;. I thought the chart<lb/>
very good but he is capable of better still. Our next one will be more of<lb/>
a practicable graphic report of work and conditions.</p>
<p>We shall be very glad to have any suggestions in regard to any special<lb/>
feature which you would like to have brought out.</p>
<p>For your convenience and information I enclose copies of the translation<lb/>
made for Sr. Burga.</p>
<p>Yesterday I received the following cablegram:</p>
<p>XAXADIDUKS BUAJPPAEXJ HAEXDEATEJ POVYNCIPUB AUNOSPFIZR</p>
<p>U</p>
<p>IBOOWIMWOR GESTCYLUMH HACIJTHESE YMOUWPFIZR GAIRZRAJEF<lb/>
ULHYDOFSOB.</p>
<p>There are evidently several errors in transmission in this message.<lb/>
After consulting the table on errors, I deciphered the message to read as follows:</p>
<p>TELEGRAM RECEIVED AND CONTENTS NOTED. EQUITABLE BALANCE $5000, DEPOSITED<lb/>
TO DATE $60 000, BOARD APPROPRIATED $10 000, EACH FOR NOVEMBER AND<lb/>
DECEMBER. WILL DEPOSIT THESE WITH $10 000, DURING MONTH OF OCTOBER AS<lb/>
REQUIRED (ON) OCTOBER 25th THIS YEAR.</p>
<p>On the next steamer we will get a confirmation of this cable by mail<lb/>
from the Cable Office in Paita, and will be able to check up the errors, as the<lb/>
errors usually occur in the telegraph offices between here and Paita. In as much as<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03059046"/>
2. Dr. Wicliffe Rose, November 2, 1921.<lb/>
there will be a steamer from the north this week I did not think necessary to ask<lb/>
you to repeat a portion of the message. The part which I was most anxious to know<lb/>
seems perfectly clear in the message, viz., that there is a balance of $5000, at the<lb/>
end of October, which corresponds with what I thought there should be but I wanted<lb/>
to be certain. This $5000, has been deposited today, at a rate of 3.50 for the<lb/>
Peruvian pound, netting us Lp.1428.5.71.</p>
<p>Our expenses are gradually growing less, and will continue that way<lb/>
unless our uneasiness in regard to Lima and Callao are to be realized. Today a<lb/>
newspaper reporter has just come in with the information that he had seen a tele-<lb/>
gram stating that a Dr. Barton had announced a case of yellow fever in Callao.<lb/>
I immediately sent a telegram to the &ldquo;Salubridad&rdquo; asking for information. They<lb/>
have not sent any information so far. When I warned them some time ago to take<lb/>
precautionary measures with the stegomya they seemed to think that it was un-<lb/>
necessary, and suspended the work which they were doing there at the time. Also<lb/>
when I requested Dr. Quiroz to investigate other rumors, he went there to consult<lb/>
them about it and they belittled the importance of such investigations. As I am<lb/>
planning to go south on the next steamer, I shall continue to Lima to investigate<lb/>
personally, and come back to Huacho, Ancash and Trujillo later. This I hope is<lb/>
simply a wild rumor, but I dont like it, it is too nearly within the range of<lb/>
possibility as I indicated in my letter of September 3rd. I had extended the<lb/>
stegomya campaign to the south as rapidly as possible, and had it not been for the<lb/>
recent delay in the ship schedules by which we shipped our last batch of 35000<lb/>
fish we would at the present time be working practically up to the city limits of<lb/>
Lima and Callao. It seems to me the only safe thing to do is to carry the campaign<lb/>
into Lima and Callao and whatever other towns of importance in the vicinity. We<lb/>
can do that for the balance of the year with what you have appropriated and with<lb/>
what I have on hand.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03059047"/>
<p>3. Dr. Wicliffe Rose, November 17, 1921.</p>
<p>The first two pages of this letter were written in<lb/>
Chiclayo, and I intended to finsih the letter aboard in case I<lb/>
received any information about the case reported from Callao.<lb/>
No information was received on this case, and for that reason I<lb/>
have brought Dr. Mendoza with me to Lima, to take charge of the<lb/>
prophylactic campaign in the Valley of the Rimac. We hope to<lb/>
have work actively under way by the first of next week.</p>
<p>The stegomya index is high all along the coast as we<lb/>
advance towards the south, and I think that as long as we keep<lb/>
up the work in the north we should also continue an active cam-<lb/>
paign in Lima Callao and all the suburbs, where we find a high<lb/>
stegomya index. This is the time to make sure of the situation.<lb/>
If it were simply a matter of controlling the epidemic I should<lb/>
say that we could stop work anytime, but in as much as the object<lb/>
is the complete extirpation of the disease on this coast it is<lb/>
far wiser to extend the campaign as much as possible to all places<lb/>
where the stegomya breeding is high. Mr. Dunn is very much of the<lb/>
same opinion. He came in for a conference last night, and reported<lb/>
that they were finding about 52% of the houses breeding <add>in</add> the i<lb/>
the Chancay Valley (this is the valley which lies between Huacho<lb/>
and Lima) and in as much as there are several fairry large towns<lb/>
and haciendas it is much safer to clean all that up. We are doing<lb/>
so by our fish method. We can take care of this section compara-<lb/>
tively rapidly if we are able to secure the necessary amount of<lb/>
fish. At present we are meeting with difficulties on account of<lb/>
the shiftless lazy nature of the local fishermen, and also because<lb/>
they seem to think they can exploit the Campaign. Unless this<lb/>
changes I shall ship fish from, Chiclayo, Guadelupe and Paijan.<lb/>
At present we still have about 30 000, fish in Huacho, but when<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03059048"/>
4. Dr. Wicliffe Rose, November 17, 1921.<lb/>
start the big work in this section that will not be near enough<lb/>
for the first distribution. We will need about 100 000, more for<lb/>
this section, besides we will need several thousand more in the<lb/>
Department of Ancash to prevent the breeding from rising there<lb/>
again. In the Departments of Lambayeque and Libertad we can be-<lb/>
gin to let up a little on the fish distribution. From now on the<lb/>
work will consist principally of watching the situation. This w<lb/>
will enable me to reduce the staff there and bring them down this<lb/>
way. I rather anticipate a difficult campaign here, but we are<lb/>
preparing for that by starting a vigorous propaganda before we<lb/>
actually &ldquo;get a going&rdquo; with the mosquito work. We have been for-<lb/>
tunate in this respect by securing the whole hearted support of<lb/>
the El Comercio, which is the most substantial paper in the country<lb/>
although it is against the present Government. They have published<lb/>
both interviews and favourable editorials, commiting themselves to<lb/>
the cause.</p>
<p>I was very much surprised to receive a cablegram from<lb/>
Corrigan stating that he could come back and that I could fix<lb/>
the salary. I have offered him $450.00 permo and if he accepts<lb/>
I will have him continue the work on the coast where he was just<lb/>
before leaving; It will be a great help to me to have him as I<lb/>
will then be able to depend almost <unclear>entirely</unclear> on him for the work in<lb/>
Ancash and the northern section of the Department of Lima. I will<lb/>
need to give considerable personal attention to the work here and<lb/>
in Callao, as well as in the large estates in this province. As I<lb/>
see things at the present time this is the section which may have<lb/>
a lurking focus and naturally should be cleaned up. If we work this<lb/>
through the coming summer season, or until April as I have suggested<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03059049"/>
5. Dr Wicliffe Rose, November 17, 1921.<lb/>
we can then turn the work over to the Health Department for them<lb/>
to continue as they see fit. I do not think that it will be ne-<lb/>
cessary for the International Health Board to continue spending<lb/>
money on the yellow fever prophylaxis after that time, unless you<lb/>
prefer to have some official representative here for the sake of<lb/>
obtaining accurate in formation for a while longer. For this pur-<lb/>
pose either Dr. Ricardo Mendoza M., or Dr. Enrique Caballero, would<lb/>
be the best and most reliable.</p>
<p>In the enclosed copy of cable which I sent you I have<lb/>
devised code names for Chiclayo and Trujillo as well as for Corri-<lb/>
gan and am submitting the following in addition in case it shall<lb/>
be necessary to refer to them in future messages:</p>
<p>PIKIT- I. W. Pickett,<lb/>
E N M O L - L.H. Dunn, Entomologist<lb/>
C A B A L - Dr. Enr&iacute;que Caballero,<lb/>
M E N D O - Dr. Ricardo Mendoza,<lb/>
S A L U D - &ldquo;Direccion de Salubridad Publica&rdquo;, Lima.<lb/>
P I U R A - Department of Piura,<lb/>
L A M B Y - Department of Lambayeque,<lb/>
L I B A D - Department of Libertad<lb/>
L I M A D - Department of Lima,<lb/>
B U R G A - Sr. Alfredo Burga Cisneros, Statistician etc.,<lb/>
S U P E R - Supervising Inspector (s)<lb/>
C A V A S - Dr. Nicolas Cavassa, Province of Pacasmayo.</p>
<p>I have registered my cable address here in according with your<lb/>
instructions in the last cable.</p>
<p>I am leaving tomorrow for Trujillo and Chiclayo and may go to<lb/>
Paita before returning to Lima. Guayaquil feels a bit nervous about<lb/>
the mosquito index in Paita and in order to have accurate personal<lb/>
knowledge I shall make an inspection as soon as possible.</p>
<p>The S.S. Essequibo arrived from New York yesterday so I pre-<lb/>
sume that I will find some mail from you in the Chiclayo or the<lb/>
the Trujillo offices on my return.</p>
<p>For the immediate future the Campaign is organized as<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03059050"/>
6. Dr. Wicliffe Rose, November 17, 1921.<lb/>
follows:<lb/>
Department of Lambayeque,<lb/>
Dr. Victor Diez Canseco, Director in Charge and<lb/>
Executive for Department,<lb/>
Mr. M.M. Seeley, Supervising Inspector for Department,<lb/>
Department of Libertad,<lb/>
Dr. Luis G. Tapia, Director in Charge and<lb/>
Executive for Department,<lb/>
Sr. Manuel Machado &amp; E. Ramirez, Supervising Inspec-<lb/>
tors for Province of Trujillo,<lb/>
Province of Pacasmayo, Department of Libertad,<lb/>
Dr. Nicolas Cavassa, Director and Supervisor for<lb/>
Province.<lb/>
Sr. Juan E. Adrienzen, Supervising Inspector for<lb/>
Province.<lb/>
Department of Ancash,<lb/>
Dr. Enrique Caballero, Director and Executive for<lb/>
Department,<lb/>
Mr. J. P. Corrigan, Supervising Inspector for<lb/>
Department.<lb/>
Sr. Arturo Sainz, Assistant Supervising Inspector,<lb/>
Department of Lima,<lb/>
Dr. Ricardo Mendoza, Director and Executive for<lb/>
Department.<lb/>
Supervision of inspections in the<lb/>
Department of Lima will be under Mr.<lb/>
Corrigan who will be assisted by Mr.<lb/>
Geo. O. Richardson, who will be loaned<lb/>
for part time by the &ldquo;Salubridad&rdquo;<lb/>
Sr. Burga Cisneros will fill the functions of Chief Clerk,<lb/>
and will have charge of statistics and<lb/>
preparation of reports. He is also the<lb/>
principal draftsman of the Campaign.</p>
<p>The Main Central Office will be established in Lima for<lb/>
the balance of the campaign. The north is well organized with<lb/>
experienced employees, the mosquito index is everywhere down to<lb/>
about 1% and in many places even less. The greater part of my time<lb/>
will be needed to watch developements in this section, as at pre-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03059051"/>
7. Dr. Wicliffe Rose, November 17, 1921.<lb/>
sent I consider this the key to the final outcome, of success or<lb/>
failure, (I dont expect the latter) - of insuring the extirpation<lb/>
of the disease on this coast this year.</p>
<p>Mr. Dunn will begin his research work in our Lima Office<lb/>
We have been fortunate in securing rooms in the Building which<lb/>
has been assigned to the Department of Public Instruction, so we<lb/>
will have no office rent to pay here. Most of the furniture will<lb/>
be provided by the Government so our expenses of establishing<lb/>
here will be minor ones.</p>
<p>Up to date Mr. Dunn has done field work exclusively<lb/>
which I think is the best preparation he could have to get ideas<lb/>
on what we want in this particular line of investigation.</p>
<p>In connection with this work I would appreciate hearing<lb/>
what you consider a justifiable expense, or how much of this work<lb/>
you consider of value to the International Health Board. We will<lb/>
have to be guided by this in the amount of work we put on the<lb/>
final report which we are preparing. Sr. Burga has gotten up a<lb/>
very complete and interesting book on the Department of Lambay-<lb/>
eque which we will send you with the final report. The trouble with<lb/>
this however is that it can not be duplicated except at consider-<lb/>
able expense. It is about five times the size of the one he got up<lb/>
for Dr. White and contains infinitely more data and valuable infor-<lb/>
mation. I am enclosing a blueprint of a chart which we got out on<lb/>
the relationship of the mosquito-index to the case rate. The line<lb/>
(or curve) showing the fish distribution gives the total distri-<lb/>
buted up to the end of July, from that time on it shown the daily<lb/>
distribution, each point indicating the number distributed that day.</p>
<p>Awaiting your further instructions in connection with<lb/>
our work, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson,</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
