<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03055001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to Lunsford D. Fricks, October 21, 1920</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Griffitts, T.H.D.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03055001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1920-10-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Fricks, Lunsford D.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Badin (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1920-10-21">October 21, 1920</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03055001</idno>
<title>Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to Lunsford D. Fricks, October 21, 1920</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Griffitts writes about the anopheles survey at Badin, North Carolina.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1920-10-21">
<head>Letter from T.H.D. Griffitts to Lunsford D. Fricks, October 21, 1920</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03055001"/>
<opener>
<hi>COPY</hi><lb/>
Health Survey<lb/>
Reporting Survey Reservoir,<lb/>
Tallassee Power Co., Badin, N. C.<lb/>
<dateline>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Norfolk, Va.,<lb/>
<date value="1920-10-21">October 21, 1920.</date>
</dateline>
Surgeon L. D. Fricks,<lb/>
Medical Officer in Charge,<lb/>
Malaria Investigations,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Memphis, Tennessee.<lb/>
Griffitts<lb/>
1920<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In compliance with instructions in your letter of October 1,<lb/>
1920, I spent October 4th, 5th and 6th, making a survey of Anopheles<lb/>
conditions on and near the lake of the Tallassee Power Company at<lb/>
Badin, North Carolina.</p>
<p>It is quite obvious that an examination of conditions made at<lb/>
this time - there has been light frost and the nights for ten days or<lb/>
more have been cool - cannot well be compared with that of 1919, when<lb/>
the examination was made during the 4th week of August. However, two<lb/>
apparent changes in this body of water in general have taken place<lb/>
which should have effected a reduction in Anopheles production, the<lb/>
present season - (a) a lessened amount of floatage, and (b) a decided<lb/>
increase in the number of minnows (<hi>gambusia affinis</hi>) destructive to<lb/>
mosquito larvae. Very few gambusia were observed in the lake last year,<lb/>
but in addition to the natural increase, the Company, after the inspec-<lb/>
tion of last year, established a minnow hatchery and from this they have<lb/>
been able to add large numbers to the reservoir this season. The follow-<lb/>
ing observations during the survey October 4th - 6th are taken from<lb/>
field notes:</p>
<p>A.</p>
<p>1. Oct. 4th. <hi>Beaver Dam Creek</hi>. Examined the bight south of Ferry<lb/>
(#. side near Roe Hall's), near lumber pile. In 25 dips collected 7<lb/>
large A. larvae and 1 A. pupa. In Hall's barn near, 8 Anopheles quad.<lb/>
and in his house 6 Anopheles quad. (Note: last year, Aug. 21, 32 A. Q.<lb/>
in this house). One child sick now, said to be malaria. Hall states<lb/>
all of family (7) had malaria this year.</p>
<p><unclear>P+</unclear></p>
<p>2. Meadow in front of P. P. Elliott's and just east of Roe Hall,<lb/>
breeding A. <unclear>11</unclear> in small pools and hoof prints. At head of bight of lake<lb/>
this area drains into breeding A <unclear>11</unclear>.</p>
<p><unclear>L+</unclear></p>
<p>3. Swamp in pasture between D. M. Elliott and L. F. Hinson, A.<unclear>111</unclear><lb/>
breeding. Caught 3 Anopheles punct. on wall of spring nearby. (Hatching<lb/>
from this area last year 100% Anopheles puncts.) Hinson's hog shed<lb/>
near - 6 Anopheles quads. and 6 Anopheles puncts. This within one-<lb/>
half mile of bight of lake nearest J. C. Elliott's.</p>
<p><unclear>L+</unclear></p>
<p>4. J. C. Elliott's claim to have all had malaria this summer.<lb/>
Did not examine house for Anopheles but in stable found 6 Anopheles<lb/>
quads., and 6 A. punct. Dipped from spring branch near J. C. Elliott's<lb/>
<unclear>L+</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>REP</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03055002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
house A<unclear>11</unclear>. In bight of lake one-quarter of mile from J.E.E. house<lb/>
A <unclear>11</unclear>. Dead trees standing in this bight and much floatage, especially<lb/>
pinebark. Minnows (gambusia affinis) in considerable numbers observed<lb/>
here.</p>
<p><unclear>P+</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>+</unclear></p>
<p>5. Oct. 5th. <hi>Glady Fork</hi>. (Near J. F. Hamilton place) House<lb/>
(now vacant) one-quarter mile away. Breeding of Anopheles in bight-<lb/>
A <unclear></unclear> all sizes and pupae. Standing dead trees and brush and much<lb/>
debris and floatage in places. No Anopheles images found in any of<lb/>
the vacant houses.</p>
<p><unclear>P+</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>+</unclear></p>
<p>6. N. M. Thayer (or Hamilton) Place. Bight of Glady Fork<lb/>
near big sawdust pile. Recent rains (5 days before) have carried<lb/>
down much debris to head of bight, and here breeding A <unclear>;;;</unclear>. A branch<lb/>
enters here, and it is probable some, at least, of the larvae were<lb/>
washed down into the pond. This collection, then, should show a high<lb/>
percentage of Anopheles punctipennis. Along the shoreline near the<lb/>
pile of sawdust only light breeding.</p>
<p><unclear>P+?</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>+</unclear></p>
<p>7. <hi>Rocky Creek</hi>. On G. W. Henderson place. Swiftly flowing<lb/>
stream, scoured by rain by days ago. No breeding found. A;<unclear>;</unclear> in<lb/>
drift and floatage at head of bight where this stream enters pond.<lb/>
Top minnows numerous here.</p>
<p>8. <hi>Glady Fork</hi>. In front of W. R. Russell's (G. W. Henderson's<lb/>
place) Anopheles breeding in fair number where not recently washed<lb/>
out.</p>
<p><unclear>V</unclear></p>
<p>9. Virgil Coggins's place. Pools in hog lot near house<lb/>
breeding Anopheles profusely (A <unclear>;;;</unclear>) In mule stall 4 Anopheles quads.<lb/>
in cow shed 5 Anopheles punct., one Anopheles quad., Coggins says<lb/>
he has lived here all his life and never had &ldquo;chills&rdquo; until two years<lb/>
ago. His boy had &ldquo;chills&rdquo; in 1912.</p>
<p><del><unclear>L+<lb/>
L+<lb/>
?</unclear></del></p>
<p><unclear>)V</unclear></p>
<p>10. <hi>Roby Coggins</hi>. Near head of Beaver Dam Creek, east side.<lb/>
Extensive flat area of pond, shallow water, growth of bulrushes. Out<lb/>
of 40 dips in selected places, only one Anopheles larvae. At spring<lb/>
nearby A <unclear>;;;</unclear> as many as 10 at a dip. This latter place not connected<lb/>
with reservoir.</p>
<p><unclear>P-</unclear><lb/>
4P<lb/>
9<lb/>
<unclear>nis</unclear> <unclear>I</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>)V</unclear></p>
<p>11. At abandoned road on Barne's place, near head of bight<lb/>
of lake (1/4 mile north of &ldquo;10&rdquo; in floatage, anopheles -- and pupae,<lb/>
300 feet above this are overflow pools in which breeding of anopheles<lb/>
<unclear>;;</unclear>. This latter not connected with lake. Valley above flat. Sub-<lb/>
ject to overflow and potential anopheles area.</p>
<p><unclear>P+</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>L+</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>P</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>V+</unclear></p>
<p>12. <hi>Alexander Coggins' Place</hi>. Mr. Coggins says he now has<lb/>
malaria. Three bed rooms searched and found one anopheles quad. None<lb/>
in stables.</p>
<p>13. &ldquo;<hi>Bully&rdquo; Hopkins' Place</hi>. No Anopheles found. Fresh water<lb/>
head of bight, near Hopkins breeding of Anopheles in fair numbers;<lb/>
in dead water below wagon bridge same degree of Anopheles breeding.</p>
<p><unclear>P+<lb/>
L+</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>+</unclear></p>
<pb n="3" id="f03055003"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>14. E. J. (Quillan) Elliott. In house, four Anopheles quad.,<lb/>
in barn one A. punct. Spring and branch near breeding Anopheles freely.<lb/>
Pool at old saw-mill place, negative. Oil on the water here. Bight<lb/>
with much standing timber, log jam, debris and floatage near new sheep<lb/>
pasture fence and within one-half mile of E. J. Elliott's breeding very<lb/>
freely (A<unclear>;;</unclear>), and an important place.</p>
<p><unclear>P+<lb/>
L+</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>LX<lb/>
X</unclear></p>
<p>15. <hi>Whitney</hi>. Pool on W. side of railroad North of Southbound<lb/>
Ry. depot, breeding very freely (A <unclear>;;</unclear>), all sizes and pupae. This part<lb/>
of the pond was examined last year and is producing Anopheles in much<lb/>
greater numbers now.</p>
<p><unclear>P+</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>X</unclear></p>
<p>B.</p>
<p>1. With a rather uniform house infestation by Anopheles quadrim-<lb/>
aculatus, though at this time a light infestation - and a rather free<lb/>
breeding of Anopheles in the portions of the lake, particularly the<lb/>
bights, examined, it would point to a common production area. In August<lb/>
of 1919 the development from the larval collections from the lake was<lb/>
100% quadrimaculatus; from the fresh (small streams) and rain water<lb/>
collection 100% Anopheles punctipennis. From our knowledge of the<lb/>
breeding habits of the two species, the opinion is justified that the<lb/>
pond has again produced A. quads., this season, though perhaps in reduced<lb/>
numbers.</p>
<p>2. It is my opinion that malaria is endemic about portions of<lb/>
the environments of the lake. What part of the lake has played in this<lb/>
incidence is difficult to estimate. I think it is well for all<lb/>
concerned to concede that the lake is responsible for a considerable<lb/>
amount of Anopheles breeding close enough to occupied dwellings to<lb/>
cause infestation by Anopheles. Likewise, a very definite amount of<lb/>
Anopheles breeding is occurring outside of the lake and in several<lb/>
insstances in places much closer to the occupied dwellings, as shown<lb/>
under &ldquo;A<unclear>#</unclear>&rdquo;.</p>
<p><unclear>)X<lb/>
V</unclear></p>
<p>3. Efforts to control anopheles production should be applied<lb/>
to (a) the portions of the lake, its bights, etc., within, say one mile<lb/>
of occupied residences, where anopheles breeding occurs; (b) streams,<lb/>
swamps, pools, etc. in and about the premises of the people in this<lb/>
area where anopheles breeding occurs.</p>
<p>4. By the making of this lake, or reservoir, Anopheles production<lb/>
has been increased in some areas, while in others, such production places<lb/>
have been destroyed. As to the latter, there seems little room for<lb/>
doubt, but that Palmerville, for instance, has been benefitted decidedly.<lb/>
Prior to the impounding this settlement had quite an Anopheles infesta-<lb/>
tion and malaria, produced principally in parts of the old French canal.<lb/>
The lake covered these places. Malaria is said to have practically<lb/>
disappeared from Palmerville. The town of Badin situated immediately<lb/>
adjacent to the lake is said to be free from malaria.</p>
<p><unclear>}A</unclear></p>
<p>5. It is suggested that the following measures be enforced.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03055004"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>(a) The shore line of the reservoir, its branches, bights<lb/>
and indentations shall be cleared of brush, trees, underbrush and<lb/>
the like, so that stumps and other projections which at any stage of<lb/>
the water will not extend beyond or sufficiently near the surface of<lb/>
the water so as to collect and hold logs, drift, debris and floatage<lb/>
in such places as to endanger the health of the people through the<lb/>
production of mosquitoes.</p>
<p>(b) The formation or existence of log-jams and collections<lb/>
of drift, debris, floatage and the like in narrow valleys, bights<lb/>
or indentations of the reservoir where wave action is absent or weak<lb/>
and where the production of mosquitoes resulting from such condition<lb/>
would endanger the life and health of the people shall be prevented<lb/>
or removed or treated in such manner and at such times as to prevent<lb/>
the development of such mosquitoes.</p>
<p>(c) Areas slightly or partially covered with water, where<lb/>
cattails, bulrushes and similar vegetation grow and constitute A.<lb/>
breeding places so as to endanger health, shall, if the conditions c<lb/>
cannot be remedied by raising and lowering the water level be made<lb/>
free from vegetation or treated with oil, or both if necessary, the<lb/>
oil to be applied once every ten days in such manner as to prevent<lb/>
anopheles production.</p>
<p>(d) The reservoir shall be stocked with fishes or minnows<lb/>
(such as <hi>Gambusia affinis</hi>) known to be destructive to the eggs and<lb/>
larvae of mosquitoes, and every effort shall be made to protect them<lb/>
against their enemies and to secure their successful propagation and<lb/>
increased numbers in the reservoir, its branches, bights and inden-<lb/>
tations.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>(s) T.H.D. Griffitts,<lb/>
Epidemiologist</signed>.
Copied Nov. 18th-20.F.<lb/>
Symbols Used:<lb/>
<unclear><del>1</del></unclear> or <unclear>t</unclear> Indicates present breeding<lb/>
<unclear><del>11</del></unclear> or <unclear>t t</unclear> " fair breeding<lb/>
<unclear><del>111</del></unclear> or <unclear>ttt</unclear> " profusely breeding<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
