<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY t03056012 SYSTEM "t03056012.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY t03056013 SYSTEM "t03056013.jpg" NDATA jpg>]>
<TEI.2 id="t03056001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Biography: George M. Sternberg, by Martha L. Sternberg, 1920</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Sternberg, Martha L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03056001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1920-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>14 pp.</extent>
<date value="1920-00-00">1920</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03056001</idno>
<title>Biography: George M. Sternberg, by Martha L. Sternberg, 1920</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This document includes excerpts from Sternberg's biography of her husband's involvement with tropical diseases, including yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="book">
<p></p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="chapter" n="14">
<head></head>
<pb n="208" id="f03056001"/>
<p>208<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi></p>
<p>be doubted whether it would be in the interest of the service<lb/>
to detail line officers to administer the affairs of these bureaus<lb/>
of the War Department. Certainly it would be a difficult task<lb/>
to name any officers of the line as competent to fill these places<lb/>
as are the present distinguished incumbents, General Wilson<lb/>
and General Buffington.</p>
<p>Finally, I would say that, with three exceptions--General<lb/>
Egan, Commissary-General, General Flagler, Chief of Ord-<lb/>
nance, who died in March, 1899, and the Paymaster-General,<lb/>
who was retired for age in January, 1899, the bureau officers<lb/>
of the War Department are the same as those upon whom was<lb/>
thrown the responsibility of providing for an army of 260,000<lb/>
men in the spring of 1898. Time is an essential element in all<lb/>
great undertakings, and it takes time to organize and equip<lb/>
an army as well as to build a battleship. No amount of money<lb/>
or energy would enable the bureau officers of the Navy to<lb/>
build a battleship in three months, and it is unreasonable to<lb/>
hold the bureau officers of the War Department responsible<lb/>
for the unavoidable difficulties and failures connected with the<lb/>
organization and equipment of a large army after war was<lb/>
declared. That we were not better prepared was not the fault<lb/>
of the War Department, for supplies could not be purchased<lb/>
without money and our estimates have for years been cut<lb/>
down by Congress. What can be accomplished by the War<lb/>
Department when the necessary money is appropriated and a<lb/>
reasonable time allowed for the accomplishment of the objects<lb/>
in view is shown by the organization, equipment and trans-<lb/>
portation of the troops now in the Philippines and on their<lb/>
way there; by the magnificent fleet of transports and hospital<lb/>
ships now owned by the Government; by the model hospitals<lb/>
which have been established in this country, in the Philippines<lb/>
and in Cuba, and, in short, by the magnificent results attained<lb/>
during the war with Spain and since, notwithstanding the<lb/>
&ldquo;unpreparedness&rdquo; to which Governor Roosevelt refers, and<lb/>
which cannot be denied, but for which it is rank injustice to<lb/>
hold the chiefs of bureaus of the War Department responsible.<lb/></p>
<p>CHAPTER FIFTEEN</p>
<p>SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS DURING THE</p>
<p>SPANISH-AMERICAN WAR<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p>General Sternberg notwithstanding the many hours of<lb/>
anxiety and the responsibilities connected with the medical<lb/>
administration of the war never lost interest in scientific<lb/>
research, to the development of which he had devoted the best<lb/>
years of his life. His continued interest is attested by the<lb/>
appointment of various boards for investigation into the<lb/>
etiology and prevention of important diseases. Reference has<lb/>
already been made to the appointment of a board of sanitary<lb/>
experts for making a searching study of the causes of the<lb/>
extensive prevalence of typhoid fever in the military camps.<lb/>
Another board for the same purpose was appointed in the<lb/>
Philippine Islands.</p>
<p>BOARD FOR STUDY OF TROPICAL DISEASES</p>
<p>But General Sternberg did not limit his interest to typhoid<lb/>
fever, for it is noted in the report of the Surgeon-General for<lb/>
1900 &ldquo;that on his recommendation a board of medical officers<lb/>
consisting of Dr. Jere B. Clayton, Dr. Richard P. Strong,<lb/>
Assistant Surgeons, U. S. Army, and Acting Assistant Surgeon<lb/>
Joseph J. Curry, was appointed to meet at one of the general<lb/>
hospitals in or near Manila, P. I. for the purpose of studying<lb/>
tropical diseases as they occur in those Islands. Special<lb/>
attention should be given to tropical dysentery, to the malarial<lb/>
fevers prevailing in the Philippines, to beriberi, to intestinal<lb/>
parasites, and in general to all tropical diseases, the etiology<lb/>
of which has not been completely worked out.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Excellent work was done by the members of this board and<lb/>
their associates in the laboratories of the large hospitals,<lb/>
which may be briefly summarized.</p>
<p>ISOLATION OF BACILLUS DYSENTERIAE</p>
<p>Lieut. Richard P. Strong made a careful study of dysentery<lb/>
cases in the laboratory of the First Reserve Hospital, Manila,<lb/>
in which work he was assisted by hospital steward, W. E. Mus-<lb/>
<pb n="210" id="f03056002"/>
210<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi><lb/>
grave, M.D., pathologist of the hospital. A report of the<lb/>
results of these investigations was issued June 17, 1900.<lb/>
During a period of ten months prior to this date, 9,063 cases<lb/>
were treated in the hospital and 1,328 (14.64 per cent.) of<lb/>
these were cases of dysentery. Of the latter patients, 581 were<lb/>
returned to duty, 125 ended fatally in the hospital, 283 were<lb/>
transferred to other hospitals in the Philippines, and 336 were<lb/>
sent to the United States for possible benefit from the sea<lb/>
voyage and change of climate. The studies included 111<lb/>
necropsies on dysenteric cases, twenty-one of which were<lb/>
classified on anatomic grounds as acute specific dysentery. A<lb/>
bacillus was isolated in seventeen of these twenty-one cases,<lb/>
and in two of eleven subacute cases. In one of the former<lb/>
and two of the latter, the bacillus was not looked for; in<lb/>
twenty-six of the amebic cases the bacillus was not found and<lb/>
in the remaining fifty-three it was not sought, while in sixty-<lb/>
eight of seventy-nine amebic cases, motile <hi rend="italic">Amoebae dysenteriae</hi><lb/>
were found. The bacillus isolated by Drs. Strong and Mus-<lb/>
grave is similar to that discovered by Shiga in Kitasato's<lb/>
laboratory in 1898, and is today recognized as the specific<lb/>
cause of bacillary dysentery.</p>
<p>Splendid work was also done by Dr. Charles F. Craig on<lb/>
subacute and chronic dysentery at the U. S. General Hospital<lb/>
at the Presidio of San Francisco, where he gave close atten-<lb/>
tion to cases coming from Manila. He isolated a bacillus<lb/>
identical with that found by Dr. Flexner in Manila, previously<lb/>
described by Shiga, which was pathogenic to small animals.</p>
<p>PLAGUE IN MANILA</p>
<p>In December, 1899, bubonic plague appeared in Manila.<lb/>
The first two cases occurred in the same house and were<lb/>
reported as typhoid fever. The disease prevailed for seven<lb/>
months, during which 225 cases were reported with fifty-eight<lb/>
recoveries, while from forty to eighty Chinese died from<lb/>
unknown cause without medical attendance; some of these pre-<lb/>
sumably were victims of plague. Lieut. W. J. Calvert, Assist-<lb/>
ant Surgeon U. S. Army, then on duty with the board of health<lb/>
in Manila, was sent on a special visit to Japan and China, for<lb/>
the purpose of studying the measures in use in dealing with<lb/>
epidemic plague.<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
211</p>
<p>In connection with this subject, General Sternberg says:</p>
<p>Fortunately this outbreak gave opportunity for competent<lb/>
bacteriologists to make scientific investigation in relation to<lb/>
the specific cause of this scourge of the human race and to the<lb/>
demonstration that it is due to a minute bacillus. The dis-<lb/>
covery was first made by the Japanese bacteriologist, Kitasato,<lb/>
who had received his training in the laboratory of the famous<lb/>
Prof. Robert Koch of Berlin. This discovery was made in<lb/>
the month of June, 1894, in one of the hospitals established<lb/>
by the English officials in Hongkong. About the same time,<lb/>
the discovery was made independently by the French bacteri-<lb/>
ologist, Yersin. From this time, the study of the plague has<lb/>
been established upon a scientific basis, and several material<lb/>
additions have been made to our knowledge with reference to<lb/>
the prevention and treatment of the disease. We have learned<lb/>
that certain of the lower animals, including rats and mice, are<lb/>
very susceptible to infection, and they play an important part<lb/>
in the propagation of the disease; also that the germs are<lb/>
found not only in the blood and in the pus from suppurating<lb/>
buboes, but also in the discharge from the bowels of infected<lb/>
individuals. This being the case, it can readily be seen how<lb/>
important a strict sanitary police is in arresting the spread of<lb/>
an epidemic. As in other filth diseases in which the germ is<lb/>
present in the excreta of the sick, insects, and especially fleas<lb/>
and house flies probably play an important part in the spread<lb/>
of the disease.&rdquo;<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. The good work of medical officers initiated by General Stern-<lb/>
berg did not cease, as Lieut.-Col. C. C. McCulloch (Scientific Monthly,<lb/>
May, 1917, p. 424) informs us. Captain Craig in the Philippines<lb/>
&ldquo;demonstrated that intracorpuscular conjugation in the parasites of<lb/>
malarial fever is the cause of latency and relapses of the disease, and<lb/>
that these are malaria carriers, that is persons who carry the malarial<lb/>
parasites about with them without being affected by the disease. In<lb/>
1906, Craig discovered a new parasite associated with dysenteric<lb/>
infections, the <hi rend="italic">Paramoeba</hi> (now called <hi rend="italic">Craigia</hi>)<hi rend="italic">hominis</hi>. With Major<lb/>
Percy M. Ashburn, he discovered another parasite, <hi rend="italic">Microfilaria philli-<lb/>
pinensis</hi>, in 1906, and demonstrated that the cause of dengue or break-<lb/>
bone fever is a filterable virus transmitted by the mosquito <hi rend="italic">Culex<lb/>
fatigans</hi> (1907). In the Philippines also, Capt. Edward B. Vedder made<lb/>
important investigations of beriberi, a tropical form of neuritis which<lb/>
has been attributed to an exclusive diet of highly milled or polished<lb/>
rice. It was found that the disease is what is now termed a &ldquo;defi-<lb/>
ciency disease,&rdquo; that is, one caused by a diet deficient in certain sub-<lb/>
stances necessary to the physiological economy of the body.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="212" id="f03056003"/>
<p>212<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi></p>
<p>DISCOVERY OF HOOKWORM IN WESTERN HEMISPHERE</p>
<p>The Spanish-American War demonstrated the existence of<lb/>
the so-called hookworm disease in the Western hemisphere.<lb/>
The disease had been recognized as a true soil disease for a<lb/>
number of years, certainly since 1879 when Perroncito demon-<lb/>
strated that the general anemia and debility among the miners<lb/>
in the construction of the St. Gothard tunnel was caused by<lb/>
this intestinal parasite. The worm is about one-half or two-<lb/>
thirds inch in length and of the thickness of a pin and produces<lb/>
its evil effects by attaching itself to the upper portion of the<lb/>
intestine and by generating toxins.</p>
<p>It was, however, through the labors of Dr. Bailey K. Ash-<lb/>
ford, a graduate of the Army Medical School, that the prev-<lb/>
alence of the disease on this continent was brought to atten-<lb/>
tion. He demonstrated, in 1899, that the pale, dropsical and<lb/>
debilitated condition of the peasant population of Porto Rico,<lb/>
was not the result of malaria, starvation and other suspected<lb/>
causes, but was due to infestation by the hookworm. He isolated<lb/>
the parasite from the dejections of the natives, and showed<lb/>
conclusively that the disease was amenable to preventive and<lb/>
curative therapy. It was pointed out that in the rural districts<lb/>
of Porto Rico, where the disease is most common, there are<lb/>
practically no privies and the soil is promiscuously polluted<lb/>
with fecal matter, as many as fifty larvae having been known<lb/>
to cling to a bit of soil the size of a pea. The larvae penetrated<lb/>
the sound skin of the barefooted farm laborers, causing<lb/>
&ldquo;ground itch&rdquo; and the disease was also conveyed by infected<lb/>
food and water. The economic importance of hookworm dis-<lb/>
ease is apparent when it is considered that about 800,000 (90<lb/>
per cent.) of the laborers in the coffee and sugar plantations<lb/>
of Porto Rico were infected. In 1902, Prof. Stiles of the<lb/>
Public Health Service demonstrated that hookworm disease<lb/>
was prevalent in our southern states, and that it was respons-<lb/>
ible for great economic losses, just as Dr. Ashford had shown it<lb/>
to be the industrial curse of Porto Rico. Indeed much of the<lb/>
so-called chronic malaria, ignorance, poverty and general<lb/>
inefficiency in the world's tropical and subtropical belts could<lb/>
be attributed to hookworm infection. The number of victims<lb/>
in the United States has been estimated at 2,000,000 and the<lb/>
economic loss at $100,000,000 per year. Dr. Ashford's cam-<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
213<lb/>
paign against hookworm disease in Porto Rico resulted in cure<lb/>
in the majority of cases, led the way to similar efforts else-<lb/>
where, and inspired the program of the Rockefeller Foun-<lb/>
dation for world wide eradication of the disease.</p>
<p>YELLOW FEVER COMMISSION</p>
<p>The most important and most brilliant piece of research<lb/>
work during this period was accomplished by a board<lb/>
appointed on the recommendation of General Sternberg in<lb/>
May, 1900, to meet at Camp Columbia, Quemados, Cuba, for<lb/>
the purpose of pursuing scientific investigations of the infec-<lb/>
tious diseases prevailing in the Island of Cuba, with special<lb/>
reference to yellow fever.</p>
<p>The board was composed of Surgeon Walter Reed, Contract<lb/>
Surgeons James Carroll, Aristides Agramonte, and Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear, U. S. Army. By a series of painstaking experiments<lb/>
it was demonstrated that the virus of yellow fever is trans-<lb/>
mitted by a certain species of mosquito (<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi>),<lb/>
and the theory that the disease could be conveyed in fomites,<lb/>
or that it was contagious in the ordinary acceptance of the<lb/>
term was disproved conclusively. The practical application of<lb/>
this discovery resulted in the eradication of the scourge from<lb/>
Havana by Dr. William C. Gorgas (lately Surgeon-General,<lb/>
U. S. Army), and in the sanitary achievements contributing<lb/>
to the successful building of the Panama Canal.</p>
<p>I may be pardoned for calling attention to the fact, that<lb/>
when this commission was appointed, the alleged discovery by<lb/>
Dr. Giuseppe Sanarelli of a specific <hi rend="italic">Bacillus icteroides</hi> had<lb/>
been confirmed by a commission of the Public Health and<lb/>
Marine Hospital Service. Had General Sternberg accepted<lb/>
this as conclusive, we might still be periodically visited by epi-<lb/>
demics of yellow fever and the Panama Canal would probably<lb/>
be far from completion.</p>
<p>It is not my purpose to detract in the slightest degree from<lb/>
the brilliant work of Dr. Walter Reed and his brave associates<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Commission, but as a loyal wife and one<lb/>
familiar with the research work of my lamented husband on<lb/>
the etiology of yellow fever, which culminated in the find-<lb/>
ings of the Reed board, I may be privileged to present certain<lb/>
illuminating facts. This is all the more important since the<lb/>
<pb n="214" id="f03056004"/>
214<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi><lb/>
medical profession was not generally informed of General<lb/>
Sternberg's preliminary work, while credit for the appoint-<lb/>
ment of the commission was even given to others, as is shown<lb/>
by a letter from Dr. William H. Welch of Johns Hopkins<lb/>
Medical School, April 16, 1910, in which he says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;As all that relates to the history and work of this com-<lb/>
mission is highly important, permit me to say that the credit<lb/>
for the creation of this commission belongs solely to General<lb/>
Sternberg, who had previously so completely exhausted the<lb/>
purely bacteriologic study of yellow fever that it was pos-<lb/>
sible for the commission to follow the new direction which<lb/>
proved so fruitful in results.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Among the official papers left by my husband, I find the<lb/>
following:</p>
<p>Surgeon-General's Office,<lb/>
Washington, May 23rd, 1900.</p>
<p>To the Adjutant-General of the Army:</p>
<p>I have the honor to recommend that Major Walter Reed,<lb/>
Surgeon, U. S. Army, and Contract Surgeon James Carroll,<lb/>
U. S. Army, be ordered to proceed from this city to Camp<lb/>
Columbia, Cuba, reporting their arrival and instructions to<lb/>
the commanding officer of the post.</p>
<p>I also recommend the organization of a medical board with<lb/>
headquarters at Camp Columbia for the purpose of pursuing<lb/>
scientific investigations with reference to the infectious dis-<lb/>
eases prevalent on the Island of Cuba and especially of yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>The board is to be constituted as follows:</p>
<p>Major Walter Reed, Surgeon U. S. Army; Contract Sur-<lb/>
geon James Carroll, U. S. Army, and Contract Surgeons<lb/>
Aristides Agramonte and Jesse W. Lazear, U. S. Army. . . .</p>
<p>The board should act under general instructions which will<lb/>
be communicated to Major Reed by the Surgeon-General of<lb/>
the Army.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
GEO. M. STERNBERG,<lb/>
Surgeon-General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>Major Walter Reed, at that time professor of bacteriology<lb/>
at the Army Medical School, was splendidly equipped for the<lb/>
duty and perfectly familiar with General Sternberg's pre-<lb/>
liminary work. They had been close friends for years and<lb/>
enjoyed each other's confidence, and a better selection could<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
215<lb/>
not have been made in the personnel of the board. Dr.<lb/>
Aristides Agramonte, the only surviving member of the board,<lb/>
has reviewed the various steps which culminated so success-<lb/>
fully. He writes regarding the preliminary instructions:</p>
<p>On the afternoon of June 25, 1900, the four officers met for<lb/>
the first time in their new capacity on the veranda of the<lb/>
officers' quarters at Columbia Barracks Hospital. We were<lb/>
fully appreciative of the trust, and aware of the responsibility<lb/>
placed upon us, and with a feeling akin to reverence heard<lb/>
the instructions which Major Reed had brought from the<lb/>
Surgeon General (Dr. Sternberg). They comprised the<lb/>
investigation also of malaria, leprosy, and unclassified febrile<lb/>
conditions, and were given with such detail and precision as<lb/>
only a man of General Sternberg's experience and knowledge<lb/>
in such matters could have prepared. . . .</p>
<p>July 2 we resumed our routine investigations, not only in<lb/>
Quemadoes, where the disease was being stamped out, but also<lb/>
in Havana at &ldquo;Las Animas&rdquo; Hospital and at Military Hospital<lb/>
No. 1, where my laboratory (the division laboratory) was<lb/>
located. There was no scarcity of material and the two<lb/>
members who until then had never seen a case of yellow fever<lb/>
(Major Reed and Dr. Carroll) had ample opportunities to<lb/>
become acquainted with the many details of its clinical picture<lb/>
which escape the ordinary practitioner.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
<p>The official history of this board records the fact that Dr.<lb/>
Carroll and Dr. Lazear volunteered to be bitten by infected<lb/>
mosquitoes. Dr. Lazear contracted the disease and died after a<lb/>
short illness. Dr. Carroll had a severe attack of yellow fever,<lb/>
a slow convalescence, and was permanently disabled thereafter<lb/>
because of involvement of the heart, from which he died<lb/>
some years later. Major Walter Reed died from appendicitis,<lb/>
Nov. 23, 1902, while Dr. Aristides Agramonte, the surviving<lb/>
member, is resident in Cuba, where he is engaged in scientific<lb/>
and professional work. All honor and glory to these phy-<lb/>
sicians, to Private Kissinger (the first volunteer) and others,<lb/>
who in the interest of humanity and for the cause of science<lb/>
faced danger and even death, in order to make a demonstra-<lb/>
tion of inestimable value to mankind. Many of the details of<lb/>
this fruitful work are recorded in several papers by General</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. Scientific Monthly, Dec., 1915, p. 216.</p>
<pb n="216" id="f03056005"/>
<p>216<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi></p>
<p>Sternberg,<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> and in a contribution presented posthumously at<lb/>
the Second Pan-American Scientific Congress, in December,<lb/>
1915.</p>
<p>Perhaps the best summary of General Sternberg's rela-<lb/>
tion to this important discovery is contained in the following<lb/>
abstract of a report of a committee composed by Drs. G.<lb/>
Wythe Cook, George M. Kober, and D. Olin Leech presented<lb/>
at the joint memorial meeting of the Medical Society and the<lb/>
Association for the Prevention of Tuberculosis of the<lb/>
District of Columbia, Jan. 19, 1916, in respect for General<lb/>
Sternberg.</p>
<p>Dr. Sternberg's investigations with reference to the etiology<lb/>
of yellow fever date back to 1871, although his search for<lb/>
the specific organism commenced in Havana in 1879, while<lb/>
a member of the Havana Yellow Fever Commission, and<lb/>
was continued for about ten years. During this time he twice<lb/>
returned to Havana during the months of yellow fever<lb/>
prevalence, and visited Rio de Janeiro and Vera Cruz, also the<lb/>
town of Decatur, Ala., during the epidemic of 1888. His report,<lb/>
published at the conclusion of these extended investigations,<lb/>
shows that all researches to that date had failed to demonstrate<lb/>
the specific cause of yellow fever. He showed that the generally<lb/>
accepted claims of Domingos Freire, of Brazil, to have dis-<lb/>
covered the germ of this disease--his <hi rend="italic">Cryptococcus xanthogeni-<lb/>
cus</hi>--and a method of producing immunity by inoculations, had<lb/>
no scientific foundation. He also showed that the bacillus of<lb/>
Gibier, Carlos Finlay's <hi rend="italic">Micrococcus tetragenus febris flavae</hi>,<lb/>
and the various microorganisms encountered by himself and<lb/>
by other investigators bore no etiologic relation to the disease.<lb/>
At the International Medical Congress, held in Berlin in August,<lb/>
1890, Dr. Kober translated Dr. Sternberg's letter to Professor<lb/>
Hirsch, giving a synopsis of his work and stating that so far the<lb/>
specific organism of yellow fever had not been discovered. It<lb/>
certainly speaks well for his painstaking work that even now,<lb/>
when we know that the infectious agent is transmitted through<lb/>
the sting of a mosquito, and the search has narrowed down to<lb/>
the body of this insect, it has not been isolated and neither he<lb/>
nor others have found it, probably because it is ultramicro-<lb/>
scopic.</p>
<p>Having exhausted the resources at his command in the<lb/>
search for the germ of yellow fever by microscopical examina-<lb/>
tion of the blood tissues, by culture methods and by experiments</p>
<p>------------</p>
<p>1. The Transmission of Yellow Fever, Popular Science Monthly,<lb/>
July, 1901. Sanitary Problems Connected with Construction of the<lb/>
Panama Canal, North American Review, September, 1902.<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
217</p>
<p>on the lower animals, he felt that the only method left which<lb/>
offered any promise of success was that of direct experiment<lb/>
on men. If the blood of a yellow fever patient contained the<lb/>
specific infectious agent, this should be shown by inoculating a<lb/>
nonimmune individual with such blood.</p>
<p>This line of research, we are informed, was pointed out<lb/>
by Surgeon-General Sternberg to Maj. Walter Reed, chairman<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Commission in 1900, as was also the<lb/>
probability that it would ultimately be found that the disease is<lb/>
transmitted from man to man by an intermediate host.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
<p>In justice to all concerned it should be remembered that<lb/>
when this commission was organized by General Sternberg<lb/>
the claim of the distinguished bacteriologist Sanarelli to have<lb/>
demonstrated the etiologic relation of his <hi rend="italic">Bacillus icteroides</hi> was<lb/>
generally accepted, and had been upheld by two medical officers<lb/>
of the Public Health and Marine Hospital Service, sent to<lb/>
Cuba for the special purpose of investigating this claim. To<lb/>
General Sternberg it appeared impossible that a bacillus, which<lb/>
is easily demonstrated under the microscope, and which grows<lb/>
in ordinary culture media, could have escaped his observation<lb/>
during his extended researches if it were in fact the specific<lb/>
cause of yellow fever. The only possibility of such causal<lb/>
connection seems to him to depend upon the identification of<lb/>
Sanarelli's bacillus as identical with a certain bacillus found by<lb/>
Sternberg in a limited number of cases during his researches in<lb/>
Havana. A comparison of cultures of the micro-organisms<lb/>
made by Major Reed at the Army Medical Museum and also<lb/>
by Dr. Agramonte,<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 1899-1900, showed that they were not<lb/>
identical, and General Sternberg, being satisfied that Sanarelli's<lb/>
bacillus was not concerned in the etiology of yellow fever,<lb/>
organized in 1900 the Yellow Fever Commission, with Major<lb/>
Reed as chairman. Major Reed's investigation resulted in the</p>
<p>-----------</p>
<p>1. The written instructions are for obvious reasons silent upon the<lb/>
subject of experimentation upon man. Dr. Aristides Agramonte, a<lb/>
member of the Commission, in the Scientific Monthly for December,<lb/>
1915, published a letter from Major Reed dated May 25, 1900, from<lb/>
which we quote the following: &ldquo;It will be our duty under verbal<lb/>
instructions from the Surgeon-General to continue the investigation<lb/>
of the causation of yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>2. Dr. Agramonte worked on this problem during the Santiago<lb/>
Campaign in 1898 and afterwards with Reed and Carroll in the bac-<lb/>
teriologic laboratory of the Army Medical Museum. He was ordered<lb/>
to Havana in December, 1898, with instructions from General Stern-<lb/>
berg and power to do all that might be necessary to clear up the<lb/>
problem. In 1899, Drs. Geddings and Wardin submitted a report<lb/>
affirming that Sanarelli's bacillus was present in almost all the cases,<lb/>
while Dr. Agramonte denied that it had such specific character, and<lb/>
showed its occurrence in cases not yellow fever He continued his<lb/>
researches until appointed a member of the Commission.</p>
<pb n="218" id="f03056006"/>
<p>218<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi></p>
<p>demonstration that in yellow fever the specific infectious agent<lb/>
is present in the blood of those suffering from the disease, and<lb/>
that the usual and probably only method of transmission of the<lb/>
disease is through the bites of mosquitoes of the genus<lb/>
Stegomyia. This brilliant demonstration by Reed and his col-<lb/>
leagues has furnished the necessary basis for preventive mea-<lb/>
sures which have been applied with entire success in the yellow<lb/>
fever zone, and the practical results are of incalculable value<lb/>
to mankind.</p>
<p>The members of your committee do not consider it unfair<lb/>
to the memory of Major Reed and his colleagues, when they<lb/>
declare that much of the success achieved was rendered pos-<lb/>
sible by the preliminary work of Dr. Sternberg, who had elimi-<lb/>
nated numerous errors committed by others, and had contested<lb/>
and overthrown the claims of several bacteriologists for the<lb/>
discovery of the specific organism. His conviction that all<lb/>
former claims were unfounded, or remained to be proven, is<lb/>
clearly evinced by the appointment of a commission which he<lb/>
personally selected.</p>
<p>It may be truly said that no history of this important dis-<lb/>
covery is complete without a just presentation of Sternberg's<lb/>
preliminary work. In giving due credit to all the participants<lb/>
of this splendid piece of research, it must be remembered that<lb/>
all of his work was of the highest scientific value, and his daily<lb/>
contact with the sick, his autopsies and bacteriologic investiga-<lb/>
tions in different countries and climes in search of the yellow<lb/>
fever organism, involved at least the same risks and heroism<lb/>
displayed by members of the Yellow Fever Commission.</p>
<p>In supporting the foregoing statement your committee sub-<lb/>
mits the following testimony from Dr. Aristides Agramonte,<lb/>
the only surviving member of the Yellow Fever Commission,<lb/>
who, on Jan. 3, 1916, wrote to Dr. Kober as follows: &ldquo;With<lb/>
regard to our work I may say that General Sternberg's instruc-<lb/>
tions to Major Reed were so precise yet so complete that they<lb/>
embraced even human experimentation, a thing until then con-<lb/>
sidered well nigh impossible, and, without the moral support<lb/>
which his reputation as a scientist of the highest order and his<lb/>
official position rendered us, I am sure we would have never<lb/>
undertaken the method of investigation with which you are<lb/>
familiar.</p>
<p>I feel in my heart that in the greatest achievement of modern<lb/>
medicine, the almost total extinction of yellow fever in our<lb/>
hemisphere, he took an important part that has not been gen-<lb/>
erally recognized, in spite of your pointing it out in your speech<lb/>
(June 8, 1908).</p>
<p>I say an important part and I would be tempted to say the<lb/>
most important part, since by the elimination of many confusing<lb/>
and erroneous ideas with reference to the cause of the disease,<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
219<lb/>
obtained by his indefatigable work in South America and<lb/>
Central America, he cleared the way for us who came after<lb/>
him, laboring in the same field of investigation; he saved us<lb/>
the work, and thus the waste of effort and time which it would<lb/>
have entailed, by dealing with the fallacies in vogue during<lb/>
the last quarter of the nineteenth century, elucidating the ques-<lb/>
tion of yellow fever in a manner nearly complete.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In addition to this just and beautiful appreciation of Stern-<lb/>
berg's work we also refer to the following resolution, adopted<lb/>
Dec. 29, 1915, in which the section of public health and medical<lb/>
science of the Second Pan-American Congress &ldquo;conscious of<lb/>
the irreparable loss suffered by the recent death of one of the<lb/>
most eminent workers in the field of etiology and preventive<lb/>
medicine, a pioneer in bacteriologic investigation in America</p>
<p>Resolved to express its profound condolence to the family<lb/>
of the late General George M. Sternberg, and to the Govern-<lb/>
ment of the United States, in whose army his counsel and<lb/>
labors were so fruitful.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It may not be amiss to quote from a letter from Hon. Elihu<lb/>
Root, one time Secretary of War, under whom General Stern-<lb/>
berg had the pleasure of serving. This tribute was published<lb/>
in the Congressional Record, Aug, 5, 1916, fourteen years<lb/>
after the retirement of General Sternberg from active service,<lb/>
and it forms a just appreciation of the labors of those engaged<lb/>
in preventive medicine.</p>
<p>Dear Mrs. Sternberg: I have received your letter of March<lb/>
6, and I respond heartily to the very moderate statements which<lb/>
you make regarding General Sternberg's merits and the claims<lb/>
of his memory to recognition by Congress. Senator Gallinger's<lb/>
bill does not rest alone upon long and faithful service, includ-<lb/>
ing both the Civil War and the War with Spain, but chiefly<lb/>
and distinctively upon the great part which General Sternberg<lb/>
played in the service rendered by the Medical Corps of the<lb/>
Army in the nine years during which he was Surgeon-General.</p>
<p>The practical extirpation of yellow fever in Cuba and on the<lb/>
Isthmus of Panama and the development of methods of pre-<lb/>
ventive medicine which have secured the phenomenal freedom<lb/>
from typhoid in recent years are achievements in which the<lb/>
Medical Corps of the Army bore a great part and won the<lb/>
highest distinction. Congress has paid great honor to the med-<lb/>
ical officers who in the field and in the camp became dis-<lb/>
tinguished for their part in this extraordinary work. Let no<lb/>
one think, however, that the man who was at the head of the<lb/>
corps can be left out of account of this creditable record.<lb/>
Such things do not happen by accident. No body of men<lb/>
<pb n="220" id="f03056007"/>
220<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi><lb/>
accomplishes what our medical officers accomplished except<lb/>
in response to leadership, incitement, encouragement, oppor-<lb/>
tunity, motive power, coming from the head of the corps.</p>
<p>The Medical Corps accomplished what it did largely because<lb/>
the man at the top was a pioneer in bacteriology, an advance<lb/>
worker in protective medicine, and had the enthusiasm and<lb/>
devotion through which science wins victories. That spirit<lb/>
communicated itself to the corps, directed its energies, made<lb/>
the field of opportunity for scientific effort, kept good men in it,<lb/>
brought good men into it, and furnished the indispensable<lb/>
element of leadership without which the work could not have<lb/>
been done. General Sternberg was the general commanding in<lb/>
that campaign. Congress has been honoring his subordinates<lb/>
gratefully and properly. It is all wrong that there should be<lb/>
no appreciation for the commander. I have not received yet<lb/>
the copies of resolutions, etc., which you have sent, but I do<lb/>
not need them for I know about this subject myself upon the<lb/>
experience of four years and a half, during which it was my<lb/>
business to observe and estimate the influences working for and<lb/>
against efficiency in the War Department.</p>
<p>Dr. J. H. Gallinger, senator from New Hampshire, wrote<lb/>
under date of March 18, 1916:</p>
<p>I have read Senator Root's letter to you with the greatest<lb/>
interest. What he says about General Sternberg is the simple<lb/>
truth and I feel sure that the medical profession of the country<lb/>
would endorse every word of it.</p>
<p>Some details of the painstaking methods and the progress<lb/>
of the experimental investigations of the Yellow Fever Com-<lb/>
mission may be gleaned from the following letters of Major<lb/>
Reed to the Surgeon-General:</p>
<p>LETTERS FROM MAJOR WALTER REED</p>
<p>My Dear General Sternberg: Your favor of the 22d inst.<lb/>
enclosing a letter from Dr. Vaughan has been received. . . .</p>
<p>We arrived at this Camp, Monday afternoon, the 25th, and<lb/>
were soon comfortably provided for by Dr. Stark. We have<lb/>
already organized as a Board and have begun work. Yester-<lb/>
day we took careful cultures from two cases that have slightly<lb/>
passed the most active stage. Lazear has cultures from three<lb/>
autopsies to be worked up. This afternoon we will take cultures<lb/>
from the blood of a case admitted to camp hospital last evening<lb/>
and will continue to take cultures each successive day. We<lb/>
can get material from another case at the detention camp. Upon<lb/>
my recommendation, Agramonte appears to have adopted wise<lb/>
measures here. Lazear and I will go probably to Cienfuegos<lb/>
next week to look into an epidemic of malarial fever amongst<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
221<lb/>
Second Infantry there. Our baggage (laboratory equipment)<lb/>
did not arrive on Sedgwick. Have asked General Humphrey<lb/>
to cable Q. M. General to have it forwarded by Ward Line of<lb/>
steamers. Please assist us at your end of the line.</p>
<p>Sincerely yours,<lb/>
WALTER REED.</p>
<p>I have been unable to find any letters from Dr. Reed indi-<lb/>
cating the progress of the work of the commission between<lb/>
June 27, and October 22, but the official records disclose that<lb/>
three cases of yellow fever, believed to be the direct result of<lb/>
mosquito inoculations, were under observation. Two of the<lb/>
patients were members of the board, Drs. Jesse W. Lazear and<lb/>
James Carroll, who voluntarily submitted themselves to experi-<lb/>
mentation. Dr. Carroll suffered a severe attack of the disease<lb/>
and recovered, but Dr. Lazear fell a victim in the cause of<lb/>
science, Sept. 25, 1900. About the same time, nine other<lb/>
volunteers were bitten by mosquitoes; in these cases the result<lb/>
was negative. The results of the investigations by the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Board up to October 22, were presented in a preliminary<lb/>
note read by Dr. Reed at the meeting of the American Public<lb/>
Health Association at Indianapolis.</p>
<p>Indianapolis, Ind., Oct. 22, 1900.</p>
<p>Dear General Sternberg:</p>
<p>Just as I was leaving the city, I dropped you a postal sug-<lb/>
gesting that the words &ldquo;with his full consent&rdquo; be erased in<lb/>
the cases of Carroll (page 12) and Lazear (page 20), as their<lb/>
absence from the history of T. C. Y. might attract attention<lb/>
and lead to the inference that his inoculation was done without<lb/>
his consent. . . .</p>
<p>I will, also, ask that you will turn to the last page of MSS.<lb/>
(22) beginning &ldquo;since we here,&rdquo; etc. Let the first paragraph<lb/>
stand as it is, but change the rest as follows:</p>
<p>From our study thus far of yellow fever, we draw the fol-<lb/>
lowing conclusions:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. <hi rend="italic">Bacillus icteroides</hi> (Sanarelli) stands in no causative rela-<lb/>
tion to yellow fever, but, when present, should be considered<lb/>
as a secondary invader in this disease.</item>
<item>2. The mosquito serves as the intermediate host for the<lb/>
parasite of yellow fever.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Strike out the remainder &ldquo;and it is highly probable that&rdquo;<lb/>
etc., as this is merely an expression of opinion which may<lb/>
<pb n="222" id="f03056008"/>
222<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi><lb/>
turn out to be right or wrong. Future observations can only<lb/>
determine this point--of course, conclusions 1 and 2 in your<lb/>
copy are to be erased entirely. . . .</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks, Quemados, Cuba.<lb/>
Nov. 13, 1900.</p>
<p>My Dear General Sternberg:</p>
<p>. . . My voyage down was fairly pleasant, although<lb/>
I was as usual a victim to sea sickness. I have been very busy<lb/>
trying to get our experimental station started. Have secured<lb/>
a good location and hope to have the detachment go out on<lb/>
Thursday, 15th. I have already had three candidates to offer<lb/>
themselves for the mosquito inoculation and will have no dif-<lb/>
ficulty in getting subjects for the infected bedding and clothing<lb/>
experiments. (I hope that you will not mention this to any-<lb/>
one). The difficulty before us now will be largely due to the<lb/>
marked change in the temperature. It is now 62&deg;--with a<lb/>
strong north-west wind. Has been cold ever since I arrived.<lb/>
As the result of this past week's cool weather, cases have drop-<lb/>
ped from 100 to 76, and I suppose we may expect a still further<lb/>
reduction in about from 5 to 7 days. If it were only August 1,<lb/>
everything would be plain sailing, but I forsee that we will be<lb/>
much handicapped by the weather.</p>
<p>We will have our small experimental buildings heated, if<lb/>
necessary, and in that way, hope to counteract the outside<lb/>
temperature.</p>
<p>Dr. Carroll arrived this afternoon and will at once take up<lb/>
the work.</p>
<p>Nov. 26, 1900.</p>
<p>. . . At this writing, the experimental station is nearly<lb/>
completed and we have already begun on our observations.<lb/>
We have several individuals, American and Spanish, willing to<lb/>
take bites or blood injections, and we hope to be able to decide<lb/>
some of the vexed questions in the etiology of this disease.<lb/>
We anticipate considerable trouble concerning the rearing of<lb/>
our mosquitoes during this cooler weather. Unless we can keep<lb/>
them alive from eighteen to twenty-four days after the infec-<lb/>
tion, we could not expect positive results, since it required<lb/>
twelve to sixteen days in the hotter weather of August to enable<lb/>
them to convey the disease.</p>
<p>Some of the Havana papers, especially <hi rend="italic">La Discussion</hi> have<lb/>
abused us soundly and have charged us with all kinds<lb/>
of inhumanity and barbarity; but since the Spanish consul, a<lb/>
most courteous and intelligent gentleman, assures us that we<lb/>
shall have his support, as long as we do not use minors and<lb/>
the individual gives his written consent, I am not at all dis-<lb/>
turbed by these newspaper attacks. . . .<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
223</p>
<p>Dec. 14, 1900.</p>
<p>Within three weeks of the establishment of our experi-<lb/>
mental station, I am able to report two cases of yellow fever<lb/>
brought about by the bites of infected mosquitoes--one occur-<lb/>
ring suddenly at 11:30 p.m., December 8, and the second 9:30<lb/>
p. m., December 12. Both cases have been seen and carefully<lb/>
examined by the board of experts, consisting of Drs. Guiteras,<lb/>
Finlay, Gorgas and Albertini, and both have been pronounced<lb/>
to be unmistakable cases of yellow fever. I thought it best<lb/>
to have these gentlemen of acknowledged experience see all<lb/>
of our cases. This they have gladly done, visiting our first case<lb/>
on the 9th, 11th, and again today. Although our second case<lb/>
is only in his second day, the symptoms are unmistakable. A<lb/>
third case bitten on the 11th at 4:30 p. m., began to sicken<lb/>
yesterday afternoon, with some fever and headache, and has,<lb/>
today, developed a temperature of 100.8&deg;. I think that he will<lb/>
be removed early tomorrow morning, as his symptoms point<lb/>
plainly in that direction. Concerning a fourth case, bitten three<lb/>
days ago, it is as yet too early to pronounce an opinion. Our<lb/>
three nonimmunes have already passed fourteen nights in a<lb/>
house horribly infected with clothing and bedding without<lb/>
showing any symptoms whatever. Perhaps it is yet too early to<lb/>
pronounce an opinion as to the probability of their escape.<lb/>
Taken altogether, we feel very much pleased with our results,<lb/>
and believe that, with your kind permission, we should present a<lb/>
supplementary note to the Pan-American Congress in February<lb/>
next.</p>
<p>I am glad that our first case, now in his sixth day, is doing<lb/>
very well. It is too early to give a prognosis in our second<lb/>
case. In view of these results, I would like to know whether<lb/>
you consider it necessary that we should try blood injections,<lb/>
as you suggested when I last saw you. Any other suggestions<lb/>
that you may make, will be much appreciated.</p>
<p>Dec. 16, 1900.</p>
<p>I cabled you again, today, as I thought that you would be<lb/>
pleased to hear that success was still attending our efforts.<lb/>
Our fourth case sickened yesterday afternoon at 2:30 o'clock,<lb/>
and at 9 p. m., had a temperature of 104.2&deg;. Four cases out of<lb/>
five inoculations is quite satisfactory, we think. This morning<lb/>
Drs. Guiteras, Finlay and Albertini were again here to see our<lb/>
third and fourth cases. Like the first two, the diagnosis was<lb/>
very plain and hence they very promptly pronounced the cases<lb/>
to be yellow fever, our first three we consider out of danger.<lb/>
The last man is still quite sick. Our third case was a very<lb/>
mild one. Although coming down four and one-half hours<lb/>
within the usual period of incubation--five days--he could have<lb/>
passed quarantine on the morning of his sixth day, and would<lb/>
<pb n="224" id="f03056009"/>
224<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi><lb/>
have been the focus of one of those epidemics ascribed to<lb/>
infected bedding, or the unpacking of trunk. For this reason,<lb/>
it is, to me, the most interesting case of the series. This week I<lb/>
hope to loose infected mosquitoes in our building No. 2, my<lb/>
intention being to demonstrate conclusively how a building<lb/>
becomes infected. Of course, every precaution has been taken<lb/>
to prevent the escape of these insects. My control subjects<lb/>
will keep on the uninfected side of the building, being pro-<lb/>
tected by a fine wire-screen partition but breathing the same<lb/>
atmosphere. I have to ask as a special favor that Acting Assist-<lb/>
ant Surgeon R. P. Cooke, who so courageously volunteered<lb/>
to take charge of affairs in our horribly infected clothing build-<lb/>
ing No. 1, may not have his contract annulled, but may be sent<lb/>
to duty in the Philippines, if he can not remain in Cuba. His<lb/>
interest in the work deserves, I think, this consideration from<lb/>
the Department.</p>
<p>The search for the parasite will be next in order.</p>
<p>Dec. 22, 1900.</p>
<p>I write to request that Dr. McConnell, of the Museum, may<lb/>
be sent down to join us on the next transport leaving New<lb/>
York. I would like to have him make drawings of the mosquito<lb/>
and larvae from live specimens. There is some other work<lb/>
here which he could also do. He should bring camera lucida<lb/>
and suitable paper for doing this work.</p>
<p>I would like also to be made a delegate to the Pan-American<lb/>
Congress, if you approve of our presenting a supplementary<lb/>
note at this meeting.</p>
<p>Jan. 1, 1901.</p>
<p>I am in receipt of your letter informing me that I would be<lb/>
detailed as a delegate to the Pan-American Congress, and thank<lb/>
you for the same. I am sure that you will be interested to know<lb/>
that our attempt to infect a new building by means of con-<lb/>
taminated mosquitoes has met with complete success. The<lb/>
insects were released in this building during the afternoon of<lb/>
December 21. A few minutes thereafter I permitted a non-<lb/>
immune to enter and lie on a bed provided for the purpose. I,<lb/>
with other nonimmunes, stood in one end of the room, pro-<lb/>
tected, of course, by a wire screen partition. The subject<lb/>
remained 30 minutes and was bitten by several insects. He<lb/>
again entered at 4 p. m. and remained 15 minutes; and again<lb/>
the next afternoon (22d) remaining 15 minutes. During each<lb/>
of which times, he was bitten by one or more insects. Four<lb/>
days later (December 25), at 9 a. m., he felt badly and had<lb/>
fever 99.6. At noon, a slight chill with rising temperature,<lb/>
100.4--backache, headache, suffused face and infected eyes--<lb/>
at 9 p. m., temperature 104.2--albumen on second evening,<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
225<lb/>
jaundice of eyes, etc.--typical symptoms of yellow fever, the<lb/>
diagnosis being confirmed by board of experts. His tempera-<lb/>
ture fell to normal yesterday, sixth day, and patient will make a<lb/>
good recovery. It is hardly necessary to add that the two non-<lb/>
immunes who have slept each night in the noninfected end of<lb/>
the same room, only protected by a wire screen partition, are<lb/>
still well and healthy. Nothing could possibly be more strik-<lb/>
ing than this observation. We shall make but few more experi-<lb/>
ments--one blood injection has given no result--we will make<lb/>
two others, if I can find the cases. I consider it now very<lb/>
important to find if possible the parasite in the body of the<lb/>
mosquito. We have preserved a number of insects of various<lb/>
ages for paraffin sectioning, when we return to Washington. I<lb/>
will, therefore, thank you very much if you will have the<lb/>
necessary order issued relieving us from duty at this post and<lb/>
authorizing our return to our proper station, so that we can<lb/>
start back immediately after the adjournment of the Pan-<lb/>
American Congress. I will request General Wood to retain<lb/>
the buildings at our camp site, so that, if necessary, we could<lb/>
resume our observations when the epidemic year begins again.<lb/>
Dr. Cooke's services at the Camp are now no longer needed.<lb/>
With greetings of the New Year,</p>
<p>WALTER REED.</p>
<p>P. S.: No results as yet in infected clothing building. Non-<lb/>
immunes sleeping every night in yellow fever beds.</p>
<p>Jan. 13, 1901.</p>
<p>Your letter of January 8, was received yesterday. I have<lb/>
made Carroll acquainted with the contents of your letter, and<lb/>
he wishes me to convey to you his sincere thanks for the honor<lb/>
which you propose to confer upon him. He will gladly remain<lb/>
in Cuba for a while, as you suggest.</p>
<p>It occurs to me that the passage of the Army Bill will<lb/>
promptly promote Major Kean to a majority in the regular<lb/>
Corps, and leave a vacancy for Carroll's promotion. If, how-<lb/>
ever, the new Army Bill limits Surgeons of Volunteers to those<lb/>
who serve in the Philippines, Carroll would not care to go there.<lb/>
If it could be so arranged that he could return to Washington<lb/>
by April 1, I would be much gratified. I would suggest that the<lb/>
order for my own return and Steward Neate's be issued soon,<lb/>
that we could get our outfit on the transport ahead of us, and<lb/>
thus not be compelled to wait several weeks for important<lb/>
material. We could then leave immediately after the adjourn-<lb/>
ment of the Pan-American Congress.</p>
<p>I feel certain that you will be much interested in the result<lb/>
from our blood injections. I think that I mentioned, in a<lb/>
letter, one case that had received a blood injection made on the<lb/>
first day of the disease. The result was negative in this case,<lb/>
<pb n="226" id="f03056010"/>
226<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi><lb/>
unless we regard slight headache and general muscular sore-<lb/>
ness, on the eighth and ninth days, as some manifestations of<lb/>
an attempt at infection. It is interesting to note that this same<lb/>
individual has since resisted the bite of mosquitoes that con-<lb/>
veyed a good typical case of yellow fever to another non-<lb/>
immune. I am inclined, therefore, in the light of other injec-<lb/>
tions, to look upon him as one having a natural immunity to<lb/>
the disease.</p>
<p>Having succeeded in getting hold of two hospital corps men,<lb/>
who were willing to take blood injections, we first infected a<lb/>
Spaniard by the bite of mosquitoes. During his primary parox-<lb/>
ysms (first day) we injected 2 c.c. of blood from a vein at<lb/>
the elbow subcutaneously in one of our subjects. In just four<lb/>
days, lacking two hours, he developed an attack of yellow fever.<lb/>
From his vein, at the end of twelve hours (temperature<lb/>
103.4&deg;), we took 1.5 c.c. of blood and injected subcutaneously<lb/>
into second subject, resulting in a pretty infection in two days,<lb/>
twelve hours. Much to my regret we had no one for another<lb/>
injection. The parasite is therefore in the general circulation,<lb/>
and yellow fever thus follows exactly the modes of convey-<lb/>
ance found in malarial fever. I have already saturated towels<lb/>
with blood of these cases and have put them in our infected<lb/>
clothing house. Probably nothing will come of this attempt to<lb/>
convey infection. We now have six successes out of seven<lb/>
attempted by means of mosquito bites (85.71 per cent.).</p>
<p>McConnell is here at work.</p>
<p>Jan. 27, 1901.</p>
<p>As McConnell has completed his drawings here, I have con-<lb/>
cluded to let him go on transport <hi rend="italic">Rawlins</hi> which leaves today<lb/>
instead of waiting for the next boat. He carries with him a<lb/>
copy of our additional note with charts. I hope that Dr. Gould<lb/>
this time will return proofs to you so that corrections can be<lb/>
made before final publication. The article would be in time,<lb/>
if it appeared about February 10-15. I trust that what I have<lb/>
written may meet with your approval. I hope to leave here<lb/>
on Ward Line steamer leaving Havana, February 9. Have no<lb/>
order yet for Neate's relief from this station, but trust that it<lb/>
will come soon as well as order relieving Private Andrus and<lb/>
assigning him to Army Medical School laboratory. I will ask<lb/>
you to make a slight change in the wording of our eighth con-<lb/>
clusion, so that the word &ldquo;contaminated&rdquo; be inserted before the<lb/>
word mosquitoes--so that it will read as follows: &ldquo;A house<lb/>
may be said to be infected with yellow fever only when there<lb/>
are present within its walls contaminated mosquitoes capable<lb/>
of conveying the parasite of this disease.&rdquo; I will, also, ask that<lb/>
you change the relative position of conclusions No. 9 and 10,<lb/>
so that No. 9 will come last.<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENTS</hi><lb/>
227</p>
<p>Jan. 31, 1901.</p>
<p>I cabled to you this afternoon, requesting that you delay<lb/>
publication of our additional note until you receive the copy<lb/>
which I shall mail in the morning. I have inserted a footnote<lb/>
of importance which I thought should accompany the note<lb/>
when published. Although our immune (mosquito made)<lb/>
cases, four in number, have shown no symptoms whatever,<lb/>
I am very uneasy about the nonimmune soldier who got the<lb/>
same quantity of blood (1 c.c.) at the same time. He seems<lb/>
to have acquired a very serious infection, his temperature run-<lb/>
ning along the 104&deg; line now for three days. Albumen appeared<lb/>
at the end of eighteen hours, but is not excessive. Should he<lb/>
die, I shall regret that I ever undertook this work. The<lb/>
responsibility for the life of a human being weighs upon me<lb/>
very heavily just at present, and I am dreadfully melancholic.<lb/>
Everything is being done for him that we know how to do.</p>
<p>This afternoon the Mexican delegates were here to see our<lb/>
cases and afterwards visited the experimental camp. They<lb/>
seemed to be wonderfully impressed with what they heard and<lb/>
saw. Please substitute the copy which I shall forward tomor-<lb/>
row for the copy McConnell brought. I will ask that McCon-<lb/>
nell change the period of incubation on chart No. 11 to five<lb/>
days, seventeen hours. Although the patient took to bed, com-<lb/>
plaining of headache, etc., at the end of four days, twenty<lb/>
hours, his febrile paroxysm did not begin till five days and<lb/>
seventeen hours. If you think that the disease begins with<lb/>
the advent of premonitory symptoms, you can let it stand as<lb/>
at present. I leave that to you entirely. I shall hope to leave<lb/>
on the <hi rend="italic">McPherson</hi> about February 8.</p>
<p>Sincerely yours,<lb/>
WALTER REED.</p>
<pb n="272" id="f03056011"/>
<p>272<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi></p>
<p>nized and properly cared for. Careful sanitary supervision is<lb/>
therefore essential; it is, moreover, economical in the interest<lb/>
of the canal and of the government which has undertaken to<lb/>
construct it, as well as of those who are engaged in the actual<lb/>
work of excavation.</p>
<p>In the army, for military reasons, the medical department<lb/>
is not given any direct authority for the execution of sanitary<lb/>
measures outside of the general and post hospitals, which are<lb/>
under the direct command of medical officers. The command-<lb/>
ing officer of a camp or of a military post is responsible for<lb/>
the execution of necessary measures which may be recom-<lb/>
mended by the Surgeon-General of the army, or by the surgeon<lb/>
of his command, or which may be required by army regulations<lb/>
and general orders from the War Department. In carrying<lb/>
out these sanitary measures the medical department has only<lb/>
an advisory function. An officer of the line, or of the engineer<lb/>
corps, or of the Quartermaster's department, is detailed, with<lb/>
enlisted men or civilian employees to assist him, to dig the<lb/>
sewer, or lay the water pipes, or drain the swamp, etc.; and<lb/>
the general sanitary police of the post or camp is maintained<lb/>
by a detail of enlisted men, or by a squad of general prisoners<lb/>
under the direction of a &ldquo;police sergeant,&rdquo; or in some cases by<lb/>
civilian employees engaged for this special service. Whether<lb/>
this method is best for the army has been seriously questioned;<lb/>
and it is contended by some medical officers that better results<lb/>
would be obtained if more authority were given to the medical<lb/>
officers, and they were made responsible for the carrying out<lb/>
of necessary sanitary measures, and not simply for making<lb/>
suitable recommendations. However this may be, there can<lb/>
be no question that the sanitary service on the line of the isth-<lb/>
mian canal should be under one head, and that the carrying<lb/>
out of measures for the prevention of disease and the care of<lb/>
the sick should be placed in the hands of a competent &ldquo;medical<lb/>
director,&rdquo; having an efficient staff and full power to act in<lb/>
accordance with his best judgment for the accomplishment of<lb/>
the desired results.</p>
<p>The cost of such a sanitary service would not be inconsid-<lb/>
erable, but it would not be great when considered in connection<lb/>
with the magnitude and importance of the work; and I do not<lb/>
hesitate to affirm that, from an economic point of view, such<lb/>
a sanitary service as I have indicated would greatly reduce the<lb/>
cost of constructing the canal, and would shorten the time<lb/>
required for its completion.</p>
<p>A single epidemic of yellow fever occurring among the<lb/>
employees along the line of the canal, at a time when the work<lb/>
was being actively prosecuted, would, without doubt, be more<lb/>
expensive than the cost of an efficient sanitary service during<lb/>
the entire period of construction.<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">LAST CONTRIBUTIONS</hi><lb/>
273</p>
<p>HISTORY OF THE YELLOW FEVER BOARD</p>
<p>Spurred on by the advice of his intimate friends and stimu-<lb/>
lated by the promised attendance of some of his scientific<lb/>
co-workers from Latin America, General Sternberg summar-<lb/>
ized, for presentation before the Pan-American Scientific Con-<lb/>
gress in 1915, the &ldquo;Researches Relating to the Etiology of<lb/>
Yellow Fever Which Culminated in the Findings of the Reed<lb/>
Board.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is generally recognized that the demonstration that yellow<lb/>
fever is transmitted by mosquitoes of the genus Stegomyia is<lb/>
one of the greatest achievements of modern sciences. And<lb/>
the credit for this demonstration is justly given to the com-<lb/>
mission of which Maj. Walter Reed, Surgeon, U. S. Army,<lb/>
was president, which was sent to Havana in 1900, on the rec-<lb/>
ommendation of the writer, then Surgeon-General of the Army.</p>
<p>Doctor Carlos Finlay of Havana had long before conceived<lb/>
the idea that the disease under consideration is transmitted by<lb/>
mosquitoes, and full credit should be given him for persistently<lb/>
advocating this theory, although his own experiments failed to<lb/>
furnish any satisfactory proof that his theory was well<lb/>
founded. Indeed, such proof was wanting in the earlier<lb/>
experiments of the Reed Board, and it was not until, as a final<lb/>
experiment, the mosquitoes, after filling themselves with blood<lb/>
from a yellow fever patient, were kept for ten or twelve days<lb/>
before allowing them to bite a susceptible individual, that suc-<lb/>
cess was attained.</p>
<p>In a report published in May, 1901, Major Reed says: &ldquo;We<lb/>
have thus far succeeded in conveying yellow fever to twelve<lb/>
individuals by means of the bites of contaminated mosquitoes.&rdquo;<lb/>
Confirmation of these results was soon after afforded by the<lb/>
experiments of Dr. Juan Guiteras, and today yellow fever<lb/>
prophylaxis is successfully based on this epochmaking<lb/>
discovery.</p>
<p>But as to the precise nature of the etiologic agent, or &ldquo;germ,&rdquo;<lb/>
we are still uncertain, although in the present state of science<lb/>
we can scarcely fail to believe in a living germ, which multi-<lb/>
plies in the blood of infected individuals, but which is so<lb/>
minute that it has not yet been demonstrated by the highest<lb/>
powers of the microscope.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. This historical r&eacute;sum&eacute; was prepared a few weeks before the<lb/>
lamented death of General Sternberg, and is an important contribution<lb/>
to the history of that momentous period. All of which the writer<lb/>
knew and a large part of which he was. John Van R. Hoff, M.D.<lb/>
(Colonel, U. S. Army, Retired).</p>
<pb n="274" id="f03056012"/>
<p>274<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi></p>
<p>I have no new facts to add to our knowledge of yellow fever<lb/>
etiology. But it has occurred to me that a brief account of<lb/>
the investigations which led up to the demonstration that<lb/>
yellow fever is transmitted by mosquitoes might be of some<lb/>
interest to the members of the Pan American Scientific Con-<lb/>
gress. Such an account must begin with the Havana Yellow<lb/>
Fever Commission of 1879.</p>
<p>The wide extent and great mortality of the yellow fever<lb/>
epidemic of 1878 led to the organization of a U. S. National<lb/>
Board of Health. And it was evidently expected that one of<lb/>
the most important duties of this board would be to attempt<lb/>
to devise methods for the prevention of similar epidemics.</p>
<p>Among the members of this National Board of Health was<lb/>
Dr. S. M. Bemis of New Orleans, who no doubt had much<lb/>
to do with the selection of the members of the commission<lb/>
which it was decided should be sent to Havana to study the<lb/>
disease in one of its principal endemic foci. The membership<lb/>
of this commission was as follows: President, Dr. Stanford<lb/>
E. Chaill&eacute;, New Orleans, Secretary, Surgeon George M. Stern-<lb/>
berg, U. S. Army; Dr. Juan Guiteras, U. S. Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service, and Mr. T. S. Hardee, a civil engineer of New<lb/>
Orleans. Mr. Rudolph Matas of New Orleans was appointed<lb/>
clerk to the commission, and Mr. Henry Mancel, a Frenchman<lb/>
living in New Orleans, was engaged as photographer.</p>
<p>In the division of our work it was decided that Dr. Chaill&eacute;<lb/>
should make investigations relating to the prevalence of yellow<lb/>
fever in the island of Cuba. This he did in a most compre-<lb/>
hensive manner, as is shown by his published report to the<lb/>
National Board of Health. Doctor Guiteras undertook the<lb/>
search for micro-organisms and for pathologic changes in the<lb/>
tissues of yellow fever cadavers. This he did, <hi rend="italic">secundum<lb/>
artem</hi>, but his painstaking labors did not throw any new light<lb/>
on the etiology of the disease. To me was assigned the exam-<lb/>
ination of the blood, culture experiments, and experiments on<lb/>
lower animals. It would be tedious to attempt to give details<lb/>
of my numerous experiments and observations, but I may say<lb/>
that I failed to find any micro-organisms in the blood of living<lb/>
patients drawn on different days of sickness and did not suc-<lb/>
ceed in producing any symptoms resembling yellow fever in<lb/>
the lower animals subjected to experiment.</p>
<p>I may say that in advance of my visit to Havana I had strong<lb/>
hopes that, by modern methods of research, the germ of this<lb/>
infectious disease might be found in the blood, and I was pre-<lb/>
pared to photograph it if found. I was provided with Zeiss<lb/>
1&sol;12 and 1&sol;18 inch homogeneous oil immersion objectives and<lb/>
I had received instructions in the art of making photomicro-<lb/>
graphs from Surgeon J. J. Woodward, U. S. Army, a pioneer<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p> Havana Yellow Fever Commission, 1879.<lb/>
1. Dr. George M. Sternberg. 2. Dr. Juan Guiteras. 3. Dr. Daniel M. Burgess.<lb/>
4. Dr. Stanford E. Chaill&eacute;. 5. Mr. A. H. Taylor. 6. Dr. Rudolph Matas.</p>
<pb n="275" id="f03056013"/>
<p>Figure 1<lb/>
Figure 4<lb/>
Figure 3<lb/>
Figure 5<lb/>
Figure 2<lb/>
Fig. 1.--Yellow fever blood; fifth day; fatal case. &times; 1,450.<lb/>
Fig. 2.--Yellow fever blood; first day; fatal case. &times; 1,450.<lb/>
Fig. 3.--Yellow fever blood; fifth day; fatal case. &times; 1,450.<lb/>
Fig. 4.--Leukocyte in yellow fever blood kept in a culture cell for two days,<lb/>
eighth day; fatal case. &times; 650.<lb/>
Fig. 5.--Leukocyte in yellow fever blood kept in culture cell for two days;<lb/>
eighth day; fatal case (same as Fig. 3). &times; 650.<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">LAST CONTRIBUTIONS</hi><lb/>
275</p>
<p>and recognized expert in the art at the Army Medical Museum.<lb/>
Ninety-eight specimens from forty-one undoubted cases of<lb/>
yellow fever were carefully studied, with a completely negative<lb/>
result, so far as micro-organisms were concerned. My photo-<lb/>
micrographs were mostly made with a magnifying power of<lb/>
1,450 diameters, obtained by the use of a Zeiss 1/18 inch<lb/>
objective and a Tolles amplifier.</p>
<p>I have a reproduction of a plate illustrating my report on<lb/>
the etiology and prevention of yellow fever, published in 1890.<lb/>
These photographs of yellow fever blood were made in Havana<lb/>
in 1879. The report embodies the researches made by me sub-<lb/>
sequent to the return of the yellow fever commission. In it<lb/>
I say:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The investigations to which this report relates were made<lb/>
in the city of Havana, in the summers of 1888 and 1889; in<lb/>
the city of Decatur, Ala., in the autumn of 1888; and in the<lb/>
laboratories of the Johns Hopkins University, where I have<lb/>
continued my researches during the intervals between my visits<lb/>
to the infected localities, and since my return from Havana,<lb/>
in September, 1889, up to the present date.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;My bacteriologic studies have been made with material<lb/>
obtained from forty-three yellow fever cadavers; from &lsquo;black<lb/>
vomit&rsquo; and feces of patients in various stages of the disease;<lb/>
and from comparison, from eighteen cadavers in which death<lb/>
occurred from some other disease than yellow fever, and from<lb/>
feces of healthy individuals.&rdquo;</p>
<p>After the extended researches in this report I state my con-<lb/>
clusions as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The experimental data recorded in this report show that:</p>
<p>The specific infectious agent in yellow fever has not been<lb/>
demonstrated.</p>
<p>The most approved bacteriologic methods fail to demonstrate<lb/>
the constant presence of any particular micro-organisms in the<lb/>
blood and tissues of yellow fever cadavers.</p>
<p>The micro-organisms which are sometimes obtained in cul-<lb/>
tures from the blood and tissues are present in comparatively<lb/>
small numbers, and the one most frequently found ( <hi rend="italic">Bacterium<lb/>
coli commune</hi>) is present in the intestines of healthy individ-<lb/>
uals, and consequently its occasional presence can not have any<lb/>
etiologic import.</p>
<p>A few scattered bacilli are present in the liver and probably<lb/>
in other organs, at the moment of death. This is shown by<lb/>
preserving portions of liver, obtained at recent autopsy, in an<lb/>
antiseptic wrapping.</p>
<p>At the end of from twenty-four to forty-eight hours the<lb/>
interior of a piece of liver so preserved contains a large num-<lb/>
ber of bacilli of various species, the most abundant being those<lb/>
<pb n="276" id="f03056014"/>
276<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi><lb/>
heretofore mentioned as occasionally found in fresh liver<lb/>
tissue, viz., <hi rend="italic">Bacterium coli commune</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bacillus cadaveris</hi>.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Having failed to demonstrate the presence of a specific<lb/>
&ldquo;germ&rdquo; in the blood and tissues it seemed possible that it is to<lb/>
be found in the alimentary canal, as is the case in cholera. But<lb/>
the extended researches made and recorded in the present<lb/>
report show that the contents of the intestines of yellow fever<lb/>
cases contain a great variety of bacilli and not a nearly pure<lb/>
culture of a single species, as is the case in recent and typical<lb/>
cases of cholera.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;On the other hand nonliquefying bacilli are very abundant.</p>
<p>The one most constantly and abundantly present is the <hi rend="italic">Bac-<lb/>
terium coli commune</hi> of Escherich.</p>
<p>This is associated with various other bacilli, some of which<lb/>
are strict anaerobics and some facultative anaerobics.</p>
<p>Among the facultative anaerobics is one--my <hi rend="italic">Bacillus X</hi>--<lb/>
which has been isolated by the culture method in a consider-<lb/>
able number of cases and may have been present in all. This<lb/>
bacillus has not been encountered in the comparative experi-<lb/>
ments made. It is very pathogenic for rabbits when injected<lb/>
into the cavity of the abdomen.</p>
<p>It is possible that this bacillus is concerned in the etiology<lb/>
of yellow fever, but no satisfactory evidence that this is the<lb/>
case has been obtained by experiments on the lower animals,<lb/>
and it has not been found in such numbers as to warrant the<lb/>
inference that it is the veritable infectious agent.</p>
<p>All other micro-organisms obtained in pure cultures from<lb/>
yellow fever cadavers appear to be excluded, either by having<lb/>
been identified with known species, or by having been found<lb/>
in comparative researches made outside of the area of yellow<lb/>
fever prevalence, or by the fact that they have been found only<lb/>
in small numbers and in a limited number of cases.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It will be seen that I did not positively exclude my <hi rend="italic">Bacillus<lb/>
X</hi> as a possible etiologic factor, but I say that it was not found<lb/>
&ldquo;in such numbers as to warrant the inference that it is the<lb/>
veritable infectious agent.&rdquo; In 1893 I was appointed Surgeon-<lb/>
General of the Army, and my opportunities for personal<lb/>
research work ceased. My published reports had apparently<lb/>
satisfied the profession that the various claims which had been<lb/>
made for the discovery of the specific germ of yellow fever<lb/>
had no substantial foundation. Among these were the claims<lb/>
of Domingos Freire of Brazil, of Carmona y Valle of Mexico,<lb/>
of Carlos Finlay <hi rend="superscript">1</hi> of Havana, and of Paul Gibier of France.</p>
<p>Since my report above referred to was published a new<lb/>
claimant appeared, viz., the Italian bacteriologist, Sanarelli.<lb/>
His researches were made in Brazil, and, singularly enough,</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>1. His micrococcus tetragenus febris flavae.<lb/>
<lb/></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">LAST CONTRIBUTIONS</hi><lb/>
277</p>
<p>he found in the blood of the first case examined by him a bacil-<lb/>
lus. It was present in large numbers, but this case is unique,<lb/>
for neither Sanarelli nor anyone else has since found it in such<lb/>
abundance. It has been found in small numbers in the blood<lb/>
and tissues of yellow fever cadavers in a certain number of<lb/>
cases examined. For a time I thought it probable that Sana-<lb/>
relli's bacillus was identical with my <hi rend="italic">Bacillus X</hi>. But the<lb/>
researches of the Reed board identified it with the bacillus of<lb/>
hog cholera, while my <hi rend="italic">Bacillus X</hi> appeared to them to belong<lb/>
to the colon group. The bacillus of Sanarelli had a certain<lb/>
amount of standing for a time because two medical officers of<lb/>
the U. S. Marine Hospital Service, who had been sent to<lb/>
Havana to study yellow fever, made a report favorable to the<lb/>
claims of Sanarelli. But the researches of Reed, Carroll and<lb/>
Agramonte have demonstrated conclusively that this bacillus<lb/>
has nothing to do with the etiology of yellow fever.</p>
<p>At the present date Dr. Aristides Agramonte is the only<lb/>
living member of the Yellow Fever Commission appointed<lb/>
upon my recommendation in 1900. Major Walter Reed, Sur-<lb/>
geon U. S. Army, was selected as president of this commission<lb/>
because he was a trained bacteriologist and at the time of his<lb/>
appointment was in charge of our bacteriologic laboratory at<lb/>
the Army Medical Museum. He died in Washington from<lb/>
appendicitis, Nov. 23, 1902, aged 51. Since his death various<lb/>
articles published in the newspapers have stated that he died<lb/>
as a result of his yellow fever investigations. This is a mis-<lb/>
take. Dr. Reed was in Washington at the time that Dr. Car-<lb/>
roll made, on himself, the first successful yellow fever inocu-<lb/>
lation, and he was not inoculated.</p>
<p>Dr. James Carroll died in Washington, March 9, 1907, of<lb/>
myocarditis which was believed by his physicians to have<lb/>
resulted from the severe attack of yellow fever which he<lb/>
suffered in 1900. Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, Contract Surgeon, U.<lb/>
S. Army, was appointed a member of the commission because<lb/>
he had had special training as a bacteriologist. He died at<lb/>
Camp Columbia, Cuba, of yellow fever, Sept. 25, 1900. His<lb/>
attack was attributed to the bite of a mosquito, while he was<lb/>
visiting the wards of a yellow fever hospital.</p>
<p>The written instructions given by me to this selected board<lb/>
of experts were as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;You will naturally give special attention to questions relat-<lb/>
ing to the etiology and prevention of yellow fever. As you<lb/>
are familiar with what has already been done by other bac-<lb/>
teriologists in this field of investigation, I do not consider it<lb/>
necessary to give you any suggestions or detailed instructions.<lb/>
But it is evident that the most important question which will<lb/>
occupy your attention is that which relates to the etiology of this<lb/>
disease.</p>
<pb n="278" id="f03056015"/>
<p>278<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">GEORGE M. STERNBERG</hi></p>
<p>You will also take advantage of such opportunities as may<lb/>
offer for the study of other infectious diseases, and especially<lb/>
of the malarial fevers prevailing on the island of Cuba. An<lb/>
important question in connection with the disease of tropical<lb/>
and semitropical countries relates to the etiology of febrile<lb/>
attacks of short duration, to which strangers are especially<lb/>
subject. Should you have time, there will be ample opportunity<lb/>
for the study of leprosy in the lepers' hospital in the city of<lb/>
Havana. Attention should also be given to the infectious dis-<lb/>
eases of the lower animals, in case any such prevail, the<lb/>
etiology of which has not been definitely determined.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In addition to these written instructions I talked freely with<lb/>
Major Reed, president of the Commission, and gave him my<lb/>
views as to the most promising lines of experiments relating<lb/>
to the etiology of yellow fever.</p>
<p>I urged that efforts should be made to ascertain definitely<lb/>
whether the disease can be communicated from man to man<lb/>
by blood inoculations. Evidently if this is the case the blood<lb/>
must contain the living infectious agent on which the propa-<lb/>
gation of the disease depends, notwithstanding the fact that all<lb/>
attempts to demonstrate the presence of such a germ in the<lb/>
blood, by means of the microscope and culture methods, had<lb/>
proved unavailing. I had previously demonstrated by repeated<lb/>
experiments that inoculations of yellow fever blood into lower<lb/>
animals--dogs, rabbits, guinea-pigs--give a negative result, but<lb/>
this negative result might be because these animals were not<lb/>
susceptible to the disease and could not be accepted as showing<lb/>
that the germ of yellow fever was not present in the blood.<lb/>
A single inoculation experiment on man had been made in my<lb/>
presence, in the city of Vera Cruz, in 1887, by Dr. Daniel Ruiz,<lb/>
who was in charge of the civil hospital in that city. But this<lb/>
experiment was inconclusive for the reason that the patient<lb/>
from whom the blood was obtained was in the eight day of<lb/>
the disease, and it was quite possible that the specific germ<lb/>
might have been present at an earlier period and that after a<lb/>
certain number of days the natural resources of the body are<lb/>
sufficient to effect its destruction, or in some way to cause its<lb/>
disappearance from the circulation.</p>
<p>I was especially anxious that this experiment should be<lb/>
repeated with the blood taken from a case in the early stages<lb/>
of the disease. I had not been able to make the experiment<lb/>
on myself, as I was immune, having suffered a severe attack<lb/>
of yellow fever in 1875.</p>
<p>The Reed Commission made this experiment with success<lb/>
after having demonstrated that the disease could be transmit-<lb/>
ted by mosquitoes which had been kept for ten or twelve days<lb/>
after biting a yellow fever patient. It is evident that if the<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">LAST CONTRIBUTIONS</hi><lb/>
279<lb/>
experiment had been made at the outset of the investigation<lb/>
a similar success would have led inevitably to the conclusion<lb/>
that yellow fever, like malarial fever, is transmitted by an inter-<lb/>
mediate host, and that this intermediate host is a mosquito.</p>
<p>So far as I am concerned, there is nothing more to be said<lb/>
about yellow fever etiology, and my excuse for writing this<lb/>
brief paper is to be found in the fact that the present genera-<lb/>
tion of physicians had not appeared on the stage when Profes-<lb/>
sor Chaill&eacute;, Dr. Juan Guiteras and myself visited Havana in<lb/>
1879, for the purpose of studying yellow fever, and probably<lb/>
few of the members of the profession have seen my published<lb/>
report of subsequent investigations made by me.</p>
<p>The following letter is here introduced as especially inter-<lb/>
esting in connection with Dr. Sternberg's research in yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>April 13, 1915.</p>
<p>My dear General Sternberg:--</p>
<p>A group of kindred spirits were discussing the eminent<lb/>
workers in American science the other evening and we all<lb/>
agreed not only in placing you among the foremost, but the<lb/>
first pioneer. It may also be some satisfaction for you to<lb/>
know that in our judgment Dame Fortune played you scurvy<lb/>
tricks, for the same amount of skill and energy devoted to<lb/>
plague, cholera, typhoid fever or any of the ordinary bacterial<lb/>
infections would have solved these riddles. However, in<lb/>
attacking the cause of yellow fever, you originated many<lb/>
methods which were afterwards used with success, and fur-<lb/>
thermore, cleared away the brush, or rather you blazed<lb/>
the trail which made it so much easier for those who<lb/>
followed. . . .</p>
<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
M. J. ROSENAU.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
