<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03059015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, April 29, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03059015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-04-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-04-29">April 29, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03059015</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, April 29, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses funding issues and a recent yellow fever outbreak.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-04-29">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, April 29, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03059015"/>
<opener>
COPY.<lb/>
DIRECCCION<lb/>
de la<lb/>
CAMPANA SANITARIA<lb/>
Contra La Fiebre Amarilla<lb/>
en Los Departamentos Del Norte<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru,<lb/>
<date value="1921-04-29">April 29, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Wicliffe Rose, General Director<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
New York, N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have thought considerably about the manner in which I ought to<lb/>
present an estimate of the amount of your participation in this campaign, and<lb/>
I very much regret that there has been so much delay in the matter. Frankly,<lb/>
I have been at a loss to know how to present this matter on account of the un-<lb/>
certainty of the financial conditions of the country. As an illustration I<lb/>
might tell you that although my contract with the Government calls for the pay<lb/>
of my salary on the first and the fifteenth of each month, up to date I have<lb/>
not been paid for either March or the first &ldquo;quincena&rdquo; of April. The Direccion<lb/>
de Salubridad has directed the Departmental Treasurer to pay me, but the Prefecto<lb/>
says that there are no funds on hand to pay with.</p>
<p>On April 5th I wrote you about the Lp1000.0.00 which we received from<lb/>
the Government for campaign expenses; this is all we have received up to date,<lb/>
and has all been used up, and we are again obliged to use of your funds for<lb/>
all campaign expenses until the local Treasurer gives us more money. These<lb/>
thousand pounds would have been sufficient for this month in this Department<lb/>
had it not been for the purchase of the Ford, which as I told you in a previous<lb/>
communication cost us Lp220.0.00. This was a necessary purchase, as we are in<lb/>
constant need of this type of transportation, both for long and short trips of<lb/>
inspection to places which can not be reached by railroad. This was bought with<lb/>
Government funds. We are sending you a copy of the financial statement to the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03059016"/>
Mr. Wicliffe Rose<lb/>
April 29, 1921<lb/>
2.<lb/>
Direccion de Salubridad of the use of the funds just mentioned, together<lb/>
with a statement of the use of funds from the International Health Board<lb/>
for this month.</p>
<p>On account of the above mentioned conditions, I made the follow-<lb/>
ing statement to Mr. Kirk, Comptroller of the Rockefeller Foundation:</p>
<p>&ldquo;My principal difficulty at present is to determine the distribu-<lb/>
tion of costs between the funds of the ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION<lb/>
and THE GOVERNMENT. If I make a fixed estimate, I may find my-<lb/>
self in the position I was before, where I have plenty of your<lb/>
funds, but none on hand from the Government. What action do<lb/>
you authorize me to take in such a case? Now I am in this<lb/>
position again.&rdquo;</p>
<p>However with the &ldquo;idea of persuading the Government to come across<lb/>
with a definite amount&rdquo; I am submitting the following statement of an estimate<lb/>
for your approval and am sending them a copy of the same. I will include copy<lb/>
of my letter to them for your information.</p>
<p>In this estimate I am taking most of the most important men on your<lb/>
payroll, with the idea of having things so arranged that I can keep the most<lb/>
important work going without any interruption. It might happen that in case<lb/>
these men were working on a strictly Government payroll, and we arrived at one<lb/>
of these times when there were no funds in sight that they would refuse to work<lb/>
without being assured of their pay, and some of them have no means of living<lb/>
without such assurance, being men away from their home circles, and I would then<lb/>
be in a serious plight with a part of the work paralyzed. It is also for the<lb/>
same reason that I have taken the principal employees of the Central Office on<lb/>
your pay roll according to this estimate. If this does not meet with your ap-<lb/>
proval kindly cable me to that effect, and I will do what I can to make other<lb/>
suitable arrangements.</p>
<p>As you will note, in the Province of Pacasmayo, in the Department of<lb/>
Libertad, I have taken all the expenses of the campaign on your account. For<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03059017"/>
Mr. Wicliffe Rose, April 29, 1921. 3.<lb/>
the rest of the Department of Libertad, I have taken the most important<lb/>
supervising Inspectors on your account as well as one Inspector for each of<lb/>
the ports of the department. These men all consider it a compliment and a<lb/>
privilege to be allowed to work on the account of the International Health<lb/>
Board, which has its advantages in that I can demand more of them, and get<lb/>
more prompt and willing work.</p>
<p>The nature of the work of the principal Inspectors on this estimate<lb/>
is such that they can not very well establish fixed residence, and it seems to<lb/>
be necessary that they receive traveling expenses, which I have calculated and<lb/>
included. For Messrs. Secley, Richardson, Guildstrand and Dr. Mendoza I am<lb/>
allowing actual expenses. For Arturo Sainz I have allowed three soles and<lb/>
fifty centavos daily, for Sr. Manuel Machado who is the best of the native<lb/>
Peruvian Inspectors, and who will have more traveling and supervisory functions<lb/>
than any except the American Inspectors I will be obliged to allow up to five<lb/>
soles daily according to the nature of his details. I am also allowing limited<lb/>
expenses for Juan E. Adrienzen, Felipe Benites, Joaquin Castillo, and E. Ramirez<lb/>
Aguirro.</p>
<p>As you will notice, I have also taken the rent for the Central Office<lb/>
on the International Health Board account, to avoid being ordered out when the<lb/>
rent falls due.</p>
<p>According to the letter from Mr. Kirk you do not plan for me to cash<lb/>
your appropriation, except as we use it, which is a natural course of procedure,<lb/>
On account of the unusually low exchange prevailing, I have wondered whether or<lb/>
not it might not be advantageous to take advantage of this prevailing rate, if<lb/>
one could know that it was not going lower. On the first five thousand we paid<lb/>
$3.95 for the Peruvian pound, on the second we paid $3.62. The Bankers say they<lb/>
can give no indication whether it will rise or fall. What do you advise?</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03059018"/>
<p>Mr. Wicliffe Rose<lb/>
April 29, 1921.<lb/>
4.<lb/>
CONDITION OF THE EPIDEMIC.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In this Department the epidemic is under control, and the cases<lb/>
are gradually declining. Our stegomya index is generally low. At the<lb/>
present time the index in Chiclayo is about 2% based on the number of con-<lb/>
tainers found with breeding in relation to the total number of containers<lb/>
inspected. In Olmos it seems that the entire population has been immunized,<lb/>
the new cases being those coming in from small villages in the interior. In<lb/>
Motupe where we had probably the most severe outbreak with the greatest<lb/>
number of cases in proportion to the size of the town, the number of cases<lb/>
has fallen to six on hand. Unfortunately for the people, the fever has ex-<lb/>
tended up the valleys into the Department of Cajamarca, but can not go very far<lb/>
in that direction, and has no importance as a means of propagation to the south,<lb/>
or north. I do not think the <del>the</del> rain is such that it will permit the reintro-<lb/>
duction into Ecuador. The department of Piura is between this Department and<lb/>
Ecuador, and we are continuing the prophylactic campaign in the Valley of the<lb/>
Morropon, i. e., in Morropon, Chullucanas, and Tambogrande, as well as in<lb/>
Catacaos, Piura, Sullana and Paita. As soon as I have inspected the work in<lb/>
Libertad I intend to arrange for Dr. Quiroz to make an inspection of the work<lb/>
in the Department of Piura.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Unfortunately the land quarantine to the south has been violated, and<lb/>
we have had cases in Guadelupe and San Pedro. Those in San Pedro were in<lb/>
soldiers from the frontier guard. This is a condition which I had hoped would<lb/>
not come to pass, but which I nevertheless feared would come, and of which I<lb/>
warned the authorities of Libertad on my first visit. They have also reported<lb/>
two cases from near Trujillo, but they have based their diagnosis (according<lb/>
to their report) on the finding of the leptospira &ldquo;Noguchi&rdquo;, and I have no con-<lb/>
fidence in their ability either to find or to recognize the leptospira. I<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03059019"/>
Mr. Wicliffe Rose,<lb/>
April 29, 1921.<lb/>
5.<lb/>
cabled you about this, and will go there on the first steamer, I started<lb/>
for there in my auto yesterday, but had to turn back when I reached Ucupe,<lb/>
on account of water in the road.</p>
<p>The stegomya index in the Province of Pacasmaya is as follows<lb/>
according to the last reports: Chepen 4%, Guadelupe 4.4%, Pacasmayo 12%,<lb/>
Pueblo Nuevo 2.4% and San Pedro 0.6%. Soldiers fell sick after arriving in<lb/>
San Pedro. The cold weather together with the arrival of Richardson, Machado,<lb/>
Ramirez and Dr. Quiroz will reinforce the work in that department to the extent<lb/>
that there ought not to be an extensive outbreak. Besides there has been an<lb/>
antistegomya campaign in progress there ever since Dr. Carter and I were there<lb/>
early in February. This naturally has not been efficient, but it has reduced<lb/>
very considerably the breeding, and under the supervision of Richardson and<lb/>
Machado it will soon become effective.</p>
<p>Up to date we have a total of known definite cases in Chiclayo of<lb/>
70. How many more there have been, we can not say at present.</p>
<p>Referring again to the matter of the American Inspectors which we<lb/>
have, I presume from what Dr. M. E. Connor told Mr. Richardson in Lima, that<lb/>
we are paying more for Inspectors than you are accustomed to pay for such men.<lb/>
When Dr. Carter went up we agreed that he should engaged a man in Panama whom<lb/>
I would take on your account, and I suggested Lp 80.0.00, but it seems that the<lb/>
agreement was made for $400.00 and traveling expenses. In the estimate I have<lb/>
put both Mr. Secley and Mr. Richardson down for Lp 80.0.00 per month. Mr.<lb/>
Richardson's original contract was for $400.00 per month and his traveling<lb/>
expenses when away from his home station. His family lives in Miraflores, and<lb/>
naturally when he is away his household expenses continue practically the same<lb/>
as if he were with the family. I thought that we might take these men for the<lb/>
Lp. 80.00 on your account, and the Government of Peru could pay the difference<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03059020"/>
Mr. Wicliffe Rose,<lb/>
April 29, 1921.<lb/>
6.<lb/>
due to the low exchange.</p>
<p>In regard to the Libertad organization I will send you more details<lb/>
either from there direct or when I return after my tour of inspection and re-<lb/>
organization of the work there,. I expect to leave here on the Chilean<lb/>
steamer Aysen on Sunday, May 1st, and will be there about ten days, depending<lb/>
on the steamer schedules.</p>
<p>Our mail and steamer service here is about as bad as such service<lb/>
could well be, sometimes we go more than two weeks between steamers and mail.<lb/>
The mail at times (from the north) is taken to Lima, and redistributed for the<lb/>
infected territory at convenience of a group of lazy and indifferent postal<lb/>
employees. It would greatly help matters if you could mail me a code, best by<lb/>
some Grace Line steamer sailing from New York, with Itinerary for Pimentel or<lb/>
Eten. If such a boat does not happen to be convenient we will have to trust to<lb/>
luck that I will get it before the campaign is finished. I have not yet lost<lb/>
hope that we will dominate the whole thing before the end of the year.</p>
<p>We have recently been informed that W. D. Wrightson has been named<lb/>
&ldquo;Director de Salubridad&rdquo; in place of Dr. J. Gil Cardenas.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) HENRY HANSON,<lb/>
Director of Sanitary Campaign</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
