<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03059021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, May 6, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03059021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-05-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-05-06">May 6, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03059021</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, May 6, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses the spread of yellow fever in Peru, and the use of fish to control mosquitoes. He also discusses funding issues.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-05-06">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, May 6, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03059021"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
<dateline>
Trujillo<lb/>
<date value="1921-05-06">May 6, 1921</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Wic<add>k</add>liffe Rose, Field Manager,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York, N.Y.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Mr. Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I cabled you before leaving Chiclayo, and also after arriv-<lb/>
ing in Trujillo. As you know I came down here in response to a notice<lb/>
about the appearance of a case of yellow fever in this place. When this<lb/>
case was first announced by the local physicians there was a great clamor<lb/>
denying that it could be true. Even the Prefecto sent me several tele-<lb/>
grams before I came insisting that it was all unfounded rumor, which was<lb/>
causing a tremendous amount of damage to the Department.</p>
<p>I arranged to come down on the first possible opportunity, to<lb/>
investigate and establish the diagnosis, but on account of the difficulties<lb/>
we have had with the itinerary of the ships, since the epidemic, there was<lb/>
a delay of about a week before I could get here. I first tried to go<lb/>
overland in our Ford, but when I got to Ucupe we found the there was so<lb/>
much water in the road across the desert that we could not get through,<lb/>
and had to go back and wait for steamer.</p>
<p>I arrived here on the 3rd and at once went to see the case, a<lb/>
Japanese, who was then in begin<add>n</add>ing convalesence, an absolutely typical case,<lb/>
with an abundance of albumen in urine, still with bleeding about the gums,<lb/>
very yellow even to the tongue itself, eyes typical, profound prostration<lb/>
and in fact with everything one needs to make a diagnosis of yellow fever.<lb/>
There could be no doubt in my mind about him.</p>
<p>With this information we have set about reorganizing the work,<lb/>
and have decided that this will be the most important as well as the stra-<lb/>
tegic place for the main office for the continuation of the campaign.<lb/>
The Lambayeque situation seems to be under complete control, and for the<lb/>
future I only expect a few cases during the period of life of the infected<lb/>
adult stegomy<add>i</add>a. There too the temperature has fallen considerably pro-<lb/>
longing the period of development of the larvae which helps very decidedly.<lb/>
In this place, Trujillo, we are at the real front of the advance of the<lb/>
epidemic, and with my presence here I do not feel that the campaign is in<lb/>
any danger of being lost, that is with the new program which we have<lb/>
organized for this section, and with a considerable training force at our<lb/>
disposal. For this purpose I have called Mr. Richardson and Sr.Manuel<lb/>
Machado and my former Lima Secretary Sr. Ramirez who also is a trained<lb/>
stegomy<add>i</add>a inspector.</p>
<p>In accordance with the information available here regarding the<lb/>
cases, I do not expect a pronounced outbreak before next week or the week<lb/>
following and possibly even later than that. It seems that we have been<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03059022"/>
Mr. Wic<add>k</add>liffe Rose<lb/>
May 6, 1921<lb/>
2.<lb/>
notified of this in its very beginning which means a great deal in con-<lb/>
trolling and stamping it out. In the past epidemics we have not had a chance<lb/>
to take a hold until the thing was well established and had had a chance<lb/>
to spread all over the territory in question. Here we also have the<lb/>
advantage that there has been a considerable amount of work done, es-<lb/>
pecially in the Province of Pacasmayo which as you know has been under the<lb/>
direction of Dr. Ricardo Mendoza, with a number of trained inspectors.<lb/>
The work there and the percentage of breeding I have already reported, in<lb/>
my letter written aboard the Aysen.</p>
<p>Since arriving I have reviewed the situation and find to my chagrin<lb/>
that the work here has not been done as well as I had hoped, and the breed-<lb/>
ing is very high. In the next few weeks I expect that we shall have an<lb/>
epidemic here in Trujillo in spite of all we can do. I say this for the<lb/>
reason that there have been two definite cases, and one other which I have<lb/>
seen and believe to be yellow fever. It is clear then that there are adult<lb/>
stegomy<add>i</add>a infected and in their period of incubation which means more cases<lb/>
of yellow fever. This according to all the rules of the game will come<lb/>
to pass notwithstanding the intensive campaign which we are organizing now.</p>
<p>We are using fish wherever it is possible. For the present we are<lb/>
catching small fish in the fresh water ponds and streams and distributing<lb/>
them for the wells and the tanks. In Pacasmayo we have some &ldquo;millions&rdquo;<lb/>
received from Dr. Pareja in Guayaquil, and are fixing up a hatchery there,<lb/>
so as to have on hand for distribution. We have also distributed fish of<lb/>
the type received from Guayaquil and those caught locally in the Department<lb/>
of Lambayeque. In addition we have the regular inspection of the &ldquo;boticas,<lb/>
tinajas&rdquo; etc.</p>
<p>Here I think I will do a little fumigation in the first foci found.<lb/>
This I know is not generally considered worth while, and I do not do it as<lb/>
a rule, but the fewer cases we can have the smaller will be the danger that<lb/>
some one is going to break through the land quarantine and spread the<lb/>
epidemic south. The south is the section to be defended if we are to acc-<lb/>
omplish our objective of eliminating the fever during the year 1921. I do<lb/>
not think that there is any real danger of it going back to Ecuador, but<lb/>
on this point I will soon have more detailed information.</p>
<p>good mor</p>
<p>I believe I told you that I arranged with Dr. Enri<add>q</add>ue Caballero<lb/>
of Catacaos to serve in the sanitary campaign, and I have directed him to<lb/>
make a preliminary inspection of the Piura frontier, both for the effi-<lb/>
cacy of the stegomy<add>i</add>a work and for any rumors of cases of suspicious illness,<lb/>
that we may have as complete data as possible from all sides of the present<lb/>
campaign. As soon as he arrives I will have him make a series of investi-<lb/>
gations in the ports to the south, between here and Callao, to find out if<lb/>
there have been any sick with symptoms resembling yellow fever. The<lb/>
&ldquo;Medicos Sanitarios&rdquo; should be the ones to furnish this information, but in<lb/>
the first place they know nothing about the bedside appearance of yellow<lb/>
fever, and in the second place they are nearly all of them corrupted by<lb/>
the rotten politics of the country to the extent that they could not be de-<lb/>
pended upon to inform me correctly if they did know of a case. To me this<lb/>
seems a perfectly justifiable expense, and means a great deal for the<lb/>
ultimate object of this campaign. Dr. Caballero is an immune and can travel<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03059023"/>
Mr. Wic<add>k</add>liffe Rose<lb/>
May 6, 1921<lb/>
3.<lb/>
freely without any quarantine restrictions.</p>
<p>In the Chiclayo office we are working up a resume of the re-<lb/>
ported cases to date and will send you this together with the financial<lb/>
statement for the past month.</p>
<p>I have worked up a budget for the Governments share of the<lb/>
campaign expenses for this Department, which is confined principally to<lb/>
the Province of Trujillo. In the budget which I sent you as the one<lb/>
proposed for the International Health Board, I indicated salaries for<lb/>
inspectors for the principal ports of the Department, but so far I have<lb/>
not engaged any men for these positions, nor do I have any men in sight<lb/>
at the present time with qualifications for these places. When I do<lb/>
place them it will probably be with salaries lower than those indicated<lb/>
in the budget. I have indicated maximum salaries in practically all those<lb/>
places, and expect to economize on those indicated where it can be done<lb/>
with safety. The budget for this campaign can not be made very rigid on<lb/>
account of the constantly changing conditions, and both the budget for the<lb/>
International Health Board and that for the Peruvian Government will have<lb/>
to be more or less flexible. For that reason in order to make a proper<lb/>
account of expenditure it will be clearer if we send you a copy of the<lb/>
financial statement to the Government covering the expenditure of Govern-<lb/>
ment funds and a copy of the financial statement of International Health<lb/>
Board funds to the Government, which will give a complete check in both<lb/>
places of the moneys spent. I have sent copies of the budgets to both<lb/>
places.</p>
<p>I am hoping to find some letters from you on my return to<lb/>
Chiclayo, in response to some of those which I have already sent upon the<lb/>
organization and on our first financial statement.</p>
<p>I am told that the exchange has risen considerably in the last<lb/>
few days, which makes me regretful that I did not convert the entire amount<lb/>
of the last $15,000.00 which you appropriated. It would have meant a great<lb/>
deal more peruvian money. I desisted from doing so on account of the<lb/>
wording of the letter of the Auditor of the Foundation. I still have<lb/>
$10,000.00 which have not yet been converted.</p>
<p>I shall be obliged to convert some of this soon for the expenses<lb/>
in the Province of Pacasmayo.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Henry Hanson,M.D.,<lb/>
Director of Sanitary Campaign</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
