<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03059040">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, June 18, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03059040</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-06-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Tapia, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Cardenas, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Vergne, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Caballero, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Pickett, I. W.</name>
<name type="person">Corrigan, John P.</name>
<name type="place">Lima (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Trujillo, (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Viru (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Libertad (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Ancash (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Callao (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-06-18">June 18, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03059040</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, June 18, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses funding and reports on yellow fever cases.  He requests more inspectors.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-06-18">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, June 18, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03059040"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION<lb/>
DE LA<lb/>
CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EL LOS DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
----<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru.,<lb/>
<date value="1921-06-18">June 18, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Wicliffe Rose, General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
51 Broadway, New York City.<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Mr Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just returned from a trip to Lima and a tour of inspection<lb/>
of the Department of Libertad. On returning I find upon my desk your letters of<lb/>
April 22, 26, May 6, 10, and 13 togather with copies of your letter to Dr. Car-<lb/>
donas of May 5, to the Minister of Fomento of May 10, and your letter to Mr.<lb/>
Pickett and Mr. Corrigan of May 10. In addition I have another letter from Mr.<lb/>
Bauch telling me that he is sending another Check book, which (the latter) has<lb/>
also been received.</p>
<p>In regard to the budgets, or detailed statements which I have sent<lb/>
I fear that you will begin to think that I am rather vacilating. It seems that<lb/>
I am unable to get up anything in the form of a budget that will actually stick.<lb/>
on account of the Government failing to live up to its share of the contract. I<lb/>
make plans to have the two accounts run along entirely separate, and then find<lb/>
that I have practically nothing but your funds to work with. Such has been the<lb/>
case since we used up the Lp 1000.0.00 which I received from the Government in<lb/>
the first week of April, and I have been running practically the entire campaign<lb/>
with your funds. This was one of the reasons for my trip to Lima. I have been<lb/>
convinced all the time that the Government would not pay up according to the<lb/>
original budgets, and for that reason made a modification approximating more<lb/>
closely what I think they should be requested to pay. Yesterday on my return I<lb/>
found a telegram waiting me stating that they had deposited, or rather passed a<lb/>
resolution, for the Italian Bank in Chiclayo to pay the commission Lp 1200.0.00<lb/>
monthly and for the same bank in Trujillo to pay Lp 850.0.00. Copy of telegram<lb/>
roads as follows:</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03059041"/>
<p>#2. W.R.,I.H.B., June 18, 1921.</p>
<p>Paseo Colon, June 15,<lb/>
Dr. Hanson .... Chiclayo.</p>
<p>Firmose resolucion para banco Italiano en Chiclayo pague una<lb/>
mensualidad por valor presupuesto ese departamento o sea mil doscientas<lb/>
libras y mismo banco en Trujillo abone ochocientas cincuenta  librus,<lb/>
valor presupuesto libertad, trascripcion va correo.- Salubridad.</p>
<p>If they will live up to this for a few months we will get along very<lb/>
nicely, because this will cover two thirds of the entire monthly expense of the<lb/>
campaign. In case we get this I will use of your funds only for special employ-<lb/>
ees whom I have definitely put on your payroll, in addition to salaries and ex-<lb/>
penses for Corrigan and Pickett.</p>
<p><hi>EPIDEMIC IN LIBERTAD</hi>.</p>
<p>Under separate cover we are sending you a copy<lb/>
of the report which we send to the &ldquo;Salubridad&rdquo; in Lima of the cases which have<lb/>
been officially seen and confirmed by the Commission, up to the end of the<lb/>
month of May. It appears that our work in connection with the cold weather<lb/>
will prevent a sharp epidemic in the city of Trujillo. Our percentage of breed-<lb/>
ing there has been reduced to 4%, as calculated by the reports turned in by the<lb/>
Inspectors and Domiciliary Visitors. This figure however does not show the<lb/>
work actually done because lately Dr. Tapia who is the Provincial Director had<lb/>
ordered that nothing but <unclear>barrels</unclear>, botijas, tinajas, tanks and wells should figure<lb/>
as a container or deposit examined. It happens that in Trujillo there are many<lb/>
&ldquo;corralaones&rdquo; i.e., a species of departments or flats, which have a common door<lb/>
or entrance from the street, and in many of these we have from ten to twenty<lb/>
apartments, in each of which there is a family. Since the campaign has been in-<lb/>
tensified all forms of containers with the exception of buckets and tin cans<lb/>
have been prohibited in these apartments, with the result that the visitor or<lb/>
inspector may visit as many as twenty families without a single large &ldquo;deposito&rdquo;<lb/>
to figure in sum on which the percentage is calculated. In Trujillo we do not<lb/>
find larvae in these small containers, the are emptied daily. In order to show<lb/>
the true percentage of foci of breeding we will have to adopt a different basis<lb/>
for the calculations and reports.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03059042"/>
<p>#3. W.R., I.H.B., June 18, 1921.</p>
<p>In regard to the true number of cases in the City of Trujillo we are<lb/>
unable to say anything definitely.beyond what we show in the official reports.<lb/>
In am quite certain that there have been many more cases, hidden in accordance<lb/>
with the habits of the people and on account of a rediculous news paper pro-<lb/>
paganda which has been started by a certain Physician who is looking for news-<lb/>
paper notoriety. He claims that we have not properly confirmed the diagnosis<lb/>
because we have not made blood cultures and recovered the leptospira icteroides<lb/>
of Noguchi, and a lot of other nonsense of that kind. This togather with the<lb/>
success of the antilarvae campaign which has diminished the number of adult<lb/>
stegomya to such an extent that there have been very few to propagate the dis-<lb/>
ease,-and there have been relatively few cases,- has been the means of crea-<lb/>
ting doubt in the public mind that it actually is yellow fever. Their concep-<lb/>
tion of the fever is based on the old epidemics when no effective work was done<lb/>
to combat it, and the cases presented themselves in very large numbers, with many<lb/>
deaths due to improper diagnosis and treatment.</p>
<p>In Libertad deaths have occurred in the following places; - Pacanga,<lb/>
Pueblo Nuevo, Guadelupe, San Pedro, Malabrigo, Paijan, Ascope, Casa Grande, and<lb/>
Trujillo. Drs. Mendoza and Cavassa are working up the statistics on the Pro-<lb/>
vince of Pacasmayo and as soon as they are received I will send you a copy.</p>
<p>*C*V**********</p>
<p>In your letter to Dr. Cardenas you speak of &ldquo;10 000 cc of vaccine<lb/>
a sufficient quantity for 25 000 persons&rdquo; is not this an error? Unless the<lb/>
dosage has been charged, or the concentration of the vaccine, this would be<lb/>
sufficient for one injection of 2cc each for five thousand persons. The old<lb/>
directions speak of from one to tow injections of from 1 to 2cc each.</p>
<p>It has been difficult to do much vaccination on account of a vicious<lb/>
propaganda against it be certain elements. In addition I have had such a multi-<lb/>
tude of details to attend to that I have had very little time to personally<lb/>
supervise the vaccinations. Col. Vergne has done more of this than I have, and<lb/>
we will work up a report on this as soon as possible.</p>
<p>So far I have not received any of the blanks for reporting  vaccinations.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03059043"/>
<p>#4. W.R.,I.H.B., June 18, 1921.</p>
<p>In so far as the spread south is concerned, that is the point which is<lb/>
causing me the greatest worry. Our land quarantine seems to be of very small value.<lb/>
The troops do not comply with their orders. If an influential individual comes along<lb/>
and offers the officer in charge of the squad five soles or a pound, it usually is,<lb/>
&ldquo;passa senor&rdquo;. We have relied on the desert of Viru, but even that is not a sure<lb/>
guarantee. I have requested a double &ldquo;cordon sanitario&rdquo;, one immediately south of<lb/>
the town of Viru, and another guarding all the principal points of the boundry be-<lb/>
tween Libertad and Ancash. All this has been faithfully promised, but promises<lb/>
constitutes one of the cheapest and most abundant commodities in Peru.</p>
<p>To have more assurance, I have engaged Dr. Enrique Caballero, for special<lb/>
investigation of the coast between Libertad and Callao. For the present he has<lb/>
been assisting in organizing the work in the Chicama valley, but in a few days<lb/>
will start on a tour of investigation of all principal points to the south. I<lb/>

will need this information as soon as possible in order to make the final dis-<lb/>
tribution of my <unclear>forces</unclear>. He is thoroughly reliable and has the same opinions in<lb/>
this matter as I do. He will figure on your payroll, salary and expenses.</p>
<p>Separately I transmit statement in regard to salary and expenses of<lb/>
Mr. I.W. Pickett and Mr. J.P.Corrigan.</p>
<p><hi>INSPECTORS</hi>.</p>
<p>In regard to Inspectors, I have taken everybody available<lb/>
from the organization which Dr. Carter and I had in Piura. In addition we have<lb/>
trained and are training a great many in both Departments (Libertad and Lambay-<lb/>
eque) but the campaign is so immense that it takes time to get a sufficient<lb/>
number of reliable men trained and located. It requires quite a considerable<lb/>
process of <unclear>selection</unclear> and elimination. The revised copy of the organization as<lb/>
at present established will give you an idea of the problem. I think there is<lb/>
material available for inspectors, but while we are developing this material<lb/>
we need reliable competent men for training them.</p>
<p>While I consider the expert supervision, which we have, costly I think<lb/>
it is justifiable in that it will be a means of training other men to to a cer-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03059044"/>
#5. W.R., I.H.B., June 18, 1921.<lb/>
tain extent to replace it more economically. The present however I consider<lb/>
the most critical period of the campaign. The number of cases is everywhere di-<lb/>
minishing, and as a result the people lose their fear and have a tendency to<lb/>
grow careless thinking that it is all over. At such a time we need the best help<lb/>
available until we have passed the critical period, and can enter the prophyl-<lb/>
actic campaign proper, by this I mean the time when we are fairly certain that<lb/>
we have had our last cases, and the quarantine restrictions can be less rigorous.<lb/>
This I expect to accomplish within the next three months, providing Dr. Caballero<lb/>
does not find that something has escaped us farther to the south. The whole thing<lb/>
depends on the latter observation; <hi>if we are still safe on this point we will do<lb/>
the job this year</hi>. The presence of Corrigan and Pickett will be needed for abo<lb/>
about tow to three months more to help assure this result. If any change in the<lb/>
situation should suddenly arise I will notify by cable.</p>
<p><hi>THE USE OF FISH</hi>.</p>
<p>We are using all the fish available in all sectors of<lb/>
the campaign. To date my reports are incomplete, but in this Department, Mr.<lb/>
Secley has distributed fish in 466 wells, for which he has used about 3000 fish.<lb/>
In addition we have used them in a large number of tanks and other containers<lb/>
which seem appropriate. We have a fish here which they call &ldquo;majarra&rdquo; which is<lb/>
a voracious larva consumer, I believe even more so than the gambusia. In Trujillo<lb/>
we placed a small majarra in a glass jar and added a vial of more than a hundred<lb/>
larvae; the following larva morning we were unable to see a single larvae remaining.</p>
<p>We are using all means we can think of to combat the larvae breeding.</p>
<p>In conclusion I wish to thank you for your kind expressions of confi-<lb/>
dence and for your generous offers of assistance. We are sparing no efforts to<lb/>
make the campaign a success. Practically no one among the ranking members of the<lb/>
Commission has had either Sundays or other holidays since we actively started the<lb/>
campaign. We are keeping up the efforts to the limit of endurance.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson, M.D.,<lb/>
Director of Campaign</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
