<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03059037">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Direccion de Salubridad, May 18, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03059037</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-05-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Tapia, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Canseco, Dies</name>
<name type="person">Cavassa, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Mendoza, Ricardo</name>
<name type="person">Caballero, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Lambayeque (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Guadalupe (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Pueblo Nuevo (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Pacasmayo (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-05-18">May 18, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03059037</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Direccion de Salubridad, May 18, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson requests an increase of funds. He discusses his dealings with local authorities and steamship companies.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-05-18">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Direccion de Salubridad, May 18, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03059037"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Chiclayo <date value="1921-05-18">May 18, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Direccion de Salubridad,<lb/>
Lima, Peru.<lb/>
<salute>Sirs:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Some time ago I wrote you about certain necessary increases in the salaries<lb/>
of the Physicians who are lending their services to the Sanitary Campaign for<lb/>
yellow fever. In reply I have received your telegram in regard to Drs. Tapia<lb/>
of Libertad and Dies Canseco of Lambayeque, in which you state that you have<lb/>
no request from me in regard to the others. I have also received, today, copy<lb/>
of the Resolution in regard to the matter.</p>
<p>In regard to Dr. Cavassa of Guadelupe I understand that he has been<lb/>
receiving Lp 10.0.00 per month for his work in connection with the bubonic<lb/>
plague in his section. During this campaign he will have a considerable amount<lb/>
of work in Guadelupe and Pueblo Nuevo and the small places in the immediate<lb/>
surrounding territory which will interfere considerably with his private prac-<lb/>
tice and I there fore recommend that he be given an additional allowance of<lb/>
Lp 20.0.000 for the duration of this campaign. He is a good physician and a<lb/>
conscientious enthusiastic worker and will be of a great deal of help to us.<lb/>
This pay should be made effective from the first of April, which corresponds<lb/>
to the time he has been working with the Commission. He will then be assigned<lb/>
all the northern section and will relieve Dr. Ricardo Mendoza for other and<lb/>
more important investigations in the valley which leads up to Chelete.</p>
<p>Dr. Ricardo Mendoza and his assistants have done excellent work in<lb/>
the Province of Pacasmayo. In my inspections there I personally did not find<del>s</del><lb/>
any pupae, and the larvae which I found were very young. From the data on hand<lb/>
I think it is safe to say that ther work there has prevented the appearance<lb/>
of the fever in epidemic form, and has placed the province in such a condition<lb/>
that an epidemic can not occur there this year.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03059038"/>
<p>12<lb/>
168</p>
<p>2.Salubridad, May 18, 1921.</p>
<p>Dr. Mendoza asked for increase in pay, and I personally think that he<lb/>
has done such good work that it ought to be recognized by an increase if such a<lb/>
thing is possible. I think that Lp 80.0.00 would be justifiable as salary for<lb/>
him.</p>
<p>While in Pacasmayo he told me that he had not been paid for ten days<lb/>
in January. He has handed me the receipts which he prapered for the Tesorero<lb/>
Fiscal here in Chiclayo, but it was not paid. He was on duty all the time from<lb/>
the date of his resolution of nomination and ought to be paid accordingly.</p>
<p>As you have noticed I included him in the budget for the International<lb/>
Health Board, but he states that he thinks the Government ought to furnish some<lb/>
of the principal men of the campaign, and in this I agree with him. I think the<lb/>
Government should pay both his salary and expenses.</p>
<p>In regard to Dr. Enrique Caballero I have engaged him at the rate of<lb/>
Lp 60.0.00 and expenses, for a special mission of investigation, to make sure<lb/>
that the fever is not going to get away from us again. He is a man who has the<lb/>
confidence of both Dr. Carter and myself and is a very valuable aquisition to<lb/>
the Sanitary Campaign. He is engaged for the duration of the anti-yellow fever<lb/>
campaign. I have already notified you about this matter, and should very much<lb/>
appreciate receiving your approval. Can you take him on the account of the<lb/>
Government or will I be obliged to take him on the International Health<lb/>
Board account?</p>
<p>I have just received word that Corrigan and Pickett are sailing on<lb/>
the first boat leaving Balboa after the date of the 15th of this month. This<lb/>
I presume has been arranged directly with the International Health Board by<lb/>
Dr. Carter, and is not a contract of mine.</p>
<p>I also wish to invite your attention to the fact that from the time<lb/>
of my arrival up to date I have only received Lp 1000.0.00 for campaign expenses<lb/>
and the Tesorero Fiscal says that he has received no more funds for the campaign.<lb/>
Is it not possible to arrange a regular monthly allowance, with instructions<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03059039"/>

3. Salubridad, May 18, 1921.<lb/>
that this amount must not be used for any other purpose? If I am notified of<lb/>
each delivery of funds to the Tesorero Fiscal I can collect it and deposit it<lb/>
in the Banco de Peru y Londres, where we carry the Government account, and show<lb/>
the use of it in each monthly statement.</p>
<p>The epidemic here is falling off, but we are still having a few<lb/>
scattered cases. This is due to the fact that the people do not take any pains<lb/>
with their water containers. The Prefecto here is very indifferent in the matter<lb/>
and it is very difficult to get any moral support from the authorities. This is<lb/>
very different in the Province of Pacasmayo where the Sub-Prefecto has been<lb/>
giving a most praiseworthy assistance, and has personally taken the trouble to<lb/>
make sure that Dr. Mendozas orders have been complied with. Where fines have<lb/>
been imposed for neglect the Sub-Prefecto has insisted that the finse be made<lb/>
effective. This has had a most excellent moral effect. If we could get the same<lb/>
kind of effect are support from the authorities here our dificulties would be<lb/>
diminished by more than one-half.</p>
<p>I believe the Prefecto of Libertad will give us all necessary assis-<lb/>
tance, for that is what he told me.</p>
<p>The measures which the steamship companies have taken unjustifiably is<lb/>
to a large extent responsible for a lot of the propaganda which has arisen against<lb/>
the campaign. It ought to be explained to them that they ought to touch those<lb/>
ports for mail and cargo, and passengers in accordance with the quarantine regu-<lb/>
lations. In regard to the latter I see no object in preventing passenger traffic<lb/>
between the points of Pimentel and Salavarry, these and all intermediate ports<lb/>
will be under the same sanitary conditions from now on till the end of the campaign.</p>
<p>I have sent you several reports and letters but have received no acknowl-<lb/>
edgement of the receipt of any of them. Kindly let me know if they have been re-<lb/>
ceived, also pointing out any objectionable features.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson, M.D.,<lb/>
Director of Sanitary Campaign</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
