<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03059028">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, May 15, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03059028</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-05-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rose, Wickliffe</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Tapia, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Mendoza, Dr.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-05-15">May 15, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03059028</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, May 15, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses financial affairs and describes various yellow fever cases.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-05-15">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, May 15, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03059028"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION<lb/>
de la<lb/>
CAMPANA SANITARIA<lb/>
contra la Fiebre Amarilla<lb/>
et los Departamentos del Norte<lb/>
<hi>C O P Y</hi><lb/>
THB<lb/>
<del>Havana</del><lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, <date value="1921-05-15">May 15, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
<hi>Funds</hi><lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
Dr. Wickliffe Rose, General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Last night I returned from my tour of inspection of the Department of<lb/>
Libertad, and the examination of the cases of yellow fever reported from Trujillo.<lb/>
As I have already informed you both by cable and letter from Trujillo, yellow fever<lb/>
exists in Trujillo, but is in its initial stages, which I will explain in more<lb/>
detail later.</p>
<p>On my return I found your letters of April the 6th (two of them), of the<lb/>
7th, and 12th all of which I have carefully noted. By the first letter of April<lb/>
6th I notice that you had already made the appropriation of the $15,000.00 before<lb/>
you received my cable about the financial situation. In regard to the use of a<lb/>
portion of this money I have already notified you that we have cashed one check<lb/>
for $5000.00 here in the Banco Mercantil Americano del Peru, in Chiclayo. This<lb/>
was turned into Peruvian currency at the rate of $3.62 for the Peruvian pound. Of<lb/>
the money spent here in this Department and in the Province of Pacasmayo Mr.<lb/>
Guildstrand is preparing a statement which we will send in the same mail with this<lb/>
letter.</p>
<p>On the ninth of May I opened an account in the Banco Mercantil Americano<lb/>
in Trujillo, with $5000.00 of your funds at the rate of $3.65 for the Peruvian<lb/>
pound, and received a net credit in the Bank of Lp 1355.8.14. I enclose copy of<lb/>
the Bank's statement of this transaction. It is rather unfortunate that these<lb/>
funds can not all be handled from the same bank. The banks however do not like<lb/>
to take checks on banks in different departments and for that reason we have the<lb/>
different accounts for the campaigns in the department in which the money is to<lb/>
be spent.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03059029"/>
<p>2. W.R., I.H.B.</p>
<p>In regard to the fever in the southern section of the Department of<lb/>
Libertad, I saw three cases while in Trujillo, one of which was the Jap mentioned<lb/>
in my letter of May 6th written from Trujillo, another in the case of a woman in<lb/>
the hospital and later another case was admitted to the Hospital the day before I<lb/>
left. In addition one of the Doctors came to my room the night before I left giving<lb/>
me the history of another case which he had seen that day, which according to the<lb/>
history is also a case of yellow fever.</p>
<p>On Sunday May the 8th in company with Dr. Tapia, the Medico Sanitario<lb/>
Departamental, for Libertad, I went for an inspection of the work in the towns of<lb/>
Ascope and Chocope, and while at Ascope we were notified of a case of suspicious<lb/>
illness in one of the peones from the Hacienda Casa  Grand<del>a</del><add>e</add>. This man had come to<lb/>
Ascope to consult the Doctor there because he did not get along as well as he<lb/>
thought he should under the treatment of the Doctor at the Hacienda. When I saw<lb/>
him he had pronounced congested and yellow conjunctivae and was very much prostrated,<lb/>
and was vomiting in the train. Examination of the urine showed an abundance of<lb/>
albumen. He also had epigastric tenderness and pain across his kidneys. Tongue<lb/>
with red margins pointed very red at tip and a heavy coat dorsally. Diagnosis<lb/>
yellow fever. On account of finding this case we proceeded from Ascope to Casa<lb/>
Grande where we met the Doctor of the hacienda and spoke to him about the case. He<lb/>
denied that he had had such a case, and even after examining the case with us would<lb/>
not accept the diagnosis of yellow fever. He also showed me another case in a soldier<lb/>
in the hospital, which in my opinion was yellow fever. This soldier had an abundance<lb/>
of albumen in the urine, yet this Doctor did not care to accept a diagnosis of yellow<lb/>
fever. I do not think he has ever seen yellow fever, and therefore his opinion does<lb/>
not mean anything to me. He is the only physician whom I encountered unreasonable<lb/>
and inclined to be pigheaded in his opinions. In addition to the cases mentioned<lb/>
there is a clear history of a case dying in Paijan.</p>
<p>The work there for the present is organized with Dr. Tapia as the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03059030"/>
3. W.R., I.H.B.<lb/>
Director pro tem for the Department, or rather for the Province of Trujillo.<lb/>
Dr. Ricardo has the Province of Pacasmayo and has done very good work there, so<lb/>
much so that there will be no epidemic of yellow fever in this province. Dr.<lb/>
Mendoza has his stegomya index now at from .6% in San Pedro, 1.% in Chepen and in<lb/>
the rest of the towns it is about 2%. Nearly all the larvae which I saw in my<lb/>
inspection were of from one to five days growth. The local authorities there are<lb/>
giving splendid cooperation.</p>
<p>In the province of Trujillo I have left Dr. Enrique Caballero, Sr. Manuel<lb/>
Machado and Sr. Ramirez in addition to Inspector Jorge Reyes whom I left in charge<lb/>
of the work in the city of Trujillo. These are all of them the choice of the men<lb/>
we had in the campaign of last year and can and will do good work. These are all<lb/>
well known to Dr. Carter.</p>
<p>Since returning I have received your cable in regard to Pickett and<lb/>
Corrigan. I presume these are the same men that I had last year in Piura, and<lb/>
will be of very great value to the campaign. These I will use in the Province of<lb/>
Trujillo, and with this reinforcement I shall feel very much safer.</p>
<p>The Prefecto in Trujillo has accepted the diagnosis and indicated his<lb/>
readiness to carry out strictly all my orders. We decided to place the &ldquo;cordon<lb/>
sanitario&rdquo; to the south of Viru where there seems that there is only one road<lb/>
communicating with the next Department to the south. This desert is a large one<lb/>
and will lend itself to defense better than the others over which the epidemic<lb/>
has advanced.</p>
<p>In the budget which I presented I had included Dr. Mendoza in your<lb/>
budget, but he says he thinks the Government should pay his salary and expenses,<lb/>
and I think he is right and will so arrange matters if possible.</p>
<p>The epidemic in this Department seems to be controlled, the stegomya<lb/>
index is falling steadily as are also the new cases of fever. The stegomya index<lb/>
in Chiclayo for the past week was 1.94%.</p>
<p>As soon as I have arranged certain matters of importance in this office<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03059031"/>
4. W.R., I.H.B.<lb/>
I expect to return to Trujillo. I am handicapped for the present in my movements<lb/>
on account of schedule of the steamers. The steamers touch the ports quarantined<lb/>
very irregularly, and it often happens that I need to make rapid trips from one<lb/>
Department to the other, which at the present time can not be made by auto by land<lb/>
on account of the water in the low places in the desert. This water comes from the<lb/>
snow and rain in the mountains, and at this season of the year. Later on all this<lb/>
section will be perfectly dry and can be passed in an auto. I have been thinking<lb/>
of asking the Government to put one of their small cruisers for duty along the coast<lb/>
so as to enable me to transfer men whenever necessary and to have means of going from<lb/>
one place to another for inspections.</p>
<p>In another letter I have mentioned Mr. Richardson for the work in the<lb/>
Department of Libertad, but it seems that Wrightson has started anti-stegomya work<lb/>
in Callao and kept Mr. Richardson for that work. With the arrival of Pickett and<lb/>
Corrigan I think we will have sufficient supervision and with their assistance we<lb/>
ought to make the campaign a real success this year.</p>
<p>Mr. M. M. Seeley is supervising the work in this Department (Lambayeque)<lb/>
and has helped a great deal to improve the inspection service, for stegomya.</p>
<p>My greatest worry is some one to manage the finances in Libertad during<lb/>
my absence.</p>
<p>In regard to the use of fish, I beg to report that we are using all the<lb/>
fish we can get in all parts. Here we have a tank in which we have placed about a<lb/>
thousand fish for distribution. In Pascasmayo all the &ldquo;Millones&rdquo; died, I do not know<lb/>
what the reason. I shall ask for more and try a breeding place here under the care<lb/>
of Sr. Arturo Mandichy who is a former Guayaquil employee, he worked with Dr. M. E.<lb/>
Connor.</p>
<p>I enclose copy of letter which Dr. W. Paraja of Guayaquil wrote me in<lb/>
response to my request for fish.</p>
<p>I trust you may be able to send me a Mission Code as none is available in<lb/>
this section.</p>
<p>Thanking you for your courteous letters and the generous offers of<lb/>
assistance, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very Respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson (Signed)<lb/>
Herny Hanson, M.D.,<lb/>
Director of Sanitary Campaign</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
<div1>
<pb n="5" id="f03059032"/>
<opener>
Copy:<lb/>
<dateline>
BANCO MERCANTIL AMERICANO DEL PERU.<lb/>
------------------------------------<lb/>
Trujillo, <date value="1921-05-10">May 10th, 1921 -</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Henry Hanson,<lb/>
City.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In conformity with our verbal agreement, we have credited<lb/>
your account with us, provisionally, and under usual reserve, with<lb/>
<hi>Lp.1.355.8.14</hi>, being the equivalent of your draft on New York for<lb/>
<hi>$5,000.00</hi>, drawn on the Equitable Trust Co., as shown in the corres-<lb/>
ponding liquidation.</p>
<p>Expressing our thanks for having started your account<lb/>
with us and wishing that our services would prove to be satisfactory.</p>
<closer>
<salute>We are Dear Sir, yours very truly,</salute>
<signed>BANCO MERCANTIL AMERICANO DEL PERU<lb/>
(Signed by Manager)</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
