<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03059008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, April 5, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03059008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-04-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Ecuador</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-04-05">April 5, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03059008</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, April 5, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson discusses outbreaks of yellow fever in Peru, and his dealings with the Peruvian government. He requests the use of International Health Board funding.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-04-05">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Wickliffe Rose, April 5, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03059008"/>
<opener>
COPY.<lb/>
DIRECCION<lb/>
de la<lb/>
CAMPANA SANITARIA<lb/>
Contra La Fierre Amarilla<lb/>
en Los Departamentos Del Norte.<lb/>
<dateline>
Chiclayo, Peru,<lb/>
<date value="1921-04-05">April 5, 1921.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Wickliffe Rose,<lb/>
General Director,<lb/>
International Health Board,<lb/>
New York, N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Rose:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your letter of the 25th of February, in which you refer to<lb/>
Dr. Carter's cable, and the one you sent him in Lima, authorizing $5000.00<lb/>
for yellow fever work in Peru. By this time you no doubt have seen and talked<lb/>
with Dr. Carter about the situation here.</p>
<p>I have also received you other communications, viz., M. E. Connor's<lb/>
&ldquo;Part Played by Fish in Yellow Fever Control in Guayaquil, Ecuador,&rdquo; and<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Fever Control in Ecuador&rdquo; as well as No. 7329, Memorandum in Reference<lb/>
to FINANCIAL PROCEDURE, OF THE INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD. In regard to the<lb/>
latter we are studying this to have our accounts conform as far as is possible.</p>
<p>As I have already told you I have used of your funds to bridge over<lb/>
the time which the Government has taken to arrange their finances for the cam-<lb/>
paign. During the last days I have been very much worried, because I had used<lb/>
up practically all your funds, and up to this morning had heard nothing from<lb/>
Lima. Had it not been for your money, the campaign would have been paralized<lb/>
during the last three weeks, and the fever certainly would have been well<lb/>
established in the Province of Pacasmayo. This I think has been avoided as a<lb/>
result of my taking the liberty to use your money wherever it was necessary to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03059009"/>
2<lb/>
keep the work going at full speed. Saturday night after paying the employees<lb/>
I found myself without funds, and sent the following cable to Lima:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quedan suspendidos trabajos hasta entrega dinero.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This had been preceded by several messages requesting them to attend to the<lb/>
matter. On March 22 I sent a radiogram urgently requesting that the matter<lb/>
be attended to, and had to send another March 29, as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Salubridad --- Lima. Sirvaso contestarme radiograma fecha<lb/>
22 actual. Ahora no hay fondos continuar Campana.&rdquo;</p>
<p>To which the Salubridad replied as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dr. Hanson, Chiclayo</p>
<p>Contesto aerograma 22 y 29 actual manifestandole haberme dirigido<lb/>
tesorero gestionahdo pago presupuosto aprobado resolucion cuatro actual.<lb/>
Salubridad, Cardenas&rdquo;</p>
<p>On March 31, I sent the following messages:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Direccion Tesoro --- Lima</p>
<p>Hasta hoy Tesorero Fiscal no ha recibido ordenes abonar gastos<lb/>
Campana Sanitaria. He pagado todo con fondos &ldquo;Rockefeller y estoy<lb/>
sin fondos continuar y pagar peones semana. Dirijome Presidente mismo<lb/>
sentido.&rdquo;</p>
<p>and this:</p>
<p>&ldquo;PRESIDENT LEGUIA ..... LIMA</p>
<p>RECEIVED NO FUNDS FROM ADUANA. ALL EXPENSES SINCE ARRIVAL PAID<lb/>
WITH ROCKEFELLER FUNDS. NOTHING LEFT TO CONTINUE WITH.<lb/>
HANSON&rdquo;</p>
<p>Only today has the matter been arranged. I have just received no-<lb/>
tice from the Prefectura, that orders have come from Lima to turn over<lb/>
Lp. 1000.0.00 to the sanitary campaign. I write you this to give you an<lb/>
idea of the difficulties we have at times, and of the dangers we confront<lb/>
in the campaign. As I have stated before, had it not been for the use of<lb/>
your funds the campaign would have been irretrievably lost during the last<lb/>
three weeks. In addition to the work in the Department of Lambayeque, all<lb/>
the expenses of the campaign in Pacasmayo have been from the funds of the<lb/>
International Health Board, which I believe is the reserve which has broken<lb/>
the advance.</p>
<p>A resume of the work in the Province of Pacasmayo shows the fol-<lb/>
lowing:</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03059010"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>Total deposits (containers) inspected 10,614</p>
<p>Containers with larvae, destroyed 988</p>
<p>I still have two places in the Province to hear from, Guadelupe<lb/>
and Pacanga.</p>
<p>Dr. Mendoza has been thoroughly impressed with the importance of<lb/>
the position which he is holding, and the indications are that he is doing<lb/>
good work.</p>
<p>On account of what I have indicated above it will be a little dif-<lb/>
ficult to present a fixed budget, because I anticipate that the government<lb/>
will be in more difficult financial straits, as time advances. The revolution-<lb/>
ary spirit is rather appalling, and no one can predict what or when something<lb/>
will happen.</p>
<p>Last night I sent you the following cable:</p>
<p>&ldquo;INTERCOM NEW YORK.</p>
<p>FINANCIAL STATUS SUCH APPEARS GOVERNMENT WILL NOT FURNISH<lb/>
SUFFICIENT FUNDS TO CARRY CAMPAIGN TO SUCCESSFUL CONCLUSION. NEED<lb/>
AVAILABLE MONTHLY ALLOWANCE TEN THOUSAND DOLLARS ON ACCOUNT EXTENT<lb/>
TERRITORY TO BE PROTECTED TO INSURE COMPLETE EXTIRPATION THIS YEAR.<lb/>
EXPLANATORY LETTERS AND ESTIMATE SENT BY MAIL. CABLE ADDRESS<lb/>
HANSON CHICLAYO.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Unless you prefer other arrangement, I propose to handle your<lb/>
funds through the Banco Mercantile Americano, in Chiclayo. I have already<lb/>
opened an account with this Bank for the money used to date.</p>
<p>Under date of March 25, I wrote you about the budgets for the dif-<lb/>
ferent Departments, but it appears very doubtful that they will furnish the<lb/>
amounts indicated. The $10,000 indicated above according to the rate of ex-<lb/>
change which prevails will be the equivalent of about Lp 2600.0.00. The ex-<lb/>
change however has fluctuated lately between about 3.70 to 4.20. for the<lb/>
peruvian pound. I presume that you will advise in more detail what part of<lb/>
the expense you expect to assume after your conference with Dr. Carter.</p>
<p>In regard to the use of fish, we have already commenced distributing<lb/>
fish for the larger tanks, and such receptacles as appear appropriate for this<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03059011"/>
4<lb/>
type of mosquito control. Here we have, however, a large number of small<lb/>
containers where the amount of water does not seem sufficient to favor the<lb/>
use of fish. I discussed this matter with Dr. M.E. Connor when he was in<lb/>
Lima, and he stated that he thought that a great many of our containers did<lb/>
not lend themselves to the use of fish with the same degree of success as<lb/>
in Guayaquil. I shall try the method out as far as is possible. I have<lb/>
today cabled Guayaquil, Dr. Pareja, to find out if we can purchase a breeding<lb/>
supply of &ldquo;Millions&rdquo; for the use in our campaign. There are places in the<lb/>
Department of Libertad, such as the Hacienda, <hi>Casa Grande</hi>, where I believe<lb/>
they will be the most effective, if not the only successful method which we<lb/>
can adopt. If we succeed in developing a good breeding ground, we can also<lb/>
distribute them to help control the culex and anopheles here.</p>
<p>The foci of epidemic in this Department are as follows: Olmos, Motupe,<lb/>
Salas, Jayanca, Illimo, Tucume, Mochumi, Ferranafe, Lambayeque, Chiclayo, Monsefu,<lb/>
Villa Eten, Puerto Eten, Cayalti, Sana, Tuman and Pomalca. The epidemic is in<lb/>
its last stages in Ferrenafe, Chiclayo, Monsefu, Villa Eten, Pomalca, Tuman and<lb/>
the port of Eten. At the present time it is severe in the north; the report from<lb/>
Motupe last night gave 31 cases with two deaths, leaving 28. We have adopted<lb/>
the habit of multiplying the number of cases reported by ten to more accurately<lb/>
approach the true number of cases existing, which would indicate at least 290<lb/>
in Motupe.</p>
<p>Col. Vergne of the French Army Medical Corps, who is in Peru with<lb/>
the French Military Mission as the, or in the capacity corresponding to that<lb/>
of, Surgeon General for the Peruvian Army Medical Corps, has been in the Department<lb/>
for about two months and is co-operating like a true ally. He left for Motupe<lb/>
yesterday for an inspection of the Military post and the condition of the epi-<lb/>
demic. I have one Dr. Alva Diaz, and four inspectors working there.</p>
<p>Dol. Vergne with a detachment from the Army is to take charge of the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03059012"/>
5<lb/>
sector in the southern part of this Province (Province of Chiclayo). He too<lb/>
is having difficulties in securing the necessary orders and co-operation from<lb/>
the Commanding Officer of the Section. He is one (the C.O.) of those who<lb/>
profess not to believe in yellow fever.</p>
<p>I have had conference with the managers of the daily papers which<lb/>
were writing the scurrilous propaganda against the campaign, and have suc-<lb/>
ceeded in suppressing such propaganda as that, of which I sent you samples.<lb/>
My principal difficulty in the personnel is with the Medico Titular, nom-<lb/>
inated for this province by the Direccion de Salubridad. He is a person<lb/>
without experience or judgment and is the main source of the opposition which<lb/>
we have at the present time. He does not figure in my budget; if he did, I<lb/>
would discharge him without delay.</p>
<p>The medical students sent up by the Direccion de Salubridad, also<lb/>
are of no value, and I shall recommend their recall, thereby saving Lp 100.0.00<lb/>
monthly.</p>
<p>I have no code available here, other than a commercial code at the<lb/>
Bank, and that does not give a saving in expense.</p>
<p>Under separate cover I send detailed estimate for campaign.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Henry Hanson, M.D.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
