<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03064001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Book Review: William Crawford Gorgas, His Life and Work, by the Editor of the The Military Surgeon, March 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03064001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-03-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Black, William M.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Havard, H.O.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Goethals, George W.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Spain</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-03-00">March 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03064001</idno>
<title>Book Review: William Crawford Gorgas, His Life and Work, by the Editor of the The Military Surgeon, March 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This editorial concerns Marie Gorgas' biography of her husband. The editor comments on the claims made concerning Gorgas' yellow fever work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1925-03-00">
<head>Book Review: William Crawford Gorgas, His Life and Work, by the Editor of the The Military Surgeon, March 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03064001"/>
<p>(Reprinted from The Military Surgeon for March, 1925)</p>
<p>EDITORIAL</p>
<p>WILLIAM CRAWFORD GORGAS<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
<p>There recently came to the editorial desk a most interesting and<lb/>
attractive story of the life of one who, if not one of the world's great<lb/>
men, certainly accomplished great things in the world. There are<lb/>
few readers of books, we opine, who will be so simple or so unreason-<lb/>
able as to expect a plain, unvarnished tale from the combined author-<lb/>
ship of a devoted wife and the editor of a popular magazine, and there-<lb/>
fore we are not surprised or aggrieved to find a portrait of high lights<lb/>
with few lines and shadows, and in which no faults or imperfections<lb/>
appear through the shining gloss of love and hero worship. How the<lb/>
&ldquo;gaunt specter of yellow fever&rdquo; confronted Gorgas at every stage of<lb/>
his career is well told, and how also this portentous destroyer was to<lb/>
him a friend in disguise to whom he owed wife, opportunity, fame and<lb/>
great place, and the personal immunity which enabled him to walk<lb/>
without fear in the shadow of death.</p>
<p>The human story of his parents, his boyhood, his courtship and<lb/>
marriage and his army career up to the time when, in 1899, he became<lb/>
the Chief Surgeon, Department of Havana, is charmingly told. Here<lb/>
he enters the limelight and the zone of historical interest where it<lb/>
would have been advisable for the narrators to check memories with<lb/>
the records and, in making claims for him, to be mindful of those of<lb/>
others. Here, therefore, the conscientious reviewer must take note of<lb/>
omissions and errors which are misleading and out of place in an his-<lb/>
torical biography.</p>
<p>The story of the cleaning up of Havana, which is here completely<lb/>
credited to Gorgas, is one in which there are in fact many overlapping<lb/>
claims. These will not be gone into further than to remark that the<lb/>
streets, which are so graphically described on page 85 as paved with<lb/>
garbage and dead cats, were never at any time under Gorgas but were<lb/>
in charge of the Street Cleaning Department under the efficient direc-<lb/>
tion of Major William M. Black, U. S. Eng. Corps, later Major<lb/>
General and Chief of Engineers. The police of the buildings and<lb/>
patios where the Engineer Department did not have the right of entry<lb/>
was under Major Davis, the Sanitary Officer, who reported directly to<lb/>
General Ludlow and was not under the Chief Surgeon, Major Gorgas,<lb/>
during all the year 1899 or up to the time when Davis was ordered<lb/>
to the Philippines in February, 1900. From our authors' account of<lb/>
-----------<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>&ldquo;William Crawford Gorgas: His Life and Work,&rdquo; by Marie D. Gorgas and Burton J.<lb/>
Hendrick. Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, Page &amp; Co., 1924.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03064002"/>
2<lb/>
The Military Surgeon--March, 1925<lb/>
&ldquo;the good scouring and good bath&rdquo; which Gorgas said to himself he<lb/>
would give the &ldquo;rotting city,&rdquo; one would never guess that the scouring<lb/>
and bathing had been going on energetically for over a year before<lb/>
he had a chance at the scrubbing brush.</p>
<p>But the central interest of the story revolves about the conquest<lb/>
of yellow fever and the share which several men had in that mighty<lb/>
accomplishment, and here, too, the careful reader is distressed to find<lb/>
a like looseness of statement and dearth of dates.</p>
<p>As is always the case in great deeds, many men contribute to make<lb/>
it possible, and it might not be easy even in a scientific work to evalu-<lb/>
ate their several donations, but three men stand out in the center of the<lb/>
stage, Finlay, the prophet, to whom none would listen, Reed, the<lb/>
scientific demonstrator, whom none but the blind could fail to follow,<lb/>
and Gorgas, the brave and pertinacious administrator, whom no<lb/>
obstacle could turn aside. Behind these in the second rank stand<lb/>
Reed's assistants, Lazear, Carroll and Agramonte, and H. R. Carter<lb/>
whose valuable observation of extrinsic incubation was an unsolved<lb/>
puzzle until Reed furnished the key. The story is, as our authors say,<lb/>
an intensely dramatic one, and as is usual in dramas it is divided into<lb/>
acts. The first act from the pronouncement of the mosquito theory<lb/>
by Finlay in 1881 to the entrance of Reed in July, 1900, covers a<lb/>
period of 19 years. The second act, the demonstration by Reed was<lb/>
finished in six months. Then there was an intermission of six weeks<lb/>
or two months occupied in the conversion of Gorgas before the<lb/>
beginning of practical application of Reed's demonstration by warfare<lb/>
against the mosquito in Havana. Then the curtain rises for the last<lb/>
act which lasted until May, 1906, when Panama was at length freed<lb/>
from yellow fever.</p>
<p>The attitude of Gorgas was very conservative and his conversion<lb/>
slow, as was the rule with those who had much experience with<lb/>
yellow fever. He was sufficiently convinced of the mosquito theory to<lb/>
begin its practical application on the first of March, 1901, and he then<lb/>
cleaned up Havana as far as mosquitos were concerned. He did not,<lb/>
however, yet accept in practice the harmlessness of fomites such as<lb/>
bedding, clothing, etc., which Reed had demonstrated with equal<lb/>
conclusiveness, and he continued these useless and expensive disinfec-<lb/>
tions until the middle of August, 1901, although the Chief Surgeon,<lb/>
Department of Cuba, Colonel Havard, had directed in April that mili-<lb/>
tary surgeons desist from them. The acceptance of Reed's conclusions<lb/>
by the other medical officers in Cuba was immediate, and the applica-<lb/>
tion of them by those having sanitary responsibilities, began at once.<lb/>
The Chief Surgeon of Western Cuba who was in intimate daily con-<lb/>
tact with Reed began operations against mosquitos on October 15,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03064003"/>
Editorial<lb/>
3<lb/>
1900, convinced (as was General Wood) by the cases of Carroll,<lb/>
Lazear and the cavalryman X. Y. On December 21, 1900, General<lb/>
Wood issued General Order No. 6 of the Department of Cuba which<lb/>
stated that &ldquo;the Chief Surgeon has reported that it is now well estab-<lb/>
lished that malaria, yellow fever and filarial infection are transmitted<lb/>
by mosquitos,&rdquo; and directed the protection of the troops at all posts by<lb/>
mosquito bars and the use of petroleum for the destruction of mosquito<lb/>
larvae in water barrels, fire buckets, post holes, old cans, cesspools<lb/>
or undrained puddles.</p>
<p>Our authors picture (page 110 et seq.) the mental attitude of Reed<lb/>
and other scientists towards the mosquito theory in the early months<lb/>
of 1901 as one of pessimism and depression. They thought that the<lb/>
discovery was academic and did not see how it greatly lessened the<lb/>
general yellow fever peril! <hi>Nothing could be further from the truth.</hi><lb/>
The dread of the unknown was dispelled and the general feeling was<lb/>
one of elation and great relief. While Gorgas still hesitated, the post<lb/>
surgeons went to work, under Reed's inspiration and General Wood's<lb/>
orders, with oil can and spade and hoe. Military sanitarians had<lb/>
already learned how to attack the mosquito from the writings of Dr.<lb/>
L. O. Howard (Chief of the Bureau of Entomology), and we find<lb/>
Reed writing to that distinguished scientist on January 13, 1901, in a<lb/>
gale of joy that &ldquo;with Howard and Kerosene we would soon knock out<lb/>
old culex fasciatus&rdquo; as the yellow fever mosquito was then called.<lb/>
Trifles often shed an interesting light on current events and the<lb/>
writer's diary recalls that on a Christmas tree at Columbia Barracks<lb/>
in 1900, gotten up by two ladies of the post for the children and a<lb/>
few of their elders, Reed's gift was a wonderful stegomyia made of<lb/>
champagne cork with a formidable probosis, and tooth pick legs<lb/>
beautifully banded, while Dr. Amador, the post sanitary officer,<lb/>
received a can of kerosene as his badge of office with doggerel verses<lb/>
describing the pursuit of the mosquito.</p>
<p>Fortunately, however, for the fame of Gorgas, ill-founded claims<lb/>
of priority and originality are not necessary to round out the great-<lb/>
ness of his achievement either at Havana or later at Panama.</p>
<p>His difficulties in Panama due to the lack of support or open hos-<lb/>
tility of his immediate superiors cannot fail to excite the surprise and<lb/>
indignation of the reader, and we are pleased to see the punishment<lb/>
which the &ldquo;Old Man of the Sea&rdquo; had so richly earned by his obstinacy<lb/>
and ignorance. It is not, however, accurate to say that Dr. C. A. L.<lb/>
Reed, who came to Gorgas' rescue in his heart-breaking struggle with<lb/>
the first Commission, was sent down by the American Medical Asso-<lb/>
ciation. He went at the request of the Secretary of War, Mr. Taft,<lb/>
and it was to the Secretary that his report was made, although he did<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03064004"/>
4<lb/>
The Military Surgeon--March, 1925<lb/>
violate the proprieties by slipping a copy of it to the editor of the A.<lb/>
M. A. Journal.</p>
<p>singular</p>
<p>It is a <del>similar</del> fact, and one which though it is shown, is not ex-<lb/>
plained in the biography, that so gentle and kindly a person as Gorgas<lb/>
did not enjoy the support but rather the opposition of so many of<lb/>
the chiefs under whom he served at Panama, as Walker, Shonts, Ma-<lb/>
goon, Wallace and Goethals. Yet they were not all &ldquo;Old Men of<lb/>
the Sea.&rdquo; Whatever the cause may be it brings out the quality<lb/>
which was the dominant and winning one in his career, the patient<lb/>
persistence with which he pursued his aims, and the far point on which<lb/>
he held his vision fixed, to the exclusion from his mind of the diffi-<lb/>
culties and annoyances which beset his path, and which like his own<lb/>
familiar stegomyia buzzed about his head or bit his ankles. Our<lb/>
sense of justice regrets the absence from the copious index of the names<lb/>
of some of those whose friendly aid saved him in critical periods of<lb/>
his career, as General Fitzhugh Lee, who when Gorgas was relieved<lb/>
from duty in Havana and ordered first to Santiago, and then to Lee's<lb/>
own staff in April, 1900, secured a revocation of the order. And<lb/>
though Dr. Lambert's intervention in his behalf is well told, no men-<lb/>
tion is made in this book of the constant assistance and loyal sup-<lb/>
port given Gorgas at every step by his own Chief, Surgeon General<lb/>
O'Reilly, a support which was often invoked and never failed him, and<lb/>
which enabled him to move steadily onward against wind and tide.<lb/>
It was well known in the Surgeon General's Office that on at least<lb/>
one occasion General O'Reilly's intercession with the Secretary of<lb/>
War saved Gorgas from recall from Panama.</p>
<p>Between the ratification of peace with Spain and our entry into<lb/>
the World War, eighteen years passed, during which General Gorgas<lb/>
saw no service with troops and gave but little time to military matters.<lb/>
During the three years that he was Surgeon General before the latter<lb/>
date he was much more occupied with the organization of the Inter-<lb/>
national Health Board, the cleansing of South America, and the other<lb/>
details of his lofty dream of the extinction of yellow fever, than with<lb/>
the complexities of medico-military organization. By what gift of<lb/>
genius or what great stroke of luck did he then succeed in meeting<lb/>
the vast responsibilities of the World War? The secret of his success<lb/>
appears to deserve mention in the story of his life and his work. It<lb/>
is the story of General O'Reilly and his successor, General Torney, and<lb/>
the devoted and united band of their assistants, who year by year<lb/>
labored to make good the errors of the Spanish War, to consolidate<lb/>
and organize, to train and prepare and make ready plans, personnel<lb/>
and mat&eacute;riel. Thus Gorgas, when he returned from his long sojourn<lb/>
in South America and found war facing the country, found a medical<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03064005"/>
Editorial<lb/>
5<lb/>
corps enlarged, united, trained and eager, awaiting with confidence the<lb/>
day of trial. There may have been in his heart some misgivings as to<lb/>
his ability to handle this complex machine, or some doubt as to his<lb/>
physical ability to stand the impending strain, for early in 1917 he<lb/>
sounded the Secretary of War as to retirement. The rupture of<lb/>
diplomatic relations with Germany intervened to prevent the grati-<lb/>
fication of this wish and he braced himself for the shock, and guided<lb/>
as best he could the multitudinous activities of the Medical Corps and<lb/>
the medical profession in these two crowded and eventful years.</p>
<p>It is not easy to evaluate the contribution of Gorgas to the splen-<lb/>
did effort of the Medical Service in the World War. He was now at<lb/>
the height of his fame and his popularity was great with Congress<lb/>
and throughout the country. This made it easy for him to obtain<lb/>
the legislation which was necessary, and greatly assisted the operation<lb/>
of the machinery which had been already prepared for the enrollment<lb/>
of the civilian practitioners. He drew about him the leaders of the<lb/>
medical profession and was liberal in the delegation of his authority.<lb/>
He wisely left a large initiative to the trained men under him. He<lb/>
was active in inspections and tireless in conferences. To say that this<lb/>
constituted the sum of his effort would be doubtless an understatement<lb/>
but not a greater assault upon our sense of proportion than is made<lb/>
by our authors in their advancement of a general claim for the credit<lb/>
of the entire medical achievement. With the service in France it is<lb/>
certain that the Surgeon General had little to do. &ldquo;In France he<lb/>
provided accommodations for 25 per cent of the American soldiers in<lb/>
the field. He constructed one hospital with 27,000 beds,&rdquo; are state-<lb/>
ments which can hardly be accepted even in a Pickwickian sense. It<lb/>
is doubtful if he ever heard the name of Mesves until that hospital<lb/>
city had already spread itself over the vineyards of Saone-et-Loire.<lb/>
It would be as just or as unjust to fix on him the responsibility for<lb/>
the costly errors committed in France with regard to the Medical<lb/>
Department, such as cutting down the medical personnel in France to<lb/>
one-half of that estimated as needful by the Chief Surgeon, or the<lb/>
production of pneumonia by order by the restriction of the air space<lb/>
in billets and hospitals, as to credit him with the work of the Chief<lb/>
Surgeon A. E. F.</p>
<p>Suffice it to say that when General Gorgas visited us in France<lb/>
in the stirring days of September, 1918, his <unclear>r&ocirc;le</unclear> was not that of<lb/>
Hector in the field, but rather that of Priam at the Scaean Gate.</p>
<p>It is pleasant to read in the final chapter of the honours and<lb/>
decorations and royal attentions which brightened the end of his fine<lb/>
and useful career, and the noble and fitting funeral at St. Paul's by<lb/>
which the British Government paid a final tribute to his memory.</p>
<closer>
<signed>J. R. K.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
