<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03060002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John P. Corrigan to Henry Hanson, August 13, 1921</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Corrigan, John P.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03060002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1921-08-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hanson, Henry</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Sainz, Arturo</name>
<name type="person">Tapia, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Thomas, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Gordon, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Caballero, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Guadalupito (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Tambol Real (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Chimbote (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Samanco (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">San Jacinto (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose (Peru)</name>
<name type="place">Casma (Peru)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1921-08-13">August 13, 1921</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03060002</idno>
<title>Letter from John P. Corrigan to Henry Hanson, August 13, 1921</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Corrigan describes inspections of various Peruvian sites for yellow fever eradication.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1921-08-13">
<head>Letter from John P. Corrigan to Henry Hanson, August 13, 1921</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03060002"/>
<opener>
DIRECCION DE LA CAMPA&Ntilde;A SANITARIA<lb/>
CONTRA LA FIEBRE AMARILLA<lb/>
EN LOS<lb/>
DEPARTAMENTOS DEL NORTE<lb/>
---<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
-----<lb/>
Copy:<lb/>
<dateline>
Casma - <date value="1921-08-13">August 13th, 1921</date>
</dateline>

Dr. Henry Hanson,<lb/>
Director - Campa&ntilde;a Sanitaria.<lb/>
Chiclayo - Peru.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>My last report was mailed to your office at Chiclayo,<lb/>
from Hacienda &ldquo;Buena Vista&rdquo;, July 21st, 1921. Therefore, this report<lb/>
will record our activities since that date.</p>
<p>Mr. Arturo Sainz and I inspected Hacienda &ldquo;Santa Clara&rdquo;,<lb/>
Guadalupito, July 23rd, Houses visited 75. Total containers 95.<lb/>
Containers with larvae 1, with pupae 1. Houses closed 7.<lb/>
The scarcity of larvae here was undoubtedly due to the presence<lb/>
of &ldquo;camarones&rdquo; (shrimps), in most all containers. These are<lb/>
brought in with the water delivered by the &ldquo;aguadores&rdquo;. Later we p<lb/>
placed fish in all containers at this place.</p>
<p>We arrived at Tambo Real July 23rd. This is a hacienda<lb/>
with a population of about 2,000. The percentage of larvae found<lb/>
in the containers was about 30. We placed fish in all containers<lb/>
and had plenty of time to note the excellent results. As a general<lb/>
rule, on the second day after distributing fish; a few larvae<lb/>
are found; but I have never found any after the third day; even in<lb/>
containers which were formerly alive with larvae and pupae.</p>
<p>We worked between Guadalupito, Tambo Real, Santa,<lb/>
Puerto of Santa and the Hacienda &ldquo;San Bartolo&rdquo; until July 31st,<lb/>
and had fish in all containers at these places on that date.</p>
<p>On August 1st, we arrived at Chimbote. We had considerable<lb/>
trouble in securing fish for that place, and were compelled to leave<lb/>
there on August 7th, with fish in all containers excepting those<lb/>
in 32 houses. We strained the water in all of these, and asked Dr.<lb/>
Tapia to send fish to the &ldquo;Alcalde&rdquo; to finish the work. There<lb/>
are about 70 wells in Chimbote. We noted stegomyia breeding<lb/>
in all that were walled up by barrels, boards, or mason work.<lb/>
In the earthen wells we found culex only. Ad our supply of fish<lb/>
were scarce, we oiled these wells with heavy films of kerosene.<lb/>
But I am anxious to get fish in all of them as the breeding at<lb/>
that place was 100 per cent.</p>
<p>Mr. John S. Thomas, of Santa, was employed effective<lb/>
August 10th, to act as Visitador for Santa and all the above mention-<lb/>
ed places, at a salary of &pound;p.8.0.00, per month; &pound;p.2.0.00 of this<lb/>
amount to pay for the use of his horse, which he will need on his<lb/>
work.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03060003"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>We arrived at Samanca Sunday afternoon, August 7th,<lb/>
and at once started a search for fish in a nearby lagoon.<lb/>
The following morning we found all the fish placed in<lb/>
fresh water containers by us the day before, dead, as the<lb/>
water in the lagoon was &ldquo;agua media salobre&rdquo;. We noticed,<lb/>
however, that the only containers in Samanca in which<lb/>
larvae was not present, were those in which we found &ldquo;renaquajos&rdquo;,<lb/>
or tadpoles. As we had to wait until the following day for<lb/>
transportation to San Jacinto, where we could get fish, we<lb/>
collected about 1,000 tadpoles and placed five or six in<lb/>
each container. The following day, July 9th, we left for<lb/>
San Jacinto and inspected 160 houses there. We found 2<lb/>
containers with larvae and pupae. On July 10th, we went<lb/>
in search for fish, and secured enough for Samanco, where<lb/>
we went and placed them the following day, July 11th. We<lb/>
especially noticed that there were very few <del>places</del> larvae<lb/>
in any of the containers at Samanca, and that the tadpoles<lb/>
had done excellent work, showing that they may be used in<lb/>
an emergency, when there is a scarcity of fish. The<lb/>
breeding at Samanco was about ninety per cent.</p>
<p>On July 12th, we took fish to San Jose, a town of<lb/>
300 inhabitants, and found no breeding. We went on to Nepe&ntilde;a,<lb/>
which has a polulation of 1800. We met the entire &ldquo;CONSEJOrdquo;,<lb/>
and at once started out putting fish in all containers.<lb/>
A great many containers already had fish, but the breeding<lb/>
there was about 30 per cent. We left a good supply of fish<lb/>
with the &ldquo;Municipalidad&rdquo;, for houses that were closed during our<lb/>
inspections, and which the members of the council agreed to<lb/>
take care of.</p>
<p>On August 13th we finished our inspection of San Jacinto,<lb/>
and in 150 houses found only one container with larvae. This made a<lb/>
total of four containers out of 310 houses counting the 160<lb/>
for July 9th, or a little over one per cent.</p>
<p>As the percentage of larvae found at San Jacinto was so<lb/>
small, we decided not to lose time placing fish in containers<lb/>
there. Mr. Gordon, Administrador General of San Jacinto is<lb/>
arranging to secure fish, and will have one of the chemists<lb/>
employed on the hacienda, distribute them in the containers.</p>
<p>On August 13th we left San Jacinto for Casma - by Samanco -<lb/>
but had tomwait at the latter place until the 15th for a boat.<lb/>
In the meantime we inpsevted containers at Samanco and found<lb/>
that the fish had disposed of all the larvae, not one larvae<lb/>
being found in any containers.</p>
<p>We reached the Port of Casma, August 15th, and the town<lb/>
of Casma that night. The following afternoon, August 16th., 700<lb/>
fish arrived from Trujillo in good condition and we started to<lb/>
distribute them; Dr. Caballero and the &ldquo;alcalde&rdquo; assisting us.<lb/>
We finished this work on the evening of August 17th. Dr. Caballero<lb/>
had already distributed fish in many houses before our arrival,<lb/>
and an inspection of the containers where he had placed fish<lb/>
showed that they had disposed of all the larvae. The breeding in<lb/>
the town of casma had been about 15 per cent.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03060004"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>To-morrow, Friday the 19th, we will re-examine the con-<lb/>
tainers where we distributed the fish to see the result.</p>
<p>Dr. Caballero believes it would be well for us to inspect<lb/>
Supe, and all the surrounding places. There will be a<lb/>
boat leaving the Port of Casma, Sunday the 21st, for Chimbote.<lb/>
Chimbote is the only place that we have worked during our trip,<lb/>
that we are not entirely satisfied with, so we are planning to<lb/>
work the Port of Casma Saturday, August the 20th, and leave<lb/>
there for Chimbote woth boat on the 21st. The same steamer will<lb/>
return south to Chimbote about the 25th, and if everything<lb/>
goes well we will catch it for Supe and work that place.<lb/>
I have asked Dr. Tapia to send us fish to Supe, by the same boat.<lb/>
In the interval, between the 21st and the 25th, we will have<lb/>
an oppurtunity to look over our work at Tambo Real, Santa,<lb/>
Guadalupito, Port of Casma, Hacienda San Botolo, and Chimbote.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully,</salute>
<signed>(signed) J. P. Corrigan,<lb/>
Inspector Sanitario</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>