<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03061001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Hanson to Florence M. Read, February 21, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hanson, Henry</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03061001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-02-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Read, Florence M.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Seely, Morris Monroe</name>
<name type="person">Caballero, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Dunn, Lawrence H.</name>
<name type="person">Olivari, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Corrigan, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Kirk, Robert H.</name>
<name type="person">Caldwell, Bert W.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Quiroz, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-02-21">February 21, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03061001</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Hanson to Florence M. Read, February 21, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hanson describes the work of the sanitary campaign against yellow fever in Peru, naming physicians and surveyors.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-02-21">
<head>Letter from Henry Hanson to Florence M. Read, February 21, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03061001"/>
<opener>
DIRECTOR GENERAL<lb/>
HENRY HANSON<lb/>
M. D.<lb/>
BAJO LOS AUSPICIOS DEL<lb/>
GOBIERNO PERUANO Y LA<lb/>
JUNTA INTERNACIONAL DE<lb/>
SANIDAD DE ROCKEPELLER<lb/>
FOUNDATION <unclear></unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
Campa&ntilde;a Sanitaria contra la Fiebre Amarilla en el Per&uacute;<lb/>
OFICINA CENTRAL<lb/>
AVENIDA PIEROLA 545 -- TELEFONO 3428<lb/>
LIMA -- PERU<lb/>
<date value="1922-02-21">February 21, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
NUMERO<lb/>
Miss Florence M. Read,<lb/>
Assistant Secretary,<lb/>
The International Health Board,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York City.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Read:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of 28Ultm was received yesterday<lb/>
in which I note that you think it proper to allow a months<lb/>
pay to certain employeed who have served a year in the Cam-<lb/>
paign, but at the same time you do not think that Mr. Seeley<lb/>
should be considered under the same ruling. It appears to<lb/>
me that Mr. Seely should be considered under the same con-<lb/>
ditions as he will have had a full years service, and has<lb/>
done exceptionally hard work, and his trip to Panama and back<lb/>
was necessary to enable him to continue. He is a man with a<lb/>
family and consequently has heavier expenses than the single<lb/>
men and on the basis of what is allowed for the others (a<lb/>
limited number of them) it is my opinion that he should be<lb/>
allowed one month without regard to what will be the outcome<lb/>
of his relationship with the Panama Canal Government. His<lb/>
work in the Department of Lambayeque has meant a great deal<lb/>
in the successful outcome of the campaign, and he was sub-<lb/>
jected to a very heavy expense on account of his coming back<lb/>
to continue for the few remaining months.</p>
<p>Dr. Caballero, Mr. Dunn and Sr. Olivari have about com-<lb/>
pleted their survey of the coast to the south and I am happy<lb/>
to report that so far they have found nothing in the line of<lb/>
suspicious illness. The Stegomya index however is very high,<lb/>
running about 50$ of more. The lowest index which they found<lb/>
was in Moquegua and Ilo, where it was about 25$. Dr. Caballero<lb/>
reports that they have been very well received and that the<lb/>
authorities have accepted them and their mission seriously.</p>
<p>Mr. Corrigan has just come in from the north Lima and<lb/>
Ancash sections and states that they are having great diffi-<lb/>
culty in securing fish on account of the flooding of the<lb/>
streams and ditches due to rains and melting snows in the<lb/>
mountains. Notwithstanding this we are keeping the index<lb/>
down even in this more or less superficially worked sector.<lb/>
I presume that I underestimated the need for fish as I thought<lb/>
that a half million would meet our needs, but as it turned out<lb/>
we used more than 800,000, up to the end of the year 1921. In<lb/>
the distribution sheet which we are sending Mr. Kirk we show<lb/>
a trifle over 700,000 which represents what was bought at so<lb/>
much per thousand, the rest was secured through fishermen who<lb/>
were working on a daily wage.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03061002"/>
<p>2.</p>
<p>Miss Florence M. Read, February 21, 1922.</p>
<p>I am very glad to have the extract from the letter<lb/>
of Dr. W.B. Caldwell to Mr. Le Prince. It is interesting to<lb/>
his remarks as to importation cases. Where do these impor-<lb/>
tation cases come from? It appears that they have some<lb/>
focus nearby where the disease is kept up. If we had such<lb/>
an occurrence here we would be afraid that a sort of &ldquo;vicious<lb/>
circle&rdquo; might be started by which we would have a long drawn<lb/>
out smoldering epidemic or endemic which after a while would<lb/>
manifest itself in a new sharp outbreak unles the Stegomya<lb/>
work were kept up sufficiently long for these other places<lb/>
immunize themselves.</p>
<p>Although we are now in the midst of the summer season<lb/>
and are having the hottest weather of the summer we have not<lb/>
yet had any reports of suspicious cases. I am &ldquo;knocking on<lb/>
wood&rdquo; and confidently hoping that we will have no more.</p>
<p>Some time ago I sent you a brief preliminary report<lb/>
of our work, and have been wondering if my estimates were<lb/>
exaggerated. Dr. Quiroz who was in Ferre&ntilde;afe and in other<lb/>
sections of the Campaign with me was in the Office yesterday<lb/>
and we discussed these matters and he stated that he did not<lb/>
think that I had exaggerated the thing beyond what actually<lb/>
did happen. It is a pity we were not more thoroughly organ-<lb/>
ized from the start so as to enable us to have gotten more<lb/>
acurate statistics during the crisis of the epidemic.</p>
<p>We are doing what we can to get all our data togather<lb/>
but it is slow work and there is a great deal of it.</p>
<p>Trusting that we shall have no further occasion to<lb/>
send you bad news, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Henry Hanson, M.D.</signed>,
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
