<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03062001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from H. McG. Robertson to Hugh S. Cumming, May 9, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Robertson, H. McG.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03062001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-05-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Cumming, Hugh S.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Creel, Asst. Attorney Gen.</name>
<name type="place">Boston (Mass.)</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-05-09">May 9, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03062001</idno>
<title>Letter from H. McG. Robertson to Hugh S. Cumming, May 9, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robertson proposes a study of fleas and bubonic plague in Boston, Philadelphia or Baltimore, Savannah, and New Orleans.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1922-05-09">
<head>Letter from H. McG. Robertson to Hugh S. Cumming, May 9, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03062001"/>
<opener>
Surgeon H. McG. Robertson.<lb/>
<dateline>
U. S. Quarantine Station,<lb/>
Marcus Hook, Pennsylvania,<lb/>
<date value="1922-05-09">May 9, 1922.</date>
</dateline>
The Surgeon General,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In an experience of 15 years in quarantine practice,<lb/>
I have been in touch with the geographical distribution of<lb/>
bubonic plague to rather an intimate degree. I have wondered<lb/>
more and more, in watching the spread of this disease, that<lb/>
in latitudes where cold weather prevailed for a portion of the<lb/>
year plague appeared either not at all or only very occasionally<lb/>
and for short periods. I have been especially struck with the<lb/>
freedom of our North Atlantic seaports from this disease, knowing<lb/>
that until recent years nothing of a practical nature was done<lb/>
to prevent the introduction of plague through infected rats.<lb/>
As late as 1911 I find that of the 1200 or more vessels arriving<lb/>
at the port of Philadelphia none were fumigated, though many<lb/>
came direct from ports in India and other plague infected dis-<lb/>
tricts. In casting about for a reasonable explanation of this<lb/>
apparent immunity of our North Atlantic Seaboard to bubonic plague,<lb/>
it has seemed to me that the only plausible explanation of this<lb/>
phenomenom is the absolute or relative freedom of the rodent<lb/>
population from fleas during certain of the colder months of<lb/>
the year. It will be readily seen that if fleas are at all<lb/>
seasons present and active the spread of plague among the rats<lb/>
of a community would eventually progress to a point where the<lb/>
human population must become affected. If, however, in certain<lb/>
seasons of more or less prolonged cold the number of fleas present<lb/>
is reduced to zero or to an &ldquo;Innocuous minimum&rdquo;, any plague<lb/>
infection which started to spread among rats at the beginning<lb/>
of the &ldquo;flea season&rdquo; would cease automatically when fleas were no<lb/>
longer present. If this &ldquo;flea season&rdquo; is relatively short and<lb/>
rats and humans not too intimately associated, an outbreak of<lb/>
human plague in any season is practically impossible. We know<lb/>
that in certain of our Southern and Western cities fleas are found<lb/>
at all seasons of the year.</p>
<p><hi>improbable</hi><lb/>
deft</p>
<p>In so far as I have learned no work has been done to<lb/>
determine the seasonal prevalence of fleas in different latitudes<lb/>
or in differing climates. It has been my desire for some time<lb/>
to make or take some part in making such an investigation. This<lb/>
was entirely apart from any idea of a survey of the rats of any<lb/>
community for the existence of plague and would entail much less<lb/>
expense. I understand from Assistant Surgeon General Creel that<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03062002"/>
-2-<lb/>
the idea of a double survey has been put into effect at Boston<lb/>
and of course it is well to know if the rats of a community are<lb/>
at any time plague infected. My idea, in detail, of the work I<lb/>
wish to do is as follows:</p>
<p>1. Make a flea survey in the following cities: Boston,<lb/>
Philadelphia or Baltimore, Savannah and New Orleans. If my<lb/>
supposition is correct that fleas are absent in certain of the<lb/>
colder months, I believe that at some point on the coast, say<lb/>
Savannah, it will be found that fleas are present on rodents in<lb/>
relatively large numbers throughout the year, and that from this<lb/>
point South plague could be continuously present in rats, with<lb/>
the possibility of human outbreaks, while North of that, or some<lb/>
near adjacent line, plague infection in rats, even if introduced<lb/>
every Summer season, would as regularly die out completely during<lb/>
the cold season, because of the absence of fleas, and consequently<lb/>
that human plague would be hardly possible.</p>
<p><unclear>apt ladies</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>out</unclear></p>
<p>2. To examine at least 15 rats daily, exclusive of Sundays and<lb/>
holidays, in the cities mentioned for an entire year, keeping a<lb/>
record of the fleas found each day. While the identification of<lb/>
all fleas found would be advisable, and I would prepare for this,<lb/>
it is unnecessary in determining their absence of presence on rats.</p>
<p>3. Keep record of temperature and any other climatic conditions<lb/>
of importance in each place where the work was done.</p>
<p>4. To examine all rats caught for the more obvious evidences of<lb/>
plague infection, and to make smears for microscopic examination<lb/>
of any organs deemed suspicious. The use of composite emulsions<lb/>
in guinea pigs would in my opinion hardly justify the increased<lb/>
expenditure it would make necessary.</p>
<p>5. The determination in the laboratory of how long a flea can<lb/>
infect an animal after having fed on an infected guinea pig.<lb/>
This would be of importance only as determining whether they would<lb/>
retain the infection during their seclusion through several months<lb/>
of cold weather.</p>
<p>How to<lb/>
<unclear>Think</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>into</unclear><lb/>
How long do they live infected.</p>
<p>If this work is confined to the limits given above it<lb/>
should not be unduly costly, yet it would, I think, be sufficiently<lb/>
inclusive to give the desired information. As to the possible<lb/>
practical good of such a work, I think it can be safely said<lb/>
that the present methods of quarantine procedure might be modified<lb/>
for Northern ports and that present practices in rat-proofing when<lb/>
a case of human plague appears might be essentially modified. It<lb/>
would of course be of great value for any community to feel<lb/>
assured that the coming of cold weather would wipe out all plague<lb/>
both in rats and men.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03062003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>As regards my qualifications to undertake this work,<lb/>
I recognize the necessity of a further and more intimate<lb/>
knowledge of fleas and their habits; of rat plague and possibly<lb/>
rats. I request that I be detailed for six weeks or two months<lb/>
at the Hygienic Laboratory for special duty, during which time<lb/>
plans for the survey can be made in detail. If it should suit<lb/>
the Bureau I would like to have immediate charge of the work in<lb/>
Philadelphia or Baltimore as determined, and a supervisory charge<lb/>
at other places, in order that I might keep in intimate touch<lb/>
with the work in its details.</p>
<p><hi>glad</hi></p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) H.McG. Robertson,<lb/>
Surgeon</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
