<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03063023">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from the Canal Zone Chief Health Officer to the Editors, Journal of the American Medical Association, September 9, 1922</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03063023</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1922-09-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1922-09-09">September 9, 1922</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03063023</idno>
<title>Letter from the Canal Zone Chief Health Officer to the Editors, Journal of the American Medical Association, September 9, 1922</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In this editorial the Canal Zone Chief Health Officer discusses malaria and public health efforts in Panama.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1922-09-09">
<head>Letter from the Canal Zone Chief Health Officer to the Editors, Journal of the American Medical Association, September 9, 1922</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03063023"/>
<p>Ac<lb/>
<unclear>Iv to L</unclear></p>
<p>Walter Reed</p>
<p>VOLUME 79<lb/>
NUMBER 11</p>
<p>CORRESPONDENCE</p>
<p>911</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<item>Frederic Milford Pendleton, Quincy, Ill.; Rush Medical<lb/>
College, Chicago, 1883; member of the Illinois State Medical<lb/>
Society; aged 63, died, July 6, at the Presbyterian Hospital,<lb/>
Chicago, following an operation for bladder trouble.</item>
<item>George M. Hamilton, Weston, W. Va.; Jefferson Medical<lb/>
College, Philadelphia, 1889; member of the West Virginia<lb/>
State Medical Association; formerly city health officer and<lb/>
county coroner; died, August 20, aged 61.</item>
<item>Henry Hannum, Bayfield, Wis.; Rush Medical College,<lb/>
Chicago, 1881; member of the State Medical Society of Wis-<lb/>
consin; in the Indian Service; died at the home of his son<lb/>
in Muskegon, Mich., August 16, aged 67.</item>
<item>William J. Stephenson, Decatur, Neb.; Medical College of<lb/>
Indiana, Indianapolis, 1886; member of the Nebraska State<lb/>
Medical Association; died recently, aged 70, from cerebral<lb/>
hemorrhage.</item>
<item>Levi Allen Neiman <unclear>+</unclear> Brooklyn; Baltimore Medical Col-<lb/>
lege, 1897; on the staff of the Lutheran Hospital; died,<lb/>
August 25, aged 60, from streptococcus septicemia and<lb/>
endocarditis.</item>
<item>William S. Scott, Dickson, Tenn.; Vanderbilt University<lb/>
Medical Department, Nashville, 1876; member of the Tennes-<lb/>
see State Medical Association; died, August 22, aged 69, from<lb/>
paresis.</item>
<item>Adolf L. Korn, Joplin, Mo.; University of Tubingen, Ger-<lb/>
many, 1902, member of the Missouri State Medical Associa-<lb/>
tion; on the staff of St. John's Hospital; died, August 16,<lb/>
aged 44.</item>
<item>Robert Charles McManus, Lancaster, S. C.; Medical<lb/>
Department of the University of the City of New York, 1881;<lb/>
died, August 9, aged 63, from carcinoma of the stomach.</item>
<item>Elnora Gilson, Whitmore, Woman's Medical School of<lb/>
Northwestern University, Chicago, 1894; member of the<lb/>
Kansas Medical Society; died, August 19, aged 56.</item>
<item>Samuel Maxwell Johnson, Brooklyn; Bellevue Hospital<lb/>
Medical College, New York, 1880; for twenty years police<lb/>
surgeon in New York; died, August 17, aged 66.</item>
<item>Samuel D. Cameron <unclear>+</unclear> Yakima, Wash.; Manitoba Medical<lb/>
College, Winnipeg, Man., Canada, 1899; was found dead in<lb/>
his office, August 19, aged 50, from heart disease.</item>
<item>John Emmet Rheim <unclear>+</unclear> Mora, Minn.; Northwestern Univer-<lb/>
sity Medical School, Chicago, 1910; died, July 31, aged 36,<lb/>
from acute dilatation of the heart.</item>
<item>Benjamin Pomeroy Wright, Schenectady, N. Y.; University<lb/>
of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, 1885; also a numis-<lb/>
matist; died, August 4, aged 64.</item>
<item>Marshall M. Chandler, Greenville, Texas; University of<lb/>
Nashville Medical Department, Nashville, Tenn., 1874; died,<lb/>
July 8, aged 83, from paresis.</item>
<item>Henry Hale Brotherlin <unclear>+</unclear> Hollidaysburg, Pa.; Jefferson<lb/>
Medical College, Philadelphia, 1883; died, August 20, aged<lb/>
62, following a long illness.</item>
<item>John Aaron Rawlins <unclear>+</unclear> Davenport, Iowa; Rush Medical<lb/>
College, Chicago, 1888; died, August 18, aged 56, at Ains-<lb/>
worth, Neb., from paresis.</item>
<item>Martin E. Thomas, Paducah, Ky.; Memphis Hospital Med-<lb/>
ical College, Memphis, Tenn., 1898; aged 48; was found dead<lb/>
on the street, August 20.</item>
<item>Donald E. MacPhail, Dayton, Ohio; University of Michi-<lb/>
gan Medical School, Ann Arbor, 1914; died, July 4, aged 32,<lb/>
from lobar pneumonia.</item>
<item>Gerson Strauss, New Haven, Conn.; Baltimore University<lb/>
School of Medicine, 1895; died, August 11, aged 55, from<lb/>
cerebral hemorrhage.</item>
<item>Charles S. Horning, Norristown, Pa.; Hahnemann Medical<lb/>
College of Philadelphia, 1881; died, August 16, from loco-<lb/>
motor ataxia.</item>
<item>John Elwyn Cochrane, Valatie, N. Y.; University of Ver-<lb/>
mont College of Medicine, Burlington, Vt., 1893; died, June<lb/>
26, aged 51.</item>
<item>Elmer Ellsworth Curl, Degraff, Ohio; Jefferson Medical<lb/>
College, Philadelphia, 1889; died, August 13, aged 60, from<lb/>
diabetes.</item>
<item>Thomas Croston, Lucas, Ia. (licensed Iowa, 1886); for<lb/>
fifty years a member of the school board; died, August 12,<lb/>
aged 76.</item>
<item>Joseph C. Purdy, Terhune, Ind. (licensed, Indiana, 1897);<lb/>
died, August 15, aged 67, from chronic nephritis.</item>
<item>B. F. Kiester, Dayton, Ohio; Medical College of Ohio,<lb/>
Cincinnati, 1875; died, August 21, aged 74.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Correspondence</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>SANITATION IN PANAMA</p>
<p>To the Editor:--In THE JOURNAL, August 5, under &ldquo;Medical<lb/>
News,&rdquo; you quote the Panama Star and Herald to the effect<lb/>
that an epidemic of malaria has developed among Canal Zone<lb/>
employees, and that breeding places of mosquitoes, which had<lb/>
been sprayed with oil the year round, are now neglected,<lb/>
with the result that there are now more mosquitoes on the<lb/>
Isthmus than ever before, since sanitation days; also that<lb/>
Ancon Hospital is overcrowded with malaria patients.</p>
<p>I believe your readers will appreciate the truth regarding<lb/>
these reports, which have had a widespread circulation in<lb/>
United States papers. The statements of the Panama Star<lb/>
and Herald, published June 18, 1922, may be categorically<lb/>
denied:</p>
<p>There is not an epidemic of malaria among the employees<lb/>
of the Panama Canal.</p>
<p>Breeding places of mosquitoes, formerly sprayed with oil<lb/>
the year round, are not now neglected.</p>
<p>There are not more mosquitoes on the Isthmus than ever<lb/>
before since sanitation days, but indeed far less than in any<lb/>
previous year. Observations made and records kept for the<lb/>
last twelve years abundantly prove this.</p>
<p>Ancon Hospital is not overcrowded with malaria patients,<lb/>
there being not only fewer cases than the average number<lb/>
in former years, but, even when the reduction of Panama<lb/>
Canal forces is considered, the relative number is less than<lb/>
the average of former years.</p>
<p>After the appearance in the Panama Star and Herald of<lb/>
the article you quote, there were others of similar tenor, and<lb/>
on June 21 the governor of the Panama Canal published this<lb/>
statement:</p>
<p>THE PANAMA CANAL<lb/>
CANAL ZONE<lb/>
EXECUTIVE OFFICE</p>
<p>Balboa Heights, C. Z., June 21, 1922.</p>
<p>TO ALL CONCERNED:</p>
<p>Certain unauthorized, entirely inaccurate, and apparently <unclear>malicious</unclear><lb/>
statements regarding the malaria situation and the work of the Health<lb/>
Department of the Panama Canal have been appearing recently in the<lb/>
daily press.</p>
<p>Even a carefully prepared statement of the chief health officer and<lb/>
other interviews have been published in a garbled manner under mis-<lb/>
leading headlines so as to give a different impression from that intended.</p>
<p>The known facts do not justify any undue alarm, nor are sanitary<lb/>
conditions on the Isthmus any worse, but rather better, than in former<lb/>
years at this season. The statistics of the health department, which are<lb/>
carefully recorded and are always available to interested inquirers, fully<lb/>
indicate the true condition.</p>
<p>At the beginning of each rainy season there is a natural increase of<lb/>
mosquito breeding, lasting through a couple of months, the most preva-<lb/>
lent variety being a harmless, though vicious biter called Aedes <unclear>taenio-<lb/>
rhynchus</unclear>. Anopheles, or malaria bearing mosquitoes, are kept under<lb/>
adequate control near our residential sections at all times.</p>
<p>The funds of the health department have been greatly curtailed in<lb/>
recent appropriations, but in anticipation of just such an eventuality,<lb/>
for several years past the division of sanitation has been carrying out a<lb/>
policy of eliminating by subsoil drainage large areas that had required<lb/>
maintenance, so that the present era of economy finds this division well<lb/>
prepared to cooperate to the fullest with the national policy of retrench-<lb/>
ment. No vital element of sanitation is being sacrificed in doing so.</p>
<p>Grass cutting about quarters, while extremely desirable from an <unclear>cathytic</unclear><lb/>
point of view, and as a measure of general policing, plays no part in<lb/>
the control of mosquito breeding, it being much more the part of wisdom<lb/>
to spend available public funds on drainage and control of <unclear>areas</unclear> in<lb/>
which mosquitoes are actually produced. This is being done, and it is<lb/>
believed our residential sections are thereby now even better protected<lb/>
than they were formerly.</p>
<p>There is not a case of blackwater fever in any of the Panama Canal<lb/>
of other hospitals, nor has there been a case originating on the Isthmus<lb/>
for several years. However, the type of malaria most prevalent in<lb/>
Panama at all times is a very serious type, unless promptly treated, and<lb/>
should never be disregarded. Under prompt and adequate treatment it<lb/>
is usually easily and permanently cured.</p>
<p>The health department has frequently issued warnings to the public<lb/>
of the danger of contracting malaria by visiting unsanitated areas after<lb/>
sundown, and this caution is again urged here. Beach parties, jungle<lb/>
trips and expeditions to native villages are safe and proper pleasures<lb/>
during daylight hours, but after nightfall, and especially in the rainy<lb/>
season, such unwarranted exposure is the height of imprudence.</p>
<p>JAY J. <unclear>MORROW</unclear>, Governor.</p>
<p>On July 5 there appeared in the New York Times an inter-<lb/>
view with Mr. W. C. Hushing, the representative of the<lb/>
Canal Zone union workers at Washington, D. C., in which<lb/>
even more fantastic statements regarding health conditions<lb/>
were uttered and graver charges made against officials of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03063024"/>
912<lb/>
QUERIES AND MINOR NOTES<lb/>
JOUR. A. M. A.<lb/>
SEPT. 9, 1922<lb/>
the government and the Panama Canal. The governor<lb/>
branded Mr. Hushing's statements as false and discharged<lb/>
him from the Panama Canal employ (that of pattern maker<lb/>
and member of the wage board). Back of this controversy<lb/>
lies a complex situation, a knowledge of which is necessary<lb/>
to a complete understanding of the attack on the administra-<lb/>
tion and the health department of the Panama Canal.</p>
<p>TABLE 1.-INCIDENCE OF MALARIA AMONG EMPLOYEES<lb/>
FOR THE LAST FOUR YEARS<lb/>
<table rows="2" cols="5">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>Rate per Thousand<lb/>
per Annum<lb/>
Among Employees</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Fiscal year 1919.................................</cell><cell>29.64</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Fiscal year 1920.................................</cell><cell><unclear>23.00</unclear></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Fiscal year 1921.................................</cell><cell>18.10</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Fiscal year 1922.................................</cell><cell>15.39</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>TABLE 2.-MALARIA INCIDENCE PER THOUSAND<lb/>
EMPLOYEES OF THE PANAMA CANAL<lb/>
<table cols="6" rows="13">
<row>
<cell>Month</cell><cell>1918</cell><cell>1919</cell><cell>1920</cell><cell>1921</cell><cell>1922</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>January .......................</cell><cell>2.53</cell><cell>2.95</cell><cell><unclear>2.62</unclear></cell><cell>1.52</cell><cell>1.08</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>February ......................</cell><cell>2.54</cell><cell>3.57</cell><cell>1.51</cell><cell>1.21</cell><cell>1.29</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>March ........................</cell><cell>2.03</cell><cell>4.34</cell><cell>1.57</cell><cell>1.19</cell><cell>0.56</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>April .........................</cell><cell>2.24</cell><cell>1.66</cell><cell>0.22</cell><cell>0.37</cell><cell>0.28</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>May ..........................</cell><cell>1.86</cell><cell>2.72</cell><cell>0.36</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell>1.65</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>June ..........................</cell><cell>1.50</cell><cell>3.53</cell><cell>2.44</cell><cell>1.69</cell><cell>1.96</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>July ..........................</cell><cell>1.66</cell><cell>7.04</cell><cell>1.97</cell><cell>1.89</cell><cell>....</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>August ........................</cell><cell>1.93</cell><cell>3.15</cell><cell>2.75</cell><cell>1.87</cell><cell>....</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>September .....................</cell><cell>0.98</cell><cell>2.06</cell><cell>2.31</cell><cell>1.13</cell><cell>....</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>October .......................</cell><cell>0.76</cell><cell>1.03</cell><cell>2.36</cell><cell>1.01</cell><cell>....</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>November .....................</cell><cell>1.51</cell><cell>1.48</cell><cell>1.25</cell><cell>0.88</cell><cell>....</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>December ......................</cell><cell>3.40</cell><cell>2.00</cell><cell>1.17</cell><cell>1.37</cell><cell>....</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>In June, 1921, a Special Panama Canal Commission,<lb/>
appointed by the Secretary of War, arrived on the Isthmus to<lb/>
investigate and report upon existing conditions relating to the care,<lb/>
maintenance, sanitation, operation and government of the Panama Canal<lb/>
and Canal Zone, including all matters affecting the Panama Railroad and<lb/>
the Panama Railroad Steamship Line, and to make recommendations<lb/>
relative to any changes in such conditions affecting the organization,<lb/>
government, and operation of the Panama Canal and Canal Zone, and<lb/>
the operations of the Panama Railroad Company.</p>
<p>This commission submitted to the Secretary of War a full<lb/>
report, with recommendations for the operation of every<lb/>
department of the Panama Canal. Many of their findings<lb/>
and recommendations were in accord with previous ones,<lb/>
and these and others received the approval of the Secretary<lb/>
of War and were placed in operation. Principally affecting,<lb/>
and objected to by, the employees was the order requiring<lb/>
them to pay rent on quarters and the cost of care of grounds<lb/>
immediately about their quarters, garbage collection, fuel,<lb/>
light, subsistence while in hospital, etc., all of which they<lb/>
had hitherto enjoyed free.</p>
<p>Also among the recommendations of the special commis-<lb/>
sion was the following:</p>
<p>It is recommended that the amounts <unclear>expended</unclear> for sanitation in the<lb/>
Canal Zone be greatly reduced and if as a result the sick and death<lb/>
rate from malaria rises above the average in twenty of the largest cities<lb/>
of the United States, the sanitary precautions may be increased.</p>
<p>This recommendation was not accepted by the Secretary<lb/>
of War and was not put into effect or included in the pub-<lb/>
lished report of the commission, although it was published<lb/>
in the daily papers on the Isthmus and elsewhere and aroused<lb/>
much unfavorable comment. Instead of this recommenda-<lb/>
tion, the Secretary of War ordered as follows:</p>
<p>The amounts expended for sanitation in the Zone shall be reduced<lb/>
as much as possible consistent with maintaining the necessary sanitary<lb/>
precautions requisite for the preservation of the health of American<lb/>
employees in tropical service.</p>
<p>This is the policy actually pursued by the health department<lb/>
for some years past.</p>
<p>Following the imposition of the charges outlined above, the<lb/>
employees attempted to obtain relief through the courts here<lb/>
and in the United States, but these ruled they had no juris-<lb/>
diction, and the employees then decided to appeal to Wash-<lb/>
ington, and sent for that purpose Mr. Hushing and another<lb/>
to represent them at the capital. Here, too, their efforts<lb/>
ended in failure, and then began, first on the Isthmus and<lb/>
later in the United States, the publication of these articles<lb/>
regarding health conditions on the Canal Zone. In the minds<lb/>
of the American people, the Panama Canal is a great monu-<lb/>
ment, first to the skill, initiative and ability of their engineers,<lb/>
and second, but in no less degree, to the far seeing wisdom,<lb/>
self-devotion and courage of their medical and sanitary<lb/>
officers. General Gorgas reaped a well deserved meed of<lb/>
fame and devotion from his own and other nations. Herein<lb/>
lies the secret of the recent attack on health conditions. The<lb/>
employees of the Panama Canal wanted the ear of the people,<lb/>
that they might not voice their complaints unheeded, and<lb/>
in this at least they appear to have succeeded.</p>
<p>Unfortunately (for them) their assertions regarding health<lb/>
and sanitation are as easy to disprove as they would be had<lb/>
they stated that the Panama Canal was failing to operate in<lb/>
a physical way--that ships are not put through on time or<lb/>
are endangered in their passage. In no other disease are<lb/>
cases reported, investigated and followed up more closely<lb/>
than in malaria. The accompanying tables show the inci-<lb/>
dence of malaria among employees for the last four years.</p>
<p>Were these figures separated for white and colored<lb/>
employees, the white rates would be even better than the<lb/>
totals. Owing to lack of work, many colored employees are<lb/>
engaged by the canal only a small portion of their time, and<lb/>
when not so employed they are roaming about, seeking food<lb/>
and small jobs, in various places outside the sanitated<lb/>
districts.</p>
<p>There was a definite increase in 1921 and 1922 in the total<lb/>
number of malaria cases on the Zone among nonemployees<lb/>
of the canal (including army and navy forces as well as<lb/>
others), but this cannot in any way be ascribed to a fault<lb/>
of the program of sanitation. The army, which shows the<lb/>
greatest increase, has been engaged from time to time in very<lb/>
necessary maneuvers and reconnaissances in the unsanitated<lb/>
parts of the Zone and the Republic of Panama, resulting, for<lb/>
a time at least, in a heavy malarial infection. The Canal<lb/>
Zone has recently been opened to repopulation by discharged<lb/>
former colored employees, who have been allotted for agri-<lb/>
cultural purposes small tracts of uninhabited land remote<lb/>
from the canal settlements and towns, and these too are now<lb/>
furnishing--as was expected--a number of malarial infections.</p>
<p>I think I have written enough to show the fallacy of the<lb/>
published accusations against the health administration of<lb/>
the Canal Zone. Were they true, I should be among the <unclear>first</unclear><lb/>
to protest publicly against the commission of so great a<lb/>
crime.</p>
<p>D. P. CURRY, M.D., Balboa Heights,<lb/>
Acting Chief Health Officer.<lb/>
Canal Zone.</p>
<p>-------------</p>
<p>Queries and Minor Notes</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>ANONYMOUS COMMUNICATIONS and queries on postal cards will not<lb/>
be noticed. Every letter must contain the writer's name and address,<lb/>
but these will be omitted, on request.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>CHENOPODIUM OIL</p>
<p>To the Editor:--In all cases of proved intestinal infestation with<lb/>
parasites. I give chenopodium oil. Its effects are really wonderful<unclear>.</unclear><lb/>
No intestinal parasite stands against it. There are, however, two serious<lb/>
objections to its use, namely, its odor and its taste. Patients, both<lb/>
adults and children, take it with much distaste, and the majority vomit<lb/>
it, losing its benefit.</p>
<p>V. RODRIGUEZ ARJONA, M.D., Mexico.</p>
<p>ANSWER--This objection has apparently been obviated by<lb/>
giving the drug in freshly prepared, hard gelatin capsules<lb/>
(Darling. Barber and Hacker: Hookworm and Malaria<lb/>
Research in Malaya, Java, and Fiji Islands, Pub. 9, Inter-<lb/>
national Health Board, 1920. Darling, S. T., and Smillie,<lb/>
W. G.: The Technic of Chenopodium Administration in<lb/>
Hookworm Disease, THE JOURNAL, Feb. 12, 1921, p. 419.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
