<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03065002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Book Review: William Crawford Gorgas, His Life and Work, by Mazyck P. Ravenel, May 9, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03065002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-05-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Hendrick, Burton J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Goethals, George Washington</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-05-09">May 9, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03065002</idno>
<title>Book Review: William Crawford Gorgas, His Life and Work, by Mazyck P. Ravenel, May 9, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This review, which appeared in the Journal of the American Medical Association, is critical of some of the accomplishments attributed to William Crawford Gorgas by Marie Gorgas and Hendrick.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1925-05-09">
<head>Book Review: William Crawford Gorgas, His Life and Work, by Mazyck P. Ravenel, May 9, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03065002"/>
<opener>
1446<lb/>
BOOK NOTICES<lb/>
<dateline>
JOUR. A. M. A.<lb/>
<date value="1925-05-09">MAY 9, 1925</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Book Notices</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>WILLIAM CRAWFORD GORGAS, HIS LIFE AND WORK. By Marie D.<lb/>
Gorgas and Burton J. Hendrick, Cloth. Price, $5. Pp. 359, with 10<lb/>
illustrations. Philadelphia; Lea &amp; Febiger<unclear>,</unclear> 1924.</p>
<p>Notable biographies in medicine are no longer a novelty;<lb/>
the Vallery-Radot &ldquo;Pasteur,&rdquo; the life of Metchnikoff by his<lb/>
wife, of Sir Victor Horsley by Paget, of Lord Lister by<lb/>
Sir Rickman Godlee, are among the best examples of true<lb/>
literary art devoted to the heroes of science. We have had<lb/>
in our own country excellent biographies of Ephraim<lb/>
McDowell and of William Beaumont, but thus far no work<lb/>
whose literary merit and whose field in the position of litera-<lb/>
ture would seem to entitle it to consideration both as a record<lb/>
of scientific achievement and as a literary accomplishment.</p>
<p>The life of William Crawford Gorgas, by his wife and<lb/>
Burton J. Hendrick, represents an unusual collaboration, a<lb/>
person intimately acquainted with the career of the subject<lb/>
working in this instance with a writer trained in the popular<lb/>
journalistic method. The real personality in the work appears<lb/>
naturally in those portions in which Mrs. Gorgas speaks in<lb/>
the first person; this is particularly apparent in the first<lb/>
chapter, which is a simple account of the first contact of<lb/>
General Gorgas with yellow fever and of his meeting at the<lb/>
same time with the girl who became his wife. Next comes a<lb/>
throw back to the ancestry and youth of the boy who was to<lb/>
become noted for stamping out one of the world's most<lb/>
devastating diseases. General Gorgas is here pictured as a<lb/>
young man with an unextinguishable desire for a military<lb/>
career; indeed, we are told that he chose medicine rather than<lb/>
law because, failing in the West Point examinations, he<lb/>
thought medicine a more direct route into the army. This<lb/>
minor point is emphasized only to show how the modern<lb/>
interpretative biographic method may sometimes yield rather<lb/>
dubious interpretations.</p>
<p>Again, the journalist with his eye centered on the con-<lb/>
spicuous figure of the book is perhaps less inclined than<lb/>
would be a scientific writer to give credit where due in exact<lb/>
proportions for certain phases of the yellow fever work.<lb/>
This aspect of the matter is particularly well reflected in an<lb/>
editorial analysis of this life of Gorgas, which appeared in<lb/>
the Military Surgeon for March, 1925. The analysis there<lb/>
made indicates that Gorgas as an administrator was slow to<lb/>
accept some of the scientific demonstrations of Reed, Lazear,<lb/>
Carroll and Agramonte, continuing the expensive disinfection<lb/>
of fomites for six months after their harmlessness had been<lb/>
demonstrated and, indeed, after another medical officer had<lb/>
accepted Reed's proof of this fact. Furthermore, the writer<lb/>
in the Military Surgeon points out that Reed and General<lb/>
Wood were already beginning to eliminate the mosquito at<lb/>
the time when Gorgas still hesitated. It is not perhaps<lb/>
entirely fair or necessary, or for that matter important, to<lb/>
analyze too closely the scientific data presented in this life<lb/>
of one of our heroes of modern sanitation.</p>
<p>The book gives us a picture of a kindly man with a sort<lb/>
of self-effacing tact, who accomplished results by rigid adher-<lb/>
ence to duty and by a persistence which, while mild, was<lb/>
extraordinarily effective. In the presentation of the story<lb/>
of the career of Gorgas, it has been well that the journalist<lb/>
was able to select incident and anecdote that give the story<lb/>
such lightness as to insure its being read. Such anecdotes as<lb/>
the following certainly lend color to the picture:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Do you know, Gorgas,&rdquo; Colonel Goethals said one day, &ldquo;that every<lb/>
mosquito you kill costs the United States government ten dollars?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;But just think,&rdquo; answered Gorgas, &ldquo;one of those ten-dollar mosquitoes<lb/>
might bite you, and what a loss that would be to the country!&rdquo;</p>
<p>By far the large majority of space in this life of Gorgas<lb/>
is devoted to the conquest of yellow fever, the entire life of<lb/>
the man being portrayed as a conquest of this particular<lb/>
disease. On the other hand, the World War is dismissed<lb/>
with some twenty pages of tribute to the manner in which<lb/>
Gorgas apparently subordinated himself to other persons. Of<lb/>
the pages referred to, ten are a quotation from Dr. Franklin<lb/>
H. Martin, of the General Medical Board of the Council of<lb/>
By Dr. Mazyck P. Ravenel<lb/>
Volume 84<lb/>
Number 19<lb/>
MEDICO<lb/>
National Defense, which, it appears from the manner of<lb/>
presentation, was in charge of medical affairs during the<lb/>
World War.</p>
<p>The Gorgas-Hendrick life of Surgeon General Gorgas,<lb/>
while a praiseworthy effort, is in no sense of the word an<lb/>
adequate biography. It is representative of the journalistic<lb/>
form of biography in that it builds about the bare facts of a<lb/>
man's life a sort of anecdotal, laudatory picture that is quite<lb/>
out of perspective with the facts. To say this is no depreca-<lb/>
tion of the real work of one of the most notable figures in<lb/>
American medicine; that, of course, has had its meed of<lb/>
praise. It remains, however, for some one to paint a picture<lb/>
of the campaign against yellow fever in which the work of<lb/>
each of the notable figures that took part shall have its due<lb/>
place; it remains for some analyst of men and manners and<lb/>
the movements of people to show what manner of man was<lb/>
William Crawford Gorgas. There is yet great opportunity<lb/>
for a biographic writer of ability to give us a life of Gorgas<lb/>
that will measure with such works as those of Vallery-Radot<lb/>
and Stephen Paget.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
