<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03107005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from James E. Peabody to Friends of the Yellow Fever Heroes of 1900, November 15, 1926</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Fitzpatrick, Elizabeth</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03107005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1926-11-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Watson, James E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, Ida E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="place">Andrews (Ind.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1926-11-22">November 22, 1926</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03107005</idno>
<title>Letter from James E. Peabody to Friends of the Yellow Fever Heroes of 1900, November 15, 1926</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Peabody describes efforts to obtain pensions for Kissinger and for widows of yellow fever commission participants.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1926-11-22">
<head>Letter from James E. Peabody to Friends of the Yellow Fever Heroes of 1900, November 15, 1926</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03107005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
The Morris High School<lb/>
166th. and Boston Road, N. Y. City,<lb/>
<date value="1926-11-15">November 15, 1926.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>To the Friends of those Yellow Fever Heroes of <unclear>1900</unclear>:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You have all been so generous in your assistance during this past<lb/>
week, and you have expressed so much interest in the case of John R.<lb/>
Kissinger, that I venture to send you this statement of events up to<lb/>
date.</p>
<p>My correspondence with Mr. Kissinger began about fifteen years<lb/>
ago. The many letters received from him all breathe the same spirit<lb/>
as that contained in a letter written December 4, 1912, in which he<lb/>
said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;It was a big triumph and I am glad that my humble self was one<lb/>
to take a small part in it, not to be called a hero or a martyr,<lb/>
but to feel in my own heart that I helped in saving thousands<lb/>
of lives and millions of dollars, and making it possible to<lb/>
accomplish the building of one of the greatest engineering works<lb/>
of the world, the Panama Canal.&rdquo;</p>
<p>On September 1st., on my way home from a five-months' trip for<lb/>
travel and study in the West, I spent an hour with Mr. Kissinger in<lb/>
his little home in Andrews, Huntington County, Indiana. I was deeply<lb/>
impressed with his self-effacing modesty, and with the courage dis-<lb/>
played by the man and his wife during all these past twenty-five years.</p>
<p>Dr. Wendell C. Phillips, President of the American Medical Associa-<lb/>
tion, secured an appointment for me with Dr. Hubert Work, Secretary<lb/>
of the Interior, and so, with the approval of Dr. Tildsley and Prin-<lb/>
cipal Bogart, I left for Washington Friday afternoon, Nov. 15. On<lb/>
reaching Princeton that evening, I spent an hour or more with Prof.<lb/>
E. G. Conklin. He urged me to get in touch with Dr. Theobald Smith,<lb/>
who over twenty years ago examined Mr. Kissinger after he was strick-<lb/>
ened with myelitis of the spine, and if possible to enlist the aid of<lb/>
Dr. William H. Welch in Baltimore. The next morning at the Rockefel-<lb/>
ler Institute, four miles out of Princeton, Dr. Smith expressed the<lb/>
greatest interest in Kissinger, and promised to find if possible the<lb/>
record of his visit at South Bend, Indiana, (Kissinger's former home).</p>
<p>Saturday evening in Baltimore I talked with Dr. Howard A. Kelly<lb/>
(the author of &ldquo;Dr. Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo;) and with Dr. W. H. Howell<lb/>
(the newly appointed Director of the Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene<lb/>
and Public Health). Both were very helpful in their advice, and they<lb/>
told me how to reach Dr. Welch, who on Sunday generously gave two<lb/>
hours of his time. (He was intimately acquainted with all the mem-<lb/>
bers of the Yellow Fever Commission, appointed in 1900 by President<lb/>
McKinley). He wrote three very urgent letters to the Washington au-<lb/>
thorities, and these, together with two others from Dr. Kelly, proved<lb/>
of invaluable assistance.</p>
<p>Dr. Hubert Work, Secretary of the Interior, Surgeon General Ire-<lb/>
land of the Army, Surgeon General Cumming of the Public Health Ser-<lb/>
vice, and Colonel Kean (who was in charge of sanitation in Cuba in<lb/>
1900 and who followed closely the details of the yellow fever exper-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03107006"/>
The Yellow Fever Heroes of 1900 (2)<lb/>
iments) were more than cordial, and it needed no words of nine to en-<lb/>
list their interest in Kissinger, since they were all familiar with<lb/>
his story, except in its later details. After some discussion all<lb/>
agreed with Colonel Kean's suggestion that every possible influence<lb/>
should be brought to bear upon Congress to secure legislation that<lb/>
would give to Mrs. Walter Reed, Mrs. Jesse Lazear, and Mrs. James<lb/>
Carroll, and to Mr. and Mrs. Kissinger an annuity of $250 per month<lb/>
for the rest of their lives. (The <unclear>three</unclear> widows receive at the pres-<lb/>
ent time $125 each per month, and Kissinger $100).</p>
<p>Dr. Vernon Kellogg, Secretary of the National Research Council,<lb/>
the office staff of Science Service (in the absence of Dr. Slosson),<lb/>
the Veterans' Bureau, and Dr. William E. Ritter, President of the<lb/>
Scripps' Foundation promised to do all they could to bring this mat-<lb/>
ter to the attention of the public.</p>
<p>I had three long talks with Mrs. Reed, and from her and from Col.<lb/>
Kean I gained invaluable first hand information relative to the <unclear>event</unclear><lb/>
of those memorable six months of 1900 in Cuba. (Since her husband's<lb/>
death Mrs. Reed has had a monthly income of $125 from the Government<lb/>
and $100 interest from a fund raised in her husband's memory; she has<lb/>
a single room in an apartment hotel in Washington, and she and her<lb/>
daughter have been obliged for years to earn money by art work in em-<lb/>
broidery).</p>
<p>In <unclear>1916</unclear>, while teaching in the Summer Session of the University of<lb/>
California, I had the son of Dr. Lazear in one of my classes. He in-<lb/>
troduced me to his mother and his young sister. Mrs. Lazear told of<lb/>
the struggle she was having to meet her bills and to educate her chil-<lb/>
dren with the sum received from the Government.</p>
<p>You do not need to be told that special legislation is not easy to<lb/>
secure from Congress. In view, however, of the urgent need of all<lb/>
the four families that would be benefitted by it, everyone with whom<lb/>
I have talked has expressed the belief that prompt action should be<lb/>
urged.</p>
<p>We trust that you will send us your suggestions as to the next<lb/>
steps that ought to be taken.</p>
<p>With deep gratitude for the help you have already given, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>James E. Peabody,<lb/>
Head of the Department of Biology,<lb/>
Morris High School, N. Y. City</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
