<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03117001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Ida E. Kissinger and John R. Kissinger to James E. Peabody, June 7, 1927</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kissinger, Ida E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03117001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-06-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Peabody, James E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Rodger, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Kane, Thomas</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Gruenberg, Benjamin C.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-06-07">June 7, 1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03117001</idno>
<title>Letter from Ida E. Kissinger and John R. Kissinger to James E. Peabody, June 7, 1927</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Peabody Fund has donated a house to the Kissingers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1927-06-07">
<head>Letter from Ida E. Kissinger and John R. Kissinger to James E. Peabody, June 7, 1927</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03117001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Andrews, Huntington County, Indiana.<lb/>
<date value="1927-06-07">June 7, 1927.</date>
</dateline>
James E. Peabody,<lb/>
<salute>Our Very Dear Friend:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of June 2nd. received on Saturday. We were very glad to hear<lb/>
from you. Dear Mr. Peabody, we never can be able to thank you and our<lb/>
many kind friends for what they have done for us. And, oh, it means so<lb/>
much to us!</p>
<p>Mrs. Shaeff was over Sunday eve for about two hours. She is certainly<lb/>
a wonderful woman. She explained to us that the papers were being fixed<lb/>
up and all records, so everything would be straight. Yes, it is a very<lb/>
pretty home, and is so nicely arranged inside, and they tell us it's a<lb/>
very warm house. We certainly love it and will take lots of comfort<lb/>
when we are settled in it.</p>
<p>I am certainly happy to know that the people in our neighborhood speak<lb/>
well of us, and I am sure any place you could ask it would be the same.<lb/>
They say to have good neighbors you have to be one, and we have always<lb/>
made an effort to be one.</p>
<p>We are so sorry for Mrs. Lazear. We<del>su</del> surely ought to try to do some-<lb/>
thing for her. Anything we could do would be freely done, so many of<lb/>
our friends are happy over our new home. Mr. Kissinger and Robert (the<lb/>
17 year old grandson of Mrs. Kissinger) were over there today cutting the<lb/>
high grass and fixing so they could have a plot plowed for potatoes.<lb/>
They told us it would be about two weeks before we could move, for they<lb/>
intended to paper and do any repairing it needed before we could go there.</p>
<p>You are certainly welcome to those papers I sent you. You can keep<lb/>
those pictures. We have thought always we would get a fire-proof box for<lb/>
our papers, but we have never been able to. We will try to have them<lb/>
secured somehow. (The papers referred to are the original yellow fever<lb/>
chart, and valuable documents relating to the experiments in Cuba). The<lb/>
Doctor who made out the Yellow Fever chart was Dr. Rodger, Port Ames.</p>
<p>Mr. Kissinger had a pleasant meeting one week ago last Saturday. The<lb/>
nurse who cared for him during the experiment read of him in the paper<lb/>
and came all the way here to visit Mr. Kissinger. He is Thomas Kane of<lb/>
Alton, Illinois. He stayed from Saturday until Monday. They surely had<lb/>
a nice visit. He had never heard from John since tha Spanish-American<lb/>
War, and they visited until they were both exhausted.</p>
<p>Mr. Peabody, I am sending you a letter we received with a dollar in<lb/>
it. How grateful we were to get it and to know the efforts that the<lb/>
people were making to help us. We have received three or four letters<lb/>
asking us about the stories, and saying they wanted to help, and said<lb/>
their letters had been returned to them by the Postmaster, so I am send-<lb/>
ing this to show you.</p>
<p>We certainly wish that Moran could be found. A party wrote us asking<lb/>
if we knew Moran's address. How we wish we did know. We will write you<lb/>
again as soon as we are settled, and if we can do anything to aid the<lb/>
workers for Mrs. Lazear, we will surely do it. We thank you <unclear>all</unclear> dear<lb/>
Dr. Gruenberg. How we wish we could thank each one individually for all<lb/>
they have done for us.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Mrs. John R. Kissinger, John R. Kissinger)</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
