<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03114002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">A Hero, by Margaret E. Grody, April 11, 1927</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03114002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-04-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-04-11">April 11, 1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03114002</idno>
<title>A Hero, by Margaret E. Grody, April 11, 1927</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>A student paper defines heroism.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1927-04-11">
<head>A Hero, by Margaret E. Grody, April 11, 1927</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03114002"/>
<opener>
E. H. S. FORM <unclear>38</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
HARLEM EVENING HIGH SCHOOL<lb/>
FOR WOMEN<lb/>
114TH, ST., BET. 7TH AND 8TH AVES.<lb/>
LILIAN M. ELLIOT, PRINCIPAL<lb/>
NEW YORK,.....<date value="1927-04-11">April 11, 1927</date>
</dateline>
<hi>A HERO</hi><lb/>
</opener>
<p>Did it ever enter your mind to take a small word and analyze<lb/>
it! If it has, you will find that one little word will afford much<lb/>
discussion in determining the real meaning. Each one considering the<lb/>
word will regard it in a different light. So it is with the word &ldquo;Hero&rdquo;.<lb/>
It is indeed a little word but it has a very broad meaning. The Diction-<lb/>
ary gives the definition of a hero as &ldquo;A man distinguished for valor,<lb/>
fortitude or bold enterprises&rdquo;. How very narrow is this definition<lb/>
when one considers the word quite fully. We have new heroes every day,<lb/>
in every part of the world and yet, often, no one knows about them. They<lb/>
are not advertised for their valor. They are not continually heroes.<lb/>
One man may give his life for another - he is a hero but he was not<lb/>
famed for his bold enterprises. And if he does become known for his act,<lb/>
how long will the fame last? Perhaps he was never even given a thought<lb/>
by his neighbors until he saved his fellowman. Probably the people who<lb/>
knew him, thought him an unusual character who had better be left alone<lb/>
and so he dragged listlessly through life. Yet he had this hidden<lb/>
attribute - the power to be a hero. His chance came, he saved a man -<lb/>
gave up his own life for the other and now he is a &ldquo;hero&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The meaning of the word lies in the individual conception of it<lb/>
and one would be surprised to hear all the different versions of a given<lb/>
number of people. The little girl of seven does not regard a hero in the<lb/>
same light as her sister of sixteen and her mother has another picture.<lb/>
Why! Because the viewpoint is decidedly different. Besides this, there are<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03114003"/>
E. H. S. FORM <unclear>38</unclear><lb/>
HARLEM EVENING HIGH SCHOOL<lb/>
FOR WOMEN<lb/>
114TH, ST., BET. 7TH AND 8TH AVES.<lb/>
LILIAN M. ELLIOT, PRINCIPAL<lb/>
NEW YORK........................19......<lb/>
A Hero (Cont'd)<lb/>
<hi>Page 2</hi><lb/>
degrees of heroism. These depend upon the person performing the deed<lb/>
and his abilities combined with the situation coped with. If a man expects<lb/>
to perform a heroic act <unclear>he</unclear> does not attain the height that another would<lb/>
who suddenly performs a great deed. A person acting on duty who performs<lb/>
a great deed is not a hero, because he was put at his post with the idea<lb/>
that he would perform just such an act, if necessity arose. On the other<lb/>
hand, if another person comes along who is totally unaware of what is<lb/>
confronting him, and who, out of love for his fellowman performs the same<lb/>
deed - he too is a hero. The first man was in duty bound to do the deed<lb/>
of valor, the other did it spontaneously, with the thought only to prevent<lb/>
disaster and so he gains the title of &ldquo;hero&rdquo;.</p>
<p>If there are so many degrees of heroism what then are the qualities<lb/>
of a hero? That he must perform a great deed is what most people seem to<lb/>
think. I disagree because the deed may not be great in the eyes of the<lb/>
world but when the situation is considered in all its phases, it may be a<lb/>
deed of great importance. Another quality of a hero is his perseverance in<lb/>
the face of adversity. We are acquainted with the lines &ldquo;The man worth<lb/>
while is the man with a smile when everything goes dead wrong.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>
<signed>Margaret E. Grody</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
