<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03114004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245"><hi rend="italic">Types of Heroes,</hi> by Anna Mahon, March 29, 1927</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03114004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-03-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Father Damien</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-03-29">March 29, 1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03114004</idno>
<title><hi rend="italic">Types of Heroes,</hi> by Anna Mahon, March 29, 1927</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>A student paper defines heroism.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1927-03-29">
<head><hi rend="italic">Types of Heroes,</hi> by Anna Mahon, March 29, 1927</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03114004"/>
<opener>
E. H. S. FORM NO. 21<lb/>
Telephone Monument 8292<lb/>
<dateline>
BOARD OF EDUCATION<lb/>
THE CITY OF NEW YORK<lb/>
HARLEM EVENING HIGH SCHOOL<lb/>
FOR WOMEN<lb/>
114th Street between 7th and 8th Avenues<lb/>
LILLIAN M. ELLIOT, Principal<lb/>
NEW YORK,.<date value="1927-03-29">March 29, 1927</date>
</dateline>
<hi>ANNA MAHON</hi>.<lb/>
<hi>TYPES OF HEROES.</hi><lb/>
</opener>
<p>Flags and bunting flying in the breeze, whistles blowing,<lb/>
sirens screaching, bells ringing, and crowds of people lined up on<lb/>
both sides of the avenue as far as eye can see. A sudden quiet<lb/>
seems to have fallen on the surging mob, but it is the lull that<lb/>
precedes the storm. Coming slowly up the avenue, preceded by a<lb/>
joyous band, comes a man. The storm breaks - a mighty shout is<lb/>
heard, cheers rend the air and hats and handkerchiefs wave on<lb/>
every side - a wild demonstration of joy for a Hero has just<lb/>
passed by! What mighty deed of valor had he done? What courage<lb/>
and fortitude had he displayed in time of danger? What act of<lb/>
heroism had he performed to warrant this manifestation of approbation<lb/>
by an appreciative and admiring public? Without doubt, his act<lb/>
included all the requisites necessary to entitle him to the renown<lb/>
and honor thus afforded him.</p>
<p>Situated on the South Sea Island is a place called Molokai.<lb/>
To this Island in the year 1873, came a young Catholic priest by the<lb/>
name of Father Damien. A more wretched, desolate, miserable place<lb/>
than this island it would be hard to find. It was the home, refuge<lb/>
of the lepers. Father Damien, a fearless Belgian priest, filled<lb/>
with Divine love for God and for his fellow man, when the call for<lb/>
service came, studied medicine in the best universities in Europe.<lb/>
He specialized in skin diseases and then, equipped to give his services<lb/>
1<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03114005"/>
E. H. S. FORM NO. 21<lb/>
Telephone Monument 8292<lb/>
BOARD OF EDUCATION<lb/>
THE CITY OF NEW YORK<lb/>
HARLEM EVENING HIGH SCHOOL<lb/>
FOR WOMEN<lb/>
114th Street between 7th and 8th Avenues<lb/>
LILLIAN M. ELLIOT, Principal<lb/>
NEW YORK,..................192....<lb/>
as priest and physician, separated himself from those near and dear<lb/>
to him, and spent his life among these poor outcasts. After ten years<lb/>
of unmitigated toil and earnest zeal to benefit this exiled leper colony,<lb/>
he contracted the fatal malady and died in his fiftieth year. Courage,<lb/>
fortitude, valor, self-renunication and nobility of soul were the<lb/>
attributes necessary for his heroic sacrifice. He gave his life that<lb/>
others might live. He laid down his life for his fellow man. His was<lb/>
the supreme test of heroism, and he met it unflinchingly. Truly we may<lb/>
say that a hero has passed by.</p>
<p>In the throngs that daily walk the busy streets in every city,<lb/>
large or small, we meet another type of heroism. It is composed of<lb/>
the vast army of plain every day people. These go about their every<lb/>
day duties, and from outward appearance all seems well. But who can<lb/>
tell the anguish of mind and anxiety of soul or the trials and suffer-<lb/>
ings that they are called upon to witness and endure? Some of us go<lb/>
through life oppressed by a burden that constantly weighs us down and<lb/>
which, at times, seems almost beyond our endurance. Does it not<lb/>
require courage, pluck, bravery, and often self-renunciation to meet<lb/>
these conditions and make us shoulder our burdens and carry on the<lb/>
battle of life which ends only in the grave? Would it not be unfair<lb/>
to place these brave, obscure, unknown, unhonored and unrenowned<lb/>
persons in any but the hero class? Are they not also Heroes passing by?</p>
<p>Therefore, in conclusion, whether we consider the home-coming<lb/>
2<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03114006"/>
E. H. S. FORM NO. 21<lb/>
Telephone Monument 8292<lb/>
BOARD OF EDUCATION<lb/>
THE CITY OF NEW YORK<lb/>
HARLEM EVENING HIGH SCHOOL<lb/>
FOR WOMEN<lb/>
114th Street between 7th and 8th Avenues<lb/>
LILLIAN M. ELLIOT, Principal<lb/>
NEW YORK,..................192....<lb/>
hero, joyously welcomed by the city, or the martyr hero dying far<lb/>
from home for a Cause, or the humble silent hero assuming another's<lb/>
heavy cross and bearing it uncomplainingly, we are confronted with<lb/>
the fact that in every particular instance the identical attributes<lb/>
of heroism were essential. Each in his own way is a hero. Each<lb/>
particular type is to some few, a hero. But may we say in God's<lb/>
sight, &ldquo;Heroes All&rdquo;.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
