<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03125002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Robert F. Nelson, August 25, 1927</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03125002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-08-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nelson, Robert F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kosslow, Elizabeth S.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James W.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Mrs.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-08-25">August 25, 1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03125002</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Robert F. Nelson, August 25, 1927</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean rejects Nelson's article on the grounds of inaccuracies. Kean informs him of the Walter Reed Memorial Association's work and Peabody's efforts to lobby Congress for pension increases for the survivors.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1927-08-25">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Robert F. Nelson, August 25, 1927</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03125002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1927-08-25">25 August, 1927.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. R. F. Nelson,<lb/>
Director of Publicity,<lb/>
Virginia State Chamber of Commerce,<lb/>
Grace-American Building,<lb/>
Richmond, Virginia.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Nelson:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wish to thank you for your letter of July 20th containing<lb/>
the story of Walter Reed by Miss Kosslow and the picture of the little<lb/>
house where Dr. Walter Reed was born. These should have been acknowledged<lb/>
sooner but I was away on my vacation when they arrived. Walter Reed<lb/>
did his work in Havana while attached to the Headquarters of General<lb/>
Fitzhugh Lee at Quemados de Marianao and as I was General Lee's Chief<lb/>
Surgeon at that time, I was familiar with his work as it was being done<lb/>
and intensely interested in it. We were besides warm personal friends.<lb/>
For these reasons I have been enormously interested in everything which<lb/>
relates to Reed and his work. I fear, however, that I cannot publish<lb/>
in The Military Surgeon Miss Kosslow's story because it has too many<lb/>
inaccuracies to appear in a scientific journal. I will mention two or<lb/>
three:</p>
<p>On page 3 the paragraph &ldquo;What Insect? He saw a peculiar<lb/>
mosquito biting a yellow fever patient&rdquo;. This is not at all the way<lb/>
the thing occurred. Miss Kosslow evidently read the official reports<lb/>
and so should have known that this was the place to mention Dr. Carlos<lb/>
Finlay who for twenty years had been publishing his theory of the mosqui-<lb/>
toes conveying yellow fever and had identified the particular mosquito<lb/>
and pointed it out to Reed as the guilty insect. Our Cuban friends<lb/>
resent bitterly the ignoring of Finlay in this story.</p>
<p>Further down on the same page Reed, were he alive, would cer-<lb/>
tainly vehemently object to the mixing up of his classical and perfectly<lb/>
controlled experiments with those of Gorgas and Guiteras which were not<lb/>
controlled and were made with another object in view. The latter were<lb/>
brought to a sudden termination by three fatalities in succession. Reed,<lb/>
on the contrary, lost none of his experimental cases, the one death being<lb/>
that of the gifted Lazear who was the experimenter and whose death could<lb/>
be regarded as a melancholy accident. I also think there is much doubt<lb/>
about any connection between Reed's experiments and the fact that Dr.<lb/>
Carroll afterwards developed a myo carditis and many years afterwards<lb/>
Kissinger became paralized. The last four lines of the article should<lb/>
also be omitted. I do not think that Reed would lay claim to any of the<lb/>
accomplishments made in them.</p>
<p>II</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03125003"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>I am returning you the picture as you have requested in<lb/>
your letter, and I would be glad if you would put me on your mailing<lb/>
list for any literature which you put out in connection with the Reed<lb/>
Memorial. You may be interested to know that there is in existence<lb/>
another Reed Memorial Association, organized just after his death and<lb/>
of which I happen to be now the President. We raised $25,000 towards<lb/>
a monument to be erected to him in Washington and have the money in-<lb/>
vested but have, in accordance with the wishes of many of the donors,<lb/>
given the interest to Mrs. Walter Reed during her life time in order<lb/>
to eke out the entirely inadequate pension which is given her by the<lb/>
United States government. A movement is now on foot, headed by Prof.<lb/>
James E. Peabody, to ask Congress to increase the pensions of Mrs. Reed,<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear, Mrs. Carroll and Kissinger. I hope your association<lb/>
will urge our Virginia representatives in the Senate and House to sup-<lb/>
port this bill.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>J. R. KEAN<lb/>
Colonel, U.S.Army, Retired<lb/>
Editor</signed>.
JRK/W<lb/>
1 incl.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
