<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03125004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Biography of Walter Reed, by Elizabeth S. Kosslow, [19--]</title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03125004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kosslow, Elizabeth S.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Porter Jones, Clarence</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="place">Belroi, Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Portsmouth (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03125004</idno>
<title>Biography of Walter Reed, by Elizabeth S. Kosslow, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kosslow writes a succinct but vivid account of Walter Reed's life, dealing with his work on typhoid and yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Biography of Walter Reed, by Elizabeth S. Kosslow, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03125004"/>
<opener>
From R. F. Nelson, Director of Publicity, Virginia State Chamber<lb/>
of Commerce, Richmond, Va.<lb/>
BY ELIZABETH S. KOSSLOW....<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Gloucester, Va., July 00--Despairing at ever inspiring the<lb/>
citizens of Gloucester County, Virginia with the necessary con-<lb/>
fidence in his medical skill because he could not raise a decent<lb/>
crop of whiskers, the badge of his profession, Dr. Walter Reed,<lb/>
17, slipped away from his picturesque birthplace, Belroi, and<lb/>
became an international hero.</p>
<p>The little weather-beaten hut, long hidden by weeds,<lb/>
today is on the way to restoration, according to the Virginia<lb/>
State Chamber of Commerce, and within six weeks the world will<lb/>
find an easy path to the tiny home of the man who earned the<lb/>
title of &ldquo;The Father of Modern Public Health&rdquo;, made the world<lb/>
free of the scourge of Yellow Fever and taught it how to combat<lb/>
typhoid successfully. He earned his title by playing the leading<lb/>
role in lengthening the span of life from thirty-eight years in<lb/>
1890 to fifty-eight in 1926, a gift of twenty years to every man!</p>
<p>Restoring Belroi was the idea of Dr. Clarence Porter-<lb/>
Jones, a local specialist whose zeal in interesting medical<lb/>
societies in the cause quickly brought material results, and the<lb/>
Walter Reed Medical Society of Virginia was empowered to effect<lb/>
the restoration. Years of vacancy and inattention had brought the<lb/>
historic house to its ebb, and immediate restoration was impera-<lb/>
tive.</p>
<p>This is only part of the big national program to per-<lb/>
petuate the memory of Reed; the medical <unclear>word</unclear> is now at work creat-<lb/>
ing a $1,000,000 fund for the establishment at the University of<lb/>
Virginia medical school of a research chair, where the experiments<lb/>
and work of the famous Virginian can be carried still farther.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03125005"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Reed's eventful life captivates the imagination of every<lb/>
member of his profession. Born in the humblest of homes in 1865,<lb/>
the son of a Methodist Circuit Rider, he struggled bitterly to<lb/>
prepare himself for the University of Virginia, was graduated<lb/>
a doctor of medicine at the age of 17 and entered Bellevue<lb/>
Medical College, New York. He left there to become an assistant<lb/>
surgeon and first lieutenant in the United States Army in 1875,<lb/>
serving at obscure posts in Arizona, Nebraska, and Dakota, where<lb/>
he distinguished himself for his devotion to the poorest dwellers<lb/>
about him.</p>
<p>Here Reed began showing the sterner qualities which made<lb/>
him famous by such tasks as riding four days through a blizzard<lb/>
to set the broken leg of a child living in a dugout, spending<lb/>
sleepless nights to save some choking child from diptheria.</p>
<p>Assigned to Baltimore, the young doctor quickly began spending<lb/>
his spare time in the great laboratories of Johns Hopkins Univer-<lb/>
sity, where he made his most important investigations, working<lb/>
untiringly and blazing the trail for modern public health. He so<lb/>
well succeeded that he was ordered to Washington and given the<lb/>
chair of bacteriology in the new Medical School, where he attracted<lb/>
world attention.</p>
<p>During the Spanish War his study of typhoid fever established<lb/>
the fact that to become infected it is necessary to swallow the<lb/>
live germs through food or drink, and that the house fly is the<lb/>
most potent carrier. One of the strangest things in history was<lb/>
the fact that this report was not published until several years<lb/>
went by. This caused a loss to the British Army alone of thousands<lb/>
of lives during the Boer War.</p>
<p>X</p>
<p>X</p>
<p>Dr. Reed's life came swiftly to its dramatic climax in 1900<lb/>
when he was sent to Cuba to Study Yellow Fever. He had as his<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03125006"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
assistant Dr. James W. Carroll, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear and A.<lb/>
Adrimonte, the latter a Cuban, immune to the disease. Reed first<lb/>
noticed that strict sanitation had nothing to do with the number<lb/>
of cases of Yellow Fever occuring at the various posts, suggest-<lb/>
ing to him that an insect was the carrier.</p>
<p>What insect? <add>no mention of the Finlay theory-</add> He saw a peculiar mosquito biting a Yellow<lb/>
Fever patient; a study of the mosquito later proved that after<lb/>
biting the patient, a period of twelve days elapsed before the in-<lb/>
sect became infectious; its ability to transmit the disease, how-<lb/>
ever, lasted through life.</p>
<p>The work then reached a dramatic point. On August 27, Dr.<lb/>
Carroll allowed one infected mosquito to bite him. Four days<lb/>
later he became ill with the disease and barely escaped death. It<lb/>
left him with a heart lesion which caused his death seven years<lb/>
later. Dr. Lazear, failing to become infected when bitten by the<lb/>
same mosquito, exposed himself again, became ill and died, the<lb/>
first martyr.</p>
<p>Feb 7 1901 - 12 cases<lb/>
and by Oct 23 1901 there had been <unclear>14</unclear> successful infections with mosquitoes<lb/>
without death &amp; <del>Later</del> 8 <unclear></unclear> blood<lb/>
infections without a death-</p>
<p>Tests were resumed in December, when two of Dr. Reed's<lb/>
colleagues, Dr. W. C. Gorgas and John Guiteras made similar ex-<lb/>
periments. Of twenty-five volunteers accepted for their excellent<lb/>
health, all contracted the disease, and due to efficient care,<lb/>
only four died; a doctor, a nurse, Miss Clara L. Masss and two<lb/>
Spaniards. Another doctor was left with a fatal heart lesion and<lb/>
one soldier left a helpless paralytic.</p>
<p>Guiteras 8 Cases &amp; 3 deaths-</p>
<p>As further proof that the disease is transmitted solely by<lb/>
the mosquito, Dr. R. P. Cook, of Winchester, Virginia and six<lb/>
private soldiers remained for twenty days in a screened enclosure<lb/>
where Yellow Fever patients had been kept. None became infected.<lb/>
Three of them were later innoculated and quickly contracted the<lb/>
disease.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03125007"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>Thus the last link in the chain was forged. Breeding places<lb/>
of the mosquito were destroyed, and Cuba was rid of the Yellow<lb/>
Fever plague that had existed in Havana for 150 years. It had<lb/>
invaded the United States 90 times, causing a loss of thousands<lb/>
of lives and millions of dollars. The more severe ravaged in<lb/>
New Orleans, Charleston, Galveston, Portsmouth, Baltimore,<lb/>
Philadelphia, New York and Memphis became history. It was an<lb/>
enemy that in Portsmouth in 1855 took every third person.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed died in Washington, November 23, 1902 of appendicitis.<lb/>
He lived to see his work accepted and plans made for important<lb/>
work in this and various other allied lines. By his labors the<lb/>
tropics were made safe, the Panama Canal made possible and the<lb/>
canal zone, recognized as the most unhealthy place on earth, made<lb/>
a health resort, with a death rate lower than Boston.</p>
<p>No</p>
<p>He laid the basis for such modern safeguards as the screen-<lb/>
ing of houses, the protection of foodstuffs, the refrigeration of<lb/>
meats, prompt chilling of milk and hundreds of other everyday<lb/>
processes that save millions of lives annually all over the world.</p>
<p>-------V S C C--------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
