<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03143002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, Chronology of the Yellow Fever Work in Cuba, 1899 and 1900 and personal experiences, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 1, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03143002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-06-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Clendennin, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Harper, Mr.</name>
<name type="person">Ludlow, William</name>
<name type="person">Davis, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Major</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Havard, H. O.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Principe (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Santiago (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cabanas (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-06-01">June 1, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03143002</idno>
<title>Report: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, Chronology of the Yellow Fever Work in Cuba, 1899 and 1900 and personal experiences, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 1, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This chronology includes Kean's personal experiences and an autographed entry noting Reed's death, in 1902.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-06-01">
<head>Report: Walter Reed and Yellow Fever, Chronology of the Yellow Fever Work in Cuba, 1899 and 1900 and personal experiences, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 1, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03143002"/>
<p><date value="1929-06-01">June 1<hi rend="superscript">??</hi> 1929-</date>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head>WALTER REED &amp; YELLOW FEVER............<lb/>
CHRONOLOGY OF THE YELLOW FEVER WORK IN CUBA, 1899 and 1900<lb/>
and personal experiences. (Gen Kean)</head>
<item>I arrived in Havana from Savannah .........................................Dec. 29, 1898</item>
<item>Saw my first case of yellow fever, an autopsy of a Private, Bat'n Engineers.... Jan. 24/99</item>
<item>Called on O'Reilly and Gorgas in Havana ....................................... Jan. 25/99</item>
<item>Became Chief Surgeon, 7th Army Corps........................................... Feb. 11/99</item>
<item>Saw case of yellow fever in 4th Ill. Inf.......................................Mar. 2/99</item>
<item>Confirmed as Lieut. Col. Vols......... .........................................Mar. 2/99</item>
<item>Walter Reed in Cuba - I met him............. ...................................May 4/99</item>
<item>Typhoid outbreak in Puerto Principe</item>
<item>Yellow fever epidemic in Santiago.......................................June &amp; July, 1899</item>
<item>Death of Major Paul Clendennin, M.C. from yellow fever.......................July 4, 1899</item>
<item>Case of yellow fever in 7th Cavalry, Camp Columbia...........................July 17 "</item>
<item>Two cases at Cabanas.........................................................Aug. 14 "</item>
<item>Fatal Case at Quemados next to Slocum's house in <unclear>Calzada</unclear>.....................Aug. 17 "</item>
<item>Mr. Harper gets yellow fever.................................................Aug. 28 "</item>
<item>Gen. Ludlow applied for me to replace Davis, Feb. 2; Gen. Ludlow left Havana Feb. 3 1900</item>
<item>Gorgas appointed Acting Chief Sanitary Officer of the City of Havana........Feb. 10, 1900</item>
<item>Davis relieved this date.................................................... " " "</item>
<item>Reed arrived in Havana to look into Electrozone Plant.......................Mar. 10 "<lb/>
At reception of General Ludlow on January 1st, he told me he has<lb/>
asked General Wood for me in presence of Gen. Lee to be Sanitary<lb/>
officer, but General Lee has refused to give me up.</item>
<item>Gorgas ordered to Santiago.................................................April 1 "</item>
<item><unclear>His</unclear> Order changed so as to report to Gen. Lee..................................May 1 "</item>
<item>Changed by cable and became Chief Sanitary Officer of Havana...May 1 "</item>
<item>Gorgas relieved as Chief Surgeon Dept. of Havana, to which he was<lb/>
appointed Jan. 13, 1899, and appointed Chief Sanitary Officer..............May 1 "</item>
<item>Yellow fever in Marianao..................................................May 19 "</item>
<item>Two other cases - 26 in a month; General Lee orders me not to see cases.</item>
<item>I am taken with yellow fever..............................................June 21 "</item>
<item>after seeing Major Edmunds about June 16th He lived at 27 Gen Lee St</item>
<item>Reed arrived in Cuba, and came to see me same day.........................June 25 "</item>
<item>Reed went to see cases at Pinar del Rio...................................July 31 "</item>
<item>Reed left Cuba for U.S. to finish report Typhoid Committee between Aug. 3 &amp; Aug. 11 "</item>
<item>First experiments by Board with mosquitoes - Dr. A.S. Pinto and others... Aug. 11 "</item>
<item>I returned to Havana from U.S............................................Aug. 13 "</item>
<item>Carroll taken sick <del><unclear></unclear></del>..........(.Bitten. Aug..27).....................Aug. 31 "</item>
<item>Pvt. Wm. H. Dean, Troop B, 7th Cav. (X.Y.) bitten.......................Aug. 31 "</item>
<item>" " " " " " " " " taken sick ................. Sept. 5 "</item>
<item>Lazear taken sick....................................................... Sept. 18 "</item>
<item>Lazear died................... ......................................... Sept. 25 "</item>
<item>Reed returns to Cuba -</item>
<item>Reed and I go to see General Wood.......................................Oct. 12 "</item>
<item>Reed leaves for the United States.......................................Oct. 13</item>
<item>I issue circular as to mosquito work. <unclear>for Doctor</unclear> Havana <unclear>&amp;</unclear> Pinar del Rio. ...Oct. 15</item>
<item>Reed returns from United States.........................................Oct. 28</item>
<item>Havard goes to U.S., and I became C.S...................................Nov. 19</item>
<item>Camp Lazear completed..................................................Nov. 20</item>
<item>Experiments began at Camp Lazear........................................Nov. 20</item>
<item>Experiments with fomites begin..........................................Nov. 30<lb/>
until Jan. 10, 1901 - Dr. R. P. Cooke and others</item>
<item>Kissinger bitten by infected mosquito Nov. 20, Nov. 23 and............. Dec. 5</item>
<item>Kissinger taken sick................................................... Dec. 9</item>
<item>Yellow Fever Board confirms cases...................................... Dec. 16</item>
<item>Gen. Order No. 6, Dept. Cuba dated..................................... Dec. 21</item>
<item>Dinner to Dr. Carlos Finlay to celebrate the demonstration <unclear>of</unclear> Reed of<lb/>
his theory............................................................. Dec. 22</item>
<item>General Wood, Finlay, Reed, Gorgas and about 60 Cuban physicians<lb/>
there. I sat on Dr. Finlay's right.<lb/>
* Oct. 4, 1900 - Reed returned. from United States</item>
<item>Havard returns to Cuba.................................................Jan. 8, 1901</item>
<item>I left Havana for Washington for examination for promotion as Major....Jan. 30 "</item>
<item>I talked to Gorgas just before leaving and urged him to join the rest<lb/>
of us in accepting Reed's demonstration before the Pan American Med. Congress<lb/>
met in Feb. He said that he believed that Reed had been able to carry it<lb/>
by the bites of mosquitoes, but he did not believe that it was the only<lb/>
way, or even <hi>the most usual</hi> way.</item>
<item><unclear>L. Wood took copy</unclear></item>
<pb n="2" id="f03143003"/>
<item>-2-</item>
<item>1901</item>
<item>Pan American Medical Congress...............................................Feb. 4 - 7</item>
<item>Reed leaves Cuba............................................................Feb. 9</item>
<item>I returned to Havana........................................... about Feb. 20</item>
<item>Gorgas begins mosquito work...............................................Mar. 1 - 15</item>
<item>Havard's circular No. 5, Dept. Cuba.......................................Apr 27</item>
<item>Last case of yellow fever originating in Havana........................... May 7</item>
<item><del><unclear></unclear></del>...........................<del>Aug. 15</del></item>
<item>Reed's article in Medical Record Aug. 10..................................Aug. 10</item>
<item>Carroll returns to Havana................................................Aug. 11</item>
<item>Gorgas ceases disinfection bedding and clothing...........................Aug. 15</item>
<item>Walter Reed died in Washington 2:05 a. m. Sunday - . Nov 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1902<lb/>
see my diary Vol V</item>
<item>FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
