<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03148001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Marie C. Oemler to Emilie Lawrence Reed, March 12, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Oemler, Marie C.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03148001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-03-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-03-12">March 12, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03148001</idno>
<title>Letter from Marie C. Oemler to Emilie Lawrence Reed, March 12, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Oemler thanks Emilie Lawrence Reed for the works of Walter Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1928-03-12">
<head>Letter from Marie C. Oemler to Emilie Lawrence Reed, March 12, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03148001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
830 Anderson Street East<lb/>
Savannah, Ga, <date value="1928-03-12">March 12, 1928</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Mrs.Reed:</salute>
</opener>
<p>How truly kind and generous of you it was to write me such a<lb/>
letter - that my portrait of a man could remind you of Walter Reed! You<lb/>
can't imagine how it made me feel - at once proud and humble, for Walter<lb/>
Reed has always seemed to me not only a very great American, but a world<lb/>
hero, one of those sublime and unselfish souls who are laying the foundation<lb/>
for the great religion of the future: a Christ-soul. I am sure my man<lb/>
would have done what yours did, had his scientific bent led him to it. I know<lb/>
a doctor who, without batting an eyelash, submitted himself to tryouts for<lb/>
tropical diseases, and studied himself and his own symtoms with perfect scien<lb/>
tific interest, impersonally. They are like that, aren't they? But how very<lb/>
fortunate you were, to have loved such a man! Most of us don't know them,<lb/>
and you haven't reached seventy not to have learned that most women are<lb/>
afraid of them, never understand them, are frightfully jealous of that scientif<lb/>
ic side which, thy are sure, is inimical to them and their interests as women<lb/>
I have known women who have tried, desperately, to deflect them, haven't you?<lb/>
I myself, madame, am Irish with a big dash of French, and a touch of English<lb/>
to steady it. But my mother's mother was Irish of the Irish, born in old, old<lb/>
Clonmel beside the river Suir; and she had the peculiar and beautiful gifts<lb/>
of the Gaelic Irish, that touch of other-world-ness, which makes them see in<lb/>
to the spirit side of things. The spiritual world was always very close to<lb/>
my mother's mother; and with such people the 'invisible things..are clearly<lb/>
seen, being understood by the things that are made...' For instance, when my<lb/>
mother's mother met, say, such a soul as Walter Reed, she would watch him<lb/>
with her clear, large hazel eyes; and she would be very thoughtful; and after<lb/>
he had gone about his Father's business, and someone else spoke of him, she<lb/>
might say, quietly &ldquo;<hi>That one possesses his soul.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>Now I happened to have been the best-loved of her grandchildren; and<lb/>
the closest to her. I have never been so keen-witted; but the spiritual side<lb/>
of life has ever meant more to me than the material; so you can imagine how<lb/>
I have never become rich, or a person of many possessions, and how my wor-<lb/>
ships have ever, necessarily, been laid before slowly built altars of my own<lb/>
makings. The sense of the Fatherhood of God, the brotherhood of man, has from<lb/>
my earliest years been very strong in me. I think your man exemplified this<lb/>
exquisitely; that he lost his mortal sense of life to find his immortal self,<lb/>
and that he is one of the great Servants, who goes on working, eternally, Some<lb/>
where Else. 'Greater love hath no man than this, that a man shall lay down his<lb/>
life for his friends. God has more servants than the thoughtless wish to<lb/>
believe. Be grateful that yours was one of the great ones.</p>
<p>I could envy you; but I am too grateful for you both. It gave me<lb/>
a real pleasure to hear from you; it gives me as true a pleasure to pay this<lb/>
slight tribute of respect to a great soul, who has, since I first learned of<lb/>
him, remained one of my heroes. You paid the price; butv it was worth it. Most<lb/>
of us pay - and it wasn't. If ever I happen to come near you, I will come to<lb/>
see you, out of pure respect. If I cannot do that, take a spiritual wireless<lb/>
from me. Once, madame, <hi>I</hi> visited Arcadia.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Faithfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Marie Conway Oemler</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
