<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t03152001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">House of Representatives Bill No. 13060, 70th Congress, 1st session, April 14, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03152001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-04-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Hamann, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, N. May</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>14 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-04-14">April 14, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03152001</idno>
<title>House of Representatives Bill No. 13060, 70th Congress, 1st session, April 14, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Congressional Bill and Report #1429 recognizes the public service of Reed and the volunteers associated with the yellow fever experiments. Biographical information is supplied in Report #1429 regarding each of the members and volunteers of the Yellow Fever Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1928-04-14">
<head>House of Representatives Bill No. 13060, 70th Congress, 1st session, April 14, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03152001"/>
<p>70TH CONGRESS<lb/>
1ST SESSION</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Private Calendar No. 557<lb/>
H. R. 13060<lb/>
[Report No. 1429]</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</p>
<p>APRIL 14, 1928</p>
<p>Mr. WAINWRIGHT introduced the following bill; which was referred to the<lb/>
Committee on Military Affairs and ordered to be printed</p>
<p>APRIL 30, 1928</p>
<p>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House,<lb/>
and ordered to be printed</p>
<p>[Insert the part printed in italic]</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>A BILL</p>
<p>To recognize the high public service rendered by Major Walter<lb/>
Reed and those associated with him in the discovery of<lb/>
the cause and means of transmission of yellow fever.</p>
<p>1 <hi rend="italic">Be it enacted by the Senate and House of Representa-</hi><lb/>
2 <hi rend="italic">tives of the United States of America in Congress assembled</hi>,<lb/>
3 That in special recognition of the high public service rendered<lb/>
4 and disabilities contracted in the interest of humanity and<lb/>
5 science as voluntary subjects for the experimentations during<lb/>
6 the yellow-fever investigations in Cuba, the Secretary of<lb/>
7 War be, and he is hereby, authorized and directed to publish<lb/>
8 annually in the Army Register a roll of honor on which<lb/>
9 shall be carried the following names: Walter Reed, James<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03152002"/>
2<lb/>
1 Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear, Aristides Agramonte, John H.<lb/>
2 Andrus, John R. Bullard, A. W. Covington, William H.<lb/>
3 Deans, Wallace Forbes, Levi E. Folk, P. Hamann, James<lb/>
4 F. Hanberry, Warren G. Jernegan, John R. Kissinger,<lb/>
5 John J. Moran, William Olson, Charles G. Sonntag, Clyde<lb/>
6 L. West, R. P. Cooke, Thomas H. England, James Hilde-<lb/>
7 brand, and Edward Weatherwalks, and to define in appropri-<lb/>
8 ate language the part which each of these persons played in<lb/>
9 the experimentations during the yellow-fever investigations<lb/>
10 in Cuba; and there is hereby authorized to be appropriated,<lb/>
11 out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropri-<lb/>
12 ated, such amounts annually as may be necessary in order<lb/>
13 to pay to the following-named persons during the remainder<lb/>
14 of their natural lives the sum of $250 per month, and such<lb/>
15 amount shall be in lieu of any and all pensions authorized<lb/>
16 by law for the following-named persons:</p>
<p>17 Mrs. Walter Reed; Mrs. James Carroll; Mrs. Jesse W.<lb/>
18 Lazear; <hi rend="italic">Mrs. William Crawford Gorgas</hi>; Doctor Aristides<lb/>
19 Agramonte; Private John H. Andrus, Hospital Corps; Mr.<lb/>
20 John R. Bullard; Private A. W. Covington, Twenty-third<lb/>
21 Battery Coast Artillery Corps; Private William H. Deans,<lb/>
22 Troop B, Seventh Cavalry; Private Wallace Forbes,<lb/>
23 Hospital Corps; Private Levi E. Folk, Hospital Corps;<lb/>
24 Private P. Hamann, Twenty-third Battery, Coast Artillery<lb/>
25 Corps; Private James F. Hanberry, Hospital Corps; Mrs.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03152003"/>
3<lb/>
1 Warren G. Jernegan; Private John R. Kissinger; Mr. John<lb/>
2 J. Moran; Private William Olson, Hospital Corps; Private<lb/>
3 Charles G. Sonntag, Hospital Corps; Private Clyde L. West,<lb/>
4 Hospital Corps; Doctor R. P. Cooke; Private Thomas H.<lb/>
5 England, Hospital Corps; Private James Hildebrand, Hos-<lb/>
6 pital Corps; and Private Edward Weatherwalks, Hospital<lb/>
7 Corps.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03152004"/>
<p>70TH CONGRESS }<lb/>
1ST SESSION }</p>
<p>PRIVATE CALENDAR NO. 557<lb/>
H. R. 13060<lb/>
[Report No. 1429]</p>
<p>======================================</p>
<p>A BILL</p>
<p>To recognize the high public service rendered<lb/>
by Major Walter Reed and those associated<lb/>
with him in the discovery of the cause and<lb/>
means of transmission of yellow fever.</p>
<p>======================================</p>
<p>By Mr. WAINWRIGHT</p>
<p>======================================</p>
<p>APRIL 14, 1928</p>
<p>Referred to the Committee on Military Affairs and<lb/>
ordered to be printed</p>
<p>APRIL 30, 1928</p>
<p>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Com-<lb/>
mittee of the Whole House, and ordered to be<lb/>
printed</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03152005"/>
<p>70TH CONGRESS }<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">1st Session</hi> }</p>
<p>HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</p>
<p>{ REPORT<lb/>
{ No. 1429</p>
<p>======================================</p>
<p>TO RECOGNIZE THE HIGH PUBLIC SERVICE RENDERED BY MAJ.<lb/>
WALTER REED AND THOSE ASSOCIATED WITH HIM IN THE DIS-<lb/>
COVERY OF THE CAUSE AND MEANS OF TRANSMISSION OF<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>APRIL 30, 1928.--Committed to the Committee of the Whole House and ordered<lb/>
to be printed</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>Mr. FROTHINGHAM, from the Committee on Military Affairs, sub-<lb/>
mitted the following</p>
<p>REPORT</p>
<p>[To accompany H. R. 13060]</p>
<p>The Committee on Military Affairs, to whom was referred the bill<lb/>
(H. R. 13060) to recognize the high public service rendered by Maj.<lb/>
Walter Reed and those associated with him in the discovery of the<lb/>
cause and means of transmission of yellow fever, introduced by Mr.<lb/>
Wainwright, having considered the same, report thereon with the<lb/>
recommendation that it do pass, with the following amendment:</p>
<p>Page 2, line 18, after the word &ldquo;Lazear&rdquo; insert the words &ldquo;Mrs.<lb/>
William Crawford Gorgas&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Hearings were held on a similar bill (H. R. 11686) on April 11,<lb/>
1928, and the following preliminary statement was made by the<lb/>
Surgeon General of the Army, Maj. Gen. M. W. Ireland:</p>
<p>Mr. Chairman and gentlemen, I am very glad to appear before the committee<lb/>
in support of this bill, because my distinguished predecessor, Gen. Robert M.<lb/>
O'Reilly, the greatest surgeon general that the Army ever had, made a similar<lb/>
recommendation as far back as 1905. He prepared a memorandum which was<lb/>
sent to the President, and which was forwarded to the Congress with this<lb/>
comment:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The inclosed papers are transmitted to the Congress in the hope that it will<lb/>
take suitable action in this matter. Major Reed's part in the experiments<lb/>
which resulted in teaching us how to cope with yellow fever was such as to<lb/>
render mankind his debtor, and this Government should in some proper fashion<lb/>
bear witness to this fact.</p>
<p>&ldquo;THEODORE ROOSEVELT.<lb/>
'DECEMBER 5, 1906.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Walter Reed was the head of a board that went to Cuba in 1900 to discover,<lb/>
if possible, the cause of yellow fever. By October, 1900, he had proven to his<lb/>
own satisfaction that it was caused by the mosquito. This was proven to the<lb/>
world very shortly afterwards, and in proving that yellow fever was transmitted<lb/>
by a certain species of mosquito he made the greatest progress in preventive<lb/>
medicine that had been made in the world up to that time; and I think it is a<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03152006"/>
2<lb/>
RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.<lb/>
very small thing for this Government to give a reward for those who were con-<lb/>
nected with these experiments * * *.</p>
<p>The following complete statement of the circumstances attending<lb/>
these investigations was prepared by Col. J. R. Kean, Medical Depart-<lb/>
ment, United States Army, retired:</p>
<p>ARMY MEDICAL MUSEUM,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Washington, D. C., April 18, 1928</hi>.</p>
<p>Hon. JOHN M. MORIN,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Chairman Committee on Military Affairs,<lb/>
House of Representatives, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
<p>SIR: In compliance with the desires of your committee as expressed at the<lb/>
hearing on April 11, 1928, on the bill H. R. 11686 for the reward of those taking<lb/>
part in the work of the yellow fever board, I submit the following statement of<lb/>
my connection with that work, and the names and status of those taking part in<lb/>
it as requested of me by Hon. J. Mayhew Wainwright, who introduced the bill.</p>
<p>The yellow fever board or commission was organized and sent to Cuba by the<lb/>
War Department upon the recommendation of Surgeon General Sternberg, in<lb/>
June, 1900, to study the cause and prevention of yellow fever, a matter whose<lb/>
vast importance, I believe, the committee well understands.</p>
<p>The members of the board were Maj. Walter Reed, surgeon United States<lb/>
Army, Acting Assistant Surgeons James Carroll, Aristides Agramonte and<lb/>
Jesse W. Lazear, United States Army. A statement with regard to each of them<lb/>
is made below.</p>
<p>My connection with the work of this board, which was of no great importance<lb/>
except that it permitted me to be familiar with all the details connected with<lb/>
their work and to furnish information which may be of value to your committee,<lb/>
arose from the following circumstances:</p>
<p>I had gone to Cuba in 1898 with the Seventh Corps, of which General Fitzhugh<lb/>
Lee was the commanding general, and of which I became the chief surgeon.<lb/>
After the discharge of the volunteers in May, 1899, General Lee was placed in<lb/>
charge of the military department of western Cuba with headquarters at<lb/>
Marianao. I was his chief surgeon with sanitary supervision of the area under<lb/>
his command. The city of Habana was, however, excepted from his command,<lb/>
being a separate military department under General Ludlow whose chief sanitary<lb/>
officer was Maj. (afterwards major general) W. C. Gorgas. Major Reed and Doctor<lb/>
Carroll arrived in Cuba June 25, 1900; the other two members of the commission,<lb/>
Doctor Agramonte and Doctor Lazear, being already on duty in Cuba. In order<lb/>
to secure quarters and office room without expense and a healthy environment<lb/>
they received General Lee's permission to locate in certain buildings at the hos-<lb/>
pital at Columbia Barracks, less than a mile from General Lee's headquarters.<lb/>
This location permitted me, in my position, to be of service to the commission<lb/>
in various ways, and I saw much of Major Reed, as we were old friends. It<lb/>
appears to me unnecessary to recount the dramatic and interesting story of the<lb/>
work of the board, as this is well covered in the first four chapters of Senate<lb/>
Document 822, Sixty-first Congress, third session, entitled, &ldquo;Yellow Fever, a<lb/>
Compilation of Various Publications,&rdquo; which the committee has resolved to<lb/>
have reprinted. It will be sufficient to say that it may be divided into several<lb/>
phases.</p>
<p>The first was the demonstration that there was no foundation in the claim of<lb/>
Sanarelli that the <hi rend="italic">Bacillus icteroides</hi> isolated by him was the cause of yellow fever.<lb/>
This occupied the month of July. Then for sound epidemiological reasons the<lb/>
board determined to investigate the theory of Dr. Carlos Finlay that yellow<lb/>
fever was transmitted by a certain variety of mosquito. This second phase,<lb/>
including the successful inoculations of Carroll and Pvt. Wm. H. Dean and the<lb/>
tragic death of Doctor Lazear, includes the period to October 12 when Reed,<lb/>
accompanied by me, had his interview with General Wood, which, by securing<lb/>
General Wood's approval of experiments on human beings, and the grant of<lb/>
money for necessary expenses, changed the whole character of the investigation.</p>
<p>Reed then went to the United States for a brief visit to consult with the Surgeon<lb/>
General and read his paper, &ldquo;The etiology of yellow fever, a preliminary note,&rdquo;<lb/>
at the annual meeting of the American Public Health Association, October 22<lb/>
to 26. Upon his return to Cuba, October 28, begins the third phase of his work,<lb/>
occupied in the construction of an experimental station, Camp Lazear, and the<lb/>
experiments thereat upon American Volunteers and Spanish immigrants, which<lb/>
demonstrated the method of the transmission of yellow fever and made clear the<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03152007"/>
RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.<lb/>
3<lb/>
way of its prevention. This phase may be considered to have been completed<lb/>
on February 4, 1901, when Reed read before the Pan American Medical Associa-<lb/>
tion in Habana the report of the board, &ldquo;The etiology of yellow fever, an addi-<lb/>
tional note,&rdquo; giving the results of their experiments and their conclusions.</p>
<p>After the adjournment of this meeting Reed and Carroll returned to Wash-<lb/>
ington, and Gorgas gave a practical application of Reed's conclusions by warfare<lb/>
upon mosquitoes in the city of Habana in accordance with the tenth conclusion<lb/>
of the board which was:</p>
<p>&ldquo;10. The spread of yellow fever can be most effectually controlled by measures<lb/>
directed to the destruction of mosquitoes and the protection of the sick against<lb/>
the bites of these insects.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll returned to Cuba during the fall of 1901 to make certain other<lb/>
experiments connected with the etiology of yellow fever by the injection of<lb/>
filtered blood from cases of that disease which demonstrated that the organism<lb/>
of the disease was a &ldquo;filterable virus&rdquo; which would pass through a pasteur por-<lb/>
celain filter, and was therefore ultramicroscopic in size.</p>
<p>STATEMENT WITH REGARD TO THE CLAIMS OF THE PERSONS NAMED IN THE BILL<lb/>
WITH PERTINENT DATA CONCERNING THEM, FIRST CATEGORY</p>
<p>1. <hi rend="italic">Mrs. Walter Reed</hi> was Emelie Lawrence, of North Carolina. Her family<lb/>
came originally from Massachusetts, and was related to the distinguished bishop,<lb/>
Right Rev. William Lawrence, of Massachusetts. They were married in 1876.<lb/>
There were two children of this marriage, both of whom are living. Since the<lb/>
death of Major Reed after an operation for appendicitis in Washington, November<lb/>
23, 1902, she has not remarried, and is a resident of the city of Washington.</p>
<p>At the time of his death the Secretary of War, the Hon. Elihu Root, had pro-<lb/>
posed in his annual report to the President that Reed being the senior major in<lb/>
his grade should be promoted to the grade of colonel in the Medical Department<lb/>
and that Maj. W. C. Gorgas should be promoted to the grade of lieutenant colonel.<lb/>
This recommendation, although it had not been published, was known to the<lb/>
writer, and Major Reed was told of it by him on his deathbed. He replied,<lb/>
&ldquo;I do not care for that now.&rdquo; The special promotion to colonel was later given<lb/>
to Major Gorgas.</p>
<p>With reference to the recognition of Reed's work by the United States Govern-<lb/>
ment, Dr. Howard A. Kelly in his work &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo;<lb/>
quotes at the beginning of Chapter X on the value of Doctor Reed's work to the<lb/>
world as follows from the Bible, Book of Esther, 6:3, &ldquo;And the King said what<lb/>
honour and dignity have been done to Mordecai for this? Then said the King's<lb/>
servants who ministered unto him, There is nothing done for him.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Surgeon General proposed that Major Reed's pay as major ($291 per<lb/>
month) be continued to Mrs. Reed as a pension. A bill providing for this was<lb/>
introduced into the Senate by Senator Martin of Virginia, and was passed with<lb/>
the amount reduced to $125 per month. A similar bill was introduced into the<lb/>
House by Mr. Maynard of Virginia, and was referred to the Pension Committee,<lb/>
but never reported out by them. On the morning of March 4, 1903, by agreement<lb/>
between the Republican and Democratic leaders of the House, and the Speaker,<lb/>
Mr. Henderson, the Pension Committee was discharged from consideration of<lb/>
the bill and the Senate bill was taken up and passed. The appropriations for<lb/>
her annuity were made for some years on the War Department appropriation<lb/>
bill, but payments are now made by the Pension Bureau.</p>
<p>Regarding the value of Major Reed's services to this country and to humanity<lb/>
it is believed that the committee is well informed. I would, therefore, only<lb/>
quote a paragraph from a letter of Prof. William H. Welch, of Johns Hopkins<lb/>
University, written soon after Reed's death, to the Secretary of War, in which<lb/>
he stated:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doctor Reed's researches in yellow fever are by far the most important<lb/>
contributions to science which have ever come from an Army surgeon. In my<lb/>
judgment, they are the most valuable contributions to medicine and public<lb/>
hygiene which have ever been made in this country, with the exception of the<lb/>
discovery of anaesthesia. They have led and will lead to the saving of thou-<lb/>
sands of lives. I am in a position to know that the credit for the original ideas<lb/>
embodied in this work belongs wholly to Major Reed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Major Reed left no property except a small life insurance, and the pension<lb/>
received by Mrs. Reed is, as the committee must realize, quite inadequate for a<lb/>
comfortable and dignified existence. This inadequacy has been made worse by<lb/>
the depreciation in the purchasing power of the dollar due to the World War,<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f03152008"/>
4<lb/>
RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.<lb/>
so that her pension now is about equivalent to one of $75 at the time it was<lb/>
given. It has been helped out to some extent by payment to her of the interest<lb/>
on a fund collected by a group of Major Reed's friends for the purpose of erecting<lb/>
a monument to him. The principal of this fund will be available to assist in the<lb/>
erection of a monument to him whenever the Government sees fit to make pro-<lb/>
vision for one, provided that adequate support for Mrs. Reed has been made.</p>
<p>2. Mrs. James Carroll was the wife of Dr. James Carroll, by whom she had<lb/>
seven children. Mrs. Carroll has, so far as is known to the writer, never re-<lb/>
married. Her present address is box 2440, St. Petersburg, Fla. She has re-<lb/>
ceived since soon after the death of Major Carroll on September 16, 1907, a<lb/>
monthly pension of $125. Doctor Carroll was born in England and enlisted in<lb/>
the Army June 9, 1874. He served in the grades of private, corporal, sergeant,<lb/>
and hospital steward, first at western posts and later in New York and Washing-<lb/>
ton. He took advantage of his opportunities as a medical department soldier to<lb/>
study medicine, and being encouraged by the medical officers under whom he<lb/>
served graduated at the University of Maryland in 1891. He then, in 1893,<lb/>
became Major Reed's laboratory assistant at the Army Medical School in<lb/>
Washington, where he served until his appointment as acting assistant surgeon,<lb/>
May 21, 1898. He served as Major Reed's assistant in the investigation of the<lb/>
typhoid-fever epidemic during the Spanish War, and, doubtless on his recommenda-<lb/>
tion, was made a member of the Yellow Fever Board in 1900. He permitted<lb/>
himself to be bitten by infected mosquitoes, and was the first experimental case<lb/>
caused by the board, being taken sick August 31, 1900. In recognition of this<lb/>
experience he was commissioned a first lieutenant and assistant surgeon in the<lb/>
Medical Corps October 27, 1902. From this grade he was promoted to major by a<lb/>
special act of Congress March 9, 1907. He died in Washington, D. C., of myo-<lb/>
carditis September 16, 1907.</p>
<p>Mrs. Carroll's pension has been, of course, inadequate for her needs and those<lb/>
of her family. This inadequacy has been much increased by the fall in the<lb/>
purchasing power of the dollar since the World War.</p>
<p>3. Mrs. Jesse W. Lazear (Mabel M. Lazear) was the wife of Dr. Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear, acting assistant surgeon and third member of the yellow fever board.<lb/>
At the time of his death at Camp Columbia, Cuba, September 25, 1900, of yellow<lb/>
fever, incurred in the line of duty, they had two young children; the youngest of<lb/>
these he never saw. She has not remarried and since his death has received<lb/>
an annuity of $125 per month. It is understood that Doctor Lazear left very<lb/>
little property and she had great difficulty in supporting herself and her children.<lb/>
Her present address is 6 Oak Vale Avenue, Berkeley, Calif.</p>
<p>Jesse W. Lazear was born in Baltimore May 2, 1866. He graduated in medicine<lb/>
at Columbia University, New York City, in 1892, after which he served two years<lb/>
at Bellevue Hospital in New York. He then spent a year in Europe, a part of it<lb/>
at the Pasteur Institute in Paris. On his return home he was made bacterio-<lb/>
logist to the medical staff of Johns Hopkins Hospital, and was also assistant in<lb/>
clinical microscopy in the university. He was one of the first men in this country<lb/>
to study the development of the malarial organism in the blood of man and in the<lb/>
mosquito, and this knowledge was of the greatest value to the yellow fever board<lb/>
when they took up the study of that disease. He was a man not only of brilliant<lb/>
professional attainments, who, but for his untimely death, would have gone far<lb/>
in his profession, but of noble character and great personal charm. He and his<lb/>
family have received no reward for his great services to the country except the<lb/>
inadequate pension above mentioned, and the naming after him of a battery in<lb/>
Baltimore Harbor.</p>
<p>4. Dr. Aristides Agramonte is the only living member of the yellow fever<lb/>
commission. He was born in Cuba during the &ldquo;ten years&rdquo; war, in which his<lb/>
father, a Cuban officer, was killed in battle by the Spaniards. The Agramonte<lb/>
family came to New York when he was 10 years old, and he grew up and was<lb/>
graduated in that city. He graduated in medicine at the College of Physicians<lb/>
and Surgeons where he and Lazear were classmates. At the beginning of the<lb/>
Spanish War he joined the Army as an acting assistant surgeon, and after the<lb/>
American occupation, had charge of the Army medical laboratory in Habana.<lb/>
Upon the organization of the yellow fever commission he was detailed as a member<lb/>
of it, and contributed materially to its success. He performed most of the autopsy<lb/>
work and the experiments on animals, and after Lazear's death had charge of the<lb/>
mosquito work. He served with the Army until the establishment of the Cuban<lb/>
Republic in May, 1902. Upon the withdrawal of the American forces he remained<lb/>
in Habana and was appointed a professor in the medical school of the University<lb/>
of Habana, a position which he still occupies. During the American government<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f03152009"/>
RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.<lb/>
5<lb/>
of pacification in Cuba, 1906-1909 he was a member of the yellow fever board in<lb/>
Habana, and rendered valuable service in the campaign against yellow fever which<lb/>
had again broken out in Habana and spread over most of the island.</p>
<p>Doctor Agramonte has never received from the United States Government<lb/>
any honor, recognition, or material reward for his distinguished services to this<lb/>
country and to humanity as a member of the yellow fever commission. The<lb/>
Cuban Government has recently set us an example in generosity by voting a<lb/>
generous pension to the widow of General Leonard Wood. It would seem that<lb/>
our country should in its turn recognize its debt to Dr. Aristides Agramonte who,<lb/>
though now a Cuban, has worn our uniform and rendered us distinguished<lb/>
service.</p>
<p>THE VOLUNTEERS WHO SUFFERED FROM EXPERIMENTAL YELLOW FEVER, SECOND<lb/>
CATEGORY</p>
<p>The second category of persons to whom these United States is indebted for<lb/>
the conquest of yellow fever consists of 14 names, 12 of whom were private<lb/>
soldiers serving in Cuba. They are arranged in the bill in alphabetical order, and<lb/>
will be considered in that order, as in the bill H. R. 11686.</p>
<p>5. John A. Andrus, private, Hospital Corps, volunteered and was infected with<lb/>
yellow fever by injection of blood at Camp Lazear, January 28, 1901. He was<lb/>
discharged from the military service April 24, 1902, at Camp George H. Thomas,<lb/>
Chickamauga, Tenn.; character excellent. He was born at Fassett, Pa. His<lb/>
present address is not known. Father's address, Seth C. Andrus, Elmira, N. Y.<lb/>
He received a donation of $200, paid by the writer from Cuban funds granted by<lb/>
the military governor, General Leonard Wood, but I understand does not receive<lb/>
any pension from the United States.</p>
<p>6. Mr. John R. Bullard was a native of Massachusetts and a graduate of Har-<lb/>
vard University, where he was a distinguished athlete; he came to Cuba in 1901,<lb/>
where he purchased land and engaged in farming. In the fall of 1901 he became<lb/>
ill with malarial fever, and was brought to Camp Columbia for treatment. He<lb/>
was treated by Doctor Carroll, who interested him in the yellow-fever work, so<lb/>
that after his recovery he offered himself as a volunteer for experiment. Doctor<lb/>
Carroll infected him with yellow fever by the injection of blood, he being taken<lb/>
sick October 23, 1901. In point of time he was the last of the series of experi-<lb/>
mental cases. Mr. Bullard has not, I believe, received any reward or recognition<lb/>
from the Government of the United States or the military government of Cuba.<lb/>
His present address is Ingenio Jatibonico, Jatibonico, Oriente, Cuba.</p>
<p>7. Albert W. Covington, private, Twenty-third Company, Coast Artillery, was<lb/>
born at Laurinsburg, N. C., enlisted at Maxton, N. C. He remained in the<lb/>
service until August 9, 1926, when he was retired for long service. Address,<lb/>
Mrs. Rose Covington, R. F. D. 3, Cohocton, N. Y.</p>
<p>He was one of the group of volunteers infected by Doctor Carroll by blood<lb/>
injections in the fall of 1901. He received an injection of filtered blood serum<lb/>
from a case of yellow fever, and became sick October 19, 1901. He received a<lb/>
donation of $200 from the undersigned from the allotment of Cuban funds made<lb/>
by General Wood for these experiments. He receives from the Government his<lb/>
retired pay for long service, but no reward for his part in the yellow-fever work.</p>
<p>8. William H. Dean, private, Troop B, Seventh Cavalry, was born at Holland,<lb/>
Ohio, enlisted at Grand Rapids, Mich., and was discharged August 17, 1902.<lb/>
His present address is unknown.</p>
<p>The case of this soldier, which followed that of Doctor Carroll, was of great<lb/>
importance as it convinced Major Reed of the truth of Doctor Finlay's mosquito-<lb/>
transmission theory. He was infected on August 31, 1900, by the same mosquito<lb/>
that had caused Doctor Carroll's illness, and on the same day that the diagnosis<lb/>
of yellow fever in Doctor Carroll's case was made. His name was concealed at<lb/>
the time under the anonymous designation &ldquo;X. Y.&rdquo; because the experiment was<lb/>
made without military authorization at Columbia Barracks at a time when it<lb/>
was under rigid quarantine against the introduction of yellow fever. He has<lb/>
never received any reward from either the United States or from the Cuban<lb/>
treasury.</p>
<p>9. Wallace W. Forbes, private, Hospital Corps, was born at Galesburg, Ill.;<lb/>
enlisted at Minneapolis, Minn. He was discharged March 1, 1905, with character<lb/>
excellent. The address of his mother whose name was not given on the record<lb/>
was 1523 Irving Avenue, Minneapolis, Minn.</p>
<p>He volunteered to be infected with yellow fever by injection of blood at Camp<lb/>
Lazear, and became sick January 24, 1901. He received a donation of $200 from<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f03152010"/>
6<lb/>
RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.<lb/>
the Cuban funds allotted by General Wood for these experiments, but is not be-<lb/>
lieved to have received any pension or other recognition from the United States.</p>
<p>10. Levi E. Folk, private, Hospital Corps, was born at Kadish, S. C.; he<lb/>
enlisted at Columbia, S. C., and was retired for long service March 30, 1923.</p>
<p>Folk was one of the men who volunteered to undergo the very trying experience<lb/>
of exposure to fomites by sleeping 20 nights in the bed clothing and body clothes<lb/>
which had been used by yellow fever patients, and which was soiled with their<lb/>
excretions.</p>
<p>It was obviously necessary to establish the fact that the men who underwent<lb/>
this experiment were not immune, and Folk volunteered to be bitten by infected<lb/>
mosquitoes, and was taken ill with yellow fever January 23, 1901.</p>
<p>He received a donation of $100 for the fomites experiment and $200 for the<lb/>
yellow fever inoculation from the Cuban funds allotted by General Wood for<lb/>
these experiments. He receives from the Government his retired pay but has<lb/>
not, so far as is known, received any pension or other reward for his services as<lb/>
a volunteer in these experiments. His present address is 374 South Third<lb/>
Street, Columbus, Ohio.</p>
<p>11. Paul Hamann, private, Twenty-third Company, Coast Artillery, was<lb/>
born in Germany and enlisted at Springfield, Ill. After long service he was<lb/>
discharged August 12, 1913.</p>
<p>Hamann was one of the group of cases infected by Doctor Carroll in the fall<lb/>
of 1901 by injection of filtered blood serum from a case of yellow fever. He<lb/>
became sick October 19, 1901.</p>
<p>He received a donation of $200 from the Cuban funds allotted by General<lb/>
Wood for these experiments, and he receives from the Government a pension of<lb/>
$20 per month. Address, care of his father, August Hamann, East Moline, Ill.</p>
<p>12. James F. Hanberry, private, Hospital Corps, was born at Denmark, S. C.;<lb/>
enlisted at Camp Onward, Ga. He deserted the service April 4, 1902, while at<lb/>
Walter Reed General Hospital, Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>Hanberry, like Folk, first underwent the fomites experiment, and then volun-<lb/>
teered to be bitten by infected mosquitoes, and in consequence was taken sick<lb/>
with yellow fever at Camp Lazear, February 9, 1901. He received donations<lb/>
amounting to $300 from the Cuban funds allotted by General Wood for these<lb/>
experiments.</p>
<p>Being a deserter he has, naturally, not received any pension or reward from the<lb/>
United States Government.</p>
<p>13. Mrs. Warren G. Jernegan (N. May Jernegan) is the widow of Warren G.<lb/>
Jernegan, private, Hospital Corps, who was born at Cone, Fla. He was dis-<lb/>
charged at Columbia Barracks, November 16, 1901, but afterwards was in the<lb/>
Government employ at Panama, and, as stated by his widow, died February 5,<lb/>
1919, while still in Government employ in Charleston, S. C.</p>
<p>He, like Folk and Hanberry, after undergoing the fomites experiment, volun-<lb/>
teered to have his immunity tested by an injection of blood from a yellow-fever<lb/>
patient, and was taken sick January 8, 1901.</p>
<p>For these two experiments he received donations amounting to $300 from the<lb/>
Cuban funds allotted by General Wood for these experiments. Mrs. Jernegan<lb/>
receives a pension of $125 per month from the United States Government.</p>
<p>14. JOHN R. KISSINGER, private, Hospital Corps, was born at McClure,<lb/>
Ohio; enlisted for the Spanish War at Indianapolis, Ind. He was discharged<lb/>
November 14, 1901, at Columbia Barracks, Cuba, with character excellent.</p>
<p>Kissinger with Moran, who will be next mentioned, were the first to volunteer<lb/>
as subjects for experiment in the second phase of the work of the board. Moran<lb/>
was first bitten, but Kissinger was the first to be infected and to suffer an attack<lb/>
of yellow fever on December 8, 1900.</p>
<p>When promised a donation by Major Reed at the time he volunteered, Kis-<lb/>
singer declined it stating he wished to undergo the experiment for the benefit of<lb/>
science and humanity. After his recovery he was promoted to be acting hospital<lb/>
steward, and was presented with a gold watch by the department surgeon at a<lb/>
military ceremony. This watch was paid for from the donation to which he<lb/>
was entitled, and he afterwards accepted the balance of the donation in money.<lb/>
His health having failed he was on March 2, 1907, granted a pension of $12 per<lb/>
month. On February 11, 1911 he was granted an annuity of $100 per month.<lb/>
His present address is R. F. D. 8, Huntington, Ind.</p>
<p>15. Mr. John J. Moran was born in Ohio and served as a volunteer in the<lb/>
Spanish War in the Seventh Army Corps. After his discharge he was employed<lb/>
by the Army at the headquarters of General Fitzhugh Lee at Marianao, as a<lb/>
clerk.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f03152011"/>
<p>RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.<lb/>
7</p>
<p>Mr. Moran disclaimed before submitting to the experiments any desire for<lb/>
reward, and has never accepted any, although he was offered the $200 from the<lb/>
Cuban funds which the others received.</p>
<p>The first bites from infected mosquitoes received by him on November 26,<lb/>
and 29 were, for some reason, unsuccessful. He was infected on the third attempt<lb/>
on December 21 and came down with yellow fever on Christmas Day, 1900.</p>
<p>After leaving Cuba he completed his education by a course of study at the<lb/>
University of Virginia, and then lived for a number of years in Panama in the<lb/>
employ of the Isthmian Canal Commission. He is at present in Mexico in the<lb/>
employment of the Firestone Tire Co., through which he can be communicated<lb/>
with.</p>
<p>He has never received, nor, so far as is known, applied for any pension or<lb/>
reward from either the Cuban Government or the Government of the United<lb/>
States.</p>
<p>16. William Olsen, private, Hospital Corps, was born in Pierce County, Wis.;<lb/>
enlisted for the Spanish War at Minneapolis, Minn., and was discharged Novem-<lb/>
ber 15, 1901, with character excellent, his address being given as 7211 San Pedro<lb/>
Street, Los Angeles, Calif.</p>
<p>He was infected with yellow fever by injection of blood at Camp Lazear and<lb/>
taken sick January 11, 1901.</p>
<p>He received a donation of $200 from the Cuban funds allotted by General<lb/>
Wood for these experiments. He is now in receipt of a pension from the Govern-<lb/>
ment of $40 per month, presumably a Spanish pension.</p>
<p>17. Charles G. Sonntag, private, Hospital Corps, was born at Charleston, S. C.,<lb/>
and enlisted at Camp Onward, Ga. He was discharged December 12, 1901, at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks, with character very good.</p>
<p>He volunteered to be bitten by infected mosquitoes and was, in consequence,<lb/>
taken sick with yellow fever at Camp Lazear, February 10, 1901. He received<lb/>
a donation of $200 from the Cuban funds allotted by General Wood for these<lb/>
experiments, and is also at present in receipt of a pension of $50 per month.<lb/>
His present address is rural route No. 3, Gaston, S. C.</p>
<p>18. Clyde L. West, private, Hospital Corps, was born at Mier, Ind., and enlisted<lb/>
for the Spanish war at Toledo, Ohio. He was discharged July 10, 1902, at Fort<lb/>
Myer, Va., character, very good.</p>
<p>West volunteered to be bitten by infected mosquitoes at Camp Lazear, and<lb/>
was taken sick with yellow fever February 3, 1901. He received a donation of<lb/>
$200 from the Cuban funds allotted by General Wood for these experiments, also<lb/>
in 1927 was given a pension of $100 per month for his services as a volunteer in<lb/>
the yellow fever work; he gets also a pension of $30 per month for his Spanish<lb/>
war services.</p>
<p>VOLUNTEERS IN FOMITES EXPERIMENTS, THIRD CATEGORY</p>
<p>19. Dr. R. P. Cooke was born in Virginia in 1874. He volunteered for experi-<lb/>
ment with fomites, and underwent the experiment with the first group who slept<lb/>
in infected bedding. He had charge of all the men engaged in these experiments.<lb/>
He entered the medical service of the Army June 9, 1900, as a contract surgeon<lb/>
and was on duty in the hospital at Piner Del Rio during the yellow-fever epidemic<lb/>
at that place in July, 1900. He left the service at his own request December 2,<lb/>
1904. He received a donation of $100 from the Cuban funds allotted by General<lb/>
Wood for these experiments, but has not received any recognition or pension<lb/>
from the United States Government.</p>
<p>20. Thomas M. England, private, Hospital Corps, was born in Chillicothe,<lb/>
Ohio, and served in the Army from January 6, 1899, to January 5, 1914, in the<lb/>
grades of private, acting hospital steward, and sergeant, first class, Hospital<lb/>
Corps. He again enlisted July 28, 1915, and served as sergeant, first class, and<lb/>
hospital sergeant and master hospital sergeant to February 15, 1918. He was<lb/>
then appointed first lieutenant Sanitary Corps in the National Army and served<lb/>
until the end of the World War. He was commissioned captain Medical Admin-<lb/>
istrative Corps in the regular service July 1, 1920, and is now serving in that<lb/>
grade.</p>
<p>He volunteered and underwent the fomites experiment, sleeping 20 nights in<lb/>
infected bedding, for which experiment he received a donation of $100 from the<lb/>
Cuban funds allotted by General Wood for these experiments. He has not<lb/>
received any pension or recognition from the United States Government. His<lb/>
present address is care of the Surgeon General, War Department, Washington,<lb/>
D. C.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f03152012"/>
<p>8<lb/>
RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.</p>
<p>21. James Hildebrand, private, Hospital Corps, was born at Decatur, Ga.,<lb/>
and enlisted at Savannah, Ga., for service in Cuba. He was discharged August<lb/>
17, 1914, at Walter Reed General Hospital, Washington, D. C., with character<lb/>
excellent.</p>
<p>Private Hildebrand underwent the fomites experiment, and then volunteered<lb/>
to be bitten with infected mosquitoes. He was, however, rejected by Major<lb/>
Reed for this experiment on account of his age, being over 40 years old. It is<lb/>
well known that yellow fever is much more fatal at that age and later than with<lb/>
young men.</p>
<p>He received a donation of $100 from Cuban funds allotted by General Wood<lb/>
for these experiments. He is now in receipt of a pension from the United States<lb/>
of $50 per month, which it is understood, is given him on account of long service<lb/>
and ill health, and not for his participation in these experiments.</p>
<p>His present address is 412 Berean Street, Atlanta, Ga.</p>
<p>22. Edward Weatherwalks, private, Hospital Corps, was born at Pompton,<lb/>
N. J., and enlisted for service in Cuba at Savannah, Ga., and was discharged<lb/>
February 12, 1901, at Columbia Barracks with character good.</p>
<p>He underwent the fomites experiment and was bitten once by mosquitoes<lb/>
without becoming infected. He afterwards declined further experiments. He<lb/>
received a donation of $100 from the Cuban funds allotted by General Wood for<lb/>
these experiments.</p>
<p>He died October 21, 1916, at Haskell, N. J.; his widow, Mrs. Lucy Weather-<lb/>
walks, lives at Lenox Avenue, Pompton Lakes, N. J., and receives a pension of<lb/>
$30 per month, presumably on account of her husband's service in the Spanish<lb/>
War.</p>
<p>SPANISH IMMIGRANTS</p>
<p>In addition to the American volunteers enumerated above there were seven<lb/>
Spanish immigrants who were employed to undergo these experiemnts. Their<lb/>
engagement to do so was a purely business arrangement which was approved by<lb/>
the Spanish consul at Habana; a signed contract was entered into with each one.<lb/>
These men who had come to Cuba to get employment realized well the danger<lb/>
of death of yellow fever, and it was explained to them that in undergoing these<lb/>
experiments they would have the best medical care and nursing, and would be<lb/>
paid what was to them a very large sum of money, $200 American gold at the<lb/>
then rate of exchange being worth about 1,300 Spanish pesetas. The names of<lb/>
these men are as follows:</p>
<p>Nicanor Fernandez, taken sick, December 13, 1900.</p>
<p>Antonio Benigno, taken sick, December 13, 1900.</p>
<p>Becente Presdeo, taken sick December 15, 1900.</p>
<p>Jose Martinez, taken sick January 3, 1901.</p>
<p>Pablo Ruiz Castillo, taken sick September 19, 1901.</p>
<p>Jacinto Mendez Alvarez, taken sick October 13, 1901.</p>
<p>Manuel Gutierrez Moran, taken sick October 20, 1901.</p>
<p>A wide distinction should, in my mind, be made between the payments to the<lb/>
Spanish peasants employed by the board and the donations made to the American<lb/>
soldiers who volunteered to take part in the experiments. In the latter case the<lb/>
payment was regarded as a gratuity which was given in recognition of their<lb/>
meritorious services in the same way that the increased pay was given to men<lb/>
who had earned a certificate of merit by gallantry in action. The only interest<lb/>
which the Spaniards took in the matter was to acquire immunity with the slightest<lb/>
possible risk, and to get a handsome payment for their services. The Americans<lb/>
on the contrary understood what it was all about and were tremenduously<lb/>
interested in the importance to humanity of a successful result.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted,</p>
<p>J. R. KEAN,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Colonel, U. S. Army, Retired</hi>.</p>
<p>The following letter from the Secretary of War reporting on H. R.<lb/>
11686, a similar bill, follows:</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Washington, April 18, 1928</hi>.</p>
<p>Hon. JOHN M. MORIN,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Chairman Committee on Military Affairs,<lb/>
House of Representatives</hi>.</p>
<p>DEAR MR. MORIN: In compliance with the request of March 14, 1928, I am<lb/>
pleased to submit herewith a report in duplicate from The Adjutant General on<lb/>
H. R. 11686, Seventieth Congress, first session.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f03152013"/>
<p>RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.<lb/>
9</p>
<p>The subject of so much of the proposed legislation as refers to the War De-<lb/>
partment provides for the placing of the names of certain individuals on the rolls<lb/>
of the department and also that, in special recognition of the high public serv-<lb/>
ices rendered and disabilities contracted by them in the interest of humanity<lb/>
and science as volunteer subjects for the experimentations during the yellow<lb/>
fever investigations in Cuba, the Secretary of War be, and hereby is, authorized<lb/>
and directed to pay to them during the remainder of their natural lives $250 per<lb/>
month in lieu of all pensions now received.</p>
<p>The Congress has heretofore enacted legislation granting to Jennie Carroll,<lb/>
widow of Maj. James Carroll, United States Army, to Mabel H. Lazear, widow<lb/>
of Jesse W. Lazear, acting assistant contract surgeon, United States Army, and to<lb/>
Mrs. Walter Reed, annuities of $125 per month; also to Clyde L. West, late of<lb/>
United States Hospital Corps, and John R. Kissinger, United States Army,<lb/>
annuities of $100 per month each, to revert to their widows, in recognition of<lb/>
eminent services performed by these men in connection with the yellow fever<lb/>
experimentation in Cuba; and provision for the payment of these annuities<lb/>
except that to Mrs. Walter Reed, which is granted as a pension under a special<lb/>
act approved March 3, 1903 (private 1118, 57th Cong., 2d sess.) and is paid by<lb/>
the Pension Bureau, has been carried in the Army appropriation bills, and is<lb/>
provided for in H. R. 10286, Seventieth Congress, first session, making appropria-<lb/>
tion for the military and nonmilitary activities of the War Department for the<lb/>
fiscal year ending June 30, 1929, approved March 23, 1928. It does not appear<lb/>
from any evidence before the War Department that the cases of these four men<lb/>
mentioned were of exceptional merit as compared with the cases of the other<lb/>
participants in the experiments.</p>
<p>The names mentioned in the bill are, with the following exceptions, already<lb/>
carried on the rolls of the War Department: Mrs. Walter Reed, Dr. Aristides<lb/>
Agramonti, John R. Bullard, Mrs. Warren J. Jernegan, John J. Moran, and<lb/>
Dr. R. P. Cooke. In the case of the last named (R. P. Cooke) H. R. 8772,<lb/>
which passed the House of Representatives on January 11 last, would provide<lb/>
payment at the rate of $100 a month. This bill has not become a law.</p>
<p>It will be noted that the present bill would raise the annuities from the $125<lb/>
per month now being paid to Jennie Carroll and Mabel H. Lazear and also the<lb/>
annuity of $100 per month now being paid to Clyde L. West and John R.<lb/>
Kissinger, to $250 per month.</p>
<p>From the report of The Adjutant General it will be seen that there are omitted<lb/>
from the bill the names of seven persons, Spaniards, who submitted themselves<lb/>
to experiments in connection with the yellow fever investigation, namely:<lb/>
Nicanor Fernandez, Antonio Benigno, Becente Presedo, Jose Martinez, Pablo<lb/>
Ruiz Castillo, Jacinto Mendez Alvarez, and Manuel Gutierrez Moran. In con-<lb/>
nection with these men it is deemed proper to call attention to the remarks made<lb/>
by Surg. Gen. George H. Torney, United States Army, in a report of the occur-<lb/>
rences which led to the appointment of the yellow fever commission as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Before taking up individually the men concerned in these experiments, in<lb/>
order to state what is known about them at the present time, it may be men-<lb/>
tioned that the Spaniards who were inoculated did so for the pecuniary induce-<lb/>
ment offered them. After receiving the reward offered them by the liberality<lb/>
of the military government of Cuba, $200 for each person successfully inocu-<lb/>
lated, they passed from the scene and nothing further is known concerning them.<lb/>
While their names should be preserved as a matter of historical interest, it is<lb/>
considered that they have been well rewarded for their share in the matter,<lb/>
especially as the idea of assisting in the advancement of science was not a con-<lb/>
trolling motive for their action.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Attention is called to the fact that James Hildebrand, whose name appears as<lb/>
a beneficiary under the bill, while he generously offered himself as a subject, was<lb/>
not accepted for inoculation by reason of minority.</p>
<p>Thomas M. England (whose name appears in the fourteenth line incorrectly<lb/>
as Thomas H. England) is now a commissioned officer in the Army and will<lb/>
probably at some time in the future come under the provisions of the retirement<lb/>
law.</p>
<p>It is deemed proper to add that section 1 of the bill in reference is substantially<lb/>
identical with H. R. 16669, Sixty-ninth Congress, second session, upon which<lb/>
a report was made by The Adjutant General to the Secretary of War on Feb-<lb/>
ruary 26, 1927, in response to the call of the chairman, Committee on Military<lb/>
Affairs, House of Representatives.</p>
<p>It would seem that in equity the Government, in establishing rewards for<lb/>
meritorious service, should consider the relative values of the services performed<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f03152014"/>
10<lb/>
RECOGNIZE PUBLIC SERVICE OF MAJ. WALTER REED ET AL.<lb/>
and adopt, as nearly as may be, equal rewards for equal services; yet, while<lb/>
the instant bill would pay to the beneficiaries thereunder $250 a month, section<lb/>
3 of the act of Congress approved April 27, 1916 (H. R. 4701, Public No. 56,<lb/>
64th Cong.), provides for payment to each surviving person, holder of the<lb/>
congressional medal, whose name has been entered on the medal of honor roll,<lb/>
who &ldquo;in action involving actual conflict with the enemy, distinguished himself<lb/>
conspicuously by gallantry or intrepidity, at the risk of his life beyond and<lb/>
above the call of duty&rdquo; a special pension of only $10 per month in addition to<lb/>
any other pension he may be receiving.</p>
<p>It has been ascertained from the Commissioner of Pensions that under the<lb/>
pension laws $125 per month is the highest pension paid under the pension<lb/>
laws, and from the Veterans' Bureau that the highest compensation paid under<lb/>
the World War veterans' act is $200 per month; both for total disability.</p>
<p>The difficulty of determining an adequate reward for services as great as<lb/>
those performed by those persons who offered themselves for experimentation<lb/>
in the yellow-fever investigation is recognized, but the facts having been stated<lb/>
above, and as the War Department is not directly concerned, I feel that a decision<lb/>
of the question should be left to the Congress as a matter of public policy.</p>
<p>Sincerely yours,<lb/>
DWIGHT F. DAVIS, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of War</hi>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
