<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03161001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from James E. Peabody to Alvah H. Doty, September 9, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Peabody, James E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03161001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-09-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Doty, Alvah H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie L.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Wainwright, J. Mayhew</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-09-09">September 9, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03161001</idno>
<title>Letter from James E. Peabody to Alvah H. Doty, September 9, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Peabody seeks clarification of information for a pamphlet on yellow fever for the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1928-09-09">
<head>Letter from James E. Peabody to Alvah H. Doty, September 9, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03161001"/>
<opener>
Can you give me any light on these pencilled questions?<lb/>
(I found no reply to this in the Peabody Collection). JP<lb/>
FROM JAMES E. PEABODY<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1928-09-09">September 9, 1928.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Alvah H. Doty,<lb/>
Medical Director <del>American Telegraph</del> <add>Western Union</add> Co.,<lb/>
195 Broadway, N. Y. City,<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Doty:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I understood you to say the other day when I talked with you that you<lb/>
would be willing to put in writing the answers to several questions which<lb/>
we discussed. I therefore beg leave to ask your further generous assistance<lb/>
in the preparation of my pamphlet for the American Museum of Natural History<lb/>
on the Conquest of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>1. I have not the copy of the minutes of the hearing before th Committee<lb/>
on Military Affairs of the House right here where I can refer to the text,<lb/>
but I am sure I heard Col. Kean say at that time and in his office that far<lb/>
too little credit has given to Dr. Agramonte in the government reports for<lb/>
his work on the Yellow Fever Board. It is not too late for the Country to<lb/>
learn the facts, and I am hoping you can secure a very specific statement<lb/>
of our debt to this Cuban doctor. In your correction of my galley proofs<lb/>
you changed my statement in regard to Dr. Agramonte (&ldquo;who had recovered from<lb/>
the disease and so was immune to further attacks&rdquo;) to read &ldquo;who was supposed<lb/>
to be immune to the disease&rdquo;. (I think after all this change was made by<lb/>
Col. Kean). Does this mean that he had an attack in childhood which was so<lb/>
light that it was not recognized? You told me that Dr. Agramonte sometimes<lb/>
comes up from Cuba to your office. Would it be an imposition to ask if I<lb/>
might meet him?</p>
<p>Can you give me Dr<lb/>
Agramonte's service</p>
<p>How does this misunderstanding<lb/>
<unclear>operate</unclear>?</p>
<p>2. I find in Dr. F. F. Russell's article in the Sigma Xi Quarterly,<lb/>
March, 1925, on &ldquo;War on Disease&rdquo; the following statement which surprised me<lb/>
much. (p.16) &ldquo;It was probably the work of Doctor Henry R. Carter of the<lb/>
United States Public Health Service rather than of Finlay which induced Reed<lb/>
to change his plans.&rdquo; Dr. H. A. Kelly in his &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo;<lb/>
certainly gives a great deal of credit to Finlay for his <hi>theory</hi>. I cannot<lb/>
find in the book a distinct statement that this Doctor conferred with Dr. Reed<lb/>
but I am sure the statement is made in many places that Dr. Lazear secured<lb/>
his Stegomyia mosquito eggs from Finlay. In &ldquo;William Crawford Gorgas--His<lb/>
Life and Work&rdquo; by Mrs. Gorgas and Burton Hendrick the highest possible trib-<lb/>
utes are given to Dr. Finlay. Among others--&ldquo;Amost lovable man in character<lb/>
and personality,&rdquo; writes Gorgas; &ldquo;no one could be thrown with Dr. Finlay daily<lb/>
as I was for several years without becoming warmly attached to him and form-<lb/>
ing the highest estimate of his scientific honesty and straightforwardness.&rdquo;<lb/>
On page 103 of the Gorgas book is the following: &ldquo;There seems something like<lb/>
the working of an intelligent fate in the fact that the three men--Carter,<lb/>
Reed, and Gorgas--who seemed indispensable to solving the yellow-fever prob-<lb/>
lem, were at work in Havana at the same time. Carter was there as Quarantine<lb/>
Officer, and naturally he presented his tables to his fellow Virginian. Reed<lb/>
gave them the most painstaking study. 'Are you sure your dates are accurate? <unclear>8</unclear><lb/>
he asked Carter. Carter had no doubt on that point. 'Then,' said Reed, 'it<lb/>
spells an insect host.'&rdquo; Do you think I should omit all reference to Finlay<lb/>
in view of these quotations? Will you give me the dates of your visits to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03161002"/>
FROM JAMES E. PEABODY<lb/>
(2).<lb/>
Cuba? The date of Carter's paper, which Dr. Russell was kind enough to let<lb/>
me read in typewritten form is June, <hi>1901</hi>. Do you know of any earlier pa-<lb/>
per? I shall try to get to the Academy of Medicine sometime this week, un-<lb/>
less you can suggest a way to give full justice to both Finlay and Carter.<lb/>
Is Carter still living?</p>
<p>I cannot find any<lb/>
such paper at N. Y.<lb/>
Academy of Med.</p>
<p>3. Another unfortunate misunderstanding seems to have arisen between the<lb/>
supporters of Reed and Gorgas. When I was in Washinton in November, 1926,<lb/>
I got the impression from at least two of the high government officials that<lb/>
Mrs. Gorgas' Life of her husband failed to give due credit to Dr. Reed. In-<lb/>
deed one of these men told me he tried his best to get Doubleday, Page and<lb/>
Co. to change the original articles which I believe appeared in the WORLD'S<lb/>
WORK before the chapters appeared in book form. I have read carefully the<lb/>
chapter in Mrs. Gorgas' book on &ldquo;Yellow Fever Meets its Master&rdquo;, and I find<lb/>
quotations like the following; &ldquo;The story of the next few months has been<lb/>
frequently told. It is the story of Reed and not the story of Gorgas. (p.<lb/>
106). &ldquo;He (Reed) had no sincerer mourner than Gorgas, who, for the rest of<lb/>
his life never missed an opportunity to witness his debt to Reed. One day<lb/>
General M. Weaver was walking down Connecticut Avenue, Washington, with his<lb/>
little granddaughter. He met Gorgas then at the height of his fame. &ldquo;Persis,<lb/>
said the General to the little girl, 'this is General Gorgas, one of our<lb/>
great men.' 'No, my child,' said Gorgas, in his soft accents, 'not a great<lb/>
man; merely one who is trying to follow in the footsteps of a great man--<lb/>
Walter Reed.'&rdquo; What higher tributes could any writer put in any book--and<lb/>
there are others in the Life of Gorgas. How extensive is the misunderstand-<lb/>
ing? Surely there is honor enough for all those heroes, and we must not let<lb/>
our young people know that there is a Sampson-Schley controversy in this<lb/>
heroic story. Will you be good enough to read again my galleys so far as<lb/>
they concern these two men, and let me know if I have been fair to both?</p>
<p>How widespread is this<lb/>
controversy</p>
<p>4. You, Dr. Russell, and I made a tentative annuity schedule for the sur-<lb/>
vivors of those yellow fever experiments and for their widows--$5000 for<lb/>
Mrs. Reed, $4000 for Dr. Agramonte, Mrs. Carroll, Mrs. Lazear, and for the<lb/>
four Doctors who have recently died (or should the latters' survivors have<lb/>
somewhat less?), and $2000 for each of the 18 privates who submitted to inoc-<lb/>
ulation by mosquitoes or to the &ldquo;fomites&rdquo;. Do you still think this fair?<lb/>
(Dr. <unclear>F.F.</unclear> Russell said, &ldquo;You cannot suggest too high an annuity for Mrs. Reed, for<lb/>
we are learning <unclear>morse</unclear> and more of his wonderful work. He was the genius<lb/>
of the whole series of experiments, and his life was so valuable that the<lb/>
military men in Cuba refused to allow him to submit his own body to the<lb/>
mosquito tests.) It is fortunate that our bill did not pass at the last ses<lb/>
sion, for it recommended a flat rate of $3000 for all. General Ireland was<lb/>
absolutely right when he said that a higher annuity should be given to the<lb/>
officers. I am exceedingly glad that Mrs. Gorgas' name was included in<lb/>
the amended bill. What do you suggest for her? Col. Wainwright, who man-<lb/>
aged that hearing with such skill, says he will be glad to talk with me nex<lb/>
week, rand I should like to get your reaction before that time, if I am not<lb/>
imposing on you with these many questions. You have information right from<lb/>
the front line of battle; hence my boldness in appealing to you.</p>
<p>Should Dr Agramontes' name he<lb/>
included? Well this <unclear>mulbate</unclear> against<lb/>
Congressional action</p>
<closer>
<salute>Gratefully yours,</salute>
<signed>Peabody</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
