<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03172001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Why Walter Reed General Hospital Was Named and Located as It Is, by P.M. Ashburn, [1929]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03172001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Manson, Patrick</name>
<name type="person">Borden, William C.</name>
<name type="person">Root, Elihu</name>
<name type="person">Forwood, William H.</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Proctor, Redfield</name>
<name type="person">Allison, William B.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="place">Belroi (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Bellevue Hospital Medical College, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Rico</name>
<name type="place">Italy</name>
<name type="place">Spain</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Kings County Hospital, N.Y.</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital</name>
<name type="hospital">Washington Barracks Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="[1929]-00-00">[1929]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03172001</idno>
<title>Why Walter Reed General Hospital Was Named and Located as It Is, by P.M. Ashburn, [1929]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ashburn's speech to an audience of student nurses is an overview of Reed's life and work. The piece includes an excerpt from the Surgeon General's report, 1900.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-00-00">
<head>Why Walter Reed General Hospital Was Named and Located as It Is, by P.M. Ashburn, [1929]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03172001"/>
<opener>
Why Walter Reed General Hospital was named and located as it is. An address to student nurses.<lb/>
by<lb/>
P. M. Ashburn, Col. M. C.<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Walter Reed was born in Belroi, Virginia in 1851. His schooling was some-<lb/>
what interfered with by the Civil War, which lasted from his 10th well into<lb/>
his 14th year, but the interruption was less than one would expect. After<lb/>
the war he attended a private school for 2 sessions, and at the age of sixteen<lb/>
he entered the University of Virginia, where, after one year of academic work,<lb/>
he took up the study of medicine and won his degree of M. D. in one year more,<lb/>
at the early age of 18.</p>
<p>In just what measure this was due to Reed's precocity and in what to low<lb/>
scholastic standards, I do not attempt to say, but the fact is indicative of<lb/>
the narrow scope of the medical course at that time. Following his graduation<lb/>
from Virginia, he went to Bellevue Hospital Medical College, where he obtained<lb/>
another M. D. after one year's work. He became an interne in Kings County Hos-<lb/>
pital, N. Y., and later entered practice in Brooklyn. Much enamored of a charm-<lb/>
ing girl, and too poor to marry, he tried the army examinations as a short road<lb/>
to a competency, as many another has done before and since Reed's time.</p>
<p>He was successful in passing the examination and getting the girl, and he<lb/>
entered the service in 1875. For the next fifteen years he served in western<lb/>
posts, doing the ordinary small round of post duties. In 1890 he was ordered<lb/>
to Johns Hopkins where he came in contact with the group of geniuses whose happy<lb/>
fellowship made that so great a place. There he took up especially the young<lb/>
science of Bacteriology.</p>
<p>In 1893, Surgeon General Sternberg established the Army Medical School<lb/>
and Walter Reed was detailed Professor of Bacteriology, a position which he<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03172002"/>
-2-<lb/>
occupied until his death from appendicitis in 1902.</p>
<p>When the Spanish-American War came, with its great epidemics of typhoid<lb/>
fever, Reed was one of a board, the other members being Victor C. Vaughan and<lb/>
Edward O. Shakespeare, to investigate that disease. The board's report was very<lb/>
full and threw much new light upon the epidemiology.</p>
<p>After the Spanish-American War, Reed was made president of a board to study<lb/>
the tropical diseases of Cuba, and as such he did his great work on yellow fever.<lb/>
Concerning this disease allow me to read an extract from a <hi>History of the Medical<lb/>
Department</hi> which I am preparing for publication.</p>
<p>&ldquo;After the treaty of peace with Spain had defined our relation to the former<lb/>
Spanish colonies, Surgeon General Sternberg promoted in all ways within his power<lb/>
the acquisition by the Medical Corps of knowledge as to the diseases and the sani-<lb/>
tation of our new possessions. Boards for the study of tropical diseases were es-<lb/>
tablished in the Philippine Islands, in Cuba and in Porto Rico. The most notable<lb/>
of these, because of its complete demonstration of the means of transmission of<lb/>
yellow fever, was the board consisting of Major Walter Reed and three contract<lb/>
surgeons, Dr. James Carroll, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear and Dr. Aristides Agramonte.</p>
<p>&ldquo;For many years Surgeon General Sternberg had himself worked at investigations<lb/>
of yellow fever, a large part of his work being the refutation of the mistakes of<lb/>
others, disproof that various announced causes of the disease were not the cause.</p>
<p>&ldquo;During the year 1898 there were 1164 cases of the disease in the army, with a<lb/>
mortality of 144 cases or 12.32 per cent. In 1899 there were 262 cases, with 55<lb/>
deaths. The very great majority of these cases occurred in Cuba, a few in Porto<lb/>
Rico and the Southern States. In 1900 a great flow of emigration from Spain to<lb/>
Cuba supplied non-immune material for the disease and it prevailed more extensively<lb/>
in the island than for some years past. A new germ, Sanarelli <hi>Bacillus icteroides</hi>,<lb/>
had been heralded to the world as the cause of yellow fever. General Sternberg,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03172003"/>
-3-<lb/>
taught caution by the many mistakes which he had had to uncover in regard to<lb/>
similar, previous announcements, as well as by his generally scientific attitude<lb/>
of mind, appointed the board to investigate the subject of yellow fever generally<lb/>
and of Sanarelli's bacillus in particular. The bacillus was disposed of in rela-<lb/>
tively short order. It was found in none of eighteen cases, eleven of which came<lb/>
to autopsy. But a happy concatenation of labors of other men speedily put the<lb/>
board upon the real trail of the mysterious vector which had made the disease so<lb/>
puzzling to the investigators of a hundred years. These important and interlinked<lb/>
labors were the following:</p>
<p>"(1) Ronald Ross, of the Indian Medical Service, had shown that malaria is<lb/>
carried by mosquitoes of the genus Anopheles. His work had been confirmed and<lb/>
elaborated in Italy.</p>
<p>"(2) The American administration in Cuba had cleaned up the city of Havana,<lb/>
without in any way improving the yellow fever situation, thus apparently eliminating<lb/>
the possibility of its being a filth disease.</p>
<p>"(3) Surgeon Henry R. Carter, United States Marine Hospital Service, in May,<lb/>
1900, published his very important observations on the epidemiology of the disease,<lb/>
especially the relation between the infecting, or imported, and the secondary cases,<lb/>
a relationship which, in the light of the work on malaria, pointed to an insect<lb/>
carrier for the disease, although Dr. Carter did not suggest this in his article.&rdquo;</p>
<p>*Carter, Henry R., New Orleans Med. &amp; Surg.Journal, LII, No. 11, p. 617-636,<lb/>
May, 1900.</p>
<p>"(4) Dr. Carlos Finlay, a resident of Cuba of Scotch and French ancestry, had<lb/>
nineteen years before published # the reasoning by which he had reached the conclu-<lb/>
# See Anales de la Real Academia de Ciencias Medicas, Fisicas y Naturales<lb/>
de la Habana - Sesion del 14 de Agosto, de 1881.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03172004"/>
-4-<lb/>
sion that yellow fever was mosquito borne and that it was carried by the mosquito<lb/>
<hi>Culex fasciatus</hi> (later called <hi>Stegomyia fasciata</hi>, <hi>Stegomyia calopus</hi>, <hi>Aedes<lb/>
aegypti</hi>), for twenty years had talked his belief, had been regarded as an amiable<lb/>
crank, and had tried, as he thought, successfully, as others thought, in vain,<lb/>
to transmit the disease by the insect's bite. His repeated failures in themselves<lb/>
seemed fair proof that he was wrong. Nevertheless he was right and his rightness<lb/>
in one of the finest bits of sound reasoning from correct observation of which there<lb/>
is any record in the history of medicine. A great mind, too great perhaps to<lb/>
mix any malice with the satisfaction which must have come when, after twenty<lb/>
years, his so-called folly was recognized as the most profound wisdom. Walter<lb/>
Reed, having these interlocking facts, was also greatly intelligent in recog-<lb/>
nizing their importance and that they interlocked. The Board set itself to test<lb/>
out Dr. Finlay's hypothesis in the light of the work of Ross and of Carter. It<lb/>
was also greatly fortunate that Doctor Finlay was stilleliving in Havana, still<lb/>
riding his hobby, still the object of amusement to the knowing ones, still trying<lb/>
to prove what his observation and reason told him was true, and still, as for<lb/>
years past, breeding <hi>Stegomyia</hi> mosquitoes and trying to transmit yellow fever<lb/>
by their bites. He indicated the mosquito to the board and furnished its eggs,<lb/>
(See S.G.Report, 1901, p. 181 &amp; 182)</p>
<p>&ldquo;There was at the time a small epidemic of yellow fever at Quemados, and<lb/>
thither the board proceeded on June 25th, 1900, and at once began its investigations.<lb/>
No inoculation experiments were made until August 11th. The first nine attempts at<lb/>
inoculation failed to convey the disease, because, as afterward became apparent,<lb/>
the mosquitoes were non-infective for one of two reasons, eigher (1) they had<lb/>
bitten the yellow fever cases too late to obtain the virus with the blood, or<lb/>
(2) They had not been kept sufficiently long to complete the developmental phase<lb/>
which the virus undergoes in the insect. It is probable that a feeling that there<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03172005"/>
-5-<lb/>
was nothing in Dr. Finlay's hypothesis had begun to possess the members of the<lb/>
board, and when Dr. Carroll was bitten on August 27th by a mosquito which had<lb/>
bitten a yellow fever patient in the second day of the disease and had been kept<lb/>
for twelve days thereafter, he apparently did not expect to get the disease. At<lb/>
any rate, when he became sick on the afternoon of the 29th and on the 30th, he<lb/>
did not take his temperature or seek a diagnosis. On the 31st he examined his<lb/>
blood for malarial parasites, and failed to find them and that evening his tem-<lb/>
perature was taken for the first time and was found to be 102&deg;. The diagnosis of<lb/>
yellow fever was made on September 1st. The case was severe but resulted in<lb/>
recovery. After the diagnosis was made there was still no proof that he had<lb/>
acquired the disease from that mosquito.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The next case to develop the disease was Case II, (xy) a soldier who accepted<lb/>
the bites in a spirit of disbelief and bravado. His case was diagnosed &ldquo;well-pro-<lb/>
nounced yellow fever.&rdquo; The third case, that of Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, resulted from<lb/>
the bite of a free mosquito in a yellow fever ward. &ldquo;On September 13, 1900 (fore-<lb/>
noon) Dr. Lazear, while on a visit to Las Animas Hospital, and while collecting<lb/>
blood from yellow fever patients for study, was bitten by a Culex mosquito (Species<lb/>
undetermined). As Dr. Lazear had been previously bitten by a contaminated insect<lb/>
without effect, he deliberately allowed this particular mosquito, which had set-<lb/>
tled on the back of his hand, to remain until it had satisfied its hunger,&rdquo; In<lb/>
five days he sickened and in twelve days he was dead.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The board thereafter produced six more cases (all of which recovered) by mos-<lb/>
quito inoculation, failed to produce it by most thorough experiments with fomites,<lb/>
and concluded:</p>
<p>&ldquo;' 1. The mosquito--<hi>C. fasciatus</hi>--serves as the intermediate host for the para-<lb/>
site of yellow fever.</p>
<p>&ldquo;'2. Yellow fever is transmitted to the non-immune
individual by means of the<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03172006"/>
-6-<lb/>
bite of the mosquito that has previously fed on the blood of those sick with this<lb/>
disease.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '3. An interval of about twelve days or more after contamination appears<lb/>
to be necessary before the mosquito is capable of conveying the infection.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '4. The bite of the mosquito at an earlier period after contamination does<lb/>
not appear to confer any immunity against a subsequent attack.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '5. Yellow fever can also be experimentally produced by the subcutaneous<lb/>
injection of blood taken from the general circulation during the first and second<lb/>
days of this disease.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '6. An attack of yellow fever, produced by the bite of the mosquito, con-<lb/>
fers immunity against the subsequent injection of the blood of an individual suf-<lb/>
fering from the non-experimental form of this disease.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '7. The period of incubation in thirteen cases of experimental yellow fever<lb/>
has varied from forty-one hours to five days and seventeen hours.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '8. Yellow fever is not conveyed by fomites, and hence disinfection of ar-<lb/>
ticles of clothing, bedding, or merchandise, supposedly contaminated by contact<lb/>
with those sick with this disease, is unnecessary.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '9. A house may be said to be infected with yellow fever only when there are<lb/>
present within its walls contaminated mosquitoes capable of conveying the parasite<lb/>
of this disease.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '10. The spread of yellow fever can be most effectually controlled by mea-<lb/>
sures directed to the destruction of mosquitoes and the protection of the sick<lb/>
against the bites of these insects.</p>
<p>&ldquo; '11. While the mode of propagation of yellow fever has now been definitely<lb/>
determined, the specific cause of this disease remains to be discovered.'<lb/>
(S. G. Report, 1901, p. 200.)</p>
<p>&ldquo;The board thus cleared up the question of the transmission of yellow fever,<lb/>
to the great glory of American medicine, the saving of thousands of lives, the<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03172007"/>
-7-<lb/>
advance of commerce and civilization, the rejuvenation of Latin-America and, not<lb/>
least, to the eternal credit of common American Manhood, the kind that enlists<lb/>
in the Army, the kind enlisted in the Hospital Corps. For it was the heroism,<lb/>
nothing less, of such men that made possible the experimentation on human beings,<lb/>
then the only known hosts of the disease. Carroll and Lazear were scientists,<lb/>
driven by the insatiable curiosity that only scientists and children know and xy<lb/>
was a scoffer.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The enlisted men who later submitted to experiment, either with mosquito<lb/>
bites or the disgusting fomites of sick or dead men, were not doctors, scientists<lb/>
or unbelievers, they knew the risk and they took it for no reason that the desire<lb/>
to do a generous thing for the good of others. It was nobly generous and nobly<lb/>
brave. That some of them, private soldiers without other money than their small<lb/>
pay, accepted money when it was offered them, does not in the least detract from<lb/>
their heroism. That John Moran refused it then and later merely showed an admir-<lb/>
able streak of pride in his make up. (I can not forbear boasting that I have<lb/>
known this fine man, then a clerk of the Panama Canal, modest, self-effacing, shy<lb/>
and efficient.)</p>
<p>&ldquo;The world sat up and took notice of the Reed board's report at once. Sir<lb/>
Patrick Manson, the foremost authority on tropical diseases then living, later<lb/>
described the meaning of the work in the fewest possible words:</p>
<p>&ldquo; 'These experiments fully explain: 1st the impunity with which a yellow fever<lb/>
patient can be visited by a non-immune if outside the endemic area; the mosquitoes<lb/>
in the vicinity are not infective. 2d, the danger of visiting the endemic area, es-<lb/>
pecially at night; the mosquitoes there are infective and active 3d, the discrep-<lb/>
ancy between the incubation period, three to five days, of the disease, and the<lb/>
incubation period, fourteen days and over, of an epidemic; the necessary evolution<lb/>
of the germ in the mosquitoes infected by the original introducing patient demanding<lb/>
the space of time indicated by the difference between these two periods. 4th the<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f03172008"/>
-8-<lb/>
clinging of yellow fever infection to ships, buildings, and localities; the persis-<lb/>
tence of the germ in infected mosquitoes which are known to be capable of surviv-<lb/>
ing for five months, and probably longer, after feeding on blood. 5th, the high<lb/>
atmospheric temperature required for epidemic extension of yellow fever; such tem-<lb/>
perature favors the activities and propagation of the mosquito, and is probably<lb/>
necessary for the evolution of the germ in the mosquito.'&rdquo;</p>
<p>During the Spanish-American War a general hospital was established at Washing-<lb/>
ton Barracks as at a number of other military posts. After the conclusion of the<lb/>
war and the demobilization of troops these hospitals were closed as rapidly as<lb/>
possible, but two, that at San Francisco and the one at Washington Barracks were<lb/>
continued for the care of overseas patients and such others as could not secure<lb/>
all needed treatment at their posts, but these, especially the one at Washington<lb/>
Barracks had no promise of permanence. Major Wm. C. Borden was the operating sur-<lb/>
geon and the Commanding Officer. He thought that a large, well equipped hospital<lb/>
of permanent nature should be established, to care for such cases as this hospital<lb/>
now cares for, to furnish teaching material for the Army Medical School and to<lb/>
serve as the nucleus for a still larger place in time of war. As he thought of<lb/>
the matter, his ideas grew and he dreamed of a medical center to include the<lb/>
hospital, the medical school and the Library and Museum of the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Office.</p>
<p>Quite on his own, he made plans, consulted architects and prepared estimates,<lb/>
and after doing all this he submitted the plans and the estimates for $9,600,000<lb/>
to Surgeon General Sternberg. That gentleman characterized it all as &ldquo;a beautiful<lb/>
dream&rdquo;, for the realization of which there was no hope. He even refused to propose<lb/>
it to the Secretary of War, but gave his permission for Borden to do so.</p>
<p>Secretary Root listened for a quarter of an hour, said the idea was excellent.<lb/>
He was about to leave the office of Secretary of War, but he was willing to indorse<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f03172009"/>
-9-<lb/>
his approval and recommendation on the plan. This he did and Major Borden then<lb/>
started to seek authorization and funds from Congress. He contrived to do so<lb/>
without success for about four years.</p>
<p>Meanwhile his success was also jeopardized in another way. Surgeon General<lb/>
Sternberg retired for age and was succeeded by Surgeon General Forwood, who did<lb/>
not like Borden. One of his first official acts was to ask an order sending the<lb/>
latter away from Washington and closing the general hospital.</p>
<p>This was frustrated by Col. (afterward Major General) Carter, an adjutant<lb/>
general, upon whose wife Borden had operated and who admired the latter and be-<lb/>
lieved in his plan. He went to the Secretary of War and presented the matter,<lb/>
with the result that Surgeon General Forwood was informed that inasmuch as his<lb/>
tenure of office was so short no changes of stations of medical officers would<lb/>
be made without the Secretary's personal approval. He did not approve Borden's<lb/>
change.</p>
<p>Thereafter General Forwood asked no more orders. He was succeeded by Gen-<lb/>
eral O'Reilly, who approved the plan, but even with his help, Borden could get<lb/>
no appreciation.</p>
<p>One morning, after some years of haunting the Capitol, Borden, still in<lb/>
pursuit of his plan, entered it again and as he did so he spoke pleasantly to<lb/>
a one-armed doorkeeper of the Senate and inquired about his health. The old<lb/>
man, a Civil War veteran, complained of pain in the stump of his arm, and con-<lb/>
sequent loss of sleep.</p>
<p>Major Borden suggested that it was due to a neuroma and offered to take the<lb/>
man into hospital and operate upon it. He consented, the Surgeon General's per-<lb/>
mission was obtained, the operation performed and the pain relieved.</p>
<p>When the old man was ready to leave the hospital he entered Major Borden's<lb/>
office, closed the door, looked carefully around to see that no one could overhear<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f031720010"/>
-10-<lb/>
and said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Major, you have been around the Capitol for several years now trying<lb/>
to get an appropriation and you don't seem to get anywhere.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, that is true.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well I have been down here now and I know this is a good thing, so I shall<lb/>
tell you something, in confidence, which may help you. I have noticed that when-<lb/>
ever Col. P. (a real estate man) is interested in an appropriation for real es-<lb/>
tate here in Washington, he usually gets it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Borden thanked him and got into touch with Col. P. who thought his plan noble<lb/>
and quite feasible. He took Borden to the Chairman of the Appropriations Committee<lb/>
of the House, who, under the explanation of the Colonel, quickly saw what a fine<lb/>
thing it would be for the country and incidentally wondered that it had not sooner<lb/>
been brought to his attention. Borden was sufficiently discreet not to mention<lb/>
that he personally had brought it to attention, at every session for four years.<lb/>
The chairman told his clerk to insert in the Sundry Civil Bill a clause appropri-<lb/>
ating $500,000 (the amount which Borden and the Colonel had thought necessary<lb/>
for a beginning). This was done but the item was rejected and the bill was sent<lb/>
to the Senate. To you and that would have seemed the end of the matter, Not so to<lb/>
Borden. He had not haunted the halls of Congress four years for nothing. He called<lb/>
the Colonel and said &ldquo;now if you can get Senator Proctor (Chairman of the Military<lb/>
Affairs Committee of the Senate) to do what we went we will get our money.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;How so?&rdquo; said the Colonel, &ldquo;Proctor is all right.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The bill will come up in the Senate at eleven o'clock tomorrow and Congress<lb/>
is to adjourn two days later. Get Senator Proctor to get Senator Allison, who has<lb/>
it in charge, to allow him to put in an item which he greatly desires but has not<lb/>
had time to get into the Military Appropriation Bill. (He had only had four years.)<lb/>
Then it will go to conference, our friends will be on the House Conference Committee<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f031720011"/>
-11-<lb/>
and will accept it, adjournment is so near there will be no haggling and it will<lb/>
pass both houses.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was done as per schedule, except that Senator Allison would not stand<lb/>
for more than $300,000. So, instead of buying the 80 acre farm on which the<lb/>
Colonel had secured an option they had to be content with 46 acres, as the hospi-<lb/>
tal also had to be built.</p>
<p>The shell of the central part of the present administration building was put<lb/>
up, without elevator, baseboards or refinements, but the thing was started. From<lb/>
that time to this it has grown. It later acquired women nurses, was named in honor<lb/>
of Walter Reed, was pushed by General Ireland, and eventually got the Nursing School.<lb/>
It has arrived. With your help it will grow yet more in favor, in usefulness and<lb/>
in beauty.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
