<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03184001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Text of Speech: To the Graduating Class of the United States Military Academy, by James W. Good, June 13, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03184001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-06-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">U.S. Military Academy, West Point (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-06-13">June 13, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03184001</idno>
<title>Text of Speech: To the Graduating Class of the United States Military Academy, by James W. Good, June 13, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Good, the Secretary of War, addresses the 1929 class of West Point and mentions the enrollment of Reed and Wood on the Roll of Honor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-06-13">
<head>Text of Speech: To the Graduating Class of the United States Military Academy, by James W. Good, June 13, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03184001"/>
<opener>
F U T U R E R E L E A S E<lb/>
N O T E D A T E<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT<lb/>
F U T U R E<lb/>
R E L E A S E<lb/>
FOR RELEASE IN THE AFTERNOON PAPERS OF THURSDAY, JUNE 13, 1929.<lb/>
ADDRESS OF THE SECRETARY OF WAR, HONORABLE JAMES W. GOOD, TO<lb/>
THE GRADUATING CLASS OF THE UNITED STATES MILITARY ACADEMY AT WEST POINT,<lb/>
<dateline>
NEW YORK, <date value="1929-06-13">June 13, 1929.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>In a dramatic scene in Shakespeare's Henry the Eighth, the great<lb/>
Cardinal Wolsey, Lord Chancellor of England, is informed that his personal<lb/>
ambition has been his ruin, that the King has discovered his chicanery, and has<lb/>
divested him of all honors, ordered him to return the Great Seal, and to for-<lb/>
feit all his goods and lends and chattels whatsoever.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I once trod the ways of glory - now mark my fall and that that ruined<lb/>
me,&rdquo; says the discredited Cardinal to his servant, Cromwell, as he warns the<lb/>
latter to avoid the pitfalls of selfish ambition that brought him to disaster.</p>
<p>Purged of his pride and worldly aspirations, the fallen statesman ex-<lb/>
horts his servant to unselfish service in the following words:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Cromwell, I charge thee, fling away ambition:<lb/>
By that sin fell the angels; how can man, then,<lb/>
The image of his Maker, hope to win by it?<lb/>
Love thyself last; cherish those hearts that hate thee;<lb/>
Corruption wins not more than honesty.<lb/>
Still in thy right hand carry gentle peace,<lb/>
To silence envious tongues; be just and fear not;<lb/>
Let all the ends thou aimest at be thy Country's,<lb/>
Thy God's and truth's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>With these words does the immortal Shakespeare entreat the seeking<lb/>
of honor through sacrifice, the winning of plaudits by service, and the con-<lb/>
secration of life to all that redounds to the welfare of country and mankind.<lb/>
This is a high conception of service - a conception that every man should cher-<lb/>
ish who marches forth from these stately halls to enter upon a career that de-<lb/>
mands the most exalted allegiance to Duty - Honor - Country, a career in which<lb/>
men become great by the might of a great love of service.</p>
<p>You are entering a profession that can rightly claim superiority in<lb/>
the matter of honor, and though other professions may resent this claim they<lb/>
cannot venture to assume it for themselves. This title to honor has been<lb/>
gratuitously conferred on the profession of arms since man began to recognize<lb/>
the nobility of courage, self-sacrifice and devotion to ideals. Until man-<lb/>
kind changes its estimate of moral values and pays the same tribute to sel-<lb/>
fishness that it does to generosity your calling will continue to be held the<lb/>
most honorable of all professions and no amount of philosophizing or political<lb/>
economizing will ever deprive it of this distinction.</p>
<p>When you decided to follow the soldier's profession you sought ad-<lb/>
mission to the soldier's university. You came to study in one of the world's<lb/>
most beautiful places whose very surroundings and traditions are enough to<lb/>
inspire the least emotional. Even the casual tourist cannot visit this pic-<lb/>
turesque site on the wooded banks of the Hudson without being uplifted by these<lb/>
historical associations, this atmosphere of devotion to high purpose, the tra-<lb/>
ditions that invest old West Point with the storied glamor of a glorious past.</p>
<p>You will recall yourselves as you came here from the ranks of the<lb/>
Regular Army, from the farm and the city. Four years here have wrought many<lb/>
changes. You are larger physically and mentally than when you came. You are<lb/>
finer, stronger, better balanced in the relation of intellect to heart, and<lb/>
will to conscience; you aspire to greater things and you have acquired greater<lb/>
power to achieve them. The splendid democracy of your life here has broken<lb/>
down all false standards among you and swept away narrowness or prejudices that<lb/>
may have been yours when you arrived. You have been taught to cherish truth<lb/>
and to believe in what is right, and the traditions of Spartan honesty and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03184002"/>
integrity you have absorbed here are priceless assets to yourself and country.</p>
<p>So much for your training and qualifications. How about your res-<lb/>
ponsibilities? Cut of the common fund to which all citizens contribute the<lb/>
nation has taken great sums to erect and maintain this splendid institution, not<lb/>
for your personal advantage but for the public good. You had no right to de-<lb/>
mand admission here to further your own personal ends. When you conformed with<lb/>
the technicalities of entrance some of you may have thought the passage of the<lb/>
Pons <unclear>Asinorum</unclear> the greatest trial, others may have dreaded the languages or his-<lb/>
tory examinations, but the greatest entrance test of all should have been your<lb/>
sense of the moral obligations involved and the question of whether or not you<lb/>
were consecrated to the ideals of service.</p>
<p>Your days at the Academy are numbered to the last few hours but your<lb/>
education is not complete. &ldquo;Instruction ends in the school-room but education<lb/>
ends only with life.&rdquo; You have but acquired the tools with which to meet the<lb/>
obligations you have incurred to the Government and the nation. You have been<lb/>
given the mental training which presages accomplishment, the sense of duty that<lb/>
impels you to service, and the strength of character that, above all else, makes<lb/>
you valuable to your country.</p>
<p>Now the Government did not maintain you and educate you for four<lb/>
years to make mere drill-masters. Nor will you be returning payment in full<lb/>
for all that you have received by merely being available for emergencies, even<lb/>
though you bring to the meeting of these emergencies courage, efficiency, and<lb/>
steadfast loyalty.</p>
<p>You have been prepared to meet a wider concept of service in peace<lb/>
and war.</p>
<p>I am reminded of the military roads that governments expend millions<lb/>
of dollars to construct. Such vast expenditure would not be justified if these<lb/>
great roads were only available for use in time of war. They must serve also<lb/>
as highways of commerce, as agencies of national development, and they must take<lb/>
a daily part in the shaping of the country's destiny.</p>
<p>There was a period in our history when the life of the Regular Army<lb/>
officer was spent within the narrow compass of army associations and his ac-<lb/>
tivities confined to the performance of military duties. That period passed<lb/>
twenty years ago. Our times make many varied demands upon the officer of the<lb/>
regular establishment. Never before has this nation been in greater need of<lb/>
men so tempered by education and training that they are quickly adaptable to<lb/>
changing conditions, whose minds are trained to adopt and adapt new ideas and<lb/>
equipped to find correct and prompt solutions for new and unforeseen problems.</p>
<p>Our country's rank among the nations, her tremendous wealth, strate-<lb/>
gic position and commercial expansion have increased her international contacts<lb/>
and so have enormously multiplied the opportunities for misunderstandings and<lb/>
conflicts in foreign policies. The Government has a right to feel that the Army<lb/>
officer makes a tactful and capable agent and is coming to use him more and<lb/>
more as its representative at home and abroad. He is entrusted with missions<lb/>
that touch every phase of national life and is sent to all parts of the world<lb/>
to further the interests of the Government. He most likely goes alone, without<lb/>
troops, and accomplishes his purpose, not through the sword, but by the ju-<lb/>
dicious use of intellect and a broad understanding of human affairs. He may be<lb/>
a Leonard Wood in the Philippines, a Pershing in South America, or a McCoy in<lb/>
Nicaragua.</p>
<p>In the performance of his varied tasks it is imperative that he es-<lb/>
tablish bonds of common purpose with his fellow men in civil life, remembering<lb/>
that &ldquo;when we assume the soldier we do not lay aside the citizen.&rdquo; His first<lb/>
consideration must always be the national defense but that does not preclude a<lb/>
rational participation in the life of the community and a sincere interest in<lb/>
its problems and projects.</p>
<p>Thus the life that you have chosen is rich in opportunities. To<lb/>
you the days will not be empty but brimming over with a manifold wealth of<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03184003"/>
experience<unclear>.</unclear> Your training and calling do not narrow, but rather they broaden<lb/>
your opportunities of service as a useful citizen of the Republic. One of<lb/>
your greatest opportunities for service will be the voluntary observance of the<lb/>
laws of the State in which you live and of the Nation whose laws you will take<lb/>
oath to obey.</p>
<p>Laws and rules of conduct are devised to assure a peaceful and or-<lb/>
derly existence of individuals and states. Let us always remember that no<lb/>
war ever will be waged without the violation of some law. No blood ever will<lb/>
be shed on a battlefield if statutes and treaties are faithfully kept. The<lb/>
habit of observance of domestic law will breed respect for international ob-<lb/>
ligations. Yours is a profession which upholds and restores peace. There-<lb/>
fore, no greater opportunity for service lies before you than the voluntary<lb/>
observance of the law. Yours is the obligation and the opportunity to become<lb/>
leaders in high thinking and right living in the communities where you will be<lb/>
stationed. The President, your Commander-in-Chief, has indicated that he<lb/>
expects you not only to do your duty as officers of the Army but also to per-<lb/>
form faithfully the no less important duties of citizenship. Even two hundred<lb/>
years ago Frederick the Great charged officers with similar responsibilities<lb/>
when he said &ldquo;I expect above all that an officer shall be an honest man and a<lb/>
good citizen of the State; without these qualities all his abilities and all<lb/>
his skill in war will be harmful rather than profitable.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The War Department is cognizant of the great opportunities opening<lb/>
to the Army for rendering public service of a broad character and conferences<lb/>
are called from time to time in which the outstanding leaders of the professions<lb/>
meet with our Department representatives and give us their ideas as to how the<lb/>
Army can promote within its own sphere the interests of citizenship, religion,<lb/>
education and other nationwide activities and programs. We can still pioneer<lb/>
and open the way for the further progress of our country and it is our duty to<lb/>
aspire to such accomplishment wherever and whenever such activities will not<lb/>
prejudice our primary functions of being efficiently prepared to protect and<lb/>
support the will of our people as expressed and represented through their con-<lb/>
stituted civil officials.</p>
<p>To take advantage of all these new opportunities to use your train-<lb/>
ing and talents in the public service is your bounden duty. Seek out these<lb/>
opportunities and approach your problems high mindedly, without selfish con-<lb/>
sideration of your personal ends.</p>
<p>Your importance as the leaders of the future cannot be over-estimated.<lb/>
There is no one of you that has not the capacity to exert more influence on the<lb/>
shaping of our national destiny than has our largest battleship or strongest<lb/>
fort.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Not in hewn stones,<lb/>
Nor well-fashioned beams,<lb/>
Not in the noblest of the builder's dreams;<lb/>
But in courageous men of purpose great,<lb/>
There is the fortress, there is the living state.&rdquo;</p>
<p>You may entertain the notion that these great opportunities for pub-<lb/>
lic service are only open to the generals and colonels and you may think that<lb/>
I have lost sight of the fact that tomorrow you will be putting your foot on<lb/>
the bottom rung of the ladder that leads as far as you will to climb it. Let<lb/>
me remind you that in human service there is no low or high degree. The un-<lb/>
selfish service to the public welfare of the second lieutenant is as sublime<lb/>
in motive and generosity as the service of the major general. &ldquo;To be great<lb/>
within his own authority and to prepare for being great in a higher area should<lb/>
be the true aim of loyalty.&rdquo; Some of the purest sacrifices to service have<lb/>
been laid on the altar of the common weal by lieutenants in our Army.</p>
<p>One of the many was Zebulon Pike who was a lieutenant but 27 years<lb/>
old when he began his great expedition. For nine months this young officer<lb/>
and his faithful band of twenty enlisted men made their way through unknown<lb/>
wastes, continually exposed to hardships and peril, depending for provisions on<lb/>
the precarious fortunes of the chase, enduring the most savage cold and cheer-<lb/>
fully submitting to the most constant and harassing toils. They went for days<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03184004"/>
without food and slept without cover on the bare earth, or the snow, during the<lb/>
frightful rigors of a northern winter. We see this young lieutenant, without<lb/>
violence or fraud inducing Indian tribes to submit to the Government of the<lb/>
United States, putting an end to the savage warfare which for years had been<lb/>
carried on with the utmost rancor and cruelty between the Sioux and the Chip-<lb/>
pewas. He also everywhere enforced the laws of the United States against sup-<lb/>
plying the savages with intoxicating licquors. The Government never had a more<lb/>
discreet and patriotic representative. He had no idol but his country's good<lb/>
and patriotic duty was the shining star that guided his career. His service to<lb/>
the nation was great in peace and war and he died in battle at Toronto with the<lb/>
captured flag of the enemy for his death pillow. His note-book, sodden with his<lb/>
blood, contained his inheritance to his young son. It was not wealth nor the<lb/>
title to vast estate but the two precious rules for guidance. &ldquo;First, preserve<lb/>
your honor from blemish. Second, be ready at all times to die for your coun-<lb/>
try.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The self-sacrifice and devoted love of country of Pike are rivalled<lb/>
by that of Walter Reed, who made his own opportunities to achieve in time of<lb/>
peace victories in behalf of humanity that are as great and far-reaching in<lb/>
their effect on man's happiness as any won on the battlefield. Like Pike he<lb/>
did not make personal success his one object in life to which all other aims were<lb/>
subordinated but his constant and unselfish devotion was to the need of others,<lb/>
and the great lesson of his life is that the secret of usefulness and happiness<lb/>
lies rather in giving what we can <hi>to</hi> life, than in getting what we can <hi>from</hi> it.<lb/>
It was his persistent adherence to this principle of conduct and endeavor that<lb/>
raised him morally so high above his fellows. His idealism is beautifully ex-<lb/>
pressed in a passage from a letter to his wife, written after his great discovery,<lb/>
in which he said: &ldquo;The prayer that has been mine for twenty years, that I<lb/>
might be permitted in some way or at some time, to do something to alleviate<lb/>
human suffering has been granted.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Pike and Reed were young junior officers when they were devoting all<lb/>
their energies to national service and so was Nathan Hale when he looked his<lb/>
last on the blue sky with eyes alight with patriotic fervor and testified with<lb/>
his life that:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Whether on the scaffold high,<lb/>
Or in the battle's van,<lb/>
The fittest place where man can die<lb/>
Is where he dies for man.&rdquo;</p>
<p>How different is the immortality of Pike and Reed and Hale who lived<lb/>
and died for others to the notoriety achieved by famous men who lived only for<lb/>
self-aggrandizement. Napoleon was undoubtedly more highly endowed with the<lb/>
qualities of intellectual greatness than any of these. Never was such a<lb/>
leader weaponed with powers of command over the rest of men. For a time he<lb/>
worked for the welfare of France but he quickly put self above the public in-<lb/>
terest. The little while that he strove sincerely to further the interests<lb/>
of his country he rose to supreme heights of personal glory and power but once<lb/>
he put his own claims before the good of humanity he started down the dreadful<lb/>
road to ruin and destruction. Emerson says that: &ldquo;The Man of Destiny did<lb/>
all that in him lay to live and thrive without moral principle. His was an<lb/>
experiment under the most favorable conditions, to test the power of intellect<lb/>
without conscience. It was the nature of things, the eternal law of man and<lb/>
of the world, which balked and ruined him; and the result, in a million at-<lb/>
tempts of this kind, will be the same.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I have referred to Napoleon because he is history's outstanding<lb/>
example of the failure of personal ambition but all through history we may find<lb/>
the stories of men who made selfish use of wealth and authority, who rose to<lb/>
great power only to have that power wrested from them by the community or death<lb/>
and then to go down to be buried in outer darkness and oblivion. Those who<lb/>
are still remembered, like Napoleon, are remembered only as horrible examples<lb/>
of the ultimate fate of selfishness and small-minded, soulless ambition. For<lb/>
a time their fame filled the world, then flickered out like those stars which,<lb/>
brightening for a moment into splendor, die down again to the lowest magnitude,<lb/>
consumed by their own internal fires.</p>
<p>The leaderships that have lived in the heart of humanity and the<lb/>
leaderships that are dear to the American people are those which have been true<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03184005"/>
to ideals and institutions based on conceptions of human welfare, <unclear>justice</unclear> and<lb/>
service to others. &ldquo;No man has come to true greatness who has not felt in<lb/>
some degree that his life belongs to his race, and that what God gives him He<lb/>
gives him for man-kind.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;If we call the roll of the sons of greatness and influence we shall<lb/>
see that they are also the sons of self-sacrifice.&rdquo;</p>
<p>And so I ask you not to be concerned with the welfare of the Army<lb/>
alone. Be solicitous for the national welfare. After all, the object of the<lb/>
Army is to safeguard that welfare in all its aspects and to protect the bigger<lb/>
and broader life of our whole citizenship and maintain the principles upon which<lb/>
our Government was founded. The Army expects you to conform to high standards<lb/>
that it has set before you but do not be content with measuring up to required<lb/>
standards. You have refinement of spirit, breadth of sympathy, physical and<lb/>
moral courage. We are not looking for too much when we expect from you new<lb/>
thoughts and new achievements. The greatest victories are yet to be won.<lb/>
The greatest deeds are yet to be done. Alexander, Caesar, Hannibal and Gus-<lb/>
tavus Adolphus won great victories but they left some for Washington, Grant and<lb/>
Pershing. They once said that Wood and Reed would get nowhere because they<lb/>
were only &ldquo;medicos&rdquo; but their names are inscribed in letters of gold on our<lb/>
national role of honor.</p>
<p>We know not what the future has in store for us. The winds of des-<lb/>
tiny may guide us surely into the calm of unbroken peace or swing us into the<lb/>
troubled waters of unrest. No man can tell whether the nation will avail it-<lb/>
self of your talents and character in the awful test of war but whether the<lb/>
years bring peace or conflict we know that they will bring for our nation and<lb/>
what it stands for grander triumphs, more splendid victories than have yet been<lb/>
won.</p>
<p>Your plain duty is to face peace as you would face war - giving all<lb/>
that is in you, without stint of measure, to the service of this blessed land<lb/>
that contains the hopes of mankind. This country of ours depends on men like<lb/>
you. &ldquo;Our hope is in heroic men, star-led to build the world again.&rdquo; Your<lb/>
character and your service is more important than mines and railroads and fertile<lb/>
fields. &ldquo;The history of the nation is the history of the men who compose the<lb/>
nation, and not of their dwelling place.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Cling to your ideals as you would cling to the flag placed in your<lb/>
keeping. They will carry you farther on the road to happiness and honor than<lb/>
ever would selfishness or expediency. I envy you your youth and enthusiasm<lb/>
but most of all I envy the opportunity that is yours to spend all the coming<lb/>
years in the service of such a country. The Army receives you with open arms<lb/>
and beckons you to new fields of endeavor and achievement.</p>
<p>E N D</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT (6-11-29) - FUTURE</p>
<p>FOR RELEASE IN THE AFTERNOON PAPERS<lb/>
OF THURSDAY, JUNE 13, 1929.</p>
<p>- 5 -</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
