<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03207001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 27, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03207001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-08-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Root, Elihu</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Hamann, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-08-27">August 27, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03207001</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 27, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean lists the yellow fever experiment participants included in the Roll of Honor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-08-27">
<head>Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 27, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03207001"/>
<opener>
Y.F.<lb/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
For Adt, Gen-<lb/>
<dateline>
Assoc's Military Surgeons, U.S.<lb/>
<date value="1929-08-27">August 27, 1929</date>
??? Editor's Office<lb/>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>ROLL OF HONOR.</p>
<p>The Secretary of War, Hon. Elihu Root, in his annual report <unclear>1903</unclear><lb/>
said with reference to the conquest of yellow fever in Cuba in 1900-1901:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The brilliant character of this scientific achievement, its<lb/>
inestimable value to mankind, the saving of thousands of lives, and<lb/>
the deliverance of the Atlantic seacoast from constant apprehension,<lb/>
demand special recognition from the Government of the United States.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Congress has, in concurrence with this opinion, by an Act<lb/>
approved February 28th, 1929 authorized and directed the Secretary<lb/>
of War to publish annually in the Army Register a Roll of Honor on<lb/>
which shall be carried the following names, and to define in appropriate<lb/>
language the part which each of these persons played in the experiments<lb/>
during the yellow fever investigations in Cuba.</p>
<p>MAJOR WALTER REED, Surgeon U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 13 September, 1851 in Gloucester Co., Virginia. He graduated in<lb/>
medicine at the University of Va., and entered the Army 1875. When sent to<lb/>
Cuba in June 1900 at the head of the Yellow Fever Board of medical officers,<lb/>
Reed was already a distinguished man. In the Spanish War he had been at the<lb/>
head of another famous Medical Board which studied the camp epidemics of<lb/>
Typhoid Fever in the Army during that war, and made a great advance in our<lb/>
knowledge of the spread of that formidable disease in Armies. He was professor<lb/>
of pathology and bacteriology at the Army Medical School, and also at the<lb/>
Columbian University in Washington, and stood high in his profession. In the<lb/>
work of the Yellow Fever Board he shared their labors and dangers, but his was<lb/>
always the originating, directing, and controlling mind.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> He died in Washington<lb/>
D.C., 23 November, 1902, following an operation for appendicitis.</p>
<p>-------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>(I). Address of Gen. Leonard Wood, p.48- Yellow Fever A Compilation, S. No. 822</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03207002"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>DR. JAMES CARROLL, Acting Assistant Surgeon, U.S. Army, later Major Medical Depart-<lb/>
ment.</p>
<p>Born in England 10 March, 1854. He enlisted in the U.S. Army in 1874, and<lb/>
served until 1898 in each of the non-commissioned grades from corporal to first<lb/>
sergeant and then as hospital steward. He took advantage of his opportunities<lb/>
to study medicine, and when on duty in Washington under Reed to graduate as a<lb/>
Doctor of Medicine. In 1898 he was appointed an Acting Assistant Surgeon, and<lb/>
assigned to duty as Reed's assistant. Early in the study of the agency of the<lb/>
mosquito as the transmitter of yellow fever, he volunteered to be bitten by an<lb/>
infected mosquito. On 31 August, 1900 he became ill and suffered a very severe<lb/>
attack of that disease. His was the first experimental case. He returned to<lb/>
Cuba a year later to make special studies of the blood of yellow fever patients.<lb/>
He died in Washington, D.C., 16 September, 1907, having been promoted to the<lb/>
grade of Major, Medical Department by special authority of Congress in recogni-<lb/>
tion of his services as a member of the Yellow Fever Board.</p>
<p>DR. ARISTIDES AGRAMONTE, Acting Assistant Surgeon, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born in Cuba in 1869, the son of a Cuban Officer who fell in battle against<lb/>
the Spaniards. He grew up and was educated in New York where his mother had<lb/>
taken refuge, and graduated in medicine at Columbia University where he was the<lb/>
classmate of Lazear. He entered the Army in 1898 and when appointed a member of<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Board was with the Army in Havana in charge of the Army Medical<lb/>
Laboratory. His special qualifications as a pathologist, and his energy and<lb/>
ability contributed greatly to the success of the Board. Of especial value were<lb/>
his contributions to the demonstration by the Board disproving the then generally<lb/>
accepted theory that the bacillus icteroides was the causative agent of yellow<lb/>
fever. He is now Professor of Pathology at the Medical School of the University<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03207003"/>
-3-<lb/>
of Havana, and is the only member of the Board now living.</p>
<p>DR. JESSE W. LAZEAR, Acting Assistant Surgeon, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born in Maryland 2 May, 1866. He graduated in Medicine at Columbia<lb/>
University, N.Y., and did postgraduate work at the Pasteur Institute in Paris,<lb/>
and at Johns Hopkins University, specializing in mosquitoes and their relation<lb/>
to malarial infections. When the Yellow Fever Board was organized he was already<lb/>
in Cuba on duty with troops, and was studying yellow fever. He had charge of<lb/>
the mosquitow work of the Board when he contracted yellow fever while visiting<lb/>
yellow fever patients in order to infect mosquitoes for experimental purposes.<lb/>
He died 25 September, 1900 of this disease, a martyr to science. By his special<lb/>
knowledge and brilliant scientific attainments, as well as by the invaluable<lb/>
notes of his observations made in the last weeks of his life which he left,<lb/>
he contributed in the highest degree to the successful outcome of the investigation.</p>
<p>? JAMES A. ANDRUS<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, Private Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born in Fassett, Pennsylvania in 1879, volunteered for experiment and was<lb/>
infected with yellow fever by an injection of blood from an experimental case.<lb/>
He became ill 28 January, 1901, being the 12th case in the series of cases at<lb/>
Camp Lazear. He left the Army in 1902 with character excellent.</p>
<p>JOHN R. BULLARD,</p>
<p>Born in Massachusetts, and a graduate of Harvard University where he was a<lb/>
distinguished athlete. Came to Cuba and was treated by Dr. James Carroll at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks for malarial fever. Becoming interested in the yellow fever<lb/>
work, he volunteered and received on 15 October, 1901 an injection of the filtered<lb/>
-------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>
(2) See memo to Adjutant General herewith.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03207004"/>
-4-<lb/>
blood of a Spaniard, an experimental case. Slight fever and discomfort were<lb/>
caused, but no illness. N week later he received a blood injection from the<lb/>
veins of an American soldier who had been infected by an injection of filtered<lb/>
blood, and became ill with yellow fever 23 October, 1901. Having thus become<lb/>
immune, he continued to reside in Cuba after his recovery.</p>
<p>A.W. COVINGTON, Private 23rd Battery, C.A.C.</p>
<p>Born 1877 in Laurinburg, North Carolina. Volunteered for experiment in the<lb/>
third series of cases when it was well understood that yellow fever would be<lb/>
the result. He was given at 11.05 A.M., 15 October, 1901 a subcutaneous injection<lb/>
of 3 c.c. of the diluted and filtered blood serum from an experimental case of<lb/>
yellow fever. He became ill 19 October with a typical attack of yellow fever,<lb/>
from which he made a good recovery, and was returned to duty with his battery.<lb/>
He remained in service twenty five years thereafter, being retired 9 August, 1926.</p>
<p>WILLIAM H. DEAN, Troop B. 7th Cavalry.</p>
<p>Born 1877 in Holland, Ohio. He was the second case of experimental yellow<lb/>
fever, being that which convinced the Board that the theory of its conveyance<lb/>
by mosquitoes was well grounded, and being mentioned in their preliminary report<lb/>
as the Case X.Y. He volunteered and was bitten 31 August, 1900 by the same mos-<lb/>
quito which had infected Dr. Carroll four days before. He was also bitten by two<lb/>
other mosquitoes which had bitten a fatal case of yellow fever 12 days before,<lb/>
and a fourth mosquito which had been fed on three severe cases of yellow fever.<lb/>
He became ill 7 September, 1900 and suffered a well marked case ofnyellow fever.<lb/>
He left the service 17 August, 1902, with an excellent character, and died 3 May,<lb/>
1928.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03207005"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>WALLACE W. FORBES, Private, Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1878 in Galesburg, Illinois. He volunteered for experiment and received<lb/>
22 January, 1901 an injection of half a cubic centimeter of blood from a case of<lb/>
experimental yellow fever. Two days later he became ill and suffered a severe<lb/>
attack of yellow fever. Private Forbes was discharged from the Army four years<lb/>
later with character excellent.</p>
<p>LEVI E. FOLK, Private Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1870 in Kadish, South Carolina. He volunteered for experiment, and<lb/>
was one of the group who underwent the trying ordeal of sleeping twenty one con-<lb/>
secutive nights in the soiled bedding used by yellow fever patients. This experi-<lb/>
ment was of vast importance commercially as well as scientifically, as it upset the<lb/>
accepted belief as to how the disease was transmitted, and resulted in the aboli-<lb/>
tion of expensive disinfections. He later was bitten by infected mosquitoes, and<lb/>
on 23 January suffered an attack of yellow fever of moderate severity, this showing<lb/>
that he was susceptible to the disease when he slept in the infected bedding. He<lb/>
was retired in 1923 after twenty five years of honorable service.</p>
<p>PAUL HAMANN, Private 23rd Battery, C.A.C.</p>
<p>Born 1876 in Germany and enlisted at Springfield, Illinois. He volunteered<lb/>
for experiment, being one of the third group of volunteers, and was infected by<lb/>
Dr. Carroll with filtered blood serum at the same time with Private Covington. He<lb/>
became sick on 19 October, 1901 and suffered a moderately severe attack of yellow<lb/>
fever. After fifteen years service he was discharged 12 August, 1913 with<lb/>
character excellent.</p>
<p>JAMES E. HANBERRY, Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1875 in Denmark, South Carolina. He volunteered for experiment, and<lb/>
was one of the group <del>ofxxxx</del> who slept twenty one consecutive nights on bedding<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03207006"/>
-6-<lb/>
which had been used by yellow fever patients, and was soiled with their bloody<lb/>
discharges. He also wore at night the soiled garments of the sick. Some weeks<lb/>
after this disagreeable, and as it was then thought dangerous, experience, he<lb/>
was bitten by the same two mosquitoes which had a few days before infected a<lb/>
companion, and on 9 February, 1901, came down with a severe attack of this painful<lb/>
disease. He left the service in 1902.</p>
<p>WARREN G. JERNEGAN, Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1872 in Cone, Florida. He volunteered for experiment and was one of<lb/>
the group of seven who underwent the long and trying ordeal of sleeping in the<lb/>
soiled and infected bedding and clothing of yellow fever patients. He then, on<lb/>
28 and 29 December, 1900, submitted to the bites of infected mosquitoes, but<lb/>
escaped infection. On 4 January, 1901 he received an injection of blood from a<lb/>
case of experimental yellow fever (Martinez) and suffered a sharp attack of that<lb/>
disease. He left the military service at the expiration of his enlistment with<lb/>
character excellent, and went to Panama where he was employed in the Canal service<lb/>
for a number of years. He died 5 February, 1919, in Charleston, South Carolina.</p>
<p>JOHN R. KISSINGER, Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1877 in McClure, Ohio, and enlisted for the Spanish War at Indianapolis,<lb/>
Ind. He and Moran were the first to volunteer of those who underwent the conclu-<lb/>
sive experiments <del>experiments</del> at Camp Lazear where they occupied the same tent.<lb/>
On 20 Nov., 1900 he was bitten by three infected mosquitoes. On 23 November he<lb/>
was bitten by one of the same three and on 5 December he was again bitten by<lb/>
five mosquitoes, two of which had been infected by fatal cases. On 9 December<lb/>
he became ill and suffered a typical attack of yellow fever. His was the first<lb/>
case of experimental yellow fever in the series at Camp Lazear. Of him Major<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03207007"/>
-7-<lb/>
Walter Reed said: &ldquo;In my opinion this exhibition of moral courage has never<lb/>
been surpassed in the annals of the Army of the United States&rdquo;. He was<lb/>
discharged from the service 14 November, 1901, with character excellent.</p>
<p>JOHN J. MORAN,</p>
<p>Born in Ohio and served as a Volunteer in the 2nd Division VII Army Corps.<lb/>
After his discharge with character excellent he was employed as a clerk at the<lb/>
Department Headquarters at Marianao. He there did clerical work for Major Reed<lb/>
and became interested in the work of the Yellow Fever Board. He and Kissinger<lb/>
were the first to volunteer for the conclusive series of experiments at Camp Lazear.<lb/>
He was bitten on 26 and 29 November by infected mosquitoes, but without result.<lb/>
On 21 December, 1900 he twice visited the infected mosquito room, and again next<lb/>
day, and was repeatedly bitten. On Christmas Day he became ill, and suffered<lb/>
a well marked and severe attack of yellow fever. Moran refused to accept the<lb/>
bonus which was given by the Governor of Cuba to each volunteer, stating that he<lb/>
was glad to be able to do this service to humanity. He afterwards served for some<lb/>
years at Panama during the construction of the Canal, and is now a resident of<lb/>
Havana.</p>
<p>WILLIAM OLSEN, Private Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1874 in Pierce Co., Wisconsin. He enlisted for the Spanish War and came<lb/>
to Cuba where he volunteered for the experimental work of the Yellow Fever Board<lb/>
at Camp Lazear. He was one of a group of four who were given injections of blood<lb/>
from a case of experimental yellow fever at the Camp, the Spaniard Martines, in<lb/>
order to decide certain questions of scientific importance. He was taken ill<lb/>
with yellow fever 11 January 1901. Private Olsen was discharged on expiration<lb/>
of his enlistment 15 November, 1901 with character excellent.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f03207008"/>
<p>-8-</p>
<p>CHARLES C. SONNTAG, Private Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1872 at Charleston, South Carolina. He volunteered for the experiments<lb/>
at Camp Lazear, and was bitten by two infected mosquitoes and came down with<lb/>
yellow fever 10 February, 1901, being the last case in the series at Camp Lazear.<lb/>
He took his discharge 12 December, 1901, with character very good.</p>
<p>CLYDE L. WEST, Private Hospital Corps, U.S. Army,</p>
<p>Born 1877 in Mier, Indiana. He enlisted at Toledo, Ohio for the Spanish<lb/>
War, and came to Cuba where, while serving at Columbia Barracks, he volunteered<lb/>
for the experiments at Camp Lazear. He was infected in the mosquito room by the<lb/>
bites of two mosquitoes which had bitten a case of yellow fever 51 days before.<lb/>
These caused a mild attack of yellow fever three days later on 9 February, 1901.<lb/>
Six days later these same mosquitoes caused the very severe case of Hanberry in<lb/>
which his life for several days hung in the balance. Private West was discharged<lb/>
10 July, 1902, with character very good.</p>
<p>ROBERT P. COOKE, Acting Assistant Surgeon, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1874 in Virginia. He entered the Medical service of the Army 9 June,<lb/>
1900, and was on duty at Pinar del Rio during the yellow fever epidemic in the<lb/>
garrison there. He volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear and with two<lb/>
privates, Folk and Jernegan, were the first to undergo the trying ordeal of<lb/>
sleeping 21 successive nights in the soiled bedding used by yellow fever patients.<lb/>
This was to determine whether the disease could be transmitted by infected bedding,<lb/>
clothing, and other objects. This experiment was of vast importance not only in<lb/>
making clear the method of transmission of the disease, but to the commerce of the<lb/>
world. Dr. Cooke resigned from the Army 2 December, 1904.</p>
<p>THOMAS M. ENGLAND, Private Hospital Corps, U.S. Army, now Captain Medical Administra-<lb/>
tive Corps.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f03207009"/>
<p>-9-</p>
<p>Born 1876 in Ohio. He enlisted for the Spanish War and came to Cuba with<lb/>
the VII Army Corps. He volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear, and under-<lb/>
went the trying ordeal of sleeping 20 nights in the beds formerly occupied by a<lb/>
yellow fever patient, and in the garment worn by him. His head lay on a towel<lb/>
stained with the blood of a case of yellow fever. He remained in the Army, serving in<lb/>
all the non-commissioned grades of the Medical Department, and won his commission<lb/>
in that Department during the World War.</p>
<p>JAMES HILDEBRAND, Private Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1862 in Georgia. Served in the Spanish War and came to Cuba with the<lb/>
VII Army Corps. He volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear, and with England<lb/>
underwent the trying ordeal of sleeping 20 nights, 11 Jan. to 31 Jan., 1901, in the<lb/>
bed and the garment used by a yellow fever patient, and with his pillow covered by<lb/>
a towel stained with yellow fever blood. Hildebrand then offered to be bitten by<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, but Major Reed refused to permit this as he was much older than<lb/>
the other volunteers, and the mortality in yellow fever is much increased with age.<lb/>
He was discharged 17 August, 1914 with character excellent.</p>
<p>EDWARD WEATHERWALKS, Private Hospital Corps, U.S. Army.</p>
<p>Born 1874 in New Jersey. He enlisted for the Spanish War and came to Cuba with<lb/>
the VII Army Corps. He volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear and underwent<lb/>
the trying ordeal of sleeping 21 nights, 21 December, 1900 to 10 January, 1901<lb/>
inclusive, on bedding which had been used by yellow fever patients and was soiled with<lb/>
their bloody discharges. He wore at night the soiled garments of the sick. As<lb/>
this experiment, like the other exposures to infected clothing had no result, Weather-<lb/>
walks was bitten on 25 January, 1901, by twelve infected mosquitoes, but for some<lb/>
reason not known escaped infection. He was discharged 21 December, 1901, with<lb/>
character good, and died 21 October, 1916.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f03207010"/>
<p>MEMORANDUM FOR THE ADJUTANT GENERAL.</p>
<p>With reference to the military records of the enlisted men and<lb/>
Mr. John J. Moran, who was a discharged soldier, the records of the<lb/>
Surgeon General's Office, and data received by that office from the<lb/>
Adjutant General do not show the records in the Spanish War of these<lb/>
men. It is recommended that this be looked up, and that it be stated<lb/>
with regard to each one the fact that he served during the Spanish War,<lb/>
if such was a fact, and the volunteer regiment or organization of the<lb/>
Regular Army in which they enlisted, with the date. The members of the<lb/>
Hospital Corps taking part in these experiments were nearly all men who<lb/>
had served in volunteer regiments, and had enlisted in the Hospital<lb/>
Corps when their organizations were mustered out of the service.</p>
<closer>
<signed><hi>JR Kean</hi></signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
