<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03214001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Interview with Merritte W. Ireland, by [Jessie Daniel Ames], October 22, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03214001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-10-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-10-22">October 22, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03214001</idno>
<title>Interview with Merritte W. Ireland, by [Jessie Daniel Ames], October 22, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ireland refuses to include Ames among the yellow fever heroes. He minimizes Ames' role in the yellow fever work, and advises [Jessie Daniel Ames] to give up in her attempt to have him honored.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-10-22">
<head>Interview with Merritte W. Ireland, by [Jessie Daniel Ames], October 22, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03214001"/>
<opener>
From Mrs Ames<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1929-10-22">October 22nd, 1929.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Interview with Surgeon General Ireland - October 22nd, 1929.</p>
<p>General Ireland is brusque and plain-spoken accord-<lb/>
ing to his picture of himself. He left the impression that he was<lb/>
following bulldozing tactics to beat down any initiative. He<lb/>
started out by accusing me of reflecting discreditably upon the<lb/>
memory of Doctor Ames in a letter written to his Department last<lb/>
spring, and upbraiding me. He said Doctor Ames' record was be-<lb/>
yond reproach and advised me to forget the whole affair. Since<lb/>
General Ireland objects to having words put in his mouth, I shall<lb/>
add that those were his exact words but his gestures and his tones<lb/>
of voice made me feel that he meant me to go back home and forget<lb/>
the whole question of recognition and he would charitably forget<lb/>
that I had dishonored the memory of my husband. In reply to my<lb/>
statement that his department was the guilty party he brusquely<lb/>
informed me that he had no sympathy with me. In reply to the<lb/>
statement that I was not asking for sympathy, he said he meant<lb/>
with my attitude. He made me feel that he thought I was guilty<lb/>
of lesemajesty if not treason in imputing guilt to the Department.<lb/>
He also said the less said about my husband being non-immune and<lb/>
having had Yellow Fever the better, and again he told me &ldquo;to for-<lb/>
get it&rdquo;. He did admit that the official war record did show that<lb/>
Doctor Ames had had Yellow Fever and while in the Experimental<lb/>
Camp. He left me under the impression that he was trying to con-<lb/>
vey to me that there was something discreditable; something which<lb/>
should he hushed up; if it were pushed back too far something<lb/>
highly unpleasant would be discovered from which he was trying to<lb/>
shield me. He said that the record of the case was official, cer-<lb/>
tified to by Major Alex Stark. I felt that as with Colonel Kean<lb/>
that this fact embarrassed him. He said that Doctor Ames had<lb/>
had a wonderful opportunity to serve, a privilege which he, General<lb/>
Ireland, would have welcomed. He also said that literally thou-<lb/>
sands of persons were seeking recognition. He inferred to my mind<lb/>
that every one in Cuba during active hostilities and throughout<lb/>
the occupation of Cuba might be considered as eligible as Doctor<lb/>
Ames. He spoke three times of a guard who served at the Experi-<lb/>
mental Camp seeking recognition. He seemed to imply that the<lb/>
guard and Doctor Ames made a contribution of equal value. How-<lb/>
ever, when asked if he did, he brusquely denied that was his<lb/>
intention, but I could take it that way if I wished. He said<lb/>
that the whole affair started thro an interest a Mr. Peabody took<lb/>
in the case of the private Kissinger, who was paralyzed from his<lb/>
waist down. He said that no doubt I knew how the women were added.<lb/>
I did not ask him to enlarge, but I did not know. He said he<lb/>
did not know what other surgeons, if any, were with Doctor Ames<lb/>
in charge of the camps. Colonel Kean would know. He said Doctor<lb/>
Ames had a wonderful record, one of which to be proud. That no<lb/>
one who had received recognition had sought it. That it had<lb/>
come unsought and tho he knew my husband slightly that he knew<lb/>
that he would never be seeking recognition for his services but<lb/>
that the consciousness of services rendered and a noble duty<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03214002"/>
done would be sufficient. When reminded that Doctor Ames had<lb/>
been dead fourteen years, he said he knew it. Again he made me<lb/>
feel as tho he was trying to convey to me that I was doing some-<lb/>
thing unworthy of my husband. He said that he and Colonel Kean<lb/>
had told me of the wonderful service my husband rendered and what<lb/>
more should I want? When he was asked how this would be trans-<lb/>
mitted to Doctor Ames' children, two of whom never knew their<lb/>
father, and the other only vaguely, he replied by asking what I<lb/>
wanted. When I told him that I wanted the same recognition for<lb/>
my husband who was the trained expert in charge of the camps and<lb/>
who was a non-immune and who had had Yellow Fever while the work<lb/>
was on, he said he would never agree to add Doctor Ames' name<lb/>
to that Act since it was limited to those who offered their<lb/>
bodies and who did the scientific work (possibly meaning labora-<lb/>
tory work) and that for me never to believe that had not Doctor<lb/>
Ames offered his services, trained as they were, there would no<lb/>
have been hundreds of others who would have. Again he left me<lb/>
under the impression that he was making light of the work done<lb/>
by Doctor Ames and that I should feel the same. He agreed to<lb/>
collaborate with Colonel Kean and write an official testimony<lb/>
of my husband's record in Cuba when I should make such a request<lb/>
of the Adjutant General.</p>
<p>Our interview was one hour long. I judge General<lb/>
Ireland to be of that type of military man who refuses to alter<lb/>
his stand, feeling that no officer can make a wrong decision.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
