<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03212001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Richard M. Hewitt to the Editor, New Orleans Medical and Surgical Journal, September 17, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03212001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-09-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hearn, Lafcadio</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Hendrick, Burton J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Gould, George M.</name>
<name type="person">Matas, Rudolph</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-09-17">September 17, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03212001</idno>
<title>Letter from Richard M. Hewitt to the Editor, New Orleans Medical and Surgical Journal, September 17, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hewitt writes about the 1878 New Orleans yellow fever outbreak and Carter's work on the transmission of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1929-09-17">
<head>Letter from Richard M. Hewitt to the Editor, New Orleans Medical and Surgical Journal, September 17, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03212001"/>
<opener>
From Dr Hewitt<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
<hi>Aug 43</hi><lb/>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
A letter of Lafcadio Hearn and an Old File of the<lb/>
New Orleans Medical and Surgical Journal<lb/>
<salute>To the editor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Do you think your colleagues would be interested<lb/>
to recall a passage from a letter of a one-time resident of New<lb/>
Orleans, and to follow the train of thought it aroused?</p>
<p>The other day, I was reading &ldquo;The Life and Letters<lb/>
of Lafacadio Hearn&rdquo; and, in a letter written to H. E. Krebiel, in<lb/>
1878, I found the following description of an outbreak of yellow<lb/>
1<lb/>
fever in New Orleans:</p>
<p>"All over town there are little white notices<lb/>
pasted on the lamp-posts or the pillars of piazzas, bearing<lb/>
the dismal words:</p>
<p>&ldquo;D&eacute;c&eacute;d&eacute;<lb/>
Ce matin, &agrave; 3 1/2 heures<lb/>
Julien<lb/>
Natif de---,<lb/>
and so on. The death notices are usually surmounted by<lb/>
an atrocious out of a weeping widow sitting beneath a<lb/>
weeping willow - with a huge mausoleum in the background.<lb/>
Yellow fever deaths occur every day close by. Somebody<lb/>
is advocating firing off cannon as a preventive. This<lb/>
plan of shooting Yellow Jack was tried in '53 without<lb/>
success. It brings on rain; but a rainy day always heralds<lb/>
an increase of the plague. You will see by the <hi>Item's</hi><lb/>
tabulated record that there is a curious periodicity in the<lb/>
increase. It might be described by a line like this -<lb/>
(Here is a rough curve of frequency, with irregularly placed<lb/>
peaks of irregular height. R.M.H.) You have doubtless seen<lb/>
the records of pulsations made by a certain instrument, for<lb/>
detecting the rapidity of blood-circulation. The fever<lb/>
actually appears to have a pulsation of graduated increase<lb/>
like that of a feverish vein. I think this demonstrates a<lb/>
regularity in the periods of germ incubation, affected, of<lb/>
course, more or less by atmospheric changes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The letter itself interested me because of the tragedies<lb/>
it recorded and the quaintness of the notices of death described.<lb/>
It seemed strange, also, that the mind of one who apparently<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03212002"/>
Hewitt -2-<lb/>
was a purely artistic genius should be thinking in terms of<lb/>
phlebograms, &ldquo;germ incubation&rdquo; and periodicity of epidemic<lb/>
disease.</p>
<p>The evening on which I read this letter was not<lb/>
a very busy one and there was time for a picture to come to mind.<lb/>
It was of a crippled old man, with a benevolent face, standing<lb/>
on the floor of a large room in the Century Club in Panama. He<lb/>
was addressing a meeting at which were assembled some of the<lb/>
world's foremost authorities in tropical medicine, and the room was<lb/>
quiet with respect for that old man. He was Henry Rose Carter.<lb/>
2<lb/>
&ldquo;Even today,&rdquo; write M. D. Gorgas and B. J. Hendrick, &ldquo;Carter's work<lb/>
is not as well known to the layman as that of Reed and Gorgas, yet<lb/>
Gorgas himself said that &lsquo;it places Carter in the class of the great<lb/>
original workers of our time.&rsquo;&rsquo;</p>
<p>Physicians know that it was Henry Rose Carter who<lb/>
first showed &ldquo;that a lapse of twelve to fifteen days is necessary<lb/>
3<lb/>
before a case of yellow fever becomes dangerous to others.&rdquo; I<lb/>
thought it would be interesting to read exactly what Carter wrote;<lb/>
so I went to the clinic's file of the &ldquo;New Orleans Medical and<lb/>
Surgical Journal&rdquo;, and this is what I found at the conclusion of<lb/>
4<lb/>
Carter's original article:</p>
<p>"There is of course, no definite limit of time at<lb/>
which we would call the situation &ldquo;safe,&rdquo; or &ldquo;unsafe,&rdquo; but<lb/>
hope of safety increases with the passage of the third week,<lb/>
and as the time beyond this passes.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This law (one will admit it at least as a working<lb/>
hypothesis) is also of value in predicting the progress of an<lb/>
epidemic which will spread. From the first (infecting) case<lb/>
to the first group of cases, infected at his house, is generally<lb/>
from two to three weeks. These form now foci (the original<lb/>
one remaining active), and in from two to three weeks more the<lb/>
second group of cases appears. At this time, four to six weeks,<lb/>
the fever should be &ldquo;scattered&rdquo; in tertiary foci<del>a</del>, just beginning.<lb/>
Prior to this it is found <hi>only in those who have had a common<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03212003"/>
Hewitt -3-<lb/>
exposure</hi>, seldom then in more than four to eight places.<lb/>
although it is not the number, but the common exposure,<lb/>
that is in question.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Carter made his study in 1898 and published it in 1900.<lb/>
Hearn wrote his letter in 1878. Hearn's graph is just a pen<lb/>
scratch; Carter's study is a scientific triumph. Is it possible<lb/>
that the content of Hearn's letter is an example of that insight of<lb/>
which an artistic nature sometimes is capable, or had he received<lb/>
a hint on the incidence of the disease from his friend, Dr. George<lb/>
M. Gould of Philadelphia or Dr. Rodolfo Matas of New Orleans to<lb/>
whom he dedicated his story &ldquo;Chita&rdquo;?</p>
<closer>
<signed>Richard M. Hewitt, M.D.<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota</signed>
September 17, 1929<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-09-17">
<head><hi>Bibliography</hi></head>
<pb n="4" id="f03212004"/>
<opener>
-4-<lb/>
</opener>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>Bibliography</hi></head>
<item>1. Bisland, Elizabeth (Mrs. Wetmore): The life and letters of<lb/>
Lafcadio Hearn. New York, Houghton, Mifflin, 1906, i, p. 185.</item>
<item>2. Gorgas, M. D., and Hendrick, B. J.: William Crawford Gorgas: his<lb/>
life and work. Philadelphia, Lea and Febiger, 1924, p. 101.</item>
<item>3. Garrison, F. H.: An introduction to the history of medicine.<lb/>
Ed. 4, Philadelphia, W. B. Saunders Co., 1929, p. 718.</item>
<item>4. Carter, H. R.: A note on the interval between infecting and<lb/>
secondary cases of yellow fever from the records of the<lb/>
yellow fever at Oswood and Taylor, Mississippi, in 1898.<lb/>
New Orleans Med. and Surg. Jour., 1900, xlii, 617-636.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
