<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03217001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [James E. Peabody] to Jonathan Mayhew Wainwright, November 18, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Peabody, James E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03217001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-11-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Fosdick, Harry E.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Cumming, Hugh S.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Copeland, Royal S.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-11-18">November 18, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03217001</idno>
<title>Letter from [James E. Peabody] to Jonathan Mayhew Wainwright, November 18, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Peabody] thanks Wainwright for his support of the bill to honor the yellow fever experiment participants. Peabody is delighted that Agramonte was included, and glad that Marie Gorgas was not.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1929-11-18">
<head>Letter from [James E. Peabody] to Jonathan Mayhew Wainwright, November 18, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03217001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1929-11-18">November 18, 1929.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Col. Wainwright:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You must think me the most ungrateful man you ever met, not to have made<lb/>
any acknowledgement of your wonderful work in getting through Congress the Yel-<lb/>
low Fever <unclear>Bill</unclear>. You will forgive me, I am sure, when I tell you that I was<lb/>
ill with neurastheia from early in January to the last of October, and that<lb/>
the writing of even a short letter to my three children seemed impossible.<lb/>
I am in fine shape once more, and since I have retired from New York School<lb/>
teaching on full pension of approximately half pay, I have the disposing of<lb/>
my time, and am enjoying life to the full--busier than ever before, but with<lb/>
no necessity to rise at 5:30 every morning in order to get to school on time.</p>
<p>I enclose a carbon copy (sorry it is not better, but perhaps you can make<lb/>
it out if you read the marked paragraphs with a sheet of white paper beneath.)<lb/>
Cor Biology Committee plan to send this out to all members of the New York As-<lb/>
sociation of Biology Teachers, to all who contributed to the Kissinger Fund,<lb/>
and to the long list of those who have helped us in the cause. As you will<lb/>
see (<unclear>ps.</unclear> 3 and 4) I plan to give my lecture in two parts: the first will be<lb/>
an account of the experiments in Cuba that led to The Conquest of Yellow Fever;<lb/>
the second, and by no means less interesting account of the later history of<lb/>
those heroes, and the story of the collection of the Kissinger fund and of<lb/>
the triumph of the Wainwright-Copeland Bill in Congress. I know of no more<lb/>
important lesson for history and civics classes, as well as for biology student.</p>
<p>Before I mimeograph this letter (see enclosed carbon copy), which will of<lb/>
course be very much briefer, I must know if you are willing to complete your<lb/>
splendid work by introducing a bill to give the four members of the Reed Board<lb/>
the $250 that was approved by the Committee on Military Affairs after the<lb/>
hearing on April 11, 1928. Can you tell me whether any objection was raised<lb/>
before the Committee voted to recommend the bill? I am sure you would have<lb/>
the enthusiastic support of Dr. Fosdick's Citizen Committee, and the active<lb/>
help of hundreds of those who know this story. I hope to use my lantern slides<lb/>
during the next six months wherever I can get an audience and enough to pay<lb/>
my expenses, Surgeon General Ireland and Surgeon General Cumming would do all<lb/>
they can to help you, for the compromise bill you had to agree to violates all<lb/>
the principles that ought to obtain in granting higher pensions to army offi-<lb/>
cers.</p>
<p>You do not know how delighted everybody is that Dr. Agramonte's name was<lb/>
included in all three of the lists. How did you do it? All the doctors and<lb/>
government leaders with whom I talked said that the inclusion of his name would<lb/>
wreck the legislation, much as it deserved to pass, if a doctor outside the<lb/>
country was named. In the amended bill, recommended by the late and lamented<lb/>
Mr. Frothingham's sub-Committee, is the name of Mrs. William Crawford Gorgas.<lb/>
We regretted the inclusion of any name not directly concerned in those memorable<lb/>
experiments of the Reed Board in 1900, and were glad this name did not appear<lb/>
in the final draft of the legislation, passed on February 28, 1929. Can you<lb/>
give me the history of this &ldquo;in&rdquo; and &ldquo;out&rdquo; of the Gorgas name, or is it a <unclear>secret</unclear><lb/>
of the Committee Room?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03217002"/>
<p>(2)</p>
<p>I find it is possible to give my lecture (using half my lantern slides)<lb/>
in about 30 minutes. This I have done when talking before Rotary and Lions<lb/>
<unclear>Glabs</unclear> and in churches and schools. But it has meant a breathless <unclear>desk</unclear> over<lb/>
the main points of the story. If I am to have only a short time at my dis-<lb/>
posal I choose to tell <hi>either</hi> the record of that marvelous six months of<lb/>
1900 down in Cuba, <hi>or</hi> to give an account of the experiences we have had in<lb/>
raising $8000 for Kissinger and in backing you and Senator Copeland in get-<lb/>
ting this long delayed justice for the Yellow Fever Heroes. You have done<lb/>
far more than that; you have opened a door for the grateful recognition of<lb/>
the heroes of peace. Is a further result of your work those past years Mrs.<lb/>
Goldberger, whose husband gave his life in researches on spotted fever, now<lb/>
receives $125 a month.</p>
<p>I come now to another way in which I bespeak your help. Opportunities<lb/>
to give my yellow fever lectures (and others as well) in this part of New<lb/>
England where I used to study and teach at Harvard, are coming in at a sur-<lb/>
prising rate. Supt. Snow of the Boston Schools says he will be only too<lb/>
glad to have me speak in any of the Boston schools. Newton and <unclear>Wellesley</unclear><lb/>
also wish the talks. I have engagements in churches and in rotary and Kiwanis<lb/>
Clubs. Some of the colleges wish the talks. I have a complete set of slides<lb/>
on the Cuban story, one that probably could not be duplicated without the<lb/>
use of my negatives. The second story, however, that of getting needed leg-<lb/>
islation, is one that appeals to me, though in a different way, about as<lb/>
strongly as the first. As I have already said in other letters my faith in<lb/>
democracy and in our public servants (in spite of the present Senate fiasco)<lb/>
has been immeasurably increased. Apparently anyone with a worthy cause and<lb/>
a determination to succeed can get a bill through Congress if he can find a<lb/>
Wainwright who will do the set for him.</p>
<p>The paragraph above is a long introduction to what I am driving at. In<lb/>
order to make that second story vivid I must have an autographed picture of<lb/>
Congressman Wainwright, a good picture of the House Office building, of your<lb/>
office, of the room in which the Committee on Military Affairs met, a picture<lb/>
of said Committee, and a number of others. I need to <unclear>scoure</unclear>, <hi>if possible</hi>,<lb/>
hundreds of copies of the original and the variously amended forms of the<lb/>
Wainwright-Copeland bill, and on the final form in which it was passed and<lb/>
signed,--a copy of each of these to be left as a sort of exhibit an schools<lb/>
where I lecture. I am sure students in history and civics would be immensely<lb/>
interested. I may find it possible to write up and have the Museum of Natural<lb/>
History publish another pamphlet similar to THE CONQUEST OF YELLOW FEVER,<lb/>
with case such title as <unclear>WA</unclear> COLONEL WAINWRIGHT BROUGHT CONGRESS TO ITS <unclear>CASES</unclear>.<lb/>
I plan to have lantern slides made of the vital points of the campaign as<lb/>
portrayed in some of the precious letters which the Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
suggests should be filed for permanent keeping in Johns Hopkins Library of<lb/>
the History of Medicine. I hope to secure also autographed pictures of the<lb/>
members of the Fosdick Citizens Committee and of various Washington Officials<lb/>
who have helped us so much. If you think it is not an imposition on your<lb/>
busy time, I should like very much to drive our car down to our old home in<lb/>
White Plains, leave my wife there for visits with friends, while I secure the<lb/>
pictures and lantern slides I need. I can <unclear>secure</unclear> more very valuable material<lb/>
from those wonderful friends in Baltimore and Washington. I should like to<lb/>
have my wife there with me at the opening of Congress. Is this all a wild<lb/>
dream, or are you willing to help me secure the needed material? We do so<lb/>
hope we can complete to the satisfaction of all that wonderful job so well be-<lb/>
gan.</p>
<p>I shall appreciate an early reply, so I may know what to do about what<lb/>
plans to make.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
