<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03224001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: National Honors for the Yellow Fever Heroes, by [Robert M. O'Reilly], [1929]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03224001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington, (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-00-00">[1929]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03224001</idno>
<title>Report: National Honors for the Yellow Fever Heroes, by [Robert M. O'Reilly], [1929]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report chronicles the path to recognition for the members of the Yellow Fever Board, beginning with a 1906 letter from Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-00-00">
<head>Report: National Honors for the Yellow Fever Heroes, by [Robert M. O'Reilly], [1929]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03224001"/>
<opener>
<hi>NATIONAL HONORS FOR THE YELLOW FEVER HEROES</hi><lb/>
(Long delayed--but finally awarded in 1929)<lb/>
The White House, December 5, 1906<lb/>
To the Senate and House of Representatives:<lb/>
The inclosed papers are transmitted to the Congress in the earnest<lb/>
hope that it will take suitable action in the matter. Major Reed's part<lb/>
in the experiments which resulted in teaching us how to cope with yellow<lb/>
fever was such as to render mankind his debtor, and this nation should<lb/>
in some proper fashion bear witness to this fact.<lb/>
Theodore Roosevelt.<lb/>
******<lb/>
<dateline>
War Department<lb/>
Office of the Surgeon General<lb/>
Washington, <date value="1906-08-30">August 30, 1906.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>The persons taking an important part in the investigations in Cuba<lb/>
which resulted in the demonstration of the fact that yellow fever is<lb/>
transmitted by a species of mosquito, were three members of the board<lb/>
appointed to investigate epidemic diseases in Cuba--Walter Reed, James Ca<lb/>
Carroll, and Jesse W. Lazear--and the individuals who submitted them-<lb/>
selves for experimentation by receiving the bites of infected mosqui-<lb/>
toes, by receiving injections of blood from yellow fever patients, and<lb/>
by sleeping in bedding which had been used by yellow fever patients. . .</p>
<p>Major Walter Reed, surgeon, United States Army, president of the<lb/>
commission to investigate and study the epidemic diseases in Cuba, died<lb/>
in Washington from appendicitis, November 23, 1902, at the age of 51.<lb/>
At the time of his death the Secretary of War had said in his report,<lb/>
which was then in press but not yet given out: &ldquo;The brilliant character<lb/>
of this scientific achievement, its inestimable value to mankind, the<lb/>
saving of thousands of lives, and the deliverance of the Atlantic sea-<lb/>
coast from constant aprehension, demand special recognition from the<lb/>
Government of the United States. Dr. Reed is ranking major in the Med-<lb/>
ical Department, and within a few months will, by operation of law, be-<lb/>
come lieutenant colonel. I ask that the President be authorized to<lb/>
appoint him Assistant Surgeon General with the rank of colonel.&rdquo; . . .</p>
<p>A bill prepared in this office for a pension for his widow, equal<lb/>
in amount to his monthly pay, was passed, but the amount was so cut<lb/>
down that while it keeps the wolf from the door it does not provide an<lb/>
adequate and comfortable income. It is not probable, however, that<lb/>
Congress would increase this pension, and an effort has been made to<lb/>
supplement it by the raising of a fund of $25,000 by the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association, incorporated for this purpose in the District of<lb/>
Columbia. The interest of this fund will be given Mrs. Reed during her<lb/>
lifetime, and the principal after her death will be devoted to some<lb/>
form of memorial. This fund lacks at present about $6,000 of comple-<lb/>
tion. The existence of this association, should its hopes be attained,<lb/>
does not, however, absolve the nation from the obligation of a fitting<lb/>
recognition for this great work, and it is the opinion of the under-<lb/>
signed, which, it is believed is shared by the vast majority of phys-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03224002"/>
Page 2.<lb/>
icians in the United States, that Congress should erect a statue to<lb/>
Walter Reed in Washington. The assistance of the President in inducing<lb/>
Congress to do so is requested. . . . . .</p>
<p>It is recommended that Congress be asked to pass a special act pro-<lb/>
moting Dr. Carroll, on account of his services in connection with this<lb/>
discovery and the courage shown by him in subjecting himself to experi-<lb/>
ment, to the rank of lieutenant colonel, the number of medical officers<lb/>
in that grade being increased by one for that purpose; also his name and<lb/>
effigy should appear on the monument to Walter Reed. . . . . .</p>
<p>At the time of Dr. Lazear's death in the course of these experi-<lb/>
ments he was 34 years old. He left a wife and two young children, the<lb/>
younger born a few months before his death, whom he never saw. Mrs.<lb/>
Lazear received from Congress a pension of $17 a month with $2 addi-<lb/>
tional for each of two minor children until they reach the age of 16.<lb/>
Also a battery in Baltimore Harbor was, by direction of the Secretary<lb/>
of War, named in his honor. It is believed that this recognition on<lb/>
the part of the nation for his services is utterly inadequate. His<lb/>
widow's pension should be increased to $100 a month, and steps should<lb/>
be taken to perpetuate his name in connection with the Walter Reed mon-<lb/>
ument above suggested. . . . . .</p>
<p>Twenty-three of the men who submitted themselves for experiments<lb/>
by the board contracted yellow fever, beginning with Dr. James Carroll,<lb/>
who was taken sick August 31, 1900, and ending with John R. Bullard, who<lb/>
was taken sick October 23, 1901.</p>
<p>Conspicuous among them was John J. Moran, a civillian clerk em-<lb/>
ployed at the headquarters of Gen. Fitzhugh Lee, at Quemados, who was<lb/>
one of the earliest volunteers for the second set of experiments, and<lb/>
whose action was dictated by the purest motives of altruism and self-<lb/>
devotion. Mr. Moran disclaimed before submitting to the experiments,<lb/>
any desire for reward, and has never accepted any since, although he was<lb/>
offered the $200 which the liberality of the military governor enabled<lb/>
the commission to give to each experimental patient, the members of the<lb/>
board excepted. Such was his modesty that he has made no effort, so far<lb/>
as is known to this office, to make known his connection with these ex-<lb/>
periments and reap the credit which is so justly due him. Mr. Moran is<lb/>
a native of Ohio. His present address is not known. to this office.<lb/>
(He is at present Manager of the Sunoco office in Havana, Cuba.) The<lb/>
first inoculations in the case of Mr. Moran were for some reason unsuc-<lb/>
cessful, on November 26 and 29. He did not suffer an attack until after<lb/>
the third inoculation on December 21.</p>
<p>The same remarks apply to the first experimental case of the second<lb/>
set, Pvt. John R. Kissinger, hospital corps, who volunteered at the same<lb/>
time with Moran, and equally disclaimed any desire for reward. . . . . .</p>
<p>Of the other experimental cases, seven were Spanish immigrants who<lb/>
submitted to experiments purley for the money which they were promised.<lb/>
With regard to those who were American soldiers, however, 10 in number<lb/>
in addition to those already mentioned, it can not be doubted that, al-<lb/>
though they received pecuniary rewards, a desire to assist in what they<lb/>
appreciated was a great and glorious work, together with the spirit of<lb/>
adventure, was the most powerful motive. The same is true of the last<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03224003"/>
Page 3.<lb/>
experimental case, Mr. John R. Bullard, a graduate of Harvard, where he<lb/>
was a distinguished athlete and captain of the university crew. The<lb/>
names of these men, with the dates of their attack is appended with<lb/>
this report.</p>
<p>It remains to mention Dr. Robert P. Cook, acting assistant surgeon<lb/>
and the six privates of the hospital corps, who were for 20 nights shut<lb/>
up in the infected bedding house at Camp Lazear. These experiments, <del>whi</del><lb/>
which were absolutely necessary to demonstrate that yellow fever could<lb/>
not be carried otherwise than by the mosquito, had for these men, so<lb/>
far as they knew, an equal element of danger with the other experiments<lb/>
and had in addition such repulsive and disagreeable features as to test<lb/>
to the full their hardihood and patience. Much of the bedding upon<lb/>
which they slept and which they were required daily to handle, was so<lb/>
soiled with the discharges of the sick as to be very repulsive to the<lb/>
nose and eye, and the last experimenters actually slept in the pajamas a<lb/>
and sheets which had been worn by severe cases of yellow fever.</p>
<p>It will be observed that three of these men--Folk, Jernegan, and<lb/>
Hanberry--afterwards submitted to the mosquito inoculation or blood in-<lb/>
jection in order to demonstrate their nonimmunity at the time of the<lb/>
first experiment.</p>
<p>It is believed that the names of all the Americans on this list<lb/>
should be placed on a tablet in connection with the monument to Walter<lb/>
Reed.</p>
<p>From the foregoing it will be seen that the total disbursements of<lb/>
this great nation in the way of rewards for those who made possible<lb/>
this discovery and their families, amounts to $146 a month. As to its<lb/>
value to the American people attention is invited to the quotation<lb/>
given above and others given in the enclosed circulars published by the<lb/>
Walter Reed Memorial Association.</p>
<p>How discreditable appears this nigardly provision, when compared<lb/>
with the action of the English Government which more than a century ago,<lb/>
when the purchasing power of money was far greater than at present,<lb/>
gave to Jenner, the discoverer of vaccination, grants amounting to<lb/>
30,000 pounds sterling. He also received from a subscription in India<lb/>
7,383 pounds sterling, while the Reed Memorial has so far succeeded in<lb/>
raising only a little over half of that sum.</p>
<p>It is believed that if the President would exert his great person-<lb/>
al influence in furtherance of the aims of that association its task<lb/>
would be soon completed.</p>
<closer>
<signed>R. M. O'Reilly,<lb/>
Surgeon General U. S. Army</signed>.
*******<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03224004"/>
Page 4.<lb/>
General Leonard Wood said of Mjor Reed in an address delivered at<lb/>
a memorial meeting of scientific men in Washington, D. C., shortly <del>a</del><lb/>
after his death: &ldquo;I know of no other man on this side of the world who<lb/>
has done so much for humanity as Dr. Reed. His discovery results in the<lb/>
saving of more lives annually than were lost in the Cuban War, and saves<lb/>
the commercial interests of the world a greater financial loss each<lb/>
year than the cost of the Cuban War. He came to Cuba at a time when<lb/>
one-third of the officers of my staff died of yellow fever, and we were<lb/>
discouraged at the <unclear>cfailure</unclear> of our efforts to control the disease. In<lb/>
the months when the disease was ordinarily worst<del>t</del> the disease was<lb/>
checked and driven from Havana. That was the first time in nearly 200<lb/>
years that the city had been rid of it. The value of his discovery<lb/>
cannot be appreciated by persons who are not familiar with the condi-<lb/>
tions in tropical countries. Hereafter it will never be possible for<lb/>
yellow fever to gain such headway that quarantine will exist from the<lb/>
mouth of the Potamac to the mouth of the Rio Grande. Future genera-<lb/>
tions will appreciate fully the value of Dr. Reed's services. His was<lb/>
the originating, directing, and controlling mind in this work, and the<lb/>
others were assistants only.&rdquo;<lb/>
In a letter from Dr. William H. Welch to the Secretary of War he<lb/>
siad: &ldquo;Dr. Reed's researches in yellow fever are by far the most import-<lb/>
<unclear>ant</unclear> contributions to science which have ever been made by any Army sur-<lb/>
geon. In my judgment they are the most valuable contributions to medi-<lb/>
cine and public hygiene which have ever been made in this country with<lb/>
the exception of the discovery of anaesthesia. They have led and will<lb/>
lead to the saving of thousands of lives. I am in a position to know<lb/>
that the credit for the original ideas embodied in this work belongs<lb/>
wholly to Major Reed.&rdquo;<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
