<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03249001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from L.O. Howard, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03249001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Thayer, William S.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Bell, Alexander Graham</name>
<name type="person">Gilman, [Daniel Coit]</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Blue, Rupert</name>
<name type="person">Chaille, [Stanford L.]</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Osler, William</name>
<name type="person">Celli, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Columbian University, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Cornell University, Ithaca (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Ithaca (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Greene County (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">North America</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Laredo (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Sierra Leone</name>
<name type="place">Gambia</name>
<name type="place">Liverpool (England)</name>
<name type="place">Rome (Italy)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03249001</idno>
<title>Memorandum from L.O. Howard, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Howard reflects on his lifetime of work with mosquitoes. He includes a transcript of a January 13, 1901 letter from Walter Reed describing the success of Reed's experiments. A transcript of a February 20, 1902 letter from Ronald Ross discusses Ross' work in Africa.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Memorandum from L.O. Howard, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03249001"/>
<p><unclear>undated - get approximate</unclear><lb/>
date.</p>
<p>FROM L. O. HOWARD<lb/>
OR LUCY HOWARD</p>
<p><hi>WRITTEN BY DR. L. O. HOWARD</hi></p>
<p>Many of my relatives and friends have caused me much embarrassment<lb/>
from time to time by unintentionally exaggerating the importance of the<lb/>
work I happen to have done concerning mosquitoes that carry disease, and<lb/>
even <unclear>certain</unclear> newspapers and magazines have also greatly overstated the<lb/>
importance of what I have done.</p>
<p>So I think it best in this memorandum to give a clear statement<lb/>
of my work in this direction, in order that I may not be accused at any<lb/>
time of claiming credit which I did not deserve.</p>
<p>I have been an entomologist of a kind since boyhood days, and<lb/>
specialized in entomology through my undergraduate degrees at Cornell.<lb/>
A post-graduate course of one year was devoted to studies preparatory to<lb/>
medicine, and in the early eighties I took a partial course in medicine<lb/>
at Columbian University in Washington, and have always been interested<lb/>
in medical matters, particularly in questions of public health, and have<lb/>
associated with medical men.</p>
<p>In 1867, when a boy of ten years of age, I used kerosene in a<lb/>
horse-trough in which <unclear>mosquitoes</unclear> were breeding at Ithaca, N. Y. <hi>In<lb/>
June, 1892 I conducted an experiment with a pool</hi> having a surface area<lb/>
of sixteen square feet in Greene County, New York. I published an account<lb/>
of this experiment in Insect Life, Volume V, pages 12 to 14, published<lb/>
September, 1892. The introductory paragraph read, &ldquo;One of the most<lb/>
reasonable of the <hi>recommendations which have been made from time</hi> to time<lb/>
and which look toward the reduction of the mosquito plague during the<lb/>
summer months is the application of <hi>kerosene</hi> to restricted and fishless<lb/>
breeding ponds. <hi>Although this remedy has often been suggested, I know</hi><lb/>
of <hi>no careful records of actual experiments</hi>, and consequently deem the<lb/>
following account of a recent experience worthy of publication.&rdquo; I then<lb/>
go on to show that not only does the kerosene application kill the wrigglers<lb/>
and pupae, but that it does not deter adult mosquitoes from alighting on<lb/>
the water and attempting to drink or <unclear>to</unclear> lay eggs, thus being caught and<lb/>
killed by the kerosene film. I estimated the amount of kerosene to be<lb/>
used as approximately one ounce to fifteen square feet of surface, and<lb/>
indicated that in midsummer it would be effective up to from a week to<lb/>
ten days. This announcement was copied widely in the newspapers and was<lb/>
speedily followed by extensive use of kerosene for this purpose in different<lb/>
parts of the country, and thus really formed a practical basis for the<lb/>
work of this kind which has been done since.</p>
<p>In 1896, in a bulletin on household insects (No. 4, new series,<lb/>
Division of Entomology, U. S. Department of Agriculture), I published a<lb/>
chapter on mosquitoes and fleas, in the preparation of which I carefully<lb/>
studied the biology of <hi>Culex pipiens</hi> (under the name of <hi>Culex pungens</hi>) and<lb/>
published a full account from original observations for the first time<lb/>
since <unclear>R&edot;amur</unclear> (150 years earlier), and mentioned the finding of <hi>Anopheles<lb/>
quadrimaculatus</hi> (now known as a prominent malaria carrier) and the obtaining<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03249002"/>
FROM L. O. HOWARD<lb/>
OR LUCY HOWARD<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
of its eggs, rearing operations being interrupted by a necessary field<lb/>
trip. In this article the question of mosquito remedies was considered<lb/>
at some length.</p>
<p>Later I followed out the full life history of the malarial<lb/>
species, <hi>Anopheles quadrimaculatus</hi>, and, following the discovery of the<lb/>
relations of Anopheles and malaria, lectured in the spring of 1900 before<lb/>
the Royal Society of Canada and before the Section of Theory and Practice<lb/>
of Medicine of the American Association at the annual meeting of the<lb/>
Association in Atlantic City on the subject of the biology of Anopheles<lb/>
as contrasted with that of Culex, illustrating both lectures with lantern<lb/>
slides showing the different stages of <hi>A</hi>. <hi>quadrimaculatus</hi> and <hi>C</hi>. <hi>pipiens</hi>.<lb/>
A full account of the biology of both species, with ten original illus-<lb/>
trations, was published in the Scientific American, Vol. 83, p. 809, July<lb/>
7, 1900. This was the first published account of the full life history<lb/>
of an American species of Anopheles.</p>
<p>This was immediately followed, July 24, 1900, by the publication<lb/>
of Bulletin 25, new series, Division of Entomology, entitled &ldquo;Notes on<lb/>
the Mosquitoes of the United States, giving some account of their structure<lb/>
and biology with remarks' on remedies.&rdquo; In the letter of transmittal it<lb/>
was stated that the bulletin &ldquo;gives some account of the structure and<lb/>
biology (of mosquitoes) and indicates the differences in all stages of<lb/>
existence between the kinds of mosquitoes which have been shown to<lb/>
transmit malaria and those which do not. It also treats of the subject<lb/>
of remedies in considerable detail. It has been written mainly from the<lb/>
popular standpoint, although scientific details of structure and classi-<lb/>
fication have been inserted for the use of physicians engaged in studying<lb/>
malaria.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Must have been <unclear>in 1899 or</unclear> Jan 1900; <unclear>conduck</unclear> have been<lb/>
later</p>
<p>During the <hi>early months of 1900</hi> I was visited by <hi>Dr. W. S. Thayer</hi><lb/>
of Johns Hopkins University and <hi>Dr. Jesse W. Lazear of</hi> Baltimore, who<lb/>
wished my assistance in clearing up certain points in regard to mosquitoes,<lb/>
since they were at that time engaged in the study of malaria. This was<lb/>
of special interest on account of Doctor Thayer's standing as an authority<lb/>
upon malaria and on account of Doctor Lazear's subsequent connection with<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Commission and his sad death during the progress of its<lb/>
investigations. I had the pleasure a little later of delivering a joint<lb/>
lecture with Doctor Thayer under the auspices of the Maryland Board of<lb/>
Health, Doctor Thayer treating of malaria and I myself handling the<lb/>
malarial mosquitoes.</p>
<p>error?<lb/>
Lazear<lb/>
<unclear>sigred</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>contract<lb/>
with</unclear> any<lb/>
Feb 5, <unclear>1900</unclear><lb/>
&amp; <unclear>left</unclear> for<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
Feb <unclear>7, 1900</unclear></p>
<p>It was during the summer of 1900 that the Army Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission was appointed by Surgeon-General Sternberg, and <hi>Doctor Reed<lb/>
and Doctor Carroll of the Commission</hi> came frequently to the Department<lb/>
of Agriculture to study mosquitoes, and during the progress of their in-<lb/>
vestigations in Cuba I was in frequent correspondence with Doctor Reed,<lb/>
who consulted this office in regard to all mosquito points. The following<lb/>
quotation from a letter received just after the final conclusion of the<lb/>
implication of the yellow fever mosquito in the carriage of disease is of<lb/>
keen interest:</p>
<p>He does not<lb/>
<unclear>here say</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>that Lazear</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>came with</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Reed.</unclear></p>
<p><unclear></unclear> is <unclear>probably</unclear> its correct version, <unclear>more so than that</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>on</unclear> <unclear></unclear> 1930 book</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03249003"/>
<p>FROM L. O. HOWARD<lb/>
OR LUCY HOWARD</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><hi>COPY</hi></p>
<p>Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba,<lb/>
January 13, 1901.</p>
<p>Dear Mr. Howard:</p>
<p>I am in receipt of yours of January 5th, and thank you very<lb/>
much for the card containing Dr. Wolfert's suggestion. I turned the<lb/>
card over to the Chief Surgeon, yesterday. I enclose a copy of the order<lb/>
relating to protection against mosquitoes. Of course, you have already<lb/>
heard from Dr. Sternberg of our complete success in repeating our former<lb/>
observations. The mosquito theory for the propagation of yellow fever<lb/>
is no longer a <hi>theory</hi>, but a <hi>well established fact</hi>. Isn't it enough to<lb/>
make a fellow feel happy? Anopheles and Culex are a gay old pair! What<lb/>
havoc they have wrought on our species during the last three centuries!<lb/>
But with &ldquo;<hi>Howard</hi> and <hi>kerosene</hi>,&rdquo; we are going to knock them out!</p>
<p>With best wishes,</p>
<p>Sincerely yours,</p>
<p>(Signed) WALTER REED.</p>
<p>Major J. R. Kean, Surgeon, U.S.A., was the Acting Chief Surgeon<lb/>
of the Division of Cuba, at the time this order was published, and it was<lb/>
he who drew it up and recommended it to Gen. Wood. He should have credit<lb/>
for it.</p>
<p>W. R.</p>
<p>The reference to General Sternberg in this letter was made since<lb/>
Doctor Reed knew that I was in the habit of meeting General Sternberg<lb/>
(at that time Surgeon General in the Army) almost daily and talking over<lb/>
matters of common interest. In fact I talked often with the General on<lb/>
this subject of the carriage of disease by mosquitoes, and, since I was<lb/>
busy that summer working on the insect fauna of human excrement with<lb/>
special reference to the carriage of typhoid, which will be referred to<lb/>
later, we had many conversations on the subject of typhoid in the Army<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03249004"/>
FROM L. O. HOWARD<lb/>
OR LUCY HOWARD<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
concentration camps during 1898.</p>
<p>Mosquito notes and additional observations on different species<lb/>
were constantly being made, and in the spring of 1901, just after the com-<lb/>
pletion of the manuscript of the Insect Book I began to prepare the manu-<lb/>
script which was subsequently published as &ldquo;Mosquitoes; How they Live;<lb/>
How they Carry Disease; How they are Classified; How they may be Destroyed.&rdquo;<lb/>
I had thought of publishing this book privately, and had been in corres-<lb/>
pondence with the Macmillan Company about it, but one day early in 1901<lb/>
Mr. Samuel Hopkins Adams, at that time connected with McClure Phillips &amp;<lb/>
Company, came into my office (I had done some work for the McClure<lb/>
syndicate through him) and asked me what I was doing. I told him about<lb/>
the mosquito book, and he asked me not to close arrangements until he<lb/>
could consult his firm. <unclear>Within</unclear> a few days I got a favorable offer from<lb/>
McClure Phillips &amp; Company, and they subsequently published the book in<lb/>
the early summer.</p>
<p>A few days later the late Dr. E. A. De Schweinitz came to me<lb/>
and said that he had <hi>heard some Army people at the Chevy</hi> Chase Club <hi>talking<lb/>
vigorously about the way in which I had treated Doctor Reed in the</hi> book,<lb/>
and I then became aware for the first time that, contrary to what I had<lb/>
stated on pages 122 and 123 of the book, Doctor Reed had undertaken his<lb/>
mosquito investigations in Havana on his own initiative and without suggestion<lb/>
from the Surgeon General. I was at that time preparing an article for<lb/>
the Review of Reviews on this general subject, and <hi>I immediately went to<lb/>
the Army Medical Museum to explain matters to Doctor Reed</hi>. He received<lb/>
me very kindly, and said that he could readily see how I had fallen into<lb/>
the error, and read the manuscript of the Review of Reviews article, which<lb/>
I worded in exact accordance with the facts as I gained them from<lb/>
Doctor Reed (See the American Monthly Review of Reviews, August 1, 1901,<lb/>
pp. 192-195, and especially the matter on p. 194). Reference should also<lb/>
be made here to an illustrated article of mine in the Century Magazine<lb/>
for April, 1901, pages 941-949, entitled &ldquo;Malaria and Certain Mosquitoes,&rdquo;<lb/>
and to another illustrated article in the same magazine for October,<lb/>
1903, on &ldquo;Yellow Fever and Mosquitoes,&rdquo; pages 851-857.</p>
<p>23</p>
<p>Doctor Reed died November 22, 1902. Dr. Howard A. Kelly, in<lb/>
his book entitled &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever,&rdquo; published by McClure<lb/>
Phillips &amp; Company in 1906, on pages 251-252 has the following: &ldquo;During<lb/>
the winter following Doctor Reed's death a strong desire arose among his<lb/>
friends as to the establishment of some memorial in his honor. The<lb/>
project first assumed definite shape at a dinner given by Prof. Alexander<lb/>
Graham Bell to a number of the members of the Association of American<lb/>
Scientists,&rdquo; etc., etc. This dinner was given during Convocation Week,<lb/>
and if I remember rightly on December 31st. It was a large dinner, and<lb/>
many prominent American scientific men were present as well as my dear<lb/>
old friend Dr. James Fletcher from Ottawa, Canada. As is always the case<lb/>
at Doctor Bell's dinners, there came a time when one person was asked to<lb/>
speak to all the rest, interrupting general conversation. This night<lb/>
Doctor Gilman, formerly President of Johns Hopkins University, with whom<lb/>
I had been talking about Reed and his discoveries, suggested that Doctor<lb/>
Bell should call upon me to tell them all what I had been telling him, and<lb/>
so I told the story as effectively as I knew how, and I hope that the<lb/>
forcible way in which I know I told it helped to inspire the movement for<lb/>
the memorial which afterwards materialized.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03249005"/>
<p>FROM L. O. HOWARD<lb/>
OR LUCY HOWARD</p>
<p>-5-</p><lb/>
<p>My interest in mosquitoes was so great and important observations<lb/>
were accumulating so rapidly, and the McClures declining to undertake a<lb/>
radical revision of the mosquito book which was soon out of date as to<lb/>
very important biological facts and as to matters of classification, I<lb/>
memorialized the newly founded Carnegie Institution of Washington in<lb/>
April, 1902, asking for a grant to enable the preparation of a monograph<lb/>
to include all possible information concerning all mosquitoes in North<lb/>
and Central American and the West Indies. The grant was made by the trustees<lb/>
in January, 1903, and the work was carried on through subsequent years.<lb/>
The story is told in the introduction to Volume 1 of the monograph.</p>
<p>Incidentally I became interested in the geographic distribution<lb/>
in North America of the yellow fever mosquito, and the Public Health<lb/>
Service in November, 1903, published a pamphlet which I wrote entitled<lb/>
&ldquo;Concerning the Geographic Distribution of the Yellow Fever Mosquito.&rdquo;<lb/>
In the course of the investigation upon which this paper was based I<lb/>
utilized the entomological service of the Department of Agriculture, and<lb/>
myself visited Mexico and followed out some interesting points regarding<lb/>
the altitude which this species reaches in that country. This happened<lb/>
to be the year of the Laredo outbreak of yellow fever, and I was forced<lb/>
to return to this country by sea in order to avoid quarantine at the Texas<lb/>
border. This pamphlet was later revised, and it was the basis of the<lb/>
quarantine work which was carried on by the Public Health Service during<lb/>
the summer of 1905, the year of the last outbreak of the fever at New Orleans.<lb/>
I was in Europe that summer, and the first news which reached me on<lb/>
landing at New York was of the condition of New Orleans and of the death<lb/>
of my old friend, Archbishop Chappell in the course of the epidemic. As<lb/>
soon as I could arrange business matters in Washington, I went south, and,<lb/>
having to visit Texas, was obliged to go to that State first, since if<lb/>
I went to New Orleans first I would not have been permitted to enter Texas.<lb/>
But I reached New Orleans late in October, and was greatly interested in<lb/>
seeing what Dr. J. H. White of the Public Health Service and his able body<lb/>
of assistants (one of whom was Dr. Rupert Blue, now Surgeon General of the<lb/>
Public Health Service) had been able to accomplish. A table drawn up by<lb/>
Doctor Chaille of New Orleans, which he gave to me, and which I have used<lb/>
many times in lectures, and which is printed in Doctor Kelly's biography<lb/>
of Doctor Reed on page 196, indicates plainly that at least 3,500 lives<lb/>
were saved that summer in New Orleans alone by the efficient application<lb/>
by Doctor White of the facts gained by Doctor Reed and his colleagues<lb/>
and by the subsequent Army work in Havana carried on by General (then Major)<lb/>
Gorgas.</p>
<p>I first met Sir Ronald Ross, when he was simply Doctor Ross, in<lb/>
1904 at the World's Congress of Arts and Sciences in St. Louis, but I had<lb/>
known him previously by correspondence. In January, 1902, he sent me an<lb/>
admirable little book entitled &ldquo;Mosquito Brigades&rdquo; inscribed on the fly-<lb/>
leaf &ldquo;L. O. Howard with the compliments of the author and his regrets that<lb/>
he had not seen &lsquo;Mosquitoes&rsquo; earlier.&rdquo; I sent him a letter of thanks and<lb/>
received the following characteristic reply:</p>
<pb n="6" id="f03249006"/>
<p>FROM L. O. HOWARD<lb/>
OR LUCY HOWARD</p>
<p>-6-</p>
<p>Liverpool, Feb. 20th, 1902.</p>
<p>My dear Professor Howard,</p>
<p>I am delighted to hear that you like my &lsquo;Mosquito Brigades.&rsquo;<lb/>
However it is not a patch on your work, which I wish I had got hold of<lb/>
before. I sail for Sierra Leone in two days, and hope to find work pro-<lb/>
gressing. We have forced the Gambia Colony to take up the same work, and<lb/>
by dint of constant driving, I think we are getting this old country to<lb/>
do something at last. It is however doubtless the example of Havana that<lb/>
has chiefly set them going. We never do anything here unless some other<lb/>
country takes it up first. Yes, I think that the Italian School requires<lb/>
a little medicine in the shape of plain speaking. I suppose that you have<lb/>
seen the last effort of Grassi and Noe, who pretend that they have found<lb/>
out about Filaria banorofti. As a matter of fact they have hardly ever<lb/>
seen one, much less found out anything about them.</p>
<p>Believe me,</p>
<p>Yours very sincerely,</p>
<p>Ronald Ross.</p>
<p>Since then I have visited Ross in his laboratories at Liverpool<lb/>
several times, and we have frequently corresponded; in fact, he asked me<lb/>
to write a chapter in his big book &ldquo;The Prevention of Malaria,&rdquo; which I<lb/>
did. It may be worth while noting also that Sir William Osler asked me<lb/>
to write the chapter on mosquitoes which occurs in his great work on<lb/>
&ldquo;The Theory and Practice of Medicine&rdquo; published in 1907.</p>
<p>In 1902 I visited Celli's laboratory in Rome, and saw something<lb/>
of the early work against malaria on the Roman Campagna. Later, at<lb/>
Celli's request, I contributed an article to the Atti Soc. Per gli Studi<lb/>
della Malaria, Volume XI, pages 67-73 (Rome) on &ldquo;The Gradual Disappearance<lb/>
of Malaria following the Settlement of a New Country and its Reappearance<lb/>
as a Result of the Dense Civilization.&rdquo; In 1910 I visited Rome again,<lb/>
and with Celli went over portions of the reclaimed Compagna and spent one<lb/>
of the most enjoyable days of my life with this wonderfully able and delightful<lb/>
man. At the same time I had the pleasure of meeting Tiraboschi and <unclear>Grassi</unclear><lb/>
characterized as &ldquo;Une veritable sottise.&rdquo; I subsequently published an<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03249007"/>
FROM L. O. HOWARD<lb/>
OR LUCY HOWARD<lb/>
-7-<lb/>
article on antimalarial work in Italy in the Acts of the Society for the<lb/>
Study of Malaria, Volume XII (Rome).</p>
<p>It will thus be seen that I had nothing whatever to do with any<lb/>
of the actual discoveries relating to the carriage of disease by mosquitoes.<lb/>
I was a pioneer in the practical study of mosquito remedies, and the ad-<lb/>
vice given both in Bulletin 25 and in the mosquito book has been of<lb/>
assistance in the fight against these disease-bearing insects. I have been<lb/>
somewhat of a publicist in this direction by means of numerous articles<lb/>
in magazines and elsewhere as well as contributions to various scientific<lb/>
journals.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
