<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03241002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Jessie Daniel Ames, May 27, 1930</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Agramonte, Aristides</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03241002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1930-05-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ames, Jessie Daniel</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1930-05-27">May 27, 1930</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03241002</idno>
<title>Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Jessie Daniel Ames, May 27, 1930</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Agramonte informs Mrs. Ames about her husband's actions and responsibilities with the yellow fever board in Cuba, enclosing answers to questions she has posed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1930-05-27">
<head>Letter from Aristides Agramonte to Jessie Daniel Ames, May 27, 1930</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03241002"/>
<p><hi>COPY</hi><lb/>
<date value="1930-05-27">May 27th, 1930</date>
Mrs. Jessie Daniel Ames,<lb/>
Atlanta, Ga.<lb/>
Dear Madam:</p>
<p>Have just received your letter of the 21st inst. with<lb/>
various statements and documents, which I hasten to answer.</p>
<p>I am very glad that I am not obliged to say that the<lb/>
events referred to, &ldquo;happened so long ago&rdquo; that I cannot remember,<lb/>
for the facts are as clearly in my mind today as when they took<lb/>
place 30 years ago, and having lived here all the time, in contin-<lb/>
uous contact with the scene of our labors, every detail is vividly<lb/>
impressed upon my memory.</p>
<p>Particularly of Dr. Ames, of whom I have been recently<lb/>
speaking with one of his relatives, Capt. Beyers of the S. S.<lb/>
Parismina, I have most distinct and pleasant recollection. Dr.<lb/>
Ames was very well thought of by everyone who knew him and I,<lb/>
personally, was much attached to him from the time that I met him<lb/>
at the Military Hospital No. 1 until he left Cuba, early in 1901.</p>
<p>His work, in the early part of the Board's experiments<lb/>
was principally in the city of Havana, visiting and disposing the<lb/>
removal to hospital of yellow fever cases and the disinfection of<lb/>
supposedly infected areas; at that time he was considered immune<lb/>
to yellow fever, himself claiming either to having had the dis-<lb/>
ease or much contact with cases in New Orleans. I do not remem-<lb/>
ber exactly on what basis his immunity was founded, but I do<lb/>
remember that it was for this reason and his evident familiarity<lb/>
with the disease, that he was detailed at Columbia Barracks to<lb/>
take care of the experimental cases. He certainly had excellent<lb/>
judgment and although the cases were all officially confirmed<lb/>
by a special expert board, he was the first who came in contact<lb/>
with them and made the earliest diagnosis.</p>
<p>Dr. Ames had no connection whatever with the yellow<lb/>
fever Board before the establishment of Camp Lazear; he attended<lb/>
the cases of Drs. Carroll and Lazear when they came down with<lb/>
the fever, in the regular course of duty at Columbia Barracks<lb/>
and because he was reputed immune to the disease; for this same<lb/>
reason, when Camp Lazear was set up, he was entrusted by the<lb/>
Board with the administration of the Camp, the payment of the<lb/>
Spaniards hired as day laborers for the later purpose of the<lb/>
experiments, provision of food, equipment, quarterly, etc. for<lb/>
the &ldquo;subjects&rdquo; and for the military guard maintained there, but<lb/>
he had absolutely nothing to do with the experiments, with the<lb/>
selection of the men, their observation, their inoculation or<lb/>
the keeping of their records, etc. His scientific services be-<lb/>
gan when a case was developed; as soon as high temperature or<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03241003"/>
the least symptom appeared, the case was removed from Camp Lazear<lb/>
to special individual barracks, two miles from the Camp, near<lb/>
the Columbia Barracks Hospital, where it was placed under Dr. Ames'<lb/>
charge until his final recovery. <hi>They all recovered,</hi> a fact that<lb/>
we all thought was &ldquo;a feather in his cap&rdquo;..</p>
<p>With regard to his alleged attack of yellow fever in<lb/>
February, 1901, I must say there was much discrepancy of opinion.<lb/>
I, for one, never believed he had yellow fever, though I think<lb/>
it went as such in the records. In the first place, it was very<lb/>
difficult to trace the source of his infection and by that time<lb/>
Maj. Gorgas had a very good hold of the situation, all cases in<lb/>
Havana and vicinity being very closely watched and recorded; be-<lb/>
sides this, the clinical picture was not very clear and some of<lb/>
the symptoms might well have been attributed to other causes.<lb/>
There was a bare possibility, given his asserted immunity, that he<lb/>
really had a second attack of yellow fever, of a mild or <unclear>a typical</unclear><lb/>
character.</p>
<p>I have endeavored to answer the <xref id="f03241001">questions</xref> you sent me to<lb/>
the best of my ability and am taking the liberty of enclosing a<lb/>
copy of an article I wrote fifteen years ago, that might interest<lb/>
you.</p>
<p>I am afraid my information may not meet your expectations<lb/>
but I know that you would not want anything except the truth and I<lb/>
certainly would make no statements otherwise, much as I would be<lb/>
happy to see some sort of recognition made in your favor.</p>
<p>I remain,</p>
<p>Very sincerely,<lb/>
Dr. Aristides Agramonte (s)</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
