<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03265001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Letter from Sidney Coe Howard to John J. Moran, December 22, 1931</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03265001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1931-12-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Colman, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Lewis, Sinclair</name>
<name type="place">Hollywood (Ca.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1931-12-22">December 22, 1931</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03265001</idno>
<title>Letter from Sidney Coe Howard to John J. Moran, December 22, 1931</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Howard requests an interview with Moran in order to inquire about the yellow fever experiments. Howard is writing a play about the work of the Yellow Fever Commission entitled "Yellow Jack."</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1931-12-22">
<head>Letter from Sidney Coe Howard to John J. Moran, December 22, 1931</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03265001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
157 EAST 82ND STREET<lb/>
NEW YORK CITY<lb/>
<date value="1931-12-22">December 22nd, 1931.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Mr. Moran:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Last week in Washington I talked about you with a friend<lb/>
of yours named Parker to whom my friend General Kean sent me. I had just<lb/>
been reading a very interesting letter of yours which was printed by a<lb/>
man named Peabody in a pamphlet about the yellow fever story. The point of<lb/>
my writing to you now is as follows.</p>
<p>I am a writer of all kinds of things, principally plays and talking<lb/>
pictures. Some three years ago I hatched the idea of writing a play about<lb/>
the yellow fever story in which you took such a part. I did not get much<lb/>
encouragement from managers. You can readily understand that they had<lb/>
very little faith in a show without love story and about so much sickness.<lb/>
Last spring, however, while I was in Hollywood, I wrote a talking picture,<lb/>
for Ronald Colman, based on Sinclair Lewis' novel, &ldquo;Arrowsmith,&rdquo; a book<lb/>
which deals with the fight a doctor makes against the bubonic plague. That<lb/>
picture has turned out to be one of the most successful movies of <unclear>recent</unclear><lb/>
years and audiences are intensely interested in the plague scenes. This<lb/>
has given me the nerve to go back to my own idea and finish up the play<lb/>
about yellow fever. I hope to finish it shortly, to put it on the stage here<lb/>
late this spring or early next fall and to make a picture from it afterwards.</p>
<p>You can be of great help to me and it just happens that January tenth<lb/>
is my wedding anniversary. My wife and I were discussing a short holiday in<lb/>
honor of the event and wondering where to go. We haven't been in Havana for<lb/>
a long time and it is a good town for a holiday. If you <unclear>are going</unclear> to be<lb/>
there about that date and can spare time to talk things over with me, we<lb/>
will come down there. I can get all the facts in the world out of books, but<lb/>
the little details and anecdotes that make a story human never get written<lb/>
down. In this story, because so many of the characters are still living,<lb/>
I had rather have them right than make them up for myself.</p>
<p>I admit that it is unusual to tell a man that it is proposed to put an<lb/>
actor up on the stage and in front of a movie camera with the express purpose<lb/>
of impersonating him. It is enough to make any man uncomfortable. I dare say<lb/>
it is the first time that a historical play or picture has ever been written<lb/>
about living characters. But that is what I propose to do. There should be<lb/>
a business side to my proposition, also. With luck, it may make a fair<lb/>
amount of money which I am certainly prepared to share in return for assistance.</p>
<p>I wish you a very merry Christmas and shall look forward to hearing from<lb/>
you regarding your plans for the days around January 10th.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very Sincerely Yours,</salute>
<signed>Sidney Howard</signed>.
<unclear>John J. Moran egy.</unclear><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
