<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03272001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Albert E. Truby to the Surgeon General, March 9, 1932</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03272001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1932-03-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1932-03-09">March 9, 1932</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03272001</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Albert E. Truby to the Surgeon General, March 9, 1932</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby states his opinion, with Kean's concurrence, regarding qualifications for inclusion in the yellow fever roll of honor. He refers to the paper written by Walter Reed et al., "The Etiology of Yellow Fever - A Preliminary Note," and he recommends A.S. Pinto not be included in the roll of honor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1932-03-09">
<head>Memorandum from Albert E. Truby to the Surgeon General, March 9, 1932</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03272001"/>
<opener>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1932-03-09">9 March, 1932.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>MEMORANDUM for The Surgeon General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The bases recommended by the Office of The Surgeon General<lb/>
of the Army and adopted by the Military Affairs Committee of the House,<lb/>
to be applied to claims for the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor with medal<lb/>
and pension, given by the Act of February 28, 1929, were as follows:</p>
<p>That in the Roll of Honor should be included only the<lb/>
members of the Board and the Americans who volunteered to<lb/>
submit to be experimented on by the Board in order to decide<lb/>
certain questions which could only be determined by actual<lb/>
experiments on human beings. Each of these volunteers had<lb/>
contributed definitely to the success of the experiments and<lb/>
exhibited courage and self-devotion by offering himself at<lb/>
what he believed to be the risk of his life. The list in-<lb/>
cludes fourteen men who <hi>actually suffered attacks of yellow<lb/>
fever</hi> as a result of these experiments, and four men who sub-<lb/>
mitted to the exceedingly important and disagreeable ordeal<lb/>
of sleeping twenty nights in the bedding which had been used<lb/>
by yellow fever patients, and which was soiled with their<lb/>
discharges. This was, at the time, generally believed to be<lb/>
more dangerous than the bites of infected mosquitoes.</p>
<p>The names of individuals who had been bitten by mosquitoes<lb/>
believed to be infected but who did not suffer an attack of yellow<lb/>
fever were not included. The reason for this is obvious. In the<lb/>
first series of experiments <hi>which were conducted secretly by the Board</hi>,<lb/>
on <hi>account of the rigid military quarantine at Columbia Barracks</hi> where<lb/>
the experiments took place, <hi>the names of the individuals were never</hi><lb/>
given out by the Board, and there is now no way of determining any<lb/>
of them except the two which were successful. These two were Dr.<lb/>
James Carroll, a member of the Board, and Private &ldquo;X.Y.&rdquo; (Private<lb/>
Wm. H. Dean) whose name was discovered some years afterwards by an<lb/>
examination of the Sick and Wounded Reports in the Adjutant General's<lb/>
Office.</p>
<p>Two reasons are evident why those not infected should not<lb/>
be placed upon the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor on a parity with men who<lb/>
actually suffered an attack. First, the theory of the transmission<lb/>
of yellow fever by the mosquito was then an unproved and discredited<lb/>
theory, and it is probable that the individuals who offered themselves<lb/>
for the experiment had little faith in it and believed that the danger<lb/>
of infection was slight or non-existent. <hi>It may be observed that<lb/>
after the demonstration of the infectivity</hi> of mosquitoes by the cases<lb/>
of Dr. James Carroll and Private X.Y., <hi>none of these individuals, so<lb/>
far as is known, came forward and offered themselves for the second<lb/>
series of experiments</hi>. <hi>Therefore, the courage shown by the non-<lb/>
infected men in the first series was not on a par with that shown by<lb/>
the men who offered themselves later</hi>. Second, a practical difficulty<lb/>
in extending the roll to include the first series of cases is that<lb/>
there being no records any individual who was then stationed at the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03272002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
hospital at Columbia Barracks could come forward and claim a medal<lb/>
and pension on his own statement without there being any possibility of<lb/>
either confirming or disproving it. The first series of cases referred<lb/>
to above is that reported by the Yellow Fever Board in their paper<lb/>
&ldquo;The Etiology of Yellow Fever- A Preliminary Note&rdquo; by Walter Reed, M.D.<lb/>
Surgeon U.S. Army James Carroll, M.D., A. Agramonte, M.D., and Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear, M.D., <add>Acting</add> Assistant Surgeon, U.S. Army. This report was published<lb/>
in Senate Document No. 822, 61st Congress, 3rd Session, and the first<lb/>
list appears on page 62.</p>
<p>I was personally on duty at Camp Columbia at that time, and<lb/>
understood that Contract Surgeon Alvin S. Pinto, U.S. Army had allowed<lb/>
himself to be bitten by one of these mosquitoes in possession of Dr.<lb/>
Lazear but I have no positive knowledge to that effect, and it is<lb/>
thought that Congress cannot consistently recognize his claim for the<lb/>
reasons above stated. I have made this statement after conference<lb/>
with General J. R. Kean and it meets with his concurrence.</p>
<closer>
<signed>A. E. TRUBY<lb/>
Colonel, M.C., U.S. Army</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
