<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03275011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Article: Unsung Heroes, by Ralph Rohrer Whittaker, [1932]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03275011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1932-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1932-00-00">[1932]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03275011</idno>
<title>Article: Unsung Heroes, by Ralph Rohrer Whittaker, [1932]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Whittaker describes the yellow fever experiments and praises Reed and the volunteers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1932-00-00">
<head>Article: Unsung Heroes, by Ralph Rohrer Whittaker, [1932]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03275011"/>
<p><hi>UNSUNG HEROES</hi></p>
<p>The microbe hunters, unsung and hardly remembered, are now<lb/>
scarcely better known to the world than the microscopic growths<lb/>
and creatures they discovered. One of the greatest of these<lb/>
death-fighters was Walter Reed, head of the Yellow Fever Com-<lb/>
mission. His is a tale of bold and persistent explorers who<lb/>
risked their lives-in the interest of science-and for humanity.<lb/>
Some of them who were too bold have died-done to death by the<lb/>
immensely small assassins they were studying-and these have passed<lb/>
to an obscure glory.</p>
<p>The yellow fever germ had killed thousands of our soldiers<lb/>
in Cuba when Major Reed was called from Washington to give special<lb/>
attention to its cause and prevention. Day after day Reed and his<lb/>
co-workers labored with tireless effort-but in vain. However, just<lb/>
as Grassi discovered the zanzarone carrying malaria because he had<lb/>
faith, Reed seemed to hear a mysterious voice cry from somewhere<lb/>
in the wilderness, &ldquo;Yellow fever is caused by a mosquito!&rdquo;</p>
<p>At this point began possibly the most audacious self-sacri-<lb/>
ficing experiments ever recorded in the annals of medical science.<lb/>
Dr. Carrol, the father of five children, and James Lazear were the<lb/>
first to expose themselves to the test. In the face of almost cer-<lb/>
tain death, they submitted to the infection of the mosquito-for<lb/>
the interest of science-and for humanity! Within forty-eight<lb/>
hours they were suffering from the effects of yellow fever- and<lb/>
then found eternal rest. Where are their monuments?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03275012"/>
<p><hi>UNSUNG HEROES</hi></p>
<p>It was the common belief of the great medical minds that un-<lb/>
sanitary conditions were the cause of yellow fever. Accordingly, Wal-<lb/>
ter Reed, who was a thorough man, let it be known to the American sol-<lb/>
diers in Cuba that there was another war being waged-a war for saving<lb/>
not destroying men. Were there men who would volunteer? Before the<lb/>
ink was dry on the announcements, four young soldiers reported to<lb/>
Reed.</p>
<p>He built two small huts- One fouler than the dankest of medi-<lb/>
eval dungeons. Here three of those courageous men tried to sleep in<lb/>
filthy cots made up with the bed clothing from yellow fever wards.<lb/>
For twenty nights they stayed there- at great risk they exploded an<lb/>
ancient fallacy. Yet where are their monuments?</p>
<p>The other little hut was thoroughly sanitary but contained<lb/>
deadly mosquitos. Here John Moran,-who knows of him now
?- lay down<lb/>
to sleep. Three days after the attack of the mosquitos he contracted<lb/>
yellow fever- fortunately he was saved, but only to live a life of<lb/>
unmerited obscurity.</p>
<p>Then Walter Reed wrote to his mother: &ldquo;The prayer that has<lb/>
been mine for twenty years, that I might be able to do something to<lb/>
alleviate human suffering, has been granted.&rdquo; It was magical. At<lb/>
this stage Walter Reed, in the prime of his life, but tired, so tired-<lb/>
died; just as the applause of the nation was growing thunderous. &ldquo;I<lb/>
am leaving my wife and daughter so little, so little&rdquo;- he murmured as<lb/>
he passed away into his last dreams.</p>
<p>Thus this strange band has made a rendezvous, each one, with<lb/>
his special and particular fate- a group who worked together so that<lb/>
now there is hardly enough of the yellow fever germ left in the world<lb/>
to put on the points of six pins. What an enobling thought it is that<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03275013"/>
<hi>UNSUNG HEROES</hi><lb/>
it is not expedient to wage wars in order to make our heroes. But<lb/>
that we may proudly boast of these courageous men, who, in peace-<lb/>
time risked their lives for a most ample and demanding cause- humanity.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
