<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03304018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Report: Final Report of the Yellow Fever Committee of the New York Association of Biology Teachers, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03304018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, Ida E.</name>
<name type="person">Wainwright, J. Mayhew</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Copeland, Royal S.</name>
<name type="person">Root, Elihu</name>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Thayer, William S.</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03304018</idno>
<title>Report of the Yellow Fever Committee of the New York Association of Biology Teachers, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The report describes efforts to pass a Congressional bill honoring the yellow fever volunteers and securing pensions.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report of the Yellow Fever Committee of the New York Association of Biology Teachers, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03304018"/>
<p>FROM JAMES E. PEABODY</p>
<p><hi>FINAL REPORT OF THE YELLOW FEVER COMMITTEE</hi><lb/>
OF THE NEW YORK ASSOCIATION OF BIOLOGY TEACHERS</p>
<p>In the autumn of 1926 this Association authorized the appointment<lb/>
of a Committee to consider ways and means of giving much needed help<lb/>
to John R. Kissinger, one of the heroes of those memorable experiments<lb/>
carried on in Cuba in 1900.... experiments which proved that the Aedes<lb/>
aegypti mosquito is the means by which that dread disease of yellow<lb/>
fever is transmitted from one individual to another. The Biology Asso-<lb/>
ciation at once sent money that enabled the Kissingers to pass the win-<lb/>
ter of 1926-1927 in comparative comfort.</p>
<p>In a remarkably short time such generous public interest was<lb/>
awakened that a sum of over $8,000 was collected. &ldquo;Dream Home&rdquo; was<lb/>
purchased together with farm equipment, and the whole was deeded to the<lb/>
Kissingers. The following distinguished Citizens' Committee consented<lb/>
to serve, and has given continuous and valuable assistance:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Harry Emerson Fosdick, Chairman, Riverside Church, New York City.</item>
<item>Henry Bruere, Bowery Savings Bank, New York City.</item>
<item>Dr. John H. Finley, Editor New York &ldquo;Times&rdquo;.</item>
<item>Dr. William H. Welch, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland.</item>
<item>Marcolm H. Ormsbee, O'Mara and Ormsbee, New York City,</item>
<item>Dr. Benjamin C. Gruenberg, Secretary and Treasurer, New York City.</item>
</list>
as the work developed it became increasingly evident that Congress-<lb/>
ional aid should be sought in behalf of all the 22 members that con-<lb/>
stituted that memorable group engaged in the yellow fever experiments.<lb/>
Bills were accordingly introduced in the Senate and the House of Rep-<lb/>
resentatives in Washington early in 1927, but these died in Committee,<lb/>
At the next session of Congress we were most fortunate in enlisting the<lb/>
aid of Senator Royal S. Copeland and Representative J. Mayhew Wain-<lb/>
wright, both of New York State. We cannot express too strongly our in-<lb/>
debtedness to these two men for their devoted service in getting the<lb/>
Wainwright-Copeland Bill through the Committees on Military Affairs of<lb/>
the House and Senate, and in finally accuring favorable action by the<lb/>
70th. Congress. The Bill was signed by President Coolidge, February 28,<lb/>
1929.</p>
<p>This Bill, the first so far as we can learn ever passed by Congress<lb/>
to honor the heroes of science, prescribes 1) that the names of the<lb/>
four members of the Yellow Fever Board and of the 18 men who voluntar-<lb/>
ily submitted to the experiments shall be published each year in the<lb/>
Army Register, together with a statement of what each did; 2) that a<lb/>
special gold medal prepared by the Secretary of the Treasury shall be<lb/>
given to each of these 22 men or to their nearest of kin; and 3) that<lb/>
each of these men or their widows shall receive $125 a month for the<lb/>
rest of their lives. After 29 long years of waiting something like jus-<lb/>
tice has been done. This Bill, too, is important because it establish-<lb/>
ed a precedent which was <unclear>folloed</unclear> almost immediately in the granting of<lb/>
a pension of $125 a month to the widow of Dr. Goldberger who repeatedly<lb/>
contracted infections during scientific investigations and ultimately<lb/>
gave his life in the cause of science.</p>
<p>Legislation similar to that contained in the Wainwright-Copeland<lb/>
Bill was sought early in the century by President Roosevelt and Sec-<lb/>
retary of War Elihu Root. The four Baltimore Doctors (Welch, Thayer,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03304019"/>
(2)<lb/>
Kelly and Howell) General Ireland, Colonel (now General) Kean, and oth-<lb/>
ers tried for years to secure similar legislation, but in vain. The hel,<lb/>
help of these influential men in this three-year campaign cannot be<lb/>
overestimated. Newspaper men and magazine writers, civic and relig-<lb/>
ious organizations, and devoted work on the part of leading scientists<lb/>
and publicists have been of invaluable assistance in securing this final<lb/>
victory.</p>
<p>The Wainwright-Copeland Bill is in every way satisfactory except<lb/>
that it failed to give the higher pensions so needed and long deserved<lb/>
by Mrs. Walter Reed, Mrs. James Carroll, and Mrs. Jesse W. Lazear, whose<lb/>
husbands gave their lives in this yellow fever investigation. To rem-<lb/>
edy this defect Senator Copeland introduced in the Senate last December<lb/>
a Bill to give Mrs. Reed $250 a month, and $200 a month to Mrs. Carroll,<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear and Dr. Agramonte. This Committee had prepared its plea<lb/>
for this Bill and the Boston papers gave generous support to this leg-<lb/>
islation. Senator Copeland and Representative Davenport who made a<lb/>
telling speech at the hearing before the House Committee on Military<lb/>
affairs, urged that copies of these articles, together with the Ameri-<lb/>
Museum pamphlet on the &ldquo;Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo; by the Chairman of<lb/>
this Committee be sent to the House and Senate members.</p>
<p>Early in January, however, Surgeon-General Ireland and General Kean,<lb/>
without whose help our work would have been fruitless, wrote us that<lb/>
they were convinced it would be unwise to press this additional legis-<lb/>
lation at the present time. &ldquo;There is now on foot,&rdquo; they said &ldquo;a move-<lb/>
ment for others who played what we consider minor roles in the work of<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Board to have their names added to the Roll of Honor.<lb/>
If this sort of thing begins, it is impossible to tell where it will<lb/>
end, and the result will be that the Roll of Honor, in losing its limi-<lb/>
tation, will lose much of its dignity and meaning. Of course General<lb/>
Ireland and I, and I suppose everybody else, would be glad to see the<lb/>
Government give the three widows of the Yellow Fever Commission and Dr.<lb/>
Agramonte handsome pensions. At the same time we do not think this is<lb/>
the proper time to do it. The time in the future when there might be<lb/>
a chance for these special pensions is when a fine monument to the Con-<lb/>
quest of Yellow Fever is erected. Further legislation just new would<lb/>
endanger the Reed Roll of Honor which has established the principle for<lb/>
which we were fighting. Meanwhile Mrs. Walter Reed has received an an-<lb/>
nuity from a private source which added to her small pension meets her<lb/>
needs.&rdquo; (After the death of Dr. Agramonte earnest attempts were made<lb/>
for the continuence of his pension for his widow, but these attempts<lb/>
proved to be fruitless. Mrs. Agramonte died in Havana in November, 1933)</p>
<p>This Committee held its final meeting in February, 1930, and voted<lb/>
unanimously that its work had been completed. In asking that the Com-<lb/>
mittee be discharged by the Biology Association, we wish to express our<lb/>
deep gratitude for the loyal and generous support we have received<lb/>
during the past three years, as well as generous financial contributions.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully submitted,</salute>
<signed>Elizabeth T. Fitzpatrick, Secretary, Charles Gramet, Fred W. Hartwell,<lb/>
George T. Hastings, Charles G. Inman, Elsbeth Kroeber, Paul B. Mann,<lb/>
Rosemary F. Mullan, Emily Topp<lb/>
James E. Peabody. Chairman</signed>
A set of 25 lantern slides on Yellow Fever can be obtained from the<lb/>
American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West, New York City.<lb/>
The Chairman of the Committee had 75 lantern slides on this subject.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
