<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03303001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Albert E. Truby] to Frederick F. Russell, January 25, 1933</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03303001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1933-01-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Wasdin [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Geddings [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Indianapolis (Ind.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1933-01-25">January 25, 1933</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03303001</idno>
<title>Letter from [Albert E. Truby] to Frederick F. Russell, January 25, 1933</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby narrates the sequence of events leading to the yellow fever experiments, noting that Walter Reed returned to United States on August 7 and came back to Cuba on October 1, 1900.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1933-01-25">
<head>Letter from [Albert E. Truby] to Frederick F. Russell, January 25, 1933</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03303001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
HEADQUARTERS ARMY MEDICAL CENTER<lb/>
WASHINGTON<lb/>
<date value="1933-01-25">January 25, 1933.</date>
</dateline>
General F. F. Russell,<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation,<lb/>
61 Broadway,<lb/>
New York, N.Y.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was pleased to receive your letter of January 17th. It has taken<lb/>
me some time to look up the dates in connection with Reed's experiments, but<lb/>
I found them all and am very glad to give you all the details.</p>
<p>Major Reed and I left Havana on the Transport &ldquo;Rawlins&rdquo; on the<lb/>
evening of August 2nd, 1900, arriving in New York Harbor on August 7th.<lb/>
Reed was on his way to the United States to read a paper and to attend to<lb/>
other matters. I returned to Camp Columbia on September 18th and automatically<lb/>
became Post Surgeon as Captain Stark was absent on a long leave. Reed returned<lb/>
to Camp Columbia <unclear><hi>October 1,</hi></unclear> 1900.</p>
<p>4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><unclear>,</unclear> Keen</p>
<p>Carroll was bitten by <unclear>one</unclear> of Lazear's mosquitoes on August 27th,<lb/>
taken on sick report August 31st and to the yellow fever wards of the Camp<lb/>
Columbia Hospital on September 1st. Dean (X.Y.) was bitten by Lazear's<lb/>
mosquitoes on August 31st. Lazear was reported to have been bitten by mos-<lb/>
quitoes on September 13th at Las Animas Hospital in Havana. I feel quite sure<lb/>
(and I know that Major Reed felt the same way) that Lazear had bitten himself<lb/>
with the same batch of mosquitoes that had bitten Carroll and X.Y. He was sick<lb/>
for a <unclear>day</unclear> or two before he called in a doctor and was seriously ill in his<lb/>
quarters on the afternoon of September 18th when I returned to Camp Columbia.<lb/>
I saw him with Doctor Ames, our yellow fever expert, and the next morning he was<lb/>
sent to our yellow fever wards (September 19th). Lazear died on September 28,<lb/>
1900.</p>
<p><unclear>(?)</unclear></p>
<p>Reed returned to Camp Columbia on October 1st and was both shocked<lb/>
and thrilled by the events which had happened at Camp Columbia just prior to<lb/>
his return. I had charge of Lazear's effects and turned over to Major Reed<lb/>
all of his papers including a small note book which contained very meager in-<lb/>
formation concerning mosquitoes and the persons bitten. No other records<lb/>
could be found. This small note book was, I understand, in Carroll's possession<lb/>
after Reed's death, and then mysteriously disappeared. I think Kean and<lb/>
Ireland have some information concerning that which I am going to try to obtain.<lb/>
The small note book contained enough information together with the facts known<lb/>
by the doctors at the hospital so that Reed could piece things together and draw<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03303002"/>
up his preliminary report. I remember very distinctly that Carroll, although<lb/>
returned to quarters from the hospital, could give Reed very little infor-<lb/>
mation about anything Lazear had done excepting, of course, his own contact<lb/>
with Lazear's mosquitoes. Carroll and Lazear were working along different<lb/>
lines and the former was distinctly not interested in the latter's work until<lb/>
Carroll became sick. It was on this account that Reed had such a hard time<lb/>
getting facts together for neither Carroll nor Agramonte (who was not at<lb/>
Camp Columbia at all up to this time) could tell him anything about Lazear's<lb/>
work.</p>
<p>Knowing that two British investigators, who had visited Reed at<lb/>
Camp Columbia in June or July, 1900, might get similar results in their<lb/>
experiments in South America, Reed felt that an immediate report of Lazear's<lb/>
results should be published. So he started in immediately and drew up his<lb/>
paper, during the next week, entitled &ldquo;The Etiology of Yellow Fever: A<lb/>
Preliminary Note.&rdquo; On October 14, 1900 he sailed from Havana enroute to<lb/>
the States to read this paper at Indianapolis, Indiana before the American<lb/>
Public Health Association at their annual meeting, October 21-27, 1900.</p>
<p><unclear>?</unclear></p>
<p>On October <unclear>31st</unclear> he sailed from New York for Havana and then im-<lb/>
mediately took up the work of definitely proving the statements made in his<lb/>
preliminary note. This paper was bitterly attacked by several people, but<lb/>
especially by Wasdin and Geddings of the Public Health Service. Their<lb/>
article was, I think, published in the Philadelphia Medical Journal <add><del><unclear></unclear></del></add><del>a week<lb/>
or two after</del> Reed's article appeared <del>in the same journal.</del> As soon as I get<lb/>
time I am going to try to find these two articles.</p>
<p>I think the above will answer all of your questions, especially<lb/>
the one about Reed's return to the States on October 14th and the fact that<lb/>
Carroll was actually bitten by Lazear's mosquitoes. If I can give you any<lb/>
other information it will be a great pleasure to do so.</p>
<p>With best regards,</p>
<p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
<p>-2-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
