<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03321001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Sidney Coe Howard to Walter De Blois Briggs, August 11, 1934</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Howard, Sidney Coe</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03321001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1934-08-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Briggs, Walter De Blois</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">de Kruif, Paul</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1934-08-11">August 11, 1934</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03321001</idno>
<title>Letter from Sidney Coe Howard to Walter De Blois Briggs, August 11, 1934</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Howard offers a justification of his characterization of Dean in his play, "Yellow Jack."</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1934-08-11">
<head>Letter from Sidney Coe Howard to Walter De Blois Briggs, August 11, 1934</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03321001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Bar Harbor, Maine<lb/>
<date value="1934-08-11">August 11th, 1934.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mr. Briggs,</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am very glad indeed to have your letter about YELLOW<lb/>
JACK and thank you for the fine things you say about the play.<lb/>
I am sorry that you were thrown off by the Dean scene, because<lb/>
it is one of the episodes which makes Lazear most attractive to<lb/>
me. It goes without saying that I am a layman and not a doctor.<lb/>
As such, however, I am deeply stirred by a man who ran the risk<lb/>
of involving himself all but criminally to establish a truth of<lb/>
such value to the mass of human kind. You are not interested,<lb/>
however, in my reactions to that scene, any of which you must<lb/>
have deduced from the fact that I wrote it. What you want, I<lb/>
take it, is my historical justification for it. I have in my<lb/>
files in New York a photostat of a pamphlet written by Agramonte,<lb/>
who claimed to have been present at the time -- it may well be<lb/>
the same to which you have reference. My impression from that<lb/>
pamphlet was that Lazear had tricked Dean. My impression was<lb/>
further substantiated by the fact that in Reed's case reports<lb/>
only Dean's name is suppressed. You will find, if you look at<lb/>
them, that he is always mentioned as &ldquo;Private X.Y.&rdquo; and it is<lb/>
my impression -- though I should have to consult my notes to<lb/>
make sure of this -- that Dean never did know how he got yellow<lb/>
fever, due to the fact that he died <add>he did not die</add> before his identity ever<lb/>
appeared in print. My faith in Dr. Agramonte's statement,<lb/>
however, was shaken when one of the officers who cooperated in<lb/>
the experiment told me, with substantial evidence to back up his<lb/>
statement, that Agramonte had nothing whatever to do with that<lb/>
episode and indeed little or nothing to do with any of the ex-<lb/>
periment, that he stayed in his own laboratory in Havana City,<lb/>
very seldom came out to Columbia Barracks and was neither liked<lb/>
nor trusted by his associates. I have no authority for the<lb/>
characterization I have given him in the play except the inalien-<lb/>
able right of a dramatist to make any role as interesting as possible.<lb/>
Returning, however, to the Dean episode: I asked Kissinger about<lb/>
it and Kissinger told me that he had understood that Dean was not<lb/>
infected in the laboratory but in barracks while he was asleep in<lb/>
his bunk. Moran, on the other hand, claimed to know the details<lb/>
of Dean's infection from Reed himself and to have learned them<lb/>
during the time when he was in quarantine in Camp Lazear and earned<lb/>
money from Reed by typing Reed's case reports for him. In other<lb/>
words, I think I am substantially correct in the play's treatment<lb/>
of the episode except that I included both Agramonte and Finlay<lb/>
in the scene and I have no authority for Finlay's presence and<lb/>
added it only because it helped me to write the scene and certainly<lb/>
did no historical damage. I am sorry that the scene has caused<lb/>
Dr. Lazear's family so much uneasiness. You need not, I think,<lb/>
concern yourselves with the movies. They are most unlikely to<lb/>
take any interest in a play which so assiduously avoids the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03321002"/>
Bar Harbor, Maine<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
romantic note. In fact, de Kruif and I have insisted on our<lb/>
supervision of any picture to be made from the play and have<lb/>
thereby killed Hollywood's slight interest in it.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Faithfully yours,</salute>
<signed><hi>Sidney Howard</hi></signed>.
Walter de Blois Briggs, Esquire.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
