<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03323001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Recollections of Personal Experiences in Connection with Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana 1898-1899-1900, by Chauncey B. Baker, November 5, 1934</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03323001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1934-11-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Williams, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Waring, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Cartwright, George</name>
<name type="person">Peterson, Matt</name>
<name type="person">Peterson, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Page, Capt.</name>
<name type="person">Dodge, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Hanna, Lt.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Brooks, E.C.</name>
<name type="person">Ferguson, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Laine, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Army Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1934-11-05">November 5, 1934</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03323001</idno>
<title>Recollections of Personal Experiences in Connection with Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana 1898-1899-1900, by Chauncey B. Baker, November 5, 1934</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Baker describes his personal experiences in connection with yellow fever epidemics in Havana, Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1934-11-05">
<head>Recollections of Personal Experiences in Connection with Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana 1898-1899-1900, by Chauncey B. Baker, November 5, 1934</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03323001"/>
<opener>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<hi>Recollections of Personal Experiences<lb/>
In Connection With<lb/>
Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana<lb/>
1898 - 1899 - 1900</hi><lb/>
Related By<lb/>
General Chauncey B. Baker<lb/>
<dateline>
At Luncheon To<lb/>
The Board of Directors Of<lb/>
The American National Fire Insurance Company<lb/>
on<lb/>
<date value="1934-11-05">November 5, 1934</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<pb n="2" id="f03323002"/>
<p>Recollections of Personal Experiences<lb/>
In Connection With<lb/>
Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana<lb/>
1898 - 1899 - 1900</p>
<p>------------------</p>
<p>(Dictated by Request)</p>
<p>Our Secretary, Mr. McLelland, has asked me to place<lb/>
on record the recital I gave at a recent meeting of out Board<lb/>
of Kirectors of episodes connected with Walter Reed and his inves-<lb/>
tigations and discoveries with reference to yellow fever.</p>
<p>In November, 1898, after we had taken Santiago and<lb/>
peace had been made, a Peace Commission, of which General Wade<lb/>
was President for the United States and General Blanco for the<lb/>
Spanish Government, was formed for the purpose of arranging the<lb/>
details of transfer of the governmental authority from the Spanish<lb/>
Crown to the United States Government. During the sittings of<lb/>
this Commission, which commenced in August, an epidemic of yellow<lb/>
fever broke out in Havana. Colonel Williams, of the United States<lb/>
Army, and Colonel Waring, head of the Sanitary Department of New<lb/>
York City, had been ordered to Havana to make preliminary provis-<lb/>
ions of transfer, respectively, of everything pertaining to the<lb/>
Quartermaster's Department and to sanitation.</p>
<p>In November these two officers, together with a large<lb/>
number of their clerical force, died of yellow fever. I was or-<lb/>
dered to Havana to take over the office of Colonel Williams and<lb/>
another officer was ordered there to take up the work of Colonel<lb/>
Waring. The second officer did not arrive, so when I reached<lb/>
Havana in November I found myself at the head of the Quartermas-<lb/>
ter's Department until the final withdrawal of our troops on the<lb/>
twentieth of May, 1902.</p>
<p>There was much sickness at this period and great anx-<lb/>
iety on account of the prevalence of yellow fever. Colonel<lb/>
Williams and Colonel Waring had occupied an office jointly next<lb/>
door to the Passaje Hotel on the Prado. Practically all the<lb/>
clerks of both these offices met me on my arrival, with resignat-<lb/>
ion in one hand and a request for transportation back to the<lb/>
United States in the other. Of the few who remained, notably<lb/>
Sergeant Merzig and Mr. Curry, I proceeded to build a new organ-<lb/>
ization for both services.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03323003"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>As the colder weather came on, the yellow fever conditions<lb/>
decreased in intensity and did not reappear again in epidemic form<lb/>
until two years later, in 1900. In that year, symptoms of the epid-<lb/>
emic appeared in Havana and various outlying centers, notably Pinar<lb/>
del Rio, Guanajai, Vedado, Quemados and various military stations.<lb/>
At this time I had become the Chief Quartermaster of the Depart-<lb/>
ment of Cuba-- General Humphrey, my predecessor, having been or-<lb/>
dered to duty in China. I occupied for my office the building<lb/>
then known as the Segundo Cabo, facing the Plaza on which was loc-<lb/>
ated the Governor General's Palace. In this same building were<lb/>
located the offices of Chief Paymaster and Chief Commissary. In<lb/>
a vacant room on the second floor of this building we organized<lb/>
a small mess, where we served our luncheons. There were eight<lb/>
people who were members of this mess, including my principal assis-<lb/>
tant, Major George Cartwright, Major Matt Peterson, Chief Commiss-<lb/>
ary Officer, Mrs. Peterson, his wife, Captain Page, and an aide-de-<lb/>
camp to the Commanding General, Colonel Dodge, the Chief Paynaster,<lb/>
Lieutenant Hanna, an aide-de-camp to the Commanding General, General<lb/>
Wood.</p>
<p>The earliest deaths from yellow fever during this epidemic<lb/>
occurred outside the limits of Havans, at Pinar del Rio and MarianaO.<lb/>
The first of this group at mess to go down with yellow fever was<lb/>
Major George Cartwright, my principal assistant, who died of the<lb/>
disease. Sitting at his left was Major Peterson, who went down with<lb/>
the disease and died. Mrs. Peterson was ill at the time and when<lb/>
she was told by Major Gorgas that he feared she had contracted the<lb/>
disease, she produced a pistol from her bag and shot herself. On<lb/>
the next day, as I followed this double funeral to the last rest-<lb/>
ing place, a carriage ahead of me turned out and I paused long<lb/>
inough to speak with the occupant, Captain Page, who informed me<lb/>
that he was so ill he could not proceed. I told him I would go on<lb/>
to the funeral and as soon as I got back would get in touch with<lb/>
him. Page occupied quarters at the top story of Segundo Cabo.<lb/>
When I returned to my office I found him there, unable to climb the<lb/>
stairs to his quarters, and with help I assisted him to his room<lb/>
at the top of the building. Within forty-eight hours he died of<lb/>
yellow fever. The next to be stricken with the disease was Colonel<lb/>
Dodge, Chief Paymaster of the Department. Fortunately, he recovered<lb/>
and later became Paymaster General of the Army. The nexp place at<lb/>
the table was vacant as Lieutenant Hanna had taken a leave of absence,<lb/>
returned to the United States, and later resigned his commission in<lb/>
the Army. That left Captain E. C. Brooks and me looking across the<lb/>
corner aof the table at on another.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03323004"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>At the advice of the surgeons, we had been in the habit of<lb/>
serving a small quantity of red wine at luncheon. Someone of the<lb/>
group, at the early inception of the epidemic, had proposed the<lb/>
old English toast: &ldquo;To those who are gone already and here's to<lb/>
the next to go&rdquo;. This toast was drunk daily until Brooks and I<lb/>
were left looking across the corner of the table at one another.<lb/>
Then, when he poured out a glass of wine, and pushed the decanter<lb/>
to me, he lifted his glass and gave the toast. I remember saying:<lb/>
&ldquo;Brooks, I won't drink that toast to myself. You had yellow fever<lb/>
in Santiago and are immune and won't have it again. Besides that,<lb/>
you are a teetotaler and don't drink. So I'll drink my wine, but<lb/>
not the toast&rdquo;. He laughed and neither he nor I was stricken with<lb/>
the disease.</p>
<p>During this same period, one after the other I placed five<lb/>
men in charge of Major Cartwright's papers, which I was anxious<lb/>
should be closed up as promptly as possible, especially in view of<lb/>
the conditions that existed. In order to make sure that they<lb/>
would be promptly closed and worked upon continuously, I set<lb/>
aside a small room back of my own office and I assigned a clerk to<lb/>
this special duty. The first that I placed in charge was Mr.<lb/>
Ferguson, a civilian clerk, wupposed to be immune, having passed<lb/>
through mor than one epidemic in New Orleans. Within twenty-four<lb/>
hours after he took charge of the papers he come to me and said<lb/>
he was too ill to go on. The next day he was dead of yellow fever.<lb/>
One after the other, five men working on these papers went down<lb/>
with yellow fever. The fifth man went down but fortunately recov-<lb/>
ered and finished the papers.</p>
<p>About this time Major Gorgas came to me and asked me<lb/>
to take his yellow fever ambulance (one that he had been using to<lb/>
haul yellow fever patients) into the shops and overhaul it. He<lb/>
assured me that there could not possibly be any contamination con-<lb/>
nected with the ambulance and it could not possibly communicate<lb/>
the disease. I explained to Gorgas that I would be very glad to<lb/>
take the ambulance in and put it through the shops, and had no mis-<lb/>
givings in regard to the communication of the disease, but I fear-<lb/>
ed for the morale of the men working on the ambulance if they knew<lb/>
it was an ambulance used to carry yellow fever patients. &ldquo;Well&rdquo;,<lb/>
he said, &ldquo;we'll try not to let them know that that is the case&rdquo;,<lb/>
and he suggested that he leave the ambulance out in the weather<lb/>
and I could pick it up and take it into my establishment and send<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03323005"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
him another ambulance to take the place of it temporarily. This<lb/>
I did. The result was that one ofter the other, the Wheelwright,<lb/>
the blacksmith, the finisher, the painter, and the superintendent<lb/>
of shops all went down with yellow fever, and all died.</p>
<p>In the meantime, Major Reed, at the head of the Board<lb/>
that has made him his greatest fame, and all members of which be-<lb/>
came famous, came to Havana for the purpose of investigating the<lb/>
source and possible prevention of the disease. In my capacity of<lb/>
Chief Quartermaster I set up his office, furnished it for him,<lb/>
furnished him transportation, and built the small buildings in which<lb/>
he carried out his investigations and experiments. I was in con-<lb/>
stant contact with him. I had already known him when he came to<lb/>
the Seventh Army Corps to amke the study of the typhoid epidemed,<lb/>
when he headed the Board known as the Reed-Vaughn-S hakespeare<lb/>
Board, and whose report is known to medical men throughout the<lb/>
world for its scientific determination of the means by which that<lb/>
diseases is carried.</p>
<p>Dr. Carlos Finley, an American physician who had<lb/>
lived and practiced in Havana for many years, had advanced the<lb/>
theory, with the result that by the end of the year 1900 he had<lb/>
conclusively shown, together with the other members of his Board<lb/>
consisting of Majors Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte, that the mos-<lb/>
quito was the guilty party in the dessemination of this dread<lb/>
disease. The methods by which he arrived at this conclusion are<lb/>
well known to the medical profession and the details of the small<lb/>
buildings which he used in determining this, are also well known.</p>
<p>Each one was divided into three compartments. The sub-<lb/>
ject would enter the first compartment after having all mosquitoes<lb/>
carefully driven away, remove his clothing, enter the next compart-<lb/>
ment and clothe himself in sleeping garments, and from there he<lb/>
would enter his sleeping apartment where he remained during the<lb/>
perion of the experiment. In order to test the possibility of the<lb/>
communication of this disease by direct contact or contamination,<lb/>
the garments and bedding in which patients had died of the disease<lb/>
were placed in the sleeping compartment of one of these buildings.<lb/>
In no case was yellow fever contracted by this means.</p>
<p>In order to satisfy the Board, infected mosquitoes<lb/>
were bottled up and after the subject had entered his sleeping<lb/>
compartment were permitted to bite him. In some instances yellow<lb/>
fever resulted, in others there was no result. By continued<lb/>
experiment it was found that only a certain breed of mosquito<lb/>
communicated the disease and eventually it was discovered that only<lb/>
the female of that breed was guilty. With further experimentation<lb/>
it was found that even she was not always capable of transmitting<lb/>
the disease. To make the transmission effective, it was necessary<lb/>
that the mosquito bite a patient suffering from the malady and at<lb/>
a particular stage of development, and in communicating it, it<lb/>
was necessary that the mosquito bite the victim at a certain time<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03323006"/>
-5-<lb/>
(about five days) after having bitten an infected person. The<lb/>
result of this was that after less than six months of experiment-<lb/>
ation, Walter Reed was able to publish his findings, to the effect<lb/>
that the disease is carried by nothing else but the mosquito, and<lb/>
one breed of mosquito, and only the female of that breed, at a cer-<lb/>
tain stage after having bitten a yellow fever patient.</p>
<p>Both Dr. Lazear and Major Carrloo submitted themselves<lb/>
to this test. Lazear, as everyone knows, was so infortunate as to<lb/>
die in this experiment. Carroll recovered but was never an entirely<lb/>
well man afterward. Practically all members of the Hospital Corps<lb/>
on duty at that time at Camp Columbis in Marianao most heroically<lb/>
submitted themselves for this tset. Fortunately, none of these<lb/>
men died. It was my pleasure, not long ago, to witness the placing<lb/>
of medals on the breasts of two of the survivors, after a period of<lb/>
something more than thirty years after the occurrence.</p>
<p>Major Reed became very much interested in my personal<lb/>
experience in connection with the disease and was rather curious as<lb/>
to why I had not been taken down with the disease, having been<lb/>
constantly living in the same conditions that so many others had<lb/>
lived and had been stricken--- in the mess and in my office and in<lb/>
the carral. It could easily be understood that the mosquito was<lb/>
the guilty party, but it could not be understood why the mosquitoes<lb/>
would not bite me as well as all of those others. He asked me<lb/>
about my medical experience during the period when I had served<lb/>
in Havana. I told him that I had been taken down with what the<lb/>
attending surgeon called calentura, and was in bed for two days,<lb/>
but continued to perform my duties from my sick-bed. He consulted<lb/>
with the attending surgeon, Major Laine, and they arrived at the<lb/>
conclusion that the fever I had had, which had been called calen-<lb/>
tura, was in all probability a light case of yellow fever and had<lb/>
not been discovered, which rendered me immune to the bites of the<lb/>
mosquito.</p>
<p>One of the most interesting features of this final discovery is to<lb/>
be found in the comparison with what was actually known of the dis-<lb/>
ease before these experiments were undertaken. For example, in<lb/>
cases it was found that the disease was curbed by prospective<lb/>
victims seeking certain localities, usually dry and free of mos-<lb/>
quitoes. In the City of Jacksonville the entire population maved<lb/>
out into the sand-hills from the city and established themselves<lb/>
in tents and temporary quarters. The men would habitually go in<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03323007"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
to the city during the daytime to ordinary business, always return-<lb/>
ing before nightfall to the sand-hills. In that way the disease<lb/>
was finally obliterated without their knowledge of the reason why.</p>
<p>As a matter of fact, the yellow fever mosquito, as a<lb/>
rule, does not go far away from her breeding place. She is not<lb/>
active except in a dark or gloomy corner or room, aor after night-<lb/>
fall. Another incident that had been noted and commented on was<lb/>
that the disease might start on a street and continue until it<lb/>
reached a high wall and ther it would be checked until something<lb/>
happened and it would seem to jump the wall and go on down the<lb/>
street. What happened was that the winds carried the infected<lb/>
mosquitoes over the wall where they continued their depradations.<lb/>
Another thing, it would go down one side ot the street and leave the<lb/>
other side free of this dread disease, until all those conditions<lb/>
would change and it would junp across the street and go down the<lb/>
other side. This was puzzling, but after the detection of the<lb/>
culprit it was easily explained. The winds would come right to<lb/>
carry the mosquitoes over the walls where they would proceed in<lb/>
their nefarious calling, or the winds would change and blow them<lb/>
across the street and there the mosquitoes would start a new<lb/>
center of infection. All of the phenomena that had been witnessed<lb/>
and commented upon in connection with yellow fever before Walter<lb/>
Reed's discovery, found a simple explanation as soon as he had<lb/>
determined that the mosquito was the culprit. The room in which<lb/>
our group held its luncheons was infested with mosquitoes which<lb/>
evidently buzzed about in the cark corners, the room being ill-<lb/>
lighted. The room in which the clerks worked on Major Cartwright's<lb/>
papers was a dark room infested with mosquitoes. All of the employ-<lb/>
ees at the shops slept in the same quarters, which were found to<lb/>
be infested with mosquitoes. All of the members of the Reed Board<lb/>
are now dead but they have left behind them their places in the his-<lb/>
tory of medical discovery that will remain so long as the medical<lb/>
profession exists.</p>
<p>I wish to add to this recital that it was of great in-<lb/>
terest to me to find that General Yruby, now in command of the<lb/>
Army Medical Center, Washington, D. C., of which Walter Reed<lb/>
Hospital is a part, was a young officer of the Medical Corps<lb/>
during the entire period of the first occupation. Truby was the<lb/>
first medical officer to reach Havana. The Eighth and Tenth In-<lb/>
fantry Regiments were on provost-martial duty in Havana until<lb/>
August, 1899, when they maved to Camp Columbia. Reed came to Cuba<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f03323008"/>
- 7 -<lb/>
and was a close personal friend of his. He and the other members<lb/>
of the Board, except Agramonte, accepted the invitaion to live<lb/>
with the Medical Staff at the Hospital at the Camp. It was a<lb/>
great satisfaction, in a recent period of hospitalization, to talk<lb/>
with General Truby and crystallize my recollections aof the incid-<lb/>
ents herein related.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
