<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03330001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to James E. Peabody, March 12, 1935</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03330001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1935-03-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Peabody, James E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Frances F.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Cespedes, Pres.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1935-03-12">March 12, 1935</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03330001</idno>
<title>Letter from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to James E. Peabody, March 12, 1935</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Leon thanks Peabody for his work in securing pensions for yellow fever participants. She discusses her mother's death and conditions in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1935-03-12">
<head>Letter from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to James E. Peabody, March 12, 1935</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03330001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Vedado, Havana, Cuba,<lb/>
<date value="1935-03-12">March 12, 1935.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. James E. Peabody,<lb/>
New York.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mr. Peabody:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In the process of settling down again in a new home after many<lb/>
months of terrible experiences, I found a drawer full of letters,<lb/>
which Mother was unable to answer before her death on November<lb/>
29, 1933. Your kind letter of September 26th of that year was<lb/>
among them. I can assure you that she reread it many times, and<lb/>
that her last days were made happier by the knowledge that you<lb/>
were to deliver lectures on mosquito-control in so many schools<lb/>
and during the special memorial session for Major Reed at the<lb/>
annual meeting of the A. P. H. Ass.</p>
<p>The deep-felt gratitude with which she followed your constant ef-<lb/>
forts on behalf of her pension makes me feel ashamed not to have<lb/>
written to you before this. Last April, upon receiving a note<lb/>
from Gen. Kean, I answered it informing him of her passing away,<lb/>
but until a short time ago I had not been able to find your ad-<lb/>
dress.</p>
<p>During the last months of her two-year illness I was often tempt-<lb/>
ed to write you. The nature of her disease -- cancer -- if known<lb/>
over there might have helped in obtaining the pension, since it<lb/>
would have been enjoyed only for so short a time. But I always<lb/>
gave up the idea of telling our sad secret, for fear that the<lb/>
publicity necessary in favoring your kind enterprise would reach<lb/>
her in some way, adding the moral pain of anticipation to her in-<lb/>
evitable physical sufferings. At the time of the first symptoms<lb/>
(December, 1931) her disease was already too far advanced for<lb/>
surgery; the only palliatives were X Ray and Radium treatments.<lb/>
We were fortunate in deceiving her always about the seriousness<lb/>
of her condition, and in avoiding the intensive pain of most<lb/>
cases similar to hers, thanks to radium and opiates. It was be-<lb/>
yond our power to relieve the discomforts of an ever-increasing<lb/>
weakness and anemia.</p>
<p>You probably knew that I held a position in the Machado Govern-<lb/>
ment. It was the only available job on our return from New Or-<lb/>
leans. The salary was sufficient, together with the difference<lb/>
in the rent of our larger home, to cover our living expenses.<lb/>
Naturally Mother's treatments and nursing could not come out of<lb/>
that; but the sale of family jewels and what &ldquo;objects d'art&rdquo; we<lb/>
still possessed took care of those extraordinaries. My work in<lb/>
the Presidential Household implied, of course, giving up my pro-<lb/>
fessorship at the University, then very much entangled in the po-<lb/>
litical intrigue which finally brought about Machado's downfall.<lb/>
It was during the days that preceded the Revolution and later,<lb/>
during the twenty-one-day-period of President Cespedes (when I<lb/>
still held my position) that I frequently intended to make a<lb/>
desperate appeal for her pension. It would have permitted us<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03330002"/>
2.<lb/>
leave Cuba, thus avoiding the hardships of civil war, which in her<lb/>
critical condition meant almost certain death. By the first of Oc-<lb/>
tober I was already without a job. The terrible events that follow-<lb/>
ed: the cannonade of the National Hotel five blocks from where we<lb/>
lived; the killing in the streets; the utter impossibility for days<lb/>
and days of obtaining medical supplies or adequate diet for a sick-<lb/>
room. I am sure all this precipitated her end.</p>
<p>I was engaged at the time to a Major in the Cuban Army, who was<lb/>
made a prisoner during the siege of the National Hotel, together<lb/>
with 200 other fellow-officers. In March, 1934, he was set free<lb/>
and we were quietly married. At first he was obliged to leave the<lb/>
country; three months ago he returned and we are trying to remake<lb/>
our home. He is also a lawyer, but in Cuba's present unsettled<lb/>
state, there seems to be no opening for a man beginning a new ca-<lb/>
reer at the age of thirty-eight. Though hard up, we are very hap-<lb/>
py together. A man of culture, with an excellent library saved<lb/>
from the wreck, we lead a quiet, retired, bookish life. With a<lb/>
few private lessons I am giving to the children of old society<lb/>
friends, I help to make ends meet and pay some of the debts still<lb/>
pending since the last weeks of Mother's illness.</p>
<p>After all the strain of the past three years the mere lack of money<lb/>
is hardly an inconvenience. We are both young and strong; it was<lb/>
different when Mother, in her grievous illness, depended on me for<lb/>
her every need and care. Sometimes, feeling I would be unable to<lb/>
provide what was necessary, I desperately longed for her U. S. pen-<lb/>
sion. Shortly after her death, it was granted. In Cuba also, the<lb/>
civil pensions are now being paid quite regularly; they were twen-<lb/>
ty months behind during all that time. Both arrived too late. I<lb/>
feel certain satisfaction in remembering that she suffered no ac-<lb/>
tual want, though of course deprived of many dainties and comforts,<lb/>
I might have desired to offer her. I prefer not to think what<lb/>
would have happened if she had lived many months more without an<lb/>
allowance of some kind. There is no bitterness in my memories of<lb/>
all those sorrowful circumstances. My grief at her loss has grad-<lb/>
ually passed into that stage of fatalistic submission which the<lb/>
living feel towards the unknown mystery of death; especially when<lb/>
life becomes as difficult as it now is, on our unhappy Island. If<lb/>
I bother you with the long tale of our woes, it is because I always<lb/>
felt I owed your kind sympathy in our tribulations some kind of an<lb/>
explanation.</p>
<p>But it is high time I brought this long letter to a close. Please<lb/>
forgive my many grammatical mistakes; English does not come to me<lb/>
as easily as it did to both my parents.</p>
<p>One more favor I would like to ask of you. Mother spoke to me<lb/>
several times about a book on Biology which you were editing and<lb/>
in which some reference was made to the work of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission. Am I imposing upon your kindness in requesting you to<lb/>
allow me a copy of it?</p>
<p>Are you still desirous of getting in touch with Mr. Moran of this<lb/>
city? If so, I would gladly try to find his present address for<lb/>
you.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03330003"/>
<p>3.</p>
<p>Please believe, Mr. Peabody, in the sincerity of my gratitude for<lb/>
all your own, and the Biology Teachers Association's generous ef-<lb/>
forts on behalf of my dear Mother. You can hardly imagine how<lb/>
much your letters helped in keeping up her spirits during her two<lb/>
years of illness. She never once lost hopes of obtaining her pen-<lb/>
sion. Her American birth, childhood and maidenhood seemed to<lb/>
sustain her faith in the justice of her claim to U. S. recognition.<lb/>
It was not your fault that her trust was rewarded too late.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Gratefully yours,</salute>
<signed>ESTELA AGRAMONTE de RODRIGUEZ LEON</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
