<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03333001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from James E. Peabody to the Members of the New York Association of Biology Teachers, May 5, 1935</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03333001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1935-05-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ward, George Sherman</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Gilchrist, Harry L.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1935-05-05">May 5, 1935</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03333001</idno>
<title>Letter from James E. Peabody to the Members of the New York Association of Biology Teachers, May 5, 1935</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Peabody urges support of a bill granting posthumous recognition to George Sherman Ward and a pension to his survivors, in recognition of Ward's part in James Carroll's typhoid experiment, in 1904.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1935-05-05">
<head>Letter from James E. Peabody to the Members of the New York Association of Biology Teachers, May 5, 1935</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03333001"/>
<opener>
FROM JAMES E. PEABODY<lb/>
<salute>To the Members of the New York Association of Biology Teachers:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On the last evening of April I attended the funeral of George Sherman<lb/>
Ward at the Columbus Chapel in New York. It is probable that no one of you<lb/>
ever heard of Ward. Neither had I until my visit with my good friends,<lb/>
General Kean and General <del>Kean</del><add>Gilchrist</add> in Washington on my way home from Florida.</p>
<p>Our Biology Association has the proud record of leadership in securing<lb/>
in 1929 the passage by Congress of the Bill to give perpetual honor, <add>a</add> gold medal<lb/>
and <add>a</add> pension<del>s</del> of $1800 a year to each of those 22 men who were engaged in those<lb/>
momentous yellow fever demonstrations in Cuba in 1900. I therefore venture to<lb/>
call your attention to the story of a man who surely deserves to be classed<lb/>
with John R. Kissinger, <add>and</add> John J. Moran, as a volunteer in the cause of science.<lb/>
Ward's story, briefly told, is as follows.</p>
<p>Back in 1904 Dr. James Carroll, one of the four members of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board, was confident he had developed an anti-typhoid serum. He had tried it<lb/>
on rabbits and guinea pigs, but he needed human beings to experiment upon<lb/>
before publishing his discovery. Ten men volunteered for this service and<lb/>
they were given through the mouth the anti-typhoid serum diluted in water.<lb/>
It was later proved that the mixture had been imperfectly sterilized. All<lb/>
but two of the men (they had previously had typhoid fever) were stricken with<lb/>
the disease, and some of them barely escaped death.</p>
<p>The account of these experiments has never been published because of the<lb/>
effect it would have on the army medical service. Recently, however, Gen-<lb/>
eral Gilchrist has prepared a complete report, and has included a statement<lb/>
of the experiences of each of the volunteers. Ten years after Carroll's<lb/>
experiments the present method of intra-venous injection was perfected by<lb/>
General F. F. Russell, now Chairman of the International Health Board of the<lb/>
Rockefeller Foundation.</p>
<p>One of the volunteers in that unfortunate experiment of 1904 was George S.<lb/>
Ward. He has suffered from his experiences, especially during these later<lb/>
years. Senator Copeland, who sponsored our Yellow Fever Bill in the Senate,<lb/>
introduced a bill to give Mr. Ward the $125 a month pension which the yellow<lb/>
fever heroes or their widows and the widow of Dr. Goldberger have been re-<lb/>
ceiving. I <unclear>found</unclear> on visiting Senator Copeland's office that there is little<lb/>
hope that this bill will be passed. General Gilchrist, however, writes me<lb/>
as follows after receiving my letter informing him of Ward's death: &ldquo;I intend<lb/>
to work just as hard for the passage of Ward's Bill. Although the recognition<lb/>
must be <del>pos</del> a posthumous one, it may be a great help to the members of his<lb/>
immediate family.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I hesitate to suggest that our Biology Association might be able to help<lb/>
in this most worthy cause. Mr. S. L. Frooks, of the firm of Frooks and Frooks,<lb/>
369 Lexington Avenue, who has worked devotedly to secure assistance for Ward,<lb/>
as well as General H. L. Gilchrist of the Army Mediacl Museum, Washington, D. <unclear>C.</unclear><lb/>
will be able to give all information needed. Cannot you biology teachers in<lb/>
your classes at least pay tribute to this another hero who volunteered in the<lb/>
service for humanity, and who at the age of 54 has passed from among us?</p>
<closer>
<signed>James E. Peabody (formerly at Morris High Sch<lb/>
Ashburnham, Mass., May 5th., 1935</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
