<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03349001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter fragment to Albert E. Truby, July 15, 1936</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03349001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1936-07-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1936-07-15">July 15, 1936</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03349001</idno>
<title>Letter fragment to Albert E. Truby, July 15, 1936</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The writer urges Truby to place his yellow fever correspondence in an archive for safekeeping and compliments Kean personally and professionally.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1936-07-15">
<head>Letter fragment to Albert E. Truby, July 15, 1936</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03349001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
1870 Wyoming Avenue,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.,<lb/>
<date value="1936-07-15">July 15, 1936</date>
</dateline>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<salute>My dear Truby,</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you very much for the interest you took about Trans-<lb/>
America. I not only received a letter with all the data I wanted but<lb/>
they put me in touch with the firm here in Washington which handles that<lb/>
stock. I am very much pleased with conditions as they are now and I have<lb/>
no fear whatever but that I am going to come out more than all right with<lb/>
my 524 shares. Isn't it too bad that poor old Kennedy could not have saved<lb/>
some of the stock that he made his fortune in? I think one of the greatest<lb/>
assets of Trans-America is A. P. Gianinne. I hope the Good Lord will let<lb/>
him live to a ripe old age. He saved the entire institution by coming back<lb/>
into the business after the New York crowd of financiers had practically<lb/>
put it on the rocks.</p>
<p>I have had a couple of talks with Hitch and he has been around to<lb/>
see Judge Pollard, the Chairman of the Board. The answer is exactly the<lb/>
same as it was six months ago--none resign, few die and Hitch made another<lb/>
observation this morning to the effect that they are all looking remarkably<lb/>
well. I am sorry. I would love it if you and Mrs. Truby could come back<lb/>
here. Then we would have the opportunity to see you and play with you both.</p>
<p>I have not seen either one of your daughters since we returned June<lb/>
16th but Richard LaGarde, who is here in the room, says that they are both<lb/>
fine. He saw them on Sunday.</p>
<p>Kean was nice enough to show me the correspondence you have had about<lb/>
the yellow fever work in Cuba. That is historic and should be placed<lb/>
where it will be available. You were so quiet about the thing that I never<lb/>
knew you were mixed up in it until you let loose one day when you were in<lb/>
my office. Kean intends to have your letter filed with the rest of the<lb/>
records. It is needless for me to say that I agree with you in everything<lb/>
you say about Kean, one of the most charming men that I ever knew with a<lb/>
constructive mind who did constructive work for the Medical Corps of the<lb/>
Army that will last as long as the Corps lasts. There was just some ele-<lb/>
ment in Kean's make-up that did not permit him to arrive. He was just<lb/>
within grasp of the Surgeon Generalcy on several occasions. The President<lb/>
had told a dozen people that he was going to make Kean Surgeon General and<lb/>
when the time came he didn't do it. That was when General O'Reilly went<lb/>
out.</p>
<p>Yesterday I telephoned to Kean and told him I would come to get him<lb/>
at 11 o'clock today and that we would then go to see Colonel Coe and then<lb/>
have lunch at the Club. We are going to take Lynch with us. Kean was just<lb/>
on the point of telephoning to me to the effect that Mrs. Coe had had a<lb/>
cerebral hemorrhage the day before and was in the Garfield Hospital. It may<lb/>
be that we will have to go over there to see Coe. I am sorry, of course,<lb/>
but since it has happened I hope the end will not be long delayed. You<lb/>
probably know that she is disabled on account of the fracture of the hip</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
