<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03401001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Radio script for The Heroes of the Yellow Fever Experiments in Cuba in 1900, prepared and produced by Young and Rubicam, January 10, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03401001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-01-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-01-10">January 10, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03401001</idno>
<title>Radio script for The Heroes of the Yellow Fever Experiments in Cuba in 1900, prepared and produced by Young and Rubicam, January 10, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This radio script presents a fictionalized version of the yellow fever experiments, and portrays Kissinger and Moran as heroes. The radio program was prepared and produced by Young &amp; Rubicam, Inc. for the program, "We The People", for their client the General Foods Corp., to promote their product "Calumet", on January 10, 1937, from 5:00-5:30 on the network WJZ.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1937-01-10">
<head>Radio script for The Heroes of the Yellow Fever Experiments in Cuba in 1900, prepared and produced by Young and Rubicam, January 10, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03401001"/>
<p>Radio Script</p>
<p>Spring 1937</p>
<p>- 1 -</p>
<p>LORD....</p>
<p>In 1900 a Yellow Fever Commission composed of Dr. Walter Reed, Dr.<lb/>
James Carroll, Dr. Aristides Agramonte and Dr. Jesse Lazear was sent<lb/>
to Havana by Congress to try and conquer Yellow Fever but no one had<lb/>
any idea how it spread. Havana was scrubbed clean, houses were burned,<lb/>
villages were fumigated, fields were flooded but still this Yellow<lb/>
Fever Murderer crept through walls -- along the ground -- through water.<lb/>
Whole villages died of the plague -- not one left to tell the story.<lb/>
Men and women and children by the thousands would turn yellow -- and die.</p>
<p>The Yellow Fever Commission was working at Camp Quemadow under the<lb/>
boiling sun -- among the dying. Dr. Reed was exhausted, broken by his<lb/>
inability to curb this dread disease. At night he and the other<lb/>
Doctors would sit in their tent hopeless -- not knowing what to do next.</p>
<p>DR. CARROLL......</p>
<p>Dr. Reed -- I believe more and more it is the bite of a certain mosquito<lb/>
which gives Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>Dr. REED....</p>
<p>I do, too, gentlemen.</p>
<p>DR. LAZEAR...</p>
<p>Our problem is doubly hard, Dr. Reed -- because we cannot experiment on<lb/>
animals. Animals don't get Yellow Fever. The only way would be to<lb/>
experiment on a human person.</p>
<p>DR. CARROLL....</p>
<p>But we can't do that. It would mean death to them.</p>
<p>DR. REED....</p>
<p>Gentlemen -- men are dying every hour -- and we sit here helpless. We<lb/>
believe it may be the mosquitoes which are carrying this Yellow Fever --<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03401002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
but we cannot progress with our work until we are sure. You gentlemen,<lb/>
can carry on this work without me. I insist I shall allow myself to<lb/>
be bitten by mosquitoes which have bitten a Yellow Fever patient.</p>
<p>ALL DOCTORS....</p>
<p>NO... WE CANNOT ALLOW YOU TO DO THAT, DR. REED.</p>
<p>DR. REED.</p>
<p>I must, gentlemen -- we must make sure it is the mosquito which carries<lb/>
Yellow Fever. I shall allow myself to be bitten.</p>
<p>(GENERAL NOS)</p>
<p>DR. CARROLL....</p>
<p>That would be unfair to humanity, Dr. Reed -- you are needed to head<lb/>
this Commission. Promise us you won't.</p>
<p>DR. REED...</p>
<p>I SHALL BE BITTEN.</p>
<p>DR. CARROLL....</p>
<p>I command you not to, Dr. Reed. Remember we decided we would always abide<lb/>
by the majority decision of this Commission. We command you not to<lb/>
allow yourself to be bitten by the Yellow Fever mosquitoes. Do you<lb/>
promise?</p>
<p>DR. REED...(PAUSE)</p>
<p>Yes -- if it's a command -- but thousands are dying -- Oh -- God --<lb/>
help us.</p>
<p>(SOBS)</p>
<p>(FADE)</p>
<p>LORD....</p>
<p>Just outside of that tent where the Yellow Fever Commission was having<lb/>
that important Conference stood Private John R. Kissinger who was in<lb/>
charge of the operating room. He could hear Dr. Reed broken-hearted<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03401003"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
sobbing inside.</p>
<p>(PAUSE)</p>
<p>(FOOTSTEPS)</p>
<p>MORAN....</p>
<p>What's the matter, Kissinger?</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>Shush -- Dr. Reed is in that tent with his head down on the table sobbing<lb/>
because the other doctors won't allow him to be bitten by the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Mosquitoes. Listen....</p>
<p>(PAUSE)</p>
<p>(STEPS ON GRAVEL)</p>
<p>MORAN...</p>
<p>Wait a minute -- where you going, Kissinger?</p>
<p>KISSINGER....</p>
<p>I'm going in to Dr. Reed -- and offer to allow the mosquitoes to bite<lb/>
<hi>me</hi> -- Then they can experiment on me.</p>
<p>MORAN...</p>
<p>You'll die -- it's the Yellow Fever...</p>
<p>KISSINGER....</p>
<p>I'm a soldier -- I'm supposed to go out and kill other men. I'd<lb/>
a lot rather give my life so other men can live.</p>
<p>MORAN...</p>
<p>All right, Kissinger -- I'll go in and do it with you.</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>You want to?</p>
<p>MORAN...</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>KISSINGER..</p>
<p>Here's my hand, Moran. (PAUSE) Let's go.</p>
<p>(STEPS INSIDE)</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03401004"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>Dr. Reed -- Dr. Reed ---sir--</p>
<p>DR. REED...</p>
<p>What -- oh yes -- yes -- never mind what it is -- I --<lb/>
can't think now.</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>Doctor -- Moran and I want to be bitten by the Yellow Jack<lb/>
mosquitoes.</p>
<p>(PAUSE)</p>
<p>DR. REED....</p>
<p>What! You're offering yourselves as an experiment?</p>
<p>BOTH....</p>
<p>Yes sir.</p>
<p>DR. LAZEAR....</p>
<p>Do you men realize it will probably mean your death?</p>
<p>BOTH....</p>
<p>Yes sir...</p>
<p>DR. REED...</p>
<p>Gentlemen -- there's nothing I can say. Of course, you understand<lb/>
you will be handsomely rewarded by the Government -- if you recover.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03401005"/>
<p>- 5 -</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>The only conditions under which we offer ourselves, sir, is that we<lb/>
receive <hi>no</hi> renumeration of any kind.</p>
<p>DR. REED...</p>
<p>(PAUSE) Gentlemen -- I salute you.</p>
<p>LORD...</p>
<p>Private Kissinger and Moran were taken to an isolated camp where there<lb/>
was no chance of their getting Yellow Fever in any other way except from<lb/>
mosquitoes. Kissinger was in a tent--his arm was exposed---</p>
<p>DR. REED...</p>
<p>Kissinger -- Dr. Lazear of our Commission has just died of Yellow Fever.<lb/>
I believe it was because he was bitten by one of these mosquitoes. These<lb/>
mosquitoes which I have here have bitten a man dying of yellow fever. If<lb/>
I allow them to bite you -- I believe you will contract it. Do you wish<lb/>
to reconsider your decision?</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>No, Dr. Reed.</p>
<p>DR. REED...</p>
<p>Then, I shall allow them to bite you--hold your arm still--this way a<lb/>
little--the mosquitoes are on it--there---</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>Are they biting my arm---</p>
<p>DR. REED...</p>
<p>Not yet--but-- yes--yes--one is--- and so's the other. The rest will<lb/>
now-- you're a brave man, Kissinger.</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>I hope I get it-- If I get it-- it'll mean you're right, won't it, Doctor?</p>
<p>DR. REED...</p>
<p>Yes--if you get Yellow Fever from these mosquitoes, we will know we are right--<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03401006"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
and thousands of lives will be saved.</p>
<p>LORD</p>
<p>For the next few days Privates Kissinger and Moran did not get Yellow Fever<lb/>
and it looked as though mosquitoes were not the carriers of this dread disease<lb/>
and then on December 8th,---as they were walking about the camp they saw a<lb/>
stray mongrel dog.</p>
<p>(WALKING STEPS)</p>
<p>MORAN....</p>
<p>See that funny looking dog, Kissinger?</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>Yes, he ought not be around this experimental camp. Let's chase him away.</p>
<p>MORAN...</p>
<p>Come on.</p>
<p>(RUNNING)</p>
<p>KISSINGER....</p>
<p>Oh-- Oh--- Moran -- hold me up---</p>
<p>MORAN....</p>
<p>What's the matter?</p>
<p>KISSINGER....</p>
<p>My head -- I've gone dizzy-- oh-- I'm getting an awful chill--<lb/>
(START TEETH CHATTERING)</p>
<p>MORAN...</p>
<p>You have a chill? Kissinger -- you're coming down with Yellow Jack--</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>I'm glad -- then the Doctors are right -- it <hi>is</hi> the mosquito that carries<lb/>
Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>LORD...</p>
<p>At four O'clock in the morning, Private Kissinger was sent to the hospital<lb/>
with Yellow Fever -- the first man ever to have contracted it scientifically.<lb/>
Mr. Kissinger hovered between life and death.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f03401007"/>
<p>- 7 -</p>
<p>LORD...(CONT)</p>
<p>He went through the tortures of that terrible illness. His face<lb/>
became jaundiced yellow-- his eyes discolored -- he shrank from<lb/>
148 pounds to 116.</p>
<p>Two weeks leter, he was up and around, but later on he lost the<lb/>
use of his legs and became partially paralyzed for 12 years. Now,<lb/>
there aren't enough Yellow Fever germs left in the whole world to<lb/>
cover a ten cent piece -- a million lives have been saved because<lb/>
of those heroic men and Mr. Kissinger's courage in offering his<lb/>
life that others might live. I wish to present Mr. John R. Kissinger<lb/>
of Huntington, Indiana, in person.</p>
<p>KISSINGER...</p>
<p>I appreciate this great honor. At first I didn't think I could<lb/>
come because of my wife's illness, but she insisted and I have her<lb/>
to thank.</p>
<p>At the time of this Yellow Fever experiment, I had no fear--for<lb/>
I felt then as I do now that my life was in the hands of God. I<lb/>
accept this honor -- not for myself -- but for the men to whom<lb/>
it really belongs. They are all dead. Dr. Lazear and Dr. Carroll<lb/>
died of the very disease they tried so hard to conquer. I consented<lb/>
to come and accept this honor in memory of those brave doctors.</p>
<p>On behalf of a grateful world, I would like to use the very words<lb/>
that Dr. Reed said to me himself -- only now I apply &ldquo;Gentlemen ---<lb/>
I salute you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(MUSIC)</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
