<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03402001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to John J. Moran, January 14, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03402001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-01-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Schwieger, John D.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">DeMille, Cecil B.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace, W.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Hamann, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Guanajay (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-01-14">January 14, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03402001</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to John J. Moran, January 14, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus provides Moran with an autobiography of his military service and a list of names and addresses of surviving yellow fever volunteers. He comments on Kissinger.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1937-01-14">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to John J. Moran, January 14, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03402001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
J. H. Andrus<lb/>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1937-01-14">1-14-37.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John J. Moran,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter brings back the old days very clearly, by<lb/>
reason of the people and places you refer to, which I<lb/>
have known. That we never met is accounted for by<lb/>
the fact that you were, apparrently, a jump or two<lb/>
ahead of me all along the line.</p>
<p>To give you the complete picture: After being mustered<lb/>
out of the Third New York Volunteer Infantry, I reenlisted<lb/>
in the regulars and, about the middle of May, 1899, joined<lb/>
Battery &ldquo;F&rdquo;, Second Field Artillery, at Camp Columbia.</p>
<p>Had been there but a short time when I developed typhoid.<lb/>
Was treated, at the Post Hospital, by Dr. Pinto and nur-<lb/>
sed by, among others, Sonntag - one of the y. f. volun-<lb/>
teers. When convalescent, was sent to Military Hospital<lb/>
No. 1, at Havana.</p>
<p>After rejoining the Battery, was still in the <del><unclear></unclear></del> &ldquo;rookey&rdquo;<lb/>
stage when, during &ldquo;monkey drill&rdquo;, was kicked from my horse,<lb/>
by the horse ahead. My fractured patella (kneecap) was<lb/>
operated on by Major Kramer, assisted by Lieut. Truby.</p>
<p>When able to hobble around, with my leg still in a cast,<lb/>
was again sent to No. 1. (Havana) I had a bugle (of my<lb/>
own) with me and used to go to a distant point in the<lb/>
hospital enclosure to practice. There was a large de-<lb/>
tachment of corps men at the hospital, they had a bugler<lb/>
(Bastable -?) who was also a cook. I was transferred<lb/>
to the corps, as bugler, and Bastable was made cook.</p>
<p>(Guess they thought that, if I was going to hang around the<lb/>
hospital all the time anyway, they might as well make me<lb/>
useful.)</p>
<p>Remained at No. 1 until it was closed and the detachment<lb/>
scattered. John D. Schwieger and I were sent to Guanajay.<lb/>
We evidently landed there after your departure. Captain<lb/>
Quinton was Post Surgeon. Had been there but a short time<lb/>
when the epidemic of yellow fever broke out. Schwieger and<lb/>
I were on night duty at the time. (Captain Quinton was<lb/>
absent from the Post at this time.) Among those I recall,<lb/>
all of whom you probably knew, are : Dr. Robert P. Cooke, -<lb/>
one of the y. f. volunteers - Dr. J. F. Dunshie and, later,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03402002"/>
2.<lb/>
Lieut. A. E. Truby. Steward Dykstra, A. H. S. Cook,<lb/>
A. H. S. Courtney, Pvts. Frank M. Dawley, Schwieger, the fat,<lb/>
ruddy faced, English cook is clear in my recollection but I<lb/>
cannot recall his name. Nor do I recall the names of<lb/>
other men I knew there - probably by reason of having been<lb/>
socked on night duty immediately upon my arrival.</p>
<p>The y. f. broke up the post and the detachment was scattered.<lb/>
I was assigned to Columbia Barracks and remained there until<lb/>
a couple of weeks before my enlistment expired, when, with<lb/>
Dr. Amador, I accompanied two troops of the Seventh Cavalry<lb/>
to Chickamauga Park, where I was discharged.</p>
<p>Am sorry I never quite caught up with you for, from what you<lb/>
tell me, I imagine we have many tastes in common. I, for<lb/>
example, have always devoured everything readable and enjoy<lb/>
discussing what I read. Unless you belie your race you<lb/>
are a keen student of politics and political affairs, if so,<lb/>
that would be a common meeting ground for, although I never<lb/>
aspired to office, I try to acquaint myself with what it is<lb/>
all about.</p>
<p>It is a shame that, after having made so valiant an effort,<lb/>
you never attained your ambition to become a physician.<lb/>
You don't have to tell me how long the grind is for my son<lb/>
put in six years at college and a year as interne before the<lb/>
state would allow him to &ldquo;peddle pills.&rdquo; (I paid the<lb/>
freight, so I know something about what it costs.)</p>
<p>Your account of how Kissinger became the outstanding hero of<lb/>
Walter Reed's experiments is interesting but not surprising.<lb/>
I have always entertained the belief that, for reasons you<lb/>
may be able to guess, he did not realize what he was letting<lb/>
himself in for. He was, when quartered in the barracks,<lb/>
the victim of more practical jokes than anyone else I recall<lb/>
and, after he was made &ldquo;Lance Acting, etc.&rdquo; the men did not<lb/>
treat him with the respect due to one in his exalted station.</p>
<p>I should feel ashamed for referring to Kissinger sarcastically<lb/>
but if, in addition to all you know of his seeking the spot-<lb/>
light, you could see a letter I had from him, telling of his<lb/>
&ldquo;lectures&rdquo; in schools, before Legion posts, chambers of com-<lb/>
merce, etc., I am not sure you would not join me.</p>
<p>If we could read that &ldquo;lecture&rdquo; I feel quite certain we would<lb/>
learn things we never knew. Did you hear him on the Lux<lb/>
Radio Theater program a couple of months ago? He was<lb/>
quizzed by Cecil B. DeMille, very briefly, and was not as bad<lb/>
as I had expected it would be.</p>
<p>Am afraid you will be disappointed in the little help I can<lb/>
give relative addresses of volunteers. I wrote all of them<lb/>
at the time I first wrote you and sent my envelopes to the<lb/>
Veterans Bureau for them to address.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03402003"/>
<p>3.</p>
<p>From replies received - and from other sources - here is the<lb/>
list as complete as I have been able to get it.</p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="3">
<row>
<cell>John J. Moran,</cell><cell>Avenida Menocal 102-A,</cell><cell>Havana Cuba.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>John R. Kissinger,</cell><cell>R - 8,</cell><cell>Huntington, Ind.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Clyde L. West,</cell><cell>Riverdale, Md.</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Captain Thomas M. England,</cell><cell>Office of the Surgeon,</cell><cell>Governors<lb/>
Island, N. Y.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>John R. Bullard,</cell><cell></cell><cell>St Augustine, Fla.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Dr. Robert P. Cooke,</cell><cell>State Dept. of Health,</cell><cell>Lexington, Va.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>John H. Andrus,</cell><cell>805 Cooper St.,</cell><cell>Camden, N. J.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>James L. Hanberry,</cell><cell></cell><cell>Denmark, S. C.</cell></row></table></p>
<p><hi>Addresses uncertain:</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="3">
<row>
<cell>Albert W. Covington,</cell><cell>Pedro Miguel,</cell><cell>Canal Zone.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Wallace W. Forbes,</cell><cell>(No address)</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Levi E. Folk,</cell><cell></cell><cell>Columbus, Ohio.</cell></row></table></p>
<p><hi>Known dead</hi>:</p>
<p>Walter Reed, James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear, Aristides Agramonte,<lb/>
William H. Dean, Paul Hamann, James Hildebrand, Warren G. Jer-<lb/>
negan, William Olsen, Charles G. Sonntag, Edward Wetherwalks.</p>
<p>You will note that I have covered all the names listed in the<lb/>
roll of honor. It seems that I have heard that Folk is<lb/>
dead but am not positive. I do not believe that the Veter-<lb/>
ans Bureau has Forbes' address.</p>
<p>I enjoyed your letter very much and hope that you will write<lb/>
again when you get an opportunity. If you ever get back<lb/>
to your headquarters (Philadelphia) please do not fail to come<lb/>
over and see me.</p>
<p>Wishing you every success and happiness,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>J H Andrus</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
