<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03413001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Albert E. Truby, April 27, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author>Moran, John J.</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03413001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-04-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, N. May</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Spain</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-04-27">April 27, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03413001</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Albert E. Truby, April 27, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran corrects identifications of individuals in a photograph and describes his military assignments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1937-04-27">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Albert E. Truby, April 27, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03413001"/>
<opener>
COMPA&Ntilde;IA SUNOCO DE CUBA, S.A.<lb/>
AGENTES EXCLUSIVOS DE<lb/>
SUN OIL COMPANY<lb/>
SUN OILS<lb/>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
CABLE Y}<lb/>
TELEGRAFO}<lb/>
&ldquo;SUNOCO&rdquo;<lb/>
CLAVE BENTLEY<lb/>
TELEFONO <unclear>U. 6848</unclear><lb/>
SUNOCO<lb/>
DESTILADO AL MERCURIO<lb/>
<dateline>
AVENIDA MENOCAL NO. 102-A<lb/>
HABANA,<lb/>
<date value="1937-04-27">April 27, 1937.</date>
</dateline>
Gen. Albert E. Truby,<lb/>
U. S. Army, Retired,<lb/>
145 Laurel Street,<lb/>
San Francisco, Cal.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thru the courtesy of General Kean I received some three weeks ago<lb/>
a copy of the photograph of the Hospital Corps Detachment, Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba, taken in September, 1900. In a recent letter from General<lb/>
Kean he informed me that I was one of the group, offering to send me the<lb/>
photograph as soon as he felt certain of my correct address.</p>
<p>I regret to inform you that No. 15, indicated as your humble servant,<lb/>
is not John J. Moran. That was a disappointment to me since I have no photo-<lb/>
graphs of my own taken prior to December, 1917. I am inclined to believe<lb/>
that No. 15 is either Folk or Weatherwalks. No. 14 is not Kneisley, I am<lb/>
morally certain, and just as morally certain am I that it is Warren G. (not J)<lb/>
Jernegan. I am sure that if you were to consult Mrs. Jernegan by sending<lb/>
her a copy of the photograph, she would bear me out.</p>
<p>There is still another reason, altho not a conclusive one, why I<lb/>
could not appear in the group. I was discharged from the Army on July 2, 1900,<lb/>
and at the time the photograph was taken I was Order Clerk in Major Robert E.<lb/>
Lee Michie's office, Headquarters of Western Cuba, Marianao, General Fitzhugh<lb/>
Lee's headquarters, Major Michie being Adjutant General. In passing, I<lb/>
might state that General Kean, at that time Major Kean, Chief Surgeon on Gen.<lb/>
Lee's staff, was instrumental in having me appointed Order Clerk. Also, in<lb/>
a group of this nature, my place would have been in a line with the non-comm-<lb/>
issioned officers seated in the row back of yourself, Doctors. Pinto, Amador<lb/>
and Cooke, having been appointed A. H. S. on recommendation of the late Col.<lb/>
George D. Deshon, at that time commandant of the Hospital School of Instruct-<lb/>
ion, Washington Barracks, D. C., under whom I took the six months' course.<lb/>
I believe I was appointed within a month after we declared war on Spain.<lb/>
Captain Deshon considered me an exemplary student, hence his recommendation<lb/>
to the Surgeon General that I be promoted.</p>
<p>No, he<lb/>
did not<lb/>
reenlist<lb/>
so was<lb/>
a civilian</p>
<p>Since the copy of photograph came to me under somewhat of a mis-<lb/>
apprehension, so to speak, I am entirely willing to surrender it altho I would<lb/>
like to hold on to it as a memento of many of the faces shown thereon and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03413002"/>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<hi>Gen. Albert E. Truby</hi>.<lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>April 27, 1937</hi>.<lb/>
whose friendship, comradeship and/or acquaintance is now a pleasant memory,<lb/>
including your goodself in one of said categories.</p>
<p>I wish to apologize for my failure to write to you immediately I<lb/>
received copy of the photograph, but think I have an alibi. I have been laid<lb/>
up for the better part of three weeks due to an infection having its inception<lb/>
in a small blister which appeared on the sole of my heel and which I punctured<lb/>
with what I thought was a sterile needle. The infection extended to my ankle<lb/>
joint, the swelling around the joint area, accompanied by discoloration and<lb/>
extreme tenderness having given me no little concern. For letter writing<lb/>
I am lost without my typewriter although I am credited with writing plainly<lb/>
and neatly. When I was at Guanajay Barracks, under Captain Quinton, the<lb/>
Sick &amp; Wounded Reports prepared and written by me elicited favorable comment<lb/>
in General Kean's office, at General Lee's headquarters, for their neatness<lb/>
and completeness. None the less, I write few letters in long hand, very<lb/>
frequently violating that phase of the social code.</p>
<p>If you should care to drop me a line in connection with the contents<lb/>
of this letter I shall be most pleased to hear from you. Much water has gone<lb/>
over the dam since February, 1901, when I bid goodbye to all of you at Columbia<lb/>
Barracks. You may recall that Kissinger and myself sailed on the Morro Castle<lb/>
with Doctor Reed, the latter headed for Washington and the former enjoying a<lb/>
furlough in God's Country. I came North to kill time until the opening of<lb/>
the session at the University of Virginia in September.</p>
<p>Please overlook the length and rambling nature of this letter and<lb/>
accept kindest personal regards of your former subordinate and friend,</p>
<closer>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>,
I replied to this but did<lb/>
not been from him again<lb/>
A E T<lb/>
Initials A E T<lb/>
Gen. Albert E. Truby<lb/>
<unclear>BH</unclear><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
