<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03414001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Radio Script for The Shell Show: The Heroes of the Yellow Fever Experiments in Cuba, May 15, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03414001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-05-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-05-15">May 15, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03414001</idno>
<title>Radio Script for The Shell Show: The Heroes of the Yellow Fever Experiments in Cuba, May 15, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This radio show script on the yellow fever experiments includes an interview with Kissinger.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1937-05-15">
<head>Radio Script for The Shell Show: The Heroes of the Yellow Fever Experiments in Cuba, May 15, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03414001"/>
<opener>
<hi>R A D I O  P R O G R A M<lb/>
THE SHELL SHOW</hi><lb/>
The Heroes of the Yellow Fever Experiments in Cuba -- June<lb/>
to December, 1900<lb/>
<dateline>
{9:30 - 10:30 P.M.} <date value="1937-05-15"><hi>May 15, 1937</hi></date>
{SATURDAY}<lb/>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>JOE</p>
<p>A couple of weeks ago when Daylight Saving Time came in, I<lb/>
turned my clock back. As a matter of fact I turned it back so<lb/>
far, I found myself in 1900. Everybody was singing &ldquo;There'll<lb/>
Be A Hot Time In The Old Town Tonight&rdquo; ---- but down in Cuba,<lb/>
they were pretty worried about the cause of Yellow Fever.<lb/>
There were a lot of experiments going on, and the great hero<lb/>
of these experiments was Doctor Walter Reed. In tonight's<lb/>
drama the part of Dr. Reed is played by one of America's fore-<lb/>
most character actors . . . Arthur Byron! And here he is -<lb/>
Arthur Byron!</p>
<p>(BYRON ENTERS . . . . APPLAUSE)</p>
<p>(INSERT DRAMA)</p>
<p>(MUSIC IN)</p>
<p>DRAMATIC SPOT -1-</p>
<p>GRAUER</p>
<p>Cuba, in July of the year 1900, - 37 years ago. In the labor-<lb/>
atory of the American Yellow Fever Commission, sweltering in<lb/>
the heat of the tropical night, young doctor John Carroll<lb/>
stands listening to the words of his chief; Dr. Walter Reed . .</p>
<p>(MUSIC OUT)</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>So, Dr. Carroll, tonight we have come to the end of our trail;<lb/>
a trail that has led into a blank wall. For all we know, the<lb/>
yellow fever microbe doesn't exist.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>Doctor Reed . . . perhaps yellow fever isn't caused by a<lb/>
microbe or virus.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Well, then what do you think does cause it, Doctor Carroll?</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>The devil only knows. But when men are dying by the hundreds,<lb/>
we can be very sure something is causing it, even if our tests<lb/>
reveal nothing.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>That is a wise observation, Doctor Carroll, but all it proves<lb/>
is that we are on the wrong track.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>Then what track shall we take? If we can't find the germ, how<lb/>
are we going to fight it?</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>There is one more possibility.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>What is that, sir?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03414002"/>
<p>DRAMATIC SPOT -2-</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>The mosquito.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>You mean a mosquito bite produces yellow fever?</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>But that's old Doctor Finlay's crazy dream. He's been preach-<lb/>
ing that fool theory for nineteen years. It's ridiculous!</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Perhaps, but we have failed so far and we can't afford to ignore<lb/>
any clue, no matter how fantastic it may sound.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>Well, assuming the mosquito is the cause - - how would you prove<lb/>
it?</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>By experimenting, of course.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>But how can you experiment, Doctor? Yellow Fever only attacks<lb/>
human beings. If it attacked animals then we'd have something<lb/>
to experiment on.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Then we must experiment on men!</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>Men!!!</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>It is the only way, Doctor.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>But hwere can we find a man who would be willing to undergo<lb/>
the tortures of yellow jack? Burning fever, sweat, aching<lb/>
bones - awful stomach retchings - and then the cold, choking<lb/>
fingers of death - No one would do it. You can't find that<lb/>
kind of human guinea pig.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Yes, Doctor Carroll, we have one.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>We have one? Who?</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Myself.</p>
<p>(MUSIC BRIDGE)</p>
<p>(SOUND: KNOCK ON DOOR)</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>Yes, come in.</p>
<p>(SOUND: DOOR OPEN)</p>
<p>REED (FADING ON)</p>
<p>You sent for me, General Wood?</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>Oh, yes, Doctor Reed. Sit down, please.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>THANK YOU.</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>Doctor Reed, I asked you to come here because of certain rumors<lb/>
that have come to my ears.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03414003"/>
<p>DRAMATIC SPOT"3</p>
<p>WOOD (cont.)</p>
<p>I know you are in complete charge of the American Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission in Cuba, but I am the Governor-General of this<lb/>
Island. I am responsible for what goes on here.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Yes, General Wood. I know that.</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>Then will you please tell me, frankly and honestly, in what<lb/>
work your commission is now engaged?</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>We are seeking the cause of yellow fever by experimenting with<lb/>
a type of mosquito known as the Stigomyia.</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>And how are you conducting those experiments?</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>I'd rather not disclose that, sir, until we arrive at some re-<lb/>
sults.</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>Then I suspect the rumors I heard are true.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Rumors, sir....?</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>That you were experimenting on yourself.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Well... as a matter of fact it is true. Humans are the only<lb/>
ones who can contract the disease so some human must risk his<lb/>
life that others may live.</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>I'm sorry, Doctor Reed, but I can't let you do it.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>And why not, sir? My life is my own.</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>No, Doctor, your life is important for the work you are doing.<lb/>
You must conduct the experiments, not take part in them. I<lb/>
am sure we can find others who are willing to be martyrs for<lb/>
science.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>But we haven't the right to order men to risk their lives.</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>But we have the right to ask for volunteers, Doctor. Every-<lb/>
one of the American soldiers here in Cuba now came, knowing<lb/>
that they were to face death. Either death from a Spanish<lb/>
bullet or the deadly Yellow Jack. I am sure we can find<lb/>
volunteers for your cause - a far greater cause than victory<lb/>
on the battlefield.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>I am a doctor, General, and I have seen men die.. but I could<lb/>
never ask a man to face that kind of death.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03414004"/>
<p>Dramatic spot -4-</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>Very well, I shall send out the call for volunteers myself.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>That is your privilege, sir.</p>
<p>WOOD</p>
<p>And your duty is to continue your experiments on these volun-<lb/>
teers.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>AS YOur say, sir. I shall be ready to experiment, General<lb/>
Wood.</p>
<p>SENTRY</p>
<p>Doctor Reed, these are the volunteers, sir.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>ALL right, Orderly. So you're the two men who volunteered.</p>
<p>MEN (MUTTERING)</p>
<p>Yes, sir. Yes, Doctor Reed . . . . etc.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>I suppose they've told you what you are to expect. I am going<lb/>
to expose you to one of the deadliest diseases known to man<lb/>
just to be sure - to be absolutely sure - where that disease<lb/>
comes from. If our experiment succeeds it means the end of a<lb/>
scourge that has killed thousands. But, you will be facing a<lb/>
terrible death. Are you willing to go through with it?</p>
<p>MEN</p>
<p>Yes, sir. We'll do it . . . . . . . etc.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>What is your name?</p>
<p>MORAN</p>
<p>John J. Moran</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>And yours?</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>I'm John Kissinger, sir.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>I'm proud to know you both. Now here is what you have to do.<lb/>
Back in the clearing we have built a special isolation camp,<lb/>
where you will have to live for the next two weeks without con-<lb/>
tact with the outside world, just to be sure you haven't had a<lb/>
chance to contract yellow fever before we start the experiment.</p>
<p>MORAN</p>
<p>We understand, sir.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Then you will be moved to a special shack we have built. It's<lb/>
clean and airy, the rooms have been fumigated and disinfected.<lb/>
There will be fifteen mosquitoes in that shack with you and you<lb/>
must expose yourselves to their bites. I warn you, the risks<lb/>
are great.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03414005"/>
<p>DRAMATIC SPOT 5</p>
<p>MORAN</p>
<p>We're ready, sir.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Then report to the isolation camp at once.</p>
<p>MORAN</p>
<p>There's just one thing, Doctor Reed. They told us the Govern-<lb/>
ment would give us $200 apiece for doin' this.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>MORAN</p>
<p>Well, we'd rather forget about the money. We're doin' this for<lb/>
somethin' more than money. Right, Kissinger?</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>Right.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Moran -- Kissinger ------- I want to shake your hands.</p>
<p>(MUSIC BRIDGE)</p>
<p>(SOUND: DOOR OPEN AND <unclear>SLAM</unclear>)</p>
<p>CARROLL (FADING ON)</p>
<p>Doctor Reed . . . Doctor Reed . . . .</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Yes, Carroll, what is it?</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>The experment is over. Kissinger has got the fever</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Kissinger! Then he must have gotten it from the mosquitoes.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>There was no other way.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>What about Moran?</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>He's still all right - but he may have a natural immunity.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Then the experiment is not over, Carroll. We still aren't<lb/>
sure.</p>
<p>CARROLL</p>
<p>But how else could Kissinger have gotten the disease? He was<lb/>
in absolutely sterile surroundings except for the mosquitoes.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>But Moran is still well . . . we still aren't sure.</p>
<p>(MUSIC BRIDGE)</p>
<p>AGRAMONTE</p>
<p>Doctor Agramonte reporting, Doctor Reed.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Yes, Doctor.</p>
<p>AGRAMONTE</p>
<p>It's Christmas Day, sir, and I have a present for you.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f03414006"/>
<p>DRAMATIC SPOT -6-</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>What is it, Doctor?</p>
<p>AGRAMONTE</p>
<p>At seven-fifteen this morning, John J. Moran, lately isolated<lb/>
in the experimental camp, showed all the symptoms of yellow<lb/>
fever. He has been removed to the hospital.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>Moran has the fever! Teh our experiment is over.</p>
<p>AGRAMONTE</p>
<p>Yes, Doctor. A complete success. You have proved the Stego-<lb/>
myia mosquito is the sole cause of yellow fever. May I be the<lb/>
first to congratulate you, Doctor Reed.</p>
<p>REED</p>
<p>You may congratulate me when and if those two men live. A<lb/>
doctor's duty has always been to save life, Doctor, but fate<lb/>
has decreed that i take the opposite course. I have sent two<lb/>
men to the gates of death. But sending them there has closed<lb/>
those gates to thousands of others. The world shall be rid of<lb/>
one more deadly enemy; we can now stamp out yellow fever. Thank<lb/>
God this was not in vain.</p>
<p>MUSIC UP FOR FINISH)</p>
<p>(INSERT KISSINGER INTERVIEW)</p>
<p>COOK</p>
<p>Thank you, Arthur Byron, for your fine performance, as Dr. Wal-<lb/>
ter Reed. And now I would like to borrow one member of your<lb/>
supporting cast - the man who played the part of John Kissinger.<lb/>
Because that man is really Kissinger himself. And I am proud<lb/>
to present him now, one of the great heroes of science - the<lb/>
man who risked his life in the cause of humanity - Mr. John<lb/>
Kissinger.</p>
<p>(KISSINGER ENTERS)</p>
<p>(APPLAUSE)</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>Thank you, Mr. Cook.</p>
<p>COOK</p>
<p>Mr. Kissinger, how did it feel living in that shack down in<lb/>
Cuba 37 years ago?</p>
<p>KISSINGER ...</p>
<p>Well, as a matter of fact, it was very pleasant. The quarters<lb/>
were nice and airy. The food was good - at least better than<lb/>
we got in the regular army. And best of all, we didn't have to<lb/>
drill.</p>
<p>COOK...</p>
<p>Just a nice restful vacation, eh?</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>That's right. There was only one trouble.</p>
<p>COOK</p>
<p>What was that?</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>The mosquitoes. They were terrible.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f03414007"/>
<p>COOK</p>
<p>It must have taken a lot of will power not to swat them when<lb/>
they started biting you.</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>It did. But we had our orders from Dr. Reed and we let them<lb/>
bite as much as they wanted - which was a-plenty, I'll tell<lb/>
you.</p>
<p>COOK</p>
<p>Then you finally got yellow fever?</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>Yes. But the worst part of it was the waiting. When the fever<lb/>
finally hit me I was almost thankful because the terrible wait-<lb/>
ing was over.</p>
<p>COOK</p>
<p>Well, I'm glad you lived through your fever, Mr. Kissinger.<lb/>
If any man ever deserved to live, you are that man.</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>Well, Dr. Reed saw that I had the best of care and I pulled out<lb/>
of it in two weeks.</p>
<p>Walter Reed was a great man.</p>
<p>COOK</p>
<p>Yes, and as far as I'm concerned so is John Kissinger. You<lb/>
did a great thing, and the whole world is proud of you.</p>
<p>KISSINGER</p>
<p>Thank you, Mr. Cook.</p>
<p>(APPLUSE)</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
