<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03425001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Roll of Honor: Participants in Yellow Fever Investigations in Cuba, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03425001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert Page</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Hamann, Paul B.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbian University, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">University of Maryland, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Harvard University, Cambridge (Mass.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-00-00">1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03425001</idno>
<title>Roll of Honor: Participants in Yellow Fever Investigations in Cuba, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This excerpt includes the Roll of Honor of the participants in the yellow fever investigations in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1937-00-00">
<head>Roll of Honor: Participants in Yellow Fever Investigations in Cuba, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03425001"/>
<opener>
Army <unclear>Register</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1937-00-00">1937</date>
</dateline>
P S Hench<lb/>
</opener>
<p>ROLL OF HONOR</p>
<p>PARTICIPANTS IN YELLOW FEVER INVESTIGATIONS IN CUBA</p>
<p>The Secretary of War, Hon. Elihu Root, in his annual report, 1902, said with reference to the conquest of yellow fever<lb/>
in Cuba in 1900-1901:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The brilliant character of this scientific achievement, its inestimable value to mankind, the saving of thousands of<lb/>
lives, and the deliverance of the Atlantic seacoast from constant apprehension, demand special recognition from the Gov-<lb/>
ernment of the United States.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Congress has, in concurrence with his opinion, by an act approved February 28, 1929, authorized and directed the<lb/>
Secretary of War to publish annually in the Army Register a Roll of Honor on which shall be carried the following names,<lb/>
and to define in appropriate language the part taken by each of these persons in the yellow fever investigation in Cuba.<lb/>
The same act provided that a gold medal be presented to each person named in the roll, or to the representatives of those<lb/>
who have died.</p>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="2">
<row>
<cell>Reed, Walter. B--Va. 13 Sept. 51. A--<lb/>
Va. M. D. Univ., Va., 69 and Belle-<lb/>
vue Med. Coll. N. Y. 72. Asst. surg.<lb/>
26 June 75; accepted 3 July 75; capt.<lb/>
Asst. Surg. 26 June 80; maj. surg. 4<lb/>
Dec. 93.</cell><cell>When sent to Cuba in June, 1900 at the head of the Yellow Fever Board of medi-<lb/>
cal officers Major Walter Reed was already a distinguished man. In the<lb/>
Spanish-American War he had been at the head of another famous medical<lb/>
board which studied the camp epidemics of typhoid fever in the Army during<lb/>
that war, and made a great advance in our knowledge of the spread of that<lb/>
formidable disease in armies. He was professor of pathology and bacteriology<lb/>
at the Army Medical School, and also at the Columbian University in Wash-<lb/>
ington, and stood high in his profession. In the work of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board he shared their labors and dangers, but his was always the originating,<lb/>
directing, and controlling mind. He died in Washington, D. C., November<lb/>
23, 1902, following an operation for appendicitis.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Carroll, James. B--Eng. 5 June 54.<lb/>
A--D. C. M. D. Univ. Md. 91. Pvt.<lb/>
corp. and sgt. Co. E 1 Inf. 9 Jan. 74 to 9<lb/>
Jan. 79; pvt. sgt. and 1 sgt. Co. C 7 Inf.<lb/>
22 Jan. to 14 Sept. 83; hosp. stewd. 15<lb/>
Sept. 83 to 21 May 98; cont. surg. 22<lb/>
May 98 to 29 Oct. 02; asst. surg. 27 Oct.<lb/>
02; accepted 30 Oct. 02; maj. surg. 6<lb/>
Mar. 07; accepted 9 Mar. 07; died 16<lb/>
Sept. 07.</cell><cell>Following his appointment as an acting assistant surgeon in 1898, Major Carroll<lb/>
was assigned to duty as assistant to Major Walter Reed. Early in the study<lb/>
of the agency of the mosquito as the transmitter of yellow fever, Major Carroll<lb/>
volunteered to be bitten by an infected mosquito. On August 31, 1900, he<lb/>
became ill and suffered a very severe attack of that disease. His was the first<lb/>
experimental case. He returned to Cuba a year later to make special studies<lb/>
of the blood of yellow-fever patients. He died in Washington, D. C., Sep-<lb/>
tember 16, 1907, having been promoted to the grade of Major, Medical Corps,<lb/>
by special authority of Congress in recognition of his services as a member of<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Board.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Agramonte, Aristides. B--Cuba 3 June<lb/>
68. M. D. Columbia Univ. 92. Cont.<lb/>
surg. 2 May 98 to 31 Aug. 00; and 11<lb/>
Feb. to 15 June 03.</cell><cell>Dr. Agramonte was born in Cuba, the son of a Cuban officer who fell in battle<lb/>
against the Spaniards. He was raised and educated in New York where his<lb/>
mother had taken refuge. He was serving with the Army in Cuba, in charge<lb/>
of the Army Medical Laboratory in Habana, when he was appointed a mem-<lb/>
ber of the Yellow Fever Board. His special qualifications as a pathologist,<lb/>
and his energy and ability contributed greatly to the success of the the board.<lb/>
Of special value were his contributions to the demonstrations by the board<lb/>
disproving the then generally accepted theory that the bacillus icteroides was<lb/>
the causative agent of yellow fever. He died August 18, 1931, in New Orleans,<lb/>
La., where he was professor of tropical medicine in the Louisiana State Uni-<lb/>
versity.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Lazear, Jesse W. B--Md. 20 May 66.<lb/>
M. D. Columbia Univ.92. Cont.surg.<lb/>
5 Feb. to 25 Sept. 00.</cell><cell>Following graduation from the University of Maryland in 1892, Dr. Lazear<lb/>
did post-graduate work at the Pasteur Institute in Paris, and Johns Hop-<lb/>
kins University, specializing in mosquitoes and their relation to malarial<lb/>
infections. When the Yellow Fever Board was organized he was already in<lb/>
Cuba on duty with troops, and was studying yellow fever. He had charge<lb/>
of the mosquito work of the board when he contracted yellow fever while<lb/>
visiting yellow-fever patients in order to infect mosquitoes for experimental<lb/>
purposes. He died, September 25, 1900, of this disease, a martyr to science.<lb/>
By his special knowledge and brilliant scientific attainments, as well as by<lb/>
the invaluable notes of his observations made in the last weeks of his life which<lb/>
he left, he cntributed in the highest degree to the successful outcome of the<lb/>
investigation.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Andrus, John H. B--Pa. 7 Oct. 79.<lb/>
Pvt. Co. L 3 N. Y. Vol. Inf. 1 May to<lb/>
10 Dec. 98.---Pvt. Btry. F 2d Arty.<lb/>
and pvt. Hosp. C.25. Apr.99 to 24 Apr.<lb/>
02.</cell><cell>John H. Andrus volunteered for experiment and was infected with yellow fever<lb/>
by an injection of blood from an experimental case. He became ill January<lb/>
28, 1901, being the twelfth case in the series of cases at Camp Lazear. He left<lb/>
the Army in 1902.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Bullard, John R. B--Mass. 5 July 72.</cell><cell>John R. Bullard, a graduate of Harvard University, at which institution he was a<lb/>
distinguished athlete, came to Cuba and was treated by Dr. James Carroll at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks for malarial fever. Becoming interested in the yellow-<lb/>
fever work, he volunteered and received, on October 15, 1901, an injection of<lb/>
the filtered blood of a Spaniard, an experimental case. The blood serum in-<lb/>
jected was the same as that employed in the cases of Privates Covington and<lb/>
Hamann and at the same time. Slight fever and discomfort were caused, but<lb/>
no illness. A week later, he received a blood injection from the veins of<lb/>
Private Hamann, who had been infected by the injection of filtered blood,<lb/>
and became ill with yellow fever, October 23, 1901. Having thus become im-<lb/>
mune, he continued to reside in Cuba after his recovery.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>1429</cell></row>
</table>
<pb n="2" id="f03425002"/>
<table rows="8" cols="2">
<row>
<cell>C2<lb/>
B7</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1430</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>ARMY REGISTER, 1937</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Cooke, Robert P. B--Va. 12 Oct. 74.<lb/>
Midshipman U.S. Naval Academy 6<lb/>
Sept. 92 to 14 Feb. 95; actg. asst. surg.<lb/>
U.S.A. 9 June 00 to 22 Dec. 04 and<lb/>
from 18 Jan. 13 to 25 May 15; 1 lt. M.<lb/>
R. C. 24 Apr. 15; accepted 6 May 15;<lb/>
A. D. 26 May 15; capt. M. R. C.<lb/>
14 Mar. 18; accepted 28 Mar. 18; hon.<lb/>
dis. 20 Aug. 19.</cell><cell>Robert P. Cooke entered the Medical Service of the Army June 9, 1900, and was<lb/>
on duty at Pinar del Rio during the yellow-fever epidemic in the garrison<lb/>
there. He volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear and with two<lb/>
privates, Folk and Jernegan, were the first to undergo the trying ordeal of<lb/>
sleeping 21 successive nights in the soiled bedding used by yellow-fever<lb/>
patients. This was to determine whether the disease could be transmitted by<lb/>
infected bedding, clothing, and other objects. This experiment was of vast<lb/>
importance not only in making clear the method of transmission of the disease,<lb/>
but to the commerce of the world.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Covington, Albert W. B--N. C. 1 July<lb/>
77. Pvt. Co. K, 1 S. C. Vol. Inf. 5<lb/>
Aug. 98 to 22 Apr. 99.---Pvt. corp.<lb/>
sgt. qm.sgt. and sgt. Btry. N 2 Arty.<lb/>
and 23 Co. C. A. C. 21 June 99 to 7<lb/>
Aug. 10; pvt. corp. and sgt. 81 Co. C.<lb/>
A. C. 13 Aug. 10 to 18 Apr. 16; pvt.<lb/>
pvt. 1 cl. and corp. 45 Co. C. A. C. 19<lb/>
Apr. 16 to 12 Sept. 17; pvt. pvt. 1 cl.<lb/>
corp. sgt. sgt. 1 cl. and staff sgt. U.S.<lb/>
D. B. Gds. 2 Feb. 18 to 1 Nov. 20; staff<lb/>
sgt. Q. M. C. 2 Nov. 20; retired 23 Aug.<lb/>
26.</cell><cell>Albert W. Covington volunteered for experiment in the third series of cases when<lb/>
it was well understoods that yellow fever would be the result. On October 15,<lb/>
1901. he was given a subcutaneous injection of 3 cubic centimeters of the<lb/>
diluted and filtered blood serum from an experimental case of yellow fever.<lb/>
He became ill October 19 with a typical attack of yellow fever, from which<lb/>
he made a good recovery, and was returned to duty with his battery. He<lb/>
remained in service 25 years thereafter, being retired on August 23, 1926.<lb/>
Died 4-20-34</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Dean, William H. B--Ohio 6 Jan. 77.<lb/>
Pvt. corp. and sgt. Tr. B 7 Cav. 18<lb/>
Aug. 99 to 17 Aug. 02.</cell><cell>The case of William H. Dean was the second case of experimental yellow fever,<lb/>
being that which convinced the board that the theory of its conveyance by<lb/>
mosquitoes was well grounded, and being mentioned in their premilinary<lb/>
report as the Case X. Y. He volunteered and was bitten August 31, 1900,<lb/>
by the same mosquito which had infected Major Carroll four days before. He<lb/>
was also bitten by two mosquitoes which had bitten a fatal case of yellow<lb/>
fever 12 days before and a fourth mosquito which had been fed on three severe<lb/>
cases of yellow fever. He left the military service, August 17, 1902, with an<lb/>
excellent character, and died May 3, 1928.<lb/>
<unclear>Capt</unclear></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>England, Thomas M. B--Ohio 14 Oct.<lb/>
76. 1 lt. Sn. C. N. A. 15 Feb. 18; ac-<lb/>
cepted 16 Feb. 18; capt. Sn. C. U. S. A.<lb/>
7 July 18; accepted 29 Aug. 18; vacated<lb/>
16 Sept. 20.---Pvt. actg. hosp. stewd.<lb/>
and sgt. 1 cl. Hosp. C. 6 Jan. 99 to 5 Jan.<lb/>
14; pvt. pvt. 1 cl. sgt. sgt. 1 cl. hosp. sgt.<lb/>
and mr. hosp. sgt. M. D. 28 July 15 to<lb/>
15 Feb. 18; capt. Med. Adm. C. 1 July<lb/>
20; accepted 16 Sept. 20.</cell><cell>Thomas M. England enlisted for the Spanish War and came to Cuba with the<lb/>
VII Army Corps. He volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear, and<lb/>
underwent the trying ordeal of sleeping 20 nights in the bed formerly occupied<lb/>
by a yellow-fever patient, and in the garment worn by him. His head lay on<lb/>
a towel stained with the blood of a case of yellow fever. He remained in the<lb/>
Army, serving in all the noncommissioned grades of the Medical Department,<lb/>
and won his commission in that department during the World War.<lb/>
Hdqrs. Governors Island (address<lb/>
Md Administrative Corps, New York- (Sep 1937</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Folk, Levi E. B--S. C. 7 Feb. 70. Pvt.<lb/>
Co. B 1 S. C. Vol. Inf. 3 May 98 to 10<lb/>
Nov. 98; 1 lt. Sn. C. U. S. A. 22 Sept. 18;<lb/>
accepted 22 Sept. 18; hon. dis. 20 Oct. 19.<lb/>
---Pvt. Hosp. C. 12 Dec. 98 to Dec.<lb/>
01; pvt. pvt. 1 cl. and sgt. Hosp. C. 17<lb/>
Feb. 02 to 2 Mar. 13; sgt. Med. Dept.<lb/>
3 Mar. 13 to 2 Mar. 17; sgt. and sgt. 1 cl.<lb/>
Med. Dept. 3 Mar. 17 to 21 Sept. 18;<lb/>
sgt. 1 cl. and sgt. Med. Dept. 21 Oct.<lb/>
19 to 20 Oct. 22; sgt. and tech. sgt. Med.<lb/>
Dept. 21 Oct. 22; retired 20 Mar. 23.</cell><cell>Levi E. Folk volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear, and with two<lb/>
others, first underwent the long and trying ordeal of sleeping 21 consecutive<lb/>
nights in the soiled bedding and clothing of yellow-fever patients. This ex-<lb/>
periment was of vast importance commercially as well as scientifically, as it<lb/>
upset the accepted belief as to how the disease was transmitted, and resulted<lb/>
in the abolition of expensive and useless disinfections. He later was bitten<lb/>
by infected mosquitoes, and on January 23, 1901, suffered an attack of yellow<lb/>
fever of moderate severity, this showing that he was nonimmune at the time<lb/>
of the former experiment. He was retired in 1923 after 25 years of honorable<lb/>
service. Died 2-9-36</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Forbes, Wallace W. B--Ill. 25 Sept. 78.<lb/>
Pvt. and pvt. 1 cl. Hosp. C. 21 Jan. 99<lb/>
to 20 Jan. 02 and from 2 Mar. 02 to 1<lb/>
Mar. 05; pvt. pvt. 1 cl., ck. mess sgt.<lb/>
and sgt. 18 Rctg. Co. G. S. I. Co. F 9<lb/>
Inf. and Co. F 37 Inf. 14 Feb. 16 to 24<lb/>
Oct. 19; sgt. Co. M 31 Inf. 25 Oct. 19 to<lb/>
24 Oct. 22; sgt. Co. L 30 Inf. 25 Oct. 22<lb/>
to 24 Nov. 26.</cell><cell>Wallace W. Forbes volunteered for experiment and received January 22, 1901, an<lb/>
injection of half a cubic centimeter of blood from a case of experimental yellow<lb/>
fever. Two days later, he became ill and suffered a severe attack of yellow<lb/>
fever. He was honorably discharged from the Army four years later.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hamann, Paul. B--Germany 14 Feb. 76.<lb/>
Pvt. Co. F 6 Ill. Vol. Inf. 9 May 98 to<lb/>
25 Nov. 98.---Pvt. Btry N 2 Arty. and<lb/>
23 Co. C. A. C. 20 July 99 to 19 July 02.</cell><cell>Paul Hamann volunteered for experiment, being one of the third group of<lb/>
volunteers, and was infected by Major Carroll with filtered blood serum at the<lb/>
same time with Private Covington. He became sick on October 19, 1901, and<lb/>
suffered a moderately severe attack of yellow fever. He was discharged from<lb/>
the service, July 19, 1902, with character excellent.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hanberry, James L. B--S. C. 12 Dec.<lb/>
75. Pvt. Co. L 1 S. C. Vol. Inf. 21 Aug.<lb/>
98 to 10 Nov. 98.---Pvt. Hosp. C. 13<lb/>
Dec. 98 to 12 Dec. 01 and from 28 Mar.<lb/>
to 4 Apr. 02.</cell><cell>James E. Hanberry volunteered for experiment, and was one of the group who<lb/>
slept 21 consecutive nights on bedding which had been used by yellow-fever<lb/>
patients, and was soiled with their bloody discharges. He also wore at night<lb/>
the soiled garments of the sick. Some weeks after this disagreeable, and as it<lb/>
was then thought dangerous<unclear>.</unclear> experience, he was bitten by the same two<lb/>
mosquitoes which had a few days before infected a companion, and on Feb-<lb/>
ruary 9, 1901, came down with a severe attack of this painful disease. He<lb/>
left the service in 1902.</cell></row>
</table>
<pb n="3" id="f03425003"/>
<table rows="8" cols="2">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>ROLL OF HONOR</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>1431</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Hildebrand, James. B--Ga. 2 Apr. 62.<lb/>
Pvt. Co. A 2 Ala. Inf. and pvt. Hosp.<lb/>
C. 23 July 98 to 24 Nov. 98; pvt. and<lb/>
pvt. 1 cl. Hosp. C. 5 Dec. 98 to 29 Nov.<lb/>
07; pvt. and pvt. 1 cl. Hosp. C. 6 Oct.<lb/>
08 to 17 Aug. 14.</cell><cell>James Hilderbrand served in the Spanish War and came to Cuba with the VII<lb/>
Army Corps. He volunteered for the experiment at Camp Lazear, and with<lb/>
England underwent the trying ordeal of sleeping 20 nights. January 11 to 31,<lb/>
1901, in the bed and garment used by a yellow-fever patient, and with his<lb/>
pillow covered by a towel stained with yellow-fever blood. Hildebrand then<lb/>
offered to be bitten by infected mosquitoes, but Major Reed refused to permit<lb/>
this as he was much older than other volunteers, and the mortality in<lb/>
yellow fever is much increase with age. He was discharged August 17, 1914,<lb/>
with character excellent.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Jernegan, Warren G. B--Fla. 8 July<lb/>
72. Pvt. Hosp. C. 17 Nov. 98 to 16<lb/>
Nov. 01.</cell><cell>Warren G. Jernegan volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear, and with<lb/>
two others, first underwent the long and trying ordeal of sleeping 21 consecu-<lb/>
tive nights in the soiled bedding and clothing of yellow-fever patients. This<lb/>
was to determine whether the disease could be transmitted by infected bed-<lb/>
ding, clothing, and other objects. This experiment was of vast importance<lb/>
not only in making clear the method of transmission of the disease, but to the<lb/>
commerce of the world. He then, on December 28 and 29, 1900, submitted to<lb/>
the bites of infected mosquitoes, but escaped infection. On January 4, 1901,<lb/>
he received an injection of blood from a case of experimental yellow fever<lb/>
(Martinez) and suffered a sharp attack of that disease, being the first case<lb/>
infected in this manner. He left the military service at the expiration of his<lb/>
enlistment with character excellent, and went to Panama, where he was<lb/>
employed in the Canal service for a number of years. He died February 5,<lb/>
1919, in Charleston, S. C.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Kissinger, John R. B--Ohio 25 July 77.<lb/>
Pvt. Co. D 157 Ind. Vol. Inf. 26 Apr. to<lb/>
1 Nov. 28.----Pvt. and actg. hosp.<lb/>
stewd. Hosp. C. 15 Nov. 98 to 14 Nov.<lb/>
01.</cell><cell>John R. Kissinger and John J. Moran were the first to volunteer of those who<lb/>
underwent the conclusive experiments at Camp Lazear where they occupied<lb/>
the same tent. On November 20, 1900, he was bitten by three infected<lb/>
mosquitoes. On November 23 he was bitten by one of the same three and on<lb/>
December 5 he was again bitten by five mosquitoes, two of which had been<lb/>
infected by fatal cases. On December 9 he became ill and suffered a typical<lb/>
attack of yellow fever. His was the first case of experimental yellow fever<lb/>
in the series at Camp Lazear. Of him, Major Walter Reed said: &ldquo;In my<lb/>
opinion, this exhibition of moral courage has never been surpassed in the<lb/>
annals of the Army of the United States.&rdquo; He was discharged from the<lb/>
service, November 14, 1901, with character excellent.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Moran, John J. B--Ireland 15 Mar. 76.<lb/>
Capt. Q. M. C. N. A. 27 May 18; ac-<lb/>
cepted 27 May 18; hon. dis. 1 Oct. 19.---<lb/>
Pvt. and actg. hosp. stewd., Hosp.<lb/>
Corps 3 July 97 to 2 July 00. B. C.<lb/>
S. Mount Hope Coll. 96.</cell><cell>John J. Moran was employed as a clerk at the department headquarters at<lb/>
Marianao, Cuba. He there did clerical work for Major Reed and became inter-<lb/>
ested in the work of the Yellow Fever Board. He and Kissinger were the first<lb/>
to volunteer for the conclusive series of experiments at Camp Lazear. He was<lb/>
bitten on November 26 and 29, by infected mosquitoes, but without result.<lb/>
On December 21, 1900, he twice visited the infected mosquito room, and again<lb/>
next day, and was repeatedly bitten. On Christmas Day he became ill, and<lb/>
suffered a well marked and severe attack of yellow fever. Moran refused to<lb/>
accept the bonus which was given by the Governor of Cuba to each volunteer,<lb/>
stating that he was glad to be able to do this service to humanity. He was<lb/>
discharged from the service, July 2, 1900, with character excellent. He served<lb/>
for some years at Panama during the construction of the Canal, and was com-<lb/>
missioned a captain in the United States Army (Emergency Forces) during<lb/>
the World War. He is now a resident of Habana, Cuba.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Olsen, William. B--Wis. 27 Aug. 74.<lb/>
Pvt. Hosp. C. 16 Nov. 98 to 15 Nov. 01.</cell><cell>William Olsen enlisted for the Spanish War and came to Cuba where he volun-<lb/>
teered for the experimental work of the Yellow Fever Board at Camp Lazear.<lb/>
He was one of a group of four who were given injections of blood from a case of<lb/>
experimental yellow fever at the camp (the Spaniard Martinez) in order to<lb/>
decide certain questions of scientific importance. He was taken ill with yellow<lb/>
fever January 11, 1901. He was discharged on expiration of his enlistment<lb/>
November 15, 1901, with character excellent. He died September 10, 1932,<lb/>
in Los Angeles, Calif.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Sonntag, Charles G. B--S. C. 20 Nov.<lb/>
72. Pvt. and corp. Co. L 1 S. C. Vol.<lb/>
Inf. 5 May to 10 Nov. 98.----Pvt. Hosp.<lb/>
C. 13 Dec. 98 to 12 Dec. 01.</cell><cell>Charles G. Sonntag volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear, and was<lb/>
bitten by two infected mosquitoes and came down with yellow fever February<lb/>
10, 1901, being the last case in the series at Camp Lazear. He took his dis-<lb/>
charge December 12, 1901, with character very good.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Weatherwalks, Edward. B--N. J. 16<lb/>
July 74. Pvt. Hosp. C. 13 Dec. 98 to<lb/>
12 Dec. 01.</cell><cell>Edward Weatherwalks enlisted for the Spanish War and came to Cuba with the<lb/>
VII Army Corps. He volunteered for the experiments at Camp Lazear and<lb/>
underwent the trying ordeal of sleeping 21 nights, December 21, 1900, to Janu-<lb/>
ary 10, 1901, inclusive, on bedding which had been used by yellow-fever<lb/>
patients and was soiled with their bloody discharges. He wore at night the<lb/>
soiled garments of the sick. As this experiment, like the other exposures to<lb/>
infected clothing, had no result, Weatherwalks was bitten on January 25, 1901,<lb/>
by 12 infected mosquitoes, but for some reason not known, escaped infection.<lb/>
He was discharged December 21, 1901, with character good, and died October<lb/>
21, 1916.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>West, Clyde L. B--Ind. 5 Apr. 77.<lb/>
Pvt. Co. B 8 Inf. and pvt. Hosp. C. 11<lb/>
July 99 to 10 July 02.</cell><cell>Clyde L. West enlisted at Toledo, Ohio, for the Spanish War, and came to Cuba,<lb/>
where, while serving at Columbia Barracks, he volunteered for the experi-<lb/>
ments at Camp Lazear. He was infected in the mosquito room by the bites<lb/>
of two mosquitoes which had bitten a case of yellow fever 51 days before.<lb/>
These caused a mild attack of yellow fever three days later on February 9, 1901.<lb/>
Six days later these same mosquitoes caused the very severe case of Hanberry<lb/>
in which his life for several days hung in the balance. He was discharged<lb/>
July 10, 1902, with character very good.</cell></row>
</table></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
