<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03422002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">&ldquo;The Story of John Moran ...,&rdquo; by John Moran, [1937]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03422002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Thomas, Lowell</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Gillan, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Kruif, Paul de</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Sidney</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Goethals, George Washington</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="place">Latin America</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Galveston (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama City (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-00-00">[1937]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03422002</idno>
<title>&ldquo;The Story of John Moran ...,&rdquo; by John Moran, [1937]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran's autobiography gives a detailed account of the yellow fever experiments in which he took part.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1937-00-00">
<head>&ldquo;The Story of John Moran ...,&rdquo; by John Moran, [1937]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03422002"/>
<p><unclear>PHench</unclear></p>
<p>&ldquo;The Story of John Moran ---&rdquo;</p>
<p>This autobiographical sketch was written for me by Mr. Moran<lb/>
(at my request) and sent to me with his letter of July 24, 1937.</p>
<p>I was born in County Galway, Ireland, on March 15, 1876, coming to<lb/>
the United States in early boyhood, residing in Youngstown, Ohio, until 1897.<lb/>
Before I was yet 16 years of age, I had ambitions to become a medico. Lacking<lb/>
the wherewithal, however, I compromised with myself by taking a commercial<lb/>
course instead, with no intention of abandoning my goal. I was still young.<lb/>
I decided to make a start by enlisting in the Hospital Corps of the U. S. Army<lb/>
at the Hospital School of Instruction, Washington Barracks, Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
completing the requisite six months' course there. Within a year after my<lb/>
enlistment came the outbreak of the Spanish-American War. I was immediately<lb/>
promoted from Private to Acting Hospital Steward (Sergeant), being ordered to<lb/>
Cuba in January, 1899, where I served until the end of my term of enlistment,<lb/>
being discharged from the Army, with EXCELLENT character, on July 2, 1900.<lb/>
Automatically, I was appointed order clerk on the staff of General Fitzhugh Lee,<lb/>
Commander of the Department of Western Cuba, with headquarters <hi>adjacent</hi> to Col-<lb/>
umbia Barracks, today known as &ldquo;Camp Columbia&rdquo; and since the first days of the<lb/>
Republic, the most imprtant garrison of the Cuban Army. While I was at General<lb/>
Lee's headquarters, during July and August, two of the General's staff officers,<lb/>
Majors Cartwright and Edmunds, were stricken with and succumbed to yellow fever.<lb/>
The disease had assumed epidemic form among American soldiers and civilians in<lb/>
the Provinces of Havana and Pinar del Rio, with a high rate of mortality. The<lb/>
medical officers of the Army were nonplussed. General Geo. M. Sternberg, then<lb/>
Surgeon General of the Army, decided that measures should be adopted to curb the<lb/>
ravages of the dread disease. He appointed a Board of Officers, headed by Major<lb/>
Walter Reed, Surgeon, U. S. Army, with Drs. James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear and<lb/>
Aristides Agramonte, as members, the latter a Cuban, &ldquo;for the purpose of pursuing<lb/>
scientific investigations with reference to the infectious diseases prevalent on<lb/>
the Island of Cuba&rdquo;. This Board was to be henceforth known as the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board and was frequently referred to as the Reed &amp; Carroll Board, especially<lb/>
during the time when the Board carried on its experiments at Camp Lazear, with<lb/>
&ldquo;infected bedding and clothing&rdquo; and the &ldquo;mosquito&rdquo; theories. The Board had its<lb/>
first meeting on June 25, 1900, at the Post Hospital, Columbia Barracks, and for the<lb/>
following four months its activities were principally devoted to laboratory work,<lb/>
with the object of discovering and isolating the yellow fever germ or microbe.<lb/>
In the meantime two members of the Board were stricken with yellow fever, one<lb/>
experimentally, the other accidentally, the latter being Dr. Jesse W. Lazear who<lb/>
succumbed to the disease in September, 1900, and the former Dr. James Carroll<lb/>
who purposely applied the &ldquo;right&rdquo; mosquito to his person. Dr. Carroll suffered<lb/>
a severe attack of yellow fever, recovering within the usual course of the disease.<lb/>
By this time Major Reed had arrived at the conclusion that the mosquito was the<lb/>
culprit and that, in order to prove it, hitherto untried methods of experiment-<lb/>
must be resorted to if the Board was to accomplish its mission. He was ready to<lb/>
face the storm of protest which was sure to follow when his plan to use &ldquo;human<lb/>
guinea pigs&rdquo; became known, and in this he was entirely correct. He was roundly<lb/>
condemned, not only by the general public but by a very respectable percentage of<lb/>
medical men as well. Playing with the lives of human beings, even for the sake<lb/>
of humanity and science, was something unheard of. Realizing that he would not<lb/>
be able to obtain &ldquo;human guinea pigs&rdquo; for his proposed experiments, unaccompanied<lb/>
by a material reward or bonus, his next predicament was to find the &ldquo;godfather&rdquo;<lb/>
who would supply the wherewithal. The Surgeon General of the Army, completely<lb/>
in accord with him and his plan, had no funds at his disposal which could be<lb/>
touched for such a purpose. Fortunately, General Leonard Wood, Military Govern-<lb/>
or of Cuba, himself a medico, came to Major Reed's assistance, appropriating the<lb/>
necessary amount out of Insular funds at his disposal. Major Reed then made it<lb/>
quietly known among the troops stationed at Columbia Barracks, including the<lb/>
members of the Hospital Corps, that he was &ldquo;fishing&rdquo; for volunteers for his yellow<lb/>
fever experiments and that a handsome bonus - perhaps as much as $500 - would be<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03422003"/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
paid to each such volunteer. Although I was then a civilian, I was permitted<lb/>
by the Post Surgeon to retain the room I was occupying when I was discharged from<lb/>
the service, Private John R. Kissinger of the Hospital Corps, who succeeded me in<lb/>
the operating room, being my roommate. Dr. Roger Post Ames, Acting Assistant<lb/>
Surgeon, on duty at the Post Hospital, knowing I was to enter the University of<lb/>
Virginia next year, to start my medical course, accosted me one afternoon and told<lb/>
me about Major Reed's quest and offer and remarking &ldquo;There's a nice chance for you,<lb/>
Johnny, to bolster your slim educational fund by $500&rdquo; I agreed with him and told<lb/>
him I would sleep over it. That evening I broke the news to Kissinger and he and<lb/>
I talked over the matter. That $500<unclear>.</unclear> would be a great help for a man who expected<lb/>
to study medicine for four years, with only sufficient for two years' tuition and<lb/>
living expenses. Then, I thought the matter over from another angle. To start<lb/>
off in medicine with such a noble act to my credit would be much more satisfying to<lb/>
my self respect than if I should accept the money. Then again it was not at all<lb/>
unlikely that I would go under. In such an event I did not much relish the idea<lb/>
of having an epitaph reading something like this appear on my tombstone &ldquo;Here lie<lb/>
the remains of Johnny Moran who lost his life in a good cause and who spoiled it<lb/>
through accepting AN INSIGNIFICANT REWARD OF $500&rdquo;. In all truth I was not act-<lb/>
uated so much by the benefits humanity might derive from my share in the proposed<lb/>
tests as I was in the benefits my act might confer on medical science, although I<lb/>
sensed that humanity and medical science in this case were synonymous and indivis-<lb/>
able. I was a doctor in embryo. I had, of course, made up my mind to offer<lb/>
myself for the experiments. Kissinger had made up his mind to do likewise. I<lb/>
tried to dissuade him, pointing out that our motives wre entirely different and<lb/>
that, after all, either of us had as good a chance of dying as we had of living<lb/>
if the mosquito should prove to be the culprit in the transmission of yellow fever.<lb/>
It was &ldquo;Love's Labor Lost&rdquo; so, having set my conscience at rest, I was very glad<lb/>
to have his company. We would both volunteer for the experiments, no material<lb/>
or money award to be involved. We let it go at that and turned out the lights<lb/>
for a few hours' sleep. Next morning we walked across the parade grounds together<lb/>
to Major Reed's room in the officers' quarters, your humble servant acting as spoke-<lb/>
sman. Major Reed, upon learning our mission, was completely taken aback, his<lb/>
surprise being further accentuated when he discovered that we were going in for the<lb/>
experiments without a money award. Like the fine and amiable Virginian that he<lb/>
was, he thanked us, accepting our offer conditional only upon passing a strict<lb/>
physical examination, explaining to us that if the tests should prove successful<lb/>
he wanted us to have a good fighting chance for recovery, that we could name any<lb/>
doctor and nurse in the Army Medical Service in Cuba, in whom we might have most<lb/>
confidence, to care for us if taken down with yellow fever, and that he would see<lb/>
that they were ordered to Columbia Barracks for that purpose. We thanked him, at<lb/>
the same time informing him that Dr. Ames and Mrs. Gillan would be acceptable to<lb/>
us as doctor and nurse, the former having had experience in the treatment of yellow<lb/>
at New Orleans, the latter being a graduate Army nurse. Throughout the years, it<lb/>
has been repeatedly made of record that Major Reed, upon learning our mission,<lb/>
stood to &ldquo;Attention&rdquo; and, suiting the action to the words, said &ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute<lb/>
you&rdquo;. Neither was the salute executed nor the words spoken. I am personally in-<lb/>
cline to believe that Major Reed was too much surprised at the time to think of it,<lb/>
afterwards fathering the gesture and the words, thereby making it a matter of record.<lb/>
The first time, to my knowledge, that it appeared in print was in Dr. Howard A.<lb/>
Kelly's book &ldquo;Walter Reed &amp; Yellow Fever&rdquo;, first published in 1906. Later, it<lb/>
appeared in &ldquo;Microbe Hunters&rdquo; by Paul de Kruif and more recently in &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;<lb/>
by Sidney Howard, the Playwright, and in many newspaper articles and editorials.</p>
<p><unclear>Sept</unclear>?</p>
<p>We took up residence in the Experimental Camp (Camp Lazear) on November<lb/>
20th, 1900. I was installed in Major Reed's office tent, so used by him when he<lb/>
visited and inspected the camp, twice daily. I acted as his secretary while<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03422004"/>
-- 3 --<lb/>
awaiting my turn to be bitten. Virtually, we were all prisoners in the camp,<lb/>
no one being allowed to leave and no visitors permitted except those invited by<lb/>
a member of the Yellow Fever Board. During the period from November 20th to<lb/>
December 25th, 1900, many of the &ldquo;Notes&rdquo; and papers on the progress of the<lb/>
experiments, as well as personal letters to General Sternberg, all written by<lb/>
or dictated to me by Major Reed, were typed by me. They were of an extremely<lb/>
confidential nature at that time. Outstandingly impressed on my memory are the<lb/>
letters Major Reed wrote to his chief, General Sternberg. I could sense the war<lb/>
from high quaters waged against Major Reed and his mosquito theory, with Washington<lb/>
as the base of operations. It can now be stated that one of the most bitter<lb/>
opponents of Reed and the mosquito theory was the then Surgeon General of the U. S.<lb/>
Public Health &amp; Marine Hospital Service, with powerful ramifications of the same<lb/>
Service in Cuba. That Service could see nothing than &ldquo;infected bedding and clothing&rdquo;<lb/>
as responsible for the spread of yellow fever. In that Service there was one notable<lb/>
exception, however, Dr. Henry R. Carter, connected with the quarantine service in<lb/>
Cuba. He was a believer in the mosquito theory from the beginning.</p>
<p><unclear>Washington</unclear></p>
<p>The first attempt to inoculate me was made on November 26th, the second<lb/>
on November 29th, mosquitoes confined in test tubes, tagged and identified, with<lb/>
a complete record of their past activities, having been allowed to feed on me<lb/>
from the inverted tubes. The results were NIL in each instance. Doctor Reed<lb/>
then decided to reserve me for his master test, as he called it, to be carried out<lb/>
in the mosquito building, then in process of construction. That building was<lb/>
divided into two main sections, one section being insect proof and the other sect-<lb/>
ion entirely unprotected against entry or exit of mosquitoes or other insects.<lb/>
On December 21, 1900, fifteen mosquitoes were set free in the mosquito section<lb/>
of this building, all of which had bitten severe cases of yellow fever from five<lb/>
to twenty-four days before. At 12 Noon, five minutes after they were set free in<lb/>
the room, I entered the compartment so that its fifteen guests might feed on me,<lb/>
clad only in a night shirt which I removed upon entering, laying down on a disin-<lb/>
fected hospital bed (the only furniture in the room) so that the guests might feed<lb/>
on me without interruption. Major Reed provided me with a hand mirror so that I<lb/>
might count the number of insects biting me. He was an interested observer on<lb/>
the other side of the wire screen partition where two non-immune &ldquo;controls&rdquo; slept<lb/>
for eighteen or twenty nights. My first visit to the mosquito room lasted twenty<lb/>
minutes, during which seven insects fed on me, reentering the room again at 4:30<lb/>
in the afternoon, being fed on by five mosquitoes. Next day, December 22nd, I<lb/>
made my third and last visit to the mosquito room, at 4:30 P. M., and was bitten<lb/>
by three mosquitoes. Therefore, by deduction, it was assumed that all fifteen<lb/>
insects had fed on me. While awaiting results, Warren G. Jernegan, a volunteer<lb/>
for the &ldquo;infected bedding and clothing&rdquo; test, offered to bet me five dollars that<lb/>
I would not eat Christmas dinner at the Experimental Camp. True to the temper-<lb/>
amental characteristics of those born in the Emerald Isle, I had to take him up.<lb/>
Another volunteer held the stakes, two five-dollar gold pieces. Come what might,<lb/>
I had made up my mind to win that bet, and I did win it. Dr. Ames informed me<lb/>
previously that, given the existence of a healthy constitution, recovery from yellow<lb/>
fever was likely, in nine cases out of ten, if recognized in time, total abstinence<lb/>
from either food or drugs being essential once the fever set in, that those stricken<lb/>
with yellow fever had unusually healthy appetites during the first hours of the<lb/>
disease. From the date of my first visit to the mosquito room Major Reed had<lb/>
instructed me to take my temerature three times daily and, should same deviate from<lb/>
normal, to take it every hour, tracing same on my temperature chart. Nothing<lb/>
happened until Christmas morning. I had slept like a top the night before and I<lb/>
had eaten a hearty breakfast. About 10:00 A. M. I felt a flushing sensation in<lb/>
my face and head. Temperature and pulse registered 100.4 and 88, respectively.<lb/>
By 1:00 P. M., the hour scheduled for dinner instead of the usual noon hour, my<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03422005"/>
-- 4 --<lb/>
temperature was 101.6 degrees F. Having made up my mind to win that bet, I<lb/>
took good care that none of my camp companions should know I had &ldquo;IT&rdquo;. Being<lb/>
in the office tent by myself, this was not very difficult. I responded to the<lb/>
call for dinner at the mess tent, bluffed it through, eating very sparingly but<lb/>
without attracting undue attention. Our Christmas dinner was a good one, con-<lb/>
sisting of everything from turkey and cranberry sauce to oldfashioned Army &ldquo;plum<lb/>
duff&rdquo; or plum pudding. The temptation to do it full justice was great but so<lb/>
was the instinct for self preservation. Jernegan, who stood to lose five dollars,<lb/>
was too busy enjoying the dinner to pay any special attention to my delicate<lb/>
appetite and the small portions I served myself. Dinner over, I asked Jernegan<lb/>
&ldquo;How about that bet&rdquo;. He replied &ldquo;Guess you win&rdquo;, adding &ldquo;Dammit, you can't kill<lb/>
an Irishman anyway&rdquo;. After collecting the bet I told him that he had lost and<lb/>
won at the same time. Looking at me tensely and full of concern, he said &ldquo;You<lb/>
don't mean to tell me that you have it, Johnny?&rdquo; I answered in the affirmative.<lb/>
Major Reed, who usually visited camp around 1:30 to 2:00 P. M. did not arrive until<lb/>
after 3:00 P. M. They also had a Christmas dinner at the officers' mess at the<lb/>
Post Hospital. When he did arrive my temperature was 103 and a fraction. He<lb/>
came direct to the office tent and, after wishing me a Merry Christmas, inquired<lb/>
if there was anything new. I pointed to the temperature chart on the field desk.<lb/>
I venture to say that the smile of satisfaction on his face could not have been<lb/>
broader had he been notified by the Secretary of War of his promotion to the rank<lb/>
of Colonel. He gleefully rubbed his hands and said &ldquo;Moran, this is one of the<lb/>
happiest days of my life&rdquo;. He had previously informed me that if the mosquito<lb/>
house test should prove successful the mosquito theory would be established in<lb/>
fool proof fashion and that the skeptics and diehards would not have a leg to<lb/>
stand on. The mule-drawn ambulance which had brough Major Reed out to Camp<lb/>
Lazear took me immediately to the special tent hospital established for the<lb/>
experimental cases, within the Post Hospital grounds at Columbia Barracks. My<lb/>
case of yellow fever was pronounced &ldquo;very pretty&rdquo; by Major Reed and his invited<lb/>
guests of the medical fraternity, Major William C. Gorgas being one of those most<lb/>
deeply interested. In ten days I was up and around, a little weak after my<lb/>
siege of fever, pain and starvation. Drugs, in the treatment of yellow fever,<lb/>
were contra-indicated. I was allowed cracked ice ad libitum, small sips of<lb/>
strained watermelon juice, tablespoonful quantities of champagne, ice packs and<lb/>
ice enemas, all intended to keep down the temperature and assist the kidneys in<lb/>
functioning. My first real nourishment in a period of ten days was a teaspoonful<lb/>
of milk. Two weeks after I became convalescent, I took the blood test from an-<lb/>
other &ldquo;pretty case&rdquo; of yellow fever, aimed to determine whether or not an immune<lb/>
could have a second attack. Results: NIL. I am confident that I am still immune.<lb/>
I left Havana in February, 1901 and entered the University of Virginia in September<lb/>
of that year, with visions of becoming an M. D. Though I lived economically at<lb/>
the University, I soon realized that the amount of money I had saved for a four-<lb/>
year course <del><unclear></unclear></del> could barely be stretched out to cover<lb/>
three years, so I was tempted to invest the major part of my educational fund in<lb/>
an oil stock, swallowing the statements made by the promoters, hook, bait and sink-<lb/>
er. Later, I had the satisfaction of knowing that I was &ldquo;one of those born every<lb/>
minute&rdquo;. My hopes of becoming an M. D. vanished. I then went to New York and<lb/>
was doing nicely in the insurance business, after two years of grilling work, when<lb/>
Colonel Gorgas offered me a position as Sanitary Inspector on the Panama Canal.<lb/>
Having had a taste of the tropics in Cuba, I could not resist the call. I served<lb/>
on the Panama Canal from 1904 to 1915, resigning to go into business for myself in<lb/>
the City of Panama. When the U. S. entered the World War, I set about disposing<lb/>
of my business in order to enter the Service. By April, 1918, I had arranged my<lb/>
affairs and made a beeline for Washington where, within forty-eight hours after<lb/>
my interview with General Goethals, I was commissioned a captain in the Quarter-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03422006"/>
-- 5 --<lb/>
master Corps of the Army, General Goethals being at that time Assistant Chief of<lb/>
Staff. General Gorgas, then Surgeon General of the Army, offered me a commission<lb/>
in the Sanitary Corps of the Army but I had come to the conclusion that, being only<lb/>
a &ldquo;near doctor&rdquo;, neither lemonade nor beer, I could render more efficient service<lb/>
in the Quartermaster Corps than I could in the Sanitary Corps. While Generals<lb/>
Goethals and Gorgas were never in harmony, except officially, while both were memb-<lb/>
ers of the Isthmian Canal Commission, I enjoyed the friendship and confidence of<lb/>
both. That personal relations between them, from the very beginning, were strained,<lb/>
was no secret to those employed on the Panama Canal. They both had their fine<lb/>
qualities and I hold the memories of both in reverence. Goethals built the Panama<lb/>
Canal and Gorgas, putting in practice <del>the</del> Major Reed's discoveries, made it possible<lb/>
to build the Canal with as little loss of life as possible from bubonic plague,<lb/>
yellow fever and pernicious malaria, diseases which had practically nullified the<lb/>
efforts of the French who originated work on the Panama Canal. I served overseas<lb/>
with the AEF in France until the latter days of September, 1919, as Disbursing<lb/>
Quartermaster, being honorably discharged from the Army at Governors Island, New<lb/>
York Harbor, on October 1, 1919. I immediately entered the service of the Mercant-<lb/>
ile Bank of the Americas, serving as branch manager in Venezuela for one of its<lb/>
affiliates until December, 1921, when the depression of 1920-1921 caused the bank<lb/>
to go into liquidation. In 1921, I accepted the position of manager with the<lb/>
Mexican Trading Corporation, distributors in the Aztec Republic for Sun Oil Company<lb/>
products and Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Company, resigning when the de la Huerta<lb/>
revolution of 1923-24 broke out. I then came to Cuba but I returned to Mexico<lb/>
and my previous position in 1926, severing my connection with Mexican Trading<lb/>
Corporation, in February, 1928, to take over the Sun Oil Company representation<lb/>
in Cuba. Here I have been ever since, making a passably decent living out of<lb/>
petroleum and its products. Uncle Sam, with his monthly cheque of $125.00,<lb/>
helps a lot towards allowing me to live comfortably and decently. While, through-<lb/>
out the years, I was a perennial applicant for a Congressional medal of some kind,<lb/>
from &ldquo;leather&rdquo; to &ldquo;gold&rdquo;, I nver applied, directly or indirectly, for a pension or<lb/>
annuity on account of the part I took in the yellow fever experiments. When it<lb/>
came to me unsolicited by the <hi>Act of February 28th, 1929</hi>, I accepted it. That Act<lb/>
gave me a Special Gold Medal, $125.00 per month during the rest of my natural life<lb/>
and to have my name placed on THE ROLL OF HONOR of the War Department to be publish-<lb/>
ed each year in the Official Army Register. That ROLL will exist and be published<lb/>
annually long after I have passed to my reward. There are 22 names on the ROLL<lb/>
OF HONOR, as follows: the four members of the Yellow Fever Board and eighteen men<lb/>
who volunteered for the experiments. Kissinger and myself volunteered without<lb/>
material reward. The other sixteen accepted it. To have my name on the ROLL<lb/>
means much more to me than do the medal and the annuity. I am also proud of the<lb/>
following words of General Jefferson R. Kean, Medical Corps, U. S. Army, Retired,<lb/>
who was Chief Surgeon on General Lee's staff here, at the time of the experiments:</p>
<p>General Kean's letters to Prof. James E. Peabody, under dates of<lb/>
September 22, 1928, and October 1, 1928, respectively.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As you have three pictures of Kissinger and one of Jernegan,<lb/>
why don't you have a picture of Moran who was the real hero of<lb/>
that bunch, the man who volunteered the same time as Kissinger,<lb/>
who always refused to accept any gratuity and has always shown<lb/>
a fine spirit of dignity and independence&rdquo; Again &ldquo;You ask whether<lb/>
I think you are stressing Kissinger too much. I have no criticism<lb/>
to make of your fine and generous enthusiasm for Kissinger, and<lb/>
prefer to say that you have stressed Moran too little. He was<lb/>
without doubt the fineest and strongest character of the group of<lb/>
men infected at Camp Lazear, and my recollection is that he and<lb/>
Kissinger volunteered at the same time&rdquo;.</p>
<closer>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
