<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03426001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, August 3, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03426001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-08-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-08-03">August 3, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03426001</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, August 3, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus compliments Truby and requests verification of certain incidents related to the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1937-08-03">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, August 3, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03426001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
J.H. Andrus<lb/>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1937-08-03">8-3-37</date>
</dateline>
General A. E. Truby,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<salute>Dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Have been tempted, many times, to write you but have<lb/>
been able to resist until now that I have what might<lb/>
pass as an excuse.</p>
<p>First, I want you to know how much I appreciate your<lb/>
kindness to me when I was in Walter Reed Hospital -<lb/>
from May 13, until Oct. 6, 1932.</p>
<p>Returned home on the latter date - after medicos had<lb/>
concluded that they could never fix me up so that I<lb/>
would be able to walk again.</p>
<p>Have been bedfast ever since returning. Thanks to<lb/>
the Walter Reed annuity of $1,500. we are able to live<lb/>
in comfort without having to draw too heavily on the<lb/>
few dollars I had been able to accumulate.</p>
<p>Have been keeping in touch with <unclear>yourvcareer</unclear>, was very<lb/>
much pleased at your elevation but disappointed when<lb/>
you were retired without becoming Surgeon General.</p>
<p>You deserve - and I sincerely hope you have - many<lb/>
years of excellent health in which to enjoy your re-<lb/>
tirement. You are one of those rare individuals<lb/>
who possess the faculty of maintaining discipline<lb/>
and, at the same time, winning and holding the re-<lb/>
spect and affection of the enlisted personnel.</p>
<p>This was true when I knew you in Cuba, as a first<lb/>
lieutenant, and equally true when, as a colonel and<lb/>
the C. O., you were head man at Walter Reed Hospital.</p>
<p>I also earnestly hope that you may not be called back<lb/>
to active service. With affairs so muddled in<lb/>
Europe and Asia it will be a miracle if there is not<lb/>
another &ldquo;world&rdquo; war.</p>
<p>And now for that &ldquo;excuse&rdquo; for writing -<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03426002"/>
Page 2.<lb/>
Am enclosing copy of a letter to the Secretary of War<lb/>
in an effort to secure revision of that section of the<lb/>
roll of honor (which appears in the Official Army<lb/>
Register) applying to me.</p>
<p>You see my son (an M. D.) and his wife have just made<lb/>
me a grandfather and - while the roll of honor, as it<lb/>
stands, suits me - I would like to have the record<lb/>
straight for those to whom I can not leave much else.</p>
<p>You will note that I have referred to you for verifi-<lb/>
cation of a number of statements. Among them:<lb/>
Duty with the Commission. - I may be wrong, but I have<lb/>
always thought that you suggested me to Major Reed.<lb/>
Someone did because he asked for me. You have<lb/>
always seemed most likely. In any event I have no<lb/>
doubt but that you remember that I was detailed for<lb/>
duty in the laboratory. I do not mean at Camp<lb/>
Lazear - but the shack which was the operating room<lb/>
when the post hospital at Camp Columbia was in tents.<lb/>
This is the layout:</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03426003"/>
<p>Page 3.</p>
<p>H - Small addition in which guinea pigs were housed.</p>
<p>As regards the second point on which I refer to you for<lb/>
fonfirmation: I feel quite confident that you know<lb/>
of <unclear>thisnincident</unclear>. Forbes had yellow fever from<lb/>
blood innoculation and the Major had Tom England lined<lb/>
up to take an injection of Forbes' blood - to continue<lb/>
the series of experiments.</p>
<p>England had slept in fomite building and was to have<lb/>
taken mosquito-bite or blood innoculation but had a<lb/>
change of heart.</p>
<p>There were other volunteers scheduled for other exper-<lb/>
iments. Rather than disrupt the schedule Major<lb/>
Reed decided to have Forbes' blood injected into him.<lb/>
It had to be done quickly, as Forbes was getting better.</p>
<p>Lieutenant Carroll threw a fit and the Major held fast.</p>
<p>All this was threshed out in my presence in the lab.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I SEEN MY DUTY - BUT I DIDN'T DONE IT&rdquo; - I had seen<lb/>
too much of yellow fever to want any.</p>
<p>The next morning the Major was still determined - then<lb/>
I volunteered.</p>
<p>I believe every<lb/>
word of this<lb/>
A E T</p>
<p>I feel quite confident that Dr. Carroll called upon you<lb/>
to help persuade the Major to give the idea up.</p>
<p>You may think I am doing a lot of guessing on all this<lb/>
but don't forget that I heard Major Reed and Dr. Carroll<lb/>
talking by the hour.</p>
<p>* * * * * *</p>
<p>Please forgive me, General, for presuming on your kind-<lb/>
ness to me in the past to burden you with all this.</p>
<p>And please accept my kindest regards and best wishes for<lb/>
your future health, happiness and prosperity.</p>
<p>Note:<lb/>
This is filed in wrong place<lb/>
A E T</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>J H Andrus</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
