<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03437001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, September 22, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03437001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-09-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-09-22">September 22, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03437001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, September 22, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Moran for the manuscript of his autobiography. He offers to help Moran publish his recollections in a medical history journal.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1937-09-22">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, September 22, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03437001"/>
<opener>
Yellow fever.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1937-09-22">September 22, 1937</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
c/o Cia. Sunoco de Cuba, S. A.<lb/>
Avenida Menocal No. 102-A<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You have an apology coming from me for not having answered<lb/>
your very courteous letters long before this. When they arrived, I was very<lb/>
rushed, and laid them aside until I had time to write you appropriately; but<lb/>
we have been so rushed here that I have simply not had time to do it. I<lb/>
appreciate very much indeed your great kindness in trying to help me in the<lb/>
preparation of my paper for the Staff Meeting of the Mayo Clinic. I particu-<lb/>
larly appreciate your going to the trouble of writing out your most interesting<lb/>
experiences, and I want to thank you very much indeed for them.</p>
<p>Your further courtesy in sending me the three reprints is<lb/>
greatly appreciated, particularly because I had not seen these before. I am<lb/>
now trying to obtain these three items--- the reprint from &ldquo;The Military<lb/>
Surgeon&rdquo;, the one from &ldquo;Popular Science&rdquo; and the &ldquo;Roll of Honor&rdquo; from the War<lb/>
Department.</p>
<p>When I visited Mr. Kissinger and heard his own personal<lb/>
story, I was immediately struck by the fact that neither you nor he, to my<lb/>
knowledge, have ever published the story in your own words. Mr. Kissinger<lb/>
frankly told me that he had not done so because he didn't feel literary enough.<lb/>
There is no question in my mind but that your own story and that of Mr. Kissinger<lb/>
certainly should be published in some journal devoted to medical history, in<lb/>
order that your contribution, as presented in your own words, may be available<lb/>
for future medical historians. I asked Mr. Kissinger if he would be willing<lb/>
to let me help in this matter and he said that he would. I have talked to some<lb/>
of my friends here whom I have interested in this story and they agree with<lb/>
me that this should be done. I shall be delighted to have the real privilege<lb/>
and pleasure of helping to do the same for your story. Please realize that<lb/>
I have no ulterior motives whatever in this suggestion. The story should be<lb/>
yours, not mine, and the only part that I would play in it would be to arrange<lb/>
for its publication in a suitable medical journal, and to help the editor of<lb/>
that journal in a little historical research to verify the accuracy of some<lb/>
personal references. As you know, the story has not been told with complete<lb/>
accuracy as far as I can find any place. Although the story is told in some<lb/>
detail, nevertheless your own version of it would be most interesting and it<lb/>
should be published under your own name. The preparation of this story for<lb/>
a medical publication would be made in an entirely different way from that<lb/>
for a lay publication. As you know, such a story as yours would have to be<lb/>
jazzed up to satisfy the editor of a laymen's magazine. Therefore, the story</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03437002"/>
<p>Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
September 22, 1937</p>
<p>as prepared for a medical journal unfortunately will not bring you any<lb/>
remuneration, as they do not pay for such items. I am sure that, regardless<lb/>
of this, you might wish to have your story on record for all time. Should<lb/>
you be willing to do this, I shall be delighted to collaborate with you<lb/>
in amplifying the story that you have already written me, and I should like<lb/>
to try to arrange with the editor of one of our medical historical journals<lb/>
that your story and Kissinger's appear at the same time together. Each of<lb/>
you will of course see the story as written by the other in order that any<lb/>
apparent contradictions or differences of opinion due to faulty memory, be<lb/>
corrected. I have noticed the tendency of some writers to try to give<lb/>
more credit to one or the other volunteers in these experiments. I, personally,<lb/>
feel that this is out of place; that all of you concerned in these experiments,<lb/>
particularly you and Mr. Kissinger, deserve equal recognition and every credit<lb/>
possible for your services. Regardless of the outcome and who happened to have<lb/>
been bitten first and whether one was sicker than the other, the fact remains<lb/>
that each of you volunteered all that you had as far as you were concerned;<lb/>
and as far as I am concerned and I am sure as far as the medical profession<lb/>
is concerned there can be no distinction, and I depricate as much as you do,<lb/>
and as I personally know Mr. Kissinger does, the attitude of the occasional<lb/>
writer who writes up the story of one to the partial exclusion of another.<lb/>
Nevertheless, this is a natural mistake made by the writers who perhaps happens<lb/>
to be in touch with only one of the participants in these researches. Naturally,<lb/>
he knows more about that one individual and therefore cannot help but stress<lb/>
his contribution.</p>
<p>Dr. Crenshaw, I am delighted to say, is still a member of<lb/>
the Mayo Clinic Staff. He is one of our most prominent members of the staff<lb/>
and you will be hearing from him shortly.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
