<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03434001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to John J. Moran, August 30, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03434001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-08-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Thomas, Lowell</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-08-30">August 30, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03434001</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to John J. Moran, August 30, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus relates his experiences as a yellow fever volunteer and criticizes Kissinger's conduct. He wants to know if other volunteers have spinal difficulties and includes a plan of the Columbia Barracks laboratory.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1937-08-30">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to John J. Moran, August 30, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03434001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
J.H. Andrus<lb/>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1937-08-30">8-30-37</date>
</dateline>
Captain John J. Moran,<lb/>
% Cia. Sunoco de Cuba, S. A.<lb/>
Avenida Menocal No. 102-A,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Captain:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Was delighted to receive your very interesting letter and<lb/>
cannot tell you how sincerely I regret that you did not<lb/>
look me up when you were in Philadelphia. As I recall,<lb/>
The Sun Co's. offices are on Walnut, above sixteenth, if<lb/>
that is right we were only about fifteen minutes apart.</p>
<p>Used to know Mr. J. Howard Pew, also Mr. Leister, of your<lb/>
Company. From 1910 until 1932 was Advertising Manager<lb/>
of The R. M. Hollingshead Co. * Whiz Auto Chemicals * and<lb/>
my Company have, for years, bought heavily from yours.</p>
<p>Was &ldquo;listening in&rdquo; the evening you were &ldquo;on&rdquo; with Lowell<lb/>
Thomas and was much pleased with your remarks. What<lb/>
you had to say was a refreshing change from the &ldquo;me and<lb/>
Walter Reed&rdquo; attitude assumed by Kissinger.</p>
<p>I agree with you that Kissinger's thirst for publicity,<lb/>
his apparent willingness to capitalize the part he took<lb/>
and the manifest egotism of his utterances have a decided<lb/>
tendency to cheapen all of us.</p>
<p>It is not surprising that you do not remember me as my<lb/>
part was very obscure. When Major Reed and Lieutenant<lb/>
Carroll moved to Cuba they brought with them - from the<lb/>
Army Medical College - Steward Neal and a private of the<lb/>
Hospital Corps.</p>
<p>Shortly after Dr. Lazear's death they took up quarters at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks and the enlistment of the Corps man<lb/>
expired. I was detailed to take his place. I was<lb/>
scrub lady, keeper of the zoo - two monkeys and a lot of<lb/>
guinea pigs - and mosquito hunter and breeder.</p>
<p>This must have been in November, 1900. Unfortunately,<lb/>
I did not keep a record. The laboratory in which I<lb/>
worked was the shack which had been the operating room<lb/>
when the hospital was under canvas. In it Major Reed<lb/>
and Lieut. Carroll had their microscopes and - ever on<lb/>
the hunt for the elusive y. f. bacillus - they spent many<lb/>
hours over their microscopes.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03434002"/>
<p>Page 2.</p>
<p>Much of the work of the Commission was planned by these<lb/>
two, in the laboratory, and they paid no more attention<lb/>
to me than to any other article of furniture.</p>
<p>Then, one morning, the Major was all steamed up because<lb/>
one of his volunteers had suffered a change of heart and<lb/>
knocked his schedule of experiments galley west.</p>
<p>Forbes had the fever and had reached the stage when they<lb/>
wanted to innoculate another with his blood. The<lb/>
Major told Lieut. Carroll he would take it. The Lieut.<lb/>
was horrified and spent the day trying to argue the Major<lb/>
out of the idea on the ground that the Major's age, and<lb/>
the fact that he was run down by a recent illness, would<lb/>
make his innoculation very hazardous.</p>
<p>I listened to all that and was afraid to do what seemed<lb/>
the obvious thing. I had nursed y. f. at Guanajay,<lb/>
had seen two men die and others critically ill with it,<lb/>
and didn't want any in mine.</p>
<p>Next morning they were still at it. I volunteered.</p>
<p>After my recovery I went on a two months furlough and,<lb/>
upon my returm, was assigned to other duty. It seems<lb/>
to me that the man who took my place - when I was innoc-<lb/>
ulated - was named Springer, but am not certain.</p>
<p>Please pardon me for being so voluminous - it is just<lb/>
between we guinea pigs - and, while I had no intention<lb/>
of going into all that I'll let it stand.</p>
<p>Perhaps all this was brought on you by your suggestion<lb/>
that I know how Kissinger came to volunteer. I do<lb/>
not - but would like awfully well to know. (With a<lb/>
hint as broad as that don't you think it is rather up<lb/>
to you?)</p>
<p>One of the reasons I wanted to get in touch with all my<lb/>
fellow guinea pigs was to ascertain if any others have<lb/>
had spinal trouble similar to mine. Was at Walter<lb/>
Reed Hospital from May 13, until Oct. 6, 1932 and the<lb/>
medicos there diagonsed my trouble as syringomyelia.<lb/>
My son, a graduate of Hahnemann Medical College, does<lb/>
not agree. He says &ldquo;spinal arthritis&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I have been bedfast since March, 1932, and am told that<lb/>
I can never walk again. Have a large, airy room,<lb/>
equipped with gadgets such as telephone, radio, hospital<lb/>
bed, <unclear>aa</unclear> cabinet to hold the things I need at hand, an<lb/>
<unclear>electricbfan</unclear> and even a typewriter with which to annoy<lb/>
my friends.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03434003"/>
<p>Page 3.</p>
<p>I assume that your occupation of the laboratory was after<lb/>
my innoculation - Jan. 28, 1901. (And just to keep<lb/>
<unclear>thatbfrom</unclear> sounding foolish there is doubt in my mind as<lb/>
to whether you mean the same laboratory that I do,)</p>
<p>Here is the one I mean:<lb/>
H<lb/>
C F G<lb/>
B<lb/>
E<lb/>
D<lb/>
A<lb/>
To wards of<lb/>
post hospital<lb/>
Path to officers'<lb/>
quarters - - -</p>
<p><list type="ordered">
<item>A, B, D and E - in main room of laboratory.</item>
<item>A - Major Reed's Microscope - <unclear>on</unclear> wide shelf - counter high.</item>
<item>B--Lieutenant Carroll's Microscope.</item>
<item>C - Quarters of Hospital Steward Neal</item>
<item>D - Table holding Mosquito-breeding jars.</item>
<item>E - Counter holding more jars, paraffine shaver, etc.</item>
<item>F - Shelves in small room - test tubes of cultures, incubator.</item>
<item>G - Shelves and counter holding supplies and two monkey cages.</item>
<item>H - Small addition in which guinea pigs were housed.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Unless I stop you will never dare write me again.</p>
<p>If you come to Philadelphia again please make it a point<lb/>
to visit me. I am but two blocks from Walt Whitman Hotel,<lb/>
which is first bus or train stop after crossing bridge<unclear>.</unclear></p>
<p>With kindest regards and best wishes for your future,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>J H Andrus</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
