<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03443001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, December 18, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03443001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-12-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-12-18">December 18, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03443001</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, December 18, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran writes to Hench about his own health, the various interpretations of the yellow fever story, and his part in the experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1937-12-18">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, December 18, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03443001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1937-12-18">Dec. 18, 1937.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You will be thinking of me as an ingrate for my failure to<lb/>
reply to your letter of September 22nd wherein you so kindly offer to assist<lb/>
Kissinger and myself in having our connection with the yellow fever experiments<lb/>
made known in all its details to the medical profession. Please know that I<lb/>
appreciate more than my ability to express it in words the offer made in your<lb/>
letter. First off, however, I want you to know that my failure to reply to<lb/>
your letter at once was due to the fact that I have had no heart to write for<lb/>
the better part of three months. I have been suffering from an old ailment,<lb/>
discovery of which came about for the first time in Bordeaux during the World<lb/>
War, namely, an ulcer of the duodenum. An X-Ray examination at the Mass.<lb/>
General Hospital Unit, near Bordeaux, revealed its existence. I think that<lb/>
Unit was known as Base Hospital No. 6. On recommendation of the major surgeon<lb/>
who examined me, I was to be &ldquo;Deed&rdquo; back to the United States so that I could be<lb/>
operated upon at Walter Reed General Hospital. With or without reason, I con-<lb/>
sidered it a disgrace to be D'd back and fought it, requesting as a last resort<lb/>
an interview with the Colonel commanding the Base Hospital. He, too, was<lb/>
adamant until I played my last card. That was my connection with the yellow<lb/>
fever experiments, an episode with which he appeared entirely familiar. I had<lb/>
my way upon promising that when and as I should get back to the United States<lb/>
I would go to Washington and have the operation performed. I never did. On<lb/>
and off, thru the intervening years, I have been subject to attacks. This last<lb/>
one, while not the most severe, lasted longer than any of the previous ones.<lb/>
<hi>An operation now, at age 62,</hi> would be out of the question as I take it. I am<lb/>
reasonably certain that I could not survive it. My better half wanted me to<lb/>
write to you for advice from the world's most famous clinic but I refrained from<lb/>
doing so. I am morally certain that I would be welcome to your advice free of<lb/>
charge. I hesitated to seek your advice because I know that the medical pro-<lb/>
fession frowns on treatment by correspondence. My mainstay, thruout the years,<lb/>
have been P. D. &amp; Co's &ldquo;Milk of Bismuth&rdquo; in the acute period of the attacks and<lb/>
&ldquo;Neutralon with Belladonna&rdquo; (Schering &amp; Kahlbaum) as a more or less steady diet.</p>
<p>I will now pass to the subject matter of your very kind<lb/>
letter. You need be in no hurry to return printed matter I sent to you some<lb/>
months ago. When you have finished with them, whenever that may be, will be<lb/>
time enough. You are entirely correct in arriving at the conclusion that<lb/>
the yellow fever story has not been correctly told so far. I know that it has<lb/>
been distorted. One thing only is certain and that is that Doctor Walter Reed<lb/>
was the guiding spirit in that famous drama. Thruout the years other idols<lb/>
have been set up to share in the honors which posterity should accord to be<lb/>
his exclusively. Intimately associated with Reed and his work as I was, I<lb/>
am none the less barred from telling the true story. As a non-medical man the<lb/>
telling of the true story does not fall within my province. Cuba, for instance,<lb/>
claims for Finlay ALL THE CREDIT for Walter Reed's findings and our American<lb/>
medicos have permitted the Cubans to steal the show in behalf of Finlay at the<lb/>
meetings of the Pan-American Medical Association had in recent years. Even<lb/>
Agramonte, notwithstanding the article published by him in the Scientific<lb/>
Monthly, in 1915, proclaimed Finlay as the real discoverer in the latter years<lb/>
of his life. In the year 1928 I discussed this matter at length with Doctor<lb/>
Agramonte, pointing out to him the discrepancy between his then point of view<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03443002"/>
<hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench</hi><lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>Dec. 18, 1937.</hi><lb/>
and that which he held in 1915 in the article he contributed to the &ldquo;Scientific<lb/>
Monthly&rdquo; entitled &ldquo;The Inside History of a Great Medical Discovery&rdquo;. He was<lb/>
completely taken aback by my reference to that article and I sensed that he did<lb/>
not know I was familiar with it or had ever read it. By all this, please do<lb/>
not think I am trying to rob Finlay of all the glory to which he is entitled<lb/>
for his contribution to Reed's eventual findings. Reed himself acknowledged in<lb/>
full Finlay's claims in the premises. True to the memory of the immortal Reed,<lb/>
I have always been willing to accord to Finlay his just measure and share in the<lb/>
eventual and conclusive results. The Cuban medical profession have consistently<lb/>
refrained from even mentioning Reed except when it was unavoidable. The medical<lb/>
profession in the United States have passively permitted the Cubans to grow bolder<lb/>
and bolder in their glorifying of Finlay as against the master, Reed. Since<lb/>
Gorgas' work in Cuba did not run counter to their claims for Finlay, they accord<lb/>
him the honors which they know are Reed's, in addition to the honors which Gorgas<lb/>
won as a sanitarian, based on Reed's findings. I am merely calling a &ldquo;spade&rdquo;<lb/>
a &ldquo;spade&rdquo;, nothing more. The Cuban medicos have made it a life business to<lb/>
laud Finlay, so much so that the present generation of medicos in Cuba ignore<lb/>
Reed entirely. In contrast, American medicos who write or lecture on Reed and<lb/>
his work, fail to get the picture and in many instances present that which they<lb/>
have hurriedly prepared as the &ldquo;inside or true story&rdquo; of the real discoverer of<lb/>
the mode of transmission of yellow fever. Who but the immortal Reed and his<lb/>
master mind conceived the idea of the &ldquo;human guinea pig&rdquo; as the medium thru<lb/>
which the mosquito theory could be exploded or established as a fact. No, my<lb/>
friend, the real story of &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo; has never been properly<lb/>
written, with all due respect to Dr. Howard A. Kelly and his book so entitled.</p>
<p>Now, my dear doctor, I will pass to your suggestion that<lb/>
Kissinger and myself write our respective accounts of the part we played in the<lb/>
yellow fever experiments. I am greatly honored by your offer to assist us<lb/>
to such an end and to have our versions published in some accredited medical journal.<lb/>
To me, however, anything more than a passing reference to my share in the<lb/>
experiments would be out of order. With Reed as the central figure, I should<lb/>
be glad to colaborate with you or any other American medico in placing the real<lb/>
story before the medical profession in the United States. Kissinger and myself<lb/>
are not even among the &ldquo;lesser lights&rdquo; in any such proposed article. The lesser<lb/>
lights would be Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte, the other three members of the<lb/>
Yello Fever Board. Kissinger and myself, including the other sixteen who vol-<lb/>
unteered for the experiments, would be entitled to such reference as &ldquo;human<lb/>
guinea pigs&rdquo; should be accorded.. We have both had a full share of fame or<lb/>
glory from the modest parts we played in the experiments. I, for my part, am<lb/>
satisfied that full justice has been done to me and my contribution to the work<lb/>
of Walter Reed. If I have had more than my share of publicity for my modest<lb/>
part in <unclear>Reed's</unclear> findings, I can truthfully state that I never sought publicity.<lb/>
It came to me unsolicited. When I sent you a lengthy story of my life, I<lb/>
did so to the end that you might be able to form an estimate of me personally<lb/>
for the address you had in mind for the members of the Mayo Clinic. I did not<lb/>
have in mind the possibility of having your article published unless, perhaps,<lb/>
the Mayo Clinic has a publication of its own for local circulation. Nor did<lb/>
I calculate that there would be any lengthy reference to myself in your article.<lb/>
I gave you more than you asked for, with the idea that reference to my share in<lb/>
the experiments would be &ldquo;boiled down&rdquo; to a few pertinent paragraphs. I belive<lb/>
that at least half of the eighteen men who volunteered for the exeperiments are<lb/>
still living. I will send you the addresses of two of them within a few days.</p>
<p>Meantime, I remain, with kind personal regards,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
A Merry Xmas and a happy<lb/>
New Year to You.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
