<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03452003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, February 24, 1938</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03452003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1938-02-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1938-02-24">February 24, 1938</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03452003</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, February 24, 1938</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran will send Hench a photograph of himself at no charge, and returns Hench's check. He offers Hench advice on contacting other yellow fever survivors and politely refuses medical treatment for his duodenal ulcer.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1938-02-24">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, February 24, 1938</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03452003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1938-02-24">Feb. 24, 1938.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Please do not think I have willingly or wittingly failed to<lb/>
respond in the desired form to your letter dated January 27th. It so happens<lb/>
that December, January, February and March of each year are our busy months<lb/>
in Cuba. Preparation for the &ldquo;grinding season&rdquo; commences in December and the<lb/>
other three months are devoted to actual grinding by the sugar mills of the<lb/>
Island. Since we have several sugar mills to which we supply lubricating oils<lb/>
and greases, considerable of my time is devoted to our sugar mill customers in<lb/>
the months indicated. Most of the mills have offices in Havana, but none the<lb/>
less we have to keep in touch with the engineers and mechanics. That means<lb/>
visiting the mills, scattered over the six provinces of the Island. Only three<lb/>
days ago was I able to get around to have that photograph taken for you. They<lb/>
are promised for Saturday, the 26th, but I may not be able to have them ready<lb/>
before Monday, the 28th. As soon as they are delivered to me I will mail one<lb/>
or two to you, together with a picture I had taken overseas during the World<lb/>
War and another which I had taken around 1910 for the late Joseph Bucklin Bishop<lb/>
for his book &ldquo;The Panama Gateway&rdquo;. I regret I have no photographs or snapshots<lb/>
of any kind taken at the time of the yellow fever experiments. I had quite a<lb/>
few such, taken in uniform and as a civilian, but as they began to fade over the<lb/>
years, I gradually threw them overboard. Being more or less of a soldier of<lb/>
fortune, since I arrived in the land of Washington and Lincoln, the throwing<lb/>
overboard usually took place when I was in the process of packing my trunks.<lb/>
Except during the past ten years or so, I have carried my wardrobe and personal<lb/>
belongings in trunks. So much to serve as an alibi for my failure to attend,<lb/>
without delay, to your appreciated and courteous request.</p>
<p>I am returning the <xref id="f03452001">ceheck</xref> you sent me. It was most thoughtful<lb/>
and delicate of you to have sent it. In an effort to emulate your delicacy, I<lb/>
am returning it. From this you must not assume that I am offended. While I<lb/>
am sometimes &ldquo;touchy&rdquo; in such matters, it does not happen to apply in the present<lb/>
instance. I am more than pleased to have the photograph taken for you at my<lb/>
own expense.</p>
<p>The following are all the additional addresses I have been<lb/>
able to obtain for you, to date, of the survivors who took the tests:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Clyde L. West, Riverdale, Md.</item>
<item>Capt. Thomas M. England, Medical Administration Corps,</item>
<item>U. S. Army, Office of the Surgeon, Governors Island, N. Y. <del>H.</del></item>
<item>Dr. Robert P. Cooke, State Dept. of Health, Lexington, Va.</item>
<item>John R. Bullard, St. Augustine, Florida.</item>
</list>
With the four listed, plus Kissinger, Andrus, Hanberry and your humble servant,<lb/>
you should be able to get in touch with at least eight of the survivors. There<lb/>
is some doubt as to whether or not Folk is still in the land of the living.<lb/>
Covington and Forbes are presumed to be still alive. Of the 22 names on the<lb/>
Roll of Honor, the known dead number eleven, including the four members of the<lb/>
&ldquo;Reed &amp; Carroll&rdquo; Yellow Fever Commission. My own impression is that there are<lb/>
ten survivors in all at the present writing. I think that if you were to<lb/>
write to the Veterans Administration, Washington, D. C., listing the three<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03452004"/>
<hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench</hi><lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>Feb. 24, 1938</hi><lb/>
supposed survivors whose addresses you do not have, instructions would be<lb/>
given you in a<del><unclear>l</unclear></del> letter as to how you might be able to get in touch with them.<lb/>
The Director of Finance, Veterans Administration, send checks each month to<lb/>
the survivors or their widows, but will not supply their addresses. The<lb/>
procedure is to write to the party in whom you may be interested, placing a<lb/>
stamp on your letter, envelope to bear the name only of such party. That<lb/>
letter should be inclosed in an envelope addressed to the Director of Finance,<lb/>
Veterans Administration, Washington, D. C., who will complete the mailing<lb/>
address on the enclosed envelope and forward same to destination. The envelope<lb/>
in which the letter for the &ldquo;missing link&rdquo; is inclosed must bear no return<lb/>
address. It must be entirely plain. The address will be shown on your own<lb/>
letter enclosed in the plain envelope, with nothing else on the envelope itself<lb/>
except the bare name and surname of the man with whom you want to get in touch.<lb/>
He may reply to your letter if he chooses. Chances are that any of the survivors<lb/>
to whom you might write would reply to your letter. The War Department rules<lb/>
in the matter of furnishing addresses are most rigid. Some months ago, I<lb/>
tried to get the names of the survivors for my own use and I have given you<lb/>
the gist of the &ldquo;red tape&rdquo; which has to be gone through in order to accomplish<lb/>
such a purpose. As a matter of fact I wanted the addresses of the survivors<lb/>
for you. I am under the impression that the Director of Finance would not<lb/>
object to inform you as to which on the list you submit are still in the land<lb/>
of the living. I am not sure that he will even do that. However, if you<lb/>
are sufficiently interested, there would be no harm in trying.</p>
<p>I have followed out your suggestions with reference to Mr.<lb/>
Andrus' case and chances are that you will be hearing from him before many<lb/>
days go by. Poor fellow, I do wish so much that something could be done for<lb/>
him to the end of releasing him from his present sorry state. I am more<lb/>
than delighted, for his sake, that his case comes within the lines in which you<lb/>
specialize. As to my own case, my dear friend, I fear me very much that I will<lb/>
have to worry along. I have a premonition that if I should ever be placed on<lb/>
the operating table for an operation on my stomach, I would not survive the<lb/>
operation. My heart action is none too good. Years ago, when I was Medical<lb/>
Supply Officer on the Panama Canal, I was operated upon for appendicitis and<lb/>
was back on duty on the morning of the eighth day dating from my first entry<lb/>
into the hospital. Being inventory time, I could not see my way clear to take<lb/>
the fifteen days which convalescents were recommended and advised to take at the<lb/>
&ldquo;Taboga Island Sanitarium&rdquo; of the Medical Department. That was some thirty<lb/>
years ago. So far as I know a man by the name of Cummings and myself were the<lb/>
only two operated upon for appendicitis on the Panama Canal to hold the seven-<lb/>
day record, and there were many of them when the force on the Panama Canal<lb/>
had reached 50,000 men and women employees. I have told you this so that you<lb/>
may not brand me as too cowardly to run the risk of an operation. Please<lb/>
accept my sincre thanks for your offer of assistance to me in connection with<lb/>
my gastric ulcer. By watching my diet and sidestepping excesses I may last<lb/>
for several years yet. When the crucial moment arrives, my only hope is that<lb/>
it will not be preceded by long and painful suffering. Please forgive me for<lb/>
this long, rambling, semi-sentimental letter. You are too busy a man to wade<lb/>
through such a long and purposeless letter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
