<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03453002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Layman's Case History, by John H. Andrus, March 1, 1938</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03453002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1938-03-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Army Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1938-03-01">March 1, 1938</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03453002</idno>
<title>Layman's Case History, by John H. Andrus, March 1, 1938</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus' medical history describes the development of the spinal condition that has left him bedridden.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1938-03-01">
<head>Layman's Case History, by John H. Andrus, March 1, 1938</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03453002"/>
<opener>
<hi>John H. Andrus</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1938-03-01">3-1-38</date>
</dateline>
<hi>Layman's Case History</hi><lb/>
</opener>
<p>Born Pennsylvania, October 7, 1879. Father died at 55 of Creep-<lb/>
ing Paralysis. Mother is vigorous and in comparatively good<lb/>
health at 80. A sister died at 24 and a brother at 36 of tuber-<lb/>
culosis.</p>
<p>In 1889, when an army recruit learning to ride, the pounding of<lb/>
a horse at a trot brought severe pain at base of spine and in ab-<lb/>
domen. This punishment lasted approximately three months when I<lb/>
was injured and, later, transferred to unmounted service.<lb/>
Xrays have shown that I have one more vertebrae than normal.<lb/>
It occurs to me that spine may have been injured at that time.</p>
<p>In 1901, during the early stages of an attack of yellow fever, pain<lb/>
in back was very severe and back arching most pronounced.</p>
<p>In 1908 or 1909 fell and struck small of back on steps. Soreness<lb/>
and lameness gradually diminished. Disappeared within few weeks.</p>
<p>About 1912 began having occasional severe pains in <unclear>abdomen</unclear>.<lb/>
Attacks gradually became more frequent. Discovered that hot appli-<lb/>
cations to BACK brought relief. About 1914 began having pains in<lb/>
back - especially at night.</p>
<p>In 1918 X-ray showed arthritis of spine. Wore spinal brace - steel<lb/>
band over hips and crutch supports under arm-pits - until bedfast.</p>
<p>On three occasions - always in the spring - condition became so<lb/>
acute had to go to bed for about six weeks. Attacks responded to<lb/>
strapping, rheumatic medication and rest.</p>
<p>From 1917 until bedfast was never a day without pain. Frequently<lb/>
cold sleep only by use of hot water bottle or pad. A chill or<lb/>
muscular exertion would mean added pain. Only able to continue<lb/>
at work because of executive position.</p>
<p>About 1922 developed bronchial cough that would not respond to<lb/>
treatment. Still have it but with greatly lessened severity.</p>
<p>About 1929 began to have occasional attacks of paroxysmal tacchy-<lb/>
cardia. Attacks increased in frequency and were at worst during<lb/>
time I was at Walter Reed Hospital. On one occasion there an<lb/>
attack lasted 22 hours with a beat of 184. This condition is<lb/>
now under control of one grain of digitalis daily.</p>
<p>In December, 1931, developed neuritis in upper arms, shoulders and<lb/>
neck with aggravation of back pains. Gradually grew worse des-<lb/>
pite medication and electrical treatments. Feet and hands grad-<lb/>
ually numbed. Began to lose power to hold things in hands.<lb/>
Stumbled in walking. Could not properly &ldquo;steer&rdquo; feet. Had to<lb/>
be helped to and from work and careened from walls to furniture<lb/>
in getting about.</p>
<p>March 1, 1932, went to bed for a &ldquo;rest&rdquo;. Am still &ldquo;resting.&rdquo;<lb/>
Hands and legs gradually became paralyzed. Hands were in clutch-<lb/>
ing position - could not be opened or closed. Numbness of hands,<lb/>
forearms and feet more pronounced.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03453003"/>
<p><hi>John H. Andrus</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Page 2</hi>.</p>
<p><hi>Layman's case History</hi>.</p>
<p>May 13, 1932, went to Walter Reed Hospital. No control of bladder<lb/>
or bowels. In efforts to ascertain cause, Wasserman, spinal <unclear>taps</unclear>,<lb/>
tubercular and blood tests all negative. It was found that I had<lb/>
a healed tubercular lesion of one lung. For a period of five weeks<lb/>
there was gradual increase in use of hands and feet. Was placed<lb/>
in wheel chair, in reclining position, and in three days was in much<lb/>
worse condition than before.</p>
<p>Bone graft of spine was considered but discarded because of wide<lb/>
involvement. Several vertebrae are fused together.</p>
<p>Oct. 6, 1932, returned home. Surgeons at Walter Reed Hospital<lb/>
told me that they could not hope to make me better but only to keep<lb/>
me from getting worse.</p>
<p>There has been a very gradual but marked improvement since that<lb/>
time. Control of bladder, bowels, hands and feet was almost nor-<lb/>
mal by the end of 1934. The sensatory nerves have never funct-<lb/>
ioned as near normal as the motor nerves.</p>
<p>For about a year I have had neuritis in the neck and shoulders and<lb/>
a constant headache. Condition is aggravated by elevating head of<lb/>
bed, even momentarily.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
