<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03469001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, July 13, 1938</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03469001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1938-07-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1938-07-13">July 13, 1938</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03469001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, July 13, 1938</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench comments on the film &ldquo;Yellow Jack.&rdquo; He defends Kissinger and proposes further investigations of the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1938-07-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, July 13, 1938</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03469001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1938-07-13">July 13, 1938</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
c/o Cia. Sunoco de Cuba, S. A.<lb/>
Avenida Menocal Nos. 455-457<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I would indeed like to be with you when you see the movie &ldquo;Yellow Jack.&rdquo;<lb/>
I think you will criticize it as did Mr. Kissinger. I saw it recently here, and<lb/>
unfortunately they put too much comedy in it, and there were only a few places where<lb/>
it was adequately dramatized with sufficient dignity. I read somewhere a story of<lb/>
Montgomery's reactions to this movie. Apparently, he and the other actors were more<lb/>
depressed than stimulated by the serious nature of the play and whenever they could,<lb/>
tried to relieve their feelings by clowning. It seems to me that this spirit was<lb/>
also that of the producers. In trying to relieve the dramatic situations, they<lb/>
&ldquo;over-relieved&rdquo; them. Nevertheless, it was an interesting movie, even if not too<lb/>
accurate.</p>
<p>You will be interested to know that we invited Kissinger up here to speak<lb/>
before an association here interested in medical research. He gave us a very inter-<lb/>
esting talk, and repeatedly stated that it was to be understood that whatever he<lb/>
had done, had been done also by you. He spoke frequently of you with the highest<lb/>
regard. He said that he wished he had had your education, said that you had come<lb/>
from a very excellent family, and in every way spoke most kindly and most highly<lb/>
of you. I think your friends have perhaps done Kissinger somewhat of an injustice.<lb/>
Naturally, those movie people see a certain amount of publicity in having one of<lb/>
the volunteers at their preview. You have the perception to know that although in<lb/>
a sense these invitations are sincere, nevertheless the movie people use their<lb/>
guests for advertising purposes. When they can't get you, they will use Kissinger.<lb/>
One cannot blame Kissinger for relieving the monotony of his quiet existence by such<lb/>
trips, nor for accepting the little extra money that he gets for doing it. He does<lb/>
it in good faith himself. As a matter of fact, his faith is too good, and recently<lb/>
he criticized the movies so frankly that he almost criticized himself out of his<lb/>
invitation. Your friends do him an injustice if they suggest to you that Kissinger<lb/>
steals the show. This is most assuredly not true. The strong part of the play is<lb/>
that of Sergeant O'Hara, taken by Montgomery, who is acting your part. As a matter<lb/>
of fact, if anyone should criticize, I should think that Kissinger's friends would<lb/>
criticize. As I see it, no one should criticize. Although it is natural for one's<lb/>
friends to come to his defense and natural for your friends to want to see you get<lb/>
your due credit, the same holds true for Kissinger's friends. We in the medical<lb/>
profession and posterity in general regard your contributions equally. You both<lb/>
offered everything you had, and the matter of who got stung first or who got sick<lb/>
first was in the hands of Fate, not in your hands, and had nothing to do with<lb/>
heightening or lessening your own contribution. I sincerely hope that your well<lb/>
meaning friends will not permit you to think, in the slightest way, ill of Kissinger.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03469002"/>
<p>Mr. John J. Moran</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>July 13, 1938</p>
<p>It is unfortunate that you are so far away and that he is on hand,<lb/>
but perhaps it is not unfortunate, for as you say, you do not enjoy these<lb/>
experiences.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I have not yet received the photographs, and hope<lb/>
they haven't been lost.</p>
<p>When Kissinger was here, I took the liberty of checking over the<lb/>
story again. There are parts of the story that do not quite agree with yours<lb/>
or with the record. This is natural, as the episode has been idealized by<lb/>
time and details have been forgotten through the years. I am therefore post-<lb/>
poning presentation of the story until I can spend considerable time and research<lb/>
on it in order that it may be as accurate as possible. I hope that it will be<lb/>
part his story and part your story, but it must agree in essence with the<lb/>
facts as given by Reed himself. You will see it long before it is published.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
