<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03476001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 30, 1938</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03476001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1938-10-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Dominguez [Roldan], Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1938-10-30">October 30, 1938</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03476001</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 30, 1938</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran relates personal news and offers his opinion on Kissinger. He has high compliments for Kean as an authoritative source. He mentions a letter of recommendation, written by Walter Reed, which he believed to be at the University of Virginia. Moran writes that he found many inaccuracies in the film &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; and suggests to Hench that he should take up the Finlay vs. Reed controversy rather than the Kissinger-Moran memoirs.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1938-10-30">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 30, 1938</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03476001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1938-10-30">Oct. 30, 1938.</date>
(Sunday)<lb/>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am going to make a trial at long-distance psychology. You will<lb/>
have been thinking that your letter of July 13th &ldquo;rubbed me&rdquo; the wrong way;<lb/>
that I had indexed you as too pro-Kissinger and that I was not &ldquo;big enough&rdquo;,<lb/>
spiritually, to take it. No doubt my long silence justified such a line of<lb/>
thinking on your part. Nothing, however, could be further from the truth.</p>
<p>When your letter was received, my wife's mother was very <add>ill</add> and on<lb/>
August 20th she passed away. She was a second mother to me, not merely a<lb/>
mother-in-law. Mrs. Moran, some four years ago, got herself into such a<lb/>
nervous state, following the death of her uncle, that she developed asthma<lb/>
which lasted for the better part of a year. That year played havoc with<lb/>
her health and my own. What with being suddenly awakened, sometimes as<lb/>
many as four times during the night, to find her gasping for breath, you can<lb/>
well imagine how we both suffered. Injections of Ephedrine ONLY afforded<lb/>
her relief. Since her mother became ill, I had to take every precaution<lb/>
against a recurrence of her old ailment. My task was to prepare her for<lb/>
the inevitable. Following her mother's death and since, that task has not<lb/>
been lightened, but I can see daylight now. I am going into this matter<lb/>
more than I othewise would for the simple reason that I value your good<lb/>
opinion. Placing it on that basis, therefore, I trust you will pardon me<lb/>
for imposing on your time with my family affairs.</p>
<p>Now, as to Kissinger and myself. I am sure our respective stories,<lb/>
as written or related to you, cannot be reconciled. The truth is that one<lb/>
or the other of us is suffering from a short memory and has so consistently<lb/>
deviated from the real truth as not to realize it, repeating the story so<lb/>
often as to be now convinced of its absolute accuracy. Since you find that<lb/>
you cannot dovetail our respective accounts, you are free to take your choice.<lb/>
I, for one, have no intention of taking issue with any of Kissinger's state-<lb/>
ments. Time has gone by for that. Kissinger's story started a long time<lb/>
ago, to be exact, when he applied for a pension because of his then unfortun-<lb/>
ate condition; later on when a national appeal was made in his behalf for<lb/>
&ldquo;Dream Home&rdquo;. Please do not think I am influenced by my friends in any<lb/>
opinion I may have formed of Kissinger and his statements. I know his story<lb/>
very well, having had it from one of those most actively engaged in bettering<lb/>
his condition in life. You asked for my story and I gave it to you. I do<lb/>
not claim infallibility and never have. At the same time I am entirely<lb/>
certain that, of all those named on the Roll of Honor, my memory of the<lb/>
episode with which we are dealing is more accurate than that of any of those<lb/>
on that Roll living today. Please do not think I am patting myself on the<lb/>
back when I make that statement.</p>
<p>You state in your letter that there are parts of my story which<lb/>
do not agree with the record. There is one omission in the record which<lb/>
I have never made any effort to correct. That refers to the blood test.<lb/>
See page four, line 37 of my story. That, of course, while true, should<lb/>
be eliminated. I am perfectly satisfied to let the record stand as it<lb/>
reads against my name on the Roll of Honor. All of General Sternberg's<lb/>
personal and official papers on the yellow fever experiments were made avail-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03476002"/>
<hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench</hi>.<lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>Oct. 30, 1938</hi>.<lb/>
able to the officer designated by the Surgeon General of the Army to prepare and<lb/>
edit the Roll of Honor, as were the letters of Major Reed to Mrs. Reed in<lb/>
the same connection. That officer was General Jefferson R. Kean, Medical<lb/>
Corps, U. S. Army, on the retired list since 1924. General Merritte W.<lb/>
Ireland, Surgeon General of the Army at the time when the <hi>Act of February<lb/>
28th, 1929</hi>, became law, designated General Kean for the task because he knew<lb/>
he was the highest living authority to pass on the Reed Board's work and on<lb/>
the respective merits of every man whose name was to appear on the Roll of<lb/>
Honor. Every word was weighed very carefully on the finished ROLL and if<lb/>
you have read it carefully you will find a statement there against my name<lb/>
that you will not find in connection with any of the remaining seventeen of<lb/>
those who volunteered for the experiments. If you have not found it, I<lb/>
certainly shall not enlighten you. Regardless of that statement, however,<lb/>
all eighteen of us took the same chance, with exception of two who did not<lb/>
contract yellow fever. Of these one was willing to take the alternative<lb/>
test, the other let it go and called it a day when the infected bedding<lb/>
and clothing test failed to give him yellow fever. I, also, consider Gen.<lb/>
Kean the highest living authority on matters connected with the conquest of<lb/>
yellow fever. He was Major Reed's intimate friend. He was a medico of<lb/>
mature years. He was Chief Surgeon of the Department in which the tests<lb/>
were carried out. His general knowledge of the experiments and of the<lb/>
connection between Reed and Finlay give him a unique status among those<lb/>
yet living and authorized to advance an opinion in the premises. In some<lb/>
respects his knowledge of certain details and incidents connected with our<lb/>
life at Camp Lazear cannot be as good as mine. I lived through them and<lb/>
was one of the camp residents from November 20th to December 25th, 1900,<lb/>
when I was taken down with yellow fever. My status at the Camp was also<lb/>
unique. A personal letter of recommendation given to me by Major Reed,<lb/>
written in his own hand, indicates my status. It reads as follows:</p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
Army Medical Museum and Library,<lb/>
WASHINGTON.</p>
<p>Feb 20</p>
<p><unclear>who</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>who</unclear></p>
<p>This is to certify that the bearer, Mr. John J. Moran,<lb/>
is a man of excellent habits and can be implicitly entrusted to<lb/>
perform whatever duty may be assigned him. He was in my employ-<lb/>
ment for several months as clerk and typewriter, and during this<lb/>
time performed his duties in the most satisfactory and painstaking<lb/>
manner. A man who volunteered, as he did, without hope of any<lb/>
pecuniary reward, but solely in the interests of humanity and<lb/>
medical science, to enter a building purposely infected with<lb/>
yellow fever, and thereby contracted an attack of the disease,<lb/>
should need no words of recommendation from any one.</p>
<p>I feel confident, therefore, that he will give entire<lb/>
satisfaction to any one who may give him employment.</p>
<p>(Signed) WALTER REED<lb/>
Surgeon, U. S. A.<lb/>
(ORIGINAL of this letter is now in possession of the U. of Va.) <add>They later<lb/>
lost it!</add></p>
<p>I had a preview of &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; on August 12th and was not a little<lb/>
surprised at myself as &ldquo;Sergeant O'Hara&rdquo;. I suppose I should have felt very<lb/>
much flattered from the prominent role accorded me. In a way, I am and in<lb/>
another sense, I am not. With a little more attention to details and person-<lb/>
alities, the picture would have been entitled to a &ldquo;monumental rating&rdquo;. How-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03476003"/>
<hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench</hi>.<lb/>
-- 3 --<lb/>
<hi>Oct. 30, 1938.</hi><lb/>
ever, I consider it better than no picture at all. It glorifies Reed and<lb/>
it certainly gives Finlay a status which he never had before, although the<lb/>
Cubans are wild about the part he is given in the play and the monocled<lb/>
actor who plays the role. Personally, I criticize the producers in that<lb/>
same respect and in giving Finlay a Scotch burr which he did not have. The<lb/>
monocle and the burr were two luxuries in which Finlay did not indulge. We<lb/>
have in Cuba a self-appointed Finlay champion, Dr. Francisco Dominguez Rol-<lb/>
dan, at one time on the Faculty of Medicine of the University of Havana, and<lb/>
later Cuban Minister to France. While there, he was elected a Member of the<lb/>
French Academy of Medicine and succeeded in having the Academy lean towards<lb/>
the theory that Finlay, and Finlay only, was entitled to <hi>all the credit</hi> for<lb/>
the conquest of yellow fever. For the past several years, led by this old<lb/>
gentleman, the Cuban medicos have followed his line of reasoning and, with<lb/>
this leadership, have practically convinced even intelligent Cubans that<lb/>
Reed is more or less of an usurper. We are all agreed, of course, that<lb/>
Finlay was correct in his species of mosquito. Those of us who are impartial<lb/>
also know that he never got anywhere with his theory. You will recall the<lb/>
Agramonte article in the Scientific Monthly, written in December, 1915, the<lb/>
same year Finlay died. Agramonte was a Cuban, not an American. Finlay, as<lb/>
a matter of fact, was a Cuban only by accident. He was born here, the son<lb/>
of a Scotch father and a French mother. However, the Cubans claim him as<lb/>
their own. He graduated in Medicine at Jefferson Medical College, Philadelph-<lb/>
ia and came back to Cuba to practice. He left Cuba as a boy and was educated<lb/>
in England and the United States, with a comparatively short sojourn in his<lb/>
mother's native country. Agramonte, in the picture, plays a rather sorry<lb/>
part. He was an upstanding specimen of Cuban manhood, spoke English as well<lb/>
as any of our university graduates. From the time he was four or five years<lb/>
old, he was taken to New York and he did not return to Cuba until some three<lb/>
years after graduating in Medicine at P. &amp; S. (Columbia University). The bent-<lb/>
over actor who represents him in the picture, and his decidedly Latin-American<lb/>
accent, are entirely out of place. I have pointed out two of the capital<lb/>
errors appearing in the picture &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;, but there are many more I could<lb/>
point out.</p>
<p>May I suggest that a clearing up of the REED-FINLAY-CONQUEST-OF-<lb/>
YELLOW<unclear>-</unclear>FEVER, or an effort to do so, on your part, is a task far more press-<lb/>
ing than publishing the Kissinger-Moran stories or memoirs. The Cuban<lb/>
Government, I understand, is preparing to publish in six languages the Finlay<lb/>
story. That story will be a repetition, more or less, of what Dr. Francisco<lb/>
Dominguez Roldan has proclaimed over the past fifteen years. It will be in<lb/>
book form and for free distribution. It is certain to charge the American<lb/>
Medical Profession and Public, either directly or indirectly, with &ldquo;stealing&rdquo;<lb/>
<unclear>for</unclear> REED what belongs to Finlay by right. I am sure you would find an able<lb/>
and willing col<add>l</add>aborator, in any such project, in General Kean. The General<lb/>
is now pretty well along in years, mentally as sound as he ever was, but<lb/>
suffering from failing sight. I am sending you a copy of a letter I received<lb/>
from him dated April 12, 1938, which is self-explanatory. Needless to state<lb/>
that any assistance I could render in such a laudable effort would be yours<lb/>
for the asking. I do not suppose I could be of very much assistance, since<lb/>
the subject is more or less taboo to non-scientists. Have mailed you <del>the</del><lb/>
a new set of pictures. While the others were marked &ldquo;Registered&rdquo;, the office<lb/>
boy who mailed them did so without registration. Evidently they are lost for-<lb/>
ever. Inquiry at the Post Office here resulted NIL. Will close for the<lb/>
present and hope you will be able to survive the ordeal of reading this.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
