<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03478001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, December 14, 1938</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03478001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1938-12-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1938-12-14">December 14, 1938</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03478001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, December 14, 1938</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Moran that he is resolved to write an accurate history of the yellow fever experiments. He discusses the relative reliability of Moran's and Kissinger's recollections.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1938-12-14">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, December 14, 1938</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03478001"/>
<opener>
Yellow Fever<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1938-12-14">December 14, 1938</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John J. <hi>Moran</hi><lb/>
c/o Cia. Sunoco de Cuba, S. A.<lb/>
Avenida Menocal Nos. 455-57<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I frankly admit that I was quite relieved to receive your recent letter, as I was<lb/>
afraid that perhaps you had taken a little offense at my frank remarks. I do appreciate<lb/>
your comments very much indeed, and I am delighted to have the honor of having received<lb/>
your autographed photographs.</p>
<p>My little, modest idea of writing a short account of the story of yourself and<lb/>
Kissinger for staff meeting here has become considerably complicated. I little dreamed<lb/>
that there were so many conflicting features about the yellow fever researches. I<lb/>
can well see how anxious you are to have some of these conflicts straightened out for<lb/>
the sake of future medical historians. I am flattered by your suggestion that I should<lb/>
make a much more comprehensive study, not just one of the parts played by yourself<lb/>
and Kissinger, and your suggestion that I become deeply involved in trying to rewrite<lb/>
in a more accurate fashion a history of the yellow fever researches is flattering and<lb/>
at the same time very intriguing. I am a very busy physician (at least I like to think<lb/>
I am) doing clinical work and medical research here of an amount that keeps me hustling.<lb/>
Nevertheless, I have always been extremely interested in medical history, and the idea<lb/>
of devoting part of my time over the next several months or years toward the yellow<lb/>
fever story is not at all distasteful. I believe I told you that when I was in England<lb/>
this Spring, haunting some old medical bookstores, I ran across several interesting<lb/>
old books on yellow fever, before the time of Reed, and one written just a few years<lb/>
after the work in Cuba. I bought these with glee and they will be helpful in my<lb/>
background notes. I sincerely hope I will be able to continue to have your most<lb/>
appreciated cooperation in this matter.</p>
<p>I wish to reiterate my complete sympathy with both you and Kissinger, and my<lb/>
understanding of reasons which might make your stories disagree in detail but not in<lb/>
principle. Having spent several hours on at least two occasions with Mr. Kissinger,<lb/>
it is not difficult to realize that from the standpoint of memory, the word of one who<lb/>
has had considerably more education than Mr. Kissinger was able to have, carries much<lb/>
weight. For the next two weeks I will be able to do nothing on the problem, and this<lb/>
is one of those things that will have to occupy my spare hours from time to time, very<lb/>
intermittently. Rest assured that I am keeping at it, and nothing will happen in any<lb/>
way, shape or form until you have had the chance to see it and criticize it in extense.<lb/>
This is not my story. It is the story of those who did the work, and I am merely the<lb/>
medium for the story.</p>
<p>Again I regret that I did not know of your living in Havana two years ago when<lb/>
I was there. I hope to go to California for my vacation this Spring, but next Winter<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03478002"/>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
December 14, 1938<lb/>
expect to go to Florida. If we are both in the land of the living I sincerely<lb/>
hope to run over to visit you in Havana at that time--in other words, fourteen<lb/>
months from now.</p>
<p>With the best of Christmas wishes, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
