<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03503002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, April 21, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03503002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-04-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="place">Havana, Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Florida</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-04-21">April 21, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03503002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, April 21, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench reveals his thoughts on Kissinger. He expresses his continued interest in the yellow fever story.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-04-21">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, April 21, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03503002"/>
<opener>
<hi>Yellow Fever</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1939-04-21">April 21, 1939</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
c/o Cia. Sunoco de Cuba, S. A.<lb/>
Avenida Menocal Nos. 455-57<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was indeed interested to hear from you again. Indeed, I have not dropped<lb/>
the Reed-Finlay matter. Not realizing that there was any particular conflict in<lb/>
the matter, my original intention was to obtain a straight-forward story from<lb/>
Kissinger and one from you and publish these with brief comments in a journal<lb/>
devoted to medical history, where they would be on record, in your own words, for<lb/>
the medical profession of all time. Then when I found that Kissinger's comments<lb/>
did not agree with some of yours, and when I found that Reed's reports did not<lb/>
agree with one or two of the other reports in the Congressional Record, I began<lb/>
to see that the story wasn't a simple one to unravel. I talked over with Kissinger<lb/>
when he visited us a number of the points in dispute, and of course part of the<lb/>
errors are simply due to the lapse of time and forgetfulness. Others may be mistakes<lb/>
that have come into his story simply because he has lived the story for so many<lb/>
years. You see, frankly Mr. Kissinger was not as fortunate as you. As far as<lb/>
he <unclear>is</unclear> concerned, his life more or less ended with the Havana experience, and<lb/>
he has been living that experience over ever since, on the insistence of friends<lb/>
who have asked him to tell the story over and over again. You, on the other hand,<lb/>
have continued an active, energetic life, most of the time too busy to spend much<lb/>
time telling the story of the Havana experience. You can see, therefore, how he<lb/>
could, without any wrong intent, dramatize his experience after so many tellings.</p>
<p>I have been collecting old books on the yellow fever story and I am preparing<lb/>
to do considerable research on the matter. It is my sincere hope that I can take<lb/>
my vacation next March partly in Florida and partly in Havana, and I am greatly<lb/>
hoping that you will be there at that time and that I can spend three or four more<lb/>
days in Havana, by which time I will have some definite inquiries to make of you<lb/>
that you can help me straighten out the contradictions. If at all possible, I am<lb/>
hopeful that you will be able to guide me to the original camp and show me some<lb/>
of the historical features. With your approval, I should like to bring my camera<lb/>
and make a few photographs to illustrate the story later. Rest assured that nothing<lb/>
is to be done that you and Mr. Kissinger, and others interested, will not know fully<lb/>
about before its publication. You can see it is going to be a matter of many months,<lb/>
perhaps two or three years, before things are ironed out, and I will most assuredly<lb/>
appreciate your help.</p>
<p>I am sorry indeed to hear that you were so very ill, but delighted to know<lb/>
that you are now improved. I am particularly interested in rheumatic diseases and<lb/>
am not much of a stomach specialist. At any rate, any advice that I could give you<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03503003"/>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
April 21, 1939<lb/>
by mail wouldn't be worth much, but if there is any way we can cooperate with your<lb/>
attending physician, either now or in the future, I am yours to command.</p>
<p>Incidentally, apropos of the clipping which you sent me, Mr. Kissinger<lb/>
was really misquoted, and this article is not fair to him. He was most careful<lb/>
to mention your name repeatedly during the talk and spoke in the highest terms<lb/>
of you. At no time did he minimize in the slightest degree your contribution,<lb/>
and I am sure your friends would have been completely satisfied and proud to have<lb/>
heard the things he said about you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
