<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03507001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, August 31, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03507001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-08-31</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Dominguez [Roldan], Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-08-31">August 31, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03507001</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, August 31, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran informs Hench that he has asked Kean to assist him in his yellow fever research. Moran writes that the Camp Lazear site is unrestricted - it is not necessary to request permission to take photographs of the area.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-08-31">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, August 31, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03507001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1939-08-31">Aug. 31, 1939.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>When I received your letter dated April 21st I was<lb/>
preparing to take a little vacation in the U. S. in company with Mrs.<lb/>
Moran, the first one in eleven years. I go North every two or three<lb/>
years on business, never spending over a week in God's Country, one<lb/>
or two days of which I devote to shopping. Since your letter did not<lb/>
call for an urgent reply, I postponed writing to you prior to my entry<lb/>
on leave. When I returned on July 1st, the exchange situation here<lb/>
had me worrying and it has kept me worrying ever since. The bottom<lb/>
began to fall out of the Cuban Peso in June and the situation became<lb/>
panicky in July. August has shown but little improvement. Today, the<lb/>
last day of the month, the Cuban Peso being worth 85-3/4&cent; of an American<lb/>
Dollar, leaves us in a bad way. We all hope, however, that it will im-<lb/>
prove before the end of the year. The Cuban Government has several<lb/>
plans in mind for stabilizing the Peso, none of which have been enforced<lb/>
or put into practice so far. Up until four years ago, our peso was on<lb/>
a par with the Dollar. The drop in its value today is a very serious<lb/>
matter for importers.</p>
<p>Now, with refrence to your proposed visit to Cuba.<lb/>
You have known right along, of course, that I would be entirely at your<lb/>
service, when and as you might decide to come here. I do not plan on<lb/>
leaving Cuba during the coming year. I would suggest, however, that<lb/>
if you could arrange to come to Havana in February, instead of March, you<lb/>
would find it more agreeable. While we do not have very hot weather in<lb/>
March, it is more agreeable in February. So far as I am concerned, it<lb/>
makes no difference as to the month you may elect. You need not worry<lb/>
that you will have any difficulty in taking all the pictures you want of<lb/>
the site of Camp Lazear. A picture of the site would have little meaning<lb/>
aside from its sentimental value. Pictures of Camp Lazear, as it was<lb/>
when we guinea pigs were there, are available on application to the Army<lb/>
Medical Library, that is to say, photostatic copies of the camp. It will<lb/>
not be necessary to apply for permits of any kind, I am quite sure.</p>
<p>Just yesterday, I wrote a very long letter to General<lb/>
Kean, informing him that I had hopes of your sponsoring, either in book<lb/>
form or in the form of an article to be published in one of the accredit-<lb/>
ed medical journals, the real history of yellow fever, with special refer-<lb/>
ence to the parts played by Reed and Finlay in what we have come to know<lb/>
as &ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. I voiced the hope that General Kean<lb/>
would collaborate with you. While he was Major Reed's intimate friend,<lb/>
his opinion would be strictly impartial. You could bank on that. The<lb/>
Cubans, based on the practically unanimous opinion of the Cuban medicos,<lb/>
claim ALL FOR FINLAY. That stand, of course, is untenable. Ignorance of<lb/>
Finlay's contribution to the conquest of yellow fever is excusable, to a<lb/>
certain extent, in the United States. Denial of Reed's share, however,<lb/>
on the part of the Cubans, is altogether inexcusable. The epidemic of<lb/>
yellow fever which was raging while his experiments were being carried on<lb/>
happened to be in Cuba and it was in this country that the experiments<lb/>
were carried out. There are too many Cuban medicos still living who<lb/>
know the facts very well. In order to glorify Finlay, they find it con-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03507002"/>
<hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench</hi>.<lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>Aug. 31, 1939.</hi><lb/>
venient to forget it. With my letter to you, dated October 30, 1938,<lb/>
I sent you a copy of a letter General Kean wrote to me, dated April 12,<lb/>
1938. That letter was read at a session of the Rotary Club here and<lb/>
its reading and publication in the Havana leading dailies next day only<lb/>
served to rile Dr. Finlay's self-appointed champion, Dr. Francisco Dominguez<lb/>
Roldan. The latter, by the way, was present at the Rotary Club session<lb/>
and when called upon for a few remarks he reiterated his well known claims<lb/>
for Finlay, classifying as spurious and pertaining to FINLAY ONLY all the<lb/>
honors accorded to Reed in marble, bronze, books on the subject written by<lb/>
American authors and the Congressional Record. You will not, if you take<lb/>
the trouble to re-read General Kean's letter, that he does not take the<lb/>
stand of the Cubans so much into account as I do. That is due to the fact<lb/>
that I am here in their midst and continually reading the claims made for<lb/>
Finlay, to the exclusion of Reed, more virulent with each passing year. So<lb/>
far as the Cubans are concerned, this matter will not be allowed to die out.</p>
<p>I think you will agree with me that the relative shares<lb/>
of Reed and Finlay have never been clearly and impartially stated in any<lb/>
of the books dealing with the subject at issue. Dr. Kelly's &ldquo;Walter Reed<lb/>
and Yellow Fever&rdquo;, the only book I know of which deals exclusively with<lb/>
the matter, contains many errors. The first edition of that book I have,<lb/>
having donated the second edition, presented to me by the author, to the<lb/>
University of Virginia, The Alderman Library having neither edition. The<lb/>
second edition contains letters and other data supplied by Dr. Carroll and<lb/>
admitted by the author, dealing principally with the experiments carried<lb/>
out by Carroll, not as a member of the Army Commission or Board headed by<lb/>
Major Reed. You will notice from &ldquo;The Roll of Honor&rdquo; that some of Dr.<lb/>
Carroll's cases occurred as late as October, 1901, while the work of the<lb/>
Reed Yellow Fevr Board wound up in February, 1901.</p>
<p>I am pleased to know that, in general, you find the<lb/>
article in the SATEVEPOST by J. C. Furnas interesting. At that, it has<lb/>
quite a few errors, correction of which, I regret, I did not have an<lb/>
opportunity to make when he finally completed it. I gave him fool-proof<lb/>
details as to names, dates and places but he evidently got a few of them<lb/>
mixed in the shuffle. That is to be expected from newspaper reporters<lb/>
and writers.</p>
<p>I am glad to inform you that my duodenal ulcer has not<lb/>
given me any trouble now in over eight months. While I was in the U. S.<lb/>
I could not live up to my regimented diet very well but none the less I<lb/>
escaped any reminder of its presence with me. I hope to be completely<lb/>
cured at the end of the year but I expect to watch my diet carefully for<lb/>
the rest of my days.</p>
<p>Will let you know of General Kean's reaction as soon as<lb/>
I hear from him. In the meantime, if you have time to write to me, your<lb/>
letters will be always very welcome. With kindest personal regards, I<lb/>
remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
