<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03516001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, November 3, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03516001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-11-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">California</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Florida</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Chicago (Ill.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Akron (Ohio)</name>
<name type="place">Princeton University</name>
<name type="place">Princeton, (N.J.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-11-03">November 3, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03516001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, November 3, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench volunteers to speak on the story of Kissinger and Moran at the Washington and Jefferson College Founders' Day program. He plans to meet Moran in Cuba. He offers a monetary contribution for Washington and Jefferson College.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-11-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, November 3, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03516001"/>
<opener>
leave<lb/>
on desk.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1939-11-03">November 3, 1939</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Hutch:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was delighted to receive your letter, and I should like indeed<lb/>
to join you in your California jaunt.</p>
<p>I am awfully glad you are planning to have the Medical Founders'<lb/>
Day, and I am already beginning to make a little list for my own pondering as to who<lb/>
might be a couple of good medical speakers. Last night I put one man on my list,<lb/>
and this morning in the paper, I noticed he had received the Nobel Prize. He is a<lb/>
German but I understand he speaks perfect English. That shows how good a picker I<lb/>
am.</p>
<p>I am in constant touch with Kissinger and Moran. Indeed, I expect<lb/>
to visit Moran in Havana in March, hopping over from Florida. I shall, of course, be<lb/>
glad to do whatever I can in a very small way, and if you think, after the thing all<lb/>
works out, that you still want a little talk by me on the story of Kissinger and Moran,<lb/>
I shall be glad to give it. As a matter of fact, I already have a number of lantern<lb/>
slides on the subject, and in Havana will take pictures of scenes of the investigative<lb/>
work as they now look; but between now and then, you may make many changes in plans,<lb/>
which may exclude me. If so, you don't have to worry about it. Just write and tell<lb/>
me about it.</p>
<p>I have long wanted to make a little contribution for your work,<lb/>
and it isn't for lack of interest in you or in W. and J that I haven't done it. I<lb/>
have simply had so many prior calls. As it is, my contributions for this and last<lb/>
year exceeded what the income tax allows me, so you see I haven't shirked. Please put<lb/>
me down for one hundred dollars for you to use in whatever way you wish, although if<lb/>
it is to be for the Lazear Building, that would please me. I wish to God it were<lb/>
ten or one hundred times that much, but I just sent Lafayett a hundred, and the local<lb/>
boy scouts have nicked me this year very well. What with these contributions, and a<lb/>
small one to Alborz College, I may get on relief yet! I am dictating this down town, as<lb/>
I am leaving on the train very shortly. Hence, a check will be sent to you after I<lb/>
return.</p>
<p>I am enroute to Chicago and New York. The Howdie Grays and the<lb/>
Henches are motoring from Chicago to New York, leaving Chicago via Akron, Ohio where<lb/>
we are visiting the Seiberlings from Sunday until Tuesday, then on to New York, arriving<lb/>
at the Hotel Roosevelt on Wednesday <add>Nov.8</add>. I will be in New York until Saturday morning. Do<lb/>
you expect to be in the neighborhood? Then the Grays and Henches expect to go to the<lb/>
Princeton game. By the way, if there is any chance of your getting near there, please<lb/>
let me know, as I may not be able to go to the game, and who knows, I may hand you my<lb/>
ticket and my wife!</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
