<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t03510001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Paul B. Barringer, October 6, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03510001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-10-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Barringer, Paul B.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Goethals, George W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Venezuela</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-10-06">October 6, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03510001</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Paul B. Barringer, October 6, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran writes of a Thanksgiving he spent with Barringer in 1901, and then recounts his financial successes and failures after he left the University of Virginia Medical School.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-10-06">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Paul B. Barringer, October 6, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03510001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, Cuba, <date value="1939-10-06">Oct. 6, 1939.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Paul B. Barringer,<lb/>
9 Oakhurst Circle,<lb/>
University Post Office,<lb/>
Charlottesville, Va.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Barringer:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am about to satisfy a desire I have had for &ldquo;a month<lb/>
of Sundays&rdquo;, viz: to drop you a line or two. I am sure you would have<lb/>
difficulty in recalling me and what I was like when I was at Virginia for a<lb/>
sojourn entirely too brief to leave an impression. I well remember you,<lb/>
however. You were most kind to me and would have helped me out, I am sure,<lb/>
had the University been as well endowed in those days as it is today. You<lb/>
may or may not recall that I slept in your house two nights during Thanks-<lb/>
giving of 1901. I happened to be one of the few students at the University<lb/>
who had no family or friends to visit. You went on a hunting or fishing<lb/>
trip and you wanted some &ldquo;grown-up&rdquo; to be present in the house so that<lb/>
Mrs. Barringer and the children might feel a little more secure. The con-<lb/>
fidence and trust implied in your invitation I have always remembered and<lb/>
appreciated. I felt very proud and highly honored.</p>
<p>Somewhere in your official or personal files there<lb/>
should be a letter of introduction for me from Walter Reed. I am not<lb/>
sure that I delivred the letter in person but if I did not, Major Reed<lb/>
mailed it to you. As Dean of the Faculty, you were, to all intents and<lb/>
purposes, President of the University. I am afraid that, as a student,<lb/>
I was not very much of a success. Even in the dissecting room, where I<lb/>
found myself very frequently as late as eleven o'clock at night, more than<lb/>
once alone, studying arteries and nerves, my thoughts were given to specu-<lb/>
lating on how I was to get through a four-year course in Medicine with the<lb/>
all-too-slim amount I had on deposit in one of the Charlottesville banks.<lb/>
I was unable to concentrate on my studies. When I invested one-half of<lb/>
the amount I had in the bank in Grace Oil Company stock, I bid goodbye to<lb/>
my medical education, without knowing it. Grace Oil Company, of Houston,<lb/>
Texas, assured me that I would double or quadruple every dollar invested,<lb/>
within six months. I read their full-page advertisement in Hearst's<lb/>
yellow JOURNAL. I soon learned that the ground-floor concessions which<lb/>
the promoters claimed to have in &ldquo;Spindletop Heights&rdquo; did not exist. The<lb/>
company was formed by a band of swindlers. I happened, for the nonce, to<lb/>
be &ldquo;one of those born every minute&rdquo;. Along came a Mr. Thomas P. Spencer,<lb/>
looking for likely candidates leaving the University that year. He was<lb/>
manager of the Metropolitan Office of the Travelers Insurance Company, in<lb/>
New York City. You recommended me to him and he took me along with him.<lb/>
I stayed with him for two years, not even earning my salt for the first<lb/>
six months. At the end of the two years, I was on my way and the results<lb/>
of my missionary work converted themselves into dividends. Then came an<lb/>
offer from Gorgas for work in Panama as Sanitary Inspector. &ldquo;The Call of<lb/>
the Tropics&rdquo;, of which I had a taste here in 1898-1900, was more than I<lb/>
could resist. I threw up my contract with Travelers, one of the capital<lb/>
errors of my life, and became a tropical tramp, so to speak. From that<lb/>
point on, my life was far from humdrum. I was one of the pioneers on<lb/>
the Panama Canal and had the great satisfaction of being one of the first<lb/>
passengers on the first steamer that traversed the Canal from the Atlantic<lb/>
to the Pacific end, 1904 men being given first choice by General Goethals.<lb/>
Gorgas and the latter were my friends. Both were personal enemies and<lb/>
while I know the cause I will not burden you with reciting it. Besides,<lb/>
it is too long a story. After the Canal was finished, I launched into<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03510002"/>
<hi>Dr. Paul B. Barringer</hi>.&nbsp;-- 2 --&nbsp;<hi>Oct. 6, 1939</hi><lb/>
the jewelry business in the City of Panama and was again &ldquo;on my way&rdquo;<lb/>
when the United States declared war on Germany. I turned down a Major's<lb/>
commission for service in the Canal Zone and instead went overseas as a<lb/>
Captain in the Q. M. Corps. The War over, I went to Venezuela for The<lb/>
Mercantile Bank of the Americas which &ldquo;blew up&rdquo; in 1921-22, just as I<lb/>
was about to be appointed manager of its affiliate, The Mercantile Over-<lb/>
seas Corporation, in Maracaibo. Had to start all over again, landing in<lb/>
Mexico with the Mexican Trading Corporation, representing Sun Oil Company<lb/>
and Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Company. The altitude being a little too<lb/>
much for me, I made a bid for Cuba for Sun Oil Company products, forming<lb/>
Compa&ntilde;ia Sunoco de Cuba and of which I was half owner until Generals<lb/>
Machado and Depression put me down and out during 1932 to 1934. Today,<lb/>
Compa&ntilde;ia Sunoco de Cuba is a 100% subsidiary of Sun Oil Company but they<lb/>
have been most considerate with me. I manage the company and their<lb/>
other interests in Cuba. Having no children, it matters little whether<lb/>
I leave much of an estate or not. My life insurance will suffice to<lb/>
provide for my better half as and when I may start on the road that has<lb/>
no turning. In the meantime, I manage to live fairly comfortable. One<lb/>
of the things I would have liked to be in position to do in past years<lb/>
would have been to send some deserving young man to the University of<lb/>
Virginia to graduate in Medicine, by way of making up for my own thwarted<lb/>
ambition.</p>
<p>But please pardon me for imposing upon your time<lb/>
and good nature with all this rambling. It is not fair and I am not sure<lb/>
that you will not be bored through reading such a long and purposeless<lb/>
letter. One of my outstanding faults, and I know it better than anyone<lb/>
else, is to write long letters. My friends tell me they find them<lb/>
interesting but I imagine they say so because they do not want to hurt<lb/>
my feelings. Mr. Clemons will probably bear me out as to the long<lb/>
letters. I sent one on its way to him a few days ago.</p>
<p>With my very kindest regards to you and yours,<lb/>
I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
John J. Moran.<lb/>
From John J. Moran,<lb/>
c/o Cia. Sunoco de Cuba, S. A.,<lb/>
Avenida Menocal Nos. 455-457,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba.</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
