<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03519001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, December 10, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03519001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-12-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, W. A.</name>
<name type="person">Houssay, Professor</name>
<name type="person">Wells, Sumner</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Hull, Secretary</name>
<name type="person">Clark, Herbert C.</name>
<name type="person">Cummings, Hugh S.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Leahy, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Balfour, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Abel, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Lafayette College</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-12-10">December 10, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03519001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, December 10, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench offers advice on the structure of the Washington and Jefferson College Founders' Day program and makes recommendations for possible speakers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-12-10">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, December 10, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03519001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1939-12-10">December 10, 1939</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Hutch:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have always known that you and I were on rapport. I was thinking of<lb/>
you and of Founder's Day the other night, and came down to the Clinic in the morning,<lb/>
prepared to write you a letter when I received yours.</p>
<p>Consider this a list of preliminary suggestions. I have discussed your<lb/>
proposed program with Dr. Louis B. Wilson, the Director Emeritus of the Mayo Foundation,<lb/>
and with Dr. Tom Magath, the head of our department of tropical and allied diseases.<lb/>
Both of these men are familiar with the ability of nationally known speakers. I believe<lb/>
you said that you wanted two or three speakers, and it seemed to us that these speeches<lb/>
should be arranged somewhat as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>Speech No. 1: An introductory, short talk, telling the laymen the human inter-<lb/>
est story of what Lazear and his colleagues actually did, omitting entirely or only<lb/>
briefly touching on the implications of their work.</item>
<item>Speech No. 2: A nationally known medical man who would bring to your<lb/>
audience the value of the work of Lazear and his colleagues, and show its influence on<lb/>
medical progress, not only in the United States but also in the world.</item>
<item>Speech No. 3: A nationally known speaker, medical or otherwise, from Latin<lb/>
America, a sort of &ldquo;hands across the sea&rdquo; speaker, which you had in mind when you thought<lb/>
of Lord Dawson. This man should again extole the work of Lazear and speak of how great<lb/>
his contribution was to the Latin American countries in <unclear>wiping</unclear> out yellow fever. He<lb/>
should also mention the importance of this work to the northern countries, particularly<lb/>
now that tripical diseases are so readily transferrable to the North by airplane<lb/>
communication.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Now as to the suggestions:</p>
<p>Our first suggestion was Dr. W. A. Sawyer, Director of the Rockefeller Founda-<lb/>
tion, to give the second speech mentioned above. You might want some important Latin<lb/>
American speaker such as Professor <unclear>Houssay</unclear>, Professior of Physiology at Buenos Aires,<lb/>
or better yet, Sumner Wells, Undersecretary of State.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Dr. W. A. Sawyer is about sixty years of age, I believe. He is Director<lb/>
of the Rockefeller Foundation, is a world authority on yellow fever, has won many medals,<lb/>
and I am informed that he is a brilliant speaker and that he knew all of the men personally<lb/>
working with Reed and Lazear. I believe he won the Walter Reed medal from the American<lb/>
Society of Tropical Medicine, and Magath tells me that he is the logical successor to<lb/>
the work of Reed and Lazear. Magath says that he is the supreme authority on yellow<lb/>
fever besides being an excellent speaker and a man who has done many important research<lb/>
problems himself on the disease.</item>
<item>2. As the layman speaker to give speech No. 3 (in lieu of a South American<lb/>
speaker), we would suggest Sumner Wells, Undersecretary of State. I am told by those<lb/>
who have heard him that he is an excellent speaker and while he might or might not know<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03519002"/>
Dr. Ralph Hutchison<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
December 10, 1939<lb/>
directly of the work of Lazear and Carroll, he could inform himself of it, and be an<lb/>
excellent man to show the social implications of the importance of their work to<lb/>
governments. As you know, Wells is a leading authority on Latin American traditions.<lb/>
He would be a good name for you on the program, and incidentally, just recently gave a<lb/>
talk on the &ldquo;policy and program of the United States government in its international<lb/>
cultural relationships.&rdquo;</item>
<item>3. Perhaps you might get Secretary Hull. Although Hull must be very busy,<lb/>
with the war going on, I understand that he is a willing speaker if he can improve inter-<lb/>
national relations and of course he would have the opportunity, not only to mention the<lb/>
outstanding work of Dr. Carlos Finlay of Cuba, (whose idea set Reed and his committee<lb/>
on the right track) but would also have a chance to give a &ldquo;hands across the sea&rdquo; talk<lb/>
using international medical <unclear>cooperation</unclear> as his theme.</item>
<item>4. As an alternate, either to Wells or Hull, Wells has an excellent assistant<lb/>
who, next to him, is the leading authority in the State Department on Latin American<lb/>
affairs. He is an excellent speaker. I don't have his name at the moment, but we could<lb/>
get it.</item>
<item>5. As an alternate for Sawyer, both Wilson and Magath recommended most highly,<lb/>
Dr. Herbert C. Clark, head of the Gorgas Institute in Panama. He, too, knew the men<lb/>
concerned with the Yellow Fever Commission, and worked with Gorgas. He is an excellent<lb/>
speaker, spends half of his time in Panama at the Gorgas Institute and the other hald<lb/>
as Professor of Pathology at the University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia.</item>
</list></p>
<p>It seemed to us that the program with Dr. Sawyer as the medical representative<lb/>
and Sumner Wells as the layman diplomatic representative would be ideal, with Herbert<lb/>
Clark as an alternate for Sawyer.</p>
<p>Other men whose names were suggested: (Their merits and demerits are as<lb/>
follows, but these men were considered of secondary importance).</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Surgeon General Hugh S. Cummings, Director of Pan-American Sanitary Bureau,<lb/>
Washington. Wilson called him a &ldquo;magnificent speaker&rdquo;. Magath called him a &ldquo;good talker&rdquo;.<lb/>
However, he is a retired Surgeon General, is about sixty five, and is perhaps too old<lb/>
to put on a program that you want to have all set six months in advance.</item>
<item>2. Dr. John A. Ferrell, Associate Director of the Rockefeller Foundation.<lb/>
Wilson called him a &ldquo;good speaker&rdquo;. Magath called him a clear speaker but one with &ldquo;a<lb/>
rather monotonous, soft voice&rdquo;.</item>
<item>3. Dr. Henry a Moe of Cuggenheim Memorial Foundation, New York City, a good<lb/>
talker who could talk on the social importance of yellow fever throughout the world.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Others who were suggested but turned down strongly for various reasons were:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Surgeon General Parran of the United States Department of Public Health.<lb/>
He is well known to the laymen and is a good talker but his two pet hobbies are venereal<lb/>
Ac<lb/>
LM<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03519003"/>
Dr. Ralph Hutchison<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
December 10, 1939<lb/>
diseases and the care of the medical indigent, and it might be very hard for him<lb/>
to speak on anything else than this, unless he were definitely assigned a topic to<lb/>
conform with your program.</item>
<item>2. Surgeon General Magic of the Army, but he was considered a poor speaker.<lb/>
he knows nothing of yellow fever and would have to look up everything.</item>
<item>3. Surgeon General McIntyre, Roosevelt's physician. His only merit would<lb/>
be that he is Roosevelt's physician and his name is known to the laymen, but he is a<lb/>
nose and throat man and doesn't know a darned thing about yellow fever.</item>
<item>4. Morris Fishbein, Editor of the Journal of the A.M.A. At another time,<lb/>
I would have recommended him heartily. He is a nationally known speaker, one of the<lb/>
most <unclear>rapid speakers</unclear> I have ever heard, and at times, one of the most excellent. He<lb/>
sprinkles his speeches with amusing stories, but you have to be a little careful be-<lb/>
cause some of those stories are slightly off color--all right for medical audiences, but<lb/>
perhaps not for laymen. At the moment, however, he is very much in the doghouse among<lb/>
American Medical men because of his uncompromising attitude regarding the problem of<lb/>
social medicine.</item>
<item>5. Rock <unclear>Sleyster</unclear>, President of the American Medical Association. But he is<lb/>
not an inspiring speaker and would probably want to give his speech No. 5, which is<lb/>
merely a rehash of his speech No. 1 on socialized medicine.</item>
</list></p>
<p>I also thought of some Nobel Prize winner, whose name would be known. Most<lb/>
of them are not very good speakers. Minot of Boston (Nobel Prize for liver for perni-<lb/>
cious anemia) is only a fair speaker--mutters and mumbles.</p>
<p>Murphy, his co-Nobel laureate, is a very poor speaker. Whipple, who was the<lb/>
third man to win the Nobel Prize for this work, is a much better speaker, but is less<lb/>
known than the others.</p>
<p>Banting, Nobel Prize for insulin, is in the army, and you don't want to count<lb/>
on him because he might be in Europe at that time. Best, co-discoverer of insulin,<lb/>
did not win the Nobel Prize, but is very well known, is a young man thirty five years<lb/>
old, and a good speaker, but not in the class with the others.</p>
<p>Domagk, the current Nobel Prize winner is in Germany, and of course, you could<lb/>
not get anybody from Europe. I doubt very much if Lord Dawson or anyone else would come<lb/>
and risk the trans-Atlantic crossing.</p>
<p>Incidentally, one of the doctors concerned with the experiments, in a minor<lb/>
role, is still living--Dr. Cook. I can send you his address. He must be fairly old<lb/>
by now. You might invite him and perhaps you would want him to speak informally.<lb/>
Indeed, you might want him to give the human interest story, but as a member of the<lb/>
group, he might be too modest to do this.</p>
<p>At this point, may I say that I don't want you to feel in the slightest<lb/>
committed to me as the one to give the human interest story. If you want two speakers,<lb/>
it is quite probable that Dr. Sawyer could give as much of the story as you want, and I<lb/>
would be delighted either to give him the material I have in <unclear>toto</unclear>, or at some very<lb/>
informal meeting to supplement his remarks by some lantern slides which I have collected,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03519004"/>
Dr. Ralph Hutchison<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
December 10, 1939<lb/>
showing the various characters concerned, the site of their army research camp, etc.<lb/>
I am completely in earnest about this, and I don't think you ought to make committments<lb/>
as far as my talk is concerned.</p>
<p>Now as to the men from here. We have no one sufficiently informed about<lb/>
yellow fever, to be in a class with the men I have mentioned.</p>
<p>Dr. Balfour is a fairly good speaker, is Director of the Mayo Foundation.</p>
<p>Dr. Wilson himself has been an excellent speaker, but has now retired, and<lb/>
is well over seventy. He is rather frail, and if you put him on the program, he might<lb/>
be dead by the time the day arrives.</p>
<p>These, confidentially, are not only my opinions, but those of Magath, and are<lb/>
of course, confidential.</p>
<p>Finally, as to the two other suggestions, Dr. Lahey of Boston is merely a<lb/>
good surgeon. His reputation among medical men is good, but his reputation among<lb/>
<unclear>laymen</unclear> is of the slightest, and he couldn't hold a candle to some I have mentioned.</p>
<p>Dr. Abel was dismissed by Dr. Wilson as &ldquo;just <unclear>another</unclear> Southern doctor.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In conclusion, our first suggestions are Dr. Sawyer and Sumner Wells.<lb/>
You mustn't feel obligated in the slightest toward these suggestions, and I shall be<lb/>
delighted to make any further inquiries that you may wish me to make, and of course<lb/>
consider it confidential.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P.S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
<seg>
P.S. I shall most certainly increase my check to $150.00 Can I send it to<lb/>
you dated January 17 Heavens to Betsy, if I can add $50.00 and get my name engraved in<lb/>
bronze at W. and J. it is most assuredly worth it<unclear>!</unclear> I will do it on one condition,<lb/>
however, that after it, you will put &ldquo;Lafayette, '16&rdquo;<unclear>!</unclear><lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
