<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03515001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, October 28, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03515001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-10-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Dawson, Lord</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Sidney</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">California</name>
<name type="place">Los Angeles (Calif.)</name>
<name type="place">Denver (Colo.)</name>
<name type="place">Garden City [s.l.]</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-10-28">October 28, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03515001</idno>
<title>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, October 28, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hutchison informs Hench that his plans for a yellow fever speech have been postponed from commencement to November 1940 (Founder's Day), to dedicate the Lazear Chemistry Building. An autograph note by Hench lists possible speakers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-10-28">
<head>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, October 28, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03515001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
THE PRESIDENT'S OFFICE<lb/>
WASHINGTON AND JEFFERSON COLLEGE<lb/>
WASHINGTON, PENNSYLVANIA<lb/>
<date value="1939-10-28">October 28, 1939</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Phil:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am distressed to learn that you have been<lb/>
ill. I can imagine that it took a good deal of strength<lb/>
out of you and that it has taken you a long time to<lb/>
come back. I hope that very soon you will find yourself<lb/>
back to normal and completely recovered.</p>
<p>I am glad you received the congratulations on<lb/>
the Jewish New Year. There is something about that<lb/>
holiday that always reminds me of you and so I always<lb/>
try to send you my affectionate regards. I do believe<lb/>
firmly in interracial equality, and I think that on one's<lb/>
New Year it is the time for amenities from one race to<lb/>
another!</p>
<p>I think that the Medical Founders' Day of which<lb/>
we have been talking for years must come to pass a year<lb/>
from now. We hope to have the Chemistry Building finished<lb/>
at that time. We have decided to name the building<lb/>
&ldquo;The Lazear Chemistry Building&rdquo;. It would therefore be<lb/>
most fitting that our long talked of plan should be<lb/>
carried out a year from now on Founders' Day, probably<lb/>
about November ninth or tenth of 1940. The boys are<lb/>
already at work on &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; which they will give<lb/>
this year and have ready to give again then. Because of<lb/>
the dedication of this building, I believe that this<lb/>
medical program will even be more effective than it would<lb/>
have been at the time we originally proposed it.</p>
<p>Now, as a first step on this proposition, we<lb/>
need to spot the key man for speaker. We use two<lb/>
speakers on Founders' Day and we really need to spot two<lb/>
key men as speakers. Both should be along medical lines.<lb/>
One might be a medical man himself, and the other one<lb/>
might be some kind of a specialist on medicine who is<lb/>
not a medical man or physician. Please turn this over<lb/>
in your mind now and let me know who you think would be<lb/>
the most attractive and draw the most attention if he<lb/>
should come as our speaker on that occasion. I am<lb/>
presuming, right from the beginning, that we cannot get<lb/>
Lord Dawson of Penn. It is too bad that Sidney Howard,<lb/>
the writer of Yellow Jack, and one of our honorary alumni,<lb/>
was killed this summer. Perhaps you saw that in the papers.</p>
<p><unclear>Donagh<lb/>
Chuck<lb/>
William S<lb/>
Minot<lb/>
Banting<lb/>
De Kr<lb/>
Sinclair Lewis<lb/>
Balfon<lb/>
Head Rockefeller<lb/>
Gen Keane<lb/>
Joslen<lb/>
Whiffle<lb/>
Sir Henry Dole Ferdon</unclear></p>
<pb n="2" id="f03515002"/>
<p>Doctor Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>October 28, 1939</p>
<p>Another question which occurs to me is this -<lb/>
how can we present most effectively and dramatize some-<lb/>
what the story of Moran and Kissinger on which stories<lb/>
you are working at the present time? My present<lb/>
thought is that you ought to give that at the dinner in<lb/>
the evening.</p>
<p>Give my love to Mary. I am anxious to see her<lb/>
and you and all of the family. I am still watching for<lb/>
a chance to get up there in order to accomplish this<lb/>
and also to take another examination.</p>
<p>In regard to Harriet, I have news which is both<lb/>
good and bad. She has steadily improved and August<lb/>
and September saw her almost completely back in shape<lb/>
and going one hundred per cent. However, this past three<lb/>
weeks she has again been having bad headaches, some<lb/>
suffering, and we are going back to further examination.<lb/>
This will wait until I come back from California.</p>
<p>I am leaving for California tomorrow, flying<lb/>
both ways. The purpose is a short, snappy financial<lb/>
campaign at Los Angeles. I will only be there about two<lb/>
days. En route, I will have a day with my father at<lb/>
Garden City and a day with Jim in Denver on which same<lb/>
day we will have a dinner for the Rocky Mountain alumni<lb/>
of Washington and Jefferson College.</p>
<p>After that trip, I hope we can get Harriet<lb/>
straightened out and then I hope I can get to Rochester<lb/>
before you go to Florida.</p>
<p>Our love to all of you, and keep well.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Affectionately yours,</salute>
<signed>Ralph Cooper Hutchison</signed>
<unclear>H</unclear><lb/>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
RCH/M<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
