<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03521003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, December 26, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03521003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-12-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, W. A.</name>
<name type="person">Mohler, Henry K.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Jefferson Medical School [Washington?, (Pa.)]</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Indiana</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-12-26">December 26, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03521003</idno>
<title>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, December 26, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hutchison informs Hench that he is to be the keynote speaker for Washington and Jefferson College Founders' Day. He muses whether Moran and Kissinger should attend as well.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-12-26">
<head>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, December 26, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03521003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
THE PRESIDENT'S OFFICE<lb/>
WASHINGTON AND JEFFERSON COLLEGE<lb/>
WASHINGTON, PENNSYLVANIA<lb/>
<date value="1939-12-26">December 26, 1939</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Phil:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In the first place, thank you for the check<lb/>
for one hundred and fifty dollars for your part in<lb/>
our Chemistry Building. This is a swell thing for<lb/>
you to do and I think I can look over the long list of<lb/>
contributions and find no other which means as much<lb/>
to me personally as this one from you and Mary. You<lb/>
can well understand the reason for that and the truth<lb/>
of it.</p>
<p>I am dictating this letter on Saturday before<lb/>
Christmas though it will not be transcribed until<lb/>
Tuesday after Christmas. This morning came your<lb/>
special delivery letter. We would be delighted to have<lb/>
the London Pictorial just as you suggest. Our children<lb/>
would be interested in it and it would keep us in<lb/>
touch with the English aspect of the war in which we<lb/>
are intensely interested. I have left your letter at<lb/>
the house in order that Harriet may read it and so<lb/>
I may not have the name of that supplement correct.<lb/>
Nevertheless we would love to have it. There is<lb/>
nothing that we would rather have and we will be delight-<lb/>
ed to receive it as a gift from you and Mary.</p>
<p>In regard to the Founders' Day, I think that<lb/>
your fear of your material being an anticlimax is not<lb/>
well founded. The plan which I am shortly to present<lb/>
to the Board of Trustees for this Founders' day program<lb/>
is as follows. On Friday evening we would have your<lb/>
lecture on the background of Doctor Lazear's work as an<lb/>
introduction to the presentation of &ldquo;Yellow Jack.&rdquo;<lb/>
You can see how this would start the program beautifully<lb/>
and make the play of &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; even more interesting.<lb/>
If you have moving pictures or still pictures, they<lb/>
would fit perfectly, and because this would be the<lb/>
kickoff in the entire program there would be no slightest<lb/>
danger of it having the effect of an anticlimax. It seems<lb/>
to me that this would be a perfect setup on Friday even-<lb/>
ing. Then on Saturday morning would be the dedication<lb/>
exercises of the Chemistry Building with the address being<lb/>
made by Doctor <hi>Sawyer</hi>. In the evening would be the Home-<lb/>
coming Dinner with the address being made, perhaps by<lb/>
Doctor Mohler, or whatever his name is, who is dean of<lb/>
Jefferson Medical School. This depends upon two things in<lb/>
my thinking. In the first place, it depends upon whether<lb/>
we discover him to be a reasonably good speaker. I have<lb/>
written to several of our students in the medical school to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03521004"/>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
December 26, 1939<lb/>
see what their judgment is about that and am looking<lb/>
forward, of course, to the information which you<lb/>
discover. In the second place, it would depend upon<lb/>
the successful rapprochement of Washington and<lb/>
Jefferson and Jefferson Medical School in the matter<lb/>
of the famous stolen portrait which I hope may be<lb/>
regained from Jefferson Medical School and presented<lb/>
to this College at that dinner.</p>
<p><unclear>get early</unclear></p>
<p>This plan was ready for presentation to our<lb/>
Executive Committee yesterday but other business<lb/>
crowded it out, and will be taken under consideration<lb/>
by the trustees during the first or second week in<lb/>
January.</p>
<p>I suppose that you are familiar with the<lb/>
story of O'Hara, or whatever his real name is, the one<lb/>
in Cuba, which appeared in the Saturday Evening Post<lb/>
in August of this year. I have sent for more copies of<lb/>
this, and if you did not see it please let me know.<lb/>
I want you to have one. He appears to be a rather<lb/>
successful business man down there and may occasionally<lb/>
come to the United States.</p>
<p>If you are going over to see him on your<lb/>
vacation, I think you ought to explore the possibilities<lb/>
of inducing him to come up on business at the time of<lb/>
this Founders' Day. Incidentally, we are setting this<lb/>
Founders' Day for Saturday, October the twenty-sixth,<lb/>
and you should put the date down now and have it in mind.<lb/>
Perhaps this man in Cuba will have a business trip to<lb/>
America next fall and could so plan it that he could<lb/>
come for these exercises. We would devise some way of<lb/>
honoring him. I do not suppose that under any possible<lb/>
stretch of imagination we could make it into a degree,<lb/>
though we could do something equally effective so far<lb/>
as he is concerned, possibly. I question whether we could<lb/>
finance the cost of bringing him from Cuba for the<lb/>
exercises, but we can make it a very nice occasion for<lb/>
him if he could come.</p>
<p>You and I can take up later the possibility<lb/>
of bringing Kissinger from Indiana which would not be such<lb/>
a great expense and which might be possible. The<lb/>
article in the Saturday Evening Post indicates that six<lb/>
or seven of the men who took part in that experiment<lb/>
are still living if I remember correctly. If I get these<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03521005"/>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
December 26, 1939<lb/>
copies I will send you one whether you have seen it or<lb/>
not, and without waiting to hear from you.</p>
<p>In summary, therefore, I think anything you<lb/>
can gather together will be right. I believe any<lb/>
pictures you can get, particularly moving pictures, would<lb/>
be very effective and I think you ought to count on<lb/>
doing a talk on the background of the Lazear work at the<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; play event on Friday night. This seems to<lb/>
me to be the right setup.</p>
<p>Give our love to Mary. I am interested<lb/>
to know that your mother will be here during the Christmas<lb/>
holidays and I will go in to see her.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Hutch</signed>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
RCH/M<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
