<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03526001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, February 5, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03526001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-02-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="place">Lafayette College</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-02-05">February 5, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03526001</idno>
<title>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, February 5, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hutchison congratulates Hench on receiving a honorary degree from their alma mater, Lafayette College.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-02-05">
<head>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, February 5, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03526001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
THE PRESIDENT'S OFFICE<lb/>
WASHINGTON AND JEFFERSON COLLEGE<lb/>
WASHINGTON, PENNSYLVANIA<lb/>
<date value="1940-02-05">February 5, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Phil:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am delighted to have your letter of January<lb/>
thirty-first telling me fine news of the honorary<lb/>
degree at Lafayette College upon which I congratulate<lb/>
you with all of my heart and soul. No one ever received<lb/>
that degree who deserved it more than you do. You need<lb/>
have no hesitancy about accepting it. You deserve<lb/>
it richly and absolutely and it is a becoming honor to<lb/>
you.</p>
<p>It means a great deal to me for you to get it.<lb/>
This letter which you have written means more to me and<lb/>
I am deeply happy in regard to the whole matter.<lb/>
However, I must disclaim responsibility, much as I would<lb/>
wish to claim it. I may have had some indirect influence<lb/>
in the matter, but I do not deserve the credit which you<lb/>
give me for direct influence. I have on several occasions<lb/>
talked with President Lewis about your fine accomplish-<lb/>
ments and your work. A few weeks ago I had lunch in<lb/>
Philadelphia with the chairman of the trustee committee<lb/>
on honorary degrees at Lafayette College, and in the<lb/>
course of our conversation I told him something of your<lb/>
fine work. However, the subject of a degree for you<lb/>
was not brought up at that time nor at any time, and I<lb/>
didn't know anything about it. The picture is further<lb/>
complicated by this fact which I now pass on to you.<lb/>
On January twenty-fifth, six days before you wrote me the<lb/>
letter about your degree at Lafayette, the trustees of<lb/>
Washington and Jefferson College took action authorizing<lb/>
the conferring of the degree of Doctor of Science upon<lb/>
you at our Founders' Day Exercises in October. There-<lb/>
fore, the degree at Lafayette College is actually a<lb/>
disappointment to me and it would be far from my purpose<lb/>
to induce them to give you a degree when I wanted to do<lb/>
it myself.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the degree from Lafayette is<lb/>
much better for you than our degree for two reasons. In<lb/>
the first place, Lafayette is your college and it will<lb/>
mean most to you to be recognized there, just as it did<lb/>
to me when I received my honorary degree there. In the<lb/>
second place, a degree from here might conceivably by<lb/>
some people be thought of as the result of my friendship<lb/>
for you. This is not true of course. You will recall, I<lb/>
think I told you, that the degree was proposed not by<lb/>
myself but by two members of the Board, one of them<lb/>
Mr. Sherrard of Pittsburgh, and the other one a man from<lb/>
elsewhere. So that the original motion for a degree for<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03526002"/>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
February 5, 1940<lb/>
you was made several years ago by others, and I was<lb/>
happy to remind them of that when the matter came up<lb/>
this time. In any case, the degree is better from<lb/>
Lafayette, though it is an intense disappointment to me<lb/>
in one respect.</p>
<p>What this degree from Lafayette will do<lb/>
to our degree in October I do not know. We will have<lb/>
to put our heads together on that. We would seem to<lb/>
be in the curious position of following the lead of<lb/>
Lafayette, whereas Lafayette is actually thinking our<lb/>
thoughts ahead of us. They are doing a few months ahead<lb/>
of us what we have planned to do for several years, but<lb/>
which we have been holding for this particular occasion.<lb/>
It is an unfortunate mixup in one sense but there is<lb/>
nothing to do about it and I am not sure what we should<lb/>
do about your degree for Founders' Day. Later, you and I<lb/>
will both have a judgment on it.</p>
<p>In any case, our hearty congratulations<lb/>
on the Lafayette degree, our deep satisfaction that you<lb/>
are being recognized as you should be, and our abundant<lb/>
joy in the deep and beautiful friendship which finds<lb/>
such perfect expression in your letter and which causes<lb/>
me to rejoice in your honor as does nothing else possible.</p>
<p>So far as being at Commencement in Easton<lb/>
I cannot do so. This year the Lafayette and the Washington<lb/>
and Jefferson dates coincide. Our Commencement is on<lb/>
Saturday, but our Baccalaureate is on Friday, the day<lb/>
that you are at Lafayette. Of course, what you might do<lb/>
is come on the sleeper that night after Commencement and be<lb/>
at our Commencement too. There is no reason for this<lb/>
but it would be nice to see you!</p>
<p>Well, I must close - congratulations,<lb/>
good wishes. We are all deeply happy for you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Hutch</signed>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
May Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
RCH/M<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
