<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03532001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Interview of John J. Moran by Philip Showalter Hench, April 3, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author></author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03532001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-04-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Furnas, Joseph C.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Neal, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Lampson, Robin</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville, (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana, Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Young, Province of Pinar del Rio, Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Salem, (N.J.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington, D. C.</name>
<name type="place">Guanajay Barracks, Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Army Medical School, Washington, D. C.</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Hospital, Cuba</name>
<name type="hospital">Yellow Fever Tent Hospital, Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-04-03">April 3, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03532001</idno>
<title>Interview of John J. Moran by Philip Showalter Hench, April 3, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench questions Moran about the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1940-04-03">
<head>Interview of John J. Moran by Philip Showalter Hench, April 3, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03532001"/>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head><hi>QUESTIONING OF Mr. MORAN BY Dr. HENCH, HAVANA, CUBA, APRIL 3, 1940.</hi></head>
<item>Q. How was Dr. Reed's request made known to the soldiers.</item>
<item>A. Principally through the medium of Dr. Roger Post Ames, by word of mouth.<lb/>
Within three days the news had spread throughout the camp.</item>
<item>Q. When did Dr. Ames mention it to you.</item>
<item>A. It was between October 31st and November 5th. The exact month and date<lb/>
would not be remembered by me since I did not consider them of such far-<lb/>
reaching importance.</item>
<item>Q. Did you broach the news to Kissinger and did he know about it before you did.</item>
<item>A. I broke the news to him and according to my absolute knowledge he did not<lb/>
know anything about it previously. Dr. Ames broke the news to me about<lb/>
4:30 in the afternoon. Kissinger and I roomed together and that same<lb/>
evening evening I told Kissinger of Dr. Ames' conversation with me and we<lb/>
discussed it, as nearly as I can remember, until 2 o'clock in the morning.</item>
<item>Q. Do you remember anything you said to each other.</item>
<item>A. I remember distinctly that after Kissinger had informed me of his determin-<lb/>
ation to volunteer for the experiments I said to him: &ldquo;John, I am going into<lb/>
these experiments as a fitting start in medicine, so please think very care-<lb/>
fully of what you propose to do because, after all, we have no certainty<lb/>
that we will survive the experiments,&rdquo; or words to that effect. He answered<lb/>
me back in the same way. &ldquo;John, (I was John to him also) whatever you do I<lb/>
am going to do. I am going with you&rdquo;. We started talking about it at<lb/>
9 o'clock and discussed it until at least 2 o'clock in the morning, cover-<lb/>
ing all phases and angles of the problem.</item>
<item>Q. Did Kissinger make up his mind to volunteer before you talked with him.</item>
<item>A. Positively not. He knew nothing about it.</item>
<item>Q. Did Kissinger ever mention to you that he had volunteered and that he had<lb/>
already been bitten by a mosquito.</item>
<item>A. No. The two preceding questions answer that.</item>
<item>Q. What was the attitude of the men around the camp and the doctors toward<lb/>
the mosquito theory at that time.</item>
<item>A. That is a question I cannot answer except in a general way. The only<lb/>
doctor I discussed it with was Dr. Ames. He did not give an opinion. He<lb/>
approached me, knowing that I intended to enter the University of Virginia<lb/>
in September of the coming year to study medicine. He called me &ldquo;Johnny&rdquo;<lb/>
as I knew him well. He said: &ldquo;This is a golden opportunity for you to add<lb/>
to your slender educational fund.&rdquo;</item>
<item>Q. He did not warn you about the danger.</item>
<item>A. No.</item>
<item>Q. If Dr. Ames did not warn you of the danger, presumably he did not think<lb/>
much of the idea himself.</item>
<item>A. It was not part of Dr. Ames' mission to warn us. His mission was to quietly<lb/>
let it be known that Major Reed was seeking volunteers.</item>
<item>Q. You went to bed for a few hours sleep. Was this all decided upon by you<lb/>
and Kissinger in one evening.</item>
<item>A. Yes.</item>
<item>Q. What time did you see Dr. Reed next morning.</item>
<item>A. It was between 8 and 9 o'clock because I had to be in General Lee's office<lb/>
by 9 o'clock and it had to be before that when we went to call on Major<lb/>
Reed</item>
<item>Q. Where did you find Major Reed.</item>
<item>A. He was in his room in the officers' quarters.</item>
<item>Q. Is it your distinct recollection that you and Kissinger went together.</item>
<item>A. Positively. There is no mistake about that.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f03532002"/>
<item>-- 2 --</item>
<item>Q. Do you recollect what you told Major Reed.</item>
<item>A. I do but I cannot tell you my exact words. In substance, the following<lb/>
happened: We knocked at his door and he received us. He seemed surprised<lb/>
as he had no idea why we were there and we knew him but slightly up to<lb/>
that time. Then we informed him, or rather I informed him what Dr. Ames<lb/>
had told me. I said: Dr. Ames has told me that you are looking for<lb/>
volunteers and we are here to offer ourselves". Those may not be the<lb/>
exact words I used, since I was somewhat excited, but according to my<lb/>
memory they are substantially correct.</item>
<item>Q. Did Kissinger do any talking.</item>
<item>A. Kissinger was the first one to say that &ldquo;we are doing this without any<lb/>
thought of compensation or bonus&rdquo;. I did not repeat this as it was under-<lb/>
stood between us and by Major Reed. We were all standing, Kissinger at<lb/>
&ldquo;attention&rdquo; because he was a soldier. I was standing &ldquo;at ease&rdquo; because<lb/>
I was a civilian. Major Reed was standing up during the entire conver-<lb/>
sation and when Kissinger and I told him we were volunteering for the<lb/>
tests he was taken aback, not so much by our offer, which was surprising<lb/>
to him, the biggest surprise of all being that we wanted to take the<lb/>
experiments without reward or compensation.</item>
<item>Q. What did Major Reed do or say.</item>
<item>A. He did not do or say very much. He thanked us and expressed appreciation<lb/>
for what we were doing but I do not remember his exact words. Recovering<lb/>
from his surprise, he said: &ldquo;Of course you know, gentlemen, that this is<lb/>
a serious matter; that you must first undergo a strict physical examination<lb/>
to find out whether you have any organic or other trouble before I accept<lb/>
you as volunteers as I am not looking for any fatalities in these experi-<lb/>
ments.&rdquo; After that, his next remarks were: &ldquo;Now, should you be taken down<lb/>
with yellow fever, I want you to know that if there is any doctor or nurse<lb/>
on the Island of Cuba that you care to have to attend you, all you have to<lb/>
do is name them and I will have General Wood see that they are ordered<lb/>
here.&rdquo; That is about he said, adding that we would have our physical<lb/>
examination in due time.</item>
<item>Q. Did Major Reed at any time rise and salute you and say: &ldquo;Gentlemen, I<lb/>
salute you&rdquo;.</item>
<item>A. No, he did not. He was standing all the time. The conversation lasted<lb/>
about fifteen minutes.</item>
<item>Q. Where did that legend come from.</item>
<item>A. The first I knew of it was when I read it in Dr. Howard A. Kelly's book<lb/>
&ldquo;Walter Reed &amp; Yellow Fever&rdquo;, first published in 1906.</item>
<item>Q. Do you know where Dr. Kelly got the legend.</item>
<item>A. No, but I discovered later from General Kean, after I informed him of its<lb/>
inaccuracy, that Major Reed had fathered the legend, adding that &ldquo;If Major<lb/>
Reed did not salute you, as alleged, he should have done so.&rdquo; but whether<lb/>
the salute was an afterthought, later reported to Dr. Kelly by Major Reed,<lb/>
I do not know.</item>
<item>Q. When did you hear from Reed or what happened thereafter.</item>
<item>A. About the 1st of November, I think it was, Major Reed told me: You are<lb/>
through at Headquarters. From now on you are with me until after you are<lb/>
through with the experiments"</item>
<item>Q. What did you do then.</item>
<item>A. I started in to do clerical work for Major Reed at Columbia Barracks. It<lb/>
was pretty much pretense on his part since my real work with him was to<lb/>
undergo the tests. Aside from a few personal letters a day and a few<lb/>
official ones, all dealing with the experiments, I was not busy over an<lb/>
average of a few hours a day. I had a &ldquo;Hammond&rdquo; typewriter upon which to<lb/>
type his letters and other notes.</item>
<item>Q. What was the reaction of your friends when they heard that you and Kissinger<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03532003"/>
-- 3 --<lb/>
had volunteered.</item>
<item>A. I cannot tell you. All I knew was that volunteers presented themselves<lb/>
right and left. You have their names. First among them were Dr. Cook,<lb/>
Jernegan and Folk, who volunteered within a week or ten days after Kiss-<lb/>
inger and I did. (Ask Kissinger about this reaction).</item>
<item>Q. Did you have any reaction when you were notified to report at Camp Lazear.</item>
<item>A. Not that I can recall.</item>
<item>Q. How were you taken to Camp Lazear.</item>
<item>A. We went in a &ldquo;Doherty Wagon&rdquo; (So known in the Army in the days of mule-<lb/>
drawn transportation)</item>
<item>Q. When did you arrive at the Camp.</item>
<item>A. On November 20th.</item>
<item>Q. When did you arrive at the Camp.</item>
<item>A. On November 20th.</item>
<item>Q. What did you do between November 20th and 26th or before you were bitten.</item>
<item>A. Clerical work for Major Reed, principally typing letters and Notes about<lb/>
the yellow fever experiments, written in long hand. I occupied the office<lb/>
tent alone. I had an Army Field Desk in there and a Hammond typewriter.<lb/>
Major Reed used the field desk when he came to the Camp.</item>
<item>Q. Were the tents numbered.</item>
<item>A. To my knowledge they were not numbered nor were they understood as being<lb/>
numbered.</item>
<item>Q. You were not the roommate of Kissinger in Tent No. 2?</item>
<item>A. No.</item>
<item>Q. Major Reed did not live in the Camp?</item>
<item>A. No, he stayed at the officers' quarters, within the Post Hospital grounds,<lb/>
at Columbia Barracks.</item>
<item>Q. Where are Reed's letters to General Sternberg.</item>
<item>A. Those of a personal nature should be in the possession of the General's<lb/>
family but those of a purely official nature should be in the files of<lb/>
The Surgeon General of the Army, in Washington.</item>
<item>Q. How long ahead of time did you know you were going to be bitten.</item>
<item>A. About ten minutes ahead of time. The mosquitoes were brought out by<lb/>
Doctor Reed from the Laboratory of the Post Hospital, one end of which<lb/>
had been assigned to his use.</item>
<item>Q. Where were you bitten.</item>
<item>A. Outside my tent, on the forearm.</item>
<item>Q. Who put them on you.</item>
<item>A. Major Reed himself put them on my forearm, if I am not mistaken.</item>
<item>Q. What were your reactions.</item>
<item>A. I do not think I had any reactions. If I did, they made no lasting<lb/>
impression on me.</item>
<item>Q. How long ahead of time did you know you were going into the infected<lb/>
mosquito building.</item>
<item>A. I think I knew it a day ahead, around December 20th.</item>
<item>Q. How long did it take to complete that building.</item>
<item>A. It was built after the &ldquo;Infected Bedding &amp; Clothing Building&rdquo;. I was<lb/>
getting impatient at the long wait. Dr. Reed tried to pacify me while<lb/>
the &ldquo;Mosquito Building&rdquo; was being put up. He gave me the excuse that<lb/>
there was not sufficient mosquitoes to put in there. I think it was<lb/>
ready approximately two weeks before I entered it.</item>
<item>Q. What time were you bitten.</item>
<item>A. Around the noon hour. I do not think anyone took official time there.</item>
<item>Q. Did only one set of men sleep on the other side of the partition in the<lb/>
&ldquo;mosquito room&rdquo;.</item>
<item>A. Only one set of men slept there prior to my entry or first visit. I was<lb/>
the first to enter the &ldquo;mosquito room&rdquo; of the &ldquo;Mosquito Building&rdquo;.</item>
<item>Q. Did the men on the other side of the partition only sleep there at night.</item>
<item>A. Yes. During the day, they had the run of the Camp.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f03532004"/>
<item>-- 4 --</item>
<item>Q. Why did Jernegan make the bet. Was he so sure you were going to get<lb/>
yellow fever.</item>
<item>A. I think it was a gambler's impulse on Jernegan's part. He made the offer<lb/>
and I took him up.</item>
<item>Q. The official record says you were dizzy at 6 o'clock Christmas morning,<lb/>
but you tell me that you ate a hearty breakfast?</item>
<item>A. I regret the necessity of contradicting the official record. I did eat a<lb/>
hearty breakfast, my temperature being normal or slightly subnormal at<lb/>
6 o'clock Christmas morning.</item>
<item>Q. You did not have any fever on the 23rd or 24th as the official chart<lb/>
shows.?</item>
<item>A. I am positive I did not. I took my own pulse and temperature regularly<lb/>
from December 21st to December 25th and had no fever until about 10<lb/>
o'clock Christmas morning.</item>
<item>Q. You were not put to bed about eleven as the record shows?</item>
<item>A. No. I had Christmas dinner, turkey with cranberry sauce, &ldquo;Plum Duff&rdquo;<lb/>
(plum pudding), eating very sparingly.</item>
<item>Q. Had anyone seen you that morning?</item>
<item>A. No. Major Reed regularly got out to Camp shortly after the noon hour, if he<lb/>
had not been out in the morning, but it being Christmas Day the officers<lb/>
at the Post Hospital had their own Christmas Dinner and it was 3 o'clock<lb/>
when he reached there.</item>
<item>Q. What were your immediate thoughts when you knew you had yellow fever.</item>
<item>A. The same gambling instinct or impulse that caused Jernegan to make the<lb/>
bet impelled me to accept it and for the time being I was more concerned<lb/>
with winning the bet than I was about the fever. I wanted to win the<lb/>
$5.00 as a matter of principle. I am afraid I cannot describe my<lb/>
thoughts. I knew for one thing that eating heart<add><unclear>il</unclear></add>y with fever, especial-<lb/>
ly yellow fever, would lessen my chances of pulling through. I ate
very<lb/>
sparingly, bluffing it through without attracting attention.</item>
<item>Q. Christmas afternoon, you were taken where?</item>
<item>A. Into the special tent hospital that was set up to take care of the ex-<lb/>
perimental cases. It was within the Post Hospital enclosure but a<lb/>
respectable distance from the wards and barracks which were frame build-<lb/>
ings. It was known as the Yellow Fever Tent Hospital.</item>
<item>Q. Who visited you there.</item>
<item>A. Major Reed was my constant visitor. Gorgas was a daily visitor, Finlay<lb/>
only once to my knowledge, and a number of others, including Doctors<lb/>
Guiteras and Albertini, all members of the Yellow Fever Board of the City<lb/>
of Havana, not to be confounded with the Yellow Fever Commission or Board</item>
<item>Q. Do you remember any of the conversations these doctors had about you.</item>
<item>A. I do remember that they referred to my case as &ldquo;a very pretty case&rdquo;.<lb/>
Reed, on the secon day, December 26th, when I still had a high temper-<lb/>
ature, sat down by my bedside and said: &ldquo;Have you any pains?&rdquo; I replied:<lb/>
&ldquo;Major, I have a lot of pains&rdquo;. He said: &ldquo;Please tell me where they are.<lb/>
Can you localize them?&rdquo; I replied: &ldquo;I am sorry but I cannot localize<lb/>
them as my entire body is a mass of pain. I cannot tell you where. &ldquo;Are<lb/>
you suffering?&rdquo; he asked and I replied that I was. &ldquo;If yelling out loud<lb/>
would relieve, then go ahead and do it,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;Major, when I went in<lb/>
for these experiments I made up my mind to take it without crying about<lb/>
it,&rdquo; I said. He said: &ldquo;All right&rdquo;.</item>
<item>Q. Do you remember any other conversations.</item>
<item>A. No. Most of their conversations were in an undertone and in medical<lb/>
terms.</item>
<item>Q. Who had charge of you.</item>
<item>A. Dr. Roger Post Ames was my attending physician.</item>
<pb n="5" id="f03532005"/>
<item>-- 5 --</item>
<item>Q. What were your thoughts? Did you think you were going to die?</item>
<item>A. For the first 48 hours I did not much care whether school kept or not. After<lb/>
that I figured I would get well.</item>
<item>Q. What were your symptoms besides pains and fever.</item>
<item>A. None.</item>
<item>Q. How long were you sick.</item>
<item>A. I was out of bed in ten days. When declared convalescent, I was still very<lb/>
weak as I had no nourishment for a period of seven days running.</item>
<item>Q. You took the blood test about two weeks after your convalescence?</item>
<item>A. About January 15th, 1901.</item>
<item>Q. Do you remember any instance of local reaction that you came across before<lb/>
you left Havana?</item>
<item>A. No.</item>
<item>Q. Why did you leave Havana in February, 1901?</item>
<item>A. I returned to the U. S. and had a position assured me in Luerssen's Drug<lb/>
Store, Salem, N. J. which, due to its nature, suited me until I should matri-<lb/>
culate as a medical student in September of the same year.</item>
<item>Q. Did you have any other conversations with Reed or Carroll about your own or<lb/>
other experiments?</item>
<item>A. None in particular that I can recall.</item>
<item>Q. Did you only meet Finlay once?</item>
<item>A. To my knowledge only once and I do not remember having any conversations with<lb/>
him. Dr. Finlay could have seen me on December 26th without my being aware of<lb/>
it. On that date, I was not a close observer.</item>
<item>Q. Do you remember any errors in Dr. Kelly's book except those we have discussed.</item>
<item>A. I do not recall any.</item>
<item>Q. You said there were errors in the Furnas article &ldquo;Death in a Mirror&rdquo;?</item>
<item>A. Yes, but not serious ones. Where he identifies Dr. Ames as a Virginia grad-<lb/>
uate, he is in error. Dr. Ames was a graduate of Tulane, I am reasonably sure.<lb/>
As I explained to Mr. Furnas, the man who suggested Virginia to me first was<lb/>
Major Alexander N. Stark, Post Surgeon, under whom I worked in the operating<lb/>
room until my term of enlistment expired on July 2, 1900. After I volunteered<lb/>
for the experiments, I discovered that Major Reed was a Virginia graduate and<lb/>
that my very good friend and benefactor, Major Jefferson R. Kean, Chief Surg-<lb/>
eon of the Department, was also a Virginia graduate. At the time I volunteered<lb/>
all three knew that I was to enter Virginia in September of the coming year.</item>
</list></p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head><hi>QUESTIONS ABOUT FURNAS' ARTICLE</hi></head>
<item>Q. The statement about the poker is true?</item>
<item>A. Yes. There were other little games too where a few dollars could be won or<lb/>
lost. Prisoners, as we were, indulgence in these pastimes helped shorten the<lb/>
day for us.</item>
<item>Q. The Conversation between you and Reed?</item>
<item>A. Essentially correct. The first time I ever heard the expression &ldquo;fool-proof&rdquo;<lb/>
was when Major Reed used it when he informed me that he was &ldquo;saving&rdquo; me for<lb/>
his &ldquo;mosquito building&rdquo; test. His elation on Christmas Day, when he found me<lb/>
with yellow fever, is much better told by Joe Furnas than I could ever hope<lb/>
to tell it.</item>
<item>Q. What about the muslin-lined walls in the mosquito room?</item>
<item>A. That is more or less correct. There were screened windows on which very fine<lb/>
copper bronze wire screening was used. The room was built from tongue and<lb/>
grooved lumber. After that, the ceiling and walls were &ldquo;papered&rdquo; with unbleach-<lb/>
ed muslin, making them insect proof.</item>
<item>Q. Did you ever have Malaria?</item>
<pb n="6" id="f03532006"/>
<item>-- 6 --</item>
<item>A. Yes, I had it for the first time at Camp Young, near Guanajay, Province of<lb/>
Pinar del Rio.</item>
<item>Q. What were your duties after you enlisted in the Army and immediately before<lb/>
your enlistment expired?</item>
<item>A. I enlisted as a Private at the Hospital School of Instruction, Washington<lb/>
Barracks, D. C., was promoted to Acting Hospital Steward (Sergeant) about a<lb/>
year later. From date of my promotion my duties were varied. At times I<lb/>
had charge of the pharmacy, accompany the surgeon in his daily visits to the<lb/>
wards, prepare &ldquo;Sick &amp; Wounded&rdquo; reports and do other clerical work. My last<lb/>
six or seven months of Army service were as assistant to Major Stark, in the<lb/>
operating room. While in Cuba, I served, respectively, at Camp Young, Guan-<lb/>
ajay Barracks and Columbia Barracks.</item>
<item>Q. How long were you in service in Cuba?</item>
<item>A. As a soldier, from January, 1899, until July 2, 1900. As a civilian or field<lb/>
clerk, from July 2, 1900, to February, 1901.</item>
<item>Q. Why did not Major Reed try the experiments on himself?</item>
<item>A. I think he was too old, which was of itself sufficient reason. He was then<lb/>
in his 50th year.</item>
<item>Q. The official record says Carroll's yellow fever was experimental. What was<lb/>
the opinion in and around the Post Hospital as to this?</item>
<item>A. That Doctor Carroll's case was accidental - not experimental. His friend and<lb/>
preceptor, Major Reed, was willing to pass his yellow fever as experimental<lb/>
and allowed it to so appear in the record. When I knew Dr. Carroll he was<lb/>
far from robust and he was in his 46th year. Although Major Reed was three<lb/>
years his senior, his chances of surviving an attack of yellow fever were<lb/>
much greater than Carroll's. The latter, I inferred at the time, was organically<lb/>
unsound. One of my doctor friends, whose name I do not care to disclose, con-<lb/>
firmed to me what was general opinion among the Post Hospital personnel.</item>
<item>see<lb/>
below</item>
<item>Q. Agramonte says that at first Lazear kept the mosquitoes not at Camp Columbia<lb/>
but in Agramonte's laboratory at Military Hospital No. 1. Is this correct?</item>
<item>A. I cannot give you a positive answer. According to my recollection, they were<lb/>
kept in the old operating room (then used as a laboratory) under the personal<lb/>
supervision of Hospital Steward Neal who accompanied Major Reed and Dr.<lb/>
Carroll to Cuba from the Army Medical School in Washington.</item>
<item>Q. Is the conversation you are supposed to have had with Kissinger, as given by<lb/>
Lampson on page 472 of his book, essentially correct.?</item>
<item>A. It is incorrect in every respect; entirely imaginary. Lampson is probably not<lb/>
responsible. I think he got his impression from the theatre version of the<lb/>
play &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;.</item>
<item>Q. On page 474?</item>
<item>A. You are entirely familiar with Major Reed's remarks when, on Christmas Day,<lb/>
1900, he found me with yellow fever, hence I will not here repeat them.</item>
</list></p>
<p><hi>NOTES FOR DOCTOR HENCH</hi></p>
<p>The FOURTH question, counting either from the top or bottom of this page,<lb/>
is mine. You are entirely free to eliminate it. It may be policy to do so.<lb/>
In this revised copy of your questionnaire, I have corrected a number of errors<lb/>
made by Mrs. Phillips, excusable always even on the part of competent steno-<lb/>
graphers when typing from shorthand notes. Instance: She used FLAT DESK where<lb/>
I said &ldquo;Field Desk&rdquo;, the latter being a portable or folding desk, used at that<lb/>
time by officers in the field.</p>
<p>I CERTIFY THAT THE FOREGOING ANSWERS ARE CORRECT, TO THE BEST OF<lb/>
MY KNOWLEDGE AND BELIEF:</p>
<closer>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
