<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03539001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, April 29, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03539001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-04-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Pew, J. Howard</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Louis</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D. C.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-04-29">April 29, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03539001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, April 29, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests copies of Cuban newspaper articles, about the work of the Yellow Fever Commission, and for maps of the Rojas farm and the site of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-04-29">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, April 29, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03539001"/>
<opener>
Yellow fever.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-04-29">April 29, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The two weeks since my return have been rather hectic. I found my desk cluttered<lb/>
with work waiting for me, we had a large medical meeting here and I had a house guest<lb/>
visiting us, and on top of that, our nine-year old boy developed acute appendicitis and<lb/>
was operated upon. But all is well that ends well, and he is getting along fine, now<lb/>
being back home.</p>
<p>I did appreciate your long and thorough revision of my questionnaire, but after<lb/>
all, it was Mrs. Phillips' job to do that, and I am sorry you went to so much trouble.<lb/>
If the occasion should arise again, please have it done in her office, and have her send<lb/>
me the bill.</p>
<p>I am sending you a number of snapshots which you wanted and if you want any more<lb/>
of them, I shall be delighted to send them to you. I am very much chagrined at the way<lb/>
one roll turned out. At the end of each film roll there is a sticker, to stick the roll<lb/>
shut. Apparently, one of these stickers tore off and got caught in the back of the<lb/>
camera, unbeknown to me. It stuck out just far enough to ruin each exposure on one film<lb/>
and it happened to be the film I was using in Marianao. Incidentally, your picture at<lb/>
General Lee's headquarters is therefore ruined, but I am going to make a separate list<lb/>
and ask you to have the young photographer take four or five more photographs more for<lb/>
me, including that one.</p>
<p>And now for some special items:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) I am returning your check, as I think there will be some expenses which you<lb/>
and Mr. Pogolotti will be under in my behalf, and I think it best, if you don't mind, for<lb/>
you to have a little money available.</item>
<item>(2) At your leisure, would you some time write me a couple of paragraphs on the<lb/>
distinction between Camp Columbia and Columbia Barracks. I understand the site was the<lb/>
same place but the one was erected by the Americans and the other by the Cubans.</item>
<item>(3) I don't know whether to ask you or Miss Cabrera to do the following but at<lb/>
least I will mention it to you, as you might be very interested anyhow. I am anxious to<lb/>
see what the Cuban papers said on certain occasions. For example, according to Kelly's<lb/>
book and otherwise, on or about November 21, 1900, one of the Cuban papers poured forth<lb/>
considerable criticism on Reed for proposing human experiments. On December 23, 1900,<lb/>
a banquet was given to Finlay and to Reed. I should certainly like to see what was said<lb/>
and the reaction of the people to the idea. On February 6, 1900, Major Reed gave his<lb/>
medical talk before the Pan-American Congress in Havana. You remember what Carroll is<lb/>
supposed to have said about that occasion. I have also seen mentioned comments by Carroll<lb/>
and Reed referring to the Havana Post of November 24 and 25, 1900, and January 31, 1901.<lb/>
I wonder if sometime you would have time to go to the Bibliotece de la Socieded Economica<lb/>
Dragones between Royal and San Nicolas, and perhaps look over the papers La Marina la<lb/>
Lucca for those dates. If you find anything interesting, sometimes a library will make<lb/>
a photostatic copy of certain items rather inexpensively. If not, you could dictate<lb/>
something to Mrs. Phillips at my expense.</item>
<item>(4) I have not yet got any old maps of Camp Columbia. I am going to write to<lb/>
Washington and also to Dr. Ramos before bothering you further about this.</item>
<item>(5) Please hold the pieces of the tree for me. I have written to Washington<lb/>
to find out whether I can bring them into our country, although I believe you were<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03539002"/>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
April 29, 1940<lb/>
going to give one piece to the wood carver in Havana, next to the restaurant, Paris<lb/>
Cafe, to see what he could do about it.</item>
<item>(6) Do you have any idea where I could get ahold of a tree expert in<lb/>
Havana who could certify as to the approximate age of the Framboyant tree at the<lb/>
Cuban Camp Lazear, and also the one by the shacks on the San Jose farm. If you could<lb/>
make some inquiries, perhaps to the Department of Agriculture in Cuba, I should<lb/>
appreciate knowing what his advice would cost. But perhaps when I get my report for<lb/>
Dr. Ramos, it would not be inappropriate for me to suggest that he have the ages of<lb/>
the trees identified by one of their government experts.</item>
<item>(7) I am writing Mr. Pew somewhat along the lines you suggested.</item>
<item>(8) I have not yet received the copies of the two maps of the Rojas farm<lb/>
from Mr. Pogolotti but this may take a little time. Please pay him the expense out<lb/>
of what I left with you.</item>
<item>(9) If the photographer has not yet taken a picture of the Lazear statue in<lb/>
Finlay Park, to be taken just about 3 P.M.--not earlier and not much later--you can<lb/>
hold this matter up until I send you in a few days, a list of the half dozen other<lb/>
pictures to take. I want him to take three or four more pictures at the San Jose<lb/>
farm and I will send you specific directions for them. I would also like to have<lb/>
him take a picture of you before General Lee's headquarters but you will hear later<lb/>
about this.</item>
</list></p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
