<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03544001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, April 30, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03544001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-04-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital #1, Havana, Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-04-30">April 30, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03544001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, April 30, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Rodriguez Leon for her photographs of Camp Lazear. He regrets the lack of recognition extended to her father for his yellow fever work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-04-30">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, April 30, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03544001"/>
<opener>
yellow fever<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-04-30">April 30, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Senora Estella Agramonte Rodreguez-Leon<lb/>
311 Calle 15 entre H et I<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora Rodreguez-Leon:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Permit me to send you a few photographs which I took in Havana, and allow<lb/>
me to thank you again for your great kindness to Mrs. Hench and to me.</p>
<p>I found a great amount of work waiting for me on my return and almost at<lb/>
once we had a medical convention here which necessitated my having a house guest.<lb/>
On top of that, our nine-year old boy developed acute appendicitis and had to be<lb/>
operated on, but is now recovering nicely.</p>
<p>I am having our photographic department try to copy the rather faded photo-<lb/>
graphs of Camp Lazear. I sincerely hope that we can get some good ones out of them,<lb/>
and I most assuredly appreciate your kindness in lending them to me. I will mail<lb/>
them shortly, by registered post.</p>
<p>I sincerely hope that you got the original carbon copy of the letter your<lb/>
father wrote to Dr. Hemmeter. I sent you also another copy that you might use for<lb/>
some other annoying inquiring reporter like myself. I have been able to find one of<lb/>
the interesting articles referred to in your father's letter to Dr. Hemmeter but not<lb/>
the other, and if I cannot borrow them from some library here, I would most assuredly<lb/>
be grateful if you would lend them to me, sending them by registered mail, but please<lb/>
do not bother about this as yet. I will try in another American library first. The<lb/>
one I cannot seem to get is the George Washington University publication, Medical<lb/>
Science Series, the article by H. H. Donnally.</p>
<p>I only wish indeed that I had been able to meet you earlier and had more time<lb/>
to go over your extremely interesting and valuable data. I should like, without bother-<lb/>
ing you further, to write up the story as best I can, and will send you a copy of it after<lb/>
some weeks. I am going to try to give due credit to everyone. I do think your father<lb/>
was slighted by the officials in Washington when the work was first published. Fortun-<lb/>
ately, the Surgeon General's office made a correction and in later publications, your<lb/>
father receives much more credit, although perhaps not nearly as much as he deserved.<lb/>
You have no idea how desirous I am to be permitted to see some of the old photographs<lb/>
which your father took or may have had taken of his colleagues on the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission, and perhaps of Camp Lazear. I have been unable to find any photographs as<lb/>
yet of Military Hospital No. 1, where your father worked. I am trying to find a photo-<lb/>
graph in the Army Museum, and perhaps, if it is not too much trouble, you may, some time<lb/>
soon, be able to find the photographs. I realize what an imposition this is to ask you<lb/>
to open up old trunks and boxes, but I am sure that you know I am only doing this in<lb/>
behalf of the honored memory of those who did such a wonderful piece of work. I left<lb/>
a small sum of money with Mr. Moran to cover certain incidental expenses for little<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03544002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
projects which I have asked him to carry out for me, and perhaps you will not think<lb/>
me <unclear>presumptuous</unclear> in suggesting that it might be easier for you to hire some husky<lb/>
handy man or drayman, whom you could take to the house where the boxes are, and have<lb/>
him push them around and open them up under your supervision. If you should care to<lb/>
do this, and thus save yourself the physical labor of doing this annoying job yourself,<lb/>
I shall be only too delighted if you will permit me to pay the expenses of this man.<lb/>
I sincerely hope that you will not think me forward in offering this. I only do so<lb/>
to show you how anxious I am to have your further help and to show you, in any case,<lb/>
how grateful I am for what you have already done for me.</p>
<p>Please give your husband our very best wishes. We recall with much interest<lb/>
the stories of the exciting adventures which he had in the Hotel Nacionale. I can<lb/>
assure you that they were much more exciting than our adventures in the same hotel:</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
<unclear>psh</unclear>:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
