<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03540001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, April 29, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03540001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-04-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">[Hench?], Mary</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Louis</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D. C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-04-29">April 29, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03540001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, April 29, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench refers to his visit to Cuba and the presumed site of Camp Lazear on Rojas' family's farm. He comments on her recollections of Camp Lazear and the yellow fever work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-04-29">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, April 29, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03540001"/>
<opener>
<unclear><hi>Yellow fever</hi></unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-04-29">April 29, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Senora Maria Teresa Loma Viuda de Rojas<lb/>
Calle 17 #207<lb/>
Vedado, Habana<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora Rojas:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I want to thank you again for the great kindness which you and your family<lb/>
showed to me during my recent Habana visit. My wife and I were both very touched<lb/>
and pleased at the lovely gift of flowers which you sent to our plane. It especially<lb/>
thrilled Mrs. Hench as she had never been so overwhelmed by having as many as eight<lb/>
gardenias at one time before. Our return flight was lovely, but on arrival home, I<lb/>
found much work waiting for me and almost immediately a large medical convention also<lb/>
opened in our town and I had house guests. In the middle of that, our nine-year old<lb/>
boy developed acute appendicitis and was operated on, but is getting along nicely.</p>
<p>I am enclosing a number of photographs which I thought you would like to have,<lb/>
and if you would like any more copies, please do not hesitate to ask for as many as you<lb/>
wish. I shall be delighted to give them to you. I had a professional photographer take<lb/>
two or three pictures of the old Rojas farm near the quarry but I want him to take three<lb/>
or four more and will arrange this through Mr. Moran. No need not bother you in the<lb/>
slightest about this. As</p>
<p>As I believe you know, I gave Mr. Pogolotti the two maps of the Rojas farm<lb/>
and he is having copies made for me. If you do not receive these within a couple of<lb/>
weeks I wish you would either write to me or call Mr. Pogolotti or Mr. Moran. I must<lb/>
see to it that these are returned to you safely, and I am sure they will be.</p>
<p>I have not yet had time to have typed your statements and those of your niece<lb/>
regarding the camp. I will have them typed and send you copies that you may return them<lb/>
and verify them. At that time, I should be very grateful if you would add a brief para-<lb/>
graph on the history of your farm, or anything pertaining to it and to the incident of<lb/>
the yellow fever experiments that you may have remembered since I saw you. I have asked<lb/>
Mr. Moran to see if he can find the name of some tree expert who might view and certify <unclear>as</unclear> to<lb/>
the approximate ages of the Framboyant tree by the shacks on the San Jose farm, and also<lb/>
identify the other three or four trees by these same shacks. I believe I gave Miss Cabrera<lb/>
one of the leaves of the other tree. Perhaps she knows some tree expert who could do<lb/>
this for me. I should be glad to pay him a small fee and will send him photographs of<lb/>
the trees that I wish identified as to age and type.</p>
<p>I mentioned also to Miss Cabrera my desire to see some Habana newspapers which<lb/>
had articles on the work at Camp Lazear, but I never did get into the library, as it was<lb/>
closed when I went there. I think you and your family may be interested in one of these<lb/>
newspapers (I don't know the name) of November 21, 1900. In that paper was launched a<lb/>
storm of criticism against Reed's idea of human experiments at Camp Lazear. In as much as<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03540002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
Camp Lazear was on your property, doubtlessly you will be interested to read of that<lb/>
historical occasion. I have asked Mr. Moran to look over the newspapers in the<lb/>
Bibliotece de la Socieded Economica Dragones, but thought your daughter and Miss Cabrera<lb/>
might like to see that paper sometime also.</p>
<p>I am preparing a report to give to the President of Washington and Jefferson<lb/>
College, and I have been also asked by Dr. Ramos, Secretary of Defense of Cuba, to give<lb/>
him a full report, establishing the claims for your San Jose farm as the true site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear. I am also sending a copy to the United States Army Museum in Washington,<lb/>
D. C. and will try to get some copies of the old photographs in Camp Lazear, takin in<lb/>
1900--the ones I showed to you. I am sure you would like to have these and I think you<lb/>
and your family should have these in your possession.</p>
<p>I shall take the liberty of writing you further from time to time as matters<lb/>
progress. I may be required to call on you for further information and help in order to<lb/>
establish proof that Camp Lazear was really on your property, and I am sure that your<lb/>
family ought to have this recognition. I left a little sum of money with Mr. Moran<lb/>
and you may find it more convenient to dictate some data to send to me from time to<lb/>
time than to write it out. If so, I shall be glad to pay the expenses of a stenographer.<lb/>
Mrs. R. Hart Phillips, Manzana de Gomez 553, did some secretarial work for me and should<lb/>
you care to use her services, please do so and have her send me the bill.</p>
<p>I cannot thank you enough for all the courtesies which you and your family<lb/>
showed me. It was delightful to meet you, and I hope we may meet again soon, perhaps<lb/>
sometime in the United States; if not, again in Cuba.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
<unclear>&middot;</unclear> I have also seen mentioned comments by Carroll and Reed referring to the<lb/>
Havana Post of November 24 and 25, 1900, and January 31, 1901.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
