<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03554001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, June 3, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03554001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-06-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Pew, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-06-03">June 3, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03554001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, June 3, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses the logistics of inviting Moran and Kissinger to the Lazear Ceremony at Washington and Jefferson College.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-06-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, June 3, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03554001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-06-03">June 3, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Hutch:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I thoroughly enjoyed your last letter and heartily agree with you that it<lb/>
might be a much better thing to invite both Moran and Kissinger. I forgot to tell<lb/>
you that Moran is certainly coming, but the circumstance of how his finances will be<lb/>
paid has not been decided. I still stand ready to pay his expenses. The night that<lb/>
I saw him first and mentioned your invitation, I had mislaid your letter to him, and<lb/>
before I got through discussing the matter he seemed so pleased and anxious to come<lb/>
that he volunteered the information that if his expenses could not be paid otherwise,<lb/>
he would pay them himself. (I do not think we should permit this but as I say, I<lb/>
am still ready to pay his expenses). Again before I could discuss this, he said that<lb/>
he thought Mr. Pew, of the Penn Petroleum Co. who is the head of the Sunoco Oil Co.,<lb/>
would be very interested to hear of the invitation and would undoubtedly not only<lb/>
give permission for him to go (and this permission will be necessary) but would also<lb/>
probably pay his expenses. When I heard this I kept mum about my own offer, not to<lb/>
save my money, but with the thought that I could do something else with the same money<lb/>
for the Lazear Memorial, such as getting together the various photographs and other<lb/>
things, framed appropriately, for perhaps some proper place in the building. As soon<lb/>
as I come back from my New York and Easton trip, I will therefore write to you, suggesting<lb/>
a letter which you, as President, should send to Mr. Pew, calling attention to this<lb/>
thing, and requesting that Mr. Moran be permitted to attend and perhaps suggesting or<lb/>
at least indicating that the Sunoco Oil Company might be sufficiently proud of Mr.<lb/>
Moran to pay his expenses. I have a tentative letter already written, which Moran and<lb/>
I got together, and I will send it to you with certain revisions shortly.</p>
<p>I agree with you also that the honorary Master's Degree might not be justified.<lb/>
It might be very appropriate for Moran, because after all, he took two years of medicine<lb/>
and is quite an adequate and smart man. He has an Irish brogue and a little stoop to<lb/>
his shoulders which makes him look rather humble and not as prepossessing as one might<lb/>
wish, but he gets things done, was a Captain in the last war, and is with all a very<lb/>
genial man and would make an appropriate exhibit. Kissinger, of course, if just a<lb/>
humble farmer with no education, very poor grammar and spelling, but nevertheless offered<lb/>
his life for these experiments, and of course deserves the tribute of the world. It would<lb/>
be very nice to have them both there, and perhaps an appropriate scroll, or some small<lb/>
medal or something like that would be better than any degree.</p>
<p>I should be anxious to get Mrs. Lazear's address, and if you can't find it, I<lb/>
hope to find it when I visit General Kean in Washington, in a couple of weeks. He was<lb/>
in Havana during the experiments and was much connected with them.</p>
<p>I cannot tell you how much I wish you could be with us at Lafayette. I know<lb/>
darned well that you had more to do with this honor than anybody else in the world, and<lb/>
I cannot tell you how grateful I am for your confidence. We shall be thinking of you<lb/>
constantly on that day.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03554002"/>
<p>Dr. Ralph C. Hutchison</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>June 3, 1940</p>
<p>Mary and I were pleased to receive your Commencement invitation, and<lb/>
amused to see what a &ldquo;hot-shot&rdquo; you had for your speaker. Your selection is certainly<lb/>
appropriate, and you surely have the ability to pick <unclear>'em:</unclear></p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
