<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03566005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, July 30, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03566005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-07-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-07-30">July 30, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03566005</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, July 30, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This letter contains Truby's recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission work and excerpts of his own [then incomplete] history of the Yellow Fever Commission - concerning Jesse W. Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-07-30">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, July 30, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03566005"/>
<p>145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<date value="1940-07-30">July 30, 1940</date>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
My dear Dr. Hench:</p>
<p>Upon my return to San Francisco I found your letter of the<lb/>
24th awaiting me, so I immediately went to work and had a few extracts<lb/>
of my article pertaining to Dr. Lazear typed for your information. I<lb/>
am sending a copy to General Kean and if he agrees that there is no<lb/>
objection to releasing this information, I shall be glad to authorize<lb/>
you to quote it in your address at the dedication of the Lazear<lb/>
Memorial.</p>
<p>I shall be interested to get your reaction to the extracts<lb/>
from my article. Of course, the story is a chronological review of<lb/>
events as they happened and extracts about Lazear may seem to be dis-<lb/>
connected. However, you can readily select the parts that fit in<lb/>
your story. When your paper is ready to review, I shall be very glad<lb/>
indeed to go over it and make comments as you suggested in your first<lb/>
letter.</p>
<p>I was interested to know about Dr. Finlay's son and the book<lb/>
he is writing. Poor old Finlay did not have a scientific mind but was<lb/>
a very successful general practitioner. I knew him very well.</p>
<p>Very sincerely yours,<lb/>
ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
Brigadier General, Med. Dept., USA<lb/>
Retired</p>
<p>2. Incls.</p>
<p>General Kean was our Chief Surgeon<lb/>
of the department in which Camp Columbia<lb/>
was located. He and Leonard Wood, did<lb/>
more to make Reed's work successful than any<lb/>
other persons <del><unclear>on</unclear></del> Both were close friends of Reed's.<lb/>
Kean is modest, but I think he distructs his<lb/>
memory in recent years. He is a master of English<lb/>
and has written much, and I hope he has recorded<lb/>
some of his observations in Cuba-</p>
<p>(Over)</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03566006"/>
<p>Ac<lb/>
T</p>
<p>I am inclosing a <add>photostat copy of a</add> letter from Walter Reed<lb/>
which describes his first experimental case-<lb/>
(Kissinger) I have presented the original<lb/>
to the Surgeon General's Library in Washington.<lb/>
I had left him a few days erlier and he<lb/>
knew how much I was interested in his work<lb/>
His discription of Kissinger's case is the first<lb/>
written account of the first experimental case of<lb/>
<unclear>Yellow Fever</unclear>. You will note that the description<lb/>
is almost identical with that of the published<lb/>
report of the case several weeks later.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03566007"/>
<p>1</p>
<p>Extracts from the manuscript of an article (not yet published) by<lb/>
Brigadier General Albert E. Truby, U. S. Army, Retired, on his experiences<lb/>
and observations in Cuba (1898-1902) with especial reference to Yellow Fever<lb/>
and the work of Walter Reed and the members of his board in the study of the<lb/>
etiology of that disease. At that time Truby was a 1st Lieutenant in the<lb/>
Medical Corps, U. S. Army. He was in command of the hospital at Columbia<lb/>
Barracks at the time of Dr. Lazear's death and during much of the time the<lb/>
Reed Board was conducting experiments at that station. <del>All cases with fever<lb/>
were admitted there, and, when a diagnosis was made, transfer to proper ward<lb/>
was accomplished. We had a small laboratory, but no one thoroughly qualified<lb/>
to operate it. Kramer and I both worked there on doubtful or special cases.</del></p>
<p>The Headquarters Department of Pinar del Rio, in which Camp Columbia was<lb/>
located, was but a short distance from the camp hospital. General Fitzhue<lb/>
Lee was in command and Major J. R. Kean was our Chief Surgeon. Kean was active,<lb/>
energetic, and always willing and anxious to help. When I explained the need<lb/>
for a full time laboratory man he promptly took steps to get a competent officer<lb/>
for that work. There was a long delay as no specialist in that work was avail-<lb/>
able in Cuba, but in February, 1900, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear arrived from the States<lb/>
under War Department orders, and took charge of the laboratory. There was much<lb/>
work to be done. Lazear did it promptly and efficiently. He also had much time<lb/>
for special research work, with especial reference to Yellow Fever, and he<lb/>
utilized it fully. Lazear soon became one of the most respected and efficient<lb/>
members of our staff. He was always courteous and agreeable and went about his<lb/>
work in our laboratory with enthusiasn. Every member of the staff was fond of<lb/>
Lazear and when Reed came, he found in Lazear a real friend and loyal supporter,<lb/>
also the ideal man for the board's work with mosquitoes. As will be seen later,<lb/>
Lazear, working entirely alone, produced the first experimental cases of Yellow<lb/>
Fever in human subjects (Carroll, &ldquo;X Y&rdquo;, and probably in himself). Besides<lb/>
being a member of the Reed Board, Lazear continued as our laboratory chief until<lb/>
his death.</p>
<p>* * * * * * * * * *</p>
<p>Lazear was placed by Reed in full charge of the mosquito work. He had<lb/>
had more experience in entomology than the other members and his selection for<lb/>
this duty was fortunate.</p>
<p>* * * * * * * * * *</p>
<p>On October 1, 1900, Major Reed returned from his trip to the United States.<lb/>
He was terribly depressed at Lazear's death, not only because of his attachment<lb/>
and high regard for Lazear, but also because this efficient assistant, having<lb/>
all but proved &ldquo;the theory&rdquo; was no longer present to help finish the work<lb/>
required to satisfy the medical world that the mosquito was the culprit. Age<lb/>
long scientific investigations had up until now been fruitless and even Dr.<lb/>
Finlay's extensive experiments with infected mosquitoes had failed completely.<lb/>
Lazear was the only member of the board who was experienced in entomology and<lb/>
who had given much time to the study of mosquitoes both in the United States<lb/>
- 1 -<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03566008"/>
2<lb/>
and in Italy. Reed realized at once how much he needed Lazear's help at that<lb/>
time.</p>
<p>We all congregated to greet Reed and he was most anxious to get first hand<lb/>
information about Lazear, and his mosquito work. I then turned over to him the<lb/>
note book and other papers found in Lazear's quarters. He lost no time in<lb/>
getting to his laboratory where Lazear's efficient assistant, Hospital Steward<lb/>
Neate, showed him a complete history of all of Lazear's infected mosquitoes<lb/>
and told him all he knew about Lazear's work in the laboratory. With this in-<lb/>
formation and the data contained in the note book, Reed began his work of find-<lb/>
ing out exactly what Lazear had done. It took some time to connect the data<lb/>
from the book with the laboratory records, but eventually he was satisfied and<lb/>
then he prepared the data which were published in Table III of the board's<lb/>
&ldquo;Preliminary Note&rdquo; on the Aetiology of Yellow Fever. Table III gives Lazear's<lb/>
results of &ldquo;Inoculation of non-immune individuals through the bite of a mosquito<lb/>
(Culex Fasciatus). Practically all of the data for this table came from the<lb/>
precious little note book which Lazear had so carefully kept in his own posses-<lb/>
sion. During his illness he left no message with us for Reed. From this I feel<lb/>
sure that he fully expected to recover. He had been in perfect health, was only<lb/>
34 years old, and from his extensive observation of Yellow Fever cases he no<lb/>
doubt concluded that the chances were all in his favor. He saw Carroll, who was<lb/>
46 and not a robust man, recovering, and he knew of the splendid record Dr. Ames<lb/>
had made in the treatment of cases in our hospital. I know that Ames felt that<lb/>
if Lazear had reported his illness promptly instead of working the first two days,<lb/>
the case might have been a mild one.</p>
<p>* * * * * * * * * *</p>
<p>(after studying the case of &ldquo;XY&rdquo; and deciding that it must have been due)<lb/>
to Lazear's <unclear>mosquitoes</unclear></p>
<p>Reed then took up the other two cases (Carroll and Lazear). In both of<lb/>
them he could not be sure of the source of the infection as they had been in<lb/>
infected areas almost daily, before and after they had been bitten by Lazear's<lb/>
laboratory mosquitoes. However, they strongly supported &ldquo;the theory&rdquo;. Both of<lb/>
them had been bitten by mosquitoes and had developed the disease, within the<lb/>
normal incubation period. Carroll had certainly been bitten by an infected<lb/>
mosquito and the same mosquito had bitten X.Y. who had promptly developed Yellow<lb/>
Fever. But how about Lazear? Had he also been bitten by the same infected<lb/>
mosquitoes? Reed thought that he had. He was not sure and he was much troubled<lb/>
as to what he should say about it in the &ldquo;Preliminary Note&rdquo;. I have a distinct<lb/>
recollection that there were some entries in Lazear's note book, which Reed<lb/>
thought were entered about mosquitoes which Lazear had applied to himself. Un-<lb/>
fortunately this important note book has mysteriously disappeared according to<lb/>
information to this effect given me by General Kean or General Ireland. Carroll,<lb/>
I think, had charge of this historical document after Reed's death. Reed was<lb/>
rather cautious in discussing this aspect of Lazear's case, but he did confide<lb/>
in Kean and me and probably discussed it with Carroll and Agramonte. He felt<lb/>
that when Lazear was taken sick he thought very seriously about the future of his<lb/>
family in case of his death. Would his life insurance become forfeited if it<lb/>
became known that he had deliberately infected himself with a fatal disease?<lb/>
Was this the reason for Lazear's incomplete entries in the note book about himself<lb/>
and was this why he told Gorgas and Carroll the story about his having been bitten<lb/>
- 2-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03566009"/>
3<lb/>
by a mosquito at Las Animas Hospital? Reed felt that it was. On the other<lb/>
hand he was just as confident that Lazear would not knowingly let any mosquito<lb/>
bite him at a Yellow Fever hospital. Lazear was a competent scientific in-<lb/>
vestigator, who having already produced two cases of Yellow Fever (Carroll and<lb/>
X.Y.) certainly would not let a mongrel mosquito bite him. He was after<lb/>
information of tremendous importance and the only way to get it was to be<lb/>
bitten by one of his own thoroughbred &ldquo;birds&rdquo; which had been hatched and in-<lb/>
fected under his own supervision, and which had a well known pedigree. There<lb/>
was no way to prove this viewpoint and so the &ldquo;Preliminary Note&rdquo; simply gave<lb/>
the story of the supposed infection by a mosquito at Las Animas Hospital.<lb/>
While it weakened the report to be unable to definitely fix the source of the<lb/>
infection, Reed, in his own mind, felt sure that Lazear's case fully supported<lb/>
his conclusions that X.Y's case was a bona-fide experimental case and that the<lb/>
mosquitoes from the laboratory had transmitted Yellow Fever in both instances.<lb/>
This viewpoint also strengthened the probability that the source of infection<lb/>
in Carroll's case was the one laboratory mosquito which Lazear had placed upon<lb/>
him and not caused by Carroll's visits to Havana and Las Animas Hospital.</p>
<p>Carroll in his Galveston address tells of Lazear's statement to him, -<lb/>
&ldquo;Dr. Lazear was applying mosquitoes, as usual, late in the afternoon, to<lb/>
patients in the Yellow Fever hospital, known as Las Animas, and while thus<lb/>
engaged a mosquito alighted upon his hand. He allowed it to take its fill, and<lb/>
concluded it was one of the common Culex mosquitoes which were present in the<lb/>
hospital in large numbers. So little importance did he attach to the incident<lb/>
that he made no note of it, and related the incident to me when first taken<lb/>
sick, five days afterward.&rdquo; (Lazear and Carroll were both sick at the time in<lb/>
the same hospital tent ward, under Dr. Ames' care).</p>
<p>In this same connection, I wish to record a discussion I had with my<lb/>
esteemed friend, the late Dr. Henry R. Carter. I was calling on him at his<lb/>
residence in Washington, D.C., in March, 1922. He was then writing a book on<lb/>
the &ldquo;History of Yellow Fever&rdquo; and he was interested in what I might be able to<lb/>
tell him about this particular matter. He wanted to show me a letter from<lb/>
Gorgas to Mrs. Gorgas written during Lazear's illness, or just after his death,<lb/>
but could not find it. A few days later I received a letter from him (Which<lb/>
I still have) quoting from the Gorgas letter as follows: &ldquo;Lazear told me that<lb/>
he saw a mosquito, which he believed to have been the one they are investigat-<lb/>
ing, on his hand at Las Animas Hospital and he let him bite as long as he<lb/>
wanted to.&rdquo; So far as I know these are the only statements made by Lazear<lb/>
during his illness about the source of his infection. Was he withholding<lb/>
facts in order to protect his dear ones at this critical moment? What do you<lb/>
think?</p>
<p>* * * * * * * * * *</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Lazear's Funeral</hi>.</p>
<p>Friends from the Post, officers from Department Headquarters, including<lb/>
Major Kean, and the entire medical personnel of the hospital were present at<lb/>
the funeral. As the cemetery was only a few hundred yards from the hospital<lb/>
on the road to La Playa everyone except the nurses walked. We were able to<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03566010"/>
4<lb/>
transport the latter in ambulances. Officers, enlisted men, and nurses<lb/>
were all in white uniforms. Carroll, who was still sick, was unable to<lb/>
attend the funeral. Full military honors were accorded and it was a<lb/>
spontaneous demonstration of affection for our lamented friend and co-<lb/>
worker, Jesse W. Lazear.</p>
<p>Reed, in his Baltimore address, April, 1901, speaking of Lazear's<lb/>
service at Columbia Barracks, said, &ldquo;During a service of less than one<lb/>
year in Cuba he won the good will and respect of his brother officers<lb/>
and the affection of his immediate associates. Almost at the beginning<lb/>
of what promised to be a life full of usefulness and good works he was<lb/>
suddenly stricken and, dying, added one more name to that imperishable<lb/>
roll of honor to which none others belong than martyrs to the cause of<lb/>
humanity.&rdquo;</p>
<p>- 4 -</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
