<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03564001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, July 2, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03564001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-07-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Army Medical Museum, Washington, (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-07-02">July 2, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03564001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, July 2, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench details his work on the yellow fever story. He asks for Truby's recollections, particularly concerning Lazear's case of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-07-02">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, July 2, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03564001"/>
<opener>
Y F.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-07-02">July 2, 1940</date>
</dateline>
General A. E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Washington and Jefferson College is dedicating a memorial building<lb/>
to Dr. James Lazear this next Fall. Lazear went to this college. The president of<lb/>
the college, a friend of mine, asked me to prepare a history of Walter Reed and the<lb/>
work of the Yellow Fever Board. I have been working on this now for three years, and<lb/>
have done much work, visiting some of the survivors of these experiments. I visited<lb/>
Kissinger at his <unclear>home</unclear>, and I also had him up here, trying to straighten out the story.<lb/>
I also visited Moran in Havana two months ago, spending about ten days there, and<lb/>
visited General Kean in Washington, and others. I have learned much, and have found<lb/>
many new things which have never been published before. I also have uncovered numer-<lb/>
ous unimportant, and a few rather important errors in the official record. I am<lb/>
writing this report up in some detail, and will send you a copy as soon as I can.</p>
<p>Among other things, I discovered that the Cuban government has<lb/>
put a memorial fence and sign on the supposed site of Camp Lazear, and the Secretary<lb/>
of War already has plans to erect a memorial on this site, which the government bought.<lb/>
To make a long story short, they have picked the wrong site, and Moran and I were<lb/>
able, after considerable trouble, to straighten it out, discovering the original<lb/>
site of Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>The point that I am particularly anxious to have your help in,<lb/>
however, concerns the question of Dr. Lazear's own case of yellow fever. You, of<lb/>
course, know the official story that, having been bitten by experimental mosquitoes<lb/>
which failed to infect him, he was later bitten by a stray mosquito while feeding<lb/>
his own experimental mosquitoes on yellow fever patients in Los <unclear>Annis</unclear> Hospital, later<lb/>
developing yellow fever spontaneously, not experimental yellow fever, from which he<lb/>
died. I first heard <unclear>suspicious</unclear> that this official story was not true through Moran.<lb/>
He told me emphatically that it was decidedly understood by those in close connection<lb/>
with the experiments that Lazear's yellow fever was just as experimental as Carroll's<lb/>
but for some personal reason the story was allowed to stand. I next learned from<lb/>
Dr. Agramonte's daughter that her father had told her many times that Dr. Lazear<lb/>
had deliberately allowed himself to be bitten, perhaps against the advise and wishes<lb/>
of Dr. Reed, in his zeal to settle the matter, and that be in truth had experimental,<lb/>
not accidental, yellow fever. It was <unclear>her</unclear> understanding that the official story was<lb/>
allowed to stand because it had something to do with a pension or something. I<lb/>
broached this subject on a recent visit to General Kean, and he smiled and said some-<lb/>
thing to this effect, &ldquo;Oh, you have heard that, too, have you? Well, so far as I know<lb/>
it is true, although I only knew it two years ago. I think that General Truby may<lb/>
be able to give you the direct information you wish.&rdquo; And it is with his permission<lb/>
that I am writing you.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03564002"/>
<p>General A. E. Truby</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>July 2, 1940</p>
<p>General Kean and the others with whom I have discussed this<lb/>
matter, agree with me that after <unclear>those</unclear> many years it can do no harm, and can do<lb/>
much good to at last tell the true story. Depending on the way I shall write it<lb/>
up, I am sure that I will be able to cast no reflections on Dr. Reed for allowing<lb/>
the other version to stand. As a matter of fact, he did it at the special request<lb/>
of Dr. Lazear himself. I know of no more fitting time nor place to give the true<lb/>
version than on the occasion of a ceremony dedicating a memorial to Dr. Lazear.<lb/>
Washington and Jefferson is planning quite a celebration, with distinguished med-<lb/>
ical men from Washington and elsewhere, and it will be quite a dignified and<lb/>
impressive affair. I sincerely hope that you agree with General Kean and me,<lb/>
and will be willing to tell me the story in as much detail as possible.</p>
<p>In order to save you the labor of writing this, I shall be only<lb/>
too glad to have you call a public stenographer or some secretary whom you know,<lb/>
and dictate to her in as much detail as you possibly can, what you know of this<lb/>
story. If you will ask her to make a couple of extra carbon copies, I shall be<lb/>
glad to pay whatever charges she makes.</p>
<p>I should appreciate taking the liberty of writing you later<lb/>
about other details of the story<unclear>,</unclear> When I get my report completed, I will send you<lb/>
a copy of the various photographs I have taken and the various ones I have obtained<lb/>
from Dr. Agramonte's dauther, the Army Medical Museum, and others. These will<lb/>
concern some of the details of the experiments and also the re-discovery of Camp<lb/>
Lazear. I am sure it will be of great interest to you, and I know that undoubtedly<lb/>
you will have many comments to make which will be extremely helpful.</p>
<p>As you may know, the Cuban government has been making deliberate<lb/>
attempts to minimize the work of Reed and the Board, and a great attempt to show<lb/>
that Finlay deserves all the credit. It is high time that the story be retold<lb/>
as authentically as possible, without, of course, in any way minimizing the great<lb/>
contribution of Dr. Finlay.</p>
<p>Can you tell me whether Mrs. Lazear is still living in California?<lb/>
I am most anxious to get in touch with her and her relatives.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
