<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03577006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, August 28, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03577006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Miss</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Moya, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A.Diaz</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-28">August 28, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03577006</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, August 28, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] thanks Rojas for her help. He will send a report to the Cuban government and hopes it will stimulate interest in the memorial. He asks her to mark the Camp Lazear location on maps.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-28">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, August 28, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03577006"/>
<opener>
Copy to Moran to show Mrs Phillips<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-28">August 28, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Senora Rojas:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The other day I wrote you the long letter which I am enclosing,<lb/>
but have been delayed in sending it to you while awaiting the photographs and maps<lb/>
to be copies, which I now enclose. In the meantime, I was delighted to receive<lb/>
your long and courteous note and hasten to express my great <unclear>appreciation</unclear> to you,<lb/>
your daughter and to Senorita Cabrera for your continued help and interest.</p>
<p>Thank you so very much for writing to the <unclear>Agronomio</unclear> Station<lb/>
of Santiago de las Vegas. Please do not bother further about this now. I am<lb/>
sending the photographs of the two trees to our Forestry Department in Washington,<lb/>
hoping that someone can, from the photographs, tell me the approximate age of the<lb/>
framboyant trees. If they cannot, I will bother you again with this matter or I<lb/>
will write to the Santiago Station myself.</p>
<p>You have been extremely kind in trying to find the newspapers<lb/>
with the data about Reed and yellow fever. I appreciate so much the notes you have<lb/>
sent me. They will be very useful. I was anxious to find the Havana Post for<lb/>
November 24 and 25, 1900, but since the material in your National Library is not<lb/>
yet in order, we must postpone hunting for the papers, and I will try to see whether<lb/>
such papers might be in the New York Public Library or the Congressional Library in<lb/>
Washington. If not, do you think some other library in Cuba, perhaps at Santiago,<lb/>
might have the Havana papers for 1900?</p>
<p>The photographs I am now sending you will be augmented by<lb/>
others that I will send you later, and rest assured that my final manuscript will<lb/>
be submitted to you for your final approval before it is published. As soon as I<lb/>
hear from you, I plan to send my formal report to the Cuban government, in care of<lb/>
Dr. Ramos, Secretary of Defense, and Dr. Moya, Secretary of Sanitation. I will send<lb/>
a copy also to Dr. Albertini and others at the Finlay Institute, and a copy to <unclear>Mesers</unclear>.<lb/>
Moran and Pogolotti. I am sure that we can interest Americans in seeing that some sort<lb/>
of a memorial is placed on the San Jose farm.</p>
<p>The one thing above all which I am anxious to obtain from you,<lb/>
is to have you mark as clearly as possible on the enclosed maps, just where you<lb/>
remember Camp Lazear was in relation to the present houses, street, and quarry.<lb/>
Will you please mark a X at the approximate center of the camp, and then line out<lb/>
the approximate dimensions of the camp. Will you please authenticate this by writing<lb/>
in your own handwriting on the front or the bottom of the map, something as follows:<lb/>
&ldquo;This is where the experimental camp was located, on the San Jose farm in 1900. This<lb/>
was the camp set up by the U. S. Army doctors to carry out their experiments which<lb/>
proved the cause of yellow fever,&rdquo; Signed by your full name. (or words to that effect)<unclear>C</unclear><lb/>
You will realize that this is the most important proof that I can have, and I will have<lb/>
this map and your drawing and statement photographed and send copies to those inter-<lb/>
ested in Cuba and in this country.</p>
<p>I cannot tell you how greatly I appreciate your wonderful help.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
- 2 -<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I believe I will need a copy of the original map<lb/>
of your farm. Was it 1850, or 1857? I will arrange for a photographer to<lb/>
call on you and copy it, if you will kindly let me do so.<lb/>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
