<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03576005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, August 15, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03576005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph C.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-15">August 15, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03576005</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, August 15, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench encloses a draft of his manuscript. He asks for her comments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-15">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, August 15, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03576005"/>
<opener>
Copy to Mrs Phillips to Show <hi>Moran</hi><lb/>
Sent Copy of Memorandum<lb/>
&amp; Photos 1-2-5-6-11b-13b-14-39-42<lb/>
45-46-53-62 &amp; her fathers old prints<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-15">August 15, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Senora Estella Agramonte Rodriguez-Leon<lb/>
311 Calle 15 entre H e I<lb/>
Vedado, Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora Rodriguez-Leon</salute>
</opener>
<p>I so appreciated your kind note and hasten to tell you that I<lb/>
think your apologies were entirely unnecessary. I know how busy you must<lb/>
be. I, myself have been very busy and only recently have been able to<lb/>
collect my notes, written often very hastily, sometimes written from memory<lb/>
at the end of the day. These I have assembled in the enclosed, confidential<lb/>
memorandum, and hasten to tell you that this memorandum is only being sent<lb/>
to Dr. Hutchison, the president of W. and J., so that he may get some of the<lb/>
background of the yellow fever work, and it is also being sent to General<lb/>
Kean and General Truby, who were so closely associated with the work of your<lb/>
father and his colleagues. A copy is going to Moran, in order that he may<lb/>
help me straighten out some of the details. Although it is long, I think you<lb/>
will find it interesting to read, and I would be most grateful indeed if you<lb/>
would read it critically, and make any comment on it that you choose to make.<lb/>
I am so anxious that the truth shall be told, insofar as it can glorify those<lb/>
concerned, and if I have through error <unclear>made</unclear> any mis-statement or misquoted you<lb/>
or anyone else, I am most anxious to have it corrected. When my final story<lb/>
is published, naturally it will be more interesting to have your remarks and<lb/>
those of others given in the first person in quotation marks, and I would be<lb/>
most grateful if you could amplify your story just as much as possible. I<lb/>
would never ask you to go to the bother of writing out corrections and ampli-<lb/>
fications in long hand. This is too much work and I am going to make a suggestion<lb/>
which I hope you will think appropriate. Mrs. R. Hart Phillips, Manzana de<lb/>
Gomez 553, Havana, is the widow of the former correspondent of the New York<lb/>
Times. She does secretarial work and helped me considerably when I was in<lb/>
Havana. Would you permit me to suggest that, at your convenience, she come<lb/>
to your house some afternoon or evening and take dictation from you, receiving<lb/>
whatever suggestions, criticisms and amplifications of this memorandum that<lb/>
you see fit to make. She will then make a carbon copy, submit it for your<lb/>
final inspection, and send it to me, and I shall be delighted to pay the cost.<lb/>
I am hoping to make this arrangement between her and two or three other Havana<lb/>
correspondents.</p>
<p>Please remember that this memorandum is confidential in the sense<lb/>
that it will not be published in this form and that any remarks I have made which<lb/>
would seem detrimental to those of the government or those from the Finlay Institute<lb/>
whom I met, are merely written here for personal reasons, and will of course never<lb/>
appear in my formal report, either to the Cuban government or in any paper that I<lb/>
may write for medical historical journals.</p>
<p>May I ask you certain specific questions?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03576006"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Paragraph 13: Did your father ever tell you anything about Dean's<lb/>
mental reactions when he had discovered that he had gotten yellow fever? Or did<lb/>
he ever tell you anything remotely resembling Kissinger's version of this affair?<lb/>
Kissinger insisted that Lazear had put the mosquito on Dean while he was asleep.</p>
<p>Par. 14: I am particularly anxious that you check this paragraph for<lb/>
me. Can you give me any further information as to the understanding between your<lb/>
father and Lazear? Was Reed involved in this understanding and was it official<lb/>
or merely a gentlemen's agreement?</p>
<p>Pars. 15 and 16: I would be most appreciative if you would amplify<lb/>
and comment on these paragraphs.</p>
<p>Par. 17: Again I am anxious to find out if there was any correspondence<lb/>
between Reed in Washington and your father and Lazear in Havana regarding Carroll's<lb/>
illness, and later regarding Lazear's death.</p>
<p>Par. 32: Do you know of any tree expert in Havana who would be willing<lb/>
to visit the tree on the false site of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; and give me some idea as to age,<lb/>
or who might be at least willing to look at my photograph of this tree and express<lb/>
an opinion?</p>
<p>Par. 50: I should appreciate your reaction to this paragraph, and I<lb/>
can assure that it is not meant as criticism on my part. I think that Americans<lb/>
know too little about Finlay and Cubans know too little about the work of Reed and<lb/>
your father.</p>
<p>Par. 52: Do you know whether the National Hospital of the Cuban<lb/>
army has yet been named for your father or whether any monument has been erected<lb/>
to Carroll?</p>
<p>Par. 99: I am of course particularly anxious for you to check over<lb/>
very carefully Par. 99 to 105, and if you can given me any more <del><unclear>informal</unclear></del> information<lb/>
on the informal pact between your father and Lazear, this would be most helpful.<lb/>
I am returning herewith the three photographs which you so kindly loaned me with<lb/>
a copy of each that we made here. Should anyone else wish copies, rather than<lb/>
lend your precious photographs again, I should be glad to send you copies from<lb/>
our films. I am still extremely anxious to find other photographs of the places<lb/>
and personalities concerned, and while I hesitate to impose upon you, <add>with</add> another<lb/>
request for you to bother to hunt for your father's photographs, were you to find<lb/>
them it would be a bonanza to me: Would you be willing to send me your father's<lb/>
manuscript written in his own hand, the unpublished address given at the time of<lb/>
the banquet. If you will register this to me, I will have it photostated and return<lb/>
you not only the original, but a photostat copy by registered, insured post.<lb/>
So far, I have been unable to obtain a copy of the <unclear>Hemmeter</unclear> or the Donnally articles.<lb/>
You were kind enough to say that if I could not find them, you would lend them to me.<lb/>
Do not bother to send them yet, as I still have one or two people I want to write<lb/>
to for them. I asked you where your father was buried. I carelessly forgot to<lb/>
write this down. I should like to know. Do you have any photographs of his grave?</p>
<p>I cannot tell you how much I appreciate all the wonderful help that you<lb/>
have given me, and if I can remind American medical men of the glorious work in which<lb/>
your father participated so nobly, I shall be satisfied to have spent so many hours<lb/>
in trying to find out new angles of this fascinating story. Mrs. Hench sends you<lb/>
her kindest regards, both to you and to your family.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P.S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
