<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03575002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, August 26, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03575002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">King, Henry S.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Major</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Presedo, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-26">August 26, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03575002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, August 26, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench encloses a draft of his manuscript with specific questions for Truby to answer.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, August 26, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03575002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1940-08-26">August 26, 1940</date>
</dateline>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
DR. CHARLES H. SLOCUMB<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>After my return from Havana, I was so busy that I could not<lb/>
set down in orderly fashion, my notes until recently. I have just finished my<lb/>
memorandum. It is quite confidential, and I am submitting it to you, to General<lb/>
Kean, Moran, and Senora Rojas in order that I may have whatever corrections, and<lb/>
amplifications that you can give me. I would appreciate it greatly if you would<lb/>
read this, answer certain special questions about certain paragraphs and then call<lb/>
in a public stenographer or secretary and dictate to her whatever answers and other<lb/>
details you can give me. I shall be only too glad to pay the expense. I do not<lb/>
wish to anticipate or to detract from your own story. Do you plan to <hi>publish</hi><lb/>
yours as a book or merely submit it to a journal? I think, however, our stories<lb/>
are quite different in scope and purpose. I understand yours will be a collection<lb/>
of personal recollections. Mine, of course, is a collection of data published, and<lb/>
unpublished, covering the work of all those concerned. May I particularly ask your<lb/>
help in answering the following questions, in order that we may have the Cuban<lb/>
government memorialize the right site of Camp Lazear. My second special request is<lb/>
that you permit me to quote you and of course give you full credit for whatever data<lb/>
you can give me as to the true nature of Lazear's illness. I am sure that General<lb/>
Kean, and I believe also Miss Agramonte are now willing for this data to be mentioned,<lb/>
in order that, on the most appropriate occasion, on the dedication of a Lazear<lb/>
Memorial, we could give Lazear some long withheld credit. May I now ask you certain<lb/>
specific questions, pertaining to the paragraphs in my memorandum.</p>
<p>ok</p>
<p>Paragraph 6: Do you know when the <hi>tent Camp Columbia was</hi> Jan. 1894<lb/>
erected, <hi>what the site was used for before that</hi> when the <hi>tent Camp Columbia was<lb/>
replaced by the wooden Columbia Barracks</hi> <add>July <unclear>1899</unclear></add> and when the latter was replaced by the<lb/>
present Military City? Do you recall the relationship of the railroad track to<lb/>
Camp Columbia or Columbia Barracks? See other side this sheet.</p>
<p>It was<lb/>
entirely<lb/>
vacant<lb/>
land</p>
<p><del>July <unclear>1894</unclear></del></p>
<p>Paragraph 11: Do you know the exact date during the first week<lb/>
in August that Reed left Havana for Washington? Aug 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 1900. I sailed with<lb/>
him on this <unclear>Transport</unclear> &ldquo;Rawlins&rdquo; but returned to Columbia Bks before Reed <unclear>died</unclear>.</p>
<p>Par. 12: Between Aug. 11 and 25, 1900, Lazear applied infected<lb/>
mosquitos to nine U.S. soldiers, which included Lazear, Carroll and Pinto. The other<lb/>
six remain unidentified. Do you have any idea who they were? No., Enlisted <unclear>men</unclear> I think<lb/>
Case no. 3 May have been Lazear but the age given is 24. Lazear was 34.</p>
<p>Par. 13: Kissinger's version of the inoculation of Dean is as<lb/>
follows: Dean, having scoffed at the yellow fever work, had the habit of napping after<lb/>
lunch in the hospital where he was a patient. On the morning that Carroll's illness<lb/>
was diagnosed as experimental yellow fever, Lazear wanted a volunteer at once. Accord-<lb/>
ing to Kissinger, Lazear found Dean asleep, and put the mosquito on him while he was<lb/>
asleep. Later, when Dean heard how he had gotten yellow fever, presumably he was angry<lb/>
at first, later enjoyed being a hero. This version differs entirely with Agramonte's<lb/>
version (see Scientific Monthly, Dec. 1915). Did you ever hear anything to support<lb/>
Kissinger's version?</p>
<p>There were<lb/>
all sorts of<lb/>
rumors <unclear>re-</unclear><lb/>
this and<lb/>
Kissingers<lb/>
<unclear>may</unclear> have<lb/>
heard this<lb/>
(see other)<lb/>
(side)</p>
<p>Agramonte's version can, I am sure, be disprove<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03575003"/>
<unclear></unclear><lb/>
T<lb/>
Our yellow fever ward was across the R.R. tracks<lb/>
near where you located it. There was <hi>no tree</hi> or<lb/>
even any chrubbery in 1900. There is quite a<lb/>
deep cut at that spot where the tracks <del><unclear></unclear></del> are<lb/>
and it was difficult for us to get over there<lb/>
so a bridge was constructed by the C.M. Dept.<lb/>
about the time Kissinger was taken <unclear>there</unclear> for<lb/>
treatment from Camp Lazear. <hi>Dr. Lazear died there</hi><lb/>
Moran was treated there.</p>
<p>I think it was approximately 200 <unclear>yds</unclear> <add>due west</add> from<lb/>
our <add>medical</add> Officer's quarters (Reed lived with us) to the<lb/>
tents of the yellow fever ward- It was a busy<lb/>
place during the Quemados epidemic, earlier in 1900-</p>
<p><hi>Par. 13.</hi></p>
<p>I feel certain that Lazear obtained Dean's<lb/>
consent to be bitten. Lazear did this all by<lb/>
himself and Agramonte was not present.<lb/>
I am sure that this can be definitely proven, if<lb/>
desired-</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03575004"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Paragraph 14: Did Lazear and Carroll have a formal pact <add>no</add> not to<lb/>
be inoculated and was this authorized by Reed? <add>No-</add> Where <add>Agramonte</add> did Carroll do his convalescing?<lb/>
Was it in the post hospital at Columbia Barracks? yes-</p>
<p>Par. 15-16: Anything on the real story of Lazear's illness <add><hi>you have it</hi></add> that I<lb/>
can quote, I shall be most grateful for, and I am delighted with whatever you have sent<lb/>
me. <hi>Do I have the authority to quote you on the occasion of my address at Washington<lb/>
and Jefferson College?</hi> yes</p>
<p>(See other side) Par. 16: Did Dr. Lazear die in the post hospital at Columbia Barracks?<lb/>
Where was he buried, when and where was the body re-interred, and where does he now lie?</p>
<p>Par. 17: Do you have any information on the correspondence between<lb/>
Reed in Washington and Carroll or Agramonte in Havana regarding Lazear's death. No.<lb/>
I think Kean probably did all the writing &amp; cabling. Both Kean &amp; I wrote to<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear.</p>
<p>Par. 19: Reed left Havana &ldquo;about the middle of October, 1900&rdquo; to<lb/>
go to Washington and Indianapolis. Do you know the exact date?- Oct 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></p>
<p>Par. 21: Reed returned to Havana &ldquo;early in November, 1900&rdquo;. Do<lb/>
you know the date? Nov 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. I am not sure which is right.</p>
<p>(See other side) Par. 22: Do you know what the exact personnel of Camp Lazear was?<lb/>
The official records do not make clear who were the eleven soldiers who went into resi-<lb/>
dence at Camp Lazear on November 20, 1900. In particular, I am anxious to have any<lb/>
information on the following points: Do you personally know anything about the circum-<lb/>
stances of the volunteer of Moran and Kissinger? Did they go to Reed together (as Moran<lb/>
says) or separately (as Kissinger says). How was the call for volunteers put out?<lb/>
by Reed? by Dr. Ames? and in what form, in written notice or by word of mouth?</p>
<p>Par. 23: What was the exact method used for inoculating Kissinger,<lb/>
Moran, Benigno, and Presedo between Nov. 20 and 30, 1900? Where, at Camp Lazear, did the<lb/>
inoculations take place, in Reed's office tent or in the volunteers' own tents? Who<lb/>
officiated and carried out the actual inoculation? Did Reed always do this? When was<lb/>
the building of the Infected Clothing Building begun? It was first occupied Nov. 30, 1900.<lb/>
When was Building No. 2 begun? It was occupied Dec. 21. Who were the two volunteers who<lb/>
slept in the Infected Mosquito Building between Dec. 21 and Jan. 8.</p>
<p>Par. 29: Do you know anything about the disbanding of Camp Lazear? no<lb/>
Did you personally ever visit the Camp? <add>yes.</add> Could you see any hilly country near the Camp? <unclear>Bathing</unclear><lb/>
Do you remember the relation of the camp to the Rojas farm house, its distance and<lb/>
direction? no.</p>
<p>Par. 49: I want your reaction to this. See <add>your</add> <unclear>mms</unclear>- par 49</p>
<p>Par. 101-104: Please give me your reaction to these. See <unclear>mms</unclear>.</p>
<p>See other side Par. 111-112: You remember that Reed spoke of the appearance of<lb/>
yellow fever at #120 Real Street and #20 General Lee St. I believe some American officers<lb/>
or soldiers were quartered there. Do you know who they were?</p>
<p>Par. 115-116: I am especially anxious for you to check these<lb/>
paragraphs. See mms.</p>
<p>Par. 118: May I have your opinion of this? See mms.</p>
<p>Par. 127: Please comment on this. No par. 127.</p>
<p>Par 120 is the last one on the mms.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03575005"/>
<p>Ac<lb/>
T</p>
<p>Par 16 Lazear died in the tent y. f. ward on<lb/>
(your false site of Camp Lazear) the west side of the<lb/>
railroad tracks I think perhaps it was a little<lb/>
further north of the tree <add>shown</add> in your photos. He<lb/>
was buried in our military cemetery a few hundred<lb/>
yards <add>from our hospital</add> down the old road to La Playa- His remains<lb/>
were removed later to the <hi>London</hi> cemetery in Balto, Md.</p>
<p>Par 22 They were mostly from the group which later<lb/>
volunteered but I have no exact list-<lb/>
Kissinger went first, and entirely independent<lb/>
of Moran. Moran is mistakened in his statement,<lb/>
but he volunteered almost immediately afterwards.<lb/>
There was no call for volunteers. It was entirely<lb/>
by word of mouth. The Officers &amp; Enlisted men all know<lb/>
of Reed's work and that the Spanish volunteers<lb/>
were an uncertain <del><unclear></unclear></del> group. When Kissinger<lb/>
&amp; Moran volunteered the rest followed promptly-</p>
<p>23. Reed did it all himself at the Camp (Lazear) but<lb/>
I was never present at such times. Carroll<lb/>
attended to the infection of mosquitos on cases<lb/>
at Las Animas. He no doubt assisted Reed<lb/>
in some cases, but Carroll was still convalescing<lb/>
from her attack of y.f. Most cases of y.f. recovered very<lb/>
promptly but Carroll was an exception. It took<lb/>
him several months to get back to normal<lb/>
Buildings 1 &amp; 2 were both begun &amp; finished at<lb/>
the same time-</p>
<p>Par. 111-112 20 General Lee St occupied <unclear>by</unclear> a<lb/>
civilian <unclear>Q.M.</unclear> packer Henry S King &amp; his wife. These were<lb/>
probably the two first cases of yellow fever in Quemados. (May 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>)<lb/>
Cases developed at 102 Real st. June 3.<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, I do not know<lb/>
their names. Maj Edmunds lived at no 17 <unclear>General</unclear> Lee st. <unclear>Heand</unclear><lb/>
his wife became sick on 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, respectively<lb/>
General Kean lived near the Edmunds. on the same st.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03575006"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>Is Dr. Ames living? <add><hi>no</hi></add> Reed's letter to Carroll Feb. 26, 1900,<lb/>
says Ames had a map of the Quemados epidemic. I wish indeed I could trace this<lb/>
map. Have you written Mrs Ames. Kean, I think, has her address.</p>
<p>I cannot tell you how much I appreciate your wonderful help.<lb/>
Your last letter was extremely interesting, and I certainly do appreciate it.<lb/>
Permit me to send you a copy of a questionnaire I sent to Gen. Kean. If you can<lb/>
give me any of the answers, I will certainly appreciate it. You may wish to<lb/>
have the secretary or stenographer who helps answer this letter make an extra<lb/>
carbon for yourself. Please ask her to send me an extra carbon also. If you<lb/>
do not mind, I know General Kean will be most anxious to see it.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
<unclear>Keep</unclear> the photos of your work. If you can tell me any<lb/>
data about then you can simply refer to the number I've<lb/>
given each one. Do you want the photostat of your<lb/>
letter from Reed or may I keep it. I'd love to.<lb/>
psh:ds<lb/>
I will keep some of the photos. Thanks-<lb/>
<unclear><hi>AET</hi></unclear><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
