<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03577004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter (English translation) from Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas to Philip Showalter Hench, August 11, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03577004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Miss</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-11">August 11, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03577004</idno>
<title>Letter (English translation) from Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas to Philip Showalter Hench, August 11, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Rojas answers some of Hench's questions about the difficulties of research and the problems with the Cuban regime.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-11">
<head>Letter (English translation) from Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas to Philip Showalter Hench, August 11, 1940 (See <xref id="f03577001">Spanish original</xref>.)</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03577004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-11">August 11, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
U. S. A.<lb/>
<salute>My esteemed Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Please forgive the delay in answering your kind<lb/>
letter. This is due to certain things I wanted to tell<lb/>
you. My daughter and Miss Cabrera are doing what I told<lb/>
them only that in this tropical climate everything is slow<lb/>
and at the end of three months of trying to do what I wanted<lb/>
I have not been able to get what I want.</p>
<p>About the trees, we have written to the Agronomic<lb/>
Station of Santiago de las Vegas, The only place where they<lb/>
know something about that because here there are no experts<lb/>
as in other countries. From that place they have promised<lb/>
us to come here to see about that but they have not done it.<lb/>
Probably they are busy with politics as many people have been<lb/>
during <unclear>these</unclear> last month and as they are Government employees<lb/>
they have to do that.</p>
<p>About the article in the newspaper, we found in<lb/>
the Sociedad Econ&oacute;mica what I am enclosing, published in Eng-<lb/>
lish from the newspaper La Lucha. In these copies there are<lb/>
some loose notes which I am sending you, that is to say, tel-<lb/>
ling you about the number of cases of yellow fever, death and<lb/>
so forth. Tell me if you are interested. In the date you tell<lb/>
me, that is November 21 of 1900, there is nothing in the news-<lb/>
papers in Spanish. Nevertheless we are still looking for them.<lb/>
On the other hand we have not seen the copies of the Havana Post<lb/>
that interested you. The archive of this paper was burned in<lb/>
1925 and the only public library in Havana that has a complete<lb/>
collection is the National Library. This, though it seems un-<lb/>
believable, has almost all its books in old boxes without<lb/>
classification and not accessible to the public. There is a<lb/>
very extreme carelessness in our government about the work of<lb/>
culture. All the investigations I have tried to do have been<lb/>
useless. They tell us that they would need a special employee<lb/>
to look around those mountains of papers that we need but if<lb/>
you consider those articles of capital interest we could find<lb/>
the services of some <unclear>employee</unclear>.</p>
<p><unclear>asks</unclear><lb/>
Havana<lb/>
<unclear>Post</unclear><lb/>
Nov 24-25, 1900</p>
<p>Mr. Pogolotti returned already the original plans<lb/>
of the farm. He himself has helped us in our investigations<lb/>
in the National Library.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03577005"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>I have not seen Mr. Moran again. Miss Cabrera<lb/>
spoke with him on the telephone and he promised to come to<lb/>
see us but so far we have not had the pleasure of receiving<lb/>
his visit.</p>
<p>I am very grateful to you for the photographs<lb/>
that you had the kindness to send me. They will remind us<lb/>
of the pleasant moments we spent with you all and we hope that<lb/>
you come again. About what you promise me about Camp Lazear,<lb/>
is of the greatest interest to me, as much for its historical<lb/>
value as for its sentimental one. For this kindness I wish<lb/>
to thank you, also for your interest in finding out about the<lb/>
<hi>real situation</hi> of the Campamento Lazear, because that is a true<lb/>
honor for us being in the farms of San Jos&eacute;.</p>
<p>actual}<lb/>
location}</p>
<p>We are waiting for the notes that you told us to<lb/>
add to the data which you wish about the history of the farm<lb/>
and something more if we remember. You may be sure that it<lb/>
will be a pleasure for us to serve you in everything we can.<lb/>
Therefore do not hesitate to occupy us or write to us as many<lb/>
times as you think it necessary.</p>
<p>We are in San Jos&eacute; spending the summer where the<lb/>
temperature is more bearable than in Vedado because this year<lb/>
the heat has been excessive.</p>
<p>Give Mrs. Hench our affectionate greetings and ask<lb/>
her forgiveness for me because I delayed answering and thank-<lb/>
ing you for sending the flowers.</p>
<p>We pray for the health of your son and I hope he<lb/>
is now very well.</p>
<p>Please give us news from you and keep us posted<lb/>
about your investigations. With regards from my daughter<lb/>
and from Miss Cabrera, I send you the expression of my sin-<lb/>
cere friendship.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) Maria Teresa L. Vda. de Rojas</signed>
(Translated by Miss Montes)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
