<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03580001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Howard A. Kelly, August 14, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03580001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Military City (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-14">August 14, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03580001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Howard A. Kelly, August 14, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench seeks information about the original Camp Lazear photographs. He draws attention to the incorrect identification of the mosquito building in Kelly's book. He inquires about the source of the &ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you&rdquo; legend, and tries to find the addresses for Blossom Reed, Mrs. Lazear, and Carroll's family.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-14">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Howard A. Kelly, August 14, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03580001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-14">August 14, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Howard A. Kelly<lb/>
1418 Eutah Place<lb/>
Baltimore, Maryland<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Kelly:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The President of Washington and Jefferson College is dedicating a<lb/>
Lazear Memorial Building at Washington, Pennsylvania this October. In connection<lb/>
therewith, he asked me a couple of years ago to give a talk on the conquest of<lb/>
yellow fever. I have spent considerable time in correspondence and in actual visits<lb/>
with certain of the survivors of the yellow fever work in Havana. I have visited<lb/>
General Kean in Washington, Kissinger in Huntington, Indiana, and recently spent<lb/>
ten days with Mr. John J. Moran in Havana. While there, I found that the Cuban<lb/>
government had lost track of the true site of Camp Lazear, and had erroneously<lb/>
marked another site much closer to Camp Columbia, which is now the site of the<lb/>
Military City. On this false site, they have <unclear>erected</unclear> a small memorial fence and<lb/>
sign and have already purchased the land in preparation for the <unclear>erection</unclear> of some<lb/>
sort of a memorial, for which I understand already two hundred thousand dollars<lb/>
have been raised. Having at hand the popular article by Agramonte, published<lb/>
in the Scientific Monthly for December, 1915, in which he precisely located Camp<lb/>
Lazear, I was able to find the old San Jose farm. Presenting my information thereafter<lb/>
to the Secretary of Defense, under whose department the development of the falsely<lb/>
located site belongs, I found considerable opposition on their part towards accepting<lb/>
my data. But, to make a long story short, they have accepted it tentatively, but<lb/>
have asked me to submit to the Cuban government a documentary statement with my proof.<lb/>
The basis of their locating the false camp site was a small photograph of a shack<lb/>
presumably one of Walter Reed's experimental buildings and immediately adjacent, a<lb/>
small framboyant (poinciana) tree. This does not resemble in any way <del><unclear>in</unclear></del> the buildings<lb/>
and trees as shown in the photograph of Camp Lazear as published in your book in 1900.<lb/>
The Cuban government has asked me to submit to them copies of the American official<lb/>
photographs of Camp Lazear. I should like your permission to send them copies of<lb/>
the two in your book, I should particularly appreciate knowing the source of your<lb/>
photographs. Did you receive them from Dr. Reed or from the army? I have not seen<lb/>
those photographs elsewhere and the U.S. Army Medical Museum in Washington does not<lb/>
have copies of those used in your book. Indeed, yours are much better than theirs.<lb/>
They merely have photographic copies (not the originals) of the two pictures in the<lb/>
Surgeon General's report for 1901. If you have the films of these two pictures, or<lb/>
any other films or photographs pertaining to Camp Lazear or Walter Reed and the<lb/>
yellow fever experiments, I would be most appreciative if you would let me have<lb/>
copies, for which I would be most glad to pay, or lend me the film.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I believe that one of your photographs is wrongly<lb/>
labeled. You have called it &ldquo;The Infected Clothing Building&rdquo; but if one compares<lb/>
the shape with the drawings of Agramonte in the Scientific Monthly for December, 1915,<lb/>
it is apparent that it is the Infected Mosquito Building. I understand that the<lb/>
man standing by this building is supposed to be Carroll. Mr. Moran was inclined to<lb/>
doubt this and I wondered if you could clarify this point.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03580002"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Both Mr. Kissinger and Moran have written for me their own stories<lb/>
which have never been published, and which I hope to publish in some medical historical<lb/>
journal under their own name. Both have told me that the legend about Walter Reed<lb/>
saluting them and saying, &ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you!&rdquo; had no basis in fact. It is<lb/>
a nice legend, but does not happen to be true. I asked Mr. Moran and General Kean<lb/>
if they knew where this legend originated, but they did not. Moran first saw it in<lb/>
your book and I would be most interested to know what the source of your information<lb/>
was. Was this Major Reed's own recollection of the event, and did he tell it to you?</p>
<p>Have you any idea where Major Reed's daughter now lives? Also where<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear lives? I have so far been unable to find their addresses. Do you<lb/>
know whether there are any survivors of Dr. Carroll? My search through the Army<lb/>
Medical Museum and the Surgeon General's offices failed to reveal the original<lb/>
papers of Reed or any others of the Board, and I am most anxious to get in touch<lb/>
with the families of these Board members.</p>
<p>I cannot tell you how I appreciate your great help in this matter.<lb/>
It would not only help me in planning my report to the Cuban government, but will<lb/>
be of great assistance in the preparation of my address to be given at the Lazear<lb/>
Memorial dedication. I will probably publish something on the subject and would be<lb/>
delighted to pay my sincere acknowledgement to you for your help.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
