<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03595001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Luis B. Pogolotti, August 26, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03595001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Pogolotti, Luis B.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Hospital Militar de Columbia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-26">August 26, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03595001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Luis B. Pogolotti, August 26, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench encloses a manuscript with specific questions in regard to a number of paragraphs.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Luis B. Pogolotti, August 26, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03595001"/>
<opener>
copy to Mrs Phillips (to show Moran )<lb/>
Photos 1-2-5-6- 11<unclear>b</unclear> -48-51-52-56-<lb/>
57-58-59<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-26">August 26, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Luis Pogolotti<lb/>
Cuba 3<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Pogolotti:</salute>
</opener>
<p>At last, permit me to send you my memorandum which I am<lb/>
so anxious to have you go over in detail and correct in any way you see fit.<lb/>
I am <unclear>also</unclear> sending another set of the snapshots which I sent you weeks ago, but<lb/>
which must have been lost in the mail. I am sending Mr. Moran one of these mem-<lb/>
oranda, and asking him to go over it with Senora Rojas, but I am most anxious to<lb/>
have your own help in regard to a number of paragraphs.</p>
<p>Paragraph 6: Do you know whon the tent Camp Columbia was<lb/>
erected, what this site was used for beforehand, and when the tent camp was replaced<lb/>
by the wooden barracks of Columbia Barracks. When was the latter torn down and the<lb/>
present Military City erected?</p>
<p>Par. 7: What is the relationship between Quemados and Marianao?<lb/>
Is this one town or two? Is there one mayor or two? Is there a public library in<lb/>
Quemados or Marianao, where I might find an old map of Marianao as of 1900? Would the<lb/>
mayor or one of the officials know of some historian of the town?</p>
<p>Par. 32: Please correct me carefully as to my directions as<lb/>
to how to get to the false site of Camp Lazear, How large is the present Military<lb/>
City? (in square miles or acres). Am I right about Calzata los Quemados. How many<lb/>
units are there to the present Hospital Militar de Columbia, that is, how many<lb/>
buildings? When was the Fourth of September Clinic erected? On one of my hastily<lb/>
sketched maps, drawn in pencil when we were visiting the false camp site, I marked<lb/>
that we went down a &ldquo;Boquetta Road&rdquo;. This is unmarked on the map. My recollection<lb/>
is that we asked the name of the road we were on, and a passerby gave us that name.<lb/>
But the maps indicate that one goes directly down Santa Rosa Street to meet the<lb/>
railroad track, where the little Carnino station now is. What is the relationship<lb/>
between Boquetta Road and Santa Rosa Street, and where should Boquetta Road be on the<lb/>
map? When did you erect the Carnino Station? What does Lidia Paradero mean?</p>
<p>I have asked Madame Rojas the name of some tree expert who could<lb/>
estimate the age of the framboyant tree at the false site, and also that near the<lb/>
shacks near the quarry on the San Jose farm.</p>
<p>Par. 35: Please check this paragraph carefully, particulaly<lb/>
regarding the new and old names of the streets. Are the houses I mentioned made of<lb/>
cement?</p>
<p>Pars. 38, 39: Please amplify this as much as possible. What was<lb/>
your brother's name, what connection did he have with the U.S. Army or with Camp<lb/>
Columbia? How did he <unclear>come</unclear> to buy the property <unclear>around</unclear> Camp Columbia? Please verify<lb/>
the dates mentioned in this paragraph. I am most anxious to get accurately the real<lb/>
estate pedigree of this false camp site, that is, when did your brother buy it, when<lb/>
did the various previous owners buy it, and is there some official number and date<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03595002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
or designation of these deeds as reporded in the offices of the recorder of deeds,<lb/>
so that if you gave me a deed number, anybody could verify our statements? I would<lb/>
not think to ask you for this information except that you said you had been all over<lb/>
this many times.</p>
<p>Par. 53: Especially please check this paragraph carefully.<lb/>
Amplify as much as possible. When did you or your brother buy this from the Rojas<lb/>
family? What is the date and legal identification marks or number of the deed. When<lb/>
did you sell that part later used as a quarry, and to whom? When was the quarry begun<lb/>
and who was the owner of the quarry company? Might he have some old photographs of the<lb/>
land from time to time. What is the exact meaning of the word &ldquo;tojar&rdquo;?</p>
<p>Par. 54: Are my directions to reach the San Jose farm correct?</p>
<p>Par. 58: Please check this paragraph, also the last line in<lb/>
Par. 59.</p>
<p>Par. 67: Please check this description.</p>
<p>Par. 121: Please check.</p>
<p>Will you identify the building in Photograph Number<lb/>
Is it one of the units of the Military Hospital? I think it is. Is it the Fourth<lb/>
of September Clinic? Kissinger gave me a photograph of Columbia Barracks and told me<lb/>
that a photographer from Quemados took the photograph. Is there some old photographic<lb/>
company or photographer in Marianao or Quemados who might have been there forty years<lb/>
ago, or some more recent company which might have taken over the films of an older<lb/>
photographer.</p>
<p>I cannot tell you how sincerely I have appreciated all of your<lb/>
wonderful help. Without it, I could have learned very little of what I have learned,<lb/>
and I earnestly request your continued help. In order to save you labor, and<lb/>
in order to get from you as much detail as possible, permit me to ask you when you<lb/>
prepare to answer those questions, to make an appointment with Mrs. R. Hart Phillips,<lb/>
Manzana do Gomes, 553, Habana. She does stenographic work, helped me while I was in<lb/>
Havana, and knows what we are trying to do. I am sure she will either meet you at<lb/>
your office, or perhaps it will be easier for you to meet her at hers. She will sub-<lb/>
mit your answers to you for your final correction and then send them to me, and I am<lb/>
only too glad to pay the expense.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
