<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03596001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Carlos E. Finlay, August 26, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03596001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Finlay, Carlos E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-26">August 26, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03596001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Carlos E. Finlay, August 26, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests permission to see a copy of Finlay's biography of his father. Hench inquires about Carlos J. Finlay's activities and papers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Carlos E. Finlay, August 26, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03596001"/>
<opener>
Copy to Mr Phillips (to show Moran)<lb/>
sent him snapshot of himself &amp; grandson.<lb/>
3/6/41 - Sent hand letter,<lb/>
<unclear>Me Post</unclear>, come etc<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-26">August 26, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Carlos E. Finlay<lb/>
25 #1057<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Finlay:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You will remember that I visited Havana in April, in preparation for<lb/>
an address which I have been asked to make at the dedication of the Lazear Memorial on<lb/>
October 26, in Washington, Pennsylvania. You were very kind, indeed, to meet Mr. Moran and<lb/>
me and to show us some of the souvenirs of your father's work. You will remember also that<lb/>
Mr. Moran and I believe that Camp Lazear has been falsely located, and I have been collecting<lb/>
documentary evidence to show that the camp was on the San Jose farm of Senora Maria Teresa<lb/>
Loma viuda de Rojas. His Excellency, Dr. Ramos, has asked me to submit my data to him.<lb/>
In preparation for this report, and also my address, I would appreciate it greatly if you<lb/>
could give me a little information.</p>
<p>I believe that you admitted to Mr. Moran and to me that you did not<lb/>
think that Camp Lazear as now marked was ever the real camp. I shall appreciate it greatly<lb/>
if you would tell me why you think so. Did your father ever tell you about visiting the<lb/>
camp and where it was? I believe that the place they have marked as &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; is<lb/>
where they brought the victims of experimental yellow fever, and cared for them in a special<lb/>
tent hospital in the rear of Columbia Barracks.</p>
<p>I was most interested to know of the manuscript which you were pub-<lb/>
lishing about the life of your father. You told me it would be published this Fall in New<lb/>
York, and I will most certainly buy a copy. But I am afraid this material will not be<lb/>
available for the preparation of my address at Washington. You said that you had an extra<lb/>
copy of your manuscript which I might borrow. I am most anxious to present to the American<lb/>
audience the view that I learned in Cuba <del><unclear>and</unclear></del><add>as</add> to the extent of your father's work. It is<lb/>
the American view that your father was entirely correct in his theory but unable to produce<lb/>
a single case of experimental yellow fever within the limits later learned to be necessary<lb/>
for inoculation and incubation. Would you be willing to trust this manuscript to the mails,<lb/>
sending it to me by registered insured post? I can assure you that I will take care of it<lb/>
most carefully and return it to you as promptly as I can, also by registered insured mail.</p>
<p>One more question: Do you know the exact date in August, 1900, when<lb/>
Major Reed called on your father for the larvae and his reprints? Do you know just which<lb/>
members of the Commission called on him, I believe it was the first week of August, 1900?<lb/>
Did your father have any letters or diaries that might give interesting and important in-<lb/>
formation as to his contributions to Dr. Reed?</p>
<p>Permit me to express to you my deep appreciation of whatever help you<lb/>
can give me in this matter. To save you the labor of answering this letter in long hand,<lb/>
if your secretary is too busy to handle the matter, would you permit me to ask Mrs. R. Hart<lb/>
Phillips, Manzana de Gomez, 553, who does secretarial work, to make an appointment at your<lb/>
convenience and take down your answers, submitting her material to you for your correction<lb/>
and signature. I shall be delighted to pay her charges.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
