<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t03597001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence [Walter L.] Reed, August 26, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03597001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.] </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-26">August 26, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03597001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence [Walter L.]Reed, August 26, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is searching for the original notes and memoranda by Walter Reed in Cuba and asks Reed if he knows the whereabouts of these items. Hench also is submitting evidence of Camp Lazear's exact location to the Cuban government, and any information Reed has would be invaluable.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence [Walter L.]  Reed, August 26, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03597001"/>
<opener>
3&sol;6&sol;41 - letter,<lb/>
<unclear>Mil. Post, come also</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-26">August 26, 1940</date>
</dateline><lb/>
General Walter L. Reed<lb/>
406 Winder Building<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Reed:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On October 26, Washington and Jefferson College at<lb/>
Washington, Pennsylvania, is dedicating the Lazear Memorial Building in<lb/>
honor of Dr. Lazear, who spen<del>d</del><add>t</add> two or three years at Washington and Jeffer-<lb/>
son before going to Johns Hopkins. The President of the college has asked<lb/>
me on this occasion to read a paper outlining the story of the conquest of<lb/>
yellow fever, and the wonderful work of your father and his colleagues.<lb/>
I have been working on this for several months and have visited General Kean<lb/>
in Washington, Mr. Moran in Havana, and Mr. Kissinger in Huntington, Indiana.<lb/>
You will remember that Kissinger and Moran were the first two to volunteer<lb/>
to your father for the experiments. I have also had some correspondence with<lb/>
General Truby.</p>
<p>When I was in Washington, General Kean told me your<lb/>
address, but unfortunately, I had to leave Washington that evening, and was<lb/>
unable to call on you to pay my respects.</p>
<p>When in Washington, I tried to locate in the Surgeon<lb/>
General's office, the original notes and memoranda that your father and the<lb/>
other members of the commission made in Havana, but nobody around the Surgeon<lb/>
General's office or the Army Museum seemed to know anything about them. Do<lb/>
you have any idea where these papers are? Do you have in your possession any<lb/>
notes or papers of your father pertaining to the yellow fever work, or old photo-<lb/>
graphs taken in Havana at the time? I shall be most grateful for this informa-<lb/>
tion and if you would be willing to let me do so, I should indeed like to have<lb/>
the opportunity of seeing them on some future visit to Washington.</p>
<p>I am particularly anxious to locate Mrs. Lazear, I understand<lb/>
that she is still living, somewhere in California, but I have been unable to find<lb/>
out where. Do you know whether any of Dr. Carroll's family still survive? I would<lb/>
be most grateful if you could either give us their addresses or call me what govern-<lb/>
mental agency might have their addresses.</p>
<p>You will be interested to know that the Cuban government has<lb/>
bought a property which they thought was the site of Camp Lazear. As I understand<lb/>
it, they have already collected quite a sum of money for a memorial building, and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03597002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
had planned, among other things, to erect a replica of Camp Lazear. Having<lb/>
studied the publis<add>hed</add> records very carefully it did not take me long to find<lb/>
that they had chosen the wrong site. To make a long story short, Mr. Moran and<lb/>
I finally found the true site of the Camp and the Cuban government has asked me<lb/>
to submit my documentary evidence so that they may re-establish the correct<lb/>
site. I shall be glad later to send you, should you wish to see it, a memorandum<lb/>
which I am preparing on these investigations and in connection with the preparation<lb/>
of this report to the Cuban government, any access to photographs or papers that<lb/>
you may have concerning the work of Camp Lazear would be extremely helpful.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
