<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03599004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo F. Ramos, August 28, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03599004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ramos, Domingo F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1</name>
<name type="hospital">Hospital Alfonso XIII</name>
<name type="hospital">General Calixtro Garcia Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-28">August 28, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03599004</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo F. Ramos, August 28, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench poses questions concerning the site of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-28">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo F. Ramos, August 28, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03599004"/>
<opener>
Copy to Moran<lb/>
" " <unclear>Mrs</unclear> Phillip<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-28">August 28, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Domingo Ramos<lb/>
Secretary of Defense<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Ramos:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You may remember that I visited Havana this April while doing<lb/>
some historical researches on the conquest of yellow fever. You will remember that I<lb/>
spent some time with Mr. Moran, one of the original survivors of the yellow fever ex-<lb/>
periments, and that we found evidence which made us believe that the site behind the<lb/>
Military City which has been temporarily memorialized as the site of Camp Lazear,<lb/>
was erroneously chosen. We found the true site of Camp Lazear on the San Jose farm<lb/>
of Senora Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas in Quemados. Senora Rojas is the widow of<lb/>
Dr. Rojas who loaned the farm to Dr. Agramonte and Major Reed. You asked me to<lb/>
submit to you and to the Cuban government documentary evidence supporting these opinions.<lb/>
I have collected considerable data since seeing you and am about ready to submit this<lb/>
evidence to you, with manuscripts and photographs. However, there was some data which<lb/>
I was unable to get when I was in Cuba, and I would be most grateful if you could help<lb/>
me obtain the following information.</p>
<p>Do you know when the original Camp Columbia, made up of tents,<lb/>
was erected and what was on this site before hand? When was Camp Columbia replaced by<lb/>
the wooden buildings of Columbia Barracks, and when was the latter torn down and replaced<lb/>
by the present Military City? Is there any written history of Columbia Barracks of<lb/>
Military City, and could I obtain a copy? Do you have any idea where I could obtain<lb/>
copies of the maps of Columbia Barracks, as of 1900?</p>
<p>Do you know how the boundaries of the present Military City compare<lb/>
with the old boundaries of Columbia Barracks? I am very anxious to obtain a photograph<lb/>
(post card, drawing, or aeroplane photograph) giving a general view of Military City.<lb/>
I should like to use this in my paper identifying the old location of Columbia Barracks.<lb/>
Can you tell me the area in acres or square miles now occupied by the Military City?</p>
<p>How many units of buildings comprize the present Military Hospital<lb/>
and when was the Fourth of September Clinic erected?</p>
<p>You remember the Alvare-Recio photograph which was used to identify<lb/>
the present memorialized site of Camp Lazear, contains a framboyant tree. We found a<lb/>
larger framboyant tree on the San Jose fram. I am anxious to obtain the name of a tree<lb/>
expert who either might visit these two trees or who will at least examine my photographs<lb/>
of them to give me an estimate of their ages. Could you give me the name of such a Cuban<lb/>
governmental tree expert in Havana?</p>
<p>May I call your attention to the fact that on the sign, now erected<lb/>
behind Military City, on the supposed site of Camp Lazear, the name of Dr. Lazear is given<lb/>
wrongly. It is spelled &ldquo;Jess&rdquo; where it should be &ldquo;Jesse&rdquo;.</p>
<p>When in Havana, I asked for several copies of your paper (&ldquo;Monuments<lb/>
to the memory of the heroes and martyrs in the struggle against yellow fever&rdquo; published in<lb/>
Informes, Vol. 2, No. 2, June, 1939. Your secretary was to send these to my hotel, but I<lb/>
never received them. I would appreciate it greatly if you would send me several copies.</p>
<p>May I ask whether the National Hospital of the Cuban army has yet been<lb/>
named for Dr. Agramonte as you suggested and has any monument yet been erected to Dr. Carroll<unclear>:</unclear><lb/>
What plans have been made for the Lazear Memorial or for the erection of a replica of Camp<lb/>
Lazear?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03599005"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Can you tell me when the supposed site of Camp Lazear, behind ghe<lb/>
Military City by the railroad track, was purchased by the government, and when was the<lb/>
sign erected?</p>
<p>Could you ask your secretary to send me, if possible, a copy of<lb/>
Sanidad y Beneficiencia, Havana, Ano <unclear>%l</unclear>, April, 1909, which contains a paper by Dr.<lb/>
Agramonte, published in English. I am most anxious to have this and do not know how<lb/>
otherwise to obtain it.</p>
<p>Received 10/14/40</p>
<p>I understand that the Cuban government is publishing a booklet<lb/>
on the life and work of Dr. Finlay, to be published in several languages. I am most<lb/>
anxious to have a copy as I wish very much to present, not only in my address on the<lb/>
occasion of the dedication of the Lazear Memorial Building at Washington and Jefferson<lb/>
College, but also in my publications to acquaint Americans more with the work of<lb/>
Dr. Finlay.</p>
<p>Do you have any idea where I can obtain a photograph of the old<lb/>
Military Hospital No. 1 where Dr. Agramonte first did his work? This was on Principe<lb/>
Hill, and I have been led to understand it was formerly the hospital Alfonso XIII<lb/>
and was later torn down, to be replaced by the General Calixtro Garcia Hospital.</p>
<p>Knowing how busy you are, I hesitate very greatly to bother you<lb/>
with this letter and these questions, but I do not know from whom I can obtain this<lb/>
information as well as from you, because of your great interest in the monuments of<lb/>
the yellow fever workers. Permit me to express my deep appreciation for your help,<lb/>
and I am sure that this help will be greatly appreciated by the President of Washington<lb/>
and Jefferson and also by the officials of the U.S. Army Medical Museum in Washington<lb/>
who have asked me to send them a copy of my formal report which I will send to you later.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
