<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03590001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, August 16, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03590001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="person">Michie, Robert E. Lee</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar Del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">General Garcia Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-16">August 16, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03590001</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, August 16, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] requests corrections to a manuscript and answers to specific questions.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-16">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, August 16, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03590001"/>
<opener>
Copy <add>sent</add> to Mrs Phillips<lb/>
Also sent to Moran<lb/>
Photos 1-2-3-5-6-7b-8b-9-10-11a-12a-13a-14-<lb/>
16a-17b-18-19-20-48-53.<lb/>
Also copies of letters to Dr Juan Castro, Supt Garcia Harp, <del>Beato</del>,<lb/>
<unclear>Alvare</unclear> - <unclear>Albertini</unclear> - Miranda &amp;<lb/>
Mrs Phillips - Ramos - Rojas II<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-16">August 16, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Herewith I send you a rather extensive memorandum made from notes<lb/>
and memory. It may be wrong in spots and I am most anxious to have you check<lb/>
every detail as carefully as you can. I have only had four or five copies made.<lb/>
One I am sending to Dr. Hutchison, president of Washington and Jefferson College,<lb/>
one to General Kean, one to General Truby, whom I have contacted, one to Mr.<lb/>
Pogolotti and one to Senora Rojas. As you will see, it is confidential. Some of<lb/>
it will never be used for publication but merely as background information. From<lb/>
this data, with additions from elsewhere, I will make my report to Dr. Ramos and<lb/>
the Cuban government, and my paper for the Lazear Memorial dedication. If, in any<lb/>
place, you see errors or misrepresentations of any sort, I will be only too grateful<lb/>
for your full and thorough criticism, and since you cannot possibly take the trouble<lb/>
to type your own answers, I will appreciate it greatly if you would get in touch<lb/>
with Mrs. Phillips and at your mutual convenience, dictate to her as fulsomely<lb/>
as you desire, whatever comes to your mind. I am writing her, asking her to act<lb/>
as my agent in this matter, not only regarding your reply, but the replies of Mr.<lb/>
Pogolotti and Senor Rojas. As my copies are limited, and I don't want them to get<lb/>
out, would you please lend yours to Mrs. Phillips that she may read it over and<lb/>
understand our problem before she gets in touch with Mr. Pogolotti and Senora<lb/>
Rojas? This arrangement is not just to spare you, but I can assure you it is partly<lb/>
selfish, as I want as detailed information as possible and think this is the best<lb/>
way to get it. I hope you do not feel that it was indiscreet for me to let Mr.<lb/>
Pogolotti and Senora Rojas, two Cubans, see these remarks. I am, of course, writing<lb/>
them that my notes are confidential and asking for whatever corrections they see fit<lb/>
to make.</p>
<p>Now as to some specific questions.</p>
<p>Paragraph 6: I still haven't found out what year the tent camp, that<lb/>
is, Camp Columbia, was erected, what year it was replaced by the wooden buildings<lb/>
of Columbia Barracks and when in turn they were torn down in favor of the present<lb/>
Military City. I am also anxious to know what the site of Camp Columbia was used for<lb/>
before it was used for that purpose. Do you have any idea where I can find these<lb/>
things out? Perhaps Dr. Beato whom we met would be willing to help us on this.</p>
<p>Paragraph 7: What is the relationship between Quemados and Marianao?<lb/>
Is the one merely a section of the latter? Is there one mayor or two? Perhaps the<lb/>
mayor would know of some local historian who could find me some 1900 maps of Quemados.<lb/>
They certainly must be in existence, in a library or some place. Please give me in<lb/>
writing information as to just where Military Hospital No. 1 was on Principe Hill.<lb/>
My recollection is that you told me it was where the General Garcia Hospital now is.<lb/>
Is this the same as the University Hospital? Was the former name of Military Hospital<lb/>
the Hospital Alfonso XIII, as indicated in my paragraph 107?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03590002"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>I wonder whether the Superintendent of this hospital could give<lb/>
me reference to some historical paper or booklet concerning the hospital, and whether<lb/>
he could tell me where I could find some old photograph of Military Hospital #1.</p>
<p>Paragraph 8: I have been unable to find any photographs of the post<lb/>
hospital at Columbia Barracks, particularly of the officers' quarters there. Will<lb/>
you in your own handwriting identify the buildings in the photograph which Kissinger<lb/>
gave me? This photograph presumably was of Columbia Barracks. Photo. # 9 &amp; 10</p>
<p>Paragraph 9: Do you know any details about the epidemic at Pinar<lb/>
Del Rio? What were the relationships, rank and position of Dr. Cooke, Captain<lb/>
Godfrey and Major Michie at Pinar?</p>
<p>Paragraph 14: Do you have any dope on this? Do you know where<lb/>
Carroll was treated and where he convalesced? Was this at the post hospital at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks?</p>
<p>Paragraphs 15 and 16: I wish you would dictate more specifically<lb/>
your understanding regarding the inaccuracy of the official version of Lazear's<lb/>
illness and the possibly true version which you mentioned to me and which has<lb/>
since been amplified by Miss Agramonte and Generals Kean and Truby. Did Dr. Lazear<lb/>
die in the post hospital at Columbia Barracks? Where was he buried? I understand<lb/>
he was buried right near Camp Columbia. When and where <del>the</del> the body re-interred and<lb/>
do you know where he is now buried.</p>
<p>Paragraph 22: Please give me your recollection as to the 11 soldiers<lb/>
who went into residence at Camp Lazear on Nov. 20? Who was the exact personnel of<lb/>
the camp?</p>
<p>Paragraph 23: The Infected Clothing Bldg. was ready for occupancy<lb/>
Nov. 30. Do you know when this building was begun? Do you know whether any of<lb/>
the nurses who took care of you and other experimental cases are still living?</p>
<p>Paragraph 27: The Infected Mosquito Bldg. No. 2 was ready for<lb/>
occupancy Dec. 21. Do you know when its building was begun? I think it was Dec. 1.<lb/>
Who were the two volunteers who slept for 18 nights in the mosquito-free side of<lb/>
the Infected Mosquito Bldg.</p>
<p>Paragraph 28: What was the arrangement whereby you were inoculated<lb/>
with infected blood after your experimental illness? Who did this and where was<lb/>
it done? And did they bring the blood from Las Animas Hospital?</p>
<p>Paragraph 29: Did you hear anything about the disbanding of the camp<lb/>
and whether the wooden buildings were torn down? You recall Senora Rojas told us<lb/>
they were. Had you heard this at the time? Do you recall that you could see any<lb/>
hilly country from Camp Lazear? You remember as we walked further away from Real<lb/>
Street beyond the quarry, the country or rather the view of the country was quite<lb/>
hilly. As no hills appear in any photographs of Camp Lazear, I think the camp<lb/>
must have been much nearer Real Street than the end of the old quarry. Do you<lb/>
remember from your own personal knowledge, the relationship of the camp to the Rojas<lb/>
farm house, its distance or direction, and do you think that the buildings <add>in the background.</add> on the right<lb/>
side of Photo. No. 16 might have been connected with the Rojas farm buildings?</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03590003"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>Paragraph 32: Are my directions as to how to get to the false Camp<lb/>
Lazear correct? Approximately how large is the territory covered by the Military<lb/>
City? I am hoping Dr. Ramos can get me an old map of Camp Columbia and Columbia<lb/>
Barracks, to compare its position and size with the present Military City. Am I<lb/>
right about Calzada a los Quemados? How many units are there to the present hospital<lb/>
Militar de Columbia? When was the Fourth of September Clinic erected? On one of<lb/>
my pencil sketches made on our way from the false camp site, I infer that we went<lb/>
down a &ldquo;Boquetta Road&rdquo; but this is unmarked on the maps. My recollection is that we<lb/>
asked the name of the road we were traversing and you were told this name from one of<lb/>
the local residents. But the maps indicate that one should go directly down Santa<lb/>
Rosa Street to meet the railroad track. What is the relationship between Boquetta<lb/>
Road and Santa Rosa Street and where should Boquetta Road be on the map? What does<lb/>
&ldquo;Linea Para <unclear>Rero</unclear>&rdquo; mean? I have also asked Senora Rojas if they knew of some governmenta<lb/>
tree expert who could visit the tree at the false site or look at our photographs of<lb/>
this tree and tell us whether it is forty years old or not, and also possibly the age<lb/>
of rhe framboyant and other trees hear the shacks beside the quarry near the true<lb/>
site of Camp Lazear. I don't want you all to be hunting for an expert, but you might<lb/>
collaborate on this point.</p>
<p>Photo 6<lb/>
Reports<lb/>
Pogolotti</p>
<p>Paragraphs 41 and 42: I am anxious to have your reaction to these.</p>
<p>Paragraph 53: I am asking Mr. Pogolotti and Senora Rojas to help on<lb/>
this. What is the exact meaning of the words Tejar, finca <del>et</del><add>and</add> Quinta? Are my directions<lb/>
to reach the finca San Jose correct?</p>
<p>Paragraphs 59 to 67: I am asking Senora Rojas to check and amplify<lb/>
these paragraphs as much as possible, but would appreciate your help too. Of<lb/>
crucial importance is to have Senora Rojas mark in ink or pencil on (Map) <del>No.</del> Photos 1 &amp; 2<lb/>
her exact recollection of where Camp Lazear was in relation to the present quarry,<lb/>
land and buildings. If you could see fit to accompany Mrs. Phillips when she<lb/>
visits Senora Rojas, this might help tremendously, particularly in this point, and<lb/>
I hope you will check her answer with my statements in Paras. 65 and 67. I am also<lb/>
asking them who owns the quarry now, in the hope that the owner may have some old<lb/>
photographs of the land before the quarries were begun.</p>
<p>Paragraph 86: Will you identify our meeting place?</p>
<p>Paragraphs 101 to 104: I want your reaction.</p>
<p>Paragraphs 115 to 116: I am anxious to have you check these.</p>
<p>Paragraphs 118: I want your opinion on this especially.</p>
<p>I assume you still have the wood. At least, I hope <unclear>so.</unclear> I have written<lb/>
the Dept. of Agriculture here, asking if they will admit this wood, as it now is,<lb/>
or whether I will have to have it already made into gavels, pen holders, etc.<lb/>
I have never heard from the wood carver that we visited next to the (was it the<lb/>
Paris) Restaurant. He was going to let us know whether he could have the wood dried<lb/>
and was going to give me an idea what objects he could made and at what cost. I<lb/>
do not believe I have his address, and I am somewhat concerned as the time is getting<lb/>
short if we are going to have something made before October. I have asked Madam<lb/>
Rojas' permission to obtain a limb from a tree nearest the true site of Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>Can you identify the building in Photo. No. 48 as the Fourth of Sept.<lb/>
Clinic? I cannot tell you how much I appreciate your wonderful helpin all this.<lb/>
But after all, you are partly to blame as you got me so much further involved in this<lb/>
interesting story than I had ever intended. Let me thank you a thousand times for this<lb/>
help.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
