<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03606001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Ralph Cooper Hutchison] to Philip Showalter Hench, September 7, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03606001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Pew, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Barker, Lewellys Franklin</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Hough, Neva Pauline</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-07">September 7, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03606001</idno>
<title>Letter from [Ralph Cooper Hutchison] to Philip Showalter Hench, September 7, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hutchison] gives Hench details on the upcoming exercises honoring Lazear at Washington and Jefferson College.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-07">
<head>Letter from [Ralph Cooper Hutchison] to Philip Showalter Hench, September 7, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03606001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
THE PRESIDENT'S OFFICE<lb/>
WASHINGTON AND JEFFERSON COLLEGE<lb/>
WASHINGTON, PENNSYLVANIA<lb/>
<date value="1940-09-07">September 7, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Phil:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am just back from our vacation and in the<lb/>
grand pile-up which we always have at this time of<lb/>
year, but I am anxious to get some word to you. I find<lb/>
two of your letters here and I particularly want to thank<lb/>
you for the gift of two hundred dollars to take care<lb/>
of the expenses of Mr. Moran, or to use otherwise as<lb/>
necessary. I tried to get a date with Mr. Pew for<lb/>
Saturday when I will be in Philadelphia, but he could not<lb/>
see me and I've got to try and get him some time a week<lb/>
later and will do so. If he should be willing to pay<lb/>
the expenses of Moran, what would you think of our using<lb/>
the money which you sent, or rather a portion of it, for<lb/>
the expenses of Kissinger? I will discuss with you<lb/>
later the use of the balance. For the moment I want to<lb/>
express our very deep and sincere gratitude for this gift.<lb/>
It helps us out tremendously. We had hard luck last year<lb/>
and went about five thousand in the hole and will have a<lb/>
very stringent budget this year. Therefore gifts at this<lb/>
time for such expenses mean a tremendous amount to us<lb/>
and to me personally as you can know. My deepest thanks<lb/>
to you.</p>
<p>Miss Hough has been working on the pictures<lb/>
which you requested and has them ready and we are sending<lb/>
them along now.</p>
<p>You will recall my writing to you about this<lb/>
Doctor Barker of Baltimore who knew a good deal about<lb/>
Lazear. I wrote him a letter and I think I sent you a<lb/>
carbon. I have received a letter from him containing<lb/>
quantities of information and I have had a copy made for<lb/>
you which I enclose herewith.</p>
<p>I take it that you are straightened out in<lb/>
regard to Doctor Lazear's course here. It was a curious<lb/>
thing that he took a Bachelor's Degree at Hopkins after<lb/>
leaving here and I do not know why that was done or how<lb/>
it happened. It is a point, however, which has no<lb/>
particular bearing and I wouldn't bother with it when you<lb/>
are here unless it appeals to you for some reason. There<lb/>
was no question about his doing his college work here.<lb/>
Apparently he was born in Baltimore and his family was<lb/>
from there and somehow they got into the Pittsburgh area<lb/>
before he went to college. We ran onto a paragraph<lb/>
concerning him this summer in a book about old Baltimore.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03606002"/>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
September 6, 1940<lb/>
The paragraph is somewhat inaccurate but it gives a little<lb/>
more light upon him. I will send you a copy of that.</p>
<p>There are a number of details to take up with<lb/>
you later as I get to them, but for the moment I think<lb/>
of one more thing on which you might be working. In as much<lb/>
as you are receiving an honorary degree at the exercises<lb/>
on Friday morning, October the twenty-sixth, we would<lb/>
like very much to send formal invitations to those exercises<lb/>
to a list of your friends and relatives. The regular<lb/>
invitation will go to them and in it will be a slip saying<lb/>
that they are receiving the invitation because you are<lb/>
receiving an honorary degree. Work up your list and send<lb/>
it in as soon as convenient.</p>
<p>Naturally, Mr. Moran has not answered the letter<lb/>
which I gave to you to carry to him. Should I not write<lb/>
him again now and repeat the invitation officially for him<lb/>
to come here? The question of what recognition or honor<lb/>
we can give to these men if they come has not been cleared,<lb/>
even in my own mind, but I think we will make it very nice<lb/>
for them no matter how it is done.</p>
<p>Hope everything is well at your house. Please<lb/>
give my love to Mary and to the children, and we are looking<lb/>
forward to Founders' Day which will be memorable for me<lb/>
because of you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
RCH/M<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

