<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03606003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, September 9, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03606003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Pew, J. Howard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="place">Jefferson Medical School, Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-09">September 9, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03606003</idno>
<title>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, September 9, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hutchison gives Hench details on the upcoming exercises honoring Lazear at Washington and Jefferson College, and discusses Hench's presentation. He encloses a list of addresses.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-09">
<head>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, September 9, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03606003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
THE PRESIDENT'S OFFICE<lb/>
WASHINGTON AND JEFFERSON COLLEGE<lb/>
WASHINGTON, PENNSYLVANIA<lb/>
<date value="1940-09-09">September 9, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Phil:</salute>
</opener>
<p>This is supplementary to my letter of a day or<lb/>
two ago since which time I have received your communica-<lb/>
tion with the pictures and the notes. I have read the<lb/>
notes through with intense interest. You have done an<lb/>
enormous amount of work and it is all most interesting.<lb/>
Your great problem will be that of reducing it to a<lb/>
popular address.</p>
<p>The first thing of importance I want to say is<lb/>
that the trustees have changed the plans and I am<lb/>
authorized to invite you to give your talk at the Home-<lb/>
coming Dinner on Saturday night, October the twenty-sixth,<lb/>
instead of at the play the evening before. We believe<lb/>
that the play will not be a good place for speaking, and<lb/>
by making you the speaker of the evening at the dinner<lb/>
it will give you a good opportunity. There will be a<lb/>
couple of hundred or maybe three hundred people at the<lb/>
dinner, it is the biggest dinner of the year here and you<lb/>
and I will be the speakers, you making the main address,<lb/>
and I finishing up with a short address on the college.<lb/>
You should take about twenty minutes if you can condense<lb/>
your material to put it across in that time. If you use<lb/>
the stereopticon or moving pictures, it will take a little<lb/>
more time of course for those, but the twenty minutes<lb/>
would apply to the speaking. I am just explaining this<lb/>
in order to suggest the kind of program which we have in<lb/>
mind. In regard to the pictures, I will not take any now.<lb/>
The Chemistry Building is not enough finished so that I can<lb/>
tell where or how we can use them. I think we had better<lb/>
leave that until after the occasion and after your use of<lb/>
the pictures has shown which ones are the most interesting.</p>
<p>In regard to the publication of the story,<lb/>
we do not have any W and J journal which would be substantial<lb/>
enough to carry the detailed story which you should write.<lb/>
I believe it would go better in some medical magazine<lb/>
as your notes suggest, and I think you feel the same way.</p>
<p>You talk then would not be on yellow fever<lb/>
primarily, but on Lazear, and only incidentally on yellow<lb/>
fever. Doctor Sawyer will make the address in the morning<lb/>
and will deal undoubtedly with the yellow fever in a general<lb/>
way. I do not think that you need to worry about getting<lb/>
into his territory if you stay by Lazear.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03606004"/>
<p>Doctor Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>September 9, 1940</p>
<p>The fact that Doctor Finley graduated from<lb/>
Jefferson Medical School in Philadelphia (if that's<lb/>
what you mean) does give us a certain connection.<lb/>
When Jefferson Medical School was founded, they could<lb/>
not secure a charter and they therefore applied to<lb/>
Jefferson College in Canonsburg to grant their degrees<lb/>
for them which it did for a number of years. Jefferson<lb/>
College was therefore instrumental and of assistance in<lb/>
the founding of Jefferson Medical School, a relationship<lb/>
of which we have been proud. In the same way, the<lb/>
Baltimore School of Physicians and Surgeons was founded<lb/>
by Washington College.</p>
<p>I am surprised to have your note of August<lb/>
fifteenth stating that you are still looking for the<lb/>
address of Mrs. Lazear. I am sure I sent it to you before<lb/>
that but I will enclose it herewith.</p>
<p>The trustees have decided, in view of your<lb/>
generous gift and the possibility that Mr. Pew may be<lb/>
induced to pay the way of Moran - to invite both Kissinger<lb/>
and Moran. I do not think we ought to invite Finlay's<lb/>
son. In the first place we have as many people as we can<lb/>
take care of, and in the second place this is a<lb/>
glorification of Lazear and not Finley.</p>
<p>I will write the letter which you suggest<lb/>
immediately to all of these people, excepting Moran,<lb/>
to whom I wish to add some other things, and who is already<lb/>
co-operating with you to the fullest extent. I still<lb/>
think it is wiser for me to see Mr. Pew than to write him<lb/>
and am planning to make a special trip to Philadelphia<lb/>
for that purpose in the next week or so.</p>
<p>Of course we are expecting Mary to be here with<lb/>
you<unclear>!</unclear></p>
<p>I will be adding more later.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Hutch</signed>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
RCH/M<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1940-09-00">
<head>Addresses for Doctor Hench, [September, 1940]</head>
<pb n="3" id="f03606005"/>
<p>WASHINGTON AND JEFFERSON COLLEGE</p>
<p><hi>ADDRESSES FOR DOCTOR HENCH</hi></p>
<p>PRESIDENT'S OFFICE<lb/>
MEMORANDUM</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mrs. Jesse W. Lazear<lb/>
116 East Padre Street<lb/>
Santa Barbara, California</item>
<item>Mr. William Huston Lazear (Son)<lb/>
1325 Fifteenth Street<lb/>
Sacramento, California</item>
<item>Mrs. W. D. Briggs (Daughter)<lb/>
106 The Uplands<lb/>
Berkeley, California</item>
<item>Mr. John M. Lazear (Cousin)<lb/>
3125 Preble Avenue<lb/>
Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania</item>
<item>Miss Frances B. Seth (Cousin)<lb/>
Windsor Mill Road<lb/>
At Gwynn's Falls Bridge<lb/>
Woodlawn P.O., Baltimore</item>
<item>Mrs. Charles P. Orr (Cousin)<lb/>
6101 Howe Street<lb/>
Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania</item>
<item>Mrs. Sidney Coe Howard<lb/>
157 East 82nd Street<lb/>
New York City</item>
</list></p>
<p>N. P. H.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
