<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03601009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Mrs. R. Hart Phillips, August 28, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03601009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Phillips, R. Hart</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-28">August 28, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03601009</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Mrs. R. Hart Phillips, August 28, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] seeks further help from Mrs. Phillips in acquiring detailed information on the location of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-28">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Mrs. R. Hart Phillips, August 28, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03601009"/>
<opener>
also copies of letter to<lb/>
Moran<lb/>
Finlay - to show Moran<lb/>
Beato -<lb/>
Angles<lb/>
Pogoloth - to Show Moran<lb/>
Rodriguez - Leon - " " "<lb/>
Ramos<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-28">August 28, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. R. Hart Phillips<lb/>
Manzana de Gomez, 553<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Phillips:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I remember with appreciation the services you were able to render<lb/>
me on my recent trip to Cuba on the historical researches in connection with yellow<lb/>
fever. May I call upon your further services? I need considerable help, and hope indeed<lb/>
that you, already knowing considerable of what I am trying to do, can help me further.<lb/>
I am trying to obtain documentary evidence from several individuals in Havana. I am<lb/>
enclosing carbon copies of my letters to them which will explain my desires. I am sure<lb/>
it would be useless for me to hope to get any real information if these individuals<lb/>
were to write me long hand, and if possible, I am anxious that you shall act for me<lb/>
not only merely in the capacity of a secretary, but in the capacity of a strenuous<lb/>
questioner and a hard-boiled taskmaster: If, for some reason, you cannot interview<lb/>
these persons yourself, I would appreciate it if you would obtain the services of a<lb/>
reliable secretary and supervise the job in a general way with the help of Mr. Moran.<lb/>
May I suggest that you wait a few days after receiving this letter in the hope that<lb/>
some of these persons will spontaneously telephone you for an appointment to answer<lb/>
these questions. But if they do not do so rather promptly, I would appreciate it<lb/>
greatly if you would telephone them very diplomatically and offer your services as my<lb/>
agent. I hope that they will come to your office, but if this does not seem feasible,<lb/>
please make a memorandum of whatever taxicab expenses you have, and I shall be only too<lb/>
glad to reimburse you, and pay your regular secretarial charges.</p>
<p>Naturally, the two most important statements are those Senora<lb/>
Rojas and from Dr. Agramonte's daughter, Senora Rodriguez Leon. May I hope that, being<lb/>
a woman, you will exert a woman's wiles and make these good ladies talk in as detailed<lb/>
a fashion as possible. I suspect that it might be much easier for you and for your<lb/>
interviewers if Mr. Moran could at least go with you to visit Senora Rojas and Senora<lb/>
Rodriguez Leon. He may be able to ask, at the appropriate time, some pertinent questions<lb/>
or correct some statements, or make some leading inquiries which will help greatly. I<lb/>
am sending him a carbon of this letter.</p>
<p>Of course, the most important thing of all is to have Senora Rojas<lb/>
draw on a map which I am sending her, as accurately as possible her recollection of the<lb/>
situation and general size of Camp Lazear. Will you or Mr. Moran particularly get her<lb/>
to do this and authenticate her identification perhaps by citing on the photograph in her<lb/>
own handwriting something as follows: &ldquo;This is where the experimental camp (Camp Lazear)<lb/>
used by the U.S. Army physicians in 1900, was located on our San Jose farm.&rdquo; Signed---etc.<lb/>
(or words to that effect).</p>
<p>I have sent Mr. Moran quite a memorandum which I will ask him to let<lb/>
you read after he has read it. I do not have enough copies to send you one also. This<lb/>
will help you greatly in the interviews and I am sure that you will consider it confidential<lb/>
and realize that if I have been too frank or been in any way unfair to any individual or<lb/>
to the Cuban government in general, that this will be straightened out before any publica-<lb/>
tions are forthcoming. I cannot tell you how much I appreciate your great help in this matter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
