<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03606006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, September 13, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03606006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, Elida</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Hough, Neva Pauline</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Pew, J. Howard</name>
<name type="person">Barker, Lewellys Franklin</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-13">September 13, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03606006</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, September 13, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] inquires about Lazear's college career. He discusses a possible guest list for the Lazear Building dedication ceremony.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-13">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, September 13, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03606006"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-09-13">September 13, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Hutch:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I shall answer much of your letter personally but hasten to answer<lb/>
at least part here. If Pew comes across, you are at liberty to use the $200.00 in<lb/>
any way you wish and I think it would be nice indeed to send part of it to Kissinger.<lb/>
I should not think you would be expected to pay the expenses of either Moran's wife<lb/>
or Kissinger's wife. They have enough money to do that.</p>
<p>Please thank Miss Hough greatly for the photographs. I am placing<lb/>
them in interested hands, and while I am not asking for any money for the memorial,<lb/>
it may occur to them that they may wish to take part.</p>
<p>I am not completely straightened out on the matter of Lazear's<lb/>
course at W. and J. Did he take his Bachelor's Degree at W. and J. and also take another<lb/>
one at Hopkins? I agree with you that it isn't necessary to stress his leaving W. and<lb/>
J. and I will merely say that he later did work at Hopkins and Columbia. I am glad to<lb/>
have Barker's letter. Most of this I knew and have already read most of his articles.</p>
<p>I still haven't located Mrs. Reed. I thought she was dead but that<lb/>
her daughter was living. General Kean just wrote me that he had written to her and I<lb/>
am asking for her address. Thank you for sending me Mrs. Lazear's address. I have<lb/>
been trying to get it, without success, and did not know that you knew it.</p>
<p>Aside from Mrs. Lazear, and perhaps Walter Reed's son and daughter,<lb/>
the five persons most concerned with the yellow fever experiments in this country are<lb/>
Moran, Kissinger, General Truby of San Francisco (who was the officer in charge of<lb/>
the hospital at Columbia Barracks, who was present at Lazear's death and who took from<lb/>
his coat the precious note book concerning his experiments), General Kean, who was<lb/>
Reed's friend, and Dr. Cooke. Whether you wish to invite Kean, Truby and Cook, I do<lb/>
not know. I should assume that they are men of sufficient means to pay their own way.<lb/>
Doubtless, they would at least appreciate the information. If you are honoring Moran<lb/>
and Kissinger, perhaps Dr. Cooke should come in for similar honor. While Moran and<lb/>
Kissinger accepted the experimental bites and developed experimental yellow fever, it was<lb/>
Dr. Cooke who sat, with two other volunteers, in the foul, Infected Clothing Building<lb/>
(see my memorandum). So putrid were the surroundings that on their first attempt, they<lb/>
had to rush out, and one of the volunteers actually vomited. They slept surrounded by<lb/>
the bloody and soiled effects of the dead, and according to the popular notion, thoroughly<lb/>
expected to get yellow fever. The fact that they did not was not their fault and<lb/>
destroyed the popular notion. Dr. Cooke still lives modestly at Lexington, Virginia.<lb/>
I have just heard from him and he will help me in any way possible in writing the story.<lb/>
These three alone never received pay for their contribution. All the rest did. I have<lb/>
no doubt that Cooke would be delighted to be invited.</p>
<p>I hope you are writing Moran so that he can plan to be there and I<lb/>
hope that Pew comes across. I hear from General Kean that Moran is to be the guest of<lb/>
honor at a dinner given by the medical faculty of the University of Virginia on October 24.<lb/>
I more or less instigated this when I was in Charlottesville last Spring.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
