<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03603002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, September 10, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03603002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-10">September 10, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03603002</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, September 10, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby criticizes some members of the Yellow Fever Commission for seeking undue credit. He verifies that his source of information on Lazear's death was Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-10">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, September 10, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03603002"/>
<opener>
<hi>CONFIDENTIAL</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-09-10">September 10, 1940.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. P. S. Hench,<lb/>
102 - 110 Second Avenue,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your memorandum and yesterday morning your air mail<lb/>
letter arrived. It will take me several days to work up the<lb/>
information you have asked for, but I will do it as expeditiously as<lb/>
possible.</p>
<p>During August I had my article typed and a week ago sent it<lb/>
on to General Kean who will go over it with General Ireland and others.<lb/>
It contains information which has never been published and there is a<lb/>
grave question as to whether or not it should be. You see Agramonte<lb/>
was not an active member of the Board. He did independent work in<lb/>
his laboratory on the <unclear>Sanarelli</unclear> organism and Reed did use that to<lb/>
supplement the results obtained by himself and Carroll. After that,<lb/>
Agramonte was fully engaged in the work of the Department Laboratory and<lb/>
Reed for that reason, and possibly for others, did not assign him to<lb/>
any duties with the board but intended to use him for making autopsies.<lb/>
However, no deaths occurred at Camp Lazear as you know.</p>
<p>Agramonte did not publish anything that I know of, about his<lb/>
work with the board, until after Carroll's death. Then he made the<lb/>
statement on PP. 25-26 of the Senate Document (822) and later published<lb/>
an article in the Scientific Monthly (1915). There are several people<lb/>
still living who know (because they were there) that Agramonte deviated<lb/>
widely from the truth. Now the question is, shall the facts be brought<lb/>
out? My article will never be published unless and until Kean and others<lb/>
can verify every controversial point.</p>
<p>In your article you have quoted Agramonte very freely or at<lb/>
least have used many of his statements. In view of what may happen, I<lb/>
suggest that you show that it (each item) was taken from one of<lb/>
Agramonte's articles.</p>
<p>I also suggest that you read what General Wood and dear old<lb/>
&ldquo;Popsie&rdquo; Welch said, after Reed's death, on p.20 of the Senate Document.<lb/>
- 1 -<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03603003"/>
They knew the facts and they also anticipated that others would claim<lb/>
much of the credit which rightly belonged to Reed.</p>
<p>It is only because of the urgent desire of prominent medical<lb/>
men that I have worked up my story of this unfortunate mess. Agramonte<lb/>
was not the only one who tried to add to their individual glory at the<lb/>
expense of Reed. Carroll was a mild offender although he owed everything<lb/>
to Reed and really was devoted to him. Friends and relatives of Gorgas, too,<lb/>
(not Gorgas himself) made unscrupulous efforts in this direction. Of<lb/>
course you know all about Finlay and what the Cubans claim for him. I<lb/>
wonder whether you have ever read the Editorial in &ldquo;The Military Surgeon&rdquo;<lb/>
for March, 1925? If not get it and I am sure you will enjoy a well written<lb/>
review of the life of General Gorgas. It is a masterpiece!</p>
<p>I have given you the above information because I realize how<lb/>
much work you have done in preparing your memorandum. It is evident that<lb/>
you have become intensely interested and should know the facts. Please<lb/>
remember that it is all strictly confidential. I will send General Kean<lb/>
a copy for his information so he will know that I have told you this<lb/>
inside &ldquo;dope&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Now to answer your question<del>s</del> in the air mail letter. &ldquo;Do you<lb/>
mean that Major Reed told you these facts himself?&rdquo; Yes. Please read<lb/>
carefully the typed extracts from my article near the bottom of page two<lb/>
stating that &ldquo;Reed was rather cautious in discussing this aspect of<lb/>
Lazear's case but he did confide in Kean and me&rdquo;, etc. He evidently did<lb/>
discuss it with Agramonte as his daughter's story about this, while<lb/>
slightly distorted, fits in very well with what I stated as &ldquo;first hand&rdquo;<lb/>
information.</p>
<p>I was amused and interested in your &ldquo;detective work&rdquo; in Havana.<lb/>
Your conclusions were right, although perhaps you did not exactly locate<lb/>
Camp Lazear or the site of our yellow fever hospital. I could promptly<lb/>
put my foot on both places including the spot where Dr. Lazear died,<lb/>
regardless of the changes shown in your photos. The military cemetery<lb/>
where Lazear was buried was a few hundred yards from the hospital, down the<lb/>
old road to La Playa, I could also locate that I am sure. The bodies were<lb/>
all removed to the U. S. Lazear's final resting place, according to Kelly,<lb/>
p. 271, first edition, is at London Park Cemetery, Baltimore. I suggest that<lb/>
the memorial to Lazear you suggest, be a monument on the site of his death.<lb/>
You may keep the photostat copy of Reed's letter to me.</p>
<p>I do not see any possibility of getting east this year, so it<lb/>
would not be practicable for me to attend the W. &amp; J. exercises in October,<lb/>
much as I would like to be present to honor Dr. Lazear's memory.</p>
<p>In a few days I will send you answers to the questionnaire you<lb/>
sent me and return your memorandum with more comment. I realize you will<lb/>
have much to do in getting ready the final draft and need a prompt answer.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
- OVER -<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03603004"/>
<unclear>As</unclear><lb/>
T<lb/>
<seg>
P. S.<lb/>
I think it would be fine if you could<lb/>
manage to get General Kean to the W &amp; J. exercises.<lb/>
He is a very fine gentleman and Reed<lb/>
depended more on his advice &amp; help than<lb/>
any other man. He has always fought hard<lb/>
to keep the records clean and straight in<lb/>
what the Reed Board did in Cuba. He was a<lb/>
friend of Lazear's as you have no doubt discovered.<lb/>
When Kean gets through with my article<lb/>
I hope to be able to let you see it.<lb/>
While your memo &amp; mine <del>are</del> cover the<lb/>
same things they are materially different<lb/>
I discribe our life at the Columbia Bks Hospital<lb/>
and the intimate associations of our staff with<lb/>
the members of the board. You will be interested<lb/>
in it I am sure-<lb/>
For your own information I wish to add<lb/>
that while Lazear &amp; Agramonte were classmates<lb/>
at their Medical School they were not friendly and<lb/>
never worked together in spite of what Agramonte<lb/>
said in his statement in the Senate document.<lb/>
This fact is I think known by Kean. It<lb/>
is strictly confidential, too, and of course I<lb/>
will never state it publicly. Agramonte &amp; I<lb/>
never had any official relationship and<lb/>
we were always on friendly terms- He<lb/>
was a fine pathologist and probably a good<lb/>
bacteriologist. I do not know what<lb/>
Major Reed thought of him, but he certainly<lb/>
did not use him-<lb/>
A E T<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
