<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03606008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, September 16, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03606008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Huston</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-16">September 16, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03606008</idno>
<title>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, September 16, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hutchison provides details of the upcoming exercises honoring Lazear at Washington and Jefferson College and discusses Hench's presentation. Hutchison also provides information on Lazear's college career.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-16">
<head>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, September 16, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03606008"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
THE PRESIDENT'S OFFICE<lb/>
WASHINGTON AND JEFFERSON COLLEGE<lb/>
WASHINGTON, PENNSYLVANIA<lb/>
<date value="1940-09-16">September 16, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Phil:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your good letter has come this morning and<lb/>
I am delighted to have it. As usual your appreciation to<lb/>
me is beyond anything which I have coming. However, I<lb/>
am always glad to receive such credit whether I deserve<lb/>
it or not and I can assure you that the joy of welcoming<lb/>
you and giving you this degree will be one of the great<lb/>
experiences of my life.</p>
<p>Now to answer the questions in your letter.<lb/>
It is perfectly O.K. to write to Horace Davis whenever you<lb/>
want to. He was delighted at the plan and approved it<lb/>
enthusiastically.</p>
<p>Your invitation list could be longer than what<lb/>
you suggest. Sometimes men in your position would invite<lb/>
forty or fifty, and we are glad to invite them all.<lb/>
It's good publicity for the college, and I should say any-<lb/>
thing up to one hundred is perfectly one hundred per cent<lb/>
O.K. I will appreciate it therefore if you will dig in<lb/>
on that list and get it to us as soon as possible.</p>
<p>In regard to dates, the program now is as<lb/>
follows. On Friday evening, October the twenty-fifth, at<lb/>
about eight o'clock, the play &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;. The rest<lb/>
of the program is on Saturday, October the twenty-sixth.<lb/>
The exercises in the morning will be at ten o'clock I<lb/>
should imagine. After that is an informal luncheon some-<lb/>
where and then the game to which you are invited, but there<lb/>
is no necessity of your going unless you want to. The<lb/>
dinner will be in the evening at about six o'clock. So far<lb/>
as this applies to your program I would answer your questions<lb/>
as follows: there is no difficulty at all in your having<lb/>
a dinner in Charlottesville on Thursday night, the twenty-<lb/>
fourth and getting here in plenty of time for the play on<lb/>
Friday night. So far as your staying at the hotel, that is<lb/>
all right and we won't argue about that now. I haven't been<lb/>
able to think that through. You could get out here from<lb/>
your home if you wanted to stay at home. There will be no<lb/>
difficulty about that. If, however, you prefer to stay at<lb/>
the hotel here, that will be all right too. You can get<lb/>
home Saturday night. The dinner will be over at about ten<lb/>
o'clock and you could be home by eleven if you want to go<lb/>
in to Pittsburgh.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03606009"/>
<p>Doctor Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>September 16, 1940</p>
<p>I am glad to be warned about Moran and the<lb/>
others. We will ask them to just give a greeting of<lb/>
about two minutes at the dinner.</p>
<p>In regard to Doctor Cook, I think he also<lb/>
should be invited. That will round out the party and make<lb/>
it very nice. I will take care of that in the near<lb/>
future.</p>
<p>I am not sure about the length of your talk<lb/>
in the evening, or the use of pictures. Personally, I<lb/>
find that pictures detract rather than add to a good<lb/>
speech, and my guess is that the whole thing would be<lb/>
easier for you if you did not attempt to use pictures<lb/>
at this dinner. What do you think about this?</p>
<p>There is no reason why you should not write<lb/>
to Doctor Sawyer at your convenience. I will try to get<lb/>
a letter off to him soon. I suppose that as yet he does<lb/>
not know what he is going to say. Personally my judgment<lb/>
is that there is very little danger of your doing very<lb/>
much overlapping even on so specific a subject. If I<lb/>
were doing it I would try and plan my own speech and not<lb/>
worry about the overlapping. You will hear his address<lb/>
in the morning and any slight modifications you will make<lb/>
quite naturally without advanced preparation.</p>
<p>I want to go back for a minute to the matter<lb/>
of the length of your speech. I think you should have<lb/>
more latitude, and I would suggest that you make it<lb/>
somewhere between twenty and thirty minutes, not less than<lb/>
twenty, not more than thirty.</p>
<p>Mrs. Lazear writes that she will be unable to<lb/>
come. Her son writes that he will be unable to come.<lb/>
Neither one of them give any reason. I presume that she<lb/>
lacks the money, perhaps the health. He probably has to<lb/>
stay on his job whatever that is.</p>
<p>If I were you I would secure as much information<lb/>
as you can from Mrs. Lazear, but I would not give her a<lb/>
chance to object to your telling anything you want to tell.<lb/>
I would word your inquiries in such a way that she would<lb/>
have no chance to object. A great deal of time has passed.<lb/>
This is the time when Doctor Lazear should receive ample<lb/>
credit and I would go ahead and say what you want to say<lb/>
regardless of what she wants, particularly since she is not<lb/>
coming. If she were to be here, it might be different.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03606010"/>
<p>Doctor Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>September 16, 1940</p>
<p>Thank you for the suggestion about what we<lb/>
shall do for Moran, Kissinger, and Doctor Cook if he comes.<lb/>
I think something such as you suggest is the proper<lb/>
solution and I will get into it just as rapidly as<lb/>
possible and work something up. I believe that the<lb/>
memorial minute, properly engraved and framed, would be<lb/>
a better proposition than the key.</p>
<p>Give our love to Mary and the children.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Affectionately yours,</salute>
<signed>Hutch</signed>
Doctor Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
RCH/M<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. Doctor Lazear, I have just learned<lb/>
for the first time, did not finish here.<lb/>
He apparently attended here for <del>three</del><add>two</add> years,<lb/>
transferred to Hopkins, and was graduated there<lb/>
with the B.S. degree. He was a member of the<lb/>
Class of 1888 here. I have been confused on this<lb/>
point myself up until this moment.<lb/>
R.C.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
