<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03613001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, September 20, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03613001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Mrs.</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-20">September 20, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03613001</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, September 20, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus comments on the U.S. Army and his health. He also mentions Lambert's problems with his pension.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-20">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, September 20, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03613001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
JHAndrus<lb/>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1940-09-20">9-20-40</date>
</dateline>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<salute>Dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It is nice to know that you remember me and that you are in-<lb/>
terested in my welfare. I have often thought of you -<lb/>
wondered if you were still on the coast and whether you have<lb/>
found it possible to occupy your retirement pleasantly.</p>
<p>Recently - since our rulers and the public have become Army-<lb/>
conscious - I have speculated as to the liklihood of your<lb/>
being called back into active service.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I become highly incensed when I read of troops,<lb/>
on maneuvers, using stove pipes for machine guns and trucks<lb/>
as tanks and think of the millions that have been squandered<lb/>
for leaf-raking and boondoggling.</p>
<p>Of course I don't blame the Army for our deplorable lack of<lb/>
preparedness. The Army has probably done the best it could<lb/>
with the funds available. The blame, in my humble opinion,<lb/>
must be placed on our legislators for regulating their official<lb/>
acts by the probable effect on their reelection.</p>
<p>Please excuse my getting off base. I watch developments so<lb/>
intently and am so concerned about what <hi>may</hi> happen that I am<lb/>
prone to forget that that what I think is not of the slightest<lb/>
interest to anyone...</p>
<p>Yes, I'm still alive. And still in bed. I have been<lb/>
bedfast since March first, 1932. Was at Walter Reed Hos-<lb/>
pital from May 13 until October sixth, 1932 and, since then,<lb/>
have been at home.</p>
<p>In all this time I have been taken care of by my wife who has<lb/>
made a virtual prisoner of herself. My son, a graduate of<lb/>
Hahnemann Medical College, practices at this address and has<lb/>
given me excellent care.</p>
<p>I am obliged to lay prone. Any weight on my spine - even<lb/>
sitting up in bed - brings back the paralysis. I can turn<lb/>
in bed, have the use of my arms and legs, have a good appetite<lb/>
and weigh more now than when I went to bed.</p>
<p>When at Walter Reed I had quite a number of attacks of paroxysmal<lb/>
tachycardia - one lasting 22 hours - but have been without an<lb/>
attack for nearly a year.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03613002"/>
<p>The yellow fever annuity has been a godsend to me. If I<lb/>
was constantly bedeviled by the thought that - in addition to<lb/>
burdening my family with my care - I was a financial liability<lb/>
I'm afraid it would have driven me crazy long ago.</p>
<p>As it is, my principal worry is that when I die the annuity<lb/>
stops.</p>
<p>Do you remember Gust E. Lambert who was Dr. Ames' right hand<lb/>
man at the yellow fever hospital? He has had several bills<lb/>
in Congress to place him on the honor roll. On two or three<lb/>
occasions his bill has passed the Senate only to be killed in<lb/>
the House.</p>
<p>This year, again, the bill was up and reported favorably by the<lb/>
House Committee on Military Affairs. When an attempt was<lb/>
made to bring it before the House, for vote, on a unanimous<lb/>
consent agreement, Representatives Hancock, Cole and Schaeffer<lb/>
objected.</p>
<p>Lambert came from his home in Chicago to appear before a sub-<lb/>
committee for a hearing. The night of the hearing his wife<lb/>
fell at their hotel. The following day, his wife's condi-<lb/>
tion was sufficiently improved so that he came to Camden to<lb/>
see me. (Just for the day.)</p>
<p>Returning to Washington, he and his wife boarded a train for<lb/>
Birmingham. His wife was stricken with a heart attack and<lb/>
they left the train in Virginia where his wife died in a hos-<lb/>
pital.</p>
<p>I feel very sorry for Lambert. He is badly crippeled with<lb/>
arthritis and his eyesight is seriously impaired.</p>
<p>Have always felt that, had Major Reed lived until the bill was<lb/>
passed creating the roll of honor and granting annuities, both<lb/>
Dr. Ames and Lambert would have appeared on the list...</p>
<p>On the group photograph of Columbia Barracks Hospital personnel,<lb/>
number 40 is John Colby. This completes the list...</p>
<p>I hope you will write again. Would like to know what you<lb/>
think of world conditions and, especially, what you think of<lb/>
the probability of our involvement.</p>
<p>With kindest regards and every good wish,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>J H Andrus</signed>
General Albert E. Truby,<lb/>
145 Laurel Street,<lb/>
San Francisco, Calif.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
