<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03610005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, September 19, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03610005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="person">Jordan, Harvey</name>
<name type="person">Pew, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Clemons, Harry</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Julia Lomas</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-19">September 19, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03610005</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, September 19, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench urges Moran to attend the two college events. Hench discusses the Camp Lazear site.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, September 19, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03610005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-09-19">September 19, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just received your letter of September 16.</p>
<p>First of all, I sincerely hope you have changed your mind, and that you<lb/>
are coming, not only to Washington and Jefferson, but also to Charlottesville,<lb/>
Virginia. When you wrote, doubtless you did not know that Dr. Hutchison had<lb/>
finally been able to see Mr. Pew. I have just had a letter from Dr. Hutchison<lb/>
who said that &ldquo;the Sun Oil Company would be delighted to pay the expense to bring<lb/>
Mr. Moran up here.&rdquo; Regardless of whether Mr. Pew had come across or not, I know<lb/>
that funds would have been available to have you come, and I see no reason why<lb/>
you should hesitate to use them. Of course, it is nicer to have the company realize<lb/>
the good will value of sending you. I have no doubt that what Dr. Hutchison told<lb/>
Mr. Pew could have done nothing but raise you in his esteem. I know the college is<lb/>
also paying the expenses of Mr. Kissinger, so please do <unclear>come:</unclear></p>
<p>I hope you will at once re-write Dr. Jordan at the University of Virginia<lb/>
and will accept their invitation. When I was there visiting my brother this Spring,<lb/>
I know they were anxious indeed to have you come. Undoubtedly, your time will be<lb/>
mostly monopolised by Dean Jordan, Mr. Clemons, and members of the medical faculty,<lb/>
but I do hope you will take enough time out to get to meet my brother somehow, and<lb/>
at least have a little chat with him. I have written him that you are coming.</p>
<p>Your letter says that your dinner at the University of Virginia was to be<lb/>
on the twenty-fifth. General Kean had written me that it was to be the twenty-fourth.<lb/>
I know that they want you in Washington, Pennsylvania, by the evening of the twenty-<lb/>
fifth, as &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; is being given that night, and I am sure that the college boys<lb/>
who are putting on this play, will get a great kick out of having you in the audience<lb/>
with Mr. Kissinger. Don't you suppose you could arrange to have the <unclear>dinner</unclear> at Char-<lb/>
lottesville on the twenty-third or twenty-fourth? I think you can leave Charlottesville<lb/>
perhaps after the dinner, late at night, and get to Pittsburgh the next morning.<lb/>
Washington, Pennsylvania is about thirty-five miles from Pittsburgh, and if you arrive,<lb/>
let us say, by noon on Friday the twenty-fifth, I <unclear>wil2</unclear> meet you and Mrs. Moran in<lb/>
Pittsburgh, and you can go up to Washington with us, either by car or by train. The<lb/>
main celebration is on Saturday, the twenty-sixth, but I do hope you can get there by<lb/>
Friday afternoon, the twenty-fifth. I am sending a copy of this, with a letter, to<lb/>
Dean Jordan, hoping perhaps to save time and in order that he may know when you have<lb/>
to be in Washington, Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>Thank you so much for your additional information. I will be expecting<lb/>
much more soon. I appreciate your kindness in trying to warn me ahead of time that much<lb/>
of our labor may be lost and that the Cubans will never memorialize the true site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear, but frankly, I never expected that they would. If we can got them to<lb/>
memorialize the site they have already picked and do it honestly, that is all that<lb/>
I can expect. But this has been an interesting research problem for me, and, regardless<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03610006"/>
Mr. John Moran<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
September 19, 1940<lb/>
of what the Cubans do, I want to publish our investigations in a suitable medical<lb/>
historical journal, and call the matter to the attention of the authorities at<lb/>
Johns Hopkins, at Washington, at the University of Virginia and elsewhere, and<lb/>
perhaps accept Miss Cabrera's suggestion to let her friend, the Havana newspaper<lb/>
man, see the material for possible publication in the Havanapapers. In this way,<lb/>
at <unclear>loast</unclear>, the truth will be known for future historians.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
