<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03610002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, September 16, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03610002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Angles, Eduardo</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Hume, Edgar Erskine</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="person">Jordan, Harvey E.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Rojas farm, San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Ruston College (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospitals">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-16">September 16, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03610002</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, September 16, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran describes his difficulties in dealing with the Cuban government regarding the Camp Lazear site. Moran will not attend the University of Virginia or the Washington and Jefferson College events.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-16">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, September 16, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03610002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1940-09-16">Sept. 16, 1940.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter dated August 16th and a last-minute note<lb/>
inclosed therewith, dated September 1st, reached me on September 10th<lb/>
and your air-mail letter dated September 11th reached me on Sept. 14th.<lb/>
Your 37-page memorandum has taken me the better part of a week to<lb/>
digest and check. I have listed in orderly fashion the various items<lb/>
called for in your memorandum and letters and will make every effort to<lb/>
comply with your wishes. When I mention that it has taken me a week,<lb/>
you will understand that I mean part time and evenings.</p>
<p>The information you call for from Dr. Ramos and other<lb/>
Cuban medicos and Cubans will probably be denied you, especially in the<lb/>
straightforward manner you would wish to have it. You will recall the<lb/>
difficulty we had in &ldquo;pinning down&rdquo; any of them while you were here last<lb/>
April. Due to your own status and the institution from which you hailed,<lb/>
you were treated with a consideration which I could not command, then or<lb/>
now. That being the case, you will appreciate that I cannot hope to<lb/>
succeed where you failed. In truth you were not lacking in either per-<lb/>
sistency or energy. When and as I can &ldquo;catch up&rdquo; with Dr. Ramos, I am<lb/>
going to proceed along new lines in order to get him to acknowledge what<lb/>
he already knows, viz: that the official site of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; was select-<lb/>
ed for convenience rather than for genuinity. If he does not &ldquo;see the<lb/>
light&rdquo;, I will intimate in your behalf that Kissinger will be brought<lb/>
here from the U. S. in order that the two of us may sign a joint affidavit<lb/>
to the effect that Camp Lazear never was on the site officially claimed<lb/>
for it; also that the sworn statements of Se&ntilde;ora Rojas and her cousin are<lb/>
to be obtained and filed with our own, all said documents to be lodged<lb/>
with the proper authorities.</p>
<p>I will also inform Dr. Ramos that Americans in general<lb/>
will welcome the present site for any memorial to Dr. Lazear and the<lb/>
other membres of the Army Board, always providing that no tablets, slabs<lb/>
or other form of word dedication will claim the site as the seat of the<lb/>
experiments. You can rest assured that, when and as the Cuban Govern-<lb/>
ment will move to perpetuate any such memorial, it will be 100% Finlay.</p>
<p>All other proofs obtainable today, by photographs or<lb/>
otherwise, cannot restore the true site of Camp Lazear. In my humble<lb/>
opinion, most of the ground upon which stood Camp Lazear has been ex-<lb/>
cavated and converted into brick long ago. From 1901, when Camp Lazear<lb/>
was abandoned, until 1936, no effort was made to perpetuate or mark the<lb/>
site. Since Camp Lazear was a purely American affair, pertaining to the<lb/>
Army of Occupation, it was incumbent on the Americans rather than the<lb/>
Cubans to perpetuate the site or at least a part of it. For this, there<lb/>
is a reason. Up to 1928-1929, little importance had been attached to<lb/>
what General Kean referred to as &ldquo;that now famous episode&rdquo; and the sole<lb/>
champion for many years favoring recognition for the members of the Board<lb/>
and the &ldquo;human guinea pigs&rdquo; was General Kean himself. Formation of the<lb/>
Committee (composed of a group of the most prominent men in the U. S)<lb/>
seeking recognition for us all was principally due to the untiring efforts<lb/>
and missionary work of General Kean, culminating in the Act of February<lb/>
28th, 1929, with which you are familiar.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03610003"/>
<p><hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench.</hi></p>
<p>-- 2 --</p>
<p><hi>Sept. 16, 1940.</hi></p>
<p>Unfortunately, when the &ldquo;official Camp Lazear&rdquo; was so hurriedly<lb/>
selected, no effort was made to locate the real site. I am now sure<lb/>
that, even though it had been located, the Cuban medicos connected with<lb/>
the Department of Sanitation would not have planned on any form of memo-<lb/>
rial on the ground which you and I went over so thoroughly. Dr. Ramos<lb/>
and his associates were entirely willing to take Dr. Angl&eacute;s' word for it.<lb/>
Dr. Ramos has known for many years that I was one of the men experimented<lb/>
upon at Camp Lazear. This was very intimately brought to his attention<lb/>
about four or five years ago, when Prof. James E. Peabody was here and<lb/>
gave a conference on the experiments at Ruston College, to which he was<lb/>
invited. At that time he was Director of Sanitation. Dr. Agramonte's<lb/>
daughter, one of the teachers at Ruston College, was also present. Doctor<lb/>
Peabody insisted on my attendance and that of my Congressional Medal. In<lb/>
illustrating his lecture, Dr. Peabody used the Metropolitan Life Insurance<lb/>
Company's film, a copy of which I gave you when you were here.</p>
<p>?</p>
<p>It is my impression that the official Camp Lazear was precipi-<lb/>
tately &ldquo;discovered&rdquo; in 1936 when Lieut-Col. Edgar Erskine Hume, Medical<lb/>
Corps, U. S. Army, was the guest here of the Cuban Government. At that<lb/>
time he was in charge of the Army Medical Library and it was during his<lb/>
incumbency at the Library that I gave my Yellow Fever Certificate to the<lb/>
Medical Corps of the Army, to be preserved with other letters and papers<lb/>
of Major Reed at the Army Medical Library. When Colonel Hume was here<lb/>
I tried on several occasions to see him and finally succeeded in making<lb/>
an appointment with him at 1:00 P. M., at the National Hotel, on September<lb/>
28, 1936, an appointment which, I regret to record, was kept by me but not<lb/>
by Col. Hume. When I reached the hotel at the appointed hour I was in-<lb/>
formed that Col. Hume was entertaining or being entertained by seven or<lb/>
eight doctors of the Cuban Army and/or medicos of the Department of San-<lb/>
itation. I properly calculated that further effort on my part to see<lb/>
him would be fruitless, so I gave it up as a bad job. His time, while he<lb/>
was here, was completely monopolized by the Cuban authorities and I am<lb/>
reasonably sure he was glad when he finally made his departure. The<lb/>
imitation bronze plaque which you saw in the &ldquo;Sala Guiteras&rdquo; (Guiteras<lb/>
Ward) of Los Animas Hospital, dedicated to Dr. Lazear, was unveiled in<lb/>
honor of Col. Hume while he was here. Please refer to the Albertini<lb/>
address which I translated into English for you and mailed to you after<lb/>
your departure from Havana. No, my friend, the Cubans interested in<lb/>
Camp Lazear, either to further their own ends or willing to do something<lb/>
to honor the memories of Major Reed and his associates, do not want to<lb/>
discover the real site of Camp Lazear. All work which you have mapped<lb/>
out for yourself to this end as well as all you have done to date is<lb/>
&ldquo;Love's Labor Lost&rdquo;. The solution I have suggested in the second para-<lb/>
graph of this letter is the best I can think of.</p>
<p>Just as soon as I can get in touch with Dr. Ramos and pin him<lb/>
down to brass tacks in this matter, I will air-mail you his reaction to<lb/>
it. In the meantime, I want to prepare you for the inevitable so that<lb/>
you can set about revising the memorandum you sent to me. I shall send<lb/>
you my own notes and observations on such points, items, etc. of the<lb/>
memorandum as conflict with my own knowledge and understanding of any<lb/>
such points in dispute. These will refer to dates, places, etc., your<lb/>
personal opinion in all other matters at issue being yours by right.</p>
<p>You mention, my good friend, that &ldquo;I got you into all this&rdquo;.<lb/>
I will admit that I did, indirectly. I still want you to write the<lb/>
Reed-Finlay story because I feel sure you will do justice to both.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03610004"/>
<hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench</hi>.<lb/>
-- 3 --<lb/>
<hi>Sept. 16, 1940</hi>.<lb/>
Reconstruction or perpetuation of the site of Camp Lazear, however, did<lb/>
not enter into my calculations. It is now too late to do that, for the<lb/>
simple reason that those who might have retained a mental picture of<lb/>
the camp and the exact place where it stood on the San Jos&eacute; Farm or<lb/>
&ldquo;Finca San Jos&eacute;&rdquo;, cannot locate the plot, what with the buildings which<lb/>
now exist on part of which might have been the site. It is almost certain<lb/>
that neither Kissinger nor myself could assert at this day that Camp Lazear<lb/>
was on the section we went over while you were here and it is equally certain<lb/>
that Se&ntilde;ora Rojas and her cousin, while they have watched the &ldquo;Finca&rdquo; in<lb/>
process of being cut up into building sub-divisions and the excavations of<lb/>
the soil suitable for brick-making, are extremely hazy on the point as to<lb/>
just where the Camp was. In addition to this uncertainty, the marking<lb/>
and perpetuation of Camp Lazear site would, of necessity, have to be a<lb/>
affair in which the Cubans and Americans would be called upon to do their<lb/>
respective shares. I will again repeat that Cuban support, Se&ntilde;ora Rojas<lb/>
aside, would not be forthcoming. I am reasonably sure that Dr. Ramos<lb/>
will admit our claims, if presented in the manner I have outlined in the<lb/>
second paragraph of this letter. That he will back any proposition to<lb/>
set up any form of memorial on the plot where we thought Camp Lazear might<lb/>
have been located, I doubt very much.</p>
<p>On second thought, I will await further instructions from you<lb/>
before seeking my interview with Dr. Ramos and acting along the lines<lb/>
suggested, in your name.</p>
<p>I have just received an invitation from the President of Wash-<lb/>
ington &amp; Jefferson College to be present at the dedication of the Lazear<lb/>
Chemistry Building on October 25th and 26th. Before answering him, I<lb/>
want to hear from you, since I propose NOT to accept the invitation. In<lb/>
the first place, I cannot afford to spend the amount which the trip would<lb/>
involve, since I feel that I would have to be accompanied by Mrs. Moran,<lb/>
should I accept the inviation. My trip to Washington, last May, stood<lb/>
me $300.00, between one thing and another. In the second place, while<lb/>
Dr. Hutchison writes me that the College will pay my own personal<lb/>
expenses, I could not accept such a proposition. To put it mildly, I<lb/>
would find it embarrasing in the extreme. In the third place, I con-<lb/>
sider that my place is in Cuba, in close contact with the affairs of<lb/>
the company, for the rest of the year and until world affairs clear up<lb/>
one way or the other. When you were here in April, I felt that there<lb/>
would be no serious obstacle to prevent my acceptance of the invitation.<lb/>
Much has happened since to knock many plans into a cocked hat. I wrote<lb/>
Dean Jordan, of the Medical Department of the University of Virginia, that<lb/>
I could not accept his invitation for a dinner in my honor at UVA on<lb/>
October 25th, that being the date he had set. This happened some weeks<lb/>
ago. Please do not think I have turned down the two invitations under<lb/>
reference, lightly. On the contrary, I do so sadly and regretfully.<lb/>
Acceptance of both would have meant much to me. Please let me hear from<lb/>
you by RETURN AIR MAIL. Kindest personal remembrances to Mrs. Hench and<lb/>
your good self from Elida <del><unclear></unclear></del> and</p>
<closer>
<salute>Your sincere friend,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
