<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03617011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Grace T. Hallock, September 13, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03617011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hallock, Grace T.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Military City (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-13">September 13, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03617011</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Grace T. Hallock, September 13, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench supplies details and references on the yellow fever experiments, correcting errors in the film strip Hallock prepared for the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Grace T. Hallock, September 13, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03617011"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-09-13">September 13, 1940</date>
Miss Grace T. Hallock<lb/>
Welfare Division<lb/>
Metropolitan Life Insurance Co.<lb/>
New York City<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Miss Hallock:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I hope indeed that my rather informal comments to Dr. Armstrong<lb/>
concerning the historical accuracy of your pamphlet &ldquo;Health Forces-Walter Reed&rdquo;<lb/>
did not disturb you. I really did not mean to criticize this pamphlet in any way. I<lb/>
merely made my comments as a point of interest, and I am answering your letter, I can<lb/>
assure you, in the most friendly spirit and without any critical views. However, because<lb/>
we are both interested in this history of Walter Reed's experiments, may I make the<lb/>
following comments.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, you entirely misunderstood which photograph I was referring<lb/>
to when I mentioned a photograph showing a river between the Infected Mosquito Building<lb/>
and the Infected Clothing Building, with mountains in the background. It was not the one<lb/>
on page 15 of the pamphlet. I of course recognize that, as I not only have the Kelly<lb/>
photographs, but also other photographs which I have got from the Army Medical Museum and<lb/>
from survivors of the experiments. The photograph I refer to is the twenty-first photo-<lb/>
graph in your film strip, placed between the picture of Lazear and the picture of Kissinger.<lb/>
It is the one entitled &ldquo;Camp Lazear in Cuba was constructed for control experiments&rdquo;.<lb/>
At my request, Dr. Armstrong kindly sent me an enlarged print of this particular picture.<lb/>
In the film which he sent me, this particular picture is printed so that the background is<lb/>
rather faint and one can't see the mountains, but in the enlarged print they are very clear,<lb/>
and the river is unmistakable. Please do not misunderstand me. This is not particularly<lb/>
important nor is it essential to have the diagrams on page 21 of your pamphlet absolutely<lb/>
correct. After all, your pamphlet is for teaching purposes. As I mentioned in my letter<lb/>
to Dr. Armstrong, so far as I can find out, the events pictured in Figures 1 and 3 on<lb/>
page 21 never occurred. I have Senate Document 822, and have been over it so thoroughly<lb/>
that I have it almost memorized. I of course knew of the Gorgas version on page 243<lb/>
but since these incidents, as pictured in Figures 1 and 3, are not mentioned in any of the<lb/>
official records of Reed, Carroll or others, nor in the informal records or papers of<lb/>
Agramonte, one must conclude that Gorgas was taking slight liberties with the truth,<lb/>
and was &ldquo;clarifying the experiments&rdquo; in his own mind. On pages 10, 86, and 100 of Senate<lb/>
Document 822, it mentions two controls only being on Side A. It is true that Reed, on<lb/>
page 99, mentions two controls and one other non-immune. That is why you have three<lb/>
figures in the left box, but as I say, on the very next page (page 100) Reed says that the<lb/>
two controls continued to sleep in that room at night. The other non-immune happens to<lb/>
have been Dr. Reed himself. Apparently, he merely entered the room briefly for the purpose<lb/>
of observing Moran being bitten. This data I found in a most detailed and interesting<lb/>
article by Agramonte in the Scientific Monthly for December, 1915, which in many ways<lb/>
gives dates and details much more clearly than in the official publications. When I<lb/>
visited his daughter this Spring in Havana, and had the opportunity of looking over his<lb/>
notes or memoranda, there was such evidence of meticulous accuracy in his notes that one<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03617012"/>
Miss Grace T. Hallock<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
September 13, 1940<lb/>
cannot doubt his data. Why do you accept Gorgas' version and insert Figures 1 and 3,<lb/>
but do not accept him in the other matters? Certainly, Reed's version should be con-<lb/>
sidered the official and correct one, and at no place does he mention data which one<lb/>
could use as the basis of Figures 1 and 3. On page 100 of the Senate Document, Reed<lb/>
says, &ldquo;The building was then closed except for the occupancy of the two non-immunes.&rdquo;<lb/>
As far as I can see, the only other man bitten in the mosquito side of the Infected<lb/>
Mosquito Building was Jerregan. Thereafter (as Reed says on the bottom of page 100)<lb/>
the volunteers were bitten in the separate annex of this Infected Mosquito Building;<lb/>
that is, the separate room in which the mosquitoes were raised, quite apart from the<lb/>
room occupied by Moran. In Agramonte's Scientific Monthly article, you will see the<lb/>
diagram of this room in relation to the rest of the building, and this will explain the<lb/>
curious shape of the building, as shown on page 17 of your pamphlet.</p>
<p>You say that you have visited the site of Camp Lazear yourself. I shall<lb/>
be most interested to know when this was and where you found the camp site. The Cuban<lb/>
government now has the supposed site marked with a temporary memorial which consists of<lb/>
a tree surrounded by a small, low, wooden fence, and a large tin sign. This is right<lb/>
behind the present Military City and within sixty-five feet of a railroad track. It is<lb/>
right behind the Military Hospital on the Military City grounds which occupy the former<lb/>
site of Camp Columbia. Is this where you saw the camp site? Unfortunately, this is not<lb/>
the true camp site. Local tradition is mistaken and this actually was the site of the<lb/>
temporary tent hospital where the patients who developed yellow fever at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
a mile away, were immediately brought for the care of the doctors stationed at Camp<lb/>
Columbia. Mr. Moran and I re-located the true site of the camp and had long conversations<lb/>
with Senora Rojas, the widow of the man who loaned the camp to Reed and Agramonte, and<lb/>
you will note in the Scientific Monthly article that Agramonte especially states that<lb/>
Camp Lazear was on the San Jose farm, a mile from Camp Columbia. The present false camp<lb/>
is much too near.</p>
<p>I have been trying to find Mrs. Reed's address, but have been unable<lb/>
to do so. Should you find her address I shall be indeed delighted to have it. <del>[Permit<lb/>
me to send you a photograph of a model of Camp Columbia, made by a Cuban in 1900. The<lb/>
model is now in the Military Barracks at Carliale, Pa. The photograph is from the Army<lb/>
Medical Museum and shows the railroad track. General Kean remembers this track and<lb/>
bridge, and the tents which formed the basis of the false identification of Camp Lazear<lb/>
were apparently right across from this small bridge.]</del></p>
<p>Would you kindly send me a dozen copies of your pamphlet &ldquo;Health Heroes&rdquo;?<lb/>
I am corresponding with a number of survivors and know they will be delighted to have<lb/>
copies.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
