<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03616015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Grace T. Hallock to Philip Showalter Hench, September 23, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hallock, Grace T.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03616015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-23">September 23, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03616015</idno>
<title>Letter from Grace T. Hallock to Philip Showalter Hench, September 23, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hallock responds to the alleged historical inaccuracies, which Hench has noted, in her Metropolitan Life Insurance-sponsored filmstrip and pamphlet about Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-23">
<head>Letter from Grace T. Hallock to Philip Showalter Hench, September 23, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03616015"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
METROPOLITAN LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY<lb/>
FREDERICK H. ECKER, Chairman of the Board<lb/>
LEROY A. LINCOLN. President<lb/>
NEW YORK CITY<lb/>
<date value="1940-09-23">September 23, 1940</date>
</dateline>
WELFARE DIVISION<lb/>
----<lb/>
DONALD B. ARMSTRONG, M.D.<lb/>
Third Vice-President<lb/>
ANTHONY J. LANZA, M.D.<lb/>
Assistant Medical Director<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you very much indeed for your comments on the Walter<lb/>
Reed material. I was not in the least disturbed by your reference to var-<lb/>
ious inaccuracies. Indeed I am very glad that you took the trouble to point<lb/>
them out. I am sorry that I misinterpreted your reference to the pictures<lb/>
of Camp Lazear. I had not seen the filmstrip for some time and, since you<lb/>
had been speaking of the pamphlet in the preceding paragraph, I jumped to<lb/>
the wrong conclusion. You are absolutely right about the picture. We are<lb/>
about to make an extensive revision of the Walter Reed filmstrip and I shall<lb/>
certainly see that this mistake is rectified. When the filmstrip was pre-<lb/>
pared I was not with the Company, and my only connection with it was the<lb/>
preparation of the first draft of the scenario and correspondence with various<lb/>
individuals who might have photographs that could be used. The material for<lb/>
the filmstrip was collected by our Film Bureau. It was made some time ago -<lb/>
1927, I believe - but there may be records available of sources of some of<lb/>
the photographs. If you have not been able to locate Mrs. Reed at either<lb/>
one of the two addresses I gave you in my letter of September 5th, I am<lb/>
afraid that I cannot help you locate her. I visited Mrs. Reed in Washington<lb/>
in the winter of 1927 and I had some correspondence with her subsequently,<lb/>
but I have not heard from her in some years. In regard to the diagram in<lb/>
the pamphlet, picturing the experiment in the infected mosquito building,<lb/>
it probably would have been better to have followed the documentary accounts<lb/>
exactly. The booklet was written 15 years ago in 1925 and I remember that<lb/>
I was particularly impressed at the time with the clear-cut definition of<lb/>
the problem and its solution, as given by Gorgas. Since then I have learned<lb/>
the wisdom of going back to the sources in gathering material for popular<lb/>
consumption. In making clear to high school students the significance of<lb/>
the problem in question, the diagram seems to have been very effective. It<lb/>
can readily be altered in the revision of the filmstrip and, if there is<lb/>
ever occasion to revise the pamphlet, I shall seriously consider making the<lb/>
change.</p>
<p>I was in Cuba in the fall of 1923. I am sure that the<lb/>
site of Camp Lazear pointed out to me was the one which you describe as &ldquo;the<lb/>
false one.&rdquo; I was in Cuba as a casual tourist and was not at that time par-<lb/>
ticularly interested in Walter Reed and the history of yellow fever, so my im-<lb/>
pression was entirely uncritical. I am glad to learn that you and Mr. Moran<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03616016"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
September 23, 1940<lb/>
have located the true site and I hope you are taking steps to have it recog-<lb/>
nized as such. I had the pleasure of talking to Mr. Moran when he was in<lb/>
New York for the opening of the play &ldquo;Yellow Jack.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am glad to send you additional copies of the pamphlet on<lb/>
Walter Reed. This booklet is one of a series and, as you may be interested<lb/>
in reviewing the other biographies in the series, I am sending you also under<lb/>
separate cover one copy of each.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially yours,</salute>
<signed>Grace T. Hallock<lb/>
Welfare Division</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
