<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03615004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on the San Jose property [by Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas?], [1940]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03615004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Pogolotti, Dino Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Morales, Dolores</name>
<name type="person">Morales, Ygnacio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Demetrio</name>
<name type="person">Sosa, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-00-00">[1940]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03615004</idno>
<title>Notes on the San Jose property [by Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas?], [1940]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Rojas?] gives a history of the San Jose property, a probable site of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1940-00-00">
<head>Notes on the San Jose property [by Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas?], [1940]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03615004"/>
<p>1</p>
<p><hi>NOTES</hi></p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 53</hi>: The property San Jose was sold to Mr. Dino<lb/>
Francisco Pogolotti on Dec. 17, 1910; but from February of 1905<lb/>
that part of the property was leased to Mr. Bartolom&eacute; Ferrer<lb/>
(who later organized a company with Pogolotti) to construct a<lb/>
brick factory. I can give you copy of said contract.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 53</hi>: The limekiln<del>ns</del> and a stone quarry were operated<lb/>
from the year 1857 with negro slaves and Chinese, various persons<lb/>
being lessees during the course of the years, the last being Sr.<lb/>
Calleja and Brother, who leased same, together with the residence,<lb/>
to July 31, 1900. When these gentlemen ceased being lessees and<lb/>
the house was vacant, the family moved in for the first time.<lb/>
(July 1900).</p>
<p>The quarry was not operated from that date until April 1907<lb/>
when it was leased to Mr. Demetrio Zunzunegui. The contract stated:<lb/>
Land occupied by the quarries now open, the kiln<del>s</del> and the well,<lb/>
which is approximately 4 to 6 acres. Also, the contract states:<lb/>
The lessee may occupy the two small wooden houses which are located<lb/>
close to the kilns, etc. I can furnish you with this contract.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraphs 54 to 62</hi>: The property San Jos&eacute; was owned by<lb/>
the Pedroso family from the middle of the XVIII century. Mrs. Rojas<lb/>
was married the first time to her cousin, Mr. Martin Javier Pedroso,<lb/>
who inherited same from his great grandfather the Count of Casa<lb/>
Pedroso y Garro. Both the residence as well as the fence in front<lb/>
existed already in 1857. Said fence is of masonry, a mixture much<lb/>
used formerly, composed of rock of all sizes, earth and clay,<lb/>
covered with adobe. All the front had this fence, on the sides<lb/>
and back the fence was of stone as shown on the plan of 1907. When<lb/>
the property was sold the sides were provisionally fenced with<lb/>
wire, the present fence, which is of brick, being constructed in<lb/>
1930. Then the old wall in front was reinforced with some pillars<lb/>
and covered with a new coat (of cement.) (Translator's note: The<lb/>
Spanish text simply states a new coat was given so it is not clear<lb/>
whether adobe or cement - customarily used in this country - was<lb/>
used. I imagine you saw the wall and know what it is.)</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 54 and 55</hi>: It appears that the Camp had no fence<lb/>
of any kind.</p>
<p>Sra. Dolores Morales is 60 years old and was some 20 years<lb/>
old when she came to live at the property for the first time in July<lb/>
1900.</p>
<p>Her brother, Sr. Ygnacio Morales was then 10 years old and<lb/>
only remembers the express detail of what he was given to feed his<lb/>
little pig. He does not remember there being any fence.</p>
<p>The sister of Sra. Morales who is ill is named Se&ntilde;orita Josefita<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03615005"/>
-2-<lb/>
Morales and lives in the house on the corner, not in the Finca.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 61</hi>: The date of the old map is 1857.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraphs 59 to 67</hi>: Calzada de Maximo Gomez is the modern<lb/>
(present) name of the Calzada from Marianao to Cerro, but no one<lb/>
uses it and continues to call it by the old names.</p>
<p>The name &ldquo;Loma Llaves&rdquo; is that given to the Reparto (Sub-divi-<lb/>
sion) when buildings were constructed on the lands of the property<lb/>
San Francisco Javier, which borders the property San Jos&eacute;.</p>
<p>Having clarified the matter of the small houses, it can be<lb/>
presumed that the wooden floors, which both Sra. Rojas and Sra.<lb/>
Morales remember, belonged to the tents. They cannot recall<lb/>
having used same for anything nor what was done with them.</p>
<p><hi>Photographs:</hi></p>
<p>Photo 17 e: Shows the stone quarry belonging to the property.</p>
<p>Photo 16 a and b: The limekiln which was not operated at<lb/>
that time. It is not known what the wooden houses at the side of<lb/>
the tents were.</p>
<p>We have never owned property (finca - farm) in the vicinity<lb/>
of Camp Columbia other than this (San Jose.).</p>
<p>You may have at your disposal the bark of all the trees on<lb/>
my property.</p>
<p>Regarding the reason why there is no tradition among the<lb/>
present inhabitants concerning Camp Lazear, this is due to the<lb/>
fact that all this land was unoccupied until many years later.<lb/>
At that time the property was occupied only by the family, the<lb/>
lessee, Mr. Antonio Sosa (now dead) and the laborers who cultivated<lb/>
the land. Nevertheless, Mr. Zunzunegui, who leased the limekilns<lb/>
six years later, recalls the story.</p>
<p>The belief and remembrance of Sra. Rojas that the land of<lb/>
the property was ceded to the American Government is due to the<lb/>
fact that this was the desire of Dr. Rojas, but according to the<lb/>
entries in the books, the lands of the property were leased to<lb/>
Mr. Antonio Sosa, who cultivated same, planting small crops, and<lb/>
they could not have been ceded. Thus a modest rent was collected,<lb/>
of which the lessee received half.</p>
<p><hi>Copy of the entries</hi></p>
<p>(Mr. Moran has seen this book)</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03615006"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><hi>Nov. 15, 1900</hi>: Today for the third time the Military Health<lb/>
Officers of the American Army entered the property San Jose in<lb/>
agreement with the lessee Don Antonio Sosa and through mediation<lb/>
of Dr. Echevarria.</p>
<p><hi>January 2, 1901</hi>: Collected the check sent by the Surgeon<lb/>
Major of the U.S.A., Mr. Reed, value $20.00, covering the first<lb/>
month's rent on the land of the San Jose property occupied by<lb/>
the experimental Commission of Yellow Fever. Of this amount one-<lb/>
half delivered to Mr. Antonio Sosa, Lessee of said lands.</p>
<p><hi>January 19, 1901</hi>: Major J. R. Kean, Surgeon U.S.A. paid<lb/>
$20., American gold, amount of the second month's rent on land<lb/>
of the property San Jos&eacute; occupied by the Yellow Fever Experimental<lb/>
Commission, from Dec. 10, 1900 to January 9, 1901.</p>
<p><hi>February 25, 1901</hi>: Major J. R. Kean, U.S.A. Surgeon, Dis-<lb/>
bursing Officer, Columbia Barracks, sent check for $40.00 American<lb/>
gold covering two months rent on land of the Property San Jose<lb/>
in Marianao occupied by the Yellow Fever Experimentation, covering<lb/>
rent from January 10th to March 9th, at the rate of $20. American<lb/>
gold per month. Half for Sosa.</p>
<p><hi>April 22, 1901</hi>: Major J. R. Kean Surgeon, U.S. Army Disbursing<lb/>
Officer today sent the vouchers to sign covering payment of the<lb/>
rent on Camp Lazear, March 9th to May 10th, located on the property<lb/>
San Jose, Marianao.</p>
<p><hi>June 11, 1901</hi>: Collected from Major J. R. Kean Surgeon, U.S.<lb/>
Army Disbursing Officer the amount of rent on lands occupied by<lb/>
Camp Lazear on the property San Jos&eacute; covering period from May 9th<lb/>
to July 10th of this year - $40.00 American gold, that is, $44.00<lb/>
Spanish.</p>
<p><hi>September 29, 1901</hi>: Today I returned the signed vouchers to<lb/>
Major J. R. Kean Surgeon, U.S.A. Disbursing Officer, covering<lb/>
two months rent on the land occupied by Camp Lazear Experimental<lb/>
Sanitary Camp on the property San Jos&eacute;, which came due on August<lb/>
10th and September 9th, at the rate of $20., American gold, per<lb/>
month - $40.00 gold.</p>
<p><hi>October <del>1</del> <add>10</add>, 1901</hi>: Today I received the last check for $20.00<lb/>
covering rent on Camp Lazear located on the property San Jose,<lb/>
up to the 9th and they left the land; <hi>delivering the two wooden<lb/>
houses which they constructed to carry out experiments on yellow<lb/>
fever and mosquitoes</hi>.</p>
<p>-:-:-</p>
<p>I believe that the place to mark on the map as the site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear is that shown on the Plan of 1907 by limekilns</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03615007"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>1. Because in the photographs of Camp Lazear the old lime-<lb/>
kilns can be seen.</p>
<p>2. Because as the two wooden houses were not torn down when<lb/>
the Camp was broken up, as shown in the entry in the Note Book,<lb/>
these were the two wooden houses, next to the limekilns, mentioned<lb/>
in the lease contract to Mr. Zunzunegui in 1907, and which are not<lb/>
mentioned in previous leases of limekilns. Another significant<lb/>
detail of this contract is that it gives the measurement of the<lb/>
land in <hi>acres</hi>, which is not used in Cuba and is used in the United<lb/>
States...</p>
<p>The statements of Mr. Zunzunegui, to which little importance<lb/>
were at first attached, may now have value. Mr. Moran interviewed<lb/>
him.</p>
<p>-:-:-</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 54</hi>: The following is correct: When Calzada<lb/>
Columbia crosses Avenida <hi>Buen Retiro</hi> one turns left (southeast)<lb/>
until Avenida <hi>Buen Retiro</hi> runs into the Calzada de Marianao.<lb/>
The latter is the old main road between Quemados, Marianao and<lb/>
Havana and is variously called Calzada Real de Marianao, Calzada<lb/>
Real, Real St. in Marianao and Calzada de Marianao. Now: Turning<lb/>
to the left in the direction of Havana, you come to the property<lb/>
&ldquo;Finca San Jose&rdquo; at the right and between the streets Villal&oacute;n and<lb/>
Jos&eacute; Miguel Gomez. A little farther on and also on the right is<lb/>
a brickyard (Tejar).</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
