<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03615002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, August 15, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03615002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-08-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Cabrera, Julia Lomas</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis</name>
<name type="person">Morales, Dolores</name>
<name type="person">Beato, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-08-15">August 15, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03615002</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, August 15, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] questions Rojas about the location of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-08-15">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, August 15, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03615002"/>
<opener>
Photos Sent - 1 (2 copies) -2 (2 copies) -5-6-11b-16a-16b<lb/>
17c-18-19 -20-21-22-23-42-45-46-48-<lb/>
53-62-64<lb/>
Copy Letter <unclear>to Beato</unclear><lb/>
Copy of this letter sent to Moran<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-08-15">August 15, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Senora Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas<lb/>
207 Calle 17,<lb/>
Vedado, Havana<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora Rojas:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Permit me to send you herewith a confidential memorandum which I have<lb/>
written up mostly for my own information. I hope to use this information, at least<lb/>
part of it, as a background for my address at the Lazear Memorial dedication.<lb/>
Part of it also will be used in my formal report to the Cuban government, in an<lb/>
attempt to have them recognize your farm as the true site of Camp Lazear. You will<lb/>
appreciate, therefore, how anxious I am to have you check over this to be sure that<lb/>
I am right in my statements. I regret that it is too long for me to have it trans-<lb/>
lated in Spanish but I am sure that your daughter and Senora Cabrera will be able<lb/>
to understand it and read it to you, and I will be most appreciative of their wonder-<lb/>
ful help in this matter. May I ask your particular attention to certain paragraphs,<lb/>
and as I am anxious to have you correct any mistakes which may appear herein and par-<lb/>
ticularly to amplify it with any information that you can give me, permit me to make<lb/>
the following suggestion. I would never ask you to go to the bother of writing a<lb/>
long, hand-written reply. Would you permit me to ask Mrs. R. Hart Phillips, of<lb/>
Manzana de <unclear>Gomez</unclear>, 533, Havana (the widow of the former Havana correspondent for the<lb/>
New York Times, who is now doing secretarial work, and who helped me considerably<lb/>
when I was there before) to call on you at your convenience and take down your<lb/>
comments and answers in shorthand. She can then write them up, submit a copy for<lb/>
your final appraisal and then send them to me. I will be more than delighted to pay<lb/>
whatever charges she makes in order that I may have from you an authorized and signed<lb/>
statement as to the historical events which took place on your farm, and your identi-<lb/>
fication of the site of these experiments.</p>
<p>Paragraph 32: Do you or any of your family know the name of some govern-<lb/>
mental tree expert who could estimate the age of the framboyant tree and the two or<lb/>
three other trees around the shacks in photograph No. These shacks are near<lb/>
the quarry behind your house. I am also anxious to have him give me the probable age<lb/>
of the framboyant tree at the false site already marked by the government.</p>
<p>Par. 53: I am asking Mr. Pogolotti to check this paragraph but would like<lb/>
to have you do so also. I am anxious to know when he or his brother bought part of your<lb/>
farm, that part where Camp Lazear was, and I also want to know when he sold the part<lb/>
now used as a quarry and to whom it was sold. Can you tell me when the quarry was<lb/>
begun, who now owns the quarry and who is its president? Perhaps they may have some old<lb/>
photographs of the land before the digging was begun.</p>
<p>Par. 54: Are my directions as to how to reach the San Jose farm correct?<lb/>
When was the fence (wall) built around your present estate? I have forgotten whether<lb/>
it is stone or concret.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03615003"/>
<p>Par. 55: I hesitate to ask for the exact age of your niece,<lb/>
Senora Dolores Morales, but considering her important recollections, it is<lb/>
important for me to know how old she was when Camp Lazear was established. I<lb/>
would appreciate it greatly if you would read the remarks that I remember she<lb/>
made to me and if she can amplify them or correct them, I would be grateful.<lb/>
Do you think her brother would have any worth-while recollections, and do you<lb/>
think it would be worthwhile for me to write him? You will appreciate that when<lb/>
I write this up, it will be much more forceful if I can use your remarks in<lb/>
quotation marks, and I will be most grateful if you will amplify them as extensively<lb/>
as you can.</p>
<p>Par. 61: What was the date of the old map framed in your parlor,<lb/>
the first map of the San Jose farm?</p>
<p>Pars. 59 to 67: I am particularly anxious that you check and amplify<lb/>
these paragraphs as much as you can. Can you tell me why, on the 1907 map,<lb/>
which you showed me, the name Calzada de Maximo Gomez is given to the street<lb/>
Calzada Real? What does the name Loma Llavos on the 1917 map indicate?<lb/>
Did the American army doctors when they abandoned Camp Lazear, leave the wooden floors<lb/>
from the tents or the wooden floors from the buildings?</p>
<p>Most important of all, will you please draw a circle on maps Nos.<lb/>
showing where you believe Camp Lazear exactly was, in terms of the present lay of<lb/>
the land, and will you please check this with my statements in paragraphs 65 and 67?<lb/>
You will appreciate that if I have a map marked by you in person and preferably with<lb/>
your signature on the side saying, &ldquo;This is where Camp Lazear was&rdquo; and signed &ldquo;Senora<lb/>
Rojas&rdquo; this will be the most important proof I can get regarding the proper identity<lb/>
of Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>Par. 68: I believe I have already asked you who owns the quarry now<lb/>
and whether they might have any old photographs of the land. I am going to ask for<lb/>
Mr. Pogolotti's help on this.</p>
<p>Par. 69: My recollection is that Dr. Beato does not understand English.<lb/>
I am going to write him a letter and will send Miss Cabrera a copy of it, and I will<lb/>
be very grateful indeed if between Miss Cabrera and Mrs. Philips, I could receive an<lb/>
answer from Dr. Beato, as to certain historical aspects mentioned in my memorandum.</p>
<p>Par. 70 and 71: I am most anxious to have your reaction to these paragraphs,<lb/>
and if you can amplify this in your statement made to Mrs. Phillips for me, I will<lb/>
appreciate it greatly.</p>
<p>Would you permit me to have a professional photographer visit the San<lb/>
Jose farm and take a photograph of the lay of the land from the upstairs porch toward<lb/>
the old site of Camp Lazear? I am very anxious to have such a photograph and through<lb/>
Mr. Moran will try to make arrangements for this if you will let me do so. Would you<lb/>
also permit me to buy a limb or a part of a limb of a tree on the San Jose farm?<lb/>
Perhaps some tree near the site of Camp Lazear, in order that I can have some small<lb/>
souvenirs made from this limb. Perhaps the tree near the shack that I have mentioned<lb/>
would be the nearest tree. Did your husband ever own any <unclear>preoprty</unclear> near Camp Columbia?<lb/>
I am afraid that the Cuban authorities may try to say that he did, and that they are still<lb/>
right in the site that they have chosen.</p>
<p>I cannot tell you how grateful I am for all the courtesies and help that<lb/>
you have given me so far, and I am sure that you will appreciate the historical signifi-<lb/>
cance of your farm and be glad to help me in establishing it as the true site of Camp<lb/>
Lazear. Whatever information you can give me will be indeed appreciated, and if I can<lb/>
have it at your earliest convenience, I will be most grateful, as the Cuban government<lb/>
wants my report soon.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
