<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03621004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, October 5, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03621004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-05">October 5, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03621004</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, October 5, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses the inclusion of Cooke for the Lazear memorial ceremony.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, October 5, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03621004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-10-05">October 5, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Hutch:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I enclose the list of friends and relatives to whom you might send invitations.<lb/>
I confess this worries me a bit. I don't want to be put in the position of looking<lb/>
as if I were advertising myself. The list of relatives is quite all right, and<lb/>
I think the list of some friends out of town is all right probably. I have in-<lb/>
cluded about twelve names of my best friends in Rochester, but I hope no one<lb/>
will get the impression that I am circularizing the Mayo Clinic.</p>
<p>I have my own cap and gown. I wore it at Lafayette, Two years ago in London<lb/>
and Oxford at the International Congress, we had to wear academic gowns so often<lb/>
it seemed quite natural. Unfortunately, Mrs. Kahler cannot come, but she would be<lb/>
delighted to receive an invitation.</p>
<p>I am glad you decided to ask Dr. Cooke. I think he has never received any<lb/>
recognition of any sort except, of course, the Congressional Medal. I had an<lb/>
air-mail answer from General Kean yesterday. He said, &ldquo;I entirely agree with you<lb/>
that Dr. Cooke is quite on the same plane as the mosquito men. At the time that<lb/>
these men volunteered, every doctor in Havana and in the United States would have<lb/>
said that the infected bedding squad ran the greater danger, as infection by<lb/>
fomites (infected bedding and clothing) was universally accepted as a means of<lb/>
transmission, while mosquito transmission was a discredited theory. In addition<lb/>
the wearing of dead men's garments and sleeping in sheets soiled with black vomit<lb/>
and excreta made it, as Reed said of it, a trying ordeal. I think I would have<lb/>
chosen the mosquitos every time before the Finlay theory had been demonstrated.&rdquo;<lb/>
Incidentally, the story goes that when Cooke and his two associate volunteers<lb/>
first entered the foul smelling experimental building, within a few minutes, they<lb/>
rushed out and one vomited. In introducing Dr. Cooke, you might polish this story<lb/>
up a bit, and say that after forty years, Washington and Jefferson wishes to replace<lb/>
the lost meal: This may not be very delicate, but it is pertinent.</p>
<p>I haven't heard from Dr. Sawyer yet, but I have tentatively revamped my entire<lb/>
idea on my talk. I suspect that I had better confine myself entirely to a brief<lb/>
tribute to Lazear, and mention very little about the general story and even mention<lb/>
the three honored guests only in passing. That being the case, I will hardly need<lb/>
any slides and would really not have to refer to any souvenir photographs. Never-<lb/>
theless, I think your idea is an excellent one, and I am sure it would please the<lb/>
honored guests. Therefore, I have picked out and am sending you by separate post<lb/>
today, a dozen photographs from which you can choose. May I suggest that they be<lb/>
numbered and somewhere on the inside of the program, these numbers be identified.</p>
<p>I enclose with them a photograph of Moran and one of Kissinger, made out to<lb/>
me. But the autographs are such that they will not interfere with your publicity<lb/>
purposes. I am sure they would not object, as both of these photographs have been<lb/>
published elsewhere. I have none of Cooke. I wrote a month ago asking for one<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03621005"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
of his old photographs. I suggest that you write him for one of his new ones.<lb/>
I am very proud of the ones of Moran and Kissinger to me, and I sincerely hope<lb/>
you will ask your photographer to take special care of them and if possible, re-<lb/>
turn not only them but also the others, or save them until I come.</p>
<p>I enclose also, for you to keep should you wish, one of the Metropolitan<lb/>
Life's little booklets on the yellow fever affair. You will notice about Kissinger<lb/>
and Moran on page 16. Now</p>
<p>Now as to the photographs. If you can do so, I would suggest that you use<lb/>
the following:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Photograph 11 a. Model of Camp Columbia Post Hospital. There are<lb/>
no adequate photographs. This is where the preliminary work<lb/>
by Reed, Lazear, etc. was done. In fact, all the work until<lb/>
after Lazear's death. Lazear's house is the one in the upper<lb/>
left hand corner. The laboratory that Reed and Lazear used<lb/>
is the little building I have indicated with a pencil.</item>
<item>Photograph 15. The heretofore unpublished photograph of Agramonte,<lb/>
Lazear, and Carroll, <unclear>loaned</unclear> me by courtesy of Dr. Agramonte's<lb/>
daughter.</item>
<item>Photograph 28. The outside of Las Animas Hospital, showing the room<lb/>
where Lazear was presumably bitten. At least he did much of<lb/>
his work, collecting <unclear>infected</unclear> blood in this yellow fever ward.</item>
<item>Photograph A. The room in Las Animas Hospital where Lazear was<lb/>
bitten, showing a memorial plaque to Lazear.</item>
<item>Photograph 56. Showing the old San Jose farm house, where Camp<lb/>
Lazear was. I know that the Rojas family would get a great<lb/>
kick out of having this photograph shown, if you can bring it in.</item>
</list></p>
<p>I would then select one or two of the old photographs of Camp Lazear. See my<lb/>
two labeled ones, and also numbers 20 and 21. I have had a composite drawing made<lb/>
of Camp Lazear showing all the tents and buildings visible in the various pictures<lb/>
that I have collected. No photograph shows them all. This drawing is being photo-<lb/>
graphed this week and you just might prefer it to the actual photograph. If you<lb/>
do, I will send it; in fact, I will send it anyhow and you can use it if you wish.</p>
<p>Next choice. I think it would be nice to show one of the three pictures of<lb/>
the sign and memorial fence at the proposed site but really false site of Camp Lazear.<lb/>
This was really not the site of Camp Lazear, but we have now identified it as the<lb/>
site of the tent hospital where Dr. Lazear died of yellow fever. The only reason<lb/>
I am sending the one of Mary and me in it is that it happens to show more than the<lb/>
other two.</p>
<p>Last selection. You might want one of the statues to Dr. Lazear. I have sent<lb/>
you four choices.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03621006"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>As you see, I have given you a selection in historical sequence, and you<lb/>
and your photographer can decide which you want, if any. I also have a photo-<lb/>
graph of the Congressional Medal, especially designed and given to those twenty-<lb/>
odd men who participated in the yellow fever experiments. I think this would<lb/>
be very nice to add. It is small and could be more or less tucked away in the<lb/>
corner of the composite photograph. I will have one printed Monday. Remember<lb/>
that the U.S. government thought so highly of the contribution of these men that<lb/>
they not only gave them this Congressional Medal and a life pension but created<lb/>
for the first time a U.S. Army Roll of Honor, which is published each year in<lb/>
perpetuity and which, by the way, contains <hi>only</hi> the names of the yellow fever<lb/>
men. There is no other Army Roll of Honor. Since Cooke's name was on that<lb/>
Roll, you will appreciate we think he deserves an invitation.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
