<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03621002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, October 5, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03621002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-05">October 5, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03621002</idno>
<title>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, October 5, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hutchison advises Hench on his speech and describes the conferring of the honorary degree.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-05">
<head>Letter from Ralph Cooper Hutchison to Philip Showalter Hench, October 5, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03621002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
THE PRESIDENT'S OFFICE<lb/>
WASHINGTON AND JEFFERSON COLLEGE<lb/>
WASHINGTON, PENNSYLVANIA<lb/>
<date value="1940-10-05">October 5, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Phil:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I sent you a telegram last night indicating<lb/>
that we had better not try the slides at this dinner<lb/>
but that we would like to take your main photographs<lb/>
and print them in the program for the dinner so that<lb/>
the people who have them not only can see while you<lb/>
talk but take with them for permanent keeping. The<lb/>
difficulty of using slides at a dinner of this kind<lb/>
is that it involves moving the people around in the<lb/>
midst of the dinner, changing their chairs, moving<lb/>
them down from the balcony, and various other compli-<lb/>
cations. Anything which causes people to move from<lb/>
their dinner table after a dinner breaks the psychology<lb/>
of the evening. This is an axiom for dinner speaking,<lb/>
and your effort will be twice as great for the same<lb/>
result if we do that. The finest group to speak to<lb/>
is that group which you catch fresh after the dinner,<lb/>
in their places, ready for the address and responsive,<lb/>
and it will be much easier for you. Our experience<lb/>
is such that we are very much afraid of pictures at a<lb/>
dinner of this kind.</p>
<p>On the other hand, we do believe that we can<lb/>
get up a program which will be a souvenir which will<lb/>
contain the program of the evening and the menu and<lb/>
carry these pictures of the &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; experiment.<lb/>
We will work this out as soon as your pictures arrive.</p>
<p>You do not speak at any other occasion during<lb/>
the week-end so you need not worry about that.</p>
<p>The conferring of the degree is very simple.<lb/>
You simply stand in the place which I will indicate to you,<lb/>
at my right on the platform, facing toward me rather than<lb/>
the audience. When I hand you the diploma, in the course<lb/>
of the citation, you take it with your left hand and<lb/>
remove your hat with your right hand so that the hood may<lb/>
be put over your head. After that, you replace the hat<lb/>
and we shake hands. I do not kiss you!</p>
<p>Buddy Groves arrived in America with his<lb/>
family on September twenty-fourth. He has decided to<lb/>
accept the position at Centre College, Danville, Kentucky,<lb/>
as Professor of Bible. He drove through on his way to<lb/>
that position, night before last, spending the night at<lb/>
our home. They are now there getting settled. You can<lb/>
address them at Centre College, Danville. I doubt if he<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03621003"/>
Doctor P. S. Hench<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
October 5, 1940<lb/>
can be up here for Founders' Day and of course I would<lb/>
rather not have him then so far as I am concerned<lb/>
because I will be too busy. However, I wouldn't be very<lb/>
busy on the following day, Sunday. We have nothing<lb/>
special then. I am hoping you folks can stay over<lb/>
so that we can have a visit. If Buddy could come up then<lb/>
I would be delighted to have him here. We will send him<lb/>
an invitation just to see what happens and you can drop<lb/>
him a note.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Affectionately yours,</salute>
<signed>Hutch</signed>
Doctor P. S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
RCH/M<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. We too originally planned for the<lb/>
use of your slides, but that was when<lb/>
we were putting your talk in between<lb/>
the acts on the night of the play.<lb/>
Now that we have shifted you to the<lb/>
major occasion, the dinner, we think<lb/>
the slides won't work as they would<lb/>
have worked on the play night. I<lb/>
forgot to make this note in writing<lb/>
the above.<lb/>
R.C.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
