<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03628001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Luis B. Pogolotti, October 15, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03628001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Pogolotti, Luis B.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estella Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-15">October 15, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03628001</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Luis B. Pogolotti, October 15, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] discusses the location of Camp Lazear and Building No. 1, expressing his doubts about the site Moran has discovered.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-15">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Luis B. Pogolotti, October 15, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03628001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-10-15">October 15, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Luis Pogolotti<lb/>
Calle Cuba 3<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Pogolotti:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sending a carbon of this to Mr. Moran, but he may have already<lb/>
left.</p>
<p>I spent several more hours last night examining the photographs and<lb/>
Moran's letter, and also the maps that you so kindly <unclear>drew</unclear> for me. At this distance<lb/>
from Cuba, it is of course hard to make a final opinion as to whether you have indeed<lb/>
found the remains of Building No. 1. I want very much to believe that you have,<lb/>
but it is difficult for me to compare a couple of the photographs now made with<lb/>
the old army photographs. The slope of the land just below the shack seems much<lb/>
greater than that in the army photograph. Nevertheless, the size of the shack is<lb/>
amazingly close to the one we are hunting for. Reed said that Building No. 1 faced<lb/>
the south. I understand that this faces mostly south but slightly east. Reed did<lb/>
not say it faced <hi>due</hi> south, so that that is not a serious objection. The one thing<lb/>
that worried me last night was that Moran said the hole for the chimney was on the<lb/>
left side as you faced the shack and your drawing places it on the left side. But<lb/>
Dr. Agramonte's drawing in the Scientific Monthly for December, 1915, places the<lb/>
stove on the right. It is of course possible that he might have made a mistake in<lb/>
the drawing if he drew it many years after the incident. I just had a letter from<lb/>
Dr. Agramonte's daughter yesterday, saying that she had found her father's original<lb/>
drawing of the old building. It would be important to find out from her if possible,<lb/>
whether these drawings were made by Dr. Agramonte in 1900 or not drawn until 1915<lb/>
and then perhaps from memory. If the latter were the case, the placing of the stove<lb/>
might easily have been wrong in the drawing. I have wondered if the building that<lb/>
you found might have been Building No. 2, or Building No. 1 facing the other way,<lb/>
but as you will see by the enclosed drawings, neither of these quite fit your own<lb/>
drawing. In my letter of yesterday, I called your attention to Reed's statement<lb/>
that Building No. 2 faced Building No. 1 eighty yards away, and wondered whether the<lb/>
supposed ruins, that is, the remains of the cement floor where Building No. 2 was,<lb/>
are in fact, eighty yards from the shack which you discovered.</p>
<p>For the above reasons, I cannot wholly satisfy myself that the shack is the<lb/>
one we are looking for. Do you agree with Mr. Moran that its construction is so un-<lb/>
usual as to erase all doubts? I await <unclear>news</unclear> from you with eagerness, but you will see<lb/>
why I don't know just how far to go in signing an option or buying the shack or making<lb/>
a final move until I have seen the Rojas family notes and have heard further from you<lb/>
or Moran, or both. You and Mr. Moran have been so wonderfully helpful that I can no<lb/>
longer take your suggestion that I write up the paper &ldquo;The true location of Camp<lb/>
Lazear&rdquo; under my own name alone, merely acknowledging your help. The help of yourself<lb/>
and Moran has been so crucial and so wonderful that you both must be co-authors whenever<lb/>
I get around to writing it up. I will leave for Washington, Pa. on October 23, will be<lb/>
here till then, and can be reached at the George Washington Hotel, Washington, Pa.<lb/>
October 25 and 26, then back here.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
