<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03622006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, October 16, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03622006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba), Rojas farm, San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-16">October 16, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03622006</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, October 16, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes valuable details on the yellow fever experiments he found in Agramonte's papers. Hench believes, along with Kean, that Agramonte has been treated unjustly.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, October 16, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03622006"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Wednesday<lb/>
<date value="1940-10-16">10/16/40</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Truby</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am writing you this in a rather unusual fashion -<lb/>
in pencil - as I am home &amp; want a carbon of this note. Please<lb/>
excuse it &amp; I hope you can read it. I hasten to mail you the<lb/>
last part of my W &amp; J talk to be given just 10 days from now<lb/>
I am so very anxious to have your approval of the manner<lb/>
<unclear>on what</unclear> I quote you. There will be plenty of time to correct or<lb/>
alter it before it is published in a Medical Journal but I have<lb/>
been asked to have a copy ready for the <hi>Press</hi> as soon as<lb/>
possible and want to be sure I have quoted you correctly<lb/>
As you see I have given all you fed me (that is as much as<lb/>
I deemed it proper to use) in quotation marks - not only to<lb/>
let the audience &amp; public understand clearly the source of<lb/>
my information, that is to give you full &amp; sole credit for<lb/>
that part but also because <unclear>that as</unclear> much more interesting<lb/>
to give it as a <hi>direct quotation</hi> &amp; I do hope you approve,</p>
<p>I will send you the first 11 pages as soon as they have<lb/>
been revised. Therein I give a running account of the<lb/>
well known orthodox version - the formation of the Board,<lb/>
the work at Columbia Barracks, Hospital, the Las Animas<lb/>
work, the death of Lazear (official <unclear>version</unclear>) &amp; then the work<lb/>
at Camp Lazear. To condense that much in 11 pages<lb/>
necessitated omitting much that I will eventually publish<lb/>
(2-3-4 years from now ??) in more ample form. But I<lb/>
was able to introduce <hi>all</hi> the characters involved, including<lb/>
yourself! Naturally in such a short account as this &amp;<lb/>
under the special circumstances I have dealts more with<lb/>
Lazear than the others and have therefore entitled this<lb/>
particular paper &ldquo;Dr Jesse W Lazear &amp; his contribution to the<lb/>
Conquest of Yellow Fever. In order not to be misunderstood<lb/>
and to be accused of playing favorites by relatives of<lb/>
C or A or by those who would favor Moran over Kissinger<lb/>
or vice versa I have attached a footnote on the front<lb/>
page as follows: on the occasion of the dedication<lb/>
of a Lazear memorial the writer deems it appropriate<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03622007"/>
(2<lb/>
to deal chiefly with the activities of Lazear but by so doing, it is<lb/>
not the writer's intention to minimize in the slightest degree the<lb/>
contribution of any of the several persons who participated in<lb/>
the conquest of this disease. The writer proposes to deal<lb/>
elsewhere &amp; more fully with the whole story.&rdquo;</p>
<p>If you approve of the way I have quoted you will you<lb/>
please wire me <hi>collect</hi> right away <unclear>-</unclear> just say &ldquo;Approved,&rdquo;<lb/>
or if you have any significant change Id appreciate it so<lb/>
much if you'd airmail it to me special delivery so that<lb/>
perhaps I can hear from you before Sunday or Monday<lb/>
I leave for the east on Wed.</p>
<p>I know you will be interested in <unclear>Miss</unclear> Agramonte's<lb/>
version. Perhaps you may criticize it where she<lb/>
gives her father's analysis of the <hi>possible</hi> motive which<lb/>
<unclear>actuated</unclear> Lazear to <unclear>inoculate</unclear> himself. And yet I,<lb/>
an outsider, found this analysis very interesting &amp; it<lb/>
is obviously only an opinion which cannot in any way<lb/>
harm Lazear's memory. I am aware of your contention<lb/>
that A. seems to have written lots more than he had the<lb/>
opportunity to know But Gen. Kean believes that he did<lb/>
an <unclear>injustice</unclear> to A in parts of the Senate Document and<lb/>
I hope I do not offend you or <unclear>seen</unclear> to show your <unclear>opinion</unclear><lb/>
any disrespect when I say that I believe Dr A <hi>must</hi><lb/>
have been more familiar with what was going on than<lb/>
some believe. When I first tried to work out the calendar<lb/>
(day to day &amp; hour to hour) of the whole story I found many<lb/>
<unclear>gaps in</unclear> the official versions &amp; several down right<lb/>
contradictions <unclear>in</unclear> dates &amp; other data as <unclear>given</unclear> in the<lb/>
various parts of the Senate Document &amp; indeed Reed's<lb/>
paper contain some contradictions. <unclear>Later</unclear> when I <unclear>offered</unclear><lb/>
Dr <unclear>A's</unclear> 1915 article I rejoiced for I (an outsider)<lb/>
found some <unclear>interest data</unclear> there that explained some of the<lb/>
contradictions &amp; other data or dates &amp; persons that<lb/>
appeared nowhere else. Let me give one example.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03622008"/>
3<lb/>
In one of Reeds papers he speaks of 2 non immunes being on the<lb/>
protected side of the mosquito Bldg. 1, later on he speaks of<lb/>
3 non immunes entering that room, still later he reverts to<lb/>
the figure two. Nobody was able to straighten me out on that<lb/>
part &amp; to show how confused others were Mrs <unclear>Hallock</unclear> who<lb/>
wrote up the Metropolitan Life Ins. Co <unclear>primer re</unclear> Reed et<lb/>
al couldn't straighten it out &amp; on their film she put<lb/>
2 persons, <unclear>in another diagram she</unclear> put 3. Well a<lb/>
perusal of Agramonte's paper explains it. In fact<lb/>
only 2 non-immunes <hi><unclear>stayed</unclear></hi> night after night in the<lb/>
protected side of the mosquito room but on the first<lb/>
day Reed himself as the other non-immune,<lb/>
went on about the other two to see how things were<lb/>
going. Only in <unclear>A's</unclear> paper is that recorded.</p>
<p>Another little point that makes me lend much<lb/>
credence to A's paper. only <unclear>his</unclear> paper tells of the story that<lb/>
the Spanish immigrants at Camp Lazear were allowed to<lb/>
acclimate themselves &amp; be studied in preliminary fashion<lb/>
while <hi>being occupied in picking up stones at the Camp</hi><lb/>
A small detail - yes let accurate &amp; to me it proved very<lb/>
useful. When we visited Mrs Rojas &amp; the San Jose farm<lb/>
I wasnt too sure whether I could trust their &ldquo;facts&rdquo;, recalled<lb/>
after 40 years. But one of the first things Mrs Rojas<lb/>
told me was the incident of the stone - picking. She<lb/>
had no knowledge that her farm had ever been called<lb/>
Camp Lazear. She didnt at first ever recall Reed's<lb/>
name. She knew nothing about the &ldquo;false Camp Lazear&rdquo;<lb/>
&amp; had never seen or heard of Agramonte's article <hi>nor<lb/>
had I mentioned the stone - picking episode</hi> &amp; yet she<lb/>
told me that It was one of the things that made <unclear>me</unclear> know<lb/>
She was telling the truth &amp; now (did I tell you this)<lb/>
they have found her husbands old day-book giving<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03622009"/>
(4<lb/>
a detailed record of the transactions <unclear>worked in</unclear> <hi>renting</hi><lb/>
Camp Lazear from &ldquo;Major Mr. Reed&rdquo; &amp; receiving checks<lb/>
from Major Kean &amp; <unclear>Dr Echeverria</unclear>. Also as a result<lb/>
we found that the Bldgs 1 &amp; 2 were <hi>NOT</hi> torn down but<lb/>
were to become the property of its owner &amp; as a further<lb/>
result we have discovered what may in truth be the<lb/>
remains of Bldg 1. - facing south &amp; measuring<lb/>
20 x 14 feet. I examined it <unclear>curiously</unclear> last spring on<lb/>
the outside but it has been altered some &amp; some<lb/>
<unclear>excesses</unclear> added &amp; it didnt look promising<lb/>
&amp; I couldn't quite reconcile it with the slope of the land<lb/>
but further study of photos, <unclear>Arpography</unclear>, new photos<lb/>
compared to old ones etc etc has made me very hopeful that<lb/>
we have indeed found one of the silent witnesses of<lb/>
great deeds. Unfortunately the Bldg # 2 was torn<lb/>
down just 5 years ago!</p>
<p>Well I have digressed but I meant to indicate<lb/>
why I have given much credence to A's remark &amp;<lb/>
to Miss A's version of <unclear>them</unclear>. She is a <hi>most charming</hi><lb/>
person, wonderfully cultured. You'd be delighted with her.<lb/>
She let me see her fathers letters &amp; papers &amp; I found so<lb/>
many evidences of (apparent?) humility that I could<lb/>
not but be impressed.</p>
<p>(By the way our Bldg # 1 has &ldquo;tongued &amp; grooved<lb/>
boards&rdquo; <unclear>too<del>"</del></unclear>!</p>
<p><unclear>My but</unclear> I wish you could be write us next Saturday.<lb/>
I do hope I may pay my respects to you in California<lb/>
before another year passes. Your <unclear>paper</unclear> is <hi>GRAND</hi> &amp;<lb/>
MUST be published. I will write you some thoughts<lb/>
on that when I got my <unclear>health</unclear>. Unfortunately I am<lb/>
not only writing up this Y F stuff but the letter<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03622010"/>
(5<lb/>
is a mere side issue which came at the time I am trying to<lb/>
finish <unclear>on</unclear> Seventh Annual Rheumatism Review which I<lb/>
edit yearly &amp; write (90%) myself. It is due in 3<lb/>
weeks &amp; is 300 pages long!! Did I send you one of<lb/>
last year? Would you like to receive the Proceedings<lb/>
of the Mayo Clinic with my complements - no cost to<lb/>
you?</p>
<p>Thank you so much for letting me keep the<lb/>
memorandum a little longer. Dare I be bold<lb/>
enough to make a wish? I am something of a<lb/>
bibliophile &amp; autograph fiend. I have a really nice<lb/>
medical library - original copies of <unclear>Waltering, Jenner,</unclear><lb/>
Beaumont - not many but some. I also have a small<lb/>
but nice collection of letters of <unclear>Pasteur, Paget,<lb/>
Addison, Lester etc etc.</unclear> <hi>IF</hi> you revise the copy<lb/>
of your mss &amp; are about to throw it away (the copy<lb/>
with your &amp; Kean's Marginal notes) I would be<lb/>
eternally grateful if you'd <hi><unclear>strive it my</unclear> way</hi> that I<lb/>
could add it to my own small yellow fever collection<lb/>
I can assure you it will <hi>always</hi> be preserved. The<lb/>
Mayo clinic library (<unclear>Museum Section</unclear>) has already<lb/>
asked me for some of my data &amp; I have promised<lb/>
full access of my data (photostats of whatever <unclear>they<lb/>
want</unclear> that is <unclear>discrete</unclear>) etc to the Univ. of Va. library<lb/>
(my brother is Prof of English literature there), also to<lb/>
the Welsh library &amp; the Army Museum.</p>
<p>But enough of my terrible handwriting.<lb/>
I would so appreciate your prompt comment<lb/>
(approval or corrections) of my paper.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Philip S Hench</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
