<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03626001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter and notes from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to Philip Showalter Hench, October 10, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03626001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Frances F.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Agramonte Memorial Library, Louisiana State University School of Medicine, New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Hospital Aristides Agramonte, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-10">October 10, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03626001</idno>
<title>Letter and notes from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to Philip Showalter Hench, October 10, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Mrs. Agramonte Rodriguez Leon discusses her father's views on Lazear's and Carroll's actions and roles in the yellow fever experiments, commenting specifically on Hench's notes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-10">
<head>Letter and notes from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to Philip Showalter Hench, October 10, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03626001"/>
<p>15 Street No. 311, Vedado,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba.-<lb/>
<date value="1940-10-10">October 10th., 1940</date>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
102-<unclear>11i</unclear> Second Avenue S.W.,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
Dear Dr. Hench:</p>
<p>I have read the carbon copy of your notes sent in August very<lb/>
carefully and found them deeply interesting. I wish to congratulate<lb/>
you on your excellent and methodical investigation of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Story.</p>
<p>In almost every point I think you have arrived at correct and im-<lb/>
partial conclusions and you have my permission to quote me or my Father<lb/>
in any of your statements, <hi>with a few corrections</hi>.</p>
<p>I hope my present notes to your paragraph 103 will not dissapoint<lb/>
you. I know, by experience<unclear>,</unclear> how easily in research work one <unclear>falls</unclear> in love<lb/>
with one's subject. In remarking upon this part of your notes I am really<lb/>
trying to be absolutely just to Lazear and at the same time historically<lb/>
exact. There is no doubt in my mind as to my Father's conviction of La-<lb/>
zear's self-experiment but, try as I may, I cannot recall his having<lb/>
ever mentioned that Lazear <hi>confessed</hi> to having done so. I am sorry if I<lb/>
gave you that impression during our two hasty interviews on the subject.</p>
<p>I have no objection to having this version of Lazear's sacrifice,<lb/>
which I believe actually existed, made public, and my Father if he were<lb/>
living would surely be willing to confirm his belief in <del><unclear></unclear></del> same. Never-<lb/>
theless <hi>I cannot truthfully quote</hi> Dr. Agramonte as having received Lazear's<lb/>
confession. Perhaps Kean or Truby, though I doubt that they were ever <unclear>mor-</unclear><lb/>
on terms of greater intimacy with Lazear than Agramonte, may have some<lb/>
proof of it.</p>
<p>There is a last scruple in the back of my mind. Have you consulted<lb/>
Lazear's widow about divulging his secret, and are you sure that your<lb/>
glorification of her husband <unclear>will</unclear> not deprive her of needed financial sup-<lb/>
port?</p>
<p>If so, I agree with you that the dedication of the Lazear Memorial<lb/>
would be a most appropiate time to make public the quiet and heroic ges-<lb/>
ture of the man and <unclear><add>the</add></unclear> scientist. Greater even, to my way of thinking <unclear>because</unclear><lb/>
he carried his secret of it to a better world, and did not offer himself<lb/>
to applause or praise. He was an extraordinary personality, and my Father<lb/>
always admired him for his charmingly distinguished manners and high moral<lb/>
and intellectual virtues.</p>
<p>I have also made a minor correction to your paragraph 29. Otherwise<lb/>
I have simply amplified or tried to check you own notes.</p>
<p>A few questions I am unable to answer yet, and understanding that <del>yo</del><lb/>
you are by now urgently pressed for time, I shall not try your patience<lb/>
any longer by making you wait. I shall <del>try</del><add>endeavor</add> to send the rest in the next<lb/>
few days (specially the copy of Reed's letters about Caroll's and Lazear's<lb/>
illness).</p>
<p>The beginning of the school term has kept me very busy. I finally<lb/>
decided to devote the holiday of Batista's &ldquo;coronation&rdquo; to the job. I<lb/>
tried to call Mrs. Philips on the telephone yesterday, but could no get in<lb/>
touch with her. Therefore, with three holidays in succession, I decided<lb/>
to give you whatever help I can, for what it may be worth, and without<lb/>
further delay. Please excuse my English and if you quote me, do not<lb/>
hesitate to make any grammatical corrections. I am typing this off as<lb/>
fast as I can in the hope of getting it into the morning airmail.</p>
<p>My husband joins me in sending his best regards. Please remember<lb/>
me to Mrs. Hench.</p>
<p>Very cordially,<lb/>
Estela Agramonte Rodr&iacute;guez Le&oacute;n.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03626002"/>
<p>(Specific remarks on Dr. Hench's notes: Lazear Memorial)-</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 13.-</hi> Your version is quite correct. You may quote Dr. Agramonte<lb/>
(The Inside History of a Great Medical Discovery) p. 4-5. I have many let-<lb/>
ters on this point of my Father to Dr. Peabody of Macmillan Co. Dr. P comple<lb/>
ted a lecture tour of more than 400 high-schools and colleges and was ins-<lb/>
trumental in obtaining the U.S. pension for the Yellow Fever Board and<lb/>
Volunteers. One of the two Senators from Mass. who passed the Bill was a<lb/>
near relation of his. He also contributed largely to the house, cow, etc<lb/>
given to Kissinger by popular collection, and was naturally quite enthu-<lb/>
siastic about Kissinger's version of the affair. My Father was able, later,<lb/>
to <unclear>disaprove</unclear> most of it, (Dean's episode in particular) entirely to Mr. P<lb/>
satisfaction. I'm afraid Dr. A. was not very kind to K. whom he considered<lb/>
an impertinent an unruly soldier, and only too willing, in after years, to<lb/>
pose as a martyr in the hopes of mercenary gain. An interesting episode in<lb/>
Mr. P campaign was during his delivery of the Story of Yellow Fever at <unclear>a</unclear><lb/>
high school in California. One of the students present introduced himself<lb/>
later. He was Lazear's son.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 14</hi>.- I am convinced that it was an agreement between Lazear and<lb/>
Agramonte. See p. 20, parag. 3 of the Agramonte paper and also <unclear>p. 19</unclear> parag. 1<lb/>
There were no orders from Reed, who agreed to the judiciousness of their<lb/>
decision when he returned in October.,(See same p. 20, line <unclear>82</unclear>) thereby ne-<lb/>
ver submitting himself to the bite of mosquitoes. Lazear, Caroll and Agra-<lb/>
monte did so many times before Carolls infection.</p>
<p>I remember hearing my <unclear>Father's</unclear> remarks on the conscience-stricken attitude<lb/>
of Lazear's after C infection. Agramonte had trouble in quieting him. Grad-<lb/>
ually the possibility that C., who had gone out of Camp several times in<lb/>
the previous days, might have contracted it elsewhere; and C own conviction<lb/>
that he had caught it in Las Animas autopsy room, contibuted to his peace<lb/>
of mind. Nevertheless, Dr. A, knowing how severely <unclear><add>Lazear</add></unclear> accused himself of C's<lb/>
infection and how passionately he cherished those &ldquo;loaded&rdquo; mosquitoes of<lb/>
theirs, always believed that Lazear might have fed some weakened and starv-<lb/>
ing insect on himself. In so doing he would have partly disregarded their<lb/>
joint resolution not <unclear>so</unclear> subject themselves to further experiments on the<lb/>
eve of their important results. He had made A. also promise solemnly not to<lb/>
rely any more on his own supposed inmunity - all expect Reed, who was away<lb/>
most of the time, had repeatedly fed the insects on themselves - since he<lb/>
had been away from the y.f. zone since early childhood. My father used to<lb/>
point out also, that at that stage of their work the exact number of days<lb/>
required for the development of the virus in the body of the mosquito had<lb/>
not yet been definitely established; that frequently infected mosquitoes<lb/>
were applied to volunteer subjects time and again on successive days without<lb/>
producing a case of y.f. It was my Father's personal surmise that Lazear<lb/>
might have risked feeding one of these, though the idea of mosquito trans-<lb/>
mission had, after C's illness, taken firm hold of their minds. Possibly,<lb/>
in so doing, his subconcious desire of atonement, for what he considered his<lb/>
responsability in Caroll's sacrifice, silenced his honourable intention of<lb/>
keeping his pledge to Agramonte, further justifying himself perhaps, in his<lb/>
own doubt as to the virulence of some of his specimen mosquitoes which<lb/>
apparently failed to porduce <del>a</del> cases of Y.F. His pathetic attempts, in his<lb/>
lucid moments, to convince C. &amp; A that he had not experimented on himself<lb/>
was gainsayed by his constant and half delirious repetition of his confidence<lb/>
in his own <unclear>inmunity</unclear> after several unsuccessful inoculations, his belief un-<lb/>
shaken even, after Caroll's and <unclear>Dean's</unclear> recent infection. (see Agramonte p. 22)<lb/>
He later recalled the bite of the &ldquo;Las Animas&rdquo; mosquito and the possibility<lb/>
of other such instances.</p>
<p>All references to Agramonte paper on these pages are from <unclear>&ldquo;</unclear>The Inside History<lb/>
of a Great Medical Discovery<unclear>&rdquo;</unclear> of which I gave you a copy.<lb/>
<unclear>E. A R.</unclear></p>
<p>Agramonte believed firmly that <hi>there were no yellow fever mosquitoes</hi><lb/>
straying around the wards, where the patients were naturally kept under<lb/>
quarantine isolation. Common mosquitoes, perhaps, but <del>aside</del> apart from<lb/>
the strictly sanitary condictions (wire, netting, etc) the stegomyai speci-<lb/>
mens which the Board used on its experiments were carefully bred and guard-<lb/>
ed in their laboratory<del>es</del> tubes and bowls. No one was allowed to touch them,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03626003"/>
(Remarks to Dr. Hench's paper on Lazear)<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
outside the members of the board. My Father was sure that if a <add>few</add> y.f. mos-<lb/>
quitoes had chosen to appear in the Las Animas or Military Hospital wards<lb/>
where y.f. patients were interned a disastrous epidemic would have rapidly<lb/>
spread through the hundreds of non-inmune troops nearby. This, fortunately<lb/>
did not occur; cases were either brought in form distant local sprouts of<lb/>
the disease or had been exposed to contagion in less strictly watched parts<lb/>
of the city or garrisons. As thier work progressed, even greater precau-<lb/>
tions and rules were observed. Actually Lazear believed that the Las Ani-<lb/>
mas mosquito bite that he remembered had been given by<del>a</del> a common or culex<lb/>
type.</p>
<p>It was my Father's opinion that Lazear's natural modesty made him shrink<lb/>
from posing as a hero in what seemed to him, on his sickbed a rather fool-<lb/>
hardy and unnecessary action after all, perhaps even unfair to the beloved<lb/>
wife and children far away.</p>
<p>Perhaps these final remarks, which you may quote in any form you wish,<lb/>
may clarify the basic moral conviction of Agramonte as to Lazear's <hi>uncon-<lb/>
fessed</hi> heroism.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 17.</hi>- There are two or three personal letters from Reed to Lazear<lb/>
&amp; Agramonte during Caroll's illness. I haven't the time to look them up<lb/>
for you now, but I came across them when searching for the pictures. Also<lb/>
a great many <hi>personal</hi> and extravagant letters to Caroll<del>s</del>, himself, quoted<lb/>
by him in the Donally and Hemmeter papers, and which my Father believed to<lb/>
be absolutely apocrifous. Really, (I remember reading them a long time ago<unclear>,)</unclear><lb/>
the style and general tone of the correspondence is very different from<lb/>
other letters of Reed, the originals of which I have. Also, I believe, a<lb/>
long cable-letter after Lazear's illness had been notified him, rather<lb/>
official in tone this last.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 19.-</hi> Reed arrived a few days after Lazear's death Sept 25. He<lb/>
returned to the U.S. two weeks later (see Agramonte p. 21, paragraphs 1 &amp; 4)<lb/>
He read the Board's Preliminary Note on Oct. 24 in Indianapolis, therefore<lb/>
sailing north before this last date.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 21.</hi>- Father's notes have the date of Reed's return in November.<lb/>
Not available today. I will try to send <add>it</add> within a few days.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 29.</hi>- Dr. Agramonte was <hi>not in</hi> on the Guiteras experiments at Las<lb/>
Animas in Aug. 1901. Neither was Caroll supposed to have anything to do<lb/>
with them. At the start the Cuban doctors were provided with the techni-<lb/>
cal findings of the Army Board by my Father, but not satisfied with the<lb/>
irregular way in which the work was being carried on (poor judgment in<lb/>
selecting volunteers, careless manipulation, etc.) he reported to Wood<lb/>
and was ordered <del><unclear>not</unclear></del> to keep out of it. When Caroll arrived my Father<lb/>
did not know of his participation in the experiments till some time later.<lb/>
Agramonte never believed that C had secret personal instructions from Reed<lb/>
to do so, but rather that he thought this might be a chance to &ldquo;get ahead&rdquo;<lb/>
of the rest of the Board in some important discovery. There was consider-<lb/>
able ill-feeling between A. and C. when the former found out he was being<lb/>
disloyal to the Board's initial pledge of doing everything as a unit, not<lb/>
individually. I have a large correspondence, official and otherwise to<lb/>
that effect; later the Hemmeter episode proved Dr. A. was right as to C<lb/>
attitude towards himself. Caroll was and odd and ego-centric sort of chap,<lb/>
suspicious of everybody and inordinately ambitious.</p>
<p>Note: the above is cofidential, of course,. Please do not include my<lb/>
Father in the Guiteras experiments, a responsability he had the foresight<lb/>
not to share.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 32.</hi>- New soldiers quarters were built in 1934 or 1935. Officers<lb/>
homes had been built by Machado in 1927-1929. I obtained the promise of<lb/>
Mr. Tom&aacute;s Roig, our best botanist, to visit the supposed site of Camp Lazear<lb/>
for examination of the flamboyant tree. He is to give me a written report<lb/>
of age which he believes very easy to estimate. Unfortunately he is away<lb/>
from Havana at present, but will return shortly after the change of gov-<lb/>
ernment (today oct. 10th). I will keep this in mind and report to you soon.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03626004"/>
<p>(Remarks to Dr. Hench's paper on Lazear)</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 50.</hi>- <del><unclear>Yours</unclear></del> Your appreciation of facts is absolutely correct. I am<lb/>
willing to <hi>support your statements at any time</hi>. It is perhaps the most un-<lb/>
biased opinion that has come to my notice on this matter.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 52.</hi>- The National Hospital of the Cuban Army was named after Agra<lb/>
monte by Army Resolution of .......... That I know of, it has never been<lb/>
officially dedicated. I have not been there but I believe Dr. Ramos would<lb/>
have notified me if any monument had been erected.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 94.-</hi> Dr. Recio was a good friend of my Father's and I have no<lb/>
reason to doubt his word but, has he any <hi>written</hi> statement of Agramonte<lb/>
in recognition of the tree or the &ldquo;false&rdquo; site of Camp Lazear? My Father<lb/>
was very exact and precise in his statements. It seems odd that I have<lb/>
found no copy of so memorable a picture among his papers. Amateur phpto<lb/>
graphy was one of his pet hobbies, we owned and he drove himself, two cars<lb/>
at the time (1920's). Wouldn't his keen sense of investigation <add><unclear>have</unclear></add> taken him<lb/>
immediately and easily to the appointed site to get some pictures of his<lb/>
own in corroboration of Recio's discovery? More so, <unclear><add>seeing that</add><del>if</del></unclear> &ldquo;The tree was the<lb/>
only thing recognizable&rdquo; in R's picture.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 102.</hi>- See my notes to paragraph 14.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 103</hi>.- I cannot vouch for the first part of this paragraph.<lb/>
Lazear, that I know of, <hi>never told Agramonte</hi> about <add>having</add> deliberately <unclear>feed<del>ing</del></unclear><lb/>
an infected mosquito on himself after their agreement. It was my Father's con<lb/>
viction that he had done so/. I have tried to give as accurate an account<lb/>
as I can of my Father's opinion on the matter in my notes to paragraph 14.<lb/>
It <add>is</add> my opinion that you can build up a very beautiful picture of his mental<lb/>
conflict and <hi>possible</hi> inoculation. I <hi>can not find any record</hi> in my Father's<lb/>
papers that he actually confessed to having subjected himself to infection.<lb/>
If he <del>had</del> really infected himself he rather sheepishly tried to explain it<lb/>
away when stricken with y.f. A further search in Agramonte's papers may per<lb/>
haps bring to light the above, but I doubt it. You are very welcome to go<lb/>
over them at any future time, and I hope you will have the opportunity to<lb/>
do so. I am sorry, but I cannot historically accept the first 10 lines<lb/>
of paragraph 103. (carbon copy of notes sent to me)</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 104.</hi>- I do not remember quoting that Lazear fell ill 8 days af-<lb/>
ter any set date of inoculation. I do no know enough about the medical<lb/>
picture of y.f. to mention technical data You may have misunderstood my<lb/>
statement that, in trying to acquit himself of blame in Caroll's inocula-<lb/>
tion, he told my Father he had often allowed himself to be bitten by those<lb/>
same mosquitoes on the days prior to C's experiment. I can even imagine<lb/>
him having fed caroll's own mosquito, not <del>acquiring</del><add><unclear>contracting</unclear></add> the disease then be-<lb/>
cause the bug was not sufficiently &ldquo;ripe&rdquo; at the time.</p>
<p><hi>Paragraph 105.</hi>- I am sending you my Father's longhand notes on his speech<lb/>
at the Gorgas and Kean banquet. You have my permission to <add>have</add> a photostatic<lb/>
copy made; perhaps, by passing india-ink over the pencil writing, it will<lb/>
become legible in print.</p>
<p>I do not quite see your angle of what you term the Agramonte &ldquo;hint&rdquo;.<lb/>
He may have referred to a voluntary inoculation (his own personal convic-<lb/>
tion) but then again he may also simply refer to one of Lazear's many bites<lb/>
immediately before their pledge or mutu<del>t</del>al agreement. Also possibly in-<lb/>
cluding a &ldquo;dig&rdquo; to Caroll's <hi>accidental</hi><del>a</del> and not experimental inoculation<lb/>
<del>, seeing</del><add><unclear>in view of the fact</unclear></add> that they all, and C especially, did not fully believe in the<lb/>
virulence of those mosquitoes.</p>
<p>You may of course quote Dr. AGramonte, but whatever conclusions you<lb/>
arrive at about the matter, please give them <hi>as your own</hi>.</p>
<p>-------------</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p><hi>Additional notes:</hi></p>
<p>Dr. AGramonte's ashes are buried in Greenwood Cemetery, Brooklyn my Moth<lb/>
ers family plot (her maiden name <unclear>was</unclear> <hi>Pierra)</hi> He was cremated in New York.<lb/>
A small headstone marks the place, I have never been in condition to afford<lb/>
bringing <del>him</del><add>his remains</add> down <del><unclear>near</unclear></del> here where I should like to have <unclear>them</unclear></p>
<pb n="5" id="f03626005"/>
<p>(Remarks to Dr. Hench's paper on Lazear)</p>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>2-I believe many of my Father's papers to be in the &ldquo;Louisiana State Medical<lb/>
Centre, Agramonte Memorial Library, to which we donated his large medical<lb/>
library with many valuable autographs of scientific interest. I am afraid<lb/>
some private correspondence was mistakenly removed with the books, as quite<lb/>
a few personal things have been traced there in later years, by my Mother<lb/>
and myself. Sometime I hope to visit the place which, I have been told, is<lb/>
really beautiful. The only monument I know erected to his memory and that<lb/>
of the Board with the exception of <add>a</add> small tablet<del><unclear>s</unclear></del> to Lazear in the Columbia<lb/>
Alumni Hall of Fame, <del>to which</del><add>where</add> they intended to add one to Agramonte. By<lb/>
the way, Agramonte was largely responsible for this small memorial to Lazear;<lb/>
around this subject he published several articles, a few letters and a short<lb/>
address on his life and works. (x)</p>
<p>3-Since you mention the Agramonte article in Scientific Monthly, Dec 1915.<lb/>
you are acquainted with the small pen and ink drawings or plans made by<lb/>
him of Camp Lazear buildings. I have copies of same, his handwriting is <unclear>cl</unclear><lb/>
clearly discernible on the reprints in the article.</p>
<p>4-I am enclsing a little picture I found interesting. Is it the same site<lb/>
of Las Animas or Military Hospital where the other picture of Lazear, Caroll<lb/>
and Agramonte was taken? Can you possibly identify it by your later inspec-<lb/>
tions of old photographs in Washington? Caroll may be the man with my Father<lb/>
though not in uniform; possibly during his second visit in Havana. Could it<lb/>
be Dr. Rojas and this one of the two buildings on Camp Lazear<unclear>?</unclear> it seems too<lb/>
open a house for the mosquito experiments, and is <del><unclear>undoubtedly mad</unclear></del><add>apparently built</add> of brick<lb/>
and cement. Please return, as it is my only copy of same.</p>
<p>-------------------------------</p>
<p>(x) Also a small exhibit, dedicated to the Board in the Natural<lb/>
History Museum of N. Y.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
