<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03627004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, October 20, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03627004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, (Havana)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-20">October 20, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03627004</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, October 20, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus discusses the yellow fever experiments and his own experience with inoculation.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-20">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, October 20, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03627004"/>
<opener>
J.H. ANDRUS<lb/>
<dateline>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1940-10-20">10-20-40</date>
</dateline>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<salute>Dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In your letter of the fifteenth you suggest that I send your<lb/>
manuscript to Lambert. I know that he would enjoy reading<lb/>
it and it is quite possible that he would be able to add de-<lb/>
tails that would be helpful. The serious drawback is that<lb/>
his eyesight is so very poor that he would be unable to read<lb/>
it. In this mail I am telling him of your suggestion and<lb/>
putting it up to him as to whether I send it or not. It may<lb/>
be that there is someone available who could read it to him.</p>
<p>As for Dr. Ames' part in the work - Some time ago I wrote<lb/>
a chapter called &ldquo;I become a Guinea pig&rdquo; which was part of a<lb/>
condensed autobiography entitled &ldquo;Big Moments in a Little<lb/>
Life&rdquo;. The chapter referred to deals, of course, with my<lb/>
personal experience with Major Reed's Board. Let me hasten<lb/>
to assure you that no part of this is intended for publica-<lb/>
tion. It is, on the contrary, merely intended to quench any<lb/>
thirst my young grandson may develop (I hope) about his<lb/>
&ldquo;Grand-poppie&rdquo; in years to come. I would not like to have<lb/>
him derive his knowledge of my yellow fever interlude from<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; or any one of several other things I have read<lb/>
on the subject.</p>
<p>Excuse me for wandering but now I'm back to Dr. Ames. In my<lb/>
story is an incident that you may find worth lifting. Just<lb/>
as soon as I am able to copy the chapter, will send it to you.<lb/>
It is not probable that you will find much in it that you can<lb/>
use but I want you to feel perfectly free to use anything you<lb/>
want. There is but one copy of my effort.</p>
<p>When I return your manuscript you will find &ldquo;I never saw Dr.<lb/>
Agramonte do <hi>anything</hi> at the laboratory except confer with<lb/>
the Major&rdquo;. In my last letter to you I did <hi>not</hi> express what<lb/>
I had in mind. The sentence I refer to should have read:<lb/>
&ldquo;Early in the exteriments, mosquitoes <hi>may have</hi> been been pro-<lb/>
cured and innoculated by Dr. Agramonte&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I was not detailed for duty with the Board until <add>early October,</add> shortly after<lb/>
Dr. Lazear's death. Then, after my innoculation, a little<lb/>
less than four months later, I did not return to duty with the<lb/>
Board. That period was the golden hour of the experiments.</p>
<p>We kept no innoculated mosquitoes at the laboratory. Our job<lb/>
was to furnish mosquitoes ready for innoculation. The &ldquo;birds&rdquo;<lb/>
were selected by Major Reed or Lieutenant Carroll and taken<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03627005"/>
2.<lb/>
away in test tubes. None, in my time, were ever taken away<lb/>
by Dr. Agramonte. I can only guess who innoculated them.<lb/>
My guess was that Dr. Agramonte MAY HAVE innoculated some of<lb/>
the earlier insects at Los Animas Hospital. After Camp La-<lb/>
zear was established and cases produced there, it is my guess<lb/>
that mosquitoes were innoculated at the yellow fever hospital,<lb/>
at Columbia Barracks, by Dr. Carroll, Major Reed or Dr. Ames.<lb/>
It is my belief that infected insects were applied to volun-<lb/>
teers, at Camp Lazear, by one of the same trio. I believe<lb/>
that liklihood, for both operations, is in the order they are<lb/>
named. (1-Carroll, 2-Reed and 3-Ames.)</p>
<p>I remember the cold spell and comment on it in my notes with<lb/>
your manuscript.</p>
<p>Am enclosing a letter from Dr. Cook. Rather, answers from<lb/>
him to questions I asked. It is not what I expected but may<lb/>
interest you.</p>
<p>With reference to my innoculation, there was a slight irreg-<lb/>
ularity. All other volunteers - after Dr. Carroll and Dean -<lb/>
had been quarantined at Camp Lazear before their innoculation.<lb/>
In my case, I had slept in the Corps men's quarters the night<lb/>
before and worked in the laboratory until a few minutes before<lb/>
my &ldquo;shot&rdquo; was given me. Then, I walked to the yellow fever<lb/>
hospital and waited outside one of the wards while blood was<lb/>
taken from Forbes' arm. It was injected in my arm right<lb/>
there, <unclear>in</unclear> the open. It seems incredible but I cannot remem-<lb/>
ber who made the innoculation. Until I was ready to put it<lb/>
on paper I would have said it was Dr. Ames. I believe, how-<lb/>
ever, that Dr. Ames was sick and in bed at the Post Hospital<lb/>
at that time.</p>
<p>Thank you for flattering my stenographer. I'll let her read<lb/>
your letter instead of giving her a &ldquo;raise&rdquo;. As a matter of<lb/>
fact I am &ldquo;her&rdquo;. I have a stand rigged up to straddle my<lb/>
body. The top is on an incline of about 45 degrees. The<lb/>
typewriter hangs from the top, in front of me, and I use it<lb/>
while flat on my back. And don't let it worry you - it is<lb/>
no more tiring than as though I was up and around.</p>
<p>You are doing me a favor to present a subject in which I am<lb/>
interested.</p>
<p>With kindest regards,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>J H Andrus</signed>
<seg>
Postscript * The photograph of hospital at Columbia Barracks<lb/>
was mailed yesterday. - JHA.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
