<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03623004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, October 7, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03623004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Julian</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis B.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Rojas farm (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Museum of the Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">Army Medical Museum, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-07">October 7, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03623004</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, October 7, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] writes that he doubts Moran has really found the infected-clothing building. [Hench] wants to buy the property.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-07">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, October 7, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03623004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-10-07">October 7, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
Avenida Menoccal 455<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was of course delighted with your airmail letter of October 3, and not<lb/>
a little amused. You were so sure that I would be angry with you. I can assure you that<lb/>
no one could ever get angry with you and the enormous help that you have given me is such<lb/>
that I am forever indebted to you. Before I forget it, I am afraid you will be running low<lb/>
on cash for the various odds and ends that I have asked you to do. I therefore enclose a<lb/>
check for twenty-five dollars and whether you will wish to pay a photographer or use this<lb/>
for some other purpose, I leave entirely up to you. Undoubtedly, you have had a number<lb/>
of taxi-cab charges, running back and forth to the camp, etc. and I must insist upon your<lb/>
letting me pay for these. I will be expecting other bills from you or from Mrs. Phillips.<lb/>
I am delighted to know that you are coming to Washington and am anxious to know the date<lb/>
you will be in Charlottesville.</p>
<p>After receiving your first letter, I waited excitedly for the second but for<lb/>
reasons which you have explained, it did not arrive until last night. You can imagine how<lb/>
delighted I am that Miss Rojas and you have uncovered her father's book showing without<lb/>
doubt that Camp Lazear was on their farm. I am extremely anxious to see the translation<lb/>
and hope you will have Mrs. Phillips hurry it along to me <hi>by airmail.</hi> It may take a dollar<lb/>
or so in postage, but it is worth it to me. (Incidentally, in your postage could you send<lb/>
me some of the eight-cent Agramonte stamps, and I should like a couple of them uncancelled.<lb/>
Obviously, this is not Dr. Agramonte. Was it his father?) When I receive your translation<lb/>
of Dr. Rojas' book, I may ask you to either have one or two pages photographed or, better<lb/>
yet, I may write Senora Rojas and ask her whether she would be willing to let you bring the<lb/>
book with you. I think it would be most interesting to our audience to show it to them<lb/>
and I should like to have it to photostat the pertinent pages. No matter how impressive or<lb/>
truthful a stenographic translation may be, for purposes of future proof, the most impressive<lb/>
would be actual photographs of the pertinent pages. I could have this done at the Clinic<lb/>
at practically no cost to me. It would doubtless be pretty expensive to have the photo-<lb/>
grapher do it in Havana unless there were only three or four pages to be photographed.</p>
<p>I was much excited by your statements regarding the possible discovery of the<lb/>
infected clothing building, but there are parts of your letter which make me rather dubious.<lb/>
Remember that the infected clothing building faced due south. It is described rather<lb/>
accurately by Reed, who mentions the windows, the entrance, the size, and the &ldquo;tongued and<lb/>
grooved boards&rdquo;, but he does not mention a concrete floor in either of the buildings, and<lb/>
the army pictures of both these buildings (see especially 17b and c) indicate that the<lb/>
infected clothing building at least was a few inches off the ground. There are apparently<lb/>
three steps leading up to it, as shown in photograph 16a. Are you absolutely sure that the<lb/>
building you are trying to identify as building no. 1 faces due south? As I visualize it on<lb/>
my map of the Rojas farm, it does not quite face south.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03623005"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>The tongued and grooved boards which you found, sound most interesting. Do<lb/>
you think that is sufficiently unique in a Cuban house to be considered satisfactory proof?<lb/>
Assuming you have a copy of your last letter to me of October 5, please note that in one<lb/>
sentence you say the mosquito building was torn down about four or five years ago. Slabs<lb/>
of the concrete floor can still be seen in the tilled field where you had some photographs<lb/>
of me taken, the site being much more to the left, viewed from the front of building no. 1,<lb/>
than where I stand in the picture. My comments on these sentences are as follows: The way<lb/>
you write it, you infer that the mosquito building had a concrete floor. I doubt this.<lb/>
Why would the mosquito building have three steps leading up to it if it had a concrete floor?<lb/>
Furthermore, how could the concrete floor concern the mosquito building if you found it<lb/>
&ldquo;much more to the left from the front of building no. 1&rdquo;? You will note in photographs<lb/>
17b and c, and 16a that the two buildings were opposite each other. You also mention Mr.<lb/>
Z.'s attempts to identify the present tree so closely to what he would have you believe to<lb/>
be building no. 1. But again note in the photograph already mentioned, that there is no<lb/>
tree near building no. 1. Either, therefore, the present trees are all younger than forty<lb/>
years, or the building is not building no. 1. There are no trees in the immediate vicinity<lb/>
of building no. 2, although there is one some yards away.</p>
<p>You remember Mr. Z's comments to us while I was there. Some of his information<lb/>
may be correct, but I suspect that most of it is not. You may be able to weed out the false<lb/>
from the true and still find that the building is no. 1. Next time you go out, could you<lb/>
take a measuring tape and measure it? Remember that it was exactly 20 x 14 feet. If this<lb/>
really were building no. 1 and if you will take photograph 16a, b or c, and stand in the<lb/>
appropriate place, should not the Rojas farmhouse be visible in these photographs? In the<lb/>
background <hi>on the left</hi>? Regardless of whether you are right or wrong, I shall be delighted<lb/>
to have whatever photographs you have had taken. I should much prefer to buy extra photo-<lb/>
graphs to get the right one than to buy too few. I hope they are all on the way. My first<lb/>
inclination last night was to wire you to have Pogolotti act as my agent and get a price<lb/>
for this shack and a small plot of land around it. Certainly the shack should be worth very<lb/>
little to anyone else. My purpose in doing this was to buy it promptly, so that it would be<lb/>
cared for until I can try to collect from interested parties enough to restore it and preserve<lb/>
it. If you are willing, I would still like you to ask Pogolotti how much he thinks it would<lb/>
cost, but I hope that Mr. Z., if he is the owner, will not jack <add>up</add> the price way out of reach<lb/>
because of our interest in it. What would be the cost for an option on this building until<lb/>
I could get down, perhaps in February? Should I buy it I would not ask the owner to leave<lb/>
(or tenant) but merely ask Mr. Pogolotti to see to it that it could be inspected every few<lb/>
weeks so that no harm would come to it. Don't misunderstand me. I would not expect the<lb/>
Cuban government to contribute a nickel, but if that really is building no. 1, I am sure<lb/>
I could raise enough money to tear down the junky additions and to restore the building<lb/>
as necessary. At the moment, I am only interested in buying enough land around it to protect<lb/>
the building. The above was my inclination as of last night. But having studied the pictures<lb/>
and documents again several hours, and not being too sure that Mr. Z has given you correct<lb/>
information, this morning I am cautious and would merely ask you and Pogolotti to make a<lb/>
quiet and tentative appraisal of the real estate value and of an option and final charge.</p>
<p>I would give my eye teeth to own Dr. Rojas' day book, but doubtless the family<lb/>
may want to keep it in their possession for awhile. It should eventually go in a museum and I<lb/>
would like to tell them this some time. If they would be willing to leave it to the Museum of<lb/>
the Mayo Clinic, I could assure them it would be properly taken care of for all time. Other<lb/>
suitable institutions would be the Army Medical Museum or Johns Hopkins, the Walter Reed<lb/>
Hospital, or University of Virginia. Naturally, I wish the Mayo Clinic may eventually win out,<lb/>
and to replace it I can assure you I would have the entire thing photostated so that they might<lb/>
have permanent record as long as they wish it. I shall of course await further letters from<lb/>
you with great interest.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely yours,</salute>
AC<lb/>
<unclear>m</unclear><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
