<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03623002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 5, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03623002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Julian</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Sosa, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Demetrio</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-05">October 5, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03623002</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 5, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran informs Hench that he has been exploring the area where Camp Lazear was located and has seen part of the infected-clothing building and the site of the mosquito building.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-05">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 5, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03623002"/>
<opener>
<hi>VIA AIR MAIL</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1940-10-05">Oct. 5, 1940.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Sorry I could not make good my promise to send you airmail<lb/>
particulars by yesterday's mail. Just as I sent the messenger to<lb/>
catch the air mail, at 1:00 P. M., on the 3rd, it began to rain cats and dogs<lb/>
and it rained steadily into the night. Miss Rojas telephoned me to put it<lb/>
off until yesterday morning, since the matter she had to discuss with me<lb/>
would involve Zunzunegui (pronounced Zoon-zoon-eggy), the chap we talked<lb/>
to and who was seven years old at the time of the experiments. Yesterday<lb/>
morning, I went to see Miss Rojas. She showed be book entries, written<lb/>
by her father, proving that the camp site was not ceded gratis but that<lb/>
a rental of $20.00 American Gold, per month, had been paid from and inclu-<lb/>
November 9th, 1900 to October 10th, 1901, Buildings No. 1 and No. 2, re-<lb/>
maining the property of the owner. All this time and prior to leasing<lb/>
of the camp site, the property belonged to Dr. Rojas but it was rented to<lb/>
a tenant named Sosa and the rental was split 50-50 between owner and<lb/>
tenant, checks being handed to Dr. Rojas, who was evidently one of the<lb/>
two parties to the contract of lease. Entries in his Journal-Cash Book<lb/>
are made regularly, the first check having been received from &ldquo;Major Mr.<lb/>
Read&rdquo; and subsequent checks from Major J. R. Kean, the latter evidently<lb/>
acting as Disbursing Quartermaster. It must be remembered that the fund<lb/>
for all expenses connected with the experimental camp was a special one,<lb/>
hence a Medical Corps officer, in this case Major Kean, acted as Disbursing<lb/>
Officer, evidently. The plot involved for the camp site was to consist<lb/>
of four to six acres. Miss Rojas is having all entries copied VERBATIM<lb/>
and will take them to Mrs. Phillips for translation. Sra. Rojas and my-<lb/>
self will certify to the translated entries, when and as they are prepared<lb/>
and ready to forward to you. When I got through with Miss Rojas, I<lb/>
went over to look for Zunzunegui who now owns the limestone quarry and<lb/>
limekilns which you saw on the way over to the far end of the quarry<lb/>
from which you took the picture. He was not at home but Mrs. Z. told me<lb/>
that he would be home for lunch around 12:00. He did not show up, so I<lb/>
left his house at 12:30, leaving my phone number. I was not able to get<lb/>
in touch with him, after a half dozen calls, until near 8:00 P. M. He<lb/>
then told me that, today being Saturday, he had to make his Saturday<lb/>
collections for lime delivered during the week. I suggested that he<lb/>
might be able to see me between 7:30 and 8:00 A. M. this morning, to which<lb/>
he agreed. I have just come from his place. Results: The oldest of<lb/>
the shacks (the one on the extreme right, facing from the road) is in<lb/>
part Bldg. No. 1 (Infecteed Clothing) and I found the tongued and grooved<lb/>
boards on the inside, weather boarding on the outside. The mosquito<lb/>
building was torn down and used for kindling wood about four or five years<lb/>
ago. Slabs of the concrete floor can still be seen in the tilled field<lb/>
where you had some photos of me taken, the site being much more to the<lb/>
left, viewed from the front of Bldg. No. 1, than where I stand in the<lb/>
picture. I wandered all over the place yesterday and discovered indeter-<lb/>
minable &ldquo;something&rdquo; appearing on the right, shown in the Army photo,<lb/>
your number 17-b, also the concrete affair, which served as a small<lb/>
reservoir, shown near Bldg. No. 2 on the extreme left of your photo No.<lb/>
16-a (Army Medical Museum No. 40731) If I can get hold of the photograph-<lb/>
er, I will go out there this afternoon and endeavor to reconstruct the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03623003"/>
<hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench.</hi><lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>Oct. 5, 1940.</hi><lb/>
whole picture as per that general view. We will try and work out the<lb/>
point from which it was taken and then show where the Poplar &ldquo;Alamo&rdquo;<lb/>
tree was that sticks out like a sore thumb in that picture. It was cut<lb/>
down and uprooted by Z's father, years ago, but he showed me where it was.<lb/>
The &ldquo;concrete affair&rdquo;, which could not figure for anything in particular,<lb/>
was built by slaves and it was the starting point for the first limestone<lb/>
excavated and the first limekiln built on the farm. Around it, a very<lb/>
extensive tract has been honeycombed and today Z. has three trucks haul-<lb/>
ing slaked lime to Havana and other points around Havana. The small<lb/>
reservoir was undoubtedly used for water for slaking the lime and maybe<lb/>
for other purposes. There was no activity whatever there when Camp<lb/>
Lazear was built. Z's father was the first to develop the business on<lb/>
a large scale and his contract, I think, is dated 1905. The quarry which<lb/>
leads to the brick plant was an entirely separate affair. Dr. Rojas was<lb/>
interested in that business with a partner. Z., however, went into the<lb/>
lime business exclusively for himself.</p>
<p>check</p>
<p><unclear>Has over</unclear> 1926<lb/>
<unclear>Tour</unclear> 1928</p>
<p><unclear><hi>get</hi></unclear></p>
<p>The roots of the poplar tree back of the No. 1 building come<lb/>
clear under the building but its limbs have never been allowed to grow<lb/>
high enough to reach much higher than the roof of the shack. It is one of<lb/>
the small trees back of Building No. 1 shown in your 16<unclear>-</unclear>a, Medical Museum<lb/>
No. 40731, so thinks Zunzunegui and he may be right. He also thinks the<lb/>
Framboyan tree, with which you are familiar, was in its infancy at that<lb/>
time for it has been there as long as he can remember. You may be entirely<lb/>
sure that none of the buildings in the Army Medical Museum photo belonged<lb/>
to the Rojas family.</p>
<p>By the way, I have three sections of the limb indicated by<lb/>
you to the old lady tenant of the shack and I want to know if you want<lb/>
me to arrange to have them sent up or try to take them with me. Please<lb/>
let me know about this by return mail.</p>
<p>Yes get some<lb/>
things made</p>
<p>It is about mail time, so will close for the present. A lot<lb/>
of the pictures we took will be of no service whatsoever, but I trust<lb/>
those to be taken today will be.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Hurriedly but sincerely,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
