<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03623006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, October 12, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03623006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Julian</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis</name>
<name type="place">Rojas farm, San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-12">October 12, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03623006</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, October 12, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] discusses the identity of the shack on the Rojas farm.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-12">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to John J. Moran, October 12, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03623006"/>
<opener>
In the long <del>ron</del><add>run</add>, I should think Mr. Z. would be proud to have his home and the<lb/>
birthplace of his children permanently memorialized, and therefore would be willing to<lb/>
deal fairly with us, perhaps selling us the shack for no more than the cost to replace<lb/>
it with a more livable affair, but I don't mean by this that I propose to build him a<lb/>
modern house in <del><unclear></unclear></del> return for the shack.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-10-12">October 12, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mr. Moran:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sending a copy of this letter to Mr. Pogolotti, as I believe you<lb/>
may not be able to carry out my request before you leave on the sixteenth. I was<lb/>
delighted with the photographs and your note, and on examining them more carefully,<lb/>
while I still have some doubt, I am much more acceptable to the idea that the shack<lb/>
may be the remains of Building No. 1. I note that already they have torn down the<lb/>
smaller shack and connecting between the two. Are they planning to tear down the<lb/>
Building No. 1 also? Will either you or Mr. Pogolotti (perhaps the latter would<lb/>
be better as he knows real estate values) act as my agent in at least sounding out<lb/>
the owner of the shack on the cost of the shack and a <hi>small</hi> parcel of land, or<lb/>
just the cost of the shack itself. It occurred to me that if the owner will treat<lb/>
me fairly, I would take an option on it and then come down in February and decide<lb/>
the matter. If I can buy the shack without too much cost, I would like to present<lb/>
it to the government or to some memorial association composed of American and Cuban<lb/>
physicians and governmental people. I am certainly not interested in taking the<lb/>
responsibility of buying now any large amount of property around the shack. I am<lb/>
only interested in protecting the shack. It might be better to move the shack<lb/>
and place it in the left-hand corner of the Rojas property, surrounded by a fence<lb/>
and protected by some sort of a concrete roof. Perhaps the Rojas family would be<lb/>
sufficiently interested to give to a memorial association just that amount of land<lb/>
on the corner of their property (that is, on Calzada Real) for the purpose. Or, it<lb/>
might be better to give it to the government, to be transferred bodily to the site<lb/>
of the false camp, and to be an integral part of their memorial. The accessories<lb/>
which have been put on the shack could be removed and the remainder restored. All<lb/>
of this depends on further investigation of the shack to assure those of us most<lb/>
concerned that it is truly remnants of Building No. 1.</p>
<p>I assume that Mr. Zumzunequi is the owner, and I do hope that he won't<lb/>
consider me a rich American, to be fleeced because of my interest in a historical<lb/>
object which he happens to own. As a piece of wood which will eventually be torn<lb/>
down anyhow, the shack probably isn't worth more than $50.00. As a historical object<lb/>
which the Cuban government might buy, you know as well as I do that they will never<lb/>
buy it, but they might graciously accept it from a private memorial association, par-<lb/>
ticularly if we suggest that they transfer it to their own choice of sites. Supposing<lb/>
I take out an option with a small down payment and by next Spring, we decide it isn't<lb/>
true Building No. 1. If the cost of the option isn't too much, I am willing to take<lb/>
this chance. I assure you I have no ulterior motive, do not wish to make any profit<lb/>
and indeed, if the cost is not too great, I plan to give it to the Cuban government,<lb/>
and will try to collect from others enough money to fix it up properly. In dealing<lb/>
with Mr. Z. remember that I am just a physician on a salary. It is a good salary but<lb/>
nonetheless I have children, taxes, etc. and cannot afford to get in this very deeply.<lb/>
I would so appreciate some sort of word at your earliest convenience. Should you wish<lb/>
to cable or send airmail letters, I will answer promptly and would feel much better if<lb/>
the deal could be closed promptly, at least as far as an option is concerned, within the<lb/>
next week or two. May I congratulate you on your zeal and thank you most heartily for<lb/>
this further evidence of your cooperation, and of course this means Mr. Pogolotti as<lb/>
well as yourself.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
