<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03627001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, October 10, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03627001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-10">October 10, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03627001</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, October 10, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus comments on Truby's draft about his Cuba experiences, especially in regards to Agramonte.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-10">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, October 10, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03627001"/>
<opener>
J. H. Andrus<lb/>
<dateline>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1940-10-10">10-10-40</date>
</dateline>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<salute>Dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you for your letter of the first and thank you for send-<lb/>
ing me the draft of your experiences in Cuba. I found it<lb/>
intensely interesting. It did not arrive until yesterday,<lb/>
so I have had time to do <add>no</add> more than read it through.</p>
<p>Am afraid you will be disappointed in the little help I will<lb/>
be able to give you.</p>
<p>Your manuscript has cleared up one subject that has been beyond<lb/>
my comprehension for years. I have a copy of volume 61,<lb/>
Senate Documents, 61st. Congress, 3rd. session (1911) It is<lb/>
probable that you also have a copy. On pages 25 and 26, the<lb/>
Surgeon General quotes a letter from Dr. Agramonte from which<lb/>
I take the following extract:</p>
<p>&ldquo;While the <unclear>experimental</unclear> station, afterward named Camp<lb/>
Lazear, in honor to the memory of our deceased colleague,<lb/>
was being established, the care of the mosquitoes and<lb/>
their infection by applying them to yellow fever cases,<lb/>
was in the hands of Dr. Agramonte, at the division lab-<lb/>
oratory; when the permanent &lsquo;mosquito building&rsquo; was<lb/>
erected at Camp Lazear (Dec. 1, 1900), these mosquitoes<lb/>
were turned over to Dr. Carroll for his care. It de-<lb/>
volved then upon Dr. Agramonte to select the mosquitoes<lb/>
from <unclear>thosemkept</unclear> by Dr. Carroll and <hi>apply them to non-<lb/>
immunes</hi>, <hi>as well as to make all subsequent direct<lb/>
innoculations</hi>, <hi>and to obtain the non-immunes</hi> (<hi>Spaniards</hi>)<lb/>
<hi>for the purpose</hi>, <hi>until the end of the work in Cuba</hi>.&rdquo;</p>
<p>From early October, 1900, until I was innoculated Jan. 25, 1901,<lb/>
I was on duty in Major Reed's laboratory every day and my main<lb/>
job was to &ldquo;raise&rdquo; mosquitoes. Early in the <unclear>experiments</unclear>,<lb/>
mosquitoes <del><unclear></unclear></del> <add>may have been</add> procured by and innoculated by Dr. Agramonte.<lb/>
Later - and during the major part of the <unclear>experimental</unclear> work -<lb/>
mosquitoes we had raised were innoculated by Major Reed, or<lb/>
Dr. Ames from experimental cases.</p>
<p>Volunteers were innoculated by mosquito AT Camp Lazear, after<lb/>
having been in quarantine there. Those innoculated by blood<lb/>
injection were taken from quarantine at Camp Lazear to OUTSIDE<lb/>
one of the yellow fever wards and, after innoculation, were<lb/>
rushed back to Camp Lazear. Dr. Agramonte was rarely at<lb/>
Camp Lazear - his work, as you know, was elsewhere - so - - -<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03627002"/>
When I first found Dr. Agramonte's statement, in 1937, I<lb/>
tried to check it with some of the volunteers but did not<lb/>
get satisfactory information.</p>
<p>Then I thought I would see if Steward Neate was where I could<lb/>
reach him. I wrote to the Surgeon General's office but<lb/>
asked about Steward Neall. (The name did not ring quite<lb/>
right but was as near as I could get to it.)</p>
<p>Now, that you have given me the correct name, I wrote yester-<lb/>
day and, if I succeed in getting in touch with him, will see<lb/>
if he cannot settle the question.</p>
<p>I made a sketch of the layout of the post hospital at Colum-<lb/>
bia Barracks and a tracing of your sketch and have sent both<lb/>
to Lambert with the request that he insert the yellow fever<lb/>
hospital buildings and anything else that we have omitted.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I have a photograph (approximately 8 x 10) of<lb/>
operating room and wards. It does not show officers' quar-<lb/>
ters, barracks or other buildings. Do you want it?<lb/>
You are welcome to it if it will be of any use.</p>
<p>A correction I will show when I return your manuscript is that<lb/>
I did not serve with Major Reed's Board after my innoculation<lb/>
and, of course, did NOT return, with him, to Washington.</p>
<p>Number 15, in the group photograph, is John Morris. His<lb/>
home is (or was) in Reading, Pa. He called on me two or<lb/>
three times but not within the last couple of years.<lb/>
From the heavy-weight he was when the photograph was taken,<lb/>
he shriveled to almost nothing. He made a career of the<lb/>
Army and retired a hospital sergeant.</p>
<p>If you need your manuscript before I get it back to you, just<lb/>
let me know. You said there was no hurry and I shall take<lb/>
you at your word.</p>
<p>And please let me know if you want the hospital photograph.</p>
<p>With every good wish,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>J. H. Andrus</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
