<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03628008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Luis B. Pogolotti to Philip Showalter Hench, September 30, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Pogolotti, Luis B.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03628008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Dino</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Rojas farm, San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Aristides Agramonte Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-30">September 30, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03628008</idno>
<title>Letter from Luis B. Pogolotti to Philip Showalter Hench, September 30, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Pogolotti replies to Hench's questions concerning place names and locations, and traces the history of the ownership of the land where Camp Lazear was located.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-30">
<head>Letter from Luis B. Pogolotti to Philip Showalter Hench, September 30, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03628008"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, Cuba.<lb/>
<date value="1940-09-30">Sept. 30, 1940.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
Mayo Clinic,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In reply to your letter of August 26th, please note<lb/>
the following:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item><p><hi>Paragraph 6</hi>:</p>
<p>The tent Camp Columbia was erected immediately after<lb/>
the arrival of the Seventh Division of the U.S. Army on Dec. 15,<lb/>
1898. The site was a farm. There is no exact date available as<lb/>
to the wooden barracks erected but construction was started imme-<lb/>
diately after the soldiers were lodged in tents. The wooden bar-<lb/>
racks were torn down in 1936 and 1937 by the present army headed<lb/>
by Colonel Fulgencio Batista, Chief of Staff at that time.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Paragraph 7</hi>:</p>
<p>Quemados is a sub-division of the town of Marianao,<lb/>
I never heard of a public library in Marianao and there are no<lb/>
maps of the town.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Paragraph 32:</hi></p>
<p>The present Military City is about 10 acres. May I<lb/>
point out that Col. Fulgencio Batista, Chief of Staff, and strong-<lb/>
man of the Island, resigned last November to run for President<lb/>
and was elected. He will take office Oct. 10th next. Colonel<lb/>
Jos&eacute; Pedraza is now Chief of Staff.</p>
<p>You are right about Calzada de los Quemados, which<lb/>
ends in front of the Hospital and is where General Lee Street<lb/>
begins.</p>
<p>In your directions how to get to the false site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear, please note the changes of direction beginning with<lb/>
the word &ldquo;Turning northwest.&rdquo; This should read &ldquo;Turning southeast<lb/>
off Calzada de Columbia at the eastern (or southeastern) entrance<lb/>
of Military City, we traversed the (approximately) southern rim<lb/>
of the grounds bounded by Calzada de los Quemados (and General Lee<lb/>
Street) passing on our right the Military Hospital.&rdquo; Then this<lb/>
should read: At the end of Calzada de Columbia we turned into<lb/>
General Lee Street for one block and then going south on Santa<lb/>
Rosa Street down to the railroad crossed the railroad and turned<lb/>
west for a block on a mud road." The part beginning with the word<lb/>
&ldquo;Proceeding&rdquo; and ending with &ldquo;railroad&rdquo; in the same sentence is<lb/>
wrong. Forget about Boquetta Road as you did not travel on it,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03628009"/>
-2-<lb/>
you were on Santa Rosa Street and possibly were at the corner of<lb/>
Boquetta Road, which is unpaved, when you asked where you were,<lb/>
since Boquetta Road crosses Santa Rosa Street.</p>
<p>I am enclosing a plan of the Military Hospital marked<lb/>
&ldquo;Hospital Aristides Agramonte - Finca La Soledad.&rdquo; The Hospital<lb/>
is known the &ldquo;Aristides Agramonte&rdquo; Hospital or the Military Hospital,<lb/>
since March 1935. The &ldquo;Fourth of September Clinic&rdquo; was built in<lb/>
1930-31 but was never finished. After the revolution on Sept. 4,<lb/>
1933 it was completed and named &ldquo;Fourth of September Clinic&rdquo;. You<lb/>
will note on the plan and the attached slip of paper that each<lb/>
building is specified.</p>
<p>The Carnino Station was erected in 1930.</p>
<p>Linea Paradero - &ldquo;Linea&rdquo; is commonly used for railroad<lb/>
altho it is really &ldquo;linea de ferrocarril&rdquo;. Paradero is the word<lb/>
used for railway station.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Paragraph 35</hi>:</p>
<p>Correct except that the houses you mention are not<lb/>
cement but brick and lumber.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Paragraphs 38th and 39th</hi>:</p>
<p>My brother came from New York with the American Inter-<lb/>
vention as a civil employee. He bought the property August 1914<lb/>
from the Dominican Fathers before the Notary Raul Galletti of<lb/>
Marianao, in whose portocol the original documents are filed. The<lb/>
Dominican Fathers obtained it from Father Zamora, a member of the<lb/>
Dominican Fathers, who left it to them as part of his estate.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Paragraph 53</hi>:</p>
<p>In this paragraph you state &ldquo;he and his brother&rdquo;. It<lb/>
was my brother who made this transaction and I was not concerned<lb/>
in same. My brother purchased San Jos&eacute; from Se&ntilde;ora Maria Teresa Loma<lb/>
y Navarrete on Dec. 17, 1910 under Deed No. 331 before the Notary<lb/>
Dr. Jacinto Pedroso. This deed was clarified by another document<lb/>
before the same Notary on January 20, 1911, Document No. 16, both<lb/>
original documents being filed in the protocol of this Notary.<lb/>
My brother, Dino Francisco Pogolotti, purchased 347,576 sq. meters.<lb/>
the Se&ntilde;ora reserving 25,000 sq. meters as her present residence.</p>
<p>On Oct. 4, 1919 my brother sold two lots to Rafecas<lb/>
Macia y Cia. under Document No. 335 before the Notary Dr. Carlos<lb/>
Alzugaray. One of 68,813 sq. meters bounded on the North by<lb/>
the Brick factory and Street<del>f</del> Luis Valdes, on the South by the<lb/>
Sugar Mill Toledo, on the East by the tillable land belonging to<lb/>
Pedroso - Acosta, and on the West by Blooks 22, 20, 12 and Pasaje.<lb/>
The other lot on which the brick factory is located composed of<lb/>
62,743 sq. meters, fronting on the Calzada, on the rear by Block<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03628010"/>
-3-<lb/>
13, part 12 and 22, on the right by land of Acosta - Pedroso and<lb/>
on the left by Blook 22. The rest of the land he made into a<lb/>
sub-division.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Tejar&rdquo; means a small brick yard. There is a brick<lb/>
yard and quarry operated by two separate companies. The quarry<lb/>
existed for many years, probably being worked in the Spanish days,<lb/>
and it was probably operating when my brother purchased it. I<lb/>
don't know.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Paragraph 54</hi>:</p>
<p>There is no Avenida de Consulado, it is Avenida de<lb/>
Buen Retiro. Directions correct until you reached Calzada de<lb/>
Marianao. At that point you turned left on the Calzada toward<lb/>
Havana going about 8 or 10 blocks to Calle Jose Miguel Gomez on<lb/>
which the estate is located. You did not pass a brick factory.<lb/>
All the rest is correct except the concrete fence. This is a stone<lb/>
fence.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Paragraph 58:</hi></p>
<p>We did not built this house.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Paragraph 67:</hi></p>
<p>I am returning your Photo No. 2 with a few notes<lb/>
answering your questions on the back of the picture as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Neither one as it is an unnamed street.</item>
<item>2. The house should be more east as I have marked.</item>
<item>3. It is correct.</item>
<item>4. Yes, I think so.</item>
<item>5. The last date of 1918 was printed on the map<lb/>
after the Municipality of Marianao had named several streets and<lb/>
a new copy of the map was issued showing names of said streets.</item>
</list></p>
<p>There are three new units <add>marked</add> A B C <add>on your photo</add> at the Military<lb/>
Hospital - &ldquo;Aristides Agramonte Hospital&rdquo;. One is the tuberculosis,<lb/>
the other is infectious diseases and the other X-Ray.</p>
<p>I am also returning your Photo 5 on which I have<lb/>
marked the route you took to the false Camp with red pencil and<lb/>
the route to the real site at San Jose in blue pencil.</p></item>
</list></p>
<p>I trust that I have answered all the above to your<lb/>
satisfaction. If you require more explanation on any of them I<lb/>
shall be delighted to do everything possible.</p>
<p>With best wishes, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>L. Pogolotti</signed>
P:h<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
