<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03623014">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 17, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03623014</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Julian</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-17">October 17, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03623014</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 17, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran writes that he is certain the shack on the Rojas farm is Camp Lazear Building No. 1, the infected-clothing building.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-17">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 17, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03623014"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1940-10-17">Oct. 17, 1940.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
ROCHESTER, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I repeat that, &ldquo;<hi>Beyond peradventure of a doubt</hi>&rdquo;, we have Bld'g<lb/>
No. 1. If you own a pipe, put that in it and smoke it. This afternoon<lb/>
I checked up on the matter of distance between the two buildings, using<lb/>
the small tree at the right of me in my photo No. 21 as a guide. The<lb/>
distance is 246 feet. It is more than likely that Major Reed or one of<lb/>
his subordinates stepped it off. The Agramonte drawing does not worry<lb/>
me in the slightest since I am morally convinced that he did not visit the<lb/>
two buildings at the time and that the drawings were made from memory, the<lb/>
particulars being dictated or roughly outlined to a draftsman by Dr. Agra-<lb/>
monte. Please get out your photo (Army) 16-a. It gives you an end view<lb/>
of Building No. 1 and if the stovepipe or chimney had existed at the right,<lb/>
it would show up in that picture. Being in the left corner of the room,<lb/>
it is not visible. You can see the vestibule in the photo and you know<lb/>
that the vestibule was in front, facing Building No. 2. There was nothing<lb/>
in the back of the shack. If you are not convinced, I GIVE IT UP. The<lb/>
buildings were put up by Army carpenters, I am sure, and one or two inches<lb/>
more or less in a building intended for a given purpose and for a period<lb/>
of months only, was nothing in their young lives.</p>
<p>I went out to the site this afternoon before I received copy<lb/>
of your letter to Pogolotti, intending to kill two birds with one stone,<lb/>
viz: take Z's declaration, short and to the point, and at the same time<lb/>
measure the distance between the two shacks. I just talked to Pogolotti<lb/>
over the telephone. Your letter has not reached him yet but it should<lb/>
be delivered to him tomorrow morning. I told him about the measurements<lb/>
and they more or less agreed with what he estimated a few days ago when<lb/>
I mentioned the matter to him. Just a matter of converting meters into<lb/>
yards or direct into feet. He is not familiar with yards, feet and in-<lb/>
ches, used very little in this country and in the country of his birth.<lb/>
The square limeslaker you see in photo 16-a and the limekilns near it, which<lb/>
are not visible in the picture, were torn down when the quarry and kilns<lb/>
were moved further. towards the base of supply of limestone, having kept on<lb/>
moving to where you saw them while you were here.</p>
<p>I have to type Z's statements, translate them to him in Spanish<lb/>
and get his signature to them in English or American. Maybe I can get them<lb/>
off to you with this letter and the nine photostats, one of which has no<lb/>
bearing on the Camp since it concerns receipt of the amount due when the<lb/>
the &ldquo;2nd Regiment of South Carolina&rdquo; occupied part of the farm from January<lb/>
1st to May 15th, 1899, payment NOT HAVING BEEN MADE until March 11, 1901,<lb/>
due, no doubt, to &ldquo;red tape&rdquo; in getting the vouchers properly certified<lb/>
by the Commanding Officer of the Regiment who had returned to the U. S. and<lb/>
had been mustered out. The entry commences &ldquo;Collected, at last,&rdquo;, etc.<lb/>
The white squares in the photostats are to indicate the entries concerned.<lb/>
(The 2nd Regiment of South Carolina" page is 94.)</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
Leaving Havana on the Sunday (7:00 P. M.) steamer,<lb/>
October 20th. My R. R. ticket is to Pittsburgh,<lb/>
Va. and Philadelphia to be covered otherwise.<lb/>
N. B. I think I have spelt Z's name wrong in several letters.<lb/>
As I first wrote to you, it is Zunzunegui (pronounced<lb/>
Zoon-zoon-eggy). In recent letters I have written it<lb/>
Zunzunequi, which is wrong. Sorry. J. J. M.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
