<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03623012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 16, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03623012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Mariano (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-16">October 16, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03623012</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 16, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran describes his discussions with the Cubans on the proposed Lazear Memorial.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-16">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 16, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03623012"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1940-10-16">Oct. 16, 1940.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>This afternoon I sought Dr. Albertini in the secluded office<lb/>
which he has maintained for years at Calle Habana No. 6. My object was<lb/>
to seek his good offices to the end that Dr. Domingo Ramos, (Secretary of<lb/>
Defense when you were here and renamed as &ldquo;Minister of Defense&rdquo; in Pres.<lb/>
Batista's new Ministry, he being the only member of the retiring Cabinet<lb/>
to be taken on in the new) voluntarily admit that the &ldquo;False Camp Lazear&rdquo;<lb/>
was not the &ldquo;Real Camp Lazear&rdquo;. I carried to Rojas &ldquo;Journal&rdquo; with me<lb/>
to convince Dr. Albertini of the legitimacy of the &ldquo;Finca San Jos&eacute;&rdquo; site.<lb/>
Imagine my surprise to find in Dr. Albertini's waiting room Sr. Giberga,<lb/>
Dr. Ramos' private secretary and Aide. While awaiting my turn to see Dr.<lb/>
Albertini, I showed the entries to Sr. Giberga but before I got to the last<lb/>
of the entries in Dr. Rojas' own handwriting, out came Dr. Ramos from the<lb/>
Sanctum Santorum of Dr. Albertini, expressing pleasure at seeing me. As<lb/>
always, he was in a great hurry but he stayed with me long enough to hear<lb/>
of our discoveries, including that of the original Building No. 1. He is<lb/>
perfectly agreeable to have the building transferred to the &ldquo;False Camp<lb/>
Lazear&rdquo; but, as near as I could guess, he has no intention of setting up<lb/>
any form of memorial there without using &ldquo;Campamento de Lazear&rdquo; in some<lb/>
manner as part and parcel of the projected memorial. He told me to con-<lb/>
sult with you and get your ideas as to a number of names, or one that you<lb/>
might consider ideal, for the projected memorial. He asked me how you<lb/>
would like to have it called &ldquo;Instituto Lazear&rdquo;, for instance. He told<lb/>
it was the intention of the Government to erect a building on the acquired<lb/>
site for the investigation of tropical diseases and that the memorial would<lb/>
be an exclusively &ldquo;Lazear Memorial&rdquo;; that it would not be a memorial to<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Board nor to Finlay. From that I infer that a bronze<lb/>
plaque or other form of tablet or slab would be placed in the Memorial<lb/>
and that the names of the four members of the Board, with that of Finlay,<lb/>
would appear thereon, in either marble or bronze. The important thing<lb/>
is, so far as Americans are concerned, as to the wording which might<lb/>
eventually be adopted. Lazear's martyrdom is acknowledged by the Cubans<lb/>
and heartily so because the names of Lazear and Finlay have never been<lb/>
in conflict when it comes to the point of determining the respective<lb/>
shares of Reed and Finlay in &ldquo;THE CONQUEST OF YELLOW FEVER&rdquo;. For the sake<lb/>
of harmony and to the end that Cubans may not be prejudiced in advance<lb/>
against your book in formation, I think your attitude from now on should<lb/>
be of directed towards &ldquo;ceding&rdquo; and &ldquo;making allowances&rdquo; so that, when your<lb/>
story is published in book form, you may not be classified as &ldquo;one sided&rdquo;.<lb/>
As you well know, I am extremely anxious that the &ldquo;Conquest of Yellow<lb/>
Fever&rdquo; should be published, after its text has been assembled and edited<lb/>
in a STRICTLY IMPARTIAL manner. That you can do that job, I am most con-<lb/>
fident. You are an investigator and analyst of no mean calibre and in the<lb/>
past month I have mentally grumbled at your thoroughness, not because I<lb/>
begrudge the time and effort but because, unfortunately, I cannot devote<lb/>
enough time to the task, having business duties to attend to. Having<lb/>
always being a stickler for accuracy and detail, I could not trust Mrs. P.<lb/>
to take care of the letters, notes, observations and data which I have<lb/>
sent you in the past three weeks. I have had to drum them out on the<lb/>
typewriter with two index fingers, many times re-writing full pages of<lb/>
single space material after finding, upon re-reading what I had written,<lb/>
that the result was far from clarifying.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03623013"/>
<p><hi>Dr. Hench</hi></p>
<p>-- 2 --</p>
<p><hi>Oct. 16, 1940.</hi></p>
<p>I am sending a copy of this letter to General Kean and will<lb/>
more than likely see him at Virginia. We will discuss the matter of<lb/>
names for the eventual Memorial and I am sure any recommendation of<lb/>
General Kean's to the Cuban authorities will be carefully weighed and,<lb/>
more than likely, given exceptional consideration. He is very highly<lb/>
respected by every member of the Cuban medical profession and those who<lb/>
knew him well honor and revere him. I am sure you will have every<lb/>
ounce of support from him towards the success of your laudable mission<lb/>
in this entire matter.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Quinta Dura&ntilde;on&rdquo;, General Lee's Headquarters, in Marianao, has<lb/>
no visible number on it, it being known all over Havana, without a number.<lb/>
The caretaker, however, told me that it was 115. It is two long blocks<lb/>
and a half distant from General Lee Street (about four average blocks).</p>
<p>Will drop you a few lines again tomorrow by AIRMAIL.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
