<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03623007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 12, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03623007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Julian</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Demetrio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Macia, Adrian</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-12">October 12, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03623007</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 12, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran informs Hench that he is sure that he has found the Camp Lazear infected-clothing building, and has investigated the acquisition of the building and surrounding land.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-12">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Philip Showalter Hench, October 12, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03623007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1940-10-12">Oct. 12, 1940.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>THERE IS NOT A SHADOW OF DOUBT but that the old shack is Build-<lb/>
ing No. 1, the &ldquo;Infected Clothing Building&rdquo;, originally baptized &ldquo;The<lb/>
Infected Bedding &amp; Clothing Building&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Yesterday, accompanied by our good and genial friend, Sr. Luis<lb/>
Pogolotti, I went over the camp site and surroundings for the STEENTH<lb/>
time. We measured the building inside and out and it is, to all intents<lb/>
and purposes, <hi>14 by 20 feet</hi>, the double board wall absorbing any little<lb/>
difference between the inside and outside measurements, as you will see<lb/>
by the enclosed pencil drawing made by Sr. Pogolotti.</p>
<p>Cuban wooden buildings do not have any such form of ceiling as<lb/>
exist in this building. If they have any ceiling at all, they would<lb/>
extend all the way up, forming an inverted V, leaving no such enclosed<lb/>
triangle as the old shack has. Most of the original flooring still<lb/>
exists, the deteriorated boards having been replaced by new or used<lb/>
boards, from time to time. Entering the front door, an aperture in the<lb/>
ceiling, in the left hand corner, indicates where the stovepipe went<lb/>
through the roof. The old lady who now occupies the house thought Sr. Z.<lb/>
had a stove under it. On our way back to the city, I casually dropped by<lb/>
Sr. Z's house, informing him that the old shack was what we were looking<lb/>
for except that it had a round hole in the ceiling which either his father<lb/>
or himself must have made there for a stovepipe. Quick as a flash, he<lb/>
said that the hole in the ceiling had been there always and that he had<lb/>
never seen a stove there during his father's lifetime nor since. Even<lb/>
though he had informed me that the aperture was made by his father or by<lb/>
himself, I would still be convinced that the main part of the shack is<lb/>
original. You know, of course, that there was a stove in the original<lb/>
Building No. 1. All that is lacking is the &ldquo;double vestibule&rdquo;, the<lb/>
window on the left hand side, having been enlarged slightly and extended<lb/>
clear down to the floor and iron-barred, shuttered by a door which opens<lb/>
inward. The porch was added and the double vestibule removed entirely<lb/>
and replaced by a wide door, to be seen in outline in my photo No. 26.<lb/>
A room was added on to the end of it, the floor of which is lower than<lb/>
that of the original shack, but communicating with the room against which<lb/>
it was built. A kitchen, the length of the original building, has been<lb/>
built against the rear wall. This has a concrete floor. I never dreamed,<lb/>
when we failed to examine this building thoroughly, that even a single<lb/>
board of it could last forty years.</p>
<p>Regardless of what the record may claim as to the direction in<lb/>
which this building faced, it is the original building, alright. It is<lb/>
probably 75% facing South, 25% East. Sr. Pogolotti and I arrived at the<lb/>
conclusion that Sra. Rojas and her relative could see the line of tents<lb/>
on the higher ground, around where she and I were photographed together<lb/>
in the condition the farm was in, in 1900, but she could not see either<lb/>
of the two shacks from the roof of the farmhouse. It is also entirely<lb/>
possible that the larger number of tents the <hi>2nd Regiment of N. C. Inf.</hi><lb/>
which had their camp in the &ldquo;Finca&rdquo;, in 1898-99, were those that they<lb/>
remembered so clearly. The latter regiment had returned to the U. S.<lb/>
long before Camp Lazear was thought of. You will see the entry in Dr.<lb/>
Rojas' book about this Regiment, when I send you the photostatic copy.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03623008"/>
<hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench.</hi><lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>Oct. 12, 1940.</hi><lb/>
These are promised to me in time to make the Monday AIRMAIL, which closes<lb/>
at 1:00 P. M. When I suggested taking the book to the U. S. I was quick<lb/>
to note that Miss Rojas and her mother would not be very agreeable to<lb/>
such a proposition, so I hastened to suggest that she trust me with the<lb/>
book in order to have photostatic copies made of the entries concerned. To<lb/>
this she readily agreed, allowing me to take the book with me. I then made<lb/>
a beeline for the photographer who specializes in that class of work, on<lb/>
Calle Obispo. The next day (today) being a holiday, followed by Sunday,<lb/>
the photographer told me the best he could do would be to make the photostats<lb/>
for me first thing Monday morning. There are altogether 8 entries on 8<lb/>
different pages and these are to be photographed in their entirety. Trans-<lb/>
lations, I hope, will be ready on Monday morning, in which case I will try<lb/>
to have them included with the photostats.</p>
<p><unclear>were?</unclear></p>
<p>My reference to the <hi>concrete slabs</hi> on the spot where Building No.<lb/>
2 WAS requires a little further explanation, if I have not mentioned it in<lb/>
one of my recent letters or in the 7-page memorandum I sent you. I asked<lb/>
Mr. Z. &ldquo;how come&rdquo; that the building had a cement floor. He told me that<lb/>
the site upon which building No. 2 was erected was extremely damp, while<lb/>
Building No. 1 stands on limestone formation. The floor of No. 2 began to<lb/>
rot several years ago and his father had it replaced by a concrete one.</p>
<p>What <unclear>did<lb/>
they used</unclear> for?</p>
<p>With reference to the trees in and around Building No. 1, you will<lb/>
notice from your Photo No. 17-b that there were no trees at all around the<lb/>
building. Sr. Z. says that those trees were planted there by his father<lb/>
to shade the building, so that none of the trees you and I saw there are<lb/>
more than 40 years old. That sound reasonable enough, since poplar and<lb/>
laurel trees grow very rapidly in this country. The poplar tree is no<lb/>
longer in vogue in the Vedado section of Havana since its roots play havoc<lb/>
with the sidewalks and the &ldquo;Alamos&rdquo; are a constant headache to the electric<lb/>
light company which once a year is obliged to cut off the limbs and branches<lb/>
in order to clear their lines. The laurel tree is being planed by house<lb/>
owners to save their sidewalks but the electric light company's problem is<lb/>
not solved by this measure. The two laurel trees in front of our house<lb/>
have been ruthlessly cut down to &ldquo;stumps&rdquo; each year of the four odd since we<lb/>
moved to our present residence. Laurel trees planted around the corner, on<lb/>
27th Street, near our house, after we moved to where we now live, are today<lb/>
as tall as the 2-storey building which they shade. You can readily imagine<lb/>
that trees planted even ten years ago, around Building No. 1, would be<lb/>
giants by this time.</p>
<p>What kind<lb/>
of <unclear>trees there<lb/>
now</unclear></p>
<p>I mentioned in a recent letter, or in my &ldquo;observations&rdquo; on your<lb/>
37-page memorandum, that Sr. Pogolotti told Mrs. Phillips of the tacit<lb/>
acknowledgement of the Cuban authorities that they had erred in placing<lb/>
Camp Lazear where it WAS NOT. Sr. Pogolotti informs me that Mrs. P.<lb/>
either misunderstood him or that I misunderstood her. He has not spoken<lb/>
to any of them on the subject, so he says. Therefore, I will have to eat<lb/>
my words in this connection. You have not informed me as to whether or<lb/>
not I should interview Dr. Ramos, nor as to his reply, if any, to your<lb/>
letter dated August 28th. I would like to know what line of argument you<lb/>
wish me to pursue in your behalf, in this matter. If they pass up the<lb/>
ROJAS BOOK EVIDENCE, I see very little use of arguing with them. I am in-<lb/>
clined to think that THEY WILL NOT ride rough shod over it. It is of too<lb/>
conclusive a nature. Se&ntilde;orita Lidia Cabrera (friend of the Rojas family)<lb/>
suggested that we could take the matter up with Colonel Batista, should<lb/>
they prove too recalcitrant, and that we would undoubtedly win out.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03623009"/>
<p><hi>Dr. Philip S. Hench.</hi></p>
<p>-- 3 --</p>
<p><hi>October 12, 1940</hi></p>
<p>I confided the entire matter of your proposed acquisition of the<lb/>
shack and a portion of the ground around it for a memorial or shrine. He<lb/>
assures me that the owner of the property, a Sr. Mac&iacute;a (I think that was<lb/>
the name), a good friend of his, would not &ldquo;hold you up&rdquo;, even opining that<lb/>
he might make you a gift of the shack as well as the land. I AM NOT SO<lb/>
OPTIMISTIC, but I may be wrong. I felt that I could serve your purpose<lb/>
better thru Sr. Pogolotti than by acting on my own account. He has been most<lb/>
unselfish in this matter throughout. He will endeavor to see Sr. Mac&iacute;a on<lb/>
Monday or Tuesday and will let me know the result of his interview. As soon<lb/>
as I have anything tangible to report, I will pass it on to you by Airmail.</p>
<p>I found that I had &ldquo;cheated&rdquo; you out of the seven negatives of the<lb/>
last photos I had taken (which I consider the most important), so I am<lb/>
sending them to you by airmail of Sunday, the 13th., by which this letter<lb/>
will also go to you, since I am finishing it on Sunday morning. I went to<lb/>
Mass before I came down to the office. &ldquo;Remember that thou keep holy the<lb/>
Sabbath Day&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Will try to enclose the &ldquo;Ignacio Agramonte&rdquo; stamps with this letter.<lb/>
This Agramonte was a General in the Cuban Army of Liberation but I cannot tell<lb/>
you whether or not he was related to Dr. Aristides Agramonte. Will try to<lb/>
find out and report to you before you leave the Mayo Clinic for W. &amp; J.<lb/>
I thought there was some reference to it in Dr. Agramonte's article. Just<lb/>
got the relationship, over the telephone from one of the Agramonte clan.<lb/>
Dr. Agramonte was the son of a cousin of GENERAL IGNACIO AGRAMONTE. Dr.<lb/>
Agramonte's father was killed in action during Cuba's wars for independence,<lb/>
following which (at a tender age), the widow took him to the U. S. where<lb/>
they lived and where Dr. Agramonte was educated from primary school to<lb/>
graduation as an M. D. at Columbia. There you have it.</p>
<p>WHAT AM I TO DO WITH THE WOOD FROM THE FRAMBOYAN TREE NEAR BLDG.<lb/>
NO. 1?</p>
<p>I think I have given you some information and CONSIDERABLE mis-<lb/>
information. If you think the other fellow better posted in some matters,<lb/>
accept his information and data. MY OPINION, in many instances, are ONLY<lb/>
my own opinion, most of it coming from memory rather than data accumulated<lb/>
by me. I should have kept a Diary, but that wish comes rather late.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
