<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03625001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on the Yellow Fever Commission, by John J. Moran, [1940]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03625001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Gillen, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Julian</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="person">Warner, Lena A.</name>
<name type="person">Echeverria, R. F.</name>
<name type="person">Baldwin, T. A.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Mariano (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Rojas farm, San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Hospital General Aristides Agramonte, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-00-00">[1940]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03625001</idno>
<title>Notes on the Yellow Fever Commission, by John J. Moran, [1940]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran sends Hench extensive notes describing locations, personalities, and other details of the yellow fever experiments and commenting on the actions and attitudes of the Cuban government regarding a Lazear memorial location.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1940-00-00">
<head>Notes on the Yellow Fever Commission, by John J. Moran, [1940]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03625001"/>
<opener>
Obviously Mr. Moran started writing this before Senora Rojas &amp; he<lb/>
discovered the journal &amp; Bldg # 1. The first part therefore<lb/>
places Camp L where we <hi>thought</hi> it was; the latter part tells where it <hi>really</hi> was. P S H<lb/>
Received<lb/>
<dateline>
about <date value="1940-10-08">Oct 8, 1940</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p><hi>THE CONQUEST OF YELLOW FEVER</hi></p>
<p>Observation and Notes of John J. Moran on Memorandum of<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench of the Mayo Clinic on this Episode.</p>
<p>oooOooo</p>
<p>Par. 5: Our military intervention in Cuba, between 1898 and 1905 are<lb/>
classified as follows: &ldquo;The Army of Invasion&rdquo; (1898); &ldquo;The Army of<lb/>
Occupation&rdquo; (1899-1902) and &ldquo;The Army of Cuban Pacification&rdquo; (1905-1906).</p>
<p>Par. 6: Camp Columbia came into existence in July-August, 1898 and<lb/>
became Columbia Barracks about July 1, 1899. In 1902, the first year<lb/>
of the Republic, it became it became &ldquo;Campamento de Columbia&rdquo; (Camp Col-<lb/>
umbia) when it was taken over by what became the nucleous of the Cuban<lb/>
Army. In 1935 it became &ldquo;Ciudad Militar&rdquo; (de Columbia). Even today,<lb/>
except in official circles, it is known as &ldquo;Campamento de Columbia&rdquo; or<lb/>
&ldquo;Columbia&rdquo;. &ldquo;Ciudad Militar&rdquo; (Military City) as a title given to<lb/>
important military garrisons in Spain, is not at all incongruos when<lb/>
applied today to the Cuban garrison. The site of &ldquo;Camp Columbia&rdquo; was<lb/>
first used by the American Army for military purposes. Prior to that, it<lb/>
was used as a &ldquo;Hippodrome&rdquo;, for horse racing and other sporting activities.</p>
<p>Par. 7: Quemados, or &ldquo;Quemados de Marianao&rdquo; has always been a district<lb/>
or section of the Municipality of Marianao and is now considered as part<lb/>
of the rambling town of Marianao. It comes under the administration of<lb/>
the Alcalde (Mayor) of Marianao.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Hospital Alfonso XII&rdquo; was always a military hospital. Its name<lb/>
was changed by the Americans to &ldquo;Military Hospital No. 1&rdquo;. After the<lb/>
Army of Occupation left Cuba, in 1902, its name was changed to Hospital<lb/>
Calixto Garcia. A few years ago it became autonamous, with the University<lb/>
of Havana, it being actually the University Hospital but being still known<lb/>
as &ldquo;Hospital Calixto Garcia&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Par. 9: In your paragraphs 9 and 123, the Pinar del Rio incident is<lb/>
fairly well covered. Captain Guy C. M. Godfrey, Assistant Surgeon, U. S.<lb/>
Army (the son of a distinguished Cavalry officer who won the M. H. (Medal<lb/>
of Honor) in the West), was Post Surgeon at Pinar del Rio Barracks. Dr.<lb/>
Robert P. Cooke, Acting Assistant Surgeon, U. S. Army (Contract Surgeon),<lb/>
was his assistant. Major Robert E. Lee Michie, U. S. Volunteers, was<lb/>
Adjutant General on the staff of General Fitzhugh Lee<del><unclear>i</unclear></del>, Commander of<lb/>
the Department of Havana &amp; Pinar del Rio, later changed to &ldquo;Department of<lb/>
Western Cuba&rdquo;, with headquarters in the town of Marianao (see photo of the<lb/>
building occupied by him, known as &ldquo;Quinta Dura&ntilde;ona&rdquo;, where I was employed<lb/>
as Field Clerk at the time of the experiments).</p>
<p>Par. 14: What was understood between Major Reed and the other three<lb/>
members of the Board to the effect that neither of them should become<lb/>
subject to experimentation is a matter in which I would be guessing,<lb/>
were I to express an opinion. I do not think that Major Reed ever<lb/>
seriously considered it incumbent upon himself to undergo experiments.<lb/>
He would not do so without authority of the Surgeon General of the Army<lb/>
and I feel morally certain that such consent would not have been obtained.<lb/>
For one thing, he was too advanced in years to have a fair chance of<lb/>
recovery from yellow fever and for another, he was in Cuba on a mission<lb/>
which would preclude any such venture on his part. I feel reasonably<lb/>
sure that Dr. Carroll, far from robust at that time, would not deliberately<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03625002"/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
walk into yellow fever. While younger than Major Reed by three years,<lb/>
the latter enjoyed good health, while Carroll did not. It was generally<lb/>
accepted that Agramonte, in common with all Cubans, was immune, it being<lb/>
presumed that all natives either had the disease in mild form, in infancy,<lb/>
if not born immune. Agramonte, in later years, claimed that he was no more<lb/>
immune than the rest of us, having been taken to the U. S. when he was<lb/>
about five years old, returning to his native country in 1898 or 25 years<lb/>
later, entering the U. S. Army as a Contract Surgeon. Of the four members<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Board, therefore, Dr. Lazear was the ideal one for<lb/>
experimentation. He was 34 at the time, in sound health and devoted to<lb/>
research work of the exact nature which the Board was expected to invest-<lb/>
igate. It may be taken for granted that the Surgeon General of the Army<lb/>
would not authorize any member of the Board to experiment upon himself nor<lb/>
on any of his associates and it is equally certain that Major Reed would<lb/>
not officially consent to any such proposal, although, in the case of Dr.<lb/>
Lazear, he might have given passive consent, knowing that he was physic-<lb/>
ally sound and would stand a good chance of surviving a possible attack of<lb/>
yellow fever. Had Dr. Lazear pulled through, I am morally certain that<lb/>
his case would have been properly made of record as experimental rather<lb/>
than accidental. Any hint dropped by Dr. Agramonte to that effect should<lb/>
carry due weight. He and Dr. Lazear were classmates and friends, both<lb/>
graduating in medicine at Columbia University in 1892.</p>
<p>Pars. 15 and 16: Major Alexander N. Stark, commanding the Post Hospital<lb/>
at Columbia Barracks, informed me, after the death of Dr. Lazear, that he<lb/>
sat next to him at dinner, at the Officers' Mess, the night before Dr.<lb/>
Lazear came down with yellow fever and that the latter complained of an<lb/>
aching body and slight fever; that he (Stark) advised him to go lightly<lb/>
on food but ate a hearty dinner just the same, stating that he had a good<lb/>
appetite, having spent the day at Las Animas Hospital where he had a light<lb/>
lunch. The following morning he had a high temperature and in seven days<lb/>
he breathed his last. Major Stark opined that his hearty meal on the eve<lb/>
of his attack was instrumental in lessening his chances of recovery. Dr.<lb/>
Stark ventured no opinion as to whether his case was accidental or experi-<lb/>
mental. With all due respect to any opinion expressed by Dr. Agramonte,<lb/>
as recollected by his daughter, I very much doubt if Dr. Lazear was bitten<lb/>
prior to September 13th. He was treated at the Post Hospital and was<lb/>
buried, I believe, near Camp Columbia. As to when his remains were dis-<lb/>
interred and shipped to the U. S., I do not know. Full details can be<lb/>
given by his widow, I imagine, as to dates and definite resting place.<lb/>
General Kean may know Mrs. Lazear's address. Dr. Carroll was treated at<lb/>
the Post Hospital, Columbia Barracks and convalesced there.</p>
<p>Par. 22: I do not recall the names of others than the five original vol-<lb/>
unteers, viz: Dr. Cooke, Folk, Jernegan, Kissinger and myself, who took<lb/>
up residence at Camp Lazear on date of its inauguration. We had a cook,<lb/>
kitchen police and guards, but I do not recall the names of any of them.</p>
<p>Par. 23: The &ldquo;Infected Clothing Building&rdquo; was ready when we occupied Camp<lb/>
Lazear but sufficient soiled clothing was not available until about ten days<lb/>
(continued on sheet 3)<lb/>
ooo0ooo<lb/>
NOTE: You will recall that Major Stark was my protector and preceptor. I<lb/>
worked with him in the operating room and he was the first to suggest to me<lb/>
that I should study medicine at his Alma Mater, the University of Virginia.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03625003"/>
-- 3 --<lb/>
after we took up residence at the camp. As near as I can recollect, the<lb/>
nurse who took care of Kissinger and myself was a Mrs. Gillan. I think she<lb/>
succeeded a Miss Warner, or it may have been Mrs. Warner. I do not know if<lb/>
she is still alive. In addition to Mrs. Gillan, two or three Hospital<lb/>
Corps men were on duty with her, but she had charge of the ward. We had<lb/>
as roustabout and ward orderly, one Gustaf Eric Lambert (No. 22 on General<lb/>
Truby's photo of the Hospital Corps Detachment. I think he is still alive<lb/>
and it may well be that General Kean, Kissinger or Andrus could give you<lb/>
his address. Last I knew of him, he was living in Chicago.</p>
<p>Par. 27: Building No. 2 was completed before December 21 but was not<lb/>
provided with the requisite number of mosquitos until that date. I do not<lb/>
know the date work was started on it nor do I remember the two men, by<lb/>
name, who slept on the mosquito-free side for 18 nights.</p>
<p>Par. 28: The blood injection was given to me at the laboratory (the old<lb/>
operating room) and it was taken from an experimental case. Major Reed<lb/>
personally requested me to take the test and accompanied me until it was<lb/>
all over. Who actually gave me the injection, I do not remember, but<lb/>
it was not Major Reed. Principally engraved in my memory and still <hi>stick-<lb/>
ing out like a sore thumb</hi> was my concern as to the purity of the blood<lb/>
but Major Reed assured me that I need have no fear on that score; that a<lb/>
second attack of yellow fever was all I had to fear. I had no fear of<lb/>
that.</p>
<p>Par. 29: After Se&ntilde;ora Rojas and myself agree as to the site of Camp Lazear,<lb/>
I shall mark on the map and have photographed what WE THINK might have been<lb/>
the site or part of the site. I think, however, that the high ground of<lb/>
which you took snapshots and from there down to the shack, with the culti-<lb/>
vated ground where you took a picture of me, with another in which appear<lb/>
Mrs. Hench, yourself and your humble servant, might have been a part of<lb/>
Camp Lazear. The latter pictures were taken by the photographer, the snap-<lb/>
shots with your own Kodak. The trees do not fit any pictures we have of<lb/>
Camp Lazear and the two trees shown in same near the entrance to the Camp.<lb/>
From Hospital Militar to &ldquo;Quinta San Jos&eacute;&rdquo; (gate), by the shortest route,<lb/>
the distance is 2 kilometers and to the high ground referred to above, the<lb/>
distance is 2.5 kilometers, respectively, a mile and a quarter and a little<lb/>
over a mile and a half. The measurements were taken by speedometer.</p>
<p>Par. 32: Your directions for reaching Camp Lazear are OK, as near as I<lb/>
can see. I could not say if the original tract taken over by the U. S.<lb/>
Army has been added to or not, but I think it has, especially in the<lb/>
direction of the Military Aviation Camp, marked AERODROMO on the Military<lb/>
map. &ldquo;Boquette&rdquo; Road is more than likely a local name and I do not find<lb/>
it on any map in my possession. The present Military Hospital is now<lb/>
officially known as HOSPITAL GENERAL &ldquo;ARISTIDES AGRAMONTE&rdquo; (The Aristides<lb/>
Agramonte General Hospital), the group consisting of eight buildings, the<lb/>
principal of which is the &ldquo;Clinica 4 de Septiembre&rdquo;, the latter being a<lb/>
new building and the rest new or remodeled and modernized under the new<lb/>
Cuban Army. Each building has a separate name but the entire group is<lb/>
known as indicated above. &ldquo;Linea Paradero&rdquo; would mean a way-station or<lb/>
&ldquo;Paradero&rdquo;, where tickets are not sold. The term &ldquo;Linea Paradero&rdquo; is not<lb/>
generally used, that I know of. The first word means &ldquo;Line&rdquo; and the<lb/>
second &ldquo;Stopping Point&rdquo; or waystation. With reference to the &ldquo;Framboyan&rdquo;<lb/>
trees on the &ldquo;Finca San Jos&eacute;&rdquo; site, I am morally certain that the one we<lb/>
were looking at could not be the one shown on the 1900-1901 pictures of<lb/>
Camp Lazear. The limb you had cut off the tree on the false site, after<lb/>
drying and testing a section of same, was declared unworkable for any form<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03625004"/>
-- 4 --<lb/>
of souvenir, such as you mentioned while we were at the Souvenir Shop<lb/>
in &ldquo;Plaza de la Catedral&rdquo; (Cathedral Plaza). I am sorry about this for<lb/>
I know you had calculated on converting the wood from one of these trees<lb/>
into souvenirs. I know you will be disappointed, but I am sure you<lb/>
would also be disappointed in anything that could be made from Framboyan<lb/>
wood. It happens to be one of the woods of Cuba good for nothing but<lb/>
firewood and not very good for even that.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Boquette&rdquo; Road is not generally known as such and not shown on<lb/>
any map available to me. I now note what you mean by &ldquo;Linea Paradero&rdquo;.<lb/>
I see where you got it from. It is shown on Pogolotti's plan of the<lb/>
&ldquo;Reparto Padre Zamora&rdquo;. Properly read, it should be &ldquo;Linea Santa Isabel&rdquo;<lb/>
and the &ldquo;Paradero&rdquo; in between "Linea and &ldquo;Sta. Isabel&rdquo; means that the<lb/>
&ldquo;Carnino&rdquo; station, named after Pogolotti's mother, is the way station<lb/>
just as you turn into the so called road to the false Camp Lazear. As you<lb/>
know, this line is not being used any more. The track is practically covered with<lb/>
with weeds just now.</p>
<p>Unless the Cuban authorities really meant what they stated when<lb/>
Colonel Hume was <del><unclear></unclear></del> here in September,<lb/>
1936, and the false Camp Lazear was &ldquo;discovered&rdquo;, there is but little<lb/>
reason for dwelling too much now on the error that was made then. It<lb/>
should be made clear, however, in your paper that the error might never<lb/>
have been discovered had you not visited Cuba. It is due to your<lb/>
initiative and your persistency in following up the matter which have<lb/>
led to the discovery of the real location of Camp Lazear. On the other<lb/>
hand, it would be most appropriate to have some form of memorial on the<lb/>
false site, property of the Cuban government, I believe, since that site<lb/>
is not lacking in historical interest. I quote from a very recent letter<lb/>
from General Kean, in this connection: &ldquo;I have had a lot of correspondence<lb/>
with Dr. P. S. Hench. It is a most interesting story how he with your<lb/>
assistance showed the Cubans that they had located Camp Lazear in the wrong<lb/>
place. Where they have located it and bought the land for a monument is<lb/>
where the yellow fever cases were treated in a temporary ward. I remember it<lb/>
well for it is where I was treated when I had yellow fever in June, 1900<lb/>
and Major Reed came to see me there. It is an appropriate place for a<lb/>
monument to Lazear, BECAUSE HE DIED THERE, but it certainly is not the<lb/>
location of the experimental camp where the Finlay theory was demonstrated<lb/>
to be true by the Reed Commission, and which was named after Lazear but had no<lb/>
other association with him. That camp was on the Rojas farm, a mile to the<lb/>
east of there (actually, 1 1/4 miles to the main entrance to the &ldquo;Finca San Jos&eacute;&rdquo;).<lb/>
I think it is proper always to speak of the transmission of yellow fever by<lb/>
mosquitoes as THE FINLAY THEORY which gives that dear old man the credit which<lb/>
shoud be his.&rdquo;" End of quote.</p>
<p><unclear>apparently</unclear><lb/>
written before the<lb/>
discovery of the<lb/>
Rojas book.</p>
<p>Par. 40: According to the written record left by Dr. Ignacio Rojas which I<lb/>
saw a few days ago, it would appear that the contract for rental of the camp<lb/>
site was made by <del><unclear></unclear></del> Dr. Echeverria, whom General Kean will recall<lb/>
and whom I remember as local Sanitary Officer for Quemados and Marianao. My<lb/>
friend, Charles Parker, was his Chief Clerk. It will also appear from the<lb/>
records and books of Dr. Rojas that a regiment of Volunteers from one of the<lb/>
Carolinas had been stationed there or rather had had their camp there, at one<lb/>
time. When I was transferred to Columbia Barracks, all the volunteer troops<lb/>
had left that post, the 7th U. S. Cavalry, under command of Colonel Baldwin,<lb/>
being the principal unit. Col. Baldwin was in command of the entire post.<lb/>
It is, of course, possible that Dr. Agramonte first spoke to Dr. Rojas about<lb/>
the Camp Lazear site, Dr. Echeverria signing the contract with Dr. Rojas. You<lb/>
will read all about this in the copied material that Miss Rojas will turn over<lb/>
to Mrs. Phillips for translation and typing.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03625005"/>
<p>-- 5 --</p>
<p>Par. 51: With reference to the last three lines of this paragraph (bracketed).<lb/>
I do not think the invitation would be advisable. I am afraid it would not<lb/>
suit him.</p>
<p>Par. 53: A &ldquo;Finca&rdquo; means a farm of 50 to 100 acres of land. From 150 acres up<lb/>
it might be known as an &ldquo;Hacienda&rdquo;. When reduced to the present acreage of<lb/>
&ldquo;Quita San Jos&eacute;&rdquo;, or even half of it, it would no longer merit the title of<lb/>
&ldquo;Finca&rdquo;. When most of the &ldquo;Finca San Jos&eacute;&rdquo; was sold, the family changed the<lb/>
name of the mansion and the ground still owned by them and walled off to<lb/>
&ldquo;Quinta San Jos&eacute;&rdquo;. A &ldquo;Tejar&rdquo; is a brick or tile factory.</p>
<p>Par. 59: Principally through my fault, we allowed Zunzunegui (pronounced Zoon-<lb/>
zoon-eggy to slip through our hands. This was due to the fact that he remarked<lb/>
that the Americanos used to pay $2.00 a head for people who would permit them-<lb/>
selves to be bitten by mosquitoes. Within the past week, howver, this man<lb/>
looms big in our investigations and his <hi>rediscovery</hi> is intimately connected<lb/>
with the &ldquo;discovery&rdquo; of Dr. Rojas' old account books and the lease for exploit-<lb/>
ation of the limestone quarries made between Dr. Rojas and Zunzunegui's father,<lb/>
which included the use and occupancy of Buildings No. 1 and No. 2. After the<lb/>
lease became effective, Zunzunegui Senior and his family moved into Building<lb/>
No. 1 and his son (Julian) lived in that little shack from that time until<lb/>
1936. After he married, 21 years ago, he and his wife lived in the shack and<lb/>
all three of his children were born there. I have made notes on the photo-<lb/>
graphs taken yesterday (Saturday), including on of Z. and his family, which<lb/>
give additional details about him. Without a shadow of a doubt, he is more<lb/>
familiar with the physical changes and transition of the &ldquo;Finca San Jos&eacute;&rdquo; than<lb/>
any other person that I know of today. As I have prevously stated, the good<lb/>
Se&ntilde;ora Rojas did not visit the part of the farm in which the Camp was located<lb/>
in many years. Stone and earth was excavated from the land with<del><unclear></unclear></del> but little<lb/>
realization on her part that it was in its present honeycombed state, with a<lb/>
limestone quarry on one side and a combination rock and brick <del><unclear></unclear></del> clay quarry<lb/>
on the other side.</p>
<p>Par. 69: Would suggest you deal carefully with this old Spanish medico. He<lb/>
was willing to talk frankly to you but I doubt very much if he would be will-<lb/>
ing to to be equally frank on paper and over his signature. In a conversation<lb/>
with Miss Cabrera, she doubted very much if it would be wise or expedient for<lb/>
him to make his statements about Finlay a matter of record. Personally, I do<lb/>
not believe that the book he talked about will be published during his life-<lb/>
time, nor after his death for the matter of that. I suggest that you soft<lb/>
pedal the statements he made about Finlay. The old chap might get himself<lb/>
into very hot water and I am sure you would not like that.</p>
<p>Par. 72: The title should read &ldquo;Secretary of Sanitation&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;Health&rdquo;.<lb/>
In Spanish it would be properly &ldquo;Secretario de Sanidad y Beneficencia&rdquo; and<lb/>
translated it would be Secretary of Sanitation and Beneficence, but the<lb/>
last word in the title may be left out in your paper.</p>
<p>Par. 79: The name of the nurse should read Miss Clara L. Maas, the surname<lb/>
having but one &ldquo;s&rdquo;.</p>
<p><unclear>Mistake-</unclear><lb/>
See letter<lb/>
of Oct 12, <unclear>1940</unclear><lb/>
p 2.</p>
<p>Par. 81: I am sure that Dr. Ramos and the other doctors who claimed their<lb/>
site as the genuine one no longer think so. In a conversation with Mrs.<lb/>
Phillips she informed me that Mr. Pogolotti had told her that the author-<lb/>
ities sent a man to wipe out the sign and when I took a picture of it some<lb/>
days ago. I noticed that the lettering had been erased. Evidently the job<lb/>
was not very well done. The sign, as you can see by my Photo No. 10, has<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03625006"/>
-- 6 --<lb/>
not been taken down. Pogolotti added that the Cuban authorities had tacitly<lb/>
admitted their error. With the new evidence now within your reach, which I<lb/>
propose to make known to Dr. Ramos as soon as I can &ldquo;catch up&rdquo; with him, it<lb/>
would be folly for them to stick to their claims. So far, they know nothing<lb/>
about the new evidence. After all, it is not a capital sin to err in good<lb/>
faith, in such a matter, and after the lapse of so many years, but it would be<lb/>
if they should pretend to stick to it, especially after the <hi>real site</hi> of Camp<lb/>
Lazear is discovered. I am personally in accord with General Kean that we<lb/>
should all bend our efforts to the end of having the Cubans build their park<lb/>
or other form of memorial to Dr. Lazear and his associates on the site of<lb/>
the tent ward in which he died. I have no doubt you could exert a healthy<lb/>
influence on Dr. Ramos &amp; Company in such a matter. From now on, I imagine<lb/>
they will have a wholesome respect for you and you are sufficiently broad-<lb/>
minded and big-hearted to overlook the hostility displayed towards us when we<lb/>
broke the news to them that they had placed Camp Lazear where it never was.<lb/>
I take it that YOUR MAIN OBJECT was and is to reconcile the American and<lb/>
Cuban points of view with reference to Reed and Finlay, giving to each his<lb/>
proper share of the credit and glory. It would serve no good purpose to<lb/>
antagonize them by placing too great an emphasis on their error in falsely<lb/>
locating Camp Lazear. After all, they may have erred in good failth, but<lb/>
they were lax in consulting those who could inform them better, or rather<lb/>
failing to consult them. The Cubans, as you may or may not know, are very<lb/>
sensitive. I think this fault is universal when the people of a small<lb/>
nation begin to compare themselves with those of a nation as powerful and as<lb/>
progressive as ours, for instance. At heart, however, the percentage of<lb/>
Cubans who do not like us and admire us is very small. The ingrates, mostly<lb/>
COMMUNISTS, are the exception. I want you to know that, personally, I do<lb/>
not fear any reprisals which might fall to my lot through my share in the<lb/>
discovery of their error. Furthermore, the fact that the Cubans have honored<lb/>
me with the Finlay Order or Medal does not change my opinion of the glory to<lb/>
which I have always considered as pertaining to Major Reed. Very largely<del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
due to General Keen's opinion in the premises, I have revised my opinion of<lb/>
Finlay and very much in his favor, but I have never revised my opinion of<lb/>
Major Reed. To me, Major Reed was THE SOUL of the episode which led to THE<lb/>
CONQUEST OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>Par. 86: We met in the building of the &ldquo;Consejo Corporativo de Educacion,<lb/>
Sanidad y Beneficencia&rdquo; (Corporate Council of Education, Sanitation &amp; Benfi-<lb/>
cence).</p>
<p>Par. 101 to 104: I am afraid I cannot add more on this matter than is<lb/>
covered by my observations on Paragraphs 14, 15 and 16 (Page 2).</p>
<p>Par. 115: The space (or at least much of it) occupied by the volunteer<lb/>
regiments was converted into a corral for horses and mules, as near as I<lb/>
can recollect.</p>
<p>Par. 116: I must admit here that I am &ldquo;stumped&rdquo; with reference to the<lb/>
bridge across the railroad track. As suggested in another paragraph,<lb/>
Gustaf Eric Lambert, who had charge of the &ldquo;Disinfection <unclear>Plant</unclear>&rdquo; could give<lb/>
particulars on both. He remained in Cuba until the Americans cleared out<lb/>
entirely (1902), I believe. I bow to General Keen's recollections in<lb/>
this connection. If I crossed any bridges to get to the hospital, after<lb/>
my recovery from yellow fever, I have forgotten all about it. This covers<lb/>
any remarks I could make about Paragraph 118.</p>
<p>p7 taken to <unclear>fla</unclear></p>
<pb n="7" id="f03625007"/>
<p><unclear>about oct 8, 1940</unclear></p>
<p>-- 7 --</p>
<p>Pars. 122 to 127, inclusive: I think a veil should be drawn on the<lb/>
personalities mentioned here, one of whom is still alive. The Agramonte-<lb/>
Hemmetr correspondence, if published, would add nothing to the glory of<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Board as a whole, I am sure. C's effort at usurpation<lb/>
would not entitle him to have his name used in any sentence or paragraph<lb/>
wherein the name of REED appeared. Dr. Cooke was young and inexperienced,<lb/>
much more especially in differentiating between Pernicious Malaria and<lb/>
Yellow Fever. As a matter of fact, few American medicos present in Cuba<lb/>
at that time had had experience with yellow fever and other trpoical<lb/>
diseases. It was an unfortunate incident, nothing more.</p>
<p>LAS ANIMAS HOSPITAL: The site and the buildings, I believe, was a Spanish<lb/>
Camp originally and was converted into a hospital only a short time before<lb/>
the American Army landed in Cuba. A hospital known as &ldquo;Los Angeles&rdquo; was<lb/>
abandoned and all its equipment was sent to the original &ldquo;Hospital Las<lb/>
Animas&rdquo;. Twice, it was used as a municipal hospital and twice as a military<lb/>
hospital. In 1899, General Wood, Military Governor, had it converted into<lb/>
a Military Hospital. In November of the same year, it was used as a<lb/>
Municipal Hospital and &ldquo;Los Angeles Hospital's&rdquo; equipment and utensils<lb/>
transferred to it. While the record is not very clear, it was at this time<lb/>
that it was baptized &ldquo;Hospital Las Animas&rdquo;. In January, 1900, it became a<lb/>
a Military Hospital once more. A Military Order of the Governor turned it<lb/>
over to the Department of Sanitation on September 7, 1900. The latter<lb/>
Department then undertook to convert it into a real hospital where infectious<lb/>
and contagious cases, of a nature dangerous to public health, could be treated<lb/>
and/or placed under observation. Even to this day, it is the only hospital<lb/>
used for the general purposes indicated above. The hospital grounds is<lb/>
about fifty acres. Used by the Engineer Corps of the Spanish Army, originally,<lb/>
it gradually changed into an isolation camp and eventually into a hospital.</p>
<p>From <unclear>Barnett.</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>any Engineering</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>not near<lb/>
Las Animas</unclear></p>
<p>IN CONCLUSION: In order to get this to you so that it may serve your<lb/>
purpose in time, should there be any notes of value in it, I am sending it<lb/>
to you today by AIR MAIL, with 27 additional photographs. I will again<lb/>
go thoroughly over your letters and YOUR MAIN PAPER, as I must have missed<lb/>
a numb<del>s</del>er of items. If I find that I can make appropriate reply to any-<lb/>
thing I have overlooked, I will send you an additional memorandum between<lb/>
now and the 20th, the date I expect to leave for God's Country.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>.
JJM:elm<lb/>
The &ldquo;elm&rdquo; stands for &ldquo;el mismo&rdquo; (himself)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
