<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03626006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, October 16, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03626006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College (Washington, Pa)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-16">October 16, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03626006</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, October 16, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench sends Leon his speech for the Lazear memorial event at Washington and Jefferson College.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, October 16, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03626006"/>
<opener>
(CARBON)<lb/>
<dateline>
Wednesday<lb/>
<date value="1940-10-16">10/16/40</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mrs Rodriguez - Leon</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am writing you in this unusual fashion in order<lb/>
to save a little precious time and to have a memorandum of this<lb/>
letter to you. Hence the pencil as I am using a carbon. I am<lb/>
enclosing the last pages of my talk to be given at the<lb/>
Washington &amp; Jefferson affair just 10 days from now. The first<lb/>
11 pages give a running account of the well-known story-<lb/>
the formation of the Board, the work at Columbia Barracks &amp; at<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital, the death of Lazear (official version)<lb/>
and then the work at Camp Lazear. To condense this into 11 pages<lb/>
necessitated omitting much that I eventually will publish in<lb/>
more ample form. But I was able to introduce <hi>all</hi> the characters<lb/>
involved. Naturally in such a short account as this is<lb/>
I have dealt, under the special circumstance, more with Lazear<lb/>
than with any others and have therefore entitled this particular<lb/>
paper &ldquo;Dr Jesse W Lazear and his contribution to the Conquest<lb/>
of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. In order not to be misunderstood and to<lb/>
be considered as favoring Lazear (and you are entirely right<lb/>
when you say that a writer can, unless he is careful, be carried<lb/>
away by one character) I have attached a footnote on the<lb/>
front page as follows: on the occasion of the dedication of<lb/>
a Lazear memorial the writer deems as appropriate to deal<lb/>
chiefly with the activities of Lazear, but by so doing it is not<lb/>
the writer's intention to minimize in the slightest degree<lb/>
the contribution of any of the many persons who participated<lb/>
in the conquest of this disease. The writer proposes to deal<lb/>
elsewhere &amp; more fully with the whole story"</p>
<p>I hasten to state that this note is <hi>NOT</hi> directed to<lb/>
you but more to the admirers of C and to still those who<lb/>
for example favor Kissinger over Moran etc etc,<lb/>
I believe you have seen enough of me to know I have no<lb/>
favorites and <unclear><del>that</del></unclear> I feel that the story is so wonderful that<lb/>
it is my self-imposed &amp; pleasant duty to re-assert<lb/>
the glory of all - not excepting Finlay by any means</p>
<p>But the main purpose of my writing this hasty letter is to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03626007"/>
beg of you to read over my interpretation of your remarks to<lb/>
me as to your father's opinions <unclear>re</unclear> Lazear and to return<lb/>
them <hi>at your very earliest convenience</hi> either with your<lb/>
corrections or if it is alright, please just cable me the<lb/>
following message <hi>COLLECT</hi> <hi>Hench - Rochester</hi>,<lb/>
<hi>Minnesota - Approve</hi>. There are no other Henches here &amp;<lb/>
it will reach me promptly. The reason I want to hear from you<lb/>
is that I dont want to quote you wrongly or attribute<lb/>
to your father erroneous statements or even thoughts<unclear>.</unclear><lb/>
We will have plenty of time to change or correct it before it<lb/>
is published in a medical journal but I have been<lb/>
asked to have a copy ready for the Press as soon as<lb/>
possible &amp; would therefore like to hear from you before Sunday<lb/>
or Monday if possible.</p>
<p>As you will see, I carefully omitted the several lines<lb/>
to which you objected (lines written by me based apparently<lb/>
on a faulty recollection of our conversation). I think I have<lb/>
<unclear>stuck</unclear> to your actual words as much as possible but<lb/>
in one or two sentences I paraphrased your remarks.<lb/>
But I do so want to use it <hi>in quotation marks</hi>-<lb/>
it makes the statements more authentic - it adds much<lb/>
punch to them &amp; not the least important it credits<lb/>
the remarks properly - assigning their authorship to<lb/>
<hi>you</hi>.</p>
<p>I am hastily doing the same thing with Gen.<lb/>
Truby - getting him to confirm my quotations.<lb/>
I see no conflict between your statements &amp; <unclear>his.</unclear><lb/>
The only difference is that your father apparently speculated<lb/>
a little more as to the possible motive of Lazear &amp; I think<lb/>
his speculations most interesting- I do hope I interpreted<lb/>
them right,</p>
<p>I think your fathers tribute to Lazear was beautiful, so<lb/>
lovely that I am using it as the closing quotation.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03626008"/>
<p>Furthermore it throws a splendid light on your fathers character-<lb/>
I refer to his one simple statement of humility - a beautiful<lb/>
attribute. I am sure the audience will be very thrilled to<lb/>
hear this version &amp; I am indeed grateful for permission to use<lb/>
it.</p>
<p>Don't think that you have heard the last of me! No such<lb/>
luck on your part. I have gotten this story into my blood<lb/>
&amp; have already collected so much data that I plan probably<lb/>
to write a small (?) monograph on it &amp; there I will need<lb/>
all the help you can give, so that I can give due credit to all<lb/>
concerned, fairly, critically but <hi><unclear>sympathetically</unclear></hi>. I will<lb/>
write later about other details in your last letter, I shall<lb/>
be most careful of the photo. <unclear>It</unclear> surely was taken at the<lb/>
same hospital as the other - the roof construction in this<lb/>
photo compares with that <unclear>in the other</unclear>. I believe it was<lb/>
probably Las Animas but on having it copied &amp; will<lb/>
send copies to some survivors so that they can help<lb/>
identify it - the place &amp; people, I assume your father is the<lb/>
figure on the <hi>right</hi>. The other vaguely resemble Lazear<lb/>
but the beard looks too full.</p>
<p>Did you forget to tell me the relationship of your father<lb/>
to the Agramonte on the postage stamps? Would you be<lb/>
willing to let me photostat your fathers entire manuscript<lb/>
instead of one page? I always like to return two for one<lb/>
when possible &amp; will if I can not only return the original<lb/>
but also a photostat copy for you to <unclear>keep</unclear> so that <hi>other<lb/>
pestiferous persons</hi> need not <del>bother</del> borrow your<lb/>
prized original. How anxious I am to see more of<lb/>
your fathers letters from Reed et al, his photographs,<lb/>
&amp; the drawings of Building #1 &amp; 2. By the way<lb/>
do you think the drawings were made in 1900 or<lb/>
did he not make <unclear>these notes</unclear> writing <unclear>his</unclear> 1915 <unclear>article</unclear>?</p>
<p>I have written Mrs Lazear preparing her for this information but<lb/>
Truby Kean (and I think army men whom they consulted) all agreed that<lb/>
now was a most appropriate time to divulge this data.</p>
<p>I await your answer with eagerness but<lb/>
some anxiety &amp; do <del><unclear>y</unclear></del> hope you will approve.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely</salute>
<signed>P. S. <hi>Hench</hi></signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
