<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03635011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Dorma V. Schnurr, October 21, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03635011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Schnurr, Dorma V.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Rojas farm, San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-21">October 21, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03635011</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Dorma V. Schnurr, October 21, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench gives Schnurr some background information for the speech he is giving at Washington and Jefferson College.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-21">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Dorma V. Schnurr, October 21, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03635011"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-10-21">October 21, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Miss Schnorr<lb/>
Rochester Post Bulletin<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Miss Schnorr:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Here is the Appe you asked for. Although the chief items of news value<lb/>
(if any) are probably confined to the last 7 pages I would appreciate it <hi>greatly</hi><lb/>
if you would read over not only my abbreviated version of the first 6 pages but<lb/>
also, if at all possible, the fuller version. I am so anxious that in this case<lb/>
the tail will not wag the dog. In your loyalty to me as a local citizen I don't<lb/>
want you to forget that the affair is the dedication of the Lazear Memorial<lb/>
Chemistry Building at Washington and Jefferson College and that it is the yellow<lb/>
fever martyr Lazear and not your humble servant who is being honored. Hence,<lb/>
my request that you read the full account so that you can have the <hi>proper back</hi>-<lb/>
<hi>ground</hi> and know why he is being honored. In his memory Washington and Jefferson<lb/>
College is honoring the American medical profession by granting honorary degrees<lb/>
to several American physicians. I don't know who they are except that one is to<lb/>
be Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer, Director of the Rockefeller International Foundation and<lb/>
the world's leading authority on yellow fever. He is the main speaker of the<lb/>
morning affair. I am the main speaker at the evening affair, but Moran and<lb/>
Kissinger are the <hi>honor guests</hi> at the whole affair. (It was the part of Moran which<lb/>
James Stewart took in the stage version and Robert Montgomery took in the movie<lb/>
version of &ldquo;Yellow Jack.&rdquo; Moran was &ldquo;O'Hara&rdquo; and Kissinger was named Brinkerhof<lb/>
in the play.) Mrs. Lazear and Dr. Cooke, were also invited but I think were unable<lb/>
to go.</p>
<p>My contribution to all this results from the historical investigations<lb/>
which I carried out this spring in Havana (and since then by voluminous<lb/>
correspondence:) with <hi>Moran</hi> and Mr. Luis 3. <hi>Pogolotti</hi> (Havana engineer) which<lb/>
began when I decided the Cuban government had erred in purchasing and marking<lb/>
the wrong site as &ldquo;Camp Lazear.&rdquo; Of news value on this angle may be, <unclear>t.</unclear> belated<lb/>
discovery of the extent of Dr. Lazear's martyrdom. He died of experimental, not<lb/>
accidental yellow fever, 2. discovery that the site marked by the Cuban government<lb/>
was not the site of Camp Lazear but the site of the yellow fever tent hospital<lb/>
where Lazear died, (Hence their mistake was a fortunate one) 3. rediscovery of<lb/>
the true site of Camp Lazear on the San Jose farm of Dr. Ignacio Rojas, including<lb/>
discovery of the Rojas diary with unmistakable proof, 4. Rediscovery of the now<lb/>
famous &ldquo;Infected Clothing Bldg.&rdquo; (Bldg. #1) where Walter Reed and his colleagues<lb/>
carried out one of the crucial series of experiments - the one which disproved<lb/>
completely the idea held at that time, that yellow fever was caused by &ldquo;infected<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03635012"/>
Miss Schnorr<lb/>
2<lb/>
October 21, 1940<lb/>
belongings&rdquo; of yellow fever victims. This last discovery resulted after the<lb/>
discovery of the Rojas day-book (Journal or diary) wherein it was stated<lb/>
distinctly that &ldquo;the two small wooden buildings were delivered over&rdquo; to the<lb/>
Rojas family and not destroyed by Walter Reed when he broke camp (as everyone,<lb/>
including the Rojas family themselves - the present members - believed until<lb/>
now).</p>
<p>Remember that <hi>Moran</hi> and <hi>Pogolotti</hi> helped me in all this (although I<lb/>
started the ball rolling and kept it rolling).</p>
<p>The Cubans are a very sensitive (but fine) people, quick to be hurt<lb/>
and quick to be pleased. And if you could mention <hi>Moran</hi>, <hi>Pogolotti</hi>, and<lb/>
<hi>Madame Rojas</hi> it would please them no end and probably help me a lot with my<lb/>
unfinished business in connection with the restoration of the little building<lb/>
and its eventual presentation to the Cuban government. (Incidentally Mrs. Rojas<lb/>
is quite a gal, a lovely, wealthy and cultured Havana lady now 80 years old.)<lb/>
May I remind you also that the Cuban <hi>government</hi> (I mean that literally) are<lb/>
much distressed because &ldquo;Americans have consistently ignored the pioneer work<lb/>
of Dr. Finlay.&rdquo; As a result they have carried on a real campaign to glorify<lb/>
Finlay's name (naturally at the expense of Reed et al). Therefore, we propose<lb/>
to try to heal this senseless feud by using the shack (Bldg. #1) as a symbol<lb/>
and means to an end, and presenting it to the Cuban government as &ldquo;the place<lb/>
where the concept of Finlay was proven to be correct and his great pioneering<lb/>
work amplified by the experiments of the United States Army Yellow Fever Board.&rdquo;</p>
<p>So if you can give a bit of a cheer for &ldquo;dear old Finlay,&rdquo; the Rochester<lb/>
Post Bulletin will help old Doc Hench mighty much the next time (this spring) I<lb/>
go down that-a-ways to Cuba where they play the tuba! (because I'll send 'em<lb/>
a copy!)</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours for Willkie,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSE:as<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I gets me an honorary Doctor of Science degree, fancy that!<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
