<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03630001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on Dinner for John J. Moran, by Atcheson Laughlin Hench, October 23, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Atcheson Laughlin</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03630001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Jordan, Harvey E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Clemons, Harry</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Moran, Elida</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Indianapolis (Ind.)</name>
<name type="place">Jamaica</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-23">October 23, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03630001</idno>
<title>Notes on Dinner for John J. Moran, by Atcheson Laughlin Hench, October 23, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Atcheson Hench describes the setting, guests, conversations, and presentations at a dinner given in honor of Moran at which Kean described the yellow fever experiments and Moran answered questions from the guests.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1940-10-23">
<head>Notes on Dinner for John J. Moran, by Atcheson Laughlin Hench, October 23, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03630001"/>
<p>This is a copy of notes I made October 23, 1940 after I came home from<lb/>
a dinner given to Mr. John J. Moran, one of Walter Reed's assistants in the discovery<lb/>
of the cause of yellow fever. The dinner was given by the doctors of the University<lb/>
of Virginia Medical School at Mrs. Beauchamp's home Myhill, east of town. I was<lb/>
invited because of my brother Phil's connection with the study of the history of the<lb/>
discovery. I made the original notes immediately after I came home.</p>
<p>A. L. Hench</p>
<p>-------------------------------------------</p>
<p>A. L.<lb/>
Hench<lb/>
J. J.<lb/>
Moran<lb/>
Dr.<lb/>
Jordan<lb/>
Gen.<lb/>
Kean<lb/>
Harry<lb/>
Clemons<lb/>
Gen.<lb/>
Kean's<lb/>
Son</p>
<p>the tables<lb/>
about 30<lb/>
doctors<lb/>
came<lb/>
About $2 a plate<lb/>
Each of us paid.<lb/>
table</p>
<p>Jordan, dean of the Medical School, was<lb/>
the introducer. With him as guests were<lb/>
Mr. Mora<del>l</del><add>n</add>; General Kean, from Washington;<lb/>
Mr. Clemons, U. Va. librarian; General<lb/>
Kean's son who drove his father (quite aged)<lb/>
up from Richmond (Young Kean was on our<lb/>
chemistry faculty here some years ago.); and<lb/>
myself.</p>
<p>During the meal Mr. Moran mentioned to Jordan or me many things that crossed<lb/>
his mind as we talked with him.</p>
<p>He said that Cubans do not recognize Reed's part in the experiments; they<lb/>
give the credit to Agramonte.</p>
<p>Mrs. Moran is with him. She lived in New York during the World War in<lb/>
1918-19 when he was in France and there picked up English, though she is still shy<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03630002"/>
2<lb/>
about talking to people in English the first few minutes of each conversation.<lb/>
She never sleeps well when he is away from home. &ldquo;I tell her,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;not to be<lb/>
afraid. Nothing ever happens to an Irishman.&rdquo; (Mrs. Jordan took care of Mrs. Moran<lb/>
and had a small supper party for her during their stay.)</p>
<p>He spoke of an honor trial here at the University (in 1902?) while he was<lb/>
a student. It was of a boy by the name of Page. He refused to leave the town, but<lb/>
hired a criminal lawyer instead. The students had nine of the faculty as jury. A<lb/>
holiday was declared and he was tried in Cabell Hall before the whole student body.</p>
<p>His health prevents him from eating raw things like celery, or steak or<lb/>
too much coffee, or any liquor. He never feels the desire for liquor anymore at<lb/>
all, now that he has given it up.</p>
<p>He praised Phil for his painstaking accuracy in tracing things. He thought<lb/>
I was Phil's younger brother. He praised Mary for letting Phil wear himself out even<lb/>
on vacation in Cuba, knowing that she couldn't stop him.</p>
<p>------------------------------------------</p>
<p>After dinner Jordan rose and spoke about as follows: "We are here tonight<lb/>
to honor Mr. Moran, one of the persons used by Walter Reed in his yellow fever studies.<lb/>
He is a shy man and is the last one to talk about himself. (Jordan had earlier told<lb/>
me that repeatedly all afternoon Moran had said he could not make a speech.) But he<lb/>
did a heroic thing and even though he himself does not consider himself a hero, he is<lb/>
so to us. He was Sergeant O'Hara in the play &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; and as such was an<lb/>
inspiration to thousands of children all over America. He is a man who, when the<lb/>
government gave each member of the group of those who submitted themselves to<lb/>
experimentation a gift of $200, refused the gift. He was a medical student here in<lb/>
1902 (?) for a term but was forced by poverty to leave.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03630003"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>&ldquo;We are proud to have here also General Kean, a close friend of Walter Reed,<lb/>
who will tell of the experiments of which Mr. Moran was a part. General Kean.&rdquo;<lb/>
(His name is pronounced as if it were Kane.)</p>
<p>General Kean began speaking standing up but soon said, &ldquo;May I speak sitting<lb/>
down? I'm a bit weak in my pins.&rdquo; (His son told me later that he has a ticklish<lb/>
heart. I think he is about 80 years old.)</p>
<p>Kean reviewed the story of the search for the cause of yellow fever. As<lb/>
well as I can remember his resum&eacute; of it, it went thus: He spoke of a Dr. Agramonte<lb/>
who had been working on a germ which later turned out to be a hog cholera germ, not<lb/>
that of yellow fever. He spoke then of a Dr. Finley who began suspecting one of the<lb/>
varieties of mosquiot, of Reed's being appointed to come down and see if he could find<lb/>
out anything, of the appointment of a board of Reed, Finley (?) and Vaughan. He told<lb/>
the story of Dr. Lazear's being bitten and questioned whether the accurate scientist<lb/>
Lazear would have allowed a stray mosquito to bit him by accident while applying an<lb/>
experimental mosquito to another one's arm. He said he believes Phil's suspicion that<lb/>
Lazear feared that he would lose the small insurance he had for his family if the<lb/>
insurance company knew that he had allowed an experimental mosquito to bit him and so<lb/>
he told the other story. Kean believes Phil is right. The test-tube method of<lb/>
application was the one used by Reed.</p>
<p>He told the story of the building of two shacks, one for positive proof,<lb/>
one for negative proof. Dr. Cooke (now county health officer of Rockingham County,<lb/>
Virginia) was in the negative shack, full of the bed clothing, towels with black<lb/>
vomit from yellow fever patients, etc. They slept on beds, wrapped towels around<lb/>
their necks to get yellow fever; for the belief was then that the clothing and<lb/>
bedding gave the disease (All clothing was usually burned.) Cooke and others never<lb/>
got the disease.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f03630004"/>
<p>4</p>
<p>The other shack was split in half and a mosquito screen was put up; the<lb/>
air in the building was the same. In the infective half of this shack the experimented-<lb/>
on persons were introduced. First, I think he said, some Spanish immigrants were used.<lb/>
They were poor and they were sure to get yellow fever anyway. So the idea was put<lb/>
forward that they be experimented on. When four or five of them got the fever, the<lb/>
rest backed out. Then the call came for Americans. Moran had been hospital assistant<lb/>
and offered; Kissinger too.</p>
<p>For a while the experimenting was secret. Then Kean went to General Wood with<lb/>
Reed and asked if he would not let the experimenting be brought out into the light and<lb/>
allot $10,000 for it. He said he would and he would also allot a second $10,000 if<lb/>
necessary.</p>
<p>He told of Reed's coming up to Indianapolis to a convention of the Public<lb/>
Health Commission (?) and reading a paper on yellow fever which because of its clarity<lb/>
and logic just knocked all others' ideas out.</p>
<p>He told of Vaughan's (?) saving the papers of Dr. Finley (?) in which were<lb/>
invaluable records of experimentation, from being thrown away after his death; and of<lb/>
their publication.</p>
<p>He mentioned a Major Michie associated with Walter Reed.</p>
<p>He spoke of his telling Reed not to subject the lives of his medical board<lb/>
to the danger of death. They were needed to prove the experiment.</p>
<p>------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Someone, possibly Jordan (or Moran himself), told that after the Cuban<lb/>
affair was over Moran came with $600 and some poker money to New York with Kissinger<lb/>
and they stopped at a cheap Mills Hotel, one of a chain of cheap hotels. Moran went<lb/>
to New Jersey and got a job as a soda fountain man and drug assistant (I don't remember<lb/>
just when this was told during the dinner.)</p>
<p>-------------------------------------------</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03630005"/>
<p>5</p>
<p>Dr. Jordan, after General Kean's account, introduced Mr. Moran and said<lb/>
that he was unable to make a speech but would answer questions put to him by the<lb/>
group.</p>
<p>Were you scared? &ldquo;No, I wasn't.&rdquo;</p>
<p>What temperature did you have? He answered by telling the story of his<lb/>
being bitten. He went into the infective room with infected mosquitoes. He lay<lb/>
down on a hospital cot with his clothes off. He was first bitten by about seven<lb/>
mosquitoes. He watched them in a mirror put above him for the purpose. Later in the<lb/>
day he was bitten by four more. On Christmas day he began getting temperature. He had<lb/>
kept a chart of temperature and pulse on a sheet. (He added parenthetically that he<lb/>
had regularly done that before in the medical corps he belonged to.) When he got<lb/>
temperature, he had been told to take it every hour. On Christmas day he wanted to<lb/>
win a bet with a man that he would eat Christmas dinner with his fellow soldiers. He<lb/>
had eaten a hearty breakfast. His temperature had come later in the morning. At<lb/>
dinner time he was weak but he wanted to win the bet. So he went to mess--grand meal<lb/>
of turkey, cranberries and plum-duff (plum pudding). He ate a little bit, knowing<lb/>
that much eating was very harmful if you had fever. Major Reed had not come in in the<lb/>
morning; he did not come in until three o'clock in the afternoon. He asked about<lb/>
Moran's temperature, was shown the chart, and was a very happy man. &ldquo;I was very useless<lb/>
for several days. I didn't care about what happened.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Question: What was Reed like personally? &ldquo;The gentlest, kindest man I<lb/>
ever knew. He was what I would imagine the finest product of the South could produce,<lb/>
a fine Virginian. He wouldn't hurt a fly, as we say--unless it was a scientific fly.&rdquo;</p>
<p>That suggested an experience which he then told: "May I tell about malaria<lb/>
at Culebra in 1904? I'd had malaria off and on for some years. The doctor there had<lb/>
figured out a way to make the Jamaica natives take quinine, by mixing it with rum.<lb/>
He said he'd soak the malaria out of me. He gave me a supply of rum enough for six<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03630006"/>
6<lb/>
months. I asked for another and got enough to last for a year (?) longer.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In Cuba I had malaria and was three times mistaken for having yellow<lb/>
fever. The nurses wouldn't believe I was immune. It took General Gorgas every time<lb/>
to get me removed to the malaria ward.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He then told a story of an officer who did not like him, but the officer<lb/>
could not court martial him. Moran got a leave of absence and went to General Kean's<lb/>
army office clerk and told him. In a week he was quietly transferred.</p>
<p>------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Dr. Jordan read a letter from Dr. Cooke (Lexington, Virginia--the man<lb/>
who was mentioned earlier as having been among those who went into the infected-<lb/>
clothing shack) saying that he was immunizing for two days and could not come over<lb/>
to the dinner.</p>
<p>------------------------------------------</p>
<p>After the dinner Mr. Moran showed his Congressional medal that he got as<lb/>
a member of the Walter Reed experimental group.</p>
<p>------------------------------------------</p>
<p>During his story about the yellow fever experiments, Mr. Moran said that<lb/>
he did not bluster before Major Reed or one of the other doctors as he was pictured<lb/>
in the movie.</p>
<p>------------------------------------------</p>
<p>This was a well-planned occasion. General Kean's account took about fifty<lb/>
minutes and nicely fitted Moran into the story as a whole. Moran talked between thirty<lb/>
and forty minutes. The whole occasion was very interesting, with Mr. Moran's story<lb/>
coming as the climax. And I was most appreciative of Doctor Jordan's putting me next<lb/>
to Mr. Moran</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
