<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03703001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, November 2, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03703001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-11-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-11-02">November 2, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03703001</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, November 2, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus solicits commentary from Truby on his article. He mentions previous correspondence with Hench and states that he does not know the details of how Kissinger and Moran became volunteers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-11-02">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, November 2, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03703001"/>
<opener>
J.H. Andrus<lb/>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-11-02">11-2-40.</date>
</dateline>
Addresses of others of <unclear>Det. H. C</unclear><lb/>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<salute>Dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In some respects your letter of the thirtieth is a disappointment.<lb/>
I hoped you would take off your gloves and frankly criticise my<lb/>
&ldquo;guinea pig&rdquo; chapter. While I have made every possible effort<lb/>
to check the known facts, I have indulged in conjecture in quite<lb/>
a number of instances and it would be too much to hope that I have<lb/>
always hit the bulls-eye.</p>
<p>I know this is asking a lot but my only reason for writing this<lb/>
episode at all is to give the FACTS and, when records must be de-<lb/>
parted from, I want to feel certain that my conclusions are reason-<lb/>
able and logical. Not only to me - but to OTHERS and, espec-<lb/>
ially, to anyone who knows what it is all about as well as you do.</p>
<p>When I read, &ldquo;I think your article is splendid&rdquo;, and you let it go<lb/>
at that, I fear you picture me in bed ready to burst in tears at<lb/>
anything but praise. Most of my working life has been spent as<lb/>
an advertising manager. I have spent hours of time and gallons<lb/>
of perspiration planning an advertising campaign - or advertising<lb/>
copy - only to sometimes see it torn to shreads by some of the<lb/>
higher officials of my company. I can still &ldquo;take it&rdquo; so, wont<lb/>
you get out your axe and go after my story? . . .</p>
<p>As for keeping the copy I sent you - you may have it.</p>
<p>Referring to specific items in your letter:</p>
<p>Page 27. Am enclosing a letter from the Surgeon General's office<lb/>
from which you will see it refers to STEWARD John Neate. While<lb/>
this does not indicate his <unclear>rank</unclear> at the time he was in Cuba, I am<lb/>
reasonably certain he was, then, a steward and not acting.</p>
<p>Was very much interested in what you say about the dedication of a<lb/>
building to the memory of Dr. Lazear and am looking forward to the<lb/>
printed proceedings you promise to send me. Back in March, 1938,<lb/>
I had an exchange of correspondence with Dr. P. S. Hench.<lb/>
He had become interested in my case through Moran and seemed to<lb/>
think the Mayo Clinic might be able to do something for me.<lb/>
It ended when I sent him my version of my case history and it was<lb/>
supplemented by a letter from my son, an M. D. Upon receipt of<lb/>
these letters, he wrote that he was going to Europe and would com-<lb/>
municate with me upon his return. There it ended.</p>
<p>Thank you for telling me about General Sternberg's book and the<lb/>
reference to me therein. I will try to get it.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03703002"/>
<p>Foot-bridge over railroad: I do not recall this bridge at all but<lb/>
you will find it described on the sketch of yellow fever hospital<lb/>
made by Lambert, which I sent you a few days ago.</p>
<p>Your reference to the political situation voices my sentiments per-<lb/>
fectly. From all I read and hear over the radio it would seem<lb/>
that Willkie has made rapid progress during the last few days.<lb/>
I am afraid, however, that Roosevelt has subsidized too many voters<lb/>
to lose the election.</p>
<p>I realize that Hoover has been too thoroughly &ldquo;smeared&rdquo; to be elect-<lb/>
ed to any office but I feel he is, by training and experience, the<lb/>
best presidential timber in the country.</p>
<p>I sometimes wonder if our democracy can endure when so many voters<lb/>
believe the most fantastic fairy tales if only they are charmingly<lb/>
voiced. . .</p>
<p>Am returning the exchange of correspondence between General Kean<lb/>
and yourself. I found this extremely interesting and did,<lb/>
indeed, find several things explained that I have been wondering<lb/>
about. I did not realize that more than one or two had attempt-<lb/>
ed to climb on the honor roll band wagon. Doesn't that seem<lb/>
strange when it is remembered that the honor roll was not created<lb/>
until late in 1929?</p>
<p>No, General, I have not been worn out by this correspondence.<lb/>
As I intimated in a previous letter, it deals with a subject in<lb/>
which I am very much interested and helps to pass time very<lb/>
pleasantly.</p>
<p>With kindest regards and every good wish,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>JH Andrus</signed>
<seg>
Postscript: I know nothing of the details about how Kissinger and<lb/>
Moran came to volunteer for innoculation except what Moran wrote me.<lb/>
I have wondered why I have had no reply to my letter asking his<lb/>
permission to send his letter to you. As you say he was to be<lb/>
present at the dedication of the Lazear memorial, that probably<lb/>
explains it. - JHA.<lb/>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
