<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03712001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Draft fragments: Walter Reed's Human Guinea Pigs (By One of Them), by John J. Moran [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03712001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry James L.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi I.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Barringer, Paul B.</name>
<name type="person">Alderman, Edwin A.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Fort Mott (N.J.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Young (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Salem (N.J.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Pittsburgh (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1 (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Hospital General Calixto Garcia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>25 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03712001</idno>
<title>Draft fragments: Walter Reed's Human Guinea Pigs (By One of Them), by John J. Moran, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a series of partial manuscripts detailing the yellow fever experiments. Topics include the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor, Moran's role in the experiments, the controversy concerning Reed's and Finlay's contributions to the conquest of yellow fever, and Moran's experiences at the University of Virginia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Draft fragments: Walter Reed's Human Guinea Pigs (By One of Them), by John J. Moran, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03712001"/>
<p><unclear>Mrs S</unclear></p>
<p><hi>WALTER REED'S HUMAN GUINEA PIGS.<lb/>
(By One of Them)</hi></p>
<p><hi>I N T R O D U C T I O N</hi></p>
<p>ROLL OF HONOR.<lb/>
Participants in Yellow Fever Investigations in Cuba.<lb/>
The Official Record.</p>
<p><hi>EXTRACT</hi></p>
<p>.................................</p>
<p>Moran, John J. B-Ireland 15 Mar. 76. Capt. Q. M. C. N. A. 27 May 18; accepted<lb/>
27 May 18; hon. dis. 1 Oct. 19. -- Pvt. and actg. hosp. stewd., Hosp. Corps<lb/>
3 July 97 to 2 July 00. B. C. S. Mount Hope Coll. 97.</p>
<p>JOHN J. MORAN was employed as a clerk at the department heaquarters at<lb/>
Marianao, Cuba. He there did clerical work for Major REED and became interested<lb/>
in the work of the Yellow Fever Board. He and KISSINGER were the first to<lb/>
volunteer for the conclusive series of experiments at Camp Lazear. He was<lb/>
bitten on November 26 and 29, by infected mosquitoes, but without result. On<lb/>
December 21, 1900, he twice visited the infected mosquito room, and again<lb/>
next day, and was repeatedly bitten. On Christmas Day he became ill, and<lb/>
suffered a well marked and severe attack of yellow fever. MORAN refused to<lb/>
accept the bonus which was given by the Governor of Cuba to each volunteer,<lb/>
stating that he was glad to be able to do this service to humanity. He was<lb/>
discharged from the service July 2, 1900, with character excellent. He served<lb/>
for some years at Panama during the construction of the Canal, and was<lb/>
commissioned a captain in the United States Army (Emergency Forces) during<lb/>
the World War.</p>
<p>see p 3</p>
<p>...............................</p>
<p><hi>Note</hi>. Published annually in the Official Army Register since 1930. The<lb/>
record will be permanent when date and place of death shall have been added.</p>
<p>The ROLL OF HONOR shows the names of the 4 members of the Yellow Fever Board<lb/>
and the 18 volunteers for experimental yellow fever. Of the 22 names on the ROLL,<lb/>
3 of us are still alive, viz: Dr. Robert P. Cooke, James L. Hanberry and the<lb/>
author of this article.</p>
<p>Following is a brief biographical resum&eacute; of the writer: Born in the Province<lb/>
of Connaught, Galway County, Ireland, on March 15, 1876. Emigrated to the U. S. A.<lb/>
at the age of ten. Six months after his arrival he set out to earn his own living.<lb/>
Self educated. Successively grocery boy, book agent, office boy and companion on<lb/>
her rounds to a lady doctor, in Youngstown, Ohio. At age 18, had saved sufficient<lb/>
to see him through a two-year commercial course at Mount Hope College, Rogers,<lb/>
Columbiana Country, Ohio.</p>
<p>Enlisted in the Hospital Corps, U. S. Army, on July 3, 1897, at the Hospital<lb/>
School of Instruction, Washington Barracks, D. C. The course there was an invariable<lb/>
six months. I was considered a model student and soldier. With that training, I<lb/>
became a full-fledged Hospital Corps man. My first regular assignment was Fort Mott,<lb/>
N. J. Transferred to Bedloes Island, N. Y. Harbor and promoted to Acting Hospital<lb/>
Steward (sergeant) in July, 1898. Ordered to Cuba in January, 1899. In Cuba, I<lb/>
served at Military Hospital No. l, in Havana; Camp Young and Guanajay Barracks, near<lb/>
Guanajay; Columbia Barracks, Marianao. My term of enlistment expired on July 2,<lb/>
1900, the date on which I was honorably discharged. Appointed a civilian clerk at<lb/>
General Fitzhugh Lee's headquarters on July 3, 1900.</p>
<p>Met Walter Reed for the first time in October, 1900, and was transferred to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03712002"/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
his service as clerk-typist-secretary, a week after I had volunteered for his<lb/>
series of experiments at Camp Lazear, then being readied for that purpose. In the<lb/>
short period of less than five months, I reckon that I learned to know him as well<lb/>
as any man in Cuba at that time. Until we parted company in February, 1901, I<lb/>
did not once merit his displeasure. To me he was the most important man in the<lb/>
U. S. Army. His wish was law to me.</p>
<p>Major Reed arrived in Cuba early in the summer of 1900, as head of the Army<lb/>
Board of Medical Officers appointed by the Surgeon General of the Army to invest-<lb/>
igate yellow fever, then raging in epidemic form among American troops and civilian<lb/>
personnel of the Army of Cuban Occupation and taking a heavy toll of lives. The<lb/>
invisible enemy lurked everywhere &ldquo;around the corner&rdquo;. Nobody knew when, where<lb/>
or how that stealthy terror might strike him. It was in the atmosphere. One of<lb/>
my office companions at headquarters appeared hale and hearty the day before. A<lb/>
week later he was in his grave. The town of Marianao was an unsafe place for any<lb/>
one not immune to &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;. Few if any Americans were immune.</p>
<p>During July and August, 1900, three of General Lee's staff officers contracted<lb/>
yellow fever, Majors Jefferson R. Kean, Chief Surgeon; Major Cartwright, Chief<lb/>
Quartermaster and Major Edmunds, Inspector General. Major Kean happily recovered<lb/>
but Cartwright and Edmunds succumbed to the disease.</p>
<p>One of the saddest cases of those days was that of Major Peterson, one of<lb/>
General Wood's staff officers, who died of yellow fever at Las Animas Hospital,<lb/>
in Havana. Like many other officers then in Cuba, Major Peterson had brought his<lb/>
wife to Cuba. A few hours after his death and while his body was still at the<lb/>
hospital, Mrs. Peterson committed suicide in the chief nurse's room. They were laid<lb/>
to rest side by side, and at the same time. Other officers scrambled to get trans-<lb/>
portation back to the States for wives and daughters. Be it recorded to the ever-<lb/>
lasting glory of American womanhood that but few wives availed themselves of the<lb/>
opportunity. They did not shirk the dangers which might be in store for their<lb/>
husbands. The second leg of this century finds me of the same opinion.</p>
<p>No man in Cuba was more profoundly moved and concerned with the situation<lb/>
described than was the mild-mannered, gentle and God-fearing Walter Reed, who<lb/>
began to fight disease at the age of 18, upon graduating as an M. D. at the<lb/>
University of Virginia, under special dispensation because of his extreme youth.<lb/>
His mission in Cuba was to run down the yellow fever &ldquo;germ&rdquo; and to find a means to<lb/>
combat it, a rather large order, considering that that ilusive microbe resisted<lb/>
isolation, passing through the finest laboratory filter.</p>
<p><unclear>See<lb/>
extra sheet<lb/>
"p 4"</unclear></p>
<p>It was in such an atmosphere of doubt and frustration that Walter Reed embraced<lb/>
a hitherto &ldquo;Lost Cause&rdquo;, the 19-year-old theory of Dr. Carlos J. Finlay, ridiculed<lb/>
and discredited, at home and abroad. Reed called on Finlay and obtained from him<lb/>
a batch of mosquito eggs laid in his own back yard by a type of mosquito then class-<lb/>
ified as CULEX FASCIATUS, later named STEGOMYIA and definitely known today as AEDES<lb/>
AEGYPTI. There began the FINLAY-REED alliance and with it, what was to be known as<lb/>
&ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. Finlay's &ldquo;voice in the wilderness&rdquo; would be heard,<lb/>
or forever stilled. Finlay was vindicated and his voice was heard around the world,<lb/>
and with startling effect.</p>
<p>Walter Reed planned his work at Camp Lazear with scientific precision. There,<lb/>
the centuries-old practice of &ldquo;Infected Bedding and Clothing&rdquo; was to be tested side<lb/>
by side with Finlay's &ldquo;Mosquito Theory&rdquo;, in fool-proof fashion. One or the other<lb/>
would stand or fall. Reed's plans involved strict secrecy, since the Anti-vivisection<lb/>
Society was then active and powerful in Washington. Using human beings as guinea<lb/>
pigs would bring down upon his innocent head the wrath of that well-meaning body of<lb/>
prominent men and women. An isolated case might get by, but not the large-scale<lb/>
number which Reed deemed essential for the success of his venture. It was fortunate<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03712003"/>
-- 3 --<lb/>
for Walter Reed that the Military Governor of Cuba, General Leonard Wood, happened<lb/>
to be a doctor before he became an officer of the line. As such, Major Reed's<lb/>
plans had his whole-hearted approval, lacking which his proposed series of experi-<lb/>
ments could not have been carried out.</p>
<p>Accompanied by Lieut-Col. Jefferson R. Kean, then acting Chief Surgeon on Gen.<lb/>
Wood's staff, Major Reed asked for and obtained an appropriation of $10,000.00 out<lb/>
of Insular Funds, with promise of more, if needed. Tents, beds, cots, etc., would<lb/>
be furnished by the Army. Most of the amount authorized was intended for cash<lb/>
bonuses, the balance for rent of the camp site and cost of two small frame build-<lb/>
ings, 20' x 14', each, one for infected clothing and bedding tests, the other for<lb/>
infected mosquito tests.</p>
<p>Little did I dream that October afternoon, as I crosssed the parade grounds of<lb/>
the Post Hospital, Columbia Barracks, that I had a date with Walter Reed and Destiny.<lb/>
I suspect that it was by design, rather than accident, that I was accosted by Dr.<lb/>
Roger Post Ames, Contract Surgeon on duty at the hospital. In the most casual way<lb/>
he informed me that Major Reed was offering a bonus of $500.00 to men who would<lb/>
volunteer for experimental yellow fever. Dr Ames knew that I intended to study<lb/>
medicine and he also knew how much that amount would mean to me, added to my far-<lb/>
from-adequate savings for a four-year course at a medical school, no matter how<lb/>
modest it might be. I would sleep over it and let him know the following day. I<lb/>
was certainly interested. Dr. Ames' missionary work for Reed was very effective<lb/>
with me. I think I was his No. 1 convert. As a matter of fact, I was.</p>
<p>That night, Private John R. Kissinger, of the Hospital Corps, my room-mate,<lb/>
and I, talked the matter over into the wee small hours of the morning. He, brave<lb/>
boy that he was, would also volunteer. My mind was made up. I would volunteer<lb/>
under one condition - no cash bonus for me. Kissinger, knowing how much the $500.<lb/>
would mean to me, frankly told me I was a fool. I have no doubt that if the bonus<lb/>
was to be $5,000.00, I would have followed a different course. But why dwell on<lb/>
&ldquo;what might have been&rdquo;? &ldquo;Well, said Kissinger, whatever you do, John, I am with<lb/>
you&rdquo;. &ldquo;We'll volunteer together&rdquo;, or words to that effect. Our motives were<lb/>
different, I am sure. If I should survive, my act would be an excellent card of<lb/>
introduction for a doctor in embryo. I could vision my professors pointing me<lb/>
out as one of Walter Reed's volunteers for experimental yellow fever, with respect-<lb/>
ful and admiring glances from members of my class. If I should succumb to the<lb/>
disease I would not have to worry about the $500.00.</p>
<p>The following morning I called on Major Reed in his room at the Officers'<lb/>
Quarters within the Post Hospital grounds. He appeared puzzled upon seeing a<lb/>
young man in civilian attire at his door. I told him who I was and why I was<lb/>
there, forgetting the little speech I had thought up for the crucial moment and,<lb/>
instead, blurting out the object of my visit in disconnected fashion. I am sure he<lb/>
was not looking for a stampede of candidates for voluntary yellow fever and, perhaps<lb/>
a free passage to a less troublesome world. I could see that he was immensely<lb/>
pleased. Neither of us had mentioned the cash bonus for the first few minutes. I<lb/>
then remarked that Dr. Ames informed me that there would be a cash bonus of $500.<lb/>
Without awaiting his reply, I told him that I was volunteering on condition that<lb/>
there would be no bonus for me, adding &ldquo;I am doing it in the interests of medical<lb/>
science&rdquo;, not as stated, time and again, that &ldquo;I was glad to be able to do this<lb/>
service to humanity&rdquo;. This, for the record.</p>
<p>I had no doubt, after that last declaration, of the esteem in which I was held<lb/>
by Major Reed. It was one of several surprises which were in store for him in the<lb/>
weeks and months to follow. With the ice broken by Kissinger and myself, the<lb/>
detachment of less than 50 hospital corpsmen at Columbia Barracks provided Walter<lb/>
Reed with 12 of the 18 volunteers whose names appear on the ROLL OF HONOR, a remark-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03712004"/>
-- 4 --<lb/>
able percentage when one considers that each of them felt morally certain of con-<lb/>
tracting yellow fever, by one route or the other, before release from Camp Lazear.<lb/>
Each of them knew the deadly nature of yellow fever. They had seen Dr. Lazear come<lb/>
down with a fatal attack of the disease and had known of the deaths of Majors<lb/>
Cartwright, Edmunds, Peterson and others. Later, I discovered that the bonus I<lb/>
passed up was not $500.00. The maximum received by any of them was $300.00 and<lb/>
the minimum $200.00. None of them, I am sure, took the risk for the bonus. What,<lb/>
then, was their governing motive? The reader will have to supply the answer, since<lb/>
I do not know it.</p>
<p>In common with every man who volunteered, I was subjected to a stiff physical<lb/>
examination, blood tests included. Major Reed was not inviting any fatalities<lb/>
among his brood of human guinea pigs. He selected them with extreme care, with<lb/>
youth playing the major role. All but one were under 30, the majority around 25.<lb/>
No man infected at Camp Lazear, under Reed, succumbed to the disease. Others infect-<lb/>
ed in October, 1901, not by Major Reed, were not so fortunate. Of 10 experimented<lb/>
upon, 3 died. Probably the doctors in charge of those experiments were not so<lb/>
careful in selecting their victims. Cuban public opinion brought their activities<lb/>
to a sudden halt. As a matter of fact, further experiments were not necessary<lb/>
after Reed's departure from Cuba, in February, 1901. With his departure, the<lb/>
conquest of yellow fever was real and effective. All that was necessary was for<lb/>
Major Gorgas, as Chief Sanitary Officer of the Island, to make effective war on<lb/>
the STEGOMYIA mosquito and the not-so-fatal ANAPHOLES, the malarial mosquito.</p>
<p>Quietly and unheralded, Camp Lazear was occupied on November 20, 1900, by the<lb/>
first nucleus of Walter Reed's brood of human guinea pigs, Kissinger and myself<lb/>
to test Finlay's mosquito theory, with Dr. Cooke, Jernegan and Folk to test the<lb/>
infected bedding and clothing theory. The small frame building for the latter<lb/>
test was designated &ldquo;Building No. 1&rdquo; and that for the mosquito tests &ldquo;Building<lb/>
No. 2&rdquo;. The number of infected mosquitoes available at the start was limited, but<lb/>
an additional supply was being prepared in the yellow fever ward of Los Animas<lb/>
Hospital, devoted exclusively to infectious and contagious diseases, as it still<lb/>
is. It was our main source of supply for infected mosquitoes and soiled bedding<lb/>
and clothing.</p>
<p><unclear>Nov. 27'<lb/>
@ to no to<lb/>
p 11<lb/>
check official<lb/>
record.</unclear></p>
<p>I was first bitten on November 26 and again on the 29th, by infected mosqui-<lb/>
toes, but without result. We did not know it at the time but later on failure<lb/>
to infect me then became clear. The &ldquo;loaded&rdquo; mosquitoes were not yet &ldquo;ripe&rdquo; for<lb/>
infection. Major Reed speculated as to such a thing as &ldquo;natural immunity&rdquo;, but<lb/>
not for very long. Kissinger, who had been similarly bitten, came down with yellow<lb/>
fever on Decembr 9th. He had the honor of being the first case of yellow fever in<lb/>
the series of experiments at Camp Lazear, an honor which I devoutly hoped would<lb/>
fall to my lot. I cannot say that I lost much sleep over it. We remained very<lb/>
good friends, so much so that we left Cuba on the same steamer, he on furlough and<lb/>
I to return to God's Country. After we parted in New York I was not to see him<lb/>
again until 1940 when we were each honored with a citation by W. &amp; J. College.</p>
<p>Three weeks rolled by before Major Reed had accumulated a sufficient number<lb/>
of infected mosquitoes for his &ldquo;Master Test&rdquo; on my humble person. That third test<lb/>
would prove whether or not I was a &ldquo;natural immune&rdquo;. On December 21, 1900, I was<lb/>
led by Major Reed to &ldquo;Building No. 2&rdquo;, garbed only in nightshirt and slippers, all<lb/>
of which I left in the vestibule of the mosquito compartment of the building,<lb/>
insect-proof from without and within. 15 infected insects had been liberated in<lb/>
that compartment an hour earlier. Its only furniture was a hospital bed with a<lb/>
new mattress and a new sheet. I was provided with a hand-mirror by Major Reed,<lb/>
with instructions to count the number of mosquitoes which might feed on me, taking<lb/>
care not to disturb them, if possible, in the counting process. On that noon visit,<lb/>
7 of the insects fed on me. I made my second visit in the same manner in the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03712005"/>
-- 5 --<lb/>
afternoon, at four o'clock. I was bitten by 4 of the insects on that second visit.<lb/>
The following day, December 22nd, I made my third and last visit to my insect<lb/>
family and was bitten by 4 insects. Theoretically, I had been fed upon by all 15<lb/>
insects, although one or more of the insects might have bitten me more than once.<lb/>
Major Reed was an interested spectator, watching through the fine-mesh, copper-bronze<lb/>
screening which divided the building in two sections, from floor to ceiling.</p>
<p>In the other section of &ldquo;Building No. 2&rdquo;, two non-immunes slept for 18 consecutive<lb/>
nights prior to December 21st, in order to prove that the building was not infected.<lb/>
Two others slept there for an additional 18 nights following my visits to the<lb/>
mosquito-infected compartment. Yes, Major Reed left nothing to imagination. His<lb/>
MODUS OPERANDI could not be attacked by the most rabbid skeptic. His master test<lb/>
was all that and fool-proof. He would now rest up until after Christmas. The<lb/>
mosquitoes would decide for me the kind of Christmas gift I should hand to Walter<lb/>
Reed - the kind that he would appreciate most.</p>
<p>It was a typical, tropical Christmas morning, that of December 25, 1900. Aside<lb/>
from the fact that we were &ldquo;prisoners&rdquo;, we had a jolly Christmas Eve. With my<lb/>
camp companions, I made the most of it. I slept soundly, not at all disturbed by<lb/>
unpleasant dreams or Christmas Eve noises from the surrounding towns and villages,<lb/>
but faintly penetrating our isolated atmosphere. I was up bright and early on<lb/>
Christmas morning, had an excellent breakfast and an appetite to match it. Yes, we<lb/>
were well fed at Camp Lazear. It was a case of &ldquo;Eat, drink and be merry, for to-<lb/>
morrow ye may die&rdquo;. None of us, of course, paid much attention to what the Grim<lb/>
Reaper might have in store for us. We were a care-free lot.</p>
<p>From the day of my first visit to the mosquito room I was instructed to take<lb/>
my temperature and pulse three times daily, every hour, once the temperature passed<lb/>
normal. Around 10:00 A. M. I knew I had IT. Temperature 100&deg; F., at 11:00 A. M.<lb/>
101&deg; F., at noon 102&deg; and at 1:00 P. M. 102.6&deg; F. I knew my face was flushed. As<lb/>
a matter of fact I felt flushed all over, a sensation which I am unable to properly<lb/>
describe. It was not a pleasant or reassuring sensation, as I recall it now, 50<lb/>
years later. Of one thing I am certain and that is: I had every desire to live,<lb/>
&ldquo;to tell the tale&rdquo;, none at all to become a dead hero. Physically, I might be a<lb/>
coward. Morally, I was brave. Major Reed later referred to me &ldquo;a plucky Ohio boy,<lb/>
Moran by name&rdquo; and &ldquo;On Christmas morning this brave lad was stricken with yellow<lb/>
fever and had a sharp attack which he bore without a murmur&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Christmas Eve, Jernegan dared me to bet $5.00 that I would have Christmas dinner<lb/>
at the camp. I accepted. Folk was the stakeholder for the the two gold pieces. I<lb/>
knew that eating a meal, once the fever had set in, would be suicidal, all aliment-<lb/>
ation, as well as drugs, being taboo in the treatment of yellow fever. Refrigeration,<lb/>
inside and out, to hold the temperature below 105&deg; Farenheit, was the order of the<lb/>
day. Our dinner hour that Christmas day was 1:00 P. M. Could I bluff my way through<lb/>
and collect the two gold coins? I would try. It worked. I played with a slice of<lb/>
turkey breast, sweet potatoes and the rest of the Christmas trimmings. Jernegan,<lb/>
with the others around me, was busy doing justice to that fine meal. Dinner over,<lb/>
I collected the bet. Jernegan was the first man in camp to know that I had IT. Fine<lb/>
son of Florida that he was, he was all concern, never giving a thought to the trick<lb/>
I had played on him. Did he think I had won the bet fairly? Of course he did.<lb/>
Well, as long as he thought so, I could die with a clean conscience, should &ldquo;Yellow<lb/>
Jack&rdquo; get the best of me.</p>
<p>Major Reed had not visited the camp that Christmas morning. He had dinner at<lb/>
the officers' mess, at the Post Hospital, arriving about 3:00 P. M. With a cheery<lb/>
&ldquo;Merry Christmas, Moran. Anything new?&rdquo; he found me lying down on my cot in the<lb/>
office tent. I pointed to the temperature chart, face down, on the field desk. One<lb/>
glance at the chart left no doubt in his mind. My temperature was then more than<lb/>
five degrees above normal. He rubbed his hands together in sheer glee, saying &ldquo;Moran,<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03712006"/>
1900<lb/>
<hi>1834</hi><lb/>
66<lb/>
-- 6 --<lb/>
this is one of the happiest days of my life&rdquo;. That was the scientist speaking. In<lb/>
a moment he became Walter Reed, the humane, God-fearing man. In less time than I<lb/>
could say Jack Robinson, the ambulance came around and I was on my way to the<lb/>
yellow fever hospital, while Major Reed followed in a Doherty wagon, the Army's<lb/>
&ldquo;Ford&rdquo; of those days. Arrived at the hospital I was placed under the competent<lb/>
care of Dr. Ames.</p>
<p>That night of December 25th and until next morning, I cared little whether<lb/>
school kept or not. I had hazy recollections of the Army nurse who hovered over<lb/>
me with a glassful of cracked ice in one hand and a teaspoon in the other, telling<lb/>
me in a soft but firm voice: &ldquo;Swallow it, don't let it melt in your mouth&rdquo;. I<lb/>
also dimly remembered being packed in ice in a portable bathtub. During 24 hours<lb/>
I felt as though I had been kicked by an army mule. My whole body was a mass of<lb/>
dull pain. Later, I learned that Major Reed had visited me several times during<lb/>
the night of December 25-26. I know I was semi-delirious.</p>
<p>I think it was on December 27th that I saw Dr. Finlay for the second time,<lb/>
the first being at Camp Lazear, when he was invited by Major Reed to inspect its<lb/>
installations. This time he was at my bedside to later on certify that I had<lb/>
yellow fever. He was President of the Yellow Fever Board of the City of Havana,<lb/>
entirely unrelated to the Army Board, headed by Major Reed. He asked me no<lb/>
questions but he was very much interested in my clinical chart. I recall that he<lb/>
remarked that I was "a very pretty case. His was an imposing patriarchal figure,<lb/>
one not be easily forgotten. Now, 50 years later, I carry a mental picture of<lb/>
that noble old gentleman. It was not my good fortune to ever meet him again.</p>
<p>My convalescence was normal and rapid. On the 8th day of my illness I was<lb/>
given a teaspoonful of milk. During the attack I was given occasional tablespoon-<lb/>
ful quantities of champagne and strained watermelon juice, no drugs or medicines<lb/>
of any kind. By January 10, 1901, I was allowed to sit up. I was weak and wobbly<lb/>
at first. I must have lost around 35-40 pounds in weight while the fever lasted.<lb/>
In less than a month I recovered the lost weight. Then, said Walter Reed &ldquo;Moran,<lb/>
would you mind having me test your immunity. I would like to give you a blood<lb/>
injection from one of your comrades at the Camp, now down with yellow fever&rdquo;, I<lb/>
told him I was at his service, being assured that his blood had been previously<lb/>
tested. I had no reaction whatsoever. I was immune, alright.</p>
<p>During the months October, 1900, to February 15, 1901, I had typed many reports<lb/>
and letters from Major Reed, many of the latter extremely confidential, most of them<lb/>
to the Surgeon General of the Army. I used the Army standard typewriter of that<lb/>
day, the Hammond. His letters were drafted in long hand, with never a dot nor a<lb/>
comma missing. Needless to add that I respected the confidence placed in me and<lb/>
which he took for granted. Nor did I ever make any copies for myself, the Major<lb/>
being his own file keeper. Those letters and reports dwelt on the progress of the<lb/>
experiments and the underground war then carried on by the officers of the U. S.<lb/>
Public Health &amp; Marine Hospital Service stationed in Havana, with ramifications in<lb/>
Washington, still steeped in the hitherto ineffective practice of fumigating or<lb/>
destroying &ldquo;Infected Bedding and Clothing&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Even the Army Medical Corps, in a large majority, had but little confidence<lb/>
in the mosquito theory of infection, but its members wisely refrained from efforts<lb/>
to discredit it. The fact that the Surgeon General of the Army and General Wood,<lb/>
Military Governor of Cuba, were giving their whole-hearted support to Reed served<lb/>
as a deterrent on the Army skeptics, not so the U. S. Public Health Service with<lb/>
its own Surgeon General in Washington, hence independent of the Army. They con-<lb/>
sidered Walter Reed a meddler in a matter which came within their exclusive sphere<lb/>
of influence. Sanitation was an army affair within military reservations and camps.<lb/>
Quarantine at ports and public health in general were responsibilities assumed by<lb/>
the U. S. P. H. &amp; M. H. S. But Major Reed was not the man to falter.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f03712007"/>
<p>-- 7 --</p>
<p>(<unclear>The alternet</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>pg 7-8</unclear><lb/>
are <unclear>better</unclear>)</p>
<p>Walter Reed's experiments at Camp Lazear converted a theory into a living<lb/>
reality. I use the term &ldquo;theory&rdquo; knowingly because up to that time Finlay's<lb/>
mosquito theory had been looked upon as illusory by the scientific world. Nowhere<lb/>
had it been more discredited than in Cuba, the country in which he was born, the<lb/>
son of a British father and a French mother. As one of the principal actors in the<lb/>
silent drama staged at Camp Lazear, I assume the right to an opinion in this matter.<lb/>
I use the word &ldquo;principal&rdquo; because of my dual role of confidential clerk and human<lb/>
guinea pig for Reed. Of all the volunteers for experimental yellow fever at Camp<lb/>
Lazear, I alone enjoyed the privilege of daily contact and association with him.</p>
<p>With the &ldquo;theory&rdquo; now &ldquo;proved&rdquo;, Major William C. Gorgas, Chief Sanitary Officer<lb/>
of Cuba, no longer the confirmed skeptic, set about organizing sanitary brigades<lb/>
to make war on the STEGOMYIA mosquito, hitherto considered a stinging nuisance<lb/>
only. In less than six months yellow fever was under control. Adult mosquitoes<lb/>
were destroyed by fumigation and their eggs, lacking still and stagnant water<lb/>
wherein to breed, were converted into harmless dust. The owners of water contain-<lb/>
ers were obliged to screen or hermetically cover such containers. Fines were<lb/>
imposed if water-barrels, etc., were found to contain wigglers or mosquito larvae.</p>
<p>Walter Reed, who had found the missing link, was acclaimed and the &ldquo;Camp Lazear<lb/>
Episode&rdquo; became another milestone in medical history. The carrier of a dreadful<lb/>
scourge was within control and its destruction assured. The man of medicine and<lb/>
the layman alike received the glad news with uncontrolled enthusiasm. The press<lb/>
of the civilized world headlined the event. In this first outburst of joy, the<lb/>
name of Carlos Finlay was lost in the shuffle. The man who directed and carried<lb/>
out the experiments at Camp Lazear had overnight, so to speak, attained immortal-<lb/>
ity. That immortality, of course, was as much Finlay's as it was Reed's, but the<lb/>
average man in Cuba, the United States of America, the Latin American republics<lb/>
and the European Continent was ignorant of the Finlay-Reed link. That average<lb/>
man was unaware of the 19-year effort of Finlay to prove his mosquito theory.</p>
<p>His task in Cuba happily finished, Walter Reed returned to Washington in<lb/>
February, 1901. During the rest of that year and until his untimely death in<lb/>
November, 1902, he was the recipient of many honors on the part of scientific<lb/>
bodies and institutions of learning, including Harvard University and the University<lb/>
of Michigan. His remains were interred at Arlington National Cemetery and a bronze<lb/>
tablet on his monument bears the following inscription:<lb/>
Walter Reed, M. D. of the University of Virginia.<lb/>
A. M. of Harvard University,<lb/>
LL.D of the University of Michigan,<lb/>
Professor of Bacteriology, Army Medical School<lb/>
and<lb/>
Columbian University, Washington, D. C.<lb/>
&ldquo;He gave to man control over that dreadful scourge,<lb/>
Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Those 11 words: &ldquo;HE GAVE TO MAN CONTROL OVER THAT DREADFUL SCOURGE, YELLOW FEVER&rdquo;<lb/>
have been the cause of more bitter controversy, over e period of almost half a<lb/>
century, than any 11 words in the history of mankind - a bitterness born in the<lb/>
minds of of the Cuban medical fraternity of that day, dormant at times but never<lb/>
allowed to wither and die to this day. The Cubans have interpreted those 11 words<lb/>
as a denial of Finlay's part in the conquest of yellow fever, with the result that<lb/>
they have defiled the memory of Walter Reed, using such adjectives as &ldquo;impostor&rdquo;,<lb/>
charging him with &ldquo;bad faith&rdquo; and being a &ldquo;salaried automat&rdquo;, lacking a &ldquo;scientific<lb/>
background&rdquo;, etc., etc. They assume that Carlos Finlay's name should have been<lb/>
included in that euology. The real authors of the epitaph were not members of the<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f03712008"/>
-- 8 --<lb/>
Reed family or the Surgeon General's Office. It was taken from the citation of<lb/>
President Eliot of Harvard University upon presentation of the honorary degree to<lb/>
him, which reads as follows:<lb/>
&ldquo;Walter Reed, graduate of the University of Virginia, the army surgeon who planned<lb/>
and directed in Cuba the experiments which have given man control over that<lb/>
fearful scourge, yellow fever&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In May, 1948, when the Fourth International Congresses of Tropical Medicine<lb/>
and Malaria met in Washington, a program was decided upon, bearing the title:<lb/>
&ldquo;Exercises to Commemorate the Demonstration by<lb/>
Walter Reed<lb/>
of the Mosquito Transmission of Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p><unclear>check Havana<lb/>
papers in<lb/>
US.</unclear></p>
<p>The Cuban delegates to the Congresses strenuously objected to the wording<lb/>
and implied meaning involved in the program's title, backed by the medical<lb/>
societies of Cuba and the Cuban press. A compromise was reached with the Cuban<lb/>
delegates, the latter reluctantly agreeing to accept Reed as Finlay's collaborator.<lb/>
With this grudging concession on the part of the Cubans, it would appear that we<lb/>
were on our way to an amicable understanding of the half-century-old controversy.<lb/>
Sad to relate that I, for one, was over-optimistic. Eleven days later, the campaign<lb/>
of defamation against Reed and his memory was reiterated in a virulent article<lb/>
authored by a Cuban doctor and published in &ldquo;BOHEMIA&rdquo;, a weekly news-magazine of<lb/>
wide circulation, under the following title:<lb/>
&ldquo;FINLAY'S WORK WAS NOT A THEORY<lb/>
NOR WAS REED HIS COLLABORATOR&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The author then proceeds to strip Walter Reed of any share in the conquest<lb/>
of yellow fever, flatly stating that he merely &ldquo;confirmed&rdquo; what Finlay had already<lb/>
&ldquo;proved&rdquo;. He charges Reed with &ldquo;bad faith&rdquo; in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note&rdquo;, read before<lb/>
The American Public Health Association, in Indianapolis, in October, 1900. He<lb/>
refers to Reed's experiments at Camp Lazear as &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; and &ldquo;unnecessary&rdquo;.<lb/>
Reed, he states, &ldquo;lacked a scientific background&rdquo; and therefore could not &ldquo;feel<lb/>
the emotions of the real scientist&rdquo;, strongly inferring that he was a mere<lb/>
salaried automat, carrying out instructions of General Wood, the Military Governor<lb/>
of Cuba. Had the author been present at Camp Lazear he would have discovered, as<lb/>
I did, that there was nothing &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; in the drama enacted there.</p>
<p>The reaction against Reed was at first modest, gradually gaining momentum. It<lb/>
was more political and national than scientific, whereas it never should have had<lb/>
any other basis than a scientific one, with facts and findings alone taken into<lb/>
consideration. Year after year, the all-out claims of the Cubans for Finlay gradually<lb/>
became an obsession. The present generation of Cuban medicos has been educated to<lb/>
the point of saturation in the unilateral point of view, so much so that they now<lb/>
firmly believe Reed was all that his defamers claim he was. Nor have the Cubans<lb/>
limited their campaign of defamation to their own native soil. Their propaganda<lb/>
has invaded every Latin American republic. In a more subtle form their efforts<lb/>
in the U. S. has been intensely pro-Finlay but not anti-Reed. In all other count-<lb/>
ries Reed is mirrored as an impostor.</p>
<p>Many years ago the American medical profession has been falling all over<lb/>
itself to make up for the slight notice given to Finlay, following the Camp Lazear<lb/>
Episode. Prominent members of the profession have done ample justice to the part<lb/>
he played in the Conquest of Yellow Fever. That is as it should be. On the other<lb/>
hand, they have been over-complacent in their failure to properly defend Reed, his<lb/>
work and memory. I presume it is a matter of difference in temperaments, since<lb/>
we lack the intense nationalism of the Latin races, Cubans being naturally proud<lb/>
of their Spanish forefathers, and justly so.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<pb n="9" id="f03712009"/>
<p>Moran <unclear>G.</unclear><lb/>
-- 5 --</p>
<p>and the college faculty, small but well versed, specialized in individual attention to<lb/>
the educational program of their charges. Many years later the college closed and the<lb/>
faculty moved in a body to a larger field, Columbus, the state capital. I graduated on<lb/>
April 24, 1897, with the imposing degree of Bachelor of Commercial Science, and with<lb/>
still a hundred odd dollars in my savings account.</p>
<p><unclear>nd<lb/>
age 2, 5<lb/>
pa<lb/>
na</unclear></p>
<p>I returned to Youngstown only long enough to bid goodbye to the Clarke family and<lb/>
my brother and sisters. Logically, I should have settled down there but I had many<lb/>
reasons for wishing to forget that city where I had arrived with such high hopes and<lb/>
where, instead of an education, I had to struggle for a living. I decided to strike out<lb/>
for new pastures. Which would it be, Cleveland or Pittsburgh? I chose Pittsburgh but<lb/>
at the last moment I bought a ticket for Beaver Falls, instead, simply because the man<lb/>
ahead of me at the ticket window bought one for that destination. I was still groping<lb/>
my way, not at all sure what I was looking for. I was far from sure of my own self-<lb/>
sufficiency. Arriving at Beaver Falls, I registered at the Central Hotel, intending<lb/>
to remain for a few days only while I could commune with my own thoughts and get my<lb/>
bearings. Evidently my neat and legible signature caught the eye of the hotel manager-<lb/>
owner, for he presently engaged me in conversation. Informing him that I was a recent<lb/>
commercial-school graduate, he expressed a wish to see my diploma. I was very proud to<lb/>
do so. Casually he mentioned that his desk clerk had resigned a few days earlier. I<lb/>
could have the job. To my protest of lack of experience he told me that would be his<lb/>
worry. He would teach me.</p>
<p>I soon learned that I was desk clerk, room clerk and cashier, but I was not over-<lb/>
worked at that. The hours were long but I didn't mind. Guests were few and that<lb/>
worried me. Some days the hotel and restaurant staff was duble the number of guests<lb/>
and I knew we were operating at a loss, but the owner did not seem to mind. I was far<lb/>
from happy there, living well at the expense of a losing business. I notified Mr. Magaw<lb/>
that I would be moving on to Pittsburgh, as I had originally planned. Was it a matter<lb/>
of salary? If so, he would increase it to $50.00 a month, room, board and laundry.<lb/>
He wanted me to stay on, so I calculated that I had made good. Had his business prosper<lb/>
ed I probably would have remained with him. He was a very considerate boss. After all,<lb/>
why should I worry about his losing business while he appeared unconcerned? I have<lb/>
never been able to find the proper answer to that question. To cinch my decision I told<lb/>
him that life in Beaver Falls did not appeal to me.</p>
<p>I arrived in Pittsburgh during the last week of June, 1897, where I hoped to take<lb/>
root, but one day and a night there was enough for me. Youngstown had its fair share<lb/>
of coal smoke and soot but that perpetual black canopy over the &ldquo;Smokey City&rdquo; would<lb/>
darken my days, so I thought. Next day I took the train to Washington, the Capital<lb/>
City, with no regrets. Ah, what a contrast! This indeed was a smokeless city and a<lb/>
beautiful one, with its tree-lined shaded walks and wide avenues, the &ldquo;City of Magnifi-<lb/>
cent Distances&rdquo;, planned as a fitting seat of government for &ldquo;the cradle of democracy&rdquo;<lb/>
and which was destined to become an Empire of Democracy for the liberty-loving and down-<lb/>
trodden peoples of the whole world. What an inspiring sight it was to this young<lb/>
dreamer and idealist!</p>
<p>It was there that my preparatory education for becoming a human guinea pig was to<lb/>
commence. With my letter of recommendation from the Clarke family, I took the liberty<lb/>
of calling on Mrs. John A. Logan, widow of the Union General of that name and formerly<lb/>
a resident of Youngstown but then living in Washington. Surely, she knew the Clarkes<lb/>
very well. How could she be of assistance to me? I told her I wished to enlist in a<lb/>
cavalry regiment. She gave me a note of introduction to Captain Todd, a troop commander<lb/>
of the 5th Cavalry at Fort Myer, Virginia, bordering on the District of Columbia. Board-<lb/>
ing a street car the following morning, I alighted at the entrance to the military<lb/>
reservation and headed for the Adjutant's office, presently meeting an officer of whom<lb/>
I inquired as to the way to headquarters. Pointing to a tall flag-pole from the top<lb/>
of which waved the Stars &amp; Stripes, he informed me that regimental headquarters was<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f03712010"/>
-- 6 --<lb/>
directly in front of it. Before I had advanced a dozen steps he called out to me,<lb/>
saying &ldquo;Young man, come back here a moment&rdquo;, he meeting me half way.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Are you by chance going to enlist in the Army?&rdquo; I told him I was; that I<lb/>
had a note of introduction from Mrs. Logan to Captain Todd. &ldquo;I am Major Arthur,<lb/>
Post Surgeon. Wont you come down to my office for a few minutes. You will have<lb/>
plenty of time as the captain is now out drilling his troop&rdquo;. The hospital was<lb/>
less than fifty yards away, so we reached it in no time. &ldquo;Why have you picked the<lb/>
cavalry? Yes, I know, you like horses, but have you ever thought of the chances<lb/>
open to you in the Hospital Corps?&rdquo; I told him I knew nothing about that corps,<lb/>
had never heard of it. He took pains to explain its part in the Army and had won<lb/>
me over before I realized it. &ldquo;While you are the Hospital Corps you may have an<lb/>
opportunity to study medicine and graduate without leaving the Army, becoming eli-<lb/>
gible for a commission&rdquo;. He then mentioned two or three names of former Hospital<lb/>
Corpsmen who were then medical officers. The Cavalry lost a recruit to the Hospital<lb/>
Corps. I never presented Mrs. Logan's note.</p>
<p>Major William H. Arthur</p>
<p>The following day, with a note from Major Arthur to Captain George D. Deshon,<lb/>
commandant of the Hospital School of Instruction, Washington Barracks, I was sworn<lb/>
into the military service as a private in the Hospital Corps, the date being July<lb/>
3, 1897. The course of instruction lasted six months and included drill, bandaging,<lb/>
application of splints, pharmacy, dietetics, etc. My comrades at the school had had<lb/>
previous military training and for a month or so they had a lot of fun at my expense<lb/>
until I learned to step off with the left foot. I accepted their joshing in a good-<lb/>
natured manner and soon gained their respect. Captain Deshon was an ideal command-<lb/>
ant for that school. He was a West Point graduate who resigned his commission to<lb/>
study medicine and re-entered the Army as a 1st Lieutenant &amp; Assistant Surgeon. It<lb/>
was under him that I learned the meaning of military discipline. I served my six<lb/>
months at the School without a reprimand and &ldquo;graduated&rdquo; with a high rating.</p>
<p>In January, 1898, I was sent to Fort Mott, N. J., a new artillery post on the<lb/>
Jersey side of the Delaware River. That was my first station and our force consist-<lb/>
ed of Captain Guy C. M. Godfrey, Assistant Surgeon, an Acting Hospital Steward and<lb/>
Private Moran. It was a one-battery post, too unimportant for a hospital. Our small<lb/>
dispensary was considered sufficient. Severe and operative cases were rare and the<lb/>
few requiring hospitalization were transferred to the nearest post hospital. Within<lb/>
four months the U. S. declared war on Spain and Captain Godfrey was ordered to Cuba<lb/>
and the Steward was transferred to another station. Our regular army of 25,000 men<lb/>
was promptly doubled and merged with the National Guard and the U. S. Volunteers, but<lb/>
the real nucleus of the combined forces was the small, well-trained and disciplined<lb/>
regular army, with most of its officers and non-commissioned officers advanced one<lb/>
number in rank. In my own class I was promoted to Acting Hospital Steward (sergeant),<lb/>
presumably based on my record in the Surgeon General's office.</p>
<p>Promoted to Acting<lb/>
Hosp. Steward<lb/>
July 28, 1898.</p>
<p>Following my promotion I was transferred to Bedloes Island, New York Harbor, in<lb/>
the shadow of the Statue of Liberty, then serving as a convalescent station for sick<lb/>
and wounded soldiers evacuated from Cuba. In the meantime I had been trying to get<lb/>
to Cuba, to no purpose. I finally succeeded just as the short-lived war was over and<lb/>
the Spanish troops were being evacuated. My first station in Cuba was at the &ldquo;Hosp-<lb/>
ital Alfonso XIII&rdquo;, presently changed to &ldquo;Military Hospital No. 1&rdquo; and later to<lb/>
&ldquo;Hospital General Calixto Garcia&rdquo;, in memory of the Cuban military hero of that name,<lb/>
unchanged to this day. It was at that hospital that I learned my first words in the<lb/>
language of Cervantes, from the few Spanish hospital corpsmen still there awaiting<lb/>
transportation back to Spain. Later on I learned that the words they taught me<lb/>
were words which could not be spoken in the presence of ladies. Since those days I<lb/>
have made considerable progress with Spanish, my accent and pronunciation being<lb/>
considered almost perfect.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f03712011"/>
<p>-- 7 --</p>
<p>After a few weeks at Military Hospital No. 1, I was regularly assigned to duty<lb/>
at Camp Young, near the town of Guanajay (pronounced one-a-high), where I first came<lb/>
to grips with pernicious malaria and 20-grain doses of quinine sulphate to combat it.<lb/>
For a few weeks that drug affected my hearing so much that I feared permanent deaf-<lb/>
ness, but I am happy to record that it was only temporary. Camp Young was a tent<lb/>
unit and soon folded up to move into Guanajay Barracks, made up of frame buildings<lb/>
and located much closer to the town. The post surgeon was Captain Q.....n, a<lb/>
regular Army officer who took a dislike to me, for no reason that I could ever fathom.<lb/>
Sensing that he would not hesitate to have me court-martialed for the slightest in-<lb/>
fraction of Army Regulations, I quietly maneuvered for a transfer to some other post.<lb/>
I had long ago made up my mind to so behave as to merit an EXCELLENT character on my<lb/>
discharge certificate upon completion of my term of enlistment. One little summary<lb/>
court-martial and a ten-dollar fine would have sufficed to bar me from that prized<lb/>
qualification.</p>
<p>I applied for and received a 24-hour pass to Havana which I used instead to lay<lb/>
my case before the Chief Surgeon of the Department in Marianao, Major Jefferson R.<lb/>
Kean, explaining my predicament to his chief clerk, Hospital Steward Hastings, who<lb/>
promised in turn to faithfully state my case to the major, assuring me that my visit<lb/>
would not be divulged if it should not prosper. Had Captain Q. known of my mission<lb/>
I am sure it would have led to reprisals. Steward Hastings informed me that I had an<lb/>
excellent record in the Chief Surgeon's office, adding that &ldquo;Sick &amp; Wounded Reports&rdquo;<lb/>
prepared by me were among the neatest and most complete passing through his office<lb/>
for transmittal to the Surgeon General. My record, he said, was in my favor, hence<lb/>
I could return to my station and await results, which I did, with my fingers crossed.<lb/>
An order for my transfer to the Post Hospital, Columbia Barracks, arrived within the<lb/>
week. Although I had not spoken a word to him, from that day on I considered Major<lb/>
Kean my savior and protector. He was my friend in need.</p>
<p>My transfer to Columbia Barracks, close to Marianao and on the outskirts of<lb/>
Havana, brought me close to the site of my subsequent activities as a human guinea<lb/>
pig and experimental yellow fever. I was fortunately assigned to the operating room<lb/>
as assistant to Captain Alexander N. Stark, Post Surgeon, who personally performed<lb/>
all major operations, surgery being his specialty, Captain Stark was a Virginian and<lb/>
a graduate of the University of Virginia. My duties were to care for and sterilize<lb/>
surgical instruments, dressings, etc., but I soon became proficient at handing him<lb/>
scalpel, bistoury and haemostat, as he called out for them. On more than one occasion<lb/>
when an operation was under way, I was allowed to continue with the anaesthetic and<lb/>
watching pulse and respiration. It was at this time that I definitely decided to<lb/>
study medicine, an aspiration in which Captain Stark encouraged me, quite naturally<lb/>
suggesting his own Alma Mater as the most desirable, informing me that entrance<lb/>
examinations at Virginia wre not rigid, but that one had to know his anatomy and<lb/>
materia medica in order to obtain a degree there. It was here, too, that I first met<lb/>
Private John R. Kissinger of the Hospital Corps who cleaned up the operating room<lb/>
after each operation.</p>
<p>I have never kept a diary of important events in my own life, depending entirely<lb/>
on memory for approximate dates, but not of the events, hence I merely guess that my<lb/>
transfer to Columbia Barracks took place around April 15, 1900. Major Walter Reed,<lb/>
heading the Army Board of medical officers appointed by the Surgeon General of the<lb/>
Army to investigate yellow fever and other tropical diseases in Cuba, arrived on the<lb/>
scene about the end of May, installing his laboratory in the old operating room, in<lb/>
one end of which I had a room in company with Kissinger. Hospital Steward Neat, whom<lb/>
Major Reed had brought with him from Washington, had a room in the same building,<lb/>
directly back of the laboratory. I learned of Major Reed's mission through Captain<lb/>
Stark. While Major Reed and his associates on the Board lived within the hospital<lb/>
reservation, Dr. Agramonte excepted, their work was more or less of a mystery to<lb/>
the rank and file of the Hospital Corpsmen, including myself, their presence there<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f03712012"/>
-- 8 --<lb/>
being merely incidental and dictated by convenience and personal safety, since none of<lb/>
the members of the Board were immune to yellow fever and the military reservation was<lb/>
not exposed to the dangers of infection then prevalent in Havana and its surrounding<lb/>
towns. Columbia Barracks was then occupied by the 7th Regiment of Cavalry, a stone's<lb/>
throw from the towns of Quemados and Marianao, yet not a single case of yellow fever<lb/>
occurred among the troops, while Americans housed in those towns registered several<lb/>
cases of that disease.</p>
<p>I knew Major Reed by sight only at this time and it was not until October that I<lb/>
spoke to him for the first time, when I volunteered for his series of experiments,<lb/>
three months after I was discharged from the Army. That happened on July 2, 1900.<lb/>
My discharge certificate read: Character: EXCELLENT. Services: HONEST AND FAITHFUL.<lb/>
The following day I donned civilian clothes for the first time in three years, the<lb/>
transition from uniform to &ldquo;civies&rdquo; having caused me to lose my bearings for the next<lb/>
few weeks. My bewilderment was not at all strange, considering that three years of<lb/>
military life and its implications could not be shed forthwith. Much of that life was<lb/>
automatic but much of it also taught me self-control and the value of discipline, both<lb/>
of which have served me well in my subsequent path through life. I am thoroughly con-<lb/>
vinced that two or three years in the armed services should form a part of every young<lb/>
man's education, regardless of his station in life.</p>
<p>On July 3, 1900, I became a civilian clerk in the office of General Fitzhugh Lee,<lb/>
commanding the Department of Western Cuba, with headquarters in the town of Marianao.<lb/>
Knowing of my desire to study medicine and of my limited resources, Captain Stark<lb/>
allowed me to continue occupying the room I had as a soldier instead of being obliged<lb/>
to pay room-rent in the town. Strictly speaking, a civilian was barred from occupying<lb/>
quarters intended for men in uniform, so I continued to be Kissinger's room-mate. Thru<lb/>
my friendship with Captain Stark, Dr. Ames and Kissinger, I was well informed of what<lb/>
was going on within the hospital grounds. I do not recall that much fuss was made<lb/>
about Dr. Carroll's attack of yellow fever, nor Dean's attack from the same mosquito<lb/>
which had infected Dr. Carroll. Captain Stark was far from satisfied that they were<lb/>
produced through the bite of a mosquito. He was not alone in that opinion but his<lb/>
and the doubts of others were dissipated, following Major Reed's series of experiments.</p>
<p>The 1900 yellow fever epidemic in Cuba got under way in the month of May and lasted<lb/>
practically unchecked until the end of the year. Americans, and Spanish immigrants<lb/>
recently arrived, were susceptible, with every one of them a potent victim. The native<lb/>
Cubans were evidently immune, since there was no case on record indicating the contrary,<lb/>
the assumption being that they had had an attack of the disease in infancy, fatal cases<lb/>
having been attributed to undetermined, infantile fevers, with the survivors acquiring<lb/>
immunity for the rest of their natural lives, since a second attack of the disease in<lb/>
the same individual was never known to have occurred. The brunt of the epidemic was<lb/>
borne largely by the Americans, military and civilian alike, who were obliged to live<lb/>
and work in the cities and under constant exposure to the disease. Among the officers<lb/>
who contracted yellow fever were Majors Kean, Edmunds and Cartwright, members of<lb/>
General Lee's staff, respectively, Chief Surgeon, Inspector General and Chief Quarter-<lb/>
master. Major Kean happily recovered but Majors Edmunds and Cartwright succumbed to<lb/>
the disease. In Havana, Major Peterson, a member of General Wood's staff, died of<lb/>
yellow fever at Las Animas Hospital, a casualty which had sad repercussions when his<lb/>
wife committed suicide a few hours after his death. Conditions had reached a near-panic<lb/>
stage and other officers whose wives were then in Cuba hastened to arrange for their<lb/>
return to the United States.</p>
<p>Between May and September, 1900, the Army Board's work was purely preparatory and<lb/>
spasmodic, so far as the mosquito was concerned, partly due to Major Reed's forced ab-<lb/>
sence in Washington, but Dr. Lazear carried on in preparation for his return, a return<lb/>
which was hastened by the untimely death of the latter who had contracted yellow fever<lb/>
while feeding and infecting one of his own mosquitoes in the yellow fever ward of Las</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<pb n="13" id="f03712013"/>
<p>-- 9 --<lb/>
Continues<lb/>
from p. 8<lb/>
Version XX<lb/>
Animas Hospital. While patiently holding a test-tubed mosquito to the abdomen of<lb/>
a patient in order to infect it, a stray mosquito alighted on his forearm and flew<lb/>
away before he could trap it, as was his intention. The intruder was evidently<lb/>
&ldquo;loaded&rdquo; or &ldquo;ripe&rdquo;, for five days later he was taken down with a fatal attack of<lb/>
yellow fever, thus cutting short a life full of promise to medical science and human-<lb/>
ity. His death, which occurred on September 25, 1900, was deplored by all who knew<lb/>
him, but especially by Major Reed who was saddened by the loss of his ablest associ-<lb/>
ate on the Yellow Fever Board. The death of Dr. Lazear added another name to the<lb/>
long list of martyrs to medical science.</p>
<p>Following Dr. Lazear's death the attention of the medical world was focused<lb/>
on the manner in which he was infected, lending credence to the hitherto doubted<lb/>
origin of the yellow fever attacks suffered by Dr. Carroll and Private Dean of the<lb/>
7th Cavalry Regiment. Those three cases, however, were not accepted as conclusive,<lb/>
hence Major Reed decided that a series of experiments should be carried out, to in-<lb/>
clude not only the mosquito tests but infected bedding and clothing, that is to say,<lb/>
the new and the age-old theory, to determine once and for all which of the two was<lb/>
responsible for the spread of yellow fever. Major Reed and his Board associates had<lb/>
earlier planned the two series of experiments, cost of which, including cash awards<lb/>
to volunteer subjects, was estimated at $10,000.00. The Surgeon General of the Army<lb/>
had no funds which could be used for such a purpose. Major Kean, Walter Reed's<lb/>
intimate friend, suggested a visit to General Leonard Wood, the Military Governor of<lb/>
Cuba, who was a captain in the Medical Corps at the outbreak of the war with Spain<lb/>
when he was commissioned colonel of &ldquo;The Rough Riders&rdquo;, with Theodore Roosevelt second<lb/>
in command. General Wood had not forgotten that he was long a medico before he became<lb/>
a Major General, so he was in whole-hearted sympathy with Major Reed's plans, making<lb/>
the amount needed available from Insular Funds. With that backing, Reed could now go<lb/>
ahead with his series of experiments.</p>
<p>Having had in mind an appropriate site for an experimental camp, arrangements<lb/>
were made for renting a plot of land in the center of an isolated farm near the town<lb/>
of Marianao, named in advance &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;, to honor the memory of the martyred<lb/>
member of the Board. At the same time, machinery was set in motion for quietly but<lb/>
effectively enlisting a sufficient number of &ldquo;human guinea pigs&rdquo; to &ldquo;go in&rdquo; for the<lb/>
experiments, allowing the volunteers to elect the route by which they were to face<lb/>
death and glory or live to enjoy it, as Fate might will. Needless to state that Major<lb/>
Reed did not expect a stampede of volunteers for a possibly early passage to the other<lb/>
world. He had calculated on maximum cash awards of $500.00 and a very limited number<lb/>
of volunteers, but there was an agreeable surprise in store for him.</p>
<p>Little did I dream that October afternoon, as I crossed the parade grounds of the<lb/>
Post Hospital on my way to my room, that I had a date with Destiny and Walter Reed. It<lb/>
was by design rather than accident that I was accosted by Dr. Roger Post Ames with a<lb/>
cheery &ldquo;Hello, Johnny, what's new over at Headquarters&rdquo;? In the most casual manner,<lb/>
Dr. Ames led up to the subject uppermost in his mind at that time, asking me: &ldquo;Did you<lb/>
know that Major Reed is offering a bonus of $500.00 to volunteers for experimental<lb/>
yellow fever?&rdquo; No, I did not, but would he please explain. That invitation was right<lb/>
down his alley as he shrewdly expected. I think I was No. 1 on his list of promising<lb/>
candidates. He knew that I intended to study medicine and that such a bonus would be<lb/>
a godsend to me and that volunteering would be a good card card of introduction for<lb/>
a starter. &ldquo;Just think, Johnny, what that $500.00 will mean to you&rdquo;, he said. I told<lb/>
him I would sleep over it and let him know &ldquo;tomorrow&rdquo;, continuing on to my room. As<lb/>
yet I had not realized that Dr. Ames was Walter Reed's missionary. That knowledge came<lb/>
to me later. Dr. Ames was an Acting Assistant Surgeon (Contract Surgeon) on duty at<lb/>
the Post Hospital, somewhat of a rough-neck, but well liked by patients and corpsmen.<lb/>
Contract Surgeons wore an officer's uniform but without rank insignia.</p>
<p>A few hours after my talk with Dr. Ames I was discussing the matter with John. R.<lb/>
Kissinger, my room-mate, telling him that I was &ldquo;going in&rdquo; for the e x p e r i m ents<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f03712014"/>
-- 10 --<lb/>
but without the bonus. He thought I would be a fool for renouncing it and told me<lb/>
so in no uncertain fashion. Most people would agree with him, I suppose, but my<lb/>
mind was made up. Least of my thoughts were that people might think I was playing to<lb/>
the grandstand. My thoughts were varied, one following the other with lightning<lb/>
rapidity. What if I should succumb to &ldquo;yellow jack&rdquo;? Did I hold my own life so<lb/>
lightly as to risk it for a paltry $500? While that sum might prove to be a little<lb/>
fortune for me, added to my slim savings in a period of three years in the Army,<lb/>
would my act be a noble one? Miser that I had been, I decided to volunteer without<lb/>
being paid for it. I discovered that I was a dreamer and idealist at heart, having<lb/>
found myself for the first time. I aspired to become a medico. Should I live to<lb/>
&ldquo;tell the tale&rdquo;, would not my act be a good start in that profession?</p>
<p>Kissinger and myself talked the matter over, pro and con, until the wee small<lb/>
hours of the morning. He, too, would volunteer and without the bonus. I tried to<lb/>
dissuade him, pointing out that we had different motives, since I was bent on the<lb/>
study of medicine, while he had no such intentions. Seeing that his mind was made<lb/>
up, I let it go at that. If he had known of Major Reed's offer before my talk with<lb/>
him, he did not confide it to me, leading me to believe that it was news to him.<lb/>
Turning out the lights, we turned in for a few hours' sleep. Although I was in the<lb/>
habit of sleeping soundly through eight or nine hours, I was awake with my thoughts<lb/>
for another hour at least, awakening with a start when the bugler sounded reveille<lb/>
at six o'clock in the morning. Kissinger and I were not in concert as to when and<lb/>
how we were to call on Major Reed, but I decided to do so that morning, even though<lb/>
I might be late at the office. If so, I could explain why. Having decided on my<lb/>
course, I wanted to strike the iron while it was hot. Was I afraid I would weaken?<lb/>
I don't think so.</p>
<p>While I had slept only a few hours of my customary eight or nine, I dressed<lb/>
hurriedly, abandoning the hospital grounds and making a bee-line for the small eating<lb/>
house in Marianao where I was accustomed to have my meals, returning to the Post<lb/>
Hospital after my light breakfast, bent on seeing Major Reed. Fortune was on my<lb/>
side, for I found the Major in his room and alone. Unperturbed, but momentarily<lb/>
confused and with a questioining look, the Major said: &ldquo;Good morning. What can I<lb/>
do for you?&rdquo; I told him my name, where I was employed then and my recent discharge<lb/>
from the Hospital Corps. I was there to offer my services for the yellow fever<lb/>
experiments which Dr. Ames had mentioned to me the previous afternoon. My offer was<lb/>
conveyed in disconnected sentences, although I had been trying to memorize my little<lb/>
speech, terse and to the point. I could see that he was surprised but the gleam in<lb/>
his eyes was eloquent of the pleasure and satisfaction he felt. He did not mention<lb/>
the cash bonus, nor did I since that was not to be a part of the bargain. I told<lb/>
him in a few simple words that I would undergo the experiments without reward of any<lb/>
kind. There was nothing dramatic about our interview. No saluting as between the<lb/>
uniformed major and the simply dressed ex-soldier.</p>
<p>Explaining to Major Reed that I was due at General Lee's headquarters, I excused<lb/>
myself, informing him that I could see him that afternoon, after office hours, or<lb/>
await his further instructions. He suggested six o'clock that afternoon as suitable<lb/>
so that he could inform me more in detail about the part I would be expected to play<lb/>
in the experiments. For the first time I reported for work a quarter of an hour<lb/>
late, explaining the reason to the chief clerk in the Adjutant General's office. That<lb/>
young fellow was so dumbfounded at what I told him that he took me in to see Major<lb/>

Robert E. Lee Michie, the Adjutant General. Major Michie wanted to take me in to<lb/>
see General Lee, but I balked. I was surprised at the importance they attached to<lb/>
the matter, and not a little embarrassed.</p>
<p>Promptly at six o'clock I was again before the Major in his combination bedroom<lb/>
and office at the Officers' Quarters. He had been thinking the matter over and had<lb/>
decided that, to start with, I was to undergo a stiff physical examination, including<lb/>
blood tests, adding that, should I be taken down with yellow fever, he wanted me to<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f03712015"/>
-- 11 --<lb/>
have every chance to pull through; that there would be no fatal cases of yellow<lb/>
fever at Camp Lazear if he could help it; that we were now two to volunteer, viz:<lb/>
Kissinger and myself and that he was very happy over the promising start already<lb/>
made and that my acceptance would be contingent upon the results of my physical<lb/>
examination, which could be made at my convenience, preferably the next day, arrange-<lb/>
ments for which he would attend to. The following day I had my physical examination<lb/>
and passed it with flying colors, including the laboratory tests.</p>
<p>Major Reed now suggested that I submit my resignation as clerk on the staff of<lb/>
General Lee and that I would be employed by him at the same salary, as clerk and type-<lb/>
writer, since he would be obliged to create such a position anyway because of the<lb/>
extra work involved in connection with Camp Lazear, calling for correspondence and<lb/>
reports which should be made on machine rather than in long hand. I was well pleased<lb/>
with that assignment and more so, later on, when I became a &ldquo;prisoner&rdquo; at the experi-<lb/>
mental camp where time might hang heavily on my hands, with nothing to do but eat and<lb/>
sleep, sleep and eat.</p>
<p>First impressions over, I gave up speculating on what might be in store for me,<lb/>
living in a state of expectancy rather than trepidation. The work which Major Reed<lb/>
gave me did not exceed three to five hours daily, most of which was in draft form,<lb/>
copying data and reports to the Surgeon General, with an occasional tracing of clinical<lb/>
charts where the originals showed ink blots, erasures, etc., the Major being a stickler<lb/>
for neatness in paper work.</p>
<p>In the meantime and with the ice broken, Dr. Ames found rich soil for his mission-<lb/>
ary work in the Hospital Corps Detachment of 35 to 40 men stationed at the Post<lb/>
Hospital, a dozen or more falling in line for the experiments. At least twelve of<lb/>
the eventual 18 volunteers were members of the Hospital Corps. Surely their moral<lb/>
bravery, with no headlines to exalt their heroism, should favorably compare with the<lb/>
physical courage of soldiers of the line on the field of battle. Major Reed certain-<lb/>
ly thought so, later putting himself on record to that effect.</p>
<p>November 20th, 1900, was the &ldquo;Great Day&rdquo; for the small group of &ldquo;human guinea<lb/>
pigs&rdquo; who were to participate in the ceremonies of inauguration of Camp Lazear, a<lb/>
miniature city of seven hospital tents, a temporary frame store-room and two small<lb/>
frame buildings, each 20 by 14 feet, designated as Building No. 1 and Building No. 2.<lb/>
No. 1 was for the &ldquo;Infected Bedding &amp; Clothing&rdquo; tests and No. 2 for the &ldquo;Mosquito&rdquo;<lb/>
tests. The interest of all concerned revolved around those two small buildings. No. 1<lb/>
was insect-proof, entry to which was through a small vestibule in which the clothing<lb/>
of the occupants was hung, including shoes or slippers. Once having entered through<lb/>
the inside door to that &ldquo;pestilent prison&rdquo;, the occupants donned soiled garments in<lb/>
which they were to sleep (if they could) from nine o'clock at night until six o'clock<lb/>
in the morning. Sheets, pillow slips, and convalescent suits worn by cases of yellow<lb/>
fever at Las Animas Hospital were hanging around the room, some of which were stained<lb/>
with black vomit and other excreta.</p>
<p>For twenty <add>one</add> consecutive nights Dr. Robert P. Cooke and Privates Levi Folk and<lb/>
Warren G. Jernegan, of the Hospital Corps, slept in the highly &ldquo;perfumed&rdquo; atmosphere<lb/>
of Building No. 1. During the day they were not allowed to associate with other<lb/>
guinea pigs, their tent being apart from the other six so as to place them in a state<lb/>
of quarantine. Conversation with the camp personnel was limited to them and could be<lb/>
carried on with the volunteers only at a respectable distance. Without knowing of<lb/>
the purgatory in store for those who elected the &ldquo;Infected Clothing&rdquo; tests, I was glad<lb/>
that I volunteered for the &ldquo;mosquito&rdquo; route. I would most assuredly have balked at<lb/>
the ordeal described by the victims sleeping in Building No. 1.</p>
<p>Nov 26<lb/>
<unclear>@ K vs S</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>p 4</unclear></p>
<p>Anxiously awaiting my turn to be bitten, I had my first test on November 27th,<lb/>
followed by another on November 29th by supposedly infected mosquitoes, fed on my<lb/>
arm from glass test tubes, but I remained hale and hearty, much to my disappointment.<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f03712016"/>
-- 12 --<lb/>
Was I naturally immune to yellow fever, thought Major Reed? He did not think so but<lb/>
he intended to make sure. There was the &ldquo;Mosquito Building&rdquo; (Building No. 2), still<lb/>
unfinished and untenanted. &ldquo;No more experiments for you, Moran, with two or three<lb/>
mosquitoes biting you from a test tube. You will be the first to occupy the mosquito<lb/>
compartment of Building No. 2, where a whole regiment of them will be set loose. That<lb/>
will be my master test and fool-proof. Just be patient. If you are a natural immune<lb/>
your case will make history, anyway, for it would be the first of its kind on record.&rdquo;</p>
<p>While awaiting Major Reed's master test, John R. Kissinger was more &ldquo;fortunate&rdquo;<lb/>
than I. On December 5th he was bitten by five mosquitoes and on December 9th one of<lb/>
those five mosquitoes had laid him low. While awaiting arrival of the ambulance to<lb/>
take him to the hospital I told him: "I wish you the best of luck, John, but I shall<lb/>
never forgive you for &ldquo;beating me to it&rdquo;, our rivalry being as to who would be the<lb/>
first to be &ldquo;taken down&rdquo; with Yellow Jack. It was no joking matter but Kissinger took<lb/>
it with a sickly grin, brave boy that he was. I sincerely prayed for his recovery<lb/>
until he had safely passed the crisis.</p>
<p>In the forenoon of December 21st, Major Reed told me to get into a nightshirt and<lb/>
slippers only. My turn had at last arrived. I walked to my fate and to whatever<lb/>
destiny had in store for me. Leaving nightshirt and slippers in the vestibule, I enter-<lb/>
ed the mosquito room, Major Reed handing me a hand-mirror, with instructions to hold it<lb/>
in one hand to enable me to count the number of insects alighting and feeding upon me.<lb/>
The little room was immaculately clean, the only furniture being a new hospital bed,<lb/>
a new mattress and sheet. I then stretched out on the bed, noting that walls and ceil-<lb/>
ing were &ldquo;papered&rdquo; with fine unbleached muslin, windows consisting of fine, copper-<lb/>
bronze metal cloth. Those observations were only momentary, being presently aware of<lb/>
the fact that I was a welcome guest to Major Reed's regiment of mosquitoes.</p>
<p>Promptly I was attacked by seven of the insects, making every effort to not disturb<lb/>
them. Perhaps I was bitten by more than seven but I could only count those alighting on<lb/>
my chest, abdomen, arms and face. In the meantime, Major Reed was an interested<lb/>
observer in the &ldquo;control&rdquo; half of the little building, watching through the fine-mesh,<lb/>
metallic screen partition. The &ldquo;control&rdquo; section of the &ldquo;Mosquito Building&rdquo; was<lb/>
occupied several days before and after my visits to the mosquito room. It was purposely<lb/>
exposed and ventilated in order that the mosquito room tests could not be questioned.<lb/>
The two men who had slept there for eighteen nights remained healthy. This, my first<lb/>
visit to the mosquito room, lasted from 12 noon to 12:30 P. M. That same afternoon,<lb/>
at 4:30, I again entered the mosquito room, being bitten by four of the insects. The<lb/>
next day, at the same hour, I made my last visit, this time being bitten by four of<lb/>
the mosquitoes. Major Reed assumed, by deduction, that all 15 of the insects had fed<lb/>
on me during the three visits.</p>
<p>From the date of my first visit, I was instructed by Major Reed to take my temper-<lb/>
ature and pulse count three times daily, noting same on a temperature chart. Nothing<lb/>
happened until Christmas morning, 1900. Upon awakening, I had no inkling of what that<lb/>
day had in store for me. I ate a hearty breakfast of &ldquo;ham and&rdquo;, buttered toast and<lb/>
muffins, and two cups of coffee, feeling as fine as a fiddle. At 10:00 A. M. I felt<lb/>
that something was going to happen to me. My temperature, taken at 8:00 A. M. was<lb/>
normal, pulse 82. During the previous four days I had not given much thought to a<lb/>
possible attack of yellow fever, losing no sleep over such a contingency. I now reached<lb/>
for the thermometer and took my temperature. It was a fraction over 100 degrees Fahren-<lb/>
heit. I then realized that Santa Claus had not forgotten me. It was my only Christ-<lb/>
mas gift in that last year and last month of the 19th Century. Well, that was a dist-<lb/>
inction that Kissinger could not boast of, I thought to myself. He was well by that<lb/>
time, and immune to Yellow Jack.</p>
<p>Ah, yes! I had almost forgotten that I had a bet on with Jernegan. He had dared<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f03712017"/>
-- 13 --<lb/>
me to wager five dollars that I would be having Christmas dinner with them at Camp<lb/>
Lazear. I was just as willing to bet that I would not, but he had chosen his end<lb/>
and so I could take it or leave it. I took him up, each of us handing Levi E. Folk<lb/>
a five-dollar gold piece, as stake-holder. Our dinner hour would be at one o'clock<lb/>
that day, instead of the customary noon hour. Dr. Ames had informed me that many a<lb/>
man had killed himself by eating after the fever had set in, unaware of the fact that<lb/>
his fever was Yellow Jack. I had no doubts about the nature of mine, but I wanted to<lb/>
win the bet. Should I try to bluff my way through dinner or tell Jernigan that he<lb/>
had won? I took my temperature at 11:00 A. M., at 12:00 noon and at five minutes<lb/>
to 1:00 P. M. It was now 103&deg; Fahrenheit. Having the office tent to myself, I told<lb/>
nobody of my attack. Yes, come what might, I would try to bluff through dinner.</p>
<p>Unobtrusively, I took my place at the dinner table. We had a real Christmas<lb/>
dinner with all the trimmings and, notwithstanding my high temperature, I had a<lb/>
ravenous appetite, so did my table companions. That roast turkey with cranberry<lb/>
sauce, mashed potatoes &amp; gravy, with three or four additional appetizing dishes,<lb/>
certainly looked good to me. Prudence would dictate that I should let food alone<lb/>
altogether. Well, I would just play with it, eating sparingly and gingerly, trusting<lb/>
to Divine Providence in my foolhardy venture. I certainly had every desire to live,<lb/>
none at all to become a dead hero, yet here I was, courting suicide. Servig myself<lb/>
small portions, I managed to simulate eating while making every effort to not attract<lb/>
the attention of my table companions, having taken great care not to sit close to<lb/>
Jernigan. He and the others were too busy to pay much attention to me, none of them<lb/>
suspecting that I had IT. The bluff worked.</p>
<p>Dinner over, I claimed the two gold coins and, in company with Jernigan, we looked<lb/>
up the stakeholder. After pocketing the coins I called Jernigan to one side, telling<lb/>
him I &ldquo;was on my way&rdquo; and had been since ten o'clock that morning. Now, all concern,<lb/>
that big-hearted and worthy son of the State of Florida said: &ldquo;You don't mean to tell<lb/>
me you have it, Johnny&rdquo;. I nodded in the affirmative. Excitedly, he said: &ldquo;Let me<lb/>
call the Steward so that he may call for the ambulance to take you to the hospital&rdquo;.<lb/>
I begged him not to, stating that Major Reed was due at any moment and that I could<lb/>
wait. Feeling a little guilty about the way I had won the bet, I asked him if he was<lb/>
satisfied. &ldquo;Sure&rdquo;, he said. &ldquo;Our bet was as to whether or not you would eat Christ-<lb/>
mas dinner at the Camp. We made no mention of yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The officers at the Post Hospital had also had their Christmas dinner at the<lb/>
Officers' Mess, hence Major Reed did not arrive at Camp Lazear until three in the<lb/>
afternoon, coming direct to the office tent where I was lying down on my cot. He<lb/>
greeted me with a &ldquo;Merry Christmas, Moran&rdquo;, followed by &ldquo;Anything new?&rdquo; For reply,<lb/>
I pointed to the temperature chart on the field desk. A rapid glance at the chart<lb/>
convinced him that my big moment had arrived. He looked at the last reading of the<lb/>
thermometer, which I had not shaken down, then looked intently at my flushed face<lb/>
while pressing the palm of his hand against my forhead. Stepping out of the tent<lb/>
he ordered the ambulance around at once. While waiting for it he remarked to me<lb/>
&ldquo;This is one of the happiest days of my life&rdquo;, meantime rubbing the palms of his<lb/>
hand together. I did not think his remark strange. Notwitstanding the fact that<lb/>
he was a kind, considerate and God-fearing man, he was none the less the scientist<lb/>
seeking to fathom and combat a fearful scourge for the benefit of humanity. He did<lb/>
not hold human life lightly. Had he not vowed to me that none of those who had<lb/>
placed their lives in his hands would succumb to yellow fever, if he could help it.</p>
<p>Major Reed preceded the ambulance in his doherty wagon, the Army &ldquo;Ford&rdquo; of<lb/>
those days, while I occupied the stretcher. We were on our way to the yellow fever<lb/>
hospital, a mile or so distant from the Camp. It was the last time I was to see<lb/>
Camp Lazear in all its glory as it was then. On the trip there I did not pay much<lb/>
attention to the surroundings. After arriving there I could only see one or two<lb/>
houses from the camp reservation. Now, on my way to the hospital, I could not see<lb/>
any of my surroundings. As a matter of fact I was not very much interested in the<lb/>
scenery just then, with my temperature around 104 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
<pb n="18" id="f03712018"/>
<p>-- 14 --</p>
<p>After my arrival at the hospital one thing followed another in quick success-<lb/>
ion. The fever did not appear to bother me very much but I must have gotten into<lb/>
a wrestling match with &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; in a one-sided battle which reduced me to a<lb/>
pulp, for I was sore in every bone and muscle, incresing in intensity, hour after<lb/>
hour. I lost track of time, where I was and what was being done to me. Automatic-<lb/>
ally, I swallowed the cracked ice fed to me from a spoon by the nurse who had charge<lb/>
of me, obediently following her instructions to &ldquo;swallow it whole. Do not allow it<lb/>
to melt in your mouth&rdquo;, encouraging me by saying &ldquo;That's a good boy. You are a good<lb/>
patient&rdquo;. God, how long that night seemed! Around midnight I must have been on the<lb/>
verge of delirium. In my sub-conscious state I remembered that I had promised my-<lb/>
self to go through the ordeal bravely; that I must not moan or groan.</p>
<p>It was the morning after Christmas. I was being gently nudged by a middle-aged<lb/>
gentleman in Army uniform, with an anxious look in his eyes and speaking to me in a<lb/>
low modulated voice. Several minutes must have elapsed before I could collect my<lb/>
thoughts, then it dawned on me that my visitor was Major Reed, patiently sitting<lb/>
there by my bed. Pulling myself together, I tried to concentrate on what he was<lb/>
saying. Was he not the man who had inspired me with such respect and admiration as<lb/>
to border on hero-worship. From him: &ldquo;Are you in pain, boy&rdquo;, my reply in a weak<lb/>
voice being &ldquo;Yes Sir&rdquo;. &ldquo;Try to localize them for me, will you&rdquo;. What did he mean<lb/>
by &ldquo;localize&rdquo;, I thought. Oh, yes, I remembered! He wanted me to point out or tell<lb/>
him where I felt the pains. I told him that I was &ldquo;just a mass of pain&rdquo;; that I was<lb/>
sore all over. &ldquo;Dont you feel like groaning&rdquo;?, followed by &ldquo;Sometimes groaning out<lb/>
loud gives relief and no one here will mind. You might try it&rdquo;. I told him that I<lb/>
had promised myself to take it with as little fuss as possible.</p>
<p>The following day, December 27th, Major Reed again visited me, this time in<lb/>
company with an old gentleman with flowing side-whiskers and a patriarchal figure.<lb/>
I had seen him just once, at Camp Lazear, as the guest of Major Reed who had invited<lb/>
him to inspect the camp and its site, shortly after its inauguration. I was not in-<lb/>
troduced to him at that time, nor now, but I knew that he was the old gentleman who<lb/>
had for years insisted that his pet type of mosquito, the CULEX FASCIATUS, as it was<lb/>
then known, was responsible for the spread of yellow fever. This old gentleman was<lb/>
Dr, Charles Finlay, known to the Cubans as Dr. Carlos Finlay. With him and Major Reed<lb/>
were Major William C. Gorgas, Chief Sanitary Officer for the Military Government of<lb/>
Cuba and Dr. Antonio Diaz Albertini, all members of the Yellow Fever Board of the City<lb/>
of Havana, as Major Reed explained to me, some days later. Neither of the three<lb/>
visitors asked me any questions but they appeared to be very much interested in my<lb/>
clinical chart. I heard Major Reed remark: &ldquo;A very pretty case&rdquo; and I assumed he<lb/>
was referring to me. Dr. Finlay and his associates were there to certify to the fact<lb/>
that I had experimental yellow fever.</p>
<p>On January 1st, 1901, I had weathered the critical seven-day period of my yellow<lb/>
fever attack, a welcome New Year's gift to me and just as welcome to Major Reed who<lb/>
was very much worried about my chances during the first forty-eight hours of my ill-<lb/>
ness, as he frankly confessed to me when I became convalescent. I &ldquo;lived to tell the<lb/>
tale&rdquo;, but it was an incident in my life which I have never forgotten and to be retold,<lb/>
time and again throughout the years. On or about January 15th, 1901, with my loss<lb/>
of weight practically restored, Major Reed asked me if I was game enough to submit to<lb/>
an immunity test by way of a blood injection from a case of yellow fever, to which I<lb/>
readily consented upon being assured that the donor's blood had been subjected to the<lb/>
usual laboratory tests. As Major Reed expected, the results were nil, leaving no<lb/>
doubt as to my immunity. With the ordeal over, I had an intense desire to return to<lb/>
God's Country. I think I was home-sick. Major Reed asked me to remain until his<lb/>
mission in Cuba should be concluded, which he thought would be of an additional<lb/>
month's duration. Major Gorgas offered me a position in the Sanitary Department,<lb/>
which I declined. Major Reed had enough work for me to keep me half busy, so I<lb/>
remained on his payroll for the rest of his stay in Cuba.</p>
<pb n="19" id="f03712019"/>
<p>-- 15 --</p>
<p>My six-day vacation in Gotham ended, I was off to Salem, New Jersey, the nearest<lb/>
town to Fort Mott for soldiers stationed there, where I had made the acquaintance of<lb/>
the leading druggist, Frank Luerssen. When I was transferred from Fort Mott to<lb/>
Bedloes Island Mr. Luerssen told me that he would always have a position for me at<lb/>
the end of my term of enlistment. From Havana I had written to remind him of his<lb/>
offer, adding that I would not hold him to it unless he actually needed my services.<lb/>
I owed him a visit anyway and he could expect me around the first of March.</p>
<p>My friend received me with open arms and he was very proud of me because of my<lb/>
yellow fever exploits. After explaining to him that my position could only be a<lb/>
temporary one because of my plans to to study medicine, plans which he took for grant-<lb/>
ed. I did not discuss the matter of salary with him, feeling confident that he would<lb/>
pay me all I was worth to him for the six months I would be with him, being in reality<lb/>
an apprentice and not a registered pharmacist authorized to fill prescriptions. He<lb/>
arranged for a room and meals for me across the street from the drug store, at the<lb/>
&ldquo;Schaefer House&rdquo;, property of the widow he had married, where I was treated with every<lb/>
consideration and lived most comfortably. I do not know what his arrangements with<lb/>
Mrs. Luerssen was, but he asked me if $50.00 a month would be satisfactory, he to<lb/>
reimburse the hotel for my room, board and laundry. Of course it was satisfactory.</p>
<p>Anxious to merit the good opinion of my friend, I made his business mine, working<lb/>
long hours without as much as a glance at the clock. During that summer I was kept<lb/>
pretty busy attending the soda fountain, with breaks between the fountain and the<lb/>
patent medicine cabinets and druggists' sundries. Except on Sunday mornings I took<lb/>
no time off, but one meets a lot of nice people at the soda fountain of a small town<lb/>
such as Salem then was. I really enjoyed my work and surroundings and made it my<lb/>
principal business to please my friend's customers. During my free hours I kept up<lb/>
with the news, read a book or magazine, all recreations which I have enjoyed all thru<lb/>
life. I had no opportunity to spend money and less inclination to spend it. At the<lb/>
end of the six months my salary was practically intact. Before saying goodbye to<lb/>
Mr. Luerssen he told me that he would always have a job for me if I wanted to return<lb/>
to Salem. But I never went back.</p>
<p>During the first week of September, 1901, I arrived in Charlottesville, Virginia,<lb/>
finding a boarding house within easy walking distance of the University and calling<lb/>
on the Dean of the Faculty, Dr. Paul B. Barringer, whose position corresponded with<lb/>
that of President. Many years later Virginia had its first president, Dr. Edwin A.<lb/>
Alderman, a nationally known educator and lecturer who gave impetus to the formation<lb/>
of an endowment fund for that fine old institution of learning and home of &ldquo;The Honor<lb/>
System&rdquo;. Dr. Barringer had received a letter from Major Reed suggesting that I be<lb/>
accorded every consideration. The Dean informed me that, unfortunately, Virginia had<lb/>
no endowment fund worthy of the name but was dependant entirely on State aid, often<lb/>
inadequate even for current expenses. Deficiency in my pre-medical education would<lb/>
not be a problem, since I would have four years in which to make up my lack of pre-<lb/>
paration. I was very much encouraged and bubbling with enthusiasm.</p>
<p>Starting the term on September 15th, I was soon deep in the study of chemistry,<lb/>
anatomy, histology and other kindred assignments of first-year medicine. In years<lb/>
and worldly experience and as a graduate of the School of Hard Knocks, I had decided<lb/>
advantages over every man in my class, most of whom were under 20. They availed me<lb/>
but little, however, against those of the youths who had graduated from primary school,<lb/>
high school or preparatory, accustomed to concentrate on a continuous and progressive<lb/>
schedule of studies leading up to a professional course. I lacked that coordination<lb/>
so essential in absorbing and retaining the material contained between the two covers<lb/>
of my text books. Nor was this my only handicap. That wily commodity, &ldquo;the root of<lb/>
all evil&rdquo;, money, a sweet root to those who have it and a bitter one to those who do<lb/>
not, was my ever present specter, interfering with profitable study.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<pb n="20" id="f03712020"/>
<p><unclear>Nos. B</unclear><lb/>
Version B<lb/>
PSH</p>
<p><hi>Sheet No. 59 &amp; continuous to Sheet No. 62</hi>.</p>
<p>..................................................................</p>
<p>And now comes the most painful part of my self-imposed task. Bitter as it may<lb/>
taste to the present generation of Cuban medicos and those Cubans who see eye to<lb/>
eye with them, it is a duty which I cannot shirk. Were I to follow the course of<lb/>
least resistance and accomodate my views to those of the Cubans, my recollections<lb/>
would be a travesty on justice and fair play to the memory of Walter Reed. Since I<lb/>
am one of the few living witnesses and actors of the drama which was enacted at<lb/>
Camp Lazear between November 20, 1900 and February 15, 1901, I claim the right to<lb/>
an opinion on the respective parts played by Finlay and Reed in what has been<lb/>
generally referred to as &ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. The fact that my relations<lb/>
with Reed were more or less intimate, while I had seen Finlay only twice, does not<lb/>
signify that I will not be impartial. On the contrary, I shall be governed and<lb/>
imbued by a spirit of entire fair play, ignoring the matter of my closer relations<lb/>
and association with Reed.</p>
<p>I have been thoroughly in accord with the Cubans in their glorification of<lb/>
Finlay but I am certainly not in accord with them when, in doing that, they vilify<lb/>
Reed and his memory. Surely, the man who helped free the Island of Cuba from a<lb/>
centuries-old scourge deserves the everlasting gratitude of its people. That<lb/>
gratitude was his in a generous measure immediately following the experiments at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, but less than two years had elapsed when personal ambitions for false<lb/>
fame, professional jealousy and exaggerated nationalism were brought into play with<lb/>
the avowed purpose of dimming his work.</p>
<p>It is true that the American people in their enthusiastic applause of Walter<lb/>
Reed and his conclusive experiments had for the moment failed to link Finlay with<lb/>
his accomplishments, but so had the rest of the world. The fact that Dr. Finlay<lb/>
had identified the right species of mosquito as the yellow fever carrier was in<lb/>
itself a notable achievement and without which Major Reed's experiments might never<lb/>
have taken place. By that same token, Dr. Finlay's theory might have continued to<lb/>
be &ldquo;a voice in the wilderness&rdquo; for the rest of his natural life, had it not been for<lb/>
the advent of Walter Reed and his Army Board. Dr. Finlay had tried to convince his<lb/>
countrymen and the rest of the world, over a period of 19 years, that yellow fever<lb/>
was spread by his pet mosquito, but no one was convinced. I merely state facts.</p>
<p>Now let us get to the root and origin of the Cuban's negation of Reed and their<lb/>
all-out claims for Finlay. It germinated and incubated in the mind of one man who<lb/>
had a very definite purpose, not exactly to exalt Finlay at the expense of Reed but<lb/>
to satisfy his own personal ambitions for honors which he could never have obtained<lb/>
in his chosen field, medical science. To that end, he set himself up as the defender<lb/>
of Finlay and the detractor of Reed. It suited his purpose to play on nationalism<lb/>
as his best weapon. Vilifying Reed, hating him and all his works, became an obsess-<lb/>
ion to him. By word and pen he became a living example of hatred towards Reed and<lb/>
his memory until the day of his death. Walter Reed had passed on to his reward<lb/>
less than two years after termination of his monumental work in Cuba, hence his<lb/>
self-appointed detractor had a free rein to continue and intensify his venemous<lb/>
campaign of vilification. There were many medicos in Cuba who could have refuted<lb/>
the detractor, but few of them had the moral courage to do so, following the line<lb/>
of least resistance. There was one exception, which I will mention later.</p>
<p>Walter Reed's &ldquo;Master Detractor&rdquo; was in reality more of a politician than a<lb/>
medico, and although he became a professor in the School of Medicine of the Univ-<lb/>
ersity of Havana, he soon managed to obtain leave and accept a diplomatic post in<lb/>
the Cuban embassy in Paris. Having married a French lady and commanding a know-<lb/>
ledge of French, he was now in his element, aided and abetted by his diplomatic<lb/>
status. There, again, he deftly played the game of nationalism, craving honors<lb/>
at the hands of the French scientific bodies. Frenchmen were proud of the fact<lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f03712021"/>
<hi>Sheets 59 to 62, inclusive.</hi><lb/>
that Dr. Finlay's mother was of their own nationality, and justifiably so, since it<lb/>
cannot be doubted that his discovery of the yellow fever mosquito was an eminently<lb/>
scientific achievement as a major step towards &ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. Major<lb/>
Walter Reed's &ldquo;Master Detractor&rdquo;, however, had other and less lofty motives - that<lb/>
of placing himself in the spotlight, so the approaching centenary of Finlay's birth<lb/>
became his golden opportunity to proclaim to proclaim to the French that Walter Reed<lb/>
was an impostor, in a book titled &ldquo;CARLOS J. FINLAY - SON CENTENAIRE&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It is assumed that French scientists did not realize that they were being<lb/>
victimized. Up to this time they had considered Finlay and Reed as collaborators.<lb/>
But surely his word could not be doubted, since the author was a man of diplomatic<lb/>
status and a graduate in medicine. No American in Paris at the time raised his<lb/>
voice in defense of Reed, so far as is known. More than likely, but few of them<lb/>
had read or noticed the French biography of Carlos Finlay by a Cuban author. If<lb/>
they had, with characteristic complacency they remained silent, secure in the know-<lb/>
ledge that Reed's immortality was safe in the hearts of his countrymen.</p>
<p>Reed's detractor had accomplished what he devoutly craved. He was rewarded<lb/>
and recognized by the French Academy for his euology of Finlay, which was at the<lb/>
same time a vilification of Reed. In the meantime he saw to it that the torch of<lb/>
hatred against Reed and his memory should not be extinguished in Cuba. His hand-<lb/>
ful of diehards were urged to intensify the campaign of defamation which he had<lb/>
so deftly fathered. It is almost inconceivable that a diseased mind could swerve<lb/>
or stultify the convictions of even a small group of professional men to such an<lb/>
extent as to create a fear of ostracism in them if they should venture to do<lb/>
justice to Reed, especially those who admired Reed for the masterly manner in<lb/>
which he carried out his series of experiments, in a conclusive finale, at &ldquo;Camp<lb/>
Lazear&rdquo;, devoid of theatrics but emotional in the extreme. Some years ago, two<lb/>
Cuban doctors who knew both Finlay and Reed well informed me that their profess-<lb/>
ional status would be placed in jeopordy if they should champion the cause of<lb/>
Reed. Sad to state, it was all too true.</p>
<p>Back in 1939, when the film &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; was being exhibited in Cuba for the<lb/>
first time, I was invited by the Rotary Club of the City of Havana to a session at<lb/>
which the yellow fever episode and Finlay were to be discussed. Also an invited<lb/>
guest was Reed's detractor. It was the first time I had seen him. Only a few days<lb/>
before that occasion, I had received a letter from General Jefferson R. Kean where-<lb/>
in he favored me with his recollections of a banquet given in honor of Finlay, on<lb/>
December 22, 1900, to which General Wood, Major Reed and himself were invited. The<lb/>

speaker of the evening was Dr. Juan Guiteras, the noted yellow fever expert. He<lb/>
went on to state that Dr. Guiteras proclaimed the experiments at Camp Lazear as a<lb/>
joint Finlay-Reed achievement, with an equal division of the glory. At my request,<lb/>
the secretary of the Rotary Club made a running translation of General Kean's<lb/>
letter for the benefit of those not familiar with the English language. No sooner<lb/>
had he finished than Reed's detractor demanded the floor, vehemently denying Reed<lb/>
any part in the conquest of yellow fever. To link Reed's name with Finlay was a<lb/>
sacrilege, he said, completely ignoring General Kean's statements as copied from<lb/>
his diary. Reed and his Army Board, he said, merely confirmed what Finlay had<lb/>
already proved. Hatred for Reed was mirrored in his countenance.</p>
<p>Some years later, when Dr. Philip S. Hench of the Mayo Clinic happened to be<lb/>
at the Finlay Institute, he learned of the presence of Reed's detractor in the<lb/>
building. Expressing a desire to meet him, we were presented. He remembered me,<lb/>
of course, and knew I was one of Walter Reed's experimental subjects. Instinct-<lb/>
ively, I knew he did not like me and when we mentioned the name of Reed I noticed<lb/>
that same look of resentment he had displayed at the Rotary Club meeting. He<lb/>
referred to the experiments at Camp Lazear as &ldquo;the Finlay experiments&rdquo; but he<lb/>
refrained from launching into his customary diatribes against his memory, probably<lb/>
because of the composition of his audience of two.</p>
<pb n="23" id="f03712023"/>
<p><hi>Sheets 59 to 62, incl</hi>.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the venemous attacks of Reed's detractor filtered through to<lb/>
most of the Latin American republics. His corps of disciples saw to that, to the<lb/>
point of saturation, the ground having been well prepared in Havana through press-<lb/>
ure on the diplomatic representatives of the respective republics, using &ldquo;Yankee<lb/>
Imperialism&rdquo; as an always ready weapon. While his following in Cuba were compara-<lb/>
tively few to start with, they were excellent propagandists. Using communistic<lb/>
tactics and with nationalism as a cloak, they were able to silence the majority.<lb/>
One of them, however, resisted the anti-Reed defamers. He was Dr. Aristides<lb/>
Agramonte, the Cuban member of the four-man Army Board of Medical Officers headed<lb/>
by Major Reed. In the December, 1915, issue of &ldquo;THE SCIENTIFUC MONTHLY&rdquo; he wrote<lb/>
an article titled &ldquo;The Inside History of a Great Medical Discovery&rdquo;, from which I<lb/>
quote:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In 1881, Dr. Carlos Finlay, of Havana, in an exhaustive paper read<lb/>
before the Royal Academy of Sciences, gave as his opinion that yellow<lb/>
fever was spread by the bite of mosquitoes &lsquo;<hi>directly contaminated by<lb/>
stinging a yellow fever patient (or perhaps by contact with or feeding<lb/>
from his discharge)</hi>&rsquo;. This latter view he held as late as 1900, which,<lb/>
although correct in the main fact of the transmission of the germ from<lb/>
a patient to a susceptible person by the mosquito, the MODUS OPERANDI,<lb/>
as he conceived it, was entirely erroneous.</p>
<p>Dr. Finlay, unfortunately was unable to produce experimentally a<lb/>
single case of fever that could withstand the mildest criticism, so<lb/>
that at the time when the Army Board came to investigate the causes of<lb/>
yellow fever in Cuba, <hi>his theory</hi>, though practically the correct one,<lb/>
had been so much discredited, in a great measure by his own failures,<lb/>
that the best-known experts considered it as an ingenious, but wholly<lb/>
fanciful, one and many thought it a fit subject for <hi>humorous and sarcas-<lb/>
tic repartee</hi>. Finlay also believed, erroneously, that repeated bites of<lb/>
contaminated insects might protect against yellow fever and that the<lb/>
moquitoes were cabable of transmitting the germ to the next generation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Following publication of that article Dr. Agramonte became a target for the<lb/>
virulent attacks of Walter Reed's master-detractor and his handful of diehards.<lb/>
They branded him as a traitor to Cuba and to Finlay. At that time Dr. Agramonte<lb/>
was professor of bacteriology and experimental pathology in the University of<lb/>
Havana. Walter Reed's detractor and his aides continued to hound him in every<lb/>
possible manner, subtly endeavoring to discredit him with his own students, who<lb/>
upon graduation would be expected to join the anti-Reed clique. Outright ostra-<lb/>
cism was talked of but it did not prosper, cooler heads visioning an internation-<lb/>
al scandal in any such measure, but the campaign of persecution against Dr.<lb/>
Agramonte continued. When I arrived in Cuba in 1928, to reside here permanently,<lb/>
even Walter Reed's one loyal voice on the Cuban scene had weakened, as I sadly<lb/>
discovered. When I reminded him of the SCIENTIFIC MONTHLY article and his mature<lb/>
opinion therein set forth, he embarrasingly changed the subject. He, too, had<lb/>
succumbed to the inevitable. Today, Walter Reed lacks a single champion among<lb/>
Cuban medicos.</p>
<p>The Cuban medical fraternity have been methodical in their all-out claims for<lb/>
Finlay. Several years ago the &ldquo;Order of Carlos J. Finlay&rdquo; was founded by the Cuban<lb/>
Government, a decoration that has been judiciously awarded to outstanding figures<lb/>
in Cuba, Latin America and the United States, not necessarily to men of scientific<lb/>
merit but always with a view to convert the recipients of the honor into proselytes<lb/>
of the FINLAY-ONLY clan. The Finlay Order is graded from the Grand Cross &amp; Sash,<lb/>
Grand Officer, etc., etc., down the line, for bestowing according to the merits or<lb/>
prominence of those elected for the medal. I am probably one of the humblest of<lb/>
the Finlay medalists, conferred upon me in Washington, at the Cuban embassy, in<lb/>
1940, in the grade of Grand Officer, an honor which I did not seek but was pleased<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f03712024"/>
<hi>Sheets 59 to 62, incl.</hi><lb/>
to accept, naturally. Throughout the years, I have respected and honored the memory<lb/>
of that fine old gentleman, known in life as Doctor Carlos J. Finlay, linking his<lb/>
name with that of Walter Reed with whom I had a date in 1900 and who presented me<lb/>
with a Christmas gift in that year, in the form of yellow fever and immunity to<lb/>
that once dread disease.</p>
<p>How well the campaign of defamation against Reed is still bearing fruit was<lb/>
demonstrated in connection with the FOURTH INTERNATIONAL CONGRESSES OF TROPICAL<lb/>
MEDICINE AND MALARIA, at their meetings in Washington, D. C., in May, 1948, during<lb/>
which a &ldquo;Reed Commemoration Meeting&rdquo; was held on May 12th, to be followed on May<lb/>
20th by the unveiling of a Bust and Tablet for Walter Reed in the Hall of Fame of<lb/>
New York University, where a niche had been reserved for him many years ago. Both<lb/>
ceremonies drew protests from the Cuban medical bodies, registered through the<lb/>
Cuban delegates attending the Congresses, vigorously resenting the honors to be<lb/>
accorded to the memory of Reed, as well as the title of the program, which read<lb/>
as follows:<lb/>
&ldquo;Exercises to Commemorate the Demonstration by<lb/>
Walter Reed<lb/>
of the Mosquito Transmission of Yellow Fever&rdquo;</p>
<p>To avert an Inter-American incident a compromise was reached, the Cubans agree-<lb/>
ing to accept Reed as Finlay's collaborator. With this concession on the part of<lb/>
the Cubans it would appear that the 48-year-old controversy was amicably settled.<lb/>
Far from it. Walter Reed's detractors would accept no such verdict. Eleven days<lb/>
later there was published in BOHEMIA, a Cuban weekly news-magazine of wide circu-<lb/>
lation, a virulent article, authored by a Cuban doctor, under the following title:<lb/>
&ldquo;NI &lsquo;TEORIA&rsquo; FUE LA OBRA DE FINLAY,<lb/>
NI REED SU COLABORADOR&rdquo;<lb/>
(Finlay's Work was not a Theory, nor was Reed his Collaborator)<lb/>
The author immediately proceeds to strip Walter Reed of any part worth mention in<lb/>
the yellow fever drama, charging him with <hi>bad faith</hi> in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note&rdquo;<lb/>
read before the American Public Health Association, in Indianapolis, in October,<lb/>
1900. He refers to Reed's experiments at Camp Lazear as &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; and entirely<lb/>
unnecessary, flatly stating that the cases of Lazear, Carroll and Dean <hi>confirmed</hi><lb/>
what Finlay had already <hi>proved</hi>. With all due respect to the author, I happen to<lb/>
know that the skeptics out numbered the believers ONE THOUSAND to ONE at that time<lb/>
and were not convinced by those three cases, for the very good reason that the<lb/>
circumstances under which they were bitten and infected by yellow fever mosquitoes<lb/>
were more or less haphazard and therefore not acceptable from a scientific point of<lb/>
view. Following the conclusive series of experiments at Camp Lazear, the three<lb/>
cases in doubt were added to the conclusive or &ldquo;fool-proof&rdquo; series as &ldquo;mosquito-<lb/>
infected&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I am a living witness to the fact that there was nothing <hi>theatrical</hi> about the<lb/>
Camp Lazear experiments. They were emotional to a certain extent for the parti-<lb/>
cipants and the camp personnel guarding the isolated camp and taking care that entry<lb/>
to the camp was prohibited to all persons unless they were accompanied by Major<lb/>
Reed or other member of the Yellow Fever Board. The term &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; would infer<lb/>
that we had an audience at Camp Lazear. As a matter of history there were only<lb/>
actors and stage hands. Major Reed was not the manner of man to risk human lives<lb/>
for staged fame or personal prestige. The author of the &ldquo;BOHEMIA&rdquo; article denies<lb/>
Reed the right to be classed as a scientist because, as he puts it, he lacked a<lb/>
scientific background. One may wonder what he means by a &ldquo;scientific background&rdquo;.<lb/>
When Walter Reed came to Cuba in June, 1900, he was already a distinguished man,<lb/>
having headed another famous medical board which studied camp epidemics of typhoid<lb/>
fever in the Army during the Spanish-American War, advancing our knowledge of the<lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f03712025"/>
<hi>Sheets 59 to 62, incl.</hi><lb/>
spread of that disease in armies. He was also professor of pathology and bacteriology<lb/>
at the Army Medical School, and at the Columbian University in Washington. Evidently,<lb/>
this background was unknown to his &ldquo;BOHEMIA&rdquo; critic and, if known to him, he chose to<lb/>
ignore it.</p>
<p>This critic goes on to say that Reed was a salaried medical officer, obliged to<lb/>
obey orders of his superiors and that therefore he could not feel the emotions of the<lb/>
real scientist. He strongly infers that Reed was a mere automat and only carried out<lb/>
the experiments at the instance of General Leonard Wood, Military Governor of Cuba,<lb/>
a manifest deviation from the truth. True, he consulted General Wood, as he did other<lb/>
members of his own corps on duty in Cuba, but he was responsible only to General Geo.<lb/>
M. Sternberg, Surgeon General of the Army, whose instructions to him were broad and<lb/>
entirely discretionary. General Wood merely supplied the funds necessary for carrying<lb/>
out the experiments, including a bonus for each volunteer. Since General Wood was<lb/>
a medico before he became an officer of the line, it is needless to state that he was<lb/>
deeply interested in the proposed experiments, in a personal, rather than an official<lb/>
way. As Military Governor of Cuba, it was his obligation to foster and advance any<lb/>
steps tending to rid the Island of its centuries-old enemy, yellow fever. It should<lb/>
be remembered that General Wood was a captain in the medical corps of the Army at the<lb/>
outbreak of the war with Spain, when he was commissioned colonel of the volunteer<lb/>
&ldquo;Rough Riders&rdquo;, with Lieutenant-Colonel Theodore Roosevelt as second in command.</p>
<p>In conclusion, I want to make my own position clear. I accord equal honors to<lb/>
Carlos J. Finlay and Walter Reed. Their work in the field of medical science has<lb/>
entitled them to immortality. It was destined that the two should share the glory<lb/>
which is their common heritage, the conquest of yellow fever. Americans, I am sure,<lb/>
will continue to honor the memories of both. All they expect of the Cubans is to<lb/>
refrain from defaming Reed when they honor and glorify Finlay. If they choose not to<lb/>
mention Reed at all, good and well. That is their privilege. If, however, they<lb/>
should mention that illustrious name they should do so in a reverant manner, simulated,<lb/>
if you will, in order to do scientific justice to the memory of a man who contributed<lb/>
so much to the advancement of medical science and humanity - a man who died poor but<lb/>
left a legacy to posterity which was priceless. The fact that Finlay was born in<lb/>
Cuba and Reed in the United States of America has no bearing in this matter. Scient-<lb/>
ists belong to no country in particular, but to the entire world, accident of birth<lb/>
playing no part in their achievements. Whether Cubans like it or not, history will<lb/>
link the names of Finlay and Reed in a common accomplishment.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<pb n="26" id="f03712026"/>
<p>HOTEL<lb/>
VARADERO</p>
<p>International VARADERO, CUBA.</p>
<p><unclear><hi>Mrs S</hi></unclear> Have her sign<lb/>
P1 - Copies of orders etc - She has <unclear>Mr O She well would</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>or marsh</unclear><lb/>
P6 - <unclear>Fever chart? 86 her</unclear> copy. <unclear>original U of Va</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Any of book.</unclear> (Kelly; See Document etc). To whom?<lb/>
<unclear>Yes. Mr O'sh.</unclear></p>
<p>C1<lb/>
B3</p>
<p>Hoteles International, S. A., Wil am Liebow, President</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
