<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03714003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Addresses concerning yellow fever work, [by Philip Showalter Hench?], [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03714003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03714003</idno>
<title>Addresses concerning yellow fever work, [by Philip Showalter Hench?], [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench?] lists names and addresses of persons connected with his work on the history of the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Addresses concerning yellow fever work, [by Philip Showalter Hench?], [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03714003"/>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>Addresses Concerning Yellow Fever Work</hi></head>
<item>A.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. A. D. Albertini, Director of the Finlay Institute, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Dr. Ignacio Alvare, 9 No. 304, Vedado, Havana.</item>
<item>Mr. J. H. Andrus,, 805 Cooper Street, Camden, N. J.</item>
<item>Dr. Eduardo Angles, #19 General Lee Street, Marianao, Havana.</item>
<item>Dr. Donald B. Armstrong, Third Vice-President, Metropolitan Life Insurance Co., New York City</item>
<item>Col. Ash (or Lt. Col. V. H. Cornell) Curator, Army Medical Museum, Washington, D. C.</item>
</list></item>
<item>B.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mr. J. Christian Bay, Librarian, John Crerar Library, Chicago, Ill.</item>
<item>Dr. Manuel Perez Beato, San Marino, Est #112, Vibora, Havana.</item>
<item>Mr. Arthur Bevan, Director U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, Forest Service, Tropical Forest<lb/>
Experimental Station, Rio Piedras, Puerto Rico.</item>
<item>Mrs. W. D. Briggs, 106 The Uplands, Berkeley, Cal. (Lazear's daughter)</item>
<item>Mr. John R. Bullard, St. Augustine, Florida.</item>
</list></item>
<item>C.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Senorita Lidia Cabrera, 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana (Rojas ward)</item>
<item>Family of Maj. James Carroll, c/o H. V. Stirling, Director of Finance, Veterans'<lb/>
Administration, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Dr. Juan D. Castro, Las Animas Hospital, Havana.</item>
<item>Mr. Harry Clemons, Librarian, Alderman Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</item>
<item>Dr. Robert P. Cooke, Lexington-Rockbridge Health Dept., Lexington, Va.</item>
</list></item>
<item>D.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Major H. A. Davis, Army Medical Museum, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Mr. H. C. Dobba, Pan American Airways, Miami, Florida.</item>
<item>Dr. Francisco Dominguez, Guiterrez Y Mendoza, Reparto San Martin, Marianao, Havana.</item>
<item>Dr. H. H. Donnally, 1612 I Street, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>(Eye)</item>
</list></item>
<item>E.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Capt. Thomas M. England, 1715 East Long Street, Columbus, Ohio.</item>
</list></item>
<item>F.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Carlos E. Finlay, Linea Numero 710, Vedado, Havana.</item>
<item>Miss Mary Fishback, Reference Dept., Indianapolis Public Library, Indianapolis.</item>
</list></item>
<item>G.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mrs. James O. Gawne, 2540 Massachusetts Ave., Washington, D. C. (Lazear's cousin)</item>
</list></item>
<item>H.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Miss Grace T. Hallock, Welfare Division, Metropolitan Life Insurance Co, New York City.</item>
<item>Mr. James L. Hanberry, 61 Summers Ave., Orangeburg, South Carolina.</item>
<item>Mrs. Polly Damrosch Howard, 157 East 82 St., New York City.</item>
</list></item>
<item>I.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Gen. Merritt W. Ireland, 1870 Wyoming Avenue, N. W., Washington, D. C.</item>
</list></item>
<item>J.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Capt. L. W. Johnson, Medical Corps, U. S. Navy, Mobile Base Hospital #1, Guantanamo Bay,<lb/>
Cuba (Magath's friend).</item>
<item>Dr. H. E. Jordan, Dean of Dept. of Medicine, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</item>
</list></item>
<item>K.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Gen. Jefferson R. Kean, 2804 N Street, N. W., Georgetown, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Mr. George Kellogg, 257 Cornelison Ave., Jersey City, N. J.</item>
<item>Dr. Howard A. Kelly, Library, 1406 Eutaw Place, Baltimore, Md.</item>
<item>Mr. John R. Kissinger, Route #8, Huntington, Indiana.</item>
</list></item>
<pb n="2" id="f03714004"/>
<item>2</item>
<item>L.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Guierllermo Lage, Ass't Director, Finlay Institute, Havana.</item>
<item>Mrs. Jesse W. Lazear, 116 East Padre Street, Santa Barbara, Cal.</item>
<item>Mr. John Lazear, 922 South Negley Avenue, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. John M. Lazear (cousin), 3125 Preble Ave., Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. William Huston Lazear (son), 1325 Fifteenth Street, Sacramento, Cal.</item>
<item>Mr. Charles Lhotka, Dept. of Documents, Public Library, Chicago, Ill.</item>
<item>Senorita Julia Lomas (niece of Mrs. Rojas), 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana.</item>
</list></item>
<item>M.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Senor Adrian Macia, Manzana de Gomez 325, Havana.</item>
<item>Mr. John R. Mason, Librarian, George Washington University, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Senor Luis Rudolf Miranda, 20 General Lee Street, Marianao, Havana.</item>
<item>Mr. John J. Moran, Sunoco Oil Co., Avenida Menocal 455, Havana.</item>
<item>Dr. Juan De Moya, Havana, Cuba.</item>
</list></item>
<item>N.</item>
<item>O.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mrs. Charles P. Orr (Lazear's cousin), 6101 Howe Street, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
</list></item>
<item>P.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mr. H. S. Parsons, Periodical Division, Congressional Library, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Miss Elizabeth Peabody, Dept. of Biology, Wilson College, Chambersburg, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. James E. Peabody, 281 Lowell Ave., Newtonville, Mass.</item>
<item>Mr. J. Howard Pew, Sun Oil Building, 1608 Walnut Street, Philadelphia, Pa.</item>
<item>Mrs. R. Hart Phillips, Manzana de Gomez 533, Havana.</item>
<item>Dr. Alva Pinto, Omaha, Neb., 1603 Farnam Street.</item>
<item>Mr. Luis Pogolotti, Calle Cuba 105, Havana</item>
</list></item>
<item>Q.</item>
<item>R.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>His Excellency Dr. Domingo F. Ramos, Minister of Defense, Havana.</item>
<item>Dr. Alberto Recio, Ave. de la Independencia Y Montoro, Havana.</item>
<item>Mrs. Walter Reed (wife), Blue Ridge Summit, Pa. (69 miles from Washington, D. C.)</item>
<item>Mrs. Blossom Reed (daughter), Blue Ridge Summit, Pa.</item>
<item>Gen. Walter L. Reed (son), 2810 Thirty-Sixth Place, N. W., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez-Leon (daughter), Calle 15, No. 311, Vedado, Havana.</item>
<item>Senorita Teresa Rojas (daughter), 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana.</item>
<item>Senora Teresa Loma, Vde. de Rojas, 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana.</item>
</list></item>
<item>S.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer, The Rockefeller Foundation, 49 West 49th St., New York City.</item>
<item>Miss Francis B. Seth, 4511 Windsor Mill Road, Woodlawn, Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
(Lazear's cousin)</item>
<item>Col. J. F. Siler, 3434 34 Place, N. W., Washington, D. C. (suggested by Gen. Reed)</item>
<item>Senor Angel Suarez-Solis, 102 Real Street, Marianao, Havana.</item>
</list></item>
<item>T.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mr. John R. Taylor, 548 Grand Ave., Upper Darby, Pa. (clerk 1901 at Los Animas,<lb/>
volunteer for Guiteras)</item>
<item>Mr. Alton P. <unclear>Tizdel,</unclear>, Supt. of Documents, U. S. Gov't Printing Office, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Gen. Albert E. Truby, 145 Laurel Street, San Francisco, Cal.</item>
</list></item>
<item>U.</item>
<item>V.</item>
<pb n="3" id="f03714005"/>
<item>3</item>
<item>W.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mr. Royal S. Webster, Divisional Engineer, Ferrocarriles Unidos de la Havana,<lb/>
Edificio Bacardi 213, Havana.</item>
<item>Mr. Clyde L. West, Riverdale, Md. (volunteer).</item>
<item>Miss Helen Wheeler, Welch Medical Library, Johns Hopkins University, 1900 East Monument St.,<lb/>
Baltimore, Md.</item>
<item>Col. John M. Willis, Acting Commandant, Medical Field Service School, Carlisle Barracks,<lb/>
Carlisle, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. D. J. Withington, John Wyett &amp; Bro., 1600 Arch St. Philadelphia, Pa.</item>
<item>Miss Frances Wood, Grand Rapids Public Library, Grand Rapids, Michigan.</item>
</list></item>
<item>Y.</item>
<item>Z.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Senor Julian Zunzunegui, Varona Suarez St., Marianao, Havana.</item>
</list></item></list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
