<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03714001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">List of persons who received copies of Conquerors of Yellow Fever, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03714001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03714001</idno>
<title>List of persons who received copies of Conquerors of Yellow Fever, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This list records names and addresses of persons in the United States and Cuba who received copies of "Conquerors of Yellow Fever."</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>List of persons who received copies of Conquerors of Yellow Fever, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03714001"/>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head>COPIES OF &ldquo;CONQUERORS OF YELLOW FEVER&rdquo; SENT TO</head>
<item>Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer, The Rockefeller Foundation, 49 W. 49 St. N.Y.</item>
<item>Anna M. Sexton, Librarian, State of N.Y. Dept. of Health, Albany, N. Y.</item>
<item>Dr. Carl Tripoli, 1405 Union Building, New Orleans, La.</item>
<item>Dr. Rudolph Matas, 3523 Prytania St., New Orleans, La.</item>
<item>Dr. Edw. Rynearson, Rochester.</item>
<item>Dr. H.K. Gray, Rochester.</item>
<item>Haines</item>
<item>12 Mr. and Mrs. John R. Kissinger, Huntington, Ind.</item>
<item>2 Miss Helen Wheeler, Welch Medical Library, 1900 E. Monument St., Baltimore, Md.</item>
<item>2 Miss Elizabeth Peabody, Wilson College, Chambersburg, Pa.</item>
<item>6 Dr. James E. Peabody, 281 Lowell Ave., Newtonville, Mass.</item>
<item>20 Gen. Jefferson R. Kean, 2804 &ldquo;N&rdquo; St. N.W., Washington, D.C.</item>
<item>20 Gen. A. E. Truby, 145 Laurel Street, San Francisco, California.</item>
<item>3 Mrs. Dorothy M. Lake, Assistant in Education, Am. Museum of Nat. Hist., N.Y.</item>
<item>Alfred Danziger, Carondelet Bldg, New Orleans, La.</item>
<item>Robert J. Usher, Librarian, Howard-Tilton Memorial Lib., Tulane Univ., New Orleans, La.</item>
<item>12 Mrs. Mabel H. Lazear, 116 E. Padre St., Santa Barbara, Calif.</item>
<item>Dr. Walter Simpson, 134 Apple Street, Dayton, Ohio</item>
<item>20 General Merritt W. Ireland, 1870 Wyoming Avenue, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>10 General W. L. Reed, 2810 Thirty-sixth Place, N.W., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>10 Mrs. Walter Reed, Blue Ridge Summit, Pennsylvania.</item>
<item>10 Mrs. Blossom Reed, c/o General W.L. Reed, 2810 Thirty-sixth Place, N.W., Washington, D.C</item>
<item>Archie Woods, 14 Wall Street, New York City</item>
<item>Cap.t. Charles S. Marsh, Corps of Engineers, Engineer Reproduction Plant, The<lb/>
Army War College, Washington, D.C.</item>
<item>Dr. Pedro Machado de Gardenas, Jefe de Redaccion y Administrador, Revista de la<lb/>
Sanidad Militar, Ciudad Militar, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Mr. James F. Waters, The Court of Missing Heirs Radio Program, 572 Madison Ave.,<lb/>
New York City.</item>
<item>3 Mr. John R. Bullard, P.O. Box 59, St. Augustine, Florida</item>
<item>Mrs. Edward J. Dimock, Enderby, Manhasset, Long Island, New York</item>
<item>6 Mr. J. H. Andrus, 805 Cooper St., Camden, N.J.</item>
<item>Mr. George I. H. Carroll, 2814 Rhode Island Avenue N.E., Washington, D.C.</item>
<item>12 Mr. Robert P. Cooke, Lexington-Rockbridge Health Dept., Lexington, Va.</item>
<item>Dr. C. E. Finlay, Linea Numero 710, Vedado, Habana, Cuba</item>
<item>Dr. A. S. Pinto, 1229 First National Bank Bldg., Omaha, Nebraska.</item>
<item>2 His Excellency, Dr. Domingo F. Ramos, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>12 Senora Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>2 Dr. Alberto Recio, Paseo de Carlos III -1117, Habana, Cuba.</item>
<item>6 Dr. J. F. Rodriguez Perez, Director de la Seccion de Publicaciones, Cientificas<lb/>
y Biblioteca, Instituto Finlay, Habana, Cuba</item>
<item>Dr. A. D. Albertini, Director of the Finlay Institute, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>2 Miss Blanca Malaret, Secretary to Dr. Saladrigas, Finlay Institute, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>6 Mr. Luis Pogolotti, Cuba 105, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>12 Mr. John J. Moran, Sunoco Oil Co., Avenida Menocal 455, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>6 Senor Adrian Macia, Manzana de Gomez 325, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Dr. Ignacio Alvare, Calle 9, No. 304, Vedado, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Dr. Francisco Dominguez, Guiteviez y Mendoza, Reparto San Martin, Marianao, Havana</item>
<item>Capt. Thomas M. England, 1715 East Long St., Columbus, Ohio.</item>
<item>Mr. James L. Hanberry, 61 Summers Ave., Orangeburg, South Carolina.</item>
<item>Mr. Clyde L. West, Riverdale, Md.</item>
<item>Miss Frances B. Seth, 4511 Windsor Mill Road, Woodlawn, Baltimore, Md.</item>
<item>Mrs. James O. Gawne, 2540 Massachusetts Ave., Washington, D.C.</item>
<item>Mrs. Charles P. Orr, 6101 Howe Street, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. William H. Lazear, 1325 Fifteenth Street, Sacramento, California.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f03714002"/>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>Miss Audrey Davis, Secretary to Dr. Howard A. Kelly, 1406 Eutaw Place, Baltimore, Md.</item>
<item>Mr. John Lazear, 922 South Negley Ave., Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. William D. Postell, Agramonte Memorial Library, Medical Center, Louisiana State<lb/>
University, New Orleans, La.</item>
<item>His Excellency, Dr. Domingo F. Ramos, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Mr. W. B. Stewart, Medical Artist, Louisiana State University, Med. Center, New Orleans.</item>
<item>Mr. John R. Taylor, 548 Grand Ave., Upper Darby, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. Royal S. Webster, Divisional Engineer, Ferrocarriles Unidos de la Habana,<lb/>
Edificio Bacardi 23, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Frances Wood, The Grand Rapids Public Library, Grand Rapids, Michigan.</item>
<item>Dr. L. G. Rowntree, 1520 Spruce St., Philadelphia, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. J. D. Heard, 121 University Place, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. Van Adams, Superintendent, The Jewish Hospital, Cincinnati, Ohio.</item>
<item>Dr. Wm. Murphy, 311 Beacon St., Boston, Mass.</item>
<item>Dr. Georgine Maria Luden, 1006 St. Charles Street, Victoria, B.C.</item>
<item>Dr. George R. Minot, Thorndike Memorial Laboratory, Boston City Hospital, Boston, Mass.</item>
<item>Dr. A. R. Shands, Alfred I. duPont Institute, Wilmington, Del.</item>
<item>Dr. Loring T. Swaim, 372 Marlborough St., Boston, Mass.</item>
<item>Dr. W. F. Wilson, Lake City, Minn.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
