<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03715007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">List of invitees [to Hench's honorary degree ceremony], [1940]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03715007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-00-00">[1940]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03715007</idno>
<title>List of invitees [to Hench's honorary degree ceremony], [1940]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This list records Hench's friends and relatives who are to be invited to the ceremony awarding him an honorary Washington and Jefferson College degree.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1940-00-00">
<head>List of invitees [to Hench's honorary degree ceremony], [1940]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03715007"/>
<p>Friends and relatives of Dr. Hench, to whom if possible, we would like to have<lb/>
invitations sent:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>RELATIVES:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mrs. J. B. Hench, 5524 Kentucky Avenue, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. A. L. Hench, East Jefferson Street, Charlottesville, Virginia.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Samuel N. Hench, Marlinton, West Virginia.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Norman M. Hench, 14 West Elm Street, Apt. 1403, Chicago, Ill.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. J. B. Ramsey, 219 Harvard Street, Brookline, Mass.</item>
<item>Mrs. H. P. Davis and family, 1221 Franklin Avenue, (Wilkinsburg) Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. George C. Hench, Elkhart, Indiana.</item>
<item>Mrs. J. H. Kahler, 527 Fourth Street, S.W., Rochester, Minn.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. J. E. Crewe, <unclear>801</unclear> Third St. S.W.</item>
</list></item>
<item>ASSOCIATES IN ROCHESTER:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. and Mrs. A. M. Snell, 709 Ninth Avenue. S. W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. E. H. Rynearson, Sunnyslopes</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. E. V. Allen, 427 Fifth Avenue S. W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. John Berkman, 12th Avenue S. W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Philip W. Brown, 729 Sixth Street, S. W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Winchell McK. Craig, 828 Eighth St. S.W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Howard K. Gray, College Apartments.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Charles H. Slocumb, 723 Ninth Street S.W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. E. F. Rosenberg, 319 Fifth Avenue S. W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Haddow M. Keith, 814 Fifth Street S. W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. A. H. Logan, 503 Ninth Avenue S. W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Andrew <unclear>Rivers</unclear>, 819 Fourth St. S. W.</item>
<item>Sister M. Pantaleon, St. Mary's Hospital</item>
</list></item>
<item>FRIENDS AND FORMER ASSOCIATES:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Dwight L. Wilbur, 490 Post Street, San Francisco, Cal.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Clifford J. Barborka, 700 N. Michigan Ave., Chicago, Ill.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Winfield L. Butsch, 333 Linwood Ave., Buffalo, N. Y.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Louis S. Faust, 1104 Republic Building, Denver, Col.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Frank Edmundson, 5317 Fifth Avenue, Pittsburg, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. E. B. Rentschler, 239 N. Fifth St., Reading, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Theodore R. Bliss, 428 Ohio Building, Akron, Ohio.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Lucius Seiberling, 97 Mayfield Avenue, Akron, Ohio.</item>
<item>Dr. John Garvin, Jenkins Arcade, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. William A. Bradshaw, 121 University Place, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. W. W. G. Maclachlan, Medical Arts Bldg., Fifth Ave., Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Alex H. Colwell, 121 University Place, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Grover C. Weil, 5867 Wilkins Ave., Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Alexander McEwen, Northern Pacific Beneficial Assn. Hosp., St. Paul,<lb/>
Minn.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Walter Kirch, 5301 Grand Ave., <unclear>Doz Noines</unclear>, Iowa</item>
<item>Mr. William McConahey, 3366 Park Avenue, Indianapolis, Indiana.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. William L. Church, 5206 Ellsworth Ave., Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mrs. William L. McEwen, 5534 Kentucky Ave., Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f03715008"/>
<item>FRIENDS AND FORMER ASSOCIATES, Continued:</item>
<item>Mr. W. S. Johnston, 709 South Negley Avenue, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. George Colvin, 1080 Chestnut Street, Coraopolis, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. S. L. Tone, 5305 Westminster Place, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. W. Z. Morrison, 746 Quinby Avenue, Wooster, Ohio.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Stuart Swenson, 5611 Howe Street, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mrs. Rose Rynearson, 5620 Howe Street, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Albert Kennedy Rowswell, 906 Bessemer Bldg., Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. George Arnett, River Road, Yardley, Pa.</item>
<item>Miss Mary C. Driscoll, Reddick Apts., 2256 Cambridge St., Los Angeles, Cal.</item>
<item>Mrs. Marian Troost, The Plaze Apts., Mankato, Minn.</item>
<item>Mrs. Charles H. Mayo, The Cottage, Mayowood, Rochester, Minn.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Bart Stewart,</item>
<item>Mrs. Nora Guthrie, The Damon Hotel, Rochester, Minn.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Karnahan Sciberling, The Farm, Northfield, Ohio.</item>
<item>Mrs. Frank Gooding, 513 Third Street S. W., Rochester, Minn.</item>
<item>Miss Helen C. Mang, Pembridge, Evanston, Illinois.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. V. C. Adams, City Hospital, Springfield, Ohio.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. William H. Von Lackum, Manhasset, New York.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Ray Bush, Gaylord, Minnesota.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. B. C. Stevens, Heather Drive, Mahopac, N.Y.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Hugh Thompkins, Asbury Park, N. J.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. A. L. Roberts, 1115 Seventh St. S. W.</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Walter A. Groves, 174 Lismore Ave., Glenside, Pa.</item>
<item>Mrs. A. L. Hench, 309 Twenty-eighth St., Charleston, W. Va.</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. John MacNab, Hotel Prince, Bismarck, N. D.</item>
<item>Mr. Robert MacNab, Jr., Baxter Hotel, Bozeman, Montana</item>
<item>Dr. and Mrs. Walter Simpson, 247 Blossom Heath Road, Dayton, Ohio</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Archic Woods, 97 Captains Lane, Rye, New York.</item>
<item>Dr. Georgine M. Luden and Miss Betty Fitzgibbon, 1006 St. Charles Street,<lb/>
Victoria, British Columbia, Canada.</item>
<item>Senor Luis Pogolotti, Cuba 3, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Senora Estella Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, 311 Calle 15 entre H y I, Vedado,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Senora Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana, Cuba.</item>
</list></item></list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
