<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03804008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">List of Yellow Fever Correspondents, [by Philip Showalter Hench?], [February 1941]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03804008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-02-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-02-00">[February 1941]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03804008</idno>
<title>List of Yellow Fever Correspondents, [by Philip Showalter Hench?], [February 1941]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench's?] list of yellow fever correspondents records the names and addresses of Americans and Cubans with whom he corresponded for his yellow fever research.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-02-00">
<head>List of Yellow Fever Correspondents, [by Philip Showalter Hench?], [February 1941]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03804008"/>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head>YELLOW FEVER ADDRESSES</head>
<item>A<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. A. D. Albertini, Director of the Finlay Institute, Havana, Cuba (dead)</item>
<item>Dr. Ignacio Alvare, 9 No. 304, Vedado, Havana</item>
<item>Mrs. Jessie Daniel Ames, Wrens Nest, Tryon, North Carolina</item>
<item>Mr. J. H. Andrus, 805 Cooper street, Camden, New Jersey (dead)</item>
<item>Dr. Jose R. Andreu, Calzada Columbia, Habana, Cuba</item>
<item>Dr. Eduardo Angles, #19 General Lee Street, Marianao, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>Hortensia Aranguren, Viuda de Guiteras (sister-in-law) Maceo #48, Matanzas, Cuba</item>
<item>Eugenio de Armas, Superintendente, City Hall, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>Dr. Donald B. Armstrong, Third Vice Pres., Metropolitan Life Ins. Co., New York City</item>
<item>Colonel Ash (or Lt. Col. V. H. Cornell) Curator Army Medica. Museum, Wash., D. C.</item>
<item>Dr. David L. Andrus, 805 Cooper Street, Camden, N.J.</item>
</list></item>
<item>B.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mr. J. Christian Bay, Librarian, John Crerar Library, Chicago, Illinois</item>
<item>Dr. Manuel Perez Beato, San Marino, Est #112, Vibora, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>Dr. Antonio Perez Benitoa, Quinta Avenue Number 8, Miramar, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>Mr. Arthur Bevan, Director, U.S. Dept. of Agric. Forest Service, Tropical Forest<lb/>
Forest Experimental Station, Rio Piedras, Puerto Rico</item>
<item>Mrs. W. D. Briggs, 106 The Uplands, Berkeley, California (Lazear's daughter)</item>
<item>Mr. Walter M. Briggs, 16 Green Lane, <unclear>Monteceto</unclear>, Santa Barbara, California</item>
<item>Mr. John R. Bullard, St. Augustine, Florida (dead)</item>
</list></item>
<item>c.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Felipe Carbonell, San Lazaro 413, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>Senorita Lidia Cabrera, 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana (Rojas ward)</item>
<item>Family of Maj. James Carroll, c/o H. V. Stirling, Direc. of Finance, V.A., Wash. D. C.</item>
<item>Dr. Juan D. Castro, Las Animas Hospital, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>Mr. Harry Clemons, Librarian, Alderman Library, Univ. of Va., Charlottesville, Va.</item>
<item>Honorato Colete, Habana 254, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>Dr. Robert P. Cooke, Lexington-Rockbridge Health Department, Lexington, Va. - dead</item>
<item>Dean Cornwell, Gainsborough Studios, 222 Central Park South, New York City</item>
<item>George S. H. Carroll, 2814 Rhode Island Ave., N.E., Washington, D. C. - dead</item>
</list></item>
<item>D.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Major H. A. Davis, Army Medical Museum, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Mr. H. C. Dobbs, Pan American Airways, Miami, Florida</item>
<item>Dr. Francisco Dominguez, Guiterrez Y Mendoza, Reparto San Martin, Marianao, Havana</item>
<item>Aldo E. Diaz (photographer) Tel A 7820 or A 5-2771</item>
<item>Dr. H. H. Donnally, 1612 Eye Street, Washington, D. C.</item>
</list></item>
<item>E.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Capt. Thomas M. England, 1715 East Long Street, Columbus, Ohio (dead)</item>
<item>His Excellency, Senor Raul de Cardenas, Vice Pres. of the Repub. of Cuba, Havana</item>
</list></item>
<item>F.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Fernando Lopez Fernandez, El Director del Hospital &ldquo;Las Animas&rdquo;, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>Senor Figueroa, American Photo Company, Neptuno 255, Havana (old photos)</item>
<item>Dr. Carlos E. Finlay, Linea Numero 710, Vedado, Havana (dead)</item>
<item>Mr. Frank Finlay, Calle 2 #6, Guna 5, Vedado, Havana</item>
<item>Miss Mary Fishback, Reference Dept, Indianapolis Public Library, Indianapolis</item>
<item>Mrs. Mary Alice Forbes, 5450 West Walton Street, Chicago, Ill. (Grand-daughter, MonaRose</item>
</list></item>
<item>G.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f03804009"/>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>g.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mrs. James O. Gawne, 2439 Tracy Place, Washington, D. C. (Lazear's cousin)</item>
<item>Dr. Gilbert Grosvenor, National Geographic Soc., 16 and M Streets, N.W., Wash., D.C.</item>
<item>Lorenzo Guerra (custodian) National Academy of Sciences, Cuba 460, Havana</item>
</list></item>
<item>H.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Miss Grace T. Hallock, Welfare Div., Metropolitan Life Ins. Col, New York City.</item>
<item>Leo Hamburg (air photos) Miami, Florida</item>
<item>Mr. James L. Hanberry, 591 Summers Avenue, Orangeburg, South Carolina</item>
<item>Mrs. Polly Damrosch Howard, 157 East 82nd Street, New York</item>
<item>Miss Lucy Howard, 45 Pondfield Road, Bronxville, New York</item>
</list></item>
<item>I.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mrs. Hans W. Ireland, Treasurer, American Security and Trust, Co., Wash., D. C.</item>
<item>Gen. Merritt W. Ireland, 1870 Wyoming Avenue, N. W. Washington, D. C.-dead</item>
</list></item>
<item>J.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Captain L. W. Johnson, Medical Corps, U.S. Navy, Mobile Base Hosp. #1, Guantanamo Bay,<lb/>
Cuba (Magath's friend)</item>
<item>Dr. H. E. Jordan, Dean of Dept. of Med., University of Va., Charlottesville, Va.</item>
</list></item>
<item>K.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item><del>Gen.</del><add><unclear>Mrs</unclear></add> Jefferson R. Kean, 2804 N Street, N. W., Georgetown, Washington, D. C. (dead)</item>
<item>Mr. George Kellogg, 41 E. 42nd Street, New York City</item>
<item>Dr. Howard A. Kelly, Library, 1406 Eutaw Place, Baltimore, Maryland (dead)</item>
<item>Mr. John R. Kissinger, Route #8, Huntington, Indiana (dead)</item>
</list></item>
<item>L.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Guierllermo Lage, Ass't Director, Finlay Institute, Havana</item>
<item>Mr. Gust E. Lambert, <del><unclear></unclear></del> 17092 Lincoln Street<unclear>,</unclear><lb/>
Hazel Crest,<lb/>
Ill</item>
<item>Mrs. Jesse W. Lazear, 116 East Padre St., Santa Barbara, California (dead)</item>
<item>Mr. John M. Lazear (cousin) 3125 Preble Avenue, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. John M. Lazear, 922 South Negley Avenue, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. William Houston Lazear (son), P. O. Box 812 Santa Barbara, California</item>
<item>Mr. Charles Lhotka, Dept. of Documents, Public Library, Chicago, Illinois</item>
<item>Senorita Julia Lomas (niece of Mrs. Rojas), 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana, Cuba</item>
<item>General Albert E. Love, 2709 Wisconsin Avenue, N. W., Washington, D. C.</item>
</list></item>
<item>M.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Senor Adrian Macia, Manzana de Gomez 325, Havana</item>
<item>Dr. John T. MacDonald, Physician to Pan-American Airways, Miami, Florida</item>
<item>Dr. Maximo Martinez, Calle M. Landa #82, Pinar del Rio, Cuba</item>
<item>Mr. John R. Mason, Librarian, George Washington Univ., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Major Gen. Frank R. McCoy, 1633 31st Street, N. W., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Dr. Jose Carlos Millar, Observatorio Nacional, Caca Blanca, Havana</item>
<item>Senor Luis Rudolf Miranda, 20 General Lee Street, Marianao, Havana</item>
<item>Mr. John J. Moran, Calle 25, #804, entre B y C, Apartment 3, Vedado, Havana (deceased)</item>
<item>Mrs. Will Morris, 515 Adams Street, New Orleans, Louisiana (Dr. Ames' sister)</item>
<item>Dr. Juan de Moya, Havana, Cuba</item>
</list></item>
<pb n="3" id="f03804010"/>
<item>3.</item>
<item>N.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Pedro Nogueira, (home) Marti 219, Marianao, Cuba</item>
</list></item>
<item>O.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mrs. Charles P. Orr (Lazear's cousin) 6101 Howe Street, Pittsburgh, Pa.</item>
</list></item>
<item>P.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mr. H. S. Parsons, Periodical Division, Congressional Library, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Miss Elizabeth Peabody, Depart. of Biology, Wilson College, Chambersburg, Pa.</item>
<item>Dr. James E. Peabody, 75 Linden Street, Brattleboro, Vermont</item>
<item>Dr. Peraza, 817 Neptuno, (over Municipal Library) Havana</item>
<item>Mr. J. Howard Pew, Sun Oil Building 1608 Walnut Street, Philadelphia, Pa.</item>
<item>Mrs. R. Hart Phillips, Manzana de Gomez 533, Havana</item>
<item>Dr. Alva Pinto, 1603 Farnam Street, Omaha, Nebraska (dead)</item>
<item>Mr. Luis Pogolotti, Calle Cuba 105, Havana (dead)</item>
<item>Dr. Jose A. Presno, Presidente de la Academia de Cuncias de la Habana, Cuba 460, Havana</item>
<item>Jacobo de Playaola, Secretario de la Administracion Municipal de la Habana (city hall)</item>
</list></item>
<item>Q.</item>
<item>R.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>His Excellency Dr. Domingo F. <unclear>Ramos</unclear>, Minister of Defense, Havana</item>
<item>Colonel Randin,</item>
<item>Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, Calle K 254, Vedado, Havana</item>
<item>Dr. Jose A. Rodriguez, Librarian, Finlay Institute, Infanta y Zaldo, Havana</item>
<item>Senorita Maria Teresa Rojas, Quinta San Jose, Calle Real, Quemados de Marianao</item>
<item>Dr. Alberto Recio, Calle Carlos III, #1117, <unclear>,</unclear> Havana (Minister de Salubridad)</item>
<item>Mrs. Walter Reed (wife), Blue Ridge Summit, Pa. (69 miles from Wash., D. C.)</item>
<item>Mrs. Blossom Reed (daughter) Blue Ridge Summit, Pa.</item>
<item>Gen. Walter L. Reed (son) 2810 Thirty-Sixth Place, N. W., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Senora Terese Loma, Vde. de Rojas, 207 Calle 17, Vedado, Havana.</item>
</list></item>
<item>S.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer, Department of State, Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Miss Frances B. Seth, 4511 Windsor Mill Road, Woodlawn, Baltimore, Md. (Lazear's cousin)</item>
<item>Col. J. F. Siler, 2220 - 20th Street N.W. Wash., D. C. (Suggested by Gen. Reed)</item>
<item>Senor Angel Suarez Solis, 102 Real Street, Marianao, Havana</item>
<item>Admiral E. R. Stitt, 1625 R Street, N. W., Washington 9, D. C.</item>
<item>Swan's Book Store, Obispo 255, Havana (old photos)</item>
</list></item>
<item>T.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mr. John R. Taylor, 548 Grand Ave., Upper Darby, Pa. (clerk at Los Animas, 1901,<lb/>
volunteer for Guiteras)</item>
<item>Mr. Alton P. Tisdel, Supt. of Documents, U. S. Gov't. Printing Office, Wash., D. C.</item>
<item>Dr. Arturo de la Torre, Alameda 200, Pinar del Rio, Cuba</item>
<item>Gen. Albert E. Truby, 145 Laurel Street, San Francisco, California</item>
</list></item>
<item>U.</item>
<item>V.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Esteban Valderrama, Manzana de Gomez 266, Havana</item>
</list></item>
<pb n="4" id="f03804011"/>
<item>4.</item>
<item>W.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mr. Royal S. Webster, Ingeniro Jefe, Estacion Central Habana</item>
<item>Mr. Clyde L. West, Hiverdale, Maryland (volunteer)</item>
<item>Miss Helen Wheeler, Welch Medical Library, Johns Hopkins Univ. 1900 E. Monument<lb/>
Street, Baltimore, Maryland.</item>
<item>Col. John M. Willis, Acting Commandant, Medical Field Service School, Carlisle<lb/>
Barracks, Carlisle, Pa.</item>
<item>Mr. D. J. Withington, John Wyett and Bro., 1600 Arch Street, Philadelphia, Pa.</item>
<item>Gen. Eric Fisher Wood, R. D. 1, <unclear>Bedford</unclear>, Pa.</item>
<item>Miss Frances Wood, Grand Rapids Public Library, Grand Rapids, Michigan</item>
<item>Miss Laura Wood (Mrs. Roper now) 2151 California St., N. W. Washington, D. C.</item>
</list></item>
<item>X.</item>
<item>Y.</item>
<item>Z.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Senor Julian Zunzunegui, Varona Suarex Street, Marianao, Havana</item>
</list></item>
</list></p>
<p>
<table rows="4" cols="1">
<row>
<cell>Ministerio de Salubridad y A. Social<lb/>
Seccion de Ingenieria y Arquitectura Janitaria</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Negociado de Arquitectura<lb/>
ANTEPROYECTO de PARQUE en el ANTIGUO</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>&ldquo;CAMPAMENTO LAZEAR&rdquo;<lb/>
Pogolotti - Marianao</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>- <unclear>Arc</unclear> 1951 -</cell></row></table></p>
<pb n="5" id="f03804012"/>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head><hi>BOARD MEMBERS OF ASSOCIATION</hi></head>
<item>Dr. Gilbert Grosvenor, National Geographic Sec., 16 and M Street, N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Mr. Hans W. Ireland, Treasurer, American Security and Trust Co., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>General M. W. Ireland, 1870 Wyoming Ave., N. W., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>General J. R. Kean, 2804 N. Street, N. W., Washington 7, D. C.</item>
<item>General Albert E. Love, 2709 Wisconsin Ave., N. W., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>General and Mrs. W. L. Reed, 2810 36th Place, N. W., Washington, D. C.</item>
<item>Mrs. Walter Reed and Mrs. Blossom Reed, Blue Ridge Summit, Pa.</item>
<item>Col. J. F. Siler, Secretary, Walter Reed Memorial Association, 1835 Eye St.,<lb/>
N. W., Washington, D. C.:<lb/>
Home: 3434 34th Place, N. W.</item>
<item>Admiral E. R. Stitt, 1625 R Street, N. W., Washington 9, D. C.</item>
</list></p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head><hi>OTHER BOARD MEMBERS</hi>:</head>
<item>Maj Gen. C. R. Reynolds, Chicago</item>
<item>Dr. L. O. Howard</item>
<item>Gen. F. R. Keefer</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
