<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03807037">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to A.W. Ide, April 18, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03807037</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-04-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ide, A. W.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Montgomery, Robert</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-04-18">April 18, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03807037</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to A.W. Ide, April 18, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench provides information about resorts in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-04-18">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to A.W. Ide, April 18, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03807037"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-04-18">April 18, 1940</date>
</dateline>
Dr. A. W. <hi>Ide</hi><lb/>
1515 Charles Street<lb/>
St. Paul, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Ide:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I promised to get some information for you regarding other likely resorts in<lb/>
Cuba.</p>
<p>I know of no hotels in Havana which I could recommend particularly for a long<lb/>
visit. Of course the Nacional Hotel is the best. It has the disadvantage of being almost<lb/>
two or three miles from down down and you have a fifty cent taxi ride every time your<lb/>
wife might want to shop. It has its own pool and a beautiful location. We had a very<lb/>
nice room with twin beds and bath for ten dollars a day, European plan. The meals are<lb/>
expensive, and are all right but not sufficiently wonderful to make one forget the expense.<lb/>
Breakfast is seventy-five cents to a dollar and a quarter, lunch or dinner a dollar and a<lb/>
half to two dollars.</p>
<p>I found mixed opinions concerning the Sevilla-Biltmore. Thirteen years ago when<lb/>
I visited Cuba first, it was the swank hotel, cost thirty dollars a day and was worth it.<lb/>
Three years ago, my wife and I stayed there. It was about eight dollars a day, and its<lb/>
main advantage was that it was in town. It was obviously run down. One Cuban friend told<lb/>
us that it was now even worse than then, another told us it was now better than then.</p>
<p>The third hotel to be recommended is the Hotel Presidente. It is even further out<lb/>
than the Nacional, being about a half mile further from town. It is a very nice hotel,<lb/>
a little less expensive than the Nacional but not so pretentious. There are many Cuban<lb/>
hotels and should you at any time wish to write my frind, Mr. John J. Moran, of 455,<lb/>
Avenida Menocal, I am sure that he might give you some dope. Incidentally, Mr. Moran is<lb/>
the John J. Moran who was one of the first two to volunteer to Walter Reed for experimental<lb/>
yellow fever. It was Mr. Moran whose part was taken by Robert Montgomery in the movie<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I have heard from time to time much favorable comment concerning Cuba's famous<lb/>
beach, Veradero Beach. It is about a hundred miles from Havana, and is really a sort of<lb/>
a rustic Atlantic City, apparently mostly a one-street affair, with small hotels facing<lb/>
the occean, one or two swanky clubs, and I think a movie or so, which is about all; but<lb/>
the beach is said to be wonderful and the water marvelous. I would like to try it sometime.<lb/>
Note the enclosures and the writeup. Another place at Varadero Beach is the Kawama Beach<lb/>
Club, run by Colonel Silva. I think this is a sort of a semi-private beach club, meaning<lb/>
that you can't go down there and get a room, but if you write ahead of time and go through<lb/>
the motions of an introduction, which I gather can be easily done, you would be admitted<lb/>
there. It might be a little nicer than the hotel.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
