<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03801004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, January 19, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03801004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-01-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">California</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-01-19">January 19, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03801004</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, January 19, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench gently chides Hutchison for omitting to send the promised autographed pictures of Kissinger and Moran. Hench requests additional copies of "A Milestone." He also solicits fundraising advice for a planned memorial in Havana, Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-01-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ralph Cooper Hutchison, January 19, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03801004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-01-19">January 19, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Hutch:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You are no better than I am! Your letter says, &ldquo;Enclosed are pictures<lb/>
from Kissinger and Moran...&rdquo; but obviously they weren't enclosed, and I imagine that<lb/>
your wiser secretary sent them by separate post. Nuts to you, and again nuts! You<lb/>
say, &ldquo;About the time you get them replaced the others will turn up somewhere.&rdquo; Again<lb/>
a thousand nuts! Apparently you still don't believe that I sent them. I have a definite<lb/>
memorandum in my own handwriting, attached to the empty envelope, in which these pictures<lb/>
were, and the memo plainly reads, &ldquo;Autographed photographs of Kissinger and Moran sent<lb/>
to W. and J.&rdquo; However, all's well that ends well.</p>
<p>I am delighted to know that you had such a swell trip to California.<lb/>
I wish that I felt as assured of heaven as you do. If I did, I would do more flying.<lb/>
My secretary fears that if I should fall, I would keep on going straight on through to<lb/>
the hot region, and I fear she knows me so well that she may be right!</p>
<p>I am glad you gave me an excuse for not having written to thank you for<lb/>
the swell Christmas present. It took me several days to recover from the holiday festivi-<lb/>
ties and when I was about to write you, you wrote and said you were off to California!<lb/>
Seriously, the plates were swell and nothing would have pleased us more. Mary was de-<lb/>
lighted also, and they fit beautifully with the others. We have planned to fill out<lb/>
your Lafayette set of plates but none are yet available. We will keep that in mind for<lb/>
a later gift.</p>
<p>And now for another request. I am sorry I didn't know you planned to<lb/>
print my address in your brochure &ldquo;A Milestone&rdquo;. It was my understanding that you were<lb/>
not going to print it anywhere. Had I known it, I would have asked to see proof, and<lb/>
checked over the manuscript a little more carefully. As it is, there are three slight<lb/>
mistakes: &ldquo;Epidemiologic&rdquo; was spelled &ldquo;epidemiologic&rdquo;, &ldquo;Pogolotti&rdquo; was misspelled<lb/>
&ldquo;Pogolotti&rdquo; and by a slip of the pencil on my part, I quoted Truby as saying that Lazear<lb/>
got sick on August 16, which should have been September 16. However, these are minor<lb/>
errors and will be corrected when I publish it in a medical journal sometime. I<lb/>
thought the brochure was grand. You say you had five thousand printed. I am wondering<lb/>
if there is any possible chance of my getting a generous number. I find that I have a<lb/>
list of almost seventy-five individuals (physicians, librarians, army people in Cuba,<lb/>
Washington and elsewhere in this country) who have given me material assistance in my<lb/>
investigations over the last two years. A great majority of them specifically requested<lb/>
a copy of my W. and J. talk, and I vaguely promised to send them one. Is there any<lb/>
possibility that you could send me (don't faint!) a hundred copies of the brochure and<lb/>
a hundred copies of the November, 1940 Alumni Bulletin? I would be certainly very glad<lb/>
to send these to the people who have been so helpful, and I think it would be an ex-<lb/>
cellent advertisement for W. and J. If you will express them to me, I will be delighted<lb/>
to send them out from here and save you about $10.00 postage, particularly because I want<lb/>
to write at least a one or two line note with each one, and will also correct the errors<lb/>
noted above. You may think that the Alumni Bulletin obviates the necessity of sending<lb/>
the brochure. I think they are both complementary and will show these earnest friends<lb/>
of Lazear's and Reed's what W. and J. really thought of Lazear, and did about it at the<lb/>
ceremony. Of these hundred copies, I would like to send about ten to personal friends.<lb/>
The rest, as I have said, are to go to those who have materially helped me in my investi-<lb/>
gation.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03801005"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Will you tell me Mr. Pew's full name and address? How did he receive<lb/>
you when you visited him on behalf of Moran's expenses? Do you think that I could<lb/>
approach him sometime in the future for a contribution toward our memorial, seeing<lb/>
as how their local co-worker and Cuban representative took such a prominent part in<lb/>
the venture. I, personally, would think that a contribution from Pew in behalf of<lb/>
this memorial in Havana would be darned good business. I am going to Havana in March<lb/>
to try and finish up the details and get the property signed, sealed and delivered,<lb/>
and discuss the question of the memorial--the type it should be, the cost, etc.---<lb/>
with the Minister of Defense. After a couple of weeks there in March, we will<lb/>
rest the first two weeks in April at Palm Beach.</p>
<p>Did you send the brochure to Mrs. Lazear and her relatives? Did you<lb/>
send her a plate, as you once said you thought you would do? If not, I would like<lb/>
the privilege of sending a plate of the Lazear Memorial Building to Mrs. Lazear,<lb/>
with my own personal compliments. She was so nice to me that I want to &ldquo;salve her<lb/>
up.&rdquo; If you haven't sent it, please consider this an order, send it to her, and<lb/>
I will send you a check and write to her that it is on the way, in my name.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
