<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03817022">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to the Chief of the War Department's Map Collection, June 23, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03817022</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-06-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-06-23">June 23, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03817022</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to the Chief of the War Department's Map Collection, June 23, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests copies of Camp Columbia maps for himself and for the Cuban Chief of Engineers of Military City. He explains his research on the yellow fever experiments and Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-06-23">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to the Chief of the War Department's Map Collection, June 23, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03817022"/>
<opener>
<unclear>Free</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-06-23"><del>May</del><add>June</add> 23, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Chief of the War Department's Map Collection<lb/>
Army War College<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p><del>A couple of</del><add>About five</add> weeks ago, General Ireland brought me to your War College, in<lb/>
an effort to get copies of old army maps of Camp Columbia, Quemados (Havana), Cuba.<lb/>
For three years I have been doing some historical researches on the work of Walter<lb/>
Reed and other army surgeons in the conquest of yellow fever. I have made two trips<lb/>
to Cuba and have been trying to find these old maps. I am especially anxious to<lb/>
get a copy of the map of Camp Columbia for 1898 and for 1899. The sergeant in<lb/>
charge of these maps showed General Ireland and me two different maps for 1899 and<lb/>
suggested that I write to you formally requesting copies of these maps. In the<lb/>
official reports of the Secretary of War for the corresponding years, I found mention<lb/>
of these maps and also mention of a property map of Camp Columbia. You may be inter-<lb/>
ested to know that this map is not in your files but is in the files of the Archives<lb/>
Building, should you wish a copy of it for your own files. The Secretary of War<lb/>
of Cuba very kindly put their maps at my disposal, but they only had fragments, quite<lb/>
torn from long use, of two or three maps which I have not been able to locate elsewhere.<lb/>
They are very anxious to exchange copies of these maps with you. They, too, would<lb/>
like to have copies of the 1898 and 1899 maps.</p>
<p>I am enclosing photographs which I had taken of the parts of these maps and<lb/>
I am so hopeful that you will have these original maps that I may have copies of them<lb/>
as well as the ones I now have. Any help you can give me in this matter will be<lb/>
greatly appreciated, and I am sure that General Ireland would give you further in-<lb/>
formation as to the reason for my request.</p>
<p>To make a long story short, on my first visit to Cuba, I found that the<lb/>
Cuban government had lost sight of Camp Lazear where Walter Reed did his work. They<lb/>
had bought a piece of property and were about to erect a memorial on the wrong site.<lb/>
Through a lucky chain of circumstances I was able to find the lost Camp Lazear, and<lb/>
actually found remaining, in pretty good condition, one of the little buildings used<lb/>
by Walter Reed in his experiments. I have bought this building and with friends I<lb/>
am trying to raise money to restore it and properly memorialize it and also Camp<lb/>
Lazear. It is in connection with these researches that I am so anxious to have<lb/>
these maps of Camp Columbia.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03817023"/>
Chief of the War Department's Map Collection - 2 -<lb/>
May 23, 1941<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. The gentlemen in the map division of the Ciudad Militar<lb/>
at Quemados, the headquarters of the Cuban Army, who requested that I get<lb/>
him copies of the old maps of Camp Columbia from you, were Captain Garcia<lb/>
Alonzo and Assistant General Velosquez, Chief of the Engineering Department.<lb/>
I suggest that you either send them to me and I will forward them, or send<lb/>
them directly to the Engineering Department of the Cuban Army.<lb/>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
