<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03824007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Helen Wheeler, August 28, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03824007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-08-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wheeler, Helen</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Angles, Eduardo</name>
<name type="person">Pogliotti, Luis B.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-08-28">August 28, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03824007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Helen Wheeler, August 28, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench returns research material borrowed from the Welch Medical Library, correcting misinformation regarding the Camp Lazear site. He inquires about the location of the tablet commemorating Lazear at Johns Hopkins University.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>

<div1 type="letter" n="1941-08-28">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Helen Wheeler, August 28, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03824007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-08-28">August 28, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Miss Helen Wheeler<lb/>
Welch Medical Library<lb/>
1900 East Monument Street<lb/>
Baltimore, Maryland<lb/>
<salute>Dear Miss Wheeler:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It is several months since you so kindly loaned me the data on yellow<lb/>
fever in your library: (1) the letters, clippings, photos, etc. from Dr. Pea-<lb/>
body and (2) a few photographs from Dr. Kelly. I have spent considerable time<lb/>
in my none too leisure time, studying these and checking the information therein<lb/>
with what I have collected by visits and correspondence with several of those<lb/>
involved in the yellow fever experiments, namely Mr. John J. Moran, Mr. Kissinger,<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear, Mrs. and Miss Reed, Generals Kean and Truby and others. Having<lb/>
your permission I have photostated a fair amount of the material you loaned me<lb/>
and am now sending it back to you by express with the exception of <del>three or four</del> 8 or 10<lb/>
small photographs and a copy of Kissinger's fever chart. I believe the photo-<lb/>
graphs were taken by Dr. Peabody and rather than try to copy the photographs I am<lb/>
writing to see if he has the negatives; if not I'll copy the photos and return<lb/>
them to you. I also want to check with Dr. Peabody on the source of Kissinger's<lb/>
fever chart and whether it is the original one or a copy. (Do you know?) I<lb/>
think I will have it copied also and then return it.</p>
<p>Let me express my deep appreciation for your kindness in this matter.<lb/>
Permit me to make some comments on the data in your collection.</p>
<p>I do not believe you have the complete file of correspondence between<lb/>
Peabody and Moran. Peabody's letter to Moran (Oct. 15, 1928) speaks of a letter<lb/>
from Moran, and Moran's letter to Peabody (July 7, 1929) mentions another letter<lb/>
(Oct. 29, 1928) neither of which are in your files. I assume you do not have<lb/>
them and will write to see if Dr. Peabody still has them.</p>
<p>To keep the record straight (?) permit me to say that there are one or two<lb/>
important differences between the story Mr. Moran told Dr. Peabody (data at the<lb/>
moment appended to Moran's letter of July 7, 1929) and the story he has told me<lb/>
by correspondence and during two visits to Havana. I am trying to iron out the<lb/>
differences. <hi>Please</hi> leave this to me; <hi>please do not correspond</hi> with Mr. Moran<lb/>
about it or you may upset the confidential relationships I am establishing with him.</p>
<p>Two of Peabody's letters are incomplete in your files; e.g. that of Nov.<lb/>
13, 1928 to Col. Kean. At least I could not find page 2.</p>
<p>The letter from Dr. Angles of Havana (unsigned by him) dated Dec. 27, 1935<lb/>
to Dr. Peabody contains 5 snapshots of what are supposed to be Camp Lazear. I can<lb/>
assure you Dr. Angles was completely wrong. They are <hi>not</hi> of Camp Lazear but are<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03824008"/>
Miss Helen Wheeler<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
August 28, 1941<lb/>
of the site where the yellow fever tent hospital (or yellow fever wards) of<lb/>
Columbia Barracks Post Hospital was in 1900-1901, right across the La Playa rail-<lb/>
road track from the Post Hospital (now the Agramonte Hospital at Ciudad Militar,<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba). I have been over every foot of this territory and also have many<lb/>
maps, etc. of this land as of 1899, 1900, 1901, 1935, etc. Mr. Moran, Mr. Pogolotti<lb/>
and I rediscovered the lost site of Camp Lazear last spring and have indisputable<lb/>
proof. We are writing up our findings and I will send them to you in due time.</p>
<p>I hope you receive your data in good shape. I have been very careful of it<lb/>
and appreciated it very much. Last May, I visited Dr. Howard Kelly who has been<lb/>
interested in my historical researches on the yellow fever conquest and he most<lb/>



graciously gave me practically all the material he had left which he had not al-<lb/>
ready given you. I could not find therein the originals or copies of the photographs<lb/>
of Camp Lazear which he published in his book, &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever.&rdquo;<lb/>
Those he used are <hi>not</hi> the ones available in the Army Museum. Kelly's were better<lb/>
and I am anxious to know where they are and if there might be others unpublished.<lb/>
Neither Dr. Kelly nor his secretary could find them in his library and Dr. Kelly<lb/>
felt sure that he had given them to your library. Indeed his material you sent<lb/>
me is meager and I wonder if you have more of it somewhere. I would appreciate it<lb/>
greatly if you could institute a search for his photographs or negatives of Camp<lb/>
Lazear. Thank you so much.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I believe there is a bronze tablet to Dr. Lazear in the clinical<lb/>
amphitheater at Hopkins. Just where is this tablet? I could not find it when<lb/>
I visited Baltimore in May. Does it have Lazear's death date as Sept. 28, 1900?<lb/>
I think I saw such a date on a photo of this tablet somewhere. If so the date is<lb/>
wrong! He died Sept. 25, 1900. I have a copy of his death certificate.<lb/>
Permit me to send you a newspaper clipping about the unveiling of Corn-<lb/>
well's painting, &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo; (Cleveland June 2, 1941). Walter<lb/>
Reed's daughter unveiled it. I had the honor of giving an address (copy enclosed).<lb/>
It will be printed in the October Hygeia with a colored insert of the painting.<lb/>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
