<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03822001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Morris Fishbein, July 2, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03822001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-07-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Fishbein, Morris</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Cleveland (Oh.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-07-02">July 2, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03822001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Morris Fishbein, July 2, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes his yellow fever research and his speech at the unveiling of the Cornwell painting, suggesting that Fishbein might be interested in publishing the speech, perhaps including a reproduction of the painting, in the journal "Hygeia."</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-07-02">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Morris Fishbein, July 2, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03822001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-07-02">July 2, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Morris Fishbein<lb/>
Editor, Journal of the A.M.A.<lb/>
535 North Dearborn Street<lb/>
Chicago, Illinois<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Fishbein:</salute>
</opener>
<p>For several years I have been making an investigation of certain unpub-<lb/>
lished data regarding the work of Walter Reed and the conquest of yellow fever. To<lb/>
obtain these data I have visited Havana twice, also a number of the survivors of the<lb/>
experiments in various parts of this country. I have obtained much data from the<lb/>
families of Drs. Reed, Agramonte and Lazear and from governmental sources in Washing-<lb/>
ton and Cuba. Because of these studies I was called upon to advise Mr. Dean Cornwell,<lb/>
the nationally known New York painter, regarding the details of the conquest as he<lb/>
prepared his painting, &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, the third in the series &ldquo;Pioneers<lb/>
in American Medicine&rdquo; sponsored by Wyeth and Brothers.</p>
<p>I was also invited to give the dedicatory address of the unveiling of this<lb/>
painting in Cleveland during the A.M.A.'s convention week as noted in the J.A.M.A.,<lb/>
May 31. The affair was indeed a nice one; the invited group was small but very<lb/>
select: The painting was unveiled by Walter Reed's daughter (Miss &ldquo;Blossom&rdquo; Reed)<lb/>
in the presence of the mayor of Cleveland, Drs. Van <unclear>Etten</unclear> and <unclear>Lahey</unclear> (see enclosed<lb/>
photos), Mr. John Kissinger, (one of the first two army privates to volunteer to<lb/>
Reed for experimental inoculations in 1900) representatives from various medical<lb/>
schools (especially Reed's alma mater, the University of Virginia) and art museums.<lb/>
A few old friends of Walter Reed were also there from Washington. These included<lb/>
Col. <unclear>Siler</unclear> and former Surgeon-General and Mrs. Ireland.</p>
<p>I mention these details to indicate that the affair was a very ethical<lb/>
as well as a most pleasant one, although it was essentially part of an advertising<lb/>
program of popular medical education sponsored by Wyeth and Brothers. Doubtless<lb/>
you are familiar with Cornwell's previous paintings of Beaumont and of Osler.</p>
<p>My short talk was mainly a synopsis of the yellow fever conquest with<lb/>
some brief passing references of new discoveries about this conquest. Dr. Walter<lb/>
Simpson of Dayton, Ohio, has written me that he mentioned my talk to you and has<lb/>
made the suggestion that it might be suitable for publication in Hygeia, since it<lb/>
is written in nontechnical language. As yet I have made no plans to publish it but<lb/>
would be glad indeed to have it considered for Hygeia. I believe that the Wyeth<lb/>
folks would like to use it or parts of it as background information for a little<lb/>
explanatory brochure which they may send out later when colored reproductions are<lb/>
made available to physicians.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03822002"/>
<p>Dr. Morris Fishbein</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>July 2, 1941</p>
<p>May I therefore submit for your consideration one of the mimeographed<lb/>
copies I had made. If you consider it in general acceptable for Hygeia I would<lb/>
like to make a few editorial changes here and there before submitting the final<lb/>
copy. If the paper is considered by you, you may prefer to omit the first two<lb/>
(introductory) pages and perhaps other allusions to the painting (page 10). In<lb/>
a way I would regret this since the painting is such a splendid and interesting<lb/>
one and one which I believe the readers of Hygeia would like to see. I believe<lb/>
the paper would gain interest for laymen if it were illustrated with one of the<lb/>
enclosed photographs, which show the painting in the background. Perhaps Drs.<lb/>
Van <unclear>Etten</unclear> or <unclear>Lahey</unclear> would permit publication of this photo which appeared in cer-<lb/>
tain newspapers, or perhaps it could be illustrated with a reproduction of the<lb/>
painting, a reproduction either in black and white or even in color. I think<lb/>
the Wyeth Company would be willing to lend color plates or even color inserts for <unclear>a</unclear><lb/>
such an article at no cost to you and expect nothing but some simple acknowledgement<lb/>
of the source or ownership of the painting.</p>
<p>But whatever you decide to do I appreciate your consideration of my<lb/>
paper.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
