<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03834034">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ignacio Alvare, November 26, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03834034</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-11-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Alvare, Ignacio</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-11-26">November 26, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03834034</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ignacio Alvare, November 26, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench sends Alvare a reprint of his yellow fever article and notes that it is the beginning of his attempts to honor Finlay's work as well as that of the yellow fever board.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-11-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Ignacio Alvare, November 26, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03834034"/>
<opener>
Enclosures 1)reprint<lb/>
2) Pogolotti map - large<lb/>
3) Alvare photo<lb/>
4) my photo of tree &amp; Moran<lb/>
5) small map of Havana<lb/>
Copy to Moran<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-11-26">November 26, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Ignacio Alvare<lb/>
Calle 9, No. 304<lb/>
Vedado, Havana<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Alvare:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I enclose a reprint of an address I gave last June when Dr. Walter<lb/>
Reed's daughter unveiled a painting honoring the conquerors of yellow fever. It<lb/>
is merely the beginning for me of a campaign to give due honor to Dr. Finlay as<lb/>
well as to the members of the American Yellow Fever Board.</p>
<p>I am now writing an article on &ldquo;The Location of Camp Lazear&rdquo; and<lb/>
would appreciate just one more item of information from you.</p>
<p>When you took the photograph of the little house and tree (enclosed)<lb/>
in 1926 do you remember whether the little building faced squarely the railroad<lb/>
track or not? The tree in <hi>your</hi> photograph is undoubtedly the one in <hi>my</hi> photo-<lb/>
graph recently surrounded by the little memorial fence and marked by the sign.<lb/>
Allowing for changes due to the growth of roots and branches during the lapse of<lb/>
14 years since your photograph was taken it is obviously the same tree. From the<lb/>
arrangement of its branches and especially from the arrangement of its base and<lb/>
roots which spread out in an individualistic manner with three roots visible and<lb/>
a hollow between roots 2 and 3 (compare the two photographs) I am sure that one<lb/>
can identify the tree in your photo as the one which is in mine. But I am <hi>most</hi><lb/>
anxious to know in what direction the little building in your photograph faced.<lb/>
This building is of course no longer there. But using your old photograph and<lb/>
estimating from the roots and branches of the tree in relationship to the little<lb/>
building in your photograph Mr. Moran and I determined that the building must have<lb/>
<hi>faced squarely the railroad track</hi> about 75 feet away. In other words the little<lb/>
building <hi>faced almost east</hi> (east by a little north). Am I correct in this? I<lb/>
feel that it is important for me to know this and to have you tell me for sure.</p>
<p>I enclose a map of Reparto Padre Zamora with the site of your photograph<lb/>
noted thereon in red, also the direction of the compass which you can check from<lb/>
the small map of Havana enclosed. If you cannot tell me for sure from a perusal<lb/>
of the maps and photographs in which direction the building faced would you be<lb/>
good enough to drive out to the site at your leisure (if you have any!) and check<lb/>
it actually on the spot? Perhaps then your memory will permit you to give me the<lb/>
exact information.</p>
<p>I hate to bother you thus but I am very anxious to have <hi>your</hi> statement<lb/>
on this. I hope to write a monograph on the whole subject and I <del>precisely</del><add><unclear></unclear></add> do<lb/>
appreciate your aid in locating <add>precisely</add> the various sites concerned. I would appreciate it<lb/>
if you will return the maps and photographs when you are through with them. Thank<lb/>
you very much.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
