<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03838001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Proposal from Philip Showalter Hench to the Mayo Clinic Publications Committee, December 11, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03838001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-12-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-12-11">December 11, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03838001</idno>
<title>Proposal from Philip Showalter Hench to the Mayo Clinic Publications Committee, December 11, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench makes a formal request to register the preparation of a book on the history of the conquest of yellow fever. He assures the Committee on Medical Education and Research at the Mayo Clinic that this work will not interfere with his research on rheumatic diseases nor his work on experimental jaundice.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-12-11">
<head>Proposal from Philip Showalter Hench to the Mayo Clinic Publications Committee, December 11, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03838001"/>
<p>Recommended to the Publications Committee for approval.</p>
<p>Committee on Medical Education and Research</p>
<p>12-22-41</p>
<p>To the Committee on Medical Education and Research for your action, and also<lb/>
for the consideration of the Committee on Publication of Books:</p>
<p>I should like to make a formal request to register the preparation<lb/>
of a book on the history of the conquest of yellow fever. As you may know, I<lb/>
have been working on this <hi>as a hobby</hi> for the last four years and have done much<lb/>
work on it myself out of hours and on personal vacations. My secretary, Miss<lb/>
Schnurr, has helped me tremendously and to date the whole thing has been rather<lb/>
informal. A good deal of the correspondence has been done in regular hours<lb/>
incidental to the publication of three papers thereon. A good deal has also<lb/>
been done out of hours for which I have paid Miss Schnurr and Miss Nelson small<lb/>
extra sums. I have collected a considerable amount of unpublished material<lb/>
based on records, the unpublished accounts of eye witnesses, the lost and now<lb/>
found notebooks of Lazear, etc. There are of sufficient historical importance<lb/>
that they should be published. I do not propose to let the preparation of this<lb/>
book interfere with my researches on rheumatic diseases and my work on experimental<lb/>
jaundice. In other words, I plan to work on the yellow fever business only as a<lb/>
hobby and essentially out of hours but would like to have it listed officially<lb/>
for various reasons. If your committee approves the eventual publication of such<lb/>
a book, would you kindly notify me or my secretary what should be done about any<lb/>
further stenographic work that she does. I have personally paid for much of the<lb/>
photographic work incidental to the three papers already written but the photo-<lb/>
graphic department has also helped me greatly. It would be rather difficult to<lb/>
separate that amount of work which I have paid for and that which Miss Schnurr<lb/>
and others have done although I do have copies of everything that we have written.</p>
<p>I have not as yet attempted to make any arrangements with any publisher.<lb/>
The book should be written to interest laymen as well as medical men. The proposed<lb/>
title would probably be &ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo; or perhaps some more arresting<lb/>
title, one more interesting to laymen. It should be a rather small book, perhaps<lb/>
150 pages but with a generous number of illustrations. As to the estimate of the<lb/>
demand for the book, I have no idea. I can only say that the yellow fever story<lb/>
continues more and more to catch the fancy of the public, as witnessed by the<lb/>
play and the movie &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;.</p>
<p>P.S. Hench, 12-11-41</p>
<p>The war may interfere with any <unclear>large</unclear> publication of the book<lb/>
and it might be well to publish it 4 or 5 years from now<lb/>
But I do want <unclear>authorization</unclear> and <unclear>advice</unclear> so that I can<lb/>
slowly collect the necessary data.</p>
<p>DoctorHench: This was approved, as you know, by the Board of<lb/>
Governors at the suggestion of our Committee.</p>
<closer>
<signed>A. R. Barnes</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
