<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03839022">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Ignacio Alvare to Philip Showalter Hench, December 8, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Alvare, Ignacio</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03839022</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-12-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Ortolazabal, Felipe</name>
<name type="person">Marrero, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">Santiago de la Vegas (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Hospital Militar, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-12-08">December 8, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03839022</idno>
<title>English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Ignacio Alvare to Philip Showalter Hench, December 8, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a full translation of Alvare's letter, in which he praises Hench for his attempt to give Finlay credit for his yellow fever work. He describes his visit with former interns from the Hospital Militar and their recollection of Camp Lazear. He explains the origin of the photograph that he recently sent Hench, identifying the photographer as Felipe Ortolazabal.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-12-08">
<head>English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Ignacio Alvare to Philip Showalter Hench, December 8, 1941 See <xref id="f03839020">Spanish original</xref>.</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03839022"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-12-08">December 8, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear friend:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Yesterday I wrote to you acknowledging receipt of your kind letter of<lb/>
November 26. I congratulate you because you propose to undertake a campaign to<lb/>
give to Dr. Finlay and the members of the American Investigating Commission the<lb/>
honor that their theory deserves. In honor to the historical truth one cannot<lb/>
speak of yellow fever and its conquest without ennobling the glorious figure of<lb/>
our wise one who, fighting against the indifference of the epoch and the disbelief<lb/>
of all, had the satisfaction of seeing proved to the last end, his magnificent<lb/>
theory by a group of honorable scientific men. If you attain to make this truth<lb/>
come out you will realize a work worthy of all praise and you will have the appre-<lb/>
ciation of all of us Cubans who feel the glories of our country.</p>
<p>Yesterday I went to Santiago de las Vegas and saw Dr. Marrero, Jr.<lb/>
who was an interne at the Hospital Militar in my time, and resided there a long<lb/>
time. Between us we are to make more concrete the information that interests you.<lb/>
Yesterday also, Dr. Arturo Sansores accompanied me, who was a physician of the<lb/>
hospital, and Dr. Ricardo Repilado, present Chief of Municipal Sanitation of Havana<lb/>
and who was a very good friend of ours. This morning at 10 o'clock we conferred<lb/>
and in order not to be mistaken, went to the Pavilion of Infectious Illnesses of the<lb/>
Military Hospital, from whose back terrace I could visualize that little house in my<lb/>
hours as an interne in that room. In the act of looking at it, I could spot the<lb/>
tree and there we directed ourselves, and together with Dr. Marrero and Dr. Sansores,<lb/>
on the ground, we recalled that the little house had faced toward the railroad line.<lb/>
There is no doubt whatever as to the identity of the tree. The front of the small<lb/>
building faced toward the north with a slight inclination toward the <unclear>east</unclear>, and from<lb/>
there one finds the railroad line a distance not more than 30 to 35 steps, that is<lb/>
some 70 feet. I remember perfectly the location of the house when as a student I<lb/>
strolled around those corners.</p>
<p>I want to clear up a mistaken impression that you have about the photograph<lb/>
that you seem to interpret was taken by me. The photograph was taken at the time of<lb/>
my interneship on a day that you already know and I had no security about the person<lb/>
who had taken it. I believed that it was one of my companions at the hospital but<lb/>
Dr. Arturo Sansores who has the same thing, informed me this morning that the photo-<lb/>
graph was taken by Lt. Felipe Ortolazabal and I know that all of us students keep<lb/>
a veneration for the historical remembrance that is portrayed therein for us. For<lb/>
that reason I delivered one to another--one of my favorite professors, Dr. Recio. I<lb/>
want you to realize all this data if mention is made of it in your work so that you will<lb/>
not think that I want to take credit for something that doesn't belong to me, because<lb/>
what there is here of worth is the preserved photograph which anyone whatever could<lb/>
obtain, and I have been no more than the conducting wire through which you have ob-<lb/>
tained this knowledge. Be sure that the information that I gave you is correct because<lb/>
I have transported myself there to recall it and after my visit to that place had en-<lb/>
graved on my mind the view of the little house with its tree and the rest of the details<lb/>
of the place. I want to congratulate you for your zeal in all this that results so<lb/>
interesting and above all because you<del>r</del> put in his true place of glory our wise Finlay<lb/>
in a deed that was of such great <unclear>trans<add>c</add>endence</unclear> for humanity.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Dr. Ignacio Alvare</signed>
<seg>
P.S. In another envelope I am sending you the photographs and <unclear>sketches</unclear>.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
