<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03843006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Radio Script: The Board of Missing Heirs, September 23, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03843006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-09-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">De Kruif, Paul</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>17 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-09-23">September 23, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03843006</idno>
<title>Radio Script: The Board of Missing Heirs, September 23, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The script gives a biographical sketch of Forbes, and states that he is wanted by the U.S. Army Finance Department so that he can be given a lump sum of $17,750 and $125 monthly for his service in the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-09-23">
<head>Radio Script: The Board of Missing Heirs, September 23, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03843006"/>
<opener>
RUTHRAUFF &amp; RYAN Inc. ADVERTISING<lb/>
RADIO DIVISION<lb/>
CLIENT: IRONIZED YEAST COMPANY<lb/>
PROGRAM: BOARD OF MISSING HEIRS<lb/>
BROADCAST: #93<lb/>
<dateline>
DATE: TUES. <date value="1941-09-23">9/23/41</date>
</dateline>
NETWORK: CBS<lb/>
8:00--8:30<lb/>
11:30-12:00<lb/>
</opener>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<item>1 ANNR: ARE YOU A MISSING HEIR?<lb/>
2 (MUSIC)</item>
<item>3 ANNR: For the ninety-third consecutive week, the makers of<lb/>
4 Ironized Yeast present radio's great public service...<lb/>
5 The Board of Missing Heirs. Tonight we again present<lb/>
6 actual true to life stories of people who have left<lb/>
7 large fortunes which are still unclaimed. Maybe you<lb/>
8 are a missing heir, maybe you can claim one of these<lb/>
9 estates. So listen carefully. And now, here is our<lb/>
10 conductor...George B. Marshall...</item>
<item>11 MC: Thank you, good evening, ladies and gentlemen. As you<lb/>
12 know, this great public service, the search for missing<lb/>
13 heirs, is made possible by the makers of Ironized Yeast.<lb/>
14 Thus far, we have located heirs to estates worth more<lb/>
15 than five hundred and seventy thousand dollars. Think<lb/>
16 of it...over a half a million dollars. Tonight you'll<lb/>
17 hear the story of ____________________________________<lb/>
18 ______________________________________________________<lb/>
19 _____________....There are more actual life<lb/>
20 life stories, too, and now we are ready for our first<lb/>
21 case.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f03843007"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-1-</item>
<item>1 M.C.: Thank you, Don Hancock, for your sensible advice.<lb/>
2 And now, ladies and gentlemen -- to our next case.</item>
<item>3 FACTS: It's the case of the estate being held for Wallace<lb/>
4 Wellington Forbes, spelled F-O-R-B-E-S, who was born in<lb/>
5 Galesburg, Illinois, on September 25, 1878, and who now<lb/>
6 stands heir to an estate valued at seventeen thousand,<lb/>
7 seven hundred and fifty dollars.</item>
<item>8 M.C.: (MUSIC SIMULTANEOUS) Ladies and gentlemen, we have been<lb/>
9 on the air now every Tuesday night for nearly two years.<lb/>
10 We have told true stories of people -- sad stories,<lb/>
11 some of them; some comical, perhaps as life is comical;<lb/>
12 some tragic or exciting. But never have we had a story<lb/>
13 so packed with the stuff of human terror and human<lb/>
14 bravery, as is the story of Wallace Wellington Forbes.<lb/>
15 Wallace Forbes is one of his country's great heroes.<lb/>
16 Tonight we are searching for this man, to turn over to<lb/>
17 him the seventeen thousand, seven hundred and fifty<lb/>
18 dollars that is due him by special grant of the Congress<lb/>
19 of the United States. We implore you to listen, ladies<lb/>
20 and gentlemen, in the hopes that maybe one of you will<lb/>
21 be able to help us find Wallace Forbes, a brave man --<lb/>
22 an American hero.<lb/>
23 (MUSIC)</item>
<item>24 VOICE: What is it that makes a hero? His family? His<lb/>
25 birthplace?</item>
<item>26 FACTS: There was nothing extraordinary in Wallace Forbes's<lb/>
27 family or background. He was born in a quiet midwestern<lb/>
28 town, Galesburg, Illinois, the only son of James<lb/>
29 Wellington Forbes and Mary Alice Forbes.</item>
<pb n="3" id="f03843008"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-2-</item>
<item>1 VOICE: What about his dreams? What fed his imagination?</item>
<item>2 FACTS: He read the dime-novels, the adventures of Nick Carter;<lb/>
3 he read of Robinson Crusoe, shipwrecked on a desert<lb/>
4 island; and in his dreams he floated down the<lb/>
5 Mississippi on a raft, with Tom Sawyer. His dreams<lb/>
6 were the same as those of the other boys of his day.<lb/>
7 (SOME SPANISH-AMERICAN WAR MUSIC: FAST SNEAK)</item>
<item>8 VOICE: Maybe there was something that was happening in the<lb/>
9 world, that fired him to heroism...<lb/>
10 (MUSIC UP AND DOWN)<lb/>
11 (OUT OF MUSIC: BIG EXPLOSION. AS IT DIES AWAY:<lb/>
12 REGISTER TICKER DOT-DASH)</item>
<item>13 VOICE OF TICKER: (DOT-DASH UNDER) Havana, Cuba -- February 15 --<lb/>
14 1898. The U.S. Battleship Maine was sunk by a mysterious<lb/>
15 explosion in the harbour of this city early this morning.<lb/>
16 It is believed that at least two hundred lives were lost,<lb/>
17 (MUSIC QUICK SWELL)<lb/>
18 and that death toll may reach as high as three hundred..<lb/>
19 (MUSIC UP AND DOWN)<lb/>
20 (OUT OF MUSIC: RUNNING STEPS ON TO MIKE: SCREEN DOOR<lb/>
21 SLAM OPEN AND SHUT)</item>
<item>WALLACE: (COMING ON: HE'S 20 YEARS OLD) Hey, Dad! Dad! Look<lb/>
23 here --</item>
<item>24 MOTHER: Wallace Forbes, I do believe you'll rip that screen door<lb/>
25 right off, one of these days --</item>
<item>26 FATHER: What is it, Wally?</item>
<item>27 WALLACE: Look -- the headlines --</item>
<pb n="4" id="f03843009"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-3-</item>
<item>1 (PAPER RUSTLE)</item>
<item>2 FATHER (PAUSE) So. He's declared war --</item>
<item>3 MOTHER: Hmp. Way things have been going, would have been a<lb/>
4 scandal if he hadn't --</item>
<item>5 WALLACE: We're at war.</item>
<item>6 FATHER: Well, maybe now the Spaniard will learn a lesson.</item>
<item>7 MOTHER: Yes. Wallace -- go up and wash. We're ready for<lb/>
8 supper --</item>
<item>9 WALLACE: Gee -- I can't eat, mom. I'm too excited --</item>
<item>10 FATHER: What? (PAUSE) See here, young man -- you don't think<lb/>
11 this war means anything to you personally, now do you?</item>
<item>12 WALLACE: See what it says in that box there on the front page?<lb/>
13 They've issued a call for young men to volunteer --<lb/>
14 (PAUSE)<lb/>
15 Well? I'm a young man, aren't I?</item>
<item>16 MOTHER: You better talk to him, Jim.</item>
<item>17 FATHER: You know, I don't think it'll do much good for either<lb/>
18 of us to talk to him, Mary. If I know that expression,<lb/>
19 he's joined up already --<lb/>
20 (MUSIC)</item>
<pb n="5" id="f03843010"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-4-</item>
<item>1 FACTS: And so the United States Army sailed for Cuba. And the<lb/>
2 United States Navy steamed for the Philippines. And<lb/>
3 there was Dewey at Manila Bay, and battles at Santiago<lb/>
4 de Cuba, and San Juan Hill. A short war--less than<lb/>
5 four months it lasted. And after the armistice, young<lb/>
6 Americans were still being held at camps in Cuba...<lb/>
7 but they weren't sure why...<lb/>
8 (AS THIS IS AN IMPRESSIONIST SCENE, IT MIGHT BE TRICKED<lb/>
9 UP WITH MUSIC B.G.)</item>
<item>10 ONE: Why they keeping us here?</item>
<item>11 TWO: Why'nt they send us home?</item>
<item>12 THREE: I could use a little old Indiana dirt under my feet<lb/>
13 again ---</item>
<item>14 ONE: Maybe you think I wouldn't like to see St. Loo.</item>
<item>15 TWO: And here we set. Drill and clean. Clean and drill.<lb/>
16 (MUSIC QUICK IN &amp; DOWN)</item>
<item>17 THREE: I hear ---</item>
<item>18 ONE: I heard a rumor---</item>
<item>19 TWO: A guy was telling me ---</item>
<item>20 THREE: Epidemic! There's an epidemic of yellow-fever---</item>
<item>21 ONE: Yellow jack!</item>
<item>22 TWO: They don't dare send us home, fear we'll take it with us--</item>
<item>23 THREE: But what're they doing about it?</item>
<item>24 ONE: They sent a doc down here---an army doc--Major Walter<lb/>
25 Reed ----<lb/>
26 (MUSIC UP &amp; DOWN)</item>
<pb n="6" id="f03843011"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-5-</item>
<item>1 REED: Well, gentlemen--three months we've spent trying to<lb/>
2 isolate that yellow-fever virus --- three months.</item>
<item>3 CARROLL: And not a sign. Reed---if it's all the same with you---<lb/>
4 I'm for packing up and getting back to the States.<lb/>
5 I'm for scientific investigation--all that---but I like<lb/>
6 what I can see.</item>
<item>7 REED: Admit we're licked? How about it, Agramonte?</item>
<item>8 AGRAMONTE: (ACCENT) I am a Cuban, Dr. Reed. In any case, I would<lb/>
9 stay here---</item>
<item>10 REED: Of course. Well, Lazear?</item>
<item>11 LAZEAR: There's what that Scot fellow suggested, Reed. You<lb/>
12 know--Dr. Finlay---</item>
<item>13 CARROLL: (OVER) Finlay? He's a crank.</item>
<item>14 REED: What was it, Lazear?</item>
<item>15 LAZEAR: That whether or not the virus could be isolated, at<lb/>
16 least we should be sure of what carries the virus. The<lb/>
17 mosquito.</item>
<item>18 CARROLL: Guesswork. It's guesswork. He has no proof---no proof<lb/>
19 whatsoever that it's the mosquito that carries<lb/>
20 yellowjack from one man to another---</item>
<item>21 AGRAMONTE: (SOFT) It is very difficult to get such proof,<lb/>
22 Dr. Carroll.</item>
<item>23 REED: What do you mean, Agramonte?</item>
<item>24 AGRAMONTE: We know of no animal except man that is susceptible to<lb/>
25 yellow-fever, Dr. Reed. Not guinea pigs, nor mice, nor<lb/>
26 even monkeys. To test this theory, to put it to proof,<lb/>
27 we would have to experiment on man himself.</item>
<pb n="7" id="f03843012"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-6-</item>
<item>1 CARROLL: Exactly. The scheme is impossible.</item>
<item>2 REED: Not---impossible.</item>
<item>3 LAZEAR: (EXCITED) No! Not impossible! Get the mosquitoes---<lb/>
4 feed 'em on sick men, have 'em bite healthy men!</item>
<item>5 CARROLL: We can't! (AGHAST) We can't do that!</item>
<item>6 REED: What do we lose, Carroll? If it doesn't work, a man<lb/>
7 is bitten by a mosquito. No more. If it does---he<lb/>
8 will be under treatment. He has a chance of living---</item>
<item>9 CARROLL: One chance in ten---</item>
<item>10 REED: He's one dead for proof, Carroll. It is for humanity.</item>
<item>11 AGRAMONTE: Remember, gentlemen---remember what the papers, what<lb/>
12 your American public will say, if you start using<lb/>
13 their soldiers as human guinea pigs --</item>
<item>14 CARROLL: I don't like it myself---</item>
<item>15 REED: We don't need the soldiers, gentlemen. We shall start<lb/>
16 on ourselves.<lb/>
17 (MUSIC)<lb/>
18 (THIS IS ANOTHER IMPRESSIONIST SCENE. TRICK UP WITH<lb/>
19 B.G. MUSIC AGAIN)</item>
<item>20 ONE: What are they doing?</item>
<item>21 TWO: Why don't those doctors hurry up?</item>
<item>22 THREE: More guys died last night--more are sick today---</item>
<pb n="8" id="f03843013"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-7-</item>
<item>1 ONE: And here we sit -- and drill and clean --</item>
<item>2 TWO: -- while they play around with mosquitoes --</item>
<item>3 THREE: Mosquitoes?</item>
<item>4 TWO: Yeah -- those docs. They got hundreds of mosquitoes up<lb/>
5 there in the lab --</item>
<item>6 ONE: I seen 'em. Looks like a flea circus --</item>
<item>7 TWO: Did you ever see a flea circus?<lb/>
8 (MUSIC SWELL UP)</item>
<item>9 THREE: I want to go home --<lb/>
10 (MUSIC QUICK IN &amp; DOWN) (BACK NEXT QUICK SCENE WITH<lb/>
11 LOVE MUSIC)</item>
<item>12 GIRL: (CUBAN ACCENT) So, Wally. You know nothing yet?</item>
<item>13 WALLACE: Golly, Rosita. I wish I did. But there's no news<lb/>
14 yet. I'm still in the army. No sign of they're<lb/>
15 letting us go --</item>
<item>16 GIRL: Why do they delay?</item>
<item>17 WALLACE: It's this yellowjack epidemic, honey. But don't<lb/>
18 worry. They'll get it licked somehow -- and then<lb/>
19 you'll be Mrs. Wallace Forbes. Eh?</item>
<item>20 GIRL: That will be when I am happy, Wally --<lb/>
21 (MUSIC UP &amp; DOWN)</item>
<item>22 REED: Well, gentlemen, let us take stock. We agreed<lb/>
23 that we are right?<lb/>
24 (AD LIB MURMURS)<lb/>
25 That it is the stegomyia mosquito that's carrying<lb/>
26 yellow-fever?</item>
<item>27 CARROLL: Lazear is dead. There is part proof.</item>
<pb n="9" id="f03843014"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-8-</item>
<item>1 REED: Agramonte?</item>
<item>2 AGRAMONTE: Dr. Reed -- we have two cases of men bitten who<lb/>
3 recovered. One case, dead.</item>
<item>4 REED: Do you feel it is proof?</item>
<item>5 AGRAMONTE: That is the trouble.</item>
<item>6 REED: You're right.</item>
<item>7 AGRAMONTE: It has not been thorough. We cannot be sure that<lb/>
8 these men were not infected some other way. Each<lb/>
9 of them was exposed --</item>
<item>10 REED: We need a thorough test. We have tried ourselves<lb/>
11 -- all of us have been exposed.</item>
<item>12 CARROLL: The soldiers?</item>
<item>13 REED: I'm going to General Wood. I'm going to ask money and<lb/>
14 full backing. We've got enough for him to go on --<lb/>
15 (MUSIC SNEAK)<lb/>
16 now we need his cooperation --<lb/>
17 (MUSIC UP &amp; DOWN)<lb/>
18 (UNDER THESE VOICES: MUSIC AGITATO)</item>
<item>19 ONE: Hey, did you hear?</item>
<item>20 TWO: About the mosquitoes?</item>
<item>21 THREE: Yeah --</item>
<item>22 TWO: What?</item>
<item>23 ONE: They want guys to volunteer to be bitten --</item>
<item>24 THREE: To get yellow-fever--</item>
<item>24A ONE: Are they crazy?</item>
<item>25 TWO: Out of their heads?</item>
<item>26 THREE: What's a guy want yellow-fever for?</item>
<item>27 TWO: It's for science --</item>
<pb n="10" id="f03843015"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-9-</item>
<item>1 ONE: For humanity --</item>
<item>2 THREE: Nuts! It's for three hundred bucks --</item>
<item>3 ONE: What do you mean?</item>
<item>4 THREE: They're offering three hundred bucks to any guy who'll<lb/>
5 get the fever --</item>
<item>6 ONE: (SCORNFUL LAUGH) What's he spend it on?</item>
<item>7 TWO: A new set of angel's wings?</item>
<item>8 THREE: They need volunteers --</item>
<item>9 TWO: Not me --</item>
<item>10 ONE: One chance in ten? Not me!</item>
<item>11 THREE: Get yellowjack? Not me!<lb/>
12 (MUSIC UP &amp; OUT)<lb/>
13 (KNOCKS ON DOOR)</item>
<item>14 REED: Come in --<lb/>
15 (DOOR OPEN)<lb/>
16</item>
<item>17 WALLACE: Major Reed?</item>
<item>18 REED: Yes --</item>
<item>19 WALLACE: I'm Private Forbes, sir. Wallace W. Come to volunteer.</item>
<pb n="11" id="f03843016"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-10-</item>
<item>1 REED: Volunteer? For what?</item>
<item>2 WALLACE: For this yellow-jack experiment, sir.</item>
<item>3 REED: (PAUSE) Oh. (PAUSE) You know, uh, you know what kind<lb/>
4 of chances you're taking?</item>
<item>5 WALLACE: Yes, sir.</item>
<item>6 REED: Never had it before?</item>
<item>7 WALLACE: No, sir.</item>
<item>8 REED: Any exposure to it that you know of?</item>
<item>9 WALLACE: No more'n anybody else, sir.</item>
<item>10 REED: Forbes, if we select you, you'll go into solitary<lb/>
11 confinement for two weeks, then be bitten by a mosquito<lb/>
12 carrying the virus of yellow fever. Understand?</item>
<item>13 WALLACE: Yes, sir.</item>
<item>14 REED: You'll be a very sick man. Of course, we'll do all we<lb/>
15 can for you, once you've been taken ill.. <hi>If</hi> you're<lb/>
16 taken ill.</item>
<item>17 WALLACE: Yes, sir.</item>
<item>18 REED: But, Forbes..</item>
<item>19 WALLACE: Yes, sir?</item>
<item>20 REED: All our care. It may do no good. I want you to be sure<lb/>
21 you understand that.</item>
<item>22 FORBES: I do, sir.</item>
<item>23 REED: And when you recover..if you recover..there's the<lb/>
24 three hundred dollars that General Wood has offered.</item>
<item>25 FORBES: Oh...Major Reed..</item>
<item>26 REED: Yes?</item>
<item>27 FORBES: There's only just the one condition I'm doing this on,<lb/>
28 sir...</item>
<pb n="12" id="f03843017"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-11-</item>
<item>1 REED: What's that?</item>
<item>2 FORBES: That I get no compensation for it, sir. I...I figure<lb/>
3 it's..it's like you said, sir. For the cause of<lb/>
4 humanity.</item>
<item>5 REED: (PAUSE) Private Forbes, I salute you.<lb/>
6 (MUSIC)</item>
<item>7 FACTS: Wallace Wellington Forbes, private, United States Army<lb/>
8 was one of six who volunteered their lives for science,<lb/>
9 their country, and humanity. One of six of the bravest<lb/>
10 men who ever lived. One of six men who were taken to<lb/>
11 Camp Lazear, placed in isolation for two weeks, then<lb/>
12 bitten with the poison-carrying mosquito..<lb/>
13 (MUSIC IN AND HOLD UNDER...)<lb/>
14 And four days after the fatal bite..</item>
<item>15 REED: (LOW AND TENSE) Temperature?</item>
<item>16 NURSE: One hundred and two and four-tenths, doctor..</item>
<item>17 REED: Pulse?</item>
<item>18 NURSE: One hundred and twelve.</item>
<item>19 REED: Eyes injected. Face diffused.</item>
<item>20 AGRAMONTE: Really it is a beautiful case, Dr. Reed..</item>
<item>21 REED: A beautiful case. Jaundiced already.</item>
<item>22 AGRAMONTE: We have won, doctor. We <unclear>ha e</unclear> proven our case.</item>
<item>23 REED: <add>Yes, I pray</add> God that the cost is not too high. Three men already...<lb/>
24 (MUSIC SWIRL UP FOR JUST A SEC AND THEN DOWN)</item>
<item>25 WALLACE: The sun..the hot sun..and I can see the shade..elms..<lb/>
26 and the sound of the lawnmowers, along, under the elms.</item>
<item>27 AGRAMONTE: What is this?</item>
<pb n="13" id="f03843018"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-12-</item>
<item>1 REED: His home, I should think. Delirium. Get the syringe,<lb/>
2 nurse. We'll give him..<lb/>
3 (MUSIC SWELL UP)<lb/>
4 another injection now, and a fourth at six o'clock..<lb/>
5 (MUSIC UP AND DOWN)</item>
<item>6 FACTS: In all, eight men died, in the army camp near Havana,<lb/>
7 that Dr. Walter Reed might prove that it was the<lb/>
8 mosquito that carried yellow fever to man, and not<lb/>
9 contagion, proximity to somebody sick. Eight men dead,<lb/>
10 that yellow fever might be stamped out, that the Panama<lb/>
11 Canal might be built, that science and progress might<lb/>
12 once more triumph over nature. Eight men. But Wallace<lb/>
13 Forbes lived.<lb/>
14 (MUSIC)</item>
<pb n="14" id="f03843019"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-13-</item>
<item>1 WALLACE: Rosita --</item>
<item>2 ROSITA: Wally, my most loved---(ALMOST A SOB OF RELIEF)</item>
<item>3 WALLACE: Here! Hey! Look at me---you're crying---</item>
<item>4 ROSITA: (THROUGH SOB) It is for happiness, Wally. I was so<lb/>
5 worried --</item>
<item>6 WALLACE: I'm okay---I'm okay. Come on, cheer up---I'm here,<lb/>
7 aren't I?</item>
<item>8 ROSITA: Yes, Wally, you are here. And now we are together<lb/>
9 again. And now we are to be married, is it not?</item>
<item>10 WALLACE: You bet it is, honey.<lb/>
11 (MUSIC SNEAK)<lb/>
12 You bet it is---just as soon as we can --<lb/>
13 (MUSIC UP &amp; DOWN)</item>
<item>14 FACTS: Wallace Forbes, married by the army chaplain, lived on<lb/>
15 in Cuba, after his honorable discharge from the army.<lb/>
16 He would have stayed there the rest of his life, but his<lb/>
17 wife and their child both died, within a tragically<lb/>
18 short time after their marriage. So Wallace Forbes<lb/>
19 went back to the States, to Minneapolis, where his<lb/>
20 family was living. But running a cigar store in the<lb/>
21 Vendome Hotel was a tame life for a man who had fought<lb/>
22 in one war and spent six years in the tropics. So in<lb/>
23 1916....</item>
<item>24 WALLACE: I'm leaving, mother---</item>
<item>25 MOTHER: Now what, Wallace?</item>
<pb n="15" id="f03843020"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-14-</item>
<item>1 WALLACE: Been talking to the officers down at the recruiting<lb/>
2 post. I can get to join Black John Pershing in<lb/>
3 Mexico, if I hurry --</item>
<item>4 MOTHER: Oh, Wallace! The army again?</item>
<item>5 WALLACE: It's a good life for me, mom. Don't worry. They can't<lb/>
6 kill me. I'll be back in the springtime,<lb/>
7 (MUSIC SNEAK)<lb/>
8 with a good tan from that Mexican sun ---<lb/>
9 (MUSIC UP &amp; DOWN)</item>
<item>10 FACTS: Wallace Forbes wrote his mother, he even visited her in<lb/>
11 Thanksgiving of 1919. He was in the Army to stay. His<lb/>
12 last letter, sent from an army post in Texas....</item>
<item>13 WALLACE: (READING) I'm being sent to duty in the Philippines,<lb/>
14 mother. After Cuba, twenty years ago, this won't be<lb/>
15 anything. Remind me to send you some presents when I<lb/>
16 get there, and give my best regards to everybody at<lb/>
17 home.<lb/>
18 (MUSIC SWELL)<lb/>
19 Signed your son, Wallace Forbes...<lb/>
20 (MUSIC UP AND DOWN)</item>
<item>21 FACTS: His family never heard from Wallace Wellington <del>Reed</del><add>Forbes</add><lb/>
22 again. He does not know of his present good fortune.<lb/>
23 Nor does he know that his father has died, and that in<lb/>
24 <del>Minneapolis</del><add>Chicago</add> his mother is still living, hoping that<lb/>
25 she will see him at least once more before she too is<lb/>
26 called away.<lb/>
27 (MUSIC)</item>
<pb n="16" id="f03843021"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-15-</item>
<item>1 M.C: Wallace Wellington Forbes performed his act of heroism<lb/>
2 in 1900, as did the other volunteers for that grave deed.<lb/>
3 It was not until February 28, 1929, after attention had<lb/>
4 been called to their bravery in Paul de Kruif's book<lb/>
5 Microbe Hunters, that the Congress passed a special<lb/>
6 enabling act to reward the men or their heirs for their<lb/>
7 heroism of almost thirty years past. By the terms of<lb/>
8 the act, Wallace Wellington Forbes was to receive one<lb/>
9 hundred and twenty-five dollars a month for the rest of<lb/>
10 his life. This money now totals seventeen thousand,<lb/>
11 seven hundred and fifty dollars; but Wallace Forbes<lb/>
12 has never been found to claim it. The Finance Department<lb/>
13 of the United States Army is looking for Wallace Forbes<lb/>
14 for this reason and no other. Only to turn over to him<lb/>
15 the fortune that is his. We hope that he, or someone<lb/>
16 who knows his whereabouts, will have heard this account<lb/>
17 of his heroism, and will thus be in a position to let<lb/>
18 us know how to get in touch with him. If you know, you<lb/>
19 will communicate with us, won't you?</item>
<item>20 ANNR: Your letters, postcards, or other communications should<lb/>
21 be sent to the Ironized Yeast Board of Missing Heirs,<lb/>
22 Box 705, New York City.</item>
<item>23 MC: And don't forget that if you are the first person to<lb/>
24 give us information which leads to this man's discovery,<lb/>
25 you will get Ironized Yeast's check for fifty dollars.</item>
<pb n="17" id="f03843022"/>
<item>FORBES</item>
<item>-16-</item>
<item>1 FACTS: This was the case of the estate being held for<lb/>
2 Wallace Wellington Forbes, spelled F-O-R-B-E-S, who<lb/>
3 would at present be sixty-two years old; had fair hair<lb/>
4 and blue eyes; a stocky build, bushy eyebrows that met<lb/>
5 over the nose, tattoo marks on both arms, and one<lb/>
6 thumb missing. The value of the fortune held for him<lb/>
7 by the Finance Department of the U.S. Army: seventeen<lb/>
8 thousand, seven hundred and fifty dollars.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
