<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03840006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Adrian Macia, November 21, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03840006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-11-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Macia, Adrian</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis B.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mable H.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-11-21">November 21, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03840006</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Adrian Macia, November 21, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench wants to know what it would cost to buy the remains of the site of Camp Lazear. Hench discusses his plans to memorialize the site.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-11-21">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Adrian Macia, November 21, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03840006"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<date value="1941-11-21">November 21, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Senor Adrian Macia<lb/>
Manzana de Gomez 325<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senor Macia:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You must have wondered why I have been silent for so long. I realize<lb/>
that I have long owed you a letter but the press of my professional work has kept<lb/>
me from writing you. My last contact with you was in April when Mr. Moran and I<lb/>
rather impolitely chased you about town in order to get the certificate of possession<lb/>
of the little building at Finca San Jose before my plane left for the States.</p>
<p>Permit me to send you by separate post (regular mail) 5 copies of an article<lb/>
on the Conquest of Yellow Fever which was just published in an American Medical<lb/>
magazine. In it you will find a copy of the photograph of your good self with Mr.<lb/>
Moran, Senor Zunzunegui and myself. I hope you do not mind my publishing your photo-<lb/>
graph. Indeed I hope that it will please you to establish publicly your interesting<lb/>
connection with this historic site. I have now in preparation another paper to be<lb/>
entitled &ldquo;The Identification of Camp Lazear&rdquo; (or some such title) which I will pub-<lb/>
lish with Senors Moran and Pogolotti as co-authors. Without their help I could never<lb/>
have found the spot and without your real interest and generosity I could never have<lb/>
hoped to memorialize the spot for the permanent edification of all who may be brought<lb/>
to see it and for the permanent glorification of those great Cuban and American physi-<lb/>
cians who conquered yellow fever. My special purpose in writing you now is to ask<lb/>
you several very important questions.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. What would it cost me to buy the remains of the site of Camp Lazear?<lb/>
I imagine I would want that part bounded by the fence behind the little houses near<lb/>
where Senor Zunzunegui lives (this to be the &ldquo;western&rdquo; boundary, i.e. about on a<lb/>
line with the northern extension of Calle Luis Carrero), the &ldquo;southern&rdquo; boundary to<lb/>
be about Pablo Calzadilla (behind the site where Building No. 2 was), the &ldquo;eastern&rdquo;<lb/>
boundary to be such as not to interfere with the present lime kilm, the &ldquo;northern&rdquo;<lb/>
boundary to be sufficiently behind the remains of Building No. 1 so as to protect it<lb/>
and yet not take in any of the old quarry. I may not have my boundaries and directions<lb/>
quite accurate but I am sure you will know what I mean. If we go ahead with this we<lb/>
should have enough land (but not too much) to make a decent-sized plot. <unclear>When</unclear> I talked<lb/>
to you in April you were hopeful that your partners who share the deed to this property<lb/>
might become more interested in this venture and might even be willing to become im-<lb/>
portant and early contributors by offering their share in this little property. The<lb/>
spot is so historical and can be made so interesting and attractive (if my hopes and<lb/>
plans come true) that I believe in the long run they might be very proud to be listed<lb/>
as among the founders or donors of the memorial. At any rate you believed that even<lb/>
if you could not enlist their full support they would be willing to help us by charg-<lb/>
ing little more than a nominal amount or certainly an amount within my modest means.<lb/>
Again let me assure you that my only motive is in the interest of medical history and<lb/>
the proper recognition of a great dead done by great man. I would appreciate it<lb/>
if you would present a copy of my Hygeia article to each of your partners so that they<lb/>
may get a better understanding of the significance of the spot.</item>
<item>2. Do you know whether Mr. Moran was able to get the remains of Building<lb/>
No. 1 temporarily repaired? I have written him twice about this but have had no<lb/>
answer, undoubtedly because of the press of work upon him. He has been such a loyal<lb/>
friend and faithful colleague in this venture that I have no doubt he has done what he<lb/>
could. But of course steps will have to be made to protect it permanently, not<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03840007"/>
Senor Adrian Macia<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 21, 1941<lb/>
temporarily.</item>
<item>3. If I am able to purchase the camp site can you give me any idea of<lb/>
how much the yearly taxes on it would be? I believe the size of the ground we want<lb/>
will be only about 150 yards square; am I right in that estimate?</item>
<item><p>4. I am hoping to see erected over the Building No. 1 (to be either<lb/>
moved nearer Camp Columbia or left on the present site) a suitable permanent building<lb/>
of one story in height, characteristic Cuban architecture and construction, size<lb/>
about 100 x 50 feet (more or less, perhaps less) arranged roughly according to the<lb/>
enclosed crude plan. It would probably need no cellar or excavated foundation and<lb/>
a minimal of heating and plumbing. My ideas are not yet crystallized and I would<lb/>
welcome suggestions on your part. There should be room for a caretaker certainly<lb/>
by day, perhaps his simple living quarters by night. There should be a small public<lb/>
rest room (i.e. lavatories for men and women) and in one corner of the building a<lb/>
small section (counter, display cases and desk) where simple souvenirs might be<lb/>
sold (photographs, post cards, a booklet on the history of the spot, etc.) by the<lb/>
caretaker. The whole thing should be simple and inexpensive yet dignified and per-<lb/>
manent. There should be a sky-light over the central part of the roof so as to admit<lb/>
extra light unless this is too expensive, in which case adequate electric lighting<lb/>
should be provided.</p>
<p>Can I ask you to give me a rough idea of how much such a little building<lb/>
would cost (1) to erect (2) to maintain yearly? Could I perhaps interest you in<lb/>
helping in the plans and building of such a little shrine? In asking you these<lb/>
questions now I know you will realize that all of my plans are tentative and in the<lb/>
formative stage, my resources are distinctly limited and I must ask you for this<lb/>
help without as yet committing myself to anything definite or putting myself under<lb/>
any obligation to pay for costly plans and specifications now.</p></item>
<item>5. If the Cuban authorities, in accepting this memorial, strongly desire<lb/>
the building to be moved to the &ldquo;false site&rdquo; of Campamento Lazear (across the railroad<lb/>
track from Camp Columbia) can you give me any idea how much it would cost to move<lb/>
the little building to the new site? Could it be moved in one piece on a large<lb/>
truck (after being temporarily spliced together with boards, chains or what not)?<lb/>
You recall the building is only 14 x 20 feet.</item>
<item>6. Have you any idea what it would cost to place on the sites of buildings<lb/>
one and two a simple boulder or simple shaft with a bronze plaque (i.e. one on each<lb/>
site) telling what had formerly been there, each plaque to be perhaps 2 or 3 feet<lb/>
by 3 or 4 feet square?</item>
</list></p>
<p>In asking these questions I do so because of the fact that I know of<lb/>
your sincere interest in the project and sympathy with me in it. You have amply<lb/>
demonstrated this already by your kind and most generous transference of the<lb/>
little building to me. Happily also you are an architect and engineer and, unless<lb/>
I am greatly mistaken, you belong to that group of civic minded individuals who<lb/>
delight in beautifying and preserving historical and civic sites and monuments.</p>
<p>As soon as I receive the above information from you, it is my plan to<lb/>
set up a committee of civic and historically minded persons in this country and in<lb/>
Havana to help me see this project through and to act as advisers and councillors.<lb/>
Already several distinguished Americans have tentatively consented to join me in<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03840008"/>
Senor Adrian Macia<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
November 21, 1941<lb/>
this venture; these include the daughter of Walter Reed, the widow of Dr. Lazear,<lb/>
3 of the high ranking army medical officers in Washington who knew Reed well, several<lb/>
very distinguished physicians, etc. I hope also that in Cuba we can have such men<lb/>
as Drs. Finlay, Ramos, Albertini, Recio, Miss Agramonte, Senora Rojas, and others on<lb/>
it, not to mention yourself and Mr. Moran of course. Perhaps too we can enlist the<lb/>
interest and patronage of the President of the Cuban Republic as well as other govern-<lb/>
mental personages in Washington and Havana so that in time the spot can be dedicated<lb/>
appropriately. But before convening such an advisory committee I must have at least<lb/>
some of the data I have herein requested of you. The first thing to be done, of<lb/>
course, is to see how much the camp site will cost and then to find out if the Cuban<lb/>
government has enough land near the Military Hospital on which to set up a memorial<lb/>
or whether a second piece of land must be bought there. I am asking Mr. Moran and Mr.<lb/>
Pogolotti to advise me as to the area near the Military Hospital owned by the govern-<lb/>
ment.</p>
<p>Believe me, my dear Senor Macia, I do most sincerely appreciate your many<lb/>
past favors and generosity. I know that you are a very busy man and I hesitate to<lb/>
burden you with these questions. But we have a little saying here in the States<lb/>
which I believe applies in this instance: &ldquo;If you really want something done,<lb/>
ask a busy man to do it:&ldquo;</p>
<p>I will await your reply with eagerness and again let me express my gratitude<lb/>
for your continued interest in what I believe to be a most worthy and altruistic<lb/>
venture. I need not tell you that this is <hi>not</hi> to be a monument to Americans, but a<lb/>
monument to glorify Finlay and Delgado <hi>equally</hi> with Reed and his associates. They<lb/>
are inseparable in history. Indeed it is to be more than that--it is to be a<lb/>
monument honoring the medical profession of Cuba and America and their humanitarian<lb/>
ideals. It delights me that I can work in a small way toward a better understanding<lb/>
between the Cuban and American people. Especially in times like these it is so<lb/>
terribly important to strengthen the bonds of friendship and comradeship between the<lb/>
peoples of our two republics.</p>
<p>I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours most sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
