<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03842002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to Philip Showalter Hench, February 2, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03842002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-02-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Montgomery, Robert</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-02-02">February 2, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03842002</idno>
<title>Letter from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to Philip Showalter Hench, February 2, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Rodriguez Leon criticizes the sketches for the Cornwell painting. She believes that they are neither historically nor culturally accurate.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-02-02">
<head>Letter from Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon to Philip Showalter Hench, February 2, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03842002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
15 Street No. 34 Vedado,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<date value="1941-02-02">February 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>/41.</date>
</dateline>
Not Received until<lb/>
March 11, 1941<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
Mayo Clinic,<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sorry to see how much I have<lb/>
delayed again in answering your letters of January<lb/>
and February. I received the brochure on your<lb/>
talk on the Yellow Fever experiments at Washington<lb/>
and Jefferson University; also the reprints of the<lb/>
preliminary sketches for the John Wyeth Co. painting<lb/>
and the page of my father's address. Thank you</p>
<p>I have been more than usually busy lately<lb/>
with Board Examinations at our school; and we<lb/>
are hoping to put on a Spanish play by our<lb/>
department, during Easter week, which will mean<lb/>
added responsability for me in the rehearsing,<lb/>
<unclear>costuming</unclear> and publicity of same. You tell<lb/>
me you expect to come to Cuba late in March,<lb/>
I certainly hope we will have the pleasure<lb/>
of renewing our very pleasant acquaintance<lb/>
with you and Mrs. Hench. I also hope that your<lb/>
stay will be prolonged into April sufficiently,<lb/>
that I may get a chance to offer you some<lb/>
assistance with your investigations (after<lb/>
my &ldquo;dramatic&rdquo; venture is over and I have some<lb/>
free time). As to the papers out at the farm, I<lb/>
am not very sure I can promise you any-<lb/>
thingdefinite. I shall try, but the place is<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03842003"/>
II<lb/>
rented and quite out of the way. I shall do my best about<lb/>
trying to get something, at least; but since all of it<lb/>
is too bulky to bring here and the cases are not<lb/>
classified I am doubtful that there is anything<lb/>
there of extreme value. Mostly, as I can remember<lb/>
they are reprints of papers and addresses; loads<lb/>
of pictures of medical conferences and missions<lb/>
etc, etc, The negatives of what seemed to be early<lb/>
photographs I brought home with me on my<lb/>
last visit, and I believe there are one or two files<lb/>
here that I didn't have time to look into with<lb/>
you on your previous visit. We may try those,<lb/>
at all events. This summer I am planning<lb/>
earnestly to go into all of it and properly<lb/>
file and organize it.</p>
<p>[ Asto the Wyeth Co. people I have not<lb/>
heard from them. I do have one or two photographs<lb/>
of my Father in uniform, but never saw any of<lb/>
his uniforms that I can remember. An old kaki<lb/>
hat (campaign type broad-brimmed. felt) we used<lb/>
to use in the attic for &ldquo;dressing up&rdquo; games I.<lb/>
have also seen the revolver, belt, buttons, etc. lying<lb/>
around in the old house. I am sure though and<lb/>
his pictures are all in <del>such</del> a one, that he usually<lb/>
wore white uniforms. I shall have some copies<lb/>
of the pictures I have, made this week and shall<lb/>
keep them on hand, in case they finally want<lb/>
them. If you wish, and there is time before you<lb/>
start south I shall send you some.</p>
<p>My personal criticism of the sketches<lb/>
is the same of the film by Robert Montgomery.<lb/>
The tendency to make father short and Latin in<lb/>
gestures and attitude is ever present. He happened<lb/>
to be the only one in the Commission who knew<lb/>
Dr. Finlay, therefore the introductions were naturally<lb/>
made by him and he would not look as<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03842004"/>
III<lb/>
&ldquo;puzzled&rdquo;at the old man's explanations as they<lb/>
make him appear in the sketches. (He had heard<lb/>
the crazy and unscientific notions of Finlay time<lb/>
and again Finlay was not <del><unclear></unclear></del> tall, stout and<lb/>
inclined to the &ldquo;paunchy&rdquo; like his son, with blinking<lb/>
myopic little scotch eyes. The erect and beautifully<lb/>
tailored old man would never fit in my imagination<lb/>
with the &ldquo;buggy-doctor&rdquo; oculist who went around<lb/>
fitting eyeglasses in <unclear>Camaguez</unclear> province. Who<lb/>
are the sitting figures (certainly not a Cuban the<lb/>
one with the Lincolnian attitude).</p>
<p>The U. S. Commission is not too bad. Reed<lb/>
of course is made bigger to command attention<lb/>
and Lazear, a distinguished type with a very quiet<lb/>
manner would naturally be quietly hearing<lb/>
and observing the interview: Carol who was<lb/>
against the thing and a grouchy sort of fellow<lb/>
of humble origin and always ill at ease among<lb/>
strangers would probably be sulking in a corner<lb/>
And as to my Father, one of the pictures is not<lb/>
so bad, the other one makes him look like a<lb/>
dwarf and I specially object to the position<lb/>
of his hands. He happened to have the most<lb/>
beautiful hands I ever have seen in a man<lb/>
but tho' <del>they were</del> always well kept, they were<lb/>
strong and nervous, manly in every gesture and<lb/>
<hi>never</hi> in the french music-master <del>gesture</del><add>posture</add> he has<lb/>
in one of the sketches (arched little finger et all)<lb/>
It seems hard to convince Americans that a<lb/>
Cuban can be 6 ft 1 inch., have dark hair, but very<lb/>
bright blue eyes and a ruddy complexion.</p>
<p>Another thing the patio-background<lb/>
is not bad in itself(.) The flag of course is ri-<lb/>
diculous; no Cuban would submit his flag to<lb/>
such disrespect as crowding it in a corner of an<lb/>
indoor patio, and he would never expose it<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03842005"/>
IV<lb/>
except on National holidays, and always on the front<lb/>
of his house (2) I imagine Finlay used to wear a Prince Albert<lb/>
like all doctors then, but he would never have white<lb/>
vests and fancy light pants (3) Again, guests would<lb/>
never be allowed to stand, and much less keep<lb/>
holding their <unclear>caps</unclear> (or is it a <unclear>cap</unclear> Reed and Carol<lb/>
are holding) (4) The kind of furniture in the picture<lb/>
&amp; books<lb/>
(heavy carved pieces) would never be placed in a<lb/>
patio in this country (remember daily showers that<lb/>
seem to drop out of a clear sky). The Cuban would<lb/>
work outside under the glare of the sun and<lb/>
less in those days with heavy clothes they wore.<lb/>
(5) Last but not least, a Cuban might entertain<lb/>
some visitors in a gallery along the sides of <unclear>the patio</unclear><lb/>
under roof always, in shady and cool comfort,<lb/>
but we, and the older generations much less, never<lb/>
considered the patio in the light <unclear>of</unclear> the Palm Beach<lb/>
or Hollywood crowd <del><unclear>does</unclear></del>. That is left to hotels<lb/>
and restaurants. A patio provides shady trees<lb/>
captures the breeze <add>gives space for there refreshing sound of a <unclear>fountain</unclear></add> and serves as communications<lb/>
for all the family from rooms, to street, to dining room.<lb/>
etc) Some of the women may even bring out their<lb/>
sewing perhaps, but the family never &ldquo;<hi>lounges</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
in it, Andalusian style. Remember that in<lb/>
the old colonial houses of the type pictured,<lb/>
even the horses were lead across the patio<lb/>
into the back yard and stables, after unhitching<lb/>
the carriage which remained in the broad entrance<lb/>
hall or &ldquo;zagu&aacute;n&rdquo;. Is it plausible that Finlay receive<lb/>
formal visitors, and spread out all his working<lb/>
materials and instruments where there is such<lb/>
little seclusion. Father expressly mentions that<lb/>
Finlay handed them a glass jar with some of<lb/>
his precious mosquitoes <hi>in his study</hi>.</p>
<p>I am very skeptical (please don't feel<lb/>
offended, because you certainly are conscientous in<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03842006"/>
V<lb/>
your research) about the general attitude of<lb/>
Americans when they set out on some scheme<lb/>
where costuming or historical accuracy is<lb/>
required. Hollywood versions of historical<lb/>
events generally dissapoint me for their<lb/>
gross incongruities. Your friends of Wyeth<lb/>
and Co will probably prefer not to hear my<lb/>
opinion in the matter. The artist was in Cuba<lb/>
last year, but he never tried to get in touch<lb/>
with me while in Havana and I tried un-<lb/>
successfully to meet him.</p>
<p>Even the theatrical set up of the patio<lb/>
is not so bad if the sun were not so strong<lb/>
on both guests and host. Also polished<lb/>
wood furniture, which would not survive<lb/>
a week of our outdoors. It would seem<lb/>
to be about noon according to the bright<lb/>
splashes of sunlight. Never, in late afternoon<lb/>
would a Cuban patio be so glaring. The sketch<lb/>
with the shutter and glass door background is<lb/>
much better in all respects than the others ones<lb/>
The type of window - grating on that one would<lb/>
naturally be the kitchen and servants quarters.<lb/>
near which no guests would loiter, specially<lb/>
in those days. The <del><unclear></unclear></del> one I prefer has the<lb/>
cap in Reed's <add>hand</add> (or is it) and Finlay's white waist-<lb/>
coat, bow-tie and fancy pants and <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>Lazear</add> (who<lb/>
would naturally be interested and attentive) is<lb/>
too much in the background, for the one member<lb/>
in the Commission who knew most about<lb/>
mosquitoes.</p>
<p>I am sure my impressions about<lb/>
this will interest you far more than Wyeth &amp;<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03842007"/>
VI<lb/>
Co. that is why I am bothering you with<lb/>
them. Hurriedly given out, at random while<lb/>
examining the pictures at first sight, they<lb/>
are probably not worth much, after all.</p>
<p>Will you tell me who the publisher<lb/>
of Finlay's biography is? I have tried<lb/>
to get it in our bookstores without<lb/>
any results and I wish to order a<lb/>
copy, as I am sure most of it must prove<lb/>
&ldquo;interesting&rdquo; to read. Charlie Finlay, Jr. is<lb/>
not at all a literary man, but I have<lb/>
heard he didn't write it, only sponsored<lb/>
and backed the contents. So much better<lb/>
for the story, because he stutters even in<lb/>
writing.</p>
<p>I apologise. I am very biting<lb/>
today; but please excuse me.</p>
<p>Please give my love to Mrs.<lb/>
Hench. We are looking forward to seeing<lb/>
you. Please telephone whenever you<lb/>
get the time, after arriving, so that we<lb/>
can arrange <unclear>some</unclear> meetings before &ldquo;the last<lb/>
day&rdquo;. -</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon</signed>.
Telephone:<lb/>
F-4954<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
