<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03841003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Alberto Recio, May 1, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03841003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-05-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Recio, Alberto</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-05-01">May 1, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03841003</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Alberto Recio, May 1, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench hopes that the sites affiliated with the conquest of yellow fever will be memorialized. Hench solicits Recio' help in obtaining a statement from the Cuban government as evidence that it accepted Hench's report on the actual site of Camp Lazear. He offers to write an abstract of the report for a Cuban medical journal, and hopes that the Cuban media will also be informed of the discovery.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-05-01">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Alberto Recio, May 1, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03841003"/>
<opener>
Copy to Mr. Moran<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-05-01">May 1, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Alberto Recio<lb/>
Ave. de la Independencia y Montero<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Recio:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I appreciate very much indeed your kind letter of April 22 in which<lb/>
you said that you had read my report to Dr. Ramos and find it to be true to the best<lb/>
of your knowledge. It has been a most interesting experience for me to be permitted<lb/>
to &ldquo;rediscover Camp Lazear&rdquo; and to help locate the sites where such wonderful work<lb/>
was done, on behalf of the conquest of yellow fever. I feel greatly encouraged to<lb/>
have the great interest of yourself and Dr. Ramos, and I sincerely hope that I can<lb/>
interest enough American friends so that we can memorialize these sites properly.<lb/>
It may be necessary to call on your government for their formal approval and perhaps<lb/>
even their help, but I am hoping that the group of American physicians can make<lb/>
this gesture to the Cuban government and the medical profession, without outside help.</p>
<p>Do you remember the morning you, Dr. Ramos and I happened to meet in<lb/>
the library of the Finlay Institute, when Dr. Ramos dictated to Miss Malaret, formally<lb/>
accepting my report? It was to be translated into English, and an English and Spanish<lb/>
copy were to be sent to me within the next three or four days. I have not yet re-<lb/>
ceived this. My local ambassador, Mr. Moran, has done his best to get it for me,<lb/>
but I gather that Dr. Ramos has been very busy and has been out of town also. Would<lb/>
it be asking too much for you to discreetly inquire from Miss Malaret as to whether<lb/>
I can expect to receive this shortly? You will understand that it is so much easier<lb/>
for me to approach my American friends for financial support when I have definite<lb/>
evidence that the Cuban government has accepted my report and believes that we have<lb/>
truly discovered the site of Camp Lazear and the remains of Building No. 1.</p>
<p>It was a great pleasure for me to meet you and I shall take the<lb/>
liberty, as Dr. Ramos suggested, of keeping you informed of my further activities<lb/>
in behalf of our project. Anything that you can do to help me by interesting other<lb/>
members of your government, I will appreciate most sincerely. Now that Dr. Ramos and<lb/>
you have read and accepted my report, do you think it would be feasible to publicize<lb/>
it somewhat? Would it be best to have a report come from Dr. Ramos' office to the<lb/>
newspapers? Would it be acceptable to have me write an abstract of the report for<lb/>
a Cuban medical journal? I shall do nothing without the full approval of yourself<lb/>
and Dr. Ramos.</p>
<p>I am having sent to you with our compliments the Proceedings of the<lb/>
Mayo Clinic Staff Meetings, which should reach you regularly and which I hope you<lb/>
will find of interest.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
