<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03840003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Adrian Macia to Philip Showalter Hench, April 2, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Macia, Adrian</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03840003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-04-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-04-02">April 2, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03840003</idno>
<title>Letter from Adrian Macia to Philip Showalter Hench, April 2, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Macia agrees with Hench that the original site of Camp Lazear is located on the Finca San Jose. He discusses the history of this area and explains physical changes on this property due to quarrying work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-04-02">
<head>Letter from Adrian Macia to Philip Showalter Hench, April 2, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03840003"/>
<opener>
ADRIAN MACIA<lb/>
INGENIERO CIVIL Y ARQUITECTO<lb/>
HABANA<lb/>
<dateline>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<date value="1941-04-02">April 2, 1941.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
Hotel Nacional,<lb/>
Havana.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Sirs:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was very happy yesterday to meet you together with Mr. Moran and I look<lb/>
back with real pleasure to the trip the three of us made to inspect the site presumed<lb/>
to be that of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; and House No. 1, where the experiments in the research<lb/>
work in connection with Yellow Fever and mosquitos as a carrying agent took place<lb/>
in 1900, and in which experiments Mr. Moran took such heroic part. The site is<lb/>
located within the section known as &ldquo;Finca San Jos&eacute;&rdquo;, property of the firm of Rafecas<lb/>
y Maci&aacute; S. en C. a partnership of which I am director.</p>
<p>I am very pleased to inform you that upon examination of the old pictures<lb/>
you showed me of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; and using them as a guide, I am absolutely convinced<lb/>
that the wooden house that exists today at &ldquo;Finca San Jos&eacute;&rdquo; is No. 1 of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;<lb/>
and is located today on the same site as that shown in the pictures.</p>
<p>Near this house there still exist the ruins of an old Lime Kiln and I was<lb/>
able to place myself in what I am sure were the positions from which two of the<lb/>
pictures you showed me were apparently taken. In each case the existing House No. 1<lb/>
and the remains of the above mentioned old Lime Kiln wall appeared in the same relative<lb/>
positions as in the picture. It is unfortunate that House No. 2 does not now exist,<lb/>
having apparently been destroyed in 1926 cyclone, but there are remains showing<lb/>
where it was located. These remains again support my conviction of the authenticity<lb/>
of the site as, if we place an object upon this site and suppose it to be House No. 2,<lb/>
we find it in the same relative position to House No. 1 and the old wall as that in<lb/>
which it actually stood as shown on both pictures mentioned.</p>
<p>We bought this property in 1919 and the old house is leased to Mr.<lb/>
Zunzunegui, whose father had rented said House No. 1 and lived in it from 1907 to<lb/>
1936. Mr. Zunzunegui has been of great assistance in locating all this as he<lb/>
perfectly remembers the family moving into there in 1907, when he was a boy of about<lb/>
14 years, and living there until 1936. He still has that section under lease, where<lb/>
he operates a quarry.</p>
<p>In addition to the foregoing, I can assure you, as an architect, that there<lb/>
are two distinct characteristics in the old house today not found in that type of<lb/>
building either of that period or later. One is a sliding window and the other the<lb/>
shape and construction of the ceiling.</p>
<p>Referring to the point you brought up that, in the old pictures, the<lb/>
ground appears to be flat while today it shows a distinct slope, I would suggest<lb/>
that this is of no great importance as this could easily be accounted for by the<lb/>
fact that quarrying work has gone on there for many years, great excavations having<lb/>
been made near by and possibly something was done in part of the old &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;<lb/>
site to provide drainage, all these changes possibly contributing to erosion of the<lb/>
top soil, making it appear as a different looking lot of land.</p>
<p>Hoping that all of this might be of interest to you, I remain</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very truly</salute>
<signed>ADRIAN MACIA</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
