<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03843024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Transcript from the Court of Missing Heirs, Program No. 93, September 23, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03843024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-09-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-09-23">September 23, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03843024</idno>
<title>Transcript from the Court of Missing Heirs, Program No. 93, September 23, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This transcript focuses on the estate of Wallace Forbes and discusses the government pension due him and his heirs for his service as a volunteer in the Yellow Fever Commission experiments, in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-09-23">
<head>Transcript from the Court of Missing Heirs, Program No. 93, September 23, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03843024"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
The COURT of MISSING HEIRS<lb/>
RADIO PROGRAM<lb/>
LOCK BOX 705 NEW YORK<lb/>
Broadcast Tuesday, <date value="1941-09-23">Sept. 23, 1941</date>
</dateline>
_______________________<lb/>
JAMES F. WATERS &middot; Authors &middot; ALFRED SHEBEL<lb/>
_______________________<lb/>
Review of Facts<lb/>
Program No. 93<lb/>
</opener>
<p><hi>Estate of Wallace Wellington Forbes</hi></p>
<p>Valuation: $17,750</p>
<p><hi>WALLACE WELLINGTON FORBES</hi> - <hi>WANTED ONLY FOR ONE REASON</hi> BY THE UNITED STATES ARMY<lb/>
FINANCE DEPARTMENT <hi>TO GIVE HIM $17,750</hi> and <hi>NO CHARGE WILL BE BROUGHT AGAINST WALLACE<lb/>
W. FORBES</hi> AND HE SHOULD HAVE NO FEAR IN APPLYING FOR THIS MONEY.</p>
<p>Wallace Wellington Forbes is a missing heir actually to his own estate for the reason<lb/>
that an Act of Congress passed on February 28, 1929 granted to six Spanish War<lb/>
Veterans $125.00 a month for life as a reward for their heroism in submitting to tests<lb/>
conducted by Major Walter Reed after the Spanish American War in Cuba in an effort to<lb/>
stamp out the disease of Yellow Fever. Wallace Wellington Forbes was born in Gales-<lb/>
burg, Illinois, the son of James Wellington Forbes and he enlisted for service in the<lb/>
Spanish-American War in 1898, from Minneapolis where his parents were living at the<lb/>
time. He lived in Minneapolis after his discharge from service in 1902 until 1916<lb/>
when he reenlisted again to serve with Pershing's Punitive Expedition into Mexico. He<lb/>
re-enlisted twice afterwards, but in 1926, at the Presidio he left the Army. Wallace<lb/>
Wellington Forbes, the missing heir to his own estate will be paid $125.00 a month for<lb/>
the balance of his life, as well as collecting the above accumulation of payments,<lb/>
payable since 1929. The physical description of the missing heir is as follows: Light<lb/>
blue eyes - blond hair - stocky build - long body and short legs - present age 62 years<lb/>
- ruddy complexion - weight when last seen approximately 150 to 165 lbs.</p>
<p><hi>Estate of Margaret Kenny</hi></p>
<p>Valuation: $11,000</p>
<p>Margaret Kenny was born Margaret Corrigan in County Cavan, Ireland. It appears from<lb/>
the record that she was married near the city of Lynn, Massachusetts or the Charles-<lb/>
town Section of Boston to Edward J. Kenny. After the marriage Margaret Kenny and her<lb/>
husband took up their residence in San Francisco. When she died she left an estate<lb/>
under terms of a Will bequeathing $4,000 as a legacy to her niece and nephew, whose<lb/>
names are Grace and Henry Hawley. It is known that the missing heirs, Grace and Henry<lb/>
Hawley, children of her sister, lived at Lynn, Mass. or in the Charlestown Section of<lb/>
Boston. These two cities are the last known whereabouts of the missing heirs.</p>
<p>HEIRS DISCOVERED</p>
<p><hi>Estate of Earl Warren</hi></p>
<p>Valuation: $1,700</p>
<p>Earl Warren was accidentally killed in Quadio, Connecticut, in 1920, due to fatal<lb/>
injuries received while being employed in a sawmill. At the time of his death he left<lb/>
six children with varying ages up to eleven years. Two of these children are today<lb/>
missing heirs who will divide equally the $1700.00 balance of a compensation award.<lb/>
The names of the missing heirs are Walter Warren and Florence Warren. It is known<lb/>
that Florence Warren was married and her married name was Mrs. George Zemek. She was<lb/>
last heard of in Mansfield, Conn. where she was living with her foster-father, but it<lb/>
is known that she came to New York City to live and may be living there today. The<lb/>
physical description of Mrs. Florence Warren Zemek is as follows: brown eyes - light<lb/>
brown hair - medium build - present age 21 years - light complexion - weight when last<lb/>
seen 126 lbs. The second missing heir Walter Warren is 29 years of age, was honorably<lb/>
discharged from the Army on Sept. 13, 1940. Walter Warren lived in Providence, R.I.<lb/>
at different times and had the address of General Delivery in that city.</p>
<p>We trust this will give you the information you desire. May we take<lb/>
this opportunity of thanking you for your interest as a listener to our program.</p>
<closer>
<signed>THE COURT OF MISSING HEIRS<lb/>
Radio Program<lb/>
Look Box 705 New York</signed>
The makers of Ironized Yeast will pay fifty dollars ($50.00) to the person from whom<lb/>
the Court of Missing Heirs first receives information, which in the opinion of the<lb/>
Administrators leads to the discovery of the heirs to any of the above cases.<lb/>
The Court of Missing Heirs is not vested with judicial power, and is not a court of law or a part of the judicial system of any<lb/>
state. Rather it is a dramatization of facts broadcast from coast to coast in an effort to find the heirs to estates unknown to them.--<lb/>
The sole purpose of this court is to render a public service gratuitously--to enable missing heirs to secure the legacies that are<lb/>
rightfully theirs. It is not the purpose of the court to give legal advice--and it does not solicit or accept compensation from anyone.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
