<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03842012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, July 11, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03842012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-07-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Cleveland (Oh.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-07-11">July 11, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03842012</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, July 11, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes the unveiling of the Cornwell painting and Kissinger's subsequent stroke. He discusses his ongoing research on the yellow fever history and inquires if she has found any data to refute criticisms of her father, Aristides Agramonte.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-07-11">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, July 11, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03842012"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-07-11">July 11, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Senora Rodriguez-Leon:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Permit me to return to you the group photograph and the six page<lb/>
manuscript of the address delivered by your father at the banquet for Doctors<lb/>
Gorgas and Kean in January, 1902. I had the former copied and enclose a copy<lb/>
with the original. I think it came out very well. I showed it to General<lb/>
Kean when I was recently in Washington but he could not identify those except<lb/>
your father, Guiteras and Finlay. I shall send copies to others (Truby, Al-<lb/>
bertini, etc.) to see if they can help. If you ever need more copies of the<lb/>
photograph I shall be glad to supply them.</p>
<p>I was for awhile concerned to note that the pages of your father's<lb/>
manuscript as numbered by somebody (perhaps your father) in the upper <hi>left</hi><lb/>
corner indicated that I had pages 1 through 5 and page 7 but no page 6. But<lb/>
then I noticed that somebody else has numbered them in the upper <hi>right</hi> hand<lb/>
corner, pages 1 through 6 consecutively and in reading the manuscript I find<lb/>
no apparent gap in the context on pages 5 and 7 (left corner numbering). I<lb/>
assume therefore that the manuscript is complete and I hope you can assure<lb/>
me that this assumption is correct. To be absolutely certain I made an ex-<lb/>
haustive search through my study, my office at the clinic, my secretary's<lb/>
data, as well as through the files of the photographic department but we<lb/>
found nothing to indicate that the manuscript was not complete as I am re-<lb/>
turning it.</p>
<p>You probably have heard that on June 2 in Cleveland during the<lb/>
week of the convention of the American Medical Association, Wyeths unveiled<lb/>
their yellow fever painting. The unveiling was in the Hotel Statler before<lb/>
a small but very select group of invited guests. The painting was unveiled<lb/>
by Walter Reed's daughter, Miss (or Mrs.) Blossom Reed, in the presence of<lb/>
the mayor of Cleveland, Doctors Van Etton and Lahey, President and President-<lb/>
elect of the American Medical Association, Mr. Kissinger, and representatives<lb/>
of various medical schools and art museums. A few old friends of Walter Reed<lb/>
were also there from Washington; these included Colonel Siler and former Sur-<lb/>
geon-General and Mrs. Ireland. The painting received much favorable comment.<lb/>
I think colored reproductions of it will be available soon. Of course it will<lb/>
not satisfy everyone but at least we all gave Mr. Cornwell our ideas on it and<lb/>
did our best. I was honored by being asked to give a brief address just after<lb/>
it was unveiled. I enclose a copy of this address. I think it will be pub-<lb/>
lished somewhere but I don't know where yet.</p>
<p>There was an unhappy aftermath to the occasion. The affair was on<lb/>
Monday noon (June 2). Just thirty-six hours later Mr. Kissinger had a severe<lb/>
stroke and was for awhile not expected to live. He still lingers, completely<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03842013"/>
AC<lb/>
Ag to Am<lb/>
Senora Rodriguez-Leon<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
July 11, 1941<lb/>
paralyzed on his right side, unable to speak or move. It is tragic and I<lb/>
hope he can be spared further suffering. I have also just heard that last<lb/>
week Walter Reed's daughter had a severe heart attack and may be confined<lb/>
to bed for months. She is aged fifty-eight years.</p>
<p>I am continuing my labors to uncover the full story of the con-<lb/>
quest. I have again visited Washington where Generals Kean and Ireland<lb/>
put me in touch with new data. I found some in the Archives Building;<lb/>
some at Fort Myers and elsewhere. I had a brief telephonic chat with Dr.<lb/>
Carroll's son; he was inexcusably and almost unspeakably rude and made me<lb/>
very suspicious that he possesses a guilty conscience for some as yet un-<lb/>
explained reason. I cannot confine the details to a letter but will tell<lb/>
you of it when next I visit Havana (war permitting). When I do, I hope I<lb/>
can come at a more convenient time for you. I am still hoping to be allowed<lb/>
to see and study your historical treasures. By the way, I found the &ldquo;Med-<lb/>
ical history of the Columbia Barracks Post Hospital&rdquo;--the written hospital<lb/>
records, and also the long filed records of the correspondence between the<lb/>
Surgeon General Sternberg and the Commission in Havana. One of my desires<lb/>
is to be able to contradict (by official records) Carroll's statement that<lb/>
your distinguished father was not in Havana when Lazear died. Have you<lb/>
found any data on this point that would be helpful to me? Also any data<lb/>
to explain the apparent contradictions in your father's published remarks<lb/>
about the first two inoculations? Undoubtedly there is a complete and<lb/>
honorable explanation somewhere and with your help we will in time find it<lb/>
and silence the petty criticism which however can never alter the main<lb/>
facts of your father's great services to humanity.</p>
<p>Please accept the best wishes of Mrs. Hench and me for yourself<lb/>
and your good husband.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
