<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03901009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo Ramos, March 4, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03901009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-03-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ramos, Domingo F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital, Military City (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-03-04">March 4, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03901009</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo Ramos, March 4, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench summarizes his research on the yellow fever commission and sends Ramos his report concerning the true site of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-03-04">
<pb n="1" id="f03901009"/>
<head>Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo Ramos, March 4, 1941</head>
<opener>
3154<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-03-04">March 4, 1941</date>
</dateline>
To: His Excellency, Dr. Domingo Ramos, Minister of National Defense,<lb/>
Government of Cuba, Havana, Cuba.<lb/>
From: Dr. Philip S. Hench, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota.<lb/>
<hi>Memorandum concerning the true site of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;</hi><lb/>
where the United States Army Yellow Fever Board (Drs. Reed, Carroll, Agramonte<lb/>
and Lazear) in 1900-1901 proved the truth of the concept of Dr. Carlos Finlay<lb/>
of Havana regarding the mosquito transmission of yellow fever.<lb/>
<salute>Your Excellency:</salute>
</opener>
<p>During part of his college career Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, the martyred member of the<lb/>
United States Army Yellow Fever Board, attended Washington and Jefferson College, Wash-<lb/>
ington, Pennsylvania. On October 26, 1940 this college dedicated a beautiful memorial<lb/>
building to the memory of Dr. Lazear. In preparation for this dedication the President<lb/>
of the College, Dr. Ralph Cooper Hutchison, asked me in 1937 to review the work of the<lb/>
<unclear>Board</unclear> in order to give an address thereon at the dedication. I reviewed the official<lb/>
<unclear>and</unclear> unofficial writings of the members of the Board and corresponded with certain sur-<lb/>
vivors of the yellow fever experiments, notably Mr. John J. Moran of Havana, and Mr.<lb/>
John R. Kissinger of Huntington, Indiana, the first two men to volunteer to receive<lb/>
<unclear>adequately</unclear> controled experimental yellow fever.</p>
<p>In April, 1940 I visited Havana to meet Mr. Moran and to view the former sites of<lb/>
Camp Columbia and Camp Lazear. Mr. Moran took me to the small plot of ground now owned<lb/>
by the Cuban government, marked off by a fence and memorialized by a sign as the site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear; this site is just across the La Playa railroad track from the rear of the<lb/>
Military Hospital at Ciudad Militar. Because of certain observations to be noted herein<lb/>
I <unclear>concluded</unclear> that the marked spot was not the true site of Camp Lazear. As a result of<lb/>
the subsequent investigations of Mr. Moran and myself with the cooperation of Mr. Luis<lb/>
<unclear>Pogolotti</unclear>, Havana engineer and real estate operator, we discovered (1) the true site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear and (2) the remains of one of the two chief buildings in which the work at<lb/>
Camp Lazear was done; we also discovered (3) what occurred at the site now falsely called<lb/>
&ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;, which occurrences formed the basis for the local tradition that resulted<lb/>
in the erroneous location of the camp. But as will be seen the latter actually was a<lb/>
fortunate mistake.</p>
<p>When I was in Havana I had the honor of presenting to you a brief outline of our<lb/>
<unclear>preliminary</unclear> investigations. You asked me to transmit to you, for the Cuban Government,<lb/>
a <unclear>documented</unclear> summary of these investigations so that the historical sites concerned<lb/>
<unclear>could</unclear> be properly preserved, marked and memorialized. In the interim I have continued<lb/>
my investigations and herewith I present you such <xref id="f03901010">documentary evidence</xref> as I have been able<lb/>
to assemble to date. I plan to revisit Havana during the next month to conclude these<lb/>
investigations and, if possible, to present a plan whereby I may be permitted to cooperate<lb/>
remaining thereon. I would greatly appreciate knowing whether you expect to be in Havana<lb/>
the last week in March or the first week in April, and whether I may have an appointment<lb/>
to discuss briefly with you the details of the plan.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
