<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03906053">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, January 15, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kellogg, George A.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03906053</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-01-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-01-15">January 15, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03906053</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, January 15, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg discusses a planned series of medical portraits.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-01-15">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, January 15, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03906053"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<date value="1942-01-15">January 15, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Willard Hotel<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have spent half of the morning and most of the<lb/>
afternoon with Doctor Alvarez, and he has been of tremendous help, both on<lb/>
the &ldquo;Pioneers of American Medicine&rdquo; series and the series on &ldquo;Gastroenter-<lb/>
ology.&rdquo; This latter series of portraits we had planned to devote entirely<lb/>
to men directly connected with the study and treatment of peptic ulcer, but<lb/>
after talking with Doctor Alvarez I think that we will revise this idea and<lb/>
have the series in the general field of gastroenterology. By doing this we<lb/>
can keep an interesting series of pictures going out for a period of years.<lb/>
If we find that the physicians like the Ernest Hamlin technique, after a<lb/>
few years we should have a most unusual series of portraits which should be<lb/>
bound in a booklet for general distribution to the medical profession.<lb/>
I was surprised to find that Doctor Alvarez was as much interested in medical<lb/>
history as he is.</p>
<p>I have been in to see the Hench yellow fever collec-<lb/>
tion in the library here, and am delighted with it. Only one thing bothered<lb/>
me and that bothers me quite a bit. When the &ldquo;Cuban Version&rdquo; sketches were<lb/>
framed I gave the framer the copy which was to be placed on the mats and<lb/>
thought that I indicated the amount of space it should occupy quite clearly.<lb/>
I was amazed to see the terrifically large black lettering which he had<lb/>
placed on the mats as I did not see the sketches after they had been framed<lb/>
or before they were shipped to you. Perhaps you do not object to the large<lb/>
size of this lettering which is certainly legible where the sketches are hang-<lb/>
ing at present, but if you wish to put them in some other place I am afraid<lb/>
that you will find it objectionable. Therefore, if you would care to have it<lb/>
done, you might send the framed sketches to someone here in Rochester who<lb/>
could remove them from the frames, make new mats and have new lettering done<lb/>
which would not hit your eye quite so hard. If you would like to have this<lb/>
done do not hesitate to send me the bill because we wish to do the job right.</p>
<p>We tried to call Mrs. Hench at the Roosevelt three<lb/>
different times in the day and a half after you left, partly because we were<lb/>
worried as to whether or not you made your train. She was out each time we<lb/>
called and so we can only hope that we did not cause you to miss what I am<lb/>
afraid was the last train that night. I am just wondering how long it is<lb/>
going to take me to get over the embarrassment which I experienced when try-<lb/>
ing to carve that roast. Between knowing that we were late with dinner and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03906054"/>
-2 Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
January 15, 1942<lb/>
my inexact knowledge as to the anatomy of the animal on which I was working,<lb/>
I was more upset than you probably realized. By this time next week it will<lb/>
probably be funny even to my wife. I am sitting in your office dictating<lb/>
this to your pro tem secretary whom I am going to ask to sign this for me as<lb/>
I am making the 5:45 plane to Chicago.</p>
<p>I should be ashamed to confess it, and I probably<lb/>
will not have the courage to do so at home, but last night again I saw<lb/>
Hildegarde. I was out with a man and his wife of the business department of<lb/>
the American Medical Association who had not seen her, and so we went to the<lb/>
Blackstone where she is appearing in what proved to be an entirely new<lb/>
repertoire. You probably will think she is preying on my mind but I really<lb/>
think both you and Mrs. Hench would have enjoyed her last night. Just to<lb/>
have something to say to her you may be shocked to know that I told her that<lb/>
Doctor and Mrs. Hench of the Mayo Clinic sent her their regards. So, should<lb/>
you see her again, do not be surprised if she remembers your name because she<lb/>
eats it up.</p>
<p>I hope you are having luck with Doctor Carroll's son.<lb/>
I cannot imagine anyone being so uncooperative as he has been.</p>
<p>If the framed picture which we sent to the Willard<lb/>
was broken I will be much chagrined. Occasionally one of them shipped alone<lb/>
does get broken and I do not think there is anything sadder than a picture with<lb/>
a broken glass.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>George Kellogg</signed>
gk:ef<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
