<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03908047">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 18, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kellogg, George A.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03908047</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-02-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Hoffmann, W.H.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-02-18">February 18, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03908047</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 18, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg writes that he has received information casting doubt on Hoffmann's professional credentials.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-02-18">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 18, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03908047"/>
<opener>
GEORGE A. KELLOGG<lb/>
<dateline>
257 CORNELISON AVENUE<lb/>
JERSEY CITY, N.J.<lb/>
<date value="1942-02-18">February 18, 1942</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>A letter from our distributors in Havana recently threw some<lb/>
doubt on the professional standing of Dr. W H. Hoffman of the<lb/>
Finlay Institute. Under separate cover you will receive a copy<lb/>
of a letter received today.</p>
<p>Your letter of something over a week ago and the letter which<lb/>
I received at home on Monday are both much appreciated. You<lb/>
may be sure that you took care of all members of the family in<lb/>
first class order. I saw Robin's letter before it was sent and<lb/>
was particularly struck with the last sentence. We, of course,<lb/>
don't edit her letters, but I was curious to know what she meant<lb/>
that your coming year should not have &ldquo;any holes&rdquo; in it. Her<lb/>
interpretation of that was that she hoped there would be no dark<lb/>
spots or trouble. In other words, she sends you her best wishes<lb/>
for the year. However, her use of the words &ldquo;error&rdquo; and &ldquo;holes&rdquo;<lb/>
I thought were very funny going to a physician. Your note to her<lb/>
and to Jonny gave them quite a lift to say the least. I have<lb/>
spent a lot of time at Cornwell's in the last few weeks on the<lb/>
McDowell painting.</p>
<p>We think we have arrived at a compromise which should please the<lb/>
majority of physicians. It certainly will not be a painting<lb/>
which is as suitable for the laity as that on &ldquo;Yellow Fever&rdquo;. We<lb/>
called in the head of the Gynecology and Obstetrics Department of<lb/>
one of the leading New York hospitals for advice as to the appear-<lb/>
ance of tumor which we decided to show in the painting, and now<lb/>
feel that from a technical standpoint the painting will be correct.</p>
<p>I am anticipating that one of our advisors, the wife of the Direct-<lb/>
or of Public Health of Kentucky, Mrs. A.T. McCormick of Louisville,<lb/>
is going to be permanently angry with us. I received a letter two<lb/>
weeks ago after I had sent her a photograph of a sketch which was<lb/>
almost blackmailed. She is editor of the &ldquo;Quarterly Journal&rdquo; repre-<lb/>
senting the Medical Women's Auxiliary of the State. Her main in-<lb/>
terest is in the patient, Jane Todd Crawford, but as Dr. Rankin<lb/>
said very pointedly, &ldquo;Thousands of patients, both men and women,<lb/>
have given themselves into the hands of their doctors before the<lb/>
McDowell operation, with possible outcomes as serious as that she<lb/>
herself faced. The important thing was that McDowell performed<lb/>
the ovariatomy and that it was successful. If Mrs. McCormick<lb/>
proceeds to excoriate us for not making Mrs. Crawford the chief<lb/>
person in the drama it will only serve to publicize the picture.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03908048"/>
-2-<lb/>
I gathered from her letter that Dr. Irwin Abell was closely assoc-<lb/>
iated with her husband and that he sympathesizes with her point of<lb/>
view. This disturbs me only insofar as I am afraid that Dr. Rankin<lb/>
is going to be too busy to speak at an unveiling and Dr. Abell was<lb/>
my second choice. If the whole thing blows up and we are not able<lb/>
to get one or the other, Rankin or Abell, we will merely exhibit<lb/>
the picture along with the other paintings at the A.M.A. at Atlantic<lb/>
City and make no attempt to have any ceremony or unveiling. As war<lb/>
conditions are today the newspapers will have very little space for<lb/>
any paintings regardless of subject and I would rather spend the<lb/>
money necessary for a bang-up occasion on reproductions of the<lb/>
picture to send to the medical profession.</p>
<p>Thanks for the page from the catalogue giving an item concerning<lb/>
Dorthea Lynde Dix. I shall order this at once even though we may<lb/>
not do Miss Dix for two or three more years.</p>
<p>I don't think I have told you how <unclear>extraordinarilly</unclear> well Dr. Alvarez<lb/>
treated me. He came through with a letter which may be of incal-<lb/>
culable value to our associates, the Bisodol Company. I really<lb/>
have to thank you for this.</p>
<p>I may be going to Seattle within the next few weeks and if I do so<lb/>
I will attempt to stop in Rochester as I will be going by plane.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>George A. Kellogg</signed>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
The Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
GAK:L<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
