<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03909026">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, March 20, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03909026</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-03-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hoffmann, W.H.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-03-20">March 20, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03909026</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, March 20, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses studies of calcium and arthritis in relation to a possible venture by Kellogg's company. He comments on Hoffmann's professional status.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-03-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, March 20, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03909026"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-03-20">March 20, 1942</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you so much for sending Dr. Crain one of the framed paintings.</p>
<p>I hope there is not going to be any mixup in the time of your passage<lb/>
through Rochester. I will be going East, as I told you, to Buffalo in about a<lb/>
week.</p>
<p>As to the studies on calcium that you sent me, I wish that we could<lb/>
talk in some detail. A letter will not permit me to discuss it satisfactorily<lb/>
with you. Because in rheumatoid arthritis there is some loss of calcium from<lb/>
the ends of bones of affected joints and because in osteoarthritis there are<lb/>
certain calcified exostoses or bony spurs certain physicians have for years<lb/>
and years felt that there might be some disturbance of the calcium metabolism.<lb/>
Every now and then some doctor goes off half <unclear>cocked</unclear> and writes an article stating<lb/>
that either the blood or urine calcium is abnormal in these diseases, but work<lb/>
in well controlled laboratories has repeatedly showed no disturbance of calcium<lb/>
metabolism. When I visited England a few years ago, a research worker in Guys<lb/>
Hospital showed me reams and reams of statistics on carefully controlled calcium<lb/>
metabolism studies. They had done months and months of work on it and could<lb/>
find nothing to write about it. Another favorite idea is that that hardness of<lb/>
the water has something to do with the local incidence of arthritis. Laymen<lb/>
think that the hard water tends to harden the joints. This is also the <unclear>bunk</unclear><lb/>
The British Ministry of Health itself made a study several years ago, of its<lb/>
incidence in communities where the water was very hard and also in communities<lb/>
where the water was quite soft. They found no difference in incidence. All<lb/>
of which makes me very unenthusiastic about the relationship of calcium to<lb/>
arthritis. Another such research problem came out of Cleveland a few years ago<lb/>
when a dentist, not a doctor, glibly talked about ionic calcium deficiencies in<lb/>
arthritis. That blew up also. So you see, we have been thinking about the<lb/>
problem but I am not interested in doing a lot of work that has a great chance<lb/>
of being useless.</p>
<p>What shall I do with the photostated article you sent me?</p>
<p>Thank you indeed for the copy of Hoffman's letter. He certainly has<lb/>
the missionary spirit if he wants to tell you, a layman, all about the pathology<lb/>
of the liver in yellow fever. I am a little <unclear>leery</unclear> of the fellow because I never<lb/>
heard of him before, despite two trips to Havana and conferences with many men<lb/>
there, but maybe he is all that he says he is. Notice, however, that he continues<lb/>
to sign himself with his professorial title. Having sent him fifty copies, I should<lb/>
think he would be satisfied. I will not send him any reprints.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
