<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03903015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Draft of Speech for the unveiling of Dean Cornwell's Painting "Conquerors of Yellow Fever," by Philip Showalter Hench, May 28, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03903015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-05-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriquez</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Presedo, Becente</name>
<name type="person">Fernandez, Nicanor</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Martinez, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis B.</name>
<name type="person">Law, Frank F.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-05-28">May 28, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03903015</idno>
<title>Draft of Speech for the unveiling of Dean Cornwell's Painting "Conquerors of Yellow Fever," by Philip Showalter Hench, May 28, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This draft includes Hench's autograph revisions.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-05-28">
<head>Draft of Speech for the unveiling of Dean Cornwell's Painting "Conquerors of Yellow Fever," by Philip Showalter Hench, May 28, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03903015"/>
<opener>
Send copy to Kissinger<lb/>
Service<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-05-28">May28'41</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>REMARKS TO BE GIVEN AT THE UNVEILING OF <add>Dean</add> CORN<del>N</del><add>W</add>ELL'S PAINTING<lb/>
<del>THE CONQUEST</del><add>&ldquo;Conquerors</add> OF YELLOW FEVER&rdquo;</p>
<p><del>PRESENTED TO THE MEDICAL PROFESSION BY WYETH &amp; CO.</del><add><del>Brothers</del></add></p>
<p>Sc.</p>
<p>PHILIP S. HENCH M.D. SC. D.<lb/>
Division of Medicine, The Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.</p>
<p><hi>Mr. Law</hi>, <add>Mr Mayor</add> Ladies and gentlemen: It has been a <hi>real privilege</hi> for me to meet those<lb/>
who are <hi>honored</hi> here this afternoon (<add><hi>Mr BLYTHYN</hi></add> <hi>Gen. Ireland</hi><del>The</del>Mayor of Cleveland, Dr. <hi>V&aacute;n Etten</hi>, etc.) but<lb/>
<hi>especially Miss Reed</hi>, the daughter of the great physician and scientist whom we<lb/>
honor today, and also Mr. <hi>John Kissinger</hi> whom I count as an old friend. <hi>It is a</hi><lb/>
organization<lb/>
<hi>pleasure</hi> for me also to renew an old friendship with the <hi>Wyeth Company</hi>. <del><hi>My first<lb/>
meeting</hi> with the</del> <add><del>men of the</del></add> <del>Wyeth people concerned</del> <add>which started</add> when I was a boy some 35 years ago. It<lb/>
happened this way.</p>
<p><hi>My father and mother</hi> were <del>very</del> devout Presbyterians who took their children<lb/>
to church every Sunday and <hi>welcomed many</hi> strangers into their pew. <hi>After church</hi> it<lb/>
was father's custom to invite some of these strangers to our home for Sunday<lb/>
dinner. <hi>One of these frequent</hi> visitors turned out to be the local representative<lb/>
<del>of the</del><add>for John</add> Wyeth <unclear>&amp;</unclear> Bros. <hi>He was a most estimable</hi> gentleman of whom my parents became<lb/>
<unclear>to me</unclear> a child<lb/>
quite fond. <hi>But I'm afraid</hi> he was just an interloper to me -- a <hi>stranger</hi> who not<lb/>
only got the first chance at <add>the <hi>whitemeat</hi></add> <hi>our Sunday chicken</hi>, but who, being a <hi>lonesome bachelor</hi>,<lb/>
stayed on long into the afternoons, on account of which my period of <hi>&ldquo;company<lb/>
maintained painfully long time<lb/>
behavior&rdquo;</hi> had to be inordinately prolonged. <hi>As if that weren't enough</hi>, being<lb/>
<hi>everhelpful</hi> in the best tradition of the <del>old time</del> Wyeth salesman, he gave my<lb/>
mother <hi>all kinds of sample medicines</hi> which she couldn't bear to throw away but used<lb/>
on me for every passing ailment. <hi>I am sure my mother's</hi> medicine chest still contains<lb/>
some of those half-used samples of Wyeth's medicines from the year 1905, <hi>and who<lb/>
knows, they are probably still</hi> as <hi>effective</hi> now as they were then. <hi>So you see</hi> what<lb/>
I first learned to know about the Wyeth folks, I learned the hard way:</p>
<pb n="2" id="f03903016"/>
<p>P</p>
<p>2.</p>
<p>Apparently through all these years <add>the men of</add> the Wyeth <del>people</del><add>organization</add> haven't changed their<lb/>
characteristics. They are still seeking to be helpful and generous to their friends,<lb/>
Mr Law &amp; his colleageues<lb/>
and so today (they) are presenting to the public and especially to their friends of the<lb/>
Start multipage copies here<lb/>
medical profession the third of a series of splendid memorials done in oil by one of<lb/>
America's finest painters, Mr. <add>Dean</add> Cornwell. Most of you are probably familiar with his<lb/>
previous paintings, that of Dr. Beaumont with Alexis St. Martin, and that of Dr.<lb/>
Osler with his pupils at old Blockley. The painting unveiled today pays tribute<lb/>
not just to one American physician but to a group of American and Cuban physicians<lb/>
and soldiers who became the conquerors of yellow fever and in so doing joined the<lb/>
great benefactors of mankind.</p>
<p>Before saying something about their conquest let me tell you a word about the<lb/>
earnest thought and planning which went into the execution of this painting. I happen<lb/>
to know that those concerned with this project exhibited an enthusiasm for it far<lb/>
beyond the ordinary demands of commercial necessity or advertising integrity. To<lb/>
insure justice in the selection of the men to be portrayed the artist and his advis<del>o</del><add>e</add>rs<lb/>
spent long hours reading the available official and unofficial records of the conquest.<lb/>
To insure historical accuracy within the limits of justifiable artistic license those<lb/>
concerned visited several of the men who actually participated in the conquest as well<lb/>
as relatives of other participants. These trips included at least one to Cuba to get<lb/>
the &ldquo;feel&rdquo; of the people and to view the country and sites where the <del>conquest</del><add>achievement</add> took<lb/>
place. <del>And I might add that I have it on unimpeachable authority that this was one<lb/>
time at least when American visitors to Havana had very little time left to spend in<lb/>
Sloppy Joe's!)</del> Governmental and other records were studied and old army <del>uniforms</del><add>equipment</add><lb/>
<del>were</del><add>as</add> purchased to insure accuracy in the representation of the uniforms with their<lb/>
confusing <del>minutise</del><add>details</add> of buttons, lapels and other insignia portrayed in the painting.<lb/>
And conferences were held to authenticate <add>even</add> the size of the whitewashed stones which<lb/>
in 1900 lined the walk to the hospital and to determine the nature of the paint used<lb/>
on the Camp Columbia Hospital building which serves as the background of this painting.</p>
<p>P. S. H.<lb/>
<unclear>Trank and word<lb/>
conquest"</unclear> here<lb/>
became <unclear>confuse</unclear><lb/>
might think it<lb/>
concerned<lb/>
conquest of<lb/>
their<lb/>
country.</p>
<p>P. S. H<lb/>
So it the<lb/>
lapels<lb/>
or the<lb/>
shoulder<lb/>
<unclear>ornaments<lb/>
epaulets</unclear>?</p>
<p>It is only fair to the artist and his sponsors that we should know something<lb/>
P S H Color?<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f03903017"/>
<hi>Through all these years</hi> the men of the Wyeth organization <hi>haven't</hi><lb/>
changed their <hi>characteristics</hi>. <unclear>They</unclear> are <hi>still seeking</hi> to be <hi>helpful</hi></p>
<p><del>REMARKS TO BE GIVEN AT THE UNVEILING OF DEAN CORNWELL'S PAINTING<lb/>
&ldquo;CONQUERORS OF YELLOW FEVER&rdquo;<lb/>
Philip S. Hench, M. D. Sc. D.<lb/>
Division of Medicine, The Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota</del></p>
<p>and <hi>generous</hi> to their friends and</p>
<p>So <hi>Today Mr. Law</hi> and his colleagues are presenting to the public and<lb/>
<del>especially</del> to their friends of the medical profession <hi>the third of a series</hi> of<lb/>
<hi>splendid memorials</hi> <del><unclear></unclear></del> in oil by one of America's finest painters, M. Dean<lb/>
Cornwell. <hi>Most of you are</hi> probably familiar with his previous <unclear>paintings</unclear>, that<lb/>
of <hi>Dr. Beaumont</hi> with Alexis St. Martin, and that of <hi>Dr. Osler with</hi> his pupils<lb/>
at old Blockley. <hi>The painting</hi> unveiled today pays tribute <del>not just to the<lb/>
American physician but</del> to a group of American and Cuban physicians and soldiers<lb/>
who became the <hi>conquerors of yellow</hi> fever and in so doing joined the great bene-<lb/>
factors of mankind.</p>
<p><del>Before saying something about their conquest</del> <hi>Let me tell</hi> you a word<lb/>
about the <hi>earnest thought</hi> and <hi>planning</hi> which wont into the <hi>execution</hi> of this<lb/>
painting. <hi>I happen to know</hi> that <hi>those concerned</hi> with this <hi>project exhibited</hi> <unclear>on</unclear><lb/>
<hi>enthusiasm for</hi> it far beyond the <hi>ordinary</hi> demands of <hi>commercial necessity</hi>, <del><unclear>or el-</unclear><lb/>
vertising integrity</del>. <hi>To insure</hi> justice in the selection of the men to be portrayed,<lb/>
the artist and his advisors spent long hours reading the <del>available official and<lb/>
unofficial</del> records of the conquest, <hi>To insure historical accuracy</hi> within the<lb/>
limits of justifiable artistic license those concerned visited several of the men<lb/>
who actually participated in the conquest as well as relatives of other participants.<lb/>
<hi>These trips included</hi> at least one to Cuba to get the &ldquo;feel&rdquo; of the people and to<lb/>
view the <del>country and</del> sites where the achievement took place. <del>Governmental and<lb/>
other records were studied and</del> <hi>Old army equipment</hi> was purchased to insure accuracy<lb/>
in the representation of the uniforms with their confusing details of buttons,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f03903018"/>
2.<lb/>
epaulets and other insignia portrayed in the painting. <del>And</del> <hi>Conferences were</hi> held<lb/>
to <del>authenticate</del><add>determine</add> even the size of the <hi>whitewashed stones</hi> which in 1900 lined the<lb/>
walk to the <add>Camp Columbia</add> hospital and to determine the <hi>color of the paint</hi> used on the <del>Camp<lb/>
Columbia</del> Hospital building which serves as the background of this painting.</p>
<p><hi>It is only fair to</hi> the artist and his sponsors that we should know some-<lb/>
thing of their loyalty to the subject and of their zeal for accuracy in its por-<lb/>
trayal. <del>Knowing of this, you may join me in believing</del> <add><hi>I believe</hi></add> <hi>that this painting</hi> will ful-<lb/>
fill the wishes of its sponsors, namely that it will be recognized by the public,<lb/>
not only as the <hi>sincere tribute of the donor</hi> to a very gallant group of men, but<lb/>
as a <hi>manifestation of the sponsor's</hi> <del>good will and</del> respect for the medical profession<lb/>
of the United States and Cuba. <hi>Above all it is an</hi> appropriate and timely reminder<lb/>
of the great tradition of the medical corps of the United States army. <hi>The artist<lb/>
and Mr. Law have</hi> expressed to me their <del>further</del> hope that the public, especially the<lb/>
school children, may learn to know this painting and the men it memorializes and<lb/>
may perhaps come to regard it as the standard visual representation of the subject<lb/>
for years to come. <hi>Happily the painting will</hi> be a mobile monument capable of<lb/>
presentation to medical and other groups throughout the country, <hi>and copies of it</hi><lb/>
will serve physicians as inspirational reminders of what is undoubtedly one of the<lb/>
finest examples of medical teamwork in the whole history of science.</p>
<p><hi>Among us today is one</hi> who actually played on that team; there are others<lb/>
here who sat <del>very close</del> on the side-lines with encouragement and help. <hi>They could</hi><lb/>
tell <del>us</del> the story of this conquest much better than I, but their <hi>modesty</hi> prevents<lb/>
them from doing so. <del>In <unclear>lies</unclear> of them</del><add><hi>Therefore</hi></add> <hi>it is my privilege</hi> to try to animate this<lb/>
painting for a few minutes while I sketch briefly for you the story of the men<lb/>
concerned.</p>
<p><del>At the close of</del><add>After</add> the <hi>Spanish-American War</hi> thousands of American soldiers<lb/>
<del>returned home to be</del> <add>were</add> received <add>home</add> like conquering heroes. <hi>But others returned</hi> home not<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f03903019"/>
3.<lb/>
so victoriously. <hi>Some were soldiers</hi> whose bodies had been weakened by fever, and<lb/>
<hi>some were in coffins</hi>--soldiers who had <del>met death at the hands of</del><add>been killed by</add> an enemy more power-<lb/>
ful than any Spaniard. <hi>For disease, especially</hi> yellow fever, had killed more soldiers<lb/>
than had the bullets of the enemy. <del>Day after day, strong young men became hot with<lb/>
fever and wracked with pain, then they turned yellow, suffered with the dreaded<lb/>
&ldquo;<unclear>bleck</unclear> vomit&rdquo; and died at the rate of as many as 200 a day.</del></p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi>We'll stop that,</hi>&rdquo; said the United States Government, <del>and with its army of<lb/>
occupation</del><add>So</add> <hi>it sent physicians</hi> <del>whose duty it was</del> to <add>try to</add> control yellow fever which had<lb/>
been endemic in Havana for more than 200 years. <hi>Among these physicians</hi> were Major<lb/>
<hi>Gorgas</hi>, who was responsible for the health of the soldiers and civilians in the city<lb/>
KANE<lb/>
of Havana, and Major <del>Jefferson</del>. <hi>Kean,</hi> whose chief responsibility was the health of<lb/>
the American soldiers at Columbia Barracks on the outskirts of Havana in the little<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> town of Quemados de Marianao, near the famous bathing beach, La Playa.</p>
<p><hi>But</hi> <del>Despite the vigorous sanitary methods which were instituted,</del> <hi>yellow fever<lb/>
continued</hi> to spread, and in May and June, 1900, Major Kean, <del>a worried man</del>, compiled<lb/>
a <hi>tragic list</hi> of the names of soldiers and civilians, of fellow-officers and their<lb/>
wives, all living in the neighboring streets of Quemados and all victims of yellow<lb/>
fever. <hi>The mortality</hi> rate among the officers on the staff of Generals Wood and Lee<lb/>
was alarming. <hi>On the desks, the clerks</hi> in General Wood's office burned sulfur<lb/>
candles as a prophylactic measure, but the candles burned in vain, and <hi>in the<lb/>
officers' mess</hi> they drank a <del>gruesome</del> toast, &ldquo;Here's to the ones who have gone. Here's<lb/>
to the next one to go!&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>As if to ridicule</hi> the puny efforts of the army medical corps, yellow<lb/>
fever next struck at the physicians themselves, and on June 21, Major Kean developed<lb/>
<del>yellow fever</del><add>the disease</add>. <hi>Could nobody stop this</hi> evil thing? <hi>What was its</hi> cause anyhow?<lb/>
<hi>One of the commonest</hi> ideas was that the mysterious cause of yellow fever arose like<lb/>
an evil spirit, a miasma from the tropical swamps. An <hi>Italian physician</hi>, Sanarelli,<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f03903020"/>
4.<lb/>
insisted it was due to a special germ, <del>which he had discovered</del>. <hi>But nobody really</hi><lb/>
knew the cause, and <hi>when a person died of</hi> yellow fever his home was often purified<lb/>
by fire to destroy his presumably infected furniture, clothing and other personal<lb/>
belongings. <del>called &ldquo;<unclear>fomites&rdquo;</unclear>.</del> <hi>Thus hundreds of</hi> thousands of dollars worth of<lb/>
<hi>military</hi> and <hi>civilian</hi> equipment went up in smoke in an attempt to control the<lb/>
disease. <hi>But it</hi> was all in vain.</p>
<p><hi>On June 25, the fourth</hi> day of Major Kean's illness, another army physician<lb/>
arrived in Havana, rushed to the bedside of his friend, the major, and <del>exemplified</del><lb/>
in him saw his first case of yellow fever. <hi>Later that day this</hi> man, Major Walter<lb/>
Reed, met with three others <del>on the veranda of the officers' quarters</del> at Columbia<lb/>
Barracks Post Hospital. <hi>The three others</hi> were Drs. James Carroll, Aristides<lb/>
Agramonte and Jesse W. Lazear, and the four men thus ended their first day's work<lb/>
as the members of the United States Army Special Yellow Fever Board.</p>
<p><hi>They first attempted</hi> to find Sanarelli's germ in the bodies of those<lb/>
sick or dead of yellow fever, but this search soon ended in failure. <del>Perhaps after</del><lb/>
Perhaps <del><unclear></unclear></del> no germ was responsible. <del>for the disease.</del> <del>Why in Quemados had the disease<lb/>
progressed so errationlly down the streets, striking in one house, skipping the<lb/>
next few houses, striking at another, then often hopping around the corner rather<lb/>
than crossing the affected street? Another</del><add><hi>A</hi></add> <hi>curious fact</hi> <add>had been</add> was noted <del>when</del><add>by</add> Reed and<lb/>
Agramonte: <del>went to study an epidemic which broke out among the soldiers at Pinar<lb/>
del Rio.</del> A <hi>soldier in a prison</hi> cell fell sick and died of yellow fever but his<lb/>
cell mates, exposed to the same food and atmosphere, remained well. <hi>Could some-</hi><lb/>
thing have entered between the bars of the open window, struck one man down and<lb/>
gone away? <hi>Could yellow fever</hi> be caused by a winged agent? <hi>Could Dr. Carlos</hi><lb/>
Finlay be right after all?</p>
<p><hi>For nineteen years this</hi> kindly old Havana physician had been trying to<lb/>
convince his medical colleagues that yellow fever was caused by a common house<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03903021"/>
5.<lb/>
mosquito. <hi>But nobody believed</hi> him simply because, although he had inoculated over<lb/>
100 volunteers with mosquitoes, he hadn't produced a single case of the disease<lb/>
which other physicians could regard as unquestionably <del>induced or</del> experimental<lb/>
rather than probably spontaneous.</p>
<p><del>When Reed and Agramonte returned from Pinar del Rio</del> <hi>The Board decided</hi> on<lb/>
August 1 to try to prove or disprove Finlay's theory once and for all. <hi>They visited</hi><lb/>
Dr. Finlay who <hi>graciously</hi> gave all the help he could including a supply of mosquito<lb/>
larvae. <del>of the suspected species.</del> <hi>The reupon a <del>momentous and</del> heroic decision</hi> had to<lb/>
be made because no animal was then known to be susceptible to yellow fever. Human<lb/>
volunteers were required. <hi>Unwilling to ask others</hi> to do what they themselves would<lb/>
not do the Board decided to inoculate each other. <del>among the first.</del> <hi>At this juncture</hi><lb/>
Reed was unfortunately ordered to Washington on important medical business. <del>Carroll<lb/>
and Agramonte continued respectively their bacteriologic and pathologic studies<lb/>
and</del> <hi>It fell to Lazear's lot</hi> to begin the mosquito work. <hi>This was fortunate</hi> be-<lb/>
cause he of all the Board was most sympathetic to the Finlay theory. <hi>Having re-</hi><lb/>
cently worked with malarial mosquitoes Lazear knew their deadly potentialities.<lb/>
<hi>He began to breed</hi> his mosquitoes and then tried to infect them by allowing them<lb/>
to bite yellow fever patients. <del>at Las Animas Hospital</del>. <hi>Between August 11 and 25</hi><lb/>
those presumably infected mosquitoes were applied to nine American soldiers in-<lb/>
cluding Drs. Lazear, Carroll and Pinto, but nothing happened. <del>They all remained<lb/>
<unclear>well</unclear></del>.</p>
<p><hi>Two days later</hi> <del>on August 27</del>, discouraged and doubting, Carroll permitted<lb/>
Lazear to inoculate him again. <hi>In a few days Carroll</hi> developed <unclear>.</unclear> severe <del>and almost<lb/>
fatal attack of</del> yellow fever. <hi>On the way from Carroll's</hi> bedside Lazear inoculated<lb/>
a scoffing volunteer soldier who &ldquo;wasn't afraid of any little old gnat.&rdquo; <hi>When<lb/>
yellow fever hit him</hi> six days later this soldier became a very surprised hero who<lb/>
later received a Congressional Medal, a life pension and a memorial <del>bridge named<lb/>
for him</del> in Grand Rapids, Michigan.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f03903022"/>
<p>6.</p>
<p><hi>Having accomplished two</hi> successful inoculations Lazear wrote his wife<lb/>
<del>(September 8)</del> &ldquo;I rather think I am on the track of the real germ.&rdquo; <hi>How right</hi> he<lb/>
was was tragically proven by what happened ten days later when he himself developed<lb/>
the dreaded disease. <hi>During his illness</hi> Dr. Lazear told two visitors, Drs. Carroll<lb/>
and Gorgas, that a few days before, while feeding his mosquitoes on yellow fever<lb/>
patients <del>at Las Animas Hospital</del> a stray mosquito had slighted on his hand; <hi>Lazear<lb/>
had allowed</hi> it to take its fill of his own blood. <hi>From the first he</hi> was very ill<lb/>
and died September 25, 1900, <del>officially</del> listed as a victim of &ldquo;accidental yellow<lb/>
fever&rdquo; but none the less a true martyr to science. <hi>such is the official</hi> version<lb/>
of this tragic incident. <hi>But I am</hi> about to tell you <hi>another</hi> version of the affair,<lb/>
<hi>one which was</hi> kept secret for forty years, and which was not even known to Dr.<lb/>
Lazear's widow until I was permitted to tell her of it last fall through the<lb/>
courtesy of those who revealed it to me: Walter Reed's colleagues, Drs. (Generals)<lb/>
Truby and Kean, and Dr. Agramonte's daughter.</p>
<p><hi>Reed hastened back</hi> to Havana <del>(October 4)</del> filled with mingled emotions.<lb/>
He <hi>was greatly depressed</hi> at Lazear's death, yet elated that success at last seemed<lb/>
at hand. <hi>But he was</hi> also <hi>confused</hi>. <hi>Why did the</hi> first nine inoculations fail and<lb/>
the next ones succeed? <del>The second successful case seemed incontrovertible: having<lb/>
been quarantined at the otherwise fever-free Post Hospital the scoffing private<lb/>
(Private Dean - &ldquo;case XY&rdquo;) had had no other conceivable source of infection than<lb/>
via the applied infected mosquito. But could one be sure that Carroll's disease<lb/>
had come from the experimental mosquito bite and not from come other source to<lb/>
which he might have exposed himself while going about town? And how could Lazear's<lb/>
tragic case be used to prove anything unless somebody know what kind of a mosquito<lb/>
had bitten him?</del></p>
<p><hi>In the pocket of</hi> the uniform blouse which Lazear had recently worn<lb/>
Lieutenant Truby, at that time commanding officer of the <del>Columbia Barracks most</del><lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f03903023"/>
7.<lb/>
Hospital, had found a small notebook containing entries about Lazear's experiments.<lb/>
<hi>Reed eagerly studied</hi> these and other notes. <hi>Herein was the</hi> solution of the age old<lb/>
mystery, a solution which became <hi>crystal clear</hi> to the <hi>brilliant</hi> mind of Walter Reed.<lb/>
<hi>Finlay's mosquito</hi> <del>(the culax <unclear>fasciatus</unclear> or Aedes Aegypti)</del> could indeed cause yellow<lb/>
fever but only under certain special conditions. <hi>By carefully noting</hi> the relative<lb/>
timings of each step in the successful and unsuccessful experiments it became <hi>obvious</hi><lb/>
that patients with yellow fever have the agent or virus of their disease circulating<lb/>
in their blood only the first three days of their illness; <hi>later when</hi> they are sicker,<lb/>
even sick unto death, the agent has strangely disappeared from the blood. <hi>Therefore,</hi><lb/>
a mosquito to become &ldquo;infected&rdquo; must bite a yellow fever victim during these first<lb/>
three days. <hi>But even then that</hi> &ldquo;infected mosquito&rdquo; cannot <del>transmit its deadly lead<lb/>
or</del> infect another person until the virus has had a chance to develop or &ldquo;ripen&rdquo;<lb/>
within the mosquito's body for at least twelve days. <hi>All of the failures</hi> of Finlay<lb/>
and of the Board were thus explained: those volunteers who had <hi>not</hi> developed yellow<lb/>
fever had either been bitten by mosquitoes which had really never been infected<lb/>
(having bitten patients too late) or had been bitten by &ldquo;infected mosquitoes&rdquo; which<lb/>
were still temporarily harmless because they had not been allowed to &ldquo;ripen&rdquo;.</p>
<p><hi>Thus Lazear's little</hi> notebook was vitally useful in solving one mystery<lb/>
but it posed another mystery, <hi>for in it</hi> Reed found some incomplete entries which<lb/>
appeared to indicate that Lazear had secretly submitted himself to other experimental<lb/>
inoculations. <hi>Reed pondered</hi> long over these entries and then concluded, <hi>according<lb/>
to Dr. (now General) Truby,</hi> that when Lazear was taken sick he worried lost his<lb/>
life insurance become forfeited if it became known that he had deliberately infected<lb/>
himself with a fatal disease. <del>The <unclear></unclear> of business might not condone human sacrifice<lb/>
no matter how worthy the cause</del>. <hi>Did <del><unclear></unclear></del></hi><add>Lazear</add> at the last fateful hour withhold<lb/>
facts to protect his loved ones? <hi>Was this why he had</hi> told Gorgas and Carroll that<lb/>
he had been bitten by a stray mosquito <del>at Las Animas</del>? <hi>Reed believed that</hi> it was.<lb/>
<hi>Having produced two cases</hi> of yellow fever and knowing the danger, Lazear would surely<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f03903024"/>
8.<lb/>
<hi>never</hi> have allowed a <hi>mongrel</hi> mosquito to bite him and vitiate his otherwise<lb/>
meticulously controlled experiments. <hi>Reed confided his</hi> suspicions to only two<lb/>
or three colleagues and then decided to permit the record to read that Lazear had<lb/>
become accidentally infected while in the performance of duty. <hi>Having made</hi> his<lb/>
quiet and heroic gesture Lazear had sought to carry his secret to a better world.<lb/>
<hi>Out of respect for the</hi> unspoken wishes of their friend, Lazear's colleagues <del>have</del><lb/>
kept that secret all these years, Reed and others having carried it to their graves.</p>
<p><hi>Knowing that a</hi> skeptical world would demand more proof than that afforded<lb/>
by these three successful inoculations Reed, Carroll and Agramonte now conceived and<lb/>
executed a series of brilliant experiments which were to write the final chapter<lb/>
of this story. <del>On the <unclear>advice</unclear> of the Major Kean</del> <hi>Reed asked General</hi> <del>Leonard</del> Wood,<lb/>
Governor General of Cuba for money with which to set up an experimental camp and<lb/>
to pay what <del>American and Spanish</del> volunteers might be secured. <hi>To the lasting credit</hi><lb/>
of General Wood who had himself been a physician, he promptly granted Reed's re-<lb/>
quest and threw behind Reed all the authority of the governor's high office.</p>
<p><hi>Yellow fever was to be given</hi> away free with premiums of $200.00. <hi>The<lb/>
victims could spend</hi> the money any way they wanted to--if they survived; a <hi>rather</hi><lb/>
big <hi>if</hi>, considering that the mortality rate of epidemic yellow fever was about 40<lb/>
per cent. <hi>But before any paid</hi> volunteers were secured two American soldiers,<lb/>
John R. Kissinger and John J. Moran, volunteered their services only on condition<lb/>
that they could do so without pay and in the interests of science. <hi>Legend has it</hi><lb/>
that Major Reed, profoundly affected, rose and said, &ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you.&rdquo;<lb/>
<hi>Actually the legend</hi> is not true, but as one writer said, &ldquo;If Reed didn't salute<lb/>
them he should have.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>A special</hi><del>ly guarded and quarantined</del> <hi>experimental station</hi> named Camp<lb/>
Lazear was set up in a secluded spot a mile from Camp Columbia. <hi>There John<lb/>
Kissinger</hi> who is your <hi>honored guest today</hi>, bared his arm for the bites of five<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, and promptly developed the first case of deliberately accepted<lb/>
and completely controlled experimental yellow fever in history. <hi>Of this Reed</hi><lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f03903025"/>
9.<lb/>
wrote, &ldquo;In my opinion this exhibition of moral courage has never been surpassed in<lb/>
tie annals of the army of the United States.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Then two small specially</hi> constructed wooden buildings were erected. <hi>The<lb/>
first</hi> <del>was called</del> Building Number One <del>or the &ldquo;Infected Clothing and Bedding Building.&rdquo;<lb/>
<unclear></unclear></del> comprised one room, <del>14 x 20 feet, had only two small windows and</del><add>which</add> was heated by<lb/>
a stove to a tropical temperature. <del>Three cots were set up and</del> <hi>Into this sweltering</hi><lb/>
room were brought the soiled and foul-smelling bed clothes of yellow fever victims.<lb/>
<hi>Night after night</hi> Dr. Robert Cooke and other soldier-volunteers <del>(Folk, Jernegan,<lb/>
Hanberry, Weatherwalks, Hildebrand and England)</del> hung these offensive <del>clothes</del><add>objects</add> around<lb/>
the walls <del>and on their beds,<add><unclear>cots</unclear></add></del> and then lay down to try to sleep on pillows and sheets<lb/>
soiled with blood and vomitus. <hi>Stomachs rebelled</hi>, but spirits remained firm and<lb/>
not one of these volunteers developed yellow fever, simply because there were no<lb/>
mosquitoes in the room. <hi>Thus was exploded the</hi> notion that <del><unclear>&ldquo;fomitus&rdquo;</unclear></del><add>personal belongings</add> carried the<lb/>
disease.</p>
<p>A <hi>second building</hi> <del>of similar <unclear>size</unclear></del> (<hi>Building</hi> Number Two) <del>or the &ldquo;Infected<lb/>
Mosquito Building&rdquo;)</del> was divided into two parts separated <del><unclear></unclear></del> by a wire screen.<lb/>
<hi>On a cot in one</hi> side of this room <unclear>Mr</unclear>. John Moran exposed his body to the bites of<lb/>
fifteen loaded mosquitoes let loose in the room. <hi>He was in the</hi> room only a little<lb/>
over an hour in all, but promptly developed yellow fever, <hi>while other</hi> volunteers<lb/>
who stayed long hours on the other side of the screen where there were no mosquitoes<lb/>
remained well.</p>
<p><hi>Thereafter In the bodies</hi> of twelve more American and Spanish volunteers <del>(Benigno,<lb/>
Fernandez, Presedo, Martinez, Jernegan, Olson, Folk, Forbes, Andrus, West, Hanberry<lb/>
and Sonntag)</del> <hi>yellow fever was produced</hi> at will <del>either through the medium of mosquito<lb/>
bites or by injections of infected blood or serum</del>. <hi>Their problem</hi> solved after just<lb/>
<hi>eight</hi> months of work the Board disbanded Camp Lazear on March 1, 1901. <hi>Now armed</hi><lb/>
with precise knowledge Gorgas within three months freed Havana of its age old scourge.<lb/>
and Later <del>with this and other knowledge</del> he made safe the Isthmus of Panama for <del>passage</del><lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f03903026"/>
10.<lb/>
<del>of</del> the commerce of the world. In <hi>these troubled days</hi> when the safe passage<lb/>
of the canal is so vital to our national defense, the <hi>conquest</hi> of yellow fever,<lb/>
<del>which is such a factor in the successful operation of the canal</del>, assumes a new<lb/>
significance. <add>In these days <unclear>mutual foundation of the Americans important important things</unclear></add> <hi>One of the strong</hi> links in the solidarity of the Western hemisphere<lb/>
has been forged by the cooperating sanitarians of the Americas who have, with the<lb/>
splendid cooperation of the Rockefeller Foundation, done so much to obliterate<lb/>
yellow fever and other tropical diseases from this side of the globe, <hi>thereby<lb/>
saving hundreds of thousands</hi> of lives and much property. <hi>Lately we have</hi> heard<lb/>
much of the four freedoms: freedom of speech, freedom of worship, freedom from<lb/>
want and freedom from fear. <hi>The conquerors of yellow fever</hi> assuredly contributed<lb/>
<del>greatly</del><add>much</add> to the eventual attainment of these latter two freedoms, for fear and want<lb/>
are the constant handmaidens of disease.</p>
<p><hi>This then is the story</hi> of these men in <hi>oils</hi>. <hi>Here you will see</hi> portrayed<lb/>
the team who won this victory: <hi>Finlay, the</hi> great Cuban physician, who for nineteen<lb/>
years dreamed the plan of battle, <hi>Walter Reed</hi> <add>The brilliant leader</add> who planned the active campaign and<lb/>
assumed command in the heat of battle, and <hi>Lazear, Agramonte</hi> and Carroll--the rest<lb/>
of the Board who nobly carried out their respective duties even when it meant death.<lb/>
<hi>Here too, represented by the</hi> soldiers Kissinger, Moran and Jernegan, by one of the<lb/>
Spanish volunteers and by Dr. Cooke, are those whose bodies bore the brunt of the<lb/>
enemy's attack. <hi>And here represented by</hi> General Wood, Major Kean and Lieutenant<lb/>
Truby are loyal colleagues who smoothed the way with encouragement and help. <hi>As a<lb/>
matter of fact this whole group</hi> of men were never actually together at any one<lb/>
time; to that extent this <hi>painting</hi> is <hi>artistic</hi> rather than factual. <hi>But these<lb/>
men were</hi> comrades in spirit and purpose, and in the records of history their names<lb/>
are inseparable.</p>
<p><hi>And what became of their</hi> battlefield, Camp Lazear? <hi>Reverting to more<lb/>
common place</hi> uses it was lost for forty years until Mr. John Moran, Mr. Luis<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f03903027"/>
11.<lb/>
Pogolotti (of Havana) and I hunted for it <add>together</add> and <hi>rediscovered</hi> it last spring.<lb/>
<hi>Building Number</hi> Two is gone, but <hi>Building Number</hi> One still stands, <hi>creaking</hi> with<lb/>
age and <hi>sleeping</hi> in the Cuban sun; at <hi>its</hi> back is an encroaching quarry; in front<lb/>
a corn field waves.</p>
<p><del>In concluding let me repeat a few words spoken recently at the dedication<lb/>
of a Lazear memorial.</del> <hi>In these days when man's</hi> inhumanity to man is so pathetically<lb/>
apparent, when the world is red with blood, it is well for us to note the example<lb/>
of these men who banded together for high adventure, not to kill or even to die for<lb/>
one country, but to die if need be for their fellow men of all countries. <hi>It is<lb/>
such as they who</hi> reassure us of the inherent <unclear>decency</unclear> and dignity of man.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
