<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03908056">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 26, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03908056</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-02-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hoffmann, W.H.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-02-26">February 26, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03908056</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 26, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench inquires about the anticipated Cuban unveiling of the Cornwell paintings, which he would like to attend if possible. He informs Kellogg that Hoffmann is a member of the Finlay Institute.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-02-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 26, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03908056"/>
<opener>
Y F<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-02-26">February 26, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
257 Cornelison Avenue<lb/>
Jersey City, N. J.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It will be months before I will get my yellow fever thing ready. I<lb/>
am still in the process of searching for material, some of which I know exists<lb/>
and some of which I don't even know exists yet which I am looking for in official<lb/>
and unofficial journals. As you say, the current interest in yellow fever will<lb/>
increase interest in the whole story greatly. Dr. Sawyer of the Rockefeller<lb/>
Institute is responsible for the vaccine--a really excellent thing and the only<lb/>
real contribution to the conquest of yellow fever since the work of the yellow<lb/>
fever board in 1900. Dr. Sawyer was a fellow speaker with me at the Washington<lb/>
and Jefferson affair last year.</p>
<p>By the way, can you give me any more dope on the anticipated Cuban<lb/>
meeting and the unveiling of the paintings, including the Cuban versions? I<lb/>
imagine if you go you would like to borrow from me the Cuban versions. I am<lb/>
really anxious to know. Already twenty of our permanent staff have left and<lb/>
about seventy of our Fellows have gone for military duty. We anticipate losing<lb/>
twenty-five more of our permanent staff within the next few months so that if<lb/>
I go, unless I can save part of my month's vacation for the Cuban trip in the<lb/>
Fall, I suspect the Clinic would not want me to go. If you are still planning<lb/>
seriously on holding the Cuban meeting, I will materially shorten my vacation to<lb/>
California at the end of April. If not, I will take my whole vacation at one<lb/>
time. You will see, therefore, why I am anxious to know. I realize that you<lb/>
yourself will not know but if you think there is a fairly good chance of holding<lb/>
it I will try to shorten my California vacation in April.</p>
<p>As to the matter of Dr. Hoffman, thanks for sending me the copy of<lb/>
his letter to you. In rereading his letter I don't know whether he wants two<lb/>
hundred copies of my reprints or simply two hundred copies of the painting. It<lb/>
looks as if he wants the latter and apparently from his letter to you, you have<lb/>
reserved that number for him. Do you know what he wants? If you have reserved<lb/>
that many for him there is no use in my sending him two hundred of my reprints.<lb/>
I have just had a letter from Dr. Albertini, who says that Dr. Hoffman is a member<lb/>
of the Finlay Institute where he is histologist and has been for long years inter-<lb/>
ested in yellow fever. He does not say much about him but what he does say seems<lb/>
to be all right. I won't write Hoffman until I hear from you. There is no use<lb/>
in sending him the whole Hygeia reprint if all he wants is the colored insert.<lb/>
Please let me know.</p>
<p>Can you send me a few more colored reproductions of the two Cuban ver-<lb/>
sions? Please don't go to any bother, certainly not to any expense to have this<lb/>
done but if you have some lying around, I would like a half dozen more.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
