<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03906016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to James E. Peabody, January 6, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03906016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-01-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Peabody, James E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-01-06">January 6, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03906016</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to James E. Peabody, January 6, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses plans for a memorial at Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-01-06">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to James E. Peabody, January 6, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03906016"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-01-06">January 6, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Dr. James E. Peabody<lb/>
281 Lowell Ave.<lb/>
Newtonville, Massachusetts<lb/>
<salute>My dear Peabody:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I must apologize sincerely for not having answered your letter of December<lb/>
14 earlier. The reason I delayed was that I am in the process of negotiating or<lb/>
rather trying to negotiate with the present owner of the Camp Lazear site. He sold<lb/>
me the little building but wants $2500.00 for the rest of the camp site. It would<lb/>
cost at least $10,000.00 to build an appropriate building to enclose Building No. 1<lb/>
and the question is whether this building should be left on the site of Camp Lazear<lb/>
or, as the Cuban authorities want me to do, whether it should be moved to the false<lb/>
site where Dr. Lazear died. The Cubans, as you know, are very lackadaisical in matters<lb/>
of correspondence. Some of them just never answer my letters at all, some take weeks<lb/>
before answering. The owner of Camp Lazear has been very gracious, when I finally<lb/>
actually met him, but has been very tardy in answering. I still have not heard but<lb/>
expect to hear shortly as I wrote him a second letter at Christmas time. I will<lb/>
therefore postpone my reply to you as the whole thing hinges on whether we can get<lb/>
the camp site.</p>
<p>Now as to your interesting story. I should be delighted to let you use<lb/>
whatever you want of any material that I have sent you and as soon as I hear from<lb/>
the owner of Camp Lazear I will send you the tentative plans that I have for the build-<lb/>
ing. I have a little rough plan drawn up which has plenty of wall space for exhibits,<lb/>
paintings, dioramas, models, photographs, maps, medals, etc.</p>
<p>As to your suggestion that one of your wealthy friends or your classmates at<lb/>
Williams College might be interested in helping to erect a suitable memorial, I am<lb/>
most interested. At this time I cannot give you a definite answer because I am myself<lb/>
in the process of trying to find out how much money is needed and what can be done.<lb/>
One individual has given me a thousand dollars. I have a promise of some more money<lb/>
from another individual. The one hitch to your plan is that, regardless of who gives<lb/>
the money, this Camp Lazear Memorial must be dedicated not to those who give the money<lb/>
but to Finlay, Lazear, Reed et al. One of the purposes of my plan for the memorial is<lb/>
to bring the Americans and Cubans together and stop this silly squabble over whether<lb/>
Finlay or Reed should have the greatest credit. Therefore, the camp must be dedicated<lb/>
to them. I greatly <unclear>doubt</unclear> whether it could be dedicated to the memory of any donor or<lb/>
donors. At the very most, on the memorial tablet at the bottom, one might be permitted<lb/>
to say &ldquo;This building erected through the generosity of so and so.&rdquo; Please do not<lb/>
consider that I am discouraging you the least bit in your plan. It is indeed wonderful<lb/>
of you to be so thoughtful and generous and to take so much of your time in starting<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03906017"/>
Dr. James E. Peabody<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
January 6, 1942<lb/>
another campaign. Your previous campain was so eminently successful that we<lb/>
certainly need your interest in this one.</p>
<p>May we leave the matter for the moment until I hear, I am sure in the<lb/>
next few days, from Cuba?</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
