<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03903001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Text of speech for the unveiling of Dean Cornwell's painting "Conquerors of Yellow Fever," by Philip Showalter Hench, [1941]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03903001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Presedo, Becente</name>
<name type="person">Fernandez, Nicanor</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Martinez, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis</name>
<name type="person">Law, Frank F.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-00-00">[1941]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03903001</idno>
<title>Text of speech for the unveiling of Dean Cornwell's painting "Conquerors of Yellow Fever," by Philip Showalter Hench, [1941]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench remarks on the history of the experiments that led to the conquest of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-00-00">
<head>Text of speech for the unveiling of Dean Cornwell's painting "Conquerors of Yellow Fever," by Philip Showalter Hench, [1941]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03903001"/>
<p>2.</p>
<p>REMARKS TO BE GIVEN AT THE UNVEILING OF DEAN CORNWELL'S PAINTING<lb/>
&ldquo;CONQUERORS OF YELLOW FEVER&rdquo;</p>
<p>Philip S. Hench, M.D. Sc.D.<lb/>
Division of Medicine, The Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota</p>
<p>Today Mr. Law and his colleagues are presenting to the public and<lb/>
especially to their friends of the medical profession the third of a series of<lb/>
splendid memorials done in oil by one of America's finest painters, Mr. <add>Dean</add> Cornwell.<lb/>
Most of you are probably familiar with his previous paintings, that of Dr. Beaumont<lb/>
with Alexis St. Martin, and that of Dr. Osler with his pupils at old Blockley.<lb/>
The painting unveiled today pays tribute not just to one American physician but<lb/>
to a group of American and Cuban physicians and soldiers who became the conquerors<lb/>
of yellow fever and in so doing joined the great benefactors of mankind.</p>
<p>Before saying something about their conquest let me tell you a word about<lb/>
the earnest thought and planning which went into the execution of this painting.<lb/>
I happen to know that those concerned with this project exhibited an enthusiasm<lb/>
for it far beyond the ordinary demands of commercial necessity or advertising<lb/>
integrity. To insure justice in the selection of the men to be portrayed, the<lb/>
artist and his advisors spent long hours reading the available official and<lb/>
unofficial records of the conquest. To insure historical accuracy within the<lb/>
limits of justifiable artistic license those concerned visited several of the<lb/>
men who actually participated in the conquest as well as relatives of other<lb/>
participants. These trips included at least one to Cuba to get the &ldquo;feel&rdquo; of the<lb/>
people and to view the country and sites where the <del>conquest</del><add>achievement</add> took place.<lb/>
<del>(And I<lb/>
might add that I have it on unimpeachable authority that this was one time at<lb/>
least when American visitors to Havana had very little time left to spend in<lb/>
Sloppy <unclear>Joe's</unclear>:)</del> Governmental and other records were studied and old army <del>uni</del><add>equipment</add><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03903002"/>
3.<lb/>
was purchased to insure accuracy in the representation of the uniforms<lb/>
<unclear>9</unclear> with their confusing <del><unclear>minutrec</unclear></del><add>details</add> of buttons, <del>lapels</del><add><unclear>opanlets</unclear></add> and other insignia<lb/>
portrayed in the painting. And conferences were even held to authenticate <add>even</add> the<lb/>
size of the whitewashed stones which in 1900 lined the walk to the hospital and<lb/>
to determine the <del>nature></del><add>color</add> of the paint used on the Camp Columbia Hospital building<lb/>
which serves as the background of this painting.</p>
<p>It is only fair to the artist and his sponsors that we should know<lb/>
something of their loyalty to the subject and <add>of</add> their zeal for accuracy in its<lb/>
portrayal. Knowing of this, you may join me in believing that this painting<lb/>
will fulfill the wishes of its sponsors, namely that it will be recognized by<lb/>
the public, not only as the sincere tribute of the <del>sponsor</del><add>donor</add> to a very gallant<lb/>
group of men, but as manifestation of the sponsor's good will and respect<lb/>
for the medical profession of the United States and Cuba. Above all it is an<lb/>
appropriate and timely <del>acknowledgement</del><add>reminder</add> of the great tradition of the medical<lb/>
corps of the United States army. The artist and <del>hissponsors</del><add>Mr. Law</add> have expressed to<lb/>
me their further hope that the public, especially the school children, may<lb/>
learn to know this painting and the men it memorializes and may perhaps come to<lb/>
regard it as the standard visual representation of the subject for years to<lb/>
come. Happily the painting will be a mobile monument capable of presentation to<lb/>
medical and other groups throughout the country, and copies of it will serve<lb/>
physicians as inspiration <add><unclear>al</unclear></add> reminders of what is undoubtedly one of the finest<lb/>
examples of medical teamwork in the whole history of science.</p>
<p>Among us today is one who actually played on that team; there are others<lb/>
here who sat very close on the side-lines with <del>vital</del> encouragement and help. They<lb/>
could tell us the story of this conquest much <del>more dramatically</del><add>better</add> than I <del><unclear>on</unclear></del>, but<lb/>
their modesty prevents them from doing so. In lieu of them it is my privilege<lb/>
to try to animate this painting for a few minutes while I sketch briefly for you<lb/>
the story of the men concerned.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f03903003"/>
<p>4.</p>
<p>At the close of the Spanish-American War thousands of American soldiers<lb/>
returned home to be received like conquering heroes. But others returned home not<lb/>
so victoriously. Some were soldiers whose bodies had been weakened by fever and some<lb/>
were in coffins--soldiers who had met death at the hands of an enemy more powerful<lb/>
than any Spaniard. For disease, especially yellow fever, had killed more soldiers<lb/>
than had the bullets of the enemy. Day after day, strong young men became hot with<lb/>
fever and wracked with pain; then they turned yellow, suffered with the dreaded<lb/>
&ldquo;black vomit&rdquo; and died at the rate of as many as 200 a day.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We'll stop that,&rdquo; said the United States Government, and with its army of<lb/>
occupation it sent physicians whose duty it was to control yellow fever which had<lb/>
been endemic in Havana for more than 200 years. Among these physicians were<lb/>
Major Gorgas, who was responsible for the health of the soldiers and civilians<lb/>
in the city of Havana, and Major Jefferson R. Kean, whose chief responsibility<lb/>
was the health of the American soldiers at Columbia Barracks on the outskirts<lb/>
of Havana in the little suburban town of Quemados de Marianao, near the famous<lb/>
bathing beach, La Playa.</p>
<p>Despite the vigorous sanitary methods which were instituted, yellow<lb/>
fever continued to spread, and in May and June, 1900, Major Kean, a worried man,<lb/>
compiled a tragic list of the names of soldiers and civilians, of fellow-officers<lb/>
and their wives, all living in the neighboring streets of Quemados and all victims<lb/>
of yellow fever. The mortality rate among the officers on the staff of Generals<lb/>
Wood and Lee was alarming. On the desks, the clerks in General Wood's office<lb/>
burned sulfur candles as a prophylactic measure, but the candles burned in vain, and<lb/>
in the officers mess they drank a gruesome toast, &ldquo;Here's to the ones who have gone.<lb/>
Here's to the next one to go!&rdquo;</p>
<p>As if to ridicule the puny efforts of the army medical corps, yellow<lb/>
fever next struck at the physicians themselves, and on June 21, Major Kean<lb/>
developed yellow fever. Could nobody stop this evil thing? What was its cause<lb/>


<pb n="4" id="f03903004"/>
5.<lb/>
anyhow? One of the commonest ideas was that the <unclear>mysterious</unclear> cause of yellow fever<lb/>
arose like an evil spirit, a miasma from the tropical swamps. An Italian physician,<lb/>
Sanarelli, insisted it was due to a special germ which he had discovered. But<lb/>
nobody really knew the cause, and when a person died of yellow fever his home was<lb/>
often purified by fire to destroy his presumably infected furniture, clothing<lb/>
and other personal belongings, called &ldquo;fomites&rdquo;. Thus hundreds of thousands of dollars<lb/>
worth of military and civilian equipment went up in smoke in an attempt to control<lb/>
the disease. But it was all in vain.</p>
<p>On June 25, the fourth day of Major Kean's illness, another army<lb/>
physician arrived in Havana, rushed to the bedside of his friend, the major, and<lb/>
exemplified in him saw his first case of yellow fever. Later that day this man,<lb/>
Major Reed, met with three others on the veranda of the officers' quarters at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks Post Hospital. The three others were Drs. James Carroll, Aristides Agramonte and Jesse W. Lazear, and the four men thus ended their first day's work<lb/>
as the members of the United States Army Special Yellow Fever Board.</p>
<p>They first attempted to find Sanarelli's germ in the bodies of those<lb/>
sick or dead of yellow fever, but this search soon ended in failure. Perhaps<lb/>
after all no germ was responsible for the disease. Why in Quemados had the<lb/>
disease progressed so erratically down the streets, striking in one house, skipping<lb/>
the new few houses, striking at another, then often hopping around the corner<lb/>
rather than crossing the affected street? Another curious fact was noted when<lb/>
Reed and Agramonte went to study an epidemic which broke out among the soldiers<lb/>
at Pinar del Rio. A soldier in a prison cell fell sick and died of yellow fever<lb/>
but his cell mates, exposed to the same food and atmosphere, remained well. Could<lb/>
something have entered between the bars of the open window, struck one man down<lb/>
and gone away? Could yellow fever be caused by a winged agent? Could Dr. Carlos<lb/>
Finlay be right after all?</p>
<pb n="5" id="f03903005"/>
<p>6.</p>
<p>For nineteen years this kindly old Havana physician had been trying to<lb/>
convince his medical colleagues that yellow fever was caused by a common house<lb/>
mosquito. But nobody believed him simply because, although he had inoculated over<lb/>
100 volunteers with <del>infected</del> mosquitoes, he hadn't produced a single case of the<lb/>
disease which other physicians could regard as unquestionably induced <add>or experimental</add> rather than<lb/>
probably spontaneous.</p>
<p>When Reed and Agramonte returned from Pinar del Rio the Board decided on<lb/>
August 1<del>st</del> to try to prove or disprove Finlay's theory once and for all. They visited<lb/>
Dr. Finlay who graciously gave all the help he could including a supply of mosquito<lb/>
larvae of the suspected species. Thereupon a momentous and heroic decision had to<lb/>
be made because no animal was then known to be susceptible to yellow fever. Human<lb/>
volunteers were required. Unwilling to ask others to do what they themselves would<lb/>
not do the Board decided to inoculate each other among the first. At this juncture<lb/>
Reed was unfortunately ordered to Washington on important medical business. Carroll<lb/>
and Agramonte continued respectively their bacteriologic and pathologic studies and<lb/>
it fell to Lazear's lot to begin the mosquito work. This was fortunate because he of<lb/>
all the Board was most sympathetic to the Finlay theory. Having recently worked with<lb/>
malarial mosquitoes Lazear knew their deadly potentialities. He began to breed his<lb/>
mosquitoes and then tried to infect them by allowing them to bite yellow fever patients<lb/>
at Las Animas Hospital. Between Aug. 11 and 25 these presumably infected mosquitoes<lb/>
were applied to nine American soldiers including Drs. Lazear, Carroll and Pinto, but<lb/>
nothing happened. They all remained <del>ridiculously</del> well.</p>
<p>Two days later on August 27, discouraged and doubting, Carroll permitted<lb/>
Lazear to inoculate him again. In a few days Carroll developed a severe and almost<lb/>
fatal attack of yellow fever. On the way from Carroll's bedside Lazear inoculated<lb/>
a scoffing <add>volunteer</add> soldier who &ldquo;wasn't afraid of any little old gnat.&rdquo; When yellow fever<lb/>
hit him six days later this soldier became a very surprised hero who later received<lb/>
a Congressional Medal, a life pension and a memorial bridge named for him in Grand<lb/>
Rapids, Michigan.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f03903006"/>
<p>7.</p>
<p>Having accomplished two successful inoculations Lazear wrote his wife<lb/>
(Sept. 8): &ldquo;I rather think I am on the track of the real germ.&rdquo; How right he was<lb/>
was tragically proven by what happened ten days later when he himself developed the<lb/>
dreaded disease. During his illness Dr. Lazear told two visitors Drs. Carroll and<lb/>
Gorgas that a few days before, while feeding his mosquitoes on yellow fever <add>patients</add> <del>cases</del> at<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital a stray mosquito had alighted on his hand; Lazear had allowed it<lb/>
to take its fill of his own blood. From the first he was very ill and died September<lb/>
25, 1900 officially listed as a victim of &ldquo;accidental yellow fever&rdquo; but none the less<lb/>
a true martyr to science. Such is the official version of this tragic incident. But<lb/>
I am about to tell you another version of the affair, one which was kept secret for<lb/>
forty years, and which was not even known to Dr. Lazear's widow until I was permitted<lb/>
to tell her of it last fall through the courtesy of those who revealed it to me:<lb/>
Walter Reed's colleagues, Drs. <add>(Generals)</add> Truby and Kean, and Dr. Agramonte's daughter.</p>
<p>Reed hastened back to Havana (Oct. 4) filled with mingled emotions. He was<lb/>
greatly depressed at Lazear's death, yet elated that success at last seemed at hand.<lb/>
But he was also confused. Why did the first nine inoculations fail and the next ones<lb/>
succeed? The second successful case seemed incontrovertible: having been quarantined<lb/>
at the otherwise fever-free Post Hospital the scoffing private (Private Dean - &ldquo;case<lb/>
XY&rdquo;) had had no other conceivable source of infection than via the applied infected<lb/>
mosquito. But could one be sure that Carroll's disease had come from the experimental<lb/>
mosquito bite and not from some other source to which he might have exposed himself<lb/>
while going about town? And how could Lazear's tragic case be used to prove anything<lb/>
unless somebody knew what kind of a mosquito had bitten him?</p>
<p>In the pocket of the uniform blouse which Lazear had recently worn Lieutenant<lb/>
Truby, <add>at that time</add> commanding officer of the Columbia Barracks Post Hospital, had found a small<lb/>
notebook containing entries about Lazear's experiments. <add>Reed eagerly studied these and other notes</add> Herein was the solution of the<lb/>
age old mystery, a solution which became crystal clear to the brilliant mind of Walter<lb/>
Reed. Finlay's mosquito (the culex fasciatus or Aedes <del>Egypti</del><add>Aegypti</add>) could indeed cause<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f03903007"/>
8.<lb/>
yellow fever but only under certain <add>special</add> conditions. By carefully noting the relative<lb/>
timings of each step in the successful and unsuccessful experiments it became obvious<lb/>
that patients with yellow fever only have the agent or virus of their disease circulating<lb/>
in their blood <add></add> the first three days of their illness; later when they are sicker, even<lb/>
sick unto death, the agent has strangely disappeared from the blood. <add>Therefore</add> <del><unclear>A</unclear></del> mosquito to<lb/>
become &ldquo;infected&rdquo; must <del>therefore</del> bite a yellow fever victim during these first three<lb/>
days. But even then that &ldquo;infected mosquito&rdquo; cannot <del>yet</del> transmit its deadly load or<lb/>
infect another person until the virus has had a chance to develop or &ldquo;ripen&rdquo; within<lb/>
the mosquito's body for at least twelve days. All of the failure of Finlay and of the<lb/>
Board were thus explained: those volunteers who had <hi>not</hi> developed yellow fever had<lb/>
either been bitten by mosquitoes which had really never been infected (having bitten<lb/>
patients too late) or had been bitten by &ldquo;infected mosquitoes&rdquo; which <add>were still <add>temporarily</add> harmless because they</add> not been<lb/>
allowed to &ldquo;ripen&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Thus Lazear's little notebook was vitally useful in solving one mystery but<lb/>
it posed another mystery, for in it Reed found some incomplete entries which appeared<lb/>
to indicate that Lazear had secretly submitted himself to other experimental inocula-<lb/>
tions. Reed pondered long over these entries and then concluded, according to Dr.<lb/>
(now Gen<add>eral</add>) Truby, that when Lazear was taken sick he worried lest his life insurance<lb/>
become forfeited if it became known that he had deliberately infected himself with<lb/>
a fatal disease. The gods of business might not condone human sacrifice no matter<lb/>
how worthy the cause. Did he therefore at the last fateful hour withhold facts to<lb/>
protect his loved ones? Was this why he had told Gorgas and Carroll that he had been<lb/>
bitten by a stray mosquito at Las Animas? Reed believed that it was. Having produced<lb/>
two cases of yellow fever and knowing the danger, Lazear would surely never have allowed<lb/>
a mongrel mosquito to bite him and vitiate his otherwise meticulously controlled ex-<lb/>
periments. Reed confided his suspicions only to two or three colleagues and then<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f03903008"/>
9.<lb/>
decided to permit the record to read that Lazear had become accidentally infected<lb/>
while in the performance of duty. Having made his quiet and heroic gesture Lazear<lb/>
had sought to carry his secret to a better world. Out of respect for the unspoken<lb/>
wishes of their friend, Lazear's colleagues have kept that secret all these years,<lb/>
Reed and others having carried it to their graves.</p>
<p>Knowing that a skeptical world would demand more proof than that afforded by<lb/>
these three successful inoculations Reed, Carroll and Agramonte now conceived and ex-<lb/>
ecuted a series of brilliant experiments which were to write the final chapter of<lb/>
this story. On the advice of Major Kean, Reed asked General Leonard Wood, Governor<lb/>
General of Cuba for money with which to set up an experimental camp and to pay what<lb/>
American and Spanish volunteers might be secured. To the lasting credit of Gen.<lb/>
Wood who had himself been a physician, he promptly granted Reed's request and threw<lb/>
behind Reed all the authority of the governor's high office.</p>
<p>Yellow fever was to be given away free with premiums of $200.00. The<lb/>
victims could spend the money any way they wanted to--if they survived; a rather<lb/>
big <hi>if</hi>, considering that the mortality rate of epidemic yellow fever was about 40<lb/>
per cent. But before any paid volunteers were secured two American soldiers,<lb/>
John R. Kissinger and John J. Moran, volunteered their services only on condition that<lb/>
they could do so without pay and in the interests of science. Legend has it that<lb/>
Major Reed, profoundly affected, rose and said, &ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you.&rdquo; Actually<lb/>
the legend is not true, but as one writer later said, &ldquo;If Reed didn't salute them<lb/>
he should have.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A specially guarded and quarantined experimental station named Camp Lazear<lb/>
was set up <del>on</del><add>in</add> a secluded spot a mile from Camp Columbia. There John Kissinger who<lb/>
is your honored guest today, bared his arm for the bites of five infected mosquitoes,<lb/>
and promptly developed the first case of deliberately accepted and completely con-<lb/>
trolled experimental yellow fever in history. Of this Reed wrote, &ldquo;In my opinion<lb/>
this exhibition of moral courage has never been surpassed in the annals of the<lb/>
army of the United States.&rdquo; <del>(Mr. Kissinger, we heartily applaud that sentiment.)</del></p>
<pb n="9" id="f03903009"/>
<p>10.</p>
<p>Then two small specially constructed wooden buildings were erected. The<lb/>
first was called Building Number One or the &ldquo;Infected Clothing and Bedding Bldg.&rdquo;<lb/>
It comprised one room, 14 x 20 feet, had only two small windows and was heated by a<lb/>
stove to a tropical temperature. Three cots were set up and into this sweltering room<lb/>
were brought the soiled and foul-smelling bed clothes of yellow fever victims. Night<lb/>
after night Dr. Robert Cooke and other soldier-volunteers (Folk, Jernegan, Hanberry,<lb/>
Weatherwalks, Hildebrand and England) hung these <del>stinking</del><add>offensive</add> clothes around the walls<lb/>
and on their beds, and then lay down to try to sleep on pillows and sheets soiled<lb/>
with blood and vomitus. Stomachs rebelled <del>at the awful stench</del>, but spirits remained<lb/>
firm, and not one of those volunteers developed yellow fever, simply because there<lb/>
were no mosquitoes in the room. Thus was exploded the notion that &ldquo;fomites&rdquo; carried<lb/>
the disease.</p>
<p>A second building of similar size (Building #2 or &ldquo;The Infected Mosquito<lb/>
Bldg.&rdquo;) was divided into two parts separated merely by a wire screen. On a cot in<lb/>
one side of this room Mr. John Moran exposed his body to the bites of fifteen loaded<lb/>
mosquitoes let loose in the room. He was in the room only a little over an hour in all,<lb/>
but promptly developed yellow fever, while other volunteers <add><unclear>who stayed</unclear> long hours</add> on the other side of the<lb/>
screen where there were no mosquitoes remained well.</p>
<p>In the bodies of twelve more American and Spanish volunteers (Benigno,<lb/>
Fernandez, Presedo, Martinez, Jernegan, Olson, Folk, Forbes, Andrus, West, Hanberry<lb/>
and Sonntag) yellow fever was produced at will either through the medium of mosquito<lb/>
bites or by injections of infected blood or serum. Their problem solved after just<lb/>
eight months of work the Board disbanded Camp Lazear on March 1, 1901. Now armed<lb/>
with precise knowledge Gorgas within three months freed Havana of its age old scourge<lb/>
and Later <add>with their and other knowledge, he</add> made safe the Isthmus of Panama <del>for the construction of the Panama Canal<lb/>
and the</del> safe <add>for</add> passage of the commerce of the world. In these troubled days when the<lb/>
safe passage <add>of the canal</add> is so vital to our national defense, the conquest of yellow fever, which<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f03903010"/>
11.<lb/>
<del>was so great</del><add>is such</add> a factor in the successful <del>construction</del><add>operation</add> of the canal, assumes a new<lb/>
significance. One of the strong links in the solidarity of the Western hemisphere<lb/>
has been forged by the cooperating sanitarians of the Americas who have, with the<lb/>
splendid cooperat<del>e</del>ion of the Rockefeller Foundation, done so much to obliterate<lb/>
yellow fever and other tropical diseases from this side of the globe, <add>thereby saving hundreds of thousands of lives and much property.</add> Lately we<lb/>
have heard much of the four freedoms: freedom of speech, freedom of worship, freedom<lb/>
from want and freedom from fear. The conquerors of yellow fever assuredly contributed<lb/>
greatly to the <add>eventual</add> attainment of these latter two freedoms, for fear and want are the<lb/>
constant handmaidens of disease.</p>
<p>This then is the story of these men in oils. Here <del>is</del> <add>you will see <unclear>portrayed</unclear></add> the team who won<lb/>
this victory: Finlay <add>the great Cuban physician</add> who for nineteen years dreamed the plan of battle, Walter Reed<lb/>
who planned the active campaign and assumed command in the heat of battle, and <del>Carroll</del><add>Lazear</add>,<lb/>
Agramonte and <del>Lazear</del><add>Carroll</add>--the rest of the Board who nobly carried out their respective<lb/>
duties even when it meant death. Here too, represented by the soldiers Kissinger,<lb/>
Moran and Jernegan, by one of the Spanish volunteers and by Dr. Cooke, are those<lb/>
whose bodies bore the brunt of the enemy's attack. And here represented by General<lb/>
Wood, Major Kean and Lieutenant Truby are loyal colleagues who smoothed the way with<lb/>
encouragement and help. <del>As you now know</del><add>As a matter of fact</add> this whole group of men were never actually<lb/>
together at any one time; to that extent this painting is artistic rather than factual.<lb/>
But these men were comrades in spirit and purpose, and in the records of history<lb/>
their names are inseparable.</p>
<p>And what became of their battlefield, Camp Lazear? Reverting to more<lb/>
commonplace uses it was lost for forty years until <del><unclear>Mesers</unclear></del><add>Mr. John</add>. Moran, <del>and</del><add>Mr. Luis</add> Pogolotti <add>(of Havana)</add> and I<lb/>
hunted for it and rediscovered it last <del>S</del>pring. Building No. 2 is gone, but Building<lb/>
No. 1 still stands, creaking with age and sleeping in the Cuban sun; at its back is an<lb/>
encroaching quarry; in front a corn field waves.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f03903011"/>
<p>12.</p>
<p>In concluding let me repeat a few words spoken recently at the dedication<lb/>
of a Lazear memorial: In these days when man's inhumanity to man is so pathetically<lb/>
apparent, when the world is red with blood, it is well for us to note the example<lb/>
of these men who banded together for high adventure, not to kill or even to die for<lb/>
one country, but to die if need be for their fellow men of all countries. It is<lb/>
such as they who reassure us of the inherent decency and dignity of man.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
