<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t03909001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from W.H. Hoffmann to George A. Kellogg, March 2, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hoffmann, W.H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>03909001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-03-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-03-02">March 2, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">03909001</idno>
<title>Letter from W.H. Hoffmann to George A. Kellogg, March 2, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hoffmann requests copies of the Cornwell painting to distribute to tropical disease specialists. He describes his years of yellow fever research and comments on the dangers of epidemic that still exist.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-03-02">
<head>Letter from W.H. Hoffmann to George A. Kellogg, March 2, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f03909001"/>
<opener>
C O P Y<lb/>
<dateline>
Habana, Cuba, <date value="1942-03-02">2 March, '42</date>
</dateline>
Cerro 1381<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I received with best thanks your kind letter of 19th Febr. today. I shall be<lb/>
grateful if through your distributors I may receive the copies which they can give<lb/>
me of the painting &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. The fifty copies which you are<lb/>
going to send directly to me by parcel post, probably will take some time when<lb/>
ordinary letters take two weeks.</p>
<p>I am personally quite uninterested in the matter, but it is a pleasure for me<lb/>
to distribute the copies in your honor, because you have undoubtedly acquired a<lb/>
great mail by ordering the reproduction of this painting. Its greatest value is,<lb/>
of course, for the specialists, with all of whom I have personal relations because<lb/>
I have been working as specialist of tropical medicine since 45 years in all the<lb/>
tropical countries, and since 25 years I have dedicated myself exclusively to the<lb/>
investigations on yellow fever here in Habana. When I started here the general<lb/>
opinion was that yellow fever had disappeared from the world. I did not believe<lb/>
that, and then I began to seek it from here. And it was my good luck to prove from<lb/>
here by anatomical examination of liver specimens, that yellow fever was still<lb/>
<hi>endemic</hi> in the whole of West Africa and of South Africa down to the cold South,<lb/>
This work took me more than ten years, till 1932, because from all the countries<lb/>
I had to ask liver material from my friends, and when I wrote them that I was seek-<lb/>
ing yellow fever, they wrote me more or less openly that I was mad, that it was<lb/>
quite impossible because they had no yellow fever and never had it. They did not<lb/>
know that they all had passed it as children, and the specimens which they sent me<lb/>
(as I asked them) from persons 11 who died suddenly in 3-4 days from an unknown<lb/>
disease all had died from yellow fever. There was no doubt possible about my results<lb/>
and all have been published, and years later have been confirmed by other new methods<lb/>
though I did not need any confirmation. My anatomical diagnosis did not admit any<lb/>
doubt. But the anatomical lesions were not generally known at that time and I had<lb/>
dedicated the first years in Habana to the anatomical study of all the great material<lb/>
which was preserved here from former epidemics, so I knew them perfectly.</p>
<p>The endemicity (?) which I found in West Africa and South America is still<lb/>
existing unaltered, and is still a permanent danger for Cuba and for U.S. and I<lb/>
doubt if this danger will ever disappear. But today we know that the danger exists,<lb/>
and so we are prepared to defend us against importation, which of course was not the<lb/>
case when everybody thought that yellow fever had disappeared from the world.</p>
<p>Today everybody who is responsible for the epidemiological work in each case<lb/>
thinks of yellow fever. If, for instance, here anybody dies suddenly from an un-<lb/>
diagnosticated disease (especially in immigrants and people coming from the steamer)<lb/>
I have the possibility to assist at the autopsy and to make immediately the examin-<lb/>
ation of the liver, and within a few hours I am absolutely sure to say, &ldquo;This is<lb/>
or is not yellow fever&rdquo;. I may say that the diagnosis of yellow fever in the patient,<lb/>
in isolated cases, is very difficult without autopsy. Therefore even today it is<lb/>
not rare that I receive specimens of liver from endemic countries where years ago I<lb/>
made the diagnosis, though in known endemic countries the responsibility is not so<lb/>
great, because they can treat any suspicious case as yellow fever, isolating him from<lb/>
mosquitos during the first three days of his disease, when he is infectious and in<lb/>
this endemic countries the danger of epidemics is not so great, because the greater<lb/>
part of the population is already immune.</p>
<p>I do not believe that all this should interest you in the least, but in such<lb/>
countries as Cuba and U.S. where yellow fever has been eradicated since nearly<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f03909002"/>
Dr. Hoffmann-continued<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
C O P Y<lb/>
forty-five years, the greatest part of the population is already highly susceptible<lb/>
(no protection by immunity) and if by accident one case (or an infection mosquito)<lb/>
is imported, an epidemic is quite easily possible today. The mosquitos once infected<lb/>
remain infectious during 3 months.</p>
<p><unclear>gash</unclear></p>
<p>Yellow Fever is still for a long time a great sanitary problem for our countries<lb/>
and is known as such.</p>
<p>With my best thanks and compliments.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>(sgd.) (Prof. W. H. Hoffmann, M.D.</signed>
Just in the moment when I had signed this letter the postman brings me the parcel<lb/>
post containing the fifty copies. This way seems the best to send them, because it<lb/>
avoids the Custom House, which it always takes some hours in the morning to get out<lb/>
something because it is directly at the harbour, about half an hour away from my In-<lb/>
stitute. I shall be very glad to pay the postage and enclose a money order over $1.<lb/>
The copies arrived in perfect condition and if you have any more to send I should<lb/>
recommend to do it in the same way. I remain very greateful for your great kindness<lb/>
and repeat my congratulation for your splendid idea to publish this painting.<lb/>
Prof. W. H. Hoffmann, M.D.<lb/>
I can easily distrubute the fifty copies to the most prominent specialists of<lb/>
tropical medicine, all my friends, and I have also many relations with the specialists<lb/>
on history of the Medicine, in which I had always some interest apart from my speciality<lb/>
of tropical medicine. If the Bestov Products have copies to spare still, I shall<lb/>
therefore be very thankful to receive them. My personal opinion is that the distri-<lb/>
bution to specialists is of greater importance than to the ordinary practitioner,<lb/>
because the specialists will conserve the copies in their Museums and use them for<lb/>
their university work and for demonstration to the students and eventually for re-<lb/>
production in their scientific publications and journals generally in your interest.<lb/>
I cannot enclose the money order because in the Post Office they refused to make<lb/>
the money order pretending (perhaps on account of my 190 cm. size) that I am a foreigner,<lb/>
which I am not. I think that one day your representative may pass here and I shall give<lb/>
him the money. He did not give me his address.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
