<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04013001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Felipe Carbonell Ponce, January 30, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04013001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-01-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ponce, Felipe Carbonell</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-01-30">January 30, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04013001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Felipe Carbonell Ponce, January 30, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench inquires about the Cuban government's interest in preserving the site of Camp Lazear. Hench stresses that he does not want the monument dedicated to one person, but rather envisions a Cuban-American memorial.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-01-30">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Felipe Carbonell Ponce, January 30, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04013001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<date value="1942-01-30">January 30, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Had no <hi>reply</hi><lb/>
Dr. Felipe Carbonell Ponce<lb/>
San Lazaro 413<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor <del>Ponce</del><add>Carbonell</add>:</salute>
</opener>
<p>My delay in answering your kind letter of January 12 has been occa-<lb/>
sioned by my absence from Rochester, attending meetings in the East. Needless to<lb/>
say, your letter was of great interest to me and it is very gratifying to know that<lb/>
I have been able to stimulate your interest so effectively. I am of course extremely<lb/>
anxious to know what results you have had with your continued conversations with<lb/>
Mr. Salas, Dr. Marruz and above all, with President Batista. You wrote me that Dr.<lb/>
Marruz was bringing the question before the Council of Ministers a couple of weeks<lb/>
ago. Have you had any word as to the result of this discussion? Before you wrote<lb/>
me, I had been in correspondence with the ownder of the property at the site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear. As you know I obtained from him a deed to the little building and I am<lb/>
buying some of the land. If governmental action is as slow in your country as it is<lb/>
in ours on occasion, I cannot be optimistic enough to hope that your government will<lb/>
at once become interested in this project. Therefore, it seems best to me to continue<lb/>
my negotiations with the purchase and proper preservation of the former camp site.<lb/>
I can assure you that if the Cuban government does wish to interest themselves in<lb/>
this project I will be glad to hand over to the Cuban authorities whatever interests<lb/>
and rights I have acquired.</p>
<p>You have interpreted my intention with absolute correctness. It is<lb/>
my intention that the little memorial building should be a monument to the Cuban-<lb/>
American medical profession and to the brave volunteers both of Finlay's and of the<lb/>
American commission's who helped to conquer yellow fever. It is not my purpose to<lb/>
have the monument dedicated to one person. Dr. Ramos was inclined to favor naming it<lb/>
&ldquo;The Lazear Memorial&rdquo;. That would of course be satisfactory to me providing it be<lb/>
known generally as a Cuban-American medical museum, dedicated to Finlay and his<lb/>
associates as well as to the Americans. In the brilliant conquest of yellow fever<lb/>
there is enough glory for all concerned and it is my purpose to heal the wounds that<lb/>
have been made as a result of the attempts of one or the other person to give more<lb/>
glory to one or another man. I am interested in your statement that you are decidedly<lb/>
against transferring the little building from Camp Lazear to the false site. Per-<lb/>
sonally, I would prefer not to transfer it although I have recognized the merits of<lb/>
this idea as proposed by Dr. Ramos and others since the little building would be then<lb/>
so much more close to the Ciudad Militar and the Military Hospital. I think that a<lb/>
smaller memorial, perhaps a boulder with a bronze plaque or some sort of a monument<lb/>
might well be erected at the false site, for this is where all the American cases of<lb/>
experimental yellow fever were cared for and this is actually where Dr. Lazear died.</p>
<p>When the venture gets well under way, certainly an advisory committee<lb/>
must be formed consisting of certain American and Cuban physicians and governmental<lb/>
personages most interested in this project. I discussed this with Dr. Charles E.<lb/>
Finlay last Spring when he was in Havana. I have already raised a little money in<lb/>
this country for our project but not as yet enough for the purchase of the property<lb/>
and building of the memorial building to enclose Building No. 1. Indeed, I have been<lb/>
delayed in getting the venture under full swing because I have not yet been able to<lb/>
find out exactly how much it would cost to purchase the entire site of Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>I am delighted that you get in touch with Mr. Pogolotti and Mr.<lb/>
Moran. They are charming gentlemen and have been of the greatest possible help to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04013002"/>
Dr. Felipe Carbonell Ponce<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
January 30, 1942<lb/>
me. Without them, the true site of Camp Lazear would never have been found and<lb/>
they must be recognized as perhaps the two most interested persons in Cuba in<lb/>
this venture. Certainly they should be on any advisory committee that is formed.<lb/>
I am distressed at not having heard from Mr. Moran for some months and have been<lb/>
wondering whether he is ill. I certainly hope not.</p>
<p>You may be interested to read a detailed report which I made to<lb/>
Dr. Dominguez Ramos, which report was prepared on the basis of an investigation<lb/>
of Mr. Moran, Mr. Pogolotti and myself. A copy of this report is in the library<lb/>
of the Finlay Institute and is illustrated with maps, various photostats, photo-<lb/>
graphs, etc., clearly showing our proof for the identification of the true and<lb/>
false sites of Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>I shall await with great interest further word from you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
