<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04016001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: History of Doctor Walter Reed's Illness from Appendicitis, by W.C. Borden, [1903]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04016001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1903-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Borden, William C.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1903-00-00">[1903]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04016001</idno>
<title>Report: History of Doctor Walter Reed's Illness from Appendicitis, by W.C. Borden, [1903]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Borden describes Reed's fatal attack of appendicitis and the treatment regimen followed before his death.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1903-00-00">
<head>Report: History of Doctor Walter Reed's Illness from Appendicitis, by W.C. Borden, [1903]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04016001"/>
<p>Notes written by the Secretary of the District<lb/>
of Columbia Medical Society - Washington<lb/>
Medical Annuals Vol 1 No 6 Jan. 1903</p>
<p>HISTORY OF DOCTOR WALTER REED'S ILLNESS FROM APPENDICITIS.<lb/>
By<lb/>
W. C. BORDEN, M. D., Major and Surgeon, U. S. A.</p>
<p>After referring to the close friendship which had existed between Dr. Reed<lb/>
and himself and the great personal responsibility which he felt in the management<lb/>
of the case, Dr. Borden said that the case well illustrated the insidious onset<lb/>
of the disease as sometimes seen, and the fact that the symptoms were often most<lb/>
treacherous in that little could be judged from them as to the severity of the<lb/>
lesion in the intestine. No other case had more thoroughly impressed upon him<lb/>
this fact.</p>
<p>When Dr. Reed first consulted him, November 14, he said that he believed<lb/>
he had appendicitis. Examination disclosed a tender spot about one-third of<lb/>
the way in from the right anterior superior spine. There was also increased<lb/>
muscular tension in that neighborhood. He had had colicky pains for three days,<lb/>
but had kept up and around. Temperature 99.4 and pulse 77. A diagnosis of<lb/>
appendicitis was made. That evening the symptoms persisted; bowels moved by<lb/>
cathartics. The next morning the patient was apparently better; there was less<lb/>
pain, tenderness and tension; temperature 98.6, pulse 60. Dr. Borden believed<lb/>
that the attack was about over, reserving however the opinion that one could<lb/>
never be certain, in dealing with appendicitis. That night, the temperature<lb/>
was 99.8, and the next morning it was 98; the same evening (Sunday) 100.4, and<lb/>
there were a few colicky pains, but the other symptoms were not increased. Al-<lb/>
though the symptoms were not at all grave, Dr. Borden advised immediate operation<lb/>
on account of the treacherous character of the disease. Next morning the tem-<lb/>
perature was 98.8, pulse 60. Operation performed by Dr. Borden at 11 A. M.</p>
<p>Some difficulty was encountered in finding the appendix and it was necessary<lb/>
to enlarge the incision. When located, it was found to be very large and was so<lb/>
closely adherent to the caput coli as to be practically embedded in it; it was<lb/>
given off from the center of the lower part of the caput. It was partly filled<lb/>
with pus and had perforated at one point; but the pus, partly in and partly filled<lb/>
with pus and had perforated at one point; but the pus, partly in and partly out<lb/>
of the appendix, was still prevented from escaping into the abdominal cavity by<lb/>
an extremely thin wall of adhesions, so thin that the pus showed through and its<lb/>
escape could have been but a matter of an extremely brief period of time. The<lb/>
field of operation was walled off with gauze. When the adhesions were separated,<lb/>
pus escaped; it was evacuated and mopped out with a dry sponge. The wall of the<lb/>
caecum was infiltrated and necrotic; this gave trouble by the tearing out of the<lb/>
stitches. The wound was closed with drainage.</p>
<p>The appendix showed signs of great previous trouble. Inquiry disclosed that<lb/>
Dr. Reed had for a long time suffered from attacks of indigestion and &ldquo;intestinal<lb/>
colic&rdquo;. The present trouble arose from the proximal end of the appendix. The<lb/>
appendix was practically a pus sac. This condition existed with a temperature<lb/>
not over 100.6 at any time and with comparatively insignificant symptoms, showing<lb/>
what serious pathologic changes may be present with slight symptoms.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed's condition at the time of the report was favorable. Nevertheless,<lb/>
it was necessary to give a guarded prognosis. On the evening of operation the<lb/>
temperature was 99; next morning 102, and the pulse 90; last night 101.8, pulse<lb/>
98; this morning 99, pulse 96; this evening 101.4, pulse 120. The rapidity of<lb/>
-1-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04016002"/>
Dr. WALTER REED'S ILLNESS. (cont'd)<lb/>
the pulse may have been due in part to the fact that Dr. Reed had been exceed-<lb/>
ingly nervous. The ether had acted badly, and nausea and vomiting persisted<lb/>
for 18 hours. He was now hardly recovered from a state bordering on nervous<lb/>
collapse. There was no evidence of peritonitis. This was the beginning of the<lb/>
third day.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed died on the sixth day after the operation with all the symptoms<lb/>
of intestinal perforation. It is probable that the necrotic caput coli sloughed<lb/>
or that the pus broke through into the general <unclear>peritoneal</unclear> cavity. No autopsy was<lb/>
made.</p>
<p>DR. NEFF said that he was present at the operation. The case was grave; it<lb/>
had been handled with consummate skill by Dr. Borden, and his would be the credit<lb/>
if Dr. Reed recovered, as all most earnestly hoped.</p>
<p>Dr. BOVEE called attention to the interest which attached to the specimen<lb/>
itself. It showed the process of gradual closure of the appendix as a result<lb/>
of chronic inflammation. Had the attacks continued, the lumen would in time have<lb/>
probably become obliterated. This would have been a fortunate result.</p>
<p>4 Pictures of the ruptured appendix<lb/>
appended to this report.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
