<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04013008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Louis Johnson, August 3, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04013008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-08-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Johnson, Louis</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-08-03">August 3, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04013008</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Louis Johnson, August 3, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is excited that Johnson might be able to interest the U.S. State Department in his plan to memorialize Camp Lazear. He feels that this would be an excellent and real opportunity to foster Pan-American solidarity. Hench estimates it would cost about $25,000 to do all he has planned.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-08-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Louis Johnson, August 3, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04013008"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-08-03">August 3, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Col. Louis Johnson<lb/>
Clarksburg<lb/>
West Virginia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Col. Johnson:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I do not want you to think I was ungrateful for the interest you<lb/>
expressed in my yellow fever historical venture. Just after seeing you I got some<lb/>
preliminary orders and I am now leaving this Thursday for active duty with the Army<lb/>
Medical Corps. In the rush of trying to get many things done before leaving, I have<lb/>
been unable to send you a synopsis of my investigations in Cuba. I do have a carbon<lb/>
copy of the formal report which I gave His Excellency Domingo Ramas, Minister of<lb/>
Defense of Cuba. The original of this copy he filed in the library of the Finlay<lb/>
Institute. It is profusely illustrated with photostatic documents and photographs.<lb/>
My own carbon copy does not have a complete set of photographs and documentary<lb/>
evidence, nor have I had time to have them made so far.</p>
<p>Because I am so delighted with your interest and with your suggestion<lb/>
that you might be able to interest the State Department in our plan to memorialize<lb/>
Camp Lazear, I shall try as soon as my army work permits, to make a shorter synopsis<lb/>
of this report, to have the appropriate photographs printed and send it to you. The<lb/>
Cuban Government and especially the Cuban medical profession are rather incensed with<lb/>
the attitude the American Government and American medical profession have taken toward<lb/>
Doctor Finlay, whom they consider their supreme medical genius and the real dis-<lb/>
coverer of the cause of yellow fever. The older school of thought in Cuba believes<lb/>
that Walter Reed and his associates merely confirmed what Findlay had already proven<lb/>
(and not merely correctly theorized). The newer generation of Cuban physicians is<lb/>
anxious to heal the breach and I know if the American Government and medical profession<lb/>
would make the kindly gesture of helping to memorialize the remains of Camp Lazear<lb/>
and help to donate and dedicate a little Cuban-American medical museum to the glory<lb/>
of the Cubans, Doctor Finlay and his associates and the American army Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission that this breach would be healed to the mutual satisfaction of all concerned.<lb/>
In my opinion this is a very excellent and real opportunity to foster Pan-American<lb/>
solidarity. The president of Cuba informally promised that if my associates and I<lb/>
could carry out such a venture, the government would make the dedication of Camp Lazear<lb/>
and of the little memorial museum a governmental affair.</p>
<p>I do not know how much this little museum would cost. My own plans<lb/>
are rather modest. I think $25,000 would do all I had planned. This would purchase<lb/>
the remains of Camp Lazear, the remains of Walter Reed's experimental building number 1<lb/>
which still is there and which we discovered, and build a little Cuban style museum<lb/>
to house the remains of building number 1 and on the surrounding walls to display<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04013009"/>
Col. Louis Johnson<lb/>
2<lb/>
August 3, 1942<lb/>
certain souvenirs of Finlay and the American Army Yellow Fever Commission, which<lb/>
I have collected. Doctor Finlay's son promised he would gladly consider housing<lb/>
in this museum many of the souvenirs of his father such as the original yellow fever<lb/>
manuscript, the original yellow fever mosquito vials, his father's microscope with<lb/>
which all the work was done, and other souvenirs. For this museum I have collected<lb/>
the original fever charts of most of the experimental cases in American soldiers.<lb/>
We will also have available the original or a replica of the Congressional medal<lb/>
presented to Reed and his associates and many other items of real interest to both<lb/>
Cuban and American physicians and laymen.</p>
<p>The Mayo Clinic has promised me that they will be glad to help<lb/>
contribute to this venture. Indeed, I know they would like to be in on it, and<lb/>
if you could interest perhaps Rockefeller's committee on Pan-American relationships<lb/>
or some other influential parties, I will indeed be very grateful.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
<unclear>PSH:as</unclear><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
