<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04013007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Adrian Macia, March 24, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04013007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-03-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Macia, Adrian</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Carbonell Ponce, Felipe</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-03-24">March 24, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04013007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Adrian Macia, March 24, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench implores Macia to preserve Building No. 1 until he has raised enough money to commemorate of the site. Hench assures him that a mutually satisfactory solution can be found for the sale of the land.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-03-24">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Adrian Macia, March 24, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04013007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-03-24">March 24, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Senor Adrian Macia<lb/>
Manzana de Gomez 325<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senor Macia:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am surprised at the return of my check for $150.00 as in your<lb/>
letter of January 6, you wrote as follows, &ldquo;In regard to the first question,<lb/>
I want to inform you that the 150 square yards of land would cost about $150.00.&rdquo;<lb/>
I assumed that that was just for the land on which the little house was. You<lb/>
will remember you warned me that legally speaking the deed which you gave me<lb/>
last year expires at the end of the year unless we have done something about<lb/>
it. That was why I was anxious to preserve the little house by purchasing<lb/>
now the land immediately there under, even though final negotiations cannot<lb/>
yet be made to purchase the corn field in front of it.</p>
<p>A few weeks ago I had a letter from Dr. Carbonell Ponce which en-<lb/>
couraged me to believe that he had aroused the interest of the Cuban government<lb/>
and that they were going to help with the project but I understand that that<lb/>
matter has been blocked for the time being.</p>
<p>First of all, may I beg of you that you will preserve the little house<lb/>
while we proceed with our plans in this country to raise the appropriate amount<lb/>
of money. I am sure that if we are permitted to purchase or receive from you<lb/>
as a gift the corn field immediately in front of the little shack with its bound-<lb/>
ary on Calle Luis Valdes Carrero, arrangements could be made to have a satisfactory<lb/>
entrance to your quarry site, with a road running down to your quarry from Manuel<lb/>
Virona Suarez. However, this is a detail that can be worked out to mutual satis-<lb/>
faction, I have no doubt.</p>
<p>The reason I have delayed somewhat in getting our campaign started was<lb/>
that I know one of the first questions which I will be asked will be, &ldquo;How much<lb/>
do they want for the land?&rdquo; I am afraid there will not be as much chance to<lb/>
raise the money until I can assure those whom I hope to interest that we actually<lb/>
can receive a deed to the property, either as a generous gift from you and your<lb/>
partner, or for a nominal and reasonable sum. As I understand it from your last<lb/>
letter and from one from Mr. Moran, you continue to be entirely sympathetic to<lb/>
our venture but do not want to commit yourself utterly until you know we are going<lb/>
to be able to raise the money. I can see your viewpoint and can sympathize fully<lb/>
with it; therefore I shall be satisfied with the kind sentiments which you have so<lb/>
far expressed and tell those whom I plan to interest that so far as I know you are<lb/>
quite willing to cooperate with us if we here show progress in raising the appro-<lb/>
priate amount of money for the memorial building. Believe me, Senor Macia, I<lb/>
appreciate greatly your continued interest in this historical venture.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
