<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04010001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, November 26, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04010001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-11-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Postell, William</name>
<name type="person">Tripoli, Dr.</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-11-26">November 26, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04010001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, November 26, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses the Cornwell yellow fever painting and the response to it in the U.S. Hench wishes that she had uncovered more material from her father's papers, but he thanks her nonetheless for providing information about Agramonte's life in New Orleans and details of his death.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-11-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, November 26, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04010001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-11-26">November 26, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez-Leon<lb/>
Calle 15 No. 311<lb/>
Vedado, Havana<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora Rodriguez-Leon:</salute>
</opener>
<p>At last the reprints of my Hygeia article have come and I am sending you<lb/>
<hi>12 copies.</hi> If you want more do not hesitate to let me know; thanks to Wyeth and Co.,<lb/>
I have an ample supply. I assume that Mr. Kellogg has sent you one or more of the<lb/>
large copies of the painting. He assured me he was going to and I know he will be<lb/>
delighted to let you have all you wish. The painting has aroused much favorable<lb/>
comment in the United States and you must be gratified I am sure to see your father<lb/>
assuming therein his rightful place. We do so hope that your countrymen will see in<lb/>
the painting a real, honest, and sincere attempt to give to Dr. Finlay his due credit.</p>
<p>I have been too busy with my medical work the past two months to do much on<lb/>
the yellow fever story but now I have more leisure and am back at it again. I hope to<lb/>
visit Washington in January to see if I can find the old records in the Surgeon General's<lb/>
office. I shall also try to find the records of your father's goings and comings,<lb/>
absences, etc. so as to refute the idea that he was not in Havana when Lazear died,<lb/>
or, if he was absent we can find out why, etc. not that his absence should permit one<lb/>
to question his motives or right to be absent. In January I go to Washington to speak<lb/>
at a medical meeting (on arthritis) and in March I hope to go with Mrs. Hench to Cali-<lb/>
fornia on vacation during which we hope to see Mrs. Lazear and Gen. Truby. Gen. Truby's<lb/>
manuscript of his experiences in Cuba with Reed, etc. is about ready for publication.<lb/>
In several places he seems uncertain as to your father's whereabouts and work and I<lb/>
have been very careful to call his attention repeatedly to your father's written state-<lb/>
ments. I sent him a copy of your father's letter to Hemmeter, etc. so that your father's<lb/>
position would be clear to him. But if you can come across any data, letters, diary,<lb/>
etc. that would be helpful I think it might cause Gen. Truby to get the picture more<lb/>
accurately.</p>
<p>I am &ldquo;sick&rdquo; to think you found so little in the boxes at the farm. Perhaps<lb/>
you will still come across the mislaid data. You say you found many more reprints.<lb/>
I wonder if you found any of the original first 3 or 4 reprints of the whole Board.<lb/>
I have been unable to get these original copies and if you ever find duplicates I<lb/>
would be more than pleased to receive what you can spare me.</p>
<p>You are always such a busy person--it seems to me you crowd three or four<lb/>
lives into one, being a mother, wife, teacher and degree-candidate. How can you do<lb/>
so much? I send you my best wishes for a rapid and successful completion of your<lb/>
Ph. D. work.</p>
<p>Mrs. Hench and I had a very nice, if hasty, visit to Pensacola and New<lb/>
Orleans. I had a very agreeable morning with Mr. William Postell, librarian at the<lb/>
Agramonte Memorial Library. He showed me your father's books and all the papers you<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04010002"/>
Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez-Leon<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 26, 1941<lb/>
left there. I went over all the latter most carefully and thinking you might like<lb/>
it, I made a list of the data they have, which list I enclose. Unfortunately,<lb/>
there was little or no data there which cleared up any of the holes in the story<lb/>
or the controversies we are trying to straighten out. In particular Mr. Postell<lb/>
told me of his careful but vain search through all your father's books and papers<lb/>
hunting for the European History Book signed by Marti. Certainly I found nothing<lb/>
in the papers along that line. Mr. Postell is very proud of the data of your father's<lb/>
which they have and would be glad indeed to have more (In that he and I are certainly<lb/>
alike:)</p>
<p>I am enclosing a couple bookplates from the library. The building shown<lb/>
is the Medical Center and the library is on one of the lower floors. In the hall out-<lb/>
side the library is a fine bas-relief in stone and metal representing, rather alle-<lb/>
gorically, the four members of the board and the tropics before and after the conquest<lb/>
of yellow fever. I tried to get a photo of it but none were available. I'll keep<lb/>
trying.</p>
<p>Mrs. Hench and I enjoyed meeting Dr. and Mrs. Tripoli. Knowing he was a<lb/>
friend of your father I assumed he was his contemporary in age and was much surprised<lb/>
to meet a young man about my own age (or even less:) We had a very pleasant dinner<lb/>
with them. I was so interested to hear from him of your father's life in New Orleans<lb/>
and of the details of his death. I hope you will not feel that I intruded in a very<lb/>
personal matter but I saw that you and your father have real friends in New Orleans<lb/>
and when the matter of your father's death was mentioned I recalled a passing remark<lb/>
you had made to me some time ago (in your letter of October 10, 1940) to the effect<lb/>
that you wished that sometime your father could rest again in Cuban (home) soil. I<lb/>
mentioned that wish to Dr. Tripoli, and I do believe that if it is still your wish,<lb/>
something could be done about it by your friends in New Orleans and elsewhere.<lb/>
Please write me and assure me that I have not been indelicate in this matter and tell<lb/>
me what your wishes are. In admiration of your father and his family I would be only<lb/>
too glad to be one of the instruments to accomplish your desire. If I have intruded<lb/>
unwisely into a very personal matter please forgive me and know that my motives were<lb/>
sympathetic.</p>
<p>Give our kindest regards to your husband and we do hope we can visit our<lb/>
good friends in Havana in the not too distant future.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
