<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04044001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank F. Law, November 23, 1944</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04044001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1944-11-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Law, Frank F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1944-11-23">November 23, 1944</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04044001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank F. Law, November 23, 1944</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes his encounter with Ramos. Ramos plans to commission a painting by Cornwell along the lines of the preliminary sketches for the Yellow Fever painting. However, this version would give Finlay the dominant position.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1944-11-23">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank F. Law, November 23, 1944</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04044001"/>
<opener>
PSH/cb<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1944-11-23">23 November, 1944</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Frank Law, President<lb/>
John Wyeth and Brothers<lb/>
1600 Arch Street<lb/>
Philadelphia, Pennsylvania<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Law:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I attended recently the meeting of the Association of<lb/>
Military Surgeons, where I put on an exhibit for the Army and Navy<lb/>
General Hospital. Although I passed the Wyeth booth several times,<lb/>
I never saw anyone I knew. I ran into Doctor Domingo Ramos, who<lb/>
was one of the distinguished guests of the convention. You remember,<lb/>
he was until recently, Minister of Defense of Cuba and is now Director<lb/>
of the Finlay Institute of Cuba. He was most anxious to arrange some-<lb/>
time for a showing of Cornwell's paintings in Cuba, and I believe he<lb/>
must have gotten in touch with you. He is, I believe, trying to arrange<lb/>
some sort of a special meeting in Cuba this Spring, and if his plans<lb/>
work out, it should be a very interesting occasion. While in New York,<lb/>
Doctor Ramos and I went to Cornwell's study and saw his latest paint-<lb/>
ing, of Oliver Wendell Holmes. I think it is excellent. I was delight-<lb/>
ed with it. Certainly Cornwell is a wonderful artist.</p>
<p>Doctor Ramos was anxious to discuss with Mr. Cornwell a<lb/>
tentative plan to have Cornwell paint, either for the Cuban Government<lb/>
or for the Finlay Institute, a finished painting along the lines of<lb/>
the preliminary sketches which Cornwell made for the Yellow Fever paint-<lb/>
ing, that is, what we have called the Cuban version. Through your<lb/>
gracious generosity, I was given these two oil sketches and they are<lb/>
hanging in the library of the Mayo Clinic, where they have been admired<lb/>
constantly. Between them hangs a copy of &ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;,<lb/>
the final version, and underneath there is framed an explanation of the<lb/>
three paintings. I offered to return these sketches to Mr. Cornwell<lb/>
(&ldquo;on loan!&rdquo;) if he needed them, provided Doctor Ramos actually did<lb/>
commission him to do this painting, but Mr. Cornwell said that he would<lb/>
prefer to start fresh. May I, however, offer to ship these two oil<lb/>
sketches to you, in case you wish to send them down to Havana with all<lb/>
the other Cornwell paintings of the medical series. Selfishly, I, of<lb/>
course, would like to have the oil sketches back, but at any time that<lb/>
you wish to exhibit them, I will be most delighted to send them to you.<lb/>
The &ldquo;Cuban version&rdquo; would, of course, be very attractive to the Cubans,<lb/>
as it gives Finlay the dominant position, and since it is essentially<lb/>
accurate, historically, (Although we don't quite know who was present<lb/>
on the occasion besides Reed, Finlay, Albertini and young Finlay.)</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04044002"/>
<p>Sheet Two</p>
<p>To: Mr. Frank Law</p>
<p>PSH/cb</p>
<p>23 November 1944</p>
<p>Did you know that a Cuban artist, Raquel Romero, is just<lb/>
finishing a mural entitled &ldquo;Martyrs of the Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;,<lb/>
which is being painted on the wall of a large lecture room in the new<lb/>
military hospital? It comprises two panels, as it were, and in the<lb/>
first panel Lazear is infecting a mosquito at Los Animos Hospital, and<lb/>
presumably being bitten by a stray mosquito. In the second panel, Miss<lb/>
Maas is being inoculated by Doctor Guiteras, and in the background are<lb/>
the two other Cuban volunteers who, with Miss Maas, died from experimental<lb/>
yellow fever in the first Cuban confirmation of Reed's work. They died<lb/>
in the Fall of 1901, so all in all, Mr. Law, you really started something<lb/>
when you commissioned Cornwell to do that fine painting.</p>
<p>After leaving New York, I spent two days in the Surgeon<lb/>
General's Office in Washington. Doctor Charles Stanley White is quite<lb/>
a prominent Surgeon in Washington, one of the most prominent Surgeons<lb/>
there; he is my wife's cousin. We were discussing Cornwell's painting<lb/>
for Wyeth's medical series and Doctor White expressed the earnest wish<lb/>
to have a set of them, if at all possible, for his offices. If it would<lb/>
be possible for you to send him a set, he would be very grateful. His<lb/>
address is &ldquo;1801 &lsquo;I&rsquo; Street.&rdquo; Incidentally, I have not, myself, received<lb/>
copies of the last three. I have none since &ldquo;The Conquerors of Yellow<lb/>
Fever&rdquo;. I would be very happy to have copies of: &ldquo;The Dawn of Abdominal<lb/>
Surgery&rdquo;, &ldquo;The Father of American Pharmacy&rdquo;, and the new one of Oliver<lb/>
Wendell Holmes, if it is available. I have them in my library at home<lb/>
and also one or two in the office at the Mayo Clinic. If possible, I<lb/>
would appreciate it if they would be sent to my home, &ldquo;517 Fourth Street,<lb/>
S.W., Rochester, Minnesota&rdquo;, rather than here. I certainly would appreciate<lb/>
this greatly.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>PHILIP S. HENCH, Lt. Col., M. C.<lb/>
Chief of the Medical Service</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
