<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04050013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo F. Ramos, November 13, 1944</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04050013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1944-11-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ramos, Domingo F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Macia</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1944-11-13">November 13, 1944</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04050013</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo F. Ramos, November 13, 1944</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench offers to lend Ramos some of his slides which deal with the yellow fever experiments. He also offers financial help to protect Building No. 1 and requests Ramos' assistance in organizing this effort.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1944-11-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Domingo F. Ramos, November 13, 1944</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04050013"/>
<opener>
Copies sent to Moran<lb/>
Rojas<lb/>
Macia<lb/>
PSH/cb<lb/>
also sent <unclear>Hougontes</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Medicos</unclear><lb/>
<hi>Ramos</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1944-11-13">13 November, 1944</date>
</dateline>
Doctor Domingo Ramos<lb/>
Finlay Institute<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Ramos:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was so delighted to meet you again in New York and to know<lb/>
of your enthusiastic interest in the plans for memorializing Camp Lazear.<lb/>

I shall be delighted indeed to participate in any of the plans you have<lb/>
for the immediate future. Also, I will be very glad to read over the<lb/>
manuscript of your Detroit address. In connection with this address, I<lb/>
promised to send you a list of the lantern slides which I have been using<lb/>
for my illustrated lecture on &ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. I have given<lb/>
this lecture many times in the last four years. I will be glad to lend<lb/>
you what slides you wish. I don't imagine you will want more than a very<lb/>
few of them. To show you what the pictures are like, I am sending you<lb/>
herewith thirty-one photographs of these slides. Unfortunately, I do not<lb/>
have here in Hot Springs the photographs of the other slides; however,<lb/>
you may remember that I presented to you, for the Finlay Institute, an<lb/>
outline of my &ldquo;proof&rdquo; of the whereabouts of Camp Lazear. This book I<lb/>
gave to you and you turned it over to the librarian of the Finlay Institute<lb/>
in 1941. In this book, you will find many of the other photographs of<lb/>
which I have had slides made and which are given in this list.</p>
<p>I would appreciate it greatly if you would return to me the<lb/>
enclosed photographs at your earliest convenience. This is the only set<lb/>
I have here in Hot Springs and on the back of these photographs are many<lb/>
notes which I am anxious to keep.</p>
<p>I am sorry I did not get to see you after your chat with<lb/>
General Kirk, to hear the details of your conversation; however, I am<lb/>
delighted to know that he seems sympathetic to your plan.</p>
<p>You may remember that I told you I had written John Moran,<lb/>
asking if he could help me make an arrangement to protect building No.<lb/>
1. I have not heard from him and I am concerned, lest the recent<lb/>
hurricane damaged the building. I would appreciate it greatly if, the<lb/>
next time you see Mr. Ma<del>r</del>cia, you would discuss this with him briefly,<lb/>
and I am willing to pay a proper sum, if it is not too great, from the<lb/>
funds I already have available, in order to preserve the little building<lb/>
properly. My original idea was to enclose building No. 1 completely<lb/>
with some sort of strong planking and tar paper so that it would be pro-<lb/>
tected from the elements, but if there is a chance that there might be<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04050014"/>
Sheet Two<lb/>
To: Dr. Domingo Ramos<lb/>
PSH/cb<lb/>
13 November 1944<lb/>
further hurricane between now and the time the little building is<lb/>
properly enclosed in a permanent building, perhaps it would be better<lb/>
to surround building No. 1 completely with a more stable structure of<lb/>
brick, or its equivalent. I am wondering how much it would cost to<lb/>
erect a brick or concrete enclosure around the building. I am going to<lb/>
write Mr. Moran, and I know that if he can help you and Mr. Ma<del>r</del>cia in<lb/>
any way, he will be glad to do so. I only wish that I were there to<lb/>
take this burden from you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>PHILIP S. HENCH, Lt. Col., M. C.<lb/>
Chief of the Medical Service</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
