<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04050002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John W. Hart to Philip Showalter Hench, October 27, 1944</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hart, John W.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04050002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1944-10-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ros, Arturo</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Division Hospital, Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1944-10-27">October 27, 1944</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04050002</idno>
<title>Letter from John W. Hart to Philip Showalter Hench, October 27, 1944</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hart informs Hench that he has become Vice President and General Manager of Winthrop Products. The article on Building No. 1 was written by the medical director of their Cuban organization, not by Hart. However, Hart does plans on writing an article about Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1944-10-27">
<head>Letter from John W. Hart to Philip Showalter Hench, October 27, 1944</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04050002"/>
<opener>
WINTHROP PRODUCTS INC.<lb/>
Pharmaceuticals Developed by Science and Dedicated to the Physician<lb/>
<dateline>
350 HUDSON STREET<lb/>
NEW YORK 14, NEW YORK<lb/>
WINTHROP<lb/>
N<lb/>
W<lb/>
E<lb/>
S<lb/>
<date value="1944-10-27">October 27, 1944</date>
</dateline>
Lt. Col. Philip S. Hench, M.C.<lb/>
Chief of the Medical Service<lb/>
Army &amp; Navy General Hospital<lb/>
Hot Springs National Park, Ark.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It was indeed a pleasure to receive your letter of<lb/>
the 16th of October concerning the Annotated Bibliography on Penicillin.<lb/>
I am having copies of both series sent you by Winthrop Chemical Company.</p>
<p>Since last we met, considerable change has come<lb/>
over the scene. The firm, &ldquo;Winthrop Products Inc.&rdquo; was organized in<lb/>
1941 for Latin American business and yours truly is now Vice President<lb/>
and General Manager of this organization. I do not get around to<lb/>
seeing the chaps at Winthrop Chemical as often as I used to but I<lb/>
will make a note to get you the Annotated Bibliography.</p>
<p>The article on Building No. 1 of yellow fever<lb/>
fame was written by the medical director of our Cuban organization,<lb/>
Dr. Arturo Ros and his interest was aroused by yours truly after he<lb/>
had introduced him to Moran and had accompanied the two of them first,<lb/>
to the site of the Division Hospital at Camp Colombia and then to the<lb/>
site of Camp Lazear and Building No. 1. I of course knew that the<lb/>
porch was not a part of the original building and know that there are<lb/>
one or two other discrepancies in his article. Had I had the oppor-<lb/>
tunity of reading the proofs before its publication, there are<lb/>
several corrections I could have made.</p>
<p>I am planning, however, to write an article on<lb/>
the site of Camp Lazear and a correction, at least in the minds of<lb/>
the medical profession in Cuba, of the beliefs that Camp Lazear existed<lb/>
at the site of the old tree or, location of the Division Hospital.</p>
<p>With reference to the building and the memorial<lb/>
to be erected at the site of the building, I look forward to having a<lb/>
part in this when the time comes and I believe that you are quite<lb/>
correct in having a protecting frame placed over the building as it<lb/>
now stands. I am wondering <del><unclear></unclear></del> however, if it would not be better to<lb/>
P.O. BOX 90 CANAL STREET STATION<lb/>
CABLE ADDRESS &ldquo;WINCOX&rdquo;<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04050003"/>
WINTHROP PRODUCTS INC.<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
make a more substantial protection than a wooden frame. The recent hurricane<lb/>
has left me with some fears as to the safety of the building and I certainly<lb/>
hope that nothing has happened.</p>
<p>We have our permanent organization in Cuba with Manager,<lb/>
Assistant Manager, Medical Director, detailmen, etc. and if any of them<lb/>
can be of service at any time to pinchhit for Mr. Moran or to assist him<lb/>
in any way, please let me know. I have such an intense interest in the<lb/>
entire project that I have taken a more or less personal view on the<lb/>
protection of the building and will, as stated above, do anything in my<lb/>
power to see that it is properly guarded.</p>
<p>I shall obtain a half dozen copies of the article as it<lb/>
appeared in our Horizontes M&eacute;dicos and if you should at any time care<lb/>
for any copies of the photographs which I made and, I believe, gave to you,<lb/>
I shall be only too glad to have enlargements printed.</p>
<p>With the kindest personal regards and looking forward to<lb/>
seeing you in the near future and with best wishes to Mrs. Hench, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially yours,</salute>
<signed>John W. Hart</signed>
jwh-jn<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. Do you expect to attend the Southern Medical at St. Louis? If so,<lb/>
I should like to see you. I shall be stopping at the Missouri Athletic<lb/>
Club.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
