<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04057001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">[Draft?] of letter from Philip Showalter Hench to [Blossom Reed?], April 5, 1945</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04057001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1945-04-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Blossom</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1945-04-05">April 5, 1945</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04057001</idno>
<title>[Draft?] of letter from Philip Showalter Hench to [Blossom Reed?], April 5, 1945</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is distressed to hear about Reed's financial problems. He offers monetary assistance.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1945-04-05">
<head>[Draft?] of letter from Philip Showalter Hench to [Blossom Reed?], April 5, 1945</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04057001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1945-04-05">5 April 1945</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mrs. ____________:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It would appear that neither you nor I had a very happy Christmas.<lb/>
You were all alone for three days; that was too bad because Christmas of<lb/>
all times is one day on which we like to share the hours with loved ones.<lb/>
I lost my dear Mother on Christmas morning just before sunrise. Let me<lb/>
inclose a letter which I wrote about her for some relatives and old friends.</p>
<p>After coming back here in January, being alone here, lonesome<lb/>
without my loving family, and sorrowed by the loss of my Mother, I became<lb/>
rather disspirited and I must admit I have been carrying on for about ten<lb/>
weeks or so without much zest in life. But my wife and that precious little<lb/>
two-year old boy of ours were able to visit me from March 3rd to 19th, and<lb/>
it has helped me so much. Finally I am coming out of my mood and finding<lb/>
optimism and energy to do more of the things I want to do, including getting<lb/>
caught up on my correspondence.</p>
<p>But I know very well how you must feel, all alone with the re-<lb/>
sponsibility of keeping up your home in war time with the servant scarcity,<lb/>
and above all with the lonesomeness entailed by your dear Mother's absence.<lb/>
I do truely hope she can be returned to you soon. Perhaps even now she and<lb/>
you are together again. I have seen you two together several times and may<lb/>
I remark again upon the wonderful loyalty you and your Mother have had for<lb/>
each other. You have carried on with such dignity and courage.</p>
<p>I am distressed at what you told me about your finances. Let me<lb/>
say that I felt honored that you felt you know me well enough to confide<lb/>
your troubles to me. To the extent that I am able I do want to help; al-<lb/>
though I have been very tardy about answering your letter, I have given it<lb/>
a great deal of thought. Perhaps by now your Mother is with you again and<lb/>
you can share her annuity. If not and if you still feel the way you did,<lb/>
I would be interested in the silver service. I am a bit worried about the<lb/>
matter. It seems so tragic that you should find it necessary to part with<lb/>
it, but if you do want to, I can sympathize fully with your great desire to<lb/>
put it in the hands of someone who would prize it, not just for its intrinsic<lb/>
value, but for its memorable associations.</p>
<p>In mentioning what I am about to mention, I <hi>do</hi> hope I am not<lb/>
offending you. Would it be possible, if you feel that you do want, or need,<lb/>
to part with something -- would it be possible that you would rather keep<lb/>
the silver service and part with a few of your Father's letters -- not the<lb/>
intimate letters he wrote to your Mother before he married, not these per-<lb/>
haps, but some of those from ____________? As you know, I am slowly<lb/>
collecting (to save for posterity in a medical museum) every item I can<lb/>
about ______ ______ ______ ______. All of those wonderful letters of his<lb/>
from ______ simply must be properly preserved. They must not be lost or<lb/>
even dissapated, <unclear>scarttered</unclear> here and there. They are of historic value and<lb/>
simply must be preserved in a proper manner.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04057002"/>
<p>Perhaps I am suggesting something which is distasteful to you.<lb/>
If so, please do forgive me, but if you do wish them to be preserved for<lb/>
a medical museum, I would be very grateful and proud to be the curator.<lb/>
I hate even to use the words &ldquo;sell them&rdquo;, but assuredly they should carry<lb/>
a monetary value as well as a historical value, and I would certainly be<lb/>
delighted to have the opportunity. Perhaps you would prefer to consider<lb/>
parting with a few rather than the collection -- or even only one or two.<lb/>
From the historical standpoint the New Year's Eve letter is one which<lb/>
should be preserved in the medical museum.</p>
<p>Were you to consider preserving some or many of the letters, I<lb/>
would be only too glad not only to see to it that they were preserved for<lb/>
posterity, first in the Mayo Clinic collection, later in the ______ ______<lb/>
Museum I still hope to establish, but I would be delighted to arrange to<lb/>
have every letter -- every page -- photostated for you so that you could<lb/>
still have copies of the complete set in case you wish later to finish<lb/>
your article about your Father.</p>
<p>I do most sincerely hope my making this suggestion has not dis-<lb/>
turbed you. How can one set a price on the letters, or even on one letter.<lb/>
Perhaps, indeed, you prefer to part with the silver service.</p>
<p>May I be frank enough to ask one thing. Will your brother be<lb/>
disturbed if you part with either the silver service or the letters? Does<lb/>
he consider them in part his or are they wholely yours? Your brother has,<lb/>
of course, the greatest possible pride in your Father and his wonderful<lb/>
work and he might consider it improper to allow these items to leave the<lb/>
family, even though they were to be preserved by loving and respectful<lb/>
strangers. I do not want to do anything which he would consider as taking<lb/>
advantage of your situation. Is it not possible that your situation may<lb/>
be only very temporary and that you might not need to part with anything?<lb/>
I would be only too glad to lend you the amount you suggested if that would<lb/>
help.</p>
<p>I know this is a delicate matter for you to discuss and, indeed,<lb/>
I find it difficult to write this as it just doesn't seem right for you to<lb/>
be put in this position, but you have honored me with your friendship and<lb/>
your confidence and I do so much want to be of service. Please do forgive<lb/>
me for answering your letter so tardily. I hope my delay has not permitted<lb/>
you to think me unsympathatic or disinterested. I shall be happy to hear<lb/>
from you very soon and I do so hope the difficulty is over. Also that your<lb/>
Mother is well enough to come back to your home to be with you. If she is<lb/>
well enough, that certainly is where she would be happiest.</p>
<p>I am so glad that you like the ______ _______ stamps. Mother<lb/>
was happy to be able to share with me the pleasure of sending them to you<lb/>
and your Mother. We had talked about it before she became so ill and she<lb/>
had asked me to try to get some for you, therefore, they were from her in<lb/>
fact and not just in name. My Mother became so interested in the stories<lb/>
of the ______ ______ ______ ______. She read everything I could get<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04057003"/>
on the matter. I showed her a few of the letters you so kindly loaned<lb/>
me and she was so greatly facinated, as she, too, had a high sense of<lb/>
their value to history.</p>
<p>I miss Mother terribly and I am very proud of the heritage she<lb/>
and my Father left us. They were wonderful Christians; the kind that is<lb/>
seen rarely in these troubled days. How very much my Mother would have<lb/>
enjoyed meeting you and your Mother and brother.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench</signed>
<seg>
P.S. I will send you a check at once if you need it.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
