<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04058003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, April 10, 1945</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04058003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1945-04-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rojas, Maria Teresa</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Macia, Adrian</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Finca San Jose (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1945-04-10">April 10, 1945</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04058003</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, April 10, 1945</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is relieved to hear that Building No. 1 was not destroyed during the latest hurricane. He assures Rojas that he will continue his campaign to raise funds for its preservation. He describes his visit with Mabel Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1945-04-10">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, April 10, 1945</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04058003"/>
<opener>
PSH/cb<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1945-04-10">10 April, 1945</date>
</dateline>
Senorita Maria Teresa Rojas<lb/>
Finca San Jose<lb/>
Redencion Marianao<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senorita Rojas:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you very much for your nice letter of March 17th.<lb/>
I am greatly relieved to hear that the little building connected with<lb/>
Walter Reed and the discovery of the cause of yellow fever, was not<lb/>
destroyed in the recent hurricane, but was remarkably, spared. It is<lb/>
difficult to understand why it was spared, although, as I remember it,<lb/>
there is a rather definite slope of the land downward from your home to<lb/>
the little building and I suppose that the force of the wind coming in<lb/>
from the ocean hit your home in full force and may have passed over the<lb/>
little building, deflected upward, due to the slope of the land. In any<lb/>
event, I am very happy that it was spared. I have written to Mr. Moran,<lb/>
asking him to see what can be done about protecting the little building<lb/>
against a future hurricane. I am willing to pay for <unclear>some</unclear> such protection,<lb/>
either to have a stout, strong frame put around it or have some other<lb/>
method of protection until we can enclose it in a suitable permanent<lb/>
building. I have also discussed with Mr. Moran possible methods for pro-<lb/>
tecting it from termites. I wrote to our Department of Agriculture here,<lb/>
asking for some information on how to protect the little building from<lb/>
termites. They sent me instructions which I, in turn, have sent to Mr.<lb/>
Moran and hope that he can get some Government Agent in Cuba to carry out<lb/>
the protective measures. If not, I am prepared to continue money to have<lb/>
a civilian do this if it does not cost too much.</p>
<p>I am very sorry that the War and my military duties have pre-<lb/>
vented me from continuing the campaign to raise funds for the preser-<lb/>
vation of the little building, but I can assure you that I propose to<lb/>
continue this as soon as possible. In the meantime, if there is anything<lb/>
you can do to maintain the interest of the local authorities, such as<lb/>
Doctor Ramos and Senor Macia, I would appreciate it greatly.</p>
<p>Did I ever tell you a little incident that occurred when I<lb/>
was visiting Mrs. Jesse Lazear in California two years ago? She is the<lb/>
widow of the doctor who died during the yellow fever experiments, and<lb/>
for whom Camp Lazear was named. She was showing me some old pictures<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04058004"/>
Sheet Two<lb/>
To: Senorita Maria Teresa Rojas<lb/>
PSH/<unclear>cb</unclear><lb/>
10 Apr. 1945<lb/>
which she had, herself, taken in Cuba in 1900. She visited Doctor<lb/>
Lazear for a few months. She used to wander around Marianao with her<lb/>
little camera. In her photograph album, I recognized a very familiar<lb/>
house and, excitedly, I asked her what the house was. She said, &ldquo;Oh,<lb/>
I don't know; it was just one of the nicest houses around there and I<lb/>
was interested in the Cuban architecture. I wandered by and took this<lb/>
picture. Nobody was there living in the house at the time, as I remember<lb/>
it<unclear>;</unclear> at least, I saw no one. One or two goats were <unclear>graving</unclear> in the front<lb/>
yard, and the shrubbery and lawn were not kept up&rdquo;. She was <unclear>amased</unclear> when<lb/>
I told her that it was a picture of the Finca San Jose, your house, and<lb/>
a few months later became the site of the Camp named after her husband.<lb/>
Did I ever send you one of those pictures of here? I had it copied and<lb/>
will be glad to send you one.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>PHILIP S. HENCH, Lt. Col., M.C.<lb/>
Chief of the Medical Service</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
