<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04064007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Minutes of the annual meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 19, 1945</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04064007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1945-11-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Love, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Stitt, Edward R.</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1945-11-19">November 19, 1945</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04064007</idno>
<title>Minutes of the annual meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 19, 1945</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>These minutes of the Walter Reed Memorial Association board cover organizational business.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1945-11-19">
<head>Minutes of the annual meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 19, 1945</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04064007"/>
<p>MINUTES<lb/>
of the<lb/>
Annual Meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial<lb/>
Association held at Washington, D. C., <date value="1945-11-19">November 19, 1945</date></p>
<p>The Board of Managers met in the Library, Trust Department, American Security and Trust<lb/>
Company, 15th St. and Pennsylvania Ave., N.W., at 10:30 A.M. and was called to order<lb/>
by its President, Brig. Gen. Jefferson R. Kean.</p>
<p><hi>Present:</hi> Brig. Gen. J. R. Kean; Major Gen. M. W. Ireland; Admiral E. R. Stitt; Brig.<lb/>
Gen. F. R. Keefer; Brig. Gen. A. G. Love; Mr. Hans W. Ireland; Col. J. F. Siler.</p>
<p><hi>Absent</hi>: Major Gen. C. R. Reynolds; Mr. Gilbert Grosvenor; Dr. L. O. Howard.</p>
<p>The minutes of the last meeting were read, approved and ordered made of record.</p>
<p>The Treasurer presented his annual report showing in summary comparative income<lb/>
and disbursements for the fiscal years ending Oct. 31, 1944 and Oct. 31, 1945 and the<lb/>
market value of the capital investments of the Memorial Fund as of Oct. 31, 1944 and<lb/>
Oct. 31, 1945, as follows:</p>
<p><hi>WALTER REED MEMORIAL FUND</hi><lb/>
<table rows="4" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand October 31, 1943</cell><cell>$ 127.46</cell><cell>Balance on hand October <unclear>31</unclear>, 1944</cell><cell>$ 160.88</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Income Oct 31, '43 to Oct 31 '44</cell><cell>1,119.47</cell><cell>Income Oct 31 '44 to Oct 31, '45</cell><cell>1,129.59</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>-------</cell><cell></cell><cell>-------</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>$1,246.93</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>$1,290.57</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="4">
<row>
<cell cols="1-2"><hi>DISBURSEMENTS 1944</hi></cell><cell cols="3-4"><hi>DISBURSEMENTS 1945</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily L. Reed</cell><cell>$1,052.00</cell><cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily L. Reed</cell><cell>$1,008.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Commissions to American Security<lb/>
and Trust Company</cell><cell>33.65</cell><cell>Commissions to American Security<lb/>
and Trust Company</cell><cell>33.68</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>To Reg mail and Insurance charges<lb/>
on securities mailed to Chi-<lb/>
cago, Illinois 3/3/44</cell><cell>.30</cell><cell>To accrued int 1000 Capital Tran-<lb/>
sit Company 1st &amp; Ref 4% due<lb/>
December 1, 1964</cell><cell>6.67</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>-------</cell><cell></cell><cell>-------</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand Oct 31 '44</cell><cell>$ 160.98</cell><cell>Balance on hand Oct 31 '45</cell><cell>$ 242.22</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p><hi>CAPITAL INVESTMENT ACCOUNT</hi><lb/>
<table rows="8" cols="4">
<row>
<cell cols="1-2"><hi>October 31, 1944</hi></cell>
<cell cols="3-4"><hi>October 31, 1945</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell><hi>Par value</hi></cell><cell>Market Value</cell><cell><hi>Par Value</hi></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>$25,900.00 Bonds</cell><cell>$29,436.00</cell><cell>$26,400.00 Bonds</cell><cell>$30,225.50</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Stocks</cell><cell>1,575.00</cell><cell>Stocks</cell><cell>1,620.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>3,000.00</cell><cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>3,000.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell>1,028.41</cell><cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell>553.41</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>-------</cell><cell></cell><cell>------</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>$35,039.41</cell><cell></cell><cell>$35,398.91</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>-------</cell><cell></cell><cell>-------</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>The report of the Treasurer was approved.</p>
<p>The following officers were elected for the forthcoming year:<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04064008"/>
<list type="simple">
<item>President Brig. Gen. Jefferson R. Kean</item>
<item>Vice President Major Gen. M. W. Ireland</item>
<item>Secretary Colonel Joseph F. Siler</item>
<item>Treasurer Mr. Hans W. Ireland</item>
</list></p>
<p>The Secretary, Colonel Siler, stated that in sending out the minutes of the last<lb/>
annual meeting to the members of the Board of Managers, he had sent a covering letter<lb/>
to those members who were absent last year, requesting that, after reviewing the dis-<lb/>
cussion relative to the eventual <unclear>disposition</unclear> of the memorial fund as a &ldquo;living&rdquo; memor-<lb/>
ial on the one hand or a &ldquo;visible&rdquo; statue, on the other, they express their opinion<lb/>
in the premises. In reply, the following opinions were expressed. Dr. L. O. Howard -<lb/>
&ldquo;I vote for the use of the endowment or its income for suitable scientific purposes.&rdquo;<lb/>
Col. Julian M. Cabell - &ldquo;As to the form of the memorial, I have had no experience in<lb/>
such things but quite approve your suggestion that the income should be used for sci-<lb/>
entific research.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The opinion expressed by Maj. Gen. C. R. Reynolds is incorporated in the follow-<lb/>
ing extracts from a letter received from him:</p>
<p>"My thought in the matter is that a fund of this size, approximately $25,000, is<lb/>
altogether too insignificant to furnish an income that will be of consequence in the<lb/>
field of medical research, nor am I certain that it is enough to build a monument to<lb/>
Walter Reed. Consequently, I would favor a movement at the present time to provide a<lb/>
much larger fund which I think might well be successful now, or immediately after the<lb/>
war, because of the great interest in preventive medicine and tropical diseases among<lb/>
a greatly increased military population as well as the general public. If, however,<lb/>
I am asked, as I assume I have been, for my opinion as to the best use of a fund of<lb/>
$25,000 I would say that a visible monument or memorial should be erected in the City<lb/>
of Washington in memory of Walter Reed. I do not recall that there is any monument in<lb/>
the District of Columbia to a doctor, except the one to Hahnemann and one's memory<lb/>
has to be scratched to think of any monument, except the John B. Murphy Memorial at <unclear>the</unclear><lb/>
American College of Surgeons and several now projected, throughout the whole United<lb/>
States.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know I am dissenting from the opinion of those who knew Walter Reed personally<lb/>
and more about his work than I do, but I am strongly of the opinion that $1,000 or<lb/>
more yearly, no matter how it is expended, will not adequately recall or memorialize<lb/>
the services of this great man.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Colonel Siler pointed out that the present market value of the endowment fund was<lb/>
$35,000 rather than $25,00 and, though the annual income is now only approximately<lb/>
$1000, it was his experience that such an amount could be used to profit and advantage<lb/>
in the prosecuation of scientific research, particularly so as it would continue from<lb/>
year to year. Furthermore, it might be practicable eventually to allow the income to<lb/>
accumulate over a period of years, thus adding to the endowment with eventual material<lb/>
increase in income.</p>
<p>In the course of the discussion it was pointed out that the Army General Hospital<lb/>
in Washington was named for Walter Reed to honor his memory and that doubtless in the<lb/>
years to come the name &ldquo;Walter Reed General Hospital&rdquo; would much better serve to keep<lb/>
the name and achievements of Walter Reed fresh in the minds and hearts of the people<lb/>
than would any statue erected in Washington. In this connection, Admiral Stitt stated<lb/>
that a number of years ago a statue of Benjamin Rush was erected in what is now the<lb/>
Naval Observatory reservation on Massachusetts Avenue and he wondered how many of those<lb/>
<unclear><del>m</del></unclear> -2-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04064009"/>
present at the meeting had any knowledge of the existence of such a memorial. As a<lb/>
matter of fact, only Admiral Stitt, General Ireland and General Kean had seen or knew<lb/>
of its existence.</p>
<p>The members of the Board present reiterated the opinion expressed at the last<lb/>
annual meeting to the effect that eventually the capital assets should constitute an<lb/>
endowment, the income of which should be used for the prosecution of suitable medical<lb/>
research.</p>
<p>General Keefer expressed the very deep regret of the members of the Board at the<lb/>
loss of one of its members, Col. Julian M. Cabell, whose death had occurred at Walter<lb/>
Reed General Hospital last week.</p>
<p>Motion was made by Colonel Siler that Dr. Philip S. Hench, of the Mayo Clinic,<lb/>
now on active duty as a Col., M.C., A.U.S. at the Army and Navy General Hospital,<lb/>
Hot Springs, be elected as a member of the Board of Managers to succeed Colonel Cabell,<lb/>
deceased. This motion was seconded and carried unanimously.</p>
<p>There being no further business, the meeting adjourned to meet at the call of the<lb/>
President.</p>
<closer>
<signed>J. F. Siler<lb/>
Col., U. S. Army, Retired<lb/>
Secretary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
