<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04064002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Minutes of the annual meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 20, 1944</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04064002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1944-11-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Love, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Siler, Joseph F.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1944-11-20">November 20, 1944</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04064002</idno>
<title>Minutes of the annual meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 20, 1944</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The minutes of the Walter Reed Memorial Association board cover organizational business.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1944-11-20">
<head>Minutes of the annual meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 20, 1944</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04064002"/>
<p><hi>COPY</hi><lb/>
<hi>COPY</hi><lb/>
Minutes of the Annual Meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association held at Washington, D. C., <date value="1944-11-20">November 20, 1944.</date></p>
<p>The Board of Managers met in the Board Room American Security and Trust Company,<lb/>
15th Street and Pennsulvania Avenue, Northwest, at 10:15 A.M. and was called to order<lb/>
by its Vice President, Majore General M. W. Ireland.</p>
<p><hi>Present:</hi> Maj. Gen. M. W. Ireland, Brig. Gen. F. R. Keefer, Mr. Gilbert Grosvenor,<lb/>
Brig. Gen. A. G. Love, Mr. Hans W. Ireland and Col. J. F. Siler.</p>
<p><unclear>Head<lb/>
mail<lb/>
Sent</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>Treas An Sec &amp; Trou &amp; Co</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>charge</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Absent:</hi> Brig. Gen. J. R. Kean (illness), Maj. Gen. C. R. Reynolds, <unclear>Rear</unclear> Admiral E. R.<lb/>
Stitt, Dr. L. O. Howard and Lt. Col. Julian M. Cabell.</p>
<p>As the <unclear>minutes</unclear> of the last meeting had been mailed to each member of the Board,<lb/>
a motion was made, seconded and carried that the reading of the minutes be omitted and<lb/>
that they be approved as written.</p>
<p>The Treasurer presented his annual report showing in summary comparative income<lb/>
and disbursements for the current and past fiscal years and the market value of the<lb/>
capital investments of the Memorial Fund as of October 31, 1943 and October 31, 1944,<lb/>
as follows:</p>
<p><hi>Walter Reed Memorial Fund</hi><lb/>
<table rows="9" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand Oct. 31, 1942</cell><cell>$ 97.54</cell><cell>Balance on hand Oct. 31, 1943</cell><cell>$ 127.46</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Income Oct 31,'42 to Oct 31,'43</cell><cell><hi>1207.32</hi></cell><cell>Income Oct 31,'43 to Oct 31,'44</cell><cell><hi>1119.47</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell><hi>$1304.86</hi></cell><cell>Total</cell><cell><hi>$1246.93</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Disbursements, 1943:</cell><cell></cell><cell>Disbursements, 1944:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily L. Reed</cell><cell>$1140.00</cell><cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily L. Reed</cell><cell>$1052.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Commissions to American Secur-<lb/>
ity and Trust Company</cell><cell>36.65</cell><cell>Commissions to American Secur-<lb/>
ity and Trust Company</cell><cell>33.65</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>War Damage Insurance on loan of<lb/>
H.L. and L.T. Breuninger</cell><cell><hi>.75</hi></cell><cell>Reg. mail and Ins. charges on<lb/>
securities mailed to Chicago</cell><cell><hi>.30</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell><hi>$1177.40</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>$1085.95</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Balanceon hand Oct. 31, 1943</cell><cell><hi>$ 127.46</hi></cell><cell>Balance on hand Oct. 31, 1944</cell><cell><hi>$ 160.98</hi></cell></row>
</table></p>
<p><hi>Capital Investment Account</hi><lb/>
<table rows="6" cols="4">
<row>
<cell cols="1-2"><hi>October 31, 1943</hi></cell><cell cols="3-4"><hi>October 31, 1944</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell><hi>Par value</hi></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell><cell><hi>Par Value</hi></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>$25,000. Bonds</cell><cell>$27,453.36</cell><cell>$25,900. Bonds</cell><cell>$29,436.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Stocks</cell><cell>1,537.50</cell><cell>Stocks</cell><cell>1,575.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>4,750.00</cell><cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>3,000.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell><hi>1,178.41</hi></cell><cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell><hi>1,028.41</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell><hi>$34,919.27</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>$35,039.41</hi></cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>The report of the Treasurer was approved.</p>
<p>The following officers were elected for the forthcoming year:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>President Brig. Gen. Jefferson R. Kean</item>
<item>Vice President Major Gen. M. W. Ireland</item>
<item>Secretary Colonel Joseph F. Siler</item>
<item>Treasurer Mr. Hans W. Ireland</item>
</list></p>
<p><unclear>General</unclear> Love called attention to the fact that there had recently been published<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04064003"/>
&ldquo;Memoirs of Walter Reed - the Yellow Fever Episode&rdquo;, by Brig. Gen. Albert E. Truby,<lb/>
U. S. Army, Retired, which contributed materially to existing knowledge of the<lb/>
experiments conducted by Walter Reed and his coworkers in demonstrating so quickly<lb/>
and so conclusively the method of transmission of yellow fever. It was resolved that<lb/>
the Board express to Gen. Truby its appreciation of his material contribution to the<lb/>
existing literature on Walter Reed. The following letter of appreciation prepared by<lb/>
Gen. Love was ssnt to Gen. Truby:</p>
<p>Washington<lb/>
21 November 1944</p>
<p>Brigadier General Albert E. Truby,<lb/>
145 Laurel Street,<lb/>
San Francisco, California.</p>
<p>My dear General Truby:</p>
<p>The Walter Reed Memorial Association at its annual meeting at 10 A.M. November<lb/>
20, 1944, by unanimous vote, directed me to express to you the sincere appreciation<lb/>
of the Association for your outstanding contribution to the Walter Reed literature<lb/>
by your &ldquo;Memoirs of Walter Reed -- the Yellow Fever Episode.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Association appreciates that it is extremely fortunate that you kept such<lb/>
accurate and timely records of your observations, and further that after many busy<lb/>
years of active military service you took advantage of the leisure afforded by your<lb/>
retirement to record and transmit, in a thorough way to your <unclear>contemporaries</unclear> and to<lb/>
posterity, so accurately and impartially, your observations of the dramatic events<lb/>
that have since affected so greatly the health and economic development of large<lb/>
sections of this hemisphere.</p>
<p>The work of Walter Reed and his associates, as recorded so effectively by you,<lb/>
will continue to be a model for such research and an inspiration to scientists.</p>
<p>The Association wishes <unclear>me</unclear> to express to you, not only its gratitude for this<lb/>
work, but its sincere regards and best wishes.</p>
<p>Cordially,<lb/>
JEFFERSON R. KEAN<lb/>
Brigadier General, U. S. A., Retired<lb/>
President, W.R.M.A.</p>
<p>J. F. SILER<lb/>
Colonel, U.S.A., Retired<lb/>
Secretary, W.R.M.A.</p>
<p>Colonel Siler stated that he thought the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association, as now constituted, should make of record an expression of their<lb/>
opinion as to the manner in which the work of Walter Reed should be perpetuated<lb/>
through the establishment, eventually, of a permanent memorial. This for the reason<lb/>
that some of the present members were his friends or close friends and others were<lb/>
contemporaries who knew him and had an intimate knowledge of his yellow fever research<lb/>
work and, thus, are best qualified to express an opinion in consonance with <unclear>present</unclear><lb/>
day conceptions of memorials as to the form the permanent memorial should take, whether<lb/>
a &ldquo;living&rdquo; memorial in the form of a Research Fund the income from which could be<lb/>
used for research or the use of the capital fund for the purchase and installation of<lb/>
a monument to Walter Reed in Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>In <unclear>finally</unclear> determining the type of permanent memorial to be established, the<lb/>
Board of Managers must of necessity take into consideration information available in<lb/>
the minutes of meetings of the original icorporators, minutes of the meetings of<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04064004"/>
their successors and information incorporated in the Articles of Incorporation. All<lb/>
minutes have been reviewed and pertinent extracts from the minutes and Articles of<lb/>
Incorporation follow:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>1) From the minutes of the meeting of the General Committee held at Bar Harbor, Maine,<lb/>
August 15, 1903: (Vol. 1, p.2) (Vol. 1, p.4)</p>
<p>&ldquo;Resolution&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Resolved, That this meeting express its approbation of the following sug-<lb/>
gestions, and commend them to the concurrence of all other committees interested<lb/>
in a memorial to Major Walter Reed:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. That an effort be made to raise a fund of $25,000 or more.</item>
<item>2. 2. That the invome thereof shall be paid to Mrs. Reed during her lifetime<lb/>
and to her daughter (if she survives her mother) during her lifetime.</item>
<item><p>3. After both deaths the principal shall be devoted to the erection of a<lb/>
suitable memorial to Major Reed in the City of Washington, or to the establish-<lb/>
ment of a fund for the promotion of research in the field to which he was de-<lb/>
voted. The decision between these projects and the carrying out of the plan<lb/>
which may be adopted shall be left absolutely to the committee below designated.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The sentiment of the persons present, afterwards confirmed by conversation,<lb/>
appeared to be in favor of placing in Washington a sculptured monument commemor-<lb/>
ating Major Reed, with a well-considered inscription which should set forth his<lb/>
great contribution to the <unclear>welfare</unclear> of mankind.&rdquo;</p></item></list></p></item>
<item><p>2) From the minutes of a meeting of the committee designated by the American Associ-<lb/>
ation for the Advancement of Science, held at Philadelphia: (Vol. 1, p.5)</p>
<p>"The <unclear>following</unclear> motions were made and carried:</p>
<p>&ldquo;That a memorial of an enduring and visible character be erected in the City<lb/>
of Washington. D.C., at a point to be later selected, to Major Reed.&rdquo;</p></item>
<item>3) From the Certificate of Incorporation: (Vol. 1, p.7)<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>"FIRST. The name of the association shall be &ldquo;The Walter Reed Memorial Associ-<lb/>
ation&rdquo;; and the objects for which it is formed are to commemorate by a suitable<lb/>
memorial the eminent scientific and public services of the late Major Walter<lb/>
Reed, Surgeon, U. S. Army, and to raise funds for that object; also to assist,<lb/>
if necessary, with the income <unclear>of</unclear> such fund the wife and daughter of said Walter<lb/>
Reed.</item>
<item>"SECOND. The existence of said association shall be until the objects for which<lb/>
it is organized have been completed and terminated.</item>
<item>"THIRD. The capital of the Association shall consist of such funds as may be<lb/>
raised for the purposes above named.</item>
<item>"FOURTH. The affairs of said Association shall be managed for the first year<lb/>
by Surgeon General R. M. O'Reilly, U.S. Army; Gen. George M. Sternberg, U.S.A.;<lb/>
Retired; Major J. R. Kean, U.S.A.; President D. C. Gilman; Dr. F. S. Nash, U.S.A.;<lb/>
Mr. A. G. Bell; Mr. W. A. Gordon; Gen. Calvin DeWitt, U.S.A., Retired; Dr. J.<lb/>
Carroll, U.S.A.; Dr. W. D. MCCaw, U.S.A.; and Dr. A.F.A. King, who shall<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04064005"/>
organize for the carrying out of the <unclear>purposes</unclear> of the Association. After the first<lb/>
year the affairs shall be conducted by such officers as the Association shall elect.&rdquo;</item>
</list></item>
<item><p>4) From a fund solicitation letter written by Gen. Sternberg for distribution to the<lb/>
Medical profession which was approved for distribution by the Executive Committee,<lb/>
Board of Managers, at its meeting in Washington, May 9, 1904: (Vol., p. 18)</p>
<p>&ldquo; - - - It is thought that at least $25,000 should be raised and it is probably<lb/>
that the exact character of the Memorial will not be determined until a con-<lb/>
siderable portion of this amount is in the hands of the Treasurer.&rdquo;</p></item>
<item><p>5) From the by-laws of the Walter Reed Memorial Association. (Vol.1, p.37)</p>
<p>&ldquo;Objects.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The objects of the Association are to commemorate by a suitable memorial<lb/>
the eminent scientific and public services of the late Major Walter Reed, Sur-<lb/>
geon, U. S. Army, and to raise funds for that object; also to assist, if necessary,<lb/>
with the income of such fund the wife and daughter of Major Reed.&rdquo;</p></item>
<item><p>6) From the minutes of a meeting of the Executive Committee held in Washington, D.C.,<lb/>
December 20, 1904: (Vol. 1, p.47)</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dr. Kean stated he had had an interview with Mrs. Walter Reed, who stated<lb/>
she would prefer having an income of the fund paid to her, and in the event of<lb/>
her death, provision made for their daughter.</p></item>
</list></p>
<p>* * * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dr. A. F. A. King offered the following: &ldquo;RESOLVED. That when the sum<lb/>
of $25,000 is received, the net income of the fund shall be paid over to Mrs.<lb/>
Walter Reed during her lifetime,&rdquo; which was seconded by Mr. Bell and carried.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The quotations from <unclear>minutes</unclear> of meetings, quoted above, indicate quite clearly that<lb/>
it was the intent that the annual income from the fund should be paid to Mrs. Walter<lb/>
Reed during her lifetime and thereafter to her daughter and that no steps should be<lb/>
taken to establish a permanent memorial until after the deaths of the two above-<lb/>
mentioned beneficiaries.</p>
<p>Extracts from minutes of meetings and other data quoted above indicate that no<lb/>
definite steps have ever been taken specifying the type of permanent memorial that<lb/>
should be established, though the data do indicate that it was the general impression,<lb/>
when the funds were being raised, that the memorial would be in the form of a statue<lb/>
erected in Washington. However, at the initial organizational meeting at Bar Harbor<lb/>
in August, 1903 a Resolution <unclear>adopted</unclear> indicated that it was the intent of the committee<lb/>
that the fund to be raised would be devoted to the erection of a suitable memorial to<lb/>
Walter Reed in Washington or to the establishment of a fund for the promotion of re-<lb/>
search, the decision between the two projects to be made at a later date by the com-<lb/>
mittee.</p>
<p>In April, 1904 the Walter Reed Memorial was <unclear>incorporated</unclear> in the District of Colum-<lb/>
bia and the Certificate of Incorporation contains no reference as to the form of perman-<lb/>
ent memorial to be established other than that one of the objects of the Association is<lb/>
to &ldquo;commemorate by a suitable memorial the eminent scientific and public services of<lb/>
the late Major Walter Reed.&rdquo; There also appears in the minutes of a meeting of the<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04064006"/>
Executive Committee on May 9, 1904 the following statement contained in a fund-raising<lb/>
letter to the medical profession, the distribution of which was approved by the Exec-<lb/>
utive Committee: &ldquo;It is thought that at least $25,000. should be raised and it is pro-<lb/>
bable that the exact character of the Memorial will not be determined until a consid-<lb/>
erable portion of this amount is in the hands of the Treasurer.&rdquo; No further references<lb/>
to this matter appear in the minutes of subsequent meetings of the Executive Committee<lb/>
or Board of Managers of the Association orther than approved statements appearing in<lb/>
letters soliciting funds, already referred to.</p>
<p>It is evident that the Board of Managers of the Association as successor to the<lb/>
original organizing committee eventually will be charged with the responsibility of<lb/>
determining the exact form of memorial to be established.</p>
<p>It was felt by Col. Siler that the facts just reviewed indicated that the Board<lb/>
of Managers could adopt one of two plans for a permanent memorial -- a &ldquo;Living&rdquo; me-<lb/>
morial in the form of a Memorial Fund, the income of which <unclear>would</unclear> be devoted to sci-<lb/>
entific research or a statue of Walter Reed to be erected in Washington. He had dis-<lb/>
cussed the matter with Gen. Ireland, Gen. Kean and Mr. Ireland and they felt as he did<lb/>
that the fund should be held intact and the annual income used for the prosecution of<lb/>
suitable research. Gen. Kean felt that as Major Reed had graduated in medicine from<lb/>
the University of Virginia it would be well to <unclear>have</unclear> the income from the fund used by<lb/>
the Medical Department of the University of Virginia for research work.</p>
<p>The matter was discussed generally at the meeting and it was the unanimous opinion<lb/>
of all the members present that the form of memorial should be use of the income from<lb/>
the fund for scientific research rather than the expenditure of the principal for the<lb/>
erection of a visible monument.</p>
<p>There being no further business to come before the meeting, it adjourned to meet<lb/>
at the call of the President.</p>
<p>J. F. SILER<lb/>
Colonel, U. S. Army, Retired<lb/>
Secretary</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
