<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04116001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Minutes of the Annual Meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 21, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04116001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-11-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-11-21">November 21, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04116001</idno>
<title>Minutes of the Annual Meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 21, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This document details the proceedings of the Walter Reed Memorial Association conference.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-11-21">
<head>Minutes of the Annual Meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 21, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04116001"/>
<p><hi>COPY</hi></p>
<p>Minutes of the<lb/>
Annual Meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial<lb/>
Association held at Washington, D.C., November 21, 1946</p>
<p>The Board met in the Board Room, American Security and Trust Company, 15th St.<lb/>
and Pennsylvania Ave., N.W., at 10:30 A.M. and was called to order by its president,<lb/>
Brig, Gen. Jefferson R. Kean.</p>
<p><hi>Present</hi>; Brig. Gen. J. R. Kean, Maj. Gen. M. W. Ireland, Rear Adm. E. R. Stitt, Brig.<lb/>
Gen. A. G. Love, Mr. Gilbert Grosvenor, Mrs. Hans W. Ireland, Dr. Philip S. Hench and<lb/>
Col. J. F. Siler</p>
<p><hi>Absent:</hi> Maj. Gen. C. R. Reynolds, Brig. Gen. F. R. Keefer and Dr. L. O. <unclear>Howard</unclear>.</p>
<p>Gen. Kean, in introducing the new member of the Board, Dr. Philip S. Hench of the<lb/>
Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn., stated that the Board was particularly fortunate in<lb/>
having Dr. Hench as a member, especially so because of his intense interest in and<lb/>
knowledge of all matters pertaining to Walter Reed and his yellow fever investigations.<lb/>
Gen. Kean stated that Dr. Hench became interested in the work of Walter Reed several<lb/>
years ago since which he had devoted much energy and time to collecting all published<lb/>
biographical data relating to Walter Reed and his work, in corresponding with and in-<lb/>
terviewing friends and coworkers of Walter Reed and the men who served as experimental<lb/>
subjects in the yellow fever investigations and in visiting the scene of the yellow<lb/>
fever investigations in Cuba and securing first-hand information from all individuals<lb/>
who had knowledge of the work. As a result of all these investigations Dr. Hench had<lb/>
a much more comprehensive knowledge of Walter Reed and his work than any living Amer-<lb/>
ican.</p>
<p>The minutes of the last meeting were read and approved.</p>
<p>The Treasurer submitted the following annual report, summarizing comparative income<lb/>
and disbursements for the fiscal years ending Oct. 31st, 1945 and Oct. 31, 1946, and<lb/>
the par and market values of capital investments of like periods of time:<lb/>
<hi>WALTER Reed MeMorial Fund</hi><lb/>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand October 31, 1944</cell><cell>$ 160.98</cell><cell>Balance on hand October 31, 1945</cell><cell>$ 242.22</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Income Oct 31,'44 to Oct 31,'45</cell><cell><hi>1,129.59</hi></cell><cell>Income Oct 31,'45 to Oct 31,'46</cell><cell><hi>1,127.18</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>$1,290.57</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>$1,369.40</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p><hi>Disbursements 1945</hi><lb/>
<hi>Disbursement 1946</hi><lb/>
<table rows="5" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily L. Reed</cell><cell>$1,008.00</cell><cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily L. Reed</cell><cell>$1,008.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Commissions to American Security<lb/>
and Trust Company</cell><cell>33.68</cell><cell>Commissions to American Security<lb/>
and Trust Company</cell><cell>33.82</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>To accrued Int 1000 Capital Tran-<lb/>
sit Co. 1st &amp; Ref 4% dur Dec-<lb/>
ember 1, 1964</cell><cell><hi>6.67</hi></cell><cell>To Reg Mail and Insurance charges<lb/>
on Securities mailed to New York</cell><cell>1.70</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>$1,048.35</cell><cell></cell><cell>$1,043.52</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand Oct 31, 1945</cell><cell>$ 242.22</cell><cell>Balance on hand Oct 31, 1946</cell><cell>$ 325.88</cell></row>
</table></p>
<pb n="2" id="f04116002"/>
<p><hi>CAPITAL INVESTMENT ACCOUNT</hi><lb/>
<table rows="6" cols="4">
<row>
<cell><hi>Par Value Oct 31, 1945</hi></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell><cell><hi>Par Value Oct 31, 1946</hi></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>$26,400 Bonds</cell><cell>$30,225.50</cell><cell>$28,915 Bonds</cell><cell>$29,797.37</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Stocks</cell><cell>1,620.00</cell><cell>Stocks</cell><cell>1,845.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>3,000.00</cell><cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>2,500.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell><hi>553.41</hi></cell><cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell><hi>1,053.14</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell><hi>$35,398.91</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>$35,195.78</hi></cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>The report of the Treasurer was approved.</p>
<p>The following officers were elected for the forthcoming year:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>President Brig. Gen, Jefferson R. Kean</item>
<item>Vice Pres Maj. Gen. M. W. Ireland</item>
<item>Secretary Col. Joseph F. Siler</item>
<item>Treasurer Mr. Hans W. Ireland</item>
</list></p>
<p>Gen Kean stated that occasionally individuals, connected indirectly with the<lb/>
yellow fever experimental work in Cuba, were <unclear>endeavoring</unclear>, through special acts of Con-<lb/>
gress, to have their names placed on the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor, notwithstanding<lb/>
the fact that the type of service rendered by them in no wise justifies such recognition.<lb/>
As such <add>cases</add> require investigations by the Medical Corps of the Army, General Kean<lb/>
suggested that it would be desirable to elect the Surgeon General of the Army to the<lb/>
Board of Managers and he asked the Secretary if this could be done at this time. The<lb/>
Articles of Incorporation and By-laws were not available at the meeting but the Secretary<lb/>
reviewed them immediately thereafter and found that the By-laws of the Association provide<lb/>
for eleven members of the Board of Managers and that at the present time there are no<lb/>
vacancies. However, these By-laws can be amended at special or annual meetings. If and<lb/>
when the By-laws are amended to include the Surgeon General of the Army as a permanent<lb/>
members of the Board, it should be understood that election would not be by name but rather<lb/>
by position as the Surgeon General of the Army irrespective of the individual who might<lb/>
be occupying the position.</p>
<p>Col. Siler brought up a question raised in a letter from Gen. Reynolds read at the<lb/>
last annual meeting, namely, whether it might be desirable ar advisable to make concerted<lb/>
efforts to secure material additions to the memorial fund. It was generally agreed that<lb/>
it would be highly desirable to do so, particularly so if the income from the fund even-<lb/>
tually is to be used for research. It was decided, however, that it would be unwise to<lb/>
undertake any campaign for additional funds <unclear>until</unclear> final decision had been reached by the<lb/>
<unclear>Board</unclear> of Managers as to the type of memorial eventually to be established. The matter<lb/>
was therefore held in abeyance for consideration at the next or subsequent annual meetings.</p>
<p>Dr. Hench reported to the Board that as a result of his visits to Cuba he felt that<lb/>
it would be highly desirable to purvhase the land and remaining sturctures at Camp Lazear<lb/>
in Havana and convert the site into a permanent memorial in honor of both the Americans<lb/>
and the Cubans who took part either directly or indirectly in the epoch-making yellow<lb/>
fever investigations. A discussion of his plans and the progress made <unclear>toward</unclear> their accom-<lb/>
plishment is summarized in Exhibit A attached to these minutes. Dr. Hench contemplates<lb/>
raising funds for the establishment of this memorial through the solicitation of contri-<lb/>
butions from a limited number of individuals, foundations and also commercial firms.</p>
<p>The members of the Board expressed their hearty approval of Dr. Hench's plans in<lb/>
general and in particular his plan to make this memorial a dual one - Cuban and American-<lb/>
and proffered their support and cooperation in any manner considered feasible by the Board.</p>
<p>There being no further business, the meeting adjourned to meet at the call of the<lb/>
President.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Signed: J. F. Siler, Secretary</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
