<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04117001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: A Memorial Project - The Preservation of Camp Lazear, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 21, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04117001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-11-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Domonguez, Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Macia, Adrian</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">San Martin, Ramon Grau</name>
<name type="person">Presno, Jose A.</name>
<name type="person">Rockefeller, Nelson</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados de Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Finca San Jose, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Agramonte General Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>12 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-11-21">November 21, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04117001</idno>
<title>Report: A Memorial Project - The Preservation of Camp Lazear, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 21, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench reports to the Reed Memorial Association board on the Finlay-Reed controversy and the ongoing attempt to memorialize Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-11-21">
<head>Report: A Memorial Project - The Preservation of Camp Lazear, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 21, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04117009"/>
<p><hi>A Memorial Project: The Preservation of Camp Lazear</hi></p>
<p><unclear><del></del></unclear> Report to the Walter Reed Memorial Association by Dr. P. S. Hench<lb/>
Nov 21, 1946<lb/>
(<hi>Semi-Confidential</hi>)</p>
<p>I have been honored indeed by my election to this Board. I know that<lb/>
General Kean proposed my name because he has been aware of my deep<lb/>
interest in the work of Dr Reed and his colleagues. One of the<lb/>
by-products of my studies has been the rediscovery of Camp Lazear<lb/>
and the remains of Reed's historic &ldquo;Building number one&rdquo; in which<lb/>
were performed the crucial experiments on the propagation of yellow<lb/>
fever. General Kean, the President of this Board, has permitted<lb/>
me to outline to you a project for the preservation of Camp Lazear.<lb/>
This project has for me much greater significance than the mere<lb/>
further honoring of Reed, Lazear and their associates. To<lb/>
explain the wider merits of the project necessitates a little<lb/>
back-ground information.</p>
<p><unclear>Insist from</unclear></p>
<p><hi>The Cuban-American Controversy: Finlay versus Reed</hi></p>
<p>You recall, of course, that Dr Carlos Finlay of Havana originated the<lb/>
mosquito theory of yellow fever in 1881, pursuing his investigations for 19<lb/>
years during which time he inoculated 103 <add>unquarrantined</add> persons of whom 16<lb/>
<unclear><del>critical</del></unclear><lb/>
subsequently developed what critical investigators <add>considered</add> then,<lb/>
and still<lb/>
consider, to have been spontaneous, not experimental yellow fever.<lb/>
Then in 1900 the American Board of Officers discovered the cause<lb/>
of the disease, proving the correctness of Finlay's theory. The Boards'<lb/>
preliminary work up to the time of Lazear's death was done <del><unclear></unclear></del> from<lb/>
the Post Hospital, Camp Columbia, outside of Havana. Thereafter <del>their</del> the<lb/>
main <del>work</del> part of the work was done at Camp Lazear, an isolated<lb/>
experimental camp established on a nearby but secluded farm.</p>
<p>The reports of Reed et al aroused two strong conflicting<lb/>
emotions in the mind of Finlay, 1) elation that his <hi>theory</hi> was<lb/>
proven, 2) depression and <add>mild</add> antagonism that his <hi>work</hi> (i e his<lb/>
&ldquo;successful inoculations&rdquo;) was rejected &amp; his cases considered<lb/>
to have been of spontaneous, not experimental disease. Finlay began<lb/>
to defend the validity of his work and to his defense there<lb/>
came certain prominent Cuban physicians, previously disbelieving<lb/>
but now fired with the zeal to &ldquo;vindicate Finlay.&rdquo; At first<lb/>
this controversy was kept by Reed on a dispassionate scientific<lb/>
plane but after Reed's death two years later, the argument became<lb/>
somewhat bitter. Doctor Finlay's son (whom I visited twice) told me<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04117010"/>
CL<lb/>
<del>At this time</del> I wish merely to acquaint you with my <add>present</add> plans<lb/>
for the project and to ask, <unclear><del>not <add>for</add> your financial support</del></unclear><lb/>
only <unclear><del>but</del></unclear> for your <del>moral support</del><add>approval</add> &amp; advice.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04117011"/>
<p>(2</p>
<p>&ldquo;their side&rdquo; of the controversy. Later in a letter to me (1942) Dr Finlay's son,<lb/>
himself also a physician, wrote me &ldquo;There is no question that among<lb/>
the <del><unclear>U. S. A. elements at first and later U. S army</unclear></del> U S A (meaning<lb/>
U S Army) elements at first and later by elements of the<lb/>
Rockefeller Foundation there was for many years a marked<lb/>
tendency to ignore and belittle my father's experimental<lb/>
work.&rdquo; This view is widely held thruout Cuba &amp; was repeatedly expressed <unclear>to me</unclear><lb/>
by Cuban physicians, sometimes with some heat and asperity. In this view Finlay's son is unfortunately partly correct.<lb/>
Certain American reports (not those of Reed) did pass by Finlay's theory<lb/>
rather ungenerously and one or two of Carroll's later papers were<lb/>
<del><unclear>were properly</unclear></del> possibly unnecessarily curt and offensive to <del>the</del><lb/>
Finlay and friends. Later <del>reporting</del> some of the <add>early</add> reports of the<lb/>
Rockefeller Foundation served to add to the misunderstanding.</p>
<p>As a reaction to this &ldquo;neglect&rdquo; of Finlay there arose and<lb/>
still exists in Cuban professional <unclear><del>our</del></unclear> and governmental<lb/>
circles a <add>rather</add> rabid pro-Finlay school headed for years by<lb/>
Dr Dominguez who, to &ldquo;Vindicate Finlay,&rdquo; wrote a book<lb/>
strongly pro-Finlay and anti-Reed (or anti-U. S) concluding<lb/>
that the Americans merely confirmed. Finlay's <hi>proven</hi> work.<lb/>
This book published in French in 1935 and translated into<lb/>
English in 1938, received sufficient recognition that its<lb/>
author was decorated by the French government.</p>
<p><hi>Cuban Honors for Finlay</hi>: <hi>Cuban <del><unclear>neglect of</unclear></del><add>attitude toward</add> Reed</hi></p>
<p>A corollary of the Cubans' desire to honor Finlay has been<lb/>
their neglect of Reed, a neglect which at times has been so obvious as to make one realize it was intended. Examples: (1) In the Courtyard of the Cuban Dept of Public Health was erected a magnificent statue to Finlay; on its <unclear>pedestal</unclear> is inscribed<lb/>
the reasons for <del><unclear></unclear></del> the honor; <del><unclear>no mention</unclear></del> Reed &amp; colleagues are<lb/>
unmentioned. (2) In the<lb/>
park in front of this building <add>is another statue of Finlay, flanked by</add><lb/>
<del><unclear>are</unclear></del> four <unclear>busts-</unclear>of <del><unclear>of Finlay</unclear></del>, Delgado, Guiteras, <add>Gorgas,</add> and Lazear;<lb/>
none of Reed; no mention of <add>him or of</add> Agramonte. (3) Agramonte<lb/>
became looked upon as something of a &ldquo;traitor&rdquo; to<lb/>
Finlay &amp; the Cuban viewpoint because he, tho a Cuban,<lb/>
defended the American Board's views. 4) I have read<lb/>
numerous articles by Cuban physicians extolling Finlay to<lb/>
the almost total neglect of the Americans. In other words<lb/>
the Cubans have vigorously participated in the very tactics<lb/>
they deplored in others.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04117012"/>
<p>(3</p>
<p><hi>The Compromising Elements in Cuban Medical Circles</hi></p>
<p>All along <del><unclear>there have been</unclear></del>certain Cuban physicians have refused to join<lb/>
in the controversy and have insisted on giving due credit to both sides.<lb/>
ALBERTINI<lb/>
Doctor Albertini, one of Cuba's most prominent physicians and Doctor Domingo<lb/>
Ramos, the physician who was first Minister of War, <unclear>'</unclear>later Minister of<lb/>
Health under Batista <del><unclear></unclear></del> notably fostered amicability. Results:<lb/>
(1) The government named the army's chief hospital the Agramonte<lb/>
General Hospital. (2) They <del>erected</del> purchased what they (erroneously) thought<lb/>
was the site of Camp Lazear (right across the railroad track from the <del><unclear></unclear></del> main Cuban army post and its hospital), put up a little memorial fence<lb/>
and sign (mentioning the American Board members) and planned<lb/>
someday to erect a memorial hospital. 3) In the Las Animas<lb/>
Hospital where Lazear <del>was</del> supposedly incurred his accidental<lb/>
fatal mosquito-bite they put up a wooden &amp; cardboard memorial plaque to Lazear: <del><unclear></unclear></del> put up &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo; about 1928<lb/>
to be replaced by a bronze one, the temporary one was still up<lb/>
in 1940. 4) Dr Ramos in 1939 published a paper<lb/>
proposing a national (medical) memorial to the &ldquo;yellow<lb/>
Fever heroes&rdquo; (Americans included);not yet erected.<lb/>
5) In 1944 a mural was done in <unclear>a</unclear> government hospital-<lb/>
it included Lazear.</p>
<p><hi>The Present Cuban Attitude</hi></p>
<p><unclear>Drs</unclear> Albertini &amp; Ramos have told me they <del><unclear></unclear></del> considered the<lb/>
anti-U S, anti-Reed, rabid pro-Finlay controversy most<lb/>
unfortunate &amp; undignified &amp; hoped it would die out as its<lb/>
more zealous participants passed away. But despite the<lb/>
grudging inclusion of the Americans in recent honors the Cuban government and<lb/>
medical profession are doing little<lb/>
about concrete memorials; it is mostly talk.They continue<lb/>
to almost deify Finlay. He is the Cuban Pasteur, growing in<lb/>
fame,<add>partly</add> because he is a martyr, an injured <unclear>,</unclear> misunderstood &amp;<lb/>
neglected genius <del>(neglected by the Cuban</del> (incidentally neglected mostly by the<lb/>
Cubans <add>themselves</add> for 19 years) and because he is their one great scientist.<lb/>
Evidences: 1) The Finlay postage stamp. (2) <del><unclear></unclear></del> Cancellation<lb/>
marks - &ldquo;To the glory of Finlay and Science&rdquo; - <del><unclear></unclear></del> used in<lb/>
recent years to cancel postage stamps, (3) Erection of the<lb/>
Finlay Institute (a sort of governmental Rockefeller Foundation,<lb/>
4) &ldquo;The Order of Finlay&rdquo; is Cuba's highest Scientific <del>honor</del> and (<del>governmental</del>) honor &amp; decoration.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04117013"/>
(4<lb/>
5) The annual Finlay birthday celebrations and orations. Many of the latter<lb/>
orations are so intemperate in their &ldquo;vindication of Finlay&rdquo; that they<lb/>
almost smack of &ldquo;hate sessions.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>The Discovery of the Lost Camp Lazear</hi></p>
<p>Reed's official reports did not exactly identify the location of Camp Lazear.<lb/>
As stated the Cuban government finally sought for it and bought what was<lb/>
supposed to be it. In 1940 <del><unclear>on</unclear></del> <add>on</add> a vacation to Havana I sought to find the<lb/>
real site; with the help of Mr. John Moran (one of Reed's first guinea-pigs)<lb/>
and Mr. Pogolotti, a Cuban real estate man, this was accomplished.<lb/>
We reported this to Cuban authorities who at first expressed<lb/>
disbelief, annoyance, &amp; resentment. I was asked to present to the<lb/>
Cuban government a documented report which I did in 1941.<lb/>
Since then my report has obviously been accepted (<del><unclear>through I was most<lb/>
</unclear></del>)because 1) the memorial sign &amp; fence at the false<lb/>
camp site were allowed to fall down &amp; were hauled away 2) the<lb/>
Lions'<del><unclear>and</unclear></del> Club of Havana has <add>just</add> placed a memorial plaque<lb/>
on a stone fence near the true camp. 3) Dr Ramos sent me a<lb/>
letter expressing &ldquo;the gratitude and appreciation of the Government of Cuba,&rdquo; etc., etc.<lb/>
(I have available all the necessary maps, photographs &amp; other<lb/>
identifying evidence). <del><unclear>propound thats "of the Cuban Government to the</unclear></del></p>
<p><hi>Importance of Memorializing Camp Lazear</hi></p>
<p>Memorializing Camp Lazear <add>as a Cuban-American Memorial,</add> and preserving the historical little<lb/>
&ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo; would serve several purposes:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1) Contribute to medical historical accuracy.</item>
<item>2) Foster Cuban-American cultural &amp; professional<lb/>
relationships</item>
<item>3) Perhaps initiate a new era <add>of professional friendship</add> &amp; stop the acrimonious<lb/>
debate by making an occasion for a &ldquo;love feast&rdquo; to<lb/>
bury the hatchet</item>
<item>4) Please and placate the Finlay family. (I discussed<lb/>
this idea with Dr Finlay; he was much pleased &amp; told me he<lb/>
would contribute some of his father's historical <unclear>mementoes</unclear>.)</item>
</list></p>
<p>Incidentally Camp Lazear is <hi>uniquely suitable</hi> as a site for <del><unclear></unclear></del> a Cuban - American memorial because<lb/>
investigation shows that on that very same farm Dr Finlay<lb/>
years before had carried out 2 or 3 of his early inoculations-<lb/>
- a fact <del><unclear>and</unclear></del> known only to very few but discussed with<lb/>
much <del><unclear>pleaure</unclear></del><add>satisfaction</add> by Doctor Finlay's son and me. (We have absolute<lb/>
proof of this.)</p>
<pb n="6" id="f04117014"/>
<p>(5</p>
<p><hi>Preliminary Ideas Regarding the Memorial</hi></p>
<p>Unfortunately the site of Camp Lazear is in an undistinguished &amp; very humble<lb/>
part of Quemados de Marianao <add>(suburb of Havana)</add>, but it is just about 3 blocks off<lb/>
the main <del>highway</del> <add>street</add>, The Calzada Real. My original idea included the<lb/>
following: 1) Purchase the Camp site: the site would comprise about<lb/>
one <add>small</add> town-block but a half-block would be sufficient if funds for the<lb/>
whole site were not available. The site is fortunately still empty; it<lb/>
is used as a corn field but workers' small 3 or 4 room houses<lb/>
surround it on 2 sides. 2) Enclose <del><unclear>the</unclear></del> the remains of &ldquo;Building 1&rdquo;<lb/>
in a modest museum. 3) <del>Restore</del> Repair Building 1 (it is only<lb/>
14 x 20 feet) and restore its interior as it was during the experiments<lb/>
(a stove<add>STOVE</add>, 3 cots, a couple trunks of blood-stained bedding)<lb/>
4) Place a small stone pile (memorial) on the site of &ldquo;Building 2,&rdquo;<lb/>
80 yards in front of Building 1. 5) Place a bronze plaque on<lb/>
the stone wall (the main wall) of the Finca San Jose of which<lb/>
Camp Lazear was a part. This wall still encloses the lovely<lb/>
old main house of the <del><unclear>finca</unclear></del> finca &amp; is on the main highway<lb/>
(main street) 2-3 blocks from the Camp. This plaque would be<lb/>
passed daily by the towns' main traffic and would indicate<lb/>
the proximity of the Camp; a road already leads directly from<lb/>
the main street to the Camp-site. 6) Collect and house in<lb/>
the small <del><unclear></unclear></del> museum building (<del><unclear>enclosing</unclear></del> to enclose<lb/>
Building one) souvenirs, photographs, original charts, etc. pertaining<lb/>
to all the Cuban &amp; American &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo;<lb/>
<del>(<unclear>aspar</unclear></del> (Finlay, Delgado, Reed, Lazear, Carroll, Agramonte,<lb/>
<del>Guiteras</del> the American volunteers, Guiteras). (I have<lb/>
already collected a mass of such data from the families of<lb/>
Reed &amp; Lazear, <del>et al</del> from Dr Howard Kelly, Generals Kean &amp; Truby, &amp; others; should it seem more &ldquo;fair&rdquo; to share<lb/>
this <del>data</del> historical data with an American <add>medical</add> museum<lb/>
it could be copied and each museum get half of the original).<lb/>
(7) Erect a little stone pile (bronze plaque) on the site of the false Camp Lazear; actually this was where the patients with experimental<lb/>
yellow fever were moved to (from Camp Lazear) and cared for &amp; where Lazear died,<lb/>
(just across a railroad track from the main hospital of the Cuban army).</p>
<p><hi>Preliminary Accomplishments</hi></p>
<p>The Rojas family which still owns the main part of the Finca San<lb/>
Jose were delighted to discover the historical facts of their old homestead.<lb/>
Madam Rojas is quite wealthy &amp; will cooperate fully; her children<lb/>
were equally pleased.</p>
<p>That part of the Rojas farm (Finca San Jose) <del><unclear>with</unclear></del> where <del><unclear>was</unclear></del> Camp<lb/>
Lazear actually the <del>the Camp</del> had been, <add>was</add> sold to Senor Macia, a wealthy<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04117015"/>
(6<lb/>
Cuban business man who uses the adjacent quarry and rents<lb/>
the Camp Lazear site as a corn field. He was most interested,<lb/>
promised full cooperation, said he would <hi>probably</hi> either <hi>give</hi><lb/>
me the site or sell it at a nominal cost when the time came <hi>provided</hi><lb/>
it be used as a memorial site. In 1941 he gave me (as a sign of<lb/>
his good faith) a deed to the little building (but not the land) but<lb/>
it was only good for 2 years (the war completely interrupted my plans).</p>
<p>Certain governmental personalities promised full cooperation.<lb/>
Dr Ramos and other Cuban medical authorities visited the camp<lb/>
with me; there was some talk of moving Building one to the<lb/>
<del>site of the</del> false site &ldquo;because that is where Lazear died and is so<lb/>
convenient to the Army Hospital - a couple hundred yards<lb/>
away.&rdquo; I was <del><unclear>introduced</unclear></del> <add>taken</add> to President Batista who in a<lb/>
very short (but polite) 5 minute interview expressed his sincere (?)<lb/>
interest &amp; said he hoped he could be present at the dedication<lb/>
&amp; make it a governmental ceremony.</p>
<p><add>Under the supervision of Mr. Moran</add> I spent about $50<hi rend="superscript">00</hi> to repair the leaky roof of Bldg one<lb/>
and a small additional sum for incidentals. (It is still<lb/>
inhabited by a tenant).</p>
<p><del>Dr Ramos in 1945 <unclear></unclear></del></p>
<p><hi>Since 1942</hi>-----</p>
<p>Batista and Ramos are out. The new President,<add>Dr. Grau San Martin,</add> is a physician<lb/>
and could be readily interested in the project <add>so I am told.</add> Certain elements<lb/>
have interested themselves but want to make it a <hi>Cuban</hi> (not a<lb/>
Cuban-American) medical memorial. Mr. Macia, owner of the Camp site,<lb/>
offered by letter to sell me the site for a <del><unclear>nominal</unclear></del> <add>nominal</add> sum-$150<hi rend="superscript">00</hi>.<lb/>
I promptly sent him a check which he returned with a<lb/>
vague <del><unclear></unclear></del> <add>letter</add>: I think he wants to do nothing until he<lb/>
<hi>knows</hi> that the plan will go through. I don't blame him<lb/>
&amp; I am sure he will sell the property without too much<lb/>
trouble although his ideas as to &ldquo;the <add>appropriate</add> price&rdquo; may be undergoing<lb/>
<del><unclear>since though</unclear></del> revision.</p>
<p>Doctor Hart, one of the chief officials of Winthrop Chemical<lb/>
Company which has large sales in Cuba became interested in<lb/>
my story, visited Havana, took photos of the Camp site<lb/>
&amp; published a story in Spanish which attracted some attention<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04117016"/>
(7<lb/>
Thereafter I understand a radio station publicized the story of the<lb/>
discovery of Camp Lazear and I believe there was a Sunday newspaper article thereon. (I didn't see it).</p>
<p>Doctor Presno, Minister of Public Health and Sanitation became<lb/>
(temporarily) <del><unclear>with</unclear></del> interested and promised to Mr. Moran certain things (help<lb/>
in protecting and repairing Building #1) but nothing has<lb/>
come of it so far. A couple Cuban physicians, having heard of all this,<lb/>
wrote me, promising enthusiastic support when needed; <del><unclear>they</unclear></del><lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> this was spontaneous on their part as I've had no time<lb/>
since 1942 to further materially the project.</p>
<p><del><unclear>Dr James Peabody</unclear></del> A New York biologist who early became intensely<lb/>
interested in the yellow fever story &amp; was responsible for the early<lb/>
pensions to the participants, became interested in our <del>proposal</del> <add>project</add> &amp;<lb/>
suggested raising funds &ldquo;in memory of a <add>college</add> classmate who had<lb/>
died of yellow fever.&rdquo; I politely declined funds that might<lb/>
necessitate memorializing the spot to one who had no<lb/>
connection with the conquest of the disease.</p>
<p><del><unclear>Dr Morris Fishbein and Dr Edgar Mazer with others<lb/>
recently formed the &ldquo;Finlay Institute of the Americas&rdquo;; Dr<lb/>
Mazer heard of my work, and visited me &amp; had some vague<lb/>
discussion about my forming forces with them (I think<lb/>
there Institute is merely a paper - affair; I think they wanted<lb/>
a project about which they could really). Dr Mazer<lb/>
wrote &amp; spoke of having me made a Director of there Institute. I made<lb/>
no commitments. Nothing came of the all this. Several certain officers of the Institute later<lb/>
vented Havana &amp; were decorated with the Finlay medal<lb/>
obviously perhaps their interest has in my perfect has dismissed.</unclear></del></p>
<p><del><hi>Present Plan</hi></del></p>
<p>It was suggested that the Department of Pan American Cultural Relationships<lb/>
of the U S Government might sponsor our project and that I see Nelson<lb/>
Rockefeller about it. Last year the Surgeon General arranged for me to meet him.<lb/>
He allowed<lb/>
me about 10 minutes, showed no interest and said their department<lb/>
was about to be re-organized &amp; would have no funds for such a<lb/>
project. (Aren't they still sending movie stars on good will trips to South America?)</p>
<p>The only concrete thing has been done by the Lions' Club<lb/>
of Havana which placed a plaque on the wall of the Finca<lb/>
San Jose.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f04117017"/>
<p>(8</p>
<p><hi>Present Plan</hi></p>
<p>Still believing that the project has merit I now wish to <del>gave more <unclear>too</unclear></del><lb/>
push it along. If others agree to its merits the <hi>first</hi> requirement and<lb/>
an urgent one, <del><unclear>into purchase the land &amp; shack with shack &amp;<lb/>
new we would</unclear></del> is to have <add>Cuban (or American.)</add> wood experts <del><unclear>mates</unclear></del> inspect the little shack &amp;<lb/>
advise us whether or how the wood can be preserved and/or restored. The <del><unclear>the</unclear></del> historical little shack is in pretty bad shape, even though it is still lived in.<lb/>
Mr. Moran is quite pessimistic about it. However, I have had some<lb/>
correspondence with the Dept of Agriculture in Washington; although my<lb/>
correspondents have only seen photos of the <del><unclear>harvest</unclear></del> shack &amp; not the<lb/>
shack itself, they believe tentatively that it can be preserved. It isn't <add>in</add> much worse <del><unclear>then</unclear></del> condition than was the little house, Reed's birth place,<lb/>
nicely restored a few years ago.</p>
<p>2) If so, the next step would be the purchase of the lot &amp; shack<lb/>
<del><unclear>or to purchase the lot &amp; could an exact replaced of teh thick.</unclear></del></p>
<p>3) Next we must <hi>at once</hi> build some sort of a temporary<lb/>
protection around it - either a strong new wood <del><unclear>on</unclear></del> or<lb/>
galvanized iron covering <del><unclear>large examples</unclear></del> to <del><unclear>allow</unclear></del> protect<lb/>
it against the elements (it survived the tornado of 1926<lb/>
which destroyed Bldg 2; miraculously it also survived the<lb/>
severe tornado of 1944). This outside cover should be large<lb/>
enough to permit workmen to begin the first stages of restoration,<lb/>
chemical protection against termites, etc. If the shack cannot<lb/>
be preserved an exact replica could be erected on the spot.</p>
<p>4) Then in greater leisure we could raise the funds necessary<lb/>
for the memorial building and the small additional markers.<lb/>
I have neither the inclination, energy or time to <del><unclear>same work</unclear></del><lb/>
&ldquo;collect nickels.&rdquo; <del>I think the</del> If the project is worthwhile<lb/>
I think it could be underwritten by a few institutions.</p>
<p>In 1950 is the 50th Anniversary of the &ldquo;Conquest of Yellow<lb/>
Fever&rdquo; a most appropriate time to finish &amp; dedicate the project.<lb/>
My <add>first</add> ideas on the cost of the building were modest: to erect<lb/>
a little museum building of simple Cuban style about<lb/>
35 x 60 feet, perhaps larger. A Cuban architect in<lb/>
1940 hazarded a <unclear>gauss</unclear> that <del><unclear>it might cost</unclear></del> $20,000 <del><unclear>might</unclear></del> would<lb/>
be enough (1940 prices). If a few <del>people</del> individuals or<lb/>
one or two institutions are to pay for it alone and<lb/>
wish to present it to the Cuban government as a modest,<lb/>
not an elaborate, memorial the cost need not be great.</p>
<p><del><unclear>In</unclear></del> Before proceeding very far we should find out<lb/>
whether the Cuban government would accept it as a<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f04117018"/>
(9<lb/>
&ldquo;national monument&rdquo; and support its care. It was my thought<lb/>
that the building should be large enough to have the shack<lb/>
in the center of the (main) room with a protecting <del><unclear>cost</unclear></del> rope<lb/>
cordon (on standards) around it; with the front &amp; 3 sides<lb/>
left intact (restored as necessary) but with the back of the<lb/>
little shack entirely open so that visitors passing around it<lb/>
would see <del><unclear>at</unclear></del> <add>the inside</add> arranged as it originally was.</p>
<p>The remaining space would be given to displays: wall<lb/>
displays, mostly, a few cabinets. In one corner would be<lb/>
the care-taker's desk, <del><unclear>with souvenir post</unclear></del> perhaps with<lb/>
souvenir postcards and a little illustrated booklet.</p>
<p>If enough funds could be raised one end of the building<lb/>
could contain a small 4 room apartment for the care-taker<lb/>
(small living room, bedroom, combined kitchen-dinette, bath).</p>
<p>It must be pre-determined whether the Cuban government<lb/>
or the Cuban medical association would consent to be<lb/>
responsible for the up keep &amp; protection of the little museum.<lb/>
Undoubtedly the Government would improve the road<lb/>
and the <del><unclear>of</unclear></del> small grounds in front of it.<lb/>
Mr. Moran, still living in Cuba, advises me <add>not to bother any more with<lb/>
procrastinating <add>and changing</add> Cuban politicians<lb/>
but</add> to get into<lb/>
direct touch with President <del><unclear>George</unclear></del> San Martin of Cuba<lb/>
which <del><unclear></unclear></del> he assures me I can readily do; Mr. Moran also<lb/>
believes that the strong support of the <del>Cuban</del> Havana Lions' Club<lb/>
can be readily obtained. I intend to correspond with<lb/>
these people in the immediate future but before doing so<lb/>
would like to be a little more sure of what American<lb/>
support I can expect so that I may not approach the<lb/>
Cubans &ldquo;empty-handed.&rdquo; Mr. Moran has been<lb/>
a most faithful and efficient &ldquo;agent&rdquo; for me in all<lb/>
my Cuban dealings. I can count on him <del><unclear>with</unclear></del> completely<lb/>
for continued guidance and help. In his opinion<lb/>
&ldquo;It is not at all unlikely that the Cuban government<lb/>
would declare the site a national monument, at<lb/>
the same time allowing you free rein to build the<lb/>
memorial according to your own plans.&rdquo;</p>
<p>If <del><unclear>wether one</unclear></del> the plans <add>are kept</add> modest perhaps $25,000-$30,000 would be<lb/>
sufficient; $20,000-$25,000 for the museum, $1,000 (nominal?) for the land<lb/>
$1,500 for restoration of the shack<lb/>
$2,500 for 2 small stone and concrete markers<lb/>
with bronze tablets at the site of<lb/>
Bldg 2 &amp; at the &ldquo;false camp-site&rdquo;<lb/>
where Lazear died &amp; the others were<lb/>
cared for (one has already been placed<lb/>
on the wall of the Finca San Jose).</p>
<p><del><unclear>Possible</unclear></del></p>
<p><del><unclear>Possible Contributions</unclear></del></p>
<p>I did not have in mind a pretentious memorial. But if<lb/>
the American or the Cuban Government or the Cuban medical profession could be<lb/>
interested in a material way, the cost of a more elaborate<lb/>
memorial might be shared. However, I deem it wise to<lb/>
start modestly &amp; expect little or no Cuban <hi>financial</hi> help.</p>
<p><del><unclear>Pasil</unclear></del></p>
<p>I have been led to understand that if or when the memorial<lb/>
is erected it will be made an official Cuban affair, with<lb/>
over<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f04117019"/>
the Cuban President on hand. It would of course be most<lb/>
appropriate to have <add>also</add> representatives of the American Government<lb/>
and of the Cuban &amp; American medical professions <add>and societies; also</add> close relatives<lb/>
of those memorialized. <del><unclear>other interest</unclear></del> The immediate relatives<lb/>
of Dr Reed and Lazear know fully of this plan &amp; <del>are</del> have been<lb/>
most helpful &amp; interested.</p>
<p>Colonel Siler</p>
<p>Sternberg book<lb/>
<unclear>Ag</unclear> p 216<lb/>
<unclear>S Y p 24 - 56</unclear></p>
<pb n="12" id="f04117020"/>
<p>(10</p>
<p><hi>Possible Contributors</hi></p>
<p>What I now say is entirely unofficial but I have been led to believe that<lb/>
the Mayo Clinic &amp; Foundation <del><unclear>with</unclear></del> may contribute materially; the matter will be<lb/>
presented officially to them very soon. (Insert from below) (The Mayo Foundation has certain Spanish-American ties: quite a few Cuban<lb/>
&amp; Latin American patients come to the clinic; we have certain Fellows<lb/>
from those countries; Doctor <add>Charles</add> Mayo also received the Finlay medal and<lb/>
other Cuban honors some years ago.)</p>
<p>I do hope that the Rockefeller Foundation (or a member of the Rockefeller<lb/>
family) may join the Mayo Foundation in this enterprise. <del><unclear>No doubt</unclear></del> This would be particu-<lb/>
larly appropriate because of the long interest of the<lb/>
Rockefeller <del><unclear>this</unclear></del> Foundation in the yellow fever researches. I have no <unclear>entre'</unclear> to<lb/>
the Foundation but have met Dr Sawyer, the former Director and<lb/>
could contact him.</p>
<p>Reed <del><unclear>is still</unclear></del> will always be a hero to the U S. Public<lb/>
Health association; perhaps their help could be obtained.</p>
<p>The <del><unclear>va</unclear></del> alumni associations of the various <add>American</add> medical<lb/>
schools and hospitals related to Finlay, Reed, <add>Carroll</add>, Lazear, and<lb/>
Agramonte might help; they <hi>all</hi> graduated from American <add>medical</add> schools.</p>
<p>The Rojas family is wealthy &amp; might desire to contribute<lb/>
something to the memorialization of their own homestead.</p>
<p>If it could be done in a proper manner certain<lb/>
pharmaceutical houses with Spanish-American interests<lb/>
might contribute.</p>
<p><hi>Present Financial Assets</hi></p>
<p>Only $1,000<hi rend="superscript">00</hi> contributed by Mrs. Hench, <add>as a &ldquo;little starter&rdquo;;</add> deposited in a<lb/>
&ldquo;Camp Lazear Memorial Fund.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Conclusion</hi>: I would be grateful for whatever suggestions and<lb/>
advice the <del><unclear>search of the Walter Reed</unclear></del> Board members<lb/>
of the Walter Reed Memorial Association may give me.<lb/>
<del>I hope that the project</del> I believe that the project<lb/>
outlined is in harmony with the spirit &amp; purposes<lb/>
of this association.</p>
<p>Respectfully submitted,<lb/>
Philip S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
Mayo Clinic</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
