<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04119002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Interview with Lawrence Reed and Blossom Reed, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 21, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04119002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-11-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>20 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-11-21">November 21, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04119002</idno>
<title>Interview with Lawrence Reed and Blossom Reed, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 21, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench questions Walter Reed's children about their father.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-11-21">
<head>Interview with Lawrence Reed and Blossom Reed, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 21, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04119002"/>
<p>INTERVIEW WITH GENERAL W. LAWRENCE REED AND MRS. BLOSSOM REED AT<lb/>
2810 - 36th PLACE, WASHINGTON, D. C., NOVEMBER 21, 1946,<lb/>
BY DR. P. S. HENCH.</p>
<p>Note: In this manuscript, for the sake of brevity, the questions will be designated<lb/>
as &ldquo;Q&rdquo; and the answers differentiated by &ldquo;L.R.&rdquo; for General Reed and &ldquo;B.R.&rdquo; for Mrs.<lb/>
Blossom Reed.)</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p># 1. Q. Please give us the story of how you entered the Army. Why weren't<lb/>
you in the Medical Corps and tell us the interesting story of how your name got<lb/>
mixed up with someone else's. Also give us the interview with your father when<lb/>
you told him you wanted to enter the Army.</p>
<p>L.R.: When the Spanish American War broke out, I was working for a coal<lb/>
firm, John P. Agnew &amp; Co. in Washington. Mr. Park Agnew, one of the members of the<lb/>
firm, asked me if I would like to become a Second Lieutenant in the new Army that<lb/>
was being raised. That was in early May, 1898. Two or three days later, Mr. Agnew<lb/>
gave me a letter addressed to the Secretary of War, signed by President McKinley,<lb/>
which said, &ldquo;If any young man is to be examined with the view of his being commissioned,<lb/>
I direct that Walter Lawrence Reed be one of them.&rdquo; I took this letter to the War<lb/>
Department and filed it with the Secretary. Subsequently, the newspaper stated that<lb/>
the list had gotten beyond control and that it would be necessary for each applicant<lb/>
to have a red line under his name in order to secure the designation for examination.<lb/>
This Mr. Agnew did by getting a second letter from the President, reiterating that<lb/>
I was to be examined. About the 12th or 13th of June, the list came out and my name<lb/>
was not on the list of men to go to Fortress Monroe to take the examination. Where-<lb/>
upon, I went to the War Department and found that an elderly clerk admitted a mistake<lb/>
had been made but it was too late to make any correction as the notification had<lb/>
already gone to the other W. L. Reed. Another young fellow who was 24 (I was then<lb/>
20 1/2) met me in front of the War and Navy Bldg. and told me that he, too, had failed<lb/>
to get on the list and what was I going to do? I said I was going down to Washington<lb/>
Barracks and enlist. He said, &ldquo;Wait until I go home and ask Mamma what I should do!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I went to Washington Barracks and tried to enlist, but the recruit-<lb/>
ing officer refused to enlist me without my father's consent because I was under age.<lb/>
My father's office then was in the old Army Medical Museum Building, at the corner<lb/>
of 7th and B Sts. N.W. I went up to my father's office and told him I wanted his<lb/>
written permission to enlist and he asked me why. I told him I wanted to get a<lb/>
commission. He said to me, &ldquo;Young man, before I give my consent, I want to ask you<lb/>
a question. Do you think that if the President of the United States would accord<lb/>
you the unusual privilege to permit you to select three officers to be on your<lb/>
board, could you find three officers who would pass you?&rdquo; I saw the necessity of<lb/>
saying &ldquo;Yes&rdquo;, which I did and he gave me his permission.</p>
<p>I was enlisted on the 17th of June, 1898. My father insisted that<lb/>
he select my Battery Commander, and I was assigned to Battery C of Second Artillery,<lb/>
Fort Warren, Boston, Mass., under Captain Alex D. Schenck, an old friend of my<lb/>
father's. We went to Havana, Cuba, in November, 1898, where we took over the city<lb/>
of Havana on the 1st of January, 1899. I was designated for examination which I took<lb/>
the 1st of June, 1900 and was commissioned a Second Lieutenant on the 25th of July,<lb/>
1900, and assigned to the Tenth Infantry as Second Lieutenant, at Cienfuegus, Cuba.</p></item>
<item><p>#1b. Why weren't you in the Medical Corps?</p>
<p>L.R. Frankly, with the exception of mathematics and allied sciences, I was<lb/>
not an apt student (in languages, literature, history, etc.). When I was in high<lb/>
school, my father asked me on more than one occasion if I had the slightest desire to<lb/>
go to Johns Hopkins University and study medicine. I always replied that I would prefer<lb/>
to prepare for The Boston Tech and become a mechanical engineer. Unfortunately, my<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04119003"/>
Reed interview<lb/>
2.<lb/>
athletic activities interfered considerably with my last year's work in high school<lb/>
(Western High School at Georgetown). On a Spring day in early May, 1895, my father<lb/>
was seated on the front steps of our house on Q Street in Georgetown, and as I<lb/>
approached the house, he said to me, &ldquo;My son, where are you doing your studying now?&rdquo;<lb/>
I said, &ldquo;Why, I am doing most of it at the school.&rdquo; He said, &ldquo;When did you last see<lb/>
your trigonometry?&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;I don't know--not so long ago.&rdquo; Whereupon he pulled<lb/>
several books from behind him and proceeded to tell me that our colored man had been<lb/>
cleaning up the hedge and had found the trigonometry and several other books in it.<lb/>
He then said that if this was the way I was going to do at school, he didn't feel he<lb/>
could afford to send me either to Johns Hopkins or The Boston Tech. I was considerably<lb/>
chagrined.</p>
<p>I was offered a job with the coal firm of John P. Agnew &amp; Co. by Mr.<lb/>
Greenleaf. He asked a crowd of boys if any of us wanted to go to work and we asked<lb/>
him, &ldquo;Doing what?&rdquo; He said, &ldquo;Weighing coal down on the wharves on the canal.&rdquo; They<lb/>
were receiving shipments of coal from Cumberland on the canal, unloading the boats and<lb/>
sending the coal to New England. He said the job required one to be there at daybreak<lb/>
and stay until sunset, boss about 45 colored men, make out the manifest for the ship<lb/>
that was going up to New England and settle for the coal that was being brought in.<lb/>
We asked him what the job paid, and he said, &ldquo;Two dollars and a half a week!&rdquo; I took<lb/>
the job and stayed with him until I enlisted (3 years).</p>
<p>But to get back to why I didn't become a doctor--even aside from my<lb/>
poor scholastic records, I never had a desire to be a doctor. I would have preferred<lb/>
to become a mechanical or construction engineer.</p></item>
<item><p>#1c. Q. Did you finish Western High School?</p>
<p>L.R.: No, I quit before the school term was completed.</p></item>
<item><p>#1d. Q. Your education was a matter of instruction in the Army, wasn't it?</p>
<p>L.R.: Yes.</p></item>
<item><p>#2. Q. Tell me about your career and arrival in Cuba, particularly in relation<lb/>
to the time your father was there on the various occasions. Your father went there<lb/>
twice in 1899 and 1900.</p>
<p>L.R. The Second Artillery, the Tenth Infantry and the Eighth Infantry of<lb/>
regular Army formed the first brigade and were sent to Cuba in November, 1898, to take<lb/>
over the city of Havana from the Spaniards on the first of January, 1899. Gen. Lee<lb/>
was in command of a large National Guard Corps that also came to Cuba early in 1899 and<lb/>
were quartered around Quemados and Camp Columbia, which was outside of Havana about six<lb/>
or eight miles as I recall it. I was a Sergeant in C Battery when we landed and shortly<lb/>
afterward was made Acting First Sergeant of the Battery, due to the illness of the First<lb/>
Sergeant, who was sent back to the States, and old soldier, entirely too old to be on<lb/>
foreign service. In March, 1899, I was selected with twenty-two other non-commissioned<lb/>
officers of the Second Artillery to go to Fort McHenry, Maryland, and form the nucleus<lb/>
for two new batteries of the Second Artillery. I became First Sergeant of Battery N<lb/>
in March, 1899. We went back to Havana in October of that year. We were stationed<lb/>
for 4 or 5 months at Morro Castle and later went over to a post called Santa Clara<lb/>
Battery. I went to Camp Columbia the first of June, 1900 to take my examination for a<lb/>
commission and I had known that my father was at a little camp somewhere near Camp<lb/>
Columbia, conducting the mosquito experiments. Back in those days it was unheard of for<lb/>
soldiers to associate with officers and it was most embarrassing for me to go to my<lb/>
father's camp and have a meal with him because of the presence of other officers, but<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04119004"/>
Reed interview<lb/>
3.<lb/>
I did so on two occasions (the summer of 1900). At that time I was still a First Sergeant.<lb/>
I don't recall having seen my father until June, 1900. It is perfectly possible that<lb/>
father did go to Cuba in 1899 while I was at Fort McHenry, from March until September,<lb/>
1899. My father may have also been in Cuba earlier in 1900 but if so I didn't see him<lb/>
until I visited him in June, 1900.</p></item>
<item><p>#2b Q. You were saying you were invited to a couple of meals with your father<lb/>
at Camp. Did you say it was embarrassing for your father?</p>
<p>L.R. I don't think it was embarrassing to him but it was to me, because in<lb/>
those days soldiers didn't associate with officers.</p></item>
<item><p>#2c. Q. General, do you have any additional comments about your relationship<lb/>
with your father during these visits? Was he very busy or did he have time to talk to<lb/>
you at length?</p>
<p>L.R. No. I visited him on two different Sundays in June and July, 1900, and<lb/>
was there just a short time before the meal hour and left very shortly after the meal<lb/>
was over.</p></item>
<item><p>#2d. Q. Where were you stationed?</p>
<p>L.R. Santa Clara Battery. When I went to Cuba the first time, in November,<lb/>
1898, I was stationed at Vedado, just out of Havana on the ocean front.</p></item>
<item><p>#2e. Q. You were at Santa Clara Battery when your father came to Cuba?</p>
<p>L.R. In 1900, yes, and when I went out to see him.</p></item>
<item><p>#2f. Q. Did he tell you anything about his work?</p>
<p>L.R. My impression at the time was that he and several other doctors, whose<lb/>
names I knew at the time--Lazear, Carroll and Agramonte--were on a board studying the<lb/>
causes of yellow fever and that is all I know about it.</p></item>
<item><p>#2g. Q. He didn't discuss it with you particularly?</p>
<p>L.R. Not at all. I just knew that was the work they were doing.</p></item>
<item><p>#2h. Q. At that time, in June and July, 1900, when you visited your father,<lb/>
they were doing the early experiments which were unsuccessful. Therefore, your father<lb/>
had nothing very exciting to tell you about it, and I assume from what you have said<lb/>
that he told you practically nothing.</p>
<p>L.R. That is correct, because the first indication I ever had that his work<lb/>
was successful was when he wrote the letter to Truby, who was then stationed at the<lb/>
same post as I was--in Cienfuegus. Truby read me the letter in which he said they had<lb/>
had successful results and to give his love to me.</p></item>
<item><p>#2i. Q. And you had no letters from your father during any of this time?</p>
<p>L.R. None that had any bearing on his work.</p></item>
<item><p>#3. Q. What did you know of your father's work later on in that summer and<lb/>
fall when their work became successful?</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04119005"/>
<p>Reed interview</p>
<p>4.</p>
<p>L.R. Strange as it may seem, I was so intent on making good as a Second<lb/>
Lieutenant during my service in Cuba, I have no recollection of knowing anything about<lb/>
my father's professional activities or achievements during those months. I left Cuba<lb/>
in February, 1901 and went to Fort Robinson, Nebraska. During the spring and summer<lb/>
of 1901 I had five different stations--short periods at each place. I was married in<lb/>
<hi>the fall of 1901</hi> and went to the Philippines in January, 1902. I don't think that I<lb/>
knew at the time my father died, in November, 1902, anything other than that his work<lb/>
had been successful and that he had discovered that the mosquito was responsible for<lb/>
the transmission of yellow fever.</p></item>
<item><p>#3b. Q. When were you made a Second Lieutenant?</p>
<p>L.R. I became a Second Lieutenant on the 25th of July, 1900. I went from<lb/>
Santa Clara Battery, Havana to the camp at Cienfuegus (Rowell Barracks). I joined them<lb/>
the 8th of August, 1900, and I was there until February, 1901. In other words, I was<lb/>
there during the entire time that my father did his work in Havana.</p></item>
<item><p>#3c. Q. General, would you give us that little humorous story that you told<lb/>
me before?</p>
<p>L.R. On one occasion, at a meeting of the American Medical Association in<lb/>
Baltimore, several doctors thought it would be a good thing to get a lot of information<lb/>
from me concerning my father's work. I told them I was awfully sorry, that when my<lb/>
father was doing his work in Cuba, I was only about 20 years old, was First Sergeant<lb/>
of a 214 man battery of artillery and at the time, I thought my work was far more<lb/>
important than anything he might possibly be doing!</p>
<p>A young fellow, under 21, with less than a year's service, responsible<lb/>
as a First Sergeant to the Captain for some 214 men has something to do and little time<lb/>
to be wondering what other people are doing. It isn't that I wouldn't have been inter-<lb/>
ested if I had had the opportunity, but my work started at the crack of dawn and was<lb/>
never through. For that reason, I didn't have time to know what my father was doing.</p></item>
<item><p>#3d. Q. When Lt. Truby received that letter from your father, did he give you<lb/>
an inkling as to how successful your father's work was or did you still not appreciate<lb/>
the significance of it?</p>
<p>L.R. Truby had discussed with me what father was doing in Cuba. He had been<lb/>
stationed at Camp Columbia and was very much interested because he was a doctor and knew<lb/>
what was going on. When he got this letter telling of the success of certain experiments,<lb/>
I realized, just as he did, that the success of the thing was going to be advantageous<lb/>
to the medical profession. It was quite an achievement. But again, although I realized<lb/>
that the success was quite an achievement, I was struggling to become a Second Lieuten-<lb/>
ant and I didn't have much time to reflect on anything else.</p></item>
<item><p>#3e. Q. During the time you were in Cuba, you received no letter from your<lb/>
father which contained information about this work?</p>
<p>L.R. The letters I received from my father were entirely personal and had<lb/>
no comments or statements concerning what he was doing. As a matter of fact, those<lb/>
letters were all of advice to me on what I'd better be doing!</p></item>
<item><p>#3f. Q. In other words, although he was writing to your mother and Miss Blossom<lb/>
about some of the details of his experiments, during that fall and the early part of<lb/>
1901, he did not write you any such letters as you remember it?</p>
<pb n="5" id="f04119006"/>
<p>Reed interview</p>
<p>5.</p>
<p>L.R. If he did, they didn't stick. If I had any letters, they were all<lb/>
destroyed. I am fairly certain that father never went into a discussion with me of<lb/>
what he was doing. I don't mind saying that my father was much concerned about my<lb/>
success as a young officer. He realized that I had not graduated from a high school<lb/>
or college, and since I had my commission, he was most anxious for me to succeed as<lb/>
a young officer. My recollection is that his letters contained valuable advice to me<lb/>
on what to do and what not to do as an officer.</p></item>
<item><p>#3g. Q. Do you remember at the moment any pertinent advice he gave you which<lb/>
is interesting, showing his character, or is it all sort of a haze?</p>
<p>L.R. I think the tenor of his letters was that I had a hard row to weed,<lb/>
that I had attempted a career with a decided disadvantage on my side, because I hadn't<lb/>
done too well in school and that it was up to me to apply myself and not flunk in any<lb/>
more of my studies.</p></item>
<item><p>#3h. Q. You don't remember any advice of an anecdotal character?</p>
<p>L.R. No, I don't.</p></item>
<item><p>#4. Q. General, what do you know of Dr. Carroll and his relationship with<lb/>
your father, then and later? Was the relationship a rather personal one or was it<lb/>
a strictly professional relationship?</p>
<p>L.R. I know this much--that prior to the Spanish-American War, Carroll was<lb/>
a high-ranking non-commissioned officer in the medical department, on duty with father<lb/>
at the Army Medical Museum. I know that he was a very valuable man, that he did his<lb/>
work very conscientiously and very carefully, and with good results. He pleased my<lb/>
father very much. I think that because of the association which was purely professional,<lb/>
father asked that Carroll be commissioned and sent to him. That is my impression. I<lb/>
don't know that to be a fact.</p></item>
<item><p>#4b. Q. Carroll was therefore an assistant to your father and not what you<lb/>
call a protege of your father/</p>
<p>L.R. Purely an enlisted assistant. And that relationship continued even<lb/>
after he became an officer. It was one of professional relationship, not close per-<lb/>
sonal relationship. I think he admired Carroll for his work. I know on more than<lb/>
one occasion he spoke very highly of Carroll's efficient work.</p></item>
<item><p>#5. Q. What was your father's opinion, as you remember it, of Dr. Lazear?</p>
<p>L.R. I have no idea.</p>
<p>B.R. Father was very devoted to him and was crushed over his death.</p></item>
<item><p>#5b. Q. Did your father speak to you of Lazear's death?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p>
<p>B.R. That happened when he was in Washington, and Father was dreadfully<lb/>
grieved.</p></item>
<item><p>#5c. Q. Did your father speak to you about Lazear at any time later?</p>
<pb n="6" id="f04119007"/>
<p>Reed interview</p>
<p>6.</p>
<p>L.R. No. I never saw my father after the Summer of 1900.I talked to my<lb/>
father on the phone when I landed at Newport News and father was in Washington, in<lb/>
February, 1901, and asked him to send me his overcoat, because it was so cold and we<lb/>
came up in khaki. With the permission of my commanding officer, I wore the overcoat<lb/>
all the way to Nebraska in a blizzard. I never saw my father after I visited him at the<lb/>
camp in 1900.</p></item>
<item><p>#5d. You remember your father allowed to become current, after Lazear's death,<lb/>
the story that Lazear was bitten accidentally by the mosquito and it was believed that<lb/>
Lazear told that story in behalf of maintaining his insurance. Did your father ever<lb/>
mention that incident?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p></item>
<item><p>#5e. Q. Would you know enough about Lazear and his character to believe this story?</p>
<p>L.R. I don't know a thing about it.</p></item>
<item><p>#5f. Q. Did you ever meet Lazear?</p>
<p>L.R. Yes, when I had dinner with Father in June or July, 1900.</p></item>
<item><p>#6. Q. What was your father's opinion of Agramonte, as you remember?</p>
<p>L.R. I have no idea. In explanation of my above answers, you must remember<lb/>
that I saw my father twice in the Summer of 1900, in the presence of these men, and<lb/>
naturally he wouldn't say anything about them, and he didn't write about them.</p></item>
<item><p>#6b. Q. When did you realize that your father had become famous?</p>
<p>L.R. I didn't realize during my tour of the Philippines, from January, 1902<lb/>
until the late Fall of 1903, that father had done any more than to succeed in his experi-<lb/>
ments, and I didn't think that his work was of much more importance than his typhoid<lb/>
board was. I knew he had been on these two big boards and there had been some success<lb/>
in both cases.</p></item>
<item><p>#6c. Q. During your tour of service in the Philippines (1901) and before your<lb/>
father died in 1902, did he write you any letters which reflected on the yellow fever<lb/>
work?</p>
<p>L.R. No, because most of the letters he wrote were addressed to my wife and<lb/>
they were purely family letters.</p></item>
<item><p>#7. Q. When I was in Cuba in 1940 and 1941, I visited the Finca San Jose, where<lb/>
Camp Lazear was, and the owner of that estate, Senora Rojas, an elderly, wealthy Cuban<lb/>
woman, told me that she remembered three or four American officers used to visit this<lb/>
camp on their farm every day for supervision of the experiments. At first, she didn't<lb/>
remember your father's name, but she said the head medical officer, who seemed to be<lb/>
in charge of the medical work, used to stop and visit with her and her husband on<lb/>
the porch of their house, coming from the office. When I showed her the pictures of the<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04119008"/>
Reed interview<lb/>
7.<lb/>
three medical officers, she immediately recognized your father as the one about whom she<lb/>
was talking. She said that your father used to stop and talk and sit on the porch, and<lb/>
that on one occasion he looked over the estate and expressed his appreciation of the<lb/>
climate and beauty of Cuba and said he would like to come and retire in Cuba some time.<lb/>
Whereupon her husband said that if he meant that and wanted to come back to Havana later<lb/>
to live, he would give him a part of their estate for a home. Did you ever hear that<lb/>
story and did you ever hear your father express any desire to live in Cuba?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p></item>
<item><p>#7b. Q. He didn't ever mention it in his letters?</p>
<p>L.R. No, not that I recall.</p>
<p>B.R. When father came back from Cuba, he used to tell mother that he loved<lb/>
Cuba and that he was going to take mother and me down there sometime and travel around.</p></item>
<item><p>#7c. Q. Do you think he actually intended to make a home on this estate or do you<lb/>
think he was merely being polite and making polite conversation with the Rojas family?</p>
<p>B.R. I don't know, but he told me that he was going to take mother and me down<lb/>
to Cuba.</p></item>
<item><p>#7d. Q. When I mentioned that story to General Kean, he thought that your father<lb/>
was merely making polite passing conversation, as he already had a summer home at Blue<lb/>
Ridge Summitt.</p>
<p>L.R. That would be my impression--that he would like to go back to visit but<lb/>
not to go to Cuba to live.</p></item>
<item><p>#8. Q. General Reed, you know I told you that when your father died, he left cer-<lb/>
tain notes and papers about the experiments, in his office. Within twenty-four hours,<lb/>
those notes and papers were missing and it was presumed by Dr. Kean and others that Dr.<lb/>
Carroll had taken them, as was his probable right. Do you have any personal knowledge<lb/>
of them at all?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p>
<p>B.R. No.</p></item>
<item><p>#9. Q. Assuming that George Carroll, the son, has them, do you have any suggestions<lb/>
as to how we can persuade him to let us study them? You told me the last time I was here<lb/>
to see Mr. C. L. Reed. I did so and wrote Mr. Reed some weeks later but had no answer. I<lb/>
meant to see him this morning but couldn't find his address. Do you have any other<lb/>
suggestions as to how we might get these notes and papers?</p>
<p>L.R. Mr. Reed came out here in June of this year and brought me some tomato<lb/>
plants. He told me then that he was still working on this Carroll case. It was an un-<lb/>
usually difficult thing to do because Carroll was so difficult to approach. Reed's<lb/>
father-in-law was Master Sgt. Tracy. He died, three or four years ago. Tracy, when<lb/>
he was a young man, was a messenger or attendant at my father's office and was devoted<lb/>
to father. Carroll knows the relationship of Reed to Tracy and of Tracy to my father,<lb/>
and through that connection Reed is the only man who can ever do anything with Carroll.</p></item>
<pb n="8" id="f04119009"/>
<item>Reed interview</item>
<item>8.</item>
<item><p>#10. Q. You and your sister were most kind to let me be the repository of your<lb/>
father's letters and other data. Do you know of any other letters of your father's?</p>
<p>L.R. No, I do not know of any.</p>
<p><unclear>Seawide</unclear></p>
<p>B.R. I have a big long letter and a very amusing letter that father wrote to<lb/>
Aunt Ellen, father's oldest sister, telling a great many things about his trip to Cuba.<lb/>
I don't think there are any other yellow fever letters.</p></item>
<item><p>#11. Q. Would you kindly give us a brief word picture of your father's character<lb/>
and nature? I have been told that he was a mixture of dignified military and scientific<lb/>
aloofness to business associates plus affectionate sentimentalism to all his relatives<lb/>
and close friends. Is that a correct appraisal?</p>
<p>L.R. I think that is probably very accurate. My own boyhood impression was<lb/>
that my father was an unusually studious man, deeply interested in what he was doing.<lb/>
My impression of his mannerism as a professional man was gained through young men who<lb/>
were students under him, for instance Col. Philip Huntington, retired Colonel of the<lb/>
Medical Corps, has often told me that my father's attitude toward students was one of<lb/>
encouragement, forebearing and helpfulness but also one of exceeding dignity. Another<lb/>
young fellow who took the entrance examination for the Medical Corps in 1893 or 1894<lb/>
told me that on one occasion he was being orally examined, and that in certain subjects<lb/>
he was very hazy as to the correct answers, but that my father's attitude was so genial<lb/>
and encouraging, with his nods, etc. that he kept on talking to beat the band, when<lb/>
he didn't know any too much what he was talking about!</p>
<p>B.R. His young students loved him so very much that when he left, one of them<lb/>
said he would have liked to kiss him goodbye.</p>
<p>L.R. As to his social life, my father was not only a splendid story teller<lb/>
but he was an exceedingly good listener and chuckful of humor. On the other hand, when<lb/>
I was not &ldquo;hitting the ball&rdquo;, he had a little way of making me realize that I wasn't<lb/>
worth wasting much more time over.</p>
<p>B.R. Father used to tell me one thing that used to impress me so. He used to<lb/>
tell me that it didn't make any difference who came to my door, that I was a lady, and<lb/>
to treat them as such. He said, &ldquo;Little daughter, remember this all your life. Pick<lb/>
out the good, leave the bad alone and you will always be so much happier as you go<lb/>
through life.&rdquo;</p>
<p>L.R. Well, he gave me a piece of advice which I have followed all my life and<lb/>
have passed it on to my children. &ldquo;When you get in a difficult situation, think the<lb/>
thing over carefully three times and then keep your mouth shut.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I will say that whatever I remember is only based on twenty years of<lb/>
knowledge of my father's life. No one that I ever heard of ever got unnecessarily<lb/>
familiar with my father. Phil Huntington said one of his characteristics that amused<lb/>
him very much was that when he was deeply in the midst of a very difficult discussion<lb/>
that as he reached the climax of this discussion, his voice always changed to a<lb/>
falsetto voice.</p></item>
<item>#12. Q. I have an article by Heilbron here, and I should like to give a copy to<lb/>
each of you.</item>
<item><p>#13. Q. The role of Surg. Gen. Sternberg in the conquest of yellow fever is not<lb/>
quite clear. We know that he had a lot to do with forming the yellow fever board. From<lb/>
what your father told Dr. Howard later and from other information, it would appear that<lb/>
Sternberg did not believe in the Finlay theory at the time the yellow fever board was<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f04119010"/>
Reed interview<lb/>
9.<lb/>
formed. Later, after your father's work was so successful, Sternberg actually wrote<lb/>
remarks which were published by Mrs. Sternberg in the biography of General Sternberg,<lb/>
to the effect that General Sternberg more or less indicated specifically to your<lb/>
father what he was supposed to do in his experiments. It would appear to me that<lb/>
Sternberg therefore &ldquo;climbed on the bandwagon&rdquo;. Do you have any comments about that?<lb/>
Do you remember any discussions of your father or your mother or others in regard to<lb/>
the role Sternberg had (1) in forming the board, and (2) in outlining the details of<lb/>
your father's work?</p>
<p>L.R. I would like to go back and say that Gen. Sternberg was persuaded by one<lb/>
of the Johns Hopkins doctors that some of the Army doctors should be studying bacter-<lb/>
iology and pathology (Welch said this) and that as a result, General Sternberg did<lb/>
succeed in getting the Secretary of War's approval to send one or two young doctors<lb/>
to Johns Hopkins. This story is entirely heresy <add>hearsay (B)</add> on my part but I will tell it just<lb/>
for whatever value it has. It is said that General Sternberg caused letters to be<lb/>
written to quite a few young doctors in the Army, inquiring whether they were interested<lb/>
in taking the course, and later on, in talking to the Secretary of War, General Stern-<lb/>
berg informed the Secretary that there were two young men who wanted to go to Johns<lb/>
Hopkins. He inquired where they were stationed. One was in California and one in<lb/>
St. Paul, and he said, &ldquo;Send the one in St. Paul--it won't cost so much to get him<lb/>
there!&rdquo; That was the opportunity for my father to go to Johns Hopkins.</p>
<p>But to answer your question--I have no knowledge at all of the discussion<lb/>
between father and Gen. Sternberg when he was sent to Cuba. I have always been impressed<lb/>
with this thought and where I got it from, I have no idea. Father had been interested<lb/>
in reports that had been written on the various outbreaks of yellow fever and I was told,<lb/>
perhaps by Truby (I say Truby because I discussed my father's work with Truby more than<lb/>
any other officer) that father had noticed that there was a distinct break in the epi-<lb/>
demic--certain lapses of time from one outbreak to another outbreak. I think he had<lb/>
noticed that before he went to Cuba and this may have had some little bearing on his<lb/>
wanting to work out Finlay's theory. As to what Sternberg's discussions were, I have<lb/>
no idea.</p></item>
<item><p>#13b. Q. Sternberg in a later discussion stated that he had given your father<lb/>
verbal and written instructions. I have never found the written instructions, and<lb/>
have never seen them published except in this biography of Sternberg. I have searched<lb/>
in the National Archives and elsewhere and have never found them, nor have they ever<lb/>
been seen by Generals Kean and Truby. Did you ever see them? (I since found them - P S. H)</p>
<p>L.R. No, but it would be perfectly easy for General Sternberg or any other man<lb/>
in administrative authority to say that he had given written instructions, when he was<lb/>
referring to written orders that father unquestionably received, directing him to pro-<lb/>
ceed to Havana for a certain purpose.</p></item>
<item><p>#13c. Q. Do you have any further knowledge of how the board was formed? Was it<lb/>
initiated by your father, as Howard wrote, or do you think that Sternberg instigated<lb/>
the first move?</p>
<p>L.R. I can only answer what my impressions are and I can't tell you where I<lb/>
got them. I certainly didn't make it out of whole cloth. My impression was that--<lb/>
but let me go back and say that my father was ordered out of Washington to the Phil-<lb/>
ippines because he had been in Washington a certain length of time and it was time<lb/>
to move on, and while he was preparing for his departure to the Philippines, to study<lb/>
tropical diseases, as I understood it, an epidemic broke out in the First Infantry,<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f04119011"/>
Reed interview<lb/>
10.<lb/>
in Pinar del Rio Province, Cuba and father's orders for the Philippines were revoked<lb/>
and he was ordered to Cuba to investigate what was wrong with the First Infantry.<lb/>
Subsequent to the completion of that work, I understood that he was to either go back<lb/>
to Cuba or remain in Cuba as the head of a committee to study yellow fever. Now I<lb/>
have this distinct impression: that he asked that Carroll be commissioned a reserve<lb/>
officer and sent to him. I have the impression that he knew Lazear when he was study-<lb/>
ing. I have the impression that Lazear was then a reserve doctor in Cuba but that<lb/>
he asked for Lazear. (It would appear that Welch recommended Lazear to your father<lb/>
and that your father didn't actually know Lazear and didn't meet him until he met<lb/>
him in Cuba.--Dr. Hench) I thought that he asked for him, maybe at Welch's suggestion<lb/>

but I didn't know that. I don't know how he got Agramonte. (Dr. Hench: Agramonte<lb/>
had already been in Cuba and had done some work on yellow fever. It was known to<lb/>
your father and the Surgeon General that he was there and had done that work.)</p>
<p>I had the feeling that my father was designated to do this job and had<lb/>
a great deal to do with selecting the men who were to work with him.</p></item>
<item><p>#13d. Q. Do you think the idea of forming a yellow fever board began with your<lb/>
father or did it begin with Sternberg and was agreeable to your father?</p>
<p>L.R. Well, of course father had done quite a little work in pathology and<lb/>
bacteriology at the Army Medical School, was teaching bacteriology and pathology at<lb/>
Columbia, which is now George Washington University, and I think he was manifestly<lb/>
one of the few Army doctors who was capable of doing this type of work and was se-<lb/>
lected by The Surgeon General for the yellow fever work in Cuba after he finished<lb/>
his work with the First Infantry in Cuba.</p></item>
<item><p>#13e. Q. In the fall of 1899?</p>
<p>L.R. Just about. I am not sure but that General Wood, who was commanding<lb/>
general at Havana, and a very close friend of my father's (associated with him in<lb/>
Washington before the Spanish-American War) may have had something to do with my<lb/>
father's selection. I don't know.</p></item>
<item><p>#13f. Q. Do you think that the yellow fever board was formed essentially at<lb/>
the request of your father or was it formed by Sternberg, with your father as the<lb/>
logical man to head it?</p>
<p>L.R. I don't know the facts.</p>
<p>B.R. I think it was General Sternberg's idea and selection. When father<lb/>
came back from Cuba and went in to see General Sternberg, he said to him, &ldquo;Reed, you<lb/>
are a lucky dog. You have accomplished what I have had in the back of my mind for<lb/>
years.&rdquo; I am absolutely sure of this. I have heard my mother repeat this many<lb/>
times.</p>
<p>L.R. What I have to say is purely to show the friendly relationship between<lb/>
Gen. Wood and my father. When I went to Cuba in the fall of 1898, Gen. Brooks was<lb/>
in command in Havana, and shortly afterwards--I don't know how soon--Gen. Wood took<lb/>
over command as a brigadier general. Very shortly after Gen. Wood assumed command,<lb/>
I was ordered by my regimental sergeant-major to report to Gen. Wood. I hadn't the<lb/>
faintest idea why I was to report, but I did. I was ushered into Gen. Wood's office<lb/>
and this is the conversation that transpired between us. &ldquo;Lawrence, I sent for you<lb/>
to see how you are getting along.&rdquo; &ldquo;Very well, Sir.&rdquo; &ldquo;If there is anything I can<lb/>
ever do for you, don't hesitate to come to me.&rdquo; &ldquo;General, I appreciate that.&rdquo;</p></item>
<pb n="11" id="f04119012"/>
<item>Reed interview</item>
<item>11.</item>
<item><p>#13g. Q. What year and month was that?</p>
<p>L.R. That was when I was at Vedado, which would be between November, 1898<lb/>
and March, 1899. I am simply stating that to show that it was the act of a friend<lb/>
of my father's.</p></item>
<item><p>#13h. Q. General Reed, can you tell me for how long before going to Cuba on the<lb/>
yellow fever board your father had been interested in yellow fever, and particularly<lb/>
in the Finlay mosquito theory?</p>
<p>L.R. I have no idea.</p></item>
<item><p>#13i. Q. Do you have any knowledge of when he became interested in the reports<lb/>
of Henry Carter?</p>
<p>L.R. He was a Public Health man, wasn't he? My knowledge of that is indirect<lb/>
and I think it is from Truby. My impression that I gained from a conversation with<lb/>
Truby (if it was Truby) is that father was deeply interested, as I said before, in the<lb/>
fact that these yellow fever epidemics, from Philadelphia to New Orleans, always had a<lb/>
break, from one outbreak to another--that there was a space of time between the out-<lb/>
breaks. That was before the Spanish-American War.</p></item>
<item><p>#13j. Q. You don't know whether your father was interested in it before or after<lb/>
the yellow fever board was formed?</p>
<p>L.R. Other than this interest he had displayed in these outbreaks, I don't<lb/>
know a thing.</p></item>
<item><p>#14. Q. Do you remember that Kissinger and Moran told me that the &ldquo;I salute you&rdquo;<lb/>
incident didn't actually happen? Do you have any comments on that? Would it have<lb/>
been in character for your father to have done such a thing?</p>
<p>L.R. I am surprised to find it didn't happen because it was so typical of<lb/>
him to have done just such a thing. I am inclined to believe that he did do it and<lb/>
those men didn't take it in.</p></item>
<item><p>#14b. Q. Would he have used a formal expression such as that?</p>
<p>L.R. He would have said, &ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you.&rdquo;</p>
<p>B.R. He had the most equisite manners and lovely charm.</p>
<p>L.R. The more humble the men, the more polite he was apt to be. Father<lb/>
wasn't talking to two soldiers as privates. He was talking to two individuals whose<lb/>
spirit he admired, and he said, &ldquo;I salute you.&rdquo; Knowing soldiers as I do and having<lb/>
been for thirty years on duty as an officer, I know that a colonel or a major can say<lb/>
something to a soldier and the soldier is so befuddled that he doesn't know what<lb/>
happened. He is overawed by the occasion and the rank so much that he doesn't take<lb/>
it in at that time. I really believed that the incident happened.</p></item>
<item><p>#15. Q. There is a little discrepancy as to just when Kissinger and Moran<lb/>
volunteered. One version said that Kissinger volunteered first, one that Moran<lb/>
volunteered first, and another that they volunteered together.</p>
<p>L.R. I have no personal knowledge, but again I want to say that an incident<lb/>
like that among enlisted men can easily be confused. They could have volunteered at<lb/>
different times but it is much more apt that they volunteered together because it was<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f04119013"/>
Reed interview<lb/>
12.<lb/>
on that occasion he said, &ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you.&rdquo; I have no other information.</p></item>
<item><p>#16. Q. Where were you when your father died?</p>
<p>L.R. I was at Catobata on the Island of Mindanopi, P.I. I received a wire<lb/>
saying, &ldquo;Your father died today,&rdquo; signed by the Surgeon General.</p>
<p>B.R. When I said I thought it was so dreadful that they didn't mention any<lb/>
details in their wire to my brother, I was told by one of the high-ranking Army<lb/>
officers that it saved money.</p>
<p>L.R. As a matter of fact, the original telegram or cablegram that was sent<lb/>
was delivered to First Lt. William L. Reed, First Infantry, Samar by mistake. Reed<lb/>
knew that the telegram was not for him and he sent a courier across the Island of<lb/>
Samar to the next port, Camp Catbalogan, where the message was sent by boat to me at<lb/>
Catobata. I received it ten days after its arrival in Manila. I received it about on<lb/>
my birthday, December 4. It was addressed to &ldquo;First Lt. W.L. Reed.&rdquo; It was two months<lb/>
before I got any details of how father died and that was a letter from an officer in<lb/>
the Office of the Surgeon General, who told me that father had been taken ill, was<lb/>
operated on by Dr. Borden and died in the hospital at Washington Barracks.</p>
<p>B.R. It was the first case of appendicitis Borden had ever lost. He had<lb/>
operated on many cases and this one was the first he had ever lost.</p></item>
<item><p>#16b. Q. When did you come back from the Philippines?</p>
<p>L.R. I left the Philippines and arrived in San Francisco either in September<lb/>
or October, 1903.</p></item>
<item><p>#17. Q. In a letter that Mrs. Blossom wrote to General Kean in August, 1945,<lb/>
it was stated that certain letters of your father's had been given to &ldquo;friends and<lb/>
libraries&rdquo; by your mother and by (I think) Mrs. Blossom. What friends and libraries?<lb/>
There are quite a number of missing letters.</p>
<p>B.R. It was some small college, it seems to me. I couldn't tell you to save<lb/>
my soul.</p>
<p>L.R. I don't know a thing about them.</p></item>
<item><p>#17b. There are no more than about ten or so missing. Are there no more letters<lb/>
in the family?</p>
<p>B.R. None on yellow fever.</p></item>
<item><p>#18. Q. On a certain day your father went with some people to see Finlay and<lb/>
discuss his theory and receive mosquito eggs. There is a dispute as to who went with<lb/>
your father. Do you know anything about this?</p>
<p>L.R. I have no idea.</p></item>
<item><p>#19. Q. When I visited Mrs. Lazear a couple of years ago, she told me that she<lb/>
remembered sitting in her parlor in Camp Columbia, some months before the yellow fever<lb/>
board was formed, on the occasion of a visit of your father for one of those investigations.<lb/>
Your father was with Dr. Lazear in the living room. She wasn't paying much attention to<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f04119014"/>
Reed interview<lb/>
13.<lb/>
the conversation when suddenly Dr. Lazear turned to her and said, &ldquo;Mabel, I have<lb/>
another convert. Dr. Reed also believes in the mosquito theory.&rdquo; Mrs. Lazear repeated<lb/>
that story to me twice with minor variations in the wording and insisted that it was a<lb/>
positive recollection. The significance of that story is that Lazear and your father<lb/>
were both interested in the mosquito theory some months before the yellow fever board<lb/>
was formed. Whether Dr. Lazear believed in the theory more than your father, nobody can<lb/>
say, but the inference would be that Dr. Lazear thought he was more concerned with the<lb/>
theory than your father and that he had made a convert of your father. Do you have any<lb/>
knowledge about that story or about the situation?</p>
<p>L.R. Not at all. But I would like to say this: Lazear was a young man compared<lb/>
to my father. Father must have been nearly fifty and Lazear was a man possibly in his<lb/>
thirties. My reaction to that would be that in the course of their conversation, Lazear<lb/>
discovered that he had found another man interested in yellow fever, but I haven't the<lb/>
faintest idea that he &ldquo;converted&rdquo; my father to the idea of the Finlay theory. I think the<lb/>
significant point is that it shows they both were interested in the Finlay theory at that<lb/>
early date and I know that my father was the type of man who would listen to any young<lb/>
man and encourage him in his ideas. But I don't for a moment think that Lazear converted<lb/>
father to the Finlay theory.</p>
<p>B.R. Absolutely.</p></item>
<item><p>#20. Q. Did your father's commission become official posthumously?</p>
<p>L.R. This is again my recollection from what I have heard. I was told that<lb/>
the War Department recommended that my father be promoted from major to colonel as a<lb/>
token of their appreciation for his work; that when the committee that was to pass on<lb/>
the promotion (Congress has to approve these recommendations) was at work on them, my<lb/>
father was unconscious at Washington Barracks. Whether the committee ever approved it,<lb/>
I don't know but father was unconscious and could not have accepted it had it been approved.</p>
<p><unclear>Rumors</unclear></p>
<p>B.R. The rumors were flying that he was going to be made Surgeon General, and<lb/>
people were flocking around us asking about it. He was to have received the Nobel Prize<lb/>
the first of January, but it could only be given to the living.</p>
<p><unclear>!!!!</unclear><lb/>
?</p></item>
<item><p>#21. Q. Senate Document, page 20, paragraph 3 states that he was being considered<lb/>
for Assistant Surgeon General with a rank of Colonel. Do you know whether that appoint-<lb/>
ment also failed to be approved officially?</p>
<p>L.R. I only know that it was up. I don't know what the result was. I was<lb/>
told that the thing failed to transpire any further because he was unconscious.</p></item>
<item><p>#22. Q. Why did your father go after two medical degrees instead of just one?<lb/>
(U. of Va.; Bellevue Med. Coll.--see Sen. Doc. p. 36).</p>
<p>L.R. I can't answer that from any knowledge of facts.</p>
<p>B.R. I think he got one medical degree graduating from the U. of Va. and the<lb/>
second M.D. for internship at Bellevue Medical College.</p></item>
<item><p>#23. Q. Do you know of any written instructions from Sternberg? (S.D. page 56)</p>
<p>Answered above.</p></item>
<item><p>#24. Q. Was Major Reed studying the mosquito theory of yellow fever before going to<lb/>
Havana?</p>
<pb n="14" id="f04119015"/>
<p>Reed interview</p>
<p>14.</p>
<p>L.R. I don't know. (Probably answered above.) I assume from the way things<lb/>
developed that he was.</p></item>
<item><p>#25. Q. Who recommended Lazear to your father? How did he become a board member?</p>
<p>L.R. I feel certain that father consulted with someone at Johns Hopkins, prob-<lb/>
ably Welch. As a matter of fact, I recall that father wanted a man from Johns Hopkins<lb/>
and Welch recommended Lazear.</p></item>
<item><p>#26. Q. This is the photograph of your father that your mother and Mrs. Blossom<lb/>
gave me, showing your father on a boat, out of uniform, in a derby hat. Do you know<lb/>
about when it was taken?</p>
<p>L.R. This picture was taken when my father was on his way to Cuba to do work<lb/>
on the yellow fever board.</p></item>
<item><p>#26b. Q. This is a group photograph at Camp Lazear, showing Dr. Cooke and others,<lb/>
and the figure in the rear, second from the right was identified by Mrs. Blossom as your<lb/>
father.</p>
<p>Both General Reed and Mrs. Blossom Reed positively identified this as their<lb/>
father.</p>
<p>L.R. That's father alright.</p></item>
<item><p>#27. Q. Do you remember in what room in Washington Barracks your father died?</p>
<p>L.R. The building was a small building with only a few rooms in it.</p>
<p>B.R. I think it was the second floor. I went down to see him but he didn't<lb/>
let me stay in the room. He looked up and said, &ldquo;Little daughter.&rdquo;</p></item>
<item>#27a. Q. It was my idea to put a little tablet on the outside of the building or<lb/>
in the hall.</item>
<item><p>#28. Q. In what building in Havana was the Pan-American Congress held Feb. 5, 1901,<lb/>
where your father read his second paper on the yellow fever work?</p>
<p>L.R. I don't know. I was on the high seas, going from Cienfuegus to Newport News.</p></item>
<item><p>#29. Q. In December, 1900, a banquet was given for Finlay, with your father an<lb/>
honored guest. I think the banquet was primarily given for Finlay on the occasion of<lb/>
your father proving the Finlay theory. On that occasion Dr. Guiteras gave a speech.<lb/>
I have been unable to find a copy of that speech. Do you have or did you ever see a<lb/>
copy of that speech?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p>
<p>B.R. No.</p></item>
<item><p>#30. Q. There are two interesting anecdotes about the Stark boys in relation to<lb/>
your father. Do you know about them?</p>
<p>B.R. We have heard these stories and remember that they are essentially true.</p></item>
<item><p>#31. Q. From reading your father's letters, it would appear that your mother was<lb/>
quite worried at one time about the fact that your father was experimenting with humans.</p>
<p>B.R. She was so afraid he was going to get yellow fever himself.</p></item>
<pb n="15" id="f04119016"/>
<item>Reed interview</item>
<item>15.</item>
<item>#32. Already answered. (How close was the relationship of Major Reed and Carroll?</item>
<item><p>#33. Q. In the table that your father constructed (Table 3) indicating the people<lb/>
who were experimented upon first, the first several people are essentially unidentified.<lb/>
We know that Pinto and Lazear were among them. No one knows who any of the others were.<lb/>
Do you know who they were?</p>
<p>L.R. No. Here's a question you might ask Gen. Truby. I thought that Truby<lb/>
told me in Cienfuegus that there were quite a few Spaniards who came out to undergo the<lb/>
experiments. Whether they were some of the people or not, I don't know.</p></item>
<item><p>#34. Q. Did your father have any insurance?</p>
<p>L.R. I don't know whether he had any insurance or not.</p>
<p>B.R. My thought would be if he did, it was terribly little because I remember<lb/>
the statement he made on his death bed that he was leaving so little.</p></item>
<item><p>#35. Q. Do you believe that your father's yellow fever papers in his office at<lb/>
the time of his death would naturally have fallen to Carroll?</p>
<p>L.R. No. My answer would be that had I died when I was the Inspector General<lb/>
of the Army, whatever personal studies or reports of professional matter I was working<lb/>
on would certainly not become the property of any officer in my office. They should<lb/>
become the property of the Inspector General's Office. I think the papers of my father<lb/>
should have gone to the Surgeon General's Office.</p>
<p>This remark of mine about the disposition of my father's papers is not in-<lb/>
tended as a reflection on Carroll. Carroll, having worked with father, may have thought<lb/>
it was perfectly proper for him to take possession. Those papers were the official<lb/>
work of a person in the Army, appointed as the head of a commission and they should<lb/>
have gone to the Surgeon General's Office. You might be able to get a court injunction<lb/>
to turn those papers over to the Surgeon General. However, one must not forget that<lb/>
some of these letters that Carroll has may be letters which father wrote to his father<lb/>
and are rightly in Carroll's possession.</p></item>
<item><p>#36. Q. Do you have any knowledge of how Camp Lazear was chosen?</p>
<p>L.R. No. It was recognized, however, that the experiments on yellow fever were<lb/>
going to be more or less of a dangerous undertaking from the contagious standpoint. I<lb/>
care say it was chosen where it would be off from other things.</p>
<p>B.R. I don't know.</p></item>
<item><p>#37. Q. Is there any statue of your father in the city except in the S.G.O. and<lb/>
Walter Reed Hospital?</p>
<p>B.R. There may be one in the Smithsonian Institute. A woman came to see me<lb/>
about a year ago who was to make another bust of father. She wanted to get some first<lb/>
hand information from me. She wanted to know if he had any photographs.</p></item>
<item><p>#38. Q. Would you mind writing for me a letter, addressed either &ldquo;To whom it may<lb/>
concern&rdquo; or to the Surgeon General or to the curator of the National Archives, indicating<lb/>
your approval of my interest in your father's work?</p>
<p>L.R. Yes, I would be only too glad to.</p></item>
<pb n="16" id="f04119017"/>
<item>Reed interview</item>
<item>#16.</item>
<item><p>#39. Q. A medical officer at Pinar del Rio, Capt. Godfrey, made a serious<lb/>
mistake. Did you hear your father criticize Godfrey?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p></item>
<item><p>#40. Q. Kissinger is the authority for the story which is accepted by Sidney<lb/>
Howard that Lazear inoculated Private Dean (XY) while the latter was asleep, which<lb/>
was a rather improper act. Did you ever hear of the story?</p>
<p>L.R. I have never heard of it.</p></item>
<item><p>#41. Q. In 1902, when your father died, did you live at 1603 - 19th Street?</p>
<p>B.R. Yes. We lived on the first floor in the left or north side apartment<lb/>
when one faces the building and the Keans lived just above us on the right or south<lb/>
side. Father was taken from there to the hospital and after his death his body lay in<lb/>
that apartment. He was buried from St. Thomas Church.</p></item>
<item><p>#42. Q. When and where were you born?</p>
<p>L.R. Fort Apache, Arizona, December 4, 1877. Sister was born at Fort<lb/>
Omaha, Neb., July 12, 1883.</p></item>
<item><p>#43. Q. When did Major Reed first become interested in the mosquito theory of<lb/>
yellow fever?</p>
<p>L.R. Before the Spanish-American War.</p></item>
<item><p>#43b. Q. When was he first interested in the Finlay theory?</p>
<p>L.R. I don't know. (Answered above.)</p></item>
<item><p>#44. Q. As I understand it, your father's home at Blue Ridge Summit was up on<lb/>
a hill about a mile or so from the present home of your mother and sister.</p>
<p>L.R. That's right.</p></item>
<item><p>#44b. Q. Are there any photographs of the home as he knew it?</p>
<p>not <unclear>answered</unclear><lb/>
check again</p>
<p>B.R. First father built a bungalow which later was part of the enlarged house.<lb/>
It was twelve feet across. It was finished the year he died--in 1902.</p></item>
<item><p>#44c. Q. How much time did he spend there?</p>
<p>B.R. He used to spend all weekends and sometimes a few days at other times.<lb/>
We lived there each summer. He just adored it. This was roughly from June to the first<lb/>
of September each year from 1899 to 1902.</p></item>
<item><p>#44d. May I borrow the two photographs you have of the house at Blue Ridge Summit?</p>
<p>B.R. Yes, I will look up the photographs at home and send them. to you.<lb/>
Mother named the house &ldquo;Keewaydin&rdquo;.</p></item>
<pb n="17" id="f04119018"/>
<item>Reed interview</item>
<item>17.</item>
<item><p>#45. Q. Was the photo of Major Reed on deck taken enroute to Cuba for the yellow<lb/>
fever work?</p>
<p>B.R. Yes, I know that positively.</p></item>
<item><p>#46. Q. In the original order creating the board, were the words &ldquo;infectious<lb/>
diseases&rdquo; and &ldquo;yellow fever&rdquo; but when the order was published by the Adjutant General,<lb/>
the words &ldquo;yellow fever&rdquo; were left out. The assumption is that the words &ldquo;yellow fever&rdquo;<lb/>
were left out for two or three reasons: (1) not to offend the Cubans, (2) to prevent<lb/>
the home folks from worrying about their soldiers who were down there, and (3) to pre-<lb/>
vent your mother from worrying (see Reed's letter of July 8, 1900 to his wife).</p>
<p>L.R. Knowing the War Department as I do, an instruction for a board to study<lb/>
infectious diseases would include yellow fever and when the final draft was made, the<lb/>
expression &ldquo;yellow fever&rdquo; was cut out not for the reasons you say, but because there was<lb/>
no use to repeat the words &ldquo;yellow fever&rdquo; when &ldquo;infectious diseases&rdquo; would include that<lb/>
disease. Then, it gives the board more leeway. It is perfectly possible that General<lb/>
Sternberg may have said (personally to father), &ldquo;Reed, I want you to concentrate on<lb/>
yellow fever.&rdquo;</p></item>
<item><p>#46b. Q. In other words, you don't think there was anything behind the exclusion<lb/>
of the phrase &ldquo;especially yellow fever&rdquo;?</p>
<p>L.R. No, because I think yellow fever is a disease included in the term<lb/>
&ldquo;infectious diseases&rdquo;.</p></item>
<item><p>#47. Q. In one of your father's letters, dated July 13, 1900, he describes to<lb/>
your mother in detail the arrangement of his room in Columbia Barracks. Do you have<lb/>
any recollection of his room there?</p>
<p>L.R. All rooms look alike to soldiers but my recollection is that it was about<lb/>
10' or 12' x 6' x 7'. In it were two windows and a door--a window on the side, one on<lb/>
the back and a door in the front. In it were the usual bunk, a table and a couple of<lb/>
chairs. I didn't go into the study. When we went in his room, he and I were alone.<lb/>
When we went out on the porch, there would be other officers with us. I don't know what<lb/>
was in the study, as we didn't sit in the study.</p></item>
<item><p>#48. Q. Did you ever visit Camp Lazear?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p></item>
<item><p>#49. Q. How would your father have addressed Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte?</p>
<p>L. R. Well, they would have all called him &ldquo;Major Reed.&rdquo; No familiarities.<lb/>
My father was not a person to easily accept the privilege of calling a man by his first<lb/>
name. I would say that my father would have addressed all those men as &ldquo;Doctor&rdquo;. He<lb/>
was much opposed to doctors being called by their military rank. He much preferred &ldquo;Doctor&rdquo;.</p></item>
<item><p>#50. Q. In your father's letters, he obviously had a number of affectionate nick-<lb/>
names for the family. Do you know of any of them?</p>
<p>B.R. I know what mine were: Girlieblossom, Little <unclear>Daughter</unclear>, Little Joy. He<lb/>
sometimes called my mother Farmer Lady and my brother Darboy.</p></item>
<pb n="18" id="f04119019"/>
<item>Reed interview</item>
<item>18.</item>
<item><p>#50.b. Did your mother actually have gout?</p>
<p>B.R. Yes, she had it for about a year, in one toe and one finger, related to<lb/>
worry over my father being in Cuba. It was diagnosed by a naval doctor, Dr. Nash.</p></item>
<item><p>#51. Q. Did you keep a diary, General?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p>
<p>B.R. No.</p></item>
<item><p>#52. Was Mrs. Reed much worried about your father?</p>
<p>B.R. I should say she was. Father spoiled her almost to death. He was the<lb/>
biggest spoiler that ever lived.</p></item>
<item><p>#53. In your father's letter of Dec. 14, 1900 he wrote to his &ldquo;precious invalid&rdquo;.<lb/>
Why was this?</p>
<p>B.R. Because she was lying on her back, &ldquo;dying&rdquo; because he was in Cuba!</p></item>
<item><p>#54. A letter of your father's of Dec. 11, 1900 mentions that Guiteras was inter-<lb/>
viewed and thought that the Finlay theory was wild and improbable. Did you ever see that<lb/>
interview published?</p>
<p>L.R. No.</p></item>
<item><p>#55. A letter of Dec. 23, 1900 indicated that your mother called your father<lb/>
&ldquo;Mr. Mosquito&rdquo;.</p>
<p>B.R. Yes, but to others it was &ldquo;Dr. Reed&rdquo;. It was a common practice.</p></item>
<item><p>#56. Where is the interesting letter of Dec. 25 or 26 describing the Christmas<lb/>
party and the poem about the mosquito?</p>
<p>B.R. There are a few more letters at Blue Ridge. I will send them to you.</p></item>
<item>#57. Duplicate of #38 about letters.</item>
<item>#58. Already answered.</item>
<item>#59. Answered.</item>
<item><p>#60. Did you ever see the full discussion of your father's first paper?</p>
<p>L.R. No. I wasn't in the States at the time.</p></item>
<item><p>#61. Were you in Havana when Guiteras did his work concerning your father's<lb/>
work--in 1901?</p>
<p>L.R. No. I left Cienfuegus in February.</p></item>
<item><p>#62. Will you give me the address of Mr. C. <unclear>L.</unclear> Reed?</p>
<p>L.R. Mr. C.L. Reed, Potomac Electric Power Co., 11th and H St., Washington, D.C.</p></item>
<pb n="19" id="f04119020"/>
<item>Reed interview</item>
<item>19.</item>
<item><p>#63. Q. What type of a memorial would you be in favor of, after Miss Blossom passes<lb/>
away?</p>
<p>L.R. In my father's letters to my mother when he was courting her, he was<lb/>
forever stressing his desire to alleviate the suffering of mankind and I think it would<lb/>
be most appropriate if, after my mother and sister die, the money be used in connection<lb/>
with scientific research at the University of Virginia where he graduated.</p>
<p>B.R. My first choice would be a place to treat children--if there were money<lb/>
enough, a hospital, or a free ward for invalid or sick children.</p>
<p>L.R. I have always had two thoughts: (1) to turn it over as a fund that can<lb/>
be used for research at the University of Virginia or any other place, but the former<lb/>
would be very appropriate because it is his Alma Mater; (2) almost on Blossom's lines but<lb/>
a little different. There are a lot of aged Army people who have to go to Walter Reed<lb/>
and who cannot afford the nurses they have to have. If the fund could be used to<lb/>
alleviate the financial stress and strain of these old people so that the nursing service<lb/>
could be given through the Walter Reed Foundation Fund, I think it would be very appro-<lb/>
priate.</p></item>
<item><p>#64. Anecdotes about your father.</p>
<p>B.R. On father's first trip, when he sailed for Havana, he was very much<lb/>
worried about being seasick and some friend told him to take a certain medicine (bromide)<lb/>
and he probably would be all right. So he promptly went to his stateroom, took the<lb/>
prescription and went to bed. He woke up the next morning and thought it had worked<lb/>
very well. He then looked out a porthole, recognized familiar scenery and found the<lb/>
boat had not sailed! They sailed in an hour or two and he just about passed out from<lb/>
seasickness!</p>
<p>When he came home on an Army hospital ship, Major Arthur was asked, &ldquo;How<lb/>
many sick men do you have?&rdquo; The answer was, &ldquo;I have many sick ones but Major Reed is the<lb/>
sickest!&rdquo; Father was just a passenger.</p>
<p>Father loved animals. We had a Christmas tree for the cats and we would<lb/>
dance around the Christmas tree, holding the cats' paws.</p></item>
<item><p>#65. Q. When you were in Cuba during the yellow fever of 1900 did you note much<lb/>
fear or concern among the soldiers and their families?</p>
<p>L.R. When I took my examinations I was quartered with part of the Second<lb/>
Cavalry. Was out there thirty days taking examinations. During the first ten days, at<lb/>
least three bandsmen in our barracks were taken out of the barracks on stretchers. When<lb/>
someone asked what was the matter, he was told &ldquo;Another yellow fever case.&rdquo; I remember<lb/>
saying to myself, "Well, son, if you worry about this, you will flunk this examination.<lb/>
If you get yellow fever, you won't have to worry about the exams.</p></item>
<item><p>#65b. Q. Was there much panic?</p>
<p>L.R. None.</p></item>
<item><p>#65c. Q. Quiet fear?</p>
<p>L.R. Soldier psychology is quite remarkable. If a soldier had any possible<lb/>
fear the last thing he would do would be to let anyone know it. There was never any<lb/>
panic. I don't think they gave a damn. We had a couple of pretty sick soldiers.<lb/>
Soldiers feel when their day comes, there is nothing to do about it.</p>
<pb n="20" id="f04119021"/>
<p>Reed interview</p>
<p>20.</p>
<p>#65c, continued:</p>
<p>L.R. Of all my acquaintances in this world, I know of no more dignified, more<lb/>
sincere, more approachable gentleman than my father was.</p>
<p>B.R. When father was ten, someone gave him a piece of tobacco and he was<lb/>
so sick from it he never used it again.</p>
<p>L.R. At Fort Robinson in the northwest corner of Nebraska, on the plains<lb/>
where the houses are eight or ten miles apart, one night a man came in and told father<lb/>
how sick his wife was. Father got permission to go out and have an orderly go with<lb/>
him, carrying supplies in saddle packs, for twelve miles.</p>
<p>B.R. He was forever called to see sick people.</p></item>
<item><p>#66. Q. When was your mother born?</p>
<p>L.R. January 14, 1856.</p></item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
