<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04112001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from J. N. Kenealy to Philip Showalter Hench, August 5, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kenealy, J. N.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04112001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-08-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hewitt, Richard M.</name>
<name type="person">Corrigan, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Canal Zone</name>
<name type="hospital">Ancon Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-08-05">August 5, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04112001</idno>
<title>Letter from J. N. Kenealy to Philip Showalter Hench, August 5, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kenealy informs Hench about several people who had some connection with yellow fever or the Canal Zone in the early 1900s. He writes that his parents lived across the street from the Ancon Hospital fever wards. His father was in charge of the hospital mess and commissaries, beginning in 1904.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1946-08-05">
<head>Letter from J. N. Kenealy to Philip Showalter Hench, August 5, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04112001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Box 1437, Balboa, C. Z.<lb/>
<date value="1946-08-05">August 5, 1946.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
102-110 Second, Ave. S. W.,<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your two articles on Yellow Fever Dr. Hewitt is sending<lb/>
me are not yet arrived but I have already promised them to Corrigan and<lb/>
he has promised me to send you a sketch of his experiences.</p>
<p>Joseph A. Corrigan, Sr. address; Gamboa, C. Z., had yellow<lb/>
fever in February '05, line of duty, a Sanitary Inspector fighting the<lb/>
mosquitoes at the time. He remained at that work through the Construc-<lb/>
tion period - went to the States and later in like capacity was with the<lb/>
United Fruit Co, covering all of their tropical holdings - he was associ-<lb/>
ated with Dr's Roland Connor, Deeks, etc. He has probably had a more<lb/>
varied experience in sanitation than any of the old group. At present<lb/>
is retired and living in Gamboa.</p>
<p>Miss Sarah De la Pena, stenographer in District Court, Ancon,<lb/>
is one of three or more children of Luis De la Pena (no middle initial).<lb/>
She says that to her knowledge her father never had yellow fever. That he<lb/>
was with Gorgas in Cuba, arrived here on that famous first boat, June 28,<lb/>
1904, carrying the first American Staff of Ancon Hospital and the Health<lb/>
Department. He later served with the American Red Cross in Europe, Serbia.<lb/>
Wound up as Chief Health Officer in Corinto, Nicarragua, where he was as-<lb/>
sasinated in February 1918: no pension allowed widow &ldquo;as not during working<lb/>
hours&rdquo;. She says she has much of her father's files, pictures, letters<lb/>
from Col. Gorgas and other correspondence. Will be only too <unclear>glad</unclear> to co-<lb/>
operate in any way possible to further your work. Her address: Box 1311,<lb/>
Ancon, C. Z.</p>
<p>Charles Stockleberg, died here about a year ago was another<lb/>
man who survived the fever here in Panama. Mrs. Frank B. Coyle, Balboa<lb/>
Heights, C. Z., as sister-in-law, could give you any information covering<lb/>
his case, if you are interested. At the time of infection he was a Fore-<lb/>
man of Plumbing for the Commission, lived to a ripe old age and acquired<lb/>
a wonderful reputation in the service of the Panaman Government, was honored<lb/>
with one of their highest decorations. In his case as in Corrigan's there<lb/>
were no after effects inpairing their efficiency or worth.</p>
<p>John Corrigan, Sr., brother of Joe, also a Sanitary Inspector<lb/>
continuosly thru his Canal employment until retirement was veteran of the<lb/>
Spanish American War, but as to whether Cuba or the Philippines or of pre-<lb/>
vious connections with Col. Gorgas, I do not know. Joe will probably in-<lb/>
clude him in his report to you as I asked him to specify as well as he<lb/>
could all associates, places etc., which might bring you a new angle -<lb/>
I've given up hopes of telling you people something new. In this connection,<lb/>
J. J. McGuigan, Ancon, C. Z., is married to some distant cousin of the Col-<lb/>
onels, ex-spanish war man and undoubtedly possesses a vast fund of knowledge<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04112002"/>
anecdotes, etc. on the Colonel and many of his official family. He re-<lb/>
tired as District Attorney for the Zone.</p>
<p>The old Ancon Hospital was far prettier than the grand scene<lb/>
it presents today. The French knew their landscaping and the wooden build-<lb/>
ings, set in narrow winding roads, to we &ldquo;Gringos&rdquo; was something knew.<lb/>
The old fever wards were located on the site now occupied by the Board of<lb/>
Health Laboratory, back in )('09 or '10, the wards were converted to the<lb/>
Eye &amp; Ear Clinic, Dr. Reeder, now in Panama Hospital, succeeded Lister,<lb/>
&ldquo;Pop&rdquo; Reeder is still going strong.</p>
<p>My parents occupied the small cottage across the street from the<lb/>
fever wards. When a big man was dying my mother would have to move out<lb/>
for the several hours involved - she used to go up and visit at the Nurses<lb/>
Quarters. Corrigan, Stockleberg were both small men, as I remember the<lb/>
strictly non-professional story was: &ldquo;a big man never stood a chance&rdquo;. The<lb/>
forced labor of a big man gasping for breath that only a good distance<lb/>
could shut out.</p>
<p>In mulling these things over the thought strikes me that Colonel<lb/>
Gorgas was most <unclear>happy</unclear> in his selection of that first boat load. They were<lb/>
a picked group that through former like experiences and contacts were able<lb/>
to roll along at a high degree of efficiency from the start. One instance,<lb/>
my father, was just retired from the Army as a Commissary <del><unclear></unclear></del> Sergeant,<lb/>
out of Puerto Rico: taking over the Hospital Mess and Commissaries, market-<lb/>
ing in Panama: he hadn't been away from like work over a period of six weeks.<lb/>
The thought struck me that if you could get the passenger list of that first<lb/>
boat load - it would be hard to picture a better grouping for the job ahead.</p>
<p>As a simple matter of giving you a couple of addresses * I appear<lb/>
to have taken more than words than was called for - I look forward with<lb/>
pleasure to reading your articles and it was nice of Dr. Hewitt to send<lb/>
them.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely</salute>
<signed>J. N. Kenealy</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
