<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04137124">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Draft of speech on Walter Reed at the University of Virginia, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 17, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04137124</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-11-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>27 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-11-17">November 17, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04137124</idno>
<title>Draft of speech on Walter Reed at the University of Virginia, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 17, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This is a draft of the speech on Reed given by Hench at the University of Virginia. The text includes [Hench's?] autograph notes and corrections.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1947-11-17">
<head>Draft of speech on Walter Reed at the University of Virginia, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 17, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04137124"/>
<opener>
35 copies - to be duplicated<lb/>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINN.<lb/>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
<dateline>
517 FOURTH ST., S. W.,<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINN.<lb/>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p><hi>Walter Reed and The Conquest of Yellow Fever.</hi></p>
<p>Talk <del><unclear>(</unclear></del> given at <add>The University of Virginia,</add> Charlottesville, <del><unclear>Vov</unclear></del> Nov. 17, 1947 <del><unclear>)</unclear></del></p>
<p>At the end of the Civil War, in the fall of 1865, a circuit-riding Meth-<lb/>
odist minister and his wife moved to Charlottesville so that their sons might im-<lb/>
prove their education. Their 14 year old boy first went to the Charlottesville<lb/>
Institute, a boys' day school <del><unclear>w</unclear></del>here. Then, just 80 years ago, in the fall of 1867,<lb/>
he tried to enter the Academic Department of this University. Although he was<lb/>
only 16 years old and under the required age, the faculty admitted <del>him</del><add>Walter Reed</add>, hoping<lb/>
for the best that he would make good. After one year in the undergraduate school<lb/>
<del>this boy</del>, Walter Reed, <hi>entered the medical school ( X )</hi> and promptly accomplished one<lb/>
of his first unusual feats. He completed the medical course in a single year, and<lb/>
on July 1, 1869, as the youngest man ever to earn a medical degree here, he received<lb/>
<hi>his diploma. ( X )</hi> (which I hold in my hand).</p>
<p>Had there been at that time a chapter of <add>The</add> Alpha Omega Alpha <add>Honorary <unclear>medical fraternity</unclear></add> here, Walter<lb/>
Reed would certainly have qualified for membership. <add>(of course he might not have been elected!)</add> At this later date you are<lb/>
honoring him by listening today to the story of &ldquo;Walter Reed and the Conquest of<lb/>
Yellow Fever.&rdquo; My story might <add>well</add> <del>have almost</del> be<del><unclear>en</unclear></del> entitled &ldquo;The University of Vir-<lb/>
ginia and the Conquest of Yellow Fever,&rdquo; because as we shall see, <del>two</del><add>three</add> other Univer-<lb/>
sity <add>of Virginia</add> men also played important roles in this drama.</p>
<p>At the close of the Spanish-American War thousands of American soldiers<lb/>
returned home to be received <hi>like conquering heroes ( X ).</hi> But others returned<lb/>
home <hi>not so gloriously ( X ).</hi> Some returned in <hi>hospital ships</hi>, <unclear>The</unclear> soldiers whose<lb/>
bodies had been weakened by fever. Some were in <hi>coffins ( X )</hi>, <unclear>The</unclear> soldiers who<lb/>
had met death at the hands of an enemy more powerful than any Spaniard. For dis-<lb/>
case, especially yellow fever, had killed more soldiers than had the bullets of<lb/>
the enemy. Day after day, strong young men became hot with fever and wracked with<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
<del>( X ) <unclear>slides</unclear></del><lb/>
X=slide<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04137125"/>
Hench - 2 - eej<lb/>
pain; then they <hi>turned yellow ( X ),</hi> suffered with the dreaded &ldquo;black vomit&rdquo; and<lb/>
died at the rate of as many as 200 a day.</p>
<p>&ldquo;We'll stop that,&rdquo; said the United States Government, and with its Army<lb/>
of Occupation it sent physicians whose duty it was to control yellow fever which<lb/>
had been endemic in Havana for more than 200 years. Among these physicians were<lb/>
Major Gorgas, who was responsible for the health of the soldiers and civilians in<lb/>
the city of Havana, and <hi>Major Jefferson R. Kean, ( X )</hi> a graduate of the Univer-<lb/>
sity of Virginia whose chief responsibility was the health of the American sol<del>d</del>-<lb/>
diers <hi>at Columbia Barracks ( X )</hi> on the outskirts of Havana in the little subur-<lb/>
ban town of Quemados de Marianao, near the famous bathing beach, La Playa.</p>
<p>Despite the vigorous sanitary methods which were instituted, yellow<lb/>
fever continued to spread, and in May and June, 1900, Major Kean, a worried man,<lb/>

compiled a tragic list of the names of soldiers and civilians, of fellow-officers<lb/>
and their wives, all living in the neighboring streets of Quemados and all vict-<lb/>
ims of yellow fever. The mortality rate among the officers on the headquarters--<lb/>
staff of Generals Wood and Lee was alarming. The clerks <hi>in General Wood's office<lb/>
( X )</hi> burned on their desks sulfur candles as a prophylactic measure, but the can-<lb/>
dies burned in vain, and in the officers' mess they drank a gruesome toast, &ldquo;Here's<lb/>
to the ones who have gone. Here's to the next one to go!&rdquo;</p>
<p>One of the earliest to go was Major Edmunds, a friend of Major Kean.<lb/>
Because General Lee had already lost so many officers and men he ordered all those<lb/>
not immediately in charge of the sick to stay away from the sick-rooms of those with<lb/>
yellow fever. Thus Major Kean could not visit Major Edmunds who lay sick unto death<lb/>
in the <hi>front room of this little house ( X )</hi>. But on the latest dawn that Major<lb/>
Edmunds was to see, Major Kean, torn between the conflicting obligations of obed-<lb/>
ience to his commanding officer and <add>of</add> loyalty to his dying friend, rose about 4 a. m.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04137126"/>
Hench - 3 - eej<lb/>
and went to this little porch where, technically not in the patient's room, he spent<lb/>
a last few minutes. During that short visit Major Kean was bitten by mosquitoes from<lb/>
the sick room but thought little of it. But a few days later on June 21 Major Kean<lb/>
suddenly developed yellow fever.</p>
<p>As if to ridicule the puny efforts of the army medical corps, the disease<lb/>
was now striking down the physicians themselves: Could nobody stop this evil thing?<lb/>
What was its cause anyhow? One of the commonest ideas was that the mysterious cause<lb/>
of yellow fever arose like an evil spirit, a <unclear>miasma</unclear> from the tropical swamps. An<lb/>
Italian physician, Sanarelli, insisted it was due to a special germ which he had dis-<lb/>
covered. But nobody really knew the cause, and when a person died of yellow fever<lb/>
his home was often purified by fire to destroy his presumably infected furniture,<lb/>
clothing and other personal belongings, called &ldquo;fomites.&rdquo; Thus hundreds of thou-<lb/>
sands of dollars worth of military and civilian equipment went up in smoke in an<lb/>
attempt to control the disease. But it was all in vain.</p>
<p>On June 25, the fourth day of Major Kean's illness, <hi>another army physician<lb/>
( X )</hi> arrived in Havana, rushed to the bedside of his friend, the major, and exempli-<lb/>
fied in him saw his first case of yellow fever. Later that day this man, Major Wal-<lb/>
ter Reed met with three others <hi>on the veranda ( X )</hi> of the officers' quarters at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks Post Hospital. The three others were Drs. <hi>James Carroll ( X ),<lb/>
Aristides Agramonte ( X )</hi> and <hi>Jesse W. Lazear ( X )</hi>, and the four men thus ended<lb/>
their first day's work as the members of the United States Army Special Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board.</p>
<p>They first attempted to find Sanarelli's germ in the bodies of those sick<lb/>
or dead of yellow fever, but this search soon ended in failure. Perhaps after all<lb/>
no germ was responsible for the disease. Why in Quemados had the disease progress-<lb/>
ed so erratically down the streets, striking <hi>first in one house ( X )</hi>, skipping the<lb/>
next few houses, then hopping <hi>around the corner ( X )</hi>, rather than crossing the af<del>f</del>-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04137127"/>
Hench - 4 - eej<lb/>
fected street? Another curious fact was noted when Reed, Agramonte and Lazear went<lb/>
to study an epidemic which broke out among the soldiers at Pinar del Rio. A sol-<lb/>
dier in <hi>a prison cell ( X )</hi> fell sick and died of yellow fever but his cell mates,<lb/>
exposed to the same food and atmosphere, remained well. Could something have en-<lb/>
tered between the bars of the open window, struck one man down and gone away?<lb/>
Could yellow fever be caused by a winged agent? Could <hi>Dr. Carlos Finlay</hi> be right<lb/>
after <hi>all? ( X )</hi>.</p>
<p>For nineteen years this kindly old Havana physician had been trying to<lb/>
convince his medical colleagues that yellow fever was caused by a common house<lb/>
mosquito. But nobody believed him, simply because, although he had inoculated ov-<lb/>
er 100 volunteers with mosquitoes, he hadn't produced a single case of the disease<lb/>
which other physicians regarded as unquestionably induced or experimental rather than<lb/>
probably spontaneous. The volunteers were not quarantined and those few who later<lb/>
developed yellow fever undoubtedly got it in the ordinary way.</p>
<p>When Reed, Agramonte and Lazear returned from Pinar del Rio the Board<lb/>
decided on August 1st to try to prove or disprove Finlay's theory once and for all.<lb/>
They <hi>visited Dr. Finlay ( X )</hi> who graciously gave all the help he could including<lb/>
a supply of mosquito larvae of the suspected species. Thereupon a momentous and<lb/>
heroic decision had to be made because no animal was then known to be susceptible<lb/>
to yellow fever. Human volunteers were required. Unwilling to ask others to do<lb/>
what they themselves would not do the Board decided to inoculate each other among<lb/>
the first. At this juncture Reed was unfortunately ordered to Washington to fin-<lb/>
ish an important medical report. <hi>Carroll and Agramonte ( X )</hi> continued respect-<lb/>
ively their bacteriologic and pathologic studies and it fell to <hi>Lazear's</hi> lot to<lb/>
begin the mosquito work. This was fortunate because he of all the Board was most<lb/>
sympathetic to the Finlay theory. Indeed for some time Lazear had been trying (so<lb/>
far unsuccessfully) to prove a relationship between mosquitoes and yellow fever.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04137128"/>
Hench -- 5 -- eej<lb/>
Thus on the very day the Army Board was officially named in Washington, Lazear in<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba, was catching mosquitoes in the room of a patient with yellow fever<lb/>
<hi>( X ), and (as shown from notes in his laboratory notebook</hi>) was examining their<lb/>
bodies for agents responsible for the disease. <hi>( X ) (<unclear>summary</unclear> of note)</hi></p>
<p><unclear>3 MD's</unclear></p>
<p>Lazear began to breed Finlay's mosquitoes in their <hi>little camp labora-<lb/>
tory ( X )</hi> and then tried to infect them by allowing them to bite yellow fever<lb/>
patients <hi>at Las Animas Hospital ( X ).</hi> Between August 11 and 25 these presumably<lb/>
infected mosquitoes were applied to nine American soldiers including Drs. Lazear<lb/>
and Pinto, but nothing happened. They all remained well.</p>
<p><hi>( X ) Two days later</hi>, on August 27, discouraged and doubting, Carroll<lb/>
permitted Lazear to inoculate him again. (<hi>Note the <del>three</del><add>four</add> U. of Va. men in Corn-<lb/>
well's painting</hi>). In a few days Carroll developed a severe and almost fatal att-<lb/>
ack of yellow fever. On the way from Carroll's bedside Lazear (without the know-<lb/>
ledge of his colleagues) inoculated a <hi>scoffing volunteer soldier ( X )</hi> who &ldquo;wasn't<lb/>
afraid of any little old <unclear>gnat</unclear>.&rdquo; When yellow fever hit him six days later this sol-<lb/>
dier became a very surprised hero whose widow later received his Congressional Med-<lb/>
al, and a <hi>memorial bridge</hi> <add><unclear>(X)</unclear></add> in Grand Rapids, Michigan <unclear>was named for him <del><unclear></unclear></del></unclear>.</p>
<p>Having accomplished two very successful inoculations Lazear wrote his<lb/>
<hi>wife ( X ) (September 8</hi>): &ldquo;I rather think I am on the track of the real germ. But<lb/>
nothing must be said as yet, not even a hint. I have not mentioned it to a soul.&rdquo;<lb/>
How right he was, was tragically proven by what happened ten days later, when he him-<lb/>
self developed the dreaded disease. During his illness Dr. Lazear told two visit-<lb/>
ors, Drs. Carroll and Gorgas, that a few days before, while feeding his mosquitoes<lb/>
on yellow fever patients <add>(in this room)</add> <hi>at Las Animas Hospital ( X )</hi> a stray mosquito had alight-<lb/>
ed <hi>on his hand ( X ).</hi> Lazear had allowed it to take its fill of his own blood.<lb/>
From the first he was very ill and died September 25, 1900, officially listed as<lb/>
a victim of &ldquo;accidental yellow fever&rdquo; but none the less a true martyr to science.<lb/>
( <hi>X - Telegram)</hi>. Such is the official version of this tragic incident. But I am<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f04137129"/>
Hench - 6 - eej<lb/>
about to tell you another version of the affair, one which was kept secret for<lb/>
forty years, and which was not even known to Dr. Lazear's widow until I was per-<lb/>
mitted to tell her of it in 1940 through the courtesy of those who revealed it to<lb/>
me: Walter Reed's colleagues, <unclear>Generals</unclear> Truby and Kean, and Dr. Agramonte's daugh-<lb/>
<del>gh</del>ter.</p>
<p>Reed hastened back to Havana (October 4) filled with mingled emotions.<lb/>
He was greatly depressed at Lazear's death, yet elated that success at last seem-<lb/>
ed at hand. But he was also confused. Why did the first nine inoculations fail<lb/>
and the next ones succeed? The second successful case seemed incontrovertible,<lb/>
having been quarantined at the otherwise fever-free Post Hospital the scoffing<lb/>
private (Private Dean -- &ldquo;case XY&rdquo;) had had no other conceivable source of in-<lb/>
fection than via the applied infected mosquito. But could one be sure that Carr-<lb/>
oll's disease had come from the experimental mosquito bite and not from some oth-<lb/>
er source to which he might have exposed himself while going about town? And how<lb/>
could Lazear's tragic case be used to prove anything unless somebody knew what kind<lb/>
of a mosquito had bitten him?</p>
<p>In the side pocket of the uniform blouse which Lazear had recently worn<lb/>
<hi>Lieutenant Truby, ( X )</hi> at that time commanding officer of the Columbia Barracks Post<lb/>
Hospital, had found a small notebook containing entries about Lazear's experiments.<lb/>
Reed eagerly studied these and other notes. Herein was the solution of the age-<lb/>
old mystery, a solution which became crystal clear to the brilliant mind of Walter<lb/>
Reed. Finlay's mosquito (the culex fasciatus or Aedes Aegypti) could indeed cause<lb/>
yellow fever but <hi>only under certain special conditions: ( X )</hi></p>
<p>(By carefully noting the relative timings of each step in the successful<lb/>
and unsuccessful experiments it became obvious that patients with yellow fever have<lb/>
the agent or virus of their disease circulating in their blood only the first three<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04137130"/>
Hench - 7 - eej<lb/>
days of their illness; later when they are sicker, even sick unto death, the agent<lb/>
has strangely disappeared from the blood. Therefore, a mosquito to become &ldquo;infect-<lb/>
ed&rdquo; must bite a yellow fever victim during these first three days. But even then<lb/>
that &ldquo;infected mosquito&rdquo; cannot transmit its deadly load or infect another person<lb/>
until the virus has had a chance to develop or &ldquo;ripen,&rdquo; within the mosquito's<lb/>
body for at least twelve days.)</p>
<p><del><unclear>talk<lb/>
firm<lb/>
slide</unclear></del><lb/>
<unclear>molade</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>omit</unclear><lb/>
in talk</p>
<p>All of the failures of Finlay and of the Board were thus explained:<lb/>
those volunteers who had <hi>not</hi> developed yellow fever had either been bitten by<lb/>
mosquitoes which had really never been infected (having bitten patients too late)<lb/>
or had been bitten by &ldquo;infected mosquitoes&rdquo; which were still temporarily harm-<lb/>
less because they had not been allowed to &ldquo;ripen&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Thus Lazear's little notebook was vitally useful in solving one mystery<lb/>
but it posed another mystery, for in it Reed found some incomplete entries which<lb/>
appeared to indicate that Lazear had secretly submitted himself to other experi-<lb/>
mental inoculations. Reed pondered long over these entries and then concluded<lb/>
that when Lazear was taken sick he must have worried lest his life insurance be-<lb/>
come forfeited if it became known that he had deliberately infected himself with<lb/>
a fatal disease. (Actually this explanation was incorrect; Mrs. Lazear told me<lb/>
Dr. Lazear left no life insurance.) But did he for some other reason at the last<lb/>
fateful hour withhold facts to protect his loved ones? Was this why he had told<lb/>
Gorgas and Carroll that he had been bitten by a stray mosquito at Las Animas? Reed<lb/>
believed that it was. Having produced two cases of yellow fever and knowing the<lb/>
danger, Lazear would surely never have allowed a mongrel mosquito to bite him and<lb/>
vitiate <add>or interrupt</add> his <del>otherwise meticulously controlled</del> experiments. Reed confided his sus-<lb/>
picions only to two or three colleagues and then decided to permit the official<lb/>
records to read that Lazear had become accidentally infected while in the per-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04137131"/>
Hench - 8 - eej<lb/>
formance of duty. Having made his quiet and heroic gesture Lazear had sought to<lb/>
carry his secret to a better world. Out of respect for the unspoken wishes of<lb/>
their friend, Lazear's colleagues have kept that secret all these years, Reed and<lb/>
others having carried it to their graves.</p>
<p>In so doing they eminently proved their loyalty to him. But it app-<lb/>
arently disturbed them to deprive Lazear of a greater fame and in the following<lb/>
<hi>unpublished remarks of Agramonte</hi> <add>X</add> I sense a wistful desire to rectify matters.<lb/>
At a Havana banquet in honor of Drs. Gorgas and Kean in June 1902 Agramonte's<lb/>
speech contained this tribute: &ldquo;The one of us who from the very inception of our<lb/>
work so strenuously believed in the mosquito theory in connection with the prop-<lb/>
ogation of yellow fever, the one of us who was best fitted by his training in the<lb/>
line of our investigation to successfully carry out the work, who in fact perform-<lb/>
ed the first successful inoculation unknown to his co-workers, Jesse W. Lazear, gave<lb/>
up his life in the pursuit of knowledge which shall immortalize his name. May he<lb/>
in the Regions of the Unknown find the glory that is his due which so unjustly has<lb/>
been witheld by man on earth.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Knowing that a skeptical world would demand more proof than that afford-<lb/>
<del>d</del>ed by these three successful but relatively uncontrolled inoculations, Reed now<lb/>
conceived, and with Carroll and Agramonte, executed a series of brilliant experiments<lb/>
which were to write the final chapter of this story. On the advice of Major Kean,<lb/>
Reed asked General Leonard Wood, Governor General of Cuba for money with which to<lb/>
<hi>set up an experimental camp ( X )</hi> and to pay what Americans and Spanish volun-<lb/>
teers might be secured. To the lasting credit of General Wood who had himself been<lb/>
a physician, he promptly granted Reed's request and threw behind Reed all the auth-<lb/>
ority of the governor's high office.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f04137132"/>
<p>Hench - 9 - eej</p>
<p>Yellow fever was to be given away free with premiums of $200.00 The<lb/>
victims could spend the money any way they wanted to -- if they survived; a rather<lb/>
<del>big</del><add>large</add> <hi>if,</hi> considering that the mortality rate of epidemic yellow fever was about 40<lb/>
per cent. But before any paid volunteers were secured two American soldiers, John<lb/>
R. <hi>Kissinger ( X )</hi> and <hi>John J. Moran ( X ),</hi> <del>the</del><add>(who</add> lat<del>t</del>er <add>was</add> a <hi><del>former</del> student at the</hi> Medical<lb/>
School of the <hi>University of Virginia</hi>) volunteered their services only on condition that they<lb/>
could do so without pay and in the interests of science. Legend has it that<lb/>
Major Reed, profoundly affected, rose and said, &ldquo;<hi>Gentlemen, I salute you.&rdquo; ( X ).</hi><lb/>
Both Kissinger and Moran told me that actually, the legend is not true, which<lb/>
Reed's widow and children were sorry to learn from me a few years ago. But as<lb/>
one writer said, &ldquo;If Reed didn't salute them, he should have!&rdquo; The world is still<lb/>
saluting them with many honors. ( <hi>X - X - X - X - X - X - X</hi>)</p>
<p>{Congressional medal<lb/>
{Walter Reed <unclear>Hosp</unclear><lb/>
{stamps<lb/>
{Finlay post-marks<lb/>
{Cornwell painting<lb/>
{Kissinger &amp; Moran at W &amp; J<lb/>
{Lazear memorial Bldg<lb/>
<unclear>omit</unclear></p>
<pb n="10" id="f04137133"/>
<p>Hench - 10 - eej</p>
<p>A specially guarded and quarantined experimental station named <hi>Camp<lb/>
Lazear</hi> was set up in a secluded spot a <hi>mile from Camp Columbia ( X )</hi>. There<lb/>
John <hi>Kissinger ( X )</hi> bared <hi>his arm in this manner ( X )</hi> for the bites of five<lb/>
infected mosquitoes, and promptly developed the first case of deliberately ac<del>c</del>-<lb/>
cepted and completely controlled experimental <hi>yellow fever in history ( X )</hi><unclear>.</unclear> <del><unclear>G</unclear></del><lb/>
of this Reed wrote, &ldquo;In my opinion this exhibition of moral courage has never been<lb/>
surpassed in the annals of the army of the United States.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>( X ) Then two small specially</hi> constructed wooden buildings were er-<lb/>
ected. The first was called Building Number One or the &ldquo;Infected Clothing and<lb/>
<hi>Bedding Building,&rdquo; ( X )</hi>. It comprised one room, 14 x 20 feet, had only two<lb/>
small windows and was heated by a stove to a tropical temperature. Three cots<lb/>
were set up and into this sweltering room were brought the soiled and foul-<lb/>
smelling bed clothes of yellow fever victims. Night after night <hi>Dr. Robert<lb/>
Cooke ( X )</hi>, <add>(U of Va Med Sch, 1897)</add> and other soldier-volunteers (Folk, Jernegan, Hanberry, Weather-<lb/>
walks, Hildebrand and England) hung these offensive clothes around the walls<lb/>
and on their beds, and then lay down to try to sleep on stinking pillows and<lb/>
sheets soiled with blood and vomitus. Stomachs rebelled, but spirits remained<lb/>
firm and not one of these volunteers developed yellow fever, simply because there<lb/>
were no mosquitoes in the room. Thus was exploded the notion that &ldquo;fomites&rdquo; car<del>r</del>-<lb/>
ried the disease.</p>
<p><hi>The second building ( X )</hi> of similar size (Building Number Two or the<lb/>
&ldquo;Infected Mosquito Building&rdquo;) was divided into two parts <hi>separated merely by</hi> a<lb/>
<hi>wire screen. ( X )</hi>. On <hi>a cot in one side of this room ( X )</hi>, John Moran, (<del>the later<lb/>
<unclear>ex-medical</unclear> student <unclear>from</unclear> this University</del>) exposed his body to the bites of fif-<lb/>
teen loaded mosquitoes let loose in the room. He was in the room only a little<lb/>
over an hour in all, but promptly developed yellow fever, while other volunteers<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f04137134"/>
Hench - 11 - eej<lb/>
who stayed long hours on the other side of the screen where there were no mos-<lb/>
quitoes remained well. (Peas <unclear>providing not</unclear>)</p>
<p>Moran took sick on Christmas day. His yellow fever was a wonderful<lb/>
Christmas gift to Walter Reed and to all the world. A few days later on New<lb/>
Year's Eve, Reed in a mood of ex<del>i</del><add>a</add>ltation and humble gratitude to God, wrote his<lb/>
family a <hi>much quoted letter which has become famous ( X )</hi>:</p>
<p>&ldquo;11:50 p. m. December 31st, 1900-- only 10 minutes of the old century<lb/>
remain. Here I have been sitting reading that most wonderful work -- La Roche<lb/>
on yellow fever, written in 1853. Forty-seven years later it has been permit-<lb/>
ted to me and my assistants to lift the impenetrable veil that has surrounded<lb/>
the causation of this most dreadful post of humanity and to put it on a rational<lb/>
and scientific basis. I thank God that this has been accomplished during the<lb/>
latter days of the old century.</p>
<p>-- The prayer that has been mine for twenty or more years, that I might<lb/>
be permitted in some way or sometime to do something to alleviate human suffering,<lb/>
has been answered.</p>
<p>12 midnight! -- Hark! There go the 24 buglers, all in concert, sound-<lb/>
ing &ldquo;Taps&rdquo; for the old year! How beautiful it floats on the midnight air ---.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(<hi>I have the original of this letter</hi> if you wish to see it)</p>
<p>In the bodies of twelve more American and Spanish volunteers (Benigno,<lb/>
Fernandez, Presedo, Martinez, Jernegan, Olson, Folk, Forbes, Andrus, West, Han-<lb/>
berry and Sonntag) yellow fever was produced at will, either through the medium<lb/>
of mosquito bites or by injections of infected blood or serum. Fortunately all<lb/>
these volunteers survived, thanks to the excellent care of Dr. Roger Post <del>a</del><add>A</add>mes (X).<lb/>
Their problem solved after just eight months of work, the Board disbanded Camp<lb/>
Lazear on March 1, 1901. Now armed with precious knowledge Gorgas within three<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f04137135"/>
Hench - 12 - eej<lb/>
months freed Havana of its age old scourge. Later, with this and other knowledge,<lb/>
he made safe the <hi>Isthmus of Panama ( X )</hi> for the passage of the commerce of the<lb/>
world.</p>
<p>Continue</p>
<pb n="13" id="f04137136"/>
<p>Hench - 13 - eej</p>
<p><hi>Rediscovery of the Lost Camp Lazear</hi></p>
<p>And what became of their battlefield, Camp Lazear? That is the last<lb/>
part of my story, a part which I think may interest, and perhaps amuse you.</p>
<p>In the spring of 1940 Mrs. Hench and I decided to visit Havana during a<lb/>
Florida vacation. I wanted to meet Johnny Moran (who had lived in Cuba for years),<lb/>
<hi>Dr. Agramonte's daughter ( X )</hi> and <hi>Dr. Finlay's son ( X )</hi>. Also I wanted to make<lb/>
&ldquo;a sentimental journey&rdquo; to see the remains of Camp Lazear, take a few photographs<lb/>
and then return home. But while pursuing this apparently simple objective, certain<lb/>
interesting complications arose.</p>
<p>Mr. Moran, smiling, genial and gracious, met me at the Hotel Nacional.<lb/>
We then started out, leaving Mrs. Hench on the hotel veranda. Poor girl, she had<lb/>
a long wait and during the next ten days, she scarcely saw us at all! <hi>( X ) Mr.<lb/>
Moran and I drove</hi> from the hotel along Calle 23 through Vedado, passed the old<lb/>
Colon Cemetery, crossed the Almendares River and soon reached Quemados and the<lb/>
site of old Camp Columbia, now the Ciudad Militar or chief army post of the dist-<lb/>
rict. <del>( X )</del> We visited briefly the fine new military hospital (officially named<lb/>
The Agramonte General Hospital) on the very site where the old Station Hospital<lb/>
PLAYA<lb/>
of Camp Columbia had stood 40 years before. Then we crossed the La Playa rail-<lb/>
road track just west of the hospital ( X ) at the little Carnino way - Station<lb/>
and turned northwest 200 or 300 yards along the track until we came to a small<lb/>
XX<lb/>
plot of ground enclosed by a low <hi>ornamental wooden fence ( X ).</hi> In the center of<lb/>
the plot <hi>was a tree <add>X</add></hi> and under the tree a <hi>large sign ( X )</hi> which proclaimed that<lb/>
&ldquo;On this spot was established El Campamento Lazear where were performed the stud-<lb/>
ies of the American commission which proved the theory of Finlay, concerning the<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever by a species of mosquitoes.&rdquo; <del>Mr. Moran hadn't seen<lb/>
the spot for 40 years until he had made, a few days before my arrival, a reconnais-<lb/>
ance tour to locate it for me.</del></p>
<pb n="14" id="f04137137"/>
<p>Hench - 14 - eej</p>
<p>For a few minutes we surveyed the historic spot while I took a few snap-<lb/>
shots. But even as I did so <hi>my thoughts were not so much on <add>X</add></hi> the little memorial-<lb/>
ized plot of ground in front of me as they were on the little single-track rail-<lb/>
road just about 70 feet behind me <del><unclear></unclear></del>. I couldn't get that railroad track out<lb/>
of my mind. Despite the identifying sign erected with all the authority of the<lb/>
Sanitary Department of the Cuban Government, I was vaguly uneasy. <hi>( X ) Here<lb/>
we were just across the railroad</hi> track from old Camp Columbia Station Hospital.<lb/>
Hadn't I read somewhere in Reed's papers that Camp Lazear was established about<lb/>
a mile from Camp Columbia? Of course, we were a mile or so from the eastern bor-<lb/>
der of the camp, but we were only a few yards from the western border. Surely,<lb/>
this was closer to Camp Columbia than I had expected <del>( X )</del>.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Where does this railroad spur lead to?&rdquo; I asked Mr. Moran, &ldquo;To La<lb/>
Playa, the famous bathing beach about a mile away,&rdquo; he replied. The La Playa<lb/>
railroad track! Surely Reed wouldn't have set up a camp for semi-secret exper-<lb/>
iments right beside a railroad track patronized by <del><unclear>bords</unclear></del><add>crowds</add> of <del>other</del> pleasure seek-<lb/>
ers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does the place look right to you, Mr. Moran? Does the lay of the<lb/>
land jibe with your recollections of Camp Lazear?&rdquo; Mr. Moran surveyed the scene<lb/>
again. &ldquo;I really can't say, Until a few days ago, I hadn't seen it for 40 years<lb/>
even though I've lived in Havana <del>for years</del><add>since 1928</add>. Of course it is all built up around<lb/>
here now. But the local <del>and governmental</del> authorities directed <del>us</del><add>me</add> here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I continued: &ldquo;Somehow it doesn't seem right to me. It doesn't sat-<lb/>
isfy my mental picture of the &lsquo;secluded spot about a mile from Camp Columbia&rsquo;,<lb/>
mentioned in the old army records.&rdquo; Our conversation was interrupted by the<lb/>
arrival of a pleasant but inquisitive young Cuban boy who wondered what we<lb/>
wanted and if he could help us. He identified himself as the employee of the<lb/>
real estate agent, Mr. Pogolotti, who was selling empty lots in this district.<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f04137138"/>
Hench - 15 - eej<lb/>
&ldquo;Where is Senor Pogolotti?&rdquo; I inquired. &ldquo;Oh, he doesn't stay around here. He has<lb/>
an office downtown and leaves me in charge.&rdquo; I had a sudden inspiration. If this<lb/>
was Camp Lazear wouldn't it be nice if I could obtain a sizeable limb of the tree<lb/>
and have it cut up into paper-weights, pen holders etc., to take back home to some<lb/>
historically minded medical friends? Mr. Moran translated the request of the crazy<lb/>
souvenir-hunting American and assured the boy that I would be glad to pay for the<lb/>
wood and the trouble. The boy's reply was unusual and pleasing, &ldquo;Why not? Limbs<lb/>
break off and fall down all the time. You might as well out one off. It's all<lb/>
right with me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>But then I got cautious. It was all right with him but would it be all<lb/>
right with his boss, the owner? The boy assured me, &ldquo;He won't care. Anyhow he<lb/>
doesn't own this one little piece of land anymore. The government <del>bought</del><add>owns</add> it <del>from<lb/>
him</del> and put up this sign.&rdquo; So that was it, nobody cared because it was govern-<lb/>
ment property. As much as I wanted my souvenirs and desired to obtain them without<lb/>
a lot of governmental red-tape, I didn't want to get in<add>to</add> trouble with the Cuban<lb/>
Government, so I whispered to Johnny Moran, &ldquo;I'd certainly like a limb right here<lb/>
and now. But we had better call the thing off and make a date to see Mr. Pogolotti<lb/>
tomorrow&rdquo;.</p>
<p>That night in the Hotel Nacional, I burned the midnight oil, Pouring<lb/>
over Reed's old papers which I had brought along, I found several brief des-<lb/>
criptions of Camp Lazear. But the precise location of the camp wasn't mentioned<lb/>
in a single one of the many medical papers of Reed or his colleagues. <hi>But in a<lb/>
reprint of a popular article <add>X</add></hi> written as late as Dec. 1915 by Dr. Argramonte<lb/>
and published in The Scientific Monthly, I found what I was looking for <del><unclear></unclear></del>.<lb/>
In this obscure article Agramonte had fortunately written: &ldquo;I was therefore fav-<lb/>
orably impressed with the seclusion offered by a spot situated a short distance<lb/>
from the main road, in a farm, named San Jose, belonging to my friend Dr. Ignacio<lb/>
Rojas of Havana. Major Reed decided upon this place after looking at many others<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f04137139"/>
Hench - 16 - eej<lb/>
in the neighborhood, so that on November 20th we inaugurated our camp which we<lb/>
named Camp Lazear ---&rdquo;.</p>
<p>&ldquo;A secluded spot on the farm of Dr. Ignacio Rojas&rdquo;----there was the<lb/>
place! No mention of any nearby railroad track to La Playa.</p>
<p><hi>X The next morning, at &ldquo;Campamento Lazear&rdquo; Mr.</hi> Moran and I met our young<lb/>
acquaintance of the previous day and his boss, Mr. Luis Pogolotti, a charming,<lb/>
American-educated, English-speaking Cuban. I decided to go after that tree limb<lb/>
before discussing the authenticity of the site; &ldquo;a bird in hand&rdquo;, you know. We<lb/>
explained the sincerity of our interest and the reason for my unusual request and<lb/>
Mr. Pogolotti insisted that nobody, including the Cuban Government, would mind if<lb/>
I chopped off a reasonably small limb, so he dispatched his young man for the<lb/>
necessary implements. While the boy was gone, I asked Mr. Pogolotti about the<lb/>
&ldquo;pedigree&rdquo; of that particular piece of land. We were indeed most fortunate in<lb/>
having run across him, because he and his brother had been in the real estate<lb/>
business in that neighborhood for years. He told me that he and his brother had<lb/>
owned that section known as Reparto Zamora, a real estate subdivision named after<lb/>
Father Zamora, a previous owner of the land. Mr. Pogolotti was still selling lots<lb/>
but had <del>sold</del><add>transferred</add> this particular plot to the Cuban Government. Before that, it was<lb/>
owned by so and so, earlier by so and so. &ldquo;How far back in the ownership of the<lb/>
land have you taken me?&rdquo; I interrupted. He laughed, &ldquo;Oh, about 100 years.&rdquo; &ldquo;But,<lb/>
how do you know all this so well?&rdquo; Again Mr. Pogolotti laughed, &ldquo;Because of a<lb/>
dispute over property rights. The government insisted they owned a small strip of<lb/>
land on this side of the railroad. My brother and I insisted the western boundary<lb/>
of Camp Columbia ended at the railroad tracks. There was a legal dispute and I<lb/>
traced most carefully all the old deeds back a couple of hundred years&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I hesitated while framing the $64.00 question, &ldquo;When, Mr. Pogolotti, was<lb/>
this owned by Dr. Ignacio Rojas? You failed to mention his name.&rdquo; Johnny Moran<lb/>
watched him sharply. &ldquo;Dr. Rojas? He never owned this place,&rdquo; Mr. Pogolotti answered<lb/>
with a ring of authority; &ldquo;Then this is <hi>not</hi> Camp Lazear,&rdquo; <add>I said</add> &ldquo;Why not?&rdquo; <del>What</del><lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f04137140"/>
Hench - 17 - eej<lb/>
What makes you say that?" Mr. Pogolotti looked disturbed. Hadn't he <del>sold</del><add>transferred</add> it to<lb/>
the government as a memorial -- etc? Who was this American, this total stranger<lb/>
to Quemados who was shattering tradition and history? Mr. Pogolotti continued:<lb/>
&ldquo;The government has evidence identifying this as Camp Lazear.&rdquo; &ldquo;I don't care,&rdquo; said I.<lb/>
&ldquo;If Dr. Rojas never owned this place, it isn't Camp Lazear. Furthermore, its<lb/>
character doesn't fit the old official descriptions of Reed, <del>either</del>. If you'll<lb/>
come back to the hotel, I would like to show you the basis for my doubts&rdquo;.</p>
<p>By now, Mr. Moran was also quite convinced that &ldquo;Campamento Lazear&rdquo;<lb/>
represented a case of mistaken identity. He urged Mr. Pogolotti to look at my<lb/>
evidence. <del>and went over completely once again with him the site's pedigree.</del> Mr.<lb/>
Pogolotti began to weaken, &ldquo;All I can say is that for 30 or 35 years, to my per-<lb/>
sonal knowledge this spot has been locally known as the place where American sol-<lb/>
diers had experimental yellow fever in 1900.&rdquo; <del>and a few years ago, some Cuban doc-<lb/>
tors gave the Minister of Health, photographic proof that it was Camp Lazear. Their<lb/>
old photograph showed one of the little yellow fever shacks right under this tree.<lb/>
The shack blew down in the tornado of 1926, but the tree remained as a marker for<lb/>
Camp Lazear".</del></p>
<p>By now the boy had returned and was whacking away at a lower branch using<lb/>
a machete, <del><unclear></unclear></del>. Seeing he was getting nowhere, I suggested he get a saw. This<lb/>
seemed to him to be a novel and puzzling idea. Being a reactionary he wasn't con-<lb/>
vinced of its usefulness and anyhow he didn't have one. After wasting more minutes,<lb/>
impatiently I gave him some money and sent him to buy a saw. The saw purchased, the<lb/>
limb was quickly felled and cut into short lengths which we tenderly gathered and<lb/>
transported to the garage of the local branch of the Sun Oil Company of which Mr.<lb/>
Moran had been president. So far as I know, the wood is still there.</p>
<p>We left with Mr. Pogolotti's promise to help us find the Rojas farm of<lb/>
1900, cheered at his parting remark that the <del>rare</del><add>name</add> &ldquo;Rojas farm&rdquo; sounded vaguely fam-<lb/>
iliar, but he couldn't place it at the moment.</p>
<pb n="18" id="f04137141"/>
<p>Hench - 18 - eej</p>
<p>The next day, Mr. Moran and I visited the Finlay Institute, a sort of<lb/>
Cuban Rockefeller Foundation, and met some of the old-time physicians. During<lb/>
our conversation, I mentioned briefly my vague doubts as to whether Camp Lazear<lb/>
had been located properly, but those who had any opinion were sure that it had<lb/>
been properly identified. <hi><add>X</add> In 1926 Dr. Ignacio Alvare, while</hi> interning at the<lb/>
new Columbia Military Hospital, was told by neighbors that <hi>a little house</hi> fac-<lb/>
ing the adjacent La Playa railroad track was all that remained of Camp Lazear.<lb/>
He took a photograph of it and gave it to Dr. Recio. On the basis of this lo-<lb/>
cal tradition, the government had memorialized the site. <del><unclear></unclear></del>. The little<lb/>
wooden house, presumably one of Reed's experimental buildings, was no longer<lb/>
there, but the tree remained. Mr. Moran and I obtained copies of this photo-<lb/>
graph and went back to the tree. It was the <hi>same tree all right ( X )</hi> as we<lb/>
could see from the arrangement of the roots and branches, but if the little<lb/>
building had been one of Reed's experimental buildings, it had to face either<lb/>
south or north as described by Reed in official papers. With <del>the</del><add>a</add> compass, Mr.<lb/>
Moran and I carefully noted that the little building in the Alvare-Recio photo-<lb/>
graph had faced east before its destruction; furthermore, the general contour<lb/>
of the building was not the shape of Reed's buildings as shown in <hi>old Army photo-<lb/>
graphs. ( X ); furthermore</hi>, if this little shack (at &ldquo;Campamento Lazear&rdquo;) were<lb/>
authentic, it meant that a railroad would have passed right between Reed's Build-<lb/>
ing<add>s</add> Number One and Two. However, the old Army photograph <del><unclear></unclear></del> showed no rail-<lb/>
road and its presence would have been most incongruous. <hi>( X ) In reconstructing</hi><lb/>
the various tents and little buildings of Camp Lazear as shown in various Army<lb/>
photographs, let me show you again the location of Buildings Number One and Two.<lb/>
Obviously the Alvare-Recio photograph had been misinterpreted and this could not<lb/>
have been either one of the Reed experimental buildings.</p>
<pb n="19" id="f04137142"/>
<p>Hench - 19 - eej</p>
<p> The next day Mr. Pogolotti thrilled us by telling us that he had actually<lb/>
<hi>located the San Jose farm. <add>(X)</add></hi> He laughed and said, &ldquo;I knew that name was vaguely fam-<lb/>
iliar; as a matter of fact, my brother and I bought part of it from the Rojas fam-<lb/>
ily a number of years ago and out it up into lots, but the main part remains.&rdquo; <del>and<lb/>
we will go there tomorrow."</del> We visited the Finca San Jose on the Calzada Real<lb/>
(&ldquo;Royal Street&rdquo;) of Quemados, and there on the <hi>old</hi> entrance gate was <del>the sign</del><add>a name plate-</add>,<lb/>
&ldquo;San Jose.&rdquo; <del><unclear></unclear></del>. <hi><add>X</add> Inside the grounds was</hi> a lovely old home surrounded by tall<lb/>
palms. We found an elderly niece of Dr. Rojas and after being introduced I<lb/>
eagerly asked her how long she had lived there. When she said she had lived<lb/>
there many years, I asked her if she had any recollection <add>which</add> concern<del>ing</del><add>ed</add> American<lb/>
soldiers and yellow fever and Camp Lazear thirty-nine years before. At once,<lb/>
she said, &ldquo;Yes, there were American soldiers with a few tents and a couple of<lb/>
buildings erected on the rear of this farm, but I don't remember that the place<lb/>
had any special name. I remember, we children had to stay away from the camp<lb/>
as it was guarded, but my little brother, bolder than I, used to talk with the<lb/>
guards and got apples and food from them for his little pig.&rdquo; I asked her if<lb/>
she would take us to that part of the farm where she believed the old camp had<lb/>
been. She hesitated, went <add>into</add> <del>to</del> the <del>home</del><add>house</add> and talked in voluble Spanish to a ser-<lb/>
vant. Mr. Moran suddenly smiled broadly. I asked what was up and he whispered<lb/>
to me, &ldquo;She isn't taking any chances with you. She told somebody that she is<lb/>
going to get into our car with us, presumably to go to another part of the farm,<lb/>
but if she doesn't return in one-half hour, please come after her. She is <del>af-</del><lb/>
afraid you might kidnap her!&rdquo; I might add that the lady was <del>about</del><add>over</add> fifty <add>years of age</add> and some-<lb/>
what heavy.</p>
<p>She showed us the place at the rear of the farm where she thought the<lb/>
camp had been and <hi>( X ) this was confirmed by Madam Rojas</hi> whom we visited in a<lb/>
day or two. She was a lovely lady and was most kind in telling us of her re-<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f04137143"/>
Hench - 20 - eej<lb/>
collections of the doings of 1900, and went with us from her town house to the Jan<lb/>
Jose farm and drove around, showing us where the American experimental camp had<lb/>
been. <hi>( X ) She got out old maps</hi> of the farm as it was in 1857 and <hi>1912. ( X )</hi><lb/>
From time to time parts of the farm had been sold and the remainder comprised a<lb/>
small estate which they used as a summer home.</p>
<p><hi>( X ) As Mr. Moran and I wandered</hi> around the rear of the old farm,<lb/>
we noticed an old shack comprised of two sections and wondered if it could pos<del>s</del>-<lb/>
sibly be either of Reed's experimental buildings. It certainly did not seem to<lb/>
be the right shape. (<del>and there were several trees adjacent to it. Old Army photo-<lb/>
graphs showed no trees adjacent to the Experimental Buildings <add>in 1900.</add></del> As we were stand-<lb/>
ing there, as had happened previously, a friendly and curious Cuban came to ask<lb/>
us what we wanted. He stated that he was Mr. Zunzunegui and that he had been raised<lb/>
in the little shack but had moved out a couple of years before with his family. When<lb/>
we asked if he had any recollections of the American soldiers and yellow fever, he<lb/>
said, &ldquo;Yes, the American soldiers lived in this building and got yellow fever. My<lb/>
father told me that.&rdquo; We could hardly believe him and because of the appearance of<lb/>
the buildings, frankly we doubted his statement. Later in discussing this with <add>The</add> Rojas's<lb/>
family they assured us that Mr. Zunzunegui was in error because as they recollected<lb/>
it, when the American soldiers left they took away the tents and tore down the two<lb/>
little buildings excepting the floors which the Rajos family used for picnics. De-<lb/>
spite our mutual doubts I found myself returning again and again to the little shack<lb/>
and I must have taken at least twenty pictures of it from all angles.</p>
<p>Armed with this information we revisited the Finlay Institute, and also<lb/>
visited Dr. Moya, a cabinet member in charge of the Department of Health who list-<lb/>
ened to us politely and referred us to Dr. Ramos, the Secretary of Defense, who as<lb/>
the former Director of Sanitation, had arranged for the memorializing of El Camp-<lb/>
amento Lazear. After a preliminary conference, Dr. Ramos arranged for a meeting of<lb/>
&ldquo;all concerned.&rdquo; It was quite a meeting with two cabinet members and secretaries,<lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f04137144"/>
Hench - 21 - eej<lb/>
several members from the Finlay Institute, Johnny Moran and me. At first, they<lb/>
were inclined to reject our findings rather vigorously. It was suggested that the<lb/>
disturbing railroad track at Camp Lazear might have been built since 1900, but Mr.<lb/>
Moran and I had already gotten an answer for that. We had seen Mr. Webster, Chief<lb/>
Engineer for the Havana Central Railroad, who had looked up the matter and had given<lb/>
us maps to prove that <del>this</del><add>that</add> particular spur was finished in 1865. When we <del>presented</del><add><unclear>tred</unclear> them</add><lb/>
this, it was suggested, &ldquo;After all, suppose you are right. From what you tell us<lb/>
the true site of Camp Lazear, surrounded by <unclear>small</unclear> <add><unclear>cheap</unclear></add> homes and adjacent to a quarry,<lb/>
is obviously not a fitting place to erect the memorial buildings we plan to build.<lb/>
What difference does it make if we erect a memorial to Dr. Lazear where the memorial<lb/>
sign now stands?&rdquo; Johnny Moran became indignant and insisted that although they might<lb/>
honor Lazear at the spot they had chosen, they should not call it Camp Lazear. Af-<lb/>
ter further meetings and discussions, Dr. Ramos settled the matter by saying, &ldquo;If we<lb/>
have erred in the matter, send me a documented report, and I will see what can be<lb/>
done&rdquo;.</p>
<p><hi>( X ) This is how matters stood when we</hi> ended our visit of 1940. It was<lb/>
the recollection of the Rojas family that the camp site had been on the rather high<lb/>
ground of the farm, a little <del>ways from</del><add>north of</add> the shack of which I had taken so many pictures.<lb/>
The Finca San Jose certainly filled the bill. It was &ldquo;a mile from Camp Columbia, in<lb/>
a secluded spot not far from the main highway&rdquo; (Calzada Real). <hi>( X ) Later, in Wash-<lb/>
ington in the photographic</hi> files of the Army Museum, I came across an <hi>old model of</hi><lb/>
the Station Hospital of Camp Columbia and lo and behold! the model indicated that<lb/>
just across <add>the railroad track</add> from the Station Hospital there were two rows of little buildings. At<lb/>
last these little buildings were identified. They were the little shacks or the<lb/>
&ldquo;yellow fever wards&rdquo; where the first patients with spontaneous yellow fever had been<lb/>
taken care of and where later the victims of the experimental yellow fever had been<lb/>
brought from Camp Lazear and had been taken care of by Dr. Ames. Actually therefore,<lb/>
the <unclear>site</unclear> of the false &ldquo;Campamento Lazear&rdquo; was well-memorialized as on this spot the brave<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="f04137145"/>
Hench - 22 - eej<lb/>
volunteers had been taken care of and also on this spot the martyr Lazear had died.</p>
<p><hi>( X ) Still later in Mrs. Reed's own scrap</hi> book of her husband, I found this<lb/>
little picture of these little huts which completed the identification.</p>
<p>That fall I was to give an address at the dedication of the Lazear<lb/>
Memorial Building at Washington and Jefferson College, Pennsylvania. That spring<lb/>
before I had left the Rojas family, I had asked if they knew of any letter or rental<lb/>
contracts between Dr. Rojas and Major Reed. Mrs. Rojas first recollected that the<lb/>
farm had been loaned free to the American doctors and she knew of no rental records.<lb/>
But just before the dedication was to be held, I wrote again to Madam Rojas asking<lb/>
if they had been able to find anything. <hi><add>X</add> To my delight, back came the word</hi> that they<lb/>
had just found the <hi>old diary or day book</hi> of Dr. Rojas with some entries that would<lb/>
undoubtedly interest me. The entry of January 2, 1901, stated <hi>as follows: <add>(X)</add></hi><lb/>
&ldquo;Collected a check sent by Major Surgeon U. S. V. Major Read, (sic) value $20.00,<lb/>
covering the first month's rent of the land on the San Jose farm occupied by the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Commission.&rdquo; The entry of April 22, 1901, referred to &ldquo;the rent on<lb/>
Camp Lezar&rdquo; (sic) <hi>( X ) Most important of all to me was the entry of October</hi> 10,<lb/>
1901. <hi>( X ) &ldquo;Today was received</hi> the last check of $20.00, amount of the rent for Camp<lb/>
Lazear on the San Jose farm which became due on the 9th and they left the farm; leav-<lb/>
ing the two wooden houses which they used to carry out the experiments on yellow fev-<lb/>
er and mosquitoes.&rdquo; Mrs. Rojas now recollected that it was the wooden floors of the<lb/>
tents that they had later used for picnicing and that these two little wooden build-<lb/>
ings had been there for years until one blew down in the cyclone of 1926.</p>
<p>You can imagine the elation of Mr. Moran and me. <hi>( X ) Later I was to</hi><lb/>
receive from General Kean the <hi>checkbook which</hi> he had kept as disbursor for Camp<lb/>
Lazear. Here you will see the actual check stubs corresponding to the payments made<lb/>
to Dr. Rojas <add>and others (cost of Camp Lazear project=<unclear>5000<hi rend="superscript">00</hi></unclear>)</add> I could hardly wait to return to Cuba in the spring of 1941. On <add>my</add> ar<del>r</del>-<lb/>
rival Mr. Moran <del>and I</del><add>took me</add> immediately <del>went</del> to visit <hi>the old house. ( X ) One of the lean-</hi><lb/>
<pb n="23" id="f04137146"/>
Hench - 23 - eej<lb/>
tos built after 1900 had already been removed, but two or three others remained. It<lb/>
was their presence that had made us doubt the word of Mr. Zunzunegui. <hi>( X ) We care-</hi><lb/>
fully made many examinations of the interior. Here were the &ldquo;<hi>tonged and grooved</hi><lb/>
boards&rdquo; and the &ldquo;<hi>double thickness wood</hi>.&rdquo; Here were the <hi>old sliding panel</hi> and the<lb/>
<hi>outside shutter</hi>, described by Reed. As it should have, the little building faced<lb/>
exactly south, <hi>( X ) and it measured twenty by fourteen</hi> feet. As a matter of fact,<lb/>
there was a slight, but amusing, discrepancy here-- the little building is slight-<lb/>
ly lopsided<unclear>ly</unclear> about four inches over-sized on two sides. Moran laughingly explain-<lb/>
ed: &ldquo;You must remember, it was built by enlisted men in the Quartermaster Corps.<lb/>
What difference did it make to them if it wasn't exact to the proper inch.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>( X ) The inside of the building</hi> was quite unique in construction as Cuban<lb/>
officials who<add>m we <unclear>invited</unclear> to</add> visit<del>ed</del> the place with us quickly agreed. Most Cuban shacks have no<lb/>
ceilings; a roof suffices. But this building had not only a roof, but a unique<lb/>
ceiling, flattened off at the top.</p>
<p><hi>( X ) A clinching point was that in one corner of the ceiling</hi> was a hole<lb/>
where a stove pipe had once been <add>(as shown in the drawing of Agramonte)</add> No Cuban shack contains a stove pipe since cook-<lb/>
ing is usually done in a lean-to. Mr. Zunzunegui told us that he and his family<lb/>
had often wondered what the hole for the stove pipe had signified. They had never<lb/>
used a stove inside the shack proper, during the many years he had lived in it.<lb/>
<hi>( X ) He said that the little outside stove pipe</hi> had fallen from the roof sometime<lb/>
before and had been kicked around by his kids and it might still be there. We hunt-<lb/>
ed for it and Mr. Moran's eagle eye spotted it right near the little building.</p>
<p><hi>( X ) Here at last were the undoubted remains</hi> of Reed's little Building<lb/>
Number One. Through this very smoke stack the long-held and expensive theory of<lb/>
(which I hold in my hand)<lb/>
&ldquo;fomites&rdquo; had literally &ldquo;gone up in smoke&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Mr. Zunzunegui located for us the site of the <hi>Building Number Two. <add>(X)</add> The</hi><lb/>
wooden floor had rotted because the ground was dampened by a nearby surface-spring.<lb/>
He had put in a <hi>cement floor</hi> which was all that remained. In <add>The <unclear>tornado</unclear> of</add> 1926 Building Number<lb/>
(Concrete <unclear>broken;</unclear> enough to interfere with growth of <unclear>corn</unclear>)<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f04137147"/>
Hench 24- eej<lb/>
Two had blown down and for quite awhile it had remained on its side. The neigh-<lb/>
borhood children used to get on top and slide down the sloping roof. Because this<lb/>
was dangerous, <del><unclear>are</unclear></del><add>Mr Zunzunegui finally</add> cut it up for kindling wood. <hi><add>X</add></hi> We carefully measured the distance<lb/>
<hi>from Building Number One to the</hi> cement floor of Building Number Two. Reed had<lb/>
stated that the two buildings were about 80 yards apart. According to our measure-<lb/>
ment, it was <del><unclear></unclear></del> 82 yards. One more thing, you remember the old Army photo-<lb/>
graph that showed the ruins of an unidentified building just to the <add>(photographic)</add> right of Build-<lb/>
ing Number Two. Although now somewhat smaller, the ruins still remained.</p>
<p><del>( X ) This photograph shows the few <unclear>venerate slate</unclear> on the site of the<lb/>
floor of Building Number Two; enough concrete remained to interfere with the growth<lb/>
of corn.</del></p>
<p><hi>( X ) In summary, here is the way Camp Lazear</hi> <add>now</add> appears. <del>in 1941.</del> The re-<lb/>
mains of Building Number One are on the right. The old floor of Building Number Two<lb/>
on the left. The tents were in the center background, and between Buildings Number<lb/>
One and Two lies the &ldquo;little valley&rdquo; which Reed mentioned in his records. <hi>( X ) To<lb/>
show you a final map of the</hi> neighborhood: here in the rear of Finca San Jose is the<lb/>
remains of Camp Lazear, a mile from the old Station Hospital. Just at the left <add>(west)</add> and<lb/>
across the <add>La Playa</add> railroad tracks from the old Station Hospital lies the marker of the false<lb/>
Campamento Lazear, (<del>actually the spot <add>w</add>here the soldiers were taken care of as soon as<lb/>
their experimental yellow fever developed at Camp Lazear</del>.)</p>
<p><hi>( X ) The last two slides show that</hi> <del><unclear>I</unclear></del><add>Mr Moran <unclear>d</unclear> and I</add> have finally triumphed, because on<lb/>
my second visit, I found that the <add>Cuban</add> government was no longer interested in the spot<lb/>
where the false camp had been marked. The sign was down; part of the fence was<lb/>
gone, and <add>a</add> cow<del>s</del> <del>were</del><add>was</add> grazing under the tree. <hi>( X ) Just this year <add>(April 1947)</add> the Cuba</hi> govern-<lb/>
ment finally made the true site of Camp Lazear and our little building a &ldquo;National<lb/>
Monument.&rdquo; Although they have done this, no money has been set aside for its preser-<lb/>
vation and some of us in this country are trying to raise money to do this.</p>
<pb n="25" id="f04137148"/>
<p>Hench - 25 - eej</p>
<p>In continuing my investigations I have had unusual luck. Miss Laura<lb/>
Wood of New York <del>and I</del> found, and <add>I helped to</add> <unclear>identify</unclear> in the New York Academy of Medicine<lb/>
<hi>one of the lost Lazear-Reed laboratory notebooks</hi>. I had spent considerable time<lb/>
hunting for the <hi>original fever charts which</hi> were not to be found anywhere in Wash-<lb/>
ington. I finally located them in <add>Atlanta, Georgia in</add> the home of <hi>Mrs. Ames</hi>, the widow of the doctor<lb/>
who had taken such good care of the soldiers during their experimental yellow fever.<lb/>
Mrs. Ames<del>, now living in Atlanta, Georgia,</del> graciously added these fever charts to<lb/>
my collection. <hi>General Kean located one of the original contracts</hi> between Reed and<lb/>
one of the volunteers which had been stolen from his office in the Army Medical Mus-<lb/>
eum. It was found many years later and recently presented to me. In an attic of a<lb/>
lovely old home outside Baltimore <hi>at &ldquo;Windsor,&rdquo; the old family home of the</hi> Lazears, I<lb/>
found a <hi>trunk full of letters, photographs and other</hi> items concerning Lazear and his<lb/>
mother, including <hi>one hundred forty letters</hi> sent by Lazear to his mother from Cuba<lb/>
and elsewhere. Miss Seth, Lazear's cousin, gave all this material to me. Lazear's<lb/>
son and daughter now live in San Francisco and presented me with one of Lazear's two<lb/>
<hi>microscopes,</hi> through which he vainly sought the organisms of yellow fever. <hi>The Reed<lb/>
family have made</hi> me the repository of all their data, <hi>Congressional Medal, scores</hi> of<lb/>
letters written by Major Reed from Cuba to his wife, describing the day to day ex-<lb/>
periments, etc. <hi>Dr. Howard Kelly</hi> who wrote the first book on Major Reed, has pre-<lb/>
sented all his data to me and <hi>Generals Kean and Truby have presented</hi> a mass of data<lb/>
that are in my possession only as caretaker, and steps have been taken for its per-<lb/>
manent care for the benefit of historians and others.</p>
<p>And so, Building Number One still stands <add>sleeping and</add> creaking in the Cuban sun. For<lb/>
all <del>I saw of</del><add>know,</add> Mrs. Hench <del>during our two Cuban vacations, she</del> may still be waiting for<lb/>
me on the porch of the Hotel Nacional, <del>but I hope not</del> creaking and sleeping in the<lb/>
Cuban sun!</p>
<p>In these days with <del>&ldquo;</del>the world so lately red with blood <del>and</del> when man's in-<lb/>
humanity to man is still so pathetically apparent, it is well for us to note the ex-<lb/>
ample of these men who banded together for high adventure, not to kill or even to die<lb/>
for one country, but to die, if need be, for their fellowmen of all countries. It is<lb/>
such as they who reassure us of the inherent decency and dignity of man<del>&rdquo;</del>.</p>
<pb n="26" id="f04137149"/>
<p>Hench - 9(a) - eej</p>
<p>(Would it be presumptious for me to suggest that this great university<lb/>
would honor itself if it erected a fine addition to the medical school or hospital<lb/>
to be named after Reed and to honor him, Jefferson Randolph Kean, <del>and</del> John Moran, and<lb/>
<del>three</del><add>Robert <unclear>Cookes</unclear> four</add> distinguished &ldquo;Virginia gentlemen&rdquo;. Would not the 50th anniversary of the<lb/>
conquest of yellow fever three years from now, in 1950, be a most appropriate time<lb/>
to dedicate such a memorial?)</p>
<pb n="27" id="f04137150"/>
<p>Hench - 9(a) - eej</p>
<p>(Would it be presumptious for me to suggest that this great university<lb/>
would honor itself if it erected a fine addition to the medical school or hospital<lb/>
to be named after Reed and to honor him, Jefferson Randolph Kean, <del>and</del> John Moran, and<lb/>
<del>three</del><add>Dr Robert Cooke, four</add> distinguished &ldquo;Virginia gentlemen&rdquo;. Would not the 50th anniversary of the<lb/>
conquest of yellow fever three years from now, in 1950, be a most appropriate time<lb/>
to dedicate such a memorial?)</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
