<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04139006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J. F. Siler, November 5, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04139006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-11-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Siler, J. F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-11-05">November 5, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04139006</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J. F. Siler, November 5, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Siler that he has accepted the invitation to speak on Walter Reed Memorial Day at the International Congress of Tropical Medicine. Hench discusses funding issues surrounding the memorialization of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-11-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J. F. Siler, November 5, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04139006"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-11-05">November 5, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Colonel J. F. Siler<lb/>
Secretary, Walter Reed Memorial<lb/>
Association<lb/>
3434 34th Place, N. W.<lb/>
Washington 16, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Colonel Siler:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your lotter of October 30, mentioning the annual meeting<lb/>
of the Walter Reed Memorial Association. First of all, let me thank you<lb/>
most sincerely for your confidence in me, as a result of which you suggested<lb/>
that I be a speaker on the &ldquo;Walter Reed Memorial Day&rdquo; of the International<lb/>
Congress on Tropical Medicine. I have had some correspondence with Doctor<lb/>
Sawyer and have accepted the invitation with pleasure.</p>
<p>I should like indeed to attend the meeting of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association this year but hesitate to ask you to change your date;<lb/>
however, if you could hold the meeting Tuesday, November 25, I believe I<lb/>
could be there. I have just returned from one trip and Mrs. Hench and I<lb/>
are leaving November 13 to attend the inauguration of one of my oldest friends<lb/>
as President of a college where I will represent my alma mater. This is in<lb/>
Kentucky, then I am speaking in Charlottesville, Virginia on Monday, November 17<lb/>
and am then going to New York where I have meetings and appointments the 18,<lb/>
19, and 20. I will leave New York at midnight, Thursday, November 20, to<lb/>
arrive in Washington, Friday morning, the 21st. I had intended renting a car<lb/>
and going at once with Mrs. Hench to Mercersburg, where our son is in school.<lb/>
He wanted us to arrive in the late afternoon. We had planned to drive to<lb/>
Mercersburg, leaving Washington about 10:00 Friday morning, the 21st, perhaps<lb/>
stopping at Blue Ridge Summit, Pennsylvania for lunch as one of the main roads<lb/>
goes right through Blue Ridge Summit. We thought to invite Blossom Reed to<lb/>
have lunch with us and pay our respects to her and Mrs. Walter Reed and then<lb/>
go on to Mercersburg, arriving their about 4:00 p.m., staying the weekend.<lb/>
We would come back to Washington Monday morning November 24. I have appoint-<lb/>
ments with two or three men in the Pentagon Building and want to see General<lb/>
Reed about a matter. I would probably not arrive in Washington until almost<lb/>
noon the 24th therefore it seems to me that the morning of the 25th would be<lb/>
much more available for me. However, Colonel Siler, if this date is not con-<lb/>
venient and if the Walter Reed Memorial Association meeting would not last too<lb/>
long and if the date of Friday, November 21 is more agreeable, I can attend the<lb/>
meeting that morning and leave for Mercersburg with Mrs. Hench after lunch.<lb/>
If we are not able to stop to see Blossom and Mrs. Reed that day, we could stop<lb/>
and see them on our return to Washington on the 24th. I must leave Washington<lb/>
the late afternoon of the 25th in order to get home Wednesday night, the 26th<lb/>
in time to have Thanksgiving with the children here. If neither the 21st nor<lb/>
the 25 (the latter being preferable to me) is suitable, please do not go to<lb/>
any bother to rearrange the date. I will simply have to be absent this year.<lb/>
I don't have much to report.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04139007"/>
<p>Colonel J. F. Siler</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>November 5, 1947</p>
<p>One of my tentative appointments in New York is with an associate<lb/>
of the Rockefellers to try to interest them in our little project with Camp<lb/>
Lazear. I have been overwhelmed with medical work this year and have been<lb/>
unable to do very little on the Camp Lazear project; however, the Cuban<lb/>
Government has finally made Camp Lazear and our little shack a &ldquo;national<lb/>
monument&rdquo; but that is merely a name, an honorary title as it were and so<lb/>
far they have not set aside any money to preserve the place. That they<lb/>
seem to be leaving up to us.</p>
<p>Mrs. Hench and I are planning our spring vacation to Florida and<lb/>
Cuba. I hope to make the Cuban Government officials &ldquo;fish or cut bait&rdquo; and<lb/>
by the spring meeting of the International Congress on Tropical Medicine I<lb/>
hope to have some definite information regarding our project.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
