<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04139002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to William H. Wranek, Jr., November 4, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04139002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-11-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wranek, Jr., William H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-11-04">November 4, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04139002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to William H. Wranek, Jr., November 4, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes that he will send Wranek a copy of his speech on Reed at the University of Virginia. He discusses the content of the speech and notes that he emphasizes Lazear's contribution as well as Reed's.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-11-04">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to William H. Wranek, Jr., November 4, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04139002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-11-04">November 4, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Mr. William H. Wranek, Jr.<lb/>
University News Service<lb/>
University of Virginia<lb/>
Charlottesville, Virginia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Wranek:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I appreciate greatly the interest which you and Mr. John Cook<lb/>
Wyllie are taking in my forthcoming visit to Charlottesville and I will<lb/>
make every effort to interest my audience in the story of Walter Reed<lb/>
and the conquest of yellow fever. Incidentally, the title of the talk<lb/>
could almost be &ldquo;The University of Virginia and the Conquest of Yellow<lb/>
Fever&rdquo; because three Virginia men (Walter Reed, Major, now General<lb/>
Jefferson R. Kean, and John J. Moran) had much to do with the affair.</p>
<p>You asked me to send you ahead of time a copy of my talk and<lb/>
I will try to do so. However, I have not yet determined exactly the<lb/>
context of the talk. This depends on the length of time allowed to me.<lb/>
On previous occasions the first half of my talk concerns the human in-<lb/>
terest story of the conquest of yellow fever. I can assure you that I<lb/>
am not going to give a medical or scientific talk. It will be completely<lb/>
understandable and I hope will interest the layman. It is the human<lb/>
story, not the medical story, that I will tell. The second part of my<lb/>
talk, about the last third, I have devoted in the past to the rather<lb/>
amusing way in which we discovered the lost Camp Lazear (where Walter<lb/>
Reed did his work) and the remains of one of Reed's little experimental<lb/>
buildings, and I also touch briefly on the finding by me in various<lb/>
attics and collars of many old letters, documents, etc., pertaining to<lb/>
the conquest of yellow fever. My audiences have seemed to be interested<lb/>
and amused by this last part, but the whole thing as I have given it in<lb/>
the past takes a whole hour and I am not sure that my hosts want me to<lb/>
talk that long this time. It may be, therefore, that I will have to con-<lb/>
fine myself just to the first part of the story.</p>
<p>Although I am pleased with your courteous thought that my talk<lb/>
might be of some news value (you even mentioned sending items air mail<lb/>
to the news bureaus in South America) I fear that the talk will have<lb/>
little or nothing of interest to you from that angle. I can hardly be-<lb/>
lieve that the following would be timely: &ldquo;FLASH -- WALTER REED CONQUERS<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER&rdquo; or &ldquo;FLASH -- UNIVERSITY BOY MAKES GOOD&rdquo;. You see what I<lb/>
mean. There is certainly nothing of any special news value in the first<lb/>
part of my talk even though I do have some new angles to it and include<lb/>
certain heretofore unknown or little known data on just what this man and<lb/>
that man did. This is mostly of interest as a human document, a story<lb/>
of courage and heroism or of interest to medical historians.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04139003"/>
<p>Mr. William H. Wranek, Jr.</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>November 4, 1947</p>
<p>In a very modest way, there might be some news interest in<lb/>
the fact that a rather important collection of historical data on Walter<lb/>
Reed and his associates is being accomplished. It would have been tragic<lb/>
had these collections in various attics and cellars not been sought and<lb/>
brought together and some of the material that I have assembled is of<lb/>
rather important historical value. But that would hardly rate more than<lb/>
an inch or two in your own University News or in some medical magazine.<lb/>
I enclose a carbon copy of a list which I just sent to Mr. John Cook<lb/>
Wyllie and I think that he will agree with the general tone of my letter<lb/>
and he can also tell you his opinion of the value of this collection.<lb/>
I am sure that you know that when a couple of bibliophiles and historians<lb/>
get together they can get quite excited about something which sounds<lb/>
completely ridiculous to others.</p>
<p>There is one little part of my talk which I will have to tell<lb/>
at the risk of offending those who would (erroneously) give Walter Reed<lb/>
all the credit. My investigations show clearly that the work of Lazear<lb/>
was of tremendous importance; that he actually in the early phases of<lb/>
the study was &ldquo;ahead of Reed&rdquo; and was sniffing up the right track a<lb/>
little bit ahead of schedule, prematurely, and &ldquo;on his own&rdquo;. As the<lb/>
result of certain secret experiments, it was he who first proved that<lb/>
the mosquito was the cause of yellow fever but died leaving incomplete<lb/>
data which proved the point conclusively to Reed but which would have<lb/>
been unacceptable to the world without the further magnificent and con-<lb/>
clusive experiments of Reed. I would, of course, have to give Lazear<lb/>
his due credit. But there is so much credit that that extra credit<lb/>
which we must give Lazear cannot and should not detract one iota from<lb/>
the glory that is firmly Reed's.</p>
<p>As soon as I hear from my hosts just how long the talk is to<lb/>
be (I fear it is not going to be at a popular hour, I think someone said<lb/>
it would be at 5:00 p.m. Who wants to hear a lecture at 5:00 p.m.?) I<lb/>
can decide on what the talk will be. I will then try to write it out<lb/>
and send it to you as soon as I can but I fear that you will be greatly<lb/>
disappointed in its news value.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
