<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04136011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John Cook Wyllie, October 30, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04136011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-10-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wyllie, John Cook</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-10-30">October 30, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04136011</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John Cook Wyllie, October 30, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Wyllie that he will not have time to carefully choose and prepare Reed materials for an exhibit in connection with Hench's upcoming lecture at the University of Virginia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-10-30">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John Cook Wyllie, October 30, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04136011"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-10-30">October 30, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John Cook Wyllie<lb/>
Curator, Rare Books Division<lb/>
Alderman Library<lb/>
University of Virginia<lb/>
Charlottesville, Virginia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Wyllie:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your letter of October 24, 1947, suggesting that I lend<lb/>
to your library for display purposes through the month of November cer-<lb/>
tain materials from my collection of data on the conquest of yellow fever,<lb/>
in particular, material concerning Walter Reed. I would like to comply<lb/>
with your request but the situation is as follows: I leave today for a<lb/>
three-day medical meeting and will return November 3. I will just have<lb/>
ten days then before leaving for Kentucky November 13 and then on to<lb/>
Charlottesville, New York and Washington. During those ten days I have<lb/>
much work to do preparing for meetings and conferences in New York and<lb/>
Washington; therefore, I am not at all sure that I can spend sufficient<lb/>
time getting the material ready and writing explanatory notes for such a<lb/>
display as you might wish. Furthermore, much of my material, indeed most<lb/>
of it, is of interest only to scholars who already know pretty much about<lb/>
the whole story and I am not sure how much of it would be of interest to<lb/>
the casual passer-by. Nevertheless, in order to give you an expression<lb/>
of my desire to cooperate, last night I spent about three hours very<lb/>
hastily going through my files and I enclose some quite hastily written<lb/>
notes which will give you an idea of what I have.</p>
<p>One thing concerns me greatly. I am, of course, aware that<lb/>
museums exchange invaluable, irreplaceable material, sent by mail or<lb/>
otherwise but in the present instance I am somewhat fearful about con-<lb/>
signing any of my material to the mails or railroads, chiefly because I<lb/>
have had practically no time to copy any of it, nor have I had time to<lb/>
make more than the most cursory notes from the various letters and docu-<lb/>
ments which you might wish to borrow. Therefore, if anything should<lb/>
happen to them, the loss would indeed be irreplaceable. Your letter<lb/>
mentioned something about the usual methods of sending and insuring such<lb/>
data but I am not aware of what these methods are. I wouldn't mind<lb/>
bringing a certain amount of data with me and perhaps leaving it there,<lb/>
having delivered it myself into your care. My own preference would<lb/>
be to leave it there until I myself could bring it back; however, I<lb/>
suppose this is foolish.</p>
<p>Permit me to append a list of the major items I have should you<lb/>
desire to make a small selection and we could certainly do something<lb/>
about it. I certainly won't have a chance to copy, photostat or photo-<lb/>
graph any significant amount of material before bringing or sending it.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04136012"/>
<p>Mr. John Cook Wyllie</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>October 30, 1947</p>
<p>By separate post, I am sending you a glossy print of myself<lb/>
which you have requested and also a reprint of my article in Hygeia and<lb/>
a mimeographed copy of the talk I gave at the unveiling of the painting<lb/>
&ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo; at the A.M.A., 1941, when the painting was<lb/>
unveiled by Walter Reed's daughter, Blossom. I also enclose a newspaper<lb/>
clipping which gives a little information on some of the material I<lb/>
found and as you have requested, I enclose a copy of a biographical<lb/>
sketch used in Who's Who, brought up to date. <unclear>I</unclear></p>
<p>I expect to arrive in Charlottesville about 10:00 Monday<lb/>
morning, November 17, and will spend the day with my brother, leaving<lb/>
Charlottesville for New York that night.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
