<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04143003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to H. Carter Redd, December 9, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04143003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-12-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Redd, H. Carter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Stitt, Edward R.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-12-09">December 9, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04143003</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to H. Carter Redd, December 9, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes to Redd about Carter's influence on Lazear and Reed in relation to the mosquito theory of yellow fever transmission. He seeks Carter correspondence to document this influence, and believes Lazear was more supportive of the mosquito theory than Reed, who intended to fully test the bacterial theory first.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-12-09">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to H. Carter Redd, December 9, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04143003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-12-09">December 9, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Mr. H. Carter Redd<lb/>
1104 Travelers Building<lb/>
Richmond, Virginia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Redd:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter addressed to me at the University of Virginia has been<lb/>
forwarded to me here. I have just returned from our eastern trip. I am de-<lb/>
lighted to receive your letter. I am trying to write up the whole story of<lb/>
the conquest of yellow fever and of those many people who helped Walter Reed.</p>
<p>One of the points which I have not been able to settle yet to my<lb/>
satisfaction concerns the help which Henry Rose Carter gave to the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Board. I have no little time trying to trace some direct correspondence<lb/>
between Reed and Carter or Lazear and Carter and until your letter arrived I<lb/>
had found nothing.</p>
<p>By separate post, I am sending you a reprint and as you read it,<lb/>
I think you will see it has been my impression that although Reed had un-<lb/>
doubtedly decided to investigate the mosquito theory, it was to be done<lb/>
&ldquo;in due time&rdquo; and after they had gotten rid of the bacterial theory.<lb/>
Lazear apparently in the early days believed in the mosquito theory much more<lb/>
strongly than did Reed. He couldn't stand the delay and was impatient to<lb/>
get going on the mosquito theory, as a letter to his wife at that time showed.<lb/>
Because of Lazear's greater interest, I have suspected that Lazear was the first<lb/>
convert to Carter's work, and I have wondered whether Carter and Lazear had any<lb/>
correspondence in the spring and early summer of 1900. I have tried to find out<lb/>
whether Carter brought his own work to Reed's attention; or whether Lazear brought<lb/>
Carter's work to Reed's attention. Please do not think that I am in any way<lb/>
trying to belittle the overwhelming importance of Reed's work, I am just trying<lb/>
to get the story in order.</p>
<p>I have visited in recent years most of the survivors of these experi-<lb/>
ments and have had innumerable conversations with General Kean and General<lb/>
Truby and others. The points mentioned above have not so far been settled and<lb/>
I would appreciate greatly your further help in the matter.</p>
<p>I am a member of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial<lb/>
Association, of which Admiral Stitt is also a member. As you already know,<lb/>
he married Laura Carter, the daughter of Henry Rose Carter. I have been<lb/>
anxious to locate relatives of Doctor Carter who might have information or<lb/>
correspondence mentioned above, but so far I have not been able to find where<lb/>
these relatives live. Last week, I had hoped to see Admiral Stitt at our meeting<lb/>
but he was ill and did not attend. Could you give me the addresses of Doctor<lb/>
Carter's close relatives. Am I correct in assuming from your name, that you<lb/>
are also a relative? I appreciate greatly indeed your kindness in writing to me.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
