<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04144021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Arthur W. Packard, October 29, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04144021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-10-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Packard, Arthur W.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-10-29">October 29, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04144021</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Arthur W. Packard, October 29, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests a meeting with Packard in New York. He relates the story of his yellow fever research, the discovery of Camp Lazear Building No. 1, and subsequent efforts to memorialize the site. He seeks the financial support of the Rockefeller Foundation, explaining that the Cubans feel Finlay was denied credit for his yellow fever work and blame the Rockefeller Foundation, in part, for championing Reed over Finlay. Hench believes this is an opportunity to recognize the work of both Finlay and the Americans.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-10-29">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Arthur W. Packard, October 29, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04144021"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-10-29">October 29, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Arthur W. Packard<lb/>

49 West 49th Street<lb/>
New York, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Packard:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Would it be possible for me to have an interview with you in New<lb/>
York City, if you are to be there, Tuesday, November 18? I enclose a letter<lb/>
of introduction written for me by Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer last July when I had<lb/>
expected to come to New York to see you but was unable to do so.</p>
<p>Let me state frankly the purpose of my interview. Some years ago<lb/>
as a hobby I took up the story of the conquest of yellow fever of Walter Reed<lb/>
and his associates. This led me to several visits to Cuba and many trips<lb/>
around the country interviewing the survivors of these illustrious experi-<lb/>
ments and I uncovered many new facts and also found a mountain of old letters,<lb/>
documents, etc., pertaining to the experiments and to the participants. These<lb/>
contain much unpublished and important material.</p>
<p>On one of my early visits to Cuba, I made a sentimental journey to<lb/>
the supposed site of Camp Lazear, the little experimental camp where Reed<lb/>
carried on the concluding experiments, which site had been eroneously located<lb/>
and marked by the Cuban Government. To make a long story short, with help<lb/>
from others, I was able to locate the actual camp site and mirabile dictu,<lb/>
we found the remains of the original little &ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo; made so<lb/>
famous by Walter Reed. I took preliminary steps to preserve the little<lb/>
building and have had some correspondence and visits with the Cuban officials<lb/>
with the aim of preserving the building permanently and enclosing it in a<lb/>
modest &ldquo;Cuban-American museum&rdquo; in memory of the conquerors of yellow fever,<lb/>
Finlay as well as the Americans. This project has been received with en-<lb/>
thusiasm by the Cubans and they have just made the little shack a national<lb/>
monument; however, their support has been more vocal than monetary.</p>
<p>The Mayo Foundation has promised me a significant contribution<lb/>
toward this little project. Because of the long-continued and present<lb/>
interest of the Rockefeller Foundation in the conquest and control of yellow<lb/>
fever, I believe or at least hope, that some members of the Rockefeller family<lb/>
might join with the Mayo Foundation and with me personally in raising a modest<lb/>
fund for the purpose mentioned. Appropriately, two years from now will occur<lb/>
the 50th anniversary of the conquest of yellow fever. In my preliminary con-<lb/>
versations with Cuban government officials, including the President of Cuba,<lb/>
they assured me that they would be delighted to join in the venture and make<lb/>
the dedication of such a memorial a Cuban-American international affair.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04144022"/>
<p>Mr. Arthur W. Packard</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>October 29, 1947</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the war and my entrance into military service interrupted<lb/>
almost entirely my efforts along the lines mentioned and only recently have I<lb/>
been able to take up the matter again. You may or may not be aware of the<lb/>
fact that many Cuban physicians and government officials believe that Finlay<lb/>
their great scientist, was robbed of most of his fame by the protagonists<lb/>
of Reed and I must tell you that in certain quarters, some of the early ap-<lb/>
proval of Reed by the Rockefeller <unclear>FoundationIwas</unclear> considered a strong factor<lb/>
in depriving Finlay of &ldquo;his just deserts&rdquo;. This most unhappy anti-Reed and<lb/>
anti-U. S. Yellow Fever Board sentiment in Cuba could, I believe, be largely<lb/>
done away with were we able to conclude the project. This little building<lb/>
and the remains of Camp Lazear represent the one remaining concrete historical<lb/>
&ldquo;souvenir&rdquo; of one of the great contributions of medical science.</p>
<p>I would appreciate it greatly if you would give me the little time<lb/>
necessary to show you photographs of the remains of the little building, a<lb/>
little documentary proof of its validity and a very few other important items.<lb/>
Should you wish me to send ahead some of this data, I shall be glad indeed to<lb/>
do so. In lieu of this, I am sending you a reprint of an article of mine pub-<lb/>
lished in Hygeia, a few years ago.</p>
<p>Let me assure you, Mr. Packard, I have no personal ax to grind in<lb/>
this matter. I have spent a considerable amount of my own funds and had a<lb/>
lot of fun doing it. I have myself contributed the first $1,000 towards our<lb/>
little fund. I have many personal friends in New York who will vouch for<lb/>
me should you wish me to name them.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
