<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04143024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Atcheson Laughlin Hench to Philip Showalter Hench, December 22, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Atcheson Laughlin</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04143024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-12-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Josiah</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-12-22">December 22, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04143024</idno>
<title>Letter from Atcheson Laughlin Hench to Philip Showalter Hench, December 22, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Atch Hench describes a book by Josiah Gorgas that he has sent to his brother as a Christmas gift. He also relates family and professional news.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-12-22">
<head>Letter from Atcheson Laughlin Hench to Philip Showalter Hench, December 22, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04143024"/>
<opener>
UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA<lb/>
CHARLOTTESVILLE, VIRGINIA<lb/>
<dateline>
Home and Mailing Address:<lb/>
The Farm Lane, East Jefferson St.,<lb/>
Charlottesville, Virginia<lb/>
<date value="1947-12-22">Dec. 22, 1947</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Phil,</salute>
</opener>
<p>Jim has already written to the whole Rochester Hench crowd<lb/>
a final note. Gifts went off days and maybe some even weeks<lb/>
ago. This is a separate letter to you.</p>
<p>You will get two small gifts from me, and then a third one<lb/>
that I sent off last week. This last item is a footnote for<lb/>
your yellow fever studies. I realize that Reed &amp; Lazear are<lb/>
your two main interests and that Gorgas is a very minor<lb/>
one. Well, the item I am sending is not a Reed or Lazear item;<lb/>
it is a Gorgas one. But I am sure you don't have it, for<lb/>
it is just off the press. Nor does it deal with Gorgas<lb/>
primarily; it deals with his father. Your Gorgas is a<lb/>
little boy in the book, named simply &ldquo;Willie.&rdquo; The book is<lb/>
The Civil War section of the diary that General Josiah Gorgas,<lb/>
head of the supply of all guns, arms, etc. to the Confederate<lb/>
Army, wrote as a journal for his boy to read. Little Willie<lb/>
lived in Richmond through the War and anybody interested<lb/>
in the whole story of the Panama-Canal-Gorgas who used Reed's<lb/>
discovery so effectively will be interested in anything that<lb/>
tells about the family he grew up in and what kind of<lb/>
boyhood he had.</p>
<p>This book tells something of that story. But don't<lb/>
expect it to be exciting. They say that General Josiah Gorgas<lb/>
was one of the most capable of the service of supply <unclear>generals</unclear>.<lb/>
But the gentleman did <hi>not</hi> write an exciting diary. Indeed<lb/>
it is pretty dull. He was terribly busy and was not<lb/>
inclined to put his army problems into his diary. So<lb/>
the book is nothing but notes about how the war was<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04143025"/>
going and how the prices of food crept up. When you come<lb/>
to the spring of 1864 when things began to look bad, the diary<lb/>
becomes fuller and more interesting. The 1864 and 1865 parts<lb/>
are the best.</p>
<p>The point of my sending you the book is that your<lb/>
General Gorgas went through all this as a boy.</p>
<p>Margaret arrived back from Swarthmore in her new fur<lb/>
coat Saturday night and immediately afterwards we all<lb/>
sped off to a wedding reception.</p>
<p>Tomorrow we all go out into the country to the farm<lb/>
of a good friend of ours who takes the kids out into the<lb/>
woods and chops down for them the Christmas tree they<lb/>
choose. It is always an occasion - <unclear>sort</unclear> of like bringing in<lb/>
the Yule log in the olden days.</p>
<p>Now for your desire that I send you some dope about<lb/>
my honors, etc. I cannot get that stuff together till<lb/>
after the meeting of the American <unclear>Dialect</unclear> Society (of which I am<lb/>
president - To be reelected, I hear, for another year) in Detroit<lb/>
next week. I am being crowded by many details in<lb/>
preparation for that meeting. So let me postpone sending<lb/>
you the dope. A further explanation for my need for time is the<lb/>
fact that Phi Beta Kappa &amp; the Raven Society elections are only<lb/>
two of several. My work &amp; my honors are bound up together.<lb/>
Article- writing for the journal <hi>American Speech</hi> produced my appoint-<lb/>
ment to the advisory editorial board of that journal. These same <del>the</del><lb/>
articles plus a lot of other stuff I sent <unclear>Mencken</unclear> produced his<lb/>
most kind mention of me in his introduction to <hi><unclear>Iberian</unclear> Language,<lb/>
Supplement I</hi>. This kind of thing - interest in research-won<lb/>
me Phi Beta Kappa. This kind of thing plus something<lb/>
vaguely called &ldquo;interest in the University over &amp; above things<lb/>
one is obligated to do&rdquo; won me the <add>faculty and,</add> student's fine compliment<lb/>
of election to the honor society of faculty <del>of</del> and students, the Ravens,</p>
<p>Then some other things came along. I'll have to look<lb/>
them up to get exact details. But I got invited to join<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04143026"/>
the advisory editorial board of Funk &amp; Wagnall's <hi>College Standard</hi><lb/>
Dictionary (you may remember I sent Susan a copy of this-<lb/>
a big red book). Then two years ago I was elected<lb/>
vice-president of the Am. Dialect Society and last year<lb/>
was elected president.</p>
<p>Also in August I was appointed on a board of<lb/>
University representatives dealing with the stimulation of<lb/>
research in the Richmond district for the Rockefeller<lb/>
sponsored Richmond Area University Center.</p>
<p>Also I'm on a committee of word-hunters, more<lb/>
pompously called lexicographers, who <unclear>run</unclear> a column or<lb/>
section of <hi>American Speech</hi> called &ldquo;Among the New Words&rdquo;<lb/>
and who publish the <unclear>cream</unclear> of their findings in the<lb/>
<hi>Britannica Year Book</hi> under the title &ldquo;Words and meanings<lb/>
of the Year, New&rdquo; each spring.</p>
<p>If you really want the low-down on me, right<lb/>
from the horse's mouth, I'll have to do some <unclear>rezearch</unclear><lb/>
into it, and that will have to be put off till after<lb/>
I'm 56 years old - next week.</p>
<p>Merry Christmas to all of you.</p>
<closer>
<salute><unclear>Asever</unclear></salute>
<signed>Atch</signed>
People continue to tell me what a fine talk you made them<lb/>
when you were here. The general idea is &ldquo;It wasn't on<lb/>
rheumatism or cancer. It was on something really<lb/>
interesting to listen to.&rdquo;<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
