<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04144007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose R. Andreu, May 16, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04144007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-05-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Andreu, Jose R.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Macia, Adrian</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-05-16">May 16, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04144007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose R. Andreu, May 16, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes in detail the background of his efforts to memorialize the Camp Lazear site, and his plans for the preservation of the site and establishment of a museum. He asks Andreu about the availability of funds from the Cuban government or private sources for building and upkeep, and about costs for these efforts. Without this information and commitment from the Cubans he will find it difficult to raise funds from American sources.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-05-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose R. Andreu, May 16, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04144007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-05-16">May 16, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Jose R. Andreu<lb/>
Minister of Public Health and Social Assistance<lb/>
Republic of Cuba<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Andreu:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of April 24th has pleased me greatly. I regret my delay<lb/>
in answering it but I have been attending medical meetings in Oregon, Colorado,<lb/>
Chicago and Arkansas. I have also received a letter from Doctor Pedro <unclear>Negueira</unclear>.</p>
<p>I am delighted to learn that the Cuban Government has named as a<lb/>
National monument the Caseta on the Finca San Jose in Quemados where Major Walter<lb/>
Reed and his associates, Doctors James Carroll and Aristides Agramonte completed<lb/>
the work which proved beyond all doubt the correctness of the splendid theory of<lb/>
Doctor Carlos Finlay. That part of the Finca San Jose used by the American<lb/>
commission was named by Major Reed <hi>Camp Lazear</hi> in honor of their dead colleague,<lb/>
Doctor Jesse W. Lazear whose preliminary <unclear>successes</unclear> led the way to the final<lb/>
victory. The Caseta which remains was &ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo; described so care-<lb/>
fully in official documents by Major Reed.</p>
<p>From the medico-historical standpoint it is a most happy coincidence<lb/>
that in earlier years Doctor Finlay had performed a few of his experiments at the<lb/>
very same Finca San Jose, presumably when the Jesuits occupied the main building<lb/>
as a summer retreat. Thus the Finca San Jose fortunately unites the memories of<lb/>
Doctor Finlay and of Major Reed and his colleagues and thus makes it eminently fitting<lb/>
as the site of a Cuban-American medical memorial.</p>
<p>I believe that Mr. John Moran of Havana, one of Major Reed's outstanding<lb/>
and earliest volunteers, has told you that the historical significance of the Finca<lb/>
San Jose and of Camp Lazear and indeed their actual location were lost sight of by<lb/>
medical and governmental authorities until 1939 when on a visit to Mr. Moran I con-<lb/>
cluded that a site marked by a temporary sign as the supposed site of Camp Lazear<lb/>
was not in fact the true site of Camp Lazear but was the location of the small<lb/>
yellow-fever hospital, across the La Playa railroad track from the Camp Columbia<lb/>
Hospital, in which certain spontaneous (natural) and experimental cases of yellow<lb/>
fever were cared for, including Major Reed's experimental cases from Camp Lazear.<lb/>
Having made this conclusion Mr. Moran, Mr. Luis Pogolotti and I set out to find the<lb/>
true location of Camp Lazear and located it correctly.</p>
<p>When we informed certain governmental and medical personages of our find-<lb/>
ings we were not surprised to note their skepticism. But despite their skepticism<lb/>
and preliminary disbelief, they received us graciously and kindly and finally upon<lb/>
the request of Doctor Domingo Ramos, then Secretary of National Defense, I pre-<lb/>
pared a statement with documentary and photographic proof identifying the true lo-<lb/>
cation of Camp Lazear and the significance of the Caseta which had fortunately and<lb/>
remarkably survived through the years. This formal statement of mine in the form<lb/>
of a loose-leaf notebook was sent to Doctor Ramos who deposited it in the library<lb/>
of the Finlay Institute and it is presumably still there.</p>
<p>In view of the great medico-historical significance of Camp Lazear and of<lb/>
the Finca San Jose it seemed to me appropriate to preserve the Caseta and enough<lb/>
of the surrounding land (which comprised Camp Lazear) for a permanent Cuban-American<lb/>
medical memorial.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04144008"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Most regretfully I had become painfully aware on my visits to Cuba of<lb/>
the unfortunate controversy between those who believe that Finlay did not receive<lb/>
enough credit from American writers and authorities and those who believe that Reed<lb/>
and his colleagues have not received their due credit at the hands of Cuban writers<lb/>
and authorities. I believe this is a most unhappy controversy because the magni-<lb/>
ficent conquest of yellow fever, the work of several hands, is of such tremendous<lb/>
importance to the world that sufficient honors can surely be given to all concerned.<lb/>
Without the astute theory and pioneer work of Doctor Finlay, Major Reed and his<lb/>
colleagues might, like others, have spent fruitless years. Without the work of the<lb/>
American Commission, Doctor Finlay's work might have continued in neglect without<lb/>
serious consideration for many more years. Together these scientists and lovers<lb/>
of their fellowmen created an immortal &ldquo;team.&rdquo; Their work is inseparable and my<lb/>
earnest hope is that through our little memorial their memories may be inseparably<lb/>
honored.</p>
<p>It was my hope, which Mr. Moran enthusiastically shared, that a small group<lb/>
of American and Cuban physicians and sanitarians might raise enough money to build<lb/>
around the Caseta an enveloping building of modest size which would become &ldquo;The<lb/>
Cuban-American Medical Memorial.&rdquo; As Finlay came before Reed in time so it seemed<lb/>
to me appropriate to designate it as the <hi>Cuban</hi>-American Memorial. My original plans<lb/>
were quite modest and I had hoped to raise $20,000 to $30,000 in the United States<lb/>
with the belief that perhaps a similar sum could be raised in Cuba.</p>
<p>My preliminary conversations with Senor Macia, the present owner of the<lb/>
land once occupied by Camp Lazear, led me to believe that he would either sell me<lb/>
the land for an appropriate price or that he might even join me in the project by<lb/>
selling it to me for a nominal price on presenting it to the sponsors of the project<lb/>
provided he was certain that the Cuban Government or medical profession would actually<lb/>
accept it and care for it as a national monument. In this spirit Senor Macia<lb/>
graciously gave me in 1940 a signed deed to the Caseta on the provise that I was<lb/>
able to complete the project at an early date. It is quite understandable that<lb/>
Senor Macia has hesitated to conclude any contract with me or others until he knew<lb/>
what use would be made of the land. I have not written to or heard from Senor Macia<lb/>
recently but I feel certain that he will continue to cooperate graciously with those<lb/>
responsible for the project.</p>
<p>My own earlier efforts to interest various persons in this project and<lb/>
to raise preliminary sums of money in this country were greatly handicapped by<lb/>
my participation in military service between 1942 and 1946. However between 1940<lb/>
and 1944 I did write on occasion to certain persons in Cuba. I regret to say that<lb/>
more often than not I had no reply..</p>
<p>In a letter to Doctor Jose A. Presno, dated December 6, 1944, I stated<lb/>
that a ranking official of the Mayo Clinic had promised me that, contingent on the<lb/>
gifts of others, the Mayo Clinic or Foundation would contribute up to $10,000 for<lb/>
the memorial project. Having had no reply from Doctor Presno we became fearful<lb/>
that the project was of no interest to Cuban medical or governmental circles. It<lb/>
is therefore with great pleasure that I have received your letter and I shall be<lb/>
happy indeed to begin again the campaign and to join you and others so that we may<lb/>
accomplish the project in the near future.</p>
<p>I had originally conceived a rather small, unpretentious memorial costing<lb/>
about $20,000 to $30,000. It was to be somewhat like the enclosed diagram<unclear>:</unclear> a white<lb/>
one-storied building of Cuban design and construction comprising essentially one large<lb/>
main room big enough to contain the Caseta in its center (the Caseta being left just<lb/>
where it has been, but restored somewhat). This main room would have sufficient wall<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04144009"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
space and additional floor space for display cabinets where would be exhibited the<lb/>
many souvenirs of the conquest of yellow fever which I have already been able to<lb/>
collect from participants in the experiments and relatives of participants. For<lb/>
example the families of Major Reed and Doctor Lazear and certain military personnel<lb/>
associated with them such as Generals J. R. Kean and Albert E. Truby have already<lb/>
contributed much which would be appropriate for display.</p>
<p>I already have a mass of material--old photographs of Camp Lazear, of the<lb/>
Finca San Jose, of Camp Columbia and its hospital, and of the yellow fever hospital<lb/>
taken in 1900; old maps of Camp Lazear and of Camp Columbia; most of the original<lb/>
fever charts of the volunteers who developed experimental yellow fever, innumerable<lb/>
letters of Major Reed to his family written from Camp Columbia in 1900 describing<lb/>
in intimate detail the day by day progress of the experiments; a few rare and im-<lb/>
portant letters written by Doctor Lazear to his wife describing his secret experi-<lb/>
ments which ended with his death; letters of Doctor Carroll to his wife, and copies<lb/>
of hundreds of <unclear>official</unclear> documents and reports concerning the conquest of yellow fever.<lb/>
I have Doctor Lazear's microscope used by him in Cuba, medals given to Major Reed,<lb/>
et cetera, et cetera.</p>
<p>To this collection should be added material copied or loaned by the<lb/>
families of Doctors Finlay, Delgado, and Agramonte as well as certain data in possession<lb/>
of the Rojas family (e.g. Doctor Rojas' day book identifying the Finca San Jose as<lb/>
the site of Camp Lazear). Thus we would have in fact a Cuban-American memorial.</p>
<p>In one corner of the main room I planned to have placed unobtrusively an<lb/>
attendant's desk and small display case where visitors would find souvenir booklets,<lb/>
photographs, postcards, et cetera, the possession of which would give them full in-<lb/>
formation on the significance of the memorial and the purchase of which souvenirs<lb/>
might add materially to the upkeep fund. On one end of the building, and adjacent<lb/>
to the main hall it would be well to have modest quarters in which the attendant or<lb/>
care-taker would live--a little apartment of perhaps four rooms, a parlor, a com-<lb/>
bination kitchen-dining room, a bedroom, and bath. Connected with the latter, but<lb/>
with entrance into the main hall, could be two small &ldquo;rest rooms&rdquo; for visitors.</p>
<p>Mr. Moran and I have examined and re-examined the Caseta itself with anxious<lb/>
eyes, wondering to what extent, if any, it could be preserved and repaired. I be-<lb/>
lieve Mr. Moran has been somewhat more pessimistic that I am. I have seen buildings<lb/>
in worse shape than that of the Caseta which were restored without too much dis-<lb/>
figuring or replacing of the original structure and it is my hopeful belief that,<lb/>
having stood the ravages of 47 years, including at least two tornadoes, the wood<lb/>
of the Caseta can be treated chemically to stop the action of termites and of decay<lb/>
so that it may be preserved as a visible shrine.</p>
<p>The additions to the original Caseta (the porch and extra rooms) should<lb/>
of course be removed, the adjacent trees out down. The original casement window<lb/>
(with sliding panel) on the left front as one views the Caseta has been made into<lb/>
a long &ldquo;French window.&rdquo; It should be closed up to resemble the original one remaining<lb/>
on the right end of the Caseta. When enclosed properly in the enveloping building<lb/>
I would surround the Caseta with a protecting rope on standards to prevent visitors<lb/>
from entering or damaging it. With the front and sides of the Caseta restored to<lb/>
their original appearance I would remove most of the rear wall, exposing the interior<lb/>
to the view of the visitors passing around to see it from the rear. The original<lb/>
wood removed from the rear wall could be used in part to fill up the enlarged front<lb/>
left window. The remainder of the original wood could be used perhaps to replace<lb/>
damaged irreparable wood. Whatever of the original wood cannot be salvaged or used<lb/>
should be carefully saved; out up into small pieces or plaques, suitably framed<lb/>
and labelled with small metal attachments this wood could provide quite a few sou-<lb/>
venirs which would be highly prized by historically minded individuals and institutions.<lb/>
(May I here speak for at least one of these for myself<unclear>!</unclear>)</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04144010"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>I would restore the interior with the appropriate number of beds, trunks<lb/>
and boxes for soiled bedding, chairs and a stove as in the original. (We have sev-<lb/>
eral accurate descriptions of the interior as it was in 1900.)</p>
<p>The approach to Camp Lazear should be improved by paving or otherwise im-<lb/>
proving the chief road now leading thereto which is, I believe, Calle Jose Miguel<lb/>
Gomez. Later another entrance should be made extending from Calle L. Valdes Carrera.<lb/>
The Camp site should be cleaned up, planted with <unclear>sed</unclear> and perhaps flowers. On the<lb/>
former site of &ldquo;Building Number Two&rdquo; (which was destroyed in the cyclone of 1926 but<lb/>
the exact location of which we know) should be erected a small stone or marble marker<lb/>
with a bronze plaque.</p>
<p>On the main wall surrounding the Finca San Jose somewhere between the<lb/>
present iron-grilled entrance gate and the corner of Calzada Real and Calle Jose<lb/>
Miguel Gomez should be placed a fairly large bronze tablet indicating the historic<lb/>
significance of the Finca San Jose and the adjacent Camp Lazear. This tablet, placed<lb/>
on the main street of Quemados, would attract and direct visitors to the Camp site<lb/>
behind the present Finca. As you now know the site across the La Playa railroad<lb/>
track adjacent to Camp Columbia (the site between this railroad track and what is<lb/>
now known as Calle San Carlos O Rene Berndes) which was formerly erroneously marked<lb/>
as the site of Camp Lazear was the site of four little yellow fever hospital shacks<lb/>
to which the victims of experimental yellow fever were taken from Camp Lazear to<lb/>
be cared for as soon as they developed their yellow fever. These little shacks had<lb/>
previously housed certain military personnel ill of natural yellow fever, such as<lb/>
General (then Major) J. R. Kean and others. It was in one of these little buildings<lb/>
that the martyr Lazear died. Therefore would it not be most fitting for the Cuban-<lb/>
American sponsors of this project to erect on this site an additional marker of<lb/>
modest size (stone or marble) with a bronze plaque indicating what happened there.<lb/>
This property already belongs to the Cuban government.</p>
<p>Doctor Andreu, in making further plans for these memorials may I ask you<lb/>
frankly the following questions?<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Will the Cuban Government be inclined to appropriate any funds to add<lb/>
to those I hope to raise here?</item>
<item>2. If the Cuban Government cannot do this, do you believe the Cuban<lb/>
medical profession would help raise funds to add to American contributions? Perhaps<lb/>
the Medical College of the City of Havana or the Colegio Medico Nacional would aid<lb/>
us in sponsoring the project.</item>
<item>3. Has Senor Macia signified his willingness to provide the camp site<lb/>
either at a suitable price or for a nominal fee as a contribution to the project?</item>
<item>4. Once the funds have been raised to erect the memorial building who<lb/>
will care for its upkeep and repairs? As a national monument will it be cared for<lb/>
by the Cuban Government or will it be necessary to raise private funds for its<lb/>
endowment or would the Cuban medical profession guarantee its care, especially if<lb/>
they do not have to contribute to the original funds?</item>
<item>5. What would be the approximate original cost at current Cuban prices<lb/>
of a little memorial building of the size and type I have outlined?</item>
<item>6. Does the Cuban Government have plans more ambitious than mine? Do<lb/>
they prefer a larger, more elaborate memorial, with the museum as merely a small<lb/>
part thereof, but the rest of a larger building to be used for other civic or social<lb/>
purposes?</item>
<item>7. Assuming we build only a small memorial as I have outlined, what would<lb/>
its upkeep cost in Havana: salary of attendant, repairs, gardening, et cetera?<lb/>
Would the upkeep cost over $4,000 annually? If the upkeep were not guaranteed by<lb/>
the government or by medical agencies it would be necessary now to raise a much<lb/>
larger sum than I had anticipated in order to create an endowment yielding $4,000-<lb/>
$5,000 a year. This is an important matter because there would be no sense for us<lb/>
to raise funds, erect a building and then allow it and its surroundings to run down<lb/>
for lack of care.</item>
</list></p>
<pb n="5" id="f04144011"/>
<p>- 5 -</p>
<p>If no agency is willing to assure the upkeep of a memorial building I be-<lb/>
lieve its erection would not be practicable. In this event the most that could be<lb/>
done now would be the beautification of the camp site, the improvement of the road<lb/>
leading thereto and the erection of four modest memorials consisting of stone or<lb/>
marble pediments with bronze tablets to be placed as follows: (1) on the wall of<lb/>
the Finca San Jose near the corner of Calzada Real and Calle Jose Miguel Gomez;<lb/>
(2) on the site of Building Number One (the remaining Caseta); (3) on the site of<lb/>
Building Number Two, and (4) on the site of the false &ldquo;Campamento Lazear&rdquo; where<lb/>
Doctor Lazear died. These four memorials would of course not cost very much, only<lb/>
a few thousand dollars, and would need a minimum of care. Certainly we must at least<lb/>
do this much<unclear>!</unclear></p>
<p>Without having some of this information at hand I cannot at this time<lb/>
guarantee that the Mayo Clinic or Foundation will renew their offer to contribute<lb/>
$10,000. Their offer, made in 1944, was, as I have said, contingent on the contribu-<lb/>
tions of others and especially on the interest and willingness of Cuban medical and<lb/>
governmental authorities to approve and join in the project or at least to accept it<lb/>
and protect it once it was donated. However, I feel fairly certain that the Mayo<lb/>
Clinic still looks with considerable favor on the project as they have a great ad-<lb/>
miration for Doctor Finlay and for Major Reed and his colleagues, as well as a great<lb/>
admiration for the Cuban people and medical profession. The governors of the Mayo<lb/>
Clinic have always been most sympathetic with my own historical investigations on<lb/>
the conquest of yellow fever. The physicians of the Mayo Clinic have welcomed many<lb/>
distinguished Cuban physicians and patients here.</p>
<p>I had hoped to come to Havana this spring for my vacation but found it<lb/>
impossible. Now that the Cuban Government has made the Caseta a national monument<lb/>
I am especially anxious to visit Havana to discuss with you and others the plans<lb/>
outlined. Perhaps a joint Cuban-American Memorial Committee should be formed to<lb/>
assure the early success of the project. Certainly immediate steps must be taken<lb/>
to protect the remains of the Caseta from wind and weather if we hope to preserve<lb/>
it. Even if the building cannot be erected for a year or so the Caseta should be<lb/>
temporarily covered with a strong wooden or galvanized iron <unclear>or/</unclear> other suitable pro-<lb/>
tection (roof and walls). I am sure that funds for such an immediate purpose would<lb/>
be available promptly.</p>
<p>As soon as I hear from you or your associates I will renew at once my<lb/>
efforts to raise an appropriate sum. Throughout all my investigations and dealings<lb/>
Mr. John Moran has been my invaluable advisor and helper. On many occasions he has<lb/>
kindly acted as my agent. He has shared my hopes and is fully aware of my plans and<lb/>
intentions. May I ask you to consult him as you may wish to know of my plans and<lb/>
motives. I can assure you I have no selfish or ulterior motive. I have just one<lb/>
idea--to honor <hi>all</hi> the conquerors of yellow fever, in particular Doctors Finlay and<lb/>
Delgado and Major Reed, his colleagues of the American Commission and their brave<lb/>
volunteers. In so doing I believe the Cuban and American medical professions can<lb/>
be joined in greater harmony to the end that an unfortunate and unhappy controversy<lb/>
can be forgotten. To this end I shall be delighted to give more time and effort.</p>
<p>Believe me,</p>
<closer>
<salute>sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
