<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04144001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Wilbur A. Sawyer, May 12, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04144001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-05-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Rockefeller, Jr., John D.</name>
<name type="person">Rockefeller, Nelson</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Finlay Institute, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-05-12">May 12, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04144001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Wilbur A. Sawyer, May 12, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Sawyer about his efforts to memorialize Camp Lazear Building No. 1. He believes this is an opportunity to forge Cuban-American bonds. The Cuban government supports this effort, and the Mayo Clinic has pledged a financial contribution. Through Sawyer, [Hench] hopes to contact the Rockefeller Foundation in order to solicit their financial support.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-05-12">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Wilbur A. Sawyer, May 12, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04144001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-05-12">May 12, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer<lb/>
49 West 49th Street<lb/>
New York, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Sawyer:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You may remember that I had the pleasure of meeting you in 1940 when<lb/>
you and I spoke at the dedication of the Lazear Memorial at Washington-Jefferson<lb/>
College. I do not want to presume on my brief acquaintanceship with you but I do<lb/>
need your help and would appreciate greatly your advice on the following matter.</p>
<p>You may remember that in 1939 and 1940 with the help of Johnny Moran<lb/>
(one of Walter Reed's guinea pigs) I rediscovered the lost Camp Lazear on the out-<lb/>
skirts of Havana and found still remaining one of Walter Reed's experimental build-<lb/>
ings--Building No. 1. It was my hope at that time to raise a modest amount of<lb/>
money to enclose the building in a permanent protection and present it to the Cuban<lb/>
Government. I had certain preliminary conversations with representatives of the<lb/>
Cuban Government who were enthusiastic (?) about my suggestions and promised their<lb/>
help. At first there was some opposition on the part of certain old-timers such<lb/>
as the Finlay Institute and others to accept the identification of Camp Lazear but<lb/>
Doctor Ramos, having asked me to submit a formal report, finally accepted this re-<lb/>
port which is now filed in the Library of the Finlay Institute. In 1940 and 1941<lb/>
I received letters from representatives of the Cuban Government indicating that<lb/>
they had indeed accepted the authenticity of the site and the little shack.</p>
<p>Then came the war and my entrance into military service. In 1942 one<lb/>
of the ranking Members of the Department of Sanitation of Cuba wrote me saying that<lb/>
the Government was about to become genuinely interested in my plans to preserve<lb/>
the site; but, after some correspondence from me, the matter was dropped. You know<lb/>
the Cuban attitude of &ldquo;manana.&rdquo; To make a long story short, at long last the Cuban<lb/>
Government has finally acted to make the shack a &ldquo;national monument.&rdquo; I have had<lb/>
some correspondence from Johnny Moran and they finally seem quite interested and<lb/>
excited about the project.</p>
<p>My original intentions and plans were modest. I had hoped to receive<lb/>
perhaps ten thousand dollars from the Mayo Clinic and perhaps a similar amount from<lb/>
the Rockefeller Foundation or a member of the Rockefeller family who might be in-<lb/>
terested and willing to join in plans for a modest memorial. In 1942 the Mayo Clinic<lb/>
did promise me that amount contingent on our raising other funds and contingent on<lb/>
the promise of the Cuban Government to join with us in this venture, preferably to<lb/>
add an equal amount to what the Americans give and to see to it that, after the<lb/>
little memorial building was erected, it would be properly taken care of by the<lb/>
Government.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04144002"/>
<p>Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>May 12, 1947</p>
<p>Now to the point of this letter. Do you believe that Mr. John D.<lb/>
Rockefeller, Jr. or a member of his family would be willing to join the Mayo Clinic<lb/>
in starting the American part of the fund? I see no hopes of having the American<lb/>
Government do anything and I have no interest in trying to collect nickels.<lb/>
I do not know whether the Rockefeller Foundation would be able or willing to make<lb/>
a contribution but certainly the Rockefeller Foundation, by its long interest in<lb/>
the problem of yellow fever and through its many contacts with Latin America, would<lb/>
be one of the institutions expected to be interested in such a project.</p>
<p>My motives in this matter are entirely unselfish. You are entirely<lb/>
familiar with the unpleasant controversy as to the respective merits of Finlay and<lb/>
Reed. By great good fortune it happens that on the very farm (part of which be-<lb/>
came Camp Lazear) Finlay himself had done two or three of his inoculations years<lb/>
before so that the San Jos&eacute; Farm is most happily related both to Finlay and Reed.<lb/>
By raising a suitable amount of American money for a modest &ldquo;Cuban-American Medi-<lb/>
cal Memorial&rdquo; I believe we can heal the wounds and do much to stop this acrimonious<lb/>
and undegnified debate. It would not surprise you I am sure to know that there<lb/>
was a certain element in Cuba which was inclined to blame the Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
in part for <del>ignoring giving</del><add><unclear>WITHHOLDING</unclear></add> credit <del>to</del><add>DUE</add> Finlay. I am not mentioning this in an<lb/>
attempt to influence the Rockefeller Foundation or any member of the Rockefeller<lb/>
family but I am stating it as a fact and because of it it would be just all the more<lb/>
gracious and appropriate if the Rockefeller family could join the Mayo Foundation<lb/>
or Mayo Clinic in such a gesture of Cuban-American good-will.</p>
<p>Recently I was made a Member of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association and gave the enclosed report to them last October. This out-<lb/>
lines the background and purposes of my project.</p>
<p>I expect to be in New York for three days from June 12th to 14th inclusive<lb/>
just after the Meeting of the American Medical Association. Is there any possibility<lb/>
that I might be able to meet, through you, Mr. Rockefeller or one of his agents to<lb/>
explain in more detail my project. I would promise to make the interview a short<lb/>
one. About two years ago when I was still in the army, friends suggested that the<lb/>
United States Government's Department of Pan-American Cultural Relations might be<lb/>
interested in this project--indeed it was suggested that this was &ldquo;right up their<lb/>
alley.&rdquo; Therefore Surgeon General Kirk made an appointment for me to see Mr. Nelson<lb/>
Rockefeller. Our interview was brief as, unfortunately, he had to tell me that his<lb/>
department was folding up. I made no attempt to interest him personally.</p>
<p>May I state that within the last two weeks I have had two letters from the<lb/>
heads of two government departments of Cuba expressing hope that my interest in<lb/>
this project has been maintained. I have been told that the President of Cuba (him-<lb/>
self a doctor) is greatly interested in the project and I have been lead to believe<lb/>
that, if and when the matter is completed, the Cuban Government will participate<lb/>
actively in the dedication and that the President of Cuba would be on hand with ap-<lb/>
propriate ceremonies, etcetera, etcetera. I do know that when I was introduced<lb/>
to President Batista four years ago he personally promised to do what he could and<lb/>
to be at the dedication ceremony if and when the affair materialized.</p>
<p>Pardon me for making this letter such a lengthy one but it is not a matter<lb/>
that I could discuss in a paragraph or two. I have no other possible contacts with<lb/>
the Rockefeller Foundation or Rockefeller family and would greatly appreciate either<lb/>
your direct help or such advice as you could give me. (Perhaps the current costs of<lb/>
such a memorial would necessite a larger sum).</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alp<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04144003"/>
Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
May 12, 1947<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. You will note in the enclosed photostat of a recent newspaper clipping which<lb/>
Johnny Moran sent me that the Cuban newspaper persisted in misinterpreting the facts<lb/>
about Camp Lazear and the &ldquo;Little Building No. 1.&rdquo; The heading of the newspaper<lb/>
photograph refers to the little building as the place where Finlay (not Reed) did<lb/>
his work. This, of course, we can straighten out and my recent letters from the<lb/>
Cuban officials indicate that they understand fully the nature of the little build-<lb/>
ing.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
