<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04201020">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Ray Sweeney to Hal R. Keeling, January 23, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Sweeney, Ray</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04201020</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-01-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Keeling, Hal R.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-01-23">January 23, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04201020</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Ray Sweeney to Hal R. Keeling, January 23, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Sweeney reports to Keeling on the material he has found concerning Reed's presentation, in 1900, to the American Public Health Association meeting, in Indianapolis.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1948-01-23">
<head>Memorandum from Ray Sweeney to Hal R. Keeling, January 23, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04201020"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-01-23">January 23, 1948</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Memorandum to Hal Keeling</p>
<p>Here's my report on the Walter Reed research:</p>
<p>PHOTOGRAPHS:</p>
<p>Attached are two photos of the old German House, now known as the Athen-<lb/>
aeum, procured from original negatives owned by W. H. Bass Photo Company,<lb/>
308 South New Jersey Street. The shots were taken, as marked on the backs,<lb/>
in 1905 and 1907. This was as close as I could get to the 1900 date. The<lb/>
Indianapolis News showed me several shots of unknown date that looked just<lb/>
a bit older, but they were in pretty poor shape to be reproduced.</p>
<p>There is available from Dr. Thurman B. Rice, 3167 North Delaware, a small<lb/>
cut of the room at the Athenaeum in which Dr. Reed delivered his report.<lb/>
It's 2 1/4 by 3 1/4 in size and is used in Dr. Rice's biography of Dr. J. N. Hurty<lb/>
titled: &ldquo;The Hoosier Health Officer&rdquo;. The caption on this picture in the<lb/>
book is: &ldquo;It was in this room that Walter Reed read his paper. The room<lb/>
was used for many years since as the meeting place of the Marion County<lb/>
Medical Society&rdquo;. It is not an extremely good photo for reproduction, but<lb/>
shouldn't be too bad. The shot is from the back of an auditorium with rows<lb/>
of seats to left and right, a small stage in front. Dr. Rice's secretary<lb/>
says she will gladly loan the cut, which is now stored in the doctor's<lb/>
basement.</p>
<p>REFERENCE BOOKS:</p>
<p>REPORTS AND PAPERS OF THE AMERICAN PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION, VOLUME XXVI,<lb/>
pages 37 thru 53, a book available at the Indiana State Library which can-<lb/>
not be removed from the premises. This contains &ldquo;The Etiology of Yellow<lb/>
Fever -- a Preliminary Note,&rdquo; by Drs. Reed, Carroll, Agramonte and Lazear<lb/>
as well as the entire proceedings, including discussions (apparently there<lb/>
were none on the Reed paper) of the Indianapolis meeting in 1900.</p>
<p>REPORTS AND PAPERS OF THE AMERICAN PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION, VOLUME XXVIII,<lb/>
page 375. This contains a report of the 30th annual meeting of the American<lb/>
Public Health Association (Indianapolis was 28th) at New Orleans in 1902.<lb/>
The proceedings at the morning session, December 12, contain a resolution<lb/>
on the death of Reed. A nice eulogy - five paragraphs long. Book can't<lb/>
be removed from Library.</p>
<p>INDIANA MEDICAL JOURNAL, OCTOBER, NOVEMBER ISSUES, 1900. October issue<lb/>
contains an editorial calling the Association meeting in Indianapolis an<lb/>
important event, says city will be hospitable, gives the street car routes<lb/>
to various meeting places. Not much interesting information, in all.</p>
<p>November issue contains a general report on the meeting, including some<lb/>
wordage on the Reed paper. This, however, is taken word for word from<lb/>
the account in the Indianapolis &ldquo;Journal&rdquo; of October 24, 1900.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04201021"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>&ldquo;THE HOOSIER HEALTH OFFICER;&rdquo; a biography of Dr. J. N. Hurty, by Thurman<lb/>
B. Rice, M. D. I have this book out of the State Library on a card. It<lb/>
contains this reference to Dr. Reed on page 114:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Up to this time nothing had been found to be of any benefit in combating<lb/>
the dread yellow scourge, but better times were in the offing. In October,<lb/>
1900, the American Public Health Association met at Indianapolis. Much<lb/>
discussion of the Sanarelli organism was arranged for the regular program<lb/>
of the meeting, but there was a surprise paper which was to become one of<lb/>
the really great medical classics of all time.</p>
<p>A young army surgeon who had been assigned to leadership in the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Commission came rushing in record time from headquarters in Cuba<lb/>
to give his preliminary report on a new line of attack on the problem.<lb/>
He was given a place on the platform though his paper was not on the<lb/>
official program of the session. At the afternoon session of October 23,<lb/>
1900, he spoke to about 150 physicians present in the old German House<lb/>
(now the Athenaeum) at the intersection of Michigan and Alabama Streets.<lb/>
The Indianapolis News of the following day has this to say of the event:</p>
<p>Surgeon Walter Reed, of the United States Army, who was sent to Cuba to<lb/>
make a personal investigation of the yellow fever scourge, received per-<lb/>
mission to read his paper, &ldquo;Some Observations on the Yellow Fever in Cuba.&rdquo;<lb/>
The article was listened to with absorbing interest and the surgeon was<lb/>
thanked by the Association.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;Monthly Bulletin&rdquo; of the Indiana State Board of Health for October,<lb/>
1900, gives a synopsis of the papers and the meetings but makes no men-<lb/>
tion of a paper by Walter Reed. That Hurty failed to realize the signif-<lb/>
icance of this paper is further shown by the fact that no mention is made<lb/>
in the Annual Report distributed a year later even though he did go into<lb/>
considerable detail to tell of the meeting of the American Public Health<lb/>
Association of the year before (1900). He does have the following to say<lb/>
concerning the yellow fever, however (pp. 444-445):</p>
<p>Yellow fever. -- This subject came up for consideration before the general<lb/>
sessions of the Association. It should be our duty to find out if the<lb/>
Sanarelli bacillus is the organism accompanying this disease. The speaker<lb/>
regarded the question as still open. It may belong to the &ldquo;hog cholera<lb/>
group.&rdquo;</p>
<p>On page 457 of the Annual Report (1901) there are other references to<lb/>
papers having to do with the etiology of yellow fever, but still no ref-<lb/>
erence to Walter Reed or his epoch-making work. It will be seen from<lb/>
this that those hearing the paper had no appreciation of its vast impor-<lb/>
tance. As one reads the accounts of the time he is impressed with the<lb/>
fact that the work of Sanarelli was much better received.</p>
<p>A synopsis of Dr. Reed's original paper and its conclusions is given:</p>
<p>The Etiology of Yellow Fever: A Preliminary Report by Reed, Carroll,<lb/>
Agramonte and Lazear. (Trans. A. P. H. A. 1900, pp. 37-53.)</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04201022"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>First: The work of Sanarelli was checked. No evidence was found that<lb/>
B. icteroides is responsible for the disease. The germ was not found in<lb/>
any of the cases examined, nor in any of the eleven cadavers dead of the<lb/>
disease.</p>
<p>Second: The work of Dr. Carlos Finlay was checked. As early as 1881 he<lb/>
had insisted that the mosquito was the vector. Also checked the work of<lb/>
Dr. Henry R. Carter, who had noted a set interval of time between the<lb/>
first case in a community and the secondary cases.</p>
<p>Third: Dr. Reed gives the details of the story, now so well known, and<lb/>
describes in detail the case of Dr. James Carroll, who was voluntarily<lb/>
inoculated by permitting himself to be bitten by a mosquito which had<lb/>
previously bitten a known case. Dr. Carroll developed tropical yellow<lb/>
fever but recovered. He also tells the story of the case of Dr. Jesse<lb/>
Lazear, who likewise was bitten and who died of the disease -- a glorious<lb/>
martyr to science, medicine and the welfare of mankind.</p>
<p>Conclusions: &lsquo;(1) Bacillus icteroides (Sanarelli) stands in no causative<lb/>
relation to yellow fever, but when present should be considered as a sec-<lb/>
ondary invader in this disease. (2) The mosquito serves as the intermed-<lb/>
iate host for the parasite of yellow fever.&rsquo;"</p>
<p>NEWSPAPERS<lb/>
&ldquo;STAR&rdquo;</p>
<p>Here is the story (front page) from the Indianapolis &ldquo;Star&rdquo;, October 12,<lb/>
1933 on the memorial banquet held to celebrate the Reed talk in 1900.<lb/>
It was headlined: &ldquo;Health Leaders Honor Heroes of Fever Conquest&rdquo; and<lb/>
the lead was largely about four men -- one of them a Hoosier -- who were<lb/>
the guests of honor. As the story picks up ...</p>
<p>"They were among the 21 men who voluntarily submitted themselves to in-<lb/>
noculation with the yellow fever agent carried by the mosquito, to assist<lb/>
Dr. Walter Reed, deceased, of the United States Army, to whose memory<lb/>
tribute was paid by those attending the dinner.</p>
<p>Several of the speakers pointed out that it was 33 years ago this month<lb/>
that Major Reed, in a paper read before the same association in a con-<lb/>
vention in Indianapolis, successfully routed opponents who contended that<lb/>
the fever was transmitted by something other than the mosquito...</p>
<p>... The reading of the honor roll by Dr. King at the banquet followed a<lb/>
complete account of the work of Major Reed and his associates in proving<lb/>
definitely that the mosquito was the carrier of the transmitting agent.<lb/>
Those who traced his work last night were Major General Robert U. Patterson,<lb/>
Surgeon General of the U.S. Army, and General Frederick F. Russell, direc-<lb/>
tor of the international health division, Rockefeller Foundation, New York ...</p>
<p>... Had it not been for the work of Major Reed and his colleagues, Dr.<lb/>
Pratt said, yellow fever deaths during the World War would have numbered<lb/>
500,000 instead of the 1,500 who fell victims to the disease ...</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04201023"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>... Hundreds of messages paying tribute to Major Reed were received from<lb/>
Army officers and civilians from all parts of the country. There was a<lb/>
storm of applause when Dr. John A. Farrell, retiring president, read the<lb/>
following letter from President Roosevelt:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have just learned that your association will hold a memorial session<lb/>
to Dr. Walter Reed on Wednesday evening, October 11, 1933 at Indianapolis.<lb/>
This nation today shares with the world untold benefits to human health<lb/>
resulting from the monumental work of Dr. Walter Reed, United States Army.<lb/>
In definitely establishing the fact that the mosquito is the transmitting<lb/>
agency of yellow fever, he earned the gratitude of humanity. I take great<lb/>
pleasure in joining you in honoring the memory of this great American.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;TIMES&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Indianapolis &ldquo;Times&rdquo; of October 12, 1933 has a page 4 story headed<lb/>
&ldquo;Public Health Workers Honor Dr. W. F. King&rdquo; which is just a short version<lb/>
of the Star coverage, except the Times refers to the <hi>18</hi> men who submitted<lb/>
to the yellow fever tests in Cuba.</p>
<p>&ldquo;NEWS&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Indianapolis &ldquo;News&rdquo;, October 12, 1933, carried a second-day-lead story<lb/>
headed &ldquo;Health Groups Turn to Hygiene&rdquo;. There is no mention of Reed.</p>
<p>RANDOM FACT ON GERMAN HOUSE: the real estate was purchased in 1892 (135'<lb/>
by 203') at the corner of New Jersey and Michigan streets. Ground was<lb/>
broken in 1893 for the first of the buildings. It was completed in '94.<lb/>
The other buildings of the group were finished in '97 and '98.</p>
<p>I have tried, without success, to locate any witnesses to Dr. Reed's talk.<lb/>
Dr. Thurman Rice doesn't seem to feel that there are any of them still<lb/>
around. Several other doctors contacted believe there might be and sug-<lb/>
gest the name of some old-timer they know. However, the old-timer says<lb/>
no and suggests an older-timer. More work could be done on this phase of<lb/>
the problem, however -- a lot of people have names to suggest.</p>
<p>Where Reed stayed in Indianapolis is a complete mystery -- no progress<lb/>
at all.</p>
<p>As for Dr. Hench's inquiry on &ldquo;lower auditorium&rdquo; vs. &ldquo;amphitheater&rdquo; --<lb/>
I think we can safely assume they are the same. I note that Dr. Rice, in<lb/>
his book, calls it a &ldquo;room&rdquo; but the room pictured is obviously an auditor-<lb/>
ium.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Ray Sweeney</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
