<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04205005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, February 10, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Siler, J.F.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04205005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-02-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Hagedorn, Hermann</name>
<name type="place">Washington Barracks, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-02-10">February 10, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04205005</idno>
<title>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, February 10, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Siler discusses the location of the room where Walter Reed died. Siler knows that Hench wants to check on information contained in Hagedorn's biography of Wood and promises to arrange a meeting with McCoy.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-02-10">
<head>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, February 10, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04205005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
1835 EYE STREET, NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1948-02-10">February 10, 1948</date>

</dateline>
EXECUTIVE OFFICES<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am just in receipt of a letter from General Truby relative to the location of<lb/>
the room in the hospital at Washington Barracks in which Walter Reed died. He had<lb/>
received the plans showing the location of the room insofar as could be determined from<lb/>
the present layout. He apparently thinks the exact location of the <unclear>room</unclear> has not yet<lb/>
been worked out and should be gone into more fully. As requested by him, I am sending<lb/>
you a copy of the letter he has written me concerning this matter. I am also to send<lb/>
copies to the Commanding Officer at Ft. McNair, Gen. Kean and Gen. Lawrence Reed.</p>
<p>Truby advises me that you will be in Washington next week and I am holding up the<lb/>
copies which are to be sent to the CO at Ft. McNair, Gen. Kean and Gen. Lawrence Reed<lb/>
until after your arrival here and we have had a chance to discuss the matter a bit.</p>
<p>The letter referred to above was dated February 4th and in the same mail yesterday<lb/>
I received an air mail letter from Gen. Truby under date of February 7th in which he en-<lb/>
closed a copy of your letter of January 9th written to Gen. Kean. Gen. Truby has incor-<lb/>
porated a number of comments on the copy of your letter to Gen. Kean which I will show you<lb/>
on your arrival in Washington next week. Your letter of Gen. Kean relates to the question<lb/>
of Major Reed's being transferred from Havana before his work could be completed and the<lb/>
steps taken by Gen. Wood to have him remain in Cuba to complete his work. I gather from<lb/>
your letter that you desire to check on this information and other information contained<lb/>
in Hagedorn's biography of Gen. Leonard Wood and that you feel that it might be possible<lb/>
to secure additional trustworthy information from Gen. McCoy. Gen. Truby asked me to look<lb/>
into the matter and find out where Gen. McCoy is living and whether it would be possible<lb/>
for you to get in touch with him.</p>
<p>Fortunately, Gen. McCoy lives here in Washington. He is connected with the State<lb/>
Department in the Far Eastern Commission. I talked to him by telephone last night and<lb/>
told him of your desire to consult him concerning this matter. He assured me that he<lb/>
would be glad to see you although he said his memory now is a bit hazy since, of course,<lb/>
all these things happened forty or fifty years ago. Gen. McCoy lives out in Georgetown<lb/>
but has an office in the old Japanese Embassy on Massachusetts Avenue. I have made a<lb/>
tentative appointment for him to see you when you are in Washington next week. He said<lb/>
that it would be very much more convenient for him to see you during the week between<lb/>
Monday and Friday, except on Tuesday and Thursday on which days he has special confer-<lb/>
ences which he must attend. I have known Gen. McCoy for a great many years and served<lb/>
with him in the Philippines when I was a member of the commission <unclear>stuying</unclear> the means<lb/>
of the transmission of dengue fever when Gen. Wood was Governor General. He is a fine<lb/>
character and I know that he will be delighted to give you any help within his power.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04205006"/>
<p>GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED</p>
<p>1835 EYE STREET, NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6, D. C.</p>
<p>EXECUTIVE OFFICES</p>
<p>We have been having terrible weather here in Washington and it has been very dif-<lb/>
ficult to get around. On top of that I am just recovering from a cold. I am hoping<lb/>
that the snow will be gone and that I will be able to see you next week.</p>
<p>As soon as the weather clears up a bit more, I will go and see Gen. Kean and show<lb/>
him all these letters from Truby.</p>
<p>With best regards, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Faithfully yours,</salute>
<signed>J. F. Siler<lb/>
Col. U.S.A., Retired</signed>
jfs k<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
