<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04204001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Interview with Frank R. McCoy, by Philip Showalter Hench, February 19, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04204001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-02-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Root, Elihu</name>
<name type="person">Hagedorn, Hermann</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-02-19">February 19, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04204001</idno>
<title>Interview with Frank R. McCoy, by Philip Showalter Hench, February 19, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>McCoy, aide to Governor-General Leonard Wood during the yellow fever experiments, comments on Wood's dismissal of the importance of Finlay's mosquito work, Wood's intervention with Surgeon General Sternberg to keep Reed's work going, and the location and arrangement of Wood's offices. McCoy stresses Wood's strong support of Reed and his work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1948-02-19">
<head>Interview with Frank R. McCoy, by Philip Showalter Hench, February 19, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04204001"/>
<p><hi>Interview with Gen. Frank M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy, Washington, D C</hi><lb/>
Feb 19, 1948 by P. S. Hench</p>


<p>Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy was a lieutenant in the Spanish-American War and became<lb/>
Gen. Wood's aide in May 1900. Wood had <unclear>became</unclear> Governor-General<lb/>
in Dec 1899.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1 I asked Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy if he recollected when or if Finlay saw Gen Wood<lb/>
(see Eric F Wood's book - p 196 bottom - 197 top). It was Gen. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy's<lb/>
recollection that Dr Finlay actually did call on Wood almost as soon<lb/>
as Wood arrived to become Gov-Gen. Wood had had a high<lb/>
regard for Finlay as a man and as a physician but not as a<lb/>
<unclear>scientist.</unclear> Indeed Wood believed that Finlay's work had practically<lb/>
resulted in <hi>disproving</hi> (not proving) his (Finlay's) theory.</item>
<item><p>2 according to Hagedorn (Biography of Leonard Wood - Harper's 1931,<lb/>
vol 1 p 332) &ldquo;<unclear>Twice</unclear> indeed the investigation (Reed's) had nearly<lb/>
been stopped by orders from the Surgeon General who needed<lb/>
his doctors and felt that too much time had already been<lb/>
wasted but each time Wood had intervened and saved the<lb/>
Commission&rdquo; (M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy from the S. G; 1929).</p>
<p>Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy has the distinct <unclear>remembrance</unclear> that Gen. Sternberg<lb/>
tried at least twice to recall Reed (in addition to the one time<lb/>
Reed <hi>was</hi> recalled to finish the Typhoid Fever Investigation). M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy<lb/>
believes Sternberg tried to recall Reed early in the summer of 1900,<lb/>
(apparently earlier than Reed's return <unclear>in</unclear> early Aug 1900). on this<lb/>
occasion, <del>Wood <unclear>interviewed</unclear></del> at the instigation of Reed, Wood<lb/>
intervened <unclear>e</unclear> the S. G. (probably by letter or telegram - Wood to<lb/>
Sternberg, possibly of a more or less personal letter as Wood was<lb/>
corresponding <del>almost</del> daily with various Washington people).<lb/>
In this case Reed's recall was stopped.</p>
<p>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy <del><unclear>believes</unclear></del> recalls that later <del>(perhaps Sept-Oct 1900)</del><lb/>
in the summer (sometime in Oct?) the S G again wanted Reed to<lb/>
return to Wash for some &ldquo;routine project.&rdquo; This time Wood had<lb/>
to intervene <unclear>with Secr.</unclear> of War Root to get the S. G. to let Reed<lb/>
alone. Wood had become much impressed with Reed's work<lb/>
and became annoyed that Sternberg should want to recall<lb/>
Reed for routine duties.</p></item>
<pb n="2" id="f04204002"/>
<item>(2</item>
<item>3 M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy says Hagedorn lives in New York City. (Hermann Hagedorn,<lb/>
Roosevelt Memorial assoc., Roosevelt House, 28 E 20th St., New York, 3, N Y.)</item>
<item><p>4 M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy located Gen Wood's offices as comprising one large room<lb/>
on the south front of the bldg; second floor, with 3 large front<lb/>
windows (as formerly located for me of Gen Kean &amp; as marked with<lb/>
an arrow in old photo (S C 113632). Wood's desk was in the<lb/>
center of the room with Wood's chair facing (west) away from the<lb/>
<unclear>windows</unclear> (Wood's back to the center of the 3 window's</p>
<p>(Ask Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy to draw rough plan of this 2nd floor front)<lb/>
When the Cuban's renovated the building between the first &amp;<lb/>
second U. S. Interventions they removed the <unclear>stucco</unclear> (seen in 1900<lb/>
photos) &amp; exposed the old underlying stone walls (as seen in<lb/>
recent <del>current</del> National Geographic Magazine photos of the old<lb/>
bldg (now the City Hall, Havana).</p>
<p>In Gen. Wood's tenure of the office there were no actual<lb/>
doors (in the <unclear>door</unclear> spaces or passage ways) between Wood's<lb/>
office &amp; the halls. The door shown in the army photo<lb/>
(S C 107499) (showing Gen <unclear>Magoun in</unclear> Wood's old office)<lb/>
was not there in Wood's day. (See Wood photo - Hagedorn p 171;<del>)</del> in<lb/>
this photo Wood faces the light, apparently the windows)</p></item>
<item><p>5 I discussed with Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy the item in Hagedorn<lb/>
(vol 1, p 281) where Wood is credited with having urged<lb/>
the S. G (Sternberg) to <unclear>appoint</unclear> the Yellow Fever Commission,<lb/>
Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy believes that Wood undoubtedly did this &amp; that he<lb/>
also suggested to Sternberg who should be on the Board.<lb/>
According to M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy the Surgeon Generals part in the formation<lb/>
(and support) of the Yellow Fever Board was rather passive<lb/>
&amp; secondary, not active &amp; primary. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy believes that<lb/>
Wood's chief role in the formation of the Y. F board can be<lb/>
documented by reviewing Wood's file of personal letters<lb/>
&amp; Woods diary, all of which were <unclear>Kept</unclear> of Wood &amp;<lb/>
left to the Congressional Library. They <unclear>constitute</unclear> &ldquo;The Wood<lb/>
Papers&rdquo; &amp; are a special collection available <add>only</add> to accredited<lb/>
historians &amp; researchers. Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy promised to ask<lb/>
the permission of Gen. Wood's daughter (<unclear>Louise</unclear> Wood) for me<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04204003"/>
(3<lb/>
to study these data, which are under control of Dr <unclear>Sions</unclear> att,<lb/>
Curator of these data (Di. St. George to <unclear>Sionesat</unclear>, Chief of Manuscripts, Division,<lb/>
Reference <unclear>Dept</unclear>, Library of Congress.).</p>
<p>The rest of Wood's voluminous records would have been filed<lb/>
with the War Dept under &ldquo;Records of the Military Governor of<lb/>
Cuba&rdquo; (They should be in the Archives Bldg).</p></item>
<item>6 Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy was not at the Dec 22, 1900 banquet for<lb/>
Finlay at <unclear>Delmonico's</unclear> restaurant, did not<lb/>
know the restaurant &amp; believed that it was not one of the<lb/>
prominent restaurants,</item>
<item>7 The photo labelled &ldquo;Wood in his office in Havana&rdquo;<lb/>
in <unclear>Holmes'</unclear> &ldquo;Life of Leonard Wood. (Double day, Page &amp; Co 1920)<lb/>
p 116 is <unclear><hi>not</hi></unclear> of Wood's office in Havana but of Wood's<lb/>
office in Santiago &amp; the other <unclear>man</unclear> in the photo is<lb/>
Ramon Mendoza (rank?) who was then Wood's aide in<lb/>
Santiago.</item>
<item>8 Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy urges me to look up John Kendrick <unclear>Bang's</unclear><lb/>
book &ldquo;Uncle Sam, Trustee&rdquo; which contains much on Wood.</item>
<item>9 Mr. V. <unclear>Swann</unclear>, a clerk in Wood's office in 1900 still live<lb/>
in Havana &amp; can be reached through Ing. (Engineer) Jose<lb/>
Garcia <unclear>Inerantz</unclear>, Tel U 7445, Apartado, P. O. Box<lb/>
404, Havana, Cuba.</item>
<item>10. The Maestranza (&ldquo;<unclear>arsenal</unclear>&rdquo; in Spanish) was in Spanish days<lb/>
an <unclear>artillery</unclear> Depot. In this old building Gorgas had his<lb/>
headquarters, also here <unclear>were</unclear> the apartments (quarters) of<lb/>
the Headquarters Staff. (Wood's Staff &amp; aides) - Scott, chief of<lb/>
Staff; Bliss, Gorgas, Black, Greble, M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy. They had their<lb/>
own mess there <unclear>also</unclear>.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f04204004"/>
<item>(4</item>
<item><p>11) according to Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy Gen. Wood left Havana for the U S. early in<lb/>
the summer of 1900. Reed and his colleagues often came in to Woods office<lb/>
for one thing or another, chiefly for money. Wood had told Lt. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy, his<lb/>
aide, that Reed was to have whatever he needed. But when Reed asked<lb/>
for this &amp; that amount of money, M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy became disturbed. He (M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy)<lb/>
was trying hard to keep track of all expenses, cut out <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
useless expenditures etc &amp; he wasnt certain just how much<lb/>
financial assistance Wood really meant Reed to have.<lb/>
on one early occasion (date?) when Reed wanted money<lb/>
M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy temporarily refused, &amp; wrote <del>Wood</del> (telegraphed?)<lb/>
Wood for clarification of his (Wood's) attitude toward Reed's<lb/>
expenses. <unclear>Back</unclear> came Wood's order to give Reed <hi>all</hi> he<lb/>
wanted. <del><unclear>Thereaf</unclear></del> Thereafter M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy did so. (M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy was, of<lb/>
course, not a <unclear>player</unclear> &amp; didnt appreciate the significance<lb/>
of Reed's work).</p>
<p>According to M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy, Gen Wood was increasingly impressed<lb/>
of Reed's results &amp; never let anything interfere with <del>the</del> its<lb/>
successful accomplishment. As matters progressed Wood<lb/>
would repeatedly evaluate Reeds work as of the very<lb/>
greatest importance.</p>
<p>On Oct 9, 1900 which was Wood's birthday Wood forgot it<lb/>
was his birthday, His wife had left Havana for the U. S &amp;<lb/>
Wood was &ldquo;alone&rdquo; in Havana. At the end of the day when the<lb/>
offices were closed &amp; the aides &amp; staff had left Wood suddenly<lb/>
remembered it was his birthday &amp; called his staff &amp; aides<lb/>
about 5 P M &amp; asked them to dine with him at 8 P M<lb/>
to <del>celebrate</del> help him celebrate. But when they all arrived<lb/>
(only men?) Wood was elated. After the dinner had progressed<lb/>
he said to his staff something as follows: &ldquo;I've been in<lb/>
communication with Dr Reed. My birthday gives me an excuse to<lb/>
gather you together with me here &amp; I want to announce the tremendous<lb/>
importance of Reed's discoveries. I want you all to know of them<lb/>
&amp; their significance. This is a most important thing. . --&rdquo;</p>
<p>Then Wood went on to tell them that Reed believed the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04204005"/>
(5<lb/>
cause of Y. F had actually been discovered, --- etc.<lb/>
(For further details of this story see Hagedorn vol 1, p 326).<lb/>
Ask Gen M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy for further details. He believes that Gen (Maj) Kean<lb/>
was at this birthday dinner (check with Gen Kean).</p></item>
<item>12.) Gen. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy's office is at 2516 Massachusetts Ave.,<lb/>
(Old Japanese Embassy). He is <del>chief</del> chairman of the<lb/>
Far Eastern Commission. (Telephone Extension 3141)<lb/>
Miss Porter is his secretary.</item>
<item>13) see Hagedorn's book for further references to <hi>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy</hi><lb/>
vol 1 - 175 - 178 - 276 - <hi>293</hi> - 313 - <hi>314</hi> - 352 - 371 - 391</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
