<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04205007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to J.F. Siler, February 4, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04205007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-02-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Siler, J.F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">Washington Barracks, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-02-04">February 4, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04205007</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to J.F. Siler, February 4, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby discusses the location of the room where Walter Reed died. Truby requested and received floor plans from the commanding officer of Washington Barracks, where Reed died. However, they do not conform with his memory. Truby feels that he cannot make any positive statement as to the exact location of the room unless they unearth something to solve this discrepancy.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-02-04">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to J.F. Siler, February 4, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04205007"/>
<opener>
copy<lb/>
<dateline>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco 18, Calif.<lb/>
<date value="1948-02-04">February 4, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Col. J. F. Siler, Ret'd.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Siler:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Dr. Hench has sent me copies of his letters to you about the room at the<lb/>
old General Hospital at Washington Barracks in which Major Walter Reed died.<lb/>
So, under separate cover, I am sending you the floor plans (2nd floor) which<lb/>
the Commanding Officer sent at my request. Dr. Hench is to be in Washington<lb/>
about the middle of this month and I feel sure he will promptly get in touch<lb/>
with you and will want to see this letter and the plans.</p>
<p>The plans are not dated and certainly do not conform to my memory of the<lb/>
second floor as it was when Major Reed died in 1902. He was in a private<lb/>
room, about 12 X 15 feet, and but one bed. No such small private room exists<lb/>
in the plans we have. The entrance of Reed's room was near the end of the<lb/>
hallway as you go back towards the west from the landing at the top of the<lb/>
stairs. (See Dr. Hench's sketch of the rooms as they now exist.)</p>
<p>As stated above, there is no small private room in the plans of the entire<lb/>
second floor. I am quite confident that General Kean will remember that<lb/>
Major Reed was in a <hi>small private room</hi> on the second floor of the old General<lb/>
Hospital, now Building 56B. Personally, I am certain of those points. Both<lb/>
Kean and I also know that Reed died in that building.</p>
<p>Only one explanation occurs to me - that as Major Borden's surgical activities<lb/>
increased, the greater part of the second floor was changed and larger rooms<lb/>
(spare wards) were made so that more patients could be accomodated in the<lb/>
small building. Now, if those changes were made late in 1902, or after that,<lb/>
I would still be hopeful that the problem can be solved for it is quite<lb/>
probable that the original plan of the building as a Post Hospital can be<lb/>
found. If so, I am sure that the rooms would be small, about the size of<lb/>
those shown in the plans of the apartments as they are today. Then there<lb/>
was one 12-bed ward on the south-side as shown in the plans. That was for<lb/>
enlisted men and was probably not altered.</p>
<p>Now, can you arrange with the Commanding Officer to have Master Sergeant<lb/>
W. A. Fields see if the date can not be found to show when the second floor<lb/>
was changed from its original plans to those of the General Hospital?<lb/>
Also try to find the <hi>original</hi> plans of the Post Hospital. The General<lb/>
Hospital probably started during the Spanish American War or soon after.<lb/>
But the large rooms shown in the plans we have may not have been necessary<lb/>
for several years.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04205008"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Unless we unearth something to solve this discrepancy between my memory<lb/>
and the plans, I cannot, of course, make any positive statement as to the<lb/>
exact location of Reed's room. I thought we had found the room, but<lb/>
evidently not if those walls are not the original ones. Somewhere in the<lb/>
Post an answer can, I think, be found. Possibly as the building is so<lb/>
small and may not be permanent, we had better just put a placque on the<lb/>
building and forget the room. At any rate, the room as it <unclear>was,</unclear> evidently<lb/>
does not exist today if the building was actually altered according to<lb/>
plans.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
