<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04205027">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Thurman B. Rice to Philip Showalter Hench, February 17, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Rice, Thurman B.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04205027</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-02-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Indianapolis (Ind.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-02-17">February 17, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04205027</idno>
<title>Letter from Thurman B. Rice to Philip Showalter Hench, February 17, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Rice discusses Reed's presentation at the Indianapolis medical conference, in 1900. Rice notes that Reed's paper was little talked about by the conference participants. Rice agrees to provide Hench with a copy of his biography of Hurty.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-02-17">
<head>Letter from Thurman B. Rice to Philip Showalter Hench, February 17, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04205027"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
INDIANA UNIVERSITY MEDICAL CENTER<lb/>
1040-1232 WEST MICHIGAN STREET<lb/>
INDIANAPOLIS 7, INDIANA<lb/>
<date value="1948-02-17">February 17, 1948</date>
</dateline>
<unclear></unclear><lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH<lb/>
Philip S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of February 10 gave me a great deal of pleasure. I would have<lb/>
answered it sooner had I not been out of the City at the time it arrived.<lb/>
Your use of this book is exactly what I would wish for it, and is the real<lb/>
reason why it was written.</p>
<p>Enclosed you will find some cards which are copies of the material to be<lb/>
found in the local newspapers as of the date just before and just after<lb/>
the coming of Walter Reed to Indianapolis on October 23, 1900. There is<lb/>
nothing at all about him before that date for the very simple reason that<lb/>
his name was not on the regular program, but was put on at an urgent request<lb/>
from him and the Army, as I understand it. Then there is almost nothing<lb/>
about the paper and no repercussions for some time after for the very simple<lb/>
reason that the people who were here did not really appreciate the signifi-<lb/>
cance of the paper. Perhaps that was asking too much of them. Evidently<lb/>
from what one of the papers said it was an interesting paper and may have<lb/>
been given a little attention simply as a shot in the dark. You will notice<lb/>
that one of the papers says that they received it with much interest and ex-<lb/>
tended the time alloted to him.</p>
<p>Concerning the surmise that he may have stayed at the Claypool Hotel, I believe<lb/>
I am certain that the Claypool Hotel was not in existence at that time. The<lb/>
site of the Claypool is on that of the old Bates House. I know that the Bates<lb/>
House was there at that time because a delegate to the convention died at the<lb/>
Bates House during the meeting of the Association. I believe the first date<lb/>
for the Claypool is about 1904. I would be strongly inclined to think that<lb/>
there is no hotel in Indianapolis now that would have records of the 1904<lb/>
registry. In the first place, the principal hotels have been built quite a<lb/>
bit since that time. The Dennison Hotel was in existence then and was very<lb/>
prominent but it has long been destroyed and I feel sure the records are lost.<lb/>
There is something in the paper which led my secretary and me to believe that<lb/>
Dr. Reed was in the city the night before he read his paper, but where he stayed<lb/>
I have no idea and am very much afraid it could not be found except perhaps by<lb/>
prodigious effort.</p>
<p>Any photographs that we have used you will be welcome to. I rather doubt if I<lb/>
have where I can put my finger on it, the original of the photograph showing<lb/>
the room where he read his paper. We do have however, the cuts from which the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04205028"/>
Dr. Hench<lb/>
Page Two<lb/>
Feb. 17, 1948<lb/>
pictures were made as shown in the book about Dr. Hurty. We will be glad to<lb/>
lend you these cuts along with the pictures showing the outer appearance of<lb/>
the old German House where the paper was read. Anything of this sort that<lb/>
you would like to have we are delighted to offer.</p>
<p>I am sure you have all the data you need about Kissinger and I doubt if you<lb/>
would be interested in the other yellow fever martyrs that have been connected<lb/>
with the State of Indiana. It is rather surprising that Indiana should have<lb/>
played so important a role in yellow fever considering the fact that so far<lb/>
as I know there was never a case this far north, though it was in southern<lb/>
Indiana.</p>
<p>If I can be of any further help to you I assure you I shall be delighted.<lb/>
Incidentally, we did find in the newspaper the names of the persons who were<lb/>
taken in as members at this meeting. By and large I suppose they would average<lb/>
younger than most of the men at the meeting, yet I feel sure that nearly all of<lb/>
them are dead. If a man were thirty years of age -- and he rarely attends a<lb/>
national meeting under that age -- it would make him now 78 years of age. It is<lb/>
very doubtful if anyone hearing that paper at that time would attach enough<lb/>
significance to it to have remembered it with any degree of accuracy. We copied<lb/>
the names of the persons taken into the organization in 1900, and almost all of<lb/>
the men I know are now certainly dead. There is one possibility; I believe that<lb/>
I am right in thinking that Dr. A. W. Bitting is alive, or at least was alive, a<lb/>
few years back. He would be an extremely old man however. He was a veterinarian<lb/>
rather than an M.D., and probably would not attach great significance to Reed's<lb/>
paper. Dr. Bitting was at that time connected with Purdue University and was one<lb/>
of the very first men in the United States to do tuberculin testing of cattle,<lb/>
and he also called attention to the fact that the milk of cows which had suffered<lb/>
from contagious abortion was not fit for human consumption. This was a very for-<lb/>
ward view to be taken about 1898. Dr. Bitting, when last I heard from him, was<lb/>
still alive and living somewhere in the west. I have an idea that the American<lb/>
Veterinary Association could tell you how to find him or to tell you if he is<lb/>
still alive. I would think however, that his chance of remembering Reed's paper<lb/>
would be very slight.</p>
<p>I think I can furnish you with copies of the Bulletin of the Indiana State Board<lb/>
of Health which carry the story of Chapters 28 and 29 of the Hurty Biography, or<lb/>
if you would wish me to send you a copy of the Hurty Biography I can do so under<lb/>
the following circumstances: This book is not arranged for sale; it can be given<lb/>
away or it can be traded for a contribution to a fund which is being used to have<lb/>
an oil painting of Dr. Hurty made to hang in the auditorium of the new State Board<lb/>
of Health building. If you will be willing to make a contribution of five or ten<lb/>
dollars, I will then make you a contribution of the book with the understanding<lb/>
that when you are through with it personally I would like for you to give it to<lb/>
some library where it could be a matter of standard reference. Please bear in<lb/>
mind that we will be glad to send you a Bulletin containing those two chapters in<lb/>
which you are most interested <del>with</del><add>at</add> no cost whatever.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Thurman B. Rice, M. D.<lb/>
Professor of Public Health</signed>
TBR/s<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
