<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04205016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jan H. Tillisch, February 16, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04205016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-02-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Tillisch, Jan H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Quemados de Marianaos</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Finca San Jose, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-02-16">February 16, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04205016</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jan H. Tillisch, February 16, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses his yellow fever research. He informs Tillisch that he is searching for an aerial photograph of the area around Camp Lazear, but has been unable to locate one.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-02-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jan H. Tillisch, February 16, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04205016"/>
<p>MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1948-02-16">February 16, 1948</date>
Dr. Jan H. Tillisch<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
My dear Jan:</p>
<p>I believe you know that I am writing a book on the &ldquo;Conquest of<lb/>
Yellow Fever&rdquo; featuring the work of Dr. Carlos Finlay of Havana and that of<lb/>
Major Walter Reed and his colleagues of the U. S. Army Board who did their<lb/>
epoch-making work in Cuba in 1900. I have spent about 9 years collecting<lb/>
material during which time I have visited Cuba three times.</p>
<p>So far I have been unable to find one item I am very anxious to<lb/>
have--an aerial photograph of a strip of land in Quemados de Marianas, suburb<lb/>
of Havana. I have searched many places for this, so far in vain. I have con-<lb/>
sulted the photographic files of the National Geographic Society in Washington.<lb/>
They have 2 or 3 fine aerial photos of Havana extending from Morro Castle on<lb/>
the east to the Hotel Nacional on the west (see enclosed photo). Recently I<lb/>
visited the Photographic Department of the U. S. Navy; they produced two good<lb/>
aerial views of the city proper but nothing as far &ldquo;west&rdquo; as Quemados.</p>
<p>The last time I was in Cuba the authorities at the Military Hospital,<lb/>
Ciudad Militar (Old Camp Columbia) gave me two or three <unclear>five</unclear> photos but they only<lb/>
showed the Hospital Militar and little else.</p>
<p>Not knowing where else to turn I asked the advice of U. S. Naval<lb/>
Photographers who suggested that the Pan American Airways Photographic or<lb/>
Publicity Offices in Havana might already have just the photos I want. Now<lb/>
this is where you come in. Having been in the humble ground forces in the late<lb/>
war I didn't get to know many Air Corps men, nor do I know anyone connected with<lb/>
Pan American here or in Havana. But I thought that you, while &ldquo;up in the wild<lb/>
blue yonder&rdquo;, might have fraternized with someone connected with Pan American<lb/>
and through you I might get a helpful introduction.</p>
<p>Mary and I are leaving this week for Florida and Cuba. I speak in<lb/>
Washington next Wednesday, February 18; then on the 19th we go to Palm Beach<lb/>
to stay at the Villa Atlantique, Palm Beach from February 19th to March 1st<lb/>
when we will go to Cuba for a week staying at the Hotel Nacional.</p>
<p>Jan, do you know anyone connected with Pan American in Miami, or<lb/>
better yet, in Havana? I certainly would like to call at their offices and see<lb/>
if per chance they do have what I have hunted for so long in vain.</p>
<p>I enclose two maps which show the strip I'd like to have a photograph<lb/>
of.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04205017"/>
<p>MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
Dr. Jan H. Tillisch<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
February 16, 1948</p>
<p>I'd love to have a photo showing the strip which stretches from the<lb/>
La Playa beach to the Oriental Park, Quemados and which would also show some-<lb/>
thing of the Military Hospital (I don't care about the rest of the camp; its of<lb/>
little interest to me), the La Playa railroad spur and in particular the Finca<lb/>
San Jose with its adjacent quarry. The Finca San Jose is an old estate (with<lb/>
remains of a farm in the rear) on Calzada Real which is well marked by an orna-<lb/>
mental sign on the iron-grilled gate. Everyone in Quemados knows it.</p>
<p>Now why do I want photos of this particular strip? For these reasons:</p>
<p>On the exact spot where the present military Hospital now stands there<lb/>
stood in 1900 the Camp Columbia Post Hospital, U. S. Army, where Walter Reed,<lb/>
Lazear and their colleagues began their work (#1 on my pencilled drawing).<lb/>
Walter Reed erected a secret experimental camp in the rear of the Finca San Jose<lb/>
and erected there their famous two little experimental buildings (&ldquo;Buildings 1 and<lb/>
2&rdquo;). In 1940 I rediscovered Building 1 which is still there! As a result the<lb/>
Cuban government recently made this little building (only a shack 14x20 feet) a<lb/>
&ldquo;National Monument.&rdquo; The remains of this little building I have marked as #2 on<lb/>
my pencilled map.</p>
<p>When the volunteers developed experimental yellow fever they were at<lb/>
once removed to a group of little wooden yellow fever &ldquo;wards&rdquo; right a cross the<lb/>
La Playa railroad track from the present Military Hospital on which site there is<lb/>
now a tree and (until recently) a memorial sign and fence. This spot is at #3 (my<lb/>
drawing).</p>
<p>The headquarters of General Lee were the Nerve-Center of Military<lb/>
activities in Quemados in 1900; these headquarters were in a fine old building<lb/>
which still stands on Calzada Real at the spot I've marked #4 (my drawing).</p>
<p>I'd love to have an air view which shows all these 4 spots and because<lb/>
American tourists know the La Playa Beach (#5 on drawing) so well it would be fine<lb/>
indeed to have that in the background (or foreground) to serve for purposes of<lb/>
orientation. In May in Washington will be held the International Congress on<lb/>
Tropical Medicine; on May 18 before a distinguished audience will be given a<lb/>
special ceremony in honor of Walter Reed. The Surgeon General and other govern-<lb/>
mental and diplomatic persons will be on the platform. I have been asked to give<lb/>
&ldquo;the principal oration&rdquo; on that occasion and expect to illustrate my address with<lb/>
slides. Two days later, May 20, a bust of Walter Reed is to be unveiled in the<lb/>
Hall of Fame, New York University; I have just been asked to assist somehow with<lb/>
the program of that event. Hence my desire to get the air views mentioned.</p>
<p>On previous visits I have travelled from Miami to Havana by Pan American.<lb/>
On one occasion I tried to photo what I wanted myself but I only have a small<lb/>
hand camera, unsuitable for good air views; also the Pan American planes never<lb/>
fly far enough west. They approach from the north, circle over the Hotel Nacional,<lb/>
then the Principe Hill or the Colm Cemetery and then circle east to land on the<lb/>
(rear) harbor. Even if I could persuade a pilot to go the 2 or 3 miles <unclear>fatther</unclear><lb/>
west I fear I could never get an adequate photo myself with my small camera. Once<lb/>
I got some movies or tried to but as one lands it gets bumpy and one goes so fast<lb/>
(and only once) over the place that my efforts were futile.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04205018"/>
<p>MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
Dr. Jan H. Tillisch<lb/>
February 16, 1948</p>
<p>I would be delighted to pay a reasonable fee for such photos but I<lb/>
am hoping they are already taken by someone. A chartered plane, etc. would<lb/>
I fear cost me more than I can allow for just 2 or 3 slides or photos. So I'm<lb/>
hoping Pan American may already have such photos or refer me to some Havana<lb/>
photo agency that might have them.</p>
<p>As far the desirable height for the photos I wouldn't dare to guess.<lb/>
The enclosed National Geographic Photo is a little high for detail but is<lb/>
pretty good at that!</p>
<p>Whatever you can do or suggest, Jan, I will surely appreciate. I<lb/>
enclose a reprint which will remind you of the story I'm so interested in.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>P. S. Hench, M. D.</p>
<p>PSH:ktb</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04205019"/>
<p>February 16, 1948</p>
<p>Jan:</p>
<p>Perhaps you might send (airmail) to Doctor McDonald the original<lb/>
copy of this letter, also one carbon in case he wants to forward it to Miami.<lb/>
Also, please send him my photos, maps and drawing. I would like to have them<lb/>
back sometime from Doctor McDonald or his associates in Havana (but, if not,<lb/>
its o.k.).</p>
<p>If Pan American doesn't have the photos, I do hope they can refer<lb/>
me to someone in Havana who might have them. Does Cuba have an air force<lb/>
which takes photos?</p>
<p>Thanks very much!</p>
<p>PSH:ktb</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
