<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04201013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Hal R. Keeling, January 19, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04201013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-01-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Keeling, Hal R.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Indianapolis (Ind.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-01-19">January 19, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04201013</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Hal R. Keeling, January 19, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench questions Keeling about the transcript of Reed's Indianapolis lecture, in 1900, that Keeling has found. Hench wants to know if the one Keeling found includes more information than Hench's copy, or if it may be Reed's actual manuscript copy.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-01-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Hal R. Keeling, January 19, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04201013"/>
<opener>
<hi>COPY</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<date value="1948-01-19">1/19/48</date>
</dateline>
<del>Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Dr. Charles H. Slocumb</del><lb/>
<add>Hal R Keeling<lb/>
5519 N <unclear>Meridean</unclear> St, Indianapolis, Ind</add><lb/>
<salute>My dear Hal:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I got a great kick out of your letter written yesterday. I'm so far<lb/>
behind in my correspondence that I dictated 7 hours today to my secretary and<lb/>
to get you a quick reply I'm writing this at home. First of all let me say<lb/>
that Mary and I regretted muchly not to have been able to show you a better<lb/>
brand of hospitality. But unfortunately we were unusually busy the whole time<lb/>
you were here. This past 10 days we've had two house guests, 3 additional vis-<lb/>
iting friends at the Kahler and 3 visiting doctors especially invited five weeks<lb/>
ago to come at this time! All this in addition to my routine work. We enjoy<lb/>
our visitors very much, but at times things get a bit complicated.</p>
<p>After getting one of our house guests into the hospital for surgery,<lb/>
Mary and I tried to locate you and were sorry to hear you had left.</p>
<p>Now, I can't tell you how thrilled I am to hear of your successes in<lb/>
finding an old &ldquo;horse &amp; buggy photo&rdquo; of the German House. That's swell! I've<lb/>
wanted that a long time. I'm also most anxious to know what other material<lb/>
may be available.</p>
<p>Since you were here I borrowed from the University of Minnesota Medi-<lb/>
cal School the Proceedings of the Indianapolis meeting (1900) to check several<lb/>
points. (We don't have that issue in the Clinic library.) In these Proceedings<lb/>
they published Reed's talk, but I can find no discussion whatever of his paper.<lb/>
Of course (as I've told you) Reed had finished his paper in Cuba so hastily that<lb/>
he hadn't gotten on the program and had to be introduced as an extra speaker by<lb/>
Dr. Henry B. Horlbeck of Charleston, South Carolina who introduced Reed thus<lb/>
(p. 253 of the Proceedings). &ldquo;Dr. Walter Reed, of the United States Army, has<lb/>
a paper on &ldquo;The Etiology of Yellow Fever&rdquo; which may be of interest to the asso-<lb/>
ciation, and I move that he be permitted to read it at this time.&rdquo;</p>
<p>You note that Horlbeck wasn't sure of its value and cautiously said<lb/>
&ldquo;--- which <hi>may</hi> be of interest.&rdquo; He was taking no chances. The official record<lb/>
doesn't tell who seconded Horlbeck's motion. The newspapers said Reed spoke<lb/>
overtime, and at the end of 20 minutes the floor voted to let him continue!<lb/>
The official Proceedings makes no mention of that.</p>
<p>Even tho' Reed's paper was not expected by the audience and nobody<lb/>
present had probably had any personal experience with the mosquito theory Reed<lb/>
was expounding, even so I cannot believe there was <hi>NO discussion</hi> whatever!!<lb/>
The newspapers and the Proceedings mention none.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04201014"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Does the transcript which you located give any dope on these<lb/>
points:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Who seconded the motion allowing Reed to talk?</item>
<item>(2) Was Reed actually stopped during his paper while<lb/>
a vote was taken to permit him to continue? If<lb/>
so, who said what?</item>
<item>(3) Was there any discussion of Reed's paper given<lb/>
in your &ldquo;complete transcription&rdquo;? That would in-<lb/>
deed be a find, not heretofore ever reported!</item>
<item>(4) Is your &ldquo;complete transcription&rdquo; the work of some<lb/>
hired medical reporter at the meeting, or is it<lb/>
<hi>Reed's actual</hi> manuscript!!!</item>
</list></p>
<p>I'm proud to have a reprint (rare and valuable) of this first<lb/>
paper of Reed's. I enclose it and if your secretary has time to compare<lb/>
it with the transcription that would be swell! If you find that the trans-<lb/>
cription is identical with mine, I won't need a copy. But if there is any<lb/>
deviation, or if your transcription includes discussion, I'm extremely an-<lb/>
xious to get a copy. And <hi>if it is Reed's actual manuscript which he brought<lb/>
and left with the association's secretary</hi>, I must have a <hi>photograph</hi> at least<lb/>
of page 1, and indeed I may want photostats of the whole thing.</p>
<p>I'd be delighted to pay whatever the cost is, but I don't want a<lb/>
photograph merely of some reporter's comments unless there are unreported<lb/>
data therein. It's a pity I can't borrow the item! Sometimes medical li-<lb/>
braries which won't lend items to individuals <hi>will</hi> lend them to other libra-<lb/>
ries. If so, I could have the librarian of the Mayo Clinic put in a formal<lb/>
request for this manuscript on <hi>inter-library loan</hi>.</p>
<closer>
<signed>P S Hench</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
