<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04205011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Thurman B. Rice, February 10, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04205011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-02-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rice, Thurman B.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Keeling, Hal</name>
<name type="person">Sweeney, Ray</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Indianapolis</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-02-10">February 10, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04205011</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Thurman B. Rice, February 10, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench introduces himself to Rice and discusses his planned book on the conquest of yellow fever. Hench wishes to purchase a copy of Rice's biography of J.W. Hurty because there is a photograph of the room in which Reed presented his paper, in 1900. He inquires if Rice knows where Reed stayed in Indianapolis for the 1900 conference.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-02-10">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Thurman B. Rice, February 10, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04205011"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-02-10">February 10, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Thurman B. Rice<lb/>
3167 North Delaware<lb/>
Indianapolis, Indiana<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Rice:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am writing a book on the conquest of yellow fever and in this<lb/>
connection have visited Cuba 3 times and most of the survivors of Walter<lb/>
Reed and his colleagues. By separate post I am sending you a reprint on<lb/>
the subject.</p>
<p>The details concerning Reed's presentation of the preliminary<lb/>
note in Indianapolis in October 1900, have not appeared in any publication<lb/>
to my knowledge. From time to time, I tried to get some information from<lb/>
public libraries in Indianapolis and did get photostatic copies of the<lb/>
newspapers of the day after Reed's talk but I was unable to find much.</p>
<p>Recently my friend, Hal Keeling, who has been a patient at the<lb/>
Clinic from time to time, was here and I enlisted his help. He and his<lb/>
colleague, Mr. Ray Sweeney, have given me much help indeed. Especially<lb/>
did they call my attention to your interesting book, &ldquo;The Hoosier Health<lb/>
Officer, <unclear>a</unclear> Biography of Dr. J. N. <unclear>Hurty</unclear>, a History of the Indiana State<lb/>
Board of Health to 1925&rdquo;. Mr. Keeling was able to borrow this book for<lb/>
me briefly but I had to return it almost immediately. Could you tell me<lb/>
if there is a possibility that I could purchase this volume somewhere?<lb/>
I notice that these articles also ran serially in the bulletin of the<lb/>
Indiana State Board of Health but unfortunately, the Mayo Clinic Library<lb/>
had <unclear>neither</unclear> this bulletin or your book. I was anxious to make extensive<lb/>
notes and get photostatic copies not only of your chapter 28 but also of two<lb/>
or three other items in your book. Mr. Ray Sweeney called my attention to the<lb/>
photograph of the room in which Walter Reed read his paper. I am most anxious<lb/>
to ask your permission to reproduce this photograph and <unclear>would</unclear> be delighted to<lb/>
give credit to you if you would let me reproduce it in my book. Do you have<lb/>
any sort of a print of this photograph, preferably a glossy print or best of<lb/>
all, the negative? If so, would you lend it to me and I shall be glad to de-<lb/>
fray whatever expense is concerned and will return it to you by insured post.<lb/>
If you do not have the film or a photograph, do you have a cut which I might<lb/>
borrow? I believe Mr. Sweeney thought that you did.</p>
<p>I expect to visit Cuba again the end of this month. The Cuban Govern-<lb/>
ment has made Camp Lazear and the little building thereon a national monument<lb/>
but has done nothing to preserve the little building and I am going to see what<lb/>
can be done about this.</p>
<p>Do you have any idea how we could find out where Reed stayed in<lb/>
Indianapolis in October 1900? I discussed this with Mr. Keeling but so far<lb/>
we have no clue. Mr. Keeling thought he might have stayed at the Claypool<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04205012"/>
C2<lb/>
<unclear>B 6</unclear><lb/>
Dr. Thurman B. Rice<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
February 10, 1948<lb/>
Hotel. I am going over the list of physicians who were members of the<lb/>
American Public Health Association in 1900 and who might have attended the<lb/>
meeting. Perhaps I can get help from then also.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
