<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04214069">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Camilo Chavez, April 28, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04214069</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-04-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Chavez, Camilo</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Mariano (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-04-28">April 28, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04214069</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Camilo Chavez, April 28, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests enlargements of the aerial photographs which Chavez obtained. He would also like to borrow the negatives.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-04-28">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Camilo Chavez, April 28, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04214069"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-04-28">April 28, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Colonel Camilo Chavez<lb/>
Cuban Army Air Force<lb/>
Ciudad Militar<lb/>
Marianao, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Colonel Chavez:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wondered if you could do me a very real favor. In Washington, May<lb/>
10 to 15, will be held an International Congress on Tropical Medicine under the<lb/>
auspices of the United States Government. Many distinguished visitors will be<lb/>
present. I have been asked to give an address on the conquest of yellow fever<lb/>
the evening of May 12. I have also been asked to set up an exhibit on the con-<lb/>
quest of yellow fever. In connection with this, I am most anxious to have some<lb/>
large photographs of the air views which you and your colleagues so kindly made<lb/>
for me. Would it be possible for me to ask for two things.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Could your department prepare for me a set of enlargements of the<lb/>
air views which you took for me. I think there were five or six in the air map<lb/>
from LaPlaya to the Hippodrome and then there were the two excellent photographs<lb/>
(the second ones taken, the tangential views of the Finca San Jose and the re-<lb/>
mains of Camp Lazear). The one was especially fine as it showed the military<lb/>
hospital of Ciudad Militar and LaPlaya in the background. I should be very<lb/>
glad to pay for these enlargements. I hesitate greatly to ask your department<lb/>
to make these but I do not believe any local organization has the facilities<lb/>
for enlarging them like the large views you gave me. Certainly the photographic<lb/>
department of the Mayo Clinic cannot do it. Otherwise, I would merely ask you<lb/>
to lend us the films and I would have it done here.</item>
<item>2. Could you also lend me for a short time, the negatives or films<lb/>
of these views. I should like to have quite a few additional prints made to<lb/>
help me in my campaign to arouse interest among American physicians in the<lb/>
preservation of Camp Lazear. I have tried to make a photographic copy of one<lb/>
of the prints you sent me and it isn't bad but it isn't nearly as clear as<lb/>
the originals.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Is there any possibility that I could receive these enlargements and<lb/>
prints by May 10 or 11. I will be arriving at the Hotel Mayflower in Washing-<lb/>
ton, D. C., and if you could air mail them to me I shall be very glad to pay<lb/>
the expense. It could be marked as follows: Dr. Philip S. Hench, Hotel<lb/>
Mayflower, Washington, D. C., &ldquo;Hold for arrival, May 11&rdquo;. I should like very<lb/>
much to exhibit some of these prints in Washington at the International Congress<lb/>
to show them where the work of Doctors Finlay and Reed and their colleagues was<lb/>
done.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04214070"/>
<p>Colonel Camilo Chavez</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>April 28, 1948</p>
<p>If you will let me know much this is I will send you my personal<lb/>
check promptly. Let me express again my sincere appreciation for the wonder-<lb/>
ful help you have given me in obtaining these views. They are quite invaluable.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P. S.: If it is impossible for you to have the enlargements made, if you<lb/>
will send me the negatives I will do the best I can here to have them en-<lb/>
larged properly.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
