<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04212038">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, March 22, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lyons, Bertha L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04212038</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-03-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Clemons, Harry</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Lucy</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-03-22">March 22, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04212038</idno>
<title>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, March 22, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lyons clears up some confusion about which items she wanted Hench to send for the Hall of Fame program. Howard will be invited to the ceremony, and she hopes he can come. She regrets that Hench will be unable to attend.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-03-22">
<head>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, March 22, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04212038"/>
<opener>
Every American is a shareholder in the Hall of Fame<lb/>
HALL OF FAME: NEW YORK UNIVERSITY<lb/>
I MADISON AVENUE &middot; NEW YORK IO, N. Y.<lb/>
Telephone: MURRAY HILL 3-4469<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-03-22">22 March 1948</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you very much for your helpful letter of<lb/>
March 19. I failed to make myself thoroughly understood in my<lb/>
letter to you of March 12 indicating items which I wished re-<lb/>
produced. If you will refer to that letter, you will find that<lb/>
the first items which I requested were those indicated in your<lb/>
<hi>letter of February 23</hi>, and the numbers used were the numbers which<lb/>
you had indicated in your suggested list. When I referred to<lb/>
the other documents wanted, I definitely referred to your general<lb/>
list and thus used the numbers indicated on that list. Items 14<lb/>
and 15 therefore are not the collective works of Finlay, and the<lb/>
Senate document No. 61. Item 14 in your letter of February 23 is<lb/>
a reproduction of part of one of Walter Reed's letters to his<lb/>
wife written during the excitement of the experiments. No. 15<lb/>
is a reproduction of a part of one of Reed's early letters to<lb/>
his fiance before they were married, in which he expressed,<lb/>
even then, early in life, an earnest desire to help humanity.<lb/>
You are right, of course, I could not use the collective works<lb/>
of Finlay, nor the Senate document No. 61, and frankly, for the<lb/>
purpose of this ceremony, we are not too interested in Finlay's<lb/>
collective works, great as was his part in the experiments in<lb/>
yellow fever. Item No. 25 may be eliminated entirely. I fear,<lb/>
since it is as technical as we both thought it was, it would not<lb/>
serve our particular purpose.</p>
<p>It was very good of you to write to Dr. Clemons,<lb/>
head of the library at the University of Virginia, asking him<lb/>
to make photostats and photographs of the items indicated in<lb/>
your letter of March 19.</p>
<p>I have already written to General Kean in an effort<lb/>
to get copies of such material as he may have on hand, and I shall<lb/>
write him again today specifically asking for the letters of<lb/>
Dr. Welch and General Wood. I shall also ask him for a copy of<lb/>
the photograph of the birthplace. We too have a post card showing<lb/>
the birthplace, which is rather inadequate, and I am hoping very<lb/>
much that he will be able to furnish us with a better copy or<lb/>
tell us where we may procure one.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04212039"/>
<p>Dr. Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>2.</p>
<p>March 22, 1948</p>
<p>I am happy to know that the Metropolitan Life<lb/>
Insurance Company has some early photographs of Walter Reed,<lb/>
and since we are in the Metropolitan Life Building, I shall<lb/>
telephone to that department and see what I can &ldquo;round up.&rdquo;<lb/>
I have had communication with that department once before<lb/>
and have given them some material from time to time, so that<lb/>
I feel certain they will be happy to turn over whatever they<lb/>
have to us for this occasion.</p>
<p>Regarding Dr. Howard, thank you for suggesting<lb/>
him and his daughter for invitations. As a matter of fact,<lb/>
Mr. Gamache of The American Foundation for Tropical Medicine, Inc.,<lb/>
who is making up our invitation<del>s</del> lists for us, had already given us<lb/>
Dr. Howard's address. We shall, of course, include his daughter<lb/>
as you suggest. We hope very much that Dr. Howard will find it<lb/>
possible to attend the ceremony. Perhaps his daughter has a car<lb/>
and if it is a good day could drive him down without too much<lb/>
difficulty.</p>
<p>You are perfectly right. I am assembling<lb/>
a great deal more material than I could possibly use in our<lb/>
program, but I must see what there is and try to get the most<lb/>
interesting things possible.</p>
<p>Again, I hesitate to put you to all this trouble<lb/>
of getting the material together for us, but since it is in<lb/>
your possession, I do not know what else we could do in the<lb/>
matter, except say, thanks loud and deep to you.</p>
<p>I regret more than I can tell you that you and<lb/>
Mrs. Hench will not be able to attend the ceremony, for I know<lb/>
that a number of your colleagues have been looking forward to<lb/>
seeing you that day, particularly Dr. Salisbury; Dr. Meleney,<lb/>
and many others, to say nothing of Dr. Angell and myself.</p>
<p>With kind regards, and again with deepest<lb/>
appreciation, believe me</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
Assistant to the Director</signed>
BLL:yz<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
