<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04212005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Siler, J.F.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04212005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-03-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">McCoy, Frank R.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Lyons, Bertha L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Fort Leslie J. McNair (Washington, D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-03-03">March 3, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04212005</idno>
<title>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Siler reports that Kean had to be hospitalized again. He agrees with Kean and Hench that the marker for the room where Walter Reed died should be placed on the outside of the building and not on the inside.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-03-03">
<head>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04212005"/>
<opener>
GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
<dateline>
1835 EYE STREET. NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6. D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1948-03-03">March 3, 1948</date>
</dateline>
EXECUTIVE OFFICES<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It was a great regret to me that I failed to see you during your very brief<lb/>
visit to Washington about ten days ago. I called the Hotel Mayflower early Thursday<lb/>
morning but you had already left. I then called General Kean who told me he had<lb/>
heard from you and expected you to come in to see him some time during the day. I<lb/>
asked that he advise me of your arrival as I would like either to see you or to talk<lb/>
with you briefly on the telephone. My last use of my telephone that morning was at<lb/>
about half past eleven. I waited for a call from you or General Kean all the after-<lb/>
noon, only to find that my telephone had been out of commission. It was repaired<lb/>
early the next morning and I immediately got in touch with General Kean but he said<lb/>
that you had already left.</p>
<p>I am delighted that you were able to see General McCoy. I had hoped I might<lb/>
have the pleasure of taking you around to see him myself. General Kean told me of<lb/>
your visit with General McCoy. I know that you can get a great deal from him<lb/>
when you come east in May for the Walter Reed Celebration meeting.</p>
<p>I am sorry to have to report that on Friday, February 20, it was necessary for<lb/>
General Kean to go into the hospital again. When I went to see him a day or so later<lb/>
he was getting along very nicely. I hope to see him again today or tomorrow.</p>
<p>I quite agree with you and General Kean that the marker <unclear></unclear> Leslie J. McNair<lb/>
should be confined to a plaque placed on the outside of the building in which we<lb/>
know Walter Reed died, this to be worded as indicated by you and General Kean. A<lb/>
copy of the wording is enclosed herewith. It is quite evident that the room in which<lb/>
Walter Reed died has been broken up and it would be impracticable to place a plaque<lb/>
in the general location of the room. I am writing General Truby that it is our<lb/>
feeling that the plaque should be placed only on the outside of the building and the<lb/>
wording should be as suggested by you and General Kean.</p>
<p>I have had some correspondence with Mrs. Lyons, of the Hall of Fame, relative<lb/>
to the unveiling of the bust of Walter Reed. In one of my letter to her, I suggested<lb/>
that it would be desirable to include in the program a reproduction of the letter<lb/>
written by Walter Reed to Mrs. Reed on the night of December 31, 1900, of which I<lb/>
understand you have the original. It also occurred to me that it might be desirable<lb/>
to include a photograph of the building in which Reed was born, with adequate explan-<lb/>
ation concerning the temporary nature of Walter Reed's mother's residence in that<lb/>
building. I have no doubt Mrs. Lyons will write you fully concerning the whole matter.</p>
<p>Thank you so much for your notes from Florida. I hope that you and Mrs. Hench<lb/>
had the rest you so much needed in Florida and a delightful visit to Cuba. With very<lb/>
best regards,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Faithfully yours,</salute>
<signed>J. F. Siler<lb/>
Col., U.S.A., Retired</signed>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minn<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
