<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04212025">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank F. Law, March 16, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04212025</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-03-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Law, Frank F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Lyons, Bertha L.</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="person">Dart, Raymond O.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04212025</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank F. Law, March 16, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Law for providing the inserts of Cornwell's painting for the Hall of Fame celebration. He says the Mayo Foundation has 600 fellows - rather than the normal 350 fellows - due to men returning from the war, and thus fellowships are very competitive.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-03-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank F. Law, March 16, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04212025"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Frank Law<lb/>
Wyeth Incorporated<lb/>
1600 Arch Street<lb/>
Philadelphia, Pennsylvania<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Law:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It was extremely kind of you and your colleagues to make available<lb/>
for the program of the Hall of Fame the colored inserts of the painting<lb/>
&ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. I hesitated to involve you in this but I could<lb/>
think of no finer time or place for dignified publicity than a Hall of Fame<lb/>
celebration. I know Miss Lyons was delighted with your cooperation.</p>
<p>Now, as to another matter. As you may know, the Fourth International<lb/>
Congress on Tropical Medicine is being held in Washington the week of May 10<lb/>
to 18. On the evening of May 12, they are having a Walter Reed celebration<lb/>
or memorial event. I am giving the &ldquo;principal oration&rdquo;. The Surgeon General<lb/>
is to be master of ceremonies I believe, etc. etc. My talk will be illustrated<lb/>
and an always, I use a slide of Cornwell's painting. I have just received word<lb/>
from Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer, the general chairman of the Program Committee, and<lb/>
from Colonel Raymond O. Dart of the Army Institute of Pathology, that they wish<lb/>
to set up a Walter Reed exhibit to be displayed during the Congress. Apparently<lb/>
another exhibit will concern Sir Ronald Ross, a conqueror of malaria and certain<lb/>
English physicians are bringing material for that exhibit. I have suggested to<lb/>
Colonel Dart that a reproduction of Cornwell's painting should certainly be on<lb/>
exhibit. I do not want to commit you to exhibit the original painting but you<lb/>
might like to consider that. They are making extensive plans for quite a large<lb/>
international congress and the Cornwell painting would have the great advantage<lb/>
of mentioning not only Reed but also Finlay, thus pleasing the Latin Americans.<lb/>
You may be hearing from Colonel Dart.</p>
<p>As to your young friend, Dr. Thomas Noone, I shall look up the situa-<lb/>
tion here in the Foundation. It has been very difficult. Before the war, we<lb/>
had about 350 fellows but during the war 250 fellows left before completing<lb/>
their fellowships and 340 other men who had received appointments for fellow-<lb/>
ships entered the military service before getting here. The Foundation con-<lb/>
sidered that it had a moral obligation to these 600 men and held the fellow-<lb/>
ships open for them. Most of them have returned and to accommodate them,<lb/>
practically no new fellowships have been given here for two years. We now<lb/>
have about 600 fellows. They are hanging from the rafters. The situation<lb/>
will adjust itself within the next year or 18 months but during that time<lb/>
it will be still quite difficult to get a fellowship here, in any subject.<lb/>
You may be surprised to know that recently the number of applications for<lb/>
fellowships here actually equalled half the number of all graduates of all<lb/>
medical schools in the country. Because of the excessive number of applica-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04212026"/>
Mr. Frank Law<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
March 16, 1948<lb/>
tions, the Foundation has been able to set up very high standards and only<lb/>
accepts the top men from the various medical schools. Knowing only little<lb/>
about Doctor Noone's record, I could not say whether he would have any chance<lb/>
for the small number of fellowships that might be available in 1948 and 1949,<lb/>
but I shall discuss your letter with the Director of the Mayo Foundation and<lb/>
drop you a note shortly.</p>
<p>If I can give Doctor Noone any encouragement it will be well for<lb/>
him to at least send for an application and when it is properly filled in and<lb/>
his references returned, it will be well for him to visit here, making<lb/>
certain that the Director and other members of the Fellowship Committee are<lb/>
to be in town when he arrives. I should be glad to take him personally<lb/>
to the Foundation Office and introduce him around.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P. S.: Have you ever published Doctor Fitz excellent talk given at the<lb/>
unveiling of the Oliver Wendell Holmes painting? I don't think I ever saw<lb/>
Fred Rankin's paper. They are both excellent and I do hope they will be<lb/>
published.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
