<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04214036">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, April 14, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lyons, Bertha L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04214036</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-04-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-04-14">April 14, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04214036</idno>
<title>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, April 14, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lyons thanks Hench for the photograph of Reed's grave and discusses courtesy lines and other details in reference to the copies of Reed items provided by Hench for the Hall of Fame exhibit.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-04-14">
<head>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, April 14, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04214036"/>
<opener>
Every American is a shareholder in the Hall of Fame<lb/>
<dateline>
HALL OF FAME : NEW YORK UNIVERSITY<lb/>
I MADISON AVENUE &middot; NEW YORK IO, N. Y.<lb/>
<date value="1948-04-14">14 April 1948</date>
</dateline>
Telephone: MURRAY HILL 3-4469<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am again indebted to you for your very compre-<lb/>
hensive letter of April 13, and for the copies of the photo<del>stats</del><add>graphs</add><lb/>
of the Walter Reed grave at Arlington. The large <del>photostat</del>, as<lb/>
you say, is not too clear, and I have just written to General<lb/>
Bliss's assistant, Colonel McNinch, asking him to kindly send<lb/>
me another <del>photostat</del>. If he sends me a good one I shall be glad<lb/>
to turn it over to you after our ceremony. In the meantime I am<lb/>
holding the large one which you sent to me and the small ones<lb/>
awaiting Colonel McNinch's reply.</p>
<p><unclear>glossy</unclear></p>
<p>photograph.</p>
<p>I am glad that you wrote to General Reed and<lb/>
Mrs. Blossom Reed asking them about the matter of the courtesy<lb/>
line to be used throughout the program in connection with Walter<lb/>
Reed's letters and I shall await their decision in the matter.<lb/>
I had a long session with my printer a few days ago and another<lb/>
one today, and have turned over to him most of the material for<lb/>
the making of cuts. I do not recall now whether I told you that<lb/>
Dr. Bettmann decided to permit us to use the wood cut and the<lb/>
drawing which you suggested, gratis, but with this proviso, that<lb/>
we do not disclose the periodicals in which they appeared. Under<lb/>
the circumstances, we have consented to treat the material in<lb/>
this way.</p>
<p>My item No. 8 mentioned in your letter, viz. the<lb/>
letter from &ldquo;General&rdquo; Reed to Major Kean of September 6, 1900,<lb/>
should have been letter from <hi>Walter</hi> Reed. That was my error<lb/>
and I hope you will pardon this temporary lapse of memory.</p>
<p>As suggested, I have just communicated with Miss<lb/>
Lucy Howard concerning the letter which Walter Reed wrote to<lb/>
her father, and I am hoping that she will permit not only the use<lb/>
of the letter but will give me the proper courtesy line.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04214037"/>
<p>Dr. Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>April 14, 1948</p>
<p>I am sorry that we left out the Congressional<lb/>
Medal for I see now that you would have liked to have seen it<lb/>
reproduced in the program. Frankly, the only reason that we<lb/>
left it out was because we had reached the point where space was<lb/>
becoming rather limited, but I assure you that when the cuts are<lb/>
made of the photographs and manuscripts and we find that we have<lb/>
an appropriate setting somewhere in the program, we shall bear the<lb/>
medal in mind and run it.</p>
<p>You are a very generous person to offer all of these<lb/>
photostats to us as your personal contribution to the Reed fund,<lb/>
and I personally feel so indebted to you now that I hardly know how<lb/>
to thank you further. Perhaps when I see you at the ceremony I<lb/>
can be a little more articulate on this subject. Meantime, let me<lb/>
assure that you will have a very good seat in the reserved section<lb/>
as a participant in the Procession, and if for any reason your<lb/>
plane should be late and you cannot walk in the Procession, your<lb/>
seat will be reserved. As for the programs, it will be a great<lb/>
pleasure to send you fifty copies as soon as they are off the<lb/>
press, <hi>without charge</hi>.</p>
<p>I regret very much that Mrs. Hench will not<lb/>
accompany you for I am sure she would have enjoyed the ceremony.<lb/>
There will be some beautiful music as well as appropriate addresses.</p>
<p>Again with the very deepest appreciation, believe<lb/>
me</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
Assistant to the Director</signed>
BLL:yz<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
Do pardon the corrections in this letter - but I wanted to<lb/>
get it off to you this evening. Many of these letters<lb/>
B L.L.<lb/>
sound like so much <unclear>greek</unclear> to<lb/>
our <unclear>stenographer!</unclear> A temporary <unclear>one</unclear>!<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
