<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04212018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Atcheson Laughlin Hench, March 16, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04212018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-03-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Atcheson Laughlin</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Hench, Kahler</name>
<name type="place">Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington D.C.</name>
<name type="place">Albemarle County (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04212018</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Atcheson Laughlin Hench, March 16, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Philip Hench discusses what day would be best for him to speak at the Albemarle County Historical Society meeting. He would like to work it in before his session at the International Congress on Tropical Medicine in Washington, but will accept any invitation with which Atcheson Hench is involved.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-03-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Atcheson Laughlin Hench, March 16, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04212018"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Dr. A. L. Hench<lb/>
East Jefferson Street<lb/>
Charlottesville, Virginia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Atch:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Mary and I had a marvelous time in Cuba and arrived home yester-<lb/>
day morning. In unpacking my bags, I found again your nice birthday note<lb/>
and reread it. To my dismay, I found that I did not answer the last para-<lb/>
graph about the possible invitation of the Albemarle County Historical<lb/>
Society. We left Palm Beach for Cuba the day after your letter arrived,<lb/>
hence this matter slipped my mind.</p>
<p>Now, here's the dope. I am giving &ldquo;the principal oration&rdquo;on the<lb/>
evening of Wednesday, May 12, in Washington, before the International Congress<lb/>
on Tropical Medicine, the evening session being given over to a memorial for<lb/>
Walter Reed as a preliminary of the unveiling of his bust in New York on May<lb/>
20 in the Hall of Fame. My talk on May 12 will be only 30 minutes. They<lb/>
have asked me to set up an exhibit on Walter Reed and I am planning to get<lb/>
back my material now at the University and put it up at Washington and then<lb/>
bring it back here. I had planned to ask the University to send the material<lb/>
from Charlottesville to Washington and I had planned to arrive in Washington<lb/>
probably Tuesday, the 11th. Now, on what days of the week does the Historical<lb/>
Society have its meetings? Would Monday, May 10th, be agreeable? If so, I<lb/>
could come straight to Charlottesville, speak that night, pick up my material,<lb/>
go to Washington the 11th and set up the little exhibit and then speak on the<lb/>
12th.</p>
<p>If Monday night, the 10th, is not agreeable, I suppose I could come<lb/>
down for Thursday night, the 13th, but as you can see, from the standpoint of<lb/>
my getting my material to Washington personally, it would be better for me to<lb/>
be in Charlottesville before, rather than after, the Washington meeting on the<lb/>
12th. Needless to say, I will accept any invitation with which you are concerned<lb/>
in any way, if I possibly can. I will not be east in April but will, of course<lb/>
attend Kahler's commencement at Mercersburg, Monday, June 7. I could come to<lb/>
Charlottesville after that but would prefer to come in May. If either of these<lb/>
dates is not suitable, I might come sometime in the fall, although I am going<lb/>
to Europe in October and don't want to connect too many side-issues with that<lb/>
trip.</p>
<p>In time I will send you a memorandum of my Cuban trip, most produc-<lb/>
tive.</p>
<p>Kahler had a grand time with Margy at Swarthmore at the inter-<lb/>
scholastic meet. Incidentally, Kahler again won first in diving against<lb/>
17 prep schools and two weeks before, at Trenton, he won the Eastern Inter-<lb/>
scholastic Diving Championship (first place in diving). Indeed, he has won<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04212019"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
first place in diving in every meet this year except one, against the Navy<lb/>
freshman; that meet I saw. Most unfortunately, his toe lightly touched the<lb/>
board on one dive and the dive and its score was cancelled. Up to that point,<lb/>
he had been ahead comfortably but that one dive made him take second place by<lb/>
about two points. A pretty good record. Also, he has raised his scholastic<lb/>
average and is now on the top honor roll, which is higher than the &ldquo;First<lb/>
Honor <unclear>Roll&rdquo;</unclear> which latter he has been on for two years. His average is now<lb/>
90. We just heard this morning that Al Snell's son is also accepted for<lb/>
Lafayette and will probably room with Kahler. We are most pleased. Margy<lb/>
mentioned the possibility of coming out this summer. She is welcome any<lb/>
time and we certainly hope she can come. She and Kahler hit it off very well<lb/>
apparently. He was delighted with her.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
