<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04214001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, April 1, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04214001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-04-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lyons, Bertha L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Pharaba W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Blossom] Emilie M.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">U.S. Army General Hospital (Washington, D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-04-01">April 1, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04214001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, April 1, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses items he is sending for the Hall of Fame ceremony. Of importance are: Finlay's first paper, fever charts, the Congressional Medal awarded to Reed, remains of Building No. 1, and yellow fever volunteer contracts.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-04-01">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, April 1, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04214001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-04-01">April 1, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Miss Bertha Lyons<lb/>
Hall of Fame<lb/>
1 Madison Avenue<lb/>
New York, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Lyons:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I regret that it has taken me this long to get you this material.<lb/>
As I wrote you, I found it more scattered than I had thought. Much was in<lb/>
my home, some in my bank box, some in the Clinic and some on exhibit at the<lb/>
University of Virginia. But, thanks to you, I now have things in somewhat<lb/>
better order.</p>
<p>Last night, in my final assembly of the material which we have dis-<lb/>
cussed in our various letters, I found that I had been notably confused by<lb/>
your letter of 12 March in which you listed your requests. Not realizing<lb/>
that you were using numbers from two different letters of mine and believing<lb/>
that your numbers were all from my general list, I had ordered certain pic-<lb/>
tures and items which I now find you don't want. Some of the unwanted items<lb/>
I have retained. I have sent a few others along, from which you can make your<lb/>
selections. The Photographic Department in the Clinic helped copy some of<lb/>
this material and printed some of the pictures but the last considerable<lb/>
batch of prints were ordered by me at a time when the department was quite<lb/>
busy and I had to take the order to be printed outside the Clinic; therefore,<lb/>
the quality of some of the prints is not as good as that of others. Rather<lb/>
than reprint anything, I am sending them all along and once you have made<lb/>
your final choice, it won't be very difficult to supply you with either a<lb/>
better or a larger print, an enlargement from some of the prints or perhaps<lb/>
clearer or <unclear>glossier</unclear> prints. I was myself surprised to find that some of the<lb/>
prints are too small for adequate representation in a published article and I<lb/>
am just now realizing that some of the copies were made for me primarily for<lb/>
slides and should be recopied for a more adequate representation in a printed<lb/>
article or program.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>MATERIAL ENCLOSED</hi><lb/>
(See numbers in red pencil on the back of items.)</head>
<item>1. Reed's birthplace - two photographs; one of the birthplace before restora-<lb/>
tion and one after restoration. Colonel Siler wanted me to remind you that if<lb/>
you publish the photo of the birthplace, it might be well to note in the title<lb/>
that Reed's father and mother were occupying this little building only tem-<lb/>
porarily. As I recall it, they had just moved to that neighborhood and the<lb/>
parsonage which was being prepared for them burned down. Rather than delay<lb/>
matters, they moved in and it was in this temporary, very modest little home<lb/>
that Reed was born. His father and mother were actually economically con-<lb/>
siderably above the &ldquo;log cabin class&rdquo;.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f04214002"/>
<item>Miss Bertha Lyons</item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>April 1, 1948</item>
<item>2. Photographs of Reed (boyhood to manhood). These are from the photographic<lb/>
film strip &ldquo;Health Heroes - Walter Reed and the Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo; put<lb/>
out by the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company - 6 photos. I had advised you<lb/>
to get these from the Metropolitan Life but my prints came out better than I<lb/>
thought.</item>
<item>3. Cartoons and drawings depicting the horrors of yellow fever in the pre-Reed<lb/>
era; 9 pages <unclear>out</unclear> of old magazines obtained by me from <unclear>Bettmann</unclear> Archives, New<lb/>
York. The arrangements one has to make with the <unclear>Bettmann</unclear> Archives should be<lb/>
understood if you plan to use of these. Technically, one gets material<lb/>
from then at a price, for one publication only and one must credit the <unclear>Bettmann</unclear><lb/>
Archives. For <unclear>$75</unclear>. I &ldquo;rented&rdquo; the originals and had them copied here and am<lb/>
allowed to use them in any non-scientific publication of mine. Technically I<lb/>
am not allowed to give them to you to use and if you use any of them, I would<lb/>
suggest that you write Doctor <unclear>Bettmann</unclear> telling him which once you plan to use,<lb/>
telling him that I submitted these to you merely to be helpful and ask him of<lb/>
the fee he would charge. I think it would be minimal, it should be. I would<lb/>
strongly urge you to use one or two because the present generation has no idea<lb/>
how horrible yellow fever <unclear>was</unclear>, thus they cannot evaluate Reed's contribution.</item>
<item>4. Finlay's first paper - the first and last page of the original paper in<lb/>
Spanish, the first page of the English translation from Finlay's selected works<lb/>
- 3 items. Although you will have Finlay represented in the Cornwell painting,<lb/>
I do think it would be diplomatic to represent Finlay a little more than that<lb/>
and either to reproduce his picture in smaller size perhaps, or to reproduce<lb/>
this first paper because of the fact that Finlay's theory was absolutely correct<lb/>
and it was that which Reed proved. You will notice that the beginning of Fin-<lb/>
lay's paper in Spanish occupies the lower half of page 147; the end of the<lb/>
paper occupied the upper half of page 169. You might wish to rearrange them<lb/>
so as to show both halves together and <unclear>those</unclear> are from Analos de la Real Academia<lb/>
de <unclear>Crencias</unclear> Medicas <unclear>Finicas</unclear> y <unclear>Naturales</unclear> de la Habana, Volume 18, 1881. If you<lb/>
want enlarged picture of the first page of Finlay's work in English, I can have<lb/>
this <unclear>made</unclear>.</item>
<item>5. Reed enroute to Cuba to begin the yellow fever work - two
different views.<lb/>
These pictures I got from Mrs. Reed. Photographically, they are not unusual<lb/>
but the smaller one showing half length has only been published once that I<lb/>
know of and so far as I know, the full length one has never been published.<lb/>
As much as I &ldquo;love&rdquo; Walter Reed, one gets tired of the <unclear>oft</unclear>-published conven-<lb/>
tional photograph of him and it is refreshing to see a new view, even if it<lb/>
isn't photographically too excellent. The full length view is about the only<lb/>
unpublished photograph of Reed that I have ever found and if you don't want<lb/>
to use it it is quite all right as I will use it in some publication of mine.<lb/>
As to the identification, Mrs. Blossom Reed has insisted that the pictures<lb/>
were taken when he was enroute to Cuba to do the yellow work.</item>
<item>6. Camp Lazear - 6 photos. I think the larger ones are the best ones but as<lb/>
you will see, I copied them from page 188, Report of the Surgeon General of<lb/>
the Army to the Secretary of War for the Fiscal year ending June 30, 1901,<lb/>
Washington, Government Printing Office, 1901. You can obtain larger, better<lb/>
prints by writing to the U. S. Army Medical Museum (in the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Library, Washington, D. C.) and asking for a copy of negative 40731 and 40732.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04214003"/>
Miss Bertha Lyons<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
April 1, 1948<lb/>
If you have to make a choice, I would suggest the latter print. The two<lb/>
middle-sized blotchy once are unpublished snapshots taken by Doctor Agramonte<lb/>
and given to me by his daughter. They merely have the merit of being now,<lb/>
unpublished ones and the blotches add &ldquo;authenticity&rdquo;. The two small ones I<lb/>
copied from Kelly's book on Walter Reed and the Conquest of Yellow Fever.<lb/>
They are the clearest of the lot but are not as comprehensive as the two<lb/>
Army photos. Please note that the one small one, opposite page 146 of Kelly's<lb/>
book, is mislabeled. It is not Building No. 1, the fomites building, but is<lb/>
Building No. 2, the infected mosquito building.</item>
<item>7. The preliminary note - the first paper of Reed and his colleagues, 1 photo,<lb/>
of the Philadelphia Medical Journal, October 7, 1900. I didn't rephotograph<lb/>
the Journal, you may wish to do so. The significance of my photograph is<lb/>
that it shows Mrs. Lazear's own copy of a reprint which she presented to me<lb/>
and it <unclear>alsy</unclear> shows the copy owned by Lazear's <unclear>mother</unclear>, who remarried and her<lb/>
signature is C. C. Sweitzer, meaning Caroline C. Sweitzer. You might prefer<lb/>
to rephotograph the first page of this paper and you can, of course, have<lb/>
this done at the New York Academy of Medicine.</item>
<item>8. Fever charts. The most important cases of experimental yellow fever, the<lb/>
charts of Carroll, Dean (&ldquo;Case XY&rdquo;), Lazear's fatal
case, two charts of Kissinger<lb/>
and one of Moran - 6 in all. Carroll's was the first case of experimental<lb/>
yellow fever and was produced by Lazear, not Reed; Dean's was the second and was<lb/>
also produced by Lazear. Lazear was the third. These 3 cases were accomplished<lb/>
while Reed was in Washington. Each has special significance but you may pre-<lb/>
fer to reproduce the chart of Kissinger, which was Reed's first experimental<lb/>
case and the first completely controlled experimental case in history. The<lb/>
other three were not completely controlled. You will note two charts for<lb/>
Kissinger. One is a photograph of the actual fever chart which is in my<lb/>
possession. The other is the published chart as <add>it</add> appears in one of the Board's<lb/>
papers, as autographed by Kissinger. Don't be fooled by the fact that the<lb/>
charts don't look alike. In the smaller chart they seem to have charted<lb/>
certain sub-normal temperatures that appear to have been omitted in the original<lb/>
chart. Actually, as the case progressed, usually no chart was made from day<lb/>
to day, they merely tabulated a record which was later charted. The latter<lb/>
charts therefore were often made at one sitting and appear to be very neat.<lb/>
However, some of the charts were actually charted from day to day and one<lb/>
notes different handwriting from day to day.</item>
<item>9. The Congressional Medal. I enclose two photographs merely as samples.<lb/>
The one is the photograph of Moran's medal, the other a photograph of Kissinger's<lb/>
medal. You will be receiving from the University of Virginia probably a better<lb/>
photograph of Reed's medal. The reason that Moran's medal doesn't show up as<lb/>
clearly is that this is a photograph of a photograph whereas I actually photo-<lb/>
graphed the Kissinger medal. It is interesting to note that it shows up nicer<lb/>
with a black rather than a white background. I didn't notice this until last<lb/>
night and if the University of Virginia sends you a photograph with a white<lb/>
background and you wish otherwise, I think they would copy it on a black<lb/>
background.</item>
<item>10. Reed's deathplace, which was in 1900 the U. S. Army General Hospital at<lb/>
Washington Barracks, Washington, D. C. The building still stands but is now<lb/>
used as quarters for non-commissioned officers and their families at the Army<lb/>
War College grounds. He died in a room on the second floor, right side, near<lb/>
where the fire escape now is. Until last year the place was officially called<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04214004"/>
Miss Bertha Lyons<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
April 1, 1948<lb/>
the Army War College but in recent letters from Colonel Siler he has used<lb/>
the name Fort Something-or-other, a name not familiar to me. If this<lb/>
photograph is not adequate you can obtain a photograph by writing the<lb/>
Commanding General, Army War College.</item>
<item>11. Remains of Building No. 1 at Camp Lazear. These were taken just last<lb/>
month by me in Cuba. I enclose two pictures, one of the little building.<lb/>
(I am on the right with <unclear>Johnny</unclear> Moran between me and Doctor Nogueira of<lb/>
Havana). The other photograph shows the little smoke stack (in my possession)<lb/>
in front of the photograph of the Building No. 1 as it now remains. It was<lb/>
up through this actual smoke stack that the theory of infected bedding, etc.,<lb/>
went.</item>
<item>12. Letter of Reed to Surgeon General Sternberg, July 24, 1900; complete<lb/>
photostat, 8 pages; photograph 4 pages. I would suggest you use the last<lb/>
page, page 8.</item>
<item>13. Letter of Reed to his wife, October 6, 1900; complete photostat of 6<lb/>
pages. I suggest you consider pages 3, 4 and 5.</item>
<item>14. Letter of Reed to his wife, December 2 - 3, 1900; photostat of 4 pages,<lb/>
photograph of 2 pages. I think this is a very good one as it mentions what the<lb/>
Havana papers were calling him and his colleagues, namely, savages and bar-<lb/>
barians.</item>
<item>15. Letter of Reed to his wife, December 18 - 19, 1900; photostat of <unclear>8</unclear> pages,<lb/>
and envelope; photograph of 4 pages.</item>
<item>16. Letter of Reed to Sternberg, December 25 - 26, 1900. You will receive<lb/>
the complete photostat of the complete letter from the University of Virginia.<lb/>
I enclose only a fragment showing in Reed's handwriting a drawing of Building<lb/>
No. 1, to compare with the enclosed drawings of Agramonte from his articles<lb/>
in the Scientific Monthly, December 1915. You will notice that Reed's drawing<lb/>
does not exactly compare with Agramonte's drawing, presumably made 15 years<lb/>
later. The &ldquo;mosquito building room&rdquo; was added to the mosquito building after the<lb/>
building was built. The only significant difference is that in Reed's letter<lb/>
the arrangement of the entrance is a little different from that shown in<lb/>
Agramonte's drawing.</item>
<item>17. Letter of Reed to his wife, the well known New Year's Eve letter of<lb/>
December 31, 1900 - January 1, 1901. I enclose a set of glossy and one of<lb/>
semi-glossy prints of the letter and the envelope and I have marked pages<lb/>
a, b, c and d. You will probably receive photostats of the letter from the<lb/>
University of Virginia. I sent you one set of prints of this letter before.<lb/>
You ask for the complete letter with signature. It doesn't exist as such.<lb/>
Remember that all of those letters were quite personal letters of Reed to his<lb/>
wife and his very young daughter. They were never meant for publication or<lb/>
for the <unclear>perusal</unclear> of others. Mrs. Reed was a kindly, sentimental woman and in<lb/>
the bosom of his family, Major Reed responded with marked affection and sen-<lb/>
timentality. They had pet names and nick names and family expressions which<lb/>
appear throughout the letters. To maintain Reed's dignity no one should pub-<lb/>
lish those parts of the letters, or at least some of these parts. I would<lb/>
urge you, therefore, to omit the &ldquo;family part&rdquo; and only reproduce the portions<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04214005"/>
Miss Bertha Lyons<lb/>
- 5 -<lb/>
April 1, 1948<lb/>
which concern the experiments. How would you like to have your own personal<lb/>
letters published in cold print? I am sure you will understand my point and<lb/>
it was because of this necessity that I asked you to get General Reed's per-<lb/>
mission to let me lend you those letters. I will trust your good judgment<lb/>
in this matter.</item>
<item>18. Letter of Reed to his wife, January 4, 1901. Photostat of envelope<lb/>
and pages a to f; 6 pages and a duplicate of one page because the margin<lb/>
<unclear>is</unclear> out off. May I suggest you consider page a, but this letter should be,<lb/>
I think, censored as it criticizes Surgeon General Sternberg. Note that<lb/>
on the envelope Blossom Reed pencilled the date January 8, 1901 but the<lb/>
letter was actually postmarked January 4.</item>
<item>19. Letter of Reed to his wife, February 5, 1901. Photostat of 4 pages<lb/>
and envelope; photograph of 4 pages. Consider pages 2 and 3. In finding<lb/>
your way through these letters, please remember that the sheets were<lb/>
folded. We unfolded the sheets for photostating and photographing. I<lb/>
have marked the page numbers on the back.</item>
<item>20. Letter of Reed to Howard, the entomologist, January 13, 1901. Please<lb/>
note Reed's human <unclear>franity</unclear> in that two weeks after New Years he was still<lb/>
dating the letter 1900, but a pencilled note by Doctor Howard <add>shows it was 1901</add> <del><unclear>and</unclear></del> as indicated<lb/>
also by the surcharge on the front page of the letter. This is the well known<lb/>
letter in which Reed acknowledges Howard's great help and outlines the value of<lb/>
kerosene. Later, others claimed that Reed had no idea on how to get rid of<lb/>
the mosquito. This letter is one of the chief arguments against that idea.</item>
<item>21. Editorial from the Washington Post, November 2, 1900. Note column 2<lb/>
&ldquo;The Mosquito Hypothesis&rdquo;. This is wonderful and I would urge you to use<lb/>
it. I suggest you use the first sentence and the last paragraph of the<lb/>
editorial, either photographically or reproduce it in print. Remember that<lb/>
by this date, November 2, Reed had given the preliminary note and had returned<lb/>
to Cuba, and was erecting the experimental camp, but in Washington the idea<lb/>
was considered &ldquo;silly and <unclear>nonsensical</unclear>&rdquo;.</item>
<item>22. Editorial, Washington Post, December 22, 1900. Column 2 &ldquo;<unclear>Still</unclear> fumbling<lb/>
with yellow fever&rdquo;. I suggest you consider the use of the first and last<lb/>
paragraphs of this editorial, either in photo or in print. About now Reed<lb/>
was producing his first case of experimental yellow fever in the person of<lb/>
Kissinger, a successful inoculation, but the Washington editor considered<lb/>
the idea &ldquo;ridiculous&rdquo;.</item>
<item>23. English and Spanish versions of the contract between Reed and one of the<lb/>
Spanish volunteers. Note that these photographs are from the Army Medical<lb/>
Museum; through the courtesy of General Kean, I actually own one of these con-<lb/>
tracts. If these photos are not suitable, I can photograph the one I have.</item>
<item>24. The isolation yellow fever hospital. The volunteers got experimental<lb/>
yellow fever at Camp Lazear. They were immediately taken to these little<lb/>
yellow fever shacks near the post hospital of Columbia Barracks where they<lb/>
were cared for. It was in one of these little buildings that Lazear died.<lb/>
This photograph is from a clipping <unclear>posted</unclear> in Mrs. Reed's scrap book concerning<lb/>
her husband.</item>
<pb n="6" id="f04214006"/>
<item>Miss Bertha Lyons</item>
<item>- 6 -</item>
<item>April 1, 1948</item>
<item>25. Five small photos of Reed, Carroll, Lazear, Agramonte and Finlay. All<lb/>
from Kelly's book.</item>
<item>26. A photograph of Doctors Agramonte, Lazear and Carroll. This has only<lb/>
been published once in the Connecticut Medical Journal. It was given to me<lb/>
by Miss Agramonte. If you wish, we could enlarge just the center part.</item>
<item>27. Two small photographs of Cornwell's two preliminary oil sketches. These<lb/>
quite beautiful sketches are in my possession. You are going to reproduce<lb/>
Cornwell's final version. These preliminary versions show Finlay presenting<lb/>
the mosquito eggs to the American Commission. I suspect you will not want to<lb/>
reproduce them also but if you do, I can have the sketches photographed again.</item>
<item>28. Stamps in honor of Finlay, Reed and Gorgas, also rather recent cancellation<lb/>
marks honoring Finlay. You may wish to reproduce a Reed stamp but if so, <unclear>got</unclear><lb/>
permission from the Post Office Department. Undoubtedly they will give it to<lb/>
you and send you a nice reproduction.</item>
<item>29. Inside cover drawing of a meeting of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Board<lb/>
used in the book on Walter Reed by Laura Wood Hoper. If you wish to use it<lb/>
I will send you Mrs. Hoper's address. I am sure the publisher would give<lb/>
you permission to use it.</item>
<item>30. Detachment of the hospital corps at Columbia Barracks Post Hospital.<lb/>
Many of this group were among the volunteers. An identifying list is enclosed.</item>
</list></p>
<p>MY CHOICE</p>
<p>I have analyzed the three programs you sent me and notice that in<lb/>
general you have used only ten to twelve items. Usually five or six small<lb/>
photographs, each one-half page; two large photographs each occupying one<lb/>
page and two to four pages of autographed material. The following would be<lb/>
my first choice and they are arranged in more or less historical sequence.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Cornwell's painting, color plate.</item>
<item>(b) Reed's birthplace - 1/2 page.</item>
<item>(c) Photograph of Reed at 17 or in 1875. These might be small and you might get<lb/>
two on 1/2 page.</item>
<item>(d) The cartoon of 1873 or of 1876 - 1/2 page.</item>
<item>(e) The drawing of New Orleans (<unclear>1873</unclear>) showing the streets abandoned except for<lb/>
hearses, or the Newport view, 1899 - <unclear>1/2</unclear> page.</item>
<item>(f) The Finlay paper - 1/2 page.</item>
<item>(g) Reed enroute to Cuba - 1/2 page.</item>
<item>(h) Camp Lazear, Army negative 40732 - 1/2 page.</item>
<item>(i) The preliminary note of October 27; 1 page.</item>
<item>(j) Editorial, Washington Post, November 2 - 1/2 page.</item>
<item>(k) Reed's letter of December 2 - 3, 1 page. (Cut out the family part.)</item>
<item>(l) Kissinger's chart, the small autographed one - 1/2 page.</item>
<item>(m) The New Year's Eve letter. I forgot to mention that many of the letters<lb/>
as saved by Mrs. Reed, indicate that she discarded the more personal<lb/>
parts. Sometimes the first page or the first folder, sometimes the<lb/>
last folder or last page were discarded. This was of course her<lb/>
right and we cannot complain but that explains why the famous New<lb/>
Year's Eve letter is not actually complete. The last page, with the<lb/>
signature, was discarded.</item>
<pb n="7" id="f04214007"/>
<item>Miss Bertha Lyons</item>
<item>- 7 -</item>
<item>April 1, 1948</item>
<item>(n) The Congressional Medal - <unclear>1/4</unclear> page.</item>
<item>(o) Walter Reed's deathplace.</item>
<item>(p) Photograph of Walter Reed Hospital. The one I have is <unclear>inadequate</unclear>. You<lb/>
can get one by writing General <unclear>Hench</unclear>, the Commanding General.</item>
<item>(q) Building No. 1 as it now is, - 1/2 page.</item>
</list></p>
<p>I do hope that you can include the last photograph, the remains of<lb/>
Building No. 1. Frankly, I have an ulterior motive. I had the privilege of<lb/>
discovering this building after it had been lost for 40 years. I have been<lb/>
successful in having the Cuban government designate the remains of this little<lb/>
building as a &ldquo;national monument&rdquo;. Last month when I visited Cuba to propose<lb/>
the erection of a Cuban-American medical museum to enclose this little building,<lb/>
I was successful in a preliminary way and the Cuban government has just set<lb/>
aside $50,000 as a starter. The Mayo Foundation is willing to contribute<lb/>
to the fund and I am receptive to help from interested persons. I am not<lb/>
asking you to participate in any way in this campaign but I do think it is<lb/>
interesting to realize that the little building still remains. It sort of<lb/>
brings the story up to date and it may pleasantly surprise some of those<lb/>
present to realize the building still remains. Isn't it possible that some-<lb/>
one might say, in effect, &ldquo;For heavens sake, is that little building still<lb/>
there? It should be preserved. Let's do something about it.&rdquo; However, if<lb/>
you decide not to include this, it is quite all right.</p>
<p>As a result of my confusion from your letter of 12 March, I have not<lb/>
gotten for you photographs of the following items: (1) The Walter Reed Hos-<lb/>
pital; (2) Reed's grave; (3) The laboratory notebook and (4) One of the early<lb/>
letters from Reed to his fiancee showing his early interest in humanity. If<lb/>
you still want any of the last three, let me know but I think you will have<lb/>
much more than you can handle. I have withheld about 20 additional items which<lb/>
I had originally planned to send you but they seem quite superfluous.</p>
<p>I would appreciate it if you would please return to me any or all of<lb/>
this material when you have used it. Your publisher may need to make certain<lb/>
notes on the back, instructions regarding cuts, etc., but even so, if you can<lb/>
return it, I would appreciate it. If there is any other way in which I can<lb/>
help, please let me know.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I hate to think that I can't be there and although I<lb/>
must return from Washington after my talk there on May 12, my present plan is<lb/>
to make a quick flying trip to your ceremony in New York, going and coming by<lb/>
plane, just staying long enough for the ceremony. I would appreciate it if<lb/>
you would let me know now what time the ceremony will be, how long it will last,<lb/>
and approximately how long it would take for me to get from the airport in to<lb/>
the ceremony and back again.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
