<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04214041">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Draft of letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Pedro Nogueira, April 15, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04214041</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-04-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Carbonell Ponce, Felipe</name>
<name type="person">Colete, Honorato</name>
<name type="person">Cardenas, Raul de</name>
<name type="person">Presno, Jose A.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Hall of Fame, New York University, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-04-15">April 15, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04214041</idno>
<title>Draft of letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Pedro Nogueira, April 15, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] discusses the funding approved, by the Minister of Public Works, for the Camp Lazear memorial. [Hench] describes his meetings, arranged by Carbonell, with the Cuban Vice-President and engineer Colete, and postulates that Colete and the Vice-President may have influenced the approval of the funds.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-04-15">
<head>Draft of letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Pedro Nogueira, April 15, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04214041"/>
<opener>
original &amp; <unclear>3 carbons</unclear><lb/>
add<lb/>
carbon to <unclear>3 Po</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-04-15">4/15/48</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr Nogueira</salute>
</opener>
<p>On my return to Rochester I found a mass of work waiting<lb/>
for me and I have had a hard time getting caught up. I have<lb/>
the most satisfactory memories of my trip to Havana and I<lb/>
am most grateful to you for your wonderful help.</p>
<p>I have just received from you through <unclear>Mr.</unclear> Moran the<lb/>
fine collection of photographs. I am delighted to have them.<lb/>
Thank you so much. I have also just received the new<lb/>
air views (the 5 perpendicular views comprising the<lb/>
air-panel or air-map, and the two new tangential<lb/>
FINE<lb/>
<del><unclear>also</unclear></del> views of Camp Lazear). They are fine and much better<lb/>
than the first ones they took. <del><unclear>I I was disturbed disturbed</unclear></del><lb/>
When I received the first set I was disturbed to note that<lb/>
in the perpendicular <del>shot</del> Views the Caseta was just off<lb/>
the edge &amp; not in the photograph; also the tangential<lb/>
views were taken somewhat too far from the Caseta. This<lb/>
was undoubtedly my fault as the rough <unclear>pencilled</unclear> circle<lb/>
I had drawn hastily on my little map for Colonel<lb/>
Chavez took in too much territory south of the Caseta.<lb/>
But the second ones are fine and I am delighted with<lb/>
them. I have <del>written a note</del> sent a telegram &amp; written a<lb/>
note of thanks to Col Chavez. Without his and your help<lb/>
I would not have been able to get these. They will be most<lb/>
useful.</p>
<p>I was delighted indeed to have a telegram from<lb/>
Dr Carbonell and Mr. Honorato Colete that the<lb/>
Minister of Public Works had affirmed a sum of<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">$</hi>50,000 toward the preservation of the <unclear>caseta</unclear>. I telegraphed<lb/>
them my sincere appreciation. I think I told you that<lb/>
Dr Carbonell <del>who</del> had come to see me the just <unclear>right</unclear> I was<lb/>
in Havana <del><unclear>&amp; who</unclear></del> Having read one of my articles on the<lb/>
Conquest of Yellow Fever <add>he</add>, had become interested in my project.<lb/>
During most of my visit he was busy with this and that<lb/>
including a day or two entertaining the King &amp; Queen<lb/>
of the <unclear>Belgians.</unclear> so I didnt see much of him until about<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04214042"/>
(2<lb/>
2 or 3 days before our departure when he <unclear>suddenly took Mrs</unclear>.<lb/>
Hench &amp; me to meet the Vice-President one night about 11 oclock.<lb/>
The Vice President expressed much interest in <unclear>our</unclear> Project<lb/>
and said he would speak about it to the President and also<lb/>
<unclear>k</unclear> the Minister of Public Works. The next day Dr Carbonell<lb/>
took me to the Ministry but the Minister was busy with<lb/>
politics. However <del>we met the <unclear>Minister's Secretary</unclear> who</del><lb/>
Dr Carbonell introduced me to Mr Colete, an official<lb/>
in the Ministry. He took us to meet the Ministers Secretary<lb/>
and I went over the project. He seemed much interested<lb/>
and wanted me to meet the Minister in 2 days. But this<lb/>
was <del><unclear></unclear></del> <unclear>way</unclear> the day before I left Havana &amp; I couldn't stay<lb/>
longer.</p>
<p>I do not know exactly what happened. You<lb/>
probably do. Apparently Mr Colete did see the Minister.<lb/>
I dont know whether the President or Vice President<lb/>
had anything to do with it; possibly they did. In any<lb/>
event Im delighted to hear that the <hi rend="superscript">$</hi>50,000 was<lb/>
assigned to the project,</p>
<p>Do you think the work will really be started soon<lb/>
or do you think there may still be delays? What <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
will happen if the work isnt started before the<lb/>
gran <del><unclear>regime</unclear></del> administration closes? Will we have to<lb/>
start all over again? I do hope not. If you can<lb/>
tell me anything about this I will greatly appreciate<lb/>
it. I had a short note about this for Mr Moran<lb/>
but he <unclear>hadnt</unclear> heard much yet. Insert p 2b</p>
<p>Since my return I have been <unclear>going</unclear> over my<lb/>
material and <del>am sending you herewith</del><add><unclear>no, no</unclear></add> not<lb/>
only copies of the photographs we took <del><unclear></unclear></del> together,<lb/>
but some photographs and other items I have<lb/>
which I hope will interest you. <unclear></unclear><lb/>
<unclear></unclear></p>
<pb n="3" id="f04214043"/>
<p>Insert</p>
<p>2 b</p>
<p>Director <del>of the Sanitary Unit of Marianao<lb/>
Dr Noguiera, since you are (I understand) Public Health<lb/>
<unclear>officer</unclear> for Quemados and Marianao</del></p>
<p>In order to be helpful I have sent <add>to the Minister of Public Works</add> a formal letter <unclear>outlining</unclear><lb/>
my plans for the memorializing &amp; preservation of Camp<lb/>
Lazear. I enclose a carbon copy of that letter <add>with the rough sketches of my ideas</add> Please<lb/>
read it carefully &amp; give me your own ideas. <del>I <unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
It would be fine if you could discuss this letter with<lb/>
Mr. Luis <unclear>Danval</unclear>, Director of Architecture of the<lb/>
Ministry of Public Works. And since you are<lb/>
Director of the Sanitary <unclear>Unit</unclear> of Marianao you<lb/>
will undoubtedly have may ideas as to just<lb/>
what kind of an additional <unclear>sanitary</unclear> unit<lb/>
it would be most useful to erect on Camp Lazear<lb/>
as part of the Cuban-American memorial.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04214044"/>
<p>(3</p>
<p><del>I hope you received my recent letter in which I asked<lb/>
if you had your own copy of Dr Howard Kelly's book<lb/>
on Walter Reed and <unclear>Yellow Fever</unclear>, just published about<lb/>
1905.; also do you have a copy of the U. S Senate<lb/>
Document 822 on yellow fever? <unclear>This</unclear> is an important &amp;<lb/>
rare document which contains most of the papers of the<lb/>
U. S. Board. If you don't have these rare books I want<lb/>
to send them to you with my sincere appreciation of all<lb/>
you did for me.</del></p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>Have you heard any more from Dr Presno about the<lb/>
Finlay diary? I am so anxious to have them<lb/>
<unclear>microfilmed</unclear> completely so that you &amp; I can both have<lb/>
copies and, more important, so that the data will<lb/>
not be lost in case the original notebooks are lost,<lb/>
stolen or destroyed by fire or other means. I think<lb/>
it is very important for <unclear>American</unclear> physicians to<lb/>
know much more, as much as possible about Dr<lb/>
Finlay &amp; it is my hope that I can help to accomplish<lb/>
this (as the Cubans should know more about Reed<lb/>
&amp; his colleagues).</p>
<p>If you have not been able to persuade Dr Presno<lb/>
to let you bring them along next month, I will ask<lb/>
the Curator or Chief <unclear>Librarian</unclear> of the Surgeon<lb/>
General's <unclear>Filiaz</unclear> or of the national archives in<lb/>
Washington to make an <hi>official</hi> &amp; <hi>formal</hi> request<lb/>
to the Academy of Sciences of Havana, through<lb/>
Dr Presno, to lend them for micro-filming.<lb/>
In this way Dr Presno &amp; his associates in the<lb/>
Academy will realize how much we desire then</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
