<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04212031">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, March 19, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04212031</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-03-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lyons, Bertha L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Clemons, Harry</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Lucy</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia (Charlottesville, Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-03-19">March 19, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04212031</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, March 19, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Lyons that he will get photostats or photographs of the items that Lyons has requested for the Hall of Fame program. He suggests she contact Kean or Siler to obtain better copies of Reed's birthplace. He also suggests that she write to the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company and ask for their Reed photos. He is not certain he will be able to attend the ceremony.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-03-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, March 19, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04212031"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-03-19">March 19, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Miss Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
Assistant to the Director<lb/>
Hall of Fame, New York University<lb/>
1 Madison Avenue<lb/>
New York 10, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Lyons:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just returned home from Florida four days ago. Since<lb/>
then I have spent considerable time trying to collect the items you wish.<lb/>
I have a date with our Photographic Department this Monday to go through<lb/>
the files and have copies made of many of the items you want. They<lb/>
should be along some time next week.</p>
<p>I have gone over your letter of 12 March very carefully. You<lb/>
have chosen much more than you can possibly use in a program and I assume<lb/>
you did this deliberately so as to give yourself the chance to pick and<lb/>
choose. Five or six of the items that you request are unfortunately not<lb/>
at the moment in my possession. I loaned them to the University of Vir-<lb/>
ginia and I am writing today to Dr. Harry Clemons, head of the Library,<lb/>
asking them to either return the material to me at once or to copy the<lb/>
photographic items for you and send them to you directly (in which case<lb/>
I will stop in Charlottesville May 10 or 11 and collect the material myself).<lb/>
I am asking Doctor Clemons to send you photographs or photostats of the<lb/>
following items:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Photostat of Reed's letter to Mrs. Reed, December 9, 1900.</item>
<item>2. Photostat of Reed's letter to Mrs. Reed, December 25 - 26, 1900.</item>
<item>3. Photostat of Reed's letter to Mrs. Reed, December 31 -<lb/>
January 1 (The New Year's Eve Letter).</item>
<item>4. Photograph of the Congressional Medal. You must use this<lb/>
by all means.</item>
<item>5. Photograph of the Walter Reed Medal of the American Society<lb/>
of Tropical Medicine.</item>
<item>6. Photograph of Lazear's microscope.</item>
<item>7. Photograph of the paper cutter made from wood from Walter<lb/>
Reed's birthplace and presented to Mrs. Reed. I am not<lb/>
certain you will wish to use this latter, but since you<lb/>
have requested it, I will ask them to photograph it.</item>
</list></p>
<p>It does not seem feasible for you to use a few of the items you<lb/>
suggested. You asked for Item 14, the collective works of Finlay. I don't<lb/>
know how you could use this as it is a big book. I am, however, sending you<lb/>
a photograph of the first page of Finlay's original paper in Spanish and the<lb/>
first page of the same paper translated by him into English, which I think<lb/>
would be much more effective. You also ask for Item 15. The Senate document<lb/>
No. 61. This is a book and I don't know how you would use it, but I am sending<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04212032"/>
Miss Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
March 19, 1948<lb/>
you a photograph of the front page of Reed's original paper, the preliminary<lb/>
note. You ask for Item 18, photostats of some of the clippings from Mrs.<lb/>
Reed's scrapbook. I have looked them over. Unfortunately, most of the items<lb/>
would not suit your purpose. Most of them are newspaper clippings about his<lb/>
death and then later articles written some time after his death. Item 25,<lb/>
Reed's last paper never published in full, is, I fear, too technical for your<lb/>
program and seems unnecessary since you are probably going to reproduce the<lb/>
first page of their much more important preliminary note. As to Item 42,<lb/>
letters of Gorgas and Wood, I don't believe you would want anything I have<lb/>
for this program and I do not have the letter which you specifically re-<lb/>
quest. I don't know where it is. You might write General Jefferson R.<lb/>
Kean, 2804 N Street, N. W., Washington, D. C. The same applies to the<lb/>
letter of Doctor Welch which you quoted. Could the latter be in the Welch<lb/>
Library at Hopkins?</p>
<p>The rest of the items you will receive as soon as possible. Most<lb/>
of them from me, next week, the remaining few from the University of Virginia.<lb/>
I am sending Doctor Clemons a carbon copy of this letter and if he prefers<lb/>
not to photograph anything but to return my whole collection to me, I will<lb/>
photograph them as soon as I can; however, at the moment, I would prefer to<lb/>
have him photograph the few items for you and let me pick up all of my material<lb/>
there in May. Enclosed find a carbon copy of this letter to him.</p>
<p>The material I send will include copies of Walter Reed's birthplace<lb/>
before and after it was restored. I am not sure how well my copies will come<lb/>
out. I merely have photographic postcards of the building before and after<lb/>
restoration. The one before restoration is somewhat faded; however, they<lb/>
may copy well. If, in the meantime, you wish to hunt for better copies, my<lb/>
suggestion would be that you write first to General Kean who gave the dedica-<lb/>
tion address at the memorializing of the birthplace and who should have some<lb/>
good photographs; and secondly, to Colonel J. F. Siler, 1835 Eye Street,<lb/>
Northwest, Washington 6, D. C., the Secretary of the Walter Reed Memorial<lb/>
Association which surely would have photographs. If you do get any copies,<lb/>
I would greatly appreciate having one of each (the one before and the one<lb/>
after restoration) for myself as mine are not too adequate.</p>
<p>In addition to the things you ask for I am sending you a few extras<lb/>
and I am certain that you will have more than you need. One more thing. May<lb/>
I suggest that you write to the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company and ask<lb/>
them for copies of the five photographs of Walter Reed from boyhood to man-<lb/>
hood which they used in an educational film strip on the conquest of yellow<lb/>
fever some years ago. Two or three of these photographs I have never seen<lb/>
before and you may wish them for your program.</p>
<p>Had you thought of inviting Dr. L. O. Howard and his daughter, Miss<lb/>
Lucy Howard. I am sure you will know who Doctor Howard is. He was the famous<lb/>
entomologist who helped Reed and his associates identify their mosquitoes. At<lb/>
your request, I am sending photostats of the letters between him and Reed.<lb/>
Doctor Howard is very feeble and would be unable to come, nevertheless he<lb/>
should be invited and it is very possible that his elderly and very charming<lb/>
daughter will come. His address is 45 Pondfield Road West, Bronxville, New York.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04212033"/>
<p>Miss Bertha L. Lyons</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>March 19, 1948</p>
<p>I am somewhat disturbed about my own possible inability to attend<lb/>
your affair. I got the notion that my talk before the International Congress<lb/>
on Tropical Medicine was in Washington on May 18, immediately after which I<lb/>
would go to New York to your affair. I am greatly disappointed to hear that<lb/>
my Washington talk is to be on May 12. Since I cannot waste the whole week<lb/>
east, I will have to come back and I hate to spend the money to come east<lb/>
again six days later for one day, although I would certainly very much like<lb/>
to attend your ceremony.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
