<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04214033">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, April 13, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04214033</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-04-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lyons, Bertha L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="place">U.S. Army Medical Museum, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Belroi (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-04-13">April 13, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04214033</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, April 13, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench sends Lyons a photograph of Reed's grave for possible inclusion in the Hall of Fame exhibit, and discusses the courtesy lines to be used for individual items in the exhibit.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-04-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, April 13, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04214033"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-04-13">April 13, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Miss Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
Assistant to the Director<lb/>
Hall of Fame, New York University<lb/>
1 Madison Avenue<lb/>
New York City, 10, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Lyons:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sending you herewith two small photographs of Reed's grave taken<lb/>
by me, and a large one taken by the U. S. Army Medical Museum. It is hard to<lb/>
know which is the front and which is the back of the grave. As you will see, one<lb/>
side has the cut inscription in the marble and this might be considered the front,<lb/>
but the side which faces the road has his name at the bottom of the stone and a bronze<lb/>
marker. I suppose that is really the front.</p>
<p>None of these pictures are very good. It is in a shady spot and the in-<lb/>
scription would not be visible in a cut. I am sure that the Army Medical Museum<lb/>
has a large one of the other side and since the film number of this one is 44042,<lb/>
I suppose the film number of the other would be 44041 or 44043. I had a copy but<lb/>
I simply can't find it. On Sunday, I actually spent four hours going through all<lb/>
of my files and records, trying to find it for you but I think I must have loaned<lb/>
it to the University of Virginia, although it is not listed specifically on the list<lb/>
of data which I got from them.</p>
<p>Now this large one is my only copy. I am not waiting to have it copied<lb/>
here, I am not sure it is good enough. You may use the two small ones any way you<lb/>
wish but please return the large one to me. Thus, you can do one of three things:<lb/>
(1) Use one of my small ones; (2) get a better print from the U. S. Army Medical<lb/>
Museum, or (3) have a Washington photographer take a special one for you. Doubt-<lb/>
less you have some connections in Washington. It wouldn't be much trouble for a<lb/>
professional to go over to Arlington. The grave is easy to find. As I remember it,<lb/>
one reports to the Lee House and it is just below the Lee House <unclear>a</unclear> short piece.</p>
<p>Now, for your letter of 9 April. I am using the numbers given by you in<lb/>
that letter.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>Item 2: Credit to U. S. <hi>Army</hi> Medical Museum (you left out the word Army).</item>
<item>Item 3: Can be credited to me.</item>
<item>Item 4: Should be credited to the Bettmann Archives. I am glad they loaned<lb/>
it to you free.</item>
</list></p>
<p>As for Items 5 and 13, the letters from Walter Reed to Mrs. Walter Reed, I<lb/>
think you should, by all means, say &ldquo;By courtesy of Mrs. Walter Reed&rdquo;. You do not<lb/>
have to bother about any book because these letters, photostats of which I loaned<lb/>
you, have never been published in photostatic form before. Extracts have been printed<lb/>
but never published in photostatic form. I am sure that this is the first time, for<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04214034"/>
Miss Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
April 13, 1948<lb/>
example, the well known New Year's letter has been published in photostatic form.</p>
<p>Now, these are the circumstances. Mrs. Walter Reed herself has always<lb/>
been most courteous to me and in the first years when I <unclear>knew</unclear> her she did all she<lb/>
could. However, she has failed so much that her obligations are carried on by her<lb/>
son, General Walter Lawrence Reed and her daughter, Mrs. Blossom Reed. It was ac-<lb/>
tually the son and daughter who together decided to put all of their collection of<lb/>
data in my hands so as far as I am concerned, it was largely by the courtesy of<lb/>
General Reed and Mrs. Blossom Reed that I have the material. As you know, I con-<lb/>
sider myself merely the custodian of the material, not actually the personal owner.<lb/>
There is only one possible reason why you might use the expression &ldquo;By courtesy of<lb/>
Mrs. Walter Reed and Dr. Philip S. Hench&rdquo; and that is to prevent Mrs. Reed herself<lb/>
from being bothered by people who, seeing your program, might want to borrow this or<lb/>
that. I would certainly vote for having you say &ldquo;By courtesy of Mrs. Walter Reed&rdquo;.<lb/>
It will be nice for the audience to know that she is still living.</p>
<p>I shall be delighted to receive from you when you are through with them the<lb/>
better photographs of the birthplace and the Walter Reed General Hospital. I don't<lb/>
actually know when the hospital was established, that is, the official date. I have<lb/>
two or three dates, one when they first talked about it and the government ordered<lb/>
it built and one when they broke ground, etc., but what date the Army considers the<lb/>
official date I do not know and I suggest you write to the commanding general of<lb/>
Walter Reed Hospital.</p>
<p>As for Item 8, you say it is a letter from General Reed to Major Kean, Septem-<lb/>
ber 6, 1900. I am not sure whether I have ever seen this letter. Perhaps General<lb/>
Kean gave me a copy. Do you mean that it is from Major Walter Reed or from Lieutenant<lb/>
(now General) Reed?<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>Item 9: Again this should be handled like Items 5 and 13.</item>
<item>Item 11: Same as for Items 5, 9 and 13. This letter is in my possession,<lb/>
I merely loaned it to the University of Virginia. It has never been published photo-<lb/>
statically.</item>
<item>Item 14: Please don't credit this to me. Please credit it to Dr. L. O.<lb/>
Howard. Dr. Howard is now quite senile and his daughter, Miss Lucy Howard gave me<lb/>
the photostat. She has the actual letter. Please write her at 45 Pondfield Road<lb/>
West, Bronxville, New York.</item>
</list></p>
<p>I am sorry that you see fit to leave out the medal. A Congressional Medal<lb/>
of course, carries a high rating and even though actually Major Reed never saw this<lb/>
medal as it was granted by Congress many years after his death; nevertheless, the<lb/>
fact that Congress so honored him and his colleagues is most impressive. Did you know<lb/>
that the names of Reed and his colleagues are the <hi>only</hi> names published (by law) every<lb/>
year on the Roll of Honor of the Army. All other names are published usually just once.</p>
<p>I am sending a note to General Reed and Mrs. Blossom Reed asking them about<lb/>
the matter of referring directly to their mother. In my opinion this is certainly<lb/>
what should be done unless they wish otherwise, in which case you might say &ldquo;By courtesy<lb/>
of the family of Major Reed&rdquo;, or some such.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04214035"/>
<p>Miss Bertha L. Lyons</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>April 13, 1948</p>
<p>You ask me to let you know what the prints cost. I don't want these to<lb/>
cost you anything. As I told you, the Clinic printed some and I had others printed<lb/>
in town, but I should like to make this small contribution to your venture and you<lb/>
can more than repay me by doing two things: (1) Let me have a fairly good seat at<lb/>
the affair and (2) Let me have the privilege of paying for about 50 programs. I<lb/>
correspond with a great many people in regard to this hobby of mine and I know many<lb/>
of them would love to have a program. At this early date, you could probably con-<lb/>
tract to have 50 extra programs printed at my expense. I don't imagine it would be<lb/>
very much.</p>
<p>Mrs. Hench will not be along.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
