<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04214013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, April 5, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lyons, Bertha L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04214013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-04-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">Belroi (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-04-05">April 5, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04214013</idno>
<title>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, April 5, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lyons is surprised and pleased at the large number of photostats of Reed material that Hench has sent to the Hall of Fame. She discusses the use of the material and gives Hench directions to the Hall of Fame, where he will attend a ceremony.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-04-05">
<head>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, April 5, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04214013"/>
<p>Every American is a shareholder in the Hall of Fame<lb/>
HALL OF FAME: NEW YORK UNIVERSITY<lb/>
I MADISON AVENUE &middot; NEW YORK IO, N. Y.<lb/>
Telephone: MURRAY HILL 3-4469<lb/>
<date value="1948-04-05">5 April 1948</date>
Dear Dr. Hench:</p>
<p>Your registered air mail letter of April 1<lb/>
with all of the photostats arrived this morning, and I must<lb/>
confess that when I opened the envelope and saw the amount of<lb/>
material that you had gone to the trouble to assemble for me,<lb/>
I had considerable pangs of conscience. However, after read-<lb/>
ing the last sentence in your first paragraph, I am selfish<lb/>
enough to believe that I have done you a good turn insofar<lb/>
as having made it possible for you to have your data under<lb/>
one roof. But, in all seriousness, I am very much indebted<lb/>
to you and scarcely know how to thank you for all of your<lb/>
trouble.</p>
<p>I have just had time enough to <add>go</add> through the<lb/>
material and mark each piece on the back, and to read your<lb/>
letter with its valuable suggestions. First of all, let me put<lb/>
your mind at ease as to the reproduction of any personal material<lb/>
relating to the Reeds contained in the letters of Walter Reed<lb/>
to his wife. We shall certainly not make use of anything but<lb/>
information which would give the lay person an idea of how Reed<lb/>
went along with his experiments, and perhaps some of his enthusiasm<lb/>
when he found himself on the road to success. I agree with you<lb/>
fully that one is entitled to privacy and we shall not invade it.</p>
<p>I have not had the time yet to compare the photo-<lb/>
stats with your recommendations of items to be reproduced in our<lb/>
program. I want to go over them all very carefully with Dr. Angell<lb/>
and get his reactions to some of these things. Really, there is<lb/>
so much of interest and so little space in our program, that I<lb/>
think we are going to find it rather difficult to make the choices<lb/>
and have the reproductions of interest to all concerned. But,<lb/>
we will do the best we can. Of that you may be sure.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04214014"/>
<p>Dr. Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>April 5, 1948</p>
<p>In reproducing the birthplace, we plan to put this<lb/>
note under it:<lb/>
<hi>The birthplace of Reed, Belro<del>y</del><add>i</add>, Gloucester County, Virginia.</hi><lb/>
This modest cabin (purchased and dedicated by the<lb/>
Virginia State Medical Society) was occupied by<lb/>
Walter Reed's parents as a temporary refuge during<lb/>
the time their <unclear>parsonage</unclear> (which had been badly damaged<lb/>
by fire) was being rebuilt.<lb/>
We submitted this to General Reed and he has given us his approval<lb/>
of it. Don't you think that it covers it pretty well?</p>
<p>I note what you say with regard to returning the<lb/>
material to you after it has served our purpose, and in the instances<lb/>
where our printer does not have to cut the photostat for deletion, etc.<lb/>
we shall certainly return everything to you.</p>
<p>I am delighted that you now plan to attend the ceremony.<lb/>
I communicated with the La Guardia Airport and learned from them that<lb/>
you should allow at least an hour after you get out of your plane <del>and</del> to<lb/>
come to New York. The limousine from the airport will land you at<lb/>
42nd Street and it will take you an additional forty-five minutes to<lb/>
go to the Heights where the ceremony will be held. If you can let<lb/>
me know about four days in advance of May 20 when you expect to arrive<lb/>
at 42nd Street in New York, perhaps I can arrange to send one of our<lb/>
cars for you. We are planning to send our participants in the pro-<lb/>
gram up to the University in special cars, and I could leave room<lb/>
in one car for you. But as I said, I would have to know at least<lb/>
four days in advance in order that I could route my cars properly.<lb/>
I understand that the trip from the Newark Airport to 42nd Street<lb/>
entails about the same amount of time, so that you would have to<lb/>
count on an hour and three-quarters, at least, after leaving the<lb/>
ceremony at University Heights.</p>
<p>There will be a Procession before the Exercises<lb/>
start and those participating in the Procession (as I hope you will)<lb/>
will assemble in the library of the University at the Heights<lb/>
no later than 2:15 D. S. T. The Procession will get under way<lb/>
precisely at 2:30 and the Exercises in the auditorium, where the<lb/>
ceremony<del>,</del> will be held, will commence promptly at 3 o'clock. The<lb/>
program should take one hour and fifteen minutes only, provided<lb/>
the speakers adhere to the time schedule which we have allotted for<lb/>
them, which would make the hour 4:15 or 4:30. After that there<lb/>
will be a Tea in the Faculty Club which we hope that you and<lb/>
Mrs. Hench can also attend. That, however, will have to be something<lb/>
which you must decide depending entirely upon your plane schedule.<lb/>
I understand that we go on Daylight Saving Time here in New York<lb/>
on the 25th of April.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04214015"/>
<p>Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
April 5, 1948</p>
<p>With every good wish to you, and with renewed<lb/>
appreciation of everything that you have done for us, believe<lb/>
me,</p>
<p>Sincerely yours,<lb/>
Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
Assistant to the Director<lb/>
BLL:YZ<lb/>
P. S. Do please tell me how much we owe you for the<lb/>
photostats!!<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
