<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04223024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, May 17, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lyons, Bertha L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04223024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-05-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-05-17">May 17, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04223024</idno>
<title>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, May 17, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lyons informs Hench that she has tried to recognize Finlay as fully as possible in the Hall of Fame event, but insists that the event honors Reed, not Finlay.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-05-17">
<head>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, May 17, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04223024"/>
<opener>
Every American is a shareholder in the Hall of Fame<lb/>
<dateline>
HALL OF FAME : NEW YORK UNIVERSITY<lb/>
I MADISON AVENUE &middot; NEW YORK IO, N.Y.<lb/>
Telephone: MURRAY HILL 3-4469<lb/>
<date value="1948-05-17">17 May 1948</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you for your letter of the 15th of May, which<lb/>
we received this morning. I think the way you handled the<lb/>
Finlay matter in Washington was very diplomatic, and I hope<lb/>
that the newspapers here will give a proper slant to their<lb/>
story. Of course you know that we issue the releases from our<lb/>
Publicity Department of the University, and frankly, so far<lb/>
as we are concerned at the moment, (and I say this without<lb/>
deprecating Finlay's part in the extermination of yellow fever)<lb/>
Reed is really the person we are honoring. As you know, I have<lb/>
tried to give Finlay as much credit as possible in the makeup<lb/>
of our own program of the event, and I purposely chose letters<lb/>
of Walter Reed in which he mentioned, not only Finlay, but<lb/>
Carroll and Lazear. As a matter of fact, Finlay is mentioned<lb/>
three times in the program: first, in the explanatory addenda<lb/>
accompanying the painting by Dean Cornwell; second, his photo-<lb/>
graph along with those of Lazear, Carroll and <unclear>Agramonte</unclear> and<lb/>
third, in the letter of December 9 in which Reed gives Finlay<lb/>
credit for the mosquito theory. I think, in a program honoring<lb/>
Walter Reed, this is more than generous to Finlay. In the final<lb/>
analysis, as you and I know, it was as Dr. Joseph Goldberger<lb/>
said, Reed who &ldquo;converted a discredited theory into an established<lb/>
doctrine.&rdquo; The Reed experiments are in many respects like the<lb/>
anaesthesia problems. Of course Wells and Long and the others<lb/>
all made their experiments with anaesthesia, but actually, until<lb/>
Morton performed the operation at the Massachusetts General<lb/>
Hospital, humanity was not benefited. Personally, I feel the<lb/>
same way about Reed and yellow fever. Finlay had his theory of<lb/>
the mosquito, but until Reed and the other members of the<lb/>
Commission were set to work nothing was done about it.</p>
<p>I know how important it is to be diplomatic with the<lb/>
Cubans in this matter, and I shall, as you suggest, call<lb/>
Dr. Nogueira on the telephone and confirm the invitation which<lb/>
was sent to him some time ago. His name was given to us a long<lb/>
time ago by the American Foundation for Tropical Medicine, and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04223025"/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
2.<lb/>
May 17, 1948<lb/>
the invitation was sent to him but we have had neither a regret<lb/>
nor an acceptance, which I think is being a little over temper-<lb/>
mental. Of course, there is the possibility that the invitation<lb/>
arrived in Cuba when he had already left for the Congresses in<lb/>
Washington.</p>
<p>In view of what you say about this whole thing and the<lb/>
controversy in general, I shall tell Dr. Angell of the situation,<lb/>
and I am sure that he will handle it diplomatically, though in all<lb/>
fairness to you, I think I must tell you that I do not feel that<lb/>
Dr. Angell will be inclined at our ceremony to give credit to<lb/>
Dr. Finlay to any measurable extent, when the ceremony is in<lb/>
honor of Walter Reed. However, I shall put the matter to<lb/>
him as diplomatically as I know how.</p>
<p>You probably have not had a chance to see any of the<lb/>
Sunday New York papers (May 16). The New York Times and the New<lb/>
York Tribune both carried good stories of the Reed ceremony on<lb/>
the 20th and gave biographical facts. This was our first story<lb/>
which we issued in connection with the event. There will be<lb/>
another story that will be released by the University for<lb/>
Thursday morning. However, this story will carry few, if any,<lb/>
biographical facts. It will merely be a story of the event,<lb/>
featuring the actual exercises, and more particularly, the<lb/>
speakers and those who will attend.</p>
<p>You may be interested to know that in the address of<lb/>
General Bliss no mention has been made of Dr. Finlay, but<lb/>
Dr. Sawyer will say this when he reads his paper on Reed:</p>
<p>&ldquo;We are here to honor Walter Reed and voice the<lb/>
gratitude of a nation to the man who freed it from the<lb/>
ever-recurring terror of yellow fever. It was he who<lb/>
conceived and directed the masterful experiments in<lb/>
Cuba which showed how the disease was spread and the<lb/>
way in which it could be prevented. These experiments<lb/>
were so simple that the man on the street could under-<lb/>
stand them and so conclusive that the scientist accepted<lb/>
the results as proof. No longer could the health<lb/>
authorities hesitate to accept the mosquito theory of<lb/>
Carlos Finlay, now so convincingly proved. With this<lb/>
new knowledge the public could be given complete<lb/>
protection against this terrible pestilence, and many<lb/>
futile and burdensome measures could be abandoned.<lb/>
To few has it been given to render so important a<lb/>
service in so short a time and with such immediate<lb/>
and vast benefit to mankind.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04223026"/>
<p>Dr. Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>3.</p>
<p>May 17, 1948</p>
<p>Farther along in his address, Dr. Sawyer says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;There were several recent developments in medical<lb/>
science that suggested the possibility of insect trans-<lb/>
mission in yellow fever. It soon became apparent to<lb/>
Reed that it ought to be settled once and for all<lb/>
whether the disease was spread by a mosquito, as had<lb/>
been maintained for nineteen years by Carlos Finlay . . .<lb/>
Dr. Finlay supplied eggs of the suspected <hi>culex fasciatus</hi><lb/>
mosquito and told Dr. Lazear how to care for the<lb/>
insects.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Incidentally, I think Dr. Sawyer's paper is an admirable one<lb/>
giving credit not only to Finlay but to all of Reed's colleagues.<lb/>
I think you will like it very much.</p>
<p>I have not yet received Dr. Salisbury's paper and so<lb/>
I do not know what he is saying in his presentation remarks.<lb/>
I doubt very much whether he will cover the biographical angle.</p>
<p>I wired you this morning advising you that the car with<lb/>
the Reed family will stop for you at the Waldorf Astoria at two<lb/>
o'clock d.s.t. on Thursday, the 20th.</p>
<p>I hope you as a physician do not think me presumptuous<lb/>
in offering my opinion regarding Finlay in this matter. Frankly,<lb/>
as a lay person I am very ignorant of the whole matter from a<lb/>
medical aspect. I am merely viewing it in the light of history<lb/>
and what history has now established, namely, that it was<lb/>
Reed's persistence and hard work and all of the experiments which<lb/>
he performed, which made it possible to eliminate the scourge of<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
Assistant to the Director</signed>
BLL:yz<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I do not know how familiar you are with the New York press,<lb/>
but it is not easy to tell our newspapers what to say and<lb/>
what not to say. They are men of very determined opinions<lb/>
of their own, but if you feel that you would like to talk<lb/>
to the members of the press after the ceremony issuing a<lb/>
statement in your own name, we certainly have no objection<lb/>
to your doing so.<lb/>
P.P.S. I have just received and read <unclear>AV. Salisbury's</unclear> address-<lb/>
<unclear>he pays a</unclear> magnificent <unclear>trebute to</unclear> Finlay &amp; the others,<lb/>
B.L.L.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
