<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04224003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, June 3, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lyons, Bertha L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04224003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-06-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-06-03">June 3, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04224003</idno>
<title>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, June 3, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lyons returns material on loan from Hench for the Hall of Fame ceremony. She also sends copies of other material which might prove useful for Hench's book.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-06-03">
<head>Letter from Bertha L. Lyons to Philip Showalter Hench, June 3, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04224003"/>
<opener>
Every American is a shareholder in the Hall of Fame<lb/>
<dateline>
HALL OF FAME : NEW YORK UNIVERSITY<lb/>
I MADISON AVENUE &middot; NEW YORK IO, N.Y.<lb/>
Telephone: MURRAY HILL 3-4469<lb/>
<date value="1948-06-03">3 June, 1948.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>For the past few days I have been going<lb/>
through all of the material returned to me from the printer,<lb/>
as well as data received from other sources in an effort<lb/>
to correlate all of the material you sent to me. I have<lb/>
found everything, and you will find enclosed, first, all<lb/>
of the material you sent to me under date of April 1, 1948,<lb/>
with the exception of your item #13, which is the photostat<lb/>
of a letter from Reed to his wife dated October 6, 1900. I<lb/>
have retained this for our own files because we reproduced<lb/>
this letter in the program. I have photostats of all of<lb/>
the other letters which we reproduced, and which came to us<lb/>
from other sources, in some instances.</p>
<p>Second: I am also enclosing the following, all of<lb/>
which I hope will be helpful to you in the publication of<lb/>
your proposed volume:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1 - A few inserts of the Wyeth reproductions of the Cornwell<lb/>
painting</item>
<item>2 - Clear photostats of Reed's letter to General Truby,<lb/>
dated December 10, 1900</item>
<item>3 - Lazear's microscope</item>
<item>4 - Paper cutter presented to Mrs. Reed by Reed</item>
<item>5 - Walter Reed Medal from the American Society of Tropical<lb/>
Medicine</item>
<item>6 - A few miscellaneous photostats of letters from Reed which<lb/>
I am sure you will recognize, and which probably are al-<lb/>
ready in your possession. I send them merely because they<lb/>
are quite clear in some respects, and there may be portions<lb/>
which you may wish to reproduce in your book</item>
<item>7 - A good photograph of the Walter Reed General Hospital</item>
<item>8 - A good photographic view of the University of Virginia</item>
<item>9 - Pathological Building, as furnished us by the Metropolitan<lb/>
Life Insurance Company</item>
<item>10 - Photographs of the tomb at Arlington (4 copies)</item>
<item>11 - Photographs of the Birthplace (2 copies)</item>
<item>12 - Photographs of Reed's Congressional Medal (1 large and 1 small)</item>
</list></p>
<pb n="2" id="f04224004"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>3 June 1948.</p>
<p>In going over all of the material, I was struck<lb/>
with the many, many things of interest which might have<lb/>
been included in our program, but which unfortunately could<lb/>
not be used for lack of space. I tried to give to the aver-<lb/>
age lay person a succinct story of yellow fever, and a glimpse<lb/>
of Reed's character, more particularly with regard to his<lb/>
relations with his colleagues during those trying days when<lb/>
he was making his experiments. Of course, physicians and<lb/>
surgeons know the story of yellow fever, or should know<lb/>
it (if I may say so), but I was trying to prepare a program<lb/>
which would be of interest to adults and children in the<lb/>
schools and colleges to whom these programs are sent for a<lb/>
few years after the event. If I have failed, I should at<lb/>
least be given &ldquo;A&rdquo; for effort.</p>
<p>For my own part, I have been thoroughly compensated<lb/>
in working on this ceremony, first, because every short biography<lb/>
I read of Reed was rather disappointing. They all seemed to<lb/>
leave me with the idea that Reed tried to get all of the credit<lb/>
for the extermination of yellow fever, whereas, after I became<lb/>
steeped in the reading of full length biographies and other<lb/>
material concerning Reed, I learned of the magnanimity of the<lb/>
man.</p>
<p>Again, my deepest appreciation to you for all of<lb/>
your aid to us in the prepar<add>a</add>tion of our material. I s<del>h</del>hall<lb/>
be looking forward, with keen anticipation, to the publication<lb/>
of your own volume.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially yours,</salute>
<signed>Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
Assistant to the Director</signed>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
