<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04223018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, May 15, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04223018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-05-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lyons, Bertha L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-05-15">May 15, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04223018</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, May 15, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses Cuban attitudes toward the &ldquo;Reed versus Finlay&rdquo; debate, and describes his reaction to a threatened protest by the Cuban delegation. Hench was careful to include Finlay items in his exhibit and slide show, and to praise Finlay in his lecture.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-05-15">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Bertha L. Lyons, May 15, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04223018"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-05-15">May 15, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Miss Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
Assistant to the Director<lb/>
Hall of Fame<lb/>
1 Madison Avenue<lb/>
New York, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Lyons:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just returned from an eastern trip which included the exercises<lb/>
to commemorate the demonstration <del>of</del><add>by</add> Walter Reed of the mosquito transmission of<lb/>
yellow fever, before the Fourth International Congress on Tropical Medicine.<lb/>
In connection with this, may I discuss two points.</p>
<p>1. The attitude of the Cubans towards &ldquo;Reed versus Finlay&rdquo;. You are<lb/>
probably familiar with some of this. Most Cubans believe that Americans neg-<lb/>
lect Finlay and give all the credit to Reed, and certainly the Cubans give<lb/>
practically all the credit to Finlay and none to Reed. The argument is an<lb/>
unfortunate one and there is much to be said for the Cuban viewpoint because<lb/>
there are many American textbooks that don't even mention Finlay in the dis-<lb/>
cussion of yellow fever. In Cuba there are dozens of memorials to Finlay,<lb/>
many in Havana alone and although there is a bust of Lazear, there is no bust<lb/>
of Reed and indeed his name is not even mentioned on the pediments of any of<lb/>
the various memorials. However, so far as I know, there is not a single statue<lb/>
or memorial to Finlay in the United States. Indeed there aren't many to Reed<lb/>
except of course the Walter Reed Hospital and the Schuler busts. In any event,<lb/>
we were disturbed in Washington by the attitude of certain Cuban delegates.</p>
<p>Under the auspices of the Surgeon General's Office, there was at the<lb/>
Congress an exhibit on Walter Reed. <unclear>I</unclear> was asked to bring certain material and<lb/>
I purposely included three items on Finlay. Two days before the memorial cere-<lb/>
mony, a Havana newspaper published a statement something to the effect that &ldquo;As<lb/>
usual the Americans are completely ignoring Finlay, etc., etc.&rdquo; The word was<lb/>
passed to the Cubans in Washington (or vice versa). Anyhow, I was informed that<lb/>
a group of angry Cubans were seen examining the Walter Reed exhibit and talking<lb/>
in very excited tones on Tuesday morning. Later that morning a delegation visited<lb/>
Doctor Soper much disturbed at the &ldquo;neglect of Finlay&rdquo;. They stated they were<lb/>
in the mood to present a formal protest to the State Department. Doctor Soper<lb/>
and I had long been aware of this controversy and I had taken great pains to in-<lb/>
clude in my illustrated lecture a photograph of Finlay, one of his paper and<lb/>
another slide quoting him. Furthermore, I side-stepped the basic controversy<lb/>
and without <unclear>d<del>is</del><add>e</add>tracting</unclear> from Reed, praised Finlay highly. Doctor Soper revamped<lb/>
his remarks considerably and at the ceremony Wednesday evening apparently we<lb/>
satisfied the Cubans because afterwards several came up to me and expressed<lb/>
their &ldquo;deep appreciation&rdquo;, etc. One of the prominent young Cuban physicians<lb/>
is Dr. Pedro Nogueira who in the last administration had a fairly high govern-<lb/>
mental position in the Health Department. He is now out politically and is now<lb/>
only health officer for Marianao but is nevertheless a dominant figure among<lb/>
younger Cubans. He is a very dynamic young man and is writing a book on the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04223019"/>
Miss Bertha L. Lyons<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
May 15, 1948<lb/>
conquest of yellow fever. He is much more fair than most Cubans and recognizes<lb/>
the relative importance of the work of Finlay and Reed. After my talk and after<lb/>
he expressed his appreciation of it, he admitted to me that the University of<lb/>
Havana had that day wired him asking him to confirm or deny the Havana newspaper<lb/>
reports of the day before. He told me that he was entirely satisfied with<lb/>
what Doctor Soper and I had said, that it was &ldquo;entirely perfect&rdquo; and that he<lb/>
was cabling Havana to that effect.</p>
<p>Now, I have told you all this so that you can avoid this trouble which<lb/>
the Congress ran into. Of course there will be few Cubans at your ceremony<lb/>
but rest assured that there will be those in the audience who will be deliberately<lb/>
looking for slights to Finlay and who will report the same to Havana. I am sure<lb/>
that your speakers all know of this controversy, certainly General Bliss and<lb/>
Doctor Sawyer do. But if possible, the newspaper reporters should get matters<lb/>
straight. Our Washington ceremony was reported in two or three papers and<lb/>
one paper reported my talk in some detail. Again, nobody mentioned Finlay.<lb/>
If therefore, you have any way of asking the New York reporters to give Finlay<lb/>
due credit, I think you could help along the cause of Cuban-American amity.</p>
<p>Bliss</p>
<p>2. Doctor Nogueira is now in New York. He heard of your ceremony<lb/>
and is very anxious to come. He will be at the Governor Clinton Hotel, New<lb/>
York City, May 17 to 31. His wife and five-year old son are with him. May<lb/>
I earnestly suggest and request that you telephone him and invite him personally<lb/>
to the affair. I don't think his wife or son would attend it (perhaps they would)<lb/>
but I know he wants to and in all fairness to him he is trying hard to show Reed's<lb/>
part in his book.</p>
<p>I had a grand time with the Reed's in Washington, a delightful dinner<lb/>
the evening of the 12th, etc. General Reed told me that as he understands it,<lb/>
the <unclear>or</unclear> that is to meet him at the Pennsylvania Hotel will pick me up at the<lb/>
Waldorf the <del>morning</del><add>afternoon</add> of the 20th. The Reeds are coming in the morning by train<lb/>
and leaving late that afternoon by train. If it would be more convenient for<lb/>
all concerned, why don't I meet them at the Hotel Pennsylvania; on the other<lb/>
hand, if they are coming up town anyhow, I suppose they could call for me at<lb/>
the Waldorf. I will do whatever you wish. I will arrive at the Waldorf about<lb/>
10 the morning of the 20th. Could you leave some sort of a message instructing<lb/>
me what to do?</p>
<p>I note on the invitation that &ldquo;academic robes may be worn but are not<lb/>
obligatory&rdquo;. I shall therefore bring my gown.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
