<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04224021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Wilbur A. Sawyer, June 29, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04224021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-06-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-06-29">June 29, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04224021</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Wilbur A. Sawyer, June 29, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench has edited the manuscript and selected photographs for the publication of his Washington, D.C. lecture.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-06-29">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Wilbur A. Sawyer, June 29, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04224021"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-06-29">June 29, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Your reference No.: IC 512.819<lb/>
Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer<lb/>
Secretary General<lb/>
Fourth International Congress on Tropical Medicine<lb/>
Department of State<lb/>
Washington 25, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Sawyer:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On the evening after I gave my talk in Washington, you told me you<lb/>
wanted the manuscript edited and the photographs selected and returned to you<lb/>
almost immediately. Regretfully I had to tell you that I was going to be away<lb/>
from town for some time. I have just returned from the east and have quickly<lb/>
made a few corrections to the copy of my manuscript which you sent to me. Most<lb/>
of the changes are very minor but the two inserts quoting contemporaneous Wash-<lb/>
ington newspapers which were not in the original draft I am anxious to have in-<lb/>
cluded.</p>
<p>If at all possible, I would like to have the article illustrated and<lb/>
I am offering you five photographs for your consideration. These are numbered<lb/>
on the back.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>Number 1 is an 1873 newspaper cartoon illustrating the horrors of a<lb/>
&ldquo;plague-stricken city&rdquo;; namely, Shreveport in the epidemic of 1873.</item>
<item>Number 2 represents one of the southern epidemics of 1888 and illustrates<lb/>
the shotgun quarrantine of yellow fever in Florida.</item>
<item>By separate post I will be sending you an enlargement of the central<lb/>
view of Number 3, showing Canal Street, New Orleans deserted except for hearses<lb/>
during one of the epidemics of yellow fever, with a pall of smoke from the tar<lb/>
pots and cannon fire hanging over the city.</item>
<item>Number 4: I will send you in a day or so also an enlargement of the<lb/>
lower central view showing the piling up of the unburied coffins.</item>
<item>Number 5 shows the remains of Building Number 1 as I visited it just<lb/>
recently in March, 1948. Dr. Pedro Hogueira of Havana is on the left (He was<lb/>
one of the official delegates to your Congress.); Johnny Moran is in the middle<lb/>
and I am on the right.</item>
</list></p>
<p>If you decide to select only three, I will let you choose. My own<lb/>
preferences would be Numbers 1, 3 and 5.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04224022"/>
<p>Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>June 29, 1948</p>
<p>I have an ulterior motive in offering Picture No. 5, the current remains<lb/>
of Building Number 1. I would like the present generation of physicians to realize<lb/>
that Camp Lazear has been rediscovered and that Building Number 1 still stands.<lb/>
As you know, I have waged a campaign to memorialize the camp and preserve Building<lb/>
Number 1. I believe I have been successful as the Cuban Government recently set<lb/>
aside $50,000 as a preliminary sum for the preservation of the camp site and<lb/>
building, but I am anxious to have those interested in tropical medicine know<lb/>
about this.</p>
<p>Will reprints be available? When we receive proof we will read it,<lb/>
correct it and return it promptly by air mail, if you wish. Please address it<lb/>
to me but I will have it returned through our Editorial Department and at that<lb/>
time we can order the desired number of reprints. You will note that at the<lb/>
bottom of the manuscript I inserted the sentence &ldquo;An illustrated lecture presented<lb/>
before.....&rdquo; It may be that you will not wish to have the last part of that sentence<lb/>
on the original printing, since obviously the proceedings is that of the Congress,<lb/>
but I would like to have at least the first three words printed in the proceedings;<lb/>
namely, &ldquo;...An illustrated address&rdquo;. We could have the whole sentence appear on<lb/>
the reprints.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
