<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04232001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">List of items related to yellow fever in the possession of Philip Showalter Hench, by [Philip Showalter Hench], [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04232001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Houston, Martha P.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Belroi (Va.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Post Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04232001</idno>
<title>List of items related to yellow fever in the possession of Philip Showalter Hench, by [Philip Showalter Hench], [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This document describes items related to yellow fever in detail; including letters, reports, medical charts, medals, artifacts, books, photographs, interview transcripts, magazines, and sketches.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>List of items related to yellow fever in the possession of Philip Showalter Hench, by [Philip Showalter Hench], [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04232001"/>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head>SOME ITEMS IN THE COLLECTION OF DATA ON THE CONQUEST OF<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER NOW IN THE POSSESSION OF DR. PHILIP S. HENCH.<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC, ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
Items concerning Major Walter Reed, Doctors Jesse Lazear,<lb/>
James Carroll, Aristides Agramonte, and the volunteers<lb/>
for the yellow fever experiments.</head>
<item>1. Original letters of Walter Reed to his <unclear>fianc&eacute;</unclear> (1875) and letters written later<lb/>
(1879) when he was stationed at western Army posts after he married Mrs. Reed.<lb/>
(Many such letters).</item>
<item>2. Original letters of Reed to Mrs. Reed June 1900 to February 1901, written from<lb/>
Camp Columbia, Cuba describing the day by day progress of the yellow fever ex-<lb/>
periments. Describing of first, and later successful cases; description and<lb/>
drawings, in Reed's own hand, of the little experimental buildings.</item>
<item>3. The original of the famous, oft-quoted &ldquo;New Year's eve letter&rdquo; from Reed to Mrs.<lb/>
Reed, written just before, at and after midnight, December 31, 1900 - January 1,<lb/>
1901, in a mood of exaltation and thankfulness to God for the successful con-<lb/>
clusion of their work.</item>
<item>4. Fragments of the last three letters (only ones remaining) written by Doctor<lb/>
Lazear to his wife; written from Cuba the last two months of Lazear's life. In<lb/>
the last one he admits to secret successful experiments &ldquo;of which I have told<lb/>
nobody, not a soul.&rdquo; (Originals)</item>
<item>5. The actual charts of the experimental cases of yellow fever, including the fever<lb/>
charts of Carroll, the first experimental case, of &ldquo;XY&rdquo; (Private Dean) the<lb/>
second case, of Lazear (fatal case) and later cases including those of Kissinger<lb/>
and Moran, the first two soldiers who volunteered to Reed for the conclusive<lb/>
experiments.</item>
<item>6. Telegram to Mrs. Lazear announcing the death of Doctor Lazear, September 25, 1900.</item>
<item>7. Special Congressional medal presented posthumously to Reed. Each of the surviving<lb/>
members of the Army Yellow Fever Board and the volunteers received one such medal.</item>
<item>8. The Walter Reed Medal presented to Mrs. Reed by the American Society of Tropical<lb/>
Medicine.</item>
<item>9. Small hand microscope of Doctor Lazear, undoubtedly used in Cuba.</item>
<item>10. The small, badly battered little smokestack (only about 7 inches long and 5 inches<lb/>
in diameter) from &ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo;, the experimental building in which it<lb/>
was proved that fomites are non-infectious. The whole theory of the infectivity<lb/>
of &ldquo;fomites&rdquo; (clothes, personal belongings, household objects, etc.) which was<lb/>
held for so many years and which cost millions and millions of dollars to sup-<lb/>
port--this theory &ldquo;went up in smoke&rdquo; through this very smokestack.</item>
<item>11. A very short biographical sketch written by Carroll in his own handwriting; a<lb/>
letter.</item>
<item>12. Letters of Agramonte defining the role he played in the experimental work.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f04232002"/>
<item>-2-</item>
<item>13. Reprints of Finlay (whose theory Reed et al proved) written before the work of<lb/>
the U. S. Arym Yellow Fever Board.</item>
<item>14. The collective works of Finlay (one volume) including the original paper on<lb/>
the mosquito hypothesis.</item>
<item>15. Senate Document No. 61, the memorial volume published by the United States<lb/>
Government which includes all the papers of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Board.<lb/>
This particular copy (my personal copy) is autographed here and there by most<lb/>
of the survivors who took part in the experiments.</item>
<item>16. Dozens of other letters by Reed, Lazear, Carroll, Agramonte, etc. Originals.</item>
<item>17. Lazear's school books, used when he was a boy in preparatory school, Trinity Hall,<lb/>
at Washington, Pennsylvania, and many original photograpsh of Lazear as boy,<lb/>
student and physician.</item>
<item>18. Mrs. Walter Reed's scrap book concerning her husband, mostly newspaper clippings.</item>
<item>19. Many old original photographs of Reed, Lazear, Carroll, Agramonte and others,<lb/>
mostly unpublished, including one small one of Reed in civilian clothes on board<lb/>
ship, enroute to Cuba to begin the yellow fever work.</item>
<item>20. Reed's captains bars, embroidered shoulder insignia for formal uniform.</item>
<item>21. Paper cutter presented to Mrs. Reed made from wood from the little building<lb/>
where Reed was born, in Belroi, Virginia.</item>
<item>22. All of Reed's diplomas and certificates (college, medical school, hospitals,<lb/>
honorary degrees) including Reed's diploma from the University of Virginia.<lb/>
I have originals and photostatic copies.</item>
<item>23. Inumerable, photographs, old and new, showing the places and buildings in Cuba<lb/>
where Lazear, Reed, and their associates performed their experiments at the<lb/>
Camp Columbia Post Hospital, the Camp Lazear, etc. These include old Army<lb/>
photographs taken in 1900 and many photographs taken by me in 1938 and 1940.</item>
<item>24. Photastats of the old diary or &ldquo;day book&rdquo; of the owner of the property rented<lb/>
to Reed which became &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;. It was our discovery of this diary which<lb/>
gave us the final proof that we had discovered the &ldquo;lost Camp Lazear&rdquo; after<lb/>
40 years of neglect.</item>
<item>25. Photostats of Reed's last paper written just before he died and never published<lb/>
in full. Part of it was used as his last published paper.</item>
<item>26. Photostats of one of the two &ldquo;lost laboratory notebooks&rdquo; of Lazear and Reed;<lb/>
about 100 pages.</item>
<item>27. In addition, over 20 box files (D-T invoice files) with copies of hundreds of<lb/>
documents, manuscripts, reports by and about Reed and his associates; mostly<lb/>
copies (photographs and photostats) of the original official Army or Governmental<lb/>
reports, orders and documents, concerning the conquest of yellow fever.</item>
<pb n="3" id="f04232003"/>
<item>- 3 -</item>
<item>28. The original check book with stubs, entries, etc., used by Major Kean to pay<lb/>
Reed's volunteers and the expenses of Camp Lazear.</item>
<item>29. Letters of Lazear to his mother from the year 1890 to September 18, 1900, the<lb/>
day he developed his fatal illness. These include the last letter written from<lb/>
Cuba before his death. Mostly personal data. He did not write of his experi-<lb/>
ments to his mother <unclear>lost</unclear> he frighten her. Lazear took sick September 18 and<lb/>
died September 25, 1900. In addition, a few boyhood letters of 1875 and 1876.</item>
<item>30. Unpublished manuscripts by Kissinger, one of Reed's volunteers telling of his<lb/>
experiences in developing experimental yellow fever.</item>
<item>31. Same for Moran, another volunteer.</item>
<item>32. Same for Andrus, another volunteer.</item>
<item>33. Same for Bullard, a late volunteer.</item>
<item>34. Stenographic interview between me and Doctor Cooke, an early volunteer.</item>
<item>35. Same for Doctor Pinto, an early volunteer.</item>
<item>36. Original description of Reed's fatal illness and death, typewritten and signed<lb/>
in 1901 by the Army Surgeon in charge.</item>
<item>37. Autographed photograph of Carroll.</item>
<item>38. Autographed photograph of Agramonte.</item>
<item>39. Original handwritten brief report of Carroll to the Surgeon General, August 29,<lb/>
1906, reviewing his own (Carroll's) part in the experiments.</item>
<item>40. Typewritten interviews between Walter Reed's son and daughter and myself.</item>
<item>41. A few original letters of Doctor Finlay.</item>
<item>42. Some original letters of Gorgas and of General Leonard Wood.</item>
<item>43. Autographed photographs of Gorgas.</item>
<item>44. Original reprints and copies of some of the original medical magazines including<lb/>
all the papers by Reed and his associates. These include copies of the original<lb/>
medical magazine with the &ldquo;Preliminary Reports&rdquo; of the Yellow Fever Board by<lb/>
Doctor Reed to Lazear's mother and wife after Lazear's death. This also in-<lb/>
cludes a reprint of the famous &ldquo;Preliminary Reports&rdquo; autographed and presented<lb/>
to me by Mrs. Lazear.</item>
<item>45. Letters between Reed and Dr. L. O. Howard, the famous entomologist who cooperated<lb/>
with Reed in developing methods to eradicate mosquitoes.</item>
<item>46. A special large file of letters from Moran, an early volunteer.</item>
<item>47. The same from Kissinger, an early volunteer.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f04232004"/>
<item>- 4 -</item>
<item>48. Photostats of many 1000 - 1901 Cuban and American newspapers with editorials,<lb/>
news items, etc., first scoffing at Reed's work, later grudgingly accepting it.</item>
<item>49. A large file of correspondence with General Jefferson Randolph Kean, who as<lb/>
Major Kean, was one of Reed's right hand men in Cuba during the experiments.</item>
<item>50. Another large file of correspondence with General Truby, who as Lieutenant<lb/>
Truby, was commanding officer at the Camp Columbia Post Hospital in Cuba<lb/>
where the Yellow Fever Board did its first work.</item>
<item>51. Diary of Lazear's mother 1894 - 1895, when she and Doctor Lazear, her son,<lb/>
took a European trip for pleasure and for some research work by Doctor Lazear.</item>
<item>52. The Dr. Howard A. Kelly collection of letters, papers, notes, etc., from which<lb/>
he prepared his book &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo; in 1905.</item>
<item>53. The Peabody collection, many items, letters, clippings, etc., concerning the<lb/>
volunteers. The data he collected was in part the basis for the Senate bill<lb/>
which belatedly gave pensions and medals to the volunteers and Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board members.</item>
<item>54. The Truby collection. All of the data (notes, photographs, and the original<lb/>
manuscripts) used by General Truby as the basis of his recent book &ldquo;Memoirs<lb/>
of Walter Reed&rdquo;.</item>
<item>55. The Kean collection. Some of this has been mentioned above. All the notes,<lb/>
reprints, letters, memoranda, collected by General Jefferson R. Kean, who as<lb/>
Major Kean, was Reed's &ldquo;right hand man&rdquo; in Cuba.</item>
<item>56. A few letters between Reed and Theobald Smith.</item>
<item>57. Unpublished manuscripts of Reed's daughter &ldquo;Blossom&rdquo; about her father.</item>
<item>58. Original cabinet photograph of Reed, the well-known photograph used for Kelly's<lb/>
book.</item>
<item>59. The two original oil sketches, each about 2 1/2 by 3 feet (in reality finished<lb/>
paintings) by the famous American artist Dean Cornwell, painted in 1940, prior<lb/>
to his final version of &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, the painting unveiled<lb/>
by Blossom Feed June 1941, at the meeting of the American Medical Association.</item>
<item>60. A preliminary crayon sketch of Reed's head by Cornwell.</item>
<item>61. &ldquo;Artists proof No. 1&rdquo; reproduction of the final painting &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow<lb/>
Fever&rdquo;.</item>
<item>62. Original contracts between Reed and one of the volunteers, presented to me<lb/>
by General Kean. Framed, about 2 by 2 feet.</item>
<item>63. Compilation of family records concerning the <unclear>gemealogy</unclear> of Dr. Lazear.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
