<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04304001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, March 3, 1949</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04304001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1949-03-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Moran, John J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1949-03-03">March 03, 1949</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04304001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, March 3, 1949</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is concerned that there is only one copy of Moran's yellow fever manuscript, and so urges Moran to send it to him to have copies made. Hench would like to have a copy of Moran's manuscript to compare with his notes, and as a basis to formulate questions for Moran.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1949-03-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John J. Moran, March 3, 1949</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04304001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1949-03-03">March 3, 1949</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
Calle 25 No. 804<lb/>
Entre B y C<lb/>
Vedado, Havana<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Johnny:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Will you please do me one great big favor? You don't realize how<lb/>
important, at least in my opinion, is your manuscript on &ldquo;My Date with Walter<lb/>
Reed and Yellow Jack&rdquo;. Incidentally, I like that title very much. Won't you<lb/>
please let me read it? I am extremely anxious to do so so that you and I can<lb/>
discuss it while we are both together in the land of the living. Please, please<lb/>
do this, Johnny. I will abide entirely with your decision as to whether it<lb/>
should be published, but please let me take a look at it.</p>
<p>I know how one feels when he has finished a paper. One has a mixed<lb/>
feeling of satisfaction and dissatisfaction. Maybe your dissatisfaction is<lb/>
over-stressed. Maybe very minor changes could be made. I can just hear you<lb/>
say &ldquo;No, I am done with it, I couldn't change another word.&rdquo; If you aren't<lb/>
willing to let the editors here see it, please let me see it in confidence.<lb/>
If you do send it, please mail it registered mail. In my opinion, it is a<lb/>
very precious document. Despite our long talks together, it is not only pos-<lb/>
sible but most likely that you have certain data therein that you and I just<lb/>
have never happened to discuss. I have kept every note of yours very carefully<lb/>
but every now and then when I go to them for something I am amazed to find<lb/>
that either we didn't discuss your view of it or I made no note. You simply<lb/>
must not wait until you are gone for me to see it! You can't do that to your<lb/>
old friend!</p>
<p>The rest of your letter depressed me but I was not surprised. I am<lb/>
quite disappointed but also not surprised that the funds allotted by the Ministry<lb/>
of Finance for the preservation of the caseta have disappeared; at least I now<lb/>
have another excuse to come to Cuba in the next few months, as I shall try to do.</p>
<p>When you have time, I should like to get the photograph of your<lb/>
Congressional Medal but there is no hurry. I agree that Doctor Nogueira can help<lb/>
copy the newspaper articles better than you can but at least I have the dates<lb/>
and know now where they are so that if necessary, I can get that when I come.</p>
<p>I have been extremely busy recently. I am General Chairman of an<lb/>
International Congress to be held at the Waldorf in May. It is a terrible<lb/>
job and I will be thankful when it is over. Also our research work here has<lb/>
been going very well indeed, which has kept me very busy. We plan to report<lb/>
this research in the spring and it may be of such a nature that even you will<lb/>
hear about it. Please give our best regards to your good wife and please let<lb/>
me hear from you shortly.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
