<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04317004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, October 13, 1949</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Siler, J.F.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04317004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1949-10-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Bliss, Raymond W.</name>
<name type="place">Fort McNair, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1949-10-13">October 13, 1949</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04317004</idno>
<title>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, October 13, 1949</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Siler agrees with Hench that Emilie Lawrence Reed's pension should be transferred to Blossom Reed. Siler requests Hench's opinion regarding the wording of the plaque to be placed on the building where Reed died. Siler regrets that the plans for the Camp Lazear preservation have fallen through, but suggests that General Bliss may be able to help with the matter.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1949-10-13">
<head>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, October 13, 1949</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04317004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
1835 EYE STREET, NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1949-10-13">October 13, 1949</date>
</dateline>
EXECUTIVE OFFICES<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you so very much for your very interesting and informative letter<lb/>
of September 29th.</p>
<p>I have just paid a visit to General Kean and gone over your letter with<lb/>
him in connection with fixing a date for the annual meeting of the Board of Managers<lb/>
of the Walter Reed Memorial Association. We feel that it will not be necessary to<lb/>
select a specific date for the meeting until we have heard further from you. I note<lb/>
that you feel that it is possible that you may go to Boston November 21 to 23 and<lb/>
that should you make the trip there it might be possible for you to go to Boston<lb/>
or return from there by way of Washington. Assuming that it might be more satisfac-<lb/>
tory for you to come by here on your way to Boston, we had thought that with your<lb/>
permission we might select the 17, 18 or 19 for our meeting with the understanding<lb/>
that if you find it impossible to come at the last minute it will be quite all right<lb/>
with us to hold the meeting on that date. As I wrote you heretofore the by-laws<lb/>
require that we give two weeks notice to members of the Board prior to holding the<lb/>
meeting. If therefore this tentative arrangement meets with your approval (with the<lb/>
understanding that you may not come), I will greatly appreciate a note from you<lb/>
stating which one of the above dates will be most satisfactory. It will be all right<lb/>
for you to wait until after the first of November before letting me know.</p>
<p>Concerning the matter of taking care of Blossom Reed after her mother's<lb/>
death, I may say that it has always been my understanding that this would be done by<lb/>
the Board. As a matter of fact, the certificate of incorporation of the Association<lb/>
reads as follows, "FIRST. The name of the association shall be &ldquo;The Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association&rdquo;; and the objects for which it is formed are to commemorate by<lb/>
a suitable memorial the eminent scientific and public services of the later Major<lb/>
Walter Reed, Surgeon, U. S. Army, and to raise funds for that object; also to assist,<lb/>
if necessary, with the income of such fund the wife and daughter of said Walter Reed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As you know, the income sent Mrs. Reed during the current year has been<lb/>
$90 per month and an extra $50 on account of unexpected expenses. At the time when<lb/>
this extra $50 per month was voted there was an excess of about $600 in treasury and<lb/>
it was not necessary to go into the principal to take care of this extra appropriation.<lb/>
I expect to see the bank within the next few days concerning continuation of this extra<lb/>
appropriation for the next year. I am sure that the Board of Managers will heartily<lb/>
approve its continuation for the next year.</p>
<p>After Mrs. Reed's death I am quite certain also that the Board will send<lb/>
Blossom Reed about $90 a month for the remainder of her life. As you know the original<lb/>
amount collected was around $25.000 and there has been appreciation in the amount<lb/>
until at the present time the fund is about $33,000 at market value. As some of<lb/>
this increase is from accumulated dividends I do not think there will be any diffi-<lb/>
culty in continuing the payment of the extra $50 per month, although, as you will<lb/>
note the certificate of incorporation states that the <hi>income</hi> of the fund may be<lb/>
used to assist Mrs. Reed and Blossom, should it become necessary. I am quite certain<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04317005"/>
GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
EXECUTIVE OFFICES<lb/>
1835 EYE STREET, NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6, D. C.<lb/>
that I have told Blossom that she could expect continuation of the income after her<lb/>
mother's death but I will make occasion to speak about it to General Reed so that<lb/>
he can confirm the information to her.</p>
<p>With reference to the sign to be placed at Ft. Leslie J. McNair, you will<lb/>
doubtless recall that in the minutes of the annual meeting of 1948 I referred to the<lb/>
fact that I had expected to get in touch with you and General Truby during the meet-<lb/>
ings of the Fourth International Congresses in May 1948 but was unable to do so.<lb/>
Then it was my hope to arrange the matter with you during one of your visits to Wash-<lb/>
ington during the year but the opportunity did not present itself. I hope to see the<lb/>
Surgeon General of the Army in the next few days and with his cooperation take the<lb/>
matter <add><unclear></unclear></add> with the Commanding General at Ft. Leslie J. McNair and arrange for placing a<lb/>
<unclear>plaque</unclear> on the building. If you have any suggestions as to the exact wording that<lb/>
should be entered on the plaque, I will be grateful for your suggestions. General<lb/>
Kean and I thought the inscription might read &ldquo;Walter Reed died in this building<lb/>
November 23, 1902&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I was much interested in your reference to the 50th Anniversary of the work<lb/>
of Walter Reed and your feeling that some notice of this event should be taken by<lb/>
the press. We will give this matter consideration at the annual meeting and hope<lb/>
you will please remember that I will be very glad indeed to give any information I<lb/>
can to the writer whom you may select to write this matter up.</p>
<p>I am terribly sorry you are having so much trouble in the matter of pro-<lb/>
tecting Building No. 1 in Cuba. We will take this matter up also at the annual meet-<lb/>
ing and it is quite possible that General Bliss may be able to do something about it<lb/>
through Secretary Johnson.</p>
<p>With kindest regards and best wishes and the hope that you will be quite<lb/>
all right again in the near future, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Faithfully yours,</salute>
<signed>J. F. Siler, Col., U.S.A., Retired<lb/>
Secretary, Walter Reed Memorial Association</signed>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minn<lb/>
jfs k<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
