<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04316010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J.F. Siler, September 29, 1949</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04316010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1949-09-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Siler, J.F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1949-09-29">September 29, 1949</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04316010</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J.F. Siler, September 29, 1949</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench doubts that he will be able to attend the Reed Memorial Association meeting, but sends suggestions regarding Association business for his colleagues to consider. He recommends that Blossom Reed continue to receive Emilie Lawrence Reed's monthly pension after the latter's death. Hench informs Siler that the Cuban government has abandoned plans to preserve Camp Lazear and refused Hench's funds to temporarily protect Building No. 1. He suggests that the Association approach contacts in the U.S. War or Defense Departments to see if diplomatic or military channels might open the way for temporary preservation of the building.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1949-09-29">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J.F. Siler, September 29, 1949</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04316010"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1949-09-29">September 29, 1949</date>
</dateline>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
DR. CHARLES H. SLOCUMB<lb/>
DR. HOWARD F. POLLEY<lb/>
Colonel J. F. Siler<lb/>
1835 Eye Street, Northwest<lb/>
Washington 26, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Colonel Siler:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your nice letter of September 7 about the November meeting<lb/>
of the Walter Reed Memorial Association. I wish indeed that I could be cer-<lb/>
tain to attend this meeting but I am not at all sure that I can. I was in<lb/>
Washington last week for about 36 hours and spent on hour with General and<lb/>
Mrs. Kean.</p>
<p>In connection with our International Congress held last June, of<lb/>
which I was General Chairman, I made so many trips to New York this spring<lb/>
and in connection with our recent research work I was absent at so many<lb/>
meetings that I used up more than my allotted time for absences from the<lb/>
Clinic for the year.</p>
<p>About eleven weeks ago, as I believe General Kean told you, I de-<lb/>
veloped a hemorrhage from an unsuspected duodenal ulcer, was knocked out four<lb/>
weeks and then had five weeks' vacation; therefore it will be very difficult<lb/>
for me to be absent from the Clinic in November. I have been invited to speak<lb/>
in Boston on November 21 and 23. I have tentatively turned these invitations<lb/>
down but if the matter is pressed or if I can see my way clear to do so, more<lb/>
clearly than now, I may take a quick trip to Boston then and if so, I could<lb/>
probably go or return by way of Washington. However that is Thanksgiving week<lb/>
so that it might be better for me to come before.</p>
<p>I am so uncertain of all this and it is so likely that I will not go<lb/>
that I think you had better plan the meeting this fall without me but I do want<lb/>
to make three or four suggestions which I shall write to you in more detail<lb/>
shortly. They are as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. As General Kean may have told you, Miss Blossom Reed wrote me that<lb/>
her mother almost passed away a few months ago but once more recovered. Never-<lb/>
theless, she is worse and necessitates extra expenditures on nursing care as she<lb/>
is practically helpless and completely bedridden. Miss Blossom has gone to<lb/>
considerable extra expense and is considerably worried financially. She wrote<lb/> 
me a nice little personal note wondering whether, at her mother's death, the<lb/>
pension would continue to the Reed Children or be withdrawn. As far as I am<lb/>
concerned, I am sure Walter Reed would consider the needs of his family above<lb/>
all else, and I would certainly not be in favor of using the pension for some<lb/>
small &ldquo;monument&rdquo; at the expense of lotting his children be in financial want.<lb/>
Assuming that General Reed has enough retirement pay, and so forth, I would<lb/>
vote to pass on the full pension to Miss Blossom upon the death of her mother,<lb/>
using whatever of the principal might also be necessary to keep her comfortable.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f04316011"/>
<item>Colonel J. F. Siler</item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>September 29, 1949</item>
<item>2. Next year is the 50th anniversary of the work of Reed and his<lb/>
colleagues. The matter of the placing of a modest wooden sign or bronze<lb/>
plaque on the old hospital building where Walter Reed died is still unfinished<lb/>
business. You will remember that General Truby and I tried to locate, two years<lb/>
ago, the precise room in which he died but the plan has been so changed that<lb/>
General Truby could not do this. In any event, it seems more appropriate to<lb/>
have a memorial on the outside of the building. It was my understanding that the<lb/>
commanding general of the military establishment where this building now is was<lb/>
going to take care of that matter himself. Certainly he could put up a wooden,<lb/>
nicely painted sign on the porch. If a small bronze plaque seems to be suitable,<lb/>
The Surgeon General of the Army may have some ideas as to how this should be<lb/>
handled.</item>
<item>3. In connection with the 50th Anniversary next year, it seems to me<lb/>
that some notice in the press of this event would be appropriate. In connection<lb/>
with our own recent researches, I have met and come to know rather well three or<lb/>
four science writers such as Mr. William Laurence of the New York Times, Mr.<lb/>
Steven Spencer of the Saturday Evening Post and others. Mr. Spencer is a very<lb/>
able writer. He wrote up our work in the Saturday Evening Post and stopped<lb/>
on his way through here a couple of weeks ago. I told him of the Reed anniversary<lb/>
next year and suggested that he might like to write some sort of an article.<lb/>
I have just had a reply which expresses his sincere interest. He wishes to<lb/>
discuss the matter with the managing editor of the Post. I told him the names<lb/>
of the survivors and if Spencer does not choose to write such an article, I am<lb/>
sure I can stimulate one or two others to write. What is the opinion of the<lb/>
Walter Reed Memorial Association toward this?</item>
<item>4. The matter of protecting Reed's Building No. 1 in Cuba. You may<lb/>
remember that I was in Cuba the spring of 1948 and after considerable effort and<lb/>
interviewing many hot-shots, including the Vice-President, they became presumably<lb/>
very interested in permanently memorializing and protecting Building No. 1. We<lb/>
even went so far as to draw up some informal plans for a building to cover<lb/>
Building No. 1, for landscaping the adjacent grounds, etc. Knowing the manana<lb/>
attitude of the Cubans, I persisted in offering to pay the expenses of putting<lb/>
a galvanized iron covering over Building No. 1 as a temporary protection but with<lb/>
many protestations of felicidad and sympatice, the Vice-President absolutely re-<lb/>
fused to allow me to spend my money, insisting that the Cuban government would<lb/>
do that at once as well as set aside funds for the memorial project. A bill was<lb/>
introduced into the Cuban congress and was passed and I saw it published in the<lb/>
Cuban newspapers allotting $50,000 for the project. Johnny Moran and I thought<lb/>
that at long last all was well. But no! This occurred just a month before the<lb/>
elections. The new regime was elected and I understand the whole thing is right<lb/>
back where it started because the habit of a new Cuban government is simply to<lb/>
ignore all financial commitments of the old one.</item>
</list></p>
<p>I don't know what to do further, at least at this distance, I may<lb/>
be able to go to Cuba next spring but in the meantime, a hurricane may well<lb/>
destroy Building No. 1 which has already survived several bad ones, including<lb/>
one last year.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04316012"/>
<p>Colonel J. F. Siler</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>September 29, 1949</p>
<p>Secretary Johnson of the Defense Department visited the Clinic as a<lb/>
patient many years ago. I think he was then assistant secretary. He happened<lb/>
to hear my illustrated lecture on the conquest of yellow fever, became very in-<lb/>
terested in it and later wrote me a note asking if he could help in any way.<lb/>
That was before the war and I was proceeding with my own plans and did not call<lb/>
upon him but it may be necessary now for us to ask the advice of Surgeon General<lb/>
Bliss of the War Department to see whether they can, through diplomatic or mili-<lb/>
tary channels, make some preliminary agreement so that at least an allocation of<lb/>
$1,000 or $1,500 can be gotten to protect Building No. 1 temporarily with a<lb/>
corregated iron covering until eventually some final disposition is made. Another<lb/>
reason they wouldn't let me do it privately on my own was because the government<lb/>
of Cuba, a couple of years ago, set aside Building No. 1 as a &ldquo;national monument&rdquo;<lb/>
which means that no private individual can touch it without the approval of<lb/>
the Cuban government.</p>
<p>These four items I should like to have considered by our colleagues<lb/>
on the committee and I am enclosing copies of this letter which you might care<lb/>
to send ahead of time to your colleagues so that they can have some preliminary<lb/>
noted on the matter before the meeting.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
