<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04319002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Minutes of the Annual Meeting, Board of Managers, Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 23, 1949</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04319002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1949-11-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Lesley McNair, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1949-11-23">November 23, 1949</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04319002</idno>
<title>Minutes of the Annual Meeting, Board of Managers, Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 23, 1949</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The minutes include a treasurer's report, a resolution to transfer a monthly allowance to Blossom Reed upon the death of her mother, a continuation of the $50 increase to Emilie L. Reed, discussion of a plaque to commemorate the location of Reed's death, and comments on the protection of Building No. 1.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1949-11-23">
<head>Minutes of the Annual Meeting, Board of Managers, Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 23, 1949</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04319002"/>
<p>MINUTES<lb/>
ANNUAL MEETING, BOARD OF MANAGERS, WALTER REED MEMORIAL ASSOCIATION<lb/>
Washington, D. C., November 23, 1949</p>
<p>The Board met at 10 A.M. in the Board Room, American Security &amp; Trust Company,<lb/>
15th Street &amp; Pennsylvania Avenue, Northwest, and was called to order by its<lb/>
President, Brig. Gen. Jefferson R. Kean, U. S. Army, Retired.</p>
<p><hi>PRESENT</hi>: Brig. Gen. J. R. Kean, President; Brig. Gen. Frank R. Keefer; Brig. Gen.<lb/>
Albert G. Love; Lt. Col. W. G. Brandstadt, M.C., U.S.A., representing Major Gen.<lb/>
R. W. Bliss, Surgeon General, U. S. Army; Dr. Fred L. Soper, Director Pan American<lb/>
Sanitary Bureau; Hans W. Ireland, Treasurer; Col. J. F. Siler, Med. Corps, U.S.A.,<lb/>
Retired, Secretary.</p>
<p><hi>ABSENT</hi>: Major Gen. M. W. Ireland, Major Gen. C. R. Reynolds, Dr. Gilbert Grosvenor,<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench and Dr. L. O. Howard.</p>
<p>In view of the fact that copies of the minutes of the last annual meeting (1948)<lb/>
had been mailed all members of the Board, the reading of the minutes of the last<lb/>
meeting was omitted and the minutes were approved as written.</p>
<p>The Treasurer submitted the following report, summarizing comparative income<lb/>
and disbursements for the fiscal years ending Oct. 31, 1948 and Oct. 31, 1949 and<lb/>
the par and market values of capital investments for like periods of time.</p>
<p><hi>WALTER REED MEMORIAL FUND, AGENCY</hi><lb/>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand 10/31/47</cell><cell>$510.40</cell><cell>Balance on hand 10/31/48</cell><cell>$675.21</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Income 10/31/47 to 10/31/48</cell><cell><hi>1,313.45</hi></cell><cell>Income 10/31/48 to 10/31/49</cell><cell><hi>1,337.08</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>$1,823.85</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>$2,012.29</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="4">
<row>
<cell cols="1-2"><hi>Disbursements 1948</hi></cell><cell cols="3-4"><hi>Disbursements 1949</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily Reed</cell><cell>$1,008.00</cell><cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily Reed</cell><cell>$1,608.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Commissions to American<lb/>
Security &amp; Trust Company</cell><cell>39.40</cell><cell>Commissions to American<lb/>
Security &amp; Trust Company</cell><cell>39.55</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>To cost of telegram Nov. 6,<lb/>
1947, to Minnesota</cell><cell>1.24</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>To Norman A. Topping, Secretary<lb/>
per resolution</cell><cell><hi>100.00</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell>----------</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>$1,148.64</cell><cell></cell><cell>$1,647.55</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand 10/31/48</cell><cell>675.21</cell><cell>Balance on hand 10/31/49</cell><cell>364.74</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>
<table rows="9" cols="6">
<row>
<cell cols="1-3"><hi>CAPITAL INVESTMENT A/C</hi><lb/>
October 31, 1948</cell><cell cols="4-6"><hi>CAPITAL INVESTMENT A/C</hi><lb/>
October 31, 1949</cell></row>
<row>
<cell><hi>Par Value</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell><cell><hi>Par Value</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>15,400.00</cell><cell>Bonds</cell><cell>17,538.00</cell><cell>15,400.00</cell><cell>Bonds</cell><cell>17,881.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>11,350.00*</cell><cell>Stocks</cell><cell>13,085.00</cell><cell>11,350.00*</cell><cell>Stocks</cell><cell>14,330.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2,500.00</cell><cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>2,500.00</cell><cell>2,500.00</cell><cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>2,500.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell><hi>110.42</hi></cell><cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell><hi>110.42</hi></cell><cell><hi>180.47</hi></cell><cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell><hi>180.47</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>29,360.42</cell><cell></cell><cell>33,233.42</cell><cell>29,430.47</cell><cell></cell><cell>34,891.47</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>*Pfd no Par c/a $100.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>*Pfd no Par c/a $100.00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>Com no Par c/a 25.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Com no Par c/a 25.00</cell><cell></cell></row>
</table></p>
<pb n="2" id="f04319003"/>
<p>The report of the Treasurer was approved.</p>
<p>The following officers were elected for the forthcoming year.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>President Brig. Gen. Jefferson R. Kean</item>
<item>Vice President Major Gen. Merritte W. Ireland</item>
<item>Treasurer Mr. Hans W. Ireland</item>
<item>Secretary Col. Joseph F. Siler</item>
</list></p>
<p>The President then asked if there was any new business to be given consideration<lb/>
by the Board.</p>
<p>Col. Siler stated that under date of Sept. 29, 1949, Dr. Hench had written him<lb/>
that it probably would be impossible for him to attend the annual meeting this year<lb/>
and he desired to make some suggestions for consideration by the Board at its annual<lb/>
meeting. Dr. Hench enclosed copies of this letter and one copy was mailed to each<lb/>
member of the Board for his consideration prior to the annual meeting.</p>
<p>Col. Siler stated that he had discussed with Gen. Kean the matters brought up<lb/>
by Dr. Hench in his letter of Sept. 29, 1949 and had replied to Dr. Hench's letter<lb/>
on Oct. 13, 1949. In a subsequent note (Oct. 20, 1949) Dr. Hench advised him that<lb/>
he would be unable to attend the annual meeting.</p>
<p>The three letters referred to are attached to these minutes as Exhibits A, B &amp; C.</p>
<p>Col. Siler then stated that he desired to present to the Board the matters taken<lb/>
up by Dr. Hench in his letter of Sept. 29 for such definitive action as may be con-<lb/>
sidered feasible in the premises. He stated that the first matter referred to by Dr.<lb/>
Hench was whether the Board could and would authorize the payment of the regular<lb/>
monthly allowance from the income from the trust fund, to Mrs. Walter Reed's daughter,<lb/>
Emily (Blossom) Reed, after the death of her mother. Col. Siler called attention to<lb/>
the fact that Article 1 of the Certificate of Incorporation of the Association reads<lb/>
as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;FIRST. The name of the association shall be &ldquo;The Walter Reed Memorial Associa-<lb/>
tion&rdquo; and the objects for which it is formed are to commemorate by a suitable memorial<lb/>
the eminent scientific and public services of the late Major Walter Reed, Surgeon,<lb/>
U. S. Army, and to raise funds for that object; also to assist, if necessary, with<lb/>
the income of such fund the wife and daughter of said Walter Reed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>To cover the matter of payment of the allowance eventually to Blossom Reed, the<lb/>
following resolution was adopted:</p>
<p>RESOLVED, That on the death of Mrs. Walter Reed the regular monthly allowance<lb/>
paid to her since October, 1906, from the income received from the trust funds be<lb/>
paid to her daughter, Emily (Blossom) Reed, until her death, in accordance with the<lb/>
provisions of the Articles of Incorporation.</p>
<p>Col. Siler stated that the members of the Board would recall that at the annual<lb/>
meeting last year a resolution was adopted authorizing the Treasurer of the Board<lb/>
to increase the monthly payment to Mrs. Reed $50.00 per month. This increase be-<lb/>
came necessary by reason of the fact that Mrs. Reed had been bedridden for more than<lb/>
two years and required constant nursing care. Her physical condition is essentially<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04319004"/>
the same as was the case last year except that she continues to lose ground<lb/>
physically and continuation of the additional $50.00 monthly payments is urgently<lb/>
required.</p>
<p>To cover these extra payments the following resolution was adopted:</p>
<p>WHEREAS, the BOARD OF MANAGERS OF THE WALTER REED MEMORIAL ASSOCIATION<lb/>
at their annual meeting held on November 15, 1948, passed a resolution authorizing<lb/>
the Treasurer of the Association to increase the monthly payment to Mrs. Emily L.<lb/>
Reed, -- $50.00 (Fifty Dollars) per month beginning November 1, 1948 and continuing<lb/>
for not more than twelve months.</p>
<p>RESOLVED: THAT the Treasurer of the Association be, and he hereby is,<lb/>
authorized to continue the increase of $50.00 (Fifty Dollars) per month to Mrs.<lb/>
Emily L. Reed, for another 12 (Twelve) months beginning November 1, 1949, and<lb/>
further, should the income of the Association not be sufficient to make this pay-<lb/>
ment, the Treasurer be, and he is hereby, authorized to sell sufficient of the<lb/>
capital assets to make such payments.</p>
<p>The second matter given consideration by Dr. Hench was that of placing a modest<lb/>
wooden sign or bronze plaque on the old hospital building at Ft. Leslie J. McNair,<lb/>
in which Major Walter Reed was a patient at the time of his death. Col. Siler re-<lb/>
ported that recently he and Maj. Gen. Walter L. Reed had visited Ft. McNair for the<lb/>
purpose of consulting with and securing the cooperation of the Post Commander in<lb/>
the installation of a plaque and to inspect the building and decide definitely just<lb/>
where the marker should be located. The Commanding Officer, Colonel E. C. Norman,<lb/>
assured us that it would give him great pleasure to cooperate and it was agreed that<lb/>
he would arrange for the preparation of a concrete base to which the plaque would<lb/>
be attached. Gen. Reed and Col. Siler then inspected the building which was erected<lb/>
more than 50 years ago, has screened porches on the first and second floor front, has<lb/>
shrubbery along the front and was converted into apartments for military personnel<lb/>
many years ago. We agreed that the only practical location for a sign or plaque would<lb/>
be on the sloping lawn between the building and the sidewalk.</p>
<p>Col. Siler stated that he consulted with Gen. Kean and was instructed to as-<lb/>
certain the estimated cost of a bronze plaque if secured from commercial sources and<lb/>
also whether a wooden marker could be prepared at the Army Medical Center without<lb/>
cost to the Association. It was agreed tentatively that the wording on the plaque<lb/>
would be as follows:<lb/>
WALTER REED<lb/>
died in this building,<lb/>
then a hospital,<lb/>
Nov 23 - 1902.</p>
<p>The Washington firm, Lamb Seal &amp; Stencil Company, was requested to submit an<lb/>
estimate of the cost of a suitable bronze plaque, corinthian style border, 20" x<lb/>
12" in size, with necessary attachments for installation. Their estimate was approxi-<lb/>
mately $79.00. A sketch of the proposed plaque, actual size, was inspected by the<lb/>
members of the Board.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04319005"/>
<p>Col. Siler stated that he also had consulted with the Executive Officer, Army<lb/>
Medical Center, relative to the preparation of a suitable wooden marker and had been<lb/>
advised that they would be pleased to prepare such a marker, approximately 20" x 12"<lb/>
in size, without cost to the Association. They suggested a black, rough, wooden<lb/>
background with gold-colored letters, suitably finished for constant exposure to the<lb/>
elements. They loaned him a completed sign showing the material and finish that<lb/>
would be used in the preparation of the proposed marker and this sign was inspected<lb/>
by the members of the Board.</p>
<p>After some discussion, the Treasurer was authorized to purchase a bronze plaque<lb/>
to cost about $80.00 with the understanding that before placing the order considera-<lb/>
tion would be given to the possibility of making such changes in the wording as might<lb/>
more definitely assure permanent designation of the site if and when the now existing<lb/>
building is replaced.</p>
<p>Col. Siler stated that the third matter referred to in Dr. Hench's letter was<lb/>
that the year 1950 will be the 50th anniversary of Walter Reed's work on yellow fever<lb/>
and it was his feeling that some notice of this event by the press would be appropri-<lb/>
ate. The members of the Board were in complete agreement with Dr. Hench concerning<lb/>
this matter and also agreed that the details of securing adequate press coverage<lb/>
should be left to him with the understanding that he would call on Gen. Kean and the<lb/>
Secretary of the Board for any pertinent data that he might consider necessary. This<lb/>
matter will be taken up with Dr. Hench when he visits Washington in the near future.</p>
<p>The fourth matter referred to by Dr. Hench in his letter related to the delay<lb/>
on the part of the Cuban Government in the matter of protecting Walter Reed's<lb/>
Building No. 1 used in the conduct of experimental transmission of yellow fever.<lb/>
Several years ago Dr. Hench and Mr. Moran located this building. Dr. Hench felt that<lb/>
the building and immediate area should be converted into a permanent memorial. The<lb/>
initial step in such a plan would be to protect, temporarily, Building No. 1 by<lb/>
covering it with galvanized iron. In 1948 Dr. Hench offered to do this at his own<lb/>
expense. Officials of the Cuban Government <unclear>aovised</unclear> him that they proposed to estab-<lb/>
lish a permanent memorial and would provide a galvanized iron covering for the<lb/>
building. Subsequently, the Cuban Government passed a bill to establish a permanent<lb/>
memorial and set aside $50,000. for the project. Shortly thereafter a newly elected<lb/>
government came into power and so far no steps have been taken to protect Building<lb/>
No. 1. Dr. Hench made inquiry as to whether it might be possible through Mr. Johnson,<lb/>
the Secretary of Defense, and diplomatic channels to prevail on the Cuban authorities<lb/>
to take steps, at least, to provide temporary protection for Building No. 1. Col.<lb/>
Siler discussed this matter with Gen. Bliss, Surgeon General of the Army, and he told<lb/>
Col. Siler that he would be very glad to give any help within his power.</p>
<p>The Board then agreed that this matter would be held in abeyance pending Dr.<lb/>
Hench's visit to Washington at which time action could be taken after he had con-<lb/>
ferred with Gen. Bliss and Gen. Kean.</p>
<p>There being no further business the meeting adjourned to meet at the call of<lb/>
the President.</p>
<closer>
<signed>J. F. Siler<lb/>
Secretary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
