<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04325001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to William A. Wood, February 1, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04325001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-02-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wood, William A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hanberry, John L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-02-01">February 1, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04325001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to William A. Wood, February 1, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench provides biographical information about some of the men involved with the yellow fever experiments. He stresses the importance of celebrating the 50<hi rend="superscrip">th</hi> anniversary of Reed's work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-02-01">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to William A. Wood, February 1, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04325001"/>
<opener>
Y f<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1950-02-01">February 1, 1950</date>
</dateline>
Mr. William A. Wood<lb/>
Division of Public Liaison<lb/>
State Department<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Wood:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Until now I was unable to find the address of Mr. John L. Hanberry.<lb/>
His address is 61 Summers Avenue, Orangeburg, South Carolina.</p>
<p>As I told you, the five men still living who had some chief con-<lb/>
cern with the conquest of yellow fever and the work of Walter Reed and his<lb/>
associates are as follows: Mr. John Moran, Calle 25 #804, entre B y C,<lb/>
Apartment 3, Vedado, Havana, Cuba; Mr. James Hanberry, address above; Dr.<lb/>
Robert Cooke, Lexington-Rockbridge Health Department, Lexington, Virginia;<lb/>
General Jefferson R. Kean, 2804 N Street, N. S., Georgetown, Washington, D. C.;<lb/>
General Albert E. Truby, 145 Laurel Street, San Francisco, California.</p>
<p>Mr. Moran was one of the first to volunteer to Walter Reed for the<lb/>
experiments and he was given experimental yellow fever. He is a very articu-<lb/>
late man and <unclear>was</unclear> for years manager of the Sun Oil Company in Cuba. He is now<lb/>
retired. He has an ulcer and I am sure will not leave Cuba unless his wife<lb/>
comes along.</p>
<p>Last year he was invited to some affair in Washington, an interna-<lb/>
tional public health congress. He was invited with expenses for himself<lb/>
alone but since he is on a small annuity he could not afford to pay his<lb/>
wife's <unclear>expenses</unclear> and therefore declined. I think I was the only one that know<lb/>
why he declined. If they had paid his wife's expenses also so that she<lb/>
could look after him and look after his diet, he probably would have come.<lb/>
In my opinion he is by far the best one. Although he speaks very ably in<lb/>
conversation, he pretends to be shy on his feet. On the occasion, three<lb/>
of four years ago, when he was being honored at the University of Virginia,<lb/>
he was asked to speak. He got up and made a few stammering remarks and then<lb/>
suggested that they merely ask him questions and he became quite articulate<lb/>
and most interesting. Therefore, if he had a script to read from I am sure<lb/>
he would do well. He is deserving of much consideration and honor.</p>
<p>Mr. Hanberry was also a volunteer and deserving of much credit.<lb/>
However, he is not as intelligent a man as Mr. Moran by any means and in-<lb/>
cidentally deserted from the Army but all was forgiven and he later received<lb/>
the special Congressional Medal. As I told you, I think he is a little more<lb/>
pleased by attention than Mr. Moran. He would be satisfactory but not as<lb/>
satisfactory as Moran.</p>
<p>Dr. Robert Cooke accepted part of the experiments. He lived in little<lb/>
Building No. 1, the filth room but did not accept experimental yellow fever.<lb/>
When I visited him a few years ago I found his memory very poor.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04325002"/>
A C<lb/>
Va<lb/>
Mr. William A. Wood<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
February 1, 1950<lb/>
If someone wrote a script for him he would undoubtedly read it off but I<lb/>
don't believe he could help much without the script.</p>
<p>These three are the only actual surviving participants of the<lb/>
experiments. General Kean was Walter Reed's right hand man and superior<lb/>
officer in Cuba. He was the surgeon for the area in which Walter Reed<lb/>
did the work. He is one of the most intelligent and intellectual men I have<lb/>
ever met and his memory is excellent; however he is around 90 years of age and<lb/>
has a bum knee. He was Deputy Surgeon General bears ago. He has been my<lb/>
prime source of knowledge and is more or less the final authority in matters<lb/>
concerning Walter Reed and the conquest of yellow fever. Whether or not he<lb/>
would be willing to go to New York for such a program, I do not know but he<lb/>
knows more about the affair than anybody else, including the survivors.</p>
<p>General Albert E. Truby was a young lieutenant and was temporary<lb/>
commanding officer of the hospital in Cuba where Walter Reed did his work.<lb/>
Four or five years ago he wrote a book on the subject, a very good one. Next<lb/>
to General Kean he knows most about the affair but was not a participant.<lb/>
He had a slight stroke three years ago but has recovered with a slight limp<lb/>
and does, on occasion, travel east.</p>
<p>The finances of all of these men are such that they would have to<lb/>
have their expenses paid. You know the average pension for a retired<lb/>
officer.</p>
<p>Walter Reed's son, daughter and widow are still living. His son<lb/>
is a very able man who became major general during the last war and held<lb/>
several very responsible positions. He is living in Washington, General<lb/>
Walter Lawrence Reed, 2810 Thirty-Sixth Place, N. W. He was a young<lb/>
lieutenant in Cuba at the time but was not stationed in Havana and although<lb/>
he knows a great deal about his father's work, it was largely through<lb/>
hearsay. He would be a highly acceptable participant in the program, should<lb/>
you wish a representative of the Reed family. Walter Reed's widow is over<lb/>
90 and hopelessly ill in Blue Ridge Summit, Pennsylvania, under the care of<lb/>
her daughter, Mrs. Blossom Reed. I think that about covers the situation.</p>
<p>It is extremely appropriate that &ldquo;WE, THE PEOPLE&rdquo; put on this<lb/>
program this year as 1950 is the 50th anniversary of the work of Walter<lb/>
Reed. They may or may not realize this. I hope you will bring this to<lb/>
their attention as it will make it especially appropriate and give a time-<lb/>
liness to the occasion.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
