<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04322001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">House of Representatives Joint Resolution No. 396, 81<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Congress, second session, January 16, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04322001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-01-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-01-16">January 16, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04322001</idno>
<title>House of Representatives Joint Resolution No. 396, 81<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Congress, second session, January 16, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This resolution establishes a Walter Reed Commemoration Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1950-01-16">
<head>House of Representatives Joint Resolution No. 396, 81<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Congress, second session, January 16, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04322001"/>
<opener>
81ST CONGRESS<lb/>
2D SESSION<lb/>
H. J. RES. 396<lb/>
--------------------<lb/>
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1950-01-16">JANUARY 16, 1950</date>
</dateline>
Mr. BLAND introduced the following joint resolution; which was referred to<lb/>
the Committee on Rules<lb/>
--------------------<lb/>
</opener>
<p>JOINT RESOLUTION</p>
<p>Establishing a Walter Reed Commemoration Commission.</p>
<p>Whereas it is important at this time when there is a world-wide<lb/>
clash of ideologies and principles that every opportunity<lb/>
be utilized to spread a knowledge of American achieve-<lb/>
ments and of the American way of life that fosters those<lb/>
achievements; and</p>
<p>Whereas one of the greatest achievements of all times was the<lb/>
program toward the elimination of yellow fever; and</p>
<p>Whereas this achievement, from which the entire world is a<lb/>
beneficiary, was the result of the devotion and skills of the<lb/>
United States Army and its medical services; and</p>
<p>Whereas the chief figure in that achievement, that has saved the<lb/>
lives of untold millions and brought prospects of pros-<lb/>
perity and security to many lands, was Major Walter Reed<lb/>
of the United States Army; and</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04322002"/>
<p>Ac<lb/>
<unclear>Va</unclear></p>
<p>2</p>
<p>Whereas 1950 is the fiftieth anniversary of the work of the<lb/>
Walter Reed Commission whose crowning achievement led<lb/>
to the near erasure of this scourge; and</p>
<p>Whereas 1951 is the one hundredth anniversary of the birth in<lb/>
Virginia of Major Walter Reed; and</p>
<p>Whereas 1952 is the fiftieth anniversary of his death; and</p>
<p>Whereas these three years provide a unique occasion and oppor-<lb/>
tunity to celebrate fittingly those invaluable services to the<lb/>
United States of America and to humanity; and to direct<lb/>
the attention of the American people and of the world at<lb/>
large to this landmark in the progress of civilization:<lb/>
Therefore be it</p>
<p>1 <hi rend="italic">Resolved by the Senate and House of Representatives</hi><lb/>
2 <hi rend="italic">of the United States of America in Congress assembled,</hi><lb/>
3 That (a) there is hereby established a commission to be<lb/>
4 known as the Walter Reed Commemoration Commission<lb/>
5 which shall be composed of three members of the Senate to<lb/>
6 be appointed by the President of the Senate, and three<lb/>
7 members of the House of Representatives to be appointed<lb/>
8 by the Speaker of the House of Representatives. Vacancies<lb/>
9 in the membership of the Commission shall not affect the<lb/>
10 power of the remaining members to execute the functions<lb/>
11 of the Commission, and shall be filled in the same manner<lb/>
12 as the original selection. The Commission shall hold its<lb/>
13 first meeting within three days following the appointment<lb/>
14 of its members, and shall select a chairman from among such<lb/>
15 members.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04322003"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>1 (b) It shall be the duty of the Commission to conduct,<lb/>
2 direct, and supervise a program of information and education<lb/>
3 to the end that the achievement of the American people,<lb/>
4 of the United States Army, and of Major Walter Reed, one<lb/>
5 of America's most illustrious sons, in successfully combating<lb/>
6 yellow fever shall be duly known and honored.</p>
<p>7 (c) In carrying out its duties under this joint resolu-<lb/>
8 tion, the Commission is authorized to prepare, publish, and<lb/>
9 distribute appropriate literature, to organize projects in<lb/>
10 cooperation with schools, veterans' organizations, medical.<lb/>
11 health, and hospital associations, patriotic societies, media<lb/>
12 of public information, national and local business, profes-<lb/>
13 sional, labor, women's, youth and other public-spirited<lb/>
14 groups, and to enlist their participation in the program<lb/>
15 authorized by subsection (b).</p>
<p>16 (d) For the purposes of this joint resolution, the Com-<lb/>
17 mission is authorized to sit and act at such places and times<lb/>
18 during the sessions, recesses, and adjourned periods of the<lb/>
19 Eighty-first and Eighty-second Congresses and, without<lb/>
20 regard to the civil-service laws and the Classification Act of<lb/>
21 1949, to appoint and fix the compensation of such clerical<lb/>
22 and other assistants, to employ such organizations, to pro-<lb/>
23 cure such printing and binding, and to make such expendi-<lb/>
24 tures as it may deem necessary.</p>
<p>25 (e) There are hereby authorized to be appropriated<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04322004"/>
Ac<lb/>
<unclear>Va</unclear><lb/>
4<lb/>
1 such sums, not to exceed $350,000 for the three-year period,<lb/>
2 as may be necessary to enable the Commission to carry out<lb/>
3 the provisions of this joint resolution, to be disbursed by the<lb/>
4 Secretary of the Senate upon vouchers approved by the<lb/>
5 chairman.</p>
<p>81ST CONGRESS<lb/>
2D SESSION</p>
<p>H. J. RES. 396</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>JOINT RESOLUTION</p>
<p>Establishing a Walter Reed Commemoration<lb/>
Commission.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>By Mr. BLAND</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>JANUARY 16, 1950</p>
<p>Referred to the Committee on Rules</p>
<pb n="5" id="f04322005"/>
<p>81ST CONGRESS<lb/>
2D SESSION</p>
<p>S. J. RES. 142</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</p>
<p>JANUARY 17 (legislative day, JANUARY 4), 1950</p>
<p>Mr. JENNER introduced the following joint resolution; which was read twice<lb/>
and referred to the Committee on Labor and Public Welfare</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>JOINT RESOLUTION</p>
<p>Establishing a Walter Reed Commemoration Commission.</p>
<p>Whereas it is important at this time when there is a world-wide<lb/>
clash of ideologies and principles that every opportunity<lb/>
be utilized to spread a knowledge of American achievements<lb/>
and of the American way of life that fosters those achieve-<lb/>
ments; and</p>
<p>Whereas one of the greatest achievements of all times was the<lb/>
program toward the elimination of yellow fever; and</p>
<p>Whereas this achievement, from which the entire world is a<lb/>
beneficiary, was the result of the devotion and skills of the<lb/>
United States Army and its medical services; and</p>
<p>Whereas the chief figure in that achievement, that has saved<lb/>
the lives of untold millions and brought prospects of pros-<lb/>
perity and security to many lands, was Major Walter Reed<lb/>
of the United States Army; and</p>
<pb n="6" id="f04322006"/>
<p>c<lb/>
<unclear>Va</unclear></p>
<p>2</p>
<p>Whereas 1950 is the fiftieth anniversary <unclear>of</unclear> the work <unclear>of</unclear> the<lb/>
Walter Reed Commission whose crowning achievement led<lb/>
to the near erasure of this scourge; and</p>
<p>Whereas 1951 is the one hundredth anniversary of the birth in<lb/>
Virginia of Major Walter Reed; and</p>
<p>Whereas 1952 is the fiftieth anniversary of his death; and</p>
<p>Whereas these three years provide a unique occasion and oppor-<lb/>
tunity to celebrate fittingly those invaluable services to the<lb/>
United States of America and to humanity; and to direct<lb/>
the attention of the American people and of the world at<lb/>
large to this landmark in the progress of civilization: There-<lb/>
fore be it</p>
<p>1 <hi rend="italic">Resolved by the Senate and House of Representatives</hi><lb/>
2 <hi rend="italic">of the United States of America in Congress assembled,</hi><lb/>
3 That (a) there is hereby established a commission to be<lb/>
4 known as the Walter Reed Commemoration Commission<lb/>
5 which shall be composed of three Members of the Senate to<lb/>
6 be appointed by the President of the Senate, and three<lb/>
7 Members of the House of Representatives to be appointed<lb/>
8 by the Speaker of the House of Representatives. Vacancies<lb/>
9 in the membership of the Commission shall not affect the<lb/>
10 power of the remaining members to execute the functions<lb/>
11 of the Commission, and shall be filled in the same manner<lb/>
12 as the original selection. The Commission shall hold its<lb/>
13 first meeting within three days following the appointment of<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04322007"/>
3<lb/>
1 its members, and shall select a Chairman from among such<lb/>
2 members.</p>
<p>3 (b) It shall be the duty of the Commission to conduct,<lb/>
4 direct, and supervise a program of information and education<lb/>
5 to the end that the achievement of the American people,<lb/>
6 of the United States Army, and of Major Walter Reed, one<lb/>
7 of America's most illustrious sons, in successfully combatting<lb/>
8 yellow fever shall be duly known and honored.</p>
<p>9 (c) In carrying out its duties under this joint resolution,<lb/>
10 the Commission is authorized to prepare, publish, and dis-<lb/>
11 tribute appropriate literature, to organize projects in coopera-<lb/>
12 ation with schools, veterans' organizations, medical, health,<lb/>
13 and hospital associations, patriotic societies, media of public<lb/>
14 information, national and local business, professional, labor,<lb/>
15 women's, youth, and other public-spirited groups, and to<lb/>
16 enlist their participation in the program authorized by<lb/>
17 subsection (b).</p>
<p>18 (d) For the purposes of this joint resolution, the Com-<lb/>
19 mission is authorized to sit and act at such places and times<lb/>
20 during the sessions, recesses, and adjourned periods of the<lb/>
21 Eighty-first and Eighty-second Congresses, and without re-<lb/>
22 gard to the civil-service laws and the Classification Act<lb/>
23 of 1949, to appoint and fix the compensation of such clerical<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04322008"/>
<unclear>Ac<lb/>
Va</unclear><lb/>
4<lb/>
1 and other assistants, to employ such organizations, to procure<lb/>
2 such printing and binding, and to make such expenditures<lb/>
3 as it may deem necessary.</p>
<p>4 (e) There are hereby authorized to be appropriated<lb/>
5 such sums, not to exceed $350,000 for the three-year period,<lb/>
6 as may be necessary to enable the Commission to carry out<lb/>
7 the provisions of this joint resolution, to be disbursed by the<lb/>
8 Secretary of the Senate upon vouchers approved by the<lb/>
9 chairman.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f04322009"/>
<p>House Joint <unclear>Rosolution 395</unclear> (introduced by Mr. Bland of Virginia)<lb/>
and Senate Joint Resolution 142 (introduced by Mr. Jenner of Indiana)<lb/>
call for the establishment of a Walter Reed Commemoration Commission,<lb/>
the duty of which shall be: &ldquo;To conduct, direct, and supervise a<lb/>
program of information and education to the end that the achievement<lb/>
of the American people, of the United States Army, and of Major Walter<lb/>
Reed, one of America's most illustrious sons, in successfully combating<lb/>
yellow fever shall be duly known and honored.&rdquo;</p>
<p>An introductory section to the Resolution points out that:</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is important at this time when there is a world-wide clash of<lb/>
ideologies and principles that every opportunity be utilized to<lb/>
apread a knowledge of American achievements and of the American way<lb/>
of life that fosters those achievements. One of the greatest achievements<lb/>
of all times was the program toward the elimination of yellow fever.<lb/>
This achievement, from which the entire world is a beneficiary, was the<lb/>
result of the devotion and skills of the United States Army and its<lb/>
medical services. The chief figure in that achievement, that has saved<lb/>
the lives of untold millions and brought prospects of prosperity and<lb/>
security to many lands, was Major Walter Reed of the United States Army.<lb/>
1950 is the fiftieth anniversary of the work of the Walter Reed Com-<lb/>
mission whose crowning achievement led to the near erasure of this<lb/>
scourge, 1951 is the one hundredth anniversary of the birth in<lb/>
Virginia of Major Walter Reed. 1952 is the fiftieth anniversary of<lb/>
his death. These three years provide a unique occasion and opportunity<lb/>
to celebrate fittingly those invaluable services to the United States<lb/>
of America and to humanity; and to direct the attention of the<lb/>
American people and of the world at large to this landmark in the<lb/>
progress of civilization.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Other considerations in regard to this Resolution are the following:</p>
<p>There is prevalent the feeling that United States military history<lb/>
has involved only episodes of destruction, even though in defence of<lb/>
our country against attack. Few appreciate the fact that out of the<lb/>
military personnel and activities of the United States Army, naval<lb/>
and air forces there have been developed creative, constructive<lb/>
enterprises of vast scope and of enduring value not only to the<lb/>
American people but to the world at large.</p>
<p>Attention is directed to the world-wide ideological clash in which<lb/>
our country is engaged against the ruthless forces of Communism.<lb/>
An important battleground in this cold war is in the Latin American<lb/>
countries. The achievement of the United States Army through the<lb/>
Walter Reed Commission was of most immediate importance in terms of<lb/>
health and economic upbuilding to the countries of this hemisphere<lb/>
directly to the south of our borders.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f04322010"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>The three-year observance of a Walter Reed program will help bring<lb/>
to large-scale public attention in those Latin American countries what<lb/>
they and their peoples owe to the American people and to the institu-<lb/>
tions that the American people have created.</p>
<p>In honoring a great individual American, in this case a great Virginian,<lb/>
we honor all of the American people. The observance of the Walter Reed<lb/>
program will make it possible to draw to public attention the fact that<lb/>
the humblest of citizens can play--as they have played--a heroic role<lb/>
in American life. The achievement that led to the eradication of yellow<lb/>
fever under the direction of Major Reed, drew into its efforts volun-<lb/>
teers from among average Americans. One of the first of the volunteers<lb/>
(at the risk of his life, incidentally) was an Indianan, a private in<lb/>
the United States Army. In the total enterprise, civilians and army<lb/>
personnel, doctors, nurses and Americans unconnected with the field of<lb/>
medicine played a significant and heroic role.</p>
<p>The need for immediate favorable action on the Resolution is indicated<lb/>
by the fact that the Walter Reed Commission was designated in May 1900.<lb/>
The semi-centennial anniversary of that event is almost upon us. In<lb/>
order to observe it fittingly, a program of information and education<lb/>
as provided in the resolution, should not be delayed.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
