<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04325003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Sidney Wallach to Philip Showalter Hench, February 21, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Wallach, Sidney</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04325003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-02-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Siler, Joseph</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-02-21">February 21, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04325003</idno>
<title>Letter from Sidney Wallach to Philip Showalter Hench, February 21, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Wallach informs Hench about the introduction of a joint congressional resolution to honor Reed and his work. Wallach hopes to receive Hench's help in mobilizing various groups who have an interest that this resolution be passed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-02-21">
<head>Letter from Sidney Wallach to Philip Showalter Hench, February 21, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04325003"/>
<opener>
Telephone: Murray Hill 4-7770<lb/>
<dateline>
SIDNEY WALLACH ASSOCIATES<lb/>
Three Eighty One Fourth Avenue, New York 16, N. Y.<lb/>
<date value="1950-02-21">February 21, 1950</date>
</dateline>
PUBLIC RELATIONS &middot; MAGAZINE MANAGEMENT &middot; CAMPAIGN PUBLICITY<lb/>
Dr. Philip Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am writing to you--and I hope you will forgive the length of the<lb/>
letter in the light of its contents--after a meeting with General<lb/>
Walter Reed and Colonel Joseph Siler in Washington, recently. I saw<lb/>
them in connection with joint congressional resolutions in regard<lb/>
to Major Walter Reed that had been introduced at this session of<lb/>
Congress. In the event you are unfamiliar with them, I am enclosing<lb/>
copies together with a covering memorandum about them.</p>
<p>Both General Reed and Colonel Siler impressed upon me the urgency of<lb/>
communicating with and, if at all possible, working with you. From what<lb/>
they told me, I would be only too happy if that could be brought about.</p>
<p>The circumstances of the enclosed resolutions are as follows:</p>
<p>For some time I have been very much interested in the career of Major<lb/>
Walter Reed and in the achievement that resulted from the work of the<lb/>
Commission that he headed up. A singular combination of events over a three-<lb/>
year period: the 50th anniversary of the naming of the Yellow Fever Com-<lb/>
mission; and of the death of Dr. Reed; and the 100th anniversary of his<lb/>
birth,--led to the development of the project as described in the resolu-<lb/>
tions. I brought this proposal to the attention of Senator Jenner of Indiana<lb/>
(one of the first of the volunteers was, as you know, a private from Indiana).</p>
<p>The Senator was enthusiastic about this proposal. I have since been<lb/>
working with him towards obtaining early and favorable action by Congress.</p>
<p>It was naturally our desire to make this a non-partisan measure introduced<lb/>
by a Republican and Democrat, a Senator and a Congressman.</p>
<p>Senator Jenner's office then took the matter up with Congressman Howard<lb/>
Smith of Virginia. He, too, liked the idea but out of congressional courtesy,<lb/>
thought that Congressman Bland who represented the district in which Major<lb/>
Reed was born, should have the opportunity, if he wished, to introduce the<lb/>
resolution in the House. To this, Congressman Bland agreed.</p>
<p>As it now stands, the Senate Resolution has been referred to the Committee<lb/>
of Labor and Public Welfare and the House Resolution to the House Rules<lb/>
Committee.</p>
<p>SIDNEY WALLACH</p>
<p>NATHAN CARO BELTH</p>
<p>IDALEE WALLACH</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04325004"/>
<p>Dr. Philip Hench</p>
<p>Page two<lb/>
February 21, 1950</p>
<p>Unfortunately, a complication arose recently with the sudden death of<lb/>
Congressman Bland. It is, however, my hope that Congressman Smith will<lb/>
want to carry on, not least, as a courtesy to his late colleague.</p>
<p>I want to acquaint you further with the fact that from my conversations<lb/>
on Capitol Hill, I have found a considerable measure of support for, and<lb/>
no opposition to the resolution. What is needed, however, is to have<lb/>
Senators and Congressmen and particularly members of the two Committees to<lb/>
which the Resolutions have been referred, receive indications from various<lb/>
medical bodies, patriotic societies, educational groups, etc., of their<lb/>
interest. If such public interest is made manifest, our legislators will<lb/>
act, first in Committee and then in full session. I think there is little<lb/>
doubt that there would be general approval. The very fact that it is non-<lb/>
partisan in character is, of course, of great help.</p>
<p>General Reed, to whom I told all this, impressed me with the fact that<lb/>
you are the one man in the country to whom this might be of significant<lb/>
interest and who could, if you wished, be of major help.</p>
<p>It is, of course, my hope and that of Senator Jenner, that the resolutions<lb/>
will pass and that I will head up the program of research, education and<lb/>
interpretation that the resolutions envisage. In that event, I should<lb/>
certainly want to work most closely with you. Indeed, I would give a<lb/>
good deal to have your wholehearted support and cooperation in this project<lb/>
from the very first.</p>
<p>I should like to add that my hopes go beyond that of the period of the<lb/>
proposed commemoration. If general public interest can be aroused in the<lb/>
story of Major Reed and of the Yellow Fever Commission during the three-<lb/>
year anniversary period, a considerable residue of interest will remain<lb/>
among private individuals and non-governmental organizations; and much of<lb/>
this interest and support can be drawn into a sustained program in behalf<lb/>
of the Walter Reed Memorial Association and of continued scientific work<lb/>
consistent with the spirit of the work done by Major Reed.</p>
<p>I look forward to hearing from you. I hope, too, that I may have the<lb/>
pleasure of an early meeting with you as I would like nothing better than<lb/>
to work closely with you for the success of this project.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Sidney Wallach</signed>
SW:ap<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
