<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04320005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Arthur C. Jacobson, November 9, 1949</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04320005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1949-11-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Jacobson, Arthur C.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="place">Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1949-11-09">November 9, 1949</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04320005</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Arthur C. Jacobson, November 9, 1949</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench compliments Jacobson on his Reed paper. Hench inquires if Jacobson saw any records indicating that Reed examined yellow fever cases in New York.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1949-11-09">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Arthur C. Jacobson, November 9, 1949</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04320005"/>
<opener>
<unclear>to run</unclear><lb/>
yellow<lb/>
fever<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1949-11-09">November 9, 1949</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Arthur C. Jacobson<lb/>
95 Pierrepont Street<lb/>
Brooklyn 2, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Jacobson:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I just received the six copies of your article this morning<lb/>
and read the material this noon with great pleasure. You have<lb/>
made a real contribution of the story of Reed's life and so far<lb/>
as I can see you have clarified a chapter in his life which has<lb/>
not been so clarified before. I am sure his friends and relatives<lb/>
will appreciate this greatly.</p>
<p>I have already taken the liberty of sending four of your copies<lb/>
to old friends of Reed, including General Kean and General Truby.<lb/>
I am sure that his relatives, his son and daughter, one or two first<lb/>
cousins, and other close friends would be anxious to have copies or<lb/>
reprints. Should you wish to send them directly, I <unclear>can later</unclear> send<lb/>
you their addresses or, if you care to send me a little supply of<lb/>
them, I would be glad to send them out from this office with your<lb/>
compliments. I am very pleased, indeed, with your whole presentation<lb/>
and your remarks about my co-operation were very gracious.</p>
<p>There is one point that I wish you would look up if you possibly<lb/>
have the time. On page 73, paragraph 5, you mentioned that cholera,<lb/>
yellow fever, and smallpox had occurred in Brooklyn and you specifically<lb/>
state that Reed ran into an epidemic of smallpox. Do your records<lb/>
you have looked over give any substantial proof in this--that Reed<lb/>
actually saw yellow fever in Brooklyn? Reed's right hand man and most<lb/>
faithful associate in Cuba was Major J. R. Kean, now Brigadier General,<lb/>
retired, living in Washington, D. C.. Actually, he was Reed's immediate<lb/>
superior officer in Cuba. General Kean is a delightful man and a man<lb/>
of <unclear>phenominal</unclear> accurate memory. It so happens that two or three days<lb/>
before Reed landed in Cuba to begin his yellow fever work, Kean came down<lb/>
with the disease himself. Reed is supposed to have rushed to the bedside<lb/>
of Kean and in Kean's person he saw his first case of yellow fever.<lb/>
Kean has told me this on numerous occasions--I have never questioned it.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04320006"/>
Dr. Arthur C. Jacobson<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 9, 1949<lb/>
I have questioned the innumerable remarks on General Kean, have<lb/>
verified and sought individual verifications on all of them which<lb/>
completely vindicate General Kean's beliefs and recollections.<lb/>
At least, it makes a nice story and I should not like to alter it<lb/>
without definite proof, but since Kean was so closely related to<lb/>
Reed in Cuba and has this distinct impression, I have no doubt that<lb/>
after Kean recovered Reed must have told him that he had never actually<lb/>
seen a case before.</p>
<p>Reed had visited Cuba on previous occasions but to study other<lb/>
problems and his visits were short. It is quite probable that he<lb/>
never was there previously during a yellow fever epidemic. In any<lb/>
event, do you recall any records indicating that Reed did see<lb/>
yellow fever in New York. If you have time to follow up this study<lb/>
further that would be an interesting additional point which you<lb/>
<unclear>might</unclear> clarify.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:mfm<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
