<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04328003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Sidney Wallach, March 13, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04328003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-03-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wallach, Sidney</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="person">Quemados de Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-03-13">March 13, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04328003</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Sidney Wallach, March 13, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench suggests a Reed memorial which would have long-range value to the public rather than a short-term publicity campaign. He discusses Camp Lazear and Building No. 1, and his efforts to have this site memorialized. Hench informs Wallach of the work of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, and other attempts to publicize Reed's work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-03-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Sidney Wallach, March 13, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04328003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1950-03-13">March 13, 1950</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Sidney Wallach<lb/>
381 Fourth Avenue<lb/>
New York 16, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Wallach:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have been away from the Clinic for awhile and have your letter<lb/>
of February 21 in which you tell me of your efforts to bring to the attention<lb/>
of the public the work of Walter Reed during the coming year or two. I am<lb/>
heartily in favor of such a venture, however I wondered if a memorial to Walter<lb/>
Reed and his colleagues involving as much as $350,000 should concern only a<lb/>
sort of publicity campaign. Wouldn't it be much better to provide a more<lb/>
lasting and suitable memorial which would have a long-range value to the public?<lb/>
Please do not misunderstand me. I am most heartily in favor of anything that<lb/>
can be done to honor the name of Dr. Walter Reed and his colleagues. I have<lb/>
for many years made the story of their work an intensely interesting hobby and<lb/>
I propose as soon as time permits to write a monograph on the subject.</p>
<p>There is one item which I think would be looked upon with favor by<lb/>
several of those concerned with the conquest of yellow fever. A few years<lb/>
ago Mr. John Moran (one of Walter Reed's first volunteers) and I rediscovered Camp<lb/>
Lazear where Reed did his work and found still standing, but in pretty rickety<lb/>
condition, the little Building No. 1 which was so crucial to the experiments.<lb/>
I tried to raise some money in this country and to get the Cuban Government<lb/>
to help memorialize the place. My plans involved an expenditure of perhaps<lb/>
$50,000 to restore the little building and build over and around it a small<lb/>
public health center for the town of Quemados de Marianao where the building<lb/>
now stands. My plans were approved heartily by the Cuban Government.I had<lb/>
an interview with a number of prominent men two or three years ago, including<lb/>
the Vice-President and they actually put through a bill authorizing an initial<lb/>
expenditure of $50,000 to preserve the little building. I constructed rough<lb/>
plans of a little memorial park etc., and the bill was passed by the Cuban<lb/>
legislature and I have a newspaper clipping indicating this. However that<lb/>
regime almost immediately went out of office and all such financial expendi-<lb/>
tures fall by the wayside when a new regime comes in.</p>
<p>I have visited Cuba several times in behalf of this little project.<lb/>
I know that the Surgeon General of the U. S. Army is interested in it and on<lb/>
one occasion several years ago Mr. Johnson, Secretary of Defense, was interested<lb/>
in it as he happened to be in Rochester and heard me give a talk. My own hope<lb/>
would be that part of your proposed bill would involve an expenditure of between<lb/>
$50,000 and $100,000 to build this little memorial and present this little health<lb/>
unit to the Cuban Government in honor of Reed and his colleagues.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04328004"/>
<p>Mr. Sidney Wallach</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>March 13, 1950</p>
<p>This involves, of course, the controversy that is still raging in Cuba<lb/>
in some less intelligent sources as to the credit for the conquest of yellow<lb/>
fever. A small but very vocal minority think that Reed and the Americans<lb/>
robbed Finlay of his just fame. That is decidedly not true and responsible<lb/>
men with whom I have talked have no patience with their vocal <unclear>brethrem</unclear>. I<lb/>
do not believe that there would be any real difficulty if American money<lb/>
was forthcoming for this project. I think the only reason that the Cubans<lb/>
haven't done it is their congenital attitude of <unclear>manana</unclear> and the fact that<lb/>
Cuban money has a habit of coming and going in various ways.</p>
<p>Mr. Wallach, I do not set myself up to decide what shall be the best<lb/>
method of memorializing Walter Reed and his colleagues. In my own little way<lb/>
I have tried to do it by writing two or three little articles and I had planned<lb/>
to write another one to appear this year, the 50th anniversary. However Fate<lb/>
has caught me up in my own medical work so that I will probably not be able<lb/>
to do this as I am working intensively on another project that cannot wait. I<lb/>
tried to interest Mr. Steven Spencer, one of the editors of the Saturday Evening<lb/>
Post, to write an article on the subject and I offered him several points that<lb/>
I thought would bring the story up to date; however they ran a story in the<lb/>
Saturday Evening Post on Moran, several years back, and the Chief Editor turned<lb/>
down Mr. <unclear>Spencer's</unclear> idea, the latter having been willing to write the article. I<lb/>
next contacted Mr. Robert Potter, a science writer now connected with the New<lb/>
York Academy of Medicine but he is so involved with his own work, a new job,<lb/>
that he cannot do it. I am about to write to two or three other science<lb/>
writers to see if they would do it. I do think that such an article should<lb/>
appear this year.</p>
<p>Recently I have had some telephonic communications with someone in<lb/>
the State Department who has been helping with the preliminary plans of the<lb/>
radio program &ldquo;We, the People&rdquo; which intends to put on a story and proposes<lb/>
to bring up one or two of the surviving volunteers to lend the personal touch<lb/>
to the story.</p>
<p>Are you aware that shortly a small plaque will be placed outside of an<lb/>
old building which in 1902 was an Army hospital in which Walter Reed died. This<lb/>
plaque has been placed through the efforts of the Walter Reed Memorial Associa-<lb/>
tion and the Surgeon General of the U. S. Army.</p>
<p>It seems to me that all of these things could be tied to one 
 project<lb/>
and undoubtedly other procedures could be added to make the memorial more ef-<lb/>
fective. I would be interested in your further comments.</p>
<p>I am sending by separate post some reprints which may interest you.<lb/>
It gives a photograph of the little shack and if you are interested in con-<lb/>
sidering the memorializing of this shack, I can later send you photographic<lb/>
copies of my plans and perhaps we might have a conference sometime with the<lb/>
Surgeon General. I have no doubt that with the help of the Surgeon General<lb/>
and the Secretary of Defense something can be done along this line. My <unclear></unclear><lb/>
great regret is that I cannot spend the necessary time on doing this.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
cc: General Reed, Blossom Reed, General Kean, General Truby, Colonel Siler<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
