<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04333002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank Carey, June 6, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04333002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-06-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carey, Frank</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed family</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="person">Mayo, William J.</name>
<name type="person">Dawson, Lord</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Rockefeller, Nelson</name>
<name type="person">Rockefeller, Jr., John D.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-06-06">June 6, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04333002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank Carey, June 6, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench sends Carey reprints of his articles on the yellow fever story. He provides a detailed account of his involvement in researching the story and his attempts to preserve Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-06-06">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frank Carey, June 6, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04333002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1950-06-06">June 6, 1950</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Frank Carey<lb/>
Science Reporter<lb/>
330 Star Building<lb/>
Washington 4, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Carey:</salute>
</opener>
<p>By separate post I am sending you three reprints that I have written<lb/>
on the yellow fever story. <del><unclear>While</unclear></del> Each one is a little different; one has<lb/>
material in it that the others do not have. The reprint of the Fourth Inter-<lb/>
national Congress on Malaria and Tropical Medicine has some historical para-<lb/>
graphs in it that are not available elsewhere. The story of how I found the<lb/>
lost Camp Lazear is given in the Pharos for May 1948. I enclose also a pro-<lb/>
gram of the unveiling of the bust and tablet of Walter Reed in the Hall of<lb/>
Fame. The letters reprinted there are all in my possession as Mrs. Reed and<lb/>
the Reed family have given me everything, letters, pamphlets, clippings, etc.,<lb/>
that they had, including the Congressional Medal and I have added to this<lb/>
large collection other material which I have gotten from many sources, in-<lb/>
cluding many of the surviving participants of the experiments.</p>
<p>I am delighted that you are writing a story as this is the 50th<lb/>
anniversary of the conquest of yellow fever by Reed and his colleagues.</p>
<p>You ask how I became interested in the subject. Very briefly, it<lb/>
was this. Doctor Lazear was a graduate of Washington and Jefferson College,<lb/>
Washington, Pennsylvania, a small college that is the oldest one west of<lb/>
the Allogheny Mountains. I did not graduate from that college but in about<lb/>
1938, Washington and Jefferson planned to erect a memorial building in honor<lb/>
of Doctor Lazear, <unclear>their</unclear> distinguished alumnus. It so happened that the Presi-<lb/>
dent of W &amp; J at that time was Dr. Ralph Hutchison, one of my oldest friends<lb/>
who often visits me in Rochester. One evening he was telling me about their<lb/>
plans and said he wanted to arrange a very attractive program on the occasion<lb/>
of the dedication. He said that they wanted to honor not only Doctor Lazear<lb/>
but the entire medical profession and that they would like to have two dis-<lb/>
tinguished speakers of international repute, one representing surgery and the<lb/>
other medicine. His idea was to invite Dr. W. J. Mayo as an American surgeon<lb/>
and Lord Dawson (King George's physician) as an internationally known physician.<lb/>
We saw Doctor Will who agreed to participate and later that year I went to<lb/>
Europe on another mission and presented to Lord Dawson the invitation. However,<lb/>
the next year Doctor Will died and of course the war came to England.</p>
<p>But to go back a bit, the night in my home that Doctor Hutchison<lb/>
brought up the matter of the dedication program he said he wanted to have<lb/>
some human interest in the program and was hoping that he could find some<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04333003"/>
Mr. Frank Carey<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
June 6, 1950<lb/>
of the surviving doctors but he was afraid they were all dead. I remembered<lb/>
the story of Walter Reed from my medical school days but know nothing about<lb/>
who the volunteers were or whether they were alive or dead but I did sug-<lb/>
gest that if the <unclear>principals</unclear> were <unclear>dead</unclear>, that is the doctors, why not get one<lb/>
or two of the human guinea pigs. To this Doctor Hutchison replied &ldquo;That<lb/>
would be a find idea, Phil. As your contribution to the program will you<lb/>
find out who they were, which ones are alive and where they live?&rdquo; Rather<lb/>
glibly I accepted this task.</p>
<p>Within the next week I read Kelly's book on Walter Reed and found<lb/>
a few of the names but had no idea how to go about finding out whether they<lb/>
were alive or dead but my first bit of luck came to me about two weeks later when<lb/>
I heard announced on the radio program of &ldquo;We, the People&rdquo; the statement that<lb/>
the dramatization of the story of the conquest of yellow fever would be given<lb/>
the following week with one of the survivors being also on the program. I<lb/>
listened to the program. It was Kissinger. I got in touch with him through<lb/>
the radio station and later visited him at his home. I assumed that the whole<lb/>
story had been told but to my surprise I found that Kissinger had never written<lb/>
down of his own personal experiences although he had frequently given them<lb/>
extemporaneously before small groups. Kissinger was a fine fellow but not<lb/>
well educated. I made many notes and later got him to Rochester as my guest<lb/>
and got a pretty complete story from him.</p>
<p>He gave me the news of a few of the survivors, chief of whom was<lb/>
Johnny Moran of Havana, Cuba. Mrs. Hench and I often go to Florida for<lb/>
Winter vacations so in the spring of 1940 Mrs. Hench and I went to Cuba from<lb/>
Florida to visit Johnny. I found from him also that the correct story had<lb/>
never been told but equally thrilling was the re-discovery of the lost Camp<lb/>
Lazear, the story of which is given in the Pharos for May 1948.</p>
<p>Through these two contacts I got slowly the addresses of all the<lb/>
survivors or their relatives and have visited practically all of them. We<lb/>
have uncovered in attics and cellars long lost records. I have spent<lb/>
literally days in the National Archives in Washington uncovering old records<lb/>
and have a voluminous series of 30 files bulging with unpublished data which,<lb/>
sometime when I retire, I hope to write up. But the important features of<lb/>
the story are as given in these reprints.</p>
<p>I have spent a great deal of time patiently trying to stimulate the<lb/>
Cubans to help preserve Building No. 1. Just before the war, through the<lb/>
courtesy of the owner of the property, I was given a deed to the little building<lb/>
but the <unclear>proviso</unclear> was that my plans would be completed in a year or two. The war<lb/>
interrupted this so that my deed lapsed. However I was able to stimulate the<lb/>
Cuban Government to declare the <unclear>little</unclear> building a national memorial. I tried to<lb/>
collect some money in this country. I interviewed Nelson Rockefeller on one<lb/>
occasion and later interviewed the Finance Secretary of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.<lb/>
They were not interested. I thought they would be because of the extensive<lb/>
interest of the Rockefeller Foundation in Latin America and particularly in<lb/>
yellow fever control. Two years ago I visited Cuba again and found that<lb/>
although the Cuban Government had set aside the building nominally as a<lb/>
national monument, they had done absolutely nothing toward preserving it.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04333004"/>
Mr. Frank Carey<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
June 6, 1950<lb/>
It is falling to pieces, and has, miraculously, survived several tornadoes.<lb/>
I went to several authorities, including the Vice President, who kindly<lb/>
received me in his home and we spent the evening going over a plan which<lb/>
I had worked out with two or three important Cuban physicians to build<lb/>
around Building No. 1 for a helth center for the community of Quemados.<lb/>
I thought the cost of the modest plan would be $50,000 to $100,000. Every-<lb/>
one concerned approved the plan heartily but knowing the &ldquo;manana&rdquo; attitude<lb/>
of the Cubans, I begged to be allowed to surround Building No. 1 with a<lb/>
galvanized protection at my expense. But with the usual Latin <unclear>politeness</unclear>,<lb/>
they wouldn't listen to such a thing and the Vice-President insisted that<lb/>
the Government would take care of the matter. Within a few weeks the<lb/>
Government did allocate $50,000 for protecting the building and laying out<lb/>
the grounds. I saw the announcement of the passage of the bill in the<lb/>
Cuban papers and there was a little advertisement with newspaper photographs<lb/>
of the little building. But thereafter, as has happened to me several times<lb/>
before, those who promised these things were swept out of office and nothing<lb/>
has happened.</p>
<p>Actually, the naming of the building as a historical monument has<lb/>
done nothing but interfere because otherwise I, as a private citizen with<lb/>
two or three other prominent sympathetic Cubans, could go ahead and make<lb/>
arrangements for protecting the little building with a galvanized iron<lb/>
covering until the full plans could be carried out.</p>
<p>I have talked to the Surgeon General of the Army about this. He is<lb/>
most sympathetic with my plan but of course has himself no power to help ex-<lb/>
cept to recomment. I thought that the U. S. Army might make a gesture of<lb/>
help combining efforts with the State Department. It would be a splendid<lb/>
thing if some american could cooperate with this venture and, among other<lb/>
things, build up friendship by doing away with the most unfortunate spat<lb/>
among the Cubans who think that the Americans and Reed robbed Finlay of<lb/>
just credit. Several years ago when Mr. Louis Johnson was a patient here<lb/>
and was, I think, an under-secretary of some sort in Washington, he heard<lb/>
me give an illustrated lecture on this subject. He sent me a note saying<lb/>
that if he could help at any time he would be glad to do so. Somewhat in<lb/>
desperation, therefore, about a month ago, when he was here for a brief<lb/>
visit, I reminded him of that, told him briefly of my plan and wondered<lb/>
whether the Government could be persuaded to allocate $50,000. His reply<lb/>
was brief and short &ldquo;Not this year. We must out down all possible ex-<lb/>
penses. Perhaps next year would be a better time.&rdquo; That is where the<lb/>
matter stands and it is a darn shame. I haven't had the time to go out<lb/>
and collect nickels and I haven't found a millionaire with $50,000 or $100,000<lb/>
and yet here a little building which saw one of the most dramatic adventures<lb/>
in history is being allowed to rot.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: Perhaps your own article might get some sympathetic readers. I wish it would.<lb/>
I have your letter of June 2. I &ldquo;rented&rdquo; the drawing of the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Epidemic in Shreveport from the Bettman Archives, 211A East 57th Street,<lb/>
New York. They rent you a print for $5 or $10 and you are supposed to send it<lb/>
back and you have to give credit to them. I am glad to send you a print of<lb/>
Building No. 1. How soon would you need this? Our photographic department<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04333005"/>
Mr. Frank Carey<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
June 6, 1950<lb/>
is completely swamped making last-minute photographs, slides and movies for<lb/>
the meeting of the American Medical Association in three weeks. Could you<lb/>
possibly wait until after then? If not, will you allow me to borrow the<lb/>
negative and have the print made (at a small cost) by some photographer<lb/>
here in town. The Clinic does not want us to send the negative out of town<lb/>
and this one now belongs to the Clinic collection.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
