<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04332001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Press release by Frank Carey, Associated Press Science Reporter, June 24, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04332001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-06-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, John L.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-06-24">June 24, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04332001</idno>
<title>Press release by Frank Carey, Associated Press Science Reporter, June 24, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carey details the 50<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary of the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-06-24">
<head>Press release by Frank Carey, Associated Press Science Reporter, June 24, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04332001"/>
<p>(ADVANCE FOR AMS OF SUNDAY, JUNE 25</p>
<p>BY FRANK CAREY</p>
<p>ASSOCIATED PRESS SCIENCE REPORTER</p>
<p>(ADVANCE) WASHINGTON, JUNE 24--(AP)--TOMORROW IS THE<lb/>
50TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE START OF HISTORIC EXPERIMENTS LEADING TO<lb/>
THE CONQUERING OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>IT WAS ON JUNE 25, 1900 THAT MAJOR WALTER REED<lb/>
OF THE ARMY MEDICAL CORPS ARRIVED IN HAVANA AT THE HEAD OF AN<lb/>
ARMY BOARD APPOINTED TO INVESTIGATE THE CAUSE OF THE <add>MYSTERIOUS</add> "SAFFRON HORRO</p>
<p>YELLOW FEVER, <add>Chief among the <unclear>diseases</unclear></add> WHICH HAD KILLED MORE AMERICANS IN<lb/>
THE RECENT SPANISH WAR THAN WERE SLAIN BY SPANISH BULLETS, WAS EPIDEMIC<lb/>
ONCE MORE IN HAVANA. ALREADY IT HAD CLAIMED MANY LIVES AMONG THE ARMY<lb/>
OF OCCUPATION.</p>
<p><del>REED WAS KNOWN AS A &ldquo;TROUBLE SHOOTER&rdquo; OF THE<lb/>
ARMY SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE. HE HAD MADE MAJOR CONTRIBUTIONS TO T<lb/>
UNDERSTANDING OF TYPHOID FEVER AND CERTAIN OTHER ILLS HAD PLAG<lb/>
THE TROOPS IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE WORLD.</del></p>
<p><del>BUT HE HAD NEVER SEEN AN ACTUAL CASE OF</del> <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04332002"/>
<p>2----</p>
<p>REED AND THREE COLLEAGUES HAD BEEN COMMISSIONED TO TACKLE<lb/>
SOMETHING WHICH HAD ELUDED MEDICAL UNDERSTANDING FOR CENTURIES--A DISEASE<lb/>
WHICH HAD TAKEN A TERRIFIC TOLL IN MANY PARTS OF THE WORLD, ESPECIALLY THE<lb/>
TROPICS.</p>
<p>IN THE UNITED STATES, IT HAD STRUCK WITH EPIDEMIC FRIGHTFULNESS<lb/>
OVER THE YEARS IN SUCH CITIES AS PHILADELPHIA, BOSTON, NEW ORLEANS,<lb/>
CHARLESTON, NORFOLK, NEW YORK AND <del><unclear></unclear></del> MEMPHIS--KILLING THOUSANDS.</p>
<p>IT WAS A DISEASE WHICH, IN PAST EPIDEMICS, HAD <add>SOMETIMES</add> CAUSED<lb/>
PEOPLE TO FALL SUDDENLY IN THE STREETS, THEIR BODIES WRACKED WITH PAIN,<lb/>
Later THEIR EYES AND FACES <add>could</add> YELLOW<del>ED</del> WITH JAUNDICE, THEIR STOMACHS RETCHING<lb/>
FORTH THE DREAD &ldquo;BLACK VOMIT.&rdquo; OTHERS DIED IN <del><unclear></unclear></del> SOLITUDE, ABANDONED BY<lb/>
THEIR LOVED ONES WHO HAD FLED TO THE HILLS FROM THE STRICKEN CITIES.</p>
<p><del>Later</del></p>
<p>SOMETIMES DEATHS WERE SO NUMEROUS THAT CORPSES LAY UNBURIED<lb/>
FOR DAYS, AND DRIVERS OF DEATH CARTS PATROLLED THE SILENT STREETS, UTTERIng<lb/>
A TERRIBLE CRY: &ldquo;BRING OUT YOUR DEAD, BRING OUT YOUR DEAD.&rdquo;</p>
<p>NO ONE KNEW THE CAUSE OF THE SICKNESS. BUT, IN THE FALSE<lb/>
BELIEF THAT IT WAS DUE TO SOME MYSTERIOUS &ldquo;POISON&rdquo; IN THE AIR, MEN<lb/>
FIRED CANNON <add>BALLS</add> INTO THE <del>AIR</del> ATMOSPHERE, OR BURNED TAR POTS--TO TRY TO<lb/>
DISPELL THE MENACE.</p>
<p>IT REMAINED FOR REED AND HIS ASSOCIATES TO DEMONSTRATE THAT<lb/>
THE DISEASE, WHATEVER ITS ACTUAL CAUSE MIGHT BE, WAS TRANSMITTED<lb/>
BY SOMETHING IN THE AIR--A MOSQUITO.</p>
<p><add>YEARS</add>
<del><unclear></unclear></del>AFTER REED'S DEATH IN 1902, SCIENTISTS DISCOVERED<lb/>
THE ACTUAL CAUSE OF YELLOW FEVER--A VIRUS--AND THIS AND OTHER FINDINGS<lb/>
HAVE RESULTED IN THE DEVELOPMENT OF A PROTECTIVE VACCINE.</p>
<p>BUT THE WORK OF REED AND HIS ASSOCIATES MADE IT POSSIBLE<lb/>
TO CONTROL YELLOW FEVER <del><unclear></unclear></del> WHEREVER IT DEVELOPED BY RIDDING THE<lb/>
AREA OF THE PARTICULAR MOSQUITO INVOLVED.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04332003"/>
<p>3----</p>
<p>THEIR RESEARCH--RATED BY SOME AUTHORITIES AS RANKING <add>close</add> IN<lb/>
IMPORTANCE WITH THE DISCOVERY OF ANESTHESIA--MADE POSSIBLE<lb/>
THE <del><unclear></unclear></del><add><hi>COMPLETION</hi></add> OF THE PANAMA CANAL, ONCE KNOWN AS THE &ldquo;WHITE MAN'S<lb/>
GRAVEYARD&rdquo; BECAUSE OF DEATHS FROM YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>THEIR PROOF THAT THE DISEASE WAS MOSQUITO-BORNE AND<lb/>
NOT CONTAGIOUS MADE IT POSSIBLE TO <del><unclear></unclear></del><add><hi>MODIFY GREATLY</hi></add> THE COSTLY QUARANTINE<lb/>
MEASURES WHICH HAD PREVIOUSLY <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>CLOSED GREAT SEAPORTS, SLOWING THE</add><lb/>
COMMERCE OF THE WORLD.</p>
<p>ALSO, THEIR PROOF THAT THE DISEASE WAS NOT PASSED FROM<lb/>
MAN TO MAN BY CONTACT MADE IT POSSIBLE TO ELIMINATE ANOTHER COSTLY<lb/>
PRACTICE--THAT OF BURNING FURNITURE, BEDDING AND CLOTHING USED BY<lb/>
VICTIMS OF THE PLAGUE.</p>
<p>BUT ALL THESE FEATS WERE THINGS OF THE FUTURE WHEN<lb/>
REED ARRIVED IN HAVANA.</p>
<p>IN FACT, HE HIMSELF HAD NEVER SEEN AN ACTUAL CASE OF<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER UP TO THAT TIME. although he had an established<lb/>
reputation as a medical &ldquo;<unclear>Trouble shooter.</unclear>&rdquo;</p>
<p><del>WHY THEN HAD HE BEEN PICKED FOR THIS TOUGH ASSIGNMENT?</del></p>
<p><del>RETIRED BRIGADIER GENERAL JEFFERSON RANDOLPH KEAN--<del><unclear></unclear></del><add>89</add><lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del> NOW LIVING IN WASHINGTON HAS THIS THEORY:</del></p>
<p><del>"REED WAS A KIND OF TROUBLE SHOOTER FOR THE ARMY<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE</del></p>
<pb n="4" id="f04332004"/>
<p>4----</p>
<p>HE SAW HIS FIRST CASE THAT DAY HE ARRIVED. HE HURRIED TO<lb/>
THE BEDSIDE OF HIS OLD FRIEND, MAJOR JEFFERSON RANDOLPH KEAN, CHIEF<lb/>
SURGEON OF THE ARMY'S DEPARTMENT OF HAVANA, WHO HAD BEEN STRICKEN WITH<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del></p>
<p>&ldquo;MY RECOLLECTION OF HIS VISIT IS VERY DIM--I WAS PRETTY<lb/>
SICK,&rdquo; KEAN TOLD A REPORTER TODAY. <del><unclear><lb/>
</unclear></del></p>
<p>BUT KEAN, NOW 89, AND A RETIRED BRIGADIER GENERAL, GAVE a<lb/>
VIVID PICTURE OF THE SITUATION THAT PREVAILED <add><hi>AT THE TIME OF REED'S ARRIVAL</hi></add> IN THE TOWN OF QUEMADOS<lb/>
NEAR HAVANA WHERE THE ARMY'S COLUMBIA BARRACKS WAS LOCATED.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WE HAD A VERY WHOLESOME TERROR OF YELLOW FEVER,&rdquo; HE<lb/>
SAID, SIPPING A SOCIABLE COCKTAIL, AS HIS THOUGHTS RACED BACK 50 YEARS.<lb/>
&ldquo;WE DIDN'T KNOW WHAT TO DO ABOUT IT.&rdquo;</p>
<p>SOLDIERS AND HIGH-PLACED OFFICERS <add><hi>INCLUDING DOCTORS</hi></add> WERE COMING DOWN<lb/>
RIGHT AND LEFT WITH THE FEVER, AND SO WERE THEIR WIVES. PEOPLE BURNED<lb/>
SULFUR CANDLES TO &ldquo;PURGE THE AIR.&rdquo; ELEGANTLY DRESSED ARMY WIVES WORE<lb/>
SMELLY BAGS OF ASAFETIDA AND SPIT CONSTANTLY OUT THEIR CARRIAGE WINDOWS<lb/>
in THE BELIEF THEY WERE OFFSETTING INFECTION. <add>THE ARMY BURNED TENTS AND BEDDING USED BY FEVER VICTIMS.</add> AND AT SUNDOWN IN THE<lb/>
OFFICERS' MESS, RECALLED THE OLD GENERAL, VETERANS OF THE INDIAN AND<lb/>
SPANISH WARS DRANK &ldquo;TO THOSE WHO HAVE ALREADY GONE-AND HERE'S TO THE<lb/>
NEXT TO GO!&rdquo;</p>
<p>KEAN SAID THERE WAS NO SPECIFIC TREATMENT. PATIENTS WERE<lb/>
DENIED FOOD WHILE THEIR FEVER WAS HIGH--&ldquo;THE FIRST THING WE GAVE THEM WAS<lb/>
CHAMPAGNE BECAUSE IT WAS NOURISHING WITHOUT REQUIRING DIGESTION.&rdquo;</p>
<p>MOSQUITOES?</p>
<p>&ldquo;THEY WERE CONSIDERED JUST A NUISANCE AT THAT TIME,&rdquo; SAId<lb/>
KEAN WITH AN IRONIC SMILE. &ldquo;DR. CARLOS FINLAY, A HAVANA PHYSICIAN, HAD<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04332005"/>
5---<lb/>
BEEN CLAIMING FOR 19 YEARS THAT MOSQUITOES WERE INVOLVED, BUT IN ALL<lb/>
THAT TIME HE HAD CONVINCED ONLY ONE OTHER HAVANA DOCTOR. UNFORTUNATELY<lb/>
DR. FINLAY HAD NOT BEEN ABLE TO PROVE HIS THEORY. IT REMAINED FOR<lb/>
REED AND HIS ASSOCIATES TO DEMONSTRATE--EMPHASIZE THAT WORD '<unclear>DEMONSTRATO</unclear>'<lb/>
--THAT OLD DOCTOR FINLAY HAD BEEN RIGHT.&rdquo;</p>
<p>HOW THEY DEMONSTRATED IT IS RECORDED IN OFFICIAL MEDICAL<lb/>
REPORTS AND OTHER RECORDS WHICH CONSTITUTE A THRILLING CHAPTER IN THE<lb/>
HISTORY OF MEDICINE.</p>
<p>REED HAD THREE ASSOCIATES ON THE &ldquo;YELLOW FEVER BOARD&rdquo;--<lb/>
DOCTORS JESSE LAZEAR, JAMES CARROLL AND ARISTIDES AGRAMONTE, THE LATTEr<lb/>
A CUBAN BY BIRTH.</p>
<p>AFTER SOME PRELIMINARY TESTS ON ANOTHER SLANT, THE BOARD<lb/>
DECIDED TO TEST THE THEORY OF DR. FINLAY. THAT WAS IN AUGUST.</p>
<p>DOCTOR CARROLL WAS THE FIRST HERO OF THE RESEARCH. HE CONTRACTed<lb/>
AN ALMOST-FATAL CASE OF FEVER AFTER TWICE ALLOWING HIMSELF TO BE BITTEn<lb/>
BY MOSQUITOES WHICH HAD FED ON YELLOW FEVER VICTIMS. DR. LAZEAR<lb/>
ALSO GOT SICK--AND DIED. (WHILE THE OFFICIAL RECORDS SAY THAT<lb/>
LAZEAR WAS ACCIDENTALLY BITTEN BY AN INFECTED MOSQUITO, GENERAL KEAN<lb/>
SAYS REED AND THE OTHERS ALWAYS BELIEVED LAZEAR PURPOSELY EXPOSED<lb/>
HIMSELF TO REPEATED BITES--AND WAS THUS A TRUE MARTYR TO THE RESEARCH.)</p>
<p>AN AMERICAN SOLDIER--WHO VOLUNTEERED TO BE BITTEN IN A SPIRIT<lb/>
OF BRAVADO AND SCOFFING--ALSO WAS <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>LISTED</add> AS AN EXPERIMENTALLY-INDUCE<lb/>
CASE OF FEVER.</p>
<p>REED HAD BEEN RECALLED TO WASHINGTON ON OTHER WORK, MEANWHILE,<lb/>
AND MISSED THESE FIRST TESTS.</p>
<p>BUT ON HIS RETURN IN THE EARLY FALL, HE MADE A BRILLIANT<lb/>
DEDUCTION BASED ON CERTAIN OBSERVATIONS RECORDED IN DR. LAZEAR'S<lb/>
LABORATORY RECORDS AND IN A PERSONAL NOTEBOOK FOUND IN LAZEAR'S<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f04332006"/>
6---<lb/>
BLOUSE AT THE TIME OF HIS DEATH.</p>
<p>THE DEDUCTION WAS THAT A MOSQUITO CAN BECOME INFECTED<lb/>
ONLY WHEN IT BITES A YELLOW FEVER VICTIM DURING THE FIRST THREE DAYS<lb/>
OF HIS ILLNESS. MOREOVER, EVEN AFTER THE INFECTION IS PASSED ONTO<lb/>
THE MOSQUITO, IT REQUIRES AT LEAST 12 DAYS FOR THE DISEASE AGENT TO<lb/>
DEVELOP IN THE INSECT'S BODY.</p>
<p>FOR THE FIRST TIME IT BECAME CLEAR WHY CERTAIN PREVIOUS<lb/>
EXPERIMENTS OF OLD DR. FINLAY AND OF THE ARMY BOARD HAD FAILED:--THE<lb/>
TIME ELEMENT WAS EXTREMELY IMPORTANT.</p>
<p>REED AND HIS COLLEAGUES RUSHED TOGETHER A REPORT OF<lb/>
THEIR RESEARCH TO DATE, AND IT WAS PRESENTED TO A MEDICAL MEETING<lb/>
BACK IN THE STATES. BUT THEY WERE PREPARED FOR THE SKEPTICISM THAT<lb/>
GREETED THE REPORT; THEY REALIZED THAT THE CASES OF EXPERIMENTAL<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER WERE NOT WHOLLY &ldquo;CONTROLLED&rdquo; CASES IN THE SCIENTIFIC<lb/>
SENSE.</p>
<p>AND SO, IN THE LATE FALL OF 1900, THEY SET UP AN<lb/>
EXPERIMENT DESIGNED TO SHOW THAT THE MOSQUITO--AND THE MOSQUITO ALONE--<lb/>
WAS THE VILLAIN IN THE PIECE. THEY ESTABLISHED AN ISOLATED CAMP WHERE<lb/>
THERE WAS NO CHANCE OF INFECTION FROM PATIENTS ALREADY SICK WITH FEVER.</p>
<p>VOLUNTEERS WERE CALLED FOR. <del><unclear></unclear></del> (&ldquo;THEY WERE TO <del><unclear></unclear></del> GET $200<lb/>
IF THEY CONTRACTED FEVER, $100 IF THEY DIDN'T,&rdquo; RECALLS GENERAL KEAN<lb/>
WHO WAS IN CHARGE OF HANDLING THE $10,000 ALLOCATED BY THE ARMY FOR<lb/>
THE EXPERIMENTS.)</p>
<p><del>SIXTEEN</del></p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear> AMERICANS, <unclear>FOUR SPANIARDS,</unclear> THREE CUBANS,ONE<lb/>
ENGLISHMAN AND ONE IRISHMAN <unclear></unclear> VOLUNTEERED. THE LATTER--JOHN J.<lb/>
MORAN--NEVER ACCEPTED A PENNY FOR HIS PART IN THE RESEARCH BECAUSE,<lb/>
HE TOLD THE ASSOCIATED PRESS RECENTLY.</del></p>
<p>&ldquo;I FELT IT WAS A CHANCE TO DO SOME GOOD IN THIS LIFE; ALSO<lb/>
I DIDN'T WANT THEM WRITING ON MY TOMBSTONE: 'HERE LIES JOHN MORAN, WHO</p>
<pb n="7" id="f04332007"/>
<p>6A</p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del></p>
<p>ALMOST A SCORE OF AMERICAN VOLUNTEERS CAME FORWARD, AND<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del><add>SOME</add> SPANIARDS. THE AMERICANS INCLUDED SOLDIERS, <add>AND OTHER ARMY-RELATED PERSONNEL,</add> A CIVILIAN LIVING<lb/>
IN CUBA AND A CIVILIAN ARMY CLERK.</p>
<p>THE LATTER, JOHN J. MORAN, AN IRISHMAN WITH A RICH<lb/>
BROGUE, HAS NEVER ACCEPTED A PENNY FOR HIS PART IN THE RESEARCH<lb/>
BECAUSE, HE TOLD THE ASSOCIATED PRESS <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>RECENTLY:</add></p>
<p>&ldquo;I FELT IT WAS A CHANCE TO DO SOME GOOD IN THIS<lb/>
LIFE; ALSO I DIDN'T WANT THEM WRITING ON MY TOMBSTONE: 'HERE<lb/>
LIES JOHN MORAN, WHO<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04332008"/>
7----<lb/>
DIED FOR ($200.)&rdquo;</p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del></p>
<p>MORAN, <del>THEN A CIVILIAN CLERK IN THE ARMY,</del> AND HIS<lb/>
ROOM-MATE, JOHN J. KISSINGER, A MEDICAL CORPS MAN, WERE THE FIRST<lb/>
TO VOLUNTEER.</p>
<p>KISSINGER WAS THE FIRST <add>TO FACE THE POSSIBILITY OF DEATH, THE FIRST</add> TO BECOME ILL. HE LET INFECTED<lb/>
MOSQUITOES BITE HIM ON THE ARM IN A TENT. REED SAID LATER OF<lb/>
KISSINGER &ldquo;IN MY OPINION THIS EXHIBITION OF MORAL COURAGE HAS<lb/>
NEVER BEEN SURPASSED IN THE ANNALS OF THE ARMY OF THE UNITED STATES.&rdquo;</p>
<p>SOME OTHER VOLUNTEERS WERE ALSO INFECTED THUS.</p>
<p>BUT THE DOCTORS WANTED TO TRY <del><unclear></unclear></del> TWO OTHER<lb/>
THINGS.</p>
<p>THEY BUILT TWO SPECIAL BUILDINGS.</p>
<p>ONE WAS DESIGNED TO PROVE OR DISPROVE THE COMMON THEORY<lb/>
THAT YELLOW FEVER COULD BE CONTRACTED FROM &ldquo;FOMITES&rdquo;--THE SOILED AND<lb/>
FILTHY BEDDING AND CLOTHING OF YELLOW FEVER VICTIMS.</p>
<p>THE SMALL, ONE-ROOM, POORLY VENTILATED BUILDING WAS<lb/>
HEATED WITH A COAL STOVE TO TEMPERATURES UP TO 100 DEGREES--&ldquo;LIKE THE<lb/>
HOLD OF A SHIP IN THE TROPICS&rdquo; ONE OF THE DOCTORS LATER RELATED. BUT<lb/>
IT WAS COMPLETELY SCREENED AGAINST MOSQUITOES.</p>
<p>INTO THAT CHAMBER WENT A NUMBER OF VOLUNTEERS. THEY HANDLED<lb/>
FOUL-SMELLING BEDDING AND CLOTHING, AND FOR 21 NIGHTS SLEPT ON FILTHY<lb/>
AND BLOOD-STAINED SHEETS. AT TIMES THEY COVERED THEIR PILLOWS WITH<lb/>
TOWELS SOILED WITH THE BLOOD AND VOMIT OF FEVER VICTIMS. THEY WORE<lb/>
NIGHTSHIRTS <del><unclear></unclear></del> USED BY FEVER VICTIMS. AT TIMES, THE STENCH<lb/>
WAS ENOUGH TO DRIVE THEM OUT, BUT ALWAYS THEY RETURNED.</p>
<p>NOT ONE OF THEM CONTRACTED YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>THE SECOND BUILDING WAS AS IMMACULATE AS THE OTHER ONE WAS<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f04332009"/>
8---<lb/>
FILTHY, AND IT WAS WELL VENTILATED.</p>
<p>THE ONE-ROOM STRUCTURE WAS DIVIDED INTO TWO PARTS BY WIRE<lb/>
SCREEN AND MUSLIN. THE IDEA WAS TO EXPOSE A MAN ON ONE SIDE OF THE<lb/>
ROOM TO THE BITES OF INFECTED MOSQUITOES, WHILE VOLUNTEERS ON THE<lb/>
OTHER SIDE WERE NOT SO EXPOSED.</p>
<p>FIRST TO BE EXPOSED IN THE &ldquo;MOSQUITO&rdquo; SIDE OF THE ROOM WAS<lb/>
JOHN J. MORAN.</p>
<p>FRESH FROM A BATH, AND CLAD ONLY IN A NIGHT SHIRT, HE WENT<lb/>
INTO THE ROOM ON THREE DIFFERENT DAYS, GOT BITTEN BY 15 MOSQUITOES<lb/>
EACH TIME. THE FIRST TWO <del><unclear></unclear></del> DAYS, NOTHING HAPPENED.</p>
<p>&ldquo;MAJOR REED WAS SUCH A HERO IN MY EYES THAT I WAS REALLY<lb/>
DISAPPOINTED WITH MYSELF, AND SO WAS HE,&rdquo; DECLARED MORAN IN AN<lb/>
ASSOCIATED PRESS INTERVIEW. HE NOW IS LIVING IN HAVANA.</p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del></p>
<p>BUT MORAN WENT INTO THE ROOM A THIRD TIME--AND A FEW DAYS<lb/>
LATER, ON CHRISTMAS DAY, DEVELOPED A FULL BLOWN CASE OF YELLOW FEVER!</p>
<p>MEANWHILE, VOLUNTEERS WHO HAD STAYED LONG PERIODS IN THE<lb/>
MOSQUITO-PROTECTED PART OF THE SAME BUILDING, REMAINED FREE OF FEVER.</p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del></p>
<p>THE SIGNIFICANCE OF THE TEST WAS CLEARLY APPARENT: THERE COULD<lb/>
BE NO QUESTION NOW ABOUT THE ROLE PLAYED BY THE MOSQUITO.</p>
<p>MORAN SAYS REED TOLD HIM ON THAT MEMORABLE CHRISTMAS DAY:</p>
<p>&ldquo;&lsquo;MR. MORAN, THIS IS ONE OF THE HAPPIEST DAYS OF MY LIFE.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p>
<p>DR. ROBERT P. COOKE, A &ldquo;CONTRACT DOCTOR&rdquo; WITH THE ARMY,<lb/>
WAS ONE OF THE VOLUNTEERS FOR THE &ldquo;INFECTED BEDDING&rdquo; TEST.</p>
<p>NOW LIVING IN RETIREMENT ON A FARM AT WHISTLE CREEK, VA.,<lb/>
NOT FAR FROM LEXINGTON, COOKE TOLD THE ASSOCIATED PRESS:</p>
<p>&ldquo;WE FIGURED TO BE DEAD OR WELL WITHIN SIX OR EIGHT DAYS<lb/>
AFTER WE STARTED THE TESTS. NO, I WASN'T PARTICULARLY SCARED....&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="10" id="f04332010"/>
<p>9---</p>
<p>MORAN, COOKE AND JAMES L. HANBERRY OF ORANGEBURG, S.C.<lb/>
ARE THE ONLY THREE KNOWN SURVIVORS AMONG THE ORIGINAL <add><unclear>american</unclear></add>VOLUNTEERS.</p>
<p><del><unclear></unclear></del></p>
<p>HANBERRY PARTICIPATED IN THE &ldquo;INFECTED BEDDING&rdquo;<lb/>
TEST, <add>AND THEN</add> LATER VOLUNTEERED TO BE BITTEN BY MOSQUITOES. HE CONTRACTED A<lb/>
SEVERE CASE OF YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>OF THE <del>15</del> 25 <add>or more</add> VOLUNTEERS, 14 GOT FEVER EITHER FROM MOSQUITO<lb/>
BITES OF <del><unclear></unclear></del> FROM INFECTED BLOOD OR SERUM INJECTED INTO THEIR<lb/>
BODIES. NONE OF THEM DIED FROM THE INFECTIONS.</p>
<p>THE NAMES OF <del><unclear>THE</unclear></del> ALL THE <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>AMERICAN VOLUNTEERS</add><lb/>
TOGETHER WITH THOSE OF REED AND HIS ASSOCIATES AND THE SOLDIER WHO<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
CONTRACTED FEVER IN THE EARLIER TESTS <del><unclear></unclear></del> CONSTITUTE A SPECIAL<lb/>
&ldquo;ROLL OF HONOR&rdquo; PUBLISHED BY LAW IN THE OFFICIAL ARMY REGISTER.</p>
<p>IT IS AN HONOR UNSHARED BY AMERICA'S HEROES ON THE<lb/>
FIELD OF BATTLE.</p>
<p>DR. PHILIP HENCH OF THE MAYO CLINIC WHO HAS MADE AN<lb/>
AVOCATION OF THE WALTER REED EPIC, AND WHO HAS CONTRIBUTED MUCH TO<lb/>
THE CLARIFICATION OF THE HISTORIC EVENTS, SAID NOT LONG AGO AT A<lb/>
MEMORIAL MEETING IN HONOR OF <del><unclear></unclear></del> REED AND THE OTHERS:</p>
<p>&ldquo;IN THESE DAYS, WHEN MAN'S INHUMANITY TO MAN IS STILL<lb/>
SO PATHETICALLY APPARENT, IT IS WELL FOR US TO NOTE THE EXAMPLE OF<lb/>
THESE MEN WHO BANDED TOGETHER FOR HIGH ADVENTURE, NOT TO KILL OR<lb/>
EVEN DIE FOR ONE COUNTRY BUT TO DIE IF NEED BE FOR THEIR FELLOW<lb/>
MEN OF ALL COUNTRIES XXX.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(END ADVANCE FOR AMS OF SUNDAY, JUNE 25)</p>
<closer>
<signed>FEC</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
