<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04330002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, April 20, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Siler, J.F.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04330002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-04-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Wallach, Sidney</name>
<name type="place">Fort Leslie McNair, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-04-20">April 20, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04330002</idno>
<title>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, April 20, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Siler describes his preparations to have the plaque memorializing Reed's death unveiled. He has not heard from Wallach and does not know the present status of the bill and the allocation of the funding. He offers his opinion on how any government funding should be spent.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-04-20">
<head>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, April 20, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04330002"/>
<opener>
GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
----<lb/>
GORGAS MEMORIAL LABORATORY<lb/>
JOSEPH F. SILER<lb/>
PRESIDENT<lb/>
MAURICE H. THATCHER<lb/>
VICE PRESIDENT AND GENERAL COUNSEL<lb/>
WALTER A. BLOEDORN<lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
<dateline>
EXECUTIVE OFFICES<lb/>
1835 EYE STREET, NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6. D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1950-04-20">April 20, 1950.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minn<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Many thanks for your note of April 17.</p>
<p>Referring first to your inquiry concerning the Walter Reed plaque to be<lb/>
placed in front of the building at Fort Leslie McNair, I am very happy to be<lb/>
able to tell you that the manufacturer of the plaque called me up earlier this<lb/>
week and said that it had been completed. I went down immediately to inspect<lb/>
it and think it will be very satisfactory. The next day I went to Fort McNair<lb/>
and talked with the Commanding Officer concerning the placing of the plaque in<lb/>
the selected location. He called in the Post Engineer and we went to inspect<lb/>
the site and decided on just about what should be done. We felt it would be<lb/>
better to place it on an incline in front of the building in such position as<lb/>
could easily be seen by people passing by on the sidewalk as well as from<lb/>
automobiles passing along the street. We felt, too, that the base should be<lb/>
of concrete and that metal uprights should be installed behind the plaque itself<lb/>
and be of such length as to permit their being inserted well underneath the<lb/>
surface of the cement base. I then got in touch with Mr. Cavanagh of the Seal<lb/>
Company who are making the plaque and, knowing that you expected to be here next<lb/>
week, I requested that he make every effort to complete the installation of the<lb/>
plaque this week. He said at first that he might not be able to finish the work<lb/>
before the first of the month but after I talked with him he agreed to make every<lb/>
effort to have it finished at an earlier date and said he would let <unclear>me</unclear> know as<lb/>
soon as he learned anything definite from the manufacturing side of their company.</p>
<p>Referring to your comments concerning Mr. Wallach, I have not seen or heard<lb/>
from him for some time. As I have written you previously, I think that his com-<lb/>
pany is interested solely in getting out publicity and it was my understanding<lb/>
that it was their intention to spend the entire $350,000 for publicity purposes,<lb/>
$150,00 the first year, $100,00 the <unclear>second</unclear> and $100,00 the third. As I also<lb/>
have written you previously, it would seem to me that Walter Reed's memory could<lb/>
be honored in much more satisfactory and profitable manner by devoting any sum<lb/>
of this amount to research rather than publicity. The expenditure of $350,00<lb/>
at the present time for publicity alone seems to me very unwise, particularly<lb/>
so in view of the deficits our government is incurring every year.</p>
<p>When I talked with Mr. Wallach during his visit here I told him that you<lb/>
could give him better advice than anyone in this country concerning this matter.<lb/>
He has not gotten in touch with me since his first visit and I am sorry to say<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04330003"/>
that I do not know the present status of the bill introduced by Senator Jenner<lb/>
and Representative Bland. I will endeavor to find out something about it before<lb/>
you arrive in Washington.</p>
<p>We so far have not given any consideration to having any formal exercises<lb/>
at the time of the installing of the plaque but as it appears that it will be<lb/>
impossible to have it installed prior to your visit, we can take the matter up<lb/>
after your arrival here.</p>
<p>I am looking forward with much pleasure to hearing your talk the latter<lb/>
part of the month.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>J. F. Siler</signed>
jfs k<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
