<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04345006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, September 12, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Siler, J.F.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04345006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-09-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Rockefeller, Jr., John D.</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Army Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">St. Elizabeth's Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-09-12">September 12, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04345006</idno>
<title>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, September 12, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Siler describes Kean's medical condition up to his death and notes that there was a beautiful service followed by burial at Monticello. He discusses Blossom Reed's health and financial situation.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-09-12">
<head>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, September 12, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04345006"/>
<opener>
GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
-----<lb/>
GORGAS MEMORIAL LABORATORY<lb/>
<dateline>
EXECUTIVE OFFICES<lb/>
1835 EYE STREET, NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1950-09-12">September 12, 1950</date>
</dateline>
JOSEPH F. SILER<lb/>
PRESIDENT<lb/>
MAURICE H. THATCHER<lb/>
VICE PRESIDENT AND GENERAL COUNSEL<lb/>
WALTER A. BLOEDORN<lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minn<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Many thanks for your letter of September 5th relative to General Kean and<lb/>
also your letter of September 6th referring to Blossom Reed.</p>
<p>As you know, Gen. Kean had complete retention due to an enlargement of the<lb/>
prostate. When he went into hospital it was necessary to keep the bladder emptied<lb/>
by the use of a catheter. I don't know the exact operation that was contemplated<lb/>
but Col. Kimborough did tell me it would not be possible to remove the prostate<lb/>
because of the General's age and the condition of his heart. They had planned<lb/>
some other operation but his condition was such that it could not be completed.<lb/>
However it is my understanding that they did drain his bladder through suprapubic<lb/>
operation. Unfortunately he had a stroke and for the last few days was confined<lb/>
under an oxygen tent. I will look into the matter more completely and after I<lb/>
have seen Col. Kimborough I will write you more definitely concerning the exact<lb/>
operative procedure.</p>
<p>I visited Gen. Kean every day or so during his stay in hospital until after<lb/>
the operation when he was under the oxygen tent and I could only converse with<lb/>
his nurse concerning him. They had a very beautiful service in the Army Medical<lb/>
Center Chapel at 11:30 last Thursday and immediately thereafter his body was<lb/>
taken to Monticello for interment. Mrs. Kean went down with the body and returned<lb/>
the same night.</p>
<p>Referring to your letter concerning Blossom Reed I am say that I am closely<lb/>
in touch with her through her brother, General Lawrence Reed. Prior to her<lb/>
mother's death, Col. Russell had written me concerning Mrs. Reed's condition as<lb/>
it was his desire to get in touch with the representative of Rockefeller Found-<lb/>
ation concerning the monthly contribution of $100 given to Mrs. Reed, presumably<lb/>
by Mr. Rockefeller although his name has never been mentioned. In replying to<lb/>
Col. Russell I told him Mrs. Reed was still alive and suggested that the same<lb/>
kind donation be made for another year. I also told him that Blossom Reed had<lb/>
been to very great expense and had used up all her reserves. I wondered if it<lb/>
might not be possible for him to advise the representative of Rockefeller Found-<lb/>
ation of Mrs. Reed's condition and to ask that is Mrs. Reed died it would be<lb/>
possible to continue the monthly gift for a few months until Blossom could make<lb/>
her plans for the future. She is more than 65 years of age and it is not pos-<lb/>
sible for her to work.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04345007"/>
<p>GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
-----<lb/>
GORGAS MEMORIAL LABORATORY</p>
<p>JOSEPH F. SILER<lb/>
PRESIDENT</p>
<p>MAURICE H. THATCHER<lb/>
VICE PRESIDENT AND GENERAL COUNSEL</p>
<p>WALTER A. BLOEDORN<lb/>
SECRETARY</p>
<p>EXECUTIVE OFFICES<lb/>
1835 EYE STREET, NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6, D. C.</p>
<p>Col. Russell's reply to my letter stated that he had forwarded it to the<lb/>
representative of Rockefeller Foundation and that he had suggested that special<lb/>
consideration be given to Blossom in case of Mrs. Reed's death.</p>
<p>I mentioned the matter to Gen. Lawrence Reed some time ago and he told me<lb/>
that Blossom had not heard from the Chase National Bank subsequent to her mother's<lb/>
death concerning continuation of the donation.</p>
<p>Concerning the monthly payment made by the Walter Reed Memorial Association<lb/>
I should like to say that this payment amounts to approximately $84 and the mem-<lb/>
bers of the Board of Directors of the organization have already made arrangements<lb/>
for continuing this same payment to Blossom Reed. As a matter of fact I arranged<lb/>
with the bank to give her the extra $50 payment for the month in which her mother<lb/>
died.</p>
<p>Now for the latest information concerning Blossom. As you know she has had<lb/>
a number of emotional upsets and on two occasions it was necessary for her to be<lb/>
placed in hospital for a considerable period of time. A few days ago General Reed<lb/>
called me up and stated that his sister was in the midst of another of these attacks.<lb/>
She was brought down to Walter Reed for care and treatment. I came down the fol-<lb/>
lowing morning and had a conference with the Chief of Psychiatric Service concerning<lb/>
her. She is getting along all right and we are in hopes that it will not be nec-<lb/>
essary to transfer her to St. Elizabeth's as it was during her last attack. I<lb/>
thank that her present condition accounts for her writing you such a letter as she<lb/>
did. The &ldquo;nest egg&rdquo; that she spoke of presumably is the $84 a month that she gets<lb/>
from the Walter Reed Memorial Association.</p>
<p>I will have a conference with her brother in the near future concerning some<lb/>
of the other matters referred to in your letter and will advise you more fully<lb/>
a little later.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>J. F. Siler<lb/>
Col., (MC), U.S.A., Retired</signed>
jfs k<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
