<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04347001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Albert G. Love to the Board of Governors, Walter Reed Memorial Association, December 14, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04347001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-12-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Bliss, Raymond W.</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Carey, Frank</name>
<name type="person">Wallach, Sidney</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">Fort McNair, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Arlington National Cemetery, Arlington (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-12-14">December 14 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04347001</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Albert G. Love to the Board of Governors, Walter Reed Memorial Association, December 14, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This memorandum records the minutes from the annual meeting of the Walter Reed Memorial Association. Included is a discussion of Blossom Reed's situation and the ongoing effort to publicize Reed's work.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1950-12-14">
<head>Memorandum from Albert G. Love to the Board of Governors, Walter Reed Memorial Association, December 14, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04347001"/>
<p>MINUTES<lb/>
ANNUAL MEETING, BOARD OF MANAGERS, WALTER REED MEMORIAL ASSOCIATION<lb/>
Washington, D. C., December 14, 1950</p>
<p>The Board met at 10 A.M., in the Board Room, American Security and Trust<lb/>
Company, 15th Street and Pennsylvania Avenue, Northwest, Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>The Board had suffered an irreparable loss as a result of the death of its<lb/>
President, Brig. Gen. Jefferson R. Kean, on September 4, 1950. The Vice President,<lb/>
Maj. Gen. M. W. Ireland was unable to be present on account of illness in hospital.<lb/>
The Secretary of the Board was requested to preside, temporarily, pending the<lb/>
election of officers. Col. J. F. Siler, the Secretary, called the meeting to order.</p>
<p>The following members were present: Maj. Gen. R. W. Bliss, Dr. Gilbert<lb/>
Grosvenor, Mr. Hans W. Ireland, Brig. Gen. F. R. Keefer, Brig. Gen. Albert G. Love,<lb/>
Col. J. F. Siler, and Dr. Fred W. Soper. Absent: Dr. Philip S. Hench, Maj. Gen.<lb/>
M. W. Ireland and Maj. Gen. C. R. Reynolds.</p>
<p>It was unanimously voted that an expression of the grief and deep sense of<lb/>
loss suffered by the Association and its Board of Managers in the loss of its<lb/>
President, Brig. Gen. Jefferson R. Kean, who died September 4, 1950, be spread upon<lb/>
the minutes of the meeting and that a letter of sympathy be sent to the widow.</p>
<p>The minutes of the last annual meeting had been mailed to all members. In<lb/>
view of the fact that no suggestions had been received relative to corrections or<lb/>
amendments, it was moved and seconded that reading of the minutes be dispensed with<lb/>
and that they be approved as recorded. The motion was carried unanimously.</p>
<p>The Treasurer submitted the following report which was approved</p>
<p><hi>WALTER REED MEMORIAL FUND, AGENCY</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="3" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand 10/31/48</cell><cell>$675.21</cell><cell>Balance on hand 10/31/49</cell><cell>$364.74</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Income 10/31/48 to 10/31/49</cell><cell><hi>1,337.08</hi></cell><cell>Income 10/31/49 to 10/31/50</cell><cell><hi>1,404.69</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total</cell><cell>$2,012.29</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>$1,769.43</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>
<table rows="8" cols="4">
<row>
<cell><hi>Disbursements 1949</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>Disbursements 1950</hi></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily Reed</cell><cell>$1,608.00</cell><cell>Payments to Mrs. Emily Reed</cell><cell>$1,072.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Commissions to American<lb/>
Security &amp; Trust Company</cell><cell><hi>39.55</hi></cell><cell>Payments to Mrs. Blossom Reed</cell><cell>386.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>$1,647.55</cell><cell>Commissions to American<lb/>
Security &amp; Trust Company</cell><cell>42.70</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>To Gudes-<lb/>
Flowers from Association at<lb/>
funeral of Mrs. Emily L.<lb/>
Reed</cell><cell>15.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Flowers Gen. Kean per<lb/>
authorization of Col. Siler</cell><cell><hi>12.24</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>$1,527.94</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Balance on hand 10/31/49</cell><cell>364.74</cell><cell>Balance on hand 10/31/50</cell><cell>241.49</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>
<table rows="10" cols="6">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell><hi>CAPITAL INVESTMENT A/C</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>CAPITAL INVESTMENT A/C</hi></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>October 31, 1949</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>October 31, 1950</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell><hi>Par Value</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell><cell><hi>Par Value</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell><hi>Market Value</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>$15,400.00</cell><cell>Bonds</cell><cell>$17,881.00</cell><cell>$15,400.00</cell><cell>Bonds</cell><cell>$17,650.80</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>$11,350.00</cell><cell>*Stocks</cell><cell>14,330.00</cell><cell>11,350.00</cell><cell>*Stocks</cell><cell>15,705.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2,500.00</cell><cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>2,500.00</cell><cell>2,500.00</cell><cell>Mortgages</cell><cell>2,500.00</cell></row>
<row>
<cell><hi>180.47</hi></cell><cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell><hi>180.47</hi></cell><cell><hi>185.70</hi></cell><cell>Capital Cash</cell><cell><hi>185.70.</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>$29,430.47</cell><cell></cell><cell>$34,891.47</cell><cell>$29,435.70</cell><cell></cell><cell>$36,041.50</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>*Pfd no Par c/a $100.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>*Pfd no Par c/a $100.00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>Com no Par c/a 25.00</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Com no Par c/a 25.00</cell><cell></cell></row>
</table></p>
<pb n="2" id="f04347002"/>
<p>The next order of business was the election of officers and new members.<lb/>
The nominating committee presented the following report:</p>
<p>Washington, D. C.<lb/>
December 14, 1950</p>
<p>TO: The Board of Managers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association</p>
<p>SUBJECT: Report of an Advisory Nominating Committee</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. As the result of the death of our beloved and honored President,<lb/>
Brig. Gen. J. R. Kean, it is necessary that we elect a new President.</item>
<item>2. In addition, it seems desirable in view of the continued incapacity<lb/>
of our beloved and honored Vice President, Maj. Gen. M. W. Ireland,<lb/>
to elect a new Vice President.</item>
<item>3. Dr. L. O. Howard, one of our esteemed members has passed on. As a<lb/>
result of his death and of that of Gen. Kean, there are two member<lb/>
vacancies. Consequently the Secretary and Acting President of the<lb/>
Association, Col. J. F. Siler, on December 12, 1950, requested Mr.<lb/>
Hans W. Ireland, Treasurer and Brig. Gen. Albert G. Love to act as<lb/>
an Advisory Nominating Committee.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The Committee submits the following suggestions:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. President, Col. J. F. Siler</item>
<item>2. Vice President, Dr. Philip S. Hench</item>
<item>3. Since it obviously would be unfair to ask Col. Siler to assume the<lb/>
duties as President and also to continue those as Secretary, the<lb/>
Committee suggests that his resignation as Secretary be accepted<lb/>
after his election as President, and that then Brig. Gen. Albert<lb/>
G. Love be elected as Secretary.</item>
<item>4. Hans W. Ireland, Treasurer</item>
<item>5. To fill the member vacancies caused by the deaths of Brig. Gen. J. R.<lb/>
Kean and Dr. L. O. Howard, the following names are submitted:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Vice Admiral Ross T. McIntyre, USN Rtd.</item>
<item>Maj. Gen. Paul H. Streit, MC USA</item>
</list>
Both of these distinguished officers have expressed their willingness<lb/>
to serve.</item>
</list></p>
<p>____________________________________</p>
<p>Hans W. Ireland, Advisory Nominating<lb/>
Committee</p>
<p>____________________________________</p>
<p>Albert G. Love, Advisory Nominating<lb/>
Committee</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04347003"/>
<p>The chairman asked if any member desired to make any other nominations. None<lb/>
were made. He then requested General Bliss to take the chair for action on the<lb/>
report of the nominating committee. It was then moved and seconded that the report<lb/>
of the nominating committee be accepted and approved. The motion was carried<lb/>
unanimously.</p>
<p>Colonel Siler stated that he felt that he was very highly honored in being<lb/>
made President of the Association and that he would make every effort to carry out<lb/>
the wishes of the Association.</p>
<p>The President stated that, as a rule, annual meetings were held on or about<lb/>
the day of the month on which Walter Reed died, namely, November 23. The annual<lb/>
meeting for this year was held in abeyance, temporarily, in the hope that it might<lb/>
be possible for Dr. Hench to stop over for the meeting on his return from one of<lb/>
the two visits to Europe that he had to make this fall, the latter of which was to<lb/>
receive one of the Nobel Prize Awards. A letter received from him recently advised<lb/>
that, to his regret, it would not be practicable for him to visit Washington until<lb/>
next spring.</p>
<p>The Chairman stated that all members of the Board were aware of the death of<lb/>
Mrs. Walter Reed on July 23, 1950, at the age of 95. Graveside services were held<lb/>
at Arlington National Cemetery and flowers were sent on behalf of the Board. He<lb/>
also stated that the monthly allowance of income from assets of the Association,<lb/>
formerly sent Mrs. Walter Reed, was now being sent each month to Mrs. Blossom Reed,<lb/>
in compliance with the provisions of the certificate of incorporation and the<lb/>
resolution adopted at the annual meeting in 1949.</p>
<p>The Chairman stated that he desired to review briefly the progress made in the<lb/>
solution of some of the matters discussed at the last annual meeting.</p>
<p>At last year's annual meeting it was decided definitely that a bronze plaque, to<lb/>
be purchased by the Association, would be placed in front of the building in which<lb/>
Walter Reed died in 1902. The inscription to be carved on the plaque, suggested at<lb/>
the meeting, was not deemed entirely satisfactory and it was decided that the exact<lb/>
wording required further consideration. Subsequent to further consultations with<lb/>
members of the Board, it was agreed that the following wording would be used:<lb/>
WALTER REED<lb/>
WHO GAVE MAN CONTROL OVER YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
DIED IN A HOSPITAL<lb/>
ON THIS SITE<lb/>
November 23, 1902<lb/>
The authorities at Ft. Lesley McNair cooperated wholeheartedly in preparing a base<lb/>
for and installing the plaque. Immediately after its installation the plaque was<lb/>
inspected by Maj. Gen. W. L. Reed, Brig. Gen. Albert G. Love and Col. Siler and was<lb/>
considered entirely satisfactory. In the immediate future, it is the intention to<lb/>
secure a photograph of the plaque and its immediate surroundings and send a print<lb/>
to each member of the Board.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04347004"/>
<p>Another matter brought up by Dr. Hench last year was that of arranging for the<lb/>
publication of information relating to Walter Reed and his work on yellow fever during<lb/>
this - the fiftieth anniversary of his work in Cuba. It is a most interesting fact<lb/>
that this year marks the 50th anniversary of Walter Reed's work in Cuba, that 1951<lb/>
will be the 100th anniversary of his birth and that 1952 will be the 50th anniversary<lb/>
of his death.</p>
<p>More than a year ago a resolution was introduced in the Congress by Congress-<lb/>
man Bland of Virginia and Senator Jenner, providing for the expenditure of $350,000.<lb/>
in a three year period to better acquaint the American people with the researches<lb/>
made by Walter Reed relative to the method of transmission of yellow fever and its<lb/>
control. No action was taken by the Congress. Last summer Mr. Frank Carey, a<lb/>
Washington correspondent of the Associated Press, advised me that he was preparing<lb/>
an article on Walter Reed. We loaned him a number of published articles relating<lb/>
to Walter Reed's work and he secured other data during an interview with General Kean.<lb/>
His article appeared locally in the Washington Post on June 25, 1950, and was sent<lb/>
out over Associated Press wire to some 1500 newspapers.</p>
<p>On August 29th the Secretary received a letter from Mr. Sidney Wallach, the head<lb/>
of a publicity firm in New York City (The Wallach Associates) advising him that Mr.<lb/>
Wallach contemplated raising a fund of $50,000. or more to be used for the preparation<lb/>
of articles on Walter Reed to be published in journals and newspapers and he desired<lb/>
to secure the cooperation and support of the Walter Reed Memorial Association. He<lb/>
came to Washington on October 4th, 1950 and outlined his plans to the following<lb/>
members of the Board: Gen. Keefer, Gen. Love, Mr. Ireland and Col. Siler. No<lb/>
definite action was taken and he was requested to submit his plans in writing for<lb/>
action by the Board at this annual meeting. No further information has been<lb/>
received from him.</p>
<p>The fourth matter referred to by Dr. Hench, the preservation of one of the<lb/>
buildings used by Walter Reed in his yellow fever transmission work in Cuba as a<lb/>
permanent memorial, is still held in abeyance pending a visit to Washington by<lb/>
Dr. Hench when he can consult with Gen. Bliss and other military and State Department<lb/>
officials.</p>
<p>There being no further business, the meeting was adjourned to meet at the call<lb/>
of the President.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Albert G. Love,<lb/>
Brig. Gen., U.S.A. Retired<lb/>
Secretary</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
