<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04349001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, March 20, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04349001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-03-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rojas, Maria Teresa</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Cabrera, Julia Lomas</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Bliss, Raymond W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Quemados, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-03-20">March 20, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04349001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, March 20, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses Lydia's arthritis. He discusses the stalled effort to preserve Building No. 1 at Camp Lazear and asks if Rojas knows of any way to break the impasse. He assures her that plans for the memorial will in no way intrude on the nearby Rojas family home.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-03-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, March 20, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04349001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1950-03-20">March 20, 1950</date>
</dateline>
Senorita Maria Titina Rojas<lb/>
Quinta San Jose<lb/>
Redencion<lb/>
Marianao, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senorita Rojas:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I must apologize most sincerely to you for the long delay in<lb/>
answering your letter to Mary dated December 20. I have been in the midst<lb/>
of a degree of activity which has kept me so busy that I am far behind<lb/>
with my correspondence. Please forgive me.</p>
<p>I am so sorry to hear that Miss Cabrera's sister has arthritis<lb/>
and I wish that there was something that I could do to help.</p>
<p>The supplies of the two hormones, cortisone and ACTH, are so<lb/>
extremely meager that they are being used only for investigative and<lb/>
research purposes. Since most patients have to take them more or less<lb/>
continuously to keep their arthritis under control, it simply cannot be<lb/>
given as treatment and we have never used the word treatment in our reports.<lb/>
We still consider our work of an investigative nature and we still have a<lb/>
lot to learn about the best means of giving it, about how to prevent un-<lb/>
desirable reactions which may occur, and so on. We are very optimistic<lb/>
about these and are certain that the problems will be solved in due time<lb/>
but it may be a year or two before these hormones are available as treatment.</p>
<p>In the meantime, I do hope that her sister is not just sitting<lb/>
waiting for these hormones but is carrying on a program under the direction<lb/>
of her attending physician using the orthodox procedures which will give<lb/>
comfort and often help prevent deformities. Should her physician wish to<lb/>
write to me at any time, I shall be glad to correspond with him.</p>
<p>May I thank you both for your many and very real kindnesses to<lb/>
Mary when she was stranded in Paris. Your friendship meant much to her.<lb/>
She was very lonesome and bored and she was thoroughly delighted with your<lb/>
companionship. She often speaks of it with great pleasure.</p>
<p>We had hoped to run down to Cuba this spring but I have been so<lb/>
excessively busy on many things that this has not been possible, but perhaps<lb/>
next spring we can do so. As you know, we are very fond of Cuba and of<lb/>
Havana.</p>
<p>I was greatly disappointed at the outcome of my last trip. As you<lb/>
know, I worked very hard, interviewed innumerable officials, including the<lb/>
Vice President; actually made and presented drawings of the plan for memorializing<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04349002"/>
Senorita Maria Titina Rojas<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
March 21, 1950<lb/>
Camp Lazear and that part of the Finca San Jose where the caseta is and<lb/>
was delighted to see in the newspaper that the Cuban government allotted<lb/>
$50,000 for the care of the little building. I had tried to get permission<lb/>
from various officials to build a protecting cover, perhaps galvanized iron,<lb/>
around the caseta so that it would not be destroyed in the next windstorm.<lb/>
We could hardly expect that it would survice much more, but I ran into the<lb/>
fact that it was now a government &ldquo;memorial&rdquo; and therefore no private in-<lb/>
dividual could do anything. I begged the Vice President to let me contribute<lb/>
one or two thousand dollars myself and called his attention to the fact<lb/>
that though it had been declared a memorial, it was still not protected and<lb/>
nothing was being done but he very graciously and politely insisted that<lb/>
they could not accept my money, that they would do that and would do so<lb/>
right away. I am sure that he was behind the $50,000 bill that was passed.<lb/>
Then I was most discouraged when I heard that with the incoming regime, all<lb/>
unfinished business passed by the previous legislature was shelved. I have<lb/>
discussed this with the Surgeon General of the United States Army and with<lb/>
one or two other prominent <unclear>personages</unclear> in Washington but in view of the fact<lb/>
that the caseta is now under the protection of the Cuban government, my<lb/>
advisors in Washington hesitate greatly to interfere with what is Cuban<lb/>
governmental business.</p>
<p>Do you know of any way that we can break this impasse?</p>
<p>Regardless of the unfortunate discussion as to the relative merits<lb/>
of Finlay and the American Commission, the fact remains that the Finca San<lb/>
Jose is a monument to both men as Finlay studied a couple of cases among monks<lb/>
who were living in your quinta years before Reed and his colleagues erected<lb/>
Camp Lazear on the rear of the Finca. Therefore, above all that spot is a place<lb/>
memorable to all concerned.</p>
<p>You may rest assured, dear friends, that in my various discussions<lb/>
I have made it clear that your home, the quinta, has no part in our plans. By<lb/>
that I mean that nobody wishes to trouble you and I am sure that the Cuban<lb/>
government understands that clearly, but it is a shame to see the little building<lb/>
fall to ruin. My plans envisaged the erection of a small public health unit<lb/>
on the spot with the little caseta in one large room and a little part for the<lb/>
neighborhood to replace the cornfield in the front. These plans appeared to<lb/>
have the hearty approval of the Vice President.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH: alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: Incidentally, this is the 50th anniversary of these events by the<lb/>
American Commission.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
