<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04341010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, August 29, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Siler, J.F.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04341010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-08-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">Fort McNair, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Army Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-08-29">August 29, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04341010</idno>
<title>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, August 29, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Siler believes that the project to publicize Reed's work, proposed by Sidney Wallach, would be a waste of money and only benefit Wallach's company. Siler informs Hench that Kean has been ill.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-08-29">
<head>Letter from J.F. Siler to Philip Showalter Hench, August 29, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04341010"/>
<opener>
GORGAS MEMORIAL INSTITUTE<lb/>
OF<lb/>
TROPICAL AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
----<lb/>
GORGAS MEMORIAL LABORATORY<lb/>
<dateline>
EXECUTIVE OFFICES<lb/>
1835 EYE STREET, NORTHWEST<lb/>
WASHINGTON 6, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1950-08-29">August 29, 1950.</date>
</dateline>
JOSEPH F. SILER<lb/>
PRESIDENT<lb/>
MAURICE H. THATCHER<lb/>
VICE PRESIDENT AND GENERAL COUNSEL<lb/>
WALTER A. BLOEDORN<lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minn<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thanks very much for your note of August 19.</p>
<p>I have delayed having the photograph made showing the memorial tablet at<lb/>
Ft. McNair until the grass lawn adjacent to it had time to grow. I expect to go<lb/>
down again within the next few days and if conditions ppear to be suitable, will<lb/>
have the photo made after which it is my intention to send one copy to each mem-<lb/>
ber of the Board and retian one copy for the files of the Association.</p>
<p>Referring to your note concerning a letter from Mr. Wallach, I am just in<lb/>
receipt of a letter from him under date of August 28 in which he advises me that<lb/>
the joint Congressional resolution introduced several months ago is now a dead<lb/>
issue because of the death of Representative Bland of Virginia. Mr. Wallach still<lb/>
feels that a national or perhaps world-wide program concerning the work of Walter<lb/>
Reed would be very highly desirable and he feels that it would be possible to work<lb/>
out such a program and secure the financial aid to cover it, this to be carried<lb/>
out under the auspices of the Walter Reed Memorial Association. He further asks<lb/>
if it would be possible for him to meet formally the authorized officers of the<lb/>
Association to consider arrangements for such a program.</p>
<p>As a matter of fact, I have always felt myself that this Mr. Wallach was<lb/>
interested in this matter primarily because it would be possible for his company<lb/>
to carry out and therefore profit financially from such a project. It has always<lb/>
seemed to me that the idea of spending $350,000 during the next three years as<lb/>
was contemplated by the resolution mentioned above would be a useless waste of<lb/>
money and that if this money could be devoted to research work rather than publi-<lb/>
city to commemorate Walter Reed's work it would be so much more highly desirable.</p>
<p>I do not know whether you know it or not but General Kean has been in<lb/>
hospital for the past week or ten days suffering from retention because of an<lb/>
enlarged prostate. I have seen him on two or three occasions add he is in fine<lb/>
shape but drainage of the bladder has to be accomplished by constant use of a<lb/>
catheter. Col. Kimborough is away for a few days but he told me before he left<lb/>
that the only permanent relief would be removal of the prostate. I know that<lb/>
before undertaking its removal, Col. Kimborough will have General Kean gone over<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04341011"/>
very carefully by the heads of the various divisions at Walter Reed Hospital,<lb/>
noting particularly of course the condition of General Kean's heart.</p>
<p>As you know, he had his ninetieth birthday recently. We had the pleasure<lb/>
of going out to see him on that day and wishing him many happy returns. He was<lb/>
in very fine condition at that time. I will, of course, keep closely in touch<lb/>
with his condition and will advise you concerning the steps that Col. Kimborough<lb/>
proposes to take.</p>
<p>With most cordial regards, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Faithfully yours,</salute>
<signed>J. F. Siler<lb/>
Col., (MC), U.S.A., Ret'd</signed>
jfa k<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
