<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04359006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. Earle [Mary] Standlee, April 16, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>

<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>

<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>

</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04359006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-04-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Standlee, Mrs. Earle [Mary]</term></keywords> </textClass>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John C.</name>
<name type="person">DeKruif, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Borden, William C.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Army Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-04-16">April 16, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04359006</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. Earle [Mary] Standlee, April 16, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench makes detailed criticisms of Standlee's manuscript on Walter Reed. His remarks are prefaced by a thorough account of his own Reed research.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-04-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. Earle [Mary] Standlee, April 16, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04359006"/>
<opener>
<hi>for WRMA</hi><lb/>
There are a few errors because I dictated this letter<lb/>
partly from memory. Corrected in my letter<lb/>
of <unclear>Apr 4, 1951</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1951-04-16">April 16, 1951</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. Earle Standlee<lb/>
The Library<lb/>
Army Medical Center<lb/>
Washington 12, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Standlee:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have gone over your manuscript twice, confining myself chiefly<lb/>
to the material between pages 38 and 66. I have enjoyed very much reading it<lb/>
and am sure that your book will be very well received. I certainly hope that<lb/>
you will let me know when it is published as I should certainly like to pur-<lb/>
chase a copy.</p>
<p>Mrs. Standlee, when I am asked to comment on a manuscript I con-<lb/>
sider it my duty to be free and <unclear>frank</unclear>. It is understood of course that you<lb/>
can do whatever you want with my suggestions. First of all, let me briefly<lb/>
give you an outline of my own studies on the yellow fever story which perhaps<lb/>
gives me the authority to criticize some of the statements made in your<lb/>
manuscript.</p>
<p>About 1938 the president of the college where Lazear <unclear>went</unclear> asked me<lb/>
to assist in the arrangement of a ceremony for the dedication of a Lazear<lb/>
memorial building. One thing <unclear>led</unclear> to another and the next year I was asked to<lb/>
give the principal address when the building was dedicated. Meanwhile I had<lb/>
made a visit to Cuba to interview Johnny Moran, one of Reed's first human<lb/>
guinea pigs and had also interviewed John Kissinger, visiting his home and<lb/>
later having him visit me here. To make a <unclear>long</unclear> story short, during the next<lb/>
several years, I visited every living survivor of the experiments, interviewed<lb/>
them all at length with stenographic records, obtained an enormous mass of<lb/>
personal and unpublished material from them and from the relatives of the chief<lb/>
participants and have spent literally weeks going through the Archives Building,<lb/>
the Surgeon General's Office and other Washington offices.</p>
<p>I started out being, in a mild sort of way, a &ldquo;Lazear man &rdquo; with no<lb/>
intention whatever of taking sides. Indeed I didn't know at that time that<lb/>
there was any controversy about the relative merits of each man. I was simply<lb/>
a &ldquo;Lazear man&rdquo; because my first speech was in connection with the Lazear<lb/>
Memorial. Almost immediately I ran into the violent controversy that has raged<lb/>
since 1900 as to the merits of Finlay versus Reed, Reed versus Carroll, Agramonte<lb/>
and Lazear versus the others and, in a lesser way, Kissinger versus Moran. I<lb/>
have no axe to grind. I have run into protagonists of each of these men and as<lb/>
a result of over ten years' rather intensive study (as a very pleasant and most<lb/>
instructive experience) I think that I have developed a rather clear picture of<lb/>
what was done. I have practically never allowed myself to have a conclusion<lb/>
<unclear>foisted</unclear> on me by the protagonists of any individual. I have <unclear>listened</unclear> patiently<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04359007"/>
Mrs. Earle Standlee<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
April 16, 1951<lb/>
but critically to all discussions but have in every case changed my opinion<lb/>
where it was necessary only when the indisputable records which I have found<lb/>
have supported the spoken word. These records are, for the most part, unpub-<lb/>
lished and are made up of official Army records in various files in the Archives<lb/>
Building in Washington and other official government records, and scores, indeed<lb/>
hundreds, of personal letters written by Reed, Lazear, Carroll, Agramonte, Kis-<lb/>
singer, Moran, Generals Kean and Truby and others. Practically none of these<lb/>
letters have been published. Most of them are in my actual possession, having<lb/>
been presented to me by the survivors to constitute a record which will be pre-<lb/>
served for all time.</p>
<p>As a result, it is obvious that Reed's was the guiding hand and the<lb/>
chief planner. It is also obvious that he had wonderful help from his associates<lb/>
within the limits of their opportunities, assignments and abilities. The greatest<lb/>
help came from Lazear who, in the early stage, was more interested in the mosquito<lb/>
theory than was Reed and much more interested than Carroll who was something of<lb/>
a <unclear>scoffer</unclear>. However when the evidence of Lazear was at hand, Reed was able to<lb/>
bring order out of Lazear's sketchy notes and plan the final experiments which<lb/>
gave <unclear>irrefutable</unclear> proof. During these later experiments Carroll was Reed's main<lb/>
assistant. Agramonte was always helpful but his opportunities and assignments<lb/>
were of lesser importance. The death of Lazear and Reed allowed the few remaining<lb/>
members of the board a certain freedom of thought or rather, one might add,<lb/>
freedom of imagination and elaboration. It is understandable that like old<lb/>
soldiers, and some of us who are not soldiers, they began to <unclear>reminisce</unclear> and<lb/>
write and talk as if they had done perhaps a little more than they actually<lb/>
had and had perhaps &ldquo;won the war single-handedly.&rdquo; I shall not deign to judge<lb/>
the motives behind some of the letters and remarks that Carroll and Agramonte<lb/>
made in relative &ldquo;safety&rdquo; after the death of Reed and Lazear. I can only tell<lb/>
you that their evaluations of their own work were exaggerated, to put it mildly,<lb/>
and some of their published remarks were absolutely contrary to the facts which<lb/>
can be easily established by the official records. In particular Hemmeter was<lb/>
led to gross errors of statement in behalf of Carroll. One must remember that<lb/>
Carroll was a dying man, a relatively poor man. Hemmeter's two articles were,<lb/>
as you know, published in very obscure journals but did not fail to receive<lb/>
considerable criticism from authoritative sources. I have seen some of the<lb/>
correspondence between <del>the latter</del> and Hemmeter and Hemmeter's defense was ex-<lb/>
tremely weak. If you were able to go over my records you would see that one<lb/>
need not be confused and in due time these records will be published.</p>
<p>Agramonte</p>
<p>in his<lb/>
<unclear>refl &amp;</unclear><lb/>
Agramonte</p>
<p>Now, Mrs. Standlee, forgive me for what I am about to say. It ap-<lb/>
pears to me <unclear>that</unclear> your write-up of Reed is written in a defensive tone but while<lb/>
defensive it <unclear>belittles</unclear> his contributions. I suspect that you have been exposed<lb/>
to, shall I say it, some &ldquo;Army politics&rdquo; and to some protagonists of this or<lb/>
that viewpoint; men who have rather fixed ideas based on conversations and hearsay,<lb/>
uncorrected by critical evaluation of records. Since the &ldquo;crowning jewel&rdquo; or<lb/>
certainly to the public mind the center of the Army Medical Center is the Walter<lb/>
Reed Hospital, and since you are certainly trying to honor the memory of those<lb/>
men who were responsible for its founding as well as to honor the memory of<lb/>
Walter Reed, I think you should adopt a more positive note and I shall try to<lb/>
point out hereafter what I mean. Let me now make some comments which I shall<lb/>
number according to the encircled pencilled numbers beginning on page 38 of<lb/>
your manuscript.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Page 38. Principe is misspelled.</item>
<pb n="3" id="f04359008"/>
<item>Mrs. Earle Standlee</item>
<item>- 3 -</item>
<item>April 16, 1951</item>
<item>2. Page 38 - Would you tell me where you got the authority for<lb/>
your statement &ldquo;On the advice of...Welch...Lazear was added to the board&rdquo;. I<lb/>
believe that is true but I have not found any correspondence in Washington or<lb/>
among Reed's papers confirming this impression. I believe it was Kelly's im-<lb/>
pression. I have only visited the Welch Library once and must go again. Please<lb/>
tell me the reference for this statement. Incidentally, Doctor Lazear's name<lb/>
was not Edward but Jesse W.</item>
<item>3-a. Page 39 - You say that Welch and Sternberg offered cogent ad-<lb/>
vice. That impression is often published but again I have found no letters or<lb/>
records to prove an intimate relationship between Welch and these men during<lb/>
their work. I have all the available Sternberg correspondence and wires to<lb/>
Reed. Sternberg's advice to Reed was indeed very limited and mostly anti<lb/>
the mosquito theory. (See Reed's letter to Maj Kean &amp; wife)</item>
<item>3-b. You say that Lazear preceded Reed and Carroll to Cuba to begin<lb/>
the study. This is not strictly correct. Lazear was already in Cuba, having<lb/>
been assigned there as a contract surgeon in charge of the laboratory at the<lb/>
Station Hospital at Camp Columbia. So far as the record shows, Lazear never<lb/>
met Reed <add>in Cuba</add> until Reed arrived with Carroll to establish the board on June 25,<lb/>
1900. In other words, both Lazear and Agramonte were already occupied in Cuba<lb/>
in two different laboratories. They were logical men to put on the board but<lb/>
Lazear was not in Washington when he was appointed and did not go to Cuba<lb/>
originally on assignment for the Yellow Fever Board.</item>
<item>&amp; didnt<lb/>
(Wrong ?<lb/>
<unclear>Lazear might<lb/>
have met<lb/>
Reed in Cuba<lb/>
in 1899</unclear></item>
<item>not Reed in<lb/>
U. S<lb/>
(Did <unclear>they</unclear><lb/>
meet<lb/>
<unclear>are<lb/>
Balto</unclear>?</item>
<item>4. Page 39 - You say that Reed and Carroll arrived from the United<lb/>
States in late June, 1899. This is incorrect. Reed arrived on June 25, 1900.<lb/>
Reed had been in Cuba at least twice before during 1899 on other assignments.</item>
<item>5. Page 39 - The sentence should read &ldquo;On arrival Dr. Reed <hi>andlb/>
Lazear</hi> confirmed the diagnosis.&rdquo; I have a letter of Lazear describing the<lb/>
visit <del>with Reed</del> to Pinar del Rio. This visit is not mentioned in Agramonte's<lb/>
account written many years later in the <unclear>Scientific American</unclear> 1915<lb/>
which incidentally contains many provable errors despite Agramonte's statement<lb/>
that it is absolutely correct and that all else is incorrect.</item>
<item><unclear>No.</unclear><lb/>
Lazear<lb/>
went a<lb/>
few days<lb/>
later</item>
<item>6. Page 39 - You say that Reed still &ldquo;seemed unwilling, as his<lb/>
later experiments indicate, to relinquish the idea that personal fomites (the<lb/>
latter word is misspelled) should be disinfected...&rdquo; You have completely mis-<lb/>
understood General Kean's reference and Reed's experiments. His experiments<lb/>
with fomites were deliberately arranged to prove that they were harmless despite<lb/>
the common conception.</item>
<item>7. Page 39 - &ldquo;Urged by the younger members of the Board, and es-<lb/>
pecially the enthusiastic Dr. Lazear, in August 1900 the investigators began<lb/>
testing...&rdquo; This is essentially correct but again carried on your tone that<lb/>
Reed was a backward believer and had to be pushed by others throughout the<lb/>
entire experiments, etc. It is true that Lazear's letters indicated that in<lb/>
the early experiments he, Lazear, was more excited about the mosquito theory<lb/>
than was any other member and Agramonte later admits this in two published and<lb/>
one unpublished statement, the latter an unpublished banquet speech which I have.<lb/>
Nevertheless, it should be made clear that once Reed had Lazear's data he was<lb/>
completely convinced. You will realize that their preliminary report was<lb/>
received with considerable skepticism in various places (as can be proven by<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04359009"/>
Mrs. Earle Standlee<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
April 16, 1951<lb/>
published articles and editorials), the second paper written by Reed with<lb/>
the names of all the four members of the Board was the clincher and without<lb/>
the names of all the four members of the Board was the clincher and without<lb/>
the second paper proof would not have been indisputably established.</item>
<item>8. Page 39. - It would be a little more correct to say that Doctor<lb/>
Reed <hi>had</hi> to return to the United States rather than to say <unclear>merely</unclear> that he did<lb/>
return. The reader gets the impression that he didn't think too much of the<lb/>
experiments and went off on another job willingly, being more interested in<lb/>
the latter. It is true that nobody, including Reed, expected them to &ldquo;hit gold&rdquo;<lb/>
so soon but the sudden death of Doctor Vaughan, Chairman of the Army's Typhoid<lb/>
Fever Board, left Reed the senior member of that Board and the Army wanted the<lb/>
report <unclear>finished</unclear> at that time. Reed therefore had to leave Cuba to complete this<lb/>
task but before he left the program of research was well laid out and the in-<lb/>
dividual responsibilities were assigned to the three other members.</item>
<item>9. Page 39 - You say that Doctor Carroll was responsible for the<lb/>
work. Only in a faint military sense is that correct. <hi>I am writing this in<lb/>
my office down town and don't have the dates of Army service at hand</hi>. Never-<lb/>
theless it is my recollection that Carroll's dates of service <unclear>antedated</unclear> that<lb/>
of the contract surgeon Lazear and Agramonte so that in the military sense<lb/>
Carroll was the senior member of the Board in Reed's absence but actually each<lb/>
man was working on his own particular job and as the letters of each written <hi>at<lb/>
that time</hi> (and not their later letters) show Lazear on his own produced the first<lb/>
evidence of the culpability of the mosquito part of the evidence being derived<lb/>
from the experiment on Carroll himself who thought so little of the experiment<lb/>
that he broke all the rules and almost vitiated the experiment by which he almost<lb/>
lost his own life. I would suggest that in the next line you insert "Carroll<lb/>
was inoculated <hi>by Lazear</hi>.</item>
<item>10. Page 39 - You state that Lazear believed himself immune. What<lb/>
is your evidence for that statement? I have Lazear's letter to his wife written<lb/>
during these crucial days. There is no evidence that Lazear believed himself<lb/>
an immune. Actually it was Agramonte who is supposed to have believed himself<lb/>
an immune. This slant to Lazear's notes has never been presented elsewhere so<lb/>
far as I know and is quite unfair to him. As a matter of fact, up to now, even<lb/>
by those who believed that Lazear, perhaps rather <unclear>carelessly</unclear>, permitted a stray<lb/>
mosquito to infect him, <hi>have given Lazear credit for some scientific curiosity<lb/>
in this incident rather than a pure careless accident</hi>. If you had available<lb/>
the data that I have (and of course I realize that you have not had much of<lb/>
this data available, therefore most of these errors are understandable) you<lb/>
would, using logic, find it extremely difficult to believe other than what has<lb/>
been so recently brought out for the first time in public; namely that the<lb/>
official story regarding Lazear's accidental mosquito bite was purposely incorrect.</item>
<item>11. Page 39 - In the last sentence on this page you mention &ldquo;Some<lb/>
forty years later...a widely circulated supposition.&rdquo; Actually, Agramonte's<lb/>
daughter spent a couple of hours in 1939 or thereabouts insisting that her<lb/>
father told her many times that Lazear had secretly inoculated himself. Quite<lb/>
independently and not having known what Miss Agramonte told me, Moran told me<lb/>
the same thing with great <unclear>credence</unclear> and the presumption is strongly supported<lb/>
by Lazear's confidential letters to his wife. I would strongly suggest that<lb/>
you rewrite this sentence or paragraph and be more responsive to the evidence.<lb/>
Here was man who had already produced yellow fever by a mosquito bite in one<lb/>
case (Carroll) with almost fatal results. <hi>It was his sole purpose to identify</hi><lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04359010"/>
Mrs. Earle Standlee<lb/>
- 5 -<lb/>
April 16, 1951<lb/>
<hi>the mosquito not only as to species but as to stage of infectivity and he</hi> had<lb/>
<hi>largely set himself to that job by his</hi> own enthusiasm and as proven by his<lb/>
letters to his wife. Can you possibly believe that he would have done such a<lb/>
&ldquo;stupid&rdquo; thing as was credited to him? Generals Kean and Truby and others on<lb/>
the spot, when presented with the full evidence, have strongly supported the<lb/>
recently published suggestions.</item>
<item>12. Page 40 - I like very much the last half of this first para-<lb/>
graph. You have gotten around a difficult division of accomplishment in a<lb/>
very good way.</item>
<item>13. Page 40. Again you speak of the advice of Sternberg and Welch.<lb/>
As far as the available records are concerned, this was meager indeed and I<lb/>
should be very grateful for further references.</item>
<item>14. Page 40. Again I think you seem to belittle Reed's work by<lb/>
accepting without sufficient criticism Hemmeter's statements. This is a gross<lb/>
error as can be proven by a close review of the day to day activities and the<lb/>
day to day letters of the men written to their own wives and others and if one<lb/>
does not have time or does not choose to go into detail, one should at least be<lb/>
sufficiently objective to look at the over-all record of these two men, Reed<lb/>
and Carroll. &ldquo;By a man's works ye shall know him.&rdquo; Long before the yellow<lb/>
fever episode Reed was an expert and experienced investigator for the Army<lb/>
Medical Corps. His letters to his wife and others give details of his plans<lb/>
for the experiments. His life was one of numerous accomplishments although<lb/>
none of course <unclear>as</unclear> dramatic as the yellow fever one. Contrast this with the record<lb/>
of Carroll. His is an honorable record but one of an assistant or, at best,<lb/>
a guided associate who before the yellow fever experiments left no particular<lb/>
record of individual unguided research and whose research in 1901-1902 at<lb/>
Los Animas Hospital left much to be desired, being characterized by deaths of<lb/>
volunteers and very little new knowledge to justify the deaths. One must<lb/>
realize that Hemmeter was strongly under the influence of Carroll, who by that time<lb/>
appears to have developed a somewhat paranoid reaction, being an ill man who<lb/>
considered himself and his family seriously neglected (or so his son told me).</item>
<item><unclear>Really the<lb/>
work changes<lb/>
of Sentence &amp;<lb/>
Gorgas</unclear></item>
<item>15. Page 40. The last sentence - &ldquo;...Reed was not especially<lb/>
original...&rdquo; and his assignment was...&ldquo;altogether too big an order.&rdquo; This<lb/>
you get from deKruif. DeKruif is not a strong authority. For years he has<lb/>
been writing books strongly slanted in a popular vein, dramatizing and exag-<lb/>
gerating many things out of proportion to the facts. From Johnny Moran I<lb/>
know a little about the effort which deKruif made to get to the basic facts.<lb/>
He spent a very short time in Havana with Moran. He was unduly influenced by<lb/>
the weak and senile John Kissinger (whom I highly respect but whose statements<lb/>
were open to much criticism and many of which were quite contrary to the facts).</item>
<item>No, <unclear><del>it</del> was<lb/>
Sydney Howard<lb/>
who visited<lb/>
Moran</unclear></item>
<item><p>16. In conclusion of this paragraph I think, therefore, that once<lb/>
again your attitude toward Reed is too defensive and you continue to &ldquo;damn<lb/>
him with faint praise.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Standlee, again let me apologize if I am speaking too frankly.<lb/>
I do not mean to hurt your feelings but I want you to be as objective as I<lb/>
have had to be in this story. My impression of your write-up is that it is<lb/>
as if you were saying something like the following, which of course I am grossly<lb/>
exaggerating: &ldquo;It is said that Reed didn't know much or do much, that others<lb/>
did most of it for him and that he was in Washington when Lazear uncovered the<lb/>
original crucial findings. However, look at Reed's papers. It is said that<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f04359011"/>
Mrs. Earle Standlee<lb/>
- 6 -<lb/>
April 16, 1951<lb/>
he was too small for his job; however he did a pretty good job, didn't he?&rdquo;<lb/>
In my opinion you are giving much too much &ldquo;value&rdquo; to the comments, published<lb/>
and unpublished, of Reed's critics. Why not examine the facts and then, having<lb/>
done so, decide for yourself what he did and then leave out all the inuendos<lb/>
or at least discuss them for what they are, inuendos based on ignorance, mis-<lb/>
understanding and jealousy.</p></item>
<item>17. Page 42 - Should it not be static x-ray machines?</item>
<item>18. Page 43 -&ldquo;In view of Reed's gift for analysis it seems un-<lb/>
important to me he may have lacked originality.&rdquo; Again this seems to me to<lb/>
be a left-handed compliment. Actually the second and crucial experiments under<lb/>
Reed's immediate supervision in Cuba were tremendously original. He may have<lb/>
borrowed a few ideas from those who had done the work on the malarial mosquito<lb/>
but even so there isn't too much evidence that he borrowed much from that data,<lb/>
which was, of course, common knowledge. His <unclear>erection</unclear> of the two experimental<lb/>
buildings, the details of the experiments and so on show, in my opinion, great<lb/>
originality. I have many long letters which he wrote to his wife during the<lb/>
experiments; one letter of which was of particular interest in which he drew<lb/>
out in long hand the exact details of the experimental huts and explained the<lb/>
necessity of this or that part of their construction.</item>
<item>19. Page 45 - In case you wish to do so, my wife's cousin, Dr.<lb/>
Charles Stanley White, the Washington surgeon, happens to have been the one<lb/>
that gave Reed the anesthetic for Doctor Borden. You might care to inter-<lb/>
view him.</item>
<item>20. Page 46 - Speaking of Reed's death, or rather of Borden's loss<lb/>
of Reed, you say &ldquo;It was one of life's small tragedies.&rdquo; Why not be generous<lb/>
and omit the word small. Surely the death of any great scientist at the prime<lb/>
of his career is not a small tragedy to the world, although of course it<lb/>
cannot be measured and one does not know what other triumphs Reed might have<lb/>
accomplished.</item>
<item>21. Page 66 - You say &ldquo;it was Kean who personally answered many of<lb/>
the letters which established Doctor Reed as the principal investigator responsible<lb/>
for this work.&rdquo; It was not Kean's letters that established Reed as the<lb/>
principal investigator. It was merely Kean's knowledge of the facts and the<lb/>
availability of the official records to Kean but the inference is that the<lb/>
pro-Reed Kean is largely responsible for the honors that tardily came to Reed.<lb/>
If you saw some of the letters written to Congressmen (some of them supported<lb/>
by Congressmen who should know better) by this and that soldier or officer who<lb/>
has, since 1900, wanted to get on the role of honor, if you knew that some of<lb/>
these people were never within miles of the place where the experiments were<lb/>
done, you would realize how important it was to have a man in the Surgeon<lb/>
General's Office who knew the facts and who could stick up for those who did<lb/>
the work and stand in the way of those who have falsely claimed credit through<lb/>
the years.</item>
<item><p>22. Page 67 - Your sentence &ldquo;The Walter Reed U. S. Army Hospital<lb/>
was no longer a nebulous plan and Kean, at least, believed it 'a nobler<lb/>
monument than any which a sculptor could create in bronze or marble.'&rdquo; Again,<lb/>
Mrs. Standlee, you allow your reader to suspect that you are not generous<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04359012"/>
Mrs. Earle Standlee<lb/>
- 7 -<lb/>
April 16, 1951<lb/>
enough to join in that conclusion. You give the quotation about &ldquo;the nobler<lb/>
monument&rdquo; but the honor that you might give Reed by using the quotation is<lb/>
diminished by your crediting it to Kean and then particularly by use of the<lb/>
next belittling words &ldquo;at least.&rdquo; It is as if you said the Reed Hospital was<lb/>
finally built and although others might not agree, at least one man believes it is a<lb/>
&ldquo;nobler monument than any....&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mrs. Standlee, I have undoubtedly given you an exaggerated reaction<lb/>
here and there to some of your statements. It is quite probable that you are<lb/>
unaware of the fact that so often where you have given a little something to<lb/>
Reed you seem to me to have taken it away by a qualifying phrase or sentence.</p></item>
</list></p>
<p>I would urge that you submit this manuscript to General Truby who<lb/>
is a stickler for facts, as Kean was. I have spent hours and hours and hours<lb/>
with each man through the last ten years. Neither one was ever willing to<lb/>
tell me something as a certainly unless he either had the proven record to<lb/>
show me or unless it was a matter of absolute personal knowledge on his own<lb/>
part. When they thought their memory might be a little faulty, they said so.<lb/>
When they know it was not, they said so. When, on a few rare occasions (and<lb/>
they were very few) I was able to <del><unclear></unclear></del> them with an official document which<lb/>
corrected or modified their memory, there was no question but that the of-<lb/>
ficial document prevailed. You might also let Mrs. Kean see it. I am sure<lb/>
that she would agree with me that you have misinterpreted at least a few of<lb/>
General Kean's comments and last of all, please remember that I have no axe<lb/>
to grind whatever. Except by the accident of having volunteered for the last<lb/>
war, I am not an Army man. I am not a pro-Reed man or a pro-Lazear man. How-<lb/>
ever, at considerable expense over a period of ten years, I have studied<lb/>
the story intensively as a most fascinating hobby and in my own conclusions<lb/>
I have tried to be generous to everyone within the limits of accuracy and<lb/>
truth.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I enclose a reprint which I do not believe you had available<lb/>
and although I am extremely busy if you want isolated proof of any important<lb/>
detail, I shall try to get it for you in the form of a photostatic copy or an<lb/>
exact copy or the reference.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
