<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04373015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John M. Gibson, September 21, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04373015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-09-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Gibson, John M.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-09-21">September 21, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04373015</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John M. Gibson, September 21, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench provides Gibson, who is publishing a biography of Sternberg, an overview of his Reed research. Hench offers his opinion of the relationship between Sternberg and Reed. Hench lists several important parts of the yellow fever story that remain in doubt and hopes that either he or Gibson might find the answers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-09-21">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John M. Gibson, September 21, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04373015"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1951-09-21">September 21, 1951</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John M. Gibson<lb/>
State Department of Health<lb/>
Montgomery 4, Alabama<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Gibson:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your letter of September 10 and <unclear>am interested</unclear> to know that you are<lb/>
publishing a book on the life of General Sternberg. You are of course familiar<lb/>
with the one that was published by the American Medical Association and<lb/>
written largely by his wife.</p>
<p>I have spent 12 or 13 years collecting data regarding the conquest of<lb/>
yellow fever in preparation to writing a book on it. I have travelled to<lb/>
many places around the country unearthing data in attics, in collars,<lb/>
visited Cuba several times, spent weeks in Washington hunting through<lb/>
various records, etc., and hope in time to write a comprehensive book<lb/>
on the subject. I am of course anxious to use the Reed-Sternberg<lb/>
material for my own book. Much of it has never been published before.<lb/>
The most important part concerns certain very personal and private letters<lb/>
written by Walter Reed to his wife with confidential comments about<lb/>
Sternberg's attitude toward the mosquito theory before and after Reed and<lb/>
his colleagues proved the validity of Finlay's theory. Naturally I should<lb/>
like to reserve these letters for my own book but if I can be helpful in<lb/>
other ways, I should be glad to serve you.</p>
<p>I think you probably already know that the protagonists of Reed are strongly<lb/>
under the opinion that before the work of the Yellow Fever Commission,<lb/>
Sternberg was not interested in Finlay's theory. Then when Reed and his col-<lb/>
leagues proved the validity of the theory, Sternberg of course accepted the<lb/>
proof and in a very natural way &ldquo;got on the band wagon&rdquo;, as it were, and most<lb/>
properly took delight in the work of one of his subordinates which reflected<lb/>
glory on the Medical Department of the Army, including the Surgeon General<lb/>
who had of course written the order creating the Board. However some of the<lb/>
Reed protagonists were of the opinion that Sternberg got on the band wagon<lb/>
rather precipitously and with such enthusiasm as to detract from the work<lb/>
of his subordinate. I am telling you in confidence that Reed seemed to have<lb/>
shared this viewpoint and expressed what might be called mild annoyance to<lb/>
at least two people - to his wife and to his very close friend Major (later<lb/>
General) Kean. Among other data I have typed interviews with General Kean on<lb/>
this point. However if Reed was annoyed he kept his feelings under control<lb/>
and maintained a strictly correct attitude in public and in his private re-<lb/>
lations with General Sternberg and other colleagues.</p>
<p>Mr. Gibson, there are two or three important parts to this story which I have<lb/>
not yet found answers for which perhaps you have and if you have not, I am<lb/>
glad to give you these suggestions because I think the answers to them would<lb/>
strengthen either your book or mine.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04373016"/>
<p>Mr. John M. Gibson</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>September 21, 1951</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Under what circumstances was the Yellow Fever Board formed? Whose<lb/>
idea was it first? Was It Reed's idea or Sternberg's? Sternberg was of<lb/>
course extremely interested in yellow fever. When the epidemic of the<lb/>
spring of 1900 broke out in Cuba he was of course concerned. Reed had<lb/>
already visited Cuba on two or three occasions in 1899, was very interested<lb/>
in yellow fever, was doing research on it and the general impression is that<lb/>
Reed probably made the suggestion to Sternberg; Sternberg thought it over and<lb/>
finally agreed and created the Board but we need much more data on this point.<lb/>
Can you tell me whether you have the dope on this? I shall not ask you for<lb/>
it as that is of course your material to use but I am curious to know.</item>
<item>(2) Just what did General Sternberg have in mind when he wrote the order<lb/>
creating the Board? You have of course read the order and know how vague<lb/>
and general it is.</item>
<item>(3) Are there any confidential notes by Sternberg to supplement the official<lb/>
order? Published records state that Sternberg talked the matter over with<lb/>
Reed as undoubtedly he did and made suggestions or &ldquo;gave orders&rdquo; to Reed by<lb/>
word of mouth. It is amazing how little is known about those discussions.</item>
<item>(4) Reed and Sternberg apparently kept in touch with each other up to a<lb/>
point when Reed was in Cuba but the letters and telegrams between the two<lb/>
that I have been able to unearth are extremely few in number.</item>
</list></p>
<p>I hope indeed that some of the questions I have raised can be answered by<lb/>
the material which the Sternberg family has given to you. You will certainly<lb/>
be doing medical history a service in clarifying the matter but it is only<lb/>
fair to you to know what I discussed in the earlier paragraphs of this letter.<lb/>
Naturally Mrs. Sternberg (Is she still living?) had every reason to give her<lb/>
husband whatever credit was his due in regard to the conquest of yellow fever<lb/>
but certain people have felt that her book was one-sided and my own opinion<lb/>
is that the relative paucity of data which Mrs. Sternberg and her colleagues<lb/>
were unable to unearth for her book would seem to indicate that the going<lb/>
was not easy. Certainly the data in her book does not demonstrate much<lb/>
initiative or primary leadership on the part of Sternberg in the matter of<lb/>
Reed's pursuit of the Finlay theory. I am trying to be very objective about<lb/>
all this and I am perfectly willing, anywhere along the line before my book<lb/>
is published, to be influenced by written records and indeed the reason I<lb/>
have not yet published my book is that I am not satisfied with several parts<lb/>
of it as it now stands. I shall be interested to hear from you further.</p>
<p>I regret that I have not had the privilege of seeing your book on Gorgas.<lb/>
This morning I found that it was not in the Mayo Clinic Library, a serious<lb/>
omission indeed.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I have written the above to you as a personal note and I would not wish<lb/>
you to quote it or any part of it without letting me know. I don't want to be<lb/>
involved prematurely in a controversy.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
