<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04378001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed and Blossom Reed, November 2, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04378001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-11-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Blossom</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-11-02">November 2, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04378001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed and Blossom Reed, November 2, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Lawrence and Blossom Reed that he is receiving numerous requests for his Reed materials. He notes that he would like to develop a policy regarding photographs and proper credit; in this matter he requests Lawrence Reed's opinion.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-11-02">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed and Blossom Reed, November 2, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04378001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1951-11-02">November 2, 1951</date>
</dateline>
General Walter Lawrence Reed<lb/>
Mrs. Blossom Reed<lb/>
<salute>Dear Friends:</salute>
</opener>
<p>As custodian of the extremely interesting and valuable material concerning<lb/>
your father, I feel a great responsibility and I feel obligated to be as<lb/>
helpful as possible to the growing number of people who write me for in-<lb/>
formation. I have also received a number of requests recently for copies<lb/>
of photographs - requests from the Army people, from Walter Reed Hospital,<lb/>
from certain newspapers and magazines. I consider it my duty to grant<lb/>
whatever requests seem dignified and in good taste. I have granted a<lb/>
number of such requests in recent months, and indeed I have spent many<lb/>
hours recently helping two or three writers but this I am delighted to do.</p>
<p>When your mother was living you may remember that I made copies of several<lb/>
photographs of your father for such affairs as the program of the unveiling<lb/>
of the Walter Reed statue in the Hall of Fame in New York. I was asked to<lb/>
give them a credit line for the photographs. Under some of them I sug-<lb/>
gested they put the name &ldquo;Mrs. Walter Reed,&rdquo; under one or two I think the<lb/>
credit line read &ldquo;Mrs. Walter Reed and Dr. P. S. Hench.&rdquo;</p>
<p>At present I am sending to Dr. W. Edwin Hemphill, History <unclear>Division</unclear>, Virginia<lb/>
State Library, Richmond, Virginia, three or four pictures (one of your<lb/>
father's medical <unclear>diploma</unclear> from the University of Virginia) for publication<lb/>
in an article which will appear shortly in the VIRGINIA CAVALCADE. I<lb/>
should like to develop a policy regarding the credit line. Would you<lb/>
like me to put under these photographs &ldquo;The Reed Family&rdquo;? This I should<lb/>
be delighted to do. On the other hand, I don't want numerous people<lb/>
bothering you, writing letters to you, unless you would like to hear from<lb/>
those who are writing articles, etc. I do not like to use just my name as<lb/>
a credit line but I do think it is best to have the magazines use a credit<lb/>
line so that perhaps some control over the use of the photographs can be<lb/>
made. In other words, I do not think that the editors of the VIRGINIA<lb/>
CAVALCADE would pass on to others the photographs which I am now sending<lb/>
them unless they had definite authority to do so, whereas if no credit<lb/>
line were given they might consider themselves at liberty to use the<lb/>
photographs in any way they or others might wish. Another way might be<lb/>
to use some such line as &ldquo;The Reed Family and Dr. P. S. Hench&rdquo; or &ldquo;The<lb/>
Reed Family through Dr. P. S. Hench.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I would appreciate it greatly if you would let me know what you would<lb/>
like to have me do in this matter. I enclose a stamped, addressed<lb/>
air mail envelope for reply.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
