<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04370002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom Reed, September 20, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04370002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-09-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Blossom</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">New York Medical College, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Bellvue Hospital, New York (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-09-20">September 20, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04370002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom Reed, September 20, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Blossom of a celebration at the Bellevue Medical Center honoring her father. Blossom has compared Hench to her father, for which he is deeply honored.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-09-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom Reed, September 20, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04370002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1951-09-20">September 20, 1951</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. Blossom Reed<lb/>
Blue Ridge Summit<lb/>
Pennsylvania<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Reed:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you very much for sending me the most interesting program of the<lb/>
celebration at your father's birthplace. I am delighted to have this<lb/>
and am so glad that you were able to represent the family.</p>
<p>The Dean of the Bellevue Medical Center is a personal friend of mine and a<lb/>
couple of weeks ago (rather tardily) I was notified about a celebration<lb/>
to be held there on September 13. I think they were going to have a tea<lb/>
and some sort of exhibit regarding your father's activities at Bellevue<lb/>
years ago. Whether or not they had any speeches or formal program I do<lb/>
not know. I sent them a long telegram to celebrate the occasion, a copy<lb/>
of which I enclose.</p>
<p>During our correspondence, they first spoke of your father as a graduate<lb/>
of Bellevue, 1897. This was obviously an error. Later they informed me<lb/>
he was listed as a graduate of 1873, but thanks to your kindness I was<lb/>
able to correct that and write them that I actually had the diploma and<lb/>
that the date of his graduation was October 1, 1872. I have offered to<lb/>
give to the Bellevue Hospital and New York Medical College a photograph<lb/>
of his medical diploma. I am sure that you would not object and indeed<lb/>
I think you would like to have me do this. I am certainly glad to do it.<lb/>
More and more I am being called upon to give data regarding your father.<lb/>
At the moment I have three requests for information, not to speak of the<lb/>
voluminous correspondence which I recently had with Mrs. Standlee. I am<lb/>
delighted of course to be of service and I think that it shows the<lb/>
propriety of collecting together as much data as possible and having one<lb/>
place where information will always be available.</p>
<p>Perhaps I was presumptuous in suggesting to the Dean of Bellevue that you<lb/>
and your brother be invited to he ceremony. Obviously you had to be<lb/>
elsewhere.</p>
<p>I must also thank you most sincerely for your gracious letter of September 3.<lb/>
To have you compare me with your beloved father is of course about the greatest<lb/>
compliment you could ever pay me. I do think that your father and mine were<lb/>
much alike. They belonged to the old school of classical scholars to whom<lb/>
right was right; they had no doubt about what was right or wrong; they be-<lb/>
lieved in gentle but definite discipline and certainly Father kept my nose<lb/>
to my books.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04370003"/>
<p>Mrs. Blossom Reed</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>September 20, 1951</p>
<p>One point in your letter was particularly useful. You wrote &ldquo;Father loved<lb/>
Doctor Lazear and Doctor Carroll and they loved him.&rdquo; I must always remember<lb/>
that because certain of Doctor Carroll's actions after your father died,<lb/>
some of his letters, remarks and so forth, one simply has to regard with<lb/>
considerable charity and from time to time I feel a little stern toward<lb/>
Carroll but, as you say, while your father was alive Carroll served him<lb/>
faithfully and your father loved him. That is the important point which<lb/>
I must remember and which gives me strength to maintain a charitable viewpoint<lb/>
toward Carroll who, after all when he wrote some of the disturbing things,<lb/>
must have been a rather sick man.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
