<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04383007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Harry J. Warthen, November 20, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04383007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-11-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Warthen, Harry J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-11-20">November 20, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04383007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Harry J. Warthen, November 20, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench suggests a list of Reed items, which can be used for a Walter Reed Exhibit during the next meeting of the History of Medicine Section of the Richmond Academy of Science.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-11-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Harry J. Warthen, November 20, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04383007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1951-11-20">November 20, 1951</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Harry J. Warthen, Chairman<lb/>
Section of History of Medicine<lb/>
Richmond Academy of Medicine<lb/>
1200 East Clay Street<lb/>
Richmond 19, Virginia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Warthen:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your request to help in the matter of a Walter Reed Exhibit on<lb/>
the occasion of the Walter Reed Night to be held by the Section on the<lb/>
History of Medicine next February.</p>
<p>The relatives of Walter Reed, Jesse Lazear and many of their associates<lb/>
in the conquest of yellow fever have made me the custodian of a great<lb/>
mass of original material which is being carefully preserved and which I<lb/>
have carefully filed. The most valuable of this material - the original<lb/>
letters of Walter Reed to his wife over a period of many years, including<lb/>
the Cuban years, and those of Lazear to his family, also Walter Reed's<lb/>
diplomas and other items are kept in a safe in my home. Unfortunately<lb/>
at the moment, these data are somewhat &ldquo;unavailable.&rdquo; This summer we made<lb/>
extensive improvements to our house, during which time a lot of extra<lb/>
furniture and other material had to be stored in the same room in which<lb/>
my yellow fever files reside. Because of the press of recent work, I<lb/>
have not been able to clear up this room but hope to do it within the<lb/>
next two or three months.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, I shall be glad to correspond with you further about the<lb/>
exhibit. Because so much of what the Reed family and others have given<lb/>
me is completely irreplaceable and invaluable, I have hesitated greatly to<lb/>
lend any of it out. Indeed I have declined all such requests except one,<lb/>
made a few years ago by the Association of Military Surgeons in connection<lb/>
with a Walter Reed Memorial and in this case the exhibit was taken by me<lb/>
to Washington and brought home by me and during the time of the exhibit it<lb/>
was under constant supervision by military and association personnel. I<lb/>
fear, therefore, that until these various items are framed, each in its<lb/>
own protective case, the originals should not be loaned out, but I should<lb/>
be glad to lend you copies of some of these originals, the most interesting<lb/>
ones. Among them are such items as the following which I shall number for<lb/>
the sake of convenience in our further correspondence.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. A photographic copy of Walter Reed's original Army commission.</item>
<item>2. Photostatic copy of Reed's application for commission in the Army, in-<lb/>
cluding a biographical sketch of himself written in his own hand.</item>
<item>3. Photographs of his birthplace, before and after renovation.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f04383008"/>
<item>Dr. Harry J. Warthen</item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>November 20, 1951</item>
<item>4. Various photographs (or copies of photographs) of Walter Reed from<lb/>
childhood on up, including one or two unpublished ones.</item>
<item>5. A selection of photostats or photographs, about a half dozen, of the<lb/>
most important letters of those which Reed sent to his wife during the<lb/>
yellow fever experiments, including photographs of his famous New Year's<lb/>
Eve letter to his wife.</item>
<item>6. Photostats of one of the long-lost laboratory notebooks started by<lb/>
Lazear, concluded by Reed, with notes concerning the yellow fever experi-<lb/>
ments.</item>
<item>7. Photographs of various buildings of Camp Columbia, Cuba, where the<lb/>
pre-Camp Lazear studies were made.</item>
<item>8. Copies of the old Army photographs of Camp Lazear taken in 1900.</item>
<item>9. Many original photographs which I took of Camp Lazear as we re-discovered<lb/>
it in 1940; in particular, many photographs inside and outside the remains<lb/>
of Reed's Building No. 1 which we re-discovered in 1940.</item>
<item>10. A few letters of Lazear.</item>
<item>11. Photographs of all of Reed's diplomas, earned and honorary, from various<lb/>
universities and hospitals.</item>
</list></p>
<p>This will give you an idea of the material that I have and if you think those<lb/>
photographs or photostats would serve your purpose about as well as the<lb/>
originals, I should be glad to cooperate in every way possible.</p>
<p>For ten years I have been trying to enlist the help of interested persons<lb/>
in what I considered to be an important and worthwhile historic project.<lb/>
In the November 4 issue of the New York Times appeared a little article on<lb/>
my project. How it happened to be published there and then I do not know.<lb/>
As a result, I have just had some correspondence with Mr. Frederick L. Rath, Jr.<lb/>
Director of the National Trust for Historic Preservation. I enclose a copy<lb/>
of the letter I have just sent to him. Do you think it would be possible for<lb/>
the Historical Section of the Richmond Academy of Medicine to help in this<lb/>
project in any way? I have been trying for so long to preserve the building<lb/>
on the basis of my own individual efforts but so far have failed for reasons<lb/>
given in the enclosed letter. I do think that we may succeed if the proper<lb/>
association is made. The Walter Reed Memorial Association is willing to be the<lb/>
sponsoring organization but needs badly the help of others. If you think that<lb/>
your organization would be interested, I should be glad to send you, in the<lb/>
near future, details about the plan, photographs of Camp Lazear and the<lb/>
little building, (taken a couple of years ago when I was there last) and<lb/>
diagrams and descriptions of the little memorial building that I had planned.<lb/>
In the meantime, permit me to send you the enclosed four reprints which I hope<lb/>
will interest you and may I call your attention in particular to the detailed<lb/>
description of the re-discovery of the lost Camp Lazear as described on pages<lb/>
3 to 7 of my reprint, &ldquo;Walter Reed and the Conquest of Yellow Fever,&rdquo; which<lb/>
appeared in The Pharos, May 1948.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
