<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04382002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Minutes from the annual meeting of the Board of Managers, Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 21, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04382002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-11-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-11-21">November 21, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04382002</idno>
<title>Minutes from the annual meeting of the Board of Managers, Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 21, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This documents records the deliberations of the Reed Memorial Association. Special attention is paid to the centennial of Reed's birth.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1951-11-21">
<head>Minutes from the annual meeting of the Board of Managers, Walter Reed Memorial Association, November 21, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04382002"/>
<p>The next order of business was the election of officers and new members. It was moved<lb/>
and seconded that the officers for the last year, namely, Col. J. F. Siler, President,<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench, Vice President, Brig. Gen. Albert G. Love, Secretary, and Mr. Hans W.<lb/>
Ireland, Treasurer, be reelected for the ensuing year. The chairman asked if any member<lb/>
desired to make any other nominations. None were made. He then requested Gen. Keefer to<lb/>
take the chair. The motion to reelect the present officers was carried unanimously.</p>
<p>There were no member vacancies.</p>
<p>The chairman called attention to the fact that 1951 is the 100th anniversary of the<lb/>
birth of Walter Reed. He stated that he wished to express his own appreciation, in which<lb/>
he was sure all of the members of the Board concurred, of the splendid publicity work done<lb/>
by the staff of the Army Medical Center in the dissemination of information during the year<lb/>
in the press and in local meetings in regard to the life and work of Walter Reed.</p>
<p>The 13th of September, 1951, the 100th anniversary of the birth of Walter Reed, was<lb/>
proclaimed &ldquo;Walter Reed Day&rdquo; by the Commissioners of the District of Columbia and by the<lb/>
Board of Supervisors of Gloucester, Va., near his birthplace at Belvoir, Va. The Governor<lb/>
of Virginia issued a proclamation for further observances throughout the State. Special<lb/>
Commemorative services were held at his birthplace, Belvoir, Va., where Gen. Earle Standlee<lb/>
spoke in lieu of Gen. Paul H. Streit who was unable to attend. Col. Joseph A. Weaver spoke<lb/>
at similar services at Harrisonburg, Va., Walter Reed's second home. There were special<lb/>
exhibits in the Army Medical Museum and at the College of Medicine, New York University,<lb/>
Major Reed's second medical school. There were appropriate services also at the Walter Reed<lb/>
Army Medical Center, including a radio program. Miss Lena Townshend, now 76, of Baltimore,<lb/>
Md., who was associated with the yellow fever experimental work as a nurse, was present and<lb/>
participated. Major Reed's daughter, Blossom Reed, was guest of honor at Gloucester, Va.,<lb/>
and placed a wreath in honor of her father. Gen. Walter Reed, son of Major Reed, participated<lb/>
in the services at the Army Medical Center. In addition, the Army Medical Center was re-<lb/>
designated the Walter Reed Army Medical Center by General Order No. 80, Department of the<lb/>
Army, Washington, 13 September 1951.</p>
<p>General Love stated that, since he had assumed the duties of Secretary of the Association,<lb/>
he found by looking through the records of the Association that Colonel Siler, while Secretary,<lb/>
had done a splendid job in recording, reworking and assembling the various important documents<lb/>
associated with the proceedings of the Association during its history of almost fifty years.<lb/>
He expressed the opinion that the Association was under great obligations to Colonel Siler for<lb/>
his fine work. His remarks received the enthusiastic approval of all present although no vote<lb/>
was requested.</p>
<p>Colonel Siler spoke of the special exhibit of Walter Reed material at the Medical<lb/>
Museum and asked that consideration be given to a suitable depository of such material. Dr.<lb/>
Fred L. Soper and Gen. F. R. Keefer both express the opinion that, should a permanent exhibit<lb/>
be arranged, suitable provisions should be made for material showing Dr. Carlos Finlay's very<lb/>
important work leading up to Major Reed's final experimental work.</p>
<p>Doctor Soper spoke of the Certificate and $500.00 award to Mr. J. A. Le Prince by the<lb/>
National Malaria Society at its recent meeting in Chicago, I11., for his outstanding contri-<lb/>
bution to the prevention of malarial infections and for his other work in tropical medicine.<lb/>
Mr. Le Prince is well known to all those interested in tropical medicine for his splendid<lb/>
work in association with Gen. William Crawford Gorgas in Havana and Panama. The address of<lb/>
Mr. J. A. Le Prince is 929 Oakmont Street, Memphis Tenn. Dr. Soper stated that Mr. Le Prince<lb/>
spoke of the interest of Mr. Guss Lambert in the Walter Reed experimental work in Cuba.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04382003"/>
Mr. Lambert has material that may be of interest for a museum exhibit.</p>
<p>There being no further business, the meeting was adjourned to meet at the call of the<lb/>
President.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Albert G. Love, Secretary</signed>
<seg>
P.S.<lb/>
Please notify the Secretary at 2709 Wisconsin Avenue, N. W., of any changes or<lb/>
amendments.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
