<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04401010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frederick L. Rath, Jr., November 17, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04401010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-11-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rath, Jr., Frederick L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Macia, Adrian</name>
<name type="person">Rockefeller, Nelson</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="person">Rockefeller, John D.</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Margaret Lazear</name>
<name type="place">Washington and Jefferson College, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Cleveland (Ohio)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-11-17">November 17, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04401010</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frederick L. Rath, Jr., November 17, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes Rath that he would appreciate any help that the National Trust for Historic Preservation could provide in preserving Camp Lazear. He describes  his attempts to enlist the support of the Cuban government and the Rockefeller Foundation.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-11-17">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Frederick L. Rath, Jr., November 17, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04401010"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1951-11-17">November 17, 1951</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Frederick L. Rath, Jr.<lb/>
Director<lb/>
National Trust for Historic Preservation<lb/>
The Octagon House<lb/>
Washington, 6, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Rath:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I appreciate very greatly your letter of November 6 commenting on the<lb/>
little article which appeared in the New York Times for Sunday, Novem-<lb/>
ber 4, the article concerning the little Building No. 1 of Walter Reed.<lb/>
Will you kindly note especially the last part (pages 3 to 7) of my article<lb/>
&ldquo;Walter Reed and the Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo; in The Pharos for May, 1948?<lb/>
That will give you the details of our rediscovery of the little building.<lb/>
What the little building was used for is described in all of the reprints<lb/>
and a photograph of the building appears in two or three of them.</p>
<p>I would certainly appreciate any advice and help that your organization<lb/>
can give me. Being a very busy physician, it has not been possible for<lb/>
me to campaign individually and write hundreds of letters to collect<lb/>
nickels and dimes for this project. When Mr. Moran and I discovered the<lb/>
little building in 1940, I discussed the letter with Doctor Ramos, then<lb/>
Secretary of <unclear>Defense</unclear>. Doctor Ramos is a Cuban physician greatly interested<lb/>
in the story of Walter Reed as well as the story of Finlay and a man who<lb/>
had previously written an article suggesting the preservation of the wrong<lb/>
Camp Lazear. In 1940 Doctor Ramos listened to our ideas with a great<lb/>
interest and promised help but shortly thereafter he went out of office<lb/>
and did nothing.</p>
<p>On two occasions when I gave this story, first at the dedication of the<lb/>
Lazear Memorial Building at Washington and Jefferson College and then<lb/>
when I told it again at the unveiling of the Cornwell painting during<lb/>
the meeting of the American Medical Association, June 1941, in Cleveland,<lb/>
I hinted to my audiences that I hoped that money could be collected for<lb/>
the preservation of the little building but no help was forthcoming.</p>
<p>Thereafter I made two or three trips to Cuba and on my last trip in 1948<lb/>
I really thought I had gotten somewhere. As a result of a previous trip<lb/>
the Cuban government had accepted the authenticity of the little shack,<lb/>
had allowed the memorial sign at the false Camp Lazear to fall down and<lb/>
become destroyed and had made the little shack a &ldquo;national memorial&rdquo; but<lb/>
they had done absolutely nothing to preserve the shack. During my 1948<lb/>
trip I visited various governmental officials, including the Vice-President<lb/>
of Cuba. I showed them a tentative plan regarding a memorial to be<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04401011"/>
Mr. Frederick L. Rath, Jr.<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 17, 1951<lb/>
erected on the spot. This plan was approved heartily by the head of the<lb/>
Engineering Department, by the Minister of Health and by the Vice-Presi-<lb/>
dent, who welcomed me kindly to his home. I found the shack deteriorated<lb/>
even worse than before and how it has survived the various tornadoes that<lb/>
hit Cuba every two or three years is incredible. Although the Cuban<lb/>
government had made the little shack and the land on which it stands a<lb/>
national monument, I found that this actually was a deterrent rather than<lb/>
a help to my plan. I went to the owner of the land on which the little<lb/>
shack stands (Mr. Adrian Macia) and asked if he wouldn't let me buy the<lb/>
little property. He said that he couldn't because it was a national monu-<lb/>
ment. I then asked him if he would let me pay the expense of having a<lb/>
galvanized iron covering put over the little building that would at least<lb/>
protect it until the Cubans got around to doing something. He said he<lb/>
hadn't the authority to let me do that either. When I repeated this<lb/>
request gently and diplomatically to the Vice-President, the latter, with<lb/>
typical Cuban protestations and gestures, assured me that the Cuban<lb/>
government could never allow me to spend my own money; that the Cuban<lb/>
government would immediately take steps to protect the little building<lb/>
until such time as the full memorial project could be developed. I was<lb/>
rather discouraged but true to his word, he and others did put through<lb/>
the Cuban congress a bill to allot $50,000 for the project. This was<lb/>
passed rather promptly and two or three clippings to that effect were<lb/>
sent to me by Cuban friends in 1948. I had high hopes for the project.</p>
<p>My project envisaged the erection of a Cuban-style building on the spot,<lb/>
a large room of which would actually enclose the little building. Around<lb/>
the walls of this room would be various photographs and other data per-<lb/>
taining to the work of Finlay, Walter Reed and his American colleagues.<lb/>
The rest of the building would be devoted to a small public health unit<lb/>
for that little suburb of Quemados, which is without such a unit but which<lb/>
needs one badly. The rest of Camp Lazear would be made into a small park<lb/>
with a little inexpensive central memorial on the site of Building No. 2.<lb/>
My advisors in this plan were Dr. Pedro Nogueira, a very aggressive and<lb/>
fine young Quemados physician interested in public health in Quemados,<lb/>
and also Mr. Johnny Moran, one of Reed's original guinea pigs.</p>
<p>To my dismay, once more that party went out of power. They lost the<lb/>
next election and none of my Cuban friends or I have ever been able to<lb/>
learn what happened to the $50,000. I have been told confidentially that<lb/>
it either went into the pockets of the Cuban officials &ldquo;in the usual<lb/>
manner&rdquo; or it was spent on some other project.</p>
<p>From time to time I have seen and tried to interest certain Americans in<lb/>
this project. Some years ago, when Nelson Rockefeller was head of some<lb/>
sort of a bureau which had to do with Latin-American cultural relation-<lb/>
ships, I tried to interest him in this project but just about the time I<lb/>
saw him his bureau folded up. With Doctor Sawyer, head of the Rockefeller<lb/>
Foundation, I saw Mr. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s chief advisor in charitable<lb/>
matters. Doctor Sawyer and I thought that, because the Rockefeller Founda-<lb/>
tion has been so interested in yellow fever, Mr. Rockefeller's advisors<lb/>
regarding donations might be interested. I regret to say that this man<lb/>
received me and showed little sympathy with the project, stating that he<lb/>
thought it was outside the realm of interest of their charity.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04401012"/>
<p>Mr. Frederick L. Rath, Jr.</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>November 17, 1951</p>
<p>I have talked about this at some length with both of the past Surgeons<lb/>
General (not the present one) and they were both strongly in favor of<lb/>
it and will do whatever is necessary. But the up-shot of it is that<lb/>
nothing constructive has happened and I can summarize the present posi-<lb/>
tion briefly:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) I doubt if the Cuban Government will authorize the proper expenditures<lb/>
unless (a) the Cuban funds are matched by American donations or (b) unless<lb/>
some Americans in official positions can get behind the unofficial efforts<lb/>
of myself and others to persuade the Cuban government to carry on the proj-<lb/>
ect.</item>
<item>(2) The fact that the Cuban government has made the little building a<lb/>
national monument prevents any private American or Cuban from doing<lb/>
anything, even temporarily to preserve the shack.</item>
<item>(3) I regret to say that from my experience I must conclude that one<lb/>
can place little reliance on the very friendly and temporarily enthusiastic<lb/>
attitude of any Cuban. Three strong forces in Cuba prevent, at present,<lb/>
the accomplishment of my desires: (a) The ingrained attitude of manana,<lb/>
their eternal procrastination despite the most solemn promises; (b) what<lb/>
my Cuban advisors privately tell me about the common grafting by officials<lb/>
of money set aside for this or that project; and (c) the fact that in<lb/>
Cuba there is still a great controversy between those who would give all<lb/>
the credit to Finlay and none to Walter Reed and those who are willing,<lb/>
rather grudgingly, to give Walter Reed and his associates some credit for<lb/>
the conquest of yellow fever. Twice since 1948 I have received newspaper<lb/>
clippings showing officials visiting Walter Reed's little shack and despite<lb/>
the absolute evidence, the photographs have been labelled &ldquo;The little shack<lb/>
where <hi>Finlay</hi> proved the cause of yellow fever.&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
<p>Despite all my discouragements I feel that I must keep trying and I am going<lb/>
to Cuba again in January. The people who own the land, Mr. Macia and the<lb/>
Rojas family, are still quite interested in the project as is Doctor<lb/>
Nogueira. I am sure that a few of the Cuban officials are quite sincere<lb/>
and it is a wonderful opportunity that in erecting a Cuban-American memorial<lb/>
honoring in full measure Finlay as well as Reed and his associates, a<lb/>
rapprochement can be accomplished and the painful argument between those<lb/>
who would honor only Finlay and those who would honor only Reed can be<lb/>
done away with finally in a spirit of real cordiality and admiration. I<lb/>
might add that on one of my visits I met President Batista who expressed<lb/>
approval of the project but of course did nothing.</p>
<p>The Walter Reed Memorial Association knows fully of my hopes and plans.<lb/>
Walter Reed's daughter and son, Lazear's son and daughter also know and<lb/>
fully approve. If we could only get organized and get official backing<lb/>
strong enough to impress the Cuban government so that they would not go<lb/>
back on their word, I am sure that we could put over this project but I<lb/>
regret that acting alone, I have not gotten anywhere to date.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, MD.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
