<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04401001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, August 6, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04401001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-08-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Rojas, Maria Teresa</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, Elida</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-08-06">August 6, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04401001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, August 6, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is discouraged by the Cuban government's lack of response to the Camp Lazear memorial. The government will not permit Hench to donate money to the site because it is a Cuban national monument, but the government has not allocated any money itself.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-08-06">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas, August 6, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04401001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1951-08-06">August 6, 1951</date>
</dateline>
Senorita Maria Teresa Rojas<lb/>
Quinta San Jose<lb/>
Calle Real<lb/>
Quemados de Marianao<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senorita Rojas:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you so much for your letter of July 22, just received. I am distressed<lb/>
that I did not receive your other letters and the clippings. These never<lb/>
reached me and I would <unclear>so much</unclear> like to have seen them. There seems to be<lb/>
some difficulty with mail between Cuba and the United States in recent months.<lb/>
After hearing of Johnny Moran's death, I sent Mrs. Moran a letter. It was re-<lb/>
turned to me two or three times marked, &ldquo;Address unknown.&rdquo; I later found that<lb/>
she was still living at the same house, sent it again and it was delivered<lb/>
after a period of two or three months.</p>
<p>I have gotten rather discouraged at the reaction of the Cuban Government toward<lb/>
my proposition to help memorialize Camp Lazear. You may remember that on my<lb/>
last visit I became very hopeful. I saw many officials, including the Vice-<lb/>
President, who assured me that the Cuban government would set aside money to<lb/>
memorialize Camp Lazear. Because the caseta had been named a national monument<lb/>
they would not let me spend some of my own money to protect it. Politely but<lb/>
firmly I requested the Vice-President to let me at least erect around the caseta<lb/>
a galvanized iron protection so that while the government is going ahead with<lb/>
their plans the caseta would be protected, but he <unclear>insisted</unclear> that the Cuban<lb/>
government would not let me do even that - that they would do it. Later Mr.<lb/>
Moran sent me a clipping saying that the government had appropriated $50,000<lb/>
for the site. Then that administration went out of office and nothing happened.<lb/>
Some time later Mr. Moran sent me a clipping which distressed me greatly. Another<lb/>
administration had renamed the caseta a national monument, but not to <unclear>Loazear</unclear><lb/>
but to Finlay. The write-up erroneously (and I suspect deliberately) stated that<lb/>
it was in this caseta that Finlay had done his work. Even so, the administra-<lb/>
tion did not set aside any money, not even a starter.</p>
<p>I feel, therefore, quite stymied. They won't let me spend my own money because<lb/>
it is a national monument and they won't spend any themselves, they won't even<lb/>
protect the building, and when they talk of it they talk of the Finlay caseta.<lb/>
When I write my book the matter should be clarified but by then it may be too<lb/>
late. I had hoped to have some American help but the Americans will not help<lb/>
if the Cuban government does not participate and particularly if the Cubans do<lb/>
not recognize the Camp for what it is - the cite where the ingenious theory<lb/>
of Finlay was proven to be correct by the work of Reed and his colleagues in<lb/>
a camp named for the martyr Lazear.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04401002"/>
<p>Senorita Maria Teresa Rojas</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>August 6, 1951</p>
<p>Although greatly discouraged, I have not given up. I hope to go to Cuba<lb/>
in January for a medical meeting and if I can summon enough enthusiasm to<lb/>
start all over again, I will try to see the appriate people. Last time I had<lb/>
even drawn up tentative plans for the memorial which I submitted to<lb/>
various officials for their comments and suggestions. They liked them<lb/>
but that was the end of that.</p>
<p>If you have any way of getting the clippings that you mention (the one Johnny<lb/>
Moran sent me <unclear>was</unclear> a small photograph with a very short paragraph) or if you<lb/>
know of any way you can help me or know whom I can see, I shall be very glad<lb/>
for your help.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
