<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04401017">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Frederick L. Rath, Jr., to Philip Showalter Hench, December 21, 1951</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Rath, Jr., Frederick L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04401017</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-12-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Grant, III, Ulysses Simpson</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-12-21">December 21, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04401017</idno>
<title>Letter from Frederick L. Rath, Jr., to Philip Showalter Hench, December 21, 1951</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Rath informs Hench that his attempt to preserve Building No. 1 lies outside the purview of the National Council for Historic Sites and Buildings because of the Cuban government's involvement. He suggests raising funds through a medical fraternity, possibly with the sanction of the American Medical Association or the Walter Reed Memorial Association.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-12-21">
<head>Letter from Frederick L. Rath, Jr., to Philip Showalter Hench, December 21, 1951</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04401017"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
National Council for Historic Sites and Buildings<lb/>
New York Avenue and 18th Street, N. W.<lb/>
The Octagon House &middot; Washington 6, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1951-12-21">December 21, 1951</date>
</dateline>
President<lb/>
U. S. GRANT, 3RD<lb/>
Chairman of Executive Board<lb/>
DAVID E. FINLEY<lb/>
Vice Presidents<lb/>
MRS. FRANCIS B. CROWNINSHIELD<lb/>
TURPIN C. BANNISTER<lb/>
Secretary<lb/>
RONALD F. LEE<lb/>
Treasurer<lb/>
KEITH MERRILL<lb/>
Telephone:<lb/>
STERLING 7056<lb/>
Director<lb/>
FREDERICK L. RATH, JR.<lb/>
Administrator<lb/>
HENRY H. SURFACE<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>A brief vacation, a broken rib, and an out-of-town business<lb/>
trip have served to pile up enough work so that I could not give full<lb/>
attention to our correspondence about Building No. 1 at Quemados, Cuba.<lb/>
Yesterday, however, General U. S. Grant, 3rd, President of the National<lb/>
Council for Historic Sites and Buildings, and I did get to discussing<lb/>
the problem confronting you.</p>
<p>As I told you, the cause you have fought for so vigorously<lb/>
has ramifications outside our experience, largely because of the smoke-<lb/>
screen built up by the Cuban government. Analysis would only seem to<lb/>
yield the conclusion that it is the present regime that must be moved<lb/>
to action - either with or without matching American donations. Even<lb/>
though you state that matching donations will be necessary, I note that<lb/>
in 1948 they refused any material help from you. Is it not possible<lb/>
that it would be a matter of pride to do the job themselves, if they<lb/>
could be impelled to act?</p>
<p>Before I deal with the matter of impelling them to act, let<lb/>
me ask whether the medical fraternity could not be enlisted to support<lb/>
a fund for the purpose, should it prove necessary? Possibly with the<lb/>
sanction of the American Medical Association, a special foundation,<lb/>
qualifying for tax exemption under Section 101 (6) of the Internal<lb/>
Revenue Code, could collect tax-free contributions from American doctors.<lb/>
It is simply an idea I thought worth mentioning, not because I believed<lb/>
you had not thought of it but because we do know how to tell you to go<lb/>
about setting such a foundation. I recognize that there is a Walter<lb/>
Reed Memorial Association. It may be that it is the only instrument<lb/>
you need to embark on such a campaign, if it properly activated, gets<lb/>
official or unofficial sanction for the project, and then solicit the<lb/>
right sources.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04401018"/>
<p>Dr. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>December 21, 1951</p>
<p>About impelling action - you have gone far along those lines<lb/>
already. Perhaps in January you can go further. It may not be signi-<lb/>
ficant, but I think we could arm you with a letter from General Grant<lb/>
supporting the project. As President of the National Council for His-<lb/>
toric Sites and Buildings, he represents a hundred organizations con-<lb/>
cerned with preservation of the American heritage. It is no stretch<lb/>
of the imagination, as we know, to include the yellow-fever battle and<lb/>
Dr. Walter Reed's part in it as part of the American heritage. We<lb/>
could urge the present Cuban government to complete the national monu-<lb/>
ment in a manner befitting the great country of Cuba - that sort of<lb/>
thing. Perhaps the present Surgeon-General might be able to do the<lb/>
same.</p>
<p>I note that you are going to Cuba in January. Would it be<lb/>
feasible at that time for you to come through Washington, if you are<lb/>
embarking from the East Coast? Barring conflict of schedules, I be-<lb/>
lieve that General Grant would be delighted to join us at lunch and a<lb/>
discussion of this matter. We should like to help in some manner,<lb/>
even if we are in no position to contribute financially to individual<lb/>
projects.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours</salute>
<signed>Frederick L. Rath, Jr.<lb/>
Director</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
