<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04415001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Speech by [Philip Showalter Hench], January 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04415001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-01-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship">YES</term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-01-00">January 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04415001</idno>
<title>Speech by [Philip Showalter Hench], January 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In this speech, to the Rotary Club of Havana, [Hench] mentions his marriage, his admiration of those involved in the yellow fever experiments, and some of the people he has met through his yellow fever research.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1952-01-00">
<head>Speech by [Philip Showalter Hench], January 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04415001"/>
<opener>
REPUBLICA DE CUBA<lb/>
---<lb/>
MINISTERIO DE SALUBRIDAD Y ASISTENCIA SOCIAL<lb/>
------<lb/>
<salute>Dr. Nogueira, Rotarians, Ladies &amp; Genttelmen:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Mrs. Hench and I are happy to be here today. My first visit<lb/>
to Havana was in 1925 when I was a young unmarried man. Right away<lb/>
the spell of Cuba must have affected me. At least it is a fact<lb/>
that<del>h</del> I want straight from Havana to Boston where a certain young<lb/>
lady was in college and asked her to marry me. But she made me<lb/>
wait two years, perhaps because she had not yet been touched by the<lb/>
magic of Havana. However shortly after we were married I brought her<lb/>
here on a visit and we have lived happyl ever since;</p>
<p>Every human heart needs inspiration, <del>from</del>inspiration from<lb/>
the One on High and inspiration from <del>t</del>his fellow man. For years I<lb/>
have been inspired by the wonderful story of the conquest of yellow<lb/>
fever. For 15 years I have spent <add>much</add> of my lisure time <del>every</del> visi-<lb/>
ting everyone still alive who took part in this event.</p>
<p>Some of the richest experiences of my life have come<lb/>
from my meetings and association with the relatives and close<lb/>
friends of those who accomplished this magnificent a<del>r</del>chi<add>e</add>vement:<lb/>
your illustrious countryman Carlos Finlay and his devoted associate<lb/>
Claudio Delgado, and my distinguished fellow <unclear>countrymen</unclear> Major Walter<lb/>
Reed and his associate<del>d</del>s Drs. Aristides Agramonte, Carrol and Lazear.</p>
<p>I shall always remenber with gratitude the wonderful<lb/>
hospitality and frienships wich Mrs. Hench and I have received from<lb/>
so many here in Havana; among them Dr. Ramos and Albertini, And<del>e</del>reu<lb/>
and Recio, se&ntilde;oras Agramonte Rodriguez-Le<del><unclear></unclear></del>on and Rojas, and not<lb/>
the least, my friend and gracious host Dr. Pedro Nogueira.</p>
<p>On this visit Mrs. Hench and I miss so very much<lb/>
that lovable Iris<del>e</del>h-American-Cuban, Johnny Moran, who lived his life<lb/>
among you until he died here last year and who in 1900 at the request<lb/>
of Major Reed and &ldquo;For the sake of humanity&rdquo; offered his own living<lb/>
body to prove the theory of Carlos Finlay.</p>
<p>So profound are the secrets of nature, so complicated was the terrible problem of<lb/>
yellow fever that no one man, however great he might be, could solve the mystery<lb/>
The conception of Carlos Finlay was one of the boldest most original and most<lb/>
precise in the whole history of science. But before the world could accept his<lb/>
ideas others, to be exact over a score of others, had to contribute their brains,<lb/>
their courage &amp; if need be, their lives.</p>
<p>Including first the inspired Dr Finlay these 25 men were 3 Cuban, 4 <unclear>Span</unclear>,<lb/>
1 <unclear>Iresh</unclear>, 1 <unclear>English</unclear> &amp; 16 <unclear>Amer</unclear>. Some were <unclear>Catolic</unclear>, some <unclear>Prot</unclear>, some <unclear>Hebrew</unclear>.<lb/>
<unclear>United</unclear> in a common cause they formed a unique service club &amp; one of<lb/>
histories <unclear>finest</unclear> examples of <unclear>humanitarian understand</unclear> cooperate.</p>
<p>That these men lived &amp; worked here among you <unclear>citizens</unclear> of Havana &amp;<lb/>
Marianao must be a <unclear>matter of tremendous satisfaction</unclear></p>
<p>To these men &amp; to <unclear>their Christian ideals</unclear> of brotherly love Mrs Hench<lb/>
&amp; I pay our most <unclear>humble</unclear> tribute</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04415002"/>
<p>Dr Nogueira, <unclear>Rotarians, Ladies</unclear> and Gentlemen.</p>
<p>Mrs Hench and I are happy to be here today. My first visit to Havana was<lb/>
in 1925 when I was a young unmarried man. Right away the spell of Cuba<lb/>
must have affected me. At least it is a fact that I <unclear>want</unclear> straight from Havana<lb/>
to Boston where a certain young lady was in college and asked her to marry<lb/>
me. But she made me wait two years, perhaps because she had not yet<lb/>
been touched by the magic of Havana. However shortly after we were<lb/>
married I brought her here on a visit and we have lived happily ever since!</p>
<p>Every human heart needs inspiration, inspiration from the one on<lb/>
High and inspiration from his fellow man. For years I have been<lb/>
inspired by the wonderful story of the Conquest of Yellow Fever. For 15<lb/>
years I have spent much of my <hi>leisure</hi> time visiting everyone <add>still</add> alive<lb/>
who <hi>took</hi> part in this event.</p>
<p>Some of the richest experiences of my life have come from my<lb/>
meetings and association with the relatives and close friends of<lb/>
those who accomplished this magnificent achievement: your<lb/>
illustrious countrymen Carlos Finlay and his devoted associate,<lb/>
Claudio Delgado, and my own distinguished fellow countrymen<lb/>
Major Walter Reed and his associates Drs Aristides Agramonte, Carroll<lb/>
and Lazear.</p>
<p>I shall always remember with gratitude the wonderful hospitality<lb/>
and friendliness which Mrs Hench and I have received from so<lb/>
many here in Havana: among them Doctors Ramos and Albertini,<lb/>
Andreu and Recio, and notthe least, my friend and gracious<lb/>
host Dr Pedro Nogueira. Senoras Agramonte Rodriguez - Leon<lb/>
and Rojas,</p>
<p>On this visit Mrs Hench and I miss so very much that<lb/>
lovable Irish-American-Cuban, Johnny Moran, who lived his<lb/>
life among you until he died here last year and who in 1900 at<lb/>
the request of Major Reed and &ldquo;for the sake of humanity&rdquo; offered<lb/>
his own living body to prove the bold theory of Carlos Finlay.</p>
<p>So profound are the secrets of nature, so complicated <del>and<lb/>
mysterious</del> was the terrible problem of yellow fever that unfortunately,<lb/>
no one man, however great he might be, could solve the mystery.<lb/>
The conception of Carlos Finlay was one of the boldest, <del>and</del> most original<lb/>
and most precise in the whole history of science. But before the world could<lb/>
accept his ideas many others, to be exact over a score of others,<lb/>
had to contribute their brains, their courage and, if need be, their lives.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04415003"/>
<p>(2</p>
<p>Including first the inspired Dr Finlay these 25 men were<lb/>
3 Cubans, 4 Spaniards, 1 Irishman, 1 Englishman and 16 Americans.<lb/>
Some were Catholic, some were Protestant, some were Hebrews. United<lb/>
in a <del><unclear></unclear></del> common cause they comprised a unique &ldquo;science-club,&rdquo;<lb/>
and one of history's finest examples of humanitarian cooperation.<lb/>
That these men lived and worked here among <unclear>your citizens</unclear><lb/>
of Havana and Marianao must be a matter of tremendous<lb/>
<unclear>satisfaction</unclear>.</p>
<p>To these men and to their Christian ideals of brotherly love<lb/>
Mrs Hench and I pay our most humble tribute.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
