<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04412002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, January 3, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04412002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-01-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Spies, Tom D.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-01-03">January 3, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04412002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, January 3, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is concerned about his responsibilities connected with the Congress on Nutrition and Vitaminology in Havana. He has received conflicting information regarding dates and paper submissions.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-01-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, January 3, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04412002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-01-03">January 3, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Tom D. Spies<lb/>
Nutrition Clinic<lb/>
Hillman Hospital<lb/>
Birmingham, Alabama<lb/>
<salute>My dear Tom:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sending you herewith two copies of my semi-final, unedited version. But<lb/>
I really don't know exactly for what purpose it is to be used.</p>
<p>In writing you the following, please do not consider me as being critical of<lb/>
you or my other hosts but I have been disturbed to find that my understanding<lb/>
of the responsibilities which I took on when I accepted this kind invitation<lb/>
has been confused if not incorrect and as a result of the confusion I have<lb/>
had to drop other urgent material and prepare the enclosed preliminary manu-<lb/>
script a couple of weeks before I thought I would have to do so and even now<lb/>
am sending you a manuscript which is certainly too long for presentation,<lb/>
which must be revised here and there and which is undoubtedly too long for<lb/>
publication in your proceedings.</p>
<p>I have had to spend much of my Christmas week, daytime as well as evenings,<lb/>
preparing this tentative draft and as I say, I don't quite know why but<lb/>
let me review some of our correspondence to show you at least the source<lb/>
of some of my confusion. I realize of course that in organizing this congress<lb/>
you have been carrying on undoubtedly an extensive correspondence with many<lb/>
people and cannot be expected to remember exactly what you might have told<lb/>
any one man at any one time.</p>
<p>Regarding the duration of the congress, in your letter of July 25 to me you<lb/>
stated that the congress would be held &ldquo;between the 20th and 26th of January.&rdquo;<lb/>
These dates were repeated in your letter of August 3, &ldquo;The congress itself<lb/>
will be from the 20th of January through the 26th.&rdquo; But on September 8 I<lb/>
had a letter from Doctor <unclear>Vieta</unclear> which stated that the congress &ldquo;will take<lb/>
place in Havana, Cuba, Friday January 25. It will begin at 8:30 a.m. and<lb/>
it will end at 6 p.m.&rdquo; When I then wrote and asked you for clarification<lb/>
of this apparent contradiction, you wrote me on September 21 that there<lb/>
would be a number of functions that you would like to have me attend if<lb/>
I could be there on the 23rd and 24th. You did not tell me what <unclear>these</unclear><lb/>
functions were. In your letter of October 1 you stated that &ldquo;The Cubans<lb/>
may have Latin speakers on the 23rd and 24th or may decide to have a function<lb/>
for the North Americans....The 25th is North American Day.&rdquo; I still am<lb/>
uncertain as to what obligations I will have on the 23rd or 24th or on the<lb/>
evening of the 25th. If the papers are all in Spanish on the 23rd and 24th<lb/>
as your letter implies and also are all on metabolism and nutrition, I had<lb/>
not expected to attend those meetings, but of course I will do what you wish<lb/>
me to do and will attend what functions it seems appropriate for me to attend.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04412003"/>
<p>Dr. Tom D. Spies</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>January 3, 1952</p>
<p>However I do wish that you would clarify my confusion. I would like to<lb/>
know just what I am getting into, whether there are other times when I<lb/>
might be called upon for discussions, informal remarks or luncheon or<lb/>
dinner remarks. I am no good at impromptu speaking. I am willing to<lb/>
tackle whatever is expected of me but only if I know ahead of time and can<lb/>
collect my thoughts.</p>
<p>Regarding the title of my talk, that was requested by you on September 15<lb/>
and was sent to you by me on September 18.</p>
<p>Regarding a summary of the talk, Doctor <unclear>Vieta's</unclear> letter of September 8 and<lb/>
your previous correspondence made no mention of a summary being necessary.<lb/>
In your letter of November 7 you ask for a summary, to be translated into<lb/>
Spanish for the program. I had to write you and tell you unfortunately that<lb/>
for many months now my obligations have been such that I have gone from one<lb/>
responsibility to another, finishing each just in the nick of time and have<lb/>
been rarely able to start whatever I had to do for the next meeting more than<lb/>
a couple of weeks ahead of time; therefore I asked you to be indulgent with<lb/>
me and told you that I had a number of things to do before I could get to the<lb/>
summary or the paper, not one word of which I had yet written. I was unable<lb/>
to get this for you until a short time ago and I am sure that you now have it.</p>
<p>Regarding publication of the paper, from my conversations with you and your<lb/>
early letters, I was led to believe that my participation in the congress was<lb/>
to be a rather casual one, that you didn't care much what I talked about and<lb/>
in reviewing our correspondence between April 16 and September 15, no mention<lb/>
was made of publication. In my last paragraph to you, letter of September 18,<lb/>
I stated &ldquo;If I remember rightly you told me I would not have to publish the<lb/>
paper. This would be a great help.&rdquo; I continued to assume that <unclear>because</unclear> in<lb/>
your letters of September 21 and 26 there was no mention of publication.<lb/>
But &ldquo;the blow fell&rdquo; when you wrote me on October 1 and stated that you did want<lb/>
&ldquo;a brief paper to be published &ldquo;in a little volume&rdquo; put out by the Journal<lb/>
of Vitamin Research. I assumed that this volume would constitute a record of<lb/>
the proceedings of the congress and not having heard of such a volume being<lb/>
put out before the Congress, I assumed that I would certainly not have to<lb/>
have anything but a speaking version ready before the Congress. But in your<lb/>
letter of October 16 you first stated that you wanted my paper &ldquo;well in ad-<lb/>
vance of the meeting as the Journal wants to set up the issue so that it can<lb/>
be published promptly.&rdquo; Although I was greatly concerned about the need for<lb/>
having any kind of a formal or semi-formal manuscript before the meeting (other<lb/>
than a speaking version and an abstract), I assumed still that publication of<lb/>
the paper by the journal would occur of course sometime after the congress<lb/>
and this notion seemed to be confirmed by the remark in your letter of Novem-<lb/>
ber 7 that you wanted the summary ahead of time for translation into Spanish<lb/>
for the programs. Therefore I was considerably disturbed when, on November 9,<lb/>
I received from Miss Maria Luisa Mas, Executive Secretary of FIM, a request<lb/>
for my whole paper. I wrote her that I was so involved in other work that I<lb/>
could not finish it much before the first of the year. I asked her whether<lb/>
she needed for translation in the program an abstract or the whole paper.<lb/>
This was in my letter to her of November 20, but I had no reply. In your<lb/>
letter of November 21 you requested an abstract or the paper for translation<lb/>
for the program. Then in your letter of December 13, instead of asking for<lb/>
the abstract <hi>or</hi> paper, you asked for the abstract <hi>and</hi> paper, to be sent off<lb/>
to the journal.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04412004"/>
<p>Dr. Tom D. Spies</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>January 3, 1952</p>
<p>I think, Tom, you will see, if you have read the above with patience and<lb/>
not too much annoyance at me, the source of my confusion. As the requests<lb/>
changed from one thing to another, there was nothing I could do about it as<lb/>
I had already committed myself irrevocably to certain undeniable obliga-<lb/>
tions. For example, I have given two rather important after-dinner banquet<lb/>
talks recently, the talks to be published, and I have been working on two<lb/>
manuscripts that had to be presented in New York recently. I just want you<lb/>
to understand why you are now receiving a version which I certainly don't<lb/>
want published as it is, either before or after the meeting. As I said above,<lb/>
the manuscript needs revision and much condensation and shortening for the<lb/>
purposes of your journal. Because since only a relatively small part of the<lb/>
paper concerns nutrition and vitamins, you will want me to preserve that in<lb/>
toto and sharply abstract most of the rest.</p>
<p>You will ask me why did <unclear>I write this</unclear> sort of a version to begin with. Again<lb/>
I must tell you that I am in the position of not being able to write a new<lb/>
paper just for one function and I have promised to give another talk in<lb/>
January; therefore this paper as you are receiving it, is really for that<lb/>
meeting and an abstract of this paper was to be for your meeting. Each<lb/>
of us has his own way of working and I modify my methods somewhat to suit<lb/>
the requirements, but in this instance, because of the fact that I was<lb/>
trying to kill two birds with one stone, I had to write the long version<lb/>
first and then will make an abstract.</p>
<p>Now, if despite the uncertainties in the correspondence, the Journal of<lb/>
Vitamin Research is about to publish this almost immediately, I think<lb/>
they will have to do one of three things: (a) Omit my paper and merely<lb/>
publish the abstract that I sent you, of (b) Wait until I can make an<lb/>
abstract of this version which will be done in the next two weeks but<lb/>
which probably will not be edited with all the bibliography, etc., until<lb/>
after I return from Cuba, or (c) Have someone make whatever sort of <unclear>on</unclear><lb/>
short version of this they think is suitable for the Journal and then, above<lb/>
all, send that to our Editorial Department for their quick review and ap-<lb/>
proval. Our Editorial Department would certainly not be happy if I published<lb/>
anything that did not go through their department. That is an established<lb/>
policy of the Clinic which has been extremely useful for all of us.</p>
<p>Now, Tom, <unclear>as I</unclear> say, I hope that having called the above things to your<lb/>
attention will not annoy you. I feel that since I have not been able<lb/>
to fulfill the recent requests which you and Miss Mas made, that I<lb/>
perhaps might be considered guilty of having misunderstood the obliga-<lb/>
tions, If <unclear>i id</unclear>, it was from lack of specific information early enough<lb/>
and because of the apparent confusion and changing request which I have<lb/>
mentioned above. Actually, I have yet to outline my slides. They must<lb/>
be done in the next two weeks because I want now slides made as I am<lb/>
sick and tired of the papers that I have given during 1951 and regarding<lb/>
that, feel very talked out indeed.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
