<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04413001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Speech: Not by Bread Alone, by Philip Showalter Hench, January 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04413001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-01-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, John</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-01-00">January 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04413001</idno>
<title>Speech: Not by Bread Alone, by Philip Showalter Hench, January 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench's speech, for the Congress on Nutrition and Vitaminology, discusses nutrition and the importance of the enrichment of flour.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1952-01-00">
<head>Speech: Not by Bread Alone, by Philip Showalter Hench, January 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04413001"/>
<p>&ldquo;NOT BY BREAD ALONE - - -&rdquo;<lb/>
Remarks by<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
The Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn.</p>
<p>Mrs. Hench and I always enjoy coming back to Cuba to see the many friends who<lb/>
have been so kind to us. Some of you may know that for fifteen years I have made<lb/>
a study of the conquest of yellow fever, the fundamentals of which were developed<lb/>
by Cuba's Dr. Carlos Finl<del>e</del><add>a</add>y, one of the world's greatest benefactors. One of my<lb/>
pleasant assignments on this trip is to present the official request of Surgeon<lb/>
General Armstrong for copies of certain documents about Dr. Finl<del>e</del><add>a</add>y for the Surgeon<lb/>
General's library in Washington.</p>
<p>A year ago when I left Havana after the impressive and colorful dedication of<lb/>
&ldquo;Campamento Lazear&rdquo; I took a set of Cuban stamps to my ten year old son John and this<lb/>
pleased him very much. A few days ago, knowing that I was coming here again he brought<lb/>
me his album to show me his collection of Cuban stamps. Of course he wanted me to see<lb/>
<hi>not</hi> the ones he <hi>had</hi> but the ones he <hi>didn't</hi> have and I expect to take the hint!</p>
<p>One of the fascinations of postage stamps is that they reveal so much of the<lb/>
history, culture and aspirations of each nation. Your stamps have appropriately<lb/>
honored the memory of those who established &ldquo;Cuba Libre&rdquo; - such distinguished military<lb/>
and political heroes as Maceo, Maximo Gomez, Jose Marti, Ignacio Agramonte, Calixto<lb/>
Garcia, Carlos Manuel de Cespedes and others.</p>
<p>The postage stamps of Cuba also reflect your very real and progressive interest<lb/>
in medical science and public health. Disseminated throughout the world have been<lb/>
your colorful stamps honoring Carlos Finl<del>e</del><add>a</add>y Nicolas Gutierrez, the Curies, our own<lb/>
Clara Ma<add>a</add>ss who died here and whom you have so graciously remembered, and others.<lb/>
Additional stamps bear witness to your war against disease and disability, and<lb/>
especially to your concern for the health of mothers and children.</p>
<p>Your sanitarians and physicians have rightly earned your respect and support<lb/>
for they have made Cuba one of the healthiest as well as one of the loveliest spots<lb/>
on earth. On each visit I have been impressed by the continuing development of new<lb/>
hospitals, clinics and public health units.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04413002"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>These activities reveal your faith in two complementary concepts: 1. to be<lb/>
healthy a nation must be &ldquo;happy&rdquo;, and conversely 2. to be happy a nation must be<lb/>
healthy. But unfortunately it is no easy task for the sociologist and social<lb/>
legislator to define and provide &ldquo;national happiness&rdquo;, nor can national health be<lb/>
insured except through the earnest, ever-continuing efforts of many cooperating<lb/>
agencies and people.</p>
<p>Now, I am informed, you are to make a new advance of considerable importance to<lb/>
public health - namely the enrichment of flour. For some years this same problem has<lb/>
engaged the attention of experts in my country, one of whom has been my teacher and<lb/>
long-time colleague on the staff of the Mayo Clinic - Dr. Russell Wilder.</p>
<p>One may say: &ldquo;But food is plentiful in Cuba and in the United States. Surely<lb/>
we can eat enough bread and other food to keep us healthy. Why should we think of<lb/>
enriching flour? What's wrong with ordinary flour and bread? If I miss anything<lb/>
in ordinary bread surely I get it with the rest of my food!&rdquo;</p>
<p>That was the belief of our forebears. But, because of certain scientific<lb/>
developments, we now know that <del>optinal</del><add>optimal</add> nutrition cannot necessarily be guaranteed<lb/>
for the individual who eats solely according to his personal food preferences.</p>
<p>Through the exercise of his intelligence man has learned through the centuries<lb/>
how to modify his environment to meet his needs. By the use of suitable clothing,<lb/>
shelter and various mechanical devices he regulates his temperature, and of late<lb/>
even his atmosphere, so that he can live with reasonable comfort in the artics or<lb/>
in the tropics, in the low deserts or high on the mountains and can fly far above<lb/>
the highest peaks. Thus, too, he has developed a large measure of protection against<lb/>
his enemies of the animal and bacterial kingdoms.</p>
<p>To insure adequate food and drink man has domesticated animals and fowls, built<lb/>
reservoirs and aqueducts and developed agriculture so successfully that, in the United<lb/>
States at least, the labor of one man is sufficient to feed fourteen others.</p>
<p>Till recent times man was concerned more about the quantity than the quality<lb/>
of his food: his primary aim was to get enough food to satisfy hunger. Whatever<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04413003"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
food choices he made were based on taste and sight, i.e. he selected what looked or<lb/>
tasted good. We now know that such food habits commonly provided diets devoid or<lb/>
deficient in certain essentials necessary for life or at least for the best of health.<lb/>
Hence many of our ancestors were not as healthy or as long-lived as they should have<lb/>
been. Theirs was still an era when only the fittest survived.</p>
<p>Then <del>our grandparents</del><add>the <unclear>chemists</unclear></add>, learning the early fundamentals of food chemistry, discovered<lb/>
that there was more to proper eating than the mere gratification of taste or gratifica-<lb/>
tion of hunger - to maintain health one must have a certain ratio of proteins, carbo-<lb/>
hudrates and fats.</p>
<p>But along with his growing knowledge of food requirements <del>our grandparents</del><add>we have</add><lb/>
developed more and more food preferences, and also made important changes in the<lb/>
preparation of food. Meats were processed by high temperatures; certain meats and<lb/>
many vegetables were canned. These processes led to greater purity and long preserva-<lb/>
tion of food. Our forebears turned from coarse flour and rough, brown bread to refined<lb/>
flour and white bread. Developing a progressive liking for sugar they came to desire<lb/>
and eat less <del>protein.</del><add>of other foods</add>.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the science of nutrition was advancing rapidly. One's daily diet, if<lb/>
regarded simply in terms of calories of protein, carbohydrates and fats became in-<lb/>
adequate and outmoded. Instead, a &ldquo;proper diet&rdquo; was one which would supply at regular<lb/>
intervals at least 30 or more specific nutrients: at least 8 essential protein-fractions<lb/>
called amino acids, several vitamins, and <add>the</add> mineral salts of sodium, potassium, calcium,<lb/>
iron, etc. Many of these are essential to life, <del>and</del> cannot be produced in the body, and<lb/>
must therefore be present in our daily ration of food.</p>
<p>Armed with this knowledge nutritionists began, about 15 years ago, to view the<lb/>
more sophisticated food habits of the American public with growing concern.</p>
<p>They found that the processing of meats by high temperatures often lowered their<lb/>
nutritional value. Although the canning and processing of vegetables has been of<lb/>
great practical value, some vitamins and amino acids are hurt thereby. Of particular<lb/>
concern was the effect of refinement on bread, the staff of life. The flour used by<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04413004"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
our grandmothers for baking bread was ground between stones, whereas ours is ground<lb/>
between steel rolls. To cater to the public's marked preference for refined flour and<lb/>
white bread American millers subject the whole wheat to 36 manipulations so as to<lb/>
separate as completely as possible the endosperm or white flour from the wheat germ<lb/>
and bran shorts. According to my colleague, Dr. Wilder, such processing reduces<lb/>
100 pounds of whole wheat to 30 pounds of &ldquo;feed&rdquo; for cattle and 70 pounds of refined<lb/>
flour. The latter is whiter but its vitamin content is markedly reduced.</p>
<p>This patent milling process (according to Dr. Sebrell of the U. S. Public Health<lb/>
Service, one of America's outstanding experts on nutrition) deprives natural flour<lb/>
of 90% of its thiamine (vitamin B1) and from 70% to 85% of its niacin (nicotinic acid),<lb/>
riboflavin (vitamin B2) and iron. As a result, the 70 pounds of refined flour used by<lb/>
man are much less nutritious than the residual 30 pounds of &ldquo;feed&rdquo; given to animals.<lb/>
The part discarded by us contains practically all of the thiamine and most of several<lb/>
other vitamins originally in the whole wheat. Hence in this respect animals are better<lb/>
fed than man.</p>
<p>Although the refinement of flour provided a potential source of vitamin deficiency,<lb/>
in view of the use of other foods was there an actual nutritional deficiency in our<lb/>
&ldquo;land of plenty&rdquo;? Careful surveys of various experts uncovered many signs of such<lb/>
deficiency. Surveys of food consumption showed (1939) that the diets of many Americans<lb/>
were deficient in thiamine, niacin, riboflavin and iron. Pellagra, caused by a<lb/>
deficiency of niacin and possibly also of riboflavin, was prevalent in various regions<lb/>
and caused a significant number of deaths. Furthermore many persons were found to<lb/>
suffer from (otherwise) unexplained lack of vigor and &ldquo;ill health&rdquo; - conditions which<lb/>
have been produced experimentally in human volunteers given food low in thiamine.<lb/>
<hi>Also a paradox was uncovered: certain persons could be obese and yet present evidence<lb/>
of specific nutritional deficiencies.</hi></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
