<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04410004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Interview with Philip Showalter Hench by a Cuban newspaper, [1952]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04410004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Murphy, William P.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-00-00">[1952]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04410004</idno>
<title>Interview with Philip Showalter Hench by a Cuban newspaper, [1952]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This interview transcription includes questions posed to Hench by a Cuban newspaper and Hench's answers. Hench expresses appreciation for receiving the Order of Finlay. He explains his thoughts on preserving Camp Lazear and emphasizes the cooperation that took place among people of different countries and different religions in discovering the cause of yellow fever. He also discusses his interest in hormones, particularly cortisone, hydrocortisone, and corticotropin.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1952-00-00">
<head>Interview with Philip Showalter Hench by a Cuban newspaper, [1952]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04410004"/>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>ANSWERS TO NEWSPAPER QUESTIONS</hi><lb/>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH, THE MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
<hi>ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA</hi></head>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION 1:</hi> Have you something to say to the people of Cuba in virtue of the Con-<lb/>
decoration of the Orden Finlay which you have just received from the hands of the<lb/>
Minister Dr. Andreu?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi>.- Please see a copy of my expression of appreciation. In addition may I<lb/>
say that, being a sentimentalist, I am particularly happy to have received this<lb/>
MURPHY<lb/>
honor in company with Dr. William P. Murphy whom I admire so much as physician and<lb/>
man, and whom I have been privileged to know as a friend for many years. Dr. Murphy<lb/>
is such a quiet and modest gentleman and is one of my country's greatest physician.<lb/>
The discovery by Drs. Minot and Murphy in Boston about 20 years ago that pernicious<lb/>
anemia could be controlled by liver extract has saved countless lives and will save<lb/>
the lives of future millions.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION 2</hi>: What is your opinion regarding the project of the Cuban government to<lb/>
preserve &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; in Quemados de Marianao?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER.</hi>- I am delighted to learn that the Cuban government is completing plans to<lb/>
preserve and memorialize the remains of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; which was part of the old Fin-<lb/>
ca San Jos&eacute; in Quemados. This location occupies a unique place in medical history<lb/>
and in Cuban-American relationships.</p>
<p>At the Finca San Jos&eacute; Dr. Carlos Finlay performed a few of his earliest inoculations<lb/>
for experimental yellow fever on volunteers of the Jesui<del>s</del>t Brotherhood, among them<lb/>
Padre Urra. Many years later Major Walter Reed, head of the Yellow Fever Board of<lb/>
the United States Army chose the very same location upon which, with the cordial co-<lb/>
operation of the owner Dr. Ignacio Rojas, to erect an experimental camp for the<lb/>
development of yellow f<del>i</del><add>e</add>ver in volunteers. This was named &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; in honor of<lb/>
the heroic martyr Dr. Jesse Lazear who had died as a result of the preliminary ex-<lb/>
periments.</p>
<p>As the investigations developed so successfully between November 1900 and Feb 1901<lb/>
Dr. Finlay in great delight visited the camp with Major Reed and his associates, Drs.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04410005"/>
Aristides Agramonte and James Carroll.</p>
<p>Here at last was unmistakable proof of the truth of the ideas hold so long and so<lb/>
tenaciously by Dr. Finlay.</p>
<p>Every human heart meeds inspiration, inspiration from the One on High and inspiration<lb/>
from one's fellow man. For years physicians like myself have been inspired by the<lb/>
wonderful story of the conquest of yellow fever.</p>
<p>So co<del>n</del><add>m</add>plicated was the terrible problem of yelIlow fever that no one man, however<lb/>
great ho might be, could alone solve completely its mystery. Before the world could<lb/>
accept the far-sighted ideas of Dr. Finlay a score of others had to contribute their brains,<lb/>
their courage and if necessary their lives. One of those who contributed so much was<lb/>
that lovable Irish-American-Cuban, Johny Moran, who lived his life here among you un-<lb/>
til he died last year.</p>
<p>Including first the inspired Dr. Finlay and his devoted associate Claudio Delgado,<lb/>
these 25 men were 3 Cubans, 1 Englishman, 1 Irishman, 4 Spaniards and 16 Americans.<lb/>
Some were Catholic, some Protestant, some Hebrews, United in a common cause they pro-<lb/>
history's<lb/>
vided one of history's finest examples of humanitarian cooperation and brotherly<lb/>
love.</p>
<p>That these men lived and accomplished their great service here among you citizens<lb/>
of Havana and Marianao must be a source of great satisfaction. Thus Camp Lazear<lb/>
constitutes a place, where, perhaps above all other locations, were united the hopes<lb/>
and aspirations, the fears, gallantry and courage of this dedicated group of men.<lb/>
When the plans of Dr. Andreu and his associates for Camp Lazear have <add>been</add> finished, this<lb/>
place will, I am sure, give great inspiration to those who visit it. Many civilian<lb/>
and military physicians in my country will feel that they owe your country a debt<lb/>
of gratitude when the learn of this gracious act of yours.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION 3</hi>: What will be your contribution to the Congress on Nutrition and Vita-<lb/>
minology now in session in Havana?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER.-</hi> My own interests have been primarily, not in the fields of vitamins and<lb/>
nutrition, but in the fields of hormones and rheumatic diseases. But many of the<lb/>
hormones, especially the newest ones, cortisone, hydrocortisone and corticotropin<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04410006"/>
handle<lb/>
(ACT5) influence the way our bodies handle most, sugars, starches, fat and enzymes.<lb/>
Among others Dr. Tom Spies and his colleagues here at the Medical School of Havana<lb/>
who have been carrying out their important nutritional studies, with the support<lb/>
of the Fundacion de Investigaciones M&eacute;dicas, have developed evidence which indicates<lb/>
the the body's production of the hormone, cortisone, in adequate amounts, may depend<lb/>
in a large measure upon the available supply of one of the vitamins. So once again<lb/>
that<lb/>
we find <unclear>that</unclear> all parts of medical science are, in fact, closely related.</p>
<p>This Congress on nutrition affords a splendid opportunity for scientists in various<lb/>
share<lb/>
fields to share with each other their views and knowledge. It is particularly<lb/>
pleasant for a Minnesota &ldquo;snow-baby&rdquo; like myself to enjoy this exchange of ideas<lb/>
under the salubrious, blue skie<del><unclear></unclear></del><add>s</add> of Havana. The twenty-second parallel is a fine<lb/>
location for a medical congress in winter-time!</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION A</hi>: Can you tell us briefly what is the position of cortisone and ACTH in<lb/>
the treatment of rheumatic and arthritic patients?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER A.-</hi> The new hormones cortisone and ACTH do not actually &ldquo;cure&rdquo; rheumatic fever<lb/>
<del>of</del><add>or</add> the disabling rheumatoid type of arthritis, in the ordinary sense. Instead they<lb/>
suppress markedly the inflamatory reactions in these and many other conditions,<lb/>
thus controlling symptoms.</p>
<p><unclear>Those</unclear> hormones are the most powerful ones ever discovered. Their effects are so<lb/>
striking and wide-spread that investigators have only begun to learn what we want<lb/>
much<lb/>
to know about them. So much remains to be learned, but much important information<lb/>
in being accumulated rapidly.</p>
<p>Although these hormones still belong as much, if not more, to the physiologists<lb/>
and clinical investigators, than they do to the general practitioners and rheumatism<lb/>
specialists they are already most useful, indeed irreplaceable, in the management<lb/>
of a number of illnesses.</p>
<p>Because in most cases the effects of cortisone and ACTH (corticotropin) do not last<lb/>
long after their administration has been stopped, the hormones are, up to the present,<lb/>
more useful and easier to handle in the treatment of acute self-limiting conditions<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04410007"/>
eyes, severe<lb/>
such as acute rheumatic fever, certain acute inflamations of the <unclear>eyes, severe</unclear> acute<lb/>
asthma, the acute allergies, and <add>when</add> other severe reactions of hypersensitivity to certain<lb/>
drugs and toxins develop.</p>
<p>As a result of three years experience my colleagues and I at the Mayo Clinic and<lb/>
certain other American rheumatologists believe that cortisone and ACTH can be used<lb/>
safely and with great satisfaction in many cases of chronic<lb/>
rheumatoid arthritis. Many patients mildly affected need the older, simpler, cheaper<lb/>
<unclear>remedice</unclear>. But for severely or progressively disabled patients, especially those<lb/>
unresponsive to other measures, the long-continued use of these hormones, especially<lb/>
of cortisone which can be taken by mouth, in carefully adjusted dos<del>i</del><add>e</add>s, constitutes a<lb/>
very promising form of treatment which may be the one of choice in selected cases.<lb/>
Success depends on the careful individualized scheme of dosage selected for each<lb/>
patient, becaus<add>e</add> the appropriate and safe dose varies in different cases, and from<lb/>
time to time in the same case.</p>
<p>The current policy is to provide as much relief as possible with dos<del>i</del><add>e</add>s which do not<lb/>
produce undesirable &ldquo;side-effects&rdquo;.</p>
<p>A new long-acting preparation of ACTH is now available and soon there will be<lb/>
available greater supplies of the newest hormone, hydrocortisone, which is also anti-<lb/>
rheumatic and which holds much promise for future usefulness.</p></item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
