<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04414001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Felipe Carbonell to the President of the Lion's Club of Havana, the Minister of Public Health, and the President of the Academy of Sciences, January 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04414001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-01-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">San Martin, Ramon Grau</name>
<name type="person">de Cardenas, Raul</name>
<name type="person">Colete, Honorato</name>
<name type="person">Salas, Manual</name>
<name type="person">Salas, William</name>
<name type="person">Kendall, Edward C.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados de Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-01-00">January 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04414001</idno>
<title>Letter from Felipe Carbonell to the President of the Lion's Club of Havana, the Minister of Public Health, and the President of the Academy of Sciences, January 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carbonell describes Hench's investigations into the yellow fever experiments and the actual location of Camp Lazear. He praises Hench as a physician and a friend while advocating the support of Hench's plans by the Cuban government.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-01-00">
<head>Letter from Felipe Carbonell to the President of the Lion's Club of Havana, the Minister of Public Health, and the President of the Academy of Sciences, January 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04414001"/>
<opener>
Mr. President of the Lion's Club of Havana.<lb/>
Mr. Minister of the Public Health.<lb/>
Mr. President of the Academy of Sciences.<lb/>
<salute>Gentlemen:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On June 2nd. - 1941, at the unveiling of &ldquo;The Conquerors of Ye-<lb/>
llow Fever&rdquo;, painted by the american artist Dean Cornwell, Dr.<lb/>
Philip S. Hench, of the Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn. made an<lb/>
explanatory speech of the painting. This speech was published<lb/>
in one of the Proceedings edited weekly by the Clinic and also<lb/>
in the panphlet that I have the pleasure of offering you.</p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Carbonell</p>
<p>It is easy to explain why Dr. Hench was chosen to do that work.<lb/>
To that purpose we are going to read an article that we broadcasted<lb/>
on January 16th-1942, through the Station of Brothers William<lb/>
and Manuel Salas who courteously offered it.</p>
<p>The article reads as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Leaving aside the scientific discussions that alwayas kept alive<lb/>
the question of the conquest of Yellow Fever, we can assure that<lb/>
the historical &lsquo;caseta&rsquo;, (barrack) of Camp Lazear was sunken in the<lb/>
dark clouds of oblivion until our times when it is rented to a<lb/>
family who actually lives there.</p>
<p>It was believed that Camp Lazear was located at the place where<lb/>
for a long time, a hospital dedicated to yellow fever patients was<lb/>
located, right by the tracks of the railroad that from Quemados de<lb/>
Marianao goes to Marianao Beach. What was the cause of this confu-<lb/>
sion? We have to confess that we don't know it. But if we consider<lb/>
that when Dr. Lazear became <add>ill</add> of the cruel sickness that he was in-<lb/>
vestigating, he was taken to said hospital where he finally died,<lb/>
we can blame to this fact <del>the</del> completely or in part, the error<lb/>
committed.</p>
<p>A tree surounded by a fence, and we have been informed that there<lb/>
existed also a small memorial, is the place that we are talking<lb/>
about.</p>
<p>That was the situation when Dr. Philip S. Hench arrived at Havana<lb/>
with the purpose of solving this question. It was this distinguished<lb/>
american phisician, in honor to truth, who located and identified<lb/>
Camp Lazear. Dr. Hench, with the advise of those who had been there<lb/>
while the experiments took place, perusing photographs and documents<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04414002"/>
-2-<lb/>
including the rent receipts, stablished beyond doubt, the identity<lb/>
and site of the caseta.</p>
<p>On other hand...What is Camp Lazear?. We'll explain it in a few<lb/>
words.</p>
<p>After Lazear's death and having the Comission in its hands enough<lb/>
details, united to those most valuable that appeared in Lazear's<lb/>
note-book found in his uniform, and having returned Dr. Reid of his<lb/>
trip to Wshington, the Comission decided to make the necessary<lb/>
experiments to prove that contagion couldn't be made by the clothes<lb/>
and objects of the patients of Yellow Fever: and then, prove and<lb/>
show, beyond doubt, that the sickness was only transmitted by the<lb/>
mosquito, according with what for 19 years had been proclaimed by<lb/>
the famous cuban doctor Carlos Finlay.</p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Carbonell</p>
<p>A far distant place, the San Jos&eacute; Farm was selected for that pur-<lb/>
pose and two barracks were built, Building No. 1 and Building No. 2,<lb/>
to-gether both were named Camp Lazear, as a homage to the deceased<lb/>
medical colleague. In building No. 1, the experiments were made to<lb/>
demonstrate that contagion by the objects of the patients was not<lb/>
possible; and in building No. 2, the inoculations by the mosquito<lb/>
bites, were made.&rdquo;</p>
<p>To here the article.</p>
<p>You all know that Mr. John F. Moran, the last of those who volun-<lb/>
teered to be bitten by the mosquito, recently died at Havana.</p>
<p>It was in the house of this extraordinary man, an excellent friend<lb/>
of mine, located in 25th St. between B and C, Vedado, where I had the<lb/>
high honor of being introduced to Dr. Philip S. Hench and to his<lb/>
lovely wife. Dr. Hench, to whom I had been writing, had come to Hava-<lb/>
na with the idea of making a Cuban-American Monument to the conque-<lb/>
rors of Yellow Fever and he had the initial offering of $10.000 to<lb/>
be donated by the Mayo Clinic; he also told me that the medical doctors<lb/>
of the United States would give a strong amount to build the monument.</p>
<p>A week or ten days after I had met Dr. Hench at Mr. Moran's house,<lb/>
I was called by Dr. Hench who told me that he was to leave Havana<lb/>
in about two days and that he was disappointed, because he had not<lb/>
succeeded in getting an interview with the President, at that time<lb/>
Dr. Ram&oacute;n Grau San Mart&iacute;n.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04414003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><unclear>Regr<add>e</add>tting</unclear> the little attention paid to Dr. Hench, a medical doc-<lb/>
tor of a Clinic that I had had the pleasure of visiting twice and where<lb/>
I have friends that had kindly cumplimented me, I remembered that I<lb/>
told him; &ldquo;Well, you couldn't see the President, and it would be very<lb/>
difficult for me to obtain an appointment with him in such a short<lb/>
time, but to-night you'll see the Vice-President&rdquo;.</p>
<p>After a telephone call to my distinguished friend Mr. Ra&uacute;l de<lb/>
C&aacute;rdenas and having had dinner in a Prado St. restaurant, Dr. Hench,<lb/>
his wife and I were kindly received, as it is his custom, by Mr.<lb/>
Ra&uacute;l de C&aacute;rdenas, at that time Vice-President of the Republic, who<lb/>
paid great attention to Dr. Hench and promised his full cooperation<lb/>
to the fulfillment of his plans.</p>
<p>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Carbonell</p>
<p>Next day, Dr. Hench and I visited my old friend Engineer Honorato<lb/>
Colete, here with us, <unclear>at<del>c</del></unclear> the Ministry of Public Works and si<add>n</add>ce that<lb/>
moment we have had the <del>pleasure</del> help of so valuable an ally in that<lb/>
Ministry. With Mr. Colete we visited the Assistant Secretary, and<lb/>
in his office, Dr. Hench, putting his hand in his pocket pretended<lb/>
to give to Mr. Colete or to me $1.000 to avoid the wreck of the caseta<lb/>
or as he said &ldquo;to prevent that the patient die while we are discussing<lb/>
the method<del>e</del> to save him&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Colete and I did not accept the generous offering, but we promised<lb/>
Dr. Hench all the aid that we could give. We have been doing so.</p>
<p>It is on account of this, that we are taking advantage of the<lb/>
brilliant oportunity presented to us by the Lions Club of Havana, to<lb/>
recall to everybody that it was Dr. Hench who localized the caseta<lb/>
of Camp Lazear and, further more, who made several trips to Cuba<lb/>
with the intention of building that monument.</p>
<p>But...Who is this Dr. Hench to whom we have been referring so often?</p>
<p>At that time he was a studious and distinguished medical doctor<lb/>
of one of the most famous Clinics in the world and the same time,<lb/>
a man as non-affected as he is agreable.</p>
<p>But, two, three, four years passed and to-day, Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
to the benefit of humanity and satisfaction of those that consider<lb/>
ourselves his friends, is the Nobel Prize of Medicine 1950, to-gether<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04414004"/>
-4-<lb/>
with Dr. Edward C. Kendall, also a member of that Mayo Clinic, so<lb/>
admired and loved by so many of us, for having made the discovery<lb/>
and firsts works with the Cortisone, that misterious hormone of the<lb/>
Supra-renal gland, called by many, the most important medical disco-<lb/>
very in the last years.</p>
<p>Gentlemen:</p>
<p>Realizing the principal part had by a scientist of<lb/>
so great personality and actuality, as Dr. Philip S. Hench has, in<lb/>
the discovery and location of the caseta at Camp Lazear, I am sure<lb/>
that, not only the Minister of Public Health, but the Lion's Club<lb/>
of Havana will back Dr. Hench's initiative and that he should be an<lb/>
honor guest of the cuban government, for the inauguration of the<lb/>
monument, to whose construction he has worked so much in this country<lb/>
in spite of the tremendous distance that separates him, from his<lb/>
brilliant activities and from his home.</p>
<closer>
<signed>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Felipe Carbonell</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
