<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04427002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed, August 11, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04427002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-08-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Lawrence</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Love, Albert G.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Landon</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-08-11">August 11, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04427002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed, August 11, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench doubts that the dedication of Camp Lazear will take place in September 1952. He does not think that the Cuban government will be able to pay travel expenses for the attendees, and suggests ways that the U.S. Army or government might pay for the Reeds and Truby to attend. Hench thinks it would be appropriate for the United States to have an official representative at the dedication, and suggests that Love approach the Surgeon General about this.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-08-11">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed, August 11, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04427002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-08-11">August 11, 1952</date>
</dateline>
General Walter L. Reed<lb/>
2810 Thirty-Sixth Place, N.W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Reed:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Although Doctor Nogueira still hopes that the dedication of Camp Lazear<lb/>
will be late in September and although I can see from the photographs he<lb/>
has sent me that the work of grading and so on is well along, I still<lb/>
doubt if it can be dedicated that soon. In any event, it would be a fine<lb/>
thing if you and Mrs. Reed could attend the dedication. I am doubtful<lb/>
that the Cuban Government will come across with much, if any, expense money<lb/>
for guests despite the suggestions of Doctor Nogueira's letter (enclosed).<lb/>
Do you think that the Surgeon General could remotivate you and possibly<lb/>
also General Truby and send you and your wives to Cuba at Army expense just<lb/>
long enough for the dedication, or would the Army or State Department have<lb/>
other ways of appointing you as an official representative?</p>
<p>Assuming that the dedication may be the end of September, I think it is<lb/>
imperative that the Surgeon General of the Army and the State Department<lb/>
be informed of the matter and of the various conflicts behind this project.<lb/>
Here is a wonderful chance to establish a new era in good feeling and get<lb/>
rid of the old anti-Reed era in Cuba. Obviously Doctor Nogueira is anxious<lb/>
to have appropriate American official sponsorship. I regret indeed that I<lb/>
am leaving this Wednesday for a long-planned two and a half weeks' vacation<lb/>
in Mexico. I enclose a letter I have sent to the Surgeon General. I wonder<lb/>
if there is any possibility that you and General Love could go over this<lb/>
data together and perhaps General Love could visit the Surgeon General first<lb/>
and later, if necessary, the appropriate persons in the State Department<lb/>
to see what they can do regarding representation. I can certainly see that<lb/>
you would not want yourself to make this suggestion or visit the Surgeon<lb/>
General in your own behalf. Certainly there should be a State Department<lb/>
representative and I suppose it might be the American Ambassador in Cuba.<lb/>
What is the possibility that Mrs. Blossom could go along with you and Mrs.<lb/>
Reed?</p>
<p>If you have any suggestions and if you want me to do anything, my mail will<lb/>
be forwarded to me, air mail, and I will handle matters from Mexico.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Copies sent to Generals Love and Truby<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
