<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04420009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">English translation [from Spanish] of the introduction to Philip Showalter Hench's presentation at the Conference on Vitamins and Nutrition in Havana, by [Pedro A. Castillo], [1952]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04420009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="place">Sweden</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-00-00">[1952]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04420009</idno>
<title>English translation [from Spanish] of the introduction to Philip Showalter Hench's presentation at the Conference on Vitamins and Nutrition in Havana, by [Pedro A. Castillo], [1952]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In an introduction to Hench's presentation at a Havana conference, [Castillo] gives an overview of Hench's Nobel prize winning research on arthritis and cortisone. See <xref id="f04420012">Spanish</xref> original.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1952-00-00">
<head>English translation [from Spanish] of the introduction to Philip Showalter Hench's presentation at the Conference on Vitamins and Nutrition in Havana, by [Pedro A. Castillo], [1952]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04420009"/>
<p>It is a great privilege for us this morning to have<lb/>
the opportunity of seeing and hearing one of the outstand-<lb/>
ing representatives of North American medicine today: Dr.<lb/>
Philip S. Hench, Professor of Medicine of the University<lb/>
of Minnesota, Director of Research in the Mayo Clinic and<lb/>
Chief of the Section of Rheumatic Diseases of that Insti-<lb/>
tution.</p>
<p>In obedience to one of the rules of this Conference,<lb/>
I have had to accept the honor of introducing our illustrious<lb/>
visitor to our assembled colleagues; having accepted the<lb/>
honor, however, I decline the mission: Dr. Hench needs no<lb/>
introduction.</p>
<p>He was introduced, not to us but to the entire Universe,<lb/>
as a man of exceptional merits on a Sunday afternoon, Decem-<lb/>
ber 10, 1950, when he received from the hands of His Majesty<lb/>
King Gustavus Adolphus of Sweden, the Nobel Prize of Physio-<lb/>
logy and Medicine, granted by the Royal Caroline Institute<lb/>
of Medicine and Surgery, together with Edward C. Kendall and<lb/>
Thaddeus Reichstein, &ldquo;for their discoveries in connection with<lb/>
cortico-adrenal hormones; their structure and biological ef-<lb/>
fects&rdquo;. This, indeed, is the highest distinction to which<lb/>
the genius and industry of man in the service of human happi-<lb/>
ness can aspire.</p>
<p>Davisson, the physicist, has said that &ldquo;the Nobel prize<lb/>
winner is transformed overnight from an extremely private ci-<lb/>
tizen into something like a semi-public institution&rdquo;, and Ken-<lb/>
dall adds that if he had received his prize in 1950, with all<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04420010"/>
-2-<lb/>
the pomp attendant upon the fiftieth anniversary of the<lb/>
foundation of the Nobel Prize, he surely would have left<lb/>
out the semi: the man emerges from the status of a private<lb/>
unit to that of a public Institution as the whole world<lb/>
looks on admiringly and applauds.</p>
<p>Any physician anywhere in the world who has followed<lb/>
the development of medical science in recent years must<lb/>
necessarily have read and pondered over the works of this<lb/>
man, to whom we are indebted for a direct contribution to<lb/>
the study and application of the cortico-adrenal hormones<lb/>
which have revolutionized endocrine physiology and which<lb/>
have so helped suffering humanity in the relief and elimi-<lb/>
nation of pain.</p>
<p>Hench was unquestionably a forerunner of these dis-<lb/>
coveries; intensely devoted to the study of rheumatoid<lb/>
arthritis (formerly called chronic infectious arthritis)<lb/>
and related affections, he pointed out in 1925 that the<lb/>
fatigue, weakness and hypotension common in these patients<lb/>
raised the possibility, in addition to the supposed infec-<lb/>
tious factor, of some metabolic disorder somehow related<lb/>
to the adrenal glands.</p>
<p>Four years later, in 1929, in observing that rheuma-<lb/>
toid arthritis patients usually improved when afflicted with<lb/>
jaundice, he insisted that it was not a fatal and progressive-<lb/>
ly uncontrollable disease, and he suggested the existence in<lb/>
such cases of some beneficial hepatic or biliar agent which<lb/>
for the time being could only be called &ldquo;antirheumatic subs-<lb/>
tance X&rdquo;.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04420011"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>In an article which was published on March 16, 1938,<lb/>
covering research conducted since 1931, he drew attention<lb/>
to the improvement caused by pregnancy in various chronic<lb/>
articular affections, and endeavored to establish some<lb/>
connection with the hypothetical substance X, which might<lb/>
be some bisexual esteroid hormone, whose action was not<lb/>
confined to articular affections but applied as well to<lb/>
other diseases such as asthma, migraine, psoriasis, etc.</p>
<p>In numerous conversations with <unclear>Kendall</unclear> efforts had<lb/>
been made, without success, to identify the supposed subs-<lb/>
tance X, and although the latter had isolated the so-called<lb/>
compound E, now known as Cortisone, from the suprarenal cortex<lb/>
since 1935, the minimum quantities obtained had not been suf-<lb/>
ficient for clinical use.</p>
<p>The cooperative research work of many scientists finally<lb/>
led in 1948 to an accomplishment of formidable scientific<lb/>
proportions and practical application: the use of powerful<lb/>
adrenal hormones, directly injected or stimulated by the<lb/>
pituitary corticotropine.</p>
<p>Now, more than a quarter of a century after having first<lb/>
advanced his theory about the hypothetical substance X, we<lb/>
shall listen with admiration and with special interest to<lb/>
this distinguished investigator, who has labored with such<lb/>
tenacity and persistence in furtherance of his farsighted<lb/>
conception.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
