<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04433023">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to the Acting Ambassador to Cuba, November 19, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04433023</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Quemados de Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-19">November 19, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04433023</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to the Acting Ambassador to Cuba, November 19, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes the upcoming Camp Lazear dedication and encourages the ambassador to attend, in support of Cuban-American friendship. He sends him background information explaining the delicacy of the situation and refers to the Finlay-Reed controversy.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to the Acting Ambassador to Cuba, November 19, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04433023"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-19">November 19, 1952</date>
</dateline>
His Excellency<lb/>
The Acting Ambassador to Cuba<lb/>
American Embassy<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>Your Excellency:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Perhaps you have already been informed that on December 3 certain Cuban<lb/>
officials will dedicate at the Finca San Jose, Quemados de Marianao, the<lb/>
old &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; where, in 1900-1901, Major Walter Reed, physician of the<lb/>
U. S. Army and his associates proved the correctness of the mosquito theory<lb/>
of the Cuban physician, Dr. Carlos Finlay. I sincerely hope that you and<lb/>
your colleagues have been invited to attend and participate in this ceremony<lb/>
which, though it may be modest, is of considerable significance as far as<lb/>
Cuban-American friendship, especially Cuban-American medical friendship,<lb/>
is concerned. When you receive the invitation, I hope most sincerely that<lb/>
you can accept and attend.</p>
<p>You are probably aware of the unfortunate debate which has continued for<lb/>
fifty years in Cuba, a debate concerning the supposed American neglect of<lb/>
Doctor Finlay in favor of Major Reed and his colleagues. There are many<lb/>
sincere Cuban physicians and officials who greatly regret this debate and<lb/>
who are joining together hoping that the Cuban memorialization of Camp<lb/>
Lazear will cause the unfortunate contention to be dropped. You are probably<lb/>
aware that until now not a single monument or honor to Reed exists in Cuba<lb/>
nor does his name even appear on tablets honoring Doctor Finlay and including<lb/>
at least some of Reed's subordinates. Therefore it is of considerable sig-<lb/>
nificance that the Cuban Government is officially honoring Camp Lazear and<lb/>
the Americans who so magnificently proved the correctness of Doctor Finlay's<lb/>
conception. They are making a gracious gesture and many in our country<lb/>
appreciate it greatly.</p>
<p>So that you may know of some of the delicate maneuvering that has preceded<lb/>
the ceremony of December 3, may I send you in confidence herewith three<lb/>
letters and a reprint. If you do not have time to read the reprint, may I<lb/>
earnestly request that your secretary make for you a synopsis of the letters.</p>
<p>General Paul Streit, Commanding General of Walter Reed Hospital, has been<lb/>
appointed by the Surgeon General of the U. S. Army to attend the ceremony<lb/>
and he will attend. I will officially represent the Mayo Foundation. The<lb/>
Mayo Foundation has asked me to honor Doctor Finlay by placing a wreath<lb/>
beneath the medallion when it is unveiled on December 3. It may well be<lb/>
that General Streit will be authorized to lay a wreath or wreaths in honor<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04433024"/>
His Excellency<lb/>
The Acting Ambassador to Cuba<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 19, 1952<lb/>
of Doctor Finlay and/or Major Reed. Whether or not you and your colleagues<lb/>
would care to do likewise I leave to you to consider and decide. If there<lb/>
might be a <unclear>plethora</unclear> of wreaths placed during the ceremonies, it might be<lb/>
well for General Streit or me to lay one on the grave of Doctor Finlay in<lb/>
a quiet little ceremony, attended we hope by your representative and a<lb/>
representative of the Cuban Government.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
