<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04435023">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Draft of speech and background notes for the dedication of the Camp Lazear Memorial, by Philip Showalter Hench, December 3, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04435023</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-12-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish">YES</term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Roderiguez Exposito, Cesar</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Chaille, Stanford L.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Pedroso family</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Warner, Lena</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Echeverria, Rafael F.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Indianapolis (Ind.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>16 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-12-03">December 3, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04435023</idno>
<title>Draft of speech and background notes for the dedication of the Camp Lazear Memorial, by Philip Showalter Hench, December 3, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In this draft, Hench discusses the Cuban-American cooperation underlying the conquest of yellow fever. He mentions the Havana Yellow Fever Commission of 1879 and the choice of the Finca San Jose as an experimental site because of its yellow fever immunity. He describes Finlay's mosquito hypothesis and experiments, and the initial lack of support for his theory. Finally, Hench outlines the work of Lazear and the Reed Commission, quotes Reed and Finlay, and concludes with praise for both the Cubans and Americans. [See 04435001 and 04435013 for a shorter draft, in Spanish and English, of the speech.]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1952-12-03">
<head>Draft of speech and background notes for the dedication of the Camp Lazear Memorial, by Philip Showalter Hench, December 3, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04435023"/>
<p><hi>THE HISTORIC ROLE OF THE FINCA SAN JOSE AND &ldquo;CAMP LAZEAR&rdquo; (QUEMADOS DE MARIANAO)<lb/>
IN THE CONQUEST OF YELLOW FEVER BY CARLOS FINLAY, WALTER REED AND THEIR ASSOCIATES</hi></p>
<p><hi>Background Notes</hi></p>
<p>(To be revised somewhat, condensed markedly, and presented at the<lb/>
Dedication of &ldquo;Camp Lazear,&rdquo; Habana, Cuba, December 3, 1952,) by<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
The Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota</p>
<p>Man is a forward looking creature with a backward looking mind. For in-<lb/>
spiration to solve the problems of today he often fruitfully turns to the dramatic<lb/>
events of the past. Thus he may search and wander over the face of the earth until<lb/>
that exciting moment when he can stop, and with the thrill of rediscovery, exclaim:<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi>This</hi> place - this is the <hi>very</hi> spot. <hi>Here</hi> is where it happened!&rdquo;</p>
<p>But too often he merely marks an &ldquo;X&rdquo; on a map and goes on his way. Ladies<lb/>
and gentlemen, that must not happen here for this is a place of tremendous significance.<lb/>
And it will not happen here because high officials of your government and distinguished<lb/>
Cuban physicians have a strong appreciation of spiritual values and of the historic<lb/>
perspective. Thus they wish the world to remember always that from this ancient Finca<lb/>
San Jose 52 years ago there was delivered to all the world the confirmation of a<lb/>
truth - a brilliant truth which changed despair into hope and gave the promise of<lb/>
life to countless millions.</p>
<p>President Batista, my countrymen are greatly honored and pleased that you and<lb/>
your countrymen choose to dedicate &ldquo;Camp Lazear.&rdquo; In a most gracious and friendly<lb/>
manner you are uniting forever the honored names of several of my countrymen with<lb/>
that of your own beloved and eminent humanitarian, Carlos Finlay, and of his associate<lb/>
Claudio Delgado.</p>
<p>It is fitting that this be done because, individually and collectively,<lb/>
they worked mightily, all at the risk of life and one at the cost of life, to defeat<lb/>
a common foe and to serve a common cause. To you, sir, and to others who have done<lb/>
so much to create this shrine, to Dr. Saladrigas, Dr. Recio, Dr. Nogueira, Dr.<lb/>
Rodriguez, Dr. Andreu, Dr. Ramos and their associates, my countrymen and I extend<lb/>
our most sincere thanks.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04435024"/>
<p>Page 2 (Havana)</p>
<p>Others have told you of those who discovered and fashioned the truth we<lb/>
memorialize today. Let me speak also about the place we dedicate today. The very<lb/>
spot where we gather saw the dramatic climax of an incredible scientific adventure,<lb/>
of a great human endeavor - the potential destruction of one of man's greatest<lb/>
enemies - yellow fever, the &ldquo;saffron horror.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Cuban-American Cooperation Underlying the Conquest of Yellow Fever</hi></p>
<p>The conquest of yellow fever was accomplished as the result of an amazing<lb/>
cooperative venture between your countrymen and mine, a venture which is still unique<lb/>
in medical annals. Underlying the individualistic genius and the strong moral courage<lb/>
of the chief participants were political and scientific statesmanship of a high order.<lb/>
The central theme which united the hopes and the varied opinions and contributions of<lb/>
many was a desire to serve mankind, if necessary above and beyond the call of duty.</p>
<p>This drama concerned many characters and scenes but it had one unifying<lb/>
stage-setting, the Finca San Jose, and three main acts or chapters provided by<lb/>
(1) the work of the Havana Yellow Fever Commission of 1879, (2) the life-long work<lb/>
of Carlos Finlay and his associate, Claudio Delgado, and (3) the work of Walter Reed<lb/>
and his associates of the U. S. Army Commission of 1900.</p>
<p>The unrestricted generosity of the Spanish-speaking peoples is legendary.<lb/>
You of Cuba uphold that tradition magnificently as I personally have reason to know,<lb/>
having been for many years the happy recipient of your friendship and kindness.<lb/>
Your willingness to share what you have is an old attribute. Thus beginning about<lb/>
1761 and for the next 140 years you graciously permitted my countrymen and others<lb/>
to export from this fair land a generous amount of yellow fever. Up to a point this<lb/>
was strictly a matter of &ldquo;free enterprise,&rdquo; presumably just a personal, man to man<lb/>
affair. But being bureaucrats, our customs and other officials eventually chose to<lb/>
look into the situation.</p>
<p><hi>The Havana Yellow Fever Commission of 1879</hi></p>
<p>And so for the first time in its history, the United States Government<lb/>
established on June 20, 1879, a sanitary expedition, named the Havana Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission of the National Board of Health. It was to cooperate with your country-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04435025"/>
Page 3 (Havana)<lb/>
men in studying yellow fever and its purpose was stated precisely: &ldquo;to serve not one<lb/>
but all nations.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The chairman of the American Commission was Dr. Stanford E. Chaille, Prof.<lb/>
of Physiology and Pathology at the University of Louisiana, New Orleans. Its secretary<lb/>
was Dr. George Sternberg of the U. S. Army, one of those you are honoring today; he<lb/>
was one of America's pre-eminent bacteriologists and later became Surgeon General of<lb/>
the U. S. Army. Another member was the Cuban, Dr. Juan Guiteras, then Prof. of Path-<lb/>
ology at the University of Pennsylvania, the well-loved physician and teacher who<lb/>
later returned to Cuba and the University of Havana.</p>
<p>In a fine spirit of international cooperation your Spanish governor-general<lb/>
Don Ramon Blanco, Marquis of Pe&ntilde;a Plata, and many distinguished citizens and physicians<lb/>
of Cuba, welcomed the American Commission most graciously. Furthermore your govern-<lb/>
ment established an auxiliary Spanish Commission of twelve eminent Cuban and Spanish<lb/>
physicians, one of whom was Carlos Finlay. Although Doctor Finlay had already<lb/>
studied yellow fever intensively for 21 years, this was his first official connection<lb/>
with sanitary work.</p>
<p>The American Commission set out to discover (among other things) those<lb/>
places in Cuba, especially in and around Habana, where the incidence of yellow fever<lb/>
was the highest and the lowest. Soon they were directed to this little town of<lb/>
Marianao where 6,863 people lived in 666 houses.</p>
<p><hi>The Curious Immunity of The Finca San Jose</hi></p>
<p>Senor Alcalde, you will be pleased to know that the American Commission<lb/>
called Marianao &ldquo;the cleanest, most attractive and beautiful town in Cuba.&rdquo; Despite<lb/>
this its annual mortality rate was high (39.5), almost twice that for the whole<lb/>
island of Cuba. But they made an interesting discovery: Although yellow fever was<lb/>
endemic in Quemados and Marianao, one spot here was practically immune - the lovely,<lb/>
quiet Finca San Jose which had belonged to the distinguished Pedroso family for about<lb/>
200 years.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04435026"/>
<p>Page 4 (Havana)</p>
<p>Because of its salubrious reputation the peaceful Quinta San Jose had been<lb/>
leased to the Jesuit fathers to whom it was a place of rest and refuge and a place<lb/>
for the &ldquo;acclimitization&rdquo; of newcomers from abroad. So long as the Jesuits remained<lb/>
at the Finca San Jose (1872-1883) none who remained there ever developed yellow fever<lb/>
although it was all around them. This intriguing fact was specially noted by the<lb/>
American Commission. But they found no reason therefor, except that the Quinta was<lb/>
&ldquo;on high ground, open, cool and well ventilated by the breezes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Thus, way back in 1879, fate, as we can see from the Chaille report, began<lb/>
to bring together not only the men who were destined to accomplish, or witness closely,<lb/>
the conquest of yellow fever, but even the very place where the final drama was to<lb/>
develop more than 20 years later.</p>
<p><hi>The Chaille Report, 1879 - Its Influence on Dr. Carlos Finlay</hi></p>
<p>Thanks largely to the help of your countrymen, the Chaille report represents<lb/>
a historic mile-stone. It masterfully separated fact from legend, truth from super-<lb/>
stition. Within its 240 crowded pages were assembled more indisputable facts than<lb/>
were to be found in any previous report. For one brief glittering moment it even<lb/>
toyed with destiny and flirted with immortality when it spoke of the &ldquo;aerial pilgrimage&rdquo;<lb/>
of the yellow fever poison (P. 128). One could find therein practically everything about<lb/>
yellow fever, everything that is, except the most important and elusive factor of all<lb/>
- its cause.</p>
<p>Thus it might be said that the eminent and zealous commissioners were full<lb/>
of facts but were deprived of that final wisdom whereby they could implement their<lb/>
encyclopedic knowledge.</p>
<p>Despite its clear exposition of all the known facts, this report of the<lb/>
Havana Yellow Fever Commission appears not to have altered notably the thinking of<lb/>
the sanitarians and physicians of my country nor that of 11 of the 12 &ldquo;Spanish<lb/>
Commissioners.&rdquo; But, fortunately for the world, it served its purpose because it<lb/>
influenced strongly the receptive mind of just one Cuban physician, one of the com-<lb/>
missioners - Carlos Finlay.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f04435027"/>
<p>Page 5 (Havana)</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Finlay's Mosquito Hypothesis - Its First Phase</hi></p>
<p>For 21 years (1858 - 1879) Dr. Finlay had held, and sometimes expounded,<lb/>
the belief that yellow fever was somehow related to the alkalinity of the atmosphere<lb/>
(Finlay's Sel. Works, P. 625). But his association with the American Commission and<lb/>
its report set his mind in ferment. Pondering the accumulated data on climatic, at-<lb/>
mospheric and other factors, Dr. Finlay concluded that his own long-held theory was,<lb/>
in his own words, now &ldquo;utterly indefensible&rdquo; and would have to be abandoned and that<lb/>
he should re-examine the whole situation from a new viewpoint.</p>
<p>Here we can observe the contrasting tenacity and flexibility of Finlay's<lb/>
mind. The teluric theory engaged his loyalty for 21 years (1858 - 1879), then the<lb/>
mosquito theory for 19 years (1881 - 1900) prior to its acceptance. Despite his<lb/>
devotion to the first theory he abandoned it quickly and willingly when faced with<lb/>
controverting facts, and a superior idea. Now sharing the Chaille Commisson's<lb/>
opinion that &ldquo;the poison of yellow fever was a living organism&rdquo; of unknown nature<lb/>
and source, Dr. Finlay began patiently to build on this feeble and nebulous fundament<lb/>
a superstructure which, after years of neglect, was to excite the admiration of the<lb/>
whole world.</p>
<p>During 1880 he formulated the first phase of his theory. As if guided by<lb/>
an unerring &ldquo;divining rod&rdquo; of his own making, he passed by thousands of bacterial and<lb/>
insect-possibilities, and, having concluded that the agent must be a winged, blood-<lb/>
sucking insect indigenous to yellow-fever localities, he chose the culex mosquito as<lb/>
the likely culprit. Later, with characteristic modesty he spoke of this epoch-making<lb/>
cerebration as the result of &ldquo;a simple reasoning,&rdquo; an example of the magnificent<lb/>
understatement of a genius.</p>
<p>In December 1880 he began to study the mosquitos collected in his own<lb/>
house. In 1881 he made his first seven inoculations, pausing in August to present<lb/>
his memorable first report which was completely ignored. In 1882 he made no inocula-<lb/>
tions, possibly because, as he stated later, he developed temporarily a doubt as to<lb/>
whether the culex was the natural transmitter of the disease.</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Finlay at the Quinta San Jose, 1883</hi></p>
<p>In 1883, fortified with highly suggestive data on the appropriate effects<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f04435028"/>
(6) (Havana)<lb/>
of heat, cold and altitude on the culex, (data analogous to that related to the develop-<lb/>
ment of spontaneous yellow fever), he confidently resumed his inoculations, and here<lb/>
for the second time the Finca San Jose became closely identified with the medical<lb/>
triumph we commemorate today. The Jesuit fathers, mentioned above, were still en-<lb/>
joying the mysterious, unexplained immunity of the Quinta San Jose. What better<lb/>
place could be found to demonstrate the malevolence of his special mosquitos than one<lb/>
where, for at least 11 years, no spontaneous yellow fever had developed.</p>
<p>Between July 15 and August 21, 1883, five volunteers (4 Jesuits and one of<lb/>
their servants) received from Doctor Finlay 8 inoculations over there in the Quinta<lb/>
San Jose. (Dr. Hench points to the Quinta San Jose.) Among these inoculations was the<lb/>
one on Padre Urra which, during the next 17 frustrating years, gave Finlay the most<lb/>
confidence and satisfaction.</p>
<p>Eleven years later, September 1894, Finlay paused to add up the score: it<lb/>
was not encouraging. He had inoculated 90 persons with results which he himself con-<lb/>
sidered positive in only 18 per cent; he had written 44 papers on his mosquito hypothesis,<lb/>
but aside from the faithful Delgado he had acquired not a single known convert. Lesser<lb/>
men might well have given up. But Dr. Finlay faced the facts squarely. Despite<lb/>
his disappointment at the unresponsiveness of his medical colleagues he conceived of<lb/>
a new approach to the problem of preventing yellow fever and proposed new suggestions.<lb/>
But these too were ignored until they were extended and successfully adopted by Gorgas<lb/>
7 years later (1901).</p>
<p>Thus, after admitting that his method of therapeutic inoculation constituted<lb/>
a &ldquo;troublesome&rdquo; procedure, one &ldquo;not likely to gain adherents,&rdquo; (Select Wks, p. 232)<lb/>
he suddenly changed pace temporarily and laid down three main indications concerning<lb/>
the prevention of contact between the appropriate mosquitos on the one hand and in-<lb/>
fected or susceptible persons on the other hand, measures which were the forerunner<lb/>
of those used so effectively by Gorgas after 1901.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f04435029"/>
<p>-7- (Havana)</p>
<p><hi>An Indifferent World</hi></p>
<p>But this period of discouragement and pessimism was to be his last, and<lb/>
represented darkness before dawn. The new revalations of 1898 that mosquitos, des-<lb/>
pised and denounced by him for to long, played a crucial role in the development of<lb/>
malaria encouraged him greatly. But even these discoveries brought to his related hy-<lb/>
pothesis no professional converts or governmental support, despite the prophetic, last<lb/>
conclusion of the Chaille Commission that the poisons of yellow fever and malaria<lb/>
require for their growth &ldquo;some conditions which are the same.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Would the world never accept the truth of his conception? Why did the<lb/>
medical profession, and the sanitarians of Cuba, the United States and elsewhere,<lb/>
so universally and unanimously disregard or discount the inductive reasoning and<lb/>
experimental evidence which seemed so convincing to Finlay. I think his son, Dr.<lb/>
Charles E. Finlay, has given us the best explanation: (1) Dr. Finlay was far ahead,<lb/>
too far ahead of his time: in 1880 nothing was known of disease-transmission by<lb/>
insects, and his work antedated all of the great mosquito-malaria discoveries of Manson,<lb/>
Ross and others. (2) In making his inoculations Finlay's objective was (according<lb/>
to his son's book) &ldquo;not demonstrative&rdquo; but primarily therapeutic (C. E. Finlay, P 76,<lb/>
American edition). He was trying less to demonstrate the production of mild experi-<lb/>
mental yellow fever than to produce an impressive, prolonged post-inoculation im-<lb/>
munity from severe, possibly fatal spontaneous yellow fever. Thus in his later re-<lb/>
ports he paid as much, if not more, attention to his long-term results (the duration<lb/>
of post-inoculation &ldquo;immunity&rdquo;) than to his short-term results (the development of<lb/>
yellow fever soon after inoculation).</p>
<p>In other words in placing the primary emphasis on the accomplishment of his<lb/>
second, or therapeutic objective, he did not deem it necessary or practicable to<lb/>
surround the first procedure (the inoculations) with every possible scientific safe-<lb/>
guard, or to carry them out under rigid conditions of <hi>absolute</hi> quarantine. To him<lb/>
the relative isolation of his volunteers before and after inoculation seemed sufficient;<lb/>
it was certainly more practical and convenient for the inoculees. But because Finlay's<lb/>
volunteers were <hi>not</hi> strictly quarantined those few who later developed yellow fever<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04435030"/>
- 8 - (Havana)<lb/>
were believed (by every official and physician except Finlay and Delgado) to have<lb/>
somehow gotten spontaneous yellow fever in the ordinary, unknown way.</p>
<p>From a study of this and other decisions which Dr. Finlay made, we can<lb/>
judge that whenever a choice concerning patients had to be made he chose to be a<lb/>
physician first - the considerate therapeutist and humanitarian, a &ldquo;cold,&rdquo; impersonal<lb/>
experimentalist second. Being the gentle, kindly, religious physician that he was,<lb/>
he could make no other decision. But this admirable attribute brought him years of<lb/>
neglect, inadequate recognition and the loss of a clear-cut and exclusively personal<lb/>
victory; I suspect that in the last analysis, after recognition was attained he<lb/>
considered the price not exorbitant and that, had he had a chance to do it all over<lb/>
again he might well have made the same hard choices.</p>
<p><hi>The Habana Yellow Fever Epidemic of 1900</hi></p>
<p>As the 20th century dawned, Cuba endured two invaders - one new, one old.<lb/>
The liberating army of Americans, non-immune to yellow fever, was waiting anxiously<lb/>
to go home; the usual spring invasion of the yellow fever poison was at hand. As<lb/>
could have been expected, the two &ldquo;invaders&rdquo; promptly collided, as if by some devilish<lb/>
chemotaxis. A new and vicious epidemic of yellow fever resulted. And what of Finlay's<lb/>
species of mosquitos? Despite his 19 years of accusation they quietly went about<lb/>
their malicious business, completely unmolested and unsuspected.</p>
<p>Some of the American soldiers from Camp Columbia had private quarters in<lb/>
Quemados. Yellow fever began to appear a few blocks from where we now are. The<lb/>
first victim lived at what was then (and still is) 102 Real Street (Calzada Real).<lb/>
From thence the poison spread, not next door, but around the corner to what was<lb/>
number 20 General Lee Street (now #404). During May and June 1900 the epidemic<lb/>
spread rapidly among the non-immunes of Habana and Quemados.</p>
<p>With the U. S. forces were two contract surgeons: one was Dr. Aristides<lb/>
Agramonte, a Cuban physician experienced in yellow fever research; the other was an<lb/>
able young physician and laboratory expert, Dr. Jesse Lazear who, unaccustomed to<lb/>
yellow fever, got busy trying to learn whatever he could about it. On hand to<lb/>
help with the diagnosis was the &ldquo;Habana Board of Yellow Fever Experts,&rdquo; established<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f04435031"/>
- 9 - (Havana)<lb/>
1899 for that purpose under the chairmanship of Dr. Finlay, other members being<lb/>
Guiteras, Albertini and Gorgas.</p>
<p><hi>The United States Army Yellow Fever Board, 1900</hi></p>
<p>Surgeon General Sternberg in Washington promptly created another com-<lb/>
mission, the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Board, chiefly because of the emergency affecting<lb/>
American <unclear>troups</unclear> in Cuba but also because it was an opportune time to investigate<lb/>
the, to him, dubious claims which were being made for the latest &ldquo;yellow fever germ&rdquo;<lb/>
- <unclear>Senarellis</unclear> bacillus. Appointed on May 24, 1900 to this Board were Major Walter<lb/>
Reed and Dr. James Carroll who were in Washington, and Drs. Agramonte and Lazear who<lb/>
were already at Camp Columbia making clinical, pathologic and laboratory studies on<lb/>
the yellow fever victims.</p>
<p>It appears that at last Dr. Finlay was about to get his second convert in<lb/>
the person of Dr. Lazear, for the record (Dr. Lazear's own hand-written laboratory<lb/>
notebook) shows that on May 23, 33 days before the Army Board had its first meeting<lb/>
at Camp Columbia (June 25), Lazear captured for his own microscopic inspection<lb/>
six mosquitos in the room of the yellow fever patient at 20 General Lee Street.</p>
<p><hi>Early Failures with Bacteria</hi></p>
<p>But to the Board as a whole Finlay's mosquito theory was just one of the<lb/>
theories they planned to investigate. Although one or more representatives of the<lb/>
Board visited Dr. Finlay late in June and received from him eggs of his culex mosquito<lb/>
(Finlay's Selected Wks., p. 411) which Lazear proceeded to breed, top priority was<lb/>
given to the bacterial theory of Sanarelli upon which the Board spent 5 busy but<lb/>
fruitless weeks as they found no significant germs in the bodily fluids and tissues<unclear><del>.</del></unclear><lb/>
of yellow fever victims.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi>Perhaps Dr. Finlay is Right</hi>!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Late in July a curious and crucial observation was made when Agramonte,<lb/>
then Reed and Lazear went to study an epidemic among Soldiers at Pinar del Rio. A<lb/>
soldier in a prison cell sickened and died of yellow fever. But his cell mates, ex-<lb/>
posed to the same food and atmosphere, remained well. Could a winged agent have<lb/>
entered between the bars of the open window, struck one man down and gone away?<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f04435032"/>
- 10 - (Havana)<lb/>
Perhaps Dr. Finlay <hi>was</hi> right after all! Returning to Camp Columbia the Board<lb/>
promptly made the study of Finlay's mosquitos its chief objective. Another visit<lb/>
was made to Doctor Finlay who graciously offered whatever help he could give. How<lb/>
happy he must have been to find at long last physicians so impressed by his ideas<lb/>
that they determined to test their validity immediately.</p>
<p>But to carry on the work human volunteers were required and the Board<lb/>
members decided to inoculate each other first. At this juncture Reed, unfortunately,<lb/>
had to return to Washington (August 2) to finish the important report of a three-man<lb/>
medical commission of which he had been a member and whose chairman had just died.</p>
<p><hi>Early Experiments at Columbia Barracks Post Hospital - Failures, Then Sudden Success<lb/>
Death of the Martyr, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear</hi></p>
<p>In August, nine American volunteers, including Dr. Lazear, were inoculated<lb/>
with presumably &ldquo;infected mosquitos&rdquo; but nothing happened. Then suddenly Dr. Lazear<lb/>
successfully produced experimental yellow fever in Dr. Carroll (August 31) and in<lb/>
Private William Dean (September 6). Two days later Lazear wrote his wife an exciting<lb/>
but cryptic letter (September 8). Then a few days later (September 18) he himself de-<lb/>
veloped the disease (His nurse was Lena Warner whom you honor today.). In a week he<lb/>
was dead of what, for official purposes, was allowed to be recorded as accidental<lb/>
yellow fever but which was (according to recently discovered data) almost certainly<lb/>
secret, self-induced experimental yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>Newly Discovered Crucial Details of the Man-Mosquito Formula</hi></p>
<p>Reed returned hastily to Habana (October 4), deeply depressed by Lazear's<lb/>
death, elated that success seemed near at hand, but confused by the contrasting nine<lb/>
negative and three &ldquo;positive experiments.&rdquo; Reed studied intently the available<lb/>
records, especially Lazear's pocket-notebook which the hospital's young commanding<lb/>
officer, Lieutenant (now General) Truby had carefully protected.</p>
<p>Herein was a key to the age-old mystery; the key was provided by data on a<lb/>
crucial point which even the genius of Finlay had not clarified precisely and which<lb/>
Lazear himself may or may not have recognized as he made his fateful notes. The notes<lb/>
would not have revealed the key to a casual reader. But Reed's clear mind (fortunately<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f04435033"/>
-11- (Havana)<lb/>
conditioned by the 1898 report of Dr. H. R. Carter on the interval between infecting<lb/>
and secondary cases of yellow fever) noted the critical differences between the<lb/>
timings of the successful and unsuccessful inoculations.</p>
<p>Under usual conditions (those present in Quemados that summer) the mosquitos<lb/>
could only become &ldquo;infected&rdquo; if they bit yellow fever patients within the first three<lb/>
days; thereafter the &ldquo;poison&rdquo; disappeared from the patients' peripheral blood. Next<lb/>
the poison had to &ldquo;ripen&rdquo; at least 12 days within the mosquito before the latter's<lb/>
bite could become harmful.</p>
<p><hi>Again The World's Indifference and Ridicule</hi></p>
<p>Reed quickly prepared the Board's preliminary note which he read in<lb/>
Indianapolis late in October. But the report received little professional support or<lb/>
public credence. Thus, for example, an editorial in a Washington paper called their<lb/>
work &ldquo;silly and nonsensical rigamarole.&rdquo; (November 2). It was now the Board's turn<lb/>
to be the recipient of the sort of indifference, skepticism and ridicule which Drs.<lb/>
Finlay and Delgado had endured for so long. But this is not surprising because these<lb/>
three inoculations, though &ldquo;successful,&rdquo; were relatively uncontrolled, as had been<lb/>
Finlay's, in that none of the 3 volunteers was under &ldquo;strict quarantine&rdquo; (in the<lb/>
experimental sense) although Private Deen had been confined within the otherwise<lb/>
fever-free Columbia Post Hospital. The skeptical world was no more receptive to, or<lb/>
impressed by Reed than it had been by Finlay and so it quite properly demanded more<lb/>
data with incontrovertible proof.</p>
<p>&ldquo;<hi>Camp Lazear&rdquo; on the Finca San Jose</hi></p>
<p>And that is what Reed, Carroll, Agramonte and their brave volunteers finally<lb/>
obtained from the experiments performed here at their experimental station, &ldquo;Camp<lb/>
Lazear,&rdquo; on the Finca San Jose between November 20, 1900 and March, 1901. The money<lb/>
for this purpose, Cuban money, was wisely allotted to Major Reed by General Leonard<lb/>
Wood, the provisional Governor General. Did ever an investment of $10,000 pay such<lb/>
rich dividends!</p>
<p>How did it happen that for the third time (1879, 1883, 1900) the Finca San<lb/>
Jose became the locale for important observations on yellow fever? The Jesuits sur-<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f04435034"/>
-12- (Havana)<lb/>
rendered the Finca San Jose in 1884, and by July 1900 its owners, Dr. Ignacio Rojas,<lb/>
his wife the former Senora Maria Teresa Lomas, viuda de Pedroso, and their family<lb/>
were permanently occupying the Quinta, but had leased part of the adjacent finca to<lb/>
Don Antonio Sosa.</p>
<p>After visiting many prospective places for their experimental camp, Major<lb/>
Reed chose the Finca San Jose. Apparently Dr. Agramonte recommended the place to<lb/>
him (Scientific Monthly, Dec. 1915). According to the entry of November 15, 1900 in<lb/>
his diary or day book, Dr. Rojas by agreement with Don Sosa, leased the finca to &ldquo;the<lb/>
Military Health officers of the American Army through the mediation of Dr. Echevarria,&rdquo;<lb/>
and thereafter received a monthly rental of &ldquo;$20.00 American gold&rdquo; from Major Reed or<lb/>
from his deputy, friend and &ldquo;right hand man,&rdquo; Major Kean, Chief Surgeon of the De-<lb/>
partment of Western Cuba.</p>
<p>Although uniquely appropriate, Reed's felicitous choice of this already-<lb/>
historic place appears to have been quite coincidental (and Dr. Charles E. Finlay,<lb/>
who as a youth visited Camp Lazear with his father and Major Reed, told me in 1941 that<lb/>
he shared this opinion). The previous contacts which Chaille (1879) and Finlay<lb/>
(1883) had had with the Finca San Jose appear to have escaped the notice of Reed<lb/>
and his colleagues (or at least of Reed) for they were not mentioned in any of the<lb/>
Board's official or unofficial writings.</p>
<p><hi>Drama at Camp Lazear: &ldquo;Buildings Number One and Two</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>The specially guarded and quarantined experimental station established on<lb/>
this spot was named &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; in honor of their martyred colleague. Several<lb/>
tents were set up right over there (Dr. Hench points). There the soldier-volunteers<lb/>
lived and slept when they were not otherwise occupied. Then two small specially<lb/>
constructed wooden buildings of equal size were erected: Building Number One or the<lb/>
&ldquo;Infected Clothing and Bedding Building,&rdquo; and Building Number Two, the &ldquo;Infected<lb/>
Mosquito Building.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This &ldquo;old warrier&rdquo; (pointing) constitutes the somewhat reconstructed remains<lb/>
of Building Number One which had only two small windows and was heated by a small stove<lb/>
to a tropical temperature. Herein several volunteers (among them Dr. Cooke who died<lb/>
just one month ago) slept for many nights on foul-smelling pillows and sheets soiled<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f04435035"/>
- 13 - (Havana)<lb/>
with the blood and vomitus of Las Animas Hospital yellow fever victims; since such<lb/>
material (&ldquo;fomites&rdquo;) had long been regarded as infectious the heroic uninformed<lb/>
volunteers fully expected to catch yellow fever, but none did, simply because there<lb/>
were no mosquitos in the building. Thus up the smoke-stack of this little building<lb/>
went, figuratively and literally, the long-held notion that &ldquo;infected belongings&rdquo;<lb/>
caused the disease, a notion which had cost uncounted millions of dollars, as such<lb/>
material was needlessly destroyed or fumigated.</p>
<p>Eighty yards in front of Building Number One was Building Number Two;<lb/>
it stood right over there (pointing) until it was blown down in the tornado of<lb/>
1926. That building was divided into two parts separated merely by a finely meshed<lb/>
wire screen.</p>
<p>As Reed, Finlay and others watched from behind the wire screen, John Moran<lb/>
lay down on a cot on the other side of the room and exposed his body for two 1/2-hour<lb/>
periods to the bites of 15 infected mosquitos. He promptly developed severe yellow<lb/>
fever, while other volunteers who stayed long hours on the opposite side of the screen<lb/>
remained well. You of Habana knew Johnny Moran well, for he lived here among you for<lb/>
many years as an honored citizen and died here September, 1950. He was my esteemed<lb/>
friend whom I often visited here.</p>
<p>In the bodies of thirteen more American and Spanish volunteers, who are named<lb/>
on the bronze tablets, yellow fever was produced at will, either through the medium<lb/>
of mosquito bites or by injections of infected blood or serum. One of them was James<lb/>
L. Hanberry, the sole surviving volunteer who is prevented by illness from being your<lb/>
guest today. Once sick, they were removed immediately from Camp Lazear to a small<lb/>
yellow fever &ldquo;hospital&rdquo; across the <unclear>La</unclear> Playa railroad tracks from the old Columbia<lb/>
Post Hospital. Fortunately, all these brave volunteers survived, thanks to the expert<lb/>
professional care of Dr. Roger P. Ames (whose widow has come all the way from<lb/>
North Carolina to be with you today), and to the devoted nursing of Gustav Lambert.</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Finlay's Professional Visits to Camp Lazear, 1900-1901</hi></p>
<p>Although Dr. Finlay did none of his own experimental work at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
he frequently visited this spot, primarily in his capacity as a member of the Habana<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f04435036"/>
- 14 - (Havana)<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board to confirm the diagnoses of experimental yellow fever, or with his<lb/>
friends, Major Reed, Dr. Carroll and Dr. Agramonte, to note with delight the final<lb/>
development of his thesis. Thus he adorned with his presence not only the Quinta San<lb/>
Jose (1883) but Camp Lazear as well (1900-1901).</p>
<p><hi>Time to Celebrate</hi>!</p>
<p>Their problem solved after eight months of work the U. S. Army Board dis-<lb/>
banded Camp Lazear on March 1, 1901 (but they kept it under lease until October 1901).<lb/>
Now armed with precise knowledge Gorgas within three months freed Habana of its age-<lb/>
old pestilence.</p>
<p>Senor Presidente, ladies and gentlemen, I wish that after these memorable<lb/>
ceremonies we could all go down to the Parque Central of Habana, enter the door of<lb/>
the narrow building next to (i.e. north of) the old Hotel Inglaterra, and climb the<lb/>
32 steps to a long narrow room on the second floor above what is now the &ldquo;Press Wire-<lb/>
less of Cuba.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Let us imagine we are doing this tonight and the time is 7 p.m., Saturday,<lb/>
December 22, 1900. The room, brightly lit, is host to about 60 men for this is Del-<lb/>
monico's Restaurant, and here are gathered a distinguished company of Cuban and Ameri-<lb/>
can governmental and medical personalities, including &ldquo;all the members of the Academy<lb/>
and of the School of Medicine&rdquo; (Dominguez, Engl. Tr., p 104). Among them we see<lb/>
Governor-General Wood who is presiding, the Cuban physicians - Drs. Dominguez, Guiteras,<lb/>
Tamayo and Presno <add>and the Americans, Reed, Carroll, Agramonte, Gorgas, and Kean.</add>. Tonight these 60 men have all come here to honor Dr. Finlay, to whom<lb/>
toasts will be drunk in &ldquo;grand Pouche Romaine au Finlay.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As Major Reed takes a seat near the guest of honor, two strong emotions<lb/>
compete within him for ascendency. In his mind is anxiety. Just today a Washington<lb/>
newspaper once more ridiculed <del><unclear>the</unclear></del> the work of Reed and his colleagues, calling them<lb/>
&ldquo;medical amateurs,&rdquo; and sarcastically dismissing the mosquito hypothesis as ridiculous<lb/>
speculation. At her home near Washington, Mrs. Reed will see the uncomplimentary<lb/>
editorial and, being a loyal wife, she will, in careful privacy, express her annoyance<lb/>
in firm but ladylike fashion.</p>
<p>However the source of Reed's concern is related, not to the foolish,<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f04435037"/>
- 15 - (Havana)<lb/>
pontifical editorialist in Washington, but to the men he left at Camp Lazear an hour<lb/>
or two ago. Just yesterday that brave Irish lad, 24 year old Johnny Moran, spent 30<lb/>
more minutes with the infected mosquitos in Building Number Two. He may well develop<lb/>
yellow fever two or three days from now. Let's see, that might be on Christmas Day.<lb/>
If so, what a wonderful Christmas gift Johnny would be giving to all the world! And<lb/>
eleven more young volunteers are waiting their turn to match their physical and<lb/>
spiritual courage against death by yellow fever.</p>
<p>Yes, the Major has ample reason for concern: the planned experiments are<lb/>
by no means finished; it may take three more months to obtain enough proof to satisfy<lb/>
the more critical scientists. But in Reed's heart is a humble joy, a thankfulness<lb/>
impossible to suppress. His gratitude <add>is</add> properly directed to many, to &ldquo;my colleagues<lb/>
Drs. Carroll and Agramonte,&rdquo; to Kissinger, Moran, Hanberry, &ldquo;Cookie&rdquo; and the rest<lb/>
of the volunteers (&ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you&rdquo;) but especially to three others:-</p>
<p>To the young martyr, Jesse Lazear &ldquo;He was a splendid, brave fellow, and<lb/>
I lament his loss more than words can tell; but his death <add>was not in vain. His name</add> will live in the history<lb/>
of those who have benefited humanity...It is my own earnest wish that whatever credit<lb/>
may be hereafter given to the work of the American Commission in Cuba during the<lb/>
past year, the name of my late colleague, Dr. Lazear, may be always associated<lb/>
therewith.&rdquo;</p>
<p>To his mentor Dr. Finlay: &ldquo;We here desire to express our sincere thanks to<lb/>
Doctor Finlay who accorded us a most courteous interview, and has gladly placed at<lb/>
our disposal his several publications relating to yellow fever during the past 19<lb/>
years; and also for the ova of the species of mosquito with which he had made his<lb/>
several inoculations....To Dr. Finlay must be given full credit for the theory of<lb/>
the propagation of yellow fever by means of the mosquito....&rdquo;</p>
<p>To his Maker: &ldquo;I thank God...the prayer that has been mine for 20 or<lb/>
more years that I might be permitted in some way or sometime to do something to<lb/>
alleviate human suffering, has been answered.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="16" id="f04435038"/>
<p>- 16 - (Havana)</p>
<p>Answered, too, is the 20 year old prayer of the honored guest, Dr. Finlay.<lb/>
The banquet is now ending and he has just been given a bronze statuette, a small<lb/>
token of esteem, a fine souvenir of this wonderful evening.</p>
<p>It is almost midnight. Listen quietly as Doctor Finlay responds briefly,<lb/>
graciously, feelingly: &ldquo;Twenty years ago, guided by indications which I deemed<lb/>
certain, I sallied forth into an arid and unknown field; I discovered therein a<lb/>
stone, rough in appearance; I picked it up and with the assistance of my efficient<lb/>
and faithful co-laborer, Dr. Claudio Delgado, polished and examined it carefully,<lb/>
arriving at the conclusion that we had discovered a rough diamond. But nobody would<lb/>
believe us, till years later there arrived a commission, composed of intelligent men,<lb/>
experts in the required kind of work, who in a short time extracted from the rough<lb/>
shell the stone to whose brilliancy none can now be blind.&rdquo; (Carlos Finlay, Dec. 22,<lb/>
1900).</p>
<p>- - - - - - - - - - - -</p>
<p>As Dr. Finlay sat down, the applause began. It has never ceased: 52 years<lb/>
later it still continues, as our presence here today testifies.</p>
<p>Of the 25 principal men whose hopes were fulfilled at Camp Lazear, three<lb/>
were Cubans (Drs. Finlay, Delgado, Agramonte), four were Spaniards, one was English,<lb/>
one was Irish and 16 were Americans. Some were humbly born; some reached high estate;<lb/>
some were civilians, others were soldiers, professionals and volunteers; some were<lb/>
catholic, some were protestant, some were Hebrews. And here on this hemisphere's<lb/>
23rd parallel they demonstrated well the potential brotherhood of man.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
