<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04433003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Austin Smith, November 5, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04433003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Smith, Austin</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-05">November 5, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04433003</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Austin Smith, November 5, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench suggests that Smith publish a short news item in "The Journal of the American Medical Association" about the upcoming dedication ceremony of Camp Lazear. He lists the names of Cuban officials involved in the project. Hench confesses his fear that the site will be called &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo; instead of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Austin Smith, November 5, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04433003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-05">November 5, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Austin Smith, Editor<lb/>
Journal of the American Medical Association<lb/>
535 North Dearborn<lb/>
Chicago, Illinois<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Smith:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have long had as a hobby the conquest of yellow fever, the work of<lb/>
Doctor Finlay of Havana and, more particularly, of Major Walter Reed<lb/>
and his associates. I have made many visits to Havana and elsewhere<lb/>
in pursuit of this hobby and one of the products of this investiga-<lb/>
tion was the rediscovery in 1940 of the &ldquo;lost&rdquo; Camp Lazear where Reed<lb/>
and his Associates did their work. Since then, I have enlisted the<lb/>
help of Cubans and others to the end that Camp Lazear be memorialized<lb/>
and at long last the Cuban Government is going to memorialize it on<lb/>
December 3. As you undoubtedly know, there has been a rather seri-<lb/>
monius debate in Cuba the last forty years by the proponents of Finlay<lb/>
who insist that the Americans have not honored Finlay sufficiently and<lb/>
that Reed was given all the credit. As a result, they have compounded<lb/>
the error, have ignored Reed entirely and set up many memorials to<lb/>
Finlay and so on.</p>
<p>This spring when I was in Havana and was shown the original blue prints<lb/>
of the plans for the memorialization of Camp Lazear, I noted that the<lb/>
camp was to be renamed &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo; and Reed's Building No. 1 was<lb/>
erroneously designated &ldquo;Caseta de Finlay.&rdquo; Dr. Pedro Nogueira is the<lb/>
spark plug of the dedication. He is working as the agent of the<lb/>
Minister of Health. I have known Doctor Nogueira for some years. He is<lb/>
a very dynamic and fine young man. When I pointed out this error to him<lb/>
he laughed and said that it would be corrected; that it was simply an<lb/>
error by the draftsmen who of course do not know medical history. He<lb/>
assured me that Reed's Building No. 1 will be properly named; however I<lb/>
fear that the name Camp Lazear will not be perpetuated but will be re-<lb/>
placed by &ldquo;Parque Finlay.&rdquo; The place is being graded and made into a<lb/>
park, streets have been put in, a stone wall has been erected upon which<lb/>
will be placed certain bronze medallions and plaques with the names of all<lb/>
or most of the volunteers; bushes and other shrubbery have been planted and<lb/>
Reed's Building No. 1 has been repaired.</p>
<p>Doctor Nogueira had hoped to have the dedication on November 20, the anni-<lb/>
versary of the date the camp was originally opened but his superiors chose<lb/>
December 3, Finlay's birthday and &ldquo;Physicians' Day&rdquo; in Cuba. That alone<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04433004"/>
Dr. Austin Smith<lb/>
Page 2<lb/>
November 5, 1952<lb/>
may make for an overly strong &ldquo;Finlay attitude&rdquo; on the day of dedication.<lb/>
I suppose that in order to get this project accomplished, I and other<lb/>
Americans interested in the affair may have to accept the compromise of<lb/>
&ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo; but none of us could possibly accept the false name of<lb/>
Reed's Building No. 1. This summer I have had considerable correspondence<lb/>
with Doctor Nogueira. He seems to want to be eminently fair and I must<lb/>
have complete faith in him, but I do not know how far he can persuade his<lb/>
superiors to approve his ideas which are in agreement with mine. The oc-<lb/>
casion could be a fine one for an expression of Cuban-American friendship,<lb/>
especially Cuban-American medical friendship and I hope indeed that no<lb/>
erroneous naming will spoil the affair. However you will note from the<lb/>
enclosure that the Havana newspapers have, accidentally or deliberately,<lb/>
chosen to perpetuate the error and to call Reed's Building No. 1 &ldquo;the<lb/>
place where Doctor Finlay...&rdquo;</p>
<p>I have been informed that certain Americans will be officially invited<lb/>
to the dedication - the Surgeon General or his deputy, the American<lb/>
Ambassador and others, myself included (I expect to fly down for the<lb/>
ceremony.), but I do not believe any official invitations have yet been<lb/>
sent out.</p>
<p>Doctor Smith, I am sure that this event will interest many American<lb/>
physicians and deserves your attention. I suppose nothing more than a<lb/>
short news item will be appropriate for the J.A.M.A. but I am sure that<lb/>
you will want at least to have that. I am suggesting to you and to the<lb/>
editors of the MILITARY SURGEON and the U. S. ARMED FORCES MEDICAL JOURNAL<lb/>
that you contact the office of the Minister of Public Health and ask for<lb/>
preliminary information regarding the dedication so that you can carry<lb/>
the appropriate news item. You could write to Dr. Jose Raimundo Andreu,<lb/>
El Ministro de Salubridad y Asistencia Social, Havana, or to the Public<lb/>
Relations Department, El Ministerio de Salubridad y Asistencia Social.<lb/>
Or you might prefer to write directly to Dr. Pedro Nogueira, Marti 219,<lb/>
Marianao, Havana, Cuba, the dynamo behind the project. Your inquiry<lb/>
would not only serve to show how much the Americans, especially the<lb/>
American medical profession, appreciate this gracious gesture on the part<lb/>
of the Cuban Government, but may definitely tend to keep them in line so<lb/>
as to use the appropriate names and not try to put anything over. I must<lb/>
hope and believe that they intend to do the right thing.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: Regarding the rediscovery of Camp Lazear, etc., please see the<lb/>
enclosed reprint, pages 3 through 7.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
