<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04433049">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George P. Berry to William W. Caswell, Jr., November 26, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Berry, George P.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04433049</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Caswell, Jr., William W.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Rodriguez Exposito, Cesar</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados de Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-26">November 26, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04433049</idno>
<title>Letter from George P. Berry to William W. Caswell, Jr., November 26, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Berry, of Harvard Medical School, explains the background and significance of the upcoming Camp Lazear dedication, and requests that Caswell represent Harvard at the ceremony.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-26">
<head>Letter from George P. Berry to William W. Caswell, Jr., November 26, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04433049"/>
<opener>
COPY<lb/>
<dateline>
HARVARD MEDICAL SCHOOL<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE DEAN<lb/>
25 SHATTUCK STREET<lb/>
BOSTON, MASSACHUSETTS<lb/>
<date value="1952-11-26">November 26, 1952</date>
</dateline>
AIR MAIL SPECIAL DELIVERY<lb/>
Wreath for <hi>wood</hi><lb/>
Mr. William W. Caswell, Jr.<lb/>
First National Bank of Boston<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mr. Caswell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You will have to blame Mr. W. H. Claflin for this letter and the favor<lb/>
which it asks.</p>
<p>On December 3rd, the anniversary of the birthday of Carlos Finlay, which<lb/>
is &ldquo;Physicians' Day in Cuba,&rdquo; the Cuban Government is memorializing the remains<lb/>
of Walter Reed's Camp Lazear in Quemados de Marianao. The remains of Building<lb/>
No. 1 have been repaired, a little park has been made and on a stone wall will<lb/>
be unveiled several individual bronze medallions, one in memory of Dr. Leonard<lb/>
Wood. Other profiles will be those of Finlay, Delgado, Reed, Carroll, Lazear<lb/>
and Agramonte. On each side of the medallions will be a bronze tablet with<lb/>
the names of the volunteers who served as guinea pigs. I understand that<lb/>
the Cuban Government has invited a number of Americans and American medical<lb/>
institutions to participate. I understand also that General Streit, Commanding<lb/>
General of Walter Reed General Hospital, will attend, representing the Surgeon<lb/>
General, and that others are planning to go. The U. S. Embassy will participate<lb/>
in the ceremonies.</p>
<p>I believe that this is a significant occasion which will mark the beginning<lb/>
of a better Cuban-American relationship. As you probably know, Dr. Wood<lb/>
graduated from the Harvard Medical School in 1884, and for this reason,<lb/>
plus the fact that it would be a gesture of international medical good-will,<lb/>
I should very much like to have a graduate of Harvard attend the ceremony and<lb/>
lay a wreath at the appropriate time and place. Unfortunately we have no<lb/>
Medical School graduate in Havana. That is why I am writing to ask if you<lb/>
will be willing to represent Harvard (and the Medical School) at this particular<lb/>
occasion. I regret that I must necessarily give you such short notice of this<lb/>
affair. The fact is that the final date for the dedication has only recently<lb/>
been set.</p>
<p>Dr. Philip S. Hench of the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, who will<lb/>
attend the ceremony and who has made arrangements with the Cuban authorities<lb/>
to make a place during the ceremony for the placing of the wreaths, suggests<lb/>
that a circular wreath of laurel leaves, perhaps 30 inches in diameter, with<lb/>
a silk ribbon either the <del>college</del><add><unclear>color</unclear></add> of the college or red, white and blue for<lb/>
the United States would be appropriate. Would you be willing to arrange for<lb/>
the preparation of such a wreath in Havana? Naturally, any costs either for<lb/>
the wreath or for your personal expenses would be borne by Harvard and I shall<lb/>
count upon you to inform me.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04433050"/>
<p>Mr. William W. Caswell, Jr.</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>November 26, 1952</p>
<p>I am sorry that I cannot give you more specific details as to time, etc.,<lb/>
at this end. However, Dr. Hench has wired me that if you will contact either<lb/>
Dr. Rodriguez Exposito or Dr. Pedro Nogueira, Marti 219, Marianao, Havana,<lb/>
they will be able to give you all the information you need. Dr. Hench expects<lb/>
to be in Havana from Sunday, November 30th, on and can be reached at the Hotel<lb/>
Nacional.</p>
<p>I realize that I am rather taking it forgranted you will be able to<lb/>
represent us next Wednesday. It is because time is so short that I have<lb/>
written in this vein. If for any reason it is not feasible for you to<lb/>
do so, Dr. Hench will see to it that the wreath is placed at the proper time.</p>
<p>In the hope that you will be able to attend, and with kindest regards,<lb/>
I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>George Packer Berry, M.D.<lb/>
Dean</signed>
Signed in Dr. Berry's absence by secretary<lb/>
CC: Dr. Hench<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
