<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04433026">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George K. Strode, November 20, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04433026</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Strode, George K.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-20">November 20, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04433026</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George K. Strode, November 20, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench hopes that Strode, or one of his Rockefeller Foundation associates, will attend the Camp Lazear dedication. In his speech Hench plans to credit Finlay with the mosquito theory and Reed with its proof.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George K. Strode, November 20, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04433026"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-20">November 20, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. G. K. Strode<lb/>
Director of International Health Division<lb/>
Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
New York, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Strode:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You may have heard that the Cuban Government has made a little park at<lb/>
Walter Reed's Camp Lazear outside of Havana and are dedicating it to<lb/>
the glories of Doctor Finlay, Major Reed and their colleagues on December 3,<lb/>
Finlay's birthday which is &ldquo;Physicians' Day in Cuba.&rdquo; Although Doctor<lb/>
Finlay will receive perhaps the major share of honors, nonetheless this is<lb/>
a very gracious gesture on the part of the Cubans for this is the first<lb/>
time they have ever honored Major Reed. I understand they propose to main-<lb/>
tain the name Camp Lazear and that Reed's Building No. 1 will retain its<lb/>
name also.</p>
<p>I believe that you and/or some of your associates will receive official<lb/>
invitations to the affair, at least I hope so. The Surgeon General has<lb/>
appointed General Paul H. Streit, Commanding General of Walter Reed Hospital,<lb/>
as his official representative. The Mayo Foundation is sending me as its<lb/>
representative. The ceremony will probably be a modest one in view of the<lb/>
humble nature of Camp Lazear, but nevertheless it will be one of real<lb/>
significance.</p>
<p>Doctor Strode, having been to Cuba often (see the enclosed reprint if you<lb/>
care to do so), I know that as one of the speakers at the dedication I will<lb/>
probably be interviewed by the patriotic Cuban press. Although I intend to<lb/>
honor Finlay in full measure, I intend of course to make no retreats, to<lb/>
speak of Finlay and his theory or conception and to speak of the <hi>proof</hi> of<lb/>
Reed Reed and his associates. But you can fortify me or help me greatly<lb/>
if you can answer for me one question. Have recent researches changed<lb/>
materially Reed's formula for the development of yellow fever? I have<lb/>
consulted your book but am not certain whether the data on page 443<lb/>
represents modern thinking or refers to the old historical investigations.<lb/>
You will remember that Reed's formula is as follows: The virus is in the<lb/>
patient's blood for only the first three days and to become harmful it<lb/>
must be incubated in the body of the mosquito for at least twelve to fourteen<lb/>
days (see your book, page 548).</p>
<p>On page 443 of your book Taylor has written that the virus remains in the<lb/>
patient's blood not over four to five days and that to be harmful it must<lb/>
incubate in the mosquito for eight to twelve days.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04433027"/>
<p><unclear>Ac</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>Hms</unclear></p>
<p>Dr. G. K. Strode</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>November 20, 1952</p>
<p>If the latter represents definite modern thinking, the formula of Reed has<lb/>
not been materially altered or at least not altered enough, so far as I can<lb/>
see, to allow us to believe that any of Doctor Finlay's cases, by modern re-<lb/>
interpretation, were of experimental (rather than natural) yellow fever. Is<lb/>
that your understanding of the situation?</p>
<p>I realize that this is a crucial question and one contentious to the Cubans.<lb/>
I propose to try to stay out of any arguments or discussions on it but it<lb/>
would give me quiet courage if I had your advice in the matter and while I<lb/>
expect to be able to avoid any unpleasant questioning, they may well ask<lb/>
me the &ldquo;$64 question&rdquo;: &ldquo;Have not modern researches shown that in all like-<lb/>
lihood Doctor Finlay's cases were actually experimental yellow fever?&rdquo;<lb/>
Can you, unofficially and confidentially, back up my intended answer: &ldquo;So<lb/>
far as I know, the formula for the development of yellow fever as outlined<lb/>
by Reed and his colleagues has not been changed sufficiently to permit us<lb/>
to believe that Doctor Finlay's experiments were actually positive, even<lb/>
though his theory was so eminently and brilliantly correct.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
