<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04433055">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Willard L. Beaulac, November 28, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04433055</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Beaulac, Willard L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="person">Rodriguez Exposito, Cesar</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Carbonell, Felipe Ponce</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-28">November 28, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04433055</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Willard L. Beaulac, November 28, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is pleased that Beaulac, the American Ambassador to Cuba, will hold a reception following the Camp Lazear dedication. Hench forwards a copy of his remarks for the dedication so that Beaulac may be better informed about the history and persons associated with Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-28">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Willard L. Beaulac, November 28, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04433055"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-28">November 28, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Willard L. Beaulac<lb/>
American Ambassador<lb/>
American Embassy<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Beaulac:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am delighted to know that you are in the land of the living. My previous<lb/>
letter was addressed as a result of misinformation given to me by a colleague<lb/>
here who is supposed to know all about such things. He is now hanging his head<lb/>
in the corner.</p>
<p>Your letter was very gracious and it is extremely kind of you to suggest giving<lb/>
a reception for certain Americans and <unclear>Cubans</unclear>. I certainly hope and expect that<lb/>
are this you have received an official invitation and information about the af-<lb/>
fair. However I know my Cuban friends well enough to know that manana can mean<lb/>
a long time. They have been mentioning the participation of the American Embassy<lb/>
in this planned ceremony for months but it may well be that you will receive the<lb/>
invitation minutes before the ceremony!</p>
<p>Although Dr. Pedro Nogueira's name does not appear on the enclosed <unclear>invitation</unclear>, he<lb/>
has really been the <unclear>dynamo</unclear> behind the Cuban affair. He sent me a dozen extra in-<lb/>
vitations to send to the relatives of yellow fever personalities but I am sending<lb/>
you one quite unofficially so that you may see who are involved. I am writing to<lb/>
Doctor Nogueira at once telling him that I assume that an invitation has already<lb/>
been sent to the American Embassy, telling him about certain American representa-<lb/>
tives who wish to place wreaths in front of the medallions at the appropriate time<lb/>
during the ceremony, etc. (His address is Marti 219, Marianao, Havana). He may<lb/>
well telephone you or your secretary <unclear>shotly</unclear>.</p>
<p>As for the reception and the optimal time for it, I could of course say little as<lb/>
I don't know exactly what they plan except I believe there is a meeting at the<lb/>
Academy of Medicine the night of December 3. It would be indeed most pleasant if<lb/>
a selected group of Americans and Cubans could <unclear>meet</unclear> at your home but I would not want<lb/>
you to make it a troublesome affair for you. Americans suggested for invitations<lb/>
would be of course General Streit, Commanding General of Walter Reed Hospital, who<lb/>
will be the representative of the Surgeon General; Dr. L. M. <unclear>Tocantins</unclear> of Jeffer-<lb/>
son Medical College, Philadelphia, from which Dr. Carlos Finlay graduated. He is<lb/>
flying down for the ceremony. I will represent the Mayo Foundation. The following<lb/>
representatives of the stated medical schools will be laying wreaths: For Harvard<lb/>
Medical School in honor of General Wood, Mr. William W. <unclear>Caswell,</unclear> Jr., First National<lb/>
Bank of Boston, Havana, Cuba; University of Maryland in honor of Doctor Carroll,<lb/>
Dr. Jose R. Echeverria, Castillo Del Principe, Havana; Bellevue Medical School,<lb/>
(New York University), in honor of Reed, Dr. <unclear>Emilio</unclear> Jayne of Havana; for the College<lb/>
of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University, to honor Agramonte, Lazear and<lb/>
Sternberg, Dr. Raimundo de Castro, President of Columbia Alumni Club of Cuba and<lb/>
Professor of Legal Medicine, University of Havana.</p>
<p>What Cubans should be invited, I leave up to you but I should think Doctor Saladrigas,<lb/>
Minister of Health, Doctor Recio, Doctor Nogueira, Dr. Rodriguez Exposito, and of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04433056"/>
Mr. Willard L. Beaulac<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 28, 1952<lb/>
course President Batista. Also in the past Cuban Administration, the following<lb/>
were very helpful with this project: Dr. Jose Andreu, the former Minister of<lb/>
Health; Dr. Domingo Ramos, former Minister of Defense. Dr. Felipe Carbonell<lb/>
has been very helpful to me and very interested in this project. I think some of<lb/>
these gentlemen don't belong to the same political party. Through the years I<lb/>
have worked with a number of conflicting elements. You will know better than I<lb/>
what to do about this or, I should think, Dr. Nogueira could give you a very<lb/>
fair summary of the situation. If I personally can be of any help, I should<lb/>
be delighted and I will be available at the Hotel Nacional this Sunday morning.<lb/>
I am indeed grateful for the interest you have shown in this matter.</p>
<p>I enclose a copy of the preliminary draft of my own remarks. They will be<lb/>
shortened materially but it will give you further information about the inter-<lb/>
relationships of the Finca San Jose, Doctor Finlay, Camp Lazear, etc.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
