<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04433008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Bennett, November 18, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04433008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Bennett, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Rodriguez Exposito, Cesar </name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados de Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-18">November 18, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04433008</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Bennett, November 18, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench inquires whether the Medical School of Jefferson College or the Medical Alumni Association would be interested in placing a wreath under the medallion of Finlay during the dedication ceremony of Camp Lazear. Finlay graduated from Jefferson Medical College in 1855.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-18">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Bennett, November 18, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04433008"/>
<opener>
11/26/52<lb/>
<unclear></unclear> Were f Paul Roke<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-18">November 18, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. George A. Bennett, Dean<lb/>
Jefferson Medical College<lb/>
Philadelphia, Pennsylvania<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Bennett:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On December 3, the anniversary of the birthday of Carlos Finlay, which<lb/>
is &ldquo;Physicians' Day in Cuba,&rdquo; the Cuban Government is memorializing the<lb/>
remains of Walter Reed's Camp Lazear in Quemados de Marianao. The re-<lb/>
mains of Building No. 1 have been repaired, a little park has been made<lb/>
and on a stone wall will be unveiled several individual bronze medallions,<lb/>
profiles of Finlay, Delgado, Reed, Carroll, Lazear, Agramonte and Wood.<lb/>
On each side will be a bronze tablet with the names of the volunteers<lb/>
who served as guinea pigs.</p>
<p>This will be, I believe, a significant occasion because heretofore there<lb/>
has been, unfortunately, a considerable feeling of animosity in certain<lb/>
Cuban circles against those who have honored Reed and his colleagues, the<lb/>
Cuban viewpoint being that American medicine has ignored the great contribu-<lb/>
tion of Finlay. Now for the first time the Cuban Government is honoring<lb/>
the contribution of the Americans by memorializing Camp Lazear in this way.<lb/>
Although I am not certain, it is possible that they may not retain the<lb/>
name Camp Lazear but may rename the place Perque Finlay. Nevertheless,<lb/>
the bronze tablets, the dedicatory speeches and so on, will make clear the<lb/>
significance of this spot and they are making a small but nevertheless fine<lb/>
beginning towards a better Cuban-American relationship.</p>
<p>I believe the Cuban Government is planning to send invitations to a number<lb/>
of Americans and American medical institutions. They have been delayed in<lb/>
doing this because of some uncertainty as to the final date for the dedica-<lb/>
tion; but the date has now been set for December 3. I know that General<lb/>
Streit, Commanding General of Walter Reed Hospital, will be there, repre-<lb/>
senting the Surgeon General and a few others are planning to go. The U. S.<lb/>
Embassy will be represented and I have been told that President Batista<lb/>
will participate in the ceremonies.</p>
<p>It seems to me that the Americans who attend this ceremony should not go<lb/>
empty-handed but should respond in a generous way to the gracious intent<lb/>
of the Cuban Government and medical profession and thus strengthen the<lb/>
friendship between the Cuban and American medical professions. It occurred<lb/>
to me that since Doctor Finlay was a graduate of Jefferson Medical College<lb/>
(1855), the Medical School or the Medical Alumni <unclear>ssociation</unclear> might wish to<lb/>
have a representative of their institution place a wreath or floral decora-<lb/>
tion under the medallion of Doctor Finlay on this occasion. Therefore I am<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04433009"/>
Dr. George A. Bennett<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 18, 1952<lb/>
writing to you asking whether you would think that would be appropriate. I<lb/>
am writing similar letters to the other half dozen institutions from which<lb/>
those who are mainly to be honored obtained their medical degrees.</p>
<p>This merely is a request for information as to whether you would think this<lb/>
gesture appropriate. If so, I shall communicate by cable with the Cuban<lb/>
authorities and ask them if they will make a place during the ceremony<lb/>
for the placing of these wreaths.</p>
<p>If you have an alumnus that lives in Havana (and it need not necessarily<lb/>
be a physician) it would be most appropriate for him to place the wreath<lb/>
at the proper time; or better yet, if one of your faculty could go (and<lb/>
I fear that the Cuban government has no monetary subsidy), that would be<lb/>
excellent and I will request that a personal invitation <unclear>he sent</unclear> for them.<lb/>
If neither of those are possible. I would myself see to it that the wreath<lb/>
was placed at the proper time, either by the American Ambassador, by General<lb/>
Streight, or by myself. However it would be much more effective if a<lb/>
representative of your institution could do that, providing this sugges-<lb/>
tion is approved first by you and then by our Cuban hosts.</p>
<p>Our local florist has told me that he thought a circular wreath of laurel<lb/>
leaves, perhaps 30 inches in diameter, would be appropriate, perhaps with<lb/>
a silk ribbon either with the colors of the college or red, white and blue<lb/>
for the United States, at a cost of perhaps $15 or so. Should you approve<lb/>
the general idea, would you care to have your own representative arrange<lb/>
for the preparation of the wreath in Havana? If not, I should be glad to<lb/>
help in any way and could either have the half dozen or so <unclear>wreaths made</unclear><lb/>
up in Havana a day or two ahead or, according to our local florist, they<lb/>
can be made up in Miami and flown to Havana and delivered to the appropriate<lb/>
person for placement.</p>
<p>I would appreciate greatly hearing from you at your earliest convenience.<lb/>
Enclosed please find a photograph of the blue print and a reprint which will<lb/>
refresh your mind on the significance of Camp Lazear.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: If it seems more appropriate, you might prefer to send a telegraphic<lb/>
message. The wire could be sent either to His Excellency, Dr. Jose Andreu,<lb/>
El Ministro de Salubridad y Asistencia Social or to one of his agents in<lb/>
this matter, Dr. Pedro Nogueira, Marti 219, Marianao, Havana, or Dr. Cesar<lb/>
Rodriguez, Exposito, Secretary, Marti 219, Marianao, Havana.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
