<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04433011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George P. Berry, November 19, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04433011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Berry, George P.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Rodriguez Exposito, Cesar</name>
<name type="place">Quemados de Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-19">November 19, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04433011</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George P. Berry, November 19, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench inquires whether the Medical School of Harvard University might wish to have a representative place a wreath under the medallion of Wood during the dedication ceremonies of Camp Lazear. Wood graduated from Harvard Medical School in the late 1880s.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George P. Berry, November 19, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04433011"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-19">November 19, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. George P. Berry<lb/>
Dean of the Medical School<lb/>
Harvard University<lb/>
Boston, Massachusetts<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Berry:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On December 3, the anniversary of the birthday of Carlos Finlay, which is<lb/>
&ldquo;Physicians' Day in Cuba,&rdquo; the Cuban Government is memorializing the re-<lb/>
mains of Walter Reed's Camp Lazear in Quemados de Marianao. The remains<lb/>
of Building No. 1 have been repaired, a little park has been made and on<lb/>
a stone wall will be unveiled several individual bronze medallions, pro-<lb/>
files of Finlay, Delgado, Reed, Carroll, Lazear, Agramonte and Wood. On<lb/>
each side will be a bronze tablet with the names of the volunteers who<lb/>
served as guinea pigs.</p>
<p>This will be, I believe, a significant occasion because heretofore there<lb/>
has been, unfortunately, a considerable feeling of animosity in certain<lb/>
Cuban circles against those who have honored Reed and his colleagues,<lb/>
the Cuban viewpoint being that American medicine has ignored the great<lb/>
contribution of Finlay. Now for the first time the Cuban government is<lb/>
honoring the contribution of the Americans by memorializing Camp Lazear<lb/>
in this way. Although I am not certain, it is possible that they may<lb/>
not retain the name Camp Lazear but may rename the place Parque Finlay.<lb/>
Nevertheless the bronze tablets, the dedicatory speeches and so on, will<lb/>
make clear the significance of this spot and they are making a small but<lb/>
nevertheless fine beginning toward a better Cuban-American relationship.</p>
<p>I believe that the Cuban Government is planning to send invitations to a<lb/>
number of Americans and American medical institutions. They have been<lb/>
delayed in doing this because of some uncertainty as to the final date<lb/>
for the dedication but the date has now been set for December 3. I know<lb/>
that General Streit, Commanding General of Walter Reed General Hospital,<lb/>
will be there, representing the Surgeon General and a few others are<lb/>
planning to go. The U. S. Embassy will participate in the ceremonies.</p>
<p>It seems to me that the Americans who attend this ceremony should not go<lb/>
empty-handed but should respond in a generous way to the gracious intent<lb/>
of the Cuban Government and medical profession and thus strengthen the<lb/>
friendship between the Cuban and American medical professions. It oc-<lb/>
curred to me that since General Wood was a graduate of the Medical School<lb/>
of Harvard University (1884, or was it 1883), the Medical School or the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04433012"/>
Dr. George P. Berry<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 19, 1952<lb/>
Medical Alumni Association might wish to have a representative of their<lb/>
institution place a wreath or floral decoration under the medallion of<lb/>
General Wood on this occasion. Therefore I am writing you asking whether<lb/>
you would think that would be appropriate. I am writing similar letters<lb/>
to the other half dozen institutions from which those who are mainly to<lb/>
be honored obtained their medical degrees.</p>
<p>This is merely a request for information as to whether you would think this<lb/>
gesture appropriate. If so, I shall communicate by cable with the Cuban<lb/>
authorities and ask them if they will make a place during the ceremony<lb/>
for the placing of these wreaths.</p>
<p>If you have an alumnus that lives in Havana (and it need not necessarily<lb/>
be a physician) it would be most appropriate for him to place the wreath<lb/>
at the proper time; or better yet, if one of your faculty could go (and<lb/>
I fear that the Cuban Government has no monetary subsidy), that would be<lb/>
excellent and I will request that a personal invitation be sent for them.<lb/>
If neither of these are possible, I would myself see to it that the wreath<lb/>
was placed at the proper time, either by the American Ambassador, by<lb/>
General Streit or by myself. However it would be much more effective if<lb/>
a representative of your institution could do that, providing this sug-<lb/>
gestion is approved first by you and then by our Cuban hosts.</p>
<p>Our local florist has told me that he thought a circular wreath of laurel<lb/>
leaves, perhaps 30 inches in diameter, would be appropriate, perhaps with<lb/>
a silk ribbon either with the colors of the college or red, white and blue<lb/>
for the United States, at a cost of perhaps $15 or so. Should you approve<lb/>
of the general idea, would you care to have your own representative arrange<lb/>
for the preparation of the wreath in Havana? If not, I should be glad to<lb/>
help in any way and could either have the half dozen or so wreaths made<lb/>
up in Havana a day or two ahead or, according to our local florist, they<lb/>
can be made up in Miami and flown to Havana and delivered to the appropriate<lb/>
person for placement.</p>
<p>I would greatly appreciate hearing from you at your earliest convenience.<lb/>
Enclosed please find a photograph of the blue print and a reprint which<lb/>
will refresh your mind on the significance of Camp Lazear.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: If it seems more appropriate, you might prefer to send a telegraphic<lb/>
message. The wire could be sent either to His Excellency Dr. Jose Andreu,<lb/>
El Ministro de Salubridad y Asistencia Social or to one of his agents in<lb/>
this matter, Dr. Pedro Nogueira, Marti 219, Marianao, Havana, or Dr. Cesar<lb/>
Rodriguez Exposito, Secretary, Marti 219, Marianao, Havana.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
