<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509026">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, November 7, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509026</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Mrs. Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Fishbein, Morris</name>
<name type="person">Spies, Tom D.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-07">November 7, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509026</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, November 7, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench suggests additional individuals to be invited to the dedication of Camp Lazear. He expresses concern about the restoration work on Building No. 1, fearing that it is replication instead of restoration. Hench requests further details about his involvement during the dedication ceremony and Science Academy Session.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-07">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, November 7, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509026"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1952-11-07">November 7, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You will want the following addresses:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California</item>
<item>Mr. James L. Hanberry<lb/>
591 Summers Avenue<lb/>
Orangeburg, South Carolina</item>
<item>Mrs. Robert P. Cooke<lb/>
Whistle Creek<lb/>
Lexington, Virginia</item>
<item>Mr. Gust E. Lambert<lb/>
4718 Woodlawn Avenue<lb/>
Chicago, Illinois</item>
</list></p>
<p>I have not corresponded with Mr. Lambert for three or four years. I hope<lb/>
this address is correct.</p>
<p>I have today written all of them telling them that you want a photograph<lb/>
of them. You did not say for what purpose you wanted it, for publicity<lb/>
purposes related to the dedication of Camp Lazear or to be framed and hung<lb/>
in the little building. If it is for publicity purposes you may want a<lb/>
glossy print. If it is to hang in the building you will want a smooth<lb/>
print, possibly with their autograph. I have told each of them that they<lb/>
will be hearing from you immediately.</p>
<p>As I wrote you, Doctor Cooke has just died; therefore I wrote to Mrs. Cooke.<lb/>
Regarding Lambert and Hanberry, neither one can afford to go to Cuba without<lb/>
financial assistance. If you must choose only one, Hanberry would of course<lb/>
be the one as he is now the only surviving volunteer</p>
<p>I just received two days ago the airplane photographs of Camp Lazear taken<lb/>
from quite high up. I am very glad to have these but I am more anxious to<lb/>
have some taken lower down, especially the tangential views which will be<lb/>
taken later. I certainly appreciate your efforts regarding this.</p>
<p>I was a little dismayed to see from the photographs that you all decided to<lb/>
remove all of the walling. Will that not make the present Building No. 1<lb/>
almost a replica rather than a restoration? We know that the inner walls<lb/>
were original, showing the tongued-and-grooved boards, also the sliding panels<lb/>
and outer shutters must have been original. I am not sure how much of the<lb/>
roof was original. Of course there was no ceiling. I do hope that you can<lb/>
use part of the original walling or, if you can't use it outside, could you<lb/>
erect a few of the original tongued-and-grooved panels inside as a demonstra-<lb/>
tion of the original construction in one part of the room? I do hope also<lb/>
you can reinsert the original sliding panel and shutters. I am indeed grateful<lb/>
to you for saving me some of this wood as I am most anxious to have it. Since<lb/>
I will be flying back, I will not be able to bring it back but I shall try to<lb/>
make arrangements for someone to pack me a box and ship it to me by freight<lb/>
or express.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04509027"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>November 7, 1952</p>
<p>Pedro, you say that you want me to talk for 8 or 10 minutes and I shall start<lb/>
collecting my thoughts. Will my talk be at the dedication? I shall keep the<lb/>
talk strictly limited to the allotted time. As I write it, I should like to<lb/>
know what the name of the camp will be. Is it to be called Camp Lazear or<lb/>
Parque Finlay or a combination of the two names, &ldquo;Parque Finlay at Camp Lazear.&rdquo;<lb/>
As you know, I have been hoping that the name Camp Lazear could be maintained<lb/>
and I assume that Building No. 1 will still be called Reed's Building No. 1.<lb/>
The reason I ask is that I want to use the proper terms in my talk and not have<lb/>
a conflict with the other talks.</p>
<p>You ask me to attend the Science Academy Session &ldquo;on the 3rd night&rdquo; where you<lb/>
will be the principal speaker. I assume that you mean on the evening of<lb/>
December 3. Will you please let me know at once whether this is correct? If<lb/>
so, I shall plan to stay over that night and will attend the session with great<lb/>
pleasure. I suspect that the speeches will be mostly in Spanish and I won't<lb/>
understand them but I shall be happy to be there to honor those concerned. You<lb/>
say that I should not forget my Finlay Medal. Will the affair be formal? Will<lb/>
there be occasion for me to bring my dinner jacket or just a dark business suit?<lb/>
What time will this affair be over in the evening? I had planned to take the<lb/>
night plane from Havana to Chicago but perhaps I had better stay over until the<lb/>
night of December 4.</p>
<p>Some months ago there seems to have been organized a Walter Reed Society sponsored<lb/>
by the National Society for Medical Research. I know nothing about it. I<lb/>
merely found a clipping on page 214 of the Journal of the American Medical<lb/>
Association, January 19, 1952. The following are the officers and you might<lb/>
wish to send them invitations:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Max Sadove, Head of the Department of Anesthesiology, University of Illinois,<lb/>
Chicago, Illinois (President).</item>
<item>Dr. Clinton H. Thienes, Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology,<lb/>
University of Southern California School of Medicine, Los Angeles,<lb/>
California (Vice President).</item>
<item>Dr. Lloyd D. Seager, Department of Physiology and Pharmacology, University of Arkansas<lb/>
Fayetteville, Arkansas (Vice President)</item>
<item>Dr. John P. McGovern, Chief of the Outpatient Department, Children's Hospital<lb/>
Washington, D. C. (Vice President).</item>
<item>Miss Betty Jenney, Research Associate, University of Illinois, Chicago, Illinois<lb/>
(Secretary-Treasurer).</item>
</list></p>
<p>I do not know how extensive your invitation list is. Undoubtedly you are in-<lb/>
viting other distinguished American physicians and perhaps U. S. Public Health<lb/>
Officials. Have you in mind to invite the President of the American Medical<lb/>
Association, Dr. Louis H. Bauer. His address is 131 Fulton Avenue, Hempstead,<lb/>
Long Island, New York; also the President-Elect of the American Medical Associa-<lb/>
tion, Dr. Edward James McCormick, 402 Madison Avenue, Toledo, Ohio. Dr. Morris<lb/>
Fishbein is, I believe, one of the active members of an organization formed a<lb/>
few years ago called the &ldquo;Finlay Institute of the Americans.&rdquo; I know nothing<lb/>
about it. I merely read a little something about it somewhere. You might care<lb/>
to invite Doctor Fishbein and some of his associates if the organization is<lb/>
still active. His address is:5543 Blackstone Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04509028"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>November 7, 1952</p>
<p>I have a special reason for having a representative group invited and I have<lb/>
talked to you about it before but I think it is now more important than ever.<lb/>
When I see you we must discuss the next move. I still hope that now that you<lb/>
and the Cuban government have made such a splendid beginning, it is time for<lb/>
our American friends to start the ball rolling for the erection of a permanent<lb/>
memorial building, in one room of which will be Building No. 1. The rest of<lb/>
the building can be devoted to some public and useful venture, perhaps a<lb/>
small public health unit. The more American doctors we can get interested in<lb/>
all of this, the easier it will be to raise the necessary money. I assume you<lb/>
are sending official invitations to the State Department and to the American<lb/>
Embassy in Cuba. You will remember that Tom Spies and Mrs. Smith of F.I.M.<lb/>
are also quite interested in the venture.</p>
<p>I hope that in thinking about foreigners, you don't forget to invite Miss<lb/>
Rojas and Miss Cabrerra to the affair. It was Miss Rojas' father of course<lb/>
who cooperated with Walter Reed in setting up the camp on the Finca San Jose.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
