<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509047">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, December 12, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509047</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-12-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-12-12">December 12, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509047</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, December 12, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Nogueira for his hospitality during his stay in Cuba. Hench is trying to salvage parts of Building No. 1 and requests Nogueira's assistance.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-12-12">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, December 12, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509047"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-12-12">December 12, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I had an uneventful return flight, much more easily accomplished than my<lb/>
down flight, and was home at 6:30 Sunday evening. Your letter and markings<lb/>
regarding the fumigation of the wood solved the problem promptly and I brought<lb/>
the wood home safely. I am delighted to have it.</p>
<p>You will recall that I had not seen, before you packed it, the large heavy ob-<lb/>
ject. When I opened it I found that it was not the sliding panel but one of<lb/>
the old shutters. The fact that it is made of tongued-and-grooved wood con-<lb/>
vinces me that it is one of the original shutters.</p>
<p>There are two items missing which I hope that you can try to salvage at once<lb/>
with the help of Juan: (1) the other shutter and (2) the solid wood sliding<lb/>
panel. In all likelihood the other shutter is also the original and I would<lb/>
urge that you at once salvage it. It does not need to be set up at the window<lb/>
of Building No. 1 but eventually it can be properly mounted and demonstrated<lb/>
inside the caseta. Regarding these solid shutters and the description of<lb/>
the windows in general, see your copy of Senate Document No. 822 (compilation<lb/>
of Reed's yellow fever papers) pages 83 and 97. Quote from page 83: &ldquo;These<lb/>
windows were both placed on the south side of the building...They were closed<lb/>
by permanent wire screen of 0.5 mm. mesh. In addition sliding glass sash were<lb/>
provided within and heavy wooden shutters without...&rdquo; Quote from page 97:<lb/>
&ldquo;Both houses were provided with wire-screen windows and double wire-screen<lb/>
doors...&rdquo;</p>
<p>I enclose two photographs; one taken for me in 1941, the other in 1948. You<lb/>
will note in each the ledges beneath and above the window on which the solid<lb/>
sliding panel slid sideways. In 1941, Zunzunegui was inclined to assure me<lb/>
that the sliding panel as well as the window shutters were original. Since<lb/>
the shutters are made of tongued and grooved boards, doubtless they are original<lb/>
but you will note on page 83 that Reed spoke of &ldquo;sliding glass sash&rdquo;. This<lb/>
means one of two things. (1) That the sliding panel in the photographs is<lb/>
not Reed's but was made sometime after 1900, presumably when the glass broke, or<lb/>
(2) perhaps the frame of the sliding panel in the photographs was original<lb/>
but there were three glass inserts which became broken and were filled with<lb/>
wood, presumably by Zunzunegui, as shown in the photographs. I should think<lb/>
that a careful examination of the sliding panel would reveal to you whether<lb/>
it looked like old 1900 American Army wood or a later product.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04509048"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>December 12, 1952</p>
<p>Frankly, although I would like to believe that the sliding panel is in part<lb/>
original, I suspect that it may not be. Nevertheless since it is in our<lb/>
photographs, copies of which will eventually be made available for demonstration<lb/>
inside the caseta and since it was used possibly from 1907 on, it is &ldquo;semi-<lb/>
historical&rdquo; and should be saved, at least temporarily.</p>
<p>Pedro, may I urge therefore that at your very earliest convenience, before<lb/>
Juan or the carpenters destroy the unsaved wood, will you please show them<lb/>
these two photographs and have them try to find at once the sliding panel<lb/>
and the other outer wooden shutter, the companion to the one which you so<lb/>
kindly gave me.</p>
<p>I will sent to you, as soon as I catch my breath, the other two or three items<lb/>
you want - the photograph from Mrs. Reed's scrapbook showing the six little<lb/>
yellow fever huts by the LaPlaya railroad track, a photographic copy of<lb/>
Agramonte's article with the drawings of the buildings, a photostat of a<lb/>
letter from Reed to his wife with an inked sketch with his plan for Building<lb/>
No. 2.</p>
<p>In closing this hasty note, may I express to you, in a very inadequate fashion,<lb/>
and to your colleagues - but first and always to you, Pedro, for your wonderful<lb/>
hospitality and cooperation all through this affair, but especially last week -<lb/>
my deep and sincere appreciation. I am most enthusiastic and have many plans<lb/>
brewing in my head which I shall write you about as soon as I can catch up<lb/>
with my work.</p>
<p>One more thing. You and I are rightfully the custodians of the souvenir wood.<lb/>
Why don't we do the thing properly? As soon as I can, I will make a list<lb/>
of the American institutions and individuals whom I think should have one or<lb/>
more pieces of the wood. You do the same for your Cuban colleagues. Before<lb/>
actually presenting any wood to one of these prospective recipients, I will,<lb/>
however, write to the person or instution and make absolutely certain that<lb/>
they not only want a piece of the wood but that they will preserve it properly.<lb/>
Then I will carefully number my pieces (and I will probably need many more which<lb/>
you can send me in due time) and keep a record of each one as I give it away.<lb/>
I would strongly suggest that you do the same thing. In that way we can make<lb/>
a sort of &ldquo;pedigreed list&rdquo; of the wood and thereafter there will be not only<lb/>
less chance of losing track of it but also a better chance to authenticate<lb/>
any piece that might turn up in someone else's hands. Indeed it has occurred<lb/>
to me that it would be nice if we could make, without too much expense, a<lb/>
little &ldquo;branding iron&rdquo;, perhaps with the seal of the United States and that<lb/>
of Cuba side by side, the whole thing about 1 by 1 1/2 inches, so that we could<lb/>
burn in the corner of each piece of wood this little branding mark which would<lb/>
authenticate each piece, perhaps burning a number in at the same time. If a<lb/>
branding mark with the seals of the two Countries would be too expensive, and<lb/>
it might be, perhaps I could get one something as follows: &ldquo;C/A - 100&rdquo;, meaning<lb/>
Cuban-American Museum, piece No. 100.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
