<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 8, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-09-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Armstrong, George E.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, John L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Houston</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Walter De Blois</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>

<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Army Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-09-08">September 8, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509010</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 8, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Nogueira that the U.S. State Department and the Surgeon General's Office would like to receive an official invitation in order to send a representative to the dedication of Camp Lazear. There remain only two survivors from the experiments: Hanberry and Cooke.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-09-08">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 8, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509010"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-09-08">September 8, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>As I told you in my letter of August 12 that I would do, I followed up<lb/>
the suggestion mentioned in paragraph 6 of your letter of August 6 and<lb/>
have obtained informally, the attitude of the Surgeon General's Depart-<lb/>
ment, U. S. Army, concerning the dedication of Camp Lazear. I have re-<lb/>
ceived a personal and also a semi-official reply from Major General<lb/>
George E. Armstrong, the Surgeon General. I enclose a copy of General<lb/>
Armstrong's letter of August 22. I have also heard from General Love<lb/>
and others in Washington. They are all delighted to know of the plans<lb/>
which you and your colleagues have been formulating. They are all<lb/>
greatly interested in the dedication of Camp Lazear and in his personal<lb/>
letter to me, General Armstrong expressed the hope that he might himself<lb/>
be able to visit Cuba for the dedication but since he did not know the<lb/>
exact date and since he was going to be away from time to time, he was<lb/>
going to suggest the possibility that Major General Paul H. Streit,<lb/>
Commanding General of Walter Reed Medical Center and of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Army Hospital, would represent him if he himself could not come.</p>
<p>Our mutual friends in Washington are certain that the State Department<lb/>
would be delighted to receive official notification and an invitation to<lb/>
have a representative at the dedication. May I state therefore that as<lb/>
soon as your plans are sufficiently definite and when you know the date<lb/>
for the dedication, that an invitation be sent to the State Department<lb/>
and another one sent to the Surgeon General of the U. S. Army, either<lb/>
directly to him in his official capacity or to him through the State<lb/>
Department. Such an invitation will receive their <unclear>anthusiastic</unclear> attention.</p>
<p>May I ask you, Pedro, if you are more certain now as to the exact time<lb/>
for the dedication? If you are planning to dedicate it the <unclear>end</unclear> of this month,<lb/>
the time is getting short and if at all possible, the invitations from<lb/>
the Cuban government should go out at their earliest convenience.</p>
<p>As I wrote you before, the only two survivors of the actual experiments<lb/>
are Dr. Robert P. Cooke, Lexington, Virginia and Mr. James L. Hanberry<lb/>
61 Summers Avenue, <unclear>Orangeburg</unclear>, South Carolina. I have not heard from<lb/>
Doctor Cooke. When I wrote Mr. Hanberry some weeks ago telling him of<lb/>
the preliminary plans, he expressed at once his hope that he might be in-<lb/>
vited but I do not believe he could go to Cuba at his own expense.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04509011"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>September 8, 1952</p>
<p>I am sure that you will want to send invitations not only to Doctor Cooke<lb/>
and Mr. Hanberry but also to the following:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>General and Mrs. Walter L. Reed, 2810 Thirty-Sixth Place N.W., Washington D.C.</item>
<item>Mrs. Blossom Reed, Blue Ridge Summit, Pennsylvania</item>
<item>Mrs. Estela Agramonte Rodrigues Leon, Calle K, Vedado, Havana (Agramonte's<lb/>
daughter)</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. Houston Lasear, P. O. Box 812, Santa Barbara, California (Lazear's son)</item>
<item>Mr. and Mrs. W. D. Briggs, 106 The Uplands, Berkeley, California (Lazear's daughter)</item>
<item>General and Mrs. Albert E. Truby, 145 Laurel Street, San Francisco, California</item>
<item>Mrs. J. R. Kean, 2804 N Street N.W., Georgetown, Washington, D. C.</item>
</list></p>
<p>May I say that all of these people would, I am sure, be delighted to have<lb/>
official invitations to come to Cuba; however I do not believe any of this<lb/>
latter group can come. At your suggestion, I wrote them informally telling<lb/>
them of the tentative plans. Unfortunately, because of their physical in-<lb/>
capacities or for other reasons, the following have stated specifically<lb/>
that although they would be delighted indeed to receive an official invita-<lb/>
tion, they do not believe they can come: General Reed, Blossom Reed, Mrs.<lb/>
Briggs, Mrs. Kean, General Truby. I have not heard from Houston Lazear.</p>
<p>I assume that at the appropriate time you and your colleagues will contact<lb/>
the American Embassy in Havana. Our Washington friends assure me that if<lb/>
invited the American Embassy would be delighted indeed to participate or<lb/>
have a representative present at the ceremony.</p>
<p>Since writing you previously about the exact names, I have not heard whether<lb/>
you plan to use the full name or the first names and initials, nor have I<lb/>
heard what names you finally decided upon. I enclose an actual copy of the<lb/>
names as sent to me from the Surgeon General's Office. They consider this<lb/>
the official spelling. However they have the middle name of Mr. Hanberry<lb/>
spelled wrong. They have spelled it <unclear>Lanard</unclear>. In his own handwriting, Mr.<lb/>
Hanberry signs his name James Leonard Hanberry.</p>
<p>Would you end your colleagues wish to send an official invitation to any<lb/>
of the officers of the Walter Reed Memorial Association? They are as follows:</p>
<p>General Albert G. Love, 2709 Wisconsin Avenue N.W., Washington, D. C., is<lb/>
now Secretary, and I will send you within a few days the names of the other<lb/>
officers.</p>
<p>Is there anything further that I can do for you? I would appreciate an<lb/>
answer to my letter of August 12.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I think I have obtained for you a copy of Sternberg's 1890 book. Did<lb/>
you receive the copy of Mrs. Sternberg's account of her husband's life which<lb/>
I sent to you on August 12?<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
