<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, July 26, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-07-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, John L.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Sidney Coe</name>
<name type="person">Kruif, Paul de</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-07-26">July 26, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, July 26, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench sends Nogueira the data on persons associated in various ways with the work of the U.S. Army Yellow Fever Board. He inquires whether a date has been set for the dedication of Camp Lazear. Hench suggests names of people who should be invited. Hench discusses the socio-political ramifications surrounding the naming of the site.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-07-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, July 26, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509007"/>
<opener>
7 . 8<lb/>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1952-07-26">July 26, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>At last I am able to send you the data on the persons associated in various ways<lb/>
with the work of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Board. In order to give you as<lb/>
much information as possible I have made the list quite complete and inclusive.<lb/>
To do so I have had to spend considerable time going over books, my voluminous<lb/>
files, etc. But I'm glad I did so, as your request forced me to check and re-<lb/>
check data so as to have names correct for perpetuation in bronze. In doing<lb/>
so I uncovered even more errors than I had noted before.</p>
<p>I do not know what policy (regarding the selection of names to be honored) you<lb/>
and your colleagues have adopted, whether you are going to honor only those<lb/>
who actually worked at Camp Lazear (plus, of course, Finlay, Delgado and Lazear)<lb/>
or whether you are going to be more inclusive and memorialize more broadly the<lb/>
&ldquo;Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I will send a copy of the enclosed data to General Truby, perhaps also to Mr.<lb/>
Hanberry (volunteer). I'm not sure that Dr. Cooke's health would permit him to<lb/>
review my data; his memory is poor. But I think General Truby and Mr. Hanberry<lb/>
may help us.</p>
<p>Incidentally the U.S. Army &ldquo;Yellow Fever Board&rdquo; was not an official designation<lb/>
even though it is often called that, or the &ldquo;Yellow Fever Commission&rdquo;. All<lb/>
sorts of &ldquo;Boards of Officers&rdquo; are created by military order; some are more or<lb/>
less permanent; others have only a temporary job to do. The wording used to<lb/>
create all such boards is customarily the same: &ldquo;A board of officers, consist-<lb/>
ing of.........., is appointed for the purpose of........&rdquo;. The order creat-<lb/>
ing the so-called &ldquo;Yellow Fever Board&rdquo; was no exception; according to the official<lb/>
wording of the order which created it, it was just another &ldquo;Board of officers&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Despite this it does need some special distinction; therefore the &ldquo;U.S. Army<lb/>
Yellow Fever <hi>Board</hi>&rdquo; is more appropriate than &ldquo;Commission&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Please let me know if you wish me to do anything more about finding the missing<lb/>
middle names or middle initials of the persons named in my list. If we have time<lb/>
I can write the Adjutant General, U.S. Army for their help. But it might take<lb/>
two weeks or so to get the missing data.</p>
<p>Have you or your colleagues set a date for the dedication of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;? I'd<lb/>
certainly like to know when it is to be, and how I wish I could come but I fear<lb/>
that I can't. If I did go I'd have to make a very quick trip. How I wish General<lb/>
and Mrs. Truby could be there and how he would love to go. But an Army officer's<lb/>
retirement pay does not allow much travel, and I don't suppose your Government<lb/>
would deem it appropriate to bring to Havana any guests. But if you are consider-<lb/>
ing American guests one thinks also of Walter Reed's son and daughter (both<lb/>
living, and Doctor Lazear's son and daughter (both in California). Unfortunately<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04509008"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
July 26, 1952<lb/>
Doctor Carroll's son is not a very congenial man; indeed he is distinctly<lb/>
antagonistic and I doubt if he would make a suitable guest. (Of course you<lb/>
have right in Havana Agramonte's daughter.)</p>
<p>Pedro, if your &ldquo;Dedication Committee&rdquo; does want two or three American guests<lb/>
it might be possible to interest the Surgeon General to send one or more re-<lb/>
presentatives. Perhaps Generals Reed and Truby, although retired, could be<lb/>
called back by the Surgeon General to act as his representatives, and be sent<lb/>
at the Army's expense. I know General Armstrong fairly well and could sound<lb/>
him out <hi>informally</hi> if you wish me to do so before you do anything official.</p>
<p>Do you have your own copy of Kelly's book on &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo;<lb/>
or a copy of Mrs. Sternberg's &ldquo;Life of General Sternberg&rdquo; (Surgeon General,<lb/>
U.S. Army who created the Yellow Fever Board, 1900)? If you do not have your<lb/>
own copies and if you would like me to do so I'll try to find copies for you<lb/>
and send them to you.</p>
<p>Thank you very much for asking the Air Force officers to take another series<lb/>
of air views (<hi>tangential</hi> as well as perpendicular). But you will recall that<lb/>
I was most anxious to be allowed either to borrow or to <hi>buy</hi> the films because<lb/>
I want some enlargements of various special areas, e.g., the area around the<lb/>
Finca San Jose, that around the false camp, etc. I want to make slides as well<lb/>
as prints of various sizes. That is why I was so anxious for them to lend me<lb/>
the other ones they took. (And if they file them so casually that they can't<lb/>
find them, or if they throw them away, I wonder if they wouldn't let me have<lb/>
them. I can assure you I will only use them for proper purposes as they would<lb/>
approve.)</p>
<p>As stated in the enclosure I am still very hopeful that sometime soon you or<lb/>
I can arrange to get complete <hi>microfilms</hi> of Doctor Finlay's &ldquo;diaries&rdquo;. I think<lb/>
somebody told me that there was now a microfilm camera somewhere in Havana.<lb/>
Perhaps Doctor Presno would permit me to have three copies made <hi>at my expense</hi>:<lb/>
one for him, one for you and one for me. Do you think we could get it done?<lb/>
Do you want me to make a formal request to him?</p>
<p>I do hope you received my letter of July 7 with its personal &ldquo;addendum&rdquo; about<lb/>
the re-naming (?) of Camp Lazear or at least about the erroneous designation<lb/>
&ldquo;caseta de Finlay&rdquo;. Perhaps you have quietly done something about this.</p>
<p>I hope very much that you have. It would be very unfortunate if that news-<lb/>
paper error were allowed to continue without correction by the Cuban Govern-<lb/>
ment. The <hi>very purpose</hi> of the memorial project at Camp Lazear would be de-<lb/>
feated or perverted. There are many fine memorials to Finlay in Havana. That<lb/>
is as it should be! But this was to be a joint memorial. I know very well<lb/>
of your own attitude, which is shared by such men as Doctor Ramos and others<lb/>
who wish to honor both Doctor Finlay and the &ldquo;Americans&rdquo;. As the time for the<lb/>
dedication approaches I'm getting somewhat more disturbed lest an unfortunate<lb/>
misunderstanding spoil our purposes.</p>
<p>If you have discussed this matter tactfully with your colleagues and if any of<lb/>
them is inclined to dismiss the erroneous designation as &ldquo;unimportant&rdquo; and not<lb/>
inclined to help you correct it (as I know you intended to do last January),<lb/>
Pedro, I beg of you to discuss it with them again.</p>
<p>Make them understand that there are many important Cubans as well as Americans<lb/>
who now know considerable about Camp Lazear and &ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo;, far too<lb/>
many for the newspapers to ignore. These include several Cuban physicians,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04509009"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
July 26, 1952<lb/>
one or two Cuban writers and others who have (of their own volition) corresponded<lb/>
with me about Camp Lazear. Also many prominent American business, social and<lb/>
official persons in Havana know the significance of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;. I refer<lb/>
to the Embassy group, to the military attache and to other Americans also cer-<lb/>
tain Havana correspondents for American newspapers. Through the past twelve<lb/>
years as I have visited Havana I have made many contacts as I sought help to<lb/>
uncover this or that data. I have kept in correspondence with many of them.</p>
<p>All of these people would be simply delighted to join with their Cuban friends<lb/>
in dedicating a joint memorial, truly a <hi>Cuban-American Memorial</hi> to Finlay, Del-<lb/>
gado and the &ldquo;Americans&rdquo; who worked at Camp Lazear. But they would feel affronted<lb/>
and distressed if the unfortunate error about which I wrote you were to be per-<lb/>
petuated or given the direct or tacit approval of either the Cuban Government<lb/>
or the civil administration of Marianao. (You recall that Sydney Howard wrote<lb/>
a popular play &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; with scenes laid at Camp Lazear; it was made into<lb/>
a movie. Also Paul de Kruif has written much about the Camp Lazear episode.<lb/>
Reader's Digest also often has something about the yellow fever story. I fear<lb/>
that some of these people, professional writers, might be disturbed if Reed's<lb/>
famous little &ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo; were improperly designated.)</p>
<p>Please write me and allay my concern. Is there anything you would like me to do?<lb/>
If you want me to write &ldquo;officially&rdquo; or confidentially to anyone I will do so<lb/>
at once. But I hope to go away on a little vacation after the middle of August<lb/>
so <hi>please write me soon</hi>.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always your friend,</salute>
<signed>Dr. P. S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota</signed>
PSH:dsl<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
