<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04501010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Austin Smith, December 23, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04501010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-12-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Smith, Austin</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-12-23">December 23, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04501010</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Austin Smith, December 23, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench suggests that Smith invite Nogueira to be the Cuban correspondent for the &ldquo;Journal of the American Medical Association.&rdquo; He praises Nogueira for fulfilling his promises in a timely fashion, knowing everyone in Cuban political life, and for his knowledge of medicine.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-12-23">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Austin Smith, December 23, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04501010"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-12-23">December 23, 1952</date>
</dateline>
REF: AS:P<lb/>
Dr. Austin Smith, Editor<lb/>
Journal of the American Medical Association<lb/>
535 North Dearborn Street<lb/>
Chicago 10, Illinois<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Smith:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In regard to your letter of December 16, if you can wait until the end of<lb/>
January, I will send you a write-up of the Camp Lazear dedication which you<lb/>
can rewrite as you choose. Would you like to have one or two photographs,<lb/>
glossy prints for reduplication?</p>
<p>With regard to your desire to get a correspondent in Havana, I have given<lb/>
the matter some thought and would suggest the name of Dr. Pedro Nogueira,<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao, Havana. Let me tell you a little about Doctor Nogueira.</p>
<p>I have visited Havana many times in the last 15 years and have become, as<lb/>
you doubtless are, quite familiar with the intense interest which their<lb/>
medical men have in politics. <unclear>Gran</unclear> was a physician of course and Dr. Domingo<lb/>
Ramos has been in and out of government as Minister of Defense, Minister of<lb/>
of Sanitation, etc. As a result, the doctors, like the rest of the Cubans,<lb/>
are strongly factional and when one political party goes in the medical<lb/>
politicians and the other <unclear>parth</unclear> often make no bones about their animosity<lb/>
towards each other. I say this because I do not think you will find any,<lb/>
or many, Cuban physicians who would be aggressive enough to send you a regular<lb/>
letter who were not involved in politics in some way and therefore who were<lb/>
not unfriendly with at least certain other Cuban physicians and factions.</p>
<p>In connection with my Camp Lazear venture, I have had many contacts with many<lb/>
Cuban physicians and politicians, high and low. Of the old school, Dr. Ramos<lb/>
was the best and most reliable but he is now rather old, in semi-retirement,<lb/>
etc. By far the most aggressive and consistently productive Cuban physician<lb/>
I have ever met is Dr. Pedro Nogueira, a young dynamo if there ever was one.<lb/>
Through the eight or ten years of my association with him, I have been simply<lb/>
amazed at his energy and through those many years he has kept faith with me<lb/>
100 per cent, fulfilling every one of innumerable promises he has made to me;<lb/>
most of the time immediately, only occasionally delayed.</p>
<p>He has two or three jobs. His chief and official one is head of the Sanitary<lb/>
Unit of Marianao. This appears to be a branch of the Finlay Institute and<lb/>
I think he is more or less the head of the Public Health Department of the<lb/>
center of Havana called Quemados de Marianao. He is also the head physician<lb/>
of one of the largest breweries, the one that runs &ldquo;Tropical Gardens.&rdquo; He is<lb/>
also physician to a rat extermination company and, in addition, runs a private<lb/>
practice. Despite his interest in industrial medicine, he <unclear>seems</unclear> to be greatly<lb/>
interested in internal medicine and seems to be pretty well up on such matters<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04501011"/>
Dr. Austin Smith<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
December 23, 1952<lb/>
as cortisone, etc. He is well known to Doctor Fishbein and other Americans<lb/>
who have visited there and indeed he may be well known to you. The one draw-<lb/>
back is that he writes English poorly but if you decided upon him and per-<lb/>
mitted him to write the letter in Spanish, then your own translators could<lb/>
work on it. Whether he would be willing or able to add this job to his other<lb/>
burdens without at least nominal financial remuneration, I do not know. But<lb/>
of one thing I am certain. If he took it on, you would probably get more<lb/>
cooperation and prompt service from him than from any other Cuban I ever met.</p>
<p>He seems to know everybody in Cuban political life. I have walked with him<lb/>
into the mayor's office, into the offices of the various ministers and Pedro<lb/>
waves a greeting to this and that person, kids the doorman and we just walk<lb/>
right in, into the inner sanctum anywhere. However, unfortunately, he is<lb/>
not in the best graces with the present administration. He is known to be<lb/>
an anti-Batista man and although he and Saladriguez, the present Minister<lb/>
of Health, cooperated well enough as far as the Camp Lazear ceremonies were<lb/>
concerned, there were some behind-the-scenes political shadows. He was<lb/>
friendly to both the <unclear>Gran</unclear> and the Prio administrations. He is a young man,<lb/>
I would say in his mid-40's.</p>
<p>If you do not wish to consider him, I think Tom Spies could give you some<lb/>
excellent suggestions as of course Tom goes to Havana about every six weeks<lb/>
in connection with his research <unclear>and</unclear> clinical work at the University of Havana.<lb/>
Two other names come to my mind: Dr. Jose Centurion, one of the better known<lb/>
internists who is about 50 years old, and Dr. Juan Portuondo, one of the<lb/>
younger internists.</p>
<p>Regardless of politics, Nogueira seems to be in the good graces of the of-<lb/>
ficers of the Academy of Science. He is quite friendly with the old president,<lb/>
Doctor Presno and on December 3, Finlay's birthday, it was Doctor Nogueira<lb/>
who gave the main oration of the evening at the Academy of Science when the<lb/>
Finlay <unclear>Condecoracions</unclear> were handed out.</p>
<p>Thank you for inquiring about the cost of the wreath. It cost me $15. It<lb/>
was a beautiful wreath of tremendous size. I was lucky to get them all from<lb/>
the same florist. When she was introduced to me she recognized my name because<lb/>
&ldquo;her mother's eyesight was saved by cortisone recently&rdquo;; therefore she gave<lb/>
me some tremendous wreaths I am sure at cost or less.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
