<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509014">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 29, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509014</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-09-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-09-29">September 29, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509014</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 29, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench expresses concern about the planned repairs to Building No. 1. He is worried that little of the original building will remain if the repairs are too extensive. Hench had envisioned that the Americans and Cubans could raise enough money to enclose Building No. 1 in a larger structure in order to protect it from the elements. Hench urges Nogueira to save as much of the discarded lumber as possible because souvenirs could be made of the remnants.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-09-29">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 29, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509014"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-09-29">September 29, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have read with great interest your letter of September 23 regarding<lb/>
the delayed dedication of Camp Lazear and the repairing of Building<lb/>
No. 1. I hope you received my wire.</p>
<p>I am somewhat concerned about the repairs. If you plan to repair it so<lb/>
that it will withstand the elements, including hurricanes, will you not<lb/>
have to do such an extensive job of repairing that little of the original<lb/>
will remain? In that case, we would end up with hardly anything but a<lb/>
replica of the original building. My own hope embodied in the original<lb/>
plan was that when the Cuban Government had gone so far as to preserve<lb/>
the camp site, the Americans and perhaps Cubans could raise enough money<lb/>
to enclose Building No. 1 in a suitable covering building, in which case<lb/>
Building No. 1 would only have to be repaired enough to keep it standing.<lb/>
In that way almost all of the original wood could be spared.</p>
<p>However in view of the plans which you and your colleagues deem necessary,<lb/>
may I ask you, Pedro, most earnestly to save as much as possible of the<lb/>
discarded original wood. I myself am very anxious to get some of it to<lb/>
use for souvenirs such as pen holders, picture frames, desk ornaments,<lb/>
etc. There are many physicians and certain institutions in this country<lb/>
who would be delighted to have a souvenir made from the original wood of<lb/>
Building No. 1. I will feel greatly relieved if you will instruct the<lb/>
repairmen to save carefully all of this wood. I hope indeed there won't<lb/>
be too much of it and that the repairs won't be so extensive that much of<lb/>
the original wood will be discarded. Later we can arrange to have you<lb/>
send me a suitable amount of this wood; probably you may want to keep<lb/>
some yourself. Or, if by chance I can get to the dedication, I could<lb/>
bring some back with me in a package.</p>
<p>Pedro, here is another thought. If there are certain areas that have to<lb/>
be removed extensively, which would be better - to remove the original<lb/>
wood and replace it with new wood or to leave the old wood as an inner<lb/>
frame and have a new, strong outer shell put on, preserving just as much<lb/>
of the original wood as possible, such as the tonged-and-grooved walls.<lb/>
In that case, although the outer part might be changed somewhat, when one<lb/>
walks into the building one would get the real impression of the building<lb/>
as it originally was.</p>
<p>I still will not be completely happy until you and I are able to engage<lb/>
in a cooperative effort to raise funds to erect a permanent protecting<lb/>
memorial about the little building, having the latter in a museum room<lb/>
which would be merely an annex to another building, useful for public<lb/>
purposes, such as a public health unit or some other type of useful<lb/>
memorial.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04509015"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>September 29, 1952</p>
<p>I certainly wish that I could come for the dedication on December 3. My<lb/>
time is so limited that I hesitate greatly to ask the Clinic for the time.<lb/>
Also my expenses have been so heavy this year that I have to think about<lb/>
that too. Nevertheless the temptation to fly to Havana and back in order<lb/>
to be there on December 3 is very great. Therefore I hope you will keep<lb/>
me in touch with the situation.</p>
<p>It would have been nice to have the dedication on November 20 since that<lb/>
was the day the camp was inaugurated but I can understand the interest of<lb/>
your colleagues in having it on December 3.</p>
<p>Regarding the Sternberg book, it was mailed to you on August 14 and was<lb/>
sent registered mail, with a return receipt requested. The delay may be<lb/>
due to the fact that it was sent regular mail instead of air mail. These<lb/>
books are not easy to find. One turns up in a catalog only every three<lb/>
or four years and I hope indeed this one has not been lost.</p>
<p>I shall await further news from you with great interest.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: Now that the date for the dedication of the camp has been changed,<lb/>
perhaps the Surgeon General could come and therefore I would suggest that<lb/>
you invite him as well as General Streit, (Head of Walter Reed Hospital).<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
