<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04506040">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul H. Streit, November 19, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04506040</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Streit, Paul H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-19">November 19, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04506040</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul H. Streit, November 19, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench makes clear that the Camp Lazear dedication is a significant affair because it is the first time the Cubans have honored Reed. He informs Streit that the Mayo Foundation is placing a wreath beneath the medallion of Finlay and suggests that the Surgeon General might like to do the same.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul H. Streit, November 19, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04506040"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-19">November 19, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Major General Paul H. Streit<lb/>
Commanding General<lb/>
Walter Reed Army Hospital<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Streit:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It occurred to me that we few Americans who will officially attend the<lb/>
little dedication ceremony on December 3 at Camp Lazear, should not go<lb/>
empty-handed. Please see the enclosed letter which I am sending to the<lb/>
deans of the six or eight medical schools concerned.</p>
<p>Although the affair will be a very modest one (a relatively small group<lb/>
of people I suspect, standing in the open in the modest surroundings of<lb/>
Camp Lazear), nevertheless the significance of the occasion is considerable<lb/>
for reasons which you know. This is the first time that the Cuban Govern-<lb/>
ment has ever recognized Reed in any way and even though they are of course<lb/>
and most properly, honoring Finlay, they are honoring Reed and all of his<lb/>
American colleagues and volunteers.</p>
<p>The Mayo Foundation wishes to express its appreciation of this Cuban at-<lb/>
titude and has authorized me to request permission from our Cuban hosts to<lb/>
place a wreath beneath the medallion of Doctor Finlay at the appropriate<lb/>
time, either before or during the ceremony. It occurred to me that the<lb/>
Surgeon General might very much wish you to do likewise and have you place<lb/>
perhaps two wreaths, one in honor of Doctor Finlay and one beneath the<lb/>
medallion of Major Reed. It would be particularly appropriate if the U. S.<lb/>
Army could, in this simple way, honor Doctor Finlay for reasons with which<lb/>
you are also familiar. Better yet, you might decide to place one<lb/>
wreath on his grave, but I leave that for you to consider and discuss with<lb/>
your colleagues. I think that if you chose to place an additional wreath<lb/>
on Finlay's grave, a representative of the Cuban Government and of the<lb/>
American Embassy (and I would be glad to also) would be glad to accompany<lb/>
you so that the thing is done properly and in order to enhance the feeling<lb/>
of good will, a photograph could be taken which could be published perhaps<lb/>
in Cuban papers, certainly in the Armed Forces Medical Journal.</p>
<p>The Walter Reed Memorial Association might wish to do something similar or<lb/>
on the other hand, might wish to send merely a telegraphic message. Please<lb/>
see the enclosed letter. Permit me to send you herewith a photograph of<lb/>
the blue print of the present plans for the little camp.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
