<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509022">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, October 25, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509022</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-10-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Alvarez, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert Page</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-10-25">October 25, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509022</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, October 25, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench generally approves of the selection of names to be honored on a plaque at the dedication of Camp Lazear. He asks to have a phrase clarified from Nogueira's last letter concerning the qualifications necessary to receive the Finlay Award.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-10-25">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, October 25, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509022"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-10-25">October 25, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am greatly disturbed that I have not been able to answer your letter sooner.<lb/>
I have been out of town a great deal recently.</p>
<p>First of all, let me give you my general approval of the decisions which you<lb/>
and your colleagues made. I personally would have liked to have seen at least<lb/>
Dean, Case XY, and perhaps Pinto, included even though they were not at Camp<lb/>
Lazear. I <unclear>realize</unclear> you have to draw a line somewhere and if you are confining<lb/>
the honors to the soldiers who served at Camp Lazear, these two men naturally<lb/>
will not be in.</p>
<p>You mention Albarez. That should be the No. 40 Alvarez, <hi>not</hi> the No. 2 Alvarez,<lb/>
listed in my alphabetical list on page 8 of my memorandum of July 21, 1952 to<lb/>
you. I don't believe we know his first name.</p>
<p>You misspelled two names in your letter. It is Hanberry, not Handberry and<lb/>
Sternberg, not <unclear>Sternberg</unclear>. I am sure these were merely typographical errors.</p>
<p>As to the exclusion of Stark, I suppose you are probably right. His contri-<lb/>
butions were <unclear>much</unclear> more in the line of duty whereas Ames' contributions,<lb/>
though essentially in line of duty were done so attentively and were so im-<lb/>
portant that they can be classified as being rather &ldquo;<unclear>beyond</unclear> the line of duty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am not sure what you mean when you ask me to tell you who I believe &ldquo;ought<lb/>
to be decorated with Finlay's to the Board.&rdquo; Perhaps you are suggesting that<lb/>
I nominate some men for the Finlay condecoration. Unfortunately I do not know<lb/>
the qualifications for these nominations. I did not receive any information along<lb/>
this line. Nor does your letter specify whether these nominations pertain to<lb/>
yellow fever personalities or to American doctors or to other distinguished<lb/>
Americans who might be visiting Cuba on December 3. If you are confining the<lb/>
matter to yellow fever personalities and if you must confine it to doctors, it<lb/>
seems to me the two outstanding nominees would be Doctor Cooke, one of the<lb/>
volunteers, and General Truby; the latter not so much because of his actual<lb/>
service in the yellow fever experiments, but because of his life-long interest<lb/>
in Cuba and his military service in its behalf. If non-medical men are eligible<lb/>
and I believe they are ad Johnny Moran was honored, I think Hanberry should be<lb/>
honored. After all, he and Cooke are the only two left.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04509023"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Page 2<lb/>
October 25, 1952</p>
<p>If non-yellow fever personalities are to be honored, General Streit, head of<lb/>
the Walter Reed Hospital, who will attend the ceremony if invited, might well<lb/>
be honored although of course perhaps the honor should go to his chief, The<lb/>
Surgeon General, but that is not for me to decide and of course General Walter<lb/>
Lawrence Reed is certainly worthy of such an honor not only because of his life-<lb/>
long service to the American Army (he was Inspector General) but, from the<lb/>
Cuban standpoint, because he served as a young private and then a lieutenant<lb/>
in Cuba in the Spanish-American War; in fact he received his commission as a<lb/>
lieutenant while in Cuba.</p>
<p>If you want other types of nominations from me, please let me know what you<lb/>
had in mind; that is, what category of men.</p>
<p>I shall certainly try to come to the dedication. I wonder if your secretary<lb/>
would make a tentative reservation for me at the Hotel Nacional? If I come,<lb/>
I can only stay two days, probably December 2 and 3. I will have to fly as<lb/>
I only have four days left of my allotted time for the entire year.</p>
<p>I hope you received my letter and wire about preserving any wood that you<lb/>
have to remove from Building No. 1. I would certainly like to have some<lb/>
with which to make souvenirs.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
