<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04505001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence and Landon Reed, Mr. and Mrs. Houston Lazear, Peggy Lazear Briggs, Albert E. Truby, and J.F. Siler, July 30, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04505001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-07-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Briggs, Margaret Lazear</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Cardenas, Raul de</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Spies, Tom</name>
<name type="person">Murphy, William</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="person">Carbonnel, Felipe Ponce</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estella Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Phillips, R. H.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Smith, Louise F.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, Elida</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Houston</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Peggy Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-07-30">July 30, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04505001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence and Landon Reed, Mr. and Mrs. Houston Lazear, Peggy Lazear Briggs, Albert E. Truby, and J.F. Siler, July 30, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench explains the difficult socio-political situation in Cuba. He focuses on the confusion surrounding his invitation to receive the Order of Finlay, his difficulties with the Cuban press, and financial irregularities regarding the Camp Lazear fund.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-07-30">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence and Landon Reed, Mr. and Mrs. Houston Lazear, Peggy Lazear Briggs, Albert E. Truby, and J.F. Siler, July 30, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04505001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1952-07-30">July 30, 1952</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Friends:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In September the Cubans are planning to dedicate the old site of &ldquo;Camp<lb/>
Lazear&rdquo; where Reed's Building Number One still stands. But I am consider-<lb/>
ably disturbed by the actions of Cuban newspapers which have been speaking<lb/>
of Reed's Building Number One as &ldquo;the caseta of Finlay&rdquo; and by the apparent<lb/>
idea of some to rename &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; and call it &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo;. When I<lb/>
was in Havana in January I politely but firmly protested these actions. I<lb/>
still hope and expect that the Cubans will not make these unfortunate mis-<lb/>
takes. But time is getting short and I want you to know of this situation.</p>
<p>May I suggest that you do nothing yourself at the moment. But for the back-<lb/>
ground of all this please read the following <hi>confidential</hi> report of my recent<lb/>
trip to Havana.</p>
<p>I would appreciate it greatly if you would send me as soon as you can (1)<lb/>
any suggestions you may have and/or (2) just a one-sentence note approving<lb/>
my own intentions:</p>
<p>I have been so busy that I have been delayed in sending to you this <hi>confiden-<lb/>
tial</hi> report of my recent trip to Havana. Having been invited to address the<lb/>
International Congress on Nutrition in January 1952, Mary and I decided to<lb/>
spend some extra time there so that we could have a little &ldquo;vacation&rdquo; during<lb/>
which I could see what had happened to the Cuban Government's (1948) plans to<lb/>
memorialize Camp Lazear and to protect the remains of Building Number One.</p>
<p>You may recall that during and just after my 1948 trip to Havana (and my in-<lb/>
terviews with <unclear>Mr.</unclear> Senor Cardenas--Vice--President of Cuba, Dr. Andreu and<lb/>
others) the Cuban Government actually set aside $50,000 as a &ldquo;starter&rdquo; for<lb/>
the memorial. This sum was &ldquo;approved&rdquo; by the Cuban Congress and the sum and<lb/>
its purpose was published in Cuban newspapers (clippings of which I have).<lb/>
But very soon (within weeks) that government was voted out of office. When<lb/>
I tried to find out by correspondence what was to become of the project, no-<lb/>
body knew. Mr. Moran told me frankly that &ldquo;as usual&rdquo; the outgoing politicians<lb/>
&ldquo;cleaned the treasury&rdquo; and our $50,000 went down the drain.</p>
<p>But through the past four years I have kept in touch with Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
of Marianao, a very energetic young Cuban physician who has been partially<lb/>
in politics (medical jobs) and who seems to have a sincere and broad interest<lb/>
in the work of the U.S. Army Yellow Fever Board and who has given me (and<lb/>
Generals Kean and Truby) numerous evidences that he is not interested in<lb/>
Finlay alone. During my last visit Dr. Nogueira was extremely kind to me,<lb/>
seemed to share completely my hopes regarding a Cuban-American Memorial at<lb/>
Camp Lazear and gave me a sound basis for my trust in him. He seemed sin-<lb/>
cerely to want to &ldquo;join forces&rdquo; with me and to do all he could to help me.</p>
<p>Apparently Dr. Nogueira kept working away on the project and kept alive the<lb/>
interest of Dr. Andreu who over several years has been in and out of office,<lb/>
formerly Senator, recently, in January 1952, the Minister of Health.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04505002"/>
<p>Dear Friends:</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>July 30, 1952</p>
<p>Mary and I reached Havana about January 19 and stayed in Havana about eight<lb/>
days, then went for a week's rest at Varadero Beach, then back to Havana for<lb/>
a couple days before leaving. I had hoped to spend only a day at the medical<lb/>
meetings, then pursue my &ldquo;Camp Lazear hobby&rdquo; uninterruptedly for the rest of<lb/>
the time. But in connection with my talk and the &ldquo;Finlay Condecoracion&rdquo; (see<lb/>
below) there was so much newspaper publicity that all sorts of interruptions<lb/>
developed (consultations, patients, interviews, etc.). As a result I didn't<lb/>
accomplish more than a fraction of what I had planned, and was greatly dis-<lb/>
appointed.</p>
<p>The Congress we attended was supported partly by the Cuban Government, partly<lb/>
by &ldquo;F.I.M.&rdquo; (Fundacion de Investigaciones Medicas), an organization sponsored<lb/>
jointly by socially prominent and wealthy Cubans, and Americans in Havana.<lb/>
The co-Presidents are the old Cuban patriot General Cosme de la Torriente,<lb/>
and Mrs. Louise F. (Gilbert) Smith, a fine extremely energetic and capable<lb/>
American. These people, stimulated in part by Cuban physicians at the Univer-<lb/>
sity of Havana and by Dr. Tom Spies of Birmingham (a well known American phy-<lb/>
sician), have raised money to support &ldquo;real modern medical research&rdquo; for the<lb/>
first time in Havana. They have been operating for a few years, I think, and<lb/>
Doctor Spies alternates between the United States and Cuba. He and his Cuban<lb/>
medical colleagues are doing some good research and clinical work at the Uni-<lb/>
versity of Havana.</p>
<p>During a social conversation with Mrs. Smith the second day we were in Havana<lb/>
she remarked casually: &ldquo;It was too bad, Dr. Hench, that you couldn't come to<lb/>
the Finlay award ceremony last fall&rdquo;. I had, no idea what she meant. She<lb/>
then told me that last fall Dr. William Murphy (Nobel Prize Winner, 1934;<lb/>
liver extract for pernicious anemia) and I had been nominated for the Finlay<lb/>
Medal. At the annual ceremony our names were read out but neither of us ap-<lb/>
peared. She was quite surprised when I told her I had never been notified<lb/>
and knew nothing about it. Whereupon she and Doctor Spies got busy and notified<lb/>
those concerned that both Doctor Murphy and I would be at the Congress and<lb/>
available for the decoration.</p>
<p>Shortly thereafter Doctor Nogueira told me much the same and when I expressed<lb/>
my concern lest my Cuban friends think I had carelessly ignored their honor,<lb/>
he too got busy, contacted Doctor Andreu (Minister of Health) and the other<lb/>
officers of the Finlay Order and notified me that I would receive the decora-<lb/>
tion in a day or two at a small ceremony for me alone at the Ministry of<lb/>
Health. But almost immediately Doctor Spies and Mrs. Smith re-arranged things<lb/>
and <unclear>had</unclear> the ceremony set up as part of the social program of the Congress,<lb/>
the ceremony to be delayed until Doctor Murphy arrived. Since it seemed pre-<lb/>
ferable to them to have one ceremony for both of us and to make it a public<lb/>
one rather than to have two small individual ceremonies, I agreed. But I<lb/>
noted or thought I noted some &ldquo;competitiveness&rdquo; between Doctor Nogueira on<lb/>
the one hand and Mrs. Smith and Doctor Spies on the other. Each quietly led<lb/>
me to believe that our nomination for this honor was largely his doings.<lb/>
(I suspect that <hi>all</hi> were concerned).</p>
<p>In preparation for the ceremony I was invited to call on Doctor Andreu. I<lb/>
was glad to do this so that he would realize that my absence at the ceremony<lb/>
last fall did not represent indifference, but simply ignorance of the whole<lb/>
affair. While there I met the Secretary or Recorder (?) of the Finlay Order<lb/>
and when he was told I hadn't received any word and that I felt reasonably<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04505003"/>
Dear Friends:<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
July 30, 1952<lb/>
sure that Doctor Murphy had not either, (he hadn't) he insisted that he cer-<lb/>
tainly had sent me an official notification. After disappearing for a moment<lb/>
he returned and said &ldquo;I sent you a letter just like this one for Doctor<lb/>
Murphy&rdquo;. But I was amused to see that the letter to Doctor Murphy was <hi>not</hi><lb/>
a carbon, but seemingly the original letter, never sent.</p>
<p>Meanwhile Doctor Nogueira told me that the former $50,000 for Camp Lazear<lb/>
had been &ldquo;approved&rdquo; by the Cuban Congress but never actually &ldquo;allotted&rdquo; by<lb/>
those who &ldquo;divie up&rdquo; Government funds (the Budget Department?) and that if<lb/>
it had been set aside it had &ldquo;disappeared&rdquo;. Then he told me with great<lb/>
satisfaction that he and Doctor Andreu had succeeded finally in having<lb/>
$25,000 not only &ldquo;approved&rdquo; but &ldquo;delivered&rdquo; into the hands of a committee of<lb/>
three: Andreu, himself and a third man who is, I think, the Mayor of Marianao.<lb/>
As he stressed it: &ldquo;We actually have the money in a separate checking account;<lb/>
nobody but us three can expend it or get at it and we can use it as we see fit.<lb/>
So you see we are really in a position to go ahead with our plans.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He invited me to visit the office of the Engineering Department of the Health<lb/>
Department where draftsmen were completing the blue prints. Their plan was<lb/>
to grade the uneven land at Camp Lazear, clear out trees, stumps, the corn<lb/>
field, the little spring and the small ruins of the &ldquo;lime kiln&rdquo; (shown in one<lb/>
of the old 1900 Army photos) and make a little park with a circular road-way<lb/>
and parking space, shrubbery, a flag pole, stone walks, and a stone wall se-<lb/>
parating the remains of Camp Lazear from the unsightly, encroaching quarry.<lb/>
(See copy of blue-print enclosed.) On the stone wall were to be five or more<lb/>
medalions with the profiles of Finlay, Reed, Carroll, Agramonte and Lazear.<lb/>
On two large tablets were to be a brief account of the significance of the<lb/>
spot and the names of &ldquo;the volunteers&rdquo;.</p>
<p>But Building Number One was <hi>not</hi> to be covered up at this time or protected in<lb/>
any special way. It was to be cleaned up; the two remaining lean-to's (not<lb/>
part of the original Building Number One) were to be removed. I expressed my<lb/>
regrets that the historic building was to be left, still at the mercy of the<lb/>
elements and the recurring tornados. But Nogueira had an acceptable answer:<lb/>
&ldquo;After all $25,000 won't go far. It is only a start. It will cost that much<lb/>
just to clean up the place and to build the roads. But it <hi>is</hi> a start and once<lb/>
we get this much done, we can always go back for more support later.&rdquo;</p>
<p>All of this seemed &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo; to me although it actually was only part of what<lb/>
I've been hoping and asking for (Building Number One enclosed in a little<lb/>
&ldquo;museum&rdquo; to be part of a &ldquo;living memorial&rdquo;--perhaps a small unit of the Marianao<lb/>
Health Department, a dispensary, a social service unit or something useful).</p>
<p>But when I saw the blue prints I noted at once the title &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo; and<lb/>
the erroneous designation &ldquo;caseta de Finlay&rdquo;. My letter of July 7 to Nogueira<lb/>
(&ldquo;Addendum&rdquo;) will tell you what I said then; (also see what I wrote July 26).<lb/>
He promised to have &ldquo;the foolish mistakes&rdquo; corrected and about two weeks later<lb/>
he did deliver to me a copy of a &ldquo;corrected blue-print&rdquo; with a change in title<lb/>
but with Reed's Building Number One still called &ldquo;caseta de Finlay&rdquo;.</p>
<p>A day or so later Nogueira asked me to speak at the weekly luncheon of the<lb/>
Rotary Club of Marianao, held at one of the beach clubs at La Playa. I thought<lb/>
this would afford me a chance to &ldquo;correct publicly the record&rdquo; in a polite way.<lb/>
After some generalities about &ldquo;the magnificent achievement of your illustrious<lb/>
countryman Carlos Finlay, his devoted associate Claudio Delgado and my dis-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04505004"/>
Dear Friends:<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
July 30, 1952<lb/>
tinguished countrymen Major Walter Reed and his associates Doctors Agramonte,<lb/>
Carroll and Lazear&rdquo;, I continued: "On this visit Mrs. Hench and I miss so<lb/>
very much that lovable Irish-American-Cuban, Johnny Moran who lived his life<lb/>
among you until he died here last year and who in 1900 at the request of<lb/>
Major Reed and &lsquo;for the sake of humanity&rsquo; offered his own living body to prove<lb/>
the theory of Carlos Finlay.</p>
<p>&ldquo;So profound are the secrets of nature, so complicated was the terrible problem<lb/>
of yellow fever that no one man, however great he might be, could solve the<lb/>
mystery. The <hi>conception</hi> of Carlos Finlay was <hi>one</hi> of the boldest, most original<lb/>
and most precise in the whole history of science. But before the world could<lb/>
accept his ideas others, to be exact over a score of others, had to contribute<lb/>
their brains, their courage and, if necessary, their lives..........&rdquo;</p>
<p>Nobody objected to my remarks (I half expected someone might) but although<lb/>
photos and written copy of my remarks were taken the newspaper account made no<lb/>
quotations, merely mentioned my work on cortisone and my praise for Finlay.</p>
<p>In connection with the &ldquo;Finlay Condecoracion&rdquo; and the Congress I was interviewed<lb/>
by reporters. One of them gave me several questions (about cortisone but also<lb/>
about my opinion regarding the plans for the &ldquo;caseta&rdquo;) and suggested that I<lb/>
hand him typewritten answers. I welcomed the chance to give him answers which<lb/>
(if <hi>correctly</hi> translated by some one) could not lead to misquotation. At<lb/>
Nogueira's request I had three or four copies made. What happened to them I<lb/>
do not know but the interview <hi>did</hi> appear, substantially correct in <hi>Avance,</hi><lb/>
January 25 and my remarks defined clearly just what Finlay's connection was<lb/>
with the Finca San Jose (a few early experiments in the main house) and what<lb/>
the relationship was between Camp Lazear and the Finca San Jose.</p>
<p>So that there would be a minimal chance for misquotation I also had ready<lb/>
copies of the few remarks I made upon accepting the Finlay Medal and these<lb/>
were given to at least three or four reporters. I decided to repeat some of<lb/>
what I had said before the smaller Rotary audience. Among other things I<lb/>
said: &ldquo;Among my most valued medical possessions is an original copy (Havana,<lb/>
1881) of Doctor Finlay's first paper on yellow fever and mosquitoes. On more<lb/>
than one occasion I have read every word of the official translation of that<lb/>
paper. My familiarity with this work and my love of medical history require<lb/>
me to say that the <hi>Conception</hi> of Carlos Finlay was <hi>one</hi> of the boldest, most<lb/>
original and precise in the long history of medicine&rdquo;. Then, having given him<lb/>
due praise I continued: &ldquo;So profound and mysterious was the secret of nature<lb/>
which he first tried to uncover that it took many years before his brilliant<lb/>
<hi>theory</hi> was proven and accepted. That is one measure of the difficulties in-<lb/>
volved.........&rdquo;</p>
<p>After I had spoken these words in English Doctor Nogueira translated them<lb/>
into Spanish. Whether he or others were responsible I do not know but my<lb/>
remarks were changed subtly in the Spanish newspaper versions. For example<lb/>
<hi>Avance</hi> (January 24) had this headline: &ldquo;La concepcion de Finlay es la mas<lb/>
grande, la mas original y la mas precisa de toda la historia de la medicina&rdquo;,<lb/>
dijo el Dr. Hench. You will see that they carefully left out &ldquo;.....<hi>one</hi> of<lb/>
the boldest, etc.....&rdquo; Also they changed subtly my later words. The Havana<lb/>
Post was no better and even though my English words needed no translation<lb/>
they too, in English, gave a &ldquo;Cubanized Version&rdquo;.</p>
<p>But El Mundo went further. Under a friendly cartoon of me they mentioned<lb/>
the Congress, and then said that Doctor Murphy and I had accepted the Finlay<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04505005"/>
Dear Friends:<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
July 30, 1952<lb/>
Medal (if my translation is correct) &ldquo;demonstrating thus that they accept<lb/>
the theories of the illustrious Camagueyano, when some of his fellow country-<lb/>
men give it with all its glory to Walter Reed (his follower) who continued<lb/>
so brilliantly along the path which he found opened by our countryman.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Another less responsible paper pulled a typical Cuban trick. After the cere-<lb/>
mony their photographer asked me to stand for a photo; as I was about to do<lb/>
so their reporter came up, simply introduced himself and said a word or two.<lb/>
As he stood with me the photographer snapped us together. Later under the<lb/>
photo appeared an entensive &ldquo;interview&rdquo; with precise questions and my &ldquo;answers&rdquo;--<lb/>
all complete fiction as he hadn't asked me a single question!</p>
<p>When later I objected about this to Nogueira he merely said that was an old<lb/>
Cuban custom and that &ldquo;intelligent readers&rdquo; would know I hadn't said that and<lb/>
that nobody paid much attention to newspapers anyway!</p>
<p>Later Doctor Spies confirmed <unclear>this</unclear>, said I had fallen into a common Cuban trick<lb/>
against which nobody had any defense except to &ldquo;keep away from reporters&rdquo;. But<lb/>
since the affair was a public ceremony in the Ministry of Health I could hard-<lb/>
ly fail to pose with my hosts or alone when requested.</p>
<p>After seeing my remarks about Camp Lazear in the papers Mrs. Smith of F.I.M.<lb/>
became quite interested; I might say, excited. She and Doctor Spies hoped<lb/>
that I could discourage Nogueira, let their immediate plan for Camp Lazear<lb/>
fall through and then let the venture be taken over by F.I.M. which would<lb/>
frankly use the &ldquo;memorial project&rdquo; at Camp Lazear as a nucleus so that they<lb/>
might collect enough money in Cuba and in the United States, not only to<lb/>
&ldquo;preserve the camp properly&rdquo; but to use the extra money for medical research<lb/>
in Cuba, which research would be a &ldquo;living memorial&rdquo; to Reed, Lazear, et al.</p>
<p>Despite their obvious purposes I think they were sincere and maybe their in-<lb/>
terest and plan may be useful later. But I could only tell them that the<lb/>
Andreu-Nogueira plan was completely out of my hands and that I didn't see how<lb/>
I could suddenly discourage them from making their &ldquo;start&rdquo; after I'd spent<lb/>
several years trying to get them to start something. But as soon as I could<lb/>
get from the engineers (through Nogueira) the &ldquo;corrected blue-prints&rdquo; I got<lb/>
in touch again with Miss Tina Rojas (who owns the main part of the Finca, the<lb/>
lovely Quinta San Jose) and her companion, Miss Lydia Cabrera.</p>
<p>These ladies, independently wealthy, have fixed up the Quinta beautifully; it<lb/>
is a veritable museum and (<hi>confidentially</hi>) they want to leave it as such to<lb/>
some responsible organization like our &ldquo;National Trust for the Preservation<lb/>
of Historic Buildings&rdquo;, etc. (There is none in Cuba). They were distressed<lb/>
by the Andreu-Nogueira plans, disturbed that the caseta was left uncovered<lb/>
and very suspicious about the erroneous (?) &ldquo;caseta de Finlay&rdquo;. They were<lb/>
inclined to be very cynical about the Cuban government and all concerned.<lb/>
They suspect frankly that &ldquo;these politicians will put up their incorrectly<lb/>
named little park and memorials, have their photos taken and after much noise<lb/>
for a few days, will forget all about it.&rdquo;</p>
<p>They could not share my confidence in Doctor Nogueira even though he himself<lb/>
called at their house while I was there, explained the plans and told them<lb/>
(as he had told me) that the camp and building <hi>would</hi> be named properly and<lb/>
that the errors merely reflected the ignorance of the draftsmen.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f04505006"/>
<p>Dear Friends:</p>
<p>-6-</p>
<p>July 30, 1952</p>
<p>Then I showed the blue prints to Dr. Felipe Carbonnel who developed some<lb/>
years ago a real interest in Camp Lazear, knows all about it and has told<lb/>
its story <hi>correctly</hi> not only in the Cuban newspapers but also over the<lb/>
radio (I have the clippings and they <hi>are</hi> correct). He was very annoyed<lb/>
but agreed that the following suggestion seemed proper. I suggested to<lb/>
him and to the Misses Rojas and Cabrera that we not interfere (last January)<lb/>
with the plans of Andreu, Nogueira, etc., that if we objected too stren-<lb/>
uously then (before they had deeply implicated themselves) they might simply<lb/>
abandon the whole project which others might not later be able to salvage<lb/>
because the caseta is still inviolate as a &ldquo;national monument&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seemed to me to be better to wait till they had publicly gotten well along<lb/>
with the grading, etc. and then pressure could be brought on them (if necessary)<lb/>
to assure us of the correct naming of the place. Then they could hardly stop<lb/>
the work but would have to go ahead.</p>
<p>I still have <hi>no definite</hi> reason to doubt the word and promises of Doctor<lb/>
Nogueira. So far he has <hi>always</hi> kept all his promises. Therefore I am still<lb/>
working through him until I find that he cannot assure us of the correct<lb/>
naming of the caseta. I'm a little disturbed that I've had no answer to<lb/>
my letter of July 7 but the Cubans <hi>never</hi> answer promptly and the &ldquo;dedication&rdquo;<lb/>
is not until September (I think) at the International Congress on Hygiene.</p>
<p>I discussed the whole thing with Agramonte's daughter also. We all agreed<lb/>
then to make no further objections to Andreu or Nogueira but to see what ef-<lb/>
fect my verbal remarks to them might have.</p>
<p>In January there seemed to be another reason for temporizing. A new elec-<lb/>
tion was impending and I found myself in a pleasantly curious situation.<lb/>
The three leading candidates for the presidency were Carlos Hevia, Roberto<lb/>
Agramonte, and Batista. Nobody expected Batista to win. But Hevia is Car-<lb/>
bonnel's cousin, Roberto Agramonte is Miss Agramonte's cousin and Batista<lb/>
is a fairly good social friend of Miss Rojas. So each of my &ldquo;allies&rdquo; told<lb/>
me that if their particular candidate won, I would have no trouble whatever.</p>
<p>Then Batista took over within a few days after Mary and I left. Silence<lb/>
from my friends; no reply to my first letters. Then very discrete notes from<lb/>
Rojas and Nogueira, betraying anxiety for Cuba, etc. Finally a letter from<lb/>
Nogueira saying they were proceeding with their plan. That was answered by<lb/>
my July 7 letter.</p>
<p>I still believe that Nogueira wants to do the right thing but he is only one<lb/>
of a committee and he may <hi>not</hi> be able to correct matters, i.e. if the &ldquo;errors&rdquo;<lb/>
were deliberate. If I don't hear from him soon I will put on more pressure<lb/>
and start naming the names of friends of mine in Havana who simply will <hi>not</hi><lb/>
allow the perpetuation of &ldquo;errors&rdquo;, such as Mr. Scott, reporter for the<lb/>
Havana Post, Mrs. R. H. Phillips--Havana reporter for the New York Times,<lb/>
Doctor Carbonnel, Miss Agramonte, Dr. Domingo Ramos (former Secretary of War),<lb/>
Mrs. Smith and Doctor Spies of F.I.M., etc. Also if worst comes to worst<lb/>
I can discretely &ldquo;orient&rdquo; the Embassy there, also the Surgeon-General in<lb/>
Washington, etc.</p>
<p>But I think, or hope, all will be well. If they identify the camp and the<lb/>
Building Number One properly in bronze, I fear that we may have to prepare<lb/>
ourselves for some such name as &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo;. But I hope not.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f04505007"/>
<p>Dear Friends:</p>
<p>-7-</p>
<p>July 30, 1952</p>
<p>If they do make a mess of it, we can always put the correct information in<lb/>
powerful Havana hands, friendly to Americans and intolerant of untruths.<lb/>
Miss Rojas would like to move the caseta within the walls of her finca<lb/>
and there protect and memorialize it properly. Doctor Carbonnel has other<lb/>
ideas. Let's wait a little longer and see what happens.</p>
<p>Please drop me just a line.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:dsl<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. Mrs. Moran is &ldquo;lost&rdquo; without Johnny. I visited his grave. She gave<lb/>
me his long (80 page) autobiographical manuscript. Very interesting.<lb/>
More of that later.<lb/>
</seg>
Copies to:<lb/>
General and Mrs. Reed<lb/>
Mrs. Blossom Reed<lb/>
Mr. and Mrs. Houston Lazear<lb/>
Mrs. Peggy Briggs<lb/>
Mrs. Kean<lb/>
General Truby<lb/>
Colonel Siler<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
