<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04506032">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert G. Love and J.F. Siler, November 4, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04506032</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Love, Albert G.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Phalon, James M</name>
<name type="person">Brandstadt, Wayne G.</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-04">November 4, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04506032</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert G. Love and J.F. Siler, November 4, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests that Love and Siler contact the editors of two military journals and encourage them to cover the dedication of Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-04">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert G. Love and J.F. Siler, November 4, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04506032"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-04">November 4, 1952</date>
</dateline>
General Albert Love<lb/>
Colonel J. F. Siler<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Friends:</salute>
</opener>
<p>So far as I know, the Cubans are going ahead with their plans to dedicate<lb/>
Camp Lazear on Finlay's Birthday, which is &ldquo;Physician's Day&rdquo; in Havana, on<lb/>
December 3. So far as I know, they are planning to invite officially cer-<lb/>
tain Americans to attend the ceremony; however I know of no official in-<lb/>
vitations as yet sent out, nor have I received one myself. I have merely<lb/>
been told unofficially by Doctor Pedro Nogueira, the spark plug of the<lb/>
movement, that I am to be invited and have been asked to speak for ten<lb/>
minutes. Therefore I am planning to go, flying both ways and making a very<lb/>
hasty trip.</p>
<p>I do think it is very important that the Cubans be permitted to know how<lb/>
much this gesture on their part is appreciated and I hope there will be<lb/>
some publicity about the dedication in the American press, certainly in<lb/>
the medical press. In view of the fact that the major contributions were<lb/>
made by American medical officers and military personnel. I think it is<lb/>
most appropriate that the two military journals, THE MILITARY SURGEON and<lb/>
the U. S. ARMED FORCES MEDICAL JOURNAL, both carry news items regarding<lb/>
this.</p>
<p>Would it not be an excellent idea if the editors of both of these journals<lb/>
were approached and told a little about it? Then I hope that they would<lb/>
both write to Doctor Nogueira just as soon as possible and ask for some in-<lb/>
formation to be published in each of <unclear>these</unclear> journals as a news item.</p>
<p>I do not want to impose upon you <unclear>gentlemen</unclear> but I wondered if, being in<lb/>
Washington and probably knowing both of the editors, you would kindly get<lb/>
in touch with these men at your earliest convenience. Col. James M. Phalon<lb/>
is Editor of The MILITARY SURGEON and Col. Wayne G. Brandstadt is Editor-in-<lb/>
Chief of the U. S. ARMED FORCES MEDICAL JOURNAL. I, in turn, am writing to<lb/>
the editor of the J.A.M.A.</p>
<p>I think the two editors in Washington could open their letters something as<lb/>
follows:<lb/>
&ldquo;Dear Doctor Nogueira:</p>
<p>We have been informed by Dr. P. S. Hench of the Mayo Clinic that the Cuban<lb/>
Government is dedicating, on December 3, Camp Lazear, the place where Major<lb/>
Walter Reed and his associates carried out their work on yellow fever in<lb/>
1900. There are a great many civilian physicians and medical officers who<lb/>
will be vitally interested in this project and who will be delighted indeed<lb/>
to hear of this gracious gesture on the part of the Cuban Government. May<lb/>
I, as Editor of the ____ ____, ask that you or your colleagues of the committee<lb/>
send to me at your early convenience some information regarding the dedica-<lb/>
tion which we can use in our journal, etc.&rdquo;</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04506033"/>
<unclear>How</unclear><lb/>
General Albert Love<lb/>
Colonel J. F. Siler<lb/>
Page 2<lb/>
November 4, 1952<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: If the editors would prefer to write not to Doctor Nogueira but to<lb/>
the Minister of Health himself, his name is Dr. Jose Raimundo Andreu, El<lb/>
Ministro (the Minister) de Salubridad y Asistencia Social, or they could<lb/>
write to the Public Relation Department of El Ministerio (the Ministry)<lb/>
de Salubridad y Asistencia Social. If the editor does not receive a prompt<lb/>
reply from Doctor Andreu directly, he might write to Dr. Nogueira, or vice<lb/>
versa.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
