<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04505008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed, Blossom Reed, Houston Lazear, Peggy Lazear Briggs, Cornelia Knox Kean, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, Albert E. Truby, J.F. Siler, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, and Albert G. Love, August 11, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04505008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-08-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Briggs, Margaret Lazear</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estella Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Landon</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mrs. Houston</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Peggy Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Walter De Blois</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Bonnie</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-08-11">August 11, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04505008</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed, Blossom Reed, Houston Lazear, Peggy Lazear Briggs, Cornelia Knox Kean, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, Albert E. Truby, J.F. Siler, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, and Albert G. Love, August 11, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes about the progress on the Camp Lazear memorial park and states that the park and remains of Building No. 1 are to be dedicated in September.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-08-11">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence Reed, Blossom Reed, Houston Lazear, Peggy Lazear Briggs, Cornelia Knox Kean, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, Albert E. Truby, J.F. Siler, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de Rojas, and Albert G. Love, August 11, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04505008"/>
<p>MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1952-08-11">August 11, 1952</date></p>
<p>Dear Friends:</p>
<p>As you know, I and others have been disturbed by certain errors concerning<lb/>
Camp Lazear and Building No. 1 of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Board, which<lb/>
have appeared in Habana newspapers these past three or four years. Camp<lb/>
Lazear is now being graded and made into a little park, thanks largely to<lb/>
Dr. Andreu (Cuban Minister of Health), Dr. Pedro Nogueira of Marianao (Habana)<lb/>
and other Cubans. On a wall being erected behind Building No. 1 will be<lb/>
bronze medallions with profiles of Finlay, Delgado, Reed, Carroll, Lazear,<lb/>
Agramonte and Wood; also bronze tablets listing the names of the volunteers<lb/>
for the yellow fever experiments.</p>
<p>Presumably the park and the remains of Building No. 1 are to be &ldquo;dedicated&rdquo;<lb/>
during a medical convention in Habana this September. I think it is either<lb/>
the Inter-American Congress of Public Health, September 26 - October 1, or<lb/>
perhaps it is the International Congress on Hygiene to be held in Habana<lb/>
this September 1952. As this date approaches, I wanted to be sure that<lb/>
the above mentioned newspaper errors would not be perpetuated. When I was<lb/>
in Habana in January, Doctor Nogueira assured me that the misunderstandings<lb/>
would be corrected. But to learn how things were going I wrote him on July<lb/>
7 and 26. Having no answer, I cabled him last week and have just received<lb/>
his letter of August 6.</p>
<p>His letter seems to me to be entirely satisfactory. I see no reason to put<lb/>
further pressure upon him at this time. Nor do I think we need to ask any-<lb/>
one else in Cuba to see him or others about this matter just now.</p>
<p>I will ask Senora Agramonte Rodriguez Leon and Senoritas Rojas and Cabrera<lb/>
(Finca San Jose) to keep me informed as to how the Habana papers, etc., are<lb/>
handling matters. If things do not proceed properly (or as Doctor Nogueira<lb/>
and I hope they will) certain other contacts can be made and certain actions<lb/>
taken before the dedication. But as I wrote before, Doctor Nogueira has<lb/>
always kept faith with me so far, and I confidently expect him to keep faith<lb/>
with us now.</p>
<p>In a recent letter to him I suggested discretely that it would be wonderful<lb/>
if certain special persons could be present on the occasion of the dedica-<lb/>
tion. In particular I had in mind General and Mrs. Reed, Mrs. Blossom Reed,<lb/>
Mr. and Mrs. Houston Lazear, Mr. and Mrs. Briggs, General and Mrs. Truby,<lb/>
Mr. Hanberry (volunteer); also official representatives of the Surgeon General,<lb/>
the State Department and the American Medical Association. Wouldn't it be<lb/>
wonderful also if Mrs. Kean and a representative of the Wood family could go?</p>
<p>I was inclined to think that Doctor Cooke was too feeble to go and that<lb/>
Major Carroll's son, George, might not be sociable enough. (As I have told<lb/>
some of you in confidence, he appears to be disgruntled, unfriendly and un-<lb/>
cooperative, perhaps even a bit paranoidal; very unfortunate.) But on<lb/>
second thought, I do not think it is proper for me to make the latter in-<lb/>
ferences about Doctor Cooke and Mr. Carroll and I am writing further to<lb/>
Doctor Nogueira.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04505009"/>
<p>August 11, 1952</p>
<p>Page 2</p>
<p>Now I have no idea how much money (if any) the Cuban Government could afford<lb/>
or would be permitted to set aside for the travelling expenses of such special<lb/>
guests. Since they only allotted $25,000 for the Camp Lazear project, I<lb/>
doubt if they will be able to allot enough to bring to Cuba more than a few<lb/>
of those I mentioned. But please see the enclosed copy of Doctor Nogueira's<lb/>
letter.</p>
<p>Perhaps some could afford to go at their <hi>own</hi> expense, if they were officially<lb/>
invited. Perhaps the Surgeon-General's Office could &ldquo;activate&rdquo; Generals Reed<lb/>
and Truby temporarily and send them at Army expense. If so, perhaps the<lb/>
Cuban Government might be able to help at least some of the others. (But<lb/>
again see Nogueira's letter, which is not very clear on this point.)</p>
<p>We must remember that so far no American contributions for the Camp Lazear<lb/>
project have been made, or even requested, partly for reasons given in one<lb/>
of my previous letters. So far the Cubans have done everything for this<lb/>
Camp Lazear renovation and Americans nothing. Therefore I wish indeed that<lb/>
we knew how to raise quickly some American funds so that the appropriate<lb/>
American &ldquo;guests&rdquo; could go for the dedication and thus demonstrate publicly<lb/>
their approval and join them in honoring Finlay and Delgado as they are<lb/>
honoring our compatriots. (I wonder if the State Department has any funds<lb/>
for such purposes?)</p>
<p>As I wrote you, there are at present no plans or funds to enclose Building No. 1<lb/>
properly. But once Camp Lazear is set aside I do hope to help start a Cuban-<lb/>
American fund raising campaign so that a permanent memorial and protection<lb/>
can be erected. Perhaps those of us who are younger would prefer to attend<lb/>
that dedication-of-the-future. But for those of us who are older, certainly<lb/>
<hi>now</hi> is the time to re-visit Camp Lazear, even though the memorial is not as<lb/>
elaborate as one might wish.</p>
<p>I shall ask Doctor Nogueira to clarify his point No. 6. Meanwhile, can you<lb/>
tell me whether those of you closely concerned with Camp Lazear would be able<lb/>
to go for the dedication (a) if the Cuban Government invited you and paid your<lb/>
way; (b) if the Cuban Government invited you but did not pay your way, but<lb/>
the American Army or State Department might; (c) if the Cuban Government in-<lb/>
vited you but no funds were available. In other words, could you go at<lb/>
your own expense, taking this as a personal vacation to Havana?</p>
<p>Please write me (care of my office at the Mayo Clinic). Your letters will be<lb/>
forwarded to me at once, air mail, while I am in Mexico the next two weeks.<lb/>
I will answer promptly (via hotel stenographer) and keep in close touch<lb/>
with Doctor Nogueira also. I am writing about all of the above to the Surgeon<lb/>
General.</p>
<p>Always sincerely yours,<lb/>
P. S. Hench, M.D.<lb/>
PSH:alc<lb/>
P.S.: Doctor Nogueira speaks English satisfactorily but writes it rather<lb/>
quaintly. For your interest and confidential information I enclose a copy<lb/>
of his letter. Let me re-write, paraphrase and summarize his letter thus:<lb/>
Copies sent to: General Reed, Blossom Reed, H. Lazear, Mrs. Briggs, Sra. Agramonte,<lb/>
Truby, Mrs. Kean, Col. Siler, Gen. Love, Sta. Rojas, Surgeon General.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04505010"/>
August 11, 1952<lb/>
Page 3<lb/>
(&ldquo;Free interpretation&rdquo; by P. S. Hench; at least this is my understanding.)<lb/>
Dear Philip:<lb/>
.........<lb/>
1. You, Philip, know me, Pedro, well enough to know that (as far as I'm con-<lb/>
cerned or can see to it?) the site of Camp Lazear will not be renamed, but<lb/>
will always be known as &ldquo;Camp Lazear,&rdquo; and the designation - &ldquo;Building<lb/>
Number One&rdquo; - will always be retained. I do not believe any one on the<lb/>
Commission will oppose that intention; we have often discussed it. Rest<lb/>
assured (or &ldquo;be quiet, Philip&rdquo;) that, if this had not been my understanding,<lb/>
I would have resigned and would no longer be a member of the Commission<lb/>
for the Preservation of the park and &ldquo;Caseta Number 1.&rdquo; I regret very<lb/>
much the newspaper errors, but I am contacting those who have been<lb/>
responsible so that the errors can be corrected. I hope that I can gradually<lb/>
get the newspapers to call the camp and caseta by their correct names.<lb/>
2. I do not believe that any other name for this place is required or will<lb/>
be used in the future and this place is, and only should be called, Camp<lb/>
Lazear.<lb/>
..........<lb/>
6. Your suggestion that Truby, Reed, Hanberry and the others whom you<lb/>
mentioned should be brought here for the inauguration seems fine to me.<lb/>
I am sure (?) that the (Cuban?) Government will find an opportunity to<lb/>
arrange for this (Or does Doctor Nogueira mean that he hopes the <hi>American</hi><lb/>
Government could make it possible to arrange this? - P.S.H.).<lb/>
Perhaps it would be prudent if you would write <hi>them</hi>, in the form of a<lb/>
&ldquo;personal question&rdquo; to learn their attitude about this. (Who does he mean<lb/>
by &ldquo;them,&rdquo; American governmental persons, or the survivors and relatives<lb/>
of the yellow-fever group? Does he mean for me to sound out <hi>our</hi> government<lb/>
or to sound out <hi>you</hi> who are closely associated with the work at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
you to whom I am writing, to see whether <hi>you</hi> would be able or willing to<lb/>
attend the dedication? I'm not quite sure which he means. - P.S.H.)<lb/>
(continuing)...It would &ldquo;elevate us&rdquo; (do honor to us) and be an unforgotten<lb/>
act if the American Embassy and the Army and Navy would send personal rep-<lb/>
resentatives (&ldquo;contribute with the personal&rdquo;). My own ideas on these matters<lb/>
will be formulated next week and you will be the first to know my ideas.<lb/>
Then you can tell me what you think about them and add your own ideas.....<lb/>
Pedro.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
