<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04506022">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J.F. Siler, September 19, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04506022</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-09-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Siler, J.F.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Love, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-09-19">September 19, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04506022</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J.F. Siler, September 19, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Siler that he has not heard from Nogueira for over a month and is concerned the park will be dedicated with a different name. He regrets that he will be unable to attend the dedication or a fall meeting of the Walter Reed Memorial Association as he has used up all his vacation and meeting time. He does intend to have a report on the Camp Lazear dedication to present to the Association.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-09-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J.F. Siler, September 19, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04506022"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-09-19">September 19, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Colonel J. F. Siler<lb/>
Gorgas Memorial Institute<lb/>
1835 Eye Street N.W.<lb/>
Washington 6, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Colonel Siler:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you very kindly for your letter of September 15. Yes, I did hear<lb/>
from General Love and have sent to Doctor Nogueira in Havana the names<lb/>
of the officers, hoping that those who are to dedicate Lazear Park would<lb/>
send them an invitation to the dedication.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I have not heard from Doctor Nogueira now for over a month<lb/>
and I am greatly concerned lest his silence be due to the fact that he<lb/>
has not been able to get his colleagues to go along with him in the matter<lb/>
of the proper naming of the park. I hardly know what to do now. Perhaps,<lb/>
as I have suspected all along, the construction of the Park has not gone<lb/>
far enough for it to be dedicated. Perhaps the delay represents the<lb/>
&ldquo;normal Cuban <unclear>manena</unclear>.&rdquo; Anyhow, I am writing him again today. If I don't<lb/>
hear within a very few days, I will cable him and if I still don't hear, I<lb/>
will have to play my last card; namely, notify four or five prominent<lb/>
Cubans and Americans of the situation and ask them to make quiet inquiries<lb/>
and suggestions that the park not be dedicated with the wrong name.</p>
<p>Most regretfully, I cannot attend the dedication. I did not know until<lb/>
early this spring that they were planning to dedicate it this fall and<lb/>
their plans, as outlined to me, were very vague. Unfortunately I have<lb/>
been under the necessity of traveling so much this year that I have not<lb/>
only used up all of my Clinic-allotted time for attendance at medical<lb/>
meetings, but I will have used up all of my vacation time as I long ago<lb/>
promised to go to a medical meeting in St. Louis on October 2 and another<lb/>
one in Boston on October 29.</p>
<p>I have for weeks been trying to figure out how I could get to a meeting<lb/>
of the Walter Reed Memorial Association this <unclear>fall</unclear> but I just don't see<lb/>
how I can. Even if the Board of Managers were gracious enough to set the date<lb/>
so that I could go enroute to Boston, I fear that I could not do it as I<lb/>
simply do not have even an extra day's time left. I am particularly<lb/>
anxious this year not to ask the Clinic for extra time as I must go to<lb/>
Europe again next summer to attend an International Congress on Rheumatic<lb/>
Diseases. The Clinic has sent me to Europe five times (three times within<lb/>
the last four years), therefore I simply cannot ask them to sponsor or pay<lb/>
for my 1953 European trip, which means that I must go and come entirely on<lb/>
my vacation time.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04506023"/>
<p>Colonel J. F. Siler</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>September 19, 1952</p>
<p>Colonel Siler, I regret very much that I have not been able to attend a<lb/>
meeting of the Walter Reed Memorial Association the last couple of years.<lb/>
I am sure you are sympathetic with the special problems which have faced<lb/>
me the last two years. I am glad to say that these responsibilities<lb/>
are <unclear>slackening</unclear> a little bit and that I am learning to say &ldquo;no&rdquo; to numerous<lb/>
invitations more frequently and more emphatically. I can assure you that<lb/>
I am happy and indeed proud that I can be associated with the Board of<lb/>
Managers and perhaps I will be forgiven for my absence and in lieu of<lb/>
my presence, will stand the time that I have spent this year in the matter<lb/>
of Lazear Park. I will certainly have for your Board a report of what has<lb/>
gone on. Whether the report will be a happy one acknowledging the proper<lb/>
actions of the Cubans or whether it will be an unhappy one reporting that<lb/>
they have gone back on their word and that more work remains to be done<lb/>
in the matter of correcting things remains to be seen. But it is a lot<lb/>
easier to name the park correctly in the beginning than it would be to re-<lb/>
name it once a false name had been established.</p>
<p>Some time ago I wrote to Doctor Nogueira sending him the information that<lb/>
the Surgeon General or one of his associates would be delighted to receive<lb/>

an invitation and that also the State Department, perhaps through the<lb/>
American Embassy in Cuba, would be glad to participate. Whether or not<lb/>
Doctor Nogueira has acted on this suggestion, I do not know.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
