<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, July 7, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-07-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship">YES</term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Macia, Adrian</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Presno, Jose A.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Finca San Jose, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-07-07">July 7, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, July 7, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses the rediscovery of Camp Lazear and his desire to erect a Cuban-American Memorial in honor of both Finlay and Reed on the site. He requests permission to personally pay for the construction of a suitable cover to protect Building No. 1.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-07-07">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, July 7, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509001"/>
<p><unclear>duplicate<lb/>
pg. 1</unclear><lb/>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1952-07-07">July 7, 1952</date>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
My dear Pedro:</p>
<p>As you know, I have been interested greatly in the dramatic story of the con-<lb/>
quest of yellow fever and have been visiting Havana since about 1939, collecting<lb/>
data concerning the work of Dr. Carlos Finlay and his assistant, Dr. Delgado<lb/>
which was begun in 1881, and that of Major Walter Reed and his associates done<lb/>
between 1900 and 1902.</p>
<p>During my several delightful visits to Havana in connection with my study, I<lb/>
have seen many Cuban physicians, government personalities and other Cubans and<lb/>
feel that I have many wonderful friends in Cuba.</p>
<p>During all these years it has been my firm hope and belief that certain unfortunate<lb/>
and undignified controversies (which have taken place in our respective countries,<lb/>
and which have concerned &ldquo;who did this and who did that,&rdquo; and how much credit<lb/>
should be given to each person) could be brought amicably to an end at long<lb/>
last. So very great were the services rendered to the whole world by the men<lb/>
who conquered yellow fever that there is more than glory enough for each!</p>
<p>In 1940 I was able, with the help of Mr. John Moran and Mr. Luis Pogolotti of<lb/>
Havana, to rediscover the site of Camp Lazear where Major Walter Reed and his<lb/>
associates did their work. To my delight I found that Camp Lazear had been part<lb/>
of the old Finca San Jose and that Dr. Finlay had carried out one or two of his<lb/>
very earliest experiments (concerning the mosquito and yellow fever) in the<lb/>
permanent house, or quinta, of this very same Finca San Jose. (On one of my<lb/>
visits to Havana I visited Dr. Carlos Finlay's son, Dr. Charles Finlay and<lb/>
confirmed this fact. I have notes to that effect written by Dr. Charles Fin-<lb/>
lay in his own handwriting on certain pages of the book he gave me, his own<lb/>
book about his father.).</p>
<p>In summary: in the main house (quinta) of the Finca San Jose were carried<lb/>
out one or two of the earliest experiments by Dr. Carlos Finlay in 1883, and<lb/>
in certain little wooden buildings (&ldquo;Buildings Number One and Two&rdquo;) erected<lb/>
at the rear of this same Finca San Jose (on a part of it used temporarily and<lb/>
named &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;) were carried out the concluding experiments of Major<lb/>
Reed and his associates in the fall of 1900 and early spring of 1901.</p>
<p>This coincidence seemed to me most fortuitous, a very happy one. Finding the<lb/>
remains of Major Reed's little Building Number One still standing, I thought<lb/>
these remains afforded a unique opportunity for interested persons to unite<lb/>
their efforts to the end that the little caseta and a small portion of the<lb/>
adjacent land (where Camp Lazear was) might be preserved and that on this<lb/>
spot would be erected a &ldquo;Cuban-American Memorial&rdquo; in honor of both Dr. Finlay<lb/>
and Dr. Reed and their various associates and volunteers (such as Dr. Delgado,<lb/>
also Padre Urra and other volunteers of Finlay; Drs. Carroll, Agramonte and<lb/>
Lazear, also Messrs. Moran, Kissinger and other volunteers of Reed et al).</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04509002"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>July 7, 1952</p>
<p>It has been my belief that Cuban and American Medical, Governmental and other<lb/>
personages could unite wholeheartedly to honor jointly the memories and deeds<lb/>
of these great humanitarians, benefactors and &ldquo;citizens&rdquo; of the whole world.</p>
<p>In connection with this idea I have visited on my several trips to Havana many<lb/>
distinguished Cubans in medical and governmental circles who seemed to be not<lb/>
only pleased but enthusiastic about the project. They have helped in many<lb/>
ways. I have also told many of my own countrymen of this proposed venture and<lb/>
found them equally interested and desirous of being helpful.</p>
<p>Certain legal and practical difficulties (related to ownership of the little<lb/>
portion of land where Camp Lazear was and where the caseta still is, also<lb/>
related to the type of memorial best suited for the location and for the<lb/>
purposes of the Havana and Marianao health departments, etc.) and also my<lb/>
four years of duty in our Army Medical Corps prevented me and my Cuban friends<lb/>
from crystallizing a definite plan or starting a definite campaign to raise<lb/>
money in my country and in yours. But preliminary drawings and ideas were<lb/>
presented to several of your distinguished countrymen and these plans re-<lb/>
ceived their general approval.</p>
<p>The little caseta was &ldquo;declared&rdquo; a national monument by the Council of Ministers<lb/>
(Consejo de Ministros) in the spring of 1947 (I believe that was the time).<lb/>
But the approval of the Council (aprobo el Consejo) was not announced until<lb/>
November 1947 (e.g. <hi>El Pais</hi>, pages 1 and 3, November 13, 1947). Despite this<lb/>
declaration and approval in 1947, no effort was made to protect the caseta<lb/>
from the ravages of time or from the recurring hurricanes, nor was any money<lb/>
set aside even for the temporary protection of the caseta.</p>
<p>During the visit to Habana that Mrs. Hench and I made in March 1948 I re-<lb/>
quested permission from several Cuban personages to be allowed to donate<lb/>
$1,000.00 of my own money so that a protective galvanized iron or other<lb/>
suitable cover could be erected at once to enclose the caseta and protect<lb/>
it thus temporarily until appropriate plans and monies could be developed<lb/>
at leisure. But because the caseta had been named a &ldquo;national monument&rdquo;<lb/>
Senor Adrian Macia, the owner of the adjacent land, had no authority to let<lb/>
me do anything to the caseta. Then I was granted a cordial interview with<lb/>
your Vice-President Cardenas. He was gracious and interested in our plan,<lb/>
but said that it would not be appropriate for Cuba to permit me, a private<lb/>
citizen, to spend my own money on such temporary expenses; he said that he<lb/>
would try to obtain the necessary funds from the Cuban Government in an ap-<lb/>
priate manner.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the ravages of time would, presumably, continue to affect the<lb/>
caseta, a &ldquo;national monument&rdquo; in name only. Stymied in this manner, I did<lb/>
not know how I could make any proposition to my own countrymen in the<lb/>
government or of the American Medical Association. But I was greatly en-<lb/>
couraged when a Cuban friend sent me a copy of El Mundo, March 25, 1948, in<lb/>
which it was announced that $50,000 was designated by &ldquo;El Consejo de Ministros&rdquo;<lb/>
as a preliminary sum to be expended for the preservation of the caseta. I<lb/>
believe that Dr. Andreu was the chief sponsor, probably with Vice-President<lb/>
Cardenas, Dr. Presno and your good self as additional friends of this movement.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04509003"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>July 7, 1952</p>
<p>In April 1948, I was informed that, although the Cuban Minister of Finance<lb/>
had signed the decree allotting the $50,000, the decree had not yet been pub-<lb/>
lished in the <hi>Official Gazette</hi>. Shortly thereafter there was a change in the<lb/>
administration; and I was greatly disappointed to learn that the plan had<lb/>
fallen through, and the money was never made available.</p>
<p>But in 1951 I was informed that, through the continuing interest and sponsor-<lb/>
ship of Dr. Andreu and others, plans for the preservation of Camp Lazear and<lb/>
the caseta had been revived and that $25,000 had been set aside for its preserva-<lb/>
tion. Various Cuban friends sent me several Habana newspaper clippings about<lb/>
this: for example, clippings from El Pais, April 25, 1951 and November 16,<lb/>
1951 and from Excelsior, December 10, 1951.</p>
<p>Many Americans were delighted to hear of these revived plans which I men-<lb/>
tioned to the Surgeon General of the United States Army and others.</p>
<p>On our recent (January 1952) visit to Habana, Mrs. Hench and I were delighted<lb/>
indeed to hear of the progression of these plans from Dr. Andreu, yourself<lb/>
and others. I was happy to express publicly my great delight and approval,<lb/>
and to offer my continuing help (if my help could be useful), during the little<lb/>
talk I gave at a Rotary Club luncheon in Marianao, also during the little<lb/>
speech I made when Dr. Andreu and others honored me greatly on the occasion<lb/>
of the Condecoration of the Finlay Medal. I also was delighted to discuss<lb/>
the preservation of Camp Lazear and the caseta, when I was interviewed by a<lb/>
certain newspaper reporter (Avance, January 25, 1952).</p>
<p>Let me assure you that my enthusiasm for a &ldquo;Cuban-American memorial&rdquo; is<lb/>
still as strong as ever. I realize that with the relatively small amount<lb/>
of money allotted ($25,000) your Ministry of Public Health and your Depart-<lb/>
ment of Public Works can only do so much at this time. I am hopeful that<lb/>
my own countrymen can join with yours so that, once the grounds around the<lb/>
caseta have been properly developed into a park, a permanent and suitable<lb/>
protection for the caseta can be erected, perhaps in connection either with<lb/>
a small &ldquo;Cuban-American Medical Museum&rdquo; or, better yet, in connection with<lb/>
an even more suitable affair; a useful, &ldquo;living memorial&rdquo; in the form of a<lb/>
small public health project or unit. As long as the historic caseta remains<lb/>
uncovered, exposed continuously to the elements, the historically minded<lb/>
people will be unhappy about the dangerous impermanency of this memorial<lb/>
which could be used so felicitously to strengthen greatly the bonds of<lb/>
friendship and understanding between our two governments and between the<lb/>
medical professions of our two countries.</p>
<p>Permit me to ask you to express to Dr. Andreu and to others who may be con-<lb/>
cerned my own personal gratitude for the very real progress that has been<lb/>
made. When the little park is dedicated I hope indeed that American news<lb/>
services will be advised because the ceremonies will interest and please<lb/>
a great many in this country.</p>
<p>Permit me to offer to Dr. Andreu, to yourself and others my services in<lb/>
developing further plans for financial and other cooperation.</p>
<p>Always sincerely yours,<lb/>
P. S. Hench, M.D.<lb/>
PSH:alc</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04509004"/>
<p>Addendum to letter of July 7, 1952</p>
<p>Pedro, will you now let me discuss with you, as one good friend to another,<lb/>
a more delicate matter that has given me and others some concern, a growing<lb/>
concern, I might add.</p>
<p>You will recall with what pleasure I discussed briefly with Doctor Andreu<lb/>
last January his plans for the preservation of the caseta at Camp Lazear.<lb/>
I have been well aware of your own important and continuing influence in<lb/>
these developments. You will recall how happy I was to go with you to the<lb/>
Ministry of Public Works to see the preliminary blue-prints for the park. I<lb/>
am sure you will remember that after expressing my general approval and<lb/>
pleasure, I hesitated a moment and then called your attention to two places<lb/>
on the blue-print: (1) the title or heading on the original blue print<lb/>
read (as I recall it) &ldquo;Anteproyecto de Parque Finlay&rdquo;; (2) the little caseta<lb/>
(Reed's &ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo;), was erroneously designated &ldquo;caseta de Finlay.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was about to leave Habana and certainly did not want to become involved in<lb/>
the old unhappy controversy with you and other wonderful Cuban friends of<lb/>
mine. But I felt that in fairness to all concerned I had to discuss this<lb/>
quietly with you. When I called these to your attention you may recall I<lb/>
said that I and others in your country as well as mine had hoped that the<lb/>
memorial might be called &ldquo;The Cuban-American Memorial&rdquo; or &ldquo;The Cuban-<lb/>
American Medical Memorial.&rdquo; Perhaps even more specifically the land might be<lb/>
called &ldquo;Parque Lazear&rdquo; or &ldquo;Campamento Lazear,&rdquo; continuing its actual historical<lb/>
name, whereas the future memorial building could be called &ldquo;The Cuban-American<lb/>
Medical Memorial&rdquo; which will house, among other things and souvenirs,<lb/>
&ldquo;Building Number One.&rdquo;</p>
<p>However I also said that if your government saw fit to discard these or<lb/>
similar suggestions and to name the site of Camp Lazear &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo; it<lb/>
would be less appropriate but perhaps &ldquo;acceptable&rdquo; to Cuba's American friends<lb/>
provided &ldquo;Reed's Building Number One&rdquo; was properly identified.</p>
<p>I was relieved when you smiled at my remarks. After talking volubly in<lb/>
Spanish with the architects you reassured me that the title of the project<lb/>
was tentative and that the &ldquo;caseta de Finlay&rdquo; was a frank mistake. Your<lb/>
explanation was quite simple and valid; as I recall it you said, &ldquo;Phil,<lb/>
that's just a mistake which must be and will be corrected. After all,<lb/>
these draftsmen in the Department of Public Works aren't medical historians.<lb/>
They know nothing about yellow fever, Camp Lazear, Walter Reed or &lsquo;Building<lb/>
Number One&rsquo;. We'll fix that up alright.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Thus reassured that the work was to be a joint memorial in honor of Finlay<lb/>
and the American investigators, I asked if I might have two blue-prints as<lb/>
I wanted later to make copies and send them to interested Americans including<lb/>
our State Department in Washington and the Surgeon General of the Army, so<lb/>
that their sympathetic interest and appreciation of what your Government was<lb/>
doing could be expressed. When you translated my request to the architect<lb/>
he promised to make available to me &ldquo;corrected copies.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In due time I received two corrected blue-prints now entitled &ldquo;Anteproyecto<lb/>
de Parque en el Antiguo &lsquo;Campamento Lazear&rsquo;.&rdquo; I had copies made here and was<lb/>
about to send them out when I noticed that the caseta of Reed was still labelled<lb/>
&ldquo;caseta de Finlay.&rdquo; I concluded that this was a simple error still uncorrected,<lb/>
and meant to write you about it so that I could get a true, corrected copy to<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04509005"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
July 7, 1952<lb/>
send to Washington and elsewhere with my personal account of what Cuba was<lb/>
planning to do. But my letter to you about this was delayed because of the<lb/>
press of medical work, attendance at medical meetings, etc.</p>
<p>Meanwhile I have received (quite unsolicited by me) from various friends<lb/>
and acquaintances in Cuba a number of newspaper clippings that first disturbed<lb/>
them and have since disturbed me somewhat also. There are in Cuba, many people<lb/>
(mostly Cubans, but also many Americans resident in Cuba, besides those in the<lb/>
American embassy) who now know something about the historical significance of<lb/>
&ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; and &ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo;. During the past ten to twelve years<lb/>
several newspaper articles in Cuban newspapers have discussed the &ldquo;rediscovery&rdquo;<lb/>
of Camp Lazear. The matter was discussed also on the radio once or twice. These<lb/>
people have interested themselves sufficiently to know the relationship between<lb/>
the work of Finlay and that of the Americans, to know something about Finlay's<lb/>
early experiments and the later ones of the Americans and their associates at<lb/>
Camp Columbia and later at &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Being thus informed they have been concerned by the continuation of the<lb/>
newspaper errors. As a reader one can readily ignore or explain away or condone<lb/>
one or two erroneous newspaper accounts. But when such continues to be pub-<lb/>
lished one is inclined to wonder whether the newspapers really do wish to get<lb/>
matters straight.</p>
<p>Because I have recently received two or three new clippings which continue<lb/>
the errors I have decided I had better call them to your attention and ask you<lb/>
for advice as to what should be done.</p>
<p>The time is approaching when &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; (regardless of whether or not it<lb/>
is called that) is to be dedicated. As I understand it the dedication will be<lb/>
during an international congress. Presumably American physicians, perhaps<lb/>
American medical officers and other personnel will be there. It would be quite<lb/>
embarassing and unfortunate if the affair were the subject of misunderstanding<lb/>
and regret.</p>
<p>It is quite possible that the concern of my correspondents in Cuba (and of<lb/>
myself) is entirely unnecessary. It is also possible that these clippings have<lb/>
not been brought to your attention, or that, reading each one at widely spaced<lb/>
intervals you did not appreciate the unfavorable reaction that they are develop-<lb/>
ing in certain quarters. Like me, you probably ignored the early ones. But<lb/>
although I did not worry about them I did keep them all in my files and perhaps<lb/>
you will best understand the situation if I transcribe excerpts from several<lb/>
representative ones in consecutive order.</p>
<p>Do you not agree with me that someone in authority should very soon explain<lb/>
the situation more clearly and accurately to the Habana newspapers? If this is<lb/>
not done soon, the papers will either not get the story right at the time of the<lb/>
dedication or they will then receive such a &ldquo;different story&rdquo; that they will<lb/>
wonder why they were not completely informed earlier.</p>
<p>If at the time of the dedication the papers should continue the errors and<lb/>
perpetuate the misunderstanding, would it not tend to undo what Dr. Andreu, Dr.<lb/>
Ramos (who once wrote a paper about Camp Lazear and recommended the erection of<lb/>
a joint memorial), you and I and many others have been trying to do.</p>
<p>Here is a grand opportunity for a joint memorial project. I personally<lb/>
always speak and write about the amazing work of Finlay in connection with my<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f04509006"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
July 7, 1952<lb/>
papers and talks on this subject. Having heard my illustrated talk in Washing-<lb/>
ton a few years ago you can vouch for that. I agree heartily that my country-<lb/>
men do not know nearly as much as they should about Finlay. I am seeing to it<lb/>
that they will know and, as you know, I have spent much time trying to learn<lb/>
the details of his life and work. When my book appears I feel sure that justice<lb/>
will be done to Finlay as well as to my countrymen and in the very nature of<lb/>
things several chapters will have to be all about Finlay.</p>
<p>But certainly Reed, Agramonte, Carroll and Lazear and their associates did<lb/>
a great service to Cuba as well as to the world. If the newspapers are permitted<lb/>
to continue to speak of &ldquo;Building Number One&rdquo; as the &ldquo;caseta de Finlay&rdquo; you and I<lb/>
and the many broad minded physicians and governmental personages who want so very<lb/>
much to do honor to <hi>all concerned</hi> will have reason for regrets and will feel that<lb/>
our efforts to develop mutual admiration and esteem have been unsuccessful. We<lb/>
want no partisanship in this fine venture and we must not let this venture be<lb/>
spoiled by repertorial ignorance or misunderstanding!</p>
<p>Pedro, will you please read over the appended quotations from selected clip-<lb/>
pings and give me your reaction. I do hope you can reassure me that the careless<lb/>
or uninformed reporters do not have any official approval. What should be done?<lb/>
What can I do? Do you think I should write Dr. Andreu or Dr. Ramos or Dr. Presno<lb/>
or the mayor of Marianao? Should I write to Mrs. Smith, President of F.I.M.?<lb/>
You might be able to discuss the matter briefly and quietly with Dr. Andreu, and<lb/>
he could &ldquo;brief&rdquo; the reporters accurately at the proper time. But the repertorial<lb/>
build-up for the dedication of the little park cannot be far off. So it seems<lb/>
that the papers should soon be told what is <hi>the happy truth</hi>, namely that the<lb/>
dedication of a memorial on the Finca San Jose is so wonderfully appropriate<lb/>
because this place unites, <hi>as no other place in the world can do</hi>, the humanitarian<lb/>
works and beneficient spirits of all the medical heroes concerned!</p>
<p>Always your friend,<lb/>
P. S. Hench, M.D.<lb/>
PSH:dsl</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
