<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509019">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Pedro Nogueira to Philip Showalter Hench, October 12, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Nogueira, Pedro</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509019</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-10-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Alvarez, Jacinto Mendez</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Fernandez, Nicanor</name>
<name type="person">Folk</name>
<name type="person">Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Martinez, Jose</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Presedo, Becente</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert Page</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Caroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Warner, Lena</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-10-12">October 12, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509019</idno>
<title>Letter from Pedro Nogueira to Philip Showalter Hench, October 12, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Nogueira sends Hench a list of names to be engraved on memorial plaques for the dedication of Camp Lazear. He explains why some were included and others excluded.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-10-12">
<head>Letter from Pedro Nogueira to Philip Showalter Hench, October 12, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509019"/>
<p>COPY<lb/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Medico Cirujano<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Telefono: BO-7577<lb/>
Marianao <date value="1952-10-12">October 12 or 1952</date>
Dr. Philip Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota, U.S..A.<lb/>
Dear Philip:</p>
<p>According to my former letters and after discussing the matter with the Patrones<lb/>
members, it has been agreed that the names to be put on the plates are those who<lb/>
served as volunteers on the Lazear's Camp, or rather these mentioned here below:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Alvarez</item>
<item>Benigno</item>
<item>Fernandez</item>
<item>Folk</item>
<item>Hanberry</item>
<item>Jernegan</item>
<item>Kissinger</item>
<item>Martinez</item>
<item>Moran</item>
<item>Presedo</item>
<item>Sonntag</item>
<item>Weatherwalks</item>
<item>West</item>
</list></p>
<p>For this list could be added the names of the fomites volunteers:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Cooke</item>
<item>England</item>
<item>Hildebrand.</item>
</list></p>
<p>And besides those on blood inoculations on Lazear's Camp, not included among the<lb/>
upper groups:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Andrus</item>
<item>Forbes</item>
<item>Olsen</item>
</list></p>
<p>It is agreed on not include the inoculations made by carroll and Reed on Columbia<lb/>
Barracks with fresh and warm serum, why those were not done in the Camp.</p>
<p>Neither are those made before by Lazear on Columbia Barracks nor Dr. Guiteras<lb/>
series and Finlay and Delgado (although they are made 5 experimental inocula-<lb/>
tions on San Jose Farm in 1883). In one word, only those on active service<lb/>
are included.</p>
<p>Finally suggested it was passed to put on the plate the following dedication:<lb/>
THESE COOPERATED TOO; here are included the names: Kean, Sternberg, Ames; Truby;<lb/>
Warner and Lambert.</p>
<p>Gorgas' name is left out as he has a memorial on Finlay Park in Havana, and with<lb/>
regard to Stark, being Reed's substitute doesnt merit sufficient, why it is un-<lb/>
known whether his influence got in the work relized.</p>
<p>Philip I want your sound opinion on this as custom which I pray your quickest reply<lb/>
waiting to send the job to the foundery and have time to get them through for<lb/>
the 3rd of December answer me right away.</p>
<p>On the other hand I'm mailing the negatives of views by registered airmail next<lb/>
Thursday. They are several for you to choose those you like best and from them<lb/>
we can take as many is necessary. Together are some photos taken on the Camp<lb/>
some persons on visit due to the Hygiene Congress.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04509020"/>
<p>C<lb/>
O<lb/>
P<lb/>
Y</p>
<p>Dr. Nogueira<lb/>
Page 2</p>
<p>Right now we are working with the brick layers and electricians and hope on<lb/>
month end to have the caseta totally finished to be able to send you some pic-<lb/>
tures, and that the park would be well on the way on that date and you would be<lb/>
able to appreciate it on the photos.</p>
<p>We are also making the program for 3rd December and we's like to know if somebody<lb/>
from the U.S.A. should occupy a space to be able to notify him on time.</p>
<p>Philip, I am happy because up to now we are on the way and we will soon see<lb/>
what we long hoped for.</p>
<p>Philip excuse again my English, every day is worse.</p>
<p>Pedro</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
