<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04506003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert G. Love, August 12, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04506003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-08-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Love, Albert G.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter L.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Landon</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Rodriguez, Estella Agramonte</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Smith, Louise F. Carbonell</name>
<name type="person">Felipe Ponce</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-08-12">August 12, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04506003</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert G. Love, August 12, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench stresses the importance of the final name for the Camp Lazear site. He also thinks it is important that the Army medical department and the State Department have representatives at the ceremony. Hench requests that Love contact Siler and Lawrence Reed to find out if they plan to attend the ceremony.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-08-12">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert G. Love, August 12, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04506003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1952-08-12">August 12, 1952</date>
</dateline>
General Albert E. Love<lb/>
2709 Wisconsin Avenue N.W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Love:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Please see the enclosed memorandum and covering letter which I am sending to<lb/>
the Surgeon General of the U.S. Army.</p>
<p>I am greatly concerned about the possibility that the Surgeon General may be<lb/>
away and that some deputy may not realize the minor urgency of this matter.<lb/>
I admit that in view of world events this matter is relatively unimportant.<lb/>
On the other hand, if the Cubans do dedicate Camp Lazear in six or seven<lb/>
weeks. I think you will agree with me that it is important that it be dedicated<lb/>
with the right names. I think you will aggree it is important also that the<lb/>
medical department of the Army, and perhaps also the State Department, have<lb/>
representatives there.</p>
<p>Can you do me a real favor? Can you first get in touch with Colonel Siler<lb/>
and General Reed, at least by telephone? (I am sending them each a copy<lb/>
of my memorandum to the Surgeon General and my letter to you.) Could you<lb/>
find out whether General Reed would be agreeable to going to Cuba for the<lb/>
dedication under the proper circumstances? With this tentative information,<lb/>
could you then call someone whom you know in the Surgeon General's Office and<lb/>
make sure that somebody there is looking over my memorandum and enclosures?<lb/>
Also, you might discretely inquire as to whether Generals Reed and Truby<lb/>
might somehow be activated long enough to go to the dedication. I hope that<lb/>
General and Mrs. Reed can make some arrangements to go if they wish to do so<lb/>
but certainly he would not make any inquiries from the Surgeon General. That<lb/>
must be handled by his friends; if possible by you on the scene and by me by<lb/>
correspondence.</p>
<p>I think it is important for the Surgeon General and for someone in the State<lb/>
Department representing Cuban affairs, to know what is going on but I hope that<lb/>
no one will upset the apple cart. In view of Doctor Nogueira's letter, I think<lb/>
we must allow him to act freely and not give him or other Cubans any indica-<lb/>
tion of any pressure at this time. I might add that as for the concern ex-<lb/>
pressed in my letters of July 7 and 26 to him, I can assure you that I was<lb/>
not alone in this concern. Indeed resting on the assurances of Doctor Nogueira,<lb/>
I was the last one to become concerned. Others who anticipated my concern<lb/>
were Miss Agramonte, Miss Rojas (owner of the Finca San Jose), Doctor Carbonell,<lb/>
Mrs. Smith (President of FIM in Cuba) and one or two others.</p>
<p>I shall be away for two weeks but whatever information you have please send to<lb/>
my address at the Clinic. My secretary is completely informed about the matter<lb/>
under discussion, has instructions as to what to do under various contingencies,<lb/>
and will forward the letters air mail to me. In any event I shall be back the<lb/>
first week in September.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Copy to Doctor Siler and Gen. Reed. &amp; Gen. Truby<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
