<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04506036">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul H. Streit, November 13, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04506036</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Streit, Paul H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-13">November 13, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04506036</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul H. Streit, November 13, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is delighted to know that Streit has accepted the Cuban invitation to come to the Camp Lazear dedication. He warns Streit that the preservation of Camp Lazear has been a politically sensitive issue. Hench thinks it is important that the Americans are appreciative, but also truthful, about what happened at Camp Lazear. He laments that Building No. 1 has been almost completely torn down in the process of repairing it.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul H. Streit, November 13, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04506036"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-13">November 13, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Major General Paul H. Streit<lb/>
Commanding General<lb/>
Walter Reed Army Hospital<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Streit:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am delighted to know that you have accepted the Cuban invitation to go<lb/>
to Havana and the dedication of Camp Lazear. As I told you, there is<lb/>
some question as to whether they calling it Camp Lazear or renaming it<lb/>
Parque Finlay.</p>
<p>I am very glad that you are going, but I must warn you that I thing you<lb/>
will give more than you will got. By that I mean that I do not anticipate<lb/>
an elaborate, impressive ceremony with all of Cuba's officialdom present<lb/>
and with the usual banquets, etc. I may be mistaken but after twelve<lb/>
years of discussion with my Cuban friends, I have found that Camp Lazear<lb/>
has been made something of a political football by various factions.<lb/>
There are sincere groups in Cuba that are just as eager as I am to see<lb/>
the proper memorialization of Camp Lazear, who are disappointed with what<lb/>
the present &ldquo;ins&rdquo; are doing and who may actually not attend the ceremony.<lb/>
But your presence and the presence of other Americans may do much to heal<lb/>
the unfortunate wounds which began 50 years ago when, according to the<lb/>
Cubans, the Rockefeller Foundation and the U. S. Army insisted on giving<lb/>
most of the credit to Reed and little to Finlay. As you know, they re-<lb/>
acted violently to the extent that Reed's name has been vilified for years<lb/>
in Cuba and although there are a few memorials to Lazear and others, there<lb/>
is not a single one to Reed. This will be the first.</p>
<p>Although they have not done what I wanted and although Reed and his col-<lb/>
leagues may once more be over-shadowed by the homage to Finlay, at least<lb/>
it is a modest beginning. To that extent I am pleased and feel that we<lb/>
must show our due appreciation, perhaps even in <unclear>excessive</unclear> language, more, actually,<lb/>
then we feel. Nevertheless, as I said over the phone, any Americans present<lb/>
there, who may speak although we can pay great tribute to Finlay, must keep<lb/>
the record clear and tell exactly what did happen at Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>I may have misadvised you in suggesting that you may be called upon to<lb/>
make some informal remarks somewhere along the line but from my experience<lb/>
in Cuba, I suspect you will; however before spending much time and effort<lb/>
in this talk, I would suggest that you write or wire your host about this<lb/>
matter. But even if he suggests that you will not be called upon, I still<lb/>
think you had better have a few thoughts collected in case you are suddenly<lb/>
called upon at a dinner or some other meeting or by the Cuban press.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04506037"/>
<p>Major General Paul H. Streit</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>November 13, 1952</p>
<p>Permit me to enclose a reprint which will refresh your mind on certain<lb/>
details and which will show how the little building looked four years<lb/>
ago. I regret to say that they have almost completely torn it down and<lb/>
made a restoration rather than a repair job. Also, to show you the dif-<lb/>
ficulties in which I have been placed, permit me to send you copies of<lb/>
two letters which I sent to Doctor Nogueira some months ago with some<lb/>
interesting newspaper clippings which will show you the attitude which I<lb/>
fear we will have to face politely and not aggressively.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I just received the enclosed.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
