<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04505012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, November 8, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04505012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Spies, Tom D.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Smith, Louise F.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-08">November 8, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04505012</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, November 8, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Spies that the dedication of Camp Lazear will be held on Finlay's birthday and &ldquo;Physicians' Day&rdquo; in Cuba. He has made his concerns known to Nogueira that Finlay will dominate the affair and that Camp Lazear will be renamed &ldquo;Parque Finlay.&rdquo; He suggests Spies visit Camp Lazear when in Cuba to see how the work is progressing.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-08">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, November 8, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04505012"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-08">November 8, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Tom D. Spies<lb/>
Nutrition Clinic<lb/>
Hillman Hospital<lb/>
Birmingham, Alabama<lb/>
<salute>My dear Tom:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have been meaning to write to you about the Camp Lazear affair. This<lb/>
spring when Doctor Nogueira told me that they were really going ahead,<lb/>
I <unclear>reacted</unclear> minimally because so many previous unkept promises and false<lb/>
starts had made me skeptical but, by golly, this time Doctor Nogueira and<lb/>
his superiors, presumably Doctor Andreu, the Minister of Health, really went<lb/>
ahead. They have cleared out part of the cornfield at Camp Lazear, extended<lb/>
a road, leveled off the ground and are erecting a stone wall to hold certain<lb/>
medallions honoring Reed, Finlay, Lazear and others and bronze tablets on<lb/>
which will appear the names of the volunteers, and so on. They had originally<lb/>
planned to dedicate it on September 20, but were <unclear>hold</unclear> up and now plan to dedicate<lb/>
it on December 3. When the September date fell through, Doctor Nogueira wanted<lb/>
to dedicate it on November 20, the anniversary of the day the camp was originally<lb/>
opened but his superiors over-ruled him and chose December 3 which was Finlay's<lb/>
birthday and &ldquo;Physician's Day&rdquo; in Cuba. This date has certain advantages<lb/>
and certain disadvantages. It has the main advantage that it is &ldquo;Physicians'<lb/>
Day,&rdquo; a day set aside to honor Doctor Finlay in particular and all medical men<lb/>
in general, a day in which, naturally, physicians will pause for special cere-<lb/>
monies. It has the disadvantage of being Finlay's birthday. He may dominate<lb/>
the whole affair.</p>
<p>I have had several communications with Doctor Nogueira this summer, discreetly<lb/>
and diplomatically urging that they maintain the name Camp Lazear but I<lb/>
strongly fear that they are going to rename it Parque Finlay. He has re-<lb/>
peatedly reassured me that Reed's Building No. 1, which the newspapers and the<lb/>
blue prints erroneously called &ldquo;caseta de Finlay&rdquo; will not be misnamed but<lb/>
will be called Reed's Building No. 1. As to the name, &ldquo;Parque Finlay,&rdquo; I<lb/>
very greatly hate to compromise but in view of the fact that the Cubans are<lb/>
doing everything toward this dedication and the Americans nothing, I have<lb/>
felt very helpless and suppose that we may have to accept that compromise<lb/>
as long as Reed's Building No. 1 is recornized for what it is and as long<lb/>
as the dedication speeches clearly point out that it was the Americans who<lb/>
did the work at Camp Lazear, not Doctor Finlay. However this spot is peculiarly<lb/>
appropriate for a joint memorial since Doctor Finlay did two or three of his<lb/>
earliest experiments in the main house or quinta of the Finca San Jose. Please<lb/>
see the enclosed copy of my letter of July 7 and I enclose an extra copy in<lb/>
case you wish to send it to Mrs. Smith of F.I.M.</p>
<p>During the last four months I have been on the verge several times of &ldquo;starting<lb/>
a backfire&rdquo; and trying to involve others in the affair, Cuban friends who<lb/>
might make certain that the naming of the Camp is not out of order; however<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04505013"/>
Dr. Tom D. Spies<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 8, 1952<lb/>
Doctor Nogueira has been so very cooperative, such a strong force behind this<lb/>
whole movement and he has reassured me so often that I must not worry, that<lb/>
they will do the right thing, that I have just not had the courage to go be-<lb/>
hind his back and demonstrate to him lack of faith. Indeed I do have complete<lb/>
faith in him and his honorable intentions, but I am not sure to what extent<lb/>
he may be over-ruled by his superiors.</p>
<p>He has not answered precisely my question as to the intended name of the<lb/>
project. I strongly suspect we may have to compromise and disappointedly<lb/>
accept the term &ldquo;Parque Finlay.&rdquo; This compromise might be acceptable so<lb/>
long as Reed's Building No. 1 is properly named.</p>
<p>Nogueira has corresponded with me extensively in regard to the names of the<lb/>
volunteers to go on the plaques and so on. They have finally made their<lb/>
decision. I could only make suggestions. Their decision is reasonably<lb/>
acceptable. They made certain exclusions which are understandable; also<lb/>
some inclusions which I suggested. When asked about those who should be<lb/>
invited, I have given them various names, but perhaps not enough. I suggested<lb/>
official invitations be sent to the President and President-Elect of the<lb/>
A.M.A., the members of the Walter Reed Memorial Association in Washington,<lb/>
the Surgeon General or his deputy, the officers of the Walter Reed Society,<lb/>
perhaps Fishbein, the relatives of the volunteers, also your name and<lb/>
Smith as well as the State Department and the American Ambassador in Cuba.<lb/>
I don't think any official invitations have been sent out as yet. There<lb/>
have been the usual delays and last-minute rush and how extensive will be<lb/>
their list, I do not know. Although I really don't have time or money to<lb/>
spare, I hope to fly down for the affair.</p>
<p>Now, Tom, I remember with great pleasure and some concern the conversation<lb/>
that you, Mrs. Smith and I had about this whole venture. I was hoping, as<lb/>
you were, that they would drop the matter for the time being and that others<lb/>
could pick it up do what we wanted; but they most assuredly did not. Things<lb/>
really began to hum after my January trip and matters were completely out of<lb/>
my hands because since Reed's Building No. 1 was an official monument, I was<lb/>
not allowed to do anything privately and they just went ahead.</p>
<p>Tom, I wonder if there isn't a fine opportunity ahead of us. Although they<lb/>
have torn down much of the original Building No. 1 so that what remains is<lb/>
more a replica than a restoration, the Cuban Government has gone this far. I<lb/>
really doubt if they will go any further. Nogueira has promised to save me<lb/>
as much of the original wood or walling as possible, which I hope to use to<lb/>
make souvenirs for various interested people and institutions. It is my hope<lb/>
that with the help of American and perhaps Cuban physicians and friends, we<lb/>
can now begin to collect money so as to enclose the remains of Building No. 1<lb/>
in one room of a permanent building, the rest of the building to be a living<lb/>
memorial (not a museum) to the conquerors of yellow fever, Reed and his as-<lb/>
sociates, the memorial perhaps to be a little research institution or public<lb/>
health unit or what have you. I shall not be happy until the little building<lb/>
has a permanent protection. Now if it seems best merely to have a little<lb/>
museum building erected over Building No. 1 and while raising funds to do<lb/>
that, to raise funds for a research project as a living memorial to be used<lb/>
by F.I.M. and others, that would be an acceptable alternative to me, providing<lb/>
only that Building No. 1 is permanently enclosed.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04505014"/>
<p>Dr. Tom D. Spies</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>November 8, 1952</p>
<p>May I suggest therefore the following two or three things:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Are you going to Havana soon on one of your periodic visits? If so, could<lb/>
you take time to contact Nogueira without involving me or indicating that<lb/>
you have perhaps been stimulated by me. Could you not drive out to Camp<lb/>
Lazear casually, &ldquo;just happen&rdquo; to see the activity their and, as a result,<lb/>
make inquiries of Doctor Nogueira as to what the present plans are? From<lb/>
there on, you can do whatever seems proper. If you have to have an excuse<lb/>
to visit Camp Lazear, you might take with you some American or other visitor<lb/>
&ldquo;who asked me to show him around <unclear>where</unclear> Camp Lazear was.&rdquo; If you don't know<lb/>
where it is, telephone Miss Maria Teresa Rojas, Finca San Jose, Calle Real,<lb/>
Quemados de Marianao, Havana, or drop in on her and her companion, Miss Lydia<lb/>
Cabrera; both are charming young women. Camp Lazear is at the rear of their<lb/>
finca on the main street of Marianao.</item>
<item>2. In discussing the matter with Doctor Nogueira, you may be able to offer<lb/>
him your support to some future project as suggested above. Certainly you<lb/>
can discuss with him the matter of further American cooperation in the<lb/>
dedication and make suggestions regarding others to be invited, either<lb/>
Americans or Cubans in Havana or Americans in the United States.</item>
<item>3. If you find that they are naming the place Parque Finlay instead of<lb/>
Camp Lazear and if you feel there is any discreet or delicate way in which<lb/>
you can suggest otherwise, I must leave that up to you. Above all, this<lb/>
must be handled diplomatically so that we can accomplish our purposes (if<lb/>
possible) without offending those who are, after all, doing a great deal<lb/>
to honor the Americans as well as Finlay. Regardless of what we Americans<lb/>
would like to see done, I was never able to get any Americans to help me<lb/>
although I have talked about this, written and given many lectures about<lb/>
it during the last 12 years. Therefore if the Cubans do it not quite the<lb/>
way we want, I fear we will have to be satisfied up to a point.</item>
</list></p>
<p>In summary, I suspect that having done what they have, that will be the end<lb/>
of their effort and now is the time for Americans, you and me and others, to<lb/>
carry on the project.</p>
<p>I am sending you a copy of this letter and also an extra copy of my letter of<lb/>
July 7 which you may send to Mrs. Smith. If you are going to be in Havana<lb/>
on December 3 perhaps you, she and I can have a conference regarding future<lb/>
possibilities. The letter of July 7 is considerably out of date because of<lb/>
the numerous letters I have had from Doctor Nogueira thereafter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I have just received your letter of November 3 requesting reprints about<lb/>
Walter Reed for Dr. J. R. Miller. The ones I enclose herewith are for you and<lb/>
perhaps Mrs. Smith. By separate post I am sending others for you and Doctor<lb/>
Miller.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
