<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04506005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench to The Surgeon General, U. S. Army, August 12, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04506005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-08-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Armstrong, George E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Landon</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Bonnie</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Peggy Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-08-12">August 12, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04506005</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench to The Surgeon General, U. S. Army, August 12, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench reports to Army Surgeon General [Armstrong] on the impending memorialization of Camp Lazear and the participation of the U.S. Army and State Department in the ceremony. Additional items covered include the tentative date for the dedication, the correct names of the volunteers, the name to be given the memorial, American representatives at the dedication, financial support of the current project, and future improvement of the project by American financial support.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-08-12">
<head>Memorandum from Philip Showalter Hench to The Surgeon General, U. S. Army, August 12, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04506005"/>
<opener>
Where is copy<lb/>
<unclear>Armstrongs</unclear> letters to<lb/>
<unclear>Presno?</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-08-12">August 12, 1952</date>
</dateline>
<salute>TO: The Surgeon General, United States Army</salute>
FROM: Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
SUBJECT:<lb/>
</opener>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Impending Memorialization of the Historical Experimental Sani-<lb/>
tary Station of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Board, 1900 - 1901<lb/>
(Walter Reed's &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;), in Quemados, Cuba, by the Cuban<lb/>
Government, Department of Public Health and Sanitation, and</item>
<item>(b) Participation of the U. S. Army and State Department in the<lb/>
Dedication Ceremony.</item>
</list></p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. <hi>Memorializing the remains of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; and of Walter Reed's<lb/>
&ldquo;Building No. 1.</hi>&rdquo; After twelve years of prodding, the Cuban Government<lb/>
(Doctor Andreu, the Minister of Health, assisted by Dr. Pedro Nogueira and<lb/>
others) is about to memorialize the remains of Walter Reed's old experimental<lb/>
station, Camp Lazear (at Quemados de Marianao, just outside Havana) and the<lb/>
remains of the famous &ldquo;Building No. 1.&rdquo; Regarding the discovery of these<lb/>
remains in 1940 by the writer and others, see enclosure 8. Regarding the<lb/>
difficulties encountered by the writer and others in having this place pre-<lb/>
served, see <unclear>encl. 1a and 6.</unclear> The &ldquo;memorials&rdquo; will consist of (a) the transforma-<lb/>
tion of the remains of Camp Lazear into a small park; (b) the partial re-<lb/>
pairing of the U.S. Army Yellow Fever Board's Building No. 1 (which however<lb/>
will unfortunately still be left exposed to the elements); (c) the erection<lb/>
of a decorative wall on which will appear medallions showing the profiles <del>of</del><lb/>
of Doctors Finlay, Delgado, Reed, Lazear, Carroll, Agramonte and General Wood;<lb/>
(d) Bronze tablets identifying the spot and giving the names of certain<lb/>
volunteers for the yellow fever experiments, i.e., certain American soldiers<lb/>
(see enclosures 3-a, 3-b and 3-c).</item>
<item>2. <hi>Tentative date for the dedication</hi>. This is a little uncertain,<lb/>
but the Cuban committee on arrangements hopes to dedicate the memorial at the<lb/>
time of an international medical congress in Havana, either the Inter-American<lb/>
Congress of Public Health, September 26 - October 1, or the International<lb/>
Congress on Hygiene to be held late in September. I have received photographs<lb/>
showing the progress of the project. Extensive grading has been done and it<lb/>
may be that the dedication can be held as scheduled, but I personally wonder<lb/>
whether they can complete the bronze tablets, wall, etc., in the next six or<lb/>
seven weeks. However it is possible that the committee on arrangements may<lb/>
decide to &ldquo;dedicate&rdquo; Camp Lazear at the time of the Congress even though the<lb/>
permanent memorials are not ready.</item>
<item>3. <hi>The correct names of the volunteers to be memorialized on the<lb/>
bronze tablets</hi>. For the committee in charge. Doctor Nogueira recently asked<lb/>
me to give him the correct names of all of the volunteers. This was not easy<lb/>
(see enclosure 5). It seemed desirable to obtain, if possible, the middle<lb/>
names as well as the correct spelling of the names of the volunteers. I would<lb/>
appreciate it greatly if the Surgeon General's Office would request the Ad-<lb/>
jutant General's Department to send to me and/or to Doctor <unclear>Nogueira* the</unclear><lb/>
Dr. Nogueira's address: Dr. Pedro Nogueira, Marti 219. Marianao, Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04506006"/>
The Surgeon General<lb/>
August 12, 1952<lb/>
Page 2<lb/>
middle names and correct spelling of the first and last names of the U. S.<lb/>
Army personnel concerned, as listed annually in the Roll of Honor of the<lb/>
Army Register, see enclosure 5, page 5. If this list could be made available<lb/>
<hi>as soon as possible</hi><unclear>,</unclear> it would be very helpful as they already are planning<lb/>
the bronze tablets. If the Adjutant General does not have the full names,<lb/>
I would appreciate it greatly if they would give me the addresses of the<lb/>
surviving relatives, insofar as they have them, and I will at once get in<lb/>
touch with them in order to obtain the desired information.</item>
<item>4. <hi>Name to be given the memorial</hi>. The small Cuban committee on<lb/>
arrangements appears to be composed of three members, Dr. Jose Andreu,<lb/>
Minister of Health, (chairman of the Committee), Dr. Pedro Nogueira (the<lb/>
man who continues to &ldquo;spark&rdquo; the affair) and a third member who, I think,<lb/>
may be the Mayor of Marianao. You are aware, I am sure, of the unfortunate<lb/>
anti-Reed and anti-American attitude of Cuban medical and governmental<lb/>
circles which has been held for 50 years, at least in certain circles.<lb/>
Recently a small group of more tolerant, broad-minded and historically<lb/>
accurate Cuban physicians have tried to change this attitude. Doctor<lb/>
Nogueira is the current leader of this movement, as Dr. Domingo Ramos<lb/>
(former Cuban Secretary of Defense) was the former leader of this movement.<lb/>
I know that it is Doctor Nogueira's personal intention to have the names<lb/>
&ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; and &ldquo;Building No. 1&rdquo; (or &ldquo;Caseta No. 1&rdquo;) retained. But there<lb/>
has been such a continuation or perpetuation of errors and nomenolature in<lb/>
the Cuban newspapers the last three or four years as to make one suspect<lb/>
that the Cuban press is in deliberate conspiracy to continue the anti-Reed,<lb/>
pro-Finlay argument (see <unclear>encl. 1b</unclear> and 2). Thus the term &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo; has<lb/>
been used in lieu of &ldquo;Camp Lazear,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Caseta de Finlay&rdquo; in lieu of the<lb/>
U.S. Army Yellow Fever Board's &ldquo;Building No. 1.&rdquo; Regarding Doctor Nogueira's<lb/>
assurances that these errors will not be perpetuated and that the present<lb/>
names will be applied to the memorial, see enclosure 7. I have asked two<lb/>
or three Cubans, personal friends of mine who are unofficially interested<lb/>
in the project, to keep me informed as to the attitude of the newspapers.<lb/>
If it appears that the historical names of Camp Lazear and Building No. 1<lb/>
are going to be changed despite Doctor Nogueira's efforts, it will be im-<lb/>
portant, I think, to put upon those concerned discrete diplomatic pressure<lb/>
at the proper time and place; perhaps the military attache of the American<lb/>
Embassy in Havana could be informed confidentially about this matter and<lb/>
could act for the moment as an unofficial observer. People in Havana who<lb/>
would be very helpful if necessary, would be two American news correspondents<lb/>
(one of them is the Havana correspondent of the New York Times), certain<lb/>
friendly Cuban physicians and others whom I know.</item>
<item><p>5. <hi>Participation of the U. S. Army, in particular the U. S.<lb/>
Army Medical Corps, and the State Department in the dedication</hi>. It has<lb/>
been the hopeful intention of those Cubans and the few Americans who have<lb/>
been pushing this project that its dedication will introduce a new era of<lb/>
good feeling among Cuban and American physicians in particular. As explained<lb/>
in enclosure No. 1, (page 1), Camp Lazear can serve as a very useful rallying<lb/>
point for this improved feeling, and as a site for a Cuban-American Memorial<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04506007"/>
The Surgeon General<lb/>
August 12, 1952<lb/>
Page 3<lb/>
in honor of <hi>both</hi> Doctor Finlay and his associates <hi>and</hi> Major Reed and his<lb/>
associates. I know it is the hope of many Cubans, as expressed by Doctor<lb/>
Nogueira (enclosure 7) that the American Army and government will partici-<lb/>
pate in the memorial.</p>
<p>In view of the long-standing and, at times acrimonious, feud,<lb/>
the anti-Reed attitude in Cuba has not entirely died down. Although one<lb/>
of the Cuban instigators of this feud died a few years ago, his place has<lb/>
been taken by another very partisan Cuban, as is attested by recent news-<lb/>
paper and magazine articles in my possession. Therefore, if the Cuban<lb/>
Government and its Health Department do really intend now to memorialize<lb/>
Camp Lazear and to perpetuate its proper historical names, they are making<lb/>
a great concession and an outstanding contribution to Cuban-American<lb/>
friendship, not only among medical circles but in lay circles. I can<lb/>
testify personally that although there are innumerable memorials to Doctor<lb/>
Finlay and even two or three rather minor memorials to Lazear, including a<lb/>
bust of Lazear in Havana, the name of Major Walter Reed did not appear<lb/>
anywhere until two or three years ago and this omission was deliberate.<lb/>
However two or three years ago a painting was unveiled, which painting in-<lb/>
cluded Doctor Finlay and the four members of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission.</p></item>
<item><p>6. <hi>American representatives at the dedication</hi>. When the Cuban<lb/>
government invites the American government to send representatives of the<lb/>
U. S. Army and/or State Department for the dedication, it is for others to<lb/>
suggest who these delegates might be. Certainly it would be extremely<lb/>
desirable to have one or more representatives from the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Office, U. S. Army. Permit me to inquire as to whether Walter Reed's son,<lb/>
Major General W. L. Reed, U. S. Army Retired (and his wife), General Albert<lb/>
E. Truby, U. S. Army Medical Corps, Retired (and his wife) might be designated<lb/>
in some way as representatives for the dedication? (This suggestion is<lb/>
<hi>entirely</hi> my own but has the informal approval of Doctor Nogueira.) General<lb/>
Truby was, for a while, commanding officer at the hospital at Camp Columbia<lb/>
while Major Reed was doing his work there, and has written an authoritative<lb/>
book on the conquest of yellow fever. I do not of course know by what means<lb/>
Generals Reed and Truby might be made delegates or representatives, whether<lb/>
they could be &ldquo;reactivated&rdquo; temporarily for this event if they are willing<lb/>
to accept the assignment, or whether other American funds might be available<lb/>
to them, assuming that the Cuban government might not have funds for this<lb/>
purpose. Walter Reed's daughter, Mrs. Blossom Reed, should certainly be invited.</p>
<p>The son and daughter of Doctor Lazear*, the martyr of the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Board, certainly deserve special consideration. They live in California.<lb/>
Being civilians, they have no connection whatever with the State Department<lb/>
or the U. S. Army. Whether or not the Cuban government would choose to do<lb/>
more than to send them an official invitation (without travelling funds)<lb/>
remains to be seen. The two living survivors of the U.S. Army Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board's experiments are the former Army contract surgeon, Dr. Robert P.<lb/>
Cooke, a retired physician of Lexington, Virginia, and the former Army<lb/>
private, James L. Hanberry, of Orangeburg, South Carolina. Their presence<lb/>
at the dedication would be most fitting.</p>
<p>*Mr. William Houston Lazear, P.O. Box 812, Santa Barbara, California<lb/>
Mrs. W. D. Briggs. 106 The Uplands, Berkeley, California</p></item>
<pb n="4" id="f04506008"/>
<item>The Surgeon General<lb/>
August 12, 1952<lb/>
Page 4</item>
<item>7. <hi>Financial Support of the Present Limited Memorial Project</hi>.<lb/>
$25,000 was allotted by the Cuban government for the present project.<lb/>
Therefore, aside from small sums of money which the writer has contributed<lb/>
himself during the last twelve years for minor repairs to Building No. 1,<lb/>
the money for the present project has been entirely given by the Cubans.</item>
<item><p>8. <hi>Future Improvement of the Present Memorial Project: American<lb/>
Financial Support</hi>. The permanent enclosure of Building No. 1 is a most<lb/>
desirable objective and one which the present fund does not make possible.<lb/>
But once the present limited project is concluded, it is the hope of certain<lb/>
Cubans and Americans that money can be raised with which to enclose Building<lb/>
No. 1 in a suitable &ldquo;Cuban-American Memorial Building,&rdquo; which building<lb/>
however should be merely a sort of &ldquo;museum room&rdquo; connected with a more<lb/>
functional type of memorial, possibly a small public health unit for the<lb/>
Health Department of Quemados de Marianao. One of the drawbacks to the<lb/>
establishment of this larger memorial has been the fact that the site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear is, unfortunately, not in a very desirable location. It has<lb/>
become surrounded by very modest homes of the working people. But to the<lb/>
historically minded, this makes no difference because this is actually the<lb/>
historic site and no other would be suitable.</p>
<p>I am making further direct inquiries of Doctor Nogueira regarding<lb/>
the exact meaning of his comments on page 2 of enclosure 7, which comments<lb/>
are numbered paragraph 6 (<unclear>i.e.</unclear>, his remarks regarding those whom the Cuban<lb/>
government might invite as guests). It is not clear to me whether or not<lb/>
any traveling allowances might be made available by the Cuban government.</p></item>
</list></p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota</signed>
Enclosures (9)<lb/>
PSH/alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
