<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04509029">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Pedro Nogueira to Philip Showalter Hench, November 7, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Nogueira, Pedro</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04509029</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="person">Armstrong, George E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Love, Albert G.</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Walter De Blois</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Margaret Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mrs. Houston</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Bonnie</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Landon</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-07">November 7, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04509029</idno>
<title>Letter from Pedro Nogueira to Philip Showalter Hench, November 7, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Nogueira proposes the Finlay award for Cooke posthumously, and notes that other individuals are being considered for the honor as well. He lists the names of persons receiving an official invitation to attend the dedication of Camp Lazear and describes Hench's role during the ceremony. Hench is to forward a copy of his speech so that it can be translated into Spanish for the Cuban media.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-07">
<head>Letter from Pedro Nogueira to Philip Showalter Hench, November 7, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04509029"/>
<opener>
DR. PEDRO NOGUEIRA<lb/>
MEDICO CIRUJANO<lb/>
TELEFONO: BO-7577<lb/>
<dateline>
MARTI 219. MARIANAO<lb/>
Marianao <date value="1952-11-07">November 7 of 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr Philip Hench.<lb/>
Mayo Clinic.<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
U.S.A.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Philip:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I just receive your letter about the death of Dr Cooke,<lb/>
for which I regret very much. I want to advance that I have proposed<lb/>
to the Board &ldquo;Finlay Order&rdquo;, to cencede him the Postum Condecoration<lb/>
on the highest grade possible so that you will please send me the<lb/>
address of the surviving family as well as, the name.</p>
<p>On the other hand please know today I put on the mail the invita-<lb/>
tions for the act on December 3rd for the following persons: Colonel<lb/>
Siler; General Streit; General Armstrong; Mrs Kean; General Love; Mr<lb/>
and Mrs Briggs; Mr and Mrs Houston Lazear; Mrs Blossom Reed; General<lb/>
and Mrs Truby; General and Mrs W. Reed; Mr Hanberry.</p>
<p>Yours isnt going, because it is not neccesary, as you are on the<lb/>
official program to speak on that ocassion. And beside the speakers<lb/>
before you, will be Board Health Minister; Dr Alberto Recio, Presi-<lb/>
dent of Patronate and may be the President of Republic will give the<lb/>
summary of the act.</p>
<p>Of course, you will have your turn before the President.- The in-<lb/>
vitations with complete program will be ready inside a few days and <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
each one of these person about mentioned. I will send one, and to<lb/>
you I will mail several, too, in case you like to give anybody that<lb/>
you think deserve them but if you prefer let me know, the name and I<lb/>
would be pleased to send them from here.-</p>
<p>Next matter Philip, has Dr Ames any family who should write?, be-<lb/>
cause it is neccesary to have this date as soon as possible.</p>
<p>An agreeable surprise to you that the goverment authorize me to<lb/>
invite Hanberry on its account to attend the acts on the 3rd and you<lb/>
will see the program where he will be the person to unveil the Medals<lb/>
and the plates with the volunteers names, and those you know have con-<lb/>
tributed on Yellow Fever discovery. At the same time I am proposing<lb/>
that Hanberry receive Finlay Order on the Highest Grade possible (may-<lb/>
be Grand Officer), as he is the only surviving of that great work.- <unclear>W</unclear><lb/>
What do you think about it?.-</p>
<p>I hope to write Hanberry on Sunday informing him all this, but I<lb/>
like to know you help me, to see the way, he should receive the money<lb/>
on the trip to come down and stay here, of course till the 4th Decem-<lb/>
ber, why at the evening on the act at the Science Academy the <unclear>Presiden</unclear><lb/>
of the Republic will pin on him the Condecoration (That is necessary<lb/>
confirmations).-</p>
<p>I recommend you write him right away and his answer, you let me<lb/>
know.- You can tell him in your letters that Wednesday o Thursday he<lb/>
can wait my letter in South Carolina.</p>
<p>I have several proposal for Finlay Decoration for the persons you<lb/>
pointed out, so that we must wait till the Board resolution.</p>
<p>I suppose the Board will meet from to 15 to 20 this month, that's<lb/>
why I need the dates I ask you about Cooke and Ames, quick as possible<lb/>
The Park is alright on Saturday I will meet with cameraman to take<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04509030"/>
DR. PEDRO NOGUEIRA<lb/>
MEDICO CIRUJANO<lb/>
MARTI 219. MARIANAO<lb/>
TELEFONO: BO-7577<lb/>
Philip ( Continuation)<lb/>
2<lb/>
some views to send you next week, you will see how the job is get<unclear>-</unclear><lb/>
ting on.</p>
<p>Today I get &ldquo;Sterberg Book&rdquo;, and for which I am much obliged<lb/>
but I should explain Philip, I was anxious Saternberg book, <unclear>subject</unclear><lb/>
&ldquo;Etiology and Prevention of Yellow Fever&rdquo;.- I thiank was written<lb/>
the last century.- I hope you will have the reference &ldquo;Gorgas and<lb/>
his life&rdquo; as you said in your former letters.</p>
<p>May be during these day as the weather is changed would be po-<lb/>
ssible to take the air views that we needs of the Camp. Now <unclear>will;</unclear><lb/>
be in your hands the others views through Mr Hess.</p>
<p>Philip nothing more today.- I am very glad you are at home to<lb/>
write you every time, there is a matter to fix, time is running<lb/>
away and the date is getting near.</p>
<p>Philip, don't forget to send me your speech to have it transla<unclear>-</unclear><lb/>
te in spanish on time, for the paapers and also let me know, what<lb/>
day, number trip and what line, you will come down to Cuba, to<lb/>
meet you on the airport.</p>
<closer>
<salute>So long:</salute>
<signed>Pedro</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
