<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04508001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Walter J. Mandel, November 10, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04508001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Mandel, Walter J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Margaret Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Surgeon General's Museum, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Medical Center, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-10">November 10, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04508001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Walter J. Mandel, November 10, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes his research on Reed and his association with the preservation of Camp Lazear. He informs Mandel, a U.S. Customs official, that he will be transporting wood to the United States from Building No. 1, and inquires about the proper way to prepare and ship it.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-10">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Walter J. Mandel, November 10, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04508001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-10">November 10, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Walter J. Mandel<lb/>
Acting Deputy <unclear>Collector</unclear><lb/>
Treasury Department<lb/>
Bureau of Customs<lb/>
St. Paul 1, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Mandel:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am a consultant on the staff of the Mayo Clinic. For years I have had<lb/>
as my hobby the story of the conquest of yellow fever. Undoubtedly you<lb/>
have heard the name of Major Walter Reed, head of a U. S. Army commission<lb/>
in Havana, Cuba, who carried on medical experiments which proved the rela-<lb/>
tionship of mosquitoes to yellow fever. This is one of the great medical<lb/>
discoveries of all time. I have frequently given lectures on the subject<lb/>
and have made many trips to Cuba to visit the little spot, &ldquo;Camp Lazear,&rdquo;<lb/>
where the experiments were done. Perhaps you will remember the play and<lb/>
motion picture, &ldquo;Yellow Jack,&rdquo; a few years ago which dramatized these ex-<lb/>
periments.</p>
<p>In connection with one of my visits to Cuba, I rediscovered Camp Lazear<lb/>
in 1940 which had been &ldquo;lost&rdquo; for 40 years. Since 1940 I have been trying<lb/>
to persuade the Cuban Government to memorialize &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; and the remains<lb/>
of Reed's Building No. 1 (See the enclosed article, especially the photograph<lb/>
on page 6). At long last the Cuban government is memorializing the spot.<lb/>
They have extensively restored the little building and the camp will be dedicated<lb/>
on December 3 in honor of Dr. Carlos Finlay whose theory, concerning mosquitoes<lb/>
and yellow fever, Major Reed and his associates proved to be correct.</p>
<p>In the restoration of Building No. 1, to my regret instead of accepting my<lb/>
advice and maintaining intact the little building as it now stands and con-<lb/>
structing an outer protecting shell, the Cubans concerned with this project<lb/>
made such an extensive restoration that what remains is more a replica than<lb/>
a restoration. In this connection they tore down practically all of the original<lb/>
walls which were specially constructed for the experiments and involved the use<lb/>
of &ldquo;tongued-and-grooved&rdquo; boards. The base of the boards were affected by<lb/>
termites but the rest of the boards were not, although there was some rotting.</p>
<p>Now here is my reason for writing you. The experiments of Major Reed and his<lb/>
associates have captured the imagination of the United States, not only of the<lb/>
medical profession but also of writers and laymen. It is my opinion that<lb/>
there are a number of institutions and individuals who would be delighted to<lb/>
have a small piece of this wood from the original building. I refer to the<lb/>
little museum of the Walter Reed Hospital in Washington, the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Museum in Washington, the museum at the University of Virginia where Reed and<lb/>
others connected with yellow fever were graduated; General Walter Lawrence<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04508002"/>
Mr. Walter J. Mandel<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 10, 1952<lb/>
Reed (Major Reed's son) and the son and daughter of Doctor Lazear, the martyr<lb/>
who died during the experiments, and others. I have asked Doctor Nogueira to<lb/>
save me some of this wood. How much he is saving I do not know but certainly<lb/>
enough to fill a small packing case. I have been officially invited by the<lb/>
Cuban Government to attend the dedication in Havana and to speak on December<lb/>
3. Since I will be flying, I <unclear>cannot</unclear> bring this box back with me at that time,<lb/>
but I should like to make the following inquires.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>1. How may I go about getting this wood admitted to the United States in the<lb/>
safest way? Also the least expensive way. It was my thought that I would<lb/>
have it boxed in Cuba, address it to myself and get in touch with the St. Paul<lb/>
Customs Office, notifying them what the box contained so that there would be<lb/>
either no customs or no significant customs duty. The building was built in<lb/>
1900 so that the wood is 52 years old.</p>
<p>I propose to give some of these boards to be displayed &ldquo;as is&rdquo; to demonstrate<lb/>
their special construction which was described by Reed, the double-thickness<lb/>
wood, the tongued-and-grooved boards, etc. From some of the wood I propose<lb/>
to have small souvenirs made, paper weights with a little bronze identifica-<lb/>
tion plate, pen holders or some such. All of this will be entirely non-<lb/>
commercial and will be done completely at my own personal expense with no<lb/>
recompense of any sort. It is merely a sentimental gesture on my part and<lb/>
a demonstration of my great interest in this particular phase of medical history.</p></item>
<item>2. Will there be any sanitary precautions that have to be taken? I don't<lb/>
believe that Cuban termites are any different from American termites and of<lb/>
course we will select wood which is as sound as possible. Need I have the<lb/>
wood treated in any way before it is sent?</item>
<item>3. Would some notation or letter or other insignia from your office, a copy<lb/>
of which could be tacked to the box in a heavy envelope or fastened to the box<lb/>
by a heavy tag, expedite the passage of this box through the American customs?<lb/>
The box could be inspected of course in the usual way.</item>
<item>4. How should the box be sealed so that it can be properly inspected by<lb/>
your associates? Ordinarily, I suppose they would merely nail the box shut<lb/>
in the usual way.</item>
<item>5. Do you have a representative in Cuba that could inspect the material be-<lb/>
fore it is shipped from Cuba to me and expedite matters in that way?</item>
</list></p>
<p>I would appreciate very greatly your early attention to this matter as I will<lb/>
be going to Cuba in about three and a half weeks from now, about December 1.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
