<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04512005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, August 5, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04512005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-08-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Scott, Hugh L.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-08-05">August 5, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04512005</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, August 5, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is disturbed that plans for the memorial park at Camp Lazear still use Finlay's name in connection with Building No. 1. He requests information regarding newspaper reports about Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-08-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, August 5, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04512005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-08-05">August 5, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon<lb/>
Calle X 254, Vedado<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora Rodriguez Leon:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You will recall that when I visited Havana in January, you and I discussed<lb/>
the proposals which were being made regarding the erection of a little<lb/>
memorial park at old Camp Lazear. This was being done, I believe, largely<lb/>
through Doctors Andreu and Nogueira. I think that I showed you the tentative<lb/>
blue prints which the engineering section of the Health Department had as<lb/>
their plans for the memorial park. The draftsmen were calling it Parque<lb/>
Lazear and had the little Building No. 1 labelled &ldquo;Caseta de Finlay.&rdquo; I<lb/>
called this to Doctor Nogueira's attention. He assured me that it was just<lb/>
a mistake as he said &ldquo;After all, Doctor Hench, these draftsmen aren't<lb/>
medical historians.&rdquo; He assured me that Building No. 1 would be properly<lb/>
named and I was of course hoping that Camp Lazear could retain its name or<lb/>
perhaps be called Parque Lazear.</p>
<p>However I have been somewhat disturbed as have certain Cuban friends who<lb/>
have written me about a continuing phraseology used in the newspapers and<lb/>
I have written Doctor Nogueira urging that he make the appropriate cor-<lb/>
rections and inform the newspapers and the public before the dedication<lb/>
ceremonies sometime in September on the occasion of the International<lb/>
Congress of Hygiene in Havana. I am hoping to hear from Doctor Nogueira<lb/>
that he is accomplishing these corrections.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, I thought that I would send you the two enclosures. First of all,<lb/>
I enclose a synopsis of certain dates showing certain of your father's activities<lb/>
between 1898 and 1902, as given by some of the material I have in my possession<lb/>
and some of the material that you already have. I promised some months ago to<lb/>
send you this. If you want additional copies, please let me know. Secondly,<lb/>
let me send you some of the excerpts from the Habana papers and you will see<lb/>
what concerns me. Anything you notice in the papers I will be interested in<lb/>
knowing about. I still have faith in, or want to have faith in, Doctor<lb/>
Nogueira and believe that they will do the proper thing.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04512006"/>
Senora Rodriguez Leon<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
August 4, 1952<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: Doctor Nogueira asked me recently to send him a correct list of the names<lb/>
of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Board and all of the volunteers. In developing<lb/>
this list I found that many of the names had been spelled various ways and it<lb/>
was not at all easy to compile a list correct enough to be perpetuated in<lb/>
bronze.<lb/>
May I ask you to help me with your father's name? I have almost uniformly<lb/>
seen it written Aristides Agramonte, with no middle name. But I have in<lb/>
my possession two letters addressing him as Aristides A. Agramonte. One is<lb/>
a letter of September 20, 1900 sent to him by H. L. Scott, Adjutant General,<lb/>
Division of Cuba; the other is a letter of September 22, 1900, sent to your<lb/>
father by Leonard Wood, Military Governor of Cuba. As I said, both of these<lb/>
letters address him as Aristides A. Agramonte. Would you kindly let me know<lb/>
at your earliest convenience whether he did have a middle name which he rarely<lb/>
used and perhaps if you have the time to do so, you might telephone Dr.<lb/>
Pedro Nogueira, Marti 219, Havana, (or drop him a short note), giving him your<lb/>
father's correct name. They may already be starting to make the bronze tablet<lb/>
and I would not want the name to be incorrect or the middle name to be left<lb/>
out if he had one.<lb/>
Perhaps for the moment it might be best for you not to mention to Doctor<lb/>
Nogueira that I sent you the excerpts from the newspapers. On the other<lb/>
hand, if you have any way of finding out from him what they plan to do, that<lb/>
would be fine. Could you innocently ask him when they plan to dedicate the<lb/>
park? You might mention that I wrote you asking you to confirm to him your<lb/>
father's middle name (as I have written him). Then you might also innocently<lb/>
mention that you have been noticing certain articles in the papers which<lb/>
indicated some confusion in the minds of the newspapers as to what went on<lb/>
at Camp Lazear and then see what he replies. I am merely trying to give him<lb/>
every opportunity to make the corrections and do not want to stir up for him<lb/>
any trouble unless such becomes necessary.<lb/>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
