<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04513007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Maria Teresa Rojas to Philip Showalter Hench, March 22, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Rojas, Maria Teresa</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04513007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-03-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Rath, Jr., Frederick L.</name>
<name type="person">Saladrigas, Enrique</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-03-22">March 22, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04513007</idno>
<title>English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Maria Teresa Rojas to Philip Showalter Hench, March 22, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Rojas informs Hench that nothing can be predicted in relation to the preservation of Camp Lazear because the political situation is unstable. She discusses visiting with Rath so that he might advise them on the preservation of the San Jose property which has historical links to Camp Lazear. Rojas believes the San Jose property may be of interest to both the United States and Cuba for this reason.
</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-03-22">
<head>English translation [from Spanish] of letter from Maria Teresa Rojas to Philip Showalter Hench, March 22, 1952 (See <xref id="f04513005">Spanish original</xref>.)</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04513007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-03-22">March 22, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>My Dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>So many and so grave events have happened since the last time we saw each<lb/>
other that I have not dared to write you, in hopes that the political<lb/>
picture would clear up a little bit and become more normal. Although<lb/>
nothing can be predicted yet and in spite of the disastrous effects<lb/>
that can be occasioned the country by a situation like this, that is, of<lb/>
not finding a legal way out for it, it would be extremely favorable for<lb/>
the realization of our plans if Dr. Enrique Saladrigas, the present<lb/>
Minister of Health, will maintain in his position. You met Dr. Saladrigas<lb/>
on one of your visits to Havana when he was the director of the Finlay<lb/>
Institute. Dr. Saladrigas is a great friend of ours and it would be easy<lb/>
to interest him in our projects concerning Camp Lazear. The Minister of<lb/>
Public Works, Ing. Jose Mendigutia is also a good friend of ours, and I<lb/>
am sure that he will give us his cooperation. So we can only desire that<lb/>
the present government may consolidate itself in a legal form and hope<lb/>
that all will return to normality before trying to do anything in this<lb/>
sense.</p>
<p>Thank you very much for all the efforts which you have made in my behalf<lb/>
with the gentlemen of the National Council for Historic Sites and Buildings.<lb/>
A few days ago I received a letter from Mr. Frederick L. Rath together with<lb/>
various explanatory folders of the societies over which he presides. I<lb/>
would be extremely pleased at the suggestion which you make me that Mr. Rath<lb/>
might come for 2 or 3 days to Havana, provided that this will not upset his<lb/>
plans and of course we would lodge him in San Jose with a great deal of<lb/>
pleasure. I think that on the ground he would be able to appreciate better<lb/>
the close ties that unite our house with Camp Lazear. Ties that will be<lb/>
made even more evident with the realization that some of our projects,<lb/>
destined to point out and to give its true relief to the participation that<lb/>
the Americans had in everything concerning the investigations and discoveries<lb/>
dealing with yellow fever which took place here and which has up to now been<lb/>
so unjustly silenced, and agree with us that for this reason it can be<lb/>
considered a place of historic interest for the United States as well as<lb/>
for Cuba. Perhaps then we shall find a solution. As you know my difficulty<lb/>
in expressing myself in English I should prefer to have you write to him<lb/>
directly in my name.</p>
<p>I hope that the period of rest has made you feel better and that the<lb/>
bothersome colds have now passed.</p>
<p>I am writing to Mary, answering her affectionate letter, telling her how<lb/>
much we miss them, remembering continuously in our conversations the very<lb/>
agreeable days that we passed together and which I hope we will be able to<lb/>
repeat before very long. With affectionate regards of Lydia and my cousin<lb/>
Julia, receive an affectionate greeting from</p>
<closer>
<signed>Maria Teresa Rojas</signed>
Translated by G.C. Harrison/drn--3-29-52.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
