<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04510001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to R. Hart Phillips, November 5, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04510001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Phillips, R. Hart</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Carbonell, Felipe</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro P.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-05">November 5, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04510001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to R. Hart Phillips, November 5, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Phillips about his interest in the fight against yellow fever, his discovery of the original site of Camp Lazear, and the Cuban government's plan to make Camp Lazear into a memorial park to honor all of those connected with the conquest of yellow fever. Hench requests that she make discreet inquiries to learn whether Camp Lazear will retain its name or will be called &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo;.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to R. Hart Phillips, November 5, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04510001"/>
<opener>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-11-05">November 5, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. R. Hart Phillips<lb/>
Havana Office<lb/>
New York Times<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Phillips:</salute>
</opener>
<p>May I write you rather confidentially and ask you to help me with two<lb/>
matters?</p>
<p>You have been long aware of my interest in the conquest of yellow fever<lb/>
and the work of Doctor Finlay and especially of my compatriots, Major<lb/>
Walter Reed and his associates. I believe you are aware of the fact that<lb/>
with the help of Mr. Johnny Moran and Mr. Luis Pogolotti of Havana, I re-<lb/>
discovered, in 1940, Camp Lazear which had been &ldquo;lost&rdquo; for forty years.<lb/>
You are also aware that I have been trying ever since then to interest<lb/>
the Cubans in memorializing this spot.</p>
<p>Several Cuban physicians have been very interested in this project. One of<lb/>
<unclear>them</unclear> was Dr. Felipe Carbonell, another was Dr. Domingo Ramos and, more recently<lb/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira of Marianao who has stimulated the Minister of Public Health<lb/>
to approve the project. Rather suddenly this spring they decided to complete<lb/>
their plans to make Camp Lazear into a memorial park to honor <hi>all</hi> of those<lb/>
connected with the conquest of yellow fever.</p>
<p>It has been my hope of course that when Camp Lazear was memorialized it would<lb/>
be allowed to retain its name. Most confidentially, when I received in January<lb/>
a copy of the blue prints of the project (from Doctor Nogueira), Walter Reed's<lb/>
Building No. 1 was erroneously labelled &ldquo;caseta de Finlay&rdquo;. When I called this<lb/>
to Doctor Nogueira's attention he laughed and said this was merely an error on<lb/>
the part of the Cuban draftsmen who &ldquo;naturally knew nothing about medical<lb/>
history.&rdquo; However I have received from time to time from Havana friends<lb/>
clippings from Havana newspapers which have perpetuated this mistake. I have<lb/>
had considerable correspondence with Doctor Nogueira this summer, trying to<lb/>
help him with his plans but urging that our Cuban friends do nothing to dis-<lb/>
tort historical fact or to hurt the feelings of the Americans. This is a<lb/>
great opportunity for Cuban-American rapprochement and it would be most un-<lb/>
fortunate if anything were allowed to spoil the affair.</p>
<p>I rather fear that they are going to rename Camp Lazear &ldquo;Parque Finlay.&rdquo; They<lb/>
have already built a road, erected a wall on which certain bronze medallions<lb/>
and memorial tablets will appear, put in shrubbery, erected a flag pole, etc.,<lb/>
preserving Reed's Building No. 1 with some repairs. It is my personal hope<lb/>
that since the Cubans have not seen fit to enclose Reed's Building No. 1, I<lb/>
can raise money in this country to erect a protecting building, which building<lb/>
should not be merely a static memorial but might be large enough so that it<lb/>
would also comprise some sort of a unit for public service, perhaps a small<lb/>
public health unit.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04510002"/>
<p>Mrs. R. Hart Phillips</p>
<p>Page 2</p>
<p>November 5, 1952</p>
<p>Now, Mrs. Phillips, you will be interested in all of this and at the ap-<lb/>
propriate time will want to carry a news item about the dedication which<lb/>
is now set for December 3, the date of Finlay's birthday and also &ldquo;Physicians'<lb/>
Day&rdquo; in Havana. I understand that the Cuban Government is going to invite<lb/>
officially certain Americans such as the Surgeon General or his Deputy, the<lb/>
American Ambassador and so on. I have been told that I am to be invited and<lb/>
will be asked to give a five or ten minute address and I plan to fly down<lb/>
for the affair. But may I ask you to step out of your usual role as a<lb/>
newspaper woman and help me to find out as diplomatically and discreetly as<lb/>
you can, just what their plans are? I know nothing except what I have<lb/>
heard from Doctor Nogueira. My own feeling is that we Americans who would<lb/>
strongly wish that the name Camp Lazear be preserved may have to compromise<lb/>
and accept the name &ldquo;Parque Finlay.&rdquo; Most certainly Doctor Finlay's name<lb/>
should be first among those memorialized as it was his theory which was<lb/>
proven on that spot to be correct, but no American can ever accept the re-<lb/>
naming of Reed's Building No. 1 to be &ldquo;Caseta de Finlay.&rdquo; For the sake of<lb/>
having the spot memorialized, I am not to happily willing to compromise on<lb/>
the name &ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo; but it would be most unfortunate if any further<lb/>
compromise were required. Also, I and other Americans are sincerely hoping<lb/>
that the errors regarding the historical accuracy of Reed's Building No. 1<lb/>
will be corrected in the Havana papers and be no longer perpetuated.</p>
<p>Here is a beautiful chance for a demonstration of Cuban-American friendship,<lb/>
especially between the professions. I do hope that nothing will mar the<lb/>
ceremony.</p>
<p>Mrs. Phillips, could you or one of your associates make discreet inquiries<lb/>
from the office of the Ministry of Health (Public Relations Officer), from<lb/>
Dr. Jose Raimundo Andreu, El Ministro de Salubridad y Asistencia Social, or<lb/>
from Dr. Pedro Nogueira of Marianao, without involving me? I have expressed<lb/>
to Doctor Nogueira my complete faith and trust in him and I do have complete<lb/>
faith in him but what I don't know is how far he can get his ideas across to<lb/>
his superiors. I am sure that Doctor Nogueira intends to do the right thing.</p>
<p>Could you perhaps say that you have noted from time to time the comments<lb/>
in the Havana papers about the memorialization of Camp Lazear, that you<lb/>
have heard that the dedication was to be some time soon and that you were<lb/>
anxious to have the proper story for the many Americans who will be delighted<lb/>
indeed to know of this gracious gesture on the part of the Cuban Government?<lb/>
I am sure that if you, as a representative of the American press and as an<lb/>
informant of the American medical profession, express an interest in this<lb/>
project there will be every effort made to carry out the dedication in such<lb/>
a way as to satisfy the pride and honor of both the Cubans and Americans.<lb/>
Any information as to what you find which you can pass on to me beforehand,<lb/>
I should be grateful to know. I want to keep out of sight in relation to<lb/>
your activities and it would be much more effective if the inquiries came from<lb/>
you, presumably without any prompting from me and of course you will approach<lb/>
the matter with the idea that everything is on the up and up and that there is<lb/>
no controversy involved. Then if you do find that the controversy which I have<lb/>
mentioned still exists and is not being resolved, perhaps something can be<lb/>
done about it, as a result of discreet inquiries on your part, or the part of<lb/>
your American friends in the American embassy (whom I have not yet contacted).</p>
<p>Dr. <unclear>Felipe</unclear> Carbonell, San Lazaro 413, Havana, has long been interested in this<lb/>
project. He is not, I believe, friendly with the present administration. I<lb/>
am writing him, as a Cuban friend, the enclosed letter. You two are my last<lb/>
hope to try to get information that all is well.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04510003"/>
<p>Mrs. R. Hart Phillips</p>
<p>Page 3</p>
<p>November 5, 1952</p>
<p>Request No. 2. On the occasion of previous visits to Havana, I have obtained<lb/>
the services of a local photographer, Mr. Aldo E. Diaz, gotten for me on<lb/>
several occasions by John Moran, now deceased. Mr. Diaz has gone with me<lb/>
on several occasions and snapped for me many photographs, allowing me to<lb/>
purchase the films to bring back home. These photographs I have used ex-<lb/>
tensively to illustrate articles, make lantern slides for lectures and also<lb/>
to make copies to send to the various yellow fever personalities in this<lb/>
country, the surviving relatives of Reed, Lazear and so on.</p>
<p>I am most anxious to have again the services of Mr. Diaz or another photographer.<lb/>
Mr. Diaz was particularly useful because he was always very agreeable and never<lb/>
charged me too much; I think 50 or 75 cents a film. I often had him make 30<lb/>
or 40 films. The last time I tried to reach him he seemed to have been on a<lb/>
bender. We had trouble locating him. I think he had a couple of telephones<lb/>
listed but no address. I wonder if you could help me out in this situation.<lb/>
I should like to get in touch with him or, failing that, I am most anxious to<lb/>
have the services of another photographer. I am anxious to have this<lb/>
photographer take for me personally quite a few photographs of the actual<lb/>
dedication, perhaps 20 or more. Then the next day, presumably on Thursday,<lb/>
December 4, I should like to go back with him to Camp Lazear and make some<lb/>
close-up photographs of the memorial, bringing the films back home, having<lb/>
them developed that day if at all possible as I plan to fly back on that night,<lb/>
Thursday, December 4. Once home I will at my leisure have either the Clinic<lb/>
photographer or a local photographer make such prints as may be necessary to<lb/>
send to the various relatives of the 25 or 30 volunteers whose names will be<lb/>
memorialized.</p>
<p>I will certainly appreciate whatever help you can give me in this matter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
ADDENDUM: Since dictating the above I have tried to find more precise data<lb/>
concerning Mr. Diaz' address. In 1941 he was connected with Informaciones<lb/>
Graficas, address Consulado 254; Telefono A-7978. However I think I last<lb/>
had his services in 1948 or thereabouts, on which occasion he gave me the<lb/>
enclosed card. Presumably he was no longer associated with Informaciones<lb/>
Graficas but was a free lance. As I recall it, Johnny Moran and I spent a day<lb/>
or two telephoning the numbers on his card, A5-2771 and A-7820. Note that no<lb/>
address is given on the card. Johnny Moran, speaking Spanish, finally got<lb/>
someone on the phone, found out at what address the one telephone was and then<lb/>
we visited it. It was a little hole-in-the-wall somewhere down town, merely<lb/>
a place where the people who owned the phone took messages for him and then<lb/>
relayed them to him later. Having left word at each of these places for him<lb/>
to call us, he did so the next day and we made the deal.<lb/>
When I was in Cuba in January, I did not need Mr. Diaz but I did try to locate<lb/>
either his name or Informaciones Graficas in the Havana directory, the white<lb/>
section or the yellow section, without success. I hate very much to bother you<lb/>
but since I have no address for him, I would greatly appreciate it if you would<lb/>
phone these two numbers and leave word for him to call you. If he will give<lb/>
you his address, I should be glad to write him or he can write me. Or on the<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04510004"/>
Mrs. R. Hart Phillips<lb/>
Page 4<lb/>
November 5, 1952<lb/>
other hand, you can tell him what I want (he will remember me) and see if<lb/>
he is willing to do it. I certainly appreciate your help.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
