<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04513022">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas and Lydia Cabrera, November 7, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04513022</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-11-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Cabrera, Lydia</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Carbonell, Felipe Ponce</name>
<name type="person">Williams, Mrs. R. Hart</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-11-07">November 7, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04513022</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas and Lydia Cabrera, November 7, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench expresses his concerns about the naming of the Camp Lazear memorial and the renovation of Building No. 1. He requests that Rojas speak with Nogueira about the project.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-11-07">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas and Lydia Cabrera, November 7, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04513022"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1952-11-07">November 7, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Miss Maria Teresa Rojas<lb/>
Miss Lydia Cabrera<lb/>
Quinta San Jose<lb/>
Calle Real<lb/>
Quemados de Marianao<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Tina and Lydia:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I suspect that by now you are back home in Havana. I wonder if you have had<lb/>
a chance to look over my letters. Have you learned anything? Have there been<lb/>
any comments in the papers about the impending dedication of Camp Lazear? I<lb/>
have received no clippings from anybody from Havana for months.</p>
<p>Although I have had frequent correspondence from Doctor Nogueira who assures<lb/>
me that all is going well and repeatedly reassured me that Reed's Building<lb/>
No. 1 will not be renamed, I strongly suspect that the place will be called<lb/>
&ldquo;Parque Finlay&rdquo; although he has not actually said so. I am sure that he wants<lb/>
to do the right thing but his superiors may over-rule him.</p>
<p>May I tell you in strictest confidence that although I have been maintaining<lb/>
my faith in Doctor Nogueira (I can do no other) I have just sent to Dr. Felipe<lb/>
Carbonell (the Cuban doctor who has been so interested in this venture) and to<lb/>
Mrs. R. Hart Phillips (Havana representative of the New York Times whom I have<lb/>
known for years) a confidential note asking them to give me whatever informa-<lb/>
tion they can, telling them the background of the affair and asking them to<lb/>
make discreet inquiries from Doctor Nogueira regarding the plans, if such seem<lb/>
in order. In your absence and not hearing from you, I felt it necessary to<lb/>
contact these to other possible agents in Havana.</p>
<p>If you are inclined to do so, perhaps you might telephone Doctor Nogueira, tell<lb/>
him that on your return from Europe you saw all the activity around Building<lb/>
No. 1, and that you wondered exactly what the plans were, when the camp was<lb/>
being dedicated, and so on. That would be a natural inquiry for you to make.</p>
<p>I hope to fly down for the ceremony. I doubt if Mary will come as it will be<lb/>
a very quick trip.</p>
<p>I have given Doctor Nogueira a list of the various Americans to receive of-<lb/>
ficial invitations. I don't believe any official invitations have gone out<lb/>
yet.</p>
<p>I have been considerably distressed by another thing. Doctor Nogueira and I<lb/>
have frequently talked about trying to preserve, as intact as possible, the<lb/>
original shell of Building No. 1. I had hoped that a new outer shell would<lb/>
be built around the original building. About a month ago, without prior<lb/>
consultation or discussion, he merely wrote me that they were already making<lb/>
extensive repairs to the building, tearing out part of the old wood. I cabled<lb/>
and wrote him at once, expressing the hope that they could preserve as much of<lb/>
the original wood as possible and asked him to save for me (to use later for<lb/>
souvenirs) as much of the old wood walls as possible. He assured me that he<lb/>
would, but photographs from him which arrived yesterday show that they removed<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04513023"/>
Miss Maria Teresa Rojas<lb/>
Miss Lydia Cabrera<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 7, 1952<lb/>
practically all of the walls which makes me believe that they will end up<lb/>
with a replica rather than a restoration. This distresses me greatly but per-<lb/>
haps it was unavoidable unless they were prepared to take special care and do<lb/>
a special job.</p>
<p>Tina, I must not ask you to fight my battles and if you feel that you should<lb/>
not contact Doctor Nogueira, that is quite all right; however if you do see<lb/>
some clippings in the papers, I should appreciate having them as it would<lb/>
keep me informed as to how things are going. Doctor Nogueira has invited<lb/>
enough Americans, including the Surgeon General, etc., so that I am sure<lb/>
they intend to do the right thing. They also have asked me to speak for<lb/>
five or ten minutes, presumably at the dedication, which they wouldn't do<lb/>
unless they were sure that I and my compatriots would be pleased with the<lb/>
whole affair.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
