<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04511020">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report to [Carlos E.] Finlay and General Grant on the Quinta San Jose, Quemados de Marianao, Cuba, by Frederick L. Rath, Jr., May 7, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04511020</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-05-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Saladrigas, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-05-07">May 7, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04511020</idno>
<title>Report to [Carlos E.] Finlay and General Grant on the Quinta San Jose, Quemados de Marianao, Cuba, by Frederick L. Rath, Jr., May 7, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Rath describes the Rojas family estate and the adjoining Camp Lazear in terms of their historic significance. He discusses preservation difficulties in Cuba, and outlines Rojas' suggestion that Building No. 1 be taken down and rebuilt on her San Jose property. Rojas would like both properties to be taken over by the American National Trust, and for the Trust to help in setting up a Cuban-American foundation to preserve the property.</p>
</div1>
</front>

<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1952-05-07">
<head>Report to [Carlos E.] Finlay and General Grant on the Quinta San Jose, Quemados de Marianao, Cuba, by Frederick L. Rath, Jr., May 7, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04511020"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1952-05-07">May 7, 1952</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Finley and General Grant<lb/>
Frederick L. Rath, Jr.<lb/>
Quinta San Jos&eacute;, Quemados de Marianao, Cuba<lb/>
</opener>
<p>As you know, at the request and expense of Dr. Phillip S. Hench,<lb/>
I went to Cuba at the end of my recent trip to Florida. There I stayed at<lb/>
the Quinta San Jos&eacute;, the estate of Senora Maria Teresa Rojas in the Havana<lb/>
suburb.</p>
<p>This family estate has interesting American connections because<lb/>
it was Senora Rojas' father who gave the land at the edge of his farm to<lb/>
Walter Reed and a group of Cuban and American medical authorities early in<lb/>
this century to conduct the final and conclusive experiments to determine<lb/>
the cause of yellow fever. That site, named Camp Lazear, is no longer part<lb/>
of the Rojas' old estate. In the slum now there, a single ramshackle struc-<lb/>
ture, the so-called Building No. 1, where it was determined that yellow fever<lb/>
cannot be transmitted by association with infected objects, still stands.<lb/>
Occupied by one or more Cuban families, the frame building has been declared<lb/>
a national monument. Two recent Cuban governments have appropriated money<lb/>
for memorializing the site and preserving Building No. 1; nothing has been<lb/>
done.</p>
<p>The Quinta San Jos&eacute; is what remains of the old original farm. To-<lb/>
day there are several walled acres in the busy suburb, as well as a fine home,<lb/>
which, I am told, is typical of Cuba. The home is filled with a collection<lb/>
of objects and art; it is a catholic collection, including European and Amer-<lb/>
ican materials, which is said to be characteristic of Cuba. Not so charac-<lb/>
teristic, perhaps, is the collection of early tiles, moldings, cornices,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04511021"/>
Report on Quinta San Jos&eacute;<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
May 7, 1952<lb/>
and so forth, saved by Senora Rojas from buildings about to be destroyed in<lb/>
Cuba.</p>
<p>Senora Rojas and her companion, Senorita Lydia Cabresa, are unusual<lb/>
women. Both are students of history and authors; they are women of broad back-<lb/>
ground and culture; finally, they are deeply concerned with the undoubted pass-<lb/>
ing of the Cuban heritage of significant sites and buildings. Their efforts<lb/>
to arouse support, to preserve some buildings have in the main failed. Dis-<lb/>
trusting the particular vagaries of Cuban government, they are seeking not<lb/>
only to help Dr. Hench assure the preservation of Camp Lazear site and Building<lb/>
No. 1 but also to assure the permanent preservation of the Quinta San Jos&eacute;.<lb/>
Senora Rojas has no heirs for her property.</p>
<p>I visited the Camp Lazear site and am inclined to think that the<lb/>
situation there is almost hopeless. Building No. 1 is backed by an operating<lb/>
quarry; the present approach to it is confused and through a slum area. Only<lb/>
$25,000 was available for the proposed memorial under the last (Prio) adminis-<lb/>
tration. Dr. Henriquez Saladrigas, the present Minister of Health under Inte-<lb/>
rim President Batista, dined with us at the Quinta San Jos&eacute; one night and pro-<lb/>
mised to investigate the present situation. In any event, perhaps as much as<lb/>
$250,000 would be needed to treat the site effectively and it is doubtful that<lb/>
the present government would consider so large an investment. Dr. Saladrigas'<lb/>
report will clarify this point later.</p>
<p>Our concern with the situation focuses on a suggestion and offer made<lb/>
by Senora Rojas. She wishes to arrange, if possible, for the taking down of<lb/>
Building No. 1 and re-erection on a portion of the present Quinta San Jos&eacute;.<lb/>
Whether she will be able to do so, I don't know; ultimately, I suspect, that<lb/>
will depend on her influence with the present government and particularly<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04511022"/>
Report on Quinta San Jos&eacute;<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
May 7, 1952<lb/>
President Batista. Furthermore, she wishes to provide for the preservation<lb/>
of the Quinta San Jos&eacute;, including Building No. 1, if it is moved, and any<lb/>
museum adjunct she might erect, in one of two ways: First, she is willing,<lb/>
if it is possible, to leave it by bequest, together with an endowment, to<lb/>
our National Trust. Alternatively, she would like to have our moral support<lb/>
in the setting up of a Cuban-American foundation that would receive the be-<lb/>
quest and administer the property after her death.</p>
<p>I explained the difficulties in the former course to Senora Rojas,<lb/>
told her that I had no authority to encourage such a hope, elaborated on the<lb/>
legal and possibly diplomatic difficulties. She requested, however, that the<lb/>
matter be brought to the attention of the Trustees of the National Trust, to<lb/>
see whether they believed it would be possible to explore the problem further<lb/>
with her. If the first course then fails - that is, acquisition by the Natio-<lb/>
nal Trust, - then she would like to have our assistance in setting up the<lb/>
Cuban-American foundation. While assuring her of our interest, I emphasized<lb/>
the number and nature of the problems now confronting our relatively young<lb/>
National Trust. She understood the position I took and could only express<lb/>
the hope that the Trustees might help her to solve this problem. There is only<lb/>
a slight hope that the Quinta San Jos&eacute; can be permanently saved in any other<lb/>
way; in fact, there is a lurking fear that the Quinta San Jos&eacute; might even be<lb/>
expropriated some day. There is no present Cuban agency, official or non-<lb/>
governmental, to deal with the problem.</p>
<p>The general problem can be presented to the Trustees on Saturday morn-<lb/>
ing, May 10th, if you are willing to have it placed on the agenda. At that time<lb/>
I shall be happy to answer any questions or to discuss aspects of the problem<lb/>
not here discussed. I believe that the Trustees should decide whether or not<lb/>
this problem lies within the province of our National Trust. Such a decision<lb/>
will enable us to determine our next move.</p>
<p>FLR:P</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
