<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04603024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Addendum: The Significance of Cuba's Memorial at Camp Lazear (Havana) and The Importance of the Official American (Diplomatic) Participation in the Dedication, by Philip Showalter Hench, [1953]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04603024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="person">Armstrong, George E.</name>
<name type="person">Beaulac, Willard</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-00-00">[1953]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04603024</idno>
<title>Addendum: The Significance of Cuba's Memorial at Camp Lazear (Havana) and The Importance of the Official American (Diplomatic) Participation in the Dedication, by Philip Showalter Hench, [1953]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench explains to Secretary of State Acheson the work of Finlay and the Yellow Fever Commission, the Finlay-Reed controversy, the rediscovery and eventual memorialization of Camp Lazear, and the significance of Ambassador Beaulac's actions in facilitating American participation at the dedication.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1953-00-00">
<head>Addendum: The Significance of Cuba's Memorial at Camp Lazear (Havana) and The Importance of the Official American (Diplomatic) Participation in the Dedication, by Philip Showalter Hench, [1953]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04603024"/>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>Addendum<lb/>
Significance of Cuba's Memorial at &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; (Havana): The Importance<lb/>
of the Official American (Diplomatic) Participation in the Dedication</hi></head>
<item>1. The Cuban physician, Dr. Carlos Finlay, first developed, in 1881, the<lb/>
brilliant theory that yellow fever, then a terrible scourge to Cuba and to<lb/>
the United States, was caused by a certain mosquito. For 19 years (1881 -<lb/>
1900) he worked to prove his theory but because his results were inconclusive<lb/>
he was almost completely ignored by the Cubans as well as by the world.</item>
<item>2. In 1900 the Surgeon General, U.S. Army, sent a four-man Medical Board<lb/>
(Reed, Carroll, Agramonte, Lazear) to study yellow fever in Cuba. After one<lb/>
false start they were able to prove the Finlay theory so that yellow fever<lb/>
has largely been controlled. The second, most important phase of their work<lb/>
was done in two little specially constructed wooden buildings at an experi-<lb/>
mental station named &ldquo;Camp Lazear,&rdquo; just outside Havana. This was truly the<lb/>
site where yellow fever was &ldquo;conquered.&rdquo;</item>
<item>3. By coincidence &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo; was part of the Finca (farm) San Jose, in<lb/>
the main house of which (Quinta San Jose) Finlay had in 1883 performed five<lb/>
of his experiments. Although Finlay did no experimental work at Camp Lazear<lb/>
(1900 - 1901) he visited it many times (with Reed) as the senior member of<lb/>
the Havana Yellow Fever Board which verified all diagnoses of yellow fever<lb/>
in or near Havana. Thus the Finca San Jose and Camp Lazear above all places<lb/>
united the aspirations, and symbolized the inter-relationship, between Finlay<lb/>
and the Americans.</item>
<item>4. For a short time only (December 1900 - summer 1901) Reed and his associates<lb/>
shared with Finlay the admiring respect of the Cuban people and medical pro-<lb/>
fession. But when the American workers found it necessary (1901 - 1902) to<lb/>
point out the differences between their work and that of Finlay, and the in-<lb/>
conclusiveness of Finlay's <hi>work</hi> (as contrasted to the correctness of his<lb/>
<hi>theory</hi>) there began in Cuba an undignified and often acrimonious debate regarding<lb/>
priority and the relative merits of those concerned.</item>
<item>5. For 50 years certain Cuban elements (physicians, writers, publications)<lb/>
have carried on this unhappy, unilateral campaign of &ldquo;justification&rdquo; (almost<lb/>
deification) of Finlay and belittling of the American Medical Board: &ldquo;The<lb/>
American Army and the American medical associates robbed Finlay of his glory.&rdquo;<lb/>
The campaign has not been materially lessened despite a growing understanding<lb/>
of the American viewpoint by certain important senior Cuban physicians.</item>
<item>6. In 1940 the &ldquo;lost site&rdquo; of Camp Lazear and the actual remains of one of<lb/>
Reed's experimental buildings were rediscovered by an American physician with<lb/>
the help of two &ldquo;Cubans.&rdquo; Certain Americans and Cubans agreed that if this<lb/>
historic spot could be preserved as a Cuban-American memorial to Finlay <hi>and</hi><lb/>
Reed <hi>and</hi> the associates of both (i.e. to <hi>all</hi> the conquerors of yellow fever)<lb/>
it might initiate a new spirit of Cuban-American friendship (professional,<lb/>
popular and governmental) and stop at last the undignified anti-American<lb/>
(anti-Reed) speeches and articles.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f04603025"/>
<item><hi>Addendum</hi> - page 2</item>
<item>7. It took twelve years (1940 - 1952) before the Cuban Government was pre-<lb/>
pared to act. But in 1952 the Cuban Government (of Prio) did restore Reed's<lb/>
historic little building and surrounded it with a small memorial park with<lb/>
bronze memorials. Despite some residual chauvinistic pressure, the Cuban<lb/>
Government chose the official designation &ldquo;Monumento Nacional Parque Campamento<lb/>
Lazear,&rdquo; set December 3, 1952, for the dedication and invited certain Americans:<lb/>
relatives of Reed, Carroll, Lazear; the sole surviving soldier-volunteer, and<lb/>
representatives of the Army Medical Corps and other American organizations.<lb/>
Here at last was an occasion for &ldquo;burying the hatchet&rdquo; and extending mutual<lb/>
felicitations all around.</item>
<item>8. The Americans concerned recognized the importance of an active and<lb/>
sympathetic participation with the Cubans, to recognize their friendly,<lb/>
gracious act toward the American Army Board and to &ldquo;match it&rdquo; with expres-<lb/>
sions of United States friendship for Doctors Finlay and Delgado. Thirteen<lb/>
American organizations (medical schools, associations, the Army) appointed<lb/>
representatives to lay floral tributes to Dr. Finlay (as well as to Reed,<lb/>
et al) at the dedication. Because in the past the Cuban malcontents have<lb/>
regarded the Army Medical Corps and the American Medical Association as<lb/>
the chief &ldquo;detractors&rdquo; of Finlay, the friendly representatives of those<lb/>
two organizations were the most important ones to be at the ceremony.</item>
<item>9. But because of two unexpected circumstances (the Eastern Airlines strike<lb/>
and the bad east-coast storm of December 1 - 2) the most important American<lb/>
representatives (from the &ldquo;diplomatic&rdquo; standpoint) were unable to reach<lb/>
Havana, chief among them Major General Streit, Commanding General of Walter<lb/>
Reed Hospital, who was representing Surgeon General George Armstrong. Thus<lb/>
on the morning of the dedication (the climax of twelve years of hoping and<lb/>
planning on the part of certain Americans) it looked as if the important<lb/>
American tribute to Cuban medical science would fall through since the other<lb/>
Americans present were civilians of academic standing but of no official or<lb/>
military importance as far as the Cubans were concerned.</item>
<item>10. When Ambassador Beaulac learned of this embarrassing situation, recognizing<lb/>
the peculiar importance of having American official participation, he quickly<lb/>
offered the services of his staff, and brought with him and Mrs. Beaulac to the<lb/>
ceremony his aides. To the great satisfaction of the Cubans (and to the great<lb/>
relief of the Americans concerned) Ambassador Beaulac accepted the invitation<lb/>
of the Cuban governmental representative (Minister of Health) to unveil the<lb/>
memorial to Walter Reed. Then four members of the Embassy staff, Mr. Earl<lb/>
Crain, Major Lampner (Medical Corps), Colonel Mason and Lt. Colonel Elmore,<lb/>
participated as most fitting and appropriate substitutes during other parts<lb/>
of the ceremony, only a very few Cubans knowing that they were substitutes.</item>
<item>11. Their participation pleased the Cubans greatly and was widely noted in<lb/>
the Cuban press which used quite a few photographs of these American participators<lb/>
at the ceremony.</item>
<item>12. What could have been a lame and unimpressive affair from the standpoint<lb/>
of American participation and expressions of our appreciation was thus carried<lb/>
out in a manner which seemed to be gratifying to all concerned. A new spirit<lb/>
of Cuban-American friendship (at least medical) was definitely apparent, and<lb/>
was enhanced by the reception given by Ambassador and Mrs. Beaulac at the<lb/>
Embassy Residence, for many Cuban personalities, and by the dinner given for<lb/>
certain American guests by President and Senora Batista.</item>
</list></p>
<closer>
<signed>Philip S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
