<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04606002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Felipe Ponce Carbonell, March 2, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04606002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-03-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ponce, Felipe Carbonell</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-03-02">March 2, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04606002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Felipe Ponce Carbonell, March 2, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench gives Carbonell advice to pass on to his wife's son about a medical fellowship in the U.S. Hench suggests Carbonell contact Nogueira and request a piece of wood from Building No. 1.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-03-02">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Felipe Ponce Carbonell, March 2, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04606002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-03-02">March 2, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Felipe Carbonell<lb/>
San Lazaro 413<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Carbonell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your letter of February 11. First of all, let me say that I did<lb/>
receive your kind gift to Mrs. Hench, the bottle of perfume, just before<lb/>
I left and my wife did write to you acknowledging it over a month ago. We<lb/>
were extremely sorry to hear that you never received her acknowledgement.<lb/>
There have been several recent dislocations in the mail service. Mrs. Hench just<lb/>
received a letter which was mailed to her over a month ago. Please accept our<lb/>
sincere apologies. We are distressed that you did not know that we got it and<lb/>
hope you will understand that we were not neglectful but most appreciative of<lb/>
your gift.</p>
<p>I do wish that your wife's son would write to Dr. Victor Johnson, Director<lb/>
of the Mayo Foundation. I do not want him to get overly enthusiastic or<lb/>
overly optimistic until he makes the appropriate inquiries and learns exactly<lb/>
what his chances for fellowship are. The standards for fellowship are ex-<lb/>
tremely high as I told you and I believe I also wrote to you that very few<lb/>
young Cuban physicians have been accepted here because so few of them have<lb/>
met the language requirement. Since all of the patients here are private<lb/>
patients and most of them of course are Americans, Spanish-speaking physicians<lb/>
who cannot speak English very well have limited usefulness here. That was<lb/>
why I suggested that if he did not otherwise qualify without a year in this<lb/>
country to learn the language, he might do so if he were to spend a year some-<lb/>
where in this country to learn the language. In view of the fact that ap-<lb/>
parently your requirements regarding internships in Cuba are not quite the same<lb/>
as they are here, I do think it would be very important for your wife's <unclear>son-to</unclear><lb/>
find out as soon as possible just what the requirements are and then if he<lb/>
wants to try for a fellowship here he can make his plans accordingly. It<lb/>
might even be advisable for your wife's son to come here for an interview some-<lb/>
time but that is not necessary yet.</p>
<p>You were very kind to ask Mr. <unclear>Tarefa</unclear> to assign me to a window seat when I<lb/>
left Cuba. Unfortunately the plane left so early in the morning that it was<lb/>
rather foggy and instead of flying rather close to the harbor as the plane<lb/>
did on my arrival, the pilot made a wide circle away from Havana so that it<lb/>
was quite useless and impossible for me to take any pictures. I think we must<lb/>
have been at least 20 miles east of the harbor at our nearest point, but I<lb/>
may have better luck next time.</p>
<p>Why don't you call Doctor Nogueira and ask him for a piece of wood from the<lb/>
caseta? Please see the enclosed letter. Doctor Nogueira is very busy. As<lb/>
you know, he is carrying on three or four jobs at once. I am sure he would<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04606003"/>
Dr. Felipe Carbonell<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
March 2, 1953<lb/>
make a date to see you and give you the wood. If he doesn't, don't concern<lb/>
yourself. When I get some from him (I haven't had time to make out my list<lb/>
yet) I will send you a piece, even if it has to be sent from Cuba here and<lb/>
then back again.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
