<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04609005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Story by Helen Cassidy, [April, 1953]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04609005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-04-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-04-00">[April, 1953]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04609005</idno>
<title>Story by Helen Cassidy, [April, 1953]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Cassidy's article briefly tells the story of the yellow fever experiments, the discovery by Hench of the correct location of Camp Lazear, and the eventual dedication of the site.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1953-04-00">
<head>Story by Helen Cassidy, [April, 1953]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04609005"/>
<p>An interest in medical history sounds like a scholarly and<lb/>
passive pursuit: reading large and dusty volumes, visiting museums,<lb/>
viewing monuments inscribed &ldquo;On this spot.........&rdquo;</p>
<p>But sometimes even <add>a</add> spare time medical historian plays a much<lb/>
more active role.</p>
<p>Take Dr. Philip S. Hench. Last December, in Marianao, Cuba<lb/>
he participated in the dedication of a memorial to the group of men<lb/>
whose work contributed to the eradication of yellow fever. <del><unclear>The</unclear></del></p>
<p>The Camp Lazear National Monument is located on the site<lb/>
where a commission of the U. S. National Board of Health, headed<lb/>
by Walter Reed, carried out work which proved the theory of the<lb/>
Cuban scientist, Dr. Carlos Finlay, that yellow fever is transmitted<lb/>
by the mosquito.</p>
<p>And it was Dr. Hench, who, by long-time study and sharp-eyed<lb/>
observation, was able to correctly identify the location of Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>It happened this way.</p>
<p>Back in 1940 Dr. Hench made a trip to Havana, Cuba. He<lb/>
wanted to see -- if they still existed -- the two wooden shacks where<lb/>
the mosquito theory had been proved. He wanted to meet the son and<lb/>
daughter of two of the men who had particpated in the work, to learn<lb/>
from them some not-in-the-history-books details of the story. He<lb/>
wanted to meet Johnny Moran, an American soldier who had volunteered<lb/>
to be biten by a &ldquo;loaded&rdquo; mosquito and developed one of the first<lb/>
cases of &ldquo;deliberately accepted and completely controlled experimental<lb/>
yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The story of the conquering of yellow fever is a dramatic one.<lb/>
Briefly it is this.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04609006"/>
<p>Hench-2-</p>
<p>In the latter part of the 1800's, incidence of yellow<lb/>
fever reached plague proportions in Cuba. During the Spanish American<lb/>
War it accounted for a major portion of the deaths among American<lb/>
soldiers. <del><unclear>In 1900</unclear></del></p>
<p>In 1900 there was created the United States Army Special<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board, to work in Cuba, whose members included Major<lb/>
Walter Reed, Drs. James Carroll, Aristides Agramonte and Jesse<lb/>
Lazear.</p>
<p>These men examined the existing theories of the cause of yellow<lb/>
fever -- that it came from a miasma that rose over tropical swamps;<lb/>
that it was due to a germ which an Italian physician believed he had<lb/>
discovered; that it was transmitted from the infected clothing and<lb/>
belongings of its victims. Finally, there was the theory of a Havana<lb/>
physician, Dr. Carlos Finlay, that yellow fever was transmitted by<lb/>
the common house mosquito, which sucked in the infection with the<lb/>
blood of a fever victim, then passed it on to persons it might later bite.</p>
<p>Lazear began to breed Finlay's mosquitos in the camp<lb/>
laboratory. Ten American soldiers -- including Drs. Lazear and Carroll --<lb/>
allowed themselves to be <unclear>bitten</unclear> by presumably infected mosquitos. Nothing<lb/>
happened. But then Dr. Carroll was re-innoculated. In a few days<lb/>
he developed a severe and almost fatal attack of yellow fever. A scoffing<lb/>
volunteer soldier who &ldquo;wasn't afraid of any little old gnat,&rdquo; died<lb/>
following an infected mosquito's bite.</p>
<p>Lazear, who happily wrote his wife, &ldquo;I rather think I am<lb/>
on the right track,&rdquo; a few days later fell <add>ill</add> and died of yellow fever.<lb/>
At the time his death was listed as due to &ldquo;accidental yellow fever.&rdquo;<lb/>
Later indications were that the disease <del><unclear></unclear></del><add>resulted from again exposing himself secretly</add><lb/>
to the bite of infected mosquitos.</p>
<p>There were now -- counting Lazear -- three cases of mosquito-induced<lb/>
yellow fever. To carry out more completely controlled experiments,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04609007"/>
Hench-3-<lb/>
to gather irrefutable evidence for their theory, Reed, Carroll and<lb/>
Agramonte set up an experimental camp, which, to honor their dead<lb/>
colleague, they named Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>Two small buildings were erected. In one, the &ldquo;infected<lb/>
clothing and bedding building,&rdquo; volunteers were exposed to clothing and<lb/>
bedding used by a yellow fever victims. None of them developed<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<p>The second building, the &ldquo;infected mosquito building,&rdquo; was<lb/>
divided into two parts by a wire screen. In one portion infected<lb/>
mosquitos were present; in the other, no mosquitos. There fourteen<lb/>
American and Spanish volunteers -- among them Johnny Moran -- allowed<lb/>
themselves to be bitten by mosquitos. They all developed yellow<lb/>
fever. Men on the other side of the screen, where there were no<lb/>
mosquitos, remained well.</p>
<p>This was accepted as conclusive evidence that yellow fever<lb/>
was transmitted by the mosquito. With this knowledge, General<lb/>
William Gorgas, U. S. Army sanitation expert, within three months<lb/>
freed Havana of yellow fever. The same knowledge later made it<lb/>
possible to complete the Panama Canal.</p>
<p>This was the story which had long intrigued the imagination<lb/>
of Dr. Hench, which in 1940 led him to Cuba on a &ldquo;sentimental journey.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Johnny Moran met him there, took him to a small enclosed<lb/>
plot of ground. A large sign stated: &ldquo;On this spot was established<lb/>
&lsquo;El Campamento Lazear&rsquo;.......&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. Hench, who had read every publication of Walter Reed<lb/>
he could get his hands on, couldn't reconcile location of the plot<lb/>
(bordering a spur railroad track which led to a bathing beach) with<lb/>
the &ldquo;secluded spot&rdquo; described in the Reed papers.</p>
<p>Back at his hotel that night he read again the papers of Reed.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04609008"/>
Hench-4-<lb/>
There he found a statement that the camp had been located &ldquo;on the<lb/>
farm of Dr. Ignacio Rojas.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A real estate man helped him identify the Rojas farm.<lb/>
Its present occupant, an elderly woman, admitted that &ldquo;Yes, there<lb/>
were American soldiers with a few tents and a couple of buildings<lb/>
erected on the <unclear>rear</unclear> of this farm.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When asked to take them to their location she hesitated, then<lb/>
spoke in Spanish to a servant. Johnny Moran, grinning, translated<lb/>
for Dr. Hench: &ldquo;She isn't taking <del><unclear></unclear></del> any chances with you. She told<lb/>
her servant she is going into our car with us to another part of the<lb/>
farm, but if she doesn't return in half an hour please come after<lb/>
her. She is afraid you might kidnap her.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Moran and Dr. Hench located a shack which, though in the<lb/>
right location didn't appear the right shape of the Camp Lazear<lb/>
buildings. But a curious and friendly Cuban told them, &ldquo;Yes, the<lb/>
American soldiers lived in this building and got yellow fever. My<lb/>
father told me that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is this building, completely reconstructed and divested<lb/>
of the lean-tos that obscured its identiy, which is the center of<lb/>
the present Camp Lazear National Monument. There are bronze medallions<lb/>
honoring the scientists who contributed to the work, the American and<lb/>
Cuban soldiers who voluntarily exposed themselves to yellow fever,<lb/>
and &ldquo;all who cooperated.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There, on the day of dedication, Dr. Hench, representing<lb/>
the Mayo Foundation, placed a wreath honoring Drs. Finlay, Reed and<lb/>
their associates. There were many more wreaths, from universities,<lb/>
medical societies, the Surgeon General of the United States.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f04609009"/>
<p>Hench-5-</p>
<p>Dr. Hench, and others, <del><unclear>in</unclear></del> see in the memorial more than a<lb/>
record of a great medical achievement. In concluding his address<lb/>
delivered at the dedication ceremonies Dr. Hench stated:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of the 25 principal men whose hopes were fulfilled at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, three were Cubans, four were Spainards, one was English,<lb/>
one was Irish and 16 were Americans. Some were humbly born; some<lb/>
reached high estate; some were civilians, others were soldiers,<lb/>
professionals and volunteers; some were Catholic, some were<lb/>
Protestant, some were Hebrews. And here on this hemisphere's 23rd<lb/>
parallel they demonstrated well the potential brotherhood of man.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
