<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04608004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom Reed, April 8, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04608004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-04-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Blossom</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-04-08">April 8, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04608004</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom Reed, April 8, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Blossom Reed that he will be happy to help her with the sale of her father's books. He discusses what makes books and autographs valuable.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-04-08">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom Reed, April 8, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04608004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-04-08">April 8, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. Blossom Reed<lb/>
Blue Ridge Summit<lb/>
Pennsylvania<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Reed:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I shall be glad to help you with the sale of the seven books of your father's.<lb/>
The difficulty however is that second-hand medical book stores do not <unclear>specialize</unclear><lb/>
particularly in autographed books; whereas autograph stores concern themselves<lb/>
almost entirely with letters and manuscripts and do not bother with books.<lb/>
Therefore an autographed book unfortunately rather falls between two commercial<lb/>
groups and I have seen many a catalog listing a book autographed by a famous<lb/>
man in which the price was based exclusively or almost so on the value of the<lb/>
book, perhaps with a dollar added for the signature.</p>
<p>Another thing about old medical books is that their value is not derived from<lb/>
their date particularly but from a combination of two things: (1) their lasting<lb/>
value; that is, if they were a classic and (2) their rarity. Many a book that<lb/>
is quite rare, but of which the contents are rather worthless or entirely out<lb/>
of date, one can buy for two or three dollars.</p>
<p>I should think that the sale of your father's seven books would be more profitable<lb/>
to you if they were put in the hands of someone interested in them simply and<lb/>
solely because they were your father's books and not because they are inherently<lb/>
worth this or that. I do not, off-hand, know the merit of the seven books you<lb/>
mention but having been a book-buyer and book-lover for years, I must in all<lb/>
honesty tell you that the dates of these books fall &ldquo;in between.&rdquo; By that I<lb/>
mean valuable books between 1600 and 1830 or 40, command a fair price but even<lb/>
so they have to fulfill the criteria mentioned above. Or a valuable book that<lb/>
is just out of print, maybe ten years old, but is still pertinent, may command a<lb/>
price. Those not between these dates have extremely variable values, depending<lb/>
entirely upon the book itself and not on the age.</p>
<p><unclear>Now</unclear> I do want to help you and it would certainly be easy for me to write to<lb/>
three or four institutions or places that might want these books for the reason<lb/>
mentioned. Do you have any idea what you would want for the seven books. I<lb/>
can ask our librarian to give me a little idea as to their intrinsic merit as<lb/>
books of a certain date. That would be the basis with the extra <unclear>cose</unclear> because of<lb/>
their very real sentimental value. If you do set a price, I will keep it con-<lb/>
fidential and will not of course pass it on to anyone without your permission<lb/>
but it will give me some idea as to who one should tackle - whether some individual<lb/>
of modest means interested in your father (and I know many) or some library or<lb/>
military institution. When I hear from you also I can either send you the names<lb/>
of three or four second-hand medical book stores in New York; also the names of<lb/>
the three or four best autograph stores.-</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04608005"/>
<p>Mrs. Blossom Reed</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>April 8, 1953</p>
<p>Of course (and please do not misunderstand me) I should like to have the first<lb/>
chance at buying the books myself but I fear that this would embarrass you as<lb/>
you do want the best price you can get for them and until we explore the matter<lb/>
I haven't any idea what that might be or whether I could meet it; however that<lb/>
is not important. The only important thing is that these books which you have<lb/>
cherished for these many years shall be put in the hands of others who will<lb/>
cherish them almost as well and in the process you will get a fair price. That<lb/>
I will certainly be glad to help you do.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
