<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04606007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul L. Tate, March 4, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04606007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-03-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Tate, Paul L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Warner, Lena A.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-03-04">March 4, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04606007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul L. Tate, March 4, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes that the Cubans asked him to help them determine the relative contributions of the Americans involved in the yellow fever work. He agrees with Tate that Warner has misrepresented her role in the experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-03-04">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul L. Tate, March 4, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04606007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-03-04">March 4, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Paul L. Tate<lb/>
1530 Tyler Street<lb/>
Berkeley 3, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Tate:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you very much indeed for your nice letter of February 23. I am glad<lb/>
to have your honest appraisal of Miss Warner's &ldquo;reminiscences.&rdquo; It is<lb/>
simply amazing how &ldquo;old soldiers&rdquo;, as the years pass by, remember things<lb/>
that never happened. The unfortunate thing is that her remarks did get<lb/>
published; if not in toto, they were quoted rather extensively by a later<lb/>
writer.</p>
<p>As to the appearance of her name on the memorial tablet at Camp Lazear which<lb/>
was dedicated last December, this was strictly the decision of the Cubans.<lb/>
They asked me to <unclear>streighten</unclear> them out on the relative contributions of every<lb/>
American concerned. At the expense of considerable work I made a more or less<lb/>
complete list of the names and even the initialed participants with a careful<lb/>
breakdown as to what each person did. Then the Cuban committee decided which<lb/>
of the Americans should be mentioned. I too was disturbed that they left off<lb/>
Captain Stark and Doctor Pinto and when I heard about it I objected to that<lb/>
but they decided to honor essentially only those who worked at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
plus of course Lazear himself. They did not even list Dean - &ldquo;XY&rdquo; and because<lb/>
whatever contribution Captain Stark made was simply in line of duty and was<lb/>
largely, if not entirely, done at the post hospital, he was left out. By this<lb/>
very definition, Miss Warner should have been left out but they decided to<lb/>
include Doctor Ames for obvious reasons (and I am delighted they did because,<lb/>
as you know, he has not been honored as much as he should have been), Lambert<lb/>
also for obvious reasons and they added Miss Warner chiefly because she ap-<lb/>
parently nursed Lazear and two or three of the earliest volunteers who developed<lb/>
experimental yellow fever and I suspect also because the records as to just<lb/>
which nurses took care of which volunteers is not clear. I think they gave<lb/>
her credit because they suspected that she may have nursed more of the<lb/>
volunteers from Camp Lazear than General Truby and others believe she did.</p>
<p>Permit me to send you a copy of a letter which I sent after my return from<lb/>
Cuba. I hope you will find it of interest.</p>
<p>I am at the moment immorsed in a project which has me hanging on the ropes but<lb/>
as soon as I finish it (in two or three weeks) I hope to send General Truby<lb/>
75 or more pictures of the Camp Lazear dedication ceremonies. I should be de-<lb/>
lighted if, while he has them, you find opportunity to call on him or, if this<lb/>
is not mutually agreeable (I know that General Truby has not been too well) I<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04606008"/>
Mr. Paul L. Tate<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
March 4, 1953<lb/>
would be quite happy to have <unclear>him</unclear> lend you these photographs for a day or<lb/>
two, remembering that they are merely being sent around to interested per-<lb/>
sons to find out if they want to order any and the longer they are held up<lb/>
the longer will be the delay in getting the photographs to the various<lb/>
interested persons.</p>
<p>I have been asked to describe the dedication of Camp Lazear before the<lb/>
staff of the Mayo Clinic which I shall do in the next two months. The<lb/>
description will be published in the Proceedings of the Staff Meetings<lb/>
of the Mayo Clinic and I will certainly send you a copy.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: Did I ever send you the article published in &ldquo;The Pharos&rdquo; which<lb/>
told how Moran, Pogolotti and I found Camp Lazear? I think I did but if<lb/>
not, let me know and I will send you one.<lb/>
I appreciate greatly your correspondence. Please don't apologize for the<lb/>
length of your letter. The more, the better. I think you know that the whole<lb/>
story has been a thrilling one to me and the project continues to occupy<lb/>
much of my thoughts. The next time I come to California (I expect to at-<lb/>
tend the meeting of the American Medical Association in San Francisco in<lb/>
June, 1954) I certainly will want to see you and spend a few hours with<lb/>
you asking you certain questions and discussing the whole thing.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
