<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04605005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Willard L. Beaulac, February 4, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04605005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-02-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Beaulac, Willard L.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Acheson, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-02-04">February 4, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04605005</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Willard L. Beaulac, February 4, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is sending Beaulac his memorandum on the dedication of Camp Lazear. He hopes the American Embassy will be called on to participate in other ceremonies at Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-02-04">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Willard L. Beaulac, February 4, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04605005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1953-02-04">February 4, 1953</date>
</dateline>
PHILIP S. HENCH, M. D.<lb/>
CHARLES H. SLOCUMB, M. D.<lb/>
HOWARD F. POLLEY, M. D.<lb/>
EMMERSON WARD, M. D.<lb/>
Mr. Willard L. Beaulac<lb/>
U. S. Ambassador to Cuba<lb/>
United States Embassy<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Beaulac:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you very kindly indeed for sending me the seating plan of the dinner.<lb/>
Actually I did not request nor did I know that there was a formal blue print<lb/>
of the seating arrangement and I am sorry that you went to some trouble to<lb/>
get this. I was merely desirous of having an identification of the people<lb/>
around the table which I thought you could give me off-hand. Nevertheless<lb/>
I am glad to have the formal diagram. I showed it to my wife last night<lb/>
and suggested that we make such a diagram from now on for every social af-<lb/>
fair at Maison Hench. Her reply was unprintable!</p>
<p>Thank you also for the extra set of pictures, a couple of which were quite<lb/>
&ldquo;fullsome&rdquo; if you know what I mean.</p>
<p>Permit me to enclose a memorandum on the dedication of Camp Lazear which<lb/>
I sent in the form of a personal letter to the one survivor and to the rela-<lb/>
tives of those most concerned. I am also enclosing a confidential memorandum<lb/>
which went only to a selected few. The confidential addendum represents<lb/>
only my personal opinions and views but I think it is essentially correct.</p>
<p>Mr. Beaulac, let me say again how very much I appreciated your help and I am sure<lb/>
that even you may not realize how important it seemed to those of us con-<lb/>
cerned with the dedication. Because of the Christmas holidays and other<lb/>
activities which I interrupted for my rather hasty trip to Cuba, I was not<lb/>
able to compose the enclosed memorandum of January 3 before that date. I<lb/>
was most desirous of expressing my appreciation of your services to the<lb/>
Secretary of State. This I did on January 12, sending it to Secretary<lb/>
Acheson. As we mailed the letter about January 14 I realized that Mr.<lb/>
Acheson's term was coming quickly to a close. I wondered in any event<lb/>
whether he would ever see such a letter but I sent it on. May I ask you<lb/>
personally whether it would serve my purpose (not yours) if I were to send<lb/>
a similar letter to Secretary Dulles? I know he has just gone to Europe<lb/>
but the Acting or Assistant Secretary might see it. Or would it be merely<lb/>
passed down the line until it came to the same department that presumably<lb/>
saw my letter of January 12? I am very sincere in wishing to let your<lb/>
chiefs in Washington know about the generous activities of yourself and<lb/>
your colleagues and indeed about the whole project.</p>
<p>Two or three of the officials connected with the dedication later said<lb/>
&ldquo;Now we have in Marianao the finest rallying point for an expression of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04605006"/>
Mr. Willard L. Beaulac<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
February 4, 1953<lb/>
Cuban American friendship and cooperation which will be rededicated each<lb/>
year on December 3 with ceremonies.&rdquo; If that is the case, your embassy<lb/>
may well be called upon to participate in other ceremonies at Camp Lazear<lb/>
and indeed I hope you will be, and your successors in Havana and your<lb/>
chiefs in Washington should know something of the true significance of the<lb/>
place.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: As a polite guest I sent my brief thanks for the dinner party to<lb/>
President Batista, a copy is enclosed.<lb/>
I enclose a photograph of you unveiling Reed's medallion. You appear in<lb/>
several other photographs in the list that I am sending to you, see Nos. 18<lb/>
through 19. Some of these appeared in the paper. Should you wish copies<lb/>
and if Doctor Nogueira did not send them to you, I have many of these films<lb/>
and we can get them printed by a local photographer.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
