<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04603002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Alberto Recio, January 3, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04603002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-01-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Recio, Alberto</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-01-03">January 3, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04603002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Alberto Recio, January 3, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Recio for his courtesies, including paying Hench's hotel bill, when Hench was in Cuba for the Camp Lazear dedication. He requests a copy of Recio's speech given at the ceremony. Hench suggests enclosing Building No. 1 and using part of the structure as a pubic health center.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-01-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Alberto Recio, January 3, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04603002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-01-03">January 3, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Alberto Recio<lb/>
Director de Salubridad<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Recio:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Permit me to express to you and to your colleagues, the patrons for the<lb/>
preservation of Camp Lazear, my very sincere appreciation for the many<lb/>
courtesies you extended to me and to the other Americans on the occasion<lb/>
of our recent visit to Havana. The other American visitors were as de-<lb/>
lighted as I with the whole affair. I have been asked to describe the<lb/>
ceremony for the staff of the Mayo Clinic. I would appreciate it greatly<lb/>
if you would send me at your earliest convenience (by airmail if at all<lb/>
possible) a complete copy of the remarks you made at the dedication of<lb/>
Camp Lazear. I noted a brief abstract of it in one of the newspapers<lb/>
but I am anxious to have your complete speech.</p>
<p>You ask me to help you with regard to the wording to be placed in or outside<lb/>
of the caseta. I am a little confused. I think you are planning to place near<lb/>
the flag pole a bronze tablet identifying the spot but I think you also had<lb/>
in mind framing and placing, either on the inside or outside wall of the<lb/>
caseta, an additional inscription. I am not sure whether you asked me to<lb/>
help with one or both. Nor am I sure how long you want the wording to be.<lb/>
I would appreciate knowing and I would be glad to cooperate in any way<lb/>
possible.</p>
<p>I was delighted to hear that you had in mind the possible development of a<lb/>
further memorial at Camp Lazear. It would be wonderful indeed if the present<lb/>
caseta could be enclosed for permanent security in a museum room which would<lb/>
be attached to a large building which could serve as a living memorial to<lb/>
Doctors Finlay, Reed and their associates and which might take the form of a<lb/>
public health unit or other useful building for the public of that district.<lb/>
I should be delighted indeed to help in any way possible. In the meantime,<lb/>
you may wish to have copies of photographs and related documents to frame and hang<lb/>
inside the caseta. I should be glad to collaborate with you and Doctor Nogueira<lb/>
and make available to you some of the photographs which I have.</p>
<p>May I thank you, Doctor Recio, and also Doctor Nogueira, for your unexpected<lb/>
kindness in paying my hotel bill. I had no expectation of such hospitality<lb/>
and it was a great surprise but a very pleasant one. I remonstrated with<lb/>
Doctor Nogueira as I certainly did not want my expenses to be taken out of<lb/>
the fund for Camp Lazear. He assured me that it was not and that my hotel<lb/>
bill was being paid for with money that had been intended for Mr. Hanberry.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04603003"/>
<p>Dr. Alberto Recio</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>January 3, 1953</p>
<p>I appreciate very greatly not only this courtesy but the thought behind it.<lb/>
I have made many trips this year attending scientific meetings at my own<lb/>
expense in addition to those sponsored by the Clinic. Therefore this extra<lb/>
courtesy on your part is very deeply appreciated.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: Permit me to send you herewith a reprint which describes the re-<lb/>
discovery of Camp Lazear, see page 3.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
