<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04603004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas and Lydia Cabrera, January 5, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04603004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-01-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Cabrera, Lydia</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-01-05">January 5, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04603004</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas and Lydia Cabrera, January 5, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests that Rojas and Cabrera give a copy of an article by Agramonte to Nogueira. He comments on a recent interview he gave.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-01-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Maria Teresa Rojas and Lydia Cabrera, January 5, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04603004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-01-05">January 5, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Senorita Maria Teresa Rojas and Senorita Lidia Cabrera<lb/>
Quinta San Jose<lb/>
Calzada <unclear>Reel</unclear> y Manuel Gomez<lb/>
Marianao, Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Friends:</salute>
</opener>
<p>When I visited you this time you may recall that I brought with me a copy<lb/>
of the article by Doctor Agramonte, published in December 1915 in the<lb/>
SCIENTIFIC MONTHLY, describing the location of Camp Lazear, and so on.<lb/>
When I was about to present it to Tina she said she thought I had already<lb/>
given her one, whereupon having described it, I gave it to Lidia. Later<lb/>
that week I found that I had never given a copy to Doctor Nogueira. I had<lb/>
merely sent him one or two photostated pages. He is very anxious to have<lb/>
a complete copy because it is the only place in the American literature<lb/>
which gives officially the location of Camp Lazear. I think he hopes<lb/>
eventually to display it inside the caseta.</p>
<p>On my return I tried to find another copy but apparently the one I brought<lb/>
to you was my last extra copy and the one I have is <unclear>podly</unclear> marked up, other-<lb/>
wise I could photostate it. Under the circumstances, would you be willing,<lb/>
after making sure that you really do have another copy, to either give or<lb/>
lend the second copy to Doctor Nogueira? Meanwhile, I shall try to locate<lb/>
another one through the second-hand book and magazine stores in New York<lb/>
but it may be months or even much longer before I can find one as it was<lb/>
very hard for me to find the ones I have already given away.</p>
<p>Professor Baker has just sent me the clippings of the two articles prepared<lb/>
from the interview which I had with the reporter on Saturday, December 6.<lb/>
I am sorry that I exhibited impatience but I had, as you know, two more ap-<lb/>
pointments that afternoon before going to the palace for dinner. I have<lb/>
not been able to translate the newspaper clippings literally. Professor<lb/>
baker says there are a number of errors in them but that is almost to be<lb/>
expected. I am sorry he did not keep his promise and read the articles back<lb/>
either to you or to Professor Baker.</p>
<p>Lidia, the reference that I meant to show you was to Dr. Francisco Cabrera,<lb/>
mentioned on page 105 of Finlay's Selected Works. Is he any relative.</p>
<p>Because of the length of the interview with the newspaper reporter, I had no<lb/>
opportunity to discuss with you the unfinished questionnaire which Tina, your<lb/>
mother and I started working on a few years ago and never finished. As soon<lb/>
as I have time, I will write this out and send it to you.</p>
<p>I certainly had a wonderful time with you all and am so sorry that Mary was<lb/>
not with me. We had a very happy Christmas with our whole family, including<lb/>
our new son-in-law.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
