<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04603029">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George E. Armstrong, January 15, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04603029</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-01-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Armstrong, George E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="person">Beaulac, Willard L.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lampner, Harold</name>
<name type="person">Mason, Robert J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Elmore, Vincent M</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-01-15">January 15, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04603029</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George E. Armstrong, January 15, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes about the Camp Lazear dedication. He hopes that the ceremony will help ease Cuban-American tensions surrounding the Reed-Finlay debate.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-01-15">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George E. Armstrong, January 15, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04603029"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-01-15">January 15, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Major General George E. Armstrong<lb/>
The Surgeon General<lb/>
Department of the Army<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Armstrong:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was so very sorry that your representative, General Streit, was prevented<lb/>
by the storm from attending the dedication of Camp Lazear in Havana. It was<lb/>
a disappointment to all concerned. You will remember that at my request<lb/>
General Streit mentioned to you the feasibility of two rather than one wreath<lb/>
being laid by your representative, one to honor the Cuban doctors, Finlay and<lb/>
Delgado and one in honor of the American soldier-volunteers.</p>
<p>In General Streit's absence, I requested help from Ambassador Beaulac who was<lb/>
most helpful. He and his aides attended the ceremony and because the repre-<lb/>
sentations from you and the American Medical Association were, in my opinion,<lb/>
by far the most important, Ambassador Beaulac designated two quite appropriate<lb/>
men to substitute for General Streit in your behalf. Major Harold Lampner, a<lb/>
member of the Medical Corps, U. S. Army, who is with some medical mission in<lb/>
Cuba, <unclear>unvailed</unclear> Doctor Carroll's memorial plaque and placed the wreath, in your<lb/>
name, substituting for General Streit, in honor of Doctors Finlay and Delgado.<lb/>
Colonel Robert J. Mason, Air Attache at the Embassy, substituted for General<lb/>
Streit and placed in your name a wreath in honor of the American soldier-<lb/>
volunteers for the yellow fever experiments.</p>
<p>The ceremony was very nice indeed and was widely reported most sympathetically<lb/>
in the Cuban press. General Streit's intended remarks were read in full at<lb/>
the ceremony, being translated into Spanish by Doctor Nogueira and were pub-<lb/>
lished essentially in full in three Cuban papers.</p>
<p>I realize, General Armstrong, that in these troublesome times you have much more<lb/>
to do than concern yourself seriously with a historical event fifty years old.<lb/>
But I am sure you realize that although the reputation of Reed and his Army<lb/>
colleagues is secure throughout the world, for fifty years, especially in Cuba<lb/>
and to a lesser extent in other South American countries, there has been a<lb/>
strong tendency to ignore Reed and his associates, to claim that they robbed<lb/>
Finlay of his glory, etc. Thus the prestige of the Army Medical Corps has<lb/>
been under some fire in Cuba for many years. I do believe that the present<lb/>
ceremony will do a great deal to stop the unpleasant argument, and your<lb/>
representation and tributes on the occasion of the dedication were extremely<lb/>
helpful and well received.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04603030"/>
<p>C2</p>
<p>B3</p>
<p>Major General George E. Armstrong</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>January 15, 1953</p>
<p>By separate post I am sending you a memorandum concerning the entire<lb/>
ceremony and the diplomatic and political overtones. It may well be that<lb/>
you will not have time to read it but at least it can be filed for future<lb/>
use and reference if necessary and I am hoping that you can read it be-<lb/>
cause I suspect that you, like I do, get some fun from turning away from<lb/>
the material problems of the day and spending a little time on &ldquo;matters<lb/>
of the heart.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am enclosing a few newspaper clippings but have sent a larger collection<lb/>
to General Streit. I will ask him to give to you, if you wish them, those<lb/>
which are not duplicates.</p>
<p>General Armstrong, the two or three members of Ambassador Beaulac's staff<lb/>
seemed to be quite pleased and proud to substitute for General Streit in<lb/>
your behalf. They were extremely helpful because the rest of the American<lb/>
delegates, although they had academic rank, were relatively unimportant to<lb/>
those Cubans to whom officialdom is important and in this instance your of-<lb/>
ficial representation was extremely important. Should you care or have<lb/>
time to drop a little note to those who represented you, I am sure they would<lb/>
appreciate it greatly. Ambassador Willard Beaulac was of course chiefly<lb/>
responsible for supplying representatives for you. He unveiled the medallion<lb/>
of Walter Reed. As mentioned above, Major Harold Lampner, Medical Corps, un-<lb/>
veiled the medallion of Doctor Carroll and laid your wreath for Doctors<lb/>
Finlay and Delgado. Colonel Robert J. Mason, Air Attache, U. S. Embassy,<lb/>
laid your wreath for the American soldier-volunteers. In addition, Lt. Colonel<lb/>
Vincent M. Elmore, Army Attache, represented the Walter Reed Memorial As-<lb/>
sociation of which I believe you are a member and laid a wreath in honor<lb/>
of Major Reed. All of these men could be addressed at the U. S. Embassy,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba.</p>
<p>The Minister of Health of Cuba officiated at the dedication and attended<lb/>
several social events in relation to the dedication and President and Mrs.<lb/>
Batista gave a dinner party for a few of us American guests. President<lb/>
Batista regretted the absence of your representative.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
