<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04603027">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Fulgencio Batista y Zaldivar, January 13, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04603027</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-01-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Wood, Louise</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Armstrong, George E.</name>
<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Blossom] Emilie M.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Margaret Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter L.</name>
<name type="person">Saladrigas, Enrique</name>
<name type="person">Lincoln, Abraham</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-01-13">January 13, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04603027</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Fulgencio Batista y Zaldivar, January 13, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Batista for the dinner party following the Camp Lazear dedication. He stresses that the establishment of the Camp Lazear monument has given pleasure to many Americans. He hopes that the site can become a living memorial by the addition of a public health center.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-01-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Fulgencio Batista y Zaldivar, January 13, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04603027"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-01-13">January 13, 1953</date>
</dateline>
The Honorable Senor President of the Republic of Cuba<lb/>
Major General Fulgencia Batista<lb/>
The Palace<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear President Batista:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On my return from Habana and the dedication of Camp Lazear I was at once<lb/>
caught up in the activities of the Christmas - New Year holidays with our<lb/>
home once again filled with all of our children back from school.</p>
<p>May I express to you, President Batista, my somewhat belated but very<lb/>
sincere thanks for your courtesy in inviting me to join you and Senora<lb/>
Batista on the happy occasion of your dinner for Miss Louise Wood at<lb/>
The Palace on the night of December 6. It was a delightful occasion<lb/>
which your five guests from the United States will always remember with<lb/>
pleasure. I have just received from Doctor Capote three more photo-<lb/>
graphs of the dinner party which I am delighted to have.</p>
<p>I regret very much that Mrs. Hench, who has visited Habana so often with<lb/>
me and who joins me in cherishing our close friendship with many Cubans,<lb/>
was unable to go with me on this felicitous occasion when you and your<lb/>
countrymen, by the act of memorializing Campamento Lazear on the Finca<lb/>
San Jose, Quemados, paid such a distinguished and lasting tribute to my<lb/>
countrymen, Drs. Walter Reed, Jesse Lazear, James Carroll and their as-<lb/>
sociates, uniting their names in honored memory with that of your pre-<lb/>
eminent and well-loved Carlos Finlay.</p>
<p>These great men, each making his own contribution to a common cause,<lb/>
together did so much, not only for the people of their own two countries,<lb/>
yours and mine, but for all mankind.</p>
<p>Your establishment of Campamento Lazear as a National Monument has given<lb/>
great satisfaction and pleasure to Americans of many classes, especially<lb/>
to the American medical profession and to the Medical Department of the<lb/>
United States Army. Major General George Armstrong, the Surgeon General,<lb/>
and his associate, Major General Streit, and officers of the American<lb/>
Medical Association have written me expressing their great interest in<lb/>
the ceremony of dedication. I am sending to them and to the sons and<lb/>
daughters of Drs. Reed, Lazear and Carroll a full report concerning this<lb/>
gracious gesture and this fine example of Cuban friendship for us. Also<lb/>
I will shortly describe the dedication of the &ldquo;Parque Monumento Nacional<lb/>
Campamento Lazear&rdquo; to my colleagues of the staff of the Mayo Clinic at<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04603028"/>
The Honorable Senor President of the Republic of Cuba<lb/>
Page 2<lb/>
January 13, 1953<lb/>
one of our general staff meetings. Furthermore it will be my privilege<lb/>
to call this new medical shrine to the attention of various United States<lb/>
associations related to medicine, public health and sanitation. Many of<lb/>
them will, I am sure, be anxious to visit it during their conventions in<lb/>
Habana.</p>
<p>Ministro Saladrigas and others, so I understand, have expressed the hope<lb/>
that the Memorial Park, fine as it is, will be only the beginning of a<lb/>
larger, living memorial for the people of Habana and Quemados which may<lb/>
take the form of a public health unit or other useful structure. Erected<lb/>
on the very site of old Campamento Lazear where the earnest hopes of<lb/>
Cuban and American scientists for the conquest of yellow fever were<lb/>
realized as a result of an unequaled cooperative adventure, such a living<lb/>
memorial would certainly <unclear>epitomize</unclear> magnificently the wonderful tradition<lb/>
of Cuban-American friendship and cooperation, and of the inter-nationality<lb/>
of scientific endeavor.</p>
<p>I would be more than delighted to cooperate in the raising of American<lb/>
funds to help support such a Cuban-American memorial.</p>
<p>President Batista, after your dinner party I was so glad to have you tell<lb/>
me of your great admiration for Abraham Lincoln and of your library of<lb/>
books about him. Permit me to send you what I am told is the latest<lb/>
book on his life, a book which is receiving excellent reviews and which<lb/>
appears to be outstanding in some ways. I do hope that this will be<lb/>
now to you and that you will enjoy it.</p>
<p>Accept it as a small token of my very real friendship for you and your<lb/>
countrymen. Please also convey to Senora Batista my kind regards and<lb/>
sincere thanks.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
