<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04603007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, January 5, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04603007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-01-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Rodriguez, Estella Agramonte</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Mrs. Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Moran, Elida</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Frank</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-01-05">January 5, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04603007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, January 5, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests that Nogueira send him information regarding the Camp Lazear dedication. He wonders if Kean could receive the Finlay decoration posthumously. He also discusses a posthumous decoration for Carroll.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-01-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, January 5, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04603007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-01-05">January 5, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Please see the enclosed letters, particularly that to Doctor Recio and that<lb/>
to Senoritas Rojas and Cabrera.</p>
<p>I have been asked to make a formal presentation to the staff of the Mayo<lb/>
Clinic describing the dedication of Camp Lazear. I am very anxious to receive<lb/>
from you the sheet of paper on which I wrote the final arrangement for the<lb/>
names of those who placed the wreaths. I have no corrected copy giving me<lb/>
the order in which the wreaths were placed and the names of those who placed<lb/>
them. I am most anxious to have this and hope that you did not discard this<lb/>
paper. The newspapers do not give the correct arrangement of the names.<lb/>
Could you also tell me in what order the medallions were unveiled? I failed<lb/>
to make a note of this. I do know who unveiled them.</p>
<p>I am of course most anxious to have the films and to make some prints to be<lb/>
sent to the many interested Americans, especially the yellow fever personalities.<lb/>
Can you tell me when they might reach me? It is my understanding that you were<lb/>
having prints made for all of those in Havana who were interested, including<lb/>
Mr. Caswell, Doctor de Castro, Mrs. Moran, Senora Rojas, Estella Agramonte and<lb/>
so on and that I was to have prints made for the yellow fever personalities<lb/>
and the American Universities which sent wreaths.</p>
<p>I promised to send you, if at all possible, an actual copy of Doctor Agramonte's<lb/>
article published in 1915 in the SCIENTIFIC MONTHLY. I find that I gave my<lb/>
last extra copy to Senorita Cabrera. Perhaps she will lend it or give it to<lb/>
you until such time as I can replace it by hunting for old copies in this<lb/>
country; however this will not be an easy task.</p>
<p>I certainly enjoyed thoroughly my week with you in Cuba; it was a fine experience.<lb/>
I would appreciate it greatly if you would send me the order in which the speeches<lb/>
were given at the dedication and <unclear>in due time</unclear> of course I want a copy of your own<lb/>
talk. Don't bother to translate it into English if this is too much of a job.<lb/>
Juse send me a Spanish copy. Could you also send me the Havana addresses of<lb/>
Mr. Frank Finlay and Senora Delgado or her son? Her son is mentioned in the<lb/>
newspapers as Dr. Alberto Delgado. Is he a physician?</p>
<p>I have one slight regret. I wish somehow that General Kean could have received<lb/>
posthumously the Finlay decoration. Perhaps it is not too late to consider this.<lb/>
Do you think it could be done at the next meeting? He did so much for Reed. He<lb/>
was Reed's right-hand man as you know and he also did a good deal for Cuba as you<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04603008"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
January 5, 1953<lb/>
well know, not only along the lines of sanitation for the Army but when for<lb/>
months he was in charge, under General Wood, of all the civilian hospitals<lb/>
and charitable institutions of Cuba. His services were such that years ago<lb/>
the Cuban government hung his painting, which I think still hangs, in the<lb/>
Sanitary Department.</p>
<p>I shall send Carroll's son some information regarding the dedication of Camp<lb/>
Lazear. It is too bad he does not respond to you. If he shows any response,<lb/>
perhaps later the Cuban government will see fit to give Carroll a posthumous<lb/>
decoration. I would rather have it go posthumously to Carroll than to his son.</p>
<p>Summarizing my letter, I have made the following requests:<lb/><lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. The order in which the wreaths were placed and those who placed them.</item>
<item>2. The order of the unveiling.</item>
<item>3. The films.</item>
<item>4. The address of Frank Finlay.</item>
<item>5. The address of Senora Delgado</item>
<item>6. The address of Dr. Alberto Delgado and is he a physician?</item>
</list></p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
