<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04604003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Article: The Experiment with Yellow Fever, by Lena Warner, June 1902</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04604003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1902-06-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Havard, V.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Tate, Paul L.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1902-06-00">June 1902</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04604003</idno>
<title>Article: The Experiment with Yellow Fever, by Lena Warner, June 1902</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Warner's article describes her role in the yellow fever experiments and how to best care for yellow fever patients. An autograph note follows the text and calls the piece a "pure fabrication as to her part."</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1902-06-00">
<head>Article: The Experiment with Yellow Fever, by Lena Warner, June 1902</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04604003"/>
<p>THE EXPERIMENT WITH YELLOW FEVER</p>
<p>As our experiment with this disease has played such a prominent part before the<lb/>
medical world of today, and especially is of vital importance to us of the South, I<lb/>
shall endeavor to relate something of my contact with the work. I shall allude only<lb/>
to the practical side, as the scientific and theoretical phases have already been<lb/>
presented to you by my superior officers.</p>
<p>We fully realize, since our experiment, that the mosquito ranks high in economic<lb/>
importance; her absence from our environment is most desirable, not only as an ordinary<lb/>
pest, but since science has proved she is pestilential, and upon her narrow shoulders<lb/>
is placed the blame of causing, or at least transmitting two of the most widespread<lb/>
and dangerous diseases of tropical and semi-tropical climates.</p>
<p>In June of 1900, our Government sent to Columbia Barracks, U. S. Army Post,<lb/>
located at Quemados, Cuba, a board of medical officers for the purpose of pursuing<lb/>
scientific <unclear>investigation</unclear> with reference to the acute contagious diseases, with<lb/>
special interest in locating Icteroid X, an unknown germ supposed to be the cause of<lb/>
Yellow Fever. As this disease was prevalent among the soldiers, on July 10 I received<lb/>
orders from Major Havard to proceed to Columbia Barracks. Here began my first exper-<lb/>
ience in the detention camp.</p>
<p>In September, Major R. Jefferson Cain telephone me from headquarters, located<lb/>
at the Palace in Havana, that he had sent three officers and one Sergeant. En route<lb/>
to our detention camp at Post Columbia, they became ill, so ill they were compelled<lb/>
to stop at Las Animas, a Civil Hospital located at Havana. As there were no other<lb/>
Yellow Fever cases at Las Animas or no immune nurses, two immune hospital corps men<lb/>
were sent to care for the four cases. I called our Hospital Corps Sergeant to ap-<lb/>
point two corps men for study, as I was going to Las Animas and would take the two<lb/>
men with me in my ambulance. We remained there three days. Major William A. Gorgas,<lb/>
A. S. U. S. Army, was Chief of Staff and also Chief Sanitarian of the Island. While<lb/>
we were far better prepared to care for the four patients than in the detention camp,<lb/>
they did not recover. The Commission, Dr. Walter Reed, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, Dr. A.<lb/>
Agramonte and Dr. James Carroll, laboratory technician, were diligently searching for<lb/>
the cause of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>My first knowledge of the mosquito as the cause was passed on to me by Dr.<lb/>
Carroll, a member of the above-mentioned Commission, while ill. He informed me that<lb/>
a mosquito bite was the means of his contracting &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;. The record of that<lb/>
bears testimony: patient delirious, - although he had asked me to stop by the<lb/>
laboratory on my rounds and drop a small bit of ripe banana in a test tube contain-<lb/>
ing two mosquitoes, describing minutely just how the cotton was to be so lightly<lb/>
replaced to prevent their escape; because I had promised - and perhaps a bit curious,<lb/>
I found the exact location he had described the test bue containing two mosquitoes.<lb/>
Yes, I fed them.</p>
<p>All of the precautions usually observed to <unclear>prevent</unclear> the spread of contagion<lb/>
was resorted to; all bedding used by the patients was burned. The bonfires and<lb/>
weird scenes of 1878 in Memphis were vividly recalled; all clothing and bedding<lb/>
contacted by the patient was burned. In the meantime, the autopsies held by Drs.<lb/>
-1-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04604004"/>
Lazear and Carroll had greatly improved the treatment. It was through autopsy the<lb/>
cause of black vomit was found and no medicine was given or food. Perhaps I should<lb/>
give the treatment, as it was by far more effective than any previously attempted.<lb/>
The patient was kept perfectly quiet, not even allowed to raise his head. Water or<lb/>
lemonade was offered every hour; as he was usually thirsty it was seldom he was urged;<lb/>
a light covering was used. Temperature, respiration and pulse were taken every three<lb/>
hours and when up to 103&deg; a cold high enema was given (saline) and while this did not<lb/>
reduce temperature, it was quieting. (We had found that sponging or even ice packs<lb/>
had no effect upon the temperature.)</p>
<p>Every drop of urine was measured and sent twice daily to the laboratory and re-<lb/>
corded on the nurse's chart. As the temperature climbs the pulse slows down after<lb/>
the first 24 hours of the attack; the common duct conveying the bile to the small<lb/>
intestine becomes so clogged with the thickened bile it begins to disseminate through-<lb/>
out the system and the entire body assumes a pale yellow color, even the whites of the<lb/>
eyes; thus the bedside chart is the physicians' guide. The vacant stare usually de-<lb/>
tected in delirium with other fever cases is absent in yellow fever cases.</p>
<p>No food, solid or liquid or of any description, is given until the temperature<lb/>
drops to normal, which is usually on the 5th or 6th day. Nor does it rise in the<lb/>
afternoon. Feeding begins with one dram of milk diluted with one dram of water given<lb/>
every hour the first six hours, then gradually increased with milk and water decreased;<lb/>
as the milk is increased the hours are lengthened until 1/2 glass is given every three<lb/>
hours. After the third day, begin with light diet; on the 10th day the patient may<lb/>
be propped up in bed and then gradually allowed to become a normal human being.</p>
<p>Shortly after Carroll's recovery, Dr. Jessie W. Lazear was stricken, and gave his<lb/>
life for the cause of Science, as he wanted to make sure of how many days should pass<lb/>
after the Stegeomia (mosquito) had bitten a yellow fever patient before she became a<lb/>
carrier. He found it was 8 days. On the 3rd day after he had turned the test tube<lb/>
containing Mrs. Stegeomia down on the back of his hand, he had a rigor, and sat up<lb/>
all night writing down and outlining direct information and procedure of what he and<lb/>
Carroll had found concerning two species of the mosquitos they had found as carriers.<lb/>
I missed the doctor on my rounds and sent my orderly to see if he was in his quarters;<lb/>
Forbes returned saying he was ill and in bed and wished to speak to me. We returned<lb/>
to Dr. Lazear's quarters and found he had a temperature of 101. I suggested the litter<lb/>
bearers would take him over to the officers' tent, set apart for the Medical Corps.<lb/>
He asked me to carefully gather up the sheets of paper he had on the table and put<lb/>
them away as they were valuable and would be needed on his recovery; his request was<lb/>
complied with. The next day he had a severe hemorrhage of the stomach (Black Vomit)<lb/>
and died the 4th night of his attack. I passed the papers over to Major Reed the next<lb/>
day, not knowing the contents. Three days afterward, Reed called up our group and told<lb/>
us of their contents. It was on this occasion three of the Hospital Corps men volun-<lb/>
teered to be experimented on. Early in November the Flag was raised and our Detention<lb/>
Camp was called Camp Lazear, and Major Reed planned a careful and systematic method of<lb/>
inoculating non-immunes. At first a test was made to prove Yellow Fever was not con-<lb/>
tagious. Twenty non-immune men and Dr. Cook, 1st Lieutenant of the Medical Department,<lb/>
volunteered. They were carefully guarded night and day in a long frame building three<lb/>
weeks. On their cots were placed blankets and sheets that Yellow Fever patients had<lb/>
died on; coal oil stoves were burned to keep an even temperature of 100&deg; F. The pe-<lb/>
culiar odor of Yellow Fever caused by the bedding could be detected five yards from<lb/>
the building.</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04604005"/>
<p>Fourteen days and nights passed and not one man went down, - then the experiment<lb/>
with old Mrs. Stegeomia Mosquito began. Several of the men, who were in the contagious<lb/>
experiment, volunteered for the mosquito test; the entire number experimented on were<lb/>
97; each man was paid $200.00 for this test. As soon as the non-immune received his<lb/>
mosquito bite, he was assigned a cot in Camp Lazear Detention Hospital. A record of each<lb/>
case was kept; temperature and pulse recorded morning, noon and evening. Before the<lb/>
5th day, each man went down. As soon as we found a rise of temperature of 99&deg;, he was<lb/>
put to bed. Dr. Wm. A. Gorgas and Dr. Agramonte were called to assume charge of the<lb/>
cases. They visited each case separately and each diagnosing it Yellow Fever. Not one<lb/>
case had Black Vomit, because previous treatments proved it could be eliminated. Other<lb/>
symptoms were identical; prognosis most favorable; the heart, kidneys and stomach are<lb/>
the chief organs attacked in this disease.</p>
<p>The third test made was by drawing with hypodermic needle one drop of blood from<lb/>
a person ill with Yellow Fever, and diluting it with one drop of water and injecting<lb/>
one-half of this mixture in the arm of a non-immune. The same results would follow<lb/>
as from the mosquito bite: a typical case of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>I am glad to state not one of those experimented upon died. Some of the 97 were<lb/>
Americans, some of them were immigrants just arriving on the Island, and three of them<lb/>
were volunteers from the Hospital Corps.</p>
<p>The Culex Fascitaus Stegeomia was found prevalent on the Island in certain loca-<lb/>
tions. She is quite timid and rarely bites one. At night she is most active. She<lb/>
intuitively realizes her eggs will not be fertile unless she draws blood from man or<lb/>
beast. We reared our own supply in the laboratory and they were harmless with their<lb/>
bite until we conveyed them to the bedside of a Yellow Fever subject and she had<lb/>
bitten him. We would carefully return her into the test tube, the same tube we carried<lb/>
her there in. She does not enjoy a long life; our oldest female lived 90 days, and<lb/>
during her life she bit six non-immunes and before the 5th day each one of them came<lb/>
down with the disease. The time lapsing after biting a fever patient before she could<lb/>
inoculate a non-immune was determined between 8 and 10 days.</p>
<p>In the meantime, Dr. Wm. A. Gorgas, Chief Sanitarian of the Island, had not been<lb/>
idle by any means. Yes, the little Island was being cleaned up, mosquitoes included.<lb/>
Many, many thousands of gallons of coal oil were used in localities where mosquitoes<lb/>
were found to destroy their eggs or larva. Every cot in Columbia Post Hospital was<lb/>
screened and every patient sent to this Hospital, placed in the Ward with other<lb/>
patients; though carefully screened off, they proved to have Yellow Fever. The<lb/>
Supervising Nurse in the Ward was Miss May Rose Holmes of Memphis, Tennessee. She<lb/>
was a non-immune, as were also the Hospital Corps men, who were her assistants. Not<lb/>
one of them ever contracted the disease. The Army Engineering Corps had located the<lb/>
Hospital on rather a high location, and there were no mosquitoes to pester the sick<lb/>
up there; our only mosquitoes were those we reared in the laboratory.</p>
<p>The adult Cubans living in Havana were immunes; some of the Cubans coming from<lb/>
different sections of the Island were stricken soon after their arrival. We inferred<lb/>
this was why Yellow Fever was never declared epidemic in Havana, as only visitors and<lb/>
foreigners were attacked and, too, it was more prevalent among the lower class.</p>
<p>From March, 1901, to March, 1902, the only cases I saw were those from our own<lb/>
experiments.</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<pb n="4" id="f04604006"/>
<p>During the summer of 1901, a party of gentlemen appeared in Havana claiming<lb/>
to have a <unclear>sure</unclear> cure; that by some process of injecting a certain fluid they had<lb/>
patented in the arm of a non-immune, they could not contract Yellow Fever. I was<lb/>
informed that two people, one man and one woman, let these gentlemen experiment on<lb/>
them. I did not witness this so-called experiment, as it was held at Las Animas,<lb/>
a Civil Hospital in Havana. Both victims died. On the first vessel sailing for<lb/>
New York the two so-called scientists were passengers.</p>
<p>(Read before Shelby County Medical Society June, 1902; en route to<lb/>
U. S. Army Hospital at presidio, San Francisco, California)</p>
<closer>
<signed>Lena A. Warner<lb/>
Chief Nurse<lb/>
U. S. Army Nurse Corps</signed>
<del>9/11/<unclear>47</unclear><lb/>
A pure fabrication <unclear>as</unclear> to her part,-<lb/>
a series of falsehoods &amp; mistakes with<lb/>
only a small <unclear>foundation</unclear> of fact - These<lb/>
facts twisted out of all <unclear>proportion</unclear><lb/>
to actual <unclear>happenings</unclear>. She wrongfully<lb/>
describes <unclear>places</unclear> she <unclear></unclear> never saw, - <unclear>things</unclear><lb/>
that never happened that way, - in <unclear>fact</unclear><lb/>
a general <unclear>mix - up</unclear> <unclear>of</unclear> in every <unclear>detail</unclear><lb/>
of what actually <unclear>occured</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Tate</unclear><lb/>
Please <unclear>return this</unclear></del><lb/>
-4-<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
