<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04603017">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Translation [from Spanish] of speech by Alberto Recio for the inauguration of Parque Lazear in Cuba, December 3, 1952</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04603017</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1952-12-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Fernandez, Nicanor</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Martinez, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Macia, Adrian</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Julian</name>
<name type="person">Ruiz, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Rodriguez Exposito, Cesar</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Orue, Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Meitin, Antonio Garcia</name>
<name type="person">Gonzalez Garrido, Eladio</name>
<name type="person">Gonzalez Garrido, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Boada, Fernando</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Louise</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Margaret Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Mrs. Claudio</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">San Jose farm, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1952-12-03">December 3, 1952</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04603017</idno>
<title>Translation [from Spanish] of speech by Alberto Recio for the inauguration of Parque Lazear in Cuba, December 3, 1952</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Recio' speech details the experiments of the Yellow Fever Commission at Camp Lazear and praises Finlay for first proposing the mosquito theory. He describes Hench's research and the actions taken by the Board of Patrons in creating the memorial.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1952-12-03">
<head>Translation [from Spanish] of speech by Alberto Recio for the inauguration of Parque Lazear in Cuba, December 3, 1952</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04603017"/>
<p>Traduccion de Frank Finlay</p>
<p>Speech delivered by Dr. Alberto Recio, upon the inauguration of<lb/>
&ldquo;Parque Lazear&rdquo; in Marianao, Havana, Cuba.</p>
<p>_______</p>
<p>Mr. Minister of Health and Social Assistance,<lb/>
Authorities, Distinguished guests,<lb/>
Ladies and Gentlemen:</p>
<p>Fifty two years ago, inside of that hut and another one like<lb/>
it opposite to it, 50 meters away and which has since disappeared,<lb/>
the experiments were carried out which confirmed, once and for all,<lb/>
the discovery of our genial Dr. Carlos J. Finlay, regarding the<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever, which he had proclaimed since 1881,<lb/>
which event may be considered, by its results, as one of the most<lb/>
important in the American Continent since it was colonized.</p>
<p>That it why we Cubans have decided to preserve this relic and<lb/>
take care of this corner for History and perpetuate in bronze the<lb/>
names of the clorious leaders of that campaign.</p>
<p>I shall give you a brief summary of the events:</p>
<p>It was during the year 1900; our War of Independence was over;<lb/>
the United States' Army had occupied the Island provisionally and,<lb/>
after overcoming the Spaniards, it continued to suffer the ravages<lb/>
in its ranks from the most terrible of foes: The Black Vomit.</p>
<p>The Military Governor, Major General Leonard Wood, whom the<lb/>
cubans will never forget after his marvelous conduct as Governor,<lb/>
who was also a physician, Major Jefferson Kean, Chief of Sanitation<lb/>
of the military camp established at Columbia. Major William Gorgas,<lb/>
Director of Sanitation Of Havana with his American and Cuban assist-<lb/>
ants, were all disconcerted because, after submitting Havana, with<lb/>
heavy expenditure, to the most thorough sanitation which could be<lb/>
carried out in any city, they found yellow fever causing panic, by<lb/>
venting its fury upon soldiers and officers alike, reaching even<lb/>
the very Chief of Sanitation, Major Kean, who suffered a serious<lb/>
attack.</p>
<p>The U.S. Government, naturally alarmed by the news from Cuba,<lb/>
then named an Army Medical Commission for the study of tropical dis-<lb/>
eases, especially yellow fever.</p>
<p>The Commission was composed of Drs. James Lazear, James Carroll,<lb/>
and Aristides Agramonte, physicians who had come over with the Army<lb/>
and, to preside it Dr. Walter Reed was sent, who was an eminent bac-<lb/>
teriologist.</p>
<p>The Commission commenced its labors towards the end of June and<lb/>
spent all the month of July in bacteriological studies, without<lb/>
arriving at any practical results of any importance at all.</p>
<p>Frankly nonplussed, they decided to look into the ideas of<lb/>
Finlay, who had come to Cuba with them in 1898, enlisted in the<lb/>
Army and who always harped among his companions upon the necessity<lb/>
of fighting the mosquito in order to fight yellow fever.</p>
<p>They had an interview with the genius, who explained his ex-<lb/>
periences in detail and gave them some eggs of the proper kind of<lb/>
mosquito which he indicted as the transmitting agent of yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>Reed went to Washington, Carrol and Agramonte finished the<lb/>
bacteriological studies, the failure of which we already referred<lb/>
to, and Jess Lazear, expert in malaria and in mosquitoes, started<lb/>
the experiments in transmission with the insects obtained from<lb/>
the eggs furnished by Finlay.</p>
<p>He infected a good many of these mosquitoes, making them bite<lb/>
patients at Las Animas Hospital and between August 11th and the 25th,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04603018"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
he applied these mosquitoes which were infected to nine soldiers<lb/>
who volunteered to submit to the tests and let himself be bitten<lb/>
as well.</p>
<p>All of them proved impervious to this inicial test, which<lb/>
turned out to be negative.</p>
<p>In a second attempt, on August 27th, Dr. Carroll and private<lb/>
Dean, who laughed at the experiments, were bitten by the same<lb/>
mosquitoes which were used in the first test. Several days later<lb/>
they were all seriously ill with yellow fever.</p>
<p>Now Dr. Lazear continued his work with more interest and,<lb/>
on September 18th. he felt seriously ill and died on the 25th.<lb/>
In the official report it was stated that days before his first<lb/>
symptoms appeared he had been bitten by one of the mosquitoes<lb/>
which flew away in the Hospital during the first experiments.<lb/>
Extra officially, Dr. Hench seems to have proved that Dr. Lazear<lb/>
deliberately let himself be bitten by one of these infected in-<lb/>
sects.</p>
<p>When Reed heard of the tragedy and greatly affected by his<lb/>
companion's death, he returned to Havana deeply thoughtful.</p>
<p>Why was it that the first nine attempts at inoculation had<lb/>
failed, while Dr. Carroll and private Dean were contaminated by<lb/>
the very same mosquitoes which had been used for the first test.</p>
<p>Could they not have been infected, these last cases as well<lb/>
as Dr, Lazear himself, in some other way? The key to the enigmas<lb/>
was found by Reed, according to Dr. Hench, in a small book of<lb/>
minutes found in the pocket of the dead companion by Dr. Amos, a<lb/>
military physician, Chief of the Military Hospital, in which the<lb/>
dates were noted on which the mosquitoes were infected and the<lb/>
days of illness of the patients to whom they had been applied, as<lb/>
well as the dates upon which the healthy subjects had been bitten.</p>
<p>It seemed likely that the mosquitoes were infected when they<lb/>
bit the sick patients during their first three days' illness and<lb/>
became infectious at least 12 days later.</p>
<p>But these concepts had to be proved incontrovertibly and, with<lb/>
this in view Reed, shrewd investigator, and his colaborators, drew<lb/>
up a plan of tests.</p>
<p>When the latter was approved by General wood and funds were<lb/>
provided to enable the Commission to carry it out, they selected<lb/>
this spot in &ldquo;San Jos&eacute;&rdquo; farm, which had been used by the Jesuit<lb/>
rathers to acclimatize priets who had just arrived, because there<lb/>
had never been a case of yellow fever in the place, which Finlay<lb/>
attributed to the absence of the Culex mosquito and also because<lb/>
he had carried out many inoculations of Jesuit Fathers on the spot.</p>
<p>Two huts were built: the one we have before us, designated as<lb/>
Hut No. 1 or the &ldquo;Hut of Vomits,&rdquo; purposely designed with poor ventil-<lb/>
ation, since the windows face the South, against the breeze.</p>
<p>The other one, more comfortable, was built in front of it,<lb/>
with a window to the North, designated as Hut No. 2 or the &ldquo;Mosquito<lb/>
Hut&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The two of them constituted &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;, named after the<lb/>
fallen comrade, to whom we also wish to offer homage, proposing<lb/>
the name of &ldquo;Parque Lazear&rdquo;.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04603019"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>Into Hut No. 1, three beds were taken, one table, three chairs<lb/>
and a coal stove to keep the climate torrid. The beds were laid<lb/>
with smelly sheets and pillows, soiled with the perspiration and<lb/>
dejections of yellow fever patients at Las Animas Hospital. Also<lb/>
infected clothes were strewn along the corners of the hut, for the<lb/>
volunteers to handle. For several nights trying to sleep they<lb/>
stayed, Dr. Robert Cooke and privates Folk, Jernegan, Westherwalks,<lb/>
Hildebrand England and John Hamberry, who is the last survivor.</p>
<p>None of these unselfish volunteers contracted yellow fever.<lb/>
The disease evidently was not acquired by contacting dejections<lb/>
from the sick.</p>
<p>Hut No. 2 was divided into two compartments, separated only<lb/>
by fine wire netting, which the mosquitoes could not penetrate.<lb/>
In one of these compartments 15 mosquitoes were loosed, which had<lb/>
bitten sick patients at the Hospital more than twelve days before,<lb/>
In the other one mosquitoes were kept out.</p>
<p>On condition of not receiving any remuneration whatever, two<lb/>
privates, John R. Kissinger and John J. Moran offered themselves<lb/>
generously for the tests.</p>
<p>Both of them stayed for an hour in the mosquito compartment<lb/>
and were bitten several times. Both were seriously ill with yellow<lb/>
fever several days later.</p>
<p>They were followed by other volunteers, spanish and american,<lb/>
who were also bitten and contracted yellow fever in more or less<lb/>
severe forms. Their names also deserve to be kept on record.<lb/>
They were Fresedo, Benigno, Fernandez, Martinez, Jernegan, Olson,<lb/>
Folk, Forbes, Andrus, Sontag and Hamberry.</p>
<p>In the adjoining compartment, free of mosquitoes, some of these<lb/>
and other volunteers spent nights, without falling ill.</p>
<p>The Commission, which continued making experiments, acquired a<lb/>
series of valuable data for the control of yellow fever; and the<lb/>
transmission of the disease through the Culex mosquito was then<lb/>
absolutely and decisively proven. From then on, the means proposed<lb/>
by Finlay for many years, i.e.: preventing patients from being<lb/>
bitten by mosquitoes and destroying these before they could attack<lb/>
healthy persons, were to be the weapons which mainly led to the enemy's<lb/>
defeat.</p>
<p>Bringing these weapons into action, with a thousand ingenious<lb/>
methods, Gorgas, Finlay and Guiteras and their efficient colaborators,<lb/>
cuband and americans, in merely three months they stamped yellow fever<lb/>
out of Havana first and the rest of the Island afterwards, after a<lb/>
losing struggle of over 200 years had been waged.</p>
<p>Likewise, in a short time the scourge was vanquished in all<lb/>
large cities of the Continent and Gorgas was able, thsough sani-<lb/>
tation, to cover himself with glory permiting the conclusion of<lb/>
the works of the Panama Canal, where the french had failed, main-<lb/>
ly due to yellow fever. And a new era was started in vast regions<lb/>
of the World's Tropical Zone, previously forbidden to civilization.</p>
<p>It is to Dr. Phillip Hench, of the famous Mayo Clinic, that we<lb/>
undoubtedly owe the localizing of this Hut. Being very much inter-<lb/>
ested in these doings and seeking for the real truth to be able to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04603020"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
to be fair to those who merited honor and name the the exact<lb/>
persons who should be remembered by posterity, he delved into<lb/>
Archives and Libraries, examined articles and photographs,<lb/>
interviewed eye witnesses and amply documented came to Havana<lb/>
to continue his investigations on the very field upon which<lb/>
the battle had been fought.</p>
<p>While researching, in 1941, he found San Jose farm, then<lb/>
belonging to Sr. Adrian Maci&aacute; and, using original photographs<lb/>
and the testimony of John Moran, who was one of the experimental<lb/>
cases and who lived in Cuba until he died, Dr. Hench identified<lb/>
what remained of Camp Lazear, represented by Hut No. 1 which, bad-<lb/>
ly damaged, had been lived in for years first by Sr. Julian Zun-<lb/>
zunegui with his family and later by Sr. Juan Ruiz, to whom we<lb/>
surely owe the fact that it was not entirely destroyed.</p>
<p>The discovery was made public by Dr. Hench in 1941, in his<lb/>
Article &ldquo;Conquistadores de la Fiebre Amarilla&rdquo;, in which events<lb/>
are described with the greatest precision.</p>
<p>In 1942, while General Batista was presiding the Republic,<lb/>
at the suggestion of Dr. Sergio Garcia Marruz, Minister of Health<lb/>
and Social Assistance, at the time, the President in a message,<lb/>
asked Congress to declare the Hut a National Monument, without<lb/>
receiving any attention from either house.</p>
<p>It was only in 1945 that Dr. Jose R. Andreu, then Minister of<lb/>
Health, obtained said declaration by a resolution of the Council<lb/>
and the care of this place, to avoid its destruction, was entrusted<lb/>
to the National Board of Archeology and Etnology, until it could<lb/>
be properly honored.</p>
<p>Considering that the proper moment had arrived, another<lb/>
Minister, Dr. Carlos Ramirez Corr&iacute;a, in a brilliant ceremony,<lb/>
laid the corner stone for the monument, but the work remained<lb/>
with speeches and good intentions.</p>
<p>At last, in 1951, when Dr. Andreu was again Minister, he pushed<lb/>
the matter further, dictating Resolution No. 203, creating the Board<lb/>
of Patrons for the maintenance of the Hut, endowing it with $25.000.<lb/>
authorized by the President of the Republic at the time, Dr. Carlos<lb/>
Prio Socarr&aacute;s.</p>
<p>I had the honor of being named President of the Board of<lb/>
Patrons, with magnificent colaborators, such as:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Secretary: Sr. Cesar Rodriguez Exp&oacute;sito</item>
<item>Treasurer: Dr. Pedro Nogueira</item>
<item>Members: Dr. Gustavo Cabarrouy and Sr. Francisco <unclear>Orue</unclear> Gonzalez</item>
<item>Architects: Sr. Antonio Garcia Meitia Sr. Eladio Gonzalez Garrido</item>
</list></p>
<p>The Board of Patrons believes that its task has been properly<lb/>
carried out, inaugurating Parque Lazear today, on the same spot on<lb/>
which Camp Lazear existed, as modest as the means available for it,<lb/>
but great in its significance and rendering full account in a report<lb/>
to the Minister of Health and Social Assistance.</p>
<p>We cannot fail now to express our gratitude in behalf of the<lb/>
Board of Patrons and of all those who are interested in our country's<lb/>
History to those who helped us in our effort, amongst which stand<lb/>
out Dr. Jos&eacute; R. Andreu, enthusiastic over the idea and who obtained<lb/>
the economic backing indispensable for the job; the brothers Eladio<lb/>
snd Ju&aacute;n Gonzalez Garrido, owners of the San Jos&eacute; farm, who gave up<lb/>
7.076,80 meters of land occupied by the park.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f04603021"/>
<p>- 5 -</p>
<p>Also the Notary Public, Dr. Antonio Millas Hernandez, before whom<lb/>
the deed of grant was gratuitously signed. The Public Registrar of<lb/>
Marianao, Dr. Manuel de Ferragut, for having inscribed the titles<lb/>
in his Registry free of charge. The sculptor Sr. Fernando Boada,<lb/>
for his excellent interpretation on the reliefs. Dr. Gustavo Adolfo<lb/>
Bock, the irreplaceable Director of the Civic Military Institute of<lb/>
Ceiba del Agua, whose pupils cast the bronzes which adorn the murals.<lb/>
Sr. Francisco Orue, Mayor of Marianao, by his valuable cooperation<lb/>
in the leveling and embellishment of the land.</p>
<p>We also express our thanks to all those who honor this act with<lb/>
their presence, very especially to Miss. Louise B. Wood, Miss Ames,<lb/>
Miss Reed, Miss Huston Lazear, to Dr. Delgado's widow and to Mr.<lb/>
Frank Finlay, descendants of exalted worthies to whom humanity owes<lb/>
so much.</p>
<p>And thanks to you, Minister of Health and Social Assistance,<lb/>
who, setting an example that dignifies the Government which you<lb/>
represent, have encouraged the good iniciatives of your predecessors<lb/>
attending this ceremony to honor it with your presence.</p>
<p>Havana, December 3rd, 1952</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
