<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04619007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lydia Cabrera, November 6, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04619007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-11-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Cabrera, Lydia</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Spies, Tom D.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Smith, Louise F.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-11-06">November 6, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04619007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lydia Cabrera, November 6, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Rojas and Cabrera for helping him to receive another honor in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-11-06">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lydia Cabrera, November 6, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04619007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-11-06">November 6, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Miss Lidia Cabrera<lb/>
Quinta San Jose<lb/>
Calzada Real<lb/>
Marianao, Havana<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Lidia:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Permit me to thank you very much indeed for your interesting and ex-<lb/>
citing letter of November 3. My hat is off to you, Lidia, and Tina. I<lb/>
never in the world thought you would accomplish this. Having been honored<lb/>
so graciously a year or two ago by my Cuban friends, it was difficult for<lb/>
me to understand the propriety or envisage the possibility of another<lb/>
honor this year. Nevertheless you very kind friends have accomplished it<lb/>
and I am deeply grateful and of course quite flattered.</p>
<p>Actually, I have heard nothing about it and have not received any official<lb/>
communication. Of course until I do receive some sort of a communication<lb/>
there is nothing for me to do and I wonder whether the officials concerned<lb/>
with this honor will notify me in time to accept Mrs. Smith's invitation or<lb/>
will see fit to present the honor at the time of Mrs. Smith's intended<lb/>
meeting. I must wait to hear more from you about this.</p>
<p>If you could send me one or two of the Havana papers, that would be most<lb/>
interesting and perhaps that will give me some information that will<lb/>
help me decide the matter. Frankly, I am delighted that if there is to be<lb/>
a presentation it will not be this next month. I am so swamped at the<lb/>
moment. As far as January is concerned, I have already accepted an in-<lb/>
vitation in Colorado Springs for January 22 and 23 and Mary had planned<lb/>
to go with me. This would not preclude my getting to Havana for the 25th<lb/>
if that were the best time; however I fear that I could not come to Havana twice<lb/>
in 1954, once for the nutrition meeting and on some other occasion for the<lb/>
decoration. Not that I wouldn't like to but because I have accepted already<lb/>
several unavoidable obligations for 1954.</p>
<p>It would be of course a great pleasure and honor to receive the Cross from<lb/>
President Batista but again, whether that is the way it shall be done, I<lb/>
have no knowledge and must wait for more information from you or official<lb/>
information from others. As for official communications, I wonder if those<lb/>
empowered to send such a communication to me may not do the same as hap-<lb/>
pened with regard to the Finlay Decoration. You will remember that I re-<lb/>
ceived no information it and naturally missed the ceremony on December 3,<lb/>
1951. It was only by the accident of my being there during a medical meeting<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04619008"/>
Miss Lidia Cabrera<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 6, 1953<lb/>
in January 1952, when someone said &ldquo;We are so sorry you couldn't be here<lb/>
for the decoration last month.&rdquo; But even if I never receive any official<lb/>
communication, let me assure you that I shall never forget the kindness<lb/>
of you and Tina in this matter. You are certainly loyal friends and honor<lb/>
me far beyond my <unclear>deserts</unclear>.</p>
<p>One more word: I am not quite certain what Mrs. Smith means by celebrating<lb/>
&ldquo;Nutrition Week&rdquo;. Are she and Doctor Spies putting on another clinic like<lb/>
the one that I attended in January 1952? As I told Doctor Spies at that<lb/>
time, I am distinctly not a nutritionist but they were kind enough to in-<lb/>
vite me anyhow.</p>
<p>Thank you for your interest in my little write-up of the Greenville rescue<lb/>
but do not let my word picture of the storm deter you and Tina from the<lb/>
joys of ocean travel.</p>
<p>Mary and I both send you our love,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
