<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04610007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, May 18, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04610007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-05-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Lawrence] Walter L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Blossom] Emilie M.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Peggy Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-05-18">May 18, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04610007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, May 18, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses the awarding of Finlay Medals to various yellow fever experiment participants.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-05-18">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, May 18, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04610007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-05-18">May 18, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I certainly appreciate greatly the photographs and films. I will keep them<lb/>
safely here and will make copies for the various American yellow fever per-<lb/>
sonalities.</p>
<p>I am glad to know that you are going to the meeting of the American Medi-<lb/>
cal Association in New York. I regret that I cannot go but my Colleagues,<lb/>
Drs. Slocumb and Ward will be attending the meeting of the American<lb/>
Rheumatism Association which will be the Friday and Saturday before the<lb/>
meeting of the American Medical Association, May 29 and 30, in the Sert<lb/>
Room at the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. You will be very welcome to attend<lb/>
these meetings if you care to do so. Doctor Ward or Doctor Slocumb will<lb/>
be presenting another summary of our own work.</p>
<p>It will be certainly fine if the Cuban Government would allow you to visit<lb/>
around and present in person the Finlay Medals. I know that the recipients<lb/>
were so pleased and one or two of them have inquired from me further. I have<lb/>
written the enclosed note to Mr. Rodriguez. As you suggest, I have said<lb/>
nothing of your excellent suggestion. It is a matter of fact that General<lb/>
Truby, Mr. Lambert and Mr. Hanberry are all getting along in years. They<lb/>
have written me wondering when they might hear further. Because of the<lb/>
passing of time, I am making the following suggestion, not knowing whether<lb/>
it can be carried out.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. General Reed and Blossom Reed - these could be presented by you with the<lb/>
help of the Cuban Embassy in Washington but Blossom lives 90 miles from<lb/>
Washington and would have to know a few days ahead of time in order to be<lb/>
there for the ceremony. That would certainly be enough.</item>
<item>2. Henberry - did you plan to visit his home?</item>
<item>3. Dr. Cooke - did you plan to visit his home to present the posthumous<lb/>
award to his widow and family?</item>
<item><p>4. Lambert. His address is 17092 Lincoln Street, Hazel Crest, Illinois, a<lb/>
suburb of Chicago. I had an idea. Would you prefer to have Lambert come to<lb/>
the office of the Cuban Consul and do the matter simply there, or would<lb/>
you like to have a little more of a ceremony which would bring more favorable<lb/>
notice both to the recipient and to the giver, the Cuban Government. It<lb/>
occurred to me that I have medical friends in Chicago (you may well have<lb/>
also) at several hospitals and at both the University of Chicago and North-<lb/>
western University Medical Schools. I am making an inquiry as to whether<lb/>
there is a medical historical society in Chicago. There may well be but<lb/>
of course the meeting of the A.M.A. is not in Chicago.</p>
<p>The ceremony might be a (1) very simple one at the Cuban consulate in Chicago<lb/>
or (2) a simple one at the office of the American Medical Association (I<lb/>
think they would be interested in it) or (3) a simple ceremony arranged to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04610008"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
May 18, 1953<lb/>
be held at one of the medical schools or hospitals, the staff of the hos-<lb/>
pital or the students of the medical school being invited. I know the<lb/>
Professor of Medicine at <unclear>Northern</unclear> University. I have no idea how he would<lb/>
react to the proposal but it seems to me that any medical school would<lb/>
enjoy participating in such a ceremony. The participation could be simple<lb/>
without much elaboration. I will not do anything about contacting the<lb/>
A.M.A. or friends in Chicago until I hear from you but it may be that the<lb/>
Cuban Consul General in Chicago would have to be consulted. You would<lb/>
know more about that than I.</p></item>
<item>5. General Truby and the Lazears in California. General Truby could not<lb/>
go to Chicago or New York but Mrs. Briggs (Peggy Lazear) and General Truby<lb/>
could receive the medal at an official ceremony either in General Truby's<lb/>
home or perhaps at the Letterman Army Hospital where General Truby was<lb/>
commanding officer. Certainly that would be a nice thing if they would<lb/>
agree to it. Houston Lazear lives at Santa Barbara, California. He and<lb/>
his wife are rather quiet and while they would tremendously appreciate<lb/>
the honor, I doubt if they would go the whole way to San Francisco for<lb/>
the ceremony. Perhaps they would. I must not speak for them.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Let me know any way I can help.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
Copy sent to General Truby<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
