<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04619009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, November 7, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04619009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-11-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Spies, Tom D.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Smith, Louise F.</name>
<name type="person">Cespedes, Carlos Manuel</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-11-07">November 7, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04619009</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, November 7, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Spies that he has heard that he, Hench, has been nominated for the decoration of Carlos Manuel de Cespedes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-11-07">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Tom D. Spies, November 7, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04619009"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-11-07">November 7, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Tom D. Spies<lb/>
Nutrition Clinic<lb/>
Hillman Hospital<lb/>
Birmingham, Alabama<lb/>
<salute>My dear Tom:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just heard from Lidia Cabrera, one of my yellow fever friends in<lb/>
Havana that my &ldquo;nomination&rdquo; for the honor &ldquo;Gran Oficial de <unclear>laBenemerita</unclear> Orden<lb/>
de Carlos Manuel de Cespedes,&rdquo; was published in the Havana newspapers.<lb/>
She &ldquo;supposed&rdquo; that I might have received already the official communication<lb/>
but I have heard nothing. This is all news to me and I strongly suspect<lb/>
that I may never hear anything or that an official communication may find<lb/>
its way to me something like that for the Finlay medal. You will remember<lb/>
that thanks to you and a few others, I was supposed to have received that<lb/>
honor on December 3, 1951 but never did hear from anybody and only learned<lb/>
of it by accident from Mrs. Smith, I believe, when I attended your meeting.</p>
<p>Now, obviously, these yellow fever frields of mine, Tina Rojas and Lidia<lb/>
Cabrera, have had considerable to do with this latest honor and they seem<lb/>
to have hopes that it might be conferred on Finlay day but Lidia now<lb/>
speaks about the possibility that I might go to Havana to help Mrs. Smith<lb/>
&ldquo;celebrate the Nutrition Week&rdquo; and be there perhaps around January 25 to 28.</p>
<p>I strongly suspect from this last suggestion that you, my dear friend, have<lb/>
also had a hand in all of this and have, for your own <unclear>purposed</unclear>, chosen not<lb/>
to say anything until the matter went through. Certainly if there is any<lb/>
Nutrition Week it would be nothing without you being in charge. Lidia's<lb/>
letter is a most informal one and her suggestions are posed as merely pre-<lb/>
liminary thinking and planning. It is all so vague and uncertain that there<lb/>
is little or nothing that I can do or say, nor is it definite for me to ac-<lb/>
cept anything but I just wanted you to know, first of all, that I have just<lb/>
today had the first news from Havana. Secondly, I always like to visit<lb/>
Havana and see my good friends there and especially if you are there to<lb/>
help with the celebration. However, as I told you before, I am not a<lb/>
nutritionist and am not sure whether my presence during that week would<lb/>
be appropriate. Nevertheless we have some ideas regarding the use of cor-<lb/>
tisone, etc., that are a distinct advance over those of two years ago and<lb/>
if an invitation were forthcoming, I could doubtless work up something,<lb/>
especially if publication were not required or if my hosts would be lenient<lb/>
if publication were required. As a new regent of the American College<lb/>
of Physicians, I have accepted the obligation to speak in Colorado Springs<lb/>
January 22 and 23 but if the suggestion from Havana becomes definite, I see<lb/>
no particular reason why Mary and I couldn't get to Havana by the 25th.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04619010"/>
<p>Dr. Tom D. Spies</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>November 7, 1953</p>
<p>Now this may be all news to you as much as it is to me (though I doubt it).<lb/>
If it is, please accept it as confidential information. All I can do is<lb/>
to wait for some further news and instructions from my wonderful friends<lb/>
in havana and in this country.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
