<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t04620004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George E. Armstrong, December 10, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04620004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-12-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Armstrong, George E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Streit, Paul H.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Presno, Jose A.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-12-10">December 10, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04620004</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George E. Armstrong, December 10, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench explains why he has not yet written his book on yellow fever. The delay is the result of the discovery of the Lazear notebook and his desire to learn more about Finlay.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-12-10">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George E. Armstrong, December 10, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04620004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-12-10">December 10, 1953</date>
</dateline>
General George Armstrong<lb/>
The Surgeon General<lb/>
Department of the Army<lb/>
Washington 25, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Armstrong:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I believe you are aware of the interest I have had in the work of the<lb/>
Army's Yellow Fever Commission and the steps that were taken to<lb/>
memorialize Walter Reed's Camp Lazear in Havana. It was too bad you<lb/>
couldn't attend the dedication ceremonies last year and we missed your<lb/>
deputy, General Streit, whose flight was cancelled by bad weather.<lb/>
My book on the whole subject is held up only by two things: (1) My<lb/>
continued search for the missing and all-important Lazear notebook<lb/>
(but I have a hot lead on this now) and (2) my need to know more about<lb/>
Finlay. You know my opinion that, as the Cubans have been very un-<lb/>
fair and don't know much about Reed and his colleagues, so we<lb/>
Americans don't know nearly enough about Finlay.</p>
<p>Two years ago, through the help of that energetic young Cuban, Dr.<lb/>
Pedro Nogueira, I ran across a gold mine, several volumes of Finlay's<lb/>
own day-book or diary. Years ago they were given to the Library of<lb/>
the Academy of Sciences and were promptly forgotten. Doctor Nogueira<lb/>
and the librarian told me that only two or three men had ever looked<lb/>
at the books over a period of many years. Doctor Finlay's own (non-<lb/>
medical) son told me that he did not even know they existed. Doctor<lb/>
Nogueira, living in Havana, has the opportunity of studying them at<lb/>
whatever leisure he may have for the purposes of his own book, but as<lb/>
there are about eight volumes, I think, and as the handwriting is<lb/>
mostly in Spanish, with some in German and a very little in English,<lb/>
it has been impossible for me to scratch the surface in the few hours<lb/>
I have been able to give to them in Havana.</p>
<p>Two years ago it was my earnest hope that I would be allowed to pay<lb/>
the cost of microfilming these eight or nine volumes. At the usual<lb/>
cost of about one cent or so a page, I figured that it would not cost<lb/>
more than perhaps $75 to microfilm everything. I made a proposition<lb/>
to Dr. Jose Presno, the distinguished old Cuban physician who is the<lb/>
president of everything down there and has been President of the<lb/>
Academy of Sciences. The proposition was that if the Library would<lb/>
lend me the books, I would bring them here to the Mayo Clinic Library<lb/>
or to the Surgeon General's Library and have three microfilms made,<lb/>
one for myself, one for the Surgeon General's Library and one for their<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04620005"/>
General George Armstrong<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
December 10, 1953<lb/>
own library in Havana, which they should have in case anything happens<lb/>
to the books. I told Doctor Presno that I would pay for these three<lb/>
films. To my delight, he momentarily agreed. I was to leave Havana<lb/>
by plane the next day and, knowing how precious these volumes were, I<lb/>
bought a special container. Doctor Nogueira and I were to meet Doctor<lb/>
Presno at 10 a.m. for the delivery of the books and my plane was to<lb/>
leave at noon, but alas, no Doctor Presno. After a frantic hour of<lb/>
telephoning, we found that he had casually mentioned his intentions<lb/>
the night before to one of the councillors of the Academy. The latter,<lb/>
knowing nothing about my intentions or integrity, alarmed Doctor Presno<lb/>
by telling him that he should by no means permit anyone to take the<lb/>
volumes away from the Library. So I left Havana sad and disappointed,<lb/>
particularly because there was no way to have them microfilmed in<lb/>
Havana and it would have cost several hundred dollars to have them<lb/>
photostated at 75 cents a page.</p>
<p>Last year, the Cuban Government chose to honor me and give me a Cuban<lb/>
decoration. During the ceremonies at the Academy of Science, I reminded<lb/>
Doctor Presno of this matter and he said that he was quite willing for<lb/>
me and the Surgeon General's Library to have a microfilm but that it<lb/>
could now be done in Havana. He suggested that if he received an of-<lb/>
ficial request from you he thought he would be able to grant the re-<lb/>
quest and suggested that I be the intermediary.</p>
<p>General Armstrong, I am sure that the historians of the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Library are almost as anxious as I am to have available this invaluable<lb/>
source of material about the man whose preliminary work was absolutely<lb/>
vital to the success of the Army's Yellow Fever Commission. I am still<lb/>
quite willing, if the Library's budget does not include such an ex-<lb/>
penditure, or if, by so doing, I can hasten the procedure, to pay not<lb/>
only for a microfilm copy for the Surgeon General's Library but also<lb/>
for one for myself. I would hope, of course, that the Library of the<lb/>
Surgeon General would see fit to &ldquo;reserve&rdquo; this data until I have had<lb/>
time to utilize it for my book, upon which I have spent almost ten<lb/>
years of effort. But if the librarian thinks otherwise, that won't<lb/>
worry me.</p>
<p>I hate to bother you in this matter, but as I am going to Cuba late<lb/>
in January for another medical meeting and can see Doctor Presno then,<lb/>
it would be most helpful to me were you able to write him directly be-<lb/>
fore then at your early convenience and perhaps authorize me to be<lb/>
your unofficial emissary in case any conversations are necessary to<lb/>
conclude matters. Perhaps you might choose to have someone else write<lb/>
the letter but I am sure you know the Cuban mind well enough to know<lb/>
that they would feel very flattered and very inclined to honor a re-<lb/>
quest from the Chief, whereas a request from a lesser individual might<lb/>
well be ignored. Your help in this matter will be greatly appreciated<lb/>
by me.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I was happy to accept Colonel Hayes invitation to give a<lb/>
Surgeon General's Lecture at Walter Reed Hospital in February.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
