<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04701012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 9, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04701012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-01-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Treanor, Wally</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Standlee, Mary</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic (Rochester, Minn.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital (Washington D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Letterman Army Medical Center (San Francisco, Cal.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-01-09">January 9, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04701012</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 9, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby discusses his health, a disagreement with Standlee over her book, and his ability to recollect Reed and members of his Board.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-01-09">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 9, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04701012"/>
<opener>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco 18, California<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1954-01-09">January 9, 1954</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thanks very much for your very nice letter of December 3, which<lb/>
I should have answered long ago, but holiday conditions prevented.<lb/>
As I told you, I think, in my last letter, Dr. Treanor's activi-<lb/>
ties have been unavoidably slowed up by special work heaped upon<lb/>
him by the PT Department which he had to take over at that time<lb/>
due to the absence of his Chief. The holiday activities then<lb/>
added to the slow up due to the fact that most all of the hospital<lb/>
work was closed up. In the midst of it all I had a very favorable<lb/>
reaction quite suddenly and the doctor said that this was the real<lb/>
thing and there will be more to follow. But the improvement did<lb/>
not seem to continue although he is still hopeful that it will as<lb/>
all the defective muscles seem to be extremely strong and are<lb/>
just ready to take over. I rather think he is right but you just<lb/>
have to wait to find out. This &ldquo;take-over&rdquo; and reinforcement<lb/>
of the exercises by the <hi>reflex centers</hi> is a wonderful process and<lb/>
I feel sure we are making progress.</p>
<p>I hope your visit to Washington in February will enable to make<lb/>
real progress in locating the small notebook which disappeared at<lb/>
the time of Reed's death and I believe that you can convince<lb/>
Mrs. Carroll that if she can find the little book it will add<lb/>
very much to clearing up this matter and be all to the credit of<lb/>
Dr. Carroll. It is known that the book was in Reed's desk at the<lb/>
Army Medical School when he died. If the book should now turn up<lb/>
it would show how carefully it was preserved by Dr. Carroll instead<lb/>
of being lost and it will be all to his credit to get it cleared up<lb/>
now.</p>
<p>I note that you have been asked to give a talk at Walter Reed<lb/>
Hospital in February. I am not surprised for I got in bad, as you<lb/>
know, with Mrs. Standlee in reviewing her book and laying stress<lb/>
upon your qualifications to pass on all of these matters and bring<lb/>
out the facts. I knew it would cause opposition from plenty of<lb/>
people in Washington but she was inconsiderate in accepting your<lb/>
views and so obstinate in her comeback to me that I was thoroughly<lb/>
disturbed about it and came back in kind. She finally cut me off<lb/>
of her list of correspondents and, as you know to keep you fully<lb/>
posted on it, I furnished you with a complete record of all the<lb/>
correspondence at the time it was written. So, if you have time<lb/>
to read it, you will have all the details. Her husband has been<lb/>
promoted in the meantime to a Major General in the Medical Corps<lb/>
and of course I am in bad as you no doubt have heard, not only at<lb/>
the Letterman but evidently in the SGO. My views apparently<lb/>
carried no weight so I am telling you this because there must be<lb/>
a definite reason for getting you to speak if it is on this subject.<lb/>
I assure you my attitude was in no way intended to be malicious<lb/>
and of course have had no intention of meddling with what is wanted.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04701013"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>I do feel though that you should be reminded that such a possibil-<lb/>
ity may exist. I was asked for my views and recommendations and<lb/>
give them my honest views. I have not written to anybody in<lb/>
Washington about this matter and I do not know what they concluded<lb/>
to do about any of my recommendations. Neither has anyone written<lb/>
to me or discussed the matter with me in any way so I may be all<lb/>
wrong in all of this. However, I've told you the situation so<lb/>
you will know all that I know about it. I am usually very reticent<lb/>
in discussing such subjects with anybody where it may appear like<lb/>
meddling when it really isn't.</p>
<p>I assure you that I will promptly be able to make a personality<lb/>
appraisal of Reed and members of his Board as soon as I feel in<lb/>
condition to do it and that might be very soon. In your letter<lb/>
of December 3 you suggested that you might be able to help me by<lb/>
asking me a few leading questions. I think that would help because<lb/>
one reason I felt inadequate to write such an appraisal was because<lb/>
I could not, for instance, give you an exact statement of the<lb/>
height, weight, color of the eyes, etc., of Reed. And while, of<lb/>
course, I think I could make a very definite and almost perfect<lb/>
<del>c</del><add>g</add>uess on most of such things they would not be facts. Naturally,<lb/>
I have very definite views about certain of the characteristics<lb/>
that were most outstanding in all of them and they would be of value.</p>
<p>I have not been a patient in the Letterman since I left there in<lb/>
September 1952 except for a few days in August 1953 when I had<lb/>
a severe fall which left me unconscious and they rushed me to the<lb/>
hospital. While I was there I had a few tests made and that is all.<lb/>
Just why you did not hear of my departure from the hospital I<lb/>
do not remember.</p>
<p>I intended to write you in the letter which left here yesterday<lb/>
but did not have time to cover all of these subjects.</p>
<p>With reference to what I said about my progress in paragraph 1 of<lb/>
this letter, my case is evidently running its own course and is<lb/>
not &ldquo;clicking&rdquo; as we expected. But while Treanor can not predict<lb/>
anything definitely, we think it will assume its normal course in<lb/>
due time.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
Albert E. Truby<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
