<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04701007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, January 7, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04701007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-01-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Pedro Nogueira</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Smith, Louise F.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Soper, Fred L.</name>
<name type="person">Presno, Jose A.</name>
<name type="person">Armstrong, George E.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic (Rochester, Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-01-07">January 7, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04701007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, January 7, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes Nogueira about his upcoming visit to Cuba, thanks him for the decoration he recently received, and enlists his aid in persuading Presno to consent to the microfilming of Finlay's daybooks.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-01-07">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, January 7, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04701007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1954-01-07">January 7, 1954</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I suspect that you may have heard that a month ago, quite unbeknownst to me,<lb/>
the Cuban Government voted me another decoration. I am extremely grateful<lb/>
to my Cuban friends and their very kind and sympathetic interest in me. I<lb/>
knew nothing about this matter but it was published in the New York Times<lb/>
and friends told me of it. Probably you not only knew something about it<lb/>
but may very well have had much to do with it. I am certainly grateful to<lb/>
you and my other friends.</p>
<p>It is probable also that you had heard that Mrs. Louise Flood Smith of F.I.M.<lb/>
has asked me to come down during their &ldquo;Nutrition Week&rdquo; and I have promised<lb/>
to do so. Mary and I will fly down, arriving in Havana late Tuesday night,<lb/>
January 26. We can only stay a very few days and will probably fly back on<lb/>
Sunday, January 31. Our friends at the Finca San Jose have invited us to<lb/>
stay with them and we have gladly accepted.</p>
<p>I must see you while we are there for two reasons: First of all, on a<lb/>
matter of interest to Doctor Soper. I understand that you and I are<lb/>
among those who are advising him regarding selected translations of the<lb/>
works of Finlay. I am glad to help in this matter and he wants me to talk<lb/>
to you.</p>
<p>Secondly, I am anxious to receive your further help in the matter of micro-<lb/>
filming the Finlay diaries as you and I have discussed before. I enclose a<lb/>
copy of a letter that I have sent to Doctor Presno. Surgeon General Arm-<lb/>
strong is very anxious to have a microfilm copy and has written me a very<lb/>
nice note asking me to be his agent in the matter. General Armstrong thinks<lb/>
that the microfilming could be done much cheaper at the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Library than anywhere else; on the other hand, if Doctor Presno feels that<lb/>
it should be done in Havana, so be it. In any event, I want Doctor Presno<lb/>
to understand that both General Armstrong and I want to have a copy made<lb/>
at our expense (if it is not too costly) to present to the Academy of<lb/>
Sciences Library. I am hoping that a negative can be made from which four<lb/>
positive copies can be made. I am not sure how they do it but in any<lb/>
event, the copies I hope to have made are one for the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Library, one for Doctor Presno and the Academy of Sciences in Havana, one<lb/>
for myself and, as a taken of my sincere appreciation of your great help,<lb/>
a fourth copy for you.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04701008"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira &nbsp;&nbsp; -2- &nbsp;&nbsp; January 7, 1954</p>
<p>In as much as I have mentioned your name in my letter to Doctor Presno,<lb/>
would it be appropriate or possible for you to contact him fairly soon<lb/>
so that perhaps by the time of my arrival he can have made up his mind<lb/>
what to do about the matter. If he will permit me this time to bring<lb/>
the books along to Washington, I will do so. If he wants the micro-<lb/>
film made in Havana, perhaps they could actually be done by the time of<lb/>
my arrival and I could bring the two back home; the copy for myself of<lb/>
course to be permanently filed in the Library of the Mayo Clinic.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
