<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04701004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose A. Presno, January 6, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04701004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-01-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Presno, Jose A.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Army Medical Library (U.S.)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-01-06">January 6, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04701004</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose A. Presno, January 6, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench tries to arrange a meeting with Presno to discuss microfilming Finlay's daybooks.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-01-06">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose A. Presno, January 6, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04701004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1954-01-06">January 6, 1954</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Jose A. Presno, President<lb/>
Academy of Sciences<lb/>
Cuba 460<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Presno:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have had the pleasure of meeting you on several occasions. The last<lb/>
time was when I had the great honor to receive the Finlay Medal at the<lb/>
Academy of Sciences in Havana in January, 1952.</p>
<p>You may remember also my great interest in the work of Doctor Finlay and<lb/>
of the members of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Commission. For ten years<lb/>
I have been collecting data on the conquest of yellow fever and it is my<lb/>
great desire to tell the Americans in my book as much as I can about<lb/>
Doctor Finlay for my countrymen do not know enough about him.</p>
<p>About three years age when I was in Havana, Dr. Pedro Nogueira called my<lb/>
attention to the eight or nine day-books or diaries of Doctor Finlay de-<lb/>
posited in the library of the Academy of Sciences. After studying these<lb/>
with great eagerness I recognize how tremendously important they were for<lb/>
anyone trying to write something on the life of Doctor Finlay. I discussed<lb/>
with you the possibility of having microfilms made of every page of these<lb/>
eight or nine volumes but at that time there was in Havana no company<lb/>
able to make such microfilms. You graciously considered the possibility<lb/>
of permitting me to take these diaries personally to the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Library so that they might have microfilms made, not only for the Surgeon<lb/>
General's Library but an extra copy for the Academy of Sciences in case<lb/>
anything should happen to the original; but at the last moment the matter<lb/>
was postponed.</p>
<p>On my return from Cuba at that time, I told the Surgeon General of the U. S.<lb/>
Army of these very important volumes and he too expressed a hope that a <lb/>
microfilm could be made sometime and deposited in the Library of the<lb/>
Surgeon General.</p>
<p>On my visit to Havana in January 1952, I spoke to you again of this matter<lb/>
and again you were quite willing for it to be done if it could be done<lb/>
under the proper auspices and with safeguards for the volumes. Recently<lb/>
the Surgeon General learned that I was to return to Havana and has, I<lb/>
believe, written to you making an official request in this matter. I have<lb/>
just heard from him and he has asked me to try to meet you and discuss the<lb/>
matter with you when I come to Havana in about three weeks, January 26 - 29.</p>
<p>It is my understanding from the Surgeon General that if they were permitted<lb/>
to have a microfilm of these volumes, they would be delighted to have a<lb/>
copy made for the Library of the Academy of Sciences. The Surgeon General<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04701005"/>
Dr. Jose A. Presno<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
January 6, 1954<lb/>
indicates to me that the microfilming could probably be done least<lb/>
expensively in the Library of the Surgeon General in Washington. There-<lb/>
fore, if you and the Librarian of the Academy would be willing to trust<lb/>
the volumes to me, I could take them to Washington and have them micro-<lb/>
filmed and then they could be taken by an agent of the Surgeon General<lb/>
to the Cuban Embassy and returned by diplomatic pouch. However we want<lb/>
to do whatever seems best and if it seems better to have them micro-<lb/>
filmed in Cuba, and this could be done at a reasonable price, that would<lb/>
be entirely satisfactory. I am sure you understand the tremendous im-<lb/>
portance of Doctor Finlay's day books to anyone who wants to study the<lb/>
conquest of yellow fever. Unfortunately, for an occasional visitor like<lb/>
me who can stay only a few days in Havana, the diaries are several in<lb/>
number and are written variously in Spanish, sometimes in German or English,<lb/>
so that it has been impossible for me to study them unless a copy were<lb/>
made available.</p>
<p>The Surgeon General having asked me to act as an agent in the matter,<lb/>
permit me to request an appointment with you perhaps for sometime Wed-<lb/>
nesday, January 27, or any day that week. I shall contact your office<lb/>
through the help of my friend, Dr. Pedro Nogueira.</p>
<p>I am coming to Havana in the interests of F.I.M. and Mrs. Hench and I<lb/>
will be the guests of our old friends, Senorits Maria Teresa Rojas and<lb/>
Senorita Lidia Cabrera at the Finca San Jose, Calle Real, Marianao,<lb/>
the old site of Camp Lazear.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Copy to Dr. Npgueira<lb/>
Senorita Rojas<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
