<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04707001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, March 1, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04707001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-03-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Inclan, Clemente</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Landon</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Mrs. George</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Mrs. Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Margaret Lazear </name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Lexington (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Army Medical Library (U.S.)</name>
<name type="place">California</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-03-01">March 1, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04707001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, March 1, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Nogueira for thinking of Cooke's widow, inquires about the decision regarding microfilming Finlay's day books, and discusses bringing the recipients of the Finlay Medals to Washington, D.C. to receive their medals from Nogueira personally.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-03-01">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, March 1, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04707001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1954-03-01">March 1, 1954</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have your letter of February 24. I forgot all about Doctor Cooke. Certainly<lb/>
his widow should have his medal and in order to hurry things along, I am<lb/>
sending you my own check for $27 to make up the difference. If, however,<lb/>
the Walter Reed Memorial Association decides to cover that also and send<lb/>
you a check, you can either return my check or simply destroy it.</p>
<p>Thank you very much for your telegram. I am sorry that Doctor Inclan<lb/>
and you have not been able to meet with the Board of the Academy of Sciences.<lb/>
I do hope that soon they will give us permission to have the microfilms<lb/>
made. Lidia Cabrera assures me that there is a microfilm machine in Havana,<lb/>
not at the public library but at some technical library. Of course if it<lb/>
could be loaned through diplomatic channels to the Surgeon General's Library,<lb/>
you and I could get the copies for much less.</p>
<p>Last week in Washington, I called on General and Mrs. Reed and Blossom Reed,<lb/>
Hoping that you will come to the U.S. between June 10 and 20, they would<lb/>
prefer to wait until then rather than have the Cuban embassy present the<lb/>
medals to them in your absence. The Reeds all hope to be reasonably well<lb/>
and on hand at that time. However General Reed has for years had a severe<lb/>
asthma and wheezes considerably on any exertion. Therefore he goes prac-<lb/>
tically nowhere. However his family assured me that they would see to it<lb/>
that he went to the Embassy for such a pleasant ceremony.</p>
<p>I also visited Mrs. George Carroll, Major Carroll's daughter-in-law and told<lb/>
her of the impending honor. She is a rather shy, withdrawn person, rather<lb/>
afraid of the world and of course, at the moment, disconsolate because of<lb/>
her husband's death. She lives in modest circumstances and in the past<lb/>
there has been some feeling between the Carrolls and the Reeds, but I am<lb/>
sure it is entirely one-sided. Mrs. George Carroll told me that Doctor<lb/>
Carroll's widow taught the children that he was robbed of his proper<lb/>
fame by Doctor Reed. This of course was nonsense as Reed was long since<lb/>
dead and I am sure the Reed family had nothing to do with it; however I am<lb/>
also sure that they could all meet amicably for the ceremony. I should<lb/>
think that Mrs. Cooke would come up from Lexington, Virginia, to Washington<lb/>
for the ceremony at the Embassy and you would, of course, I assume suggest<lb/>
to the Cuban Ambassador that the recipients be allowed to have a few rela-<lb/>
tives personal friends as guests, including the members of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association, for the little ceremony. Will you be able to go to<lb/>
California to help the Consul present the medals to the Lazears and General<lb/>
Truby?</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.<unclear>D</unclear>.</signed>
PSH:ALC<lb/>
<seg>P.S.: I shall await with eagerness further news regarding the microfilm.</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
