<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04718004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence [Walter L.] Reed, August 30, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04718004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-08-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Schnurr, Dorma V.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Blue Ridge Summit (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-08-30">August 30, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04718004</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence [Walter L.] Reed, August 30, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench sends Lawrence Reed a list of questions regarding the specific characteristics of his father.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-08-30">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lawrence [Walter L.] Reed, August 30, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04718004"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1954-08-30">August 30, 1954</date>
</dateline><lb/>
General Walter L. Reed<lb/>
2810 - 36th Place, N.W.<lb/>
Washington 7, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Reed:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have had a very nice letter from your good wife saying that she is off<lb/>
to England and telling me that she will return my medal on her return<lb/>
even though you have not yet gotten yours back. General Reed, I don't<lb/>
want mine back until you get yours. There is absolutely no hurry about<lb/>
this and I want you to keep mine as long as you need it.</p>
<p>The next time I come to Washington, I want to ask you a few more questions<lb/>
about your father. Perhaps you could be thinking these over.</p>
<p>1. I want to know his height. On my last visit, you stated you thought he<lb/>
was 5&prime; 11&Prime; - Miss Blossom thought he was 6 feet. His weight was around<lb/>
150 to 156. He had dark brown hair, sprinkled with grey, blue eyes and a<lb/>
&ldquo;Chinaman's moustache&rdquo;.</p>
<p>2. As you know, he has been written up in such hallowed terms that, ac-<lb/>
cording to some writers, he was almost a god and not human. I am sure<lb/>
you would not have me portray him in that manner. One of the Cuban nurses<lb/>
wrote that your father, one time at the mess at the post hospital, Camp<lb/>
Columbia, got up and walked out because a couple of his younger officers<lb/>
used profanity. I have no doubt your father knew that there was a time and place<lb/>
for the milder type of profanity, and that he would be intolerant of a cer-<lb/>
tain type of profanity, especially of smut, but I can't picture your father<lb/>
as being a prude and, if my memory serves me correctly, in some of his letters<lb/>
to very close friends, he occasionally used the word &ldquo;damn&rdquo; very effectively.<lb/>
I should like to ask you about this side of his personality and, as I under-<lb/>
stand him, while he had an air of great dignity, he was not unapproachable,<lb/>
and in the bosom of friends he was even gay. From incidents that have oc-<lb/>
curred I know, too, that he had a subtle humor and some whimsey and of<lb/>
course from his letters to his family, it is obvious that in the bosom of<lb/>
those whom he loved so much, he was a doting father, a tender and worshiping<lb/>
husband and threw all reserve to the winds.</p>
<p>As I understand it, he was on very good terms of friendship (though not a<lb/>
first name caller) with his medical colleagues of all ages, from General<lb/>
Kean to Lt. Truby, more reserved with other medical officers whom he called<lb/>
&ldquo;doctor&rdquo; rather than by their military rank, and quite dignified with soldiers<lb/>
and strangers in general. Though dignified and reserved, I believe he was<lb/>
approachable and friendly to any soldier whose reason for conversation with<lb/>
him was valid.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04718005"/>
<p>General Walter L. Reed &nbsp;&nbsp; - 2 - 
&nbsp;&nbsp; August 30, 1954</p>
<p>3. Can you tell me a little of his sense of humor? I have numerous<lb/>
incidents upon which to base my own opinion but would like your own.</p>
<p>4. What was his attitude on liquor? I believe he drank socially. Did<lb/>
he have any firm rules for himself and others?</p>
<p>5. Did he smoke?</p>
<p>6. What were his chief recreations? I seem to have little data on this.</p>
<p>7. Did he like the theater? If so, what type - vandeville, musical<lb/>
comedy, operettas, drama, farce?</p>
<p>8. What were his hobbies and antipathies?</p>
<p>9. Did he like the company of men and women? He certainly was entirely<lb/>
sociable but was he sociable enough to enjoy going to an evening affair where<lb/>
only relative strangers or acquaintances were present? Did he enjoy the<lb/>
company of women friends? What was his favorite type of man?</p>
<p>10. What were his clothing habits? In the pictures I have seen of him he<lb/>
was meticulously dressed whether in uniform or civilian clothes. Did he<lb/>
ever unbend and wear lounging clothes?</p>
<p>11. Did he work in the garden much at Blue Ridge Summit? How did he oc-<lb/>
cupy his time at Blue Ridge Summit?</p>
<p>12. What kind of a reader was he - an avid reader? What kind of books<lb/>
did he like most?</p>
<p>13. What were his ambitions, primary and secondary? Of course in his<lb/>
famous New Year's letter to your mother, he expressed his deep satisfac-<lb/>
tion for having fulfilled his ambition to serve humanity through medicine.<lb/>
Did he ever discuss with you his ambitions in less spiritual terms? Fate<lb/>
made him, certainly in his later years, more the researcher than the<lb/>
medical practitioner. Did he do research from a sense of duty or with a<lb/>
burning desire, and do you think that medical research - the typhoid in-<lb/>
vestigation, the yellow fever investigation (bacteriology in general), was<lb/>
his main ambition and the practice of medicine secondary, or did he actually<lb/>
enjoy practicing Army medicine? Certainly he must have been willing to<lb/>
lower his financial ambitions, if any, when he decided to stay in the Army.<lb/>
Certainly he had compensations in lieu of finances. Did he ever discuss<lb/>
this matter with you?</p>
<p>14. What was his attitude on religion? His personal attitude? His<lb/>
formal attitude? Obviously he was deeply spiritual but was he also<lb/>
strongly interested in formalized religion? Of course I know the ministerial<lb/>
background of the family.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04718006"/>
<p>General Walter L. Reed &nbsp;&nbsp; - 3 - &nbsp;&nbsp; August 30, 1954</p>
<p>Of these things I should like to talk to you more and if, between now and<lb/>
when we meet you should have the ambition to jot down a few words, we<lb/>
could amplify them by a little &ldquo;interview&rdquo; later. Would you be willing<lb/>
to have me ask my former secretary in Washington, Miss Dorma Schnurr, to<lb/>
come over for an hour every now and then, completely at your convenience,<lb/>
so that she could take down your answers to these questions and in that<lb/>
way, you wouldn't have to write a note and I could send Miss Schnurr a<lb/>
copy of these questions ahead of time so that she could familiarize herself<lb/>
with them and save for you as much of your time as possible.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
<seg>PSH:alc<lb/>
Dictated but not read or signed by Dr. Hench.</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
