<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04724002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Robert F. Woodward, October 5, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04724002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-10-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Woodward, Robert F.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Beauperthuy, Louise Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-10-05">October 5, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04724002</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Robert F. Woodward, October 5, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench states that Finlay and Reed were the two men who made the greatest contribution to mankind in the conquest of yellow fever. Other men only published interesting ideas.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-10-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Robert F. Woodward, October 5, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04724002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1954-10-05">October 5, 1954</date>
</dateline><lb/>
REF: A.R.A.<lb/>
Mr. Robert F. Woodward<lb/>
Acting Assistant Secretary<lb/>
for Inter-American Affairs<lb/>
Department of State<lb/>
Washington 25, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Woodward:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just returned from Europe and have your letter of September 8<lb/>
in which you tell me that presumably at an international medical meeting<lb/>
in Rome in November, a French delegation is planning to present a resolu-<lb/>
tion to the effect that a French physician (I presume you mean Beauperthy)<lb/>
was the original discoverer of the mosquito theory of yellow fever.</p>
<p>You ask me &ldquo;to provide evidence which would support the Cuban assertion,&rdquo;<lb/>
that Dr. Carlos Finlay was the first proponent of this theory. I am<lb/>
quite familiar with this argument and it is distressing to me to see the<lb/>
contention that still attends this great contribution to mankind. In<lb/>
essence, there are only two men or two groups that deserve to be men-<lb/>
tioned seriously in connection with the conquest of yellow fever. They<lb/>
are Dr. Carlos Finlay who, practically alone, developed the theory that<lb/>
yellow fever is caused by the Aedes Aegypti mosquito and who, with a<lb/>
colleague, worked on the theory for 19 years and, second, there is Walter<lb/>
Walter Reed and his group who, using advanced techniques and so on, were<lb/>
able to prove the correctness of Doctor Finlay's theory. Before Doctor<lb/>
Finlay, there were two or three men who put in writing the notion that<lb/>
perhaps yellow fever might be caused by some agent such as a mosquito<lb/>
and so on, but these worthy gentlemen were doing nothing more than pub-<lb/>
lishing an interesting idea. They deserve hardly more than a footnote.</p>
<p>I am a great admirer of Dr. Carlos Finlay and his magnificent work. It<lb/>
is true that he was not able to present convincing data for various<lb/>
reasons, one of which was that he had a different purpose (according to<lb/>
his son) from that of the U.S. Army Commission. I have investigated this<lb/>
matter over a period of 14 years and have made it my hobby. I have<lb/>
visited Cuba many times and am preparing a book on the subject. There<lb/>
are only two things that are holding me up. I still have not obtained<lb/>
certain important information about Doctor Finlay and there is still a<lb/>
missing notebook of the Army Commission to find.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04724003"/>
<p>Mr. Robert F. Woodward &nbsp;&nbsp; - 2 - &nbsp;&nbsp; October 5, 1954</p>
<p>I shall be delighted to defend Doctor Finlay's work and there is no real<lb/>
conflict between the glory that must be his and that which should go to<lb/>
the Army Commission. These two works stand together and together they<lb/>
stand alone.</p>
<p>Now precisely what do you want me to do? Without knowing what the French<lb/>
resolution is to be and not even knowing what French doctor they are re-<lb/>
ferring to, I am not quite certain what our Cuban friends have in mind in<lb/>
the way of our help. I note that the convention is to be in November.<lb/>
Therefore we still have some time and if you will find out from your col-<lb/>
leagues in the American Embassy in Havana just what they would like to<lb/>
have me do, I should be glad to do it.</p>
<p>Ten days ago I was in Stockholm for a week at an International Congress<lb/>
and the Americans were invited to the Embassy. I remembered with pleasure<lb/>
the luncheon that the ambassador gave for the Kendalls, Mrs. Hench and me<lb/>
in 1950 and I also remember you with pleasure.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04724004"/>
<seg>CONFIDENTIAL ADDENDUM:<lb/>
Mr. Woodward, it may be that you will want to send the enclosed carbon<lb/>
copy to Havana and someone there may wish to show it to our Cuban friends.<lb/>
You are of course aware of the fact that the Cubans have long been vexed<lb/>
with the proponents of Walter Reed and have tended to be overly<lb/>
chauvinistic and have refused to see that it was Reed and his colleagues<lb/>
who proved the veracity of the Finlay theory. Perhaps our Cuban friends<lb/>
would merely want me to sign my name to a counter resolution they decide<lb/>
to present. I should be glad to sign it, provided the resolution defends<lb/>
Finlay properly and not at the expense of the American Commission. I<lb/>
shall await further instructions.</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
