<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04732003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Essay: Lambert Breaks Quarantine, by [Paul L. Tate], [1954]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Tate, Paul L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04732003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Lewis, Winifred</name>
<name type="person">Cook, Lottie</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-00-00">1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04732003</idno>
<title>Essay: Lambert Breaks Quarantine, by [Paul L. Tate], [1954]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Tate] explains that Andrus was exceedingly ill and Lambert, in an act of bravery, broke quarantine to fetch Ames.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1954-00-00">
<head>Essay: Lambert Breaks Quarantine, by [Paul L. Tate], [1954]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04732003"/>
<p>LAMBERT BREAKS QUAR<del>R</del>ANTINE</p>
<p>Two practical nurses had just arrived at the Post Hospital.<lb/>
<del>t</del><add>T</add>hey were yellow fever immunes. One named Lottie (I have<lb/>
forgotten her last name) was sent down to assist Lambert.</p>
<p>Lambert told me about this afterward. He says he was get-<lb/>
ting a long needed rest, when Lottie came and said there<lb/>
was something wrong about the patient (Andrus),--He wanted<lb/>
to be on his knees on the bed all the time.</p>
<p>Lambert went down and found him that way. He turned him<lb/>
over but Andrus immediately resumed his strange position.<lb/>
Lambert looked at the chart and found that the liquid in-<lb/>
take exceeded the output, and asked the nurse if he had<lb/>
been catherized. She knew nothing of such a thing! So,<lb/>
Lambert catherized him, as it was a strict rule that in<lb/>
these cases the urinal output should closely approximate<lb/>
the intake of liquid. Then he left, thinking that was the<lb/>
trouble.</p>
<p>Shortly afterward Lottie came again, saying the patient<lb/>
was acting so strangely she did not know what to do. Lam-<lb/>
bert saw Andrus was in a condition that he knew nothing<lb/>
of, and that he must get relief or Major Reed might lose<lb/>
his favorite patient and break the long record of cures.<lb/>
Lambert, realizing the seriousness of this, decided to<lb/>
do something which all his instinct and training tended<lb/>
to keep him from doing--Break quararantine and get Doctor<lb/>
Ames.</p>
<p>He crossed the railway ditch and across the parade ground<lb/>
and finding Doctor Ames' quarters, entered and told Ames<lb/>
the trouble. <add>(</add>Here a differance appears in Lambert's story<lb/>
and that of Miss Winifred Lewis' account. I attach a pho-<lb/>
&check; tostat of Miss Lewis' version.<add>)</add> Lambert said that The nurse<lb/>
was not there, but came back from lunch and missing her<lb/>
patient, bed and all, came running across the parade ground<lb/>
after them, and that Ames reassured her.</p>
<p>Lambert and Hardy carried Ames to the pest house and he<lb/>
found <del>to be</del> a carbuncle to be the cause of the trouble.<lb/>
He lanced it and Lambert dressed it and they returned to<lb/>
find a very stormy office<add>r</add> aw<unclear>a</unclear>iting them. Captain Stark,<lb/>
who used language that made Miss Lewis cringe. Lambert<lb/>
went back, satis<del>s</del><add>f</add>ied he had saved his case.</p>
<p>Personally, I know this happened. That day I was lying on<lb/>
my bunk after lunch, when Hardy came in terribly excited.<lb/>
He told me that after leaving the mess hall a<del>g</del><add>f</add>ter lunch,<lb/>
&check; Lambert had met him and said that Doctor Ames wanted him<lb/>
to help carry him to the pest house, (we always used that<lb/>
term). Said he had done so and when they had carried Ames<lb/>
back, Captain Stark was waiting there and had used words<lb/>
of denunciation he had never heard before. (Stark was a real<lb/>
expert at that!) He was sure he was going to be court-ma<unclear>ri</unclear>tialed<lb/>
and discharged. He was <add>a</add> simple, literally minded fellow and<lb/>
was all broken up over it. Asked me if when I went to the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04732004"/>
Captain's office if I would let him know what they were going<lb/>
to do to him. When I went to the office Captain Stark was<lb/>
there, but never mentioned the matter. Of course Ames had<lb/>
told Stark the necessity of the affair and assumed any b<unclear>la</unclear>me<lb/>
himself.</p>
<p>One who was not there and acquainted with the strict mili-<lb/>
tary rules enforced can <add>not</add> appreciate the bravery of Lambert<lb/>
in performing this act.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
