<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04803011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench, January 22, 1955</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04803011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1955-01-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Houston</name>
<name type="person">Briggs, Margaret Lazear</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jane</name>
<name type="person">Gawne, J. O.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, John M.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1955-01-22">January 22, 1955</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04803011</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench, January 22, 1955</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench gives an account of the Lazear family since the death of Jesse W. Lazear. Hench discusses a rift in the Lazear family.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1955-01-22">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench, January 22, 1955</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04803011"/>
<opener>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1955-01-22">January 22, 1955</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Friends:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Captain and Mrs. James O. Gawne of Washington, D.C. and Mr. and Mrs. John<lb/>
Lazear of Naples, Florida and Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, intend to fly to<lb/>
Havana sometime between February 15 and 24 for the sole purpose of seeing<lb/>
Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>Mrs. Gawne was Jane Lazear and she and her brother (who will be with her)<lb/>
are the first cousins of Dr. Jesse W. Lazear of yellow fever fame after<lb/>
whom Camp Lazear was named. They are of course anxious not only to see<lb/>
Camp Lazear but to meet two or three of the people they have heard me talk<lb/>
about so often and I am especially anxious also that they have this pleasure<lb/>
for reasons which I shall summarize briefly. Please consider the rest of this<lb/>
letter semi-confidential. I am not sure how much of the following the Gawnes<lb/>
and Lazears know. They know some of it. It is a touchy subject and even if<lb/>
they know all of it they may or may not be willing to discuss it. Neverthe-<lb/>
less, I want you to know it so that you will understand that there is some<lb/>
delicacy to the matter of their visit and that it represents much more than<lb/>
a casual visit.</p>
<p>You will remember that in the spring of 1900, Mrs. Jesse Lazear and their<lb/>
baby boy, Houston, were stationed at Camp Columbia with Doctor Lazear, but<lb/>
he sent his wife and little boy back to the States for two reasons: She<lb/>
was pregnant and, secondly, the yellow fever epidemic was impending. Mrs.<lb/>
Lazear went to Boston and the little girl was born just about the time<lb/>
Doctor Lazear died. He never saw her. Doctor Lazear had intended to ask<lb/>
for a leave that spring and go to Boston to be with his wife at the time<lb/>
of her delivery. Then he got caught up in the yellow fever business and,<lb/>
to top matters, was appointed to the Army's Yellow Fever Board. Because<lb/>
of this tremendous challenge to his scientific interests as well as to his<lb/>
sense of duty, he must have decided not to ask for the furlough or to be<lb/>
with his wife at the time of her delivery. But the trouble was in order<lb/>
not to worry his wife, he could not tell her exactly what he was doing or<lb/>
why he couldn't come home to be with her (I have some of his letters<lb/>
written to her from Cuba at that time and some of those written by him<lb/>
to his own mother; they indicate that his wife was getting concerned and<lb/>
that, seemingly, some little friction was arising because she simply<lb/>
couldn't understand why he couldn't come to be with her. She apparently<lb/>
thought that his duty at that time was with her, especially as he had a<lb/>
leave coming up.).</p>
<p>It is important to understand this background. Doctor Lazear wrote his<lb/>
wife two or three cryptic notes hinting vaguely that he was involved in<lb/>
something big connected with yellow fever and yet trying not to frighten<lb/>
her with the knowledge of the inoculations. Then suddenly, without warning,<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear received the blunt telegraphic news that Doctor Lazear had died.<lb/>
She didn't even know he was sick and the telegram announcing his death was<lb/>
delayed twelve hours in reaching her because the Surgeon General's Office in<lb/>
Washington didn't know her exact Boston address.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04803012"/>
<p>January 22, 1955<lb/>
Page 2</p>
<p>Remember that at this time Major Reed was in Washington, having been recalled<lb/>
to finish the typhoid fever report. He knew a little more about Lazear's<lb/>
sickness and death but not very much more than Mrs. Lazear. The latter<lb/>
hastened to Washington to visit Reed to find out the details of her husband's<lb/>
death. Unannounced, she merely sent in her name, M.H. Lazear. Reed ex-<lb/>
pected to meet a male relative and was surprised to meet Mrs. Lazear, also<lb/>
embarrassed because he could tell her so little. As a result, the &ldquo;bitterness&rdquo;<lb/>
which had begun to develop before her pregnancy&sol;delivery in Boston was<lb/>
crystallized and she allowed herself to believe that her husband had more or<lb/>
less abandoned her in favor of some scientific foolishness and had been so<lb/>
careless as to let himself get killed.</p>
<p>Unfortunate consequences resulted. She more or less cut herself off from<lb/>
the Lazear relatives (all easterners), went back to California (her home)<lb/>
and raised her children there with the notion that their father had done<lb/>
some reprehensible thing, more or less abandoning her and dying, leaving<lb/>
her with no money and two little children to support. It was years before<lb/>
Doctor Lazear's two children knew the facts.</p>
<p>The eastern Lazears tried to keep in touch with Mrs. Lazear but fundamentally<lb/>
she was a sensitive, diffident and somewhat &ldquo;difficult&rdquo; person with intense<lb/>
feelings which she tried to hide but which broke out at times. Only a year<lb/>
or so before Mrs. Lazear died, and I hope through my correspondence and<lb/>
visits with her, did she fully understand the situation and (as I understand<lb/>
it) begin correspondence with the eastern Lazears.</p>
<p>The latter have been of course increasingly proud of their relative and their<lb/>
interest in him has been growing apace. They are fine people. Captain Gawne<lb/>
was an outstanding naval officer and I believe was a temporary admiral during<lb/>
World War II, retiring recently with the permanent rank of captain. Mrs.<lb/>
Gawne is a very intelligent, charming woman. John Lazear was, around 1910-12<lb/>
a schoolmate of mine at Pittsburgh. Incidentally, he married a very wealthy<lb/>
wife whom I have met only casually. They are so anxious to renew their con-<lb/>
tacts with the Lazear children, Houston and Peggy, both of whom live in<lb/>
California. They were delighted to hear of the dedication of Camp Lazear<lb/>
and of the more recent honors (Finlay Medals) to Houston and Peggy. They<lb/>
are collecting data on the family history, especially concerning Jesse and<lb/>
they are also anxious, in a delicate way, to have Doctor Lazear's grave<lb/>
marked appropriately. Because of the misunderstanding noted above, I<lb/>
don't believe Mrs. Lazear ever saw Doctor Lazear's grave. His body was re-<lb/>
turned from Cuba to Baltimore and buried there by the eastern relatives.<lb/>
One of the saddest and strangest moments came to me when I first met Houston<lb/>
Lazear, the son, and he turned to me and said, &ldquo;Doctor Hench, where is my<lb/>
father buried?&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am so anxious, therefore, for my friends in Cuba to give these closest<lb/>
living relatives<add>*</add> of Doctor Lazear a suitable welcome. Their visit to<lb/>
Camp Lazear will mean a tremendous thing spiritually, for them and they<lb/>
will come home prepared to do for their relative what has not yet been<lb/>
done - improve the grave and see to it that their connections with the<lb/>
children of Doctor Lazear and improved, the family ties strengthened and<lb/>
the ranks closed.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
* (except the two children)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
