<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04804003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J. O. Gawne, Mrs. Gawne, and Mr. and Mrs. John M. Lazear, February 7, 1955</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04804003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1955-02-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Gawne, J. O.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Gawne, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, John M.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mrs. John M.</name>
<name type="person">Nougeira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Smith, Louise F.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, Elida</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Tina</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1955-02-07">February 7, 1955</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04804003</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J. O. Gawne, Mrs. Gawne, and Mr. and Mrs. John M. Lazear, February 7, 1955</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench gives explicit instructions on the procedures and protocol for the Lazear family in their visit to Cuba in order to honor Jesse Lazear and Finlay.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1955-02-07">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to J. O. Gawne, Mrs. Gawne, and Mr. and Mrs. John M. Lazear, February 7, 1955</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04804003"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1955-02-07">February 7, 1955</date><lb/>
</dateline>
Captain and Mrs. James O. Gawne<lb/>
Mr. and Mrs. John Lazear<lb/>
Naples, Florida<lb/>
<salute>Dear Friends:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Please wire me at your earliest convenience your intended date of arrival<lb/>
at Havana and where you will be staying so that you can be gotten in<lb/>
touch with and be sure to tell me also how long you expect to stay there<lb/>
and when you expect to leave. May I suggest that, if possible, your de-<lb/>
parture be flexible in case any friend of mine and admirer of Doctor<lb/>
Lazear wants to show you around and in case you want to accept, in other<lb/>
words, in case you find your visit gets more pleasant and instructive<lb/>
than you might think.</p>
<p>With regard to your tentative decision to go to the Sevilla Biltmore, may<lb/>
I suggest that if you are only going to be in Havana a very short time,<lb/>
such as two days and a night, the Sevilla might be preferable, but if you<lb/>
are going to be there at least three or four days, and if a very few<lb/>
dollars more per day is not important, I would urge that you go to the<lb/>
Nacional. The ladies will like it much better and by taxi it is hardly<lb/>
more than six or seven minutes downtown. Another point: The Hotel<lb/>
Nacional is distinctly a better &ldquo;social address&rdquo; for our Cuban friends<lb/>
to reach you at and, most important of all, the Nacional is actually two<lb/>
miles nearer Camp Lazear and Quemados than is the Sevilla Biltmore. That <lb/>
is, the Nacional is right between the two main locations you will be<lb/>
visiting: (a) Downtown Havana and (b) Quemados. The hotel pool, etc., is<lb/>
magnificent and a delightful place for you to sit and sip, even though<lb/>
you don't swim.</p>
<p>Undoubtedly, you planned your trip as a private personal one and I strongly<lb/>
suspect that you may be concerned lest I take you trip too seriously<lb/>
and complicate it by involving you with obligations but primarily, I<lb/>
am so very anxious for you to see not just the one place, Camp Lazear,<lb/>
but the many places related to Doctor Lazear and his American associates,<lb/>
including the additional bust, painting, etc., of him as described in my<lb/>
notes. Also, I am quite anxious for you to meet and to be met by a few<lb/>
special friends by whom the memory of Doctor Lazear is cherished. I have<lb/>
had two or three nice letters from Dr. Pedro Nogueira, just recovering<lb/>
from chickenpox. He is very anxious to do whatever he possibly can and<lb/>
as far as your seeing the proper sights and people is concerned, he is<lb/>
the main fellow; but I am very anxious for you to meet Tina Rojas and<lb/>
her companion, Lydia Cabrera, who own the Finca San Jose. I have had<lb/>
no reply from my letter to them and suspect that they may be away, pos-<lb/>
sibly back in Europe (they go yearly; I met them in Paris last fall).</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04804004"/>
<p>Page 2 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; February 7, 1955</p>
<p>Ordinarily they reply promptly, but they might be simply away for a short<lb/>
time. Be sure to telephone their home (it may be listed in the Quemados<lb/>
section of the Havana phone book) and if, per chance, you can't reach them,<lb/>
by all means stop by yourself or have Pedro take you there. You simply<lb/>
must see the house and grounds. A cousin, Miss Julia Lomas, should be<lb/>
there and knows all about Doctor Lazear. The ladies will thoroughly enjoy<lb/>
seeing the inside of this lovely 150-year old Cuban finca or quinta, the<lb/>
only one remaining in or near Havana. They have made it a veritable museum.<lb/>
Incidentally if nobody is there but the servants, let them show you around<lb/>
and if they don't understand English, just write my name on a piece of paper;<lb/>
they will understand. Also, if Tina offers to send you their car and<lb/>
chauffeur or any kind of service, by all means accept.</p>
<p>I am so anxious that you not be disappointed by the area in which the little<lb/>
Camp Lazear Memorial stands. It is surrounded by homes and especially the<lb/>
disfiguring quarry, but that can't be helped. That is where it happened.<lb/>
So be it. Please do not be disappointed either by the modesty of the<lb/>
memorial (by American standards). This is just a beginning, I assure you,<lb/>
and in Cuba there is being formed &ldquo;the friends of Camp Lazear,&rdquo; to be sup-<lb/>
ported by prominent Cuban-Americans, sparked by Doctor Nogueira and perhaps<lb/>
a very prominent American woman, Mrs. Louise Smith and two or three very<lb/>
influential American men. They have kept out of matters until now as the<lb/>
early planning had to be Cuban, but now these folks will push and may well<lb/>
complete the unfinished business.</p>
<p>Another point: If you are historically minded and find yourself disturbed<lb/>
by the extensive restoration of Building No. 1, don't let Pedro know. You<lb/>
can discuss it with Rojas and Cabrera. We planned an expert reconstruction<lb/>
to save every possible bit of original wood but that's one thing Pedro<lb/>
went ahead with, without consulting me. He just couldn't understand the<lb/>
importance of preserving as much of the original as possible. Therefore,<lb/>
as I recall it, a generous amount of the present building is of new wood,<lb/>
although there is still much of the old wood present and Pedro and the<lb/>
other patrons are very proud of it. We can't let them down.</p>
<p>I hope that you have time to meet Senora Estella Agramonte Rodriguez Leon,<lb/>
Agramonte's daughter, one of the most alert and intelligent women I have<lb/>
ever met. She is a wife, mother and teacher and occasionally too busy to<lb/>
be 100% hospitable but she is charming and I think would feel hurt if she<lb/>
did not at least see you, perhaps only for a cocktail at the hotel. Her<lb/>
husband, a former Cuban Army officer, is pleasant but speaks inferior<lb/>
English, whereas Estella is linguistically perfect. I am taking the<lb/>
liberty of dropping her a note; also Mrs. John Moran. Her present ad-<lb/>
dress is B #258 entre 16 y 18, Reparto Almendares, Havana. I do not have<lb/>
her telephone number. She is shy, lets on she speaks little English, etc.<lb/>
Perhaps Pedro will have you meet the Mayor of Marianao. If so, please<lb/>
remember that he unveiled Doctor Lazear's bronze; he wanted that honor.</p>
<p>Now, if you are willing to do the following, please consider it even<lb/>
though your first inclination may be unfavorable. I think you might make<lb/>
a ten-strike if you would lay a wreath not only in honor of Doctor Lazear,<lb/>
but also one in honor of Doctor Finlay. I think it would please the Cubans<lb/>
no end and would be the finest expression you could give (as representa-<lb/>
tives of the Lazear family, the only ones who have visited there yet) to<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04804005"/>
Page 3 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; February 7, 1955<lb/>
show your appreciation not only of Doctor Finlay but particularly of what<lb/>
the Cubans have done for Doctor Lazear. May I suggest the delicate ap-<lb/>
proach? Captain Gawne might quietly say that, as a family, you would<lb/>
like to lay a wreath at the Lazear Memorial in front of Doctor Lazear's <lb/>
profile but that you would very much like to honor Finlay also and would<lb/>
it be presumptuous or inappropriate if you did this. If not, should the<lb/>
wreath be laid at Finlay's grave at Colon Cemetery, or beneath Finlay's<lb/>
bronze at Camp Lazear. If you went out of the way to lay it in Colon<lb/>
Cemetery, it might be construed as a higher tribute. On the other hand,<lb/>
you might not want to lay a wreath simply for Doctor Lazear at the Memorial<lb/>
and might prefer to lay the Finlay wreath there also. I suspect that Pedro<lb/>
will pick this idea up and carry the ball eagerly and if you need any fur-<lb/>
ther advice you, Captain Gawne, could simply telephone the naval attache<lb/>
of the U. S. Embassy or Ambassador Gardner himself. I am anxious of course<lb/>
that this idea be your own and that they recognize it as such but if you<lb/>
feel embarrassed, you might quietly use my name with the Ambassador or<lb/>
attache in any way you wish, saying that Doctor Hench thought so and so.<lb/>
But use me only to put on me any responsibility you may not want entirely<lb/>
for yourself. If Pedro does as I suspect he will, suggests that the wreath<lb/>
be placed semi-publicly in the presence of a photographer and perhaps the<lb/>
Mayor of Marianao and&sol;or the patrons (there is no occasion for them now to<lb/>
have anything but a little semi-public wreath-laying), even that would<lb/>
please them no end. It would show Pedro, the patrons and the Mayor how much<lb/>
you appreciate what they did for Doctor Lazear and what Finlay did. It<lb/>
would make for good feelings all around and help those of us, both here<lb/>
and in Havana, who wish to do more.</p>
<p>If you decide to do the above, may I suggest that you get the flowers at<lb/>
that lovely flower store halfway down the Prado on the left side, facing<lb/>
Morro Castle. The name is Milagros Flores and be sure to ask for the<lb/>
young proprietress. She is a charming youngish woman of 30-some years<lb/>
who was so wonderful with respect to all the flowers placed at the Camp<lb/>
Lazear dedication. Her name was Senora Lucilla Schumann and be sure to<lb/>
give her my best and tell her I sent you. To save money, I suggest the<lb/>
following: Tell her you want nothing too fancy or expensive (the Cubans<lb/>
go in for tremendous floral pieces); suggest perhaps $10 as top price for<lb/>
each of the one or two pieces (if one for Finlay also). She may well do<lb/>
for you what she did for me. I paid her $10 each and she made tremendous<lb/>
beautiful floral pieces, &ldquo;because she wanted to share the honor.&rdquo; In the<lb/>
United States they would have cost $100 each and they were very tasteful.</p>
<p>Political and social divisions are more precise in Cuba than here. Doctor<lb/>
Nogueira is, perhaps, socially quite unimportant and I think Tina and Lydia<lb/>
consider him rather inconsequential. To them he lacks the finer cultures.<lb/>
But for ten years he was the only one that really worked for the preserva-<lb/>
tion of Camp Lazear; all the other Cubans just talked. Pedro acted and<lb/>
kept at it steadily for ten years, at times in the face of real dis-<lb/>
couragement. He is 99% responsible for the Camp Lazear Memorial, for the<lb/>
honors recently paid to relatives by the Cuban government (to Peggy and<lb/>
Houston) and, above all perhaps, for insisting that the name Camp <hi>Lazear</hi><lb/>
be preserved when other Cubans, even friendly ones, were inclined to call<lb/>
it the Finlay Memorial. Those of us interested in bringing this project<lb/>
to a successful conclusion and in fostering Cuban-American harmony owe<lb/>
him a great debt. If, per chance, you should want to invite his wife to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04804006"/>
Page 4 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; February 7, 1955<lb/>
the hotel for cocktails or dinner, she would love it but she speaks poor<lb/>
English, is not easy to talk to and is not a grand lady like Tina or Lydia.<lb/>
She and Pedro are about in their late 30's or early 40's. He is a very<lb/>
dynamic physician in and out of politics, known by everybody although of<lb/>
the opposite party from Batista. And, above all, he produces!</p>
<p>Accept any invitations from Tina or Lydia that you are inclined to accept.<lb/>
Tina at least is quite wealthy; both are very pro-U.S. and pro-Lazear and<lb/>
have done <hi>much</hi> for this whole project but in an entirely different way<lb/>
and on a different level from Pedro.</p>
<p>The enclosed manuscripts are not for publication nor are they yet in shape<lb/>
for critical reading by everybody. The manuscript needs a little shift of<lb/>
emphasis here and there to satisfy all concerned. It would not yet satisfy<lb/>
Estella Agremonte or Mrs. Moran - not enough yet about their relative.<lb/>
Therefore I am not sending them copies yet and I suggest that you not show<lb/>
it to them but you can show anything or everything to Tina, Lydia and<lb/>
Pedro. They understand informal, incomplete manuscripts.</p>
<p>You will see that I am still uncertain about a few things: (1) The cementery -<lb/>
we are making headway on its precise location; there are still two rival<lb/>
spots but they are only 100 or 200 yards apart, and (2) regarding item<lb/>
10-A, page 1 of the &ldquo;wanderings&rdquo; - my positioning of the old Post Hospital<lb/>
Buildings with respect to the new Cuban Hospital Buildings is the best I<lb/>
can do myself. I plan to have an architect-friend do a finished job for<lb/>
me.</p>
<p>Keep the copies of the talk and the geographic locations and the two 1950<lb/>
maps of Havana (sorry I only marked up one map) but please return all my<lb/>
photographs, some of them are my only copies. Later I can make copies<lb/>
of some if you wish.</p>
<p>If you can well do the following for me, I would deeply appreciate it.<lb/>
(1) Please show Pedro the photographs and maps and comments about the<lb/>
cemetery and ask him how he is coming along with his own identification.<lb/>
He has not seen my latest location of it as indicated on these maps.<lb/>
(2) If time permits, will you get me the present number of old #16 General<lb/>
Lee Street directly opposite the present #103; also the present number of<lb/>
Lee's headquarters, if it has a number. (3) Is the new small Lions'<lb/>
Memorial to Finlay across the Miramar Bridge over the Almendares River<lb/>
or have I misnamed the bridge? (4) If you visit the Travel Bureau for<lb/>
other maps and if they have a newer one than the 1950 one, please swipe<lb/>
one for me. I suggest that you get two or three and mark them up for<lb/>
other members of the family. (5) Tell Pedro I will send very soon the<lb/>
data for the &ldquo; Friends of Camp Lazear.&rdquo; I am all for it and will help<lb/>
aggressively. (6) In particular, would you ask Pedro if he has made<lb/>
any progress towards getting me the microfilm of Finlay's diaries which<lb/>
I have been trying to get for five years now. Also ask Tina or Lydia<lb/>
the same thing, but don't let Pedro know that you made two inquiries or<lb/>
vice versa as I am having each try to work on this for me. They will<lb/>
understand fully.</p>
<p>Best wishes for a wonderful time.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH: alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
(Dictated by Dr. Hench but signed, in his absence, by secretary)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
