<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04816001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 2, 1955</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04816001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1955-09-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Nogueira, Pedro</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Harwick, Harry</name>
<name type="person">Fishbein, Morris</name>
<name type="person">Spies, Tom D.</name>
<name type="person">Smith, Louise F.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Tina</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cabrera, Lydia</name>
<name type="person">Caswell, Jr., William W.</name>
<name type="person">Perez, Yldefonso</name>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1955-09-02">September 2, 1955</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04816001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 2, 1955</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is concerned about the status of Camp Lazear, and wants anything done that would expedite its becoming a museum.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1955-09-02">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Pedro Nogueira, September 2, 1955</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04816001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1955-09-02">September 2, 1955</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira<lb/>
Marti 219, Marianao<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Pedro:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I shall be interested to see you in Philadelphia and go over your discoveries<lb/>
with respect to the old American cemetery and I will certainly try to re-<lb/>
member to bring with me your previous correspondence thereon.</p>
<p>I have not quite finished my Philadelphia talk because Tocantins has not told<lb/>
me what to omit to avoid over-lapping.</p>
<p>With respect to your item #3, let me put your mind at rest at once. Pedro,<lb/>
you and I have had such a happy and sympathetic relationship that you must<lb/>
know I would never do anything intentionally to hurt you or your colleagues<lb/>
or do anything important behind your back. The situation is this.</p>
<p>First and flatly, your informant, whoever he is, is almost 100% wrong but<lb/>
whatever truth there is in it is as follows: You may remember that several<lb/>
years ago, in order to try to stimulate the preservation of Camp Lazear (long<lb/>
before your influence in this behalf began to be felt in Cuba and long before<lb/>
the patronates were organized), I got an informal promise of $10,000 from the<lb/>
Mayo Clinic through Mr. Harry Harwick who was then the head of the Executive<lb/>
Department and, in some ways, the informal &ldquo;head of the Clinic.&rdquo; This was in<lb/>
the days before I knew you very well and I think most of my contacts were with<lb/>
and through General Ramos. I was permitted to make that tentative offer of<lb/>
support in a letter to someone and later noticed that the offer was published<lb/>
in the Havana newspapers. Those were the days that Johnny Moran was my main<lb/>
associate. But nothing happened.</p>
<p>Some time later, after the camp-site had been made a national monument, but<lb/>
before anything was done to preserve it, I visited the Vice-President of Cuba<lb/>
and during a conversation, offered him my own personal check for $1,000 just<lb/>
to have the privilege of having a corr<del>e</del><add>u</add>gated iron protection put around the<lb/>
caseta until such time as the Cuban Government would protect it. But my offer<lb/>
was politely refused. Nothing more happened until you organized the patrons.</p>
<p>Since then, Mr. Harwick has retired and I must confess the spirit of our<lb/>
Executive Department is now somewhat less generous and more realistic and<lb/>
whether the Clinic would renew this offer, I frankly do not know. I intend<lb/>
to find out in the near future but must handle the matter diplomatically.<lb/>
I should first see Mr. Harwick because if he, though retired, could speak<lb/>
for me and have the Executive Department of the Clinic reactivate this offer,<lb/>
that would be by far the best.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04816002"/>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira &nbsp;&nbsp; - 2 - &nbsp;&nbsp; September 2, 1955</p>
<p>The simple reason that the Clinic is less generous now in all such extra-<lb/>
mural contributions is that we have had to build a $14,000,000 building,<lb/>
just completed a year ago, which I imagine is not yet paid for, and even<lb/>
more important, the extra facilities have required a fairly large expan-<lb/>
sion of personnel. Therefore, like all sensible institutions, the Clinic<lb/>
has been retrenching in less important expenditures and we are going<lb/>
through a period of &ldquo;careful expenditures,&rdquo; to speak mildly. This has<lb/>
been fairly extensive and has involved actually the reorganization of two<lb/>
or three ancillary departments - research departments which had little or<lb/>
no direct contact with clinical medicine. Therefore a gift of $10,000<lb/>
today for this project would be reviewed much more carefully than when it<lb/>
was previously made. I do not actually know that the offer has been can-<lb/>
celled or would not be renewed but I imagine, under the circumstances, it has<lb/>
just lapsed by default.</p>
<p>This is the extent of any information I have regarding any &ldquo;thousands of<lb/>
dollars&rdquo; from the Clinic for any project whatever.</p>
<p>During the many years that I have been trying to do something about Camp<lb/>
Lazear, I made numerous contacts. Most of them were pleasant but relatively<lb/>
unprofitable. For example, in earlier years, I occasionally contacted Doctor<lb/>
Carbonell who, in his own time, was helpful and it was he who got me<lb/>
to see the Vice-President. In the last two or three years, I have only seen<lb/>
him socially and have not discussed any moves with respect to Camp Lazear.<lb/>
Now, as you know, I have been planning to develop, at the appropriate time,<lb/>
a committee of what might be called the &ldquo;American Friends of Camp Lazear,&rdquo;<lb/>
but three things have prevented the organization of this group to date.<lb/>
First, because of the long Cuban delays, I had nothing tangible to propose<lb/>
to such an American group. Since I could not even myself spend $1,000 to<lb/>
protect the &ldquo;national monument&rdquo;, there was no use for me to interest any<lb/>
Americans as the legalization of the caseta as a national monument, tem-<lb/>
porarily at least, prevented any private contributions or suggestions.</p>
<p>Secondly, the war began just as I was starting correspondence with Fishbein<lb/>
and others in the American Medical Association with respect to the formation<lb/>
of such a group and, third, cortisone hit and has preoccupied me intensely<lb/>
ever since.</p>
<p>The main reason, however, that I have not gotten back to this project is be-<lb/>
cause I have not been sure of myself and of just what any outside group could<lb/>
propose or do for Camp Lazear. Although you and I have discussed this often<lb/>
in general terms, actually, Pedro, you and I have never gotten down to &ldquo;brass<lb/>
tacks&rdquo; and this you and I must do in the near future. Meanwhile the various<lb/>
contacts I previously made in Cuba have entertained me socially from time to<lb/>
time and we have always discussed the support of the Camp Lazear project but<lb/>
in very general terms. The contacts have included Tom Spies and Mrs. Louise<lb/>
Smith, chiefly, and various friends of theirs.</p>
<p>Confidentially, Pedro, at the time I came to Havana for the Nutrition Congress<lb/>
about two or three years ago, I found three groups pulling me, pleasantly, in<lb/>
three different directions. You and your developing group were by far the<lb/>
most important, indeed the only important group, but Tom Spies had some ideas<lb/>
of his own and Mrs. Smith had some ideas. The latter were interested because<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04816003"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira &nbsp;&nbsp; - 3 - &nbsp;&nbsp; September 2, 1955<lb/>
they weren't yet sure that you and your associates were actually going to be<lb/>
able to do anything. I allowed myself to explore various ideas with these<lb/>
friends without committing myself to anything. These friends were quite un-<lb/>
selfish and merely wanted to help in case the Cuban Government did nothing.<lb/>
You can be positively assured of that. One suggestion was that if the Cuban<lb/>
Government would do nothing, I would meet with a small group of Mrs. Smith's<lb/>
friends and perhaps they, with or without the auspices of F.I.M., would help<lb/>
me raise money and use Camp Lazear as a symbol of Cuban American mutual in-<lb/>
terest and friendship. Again, I can assure you positively that this was their<lb/>
only motive and, to the extent that this idea still persists (as I shall men-<lb/>
tion shortly) that is still their only intention. Of course, let us be frank.<lb/>
To the extent that these good people, acting purely as local Cuban-American<lb/>
friends of Camp Lazear or under the general sponsorship of F.I.M., might get<lb/>
some pleasant and quite bona fide publicity for F.I.M., that would be to the<lb/>
credit of F.I.M.</p>
<p>Pedro, I have done not one single thing underhandedly. I thought you knew<lb/>
that Mrs. Smith was interested. I am sure I told you and I suspect that I<lb/>
have written you a little of this, although I am dictating this from my<lb/>
office without reviewing any correspondence. In any event, the situation<lb/>
is simply this. You and I know that much remains to be done at Camp Lazear<lb/>
to satisfy not others, perhaps, but you and me with our higher ambitions.<lb/>
I think we both would like to see the caseta under permanent cover, sur-<lb/>
rounded by an appropriate little museum. We both want the former site of<lb/>
Building No. 2 purchased, preserved and marked. We both want to have pre-<lb/>
served enough of the land to stop the encroaching quarries. We both want to<lb/>
fill up (if not a little museum) at least the inside of the caseta with<lb/>
photographs, display cabinets, etc. We both want a stone and bronze marker<lb/>
on the site of Building No. 2 and an explanatory bronze tablet outside the<lb/>
caseta. The lesser of our larger plan is to have the caseta enclosed in a<lb/>
little museum and in the rooms thereof a rather complete historical display<lb/>
to include many items that I have and that you have, and that we may get<lb/>
from the Finlay family. Under such circumstances, we both want to have<lb/>
the caseta refurnished as it was in 1901.</p>
<p>The larger phase of our bigger plan would be to connect all of this with a<lb/>
living memorial, either a public health unit or some other structure (of<lb/>
which the museum would be an annex) which would be of public service to the<lb/>
people of Quemados de Marianao. So much for the larger plan.</p>
<p>Some immediate requirements we have discussed include the purchase of the land<lb/>
in front of the caseta, that is, where Building No. 2 was; the improvement of<lb/>
the road; the marker at the site of Building No. 2, and the production of a<lb/>
little souvenir booklet, printed in English and Spanish to be sold at the<lb/>
caseta, and also the designation of the caseta as a point of historical<lb/>
interest for tourists and to be mentioned in the various guide books and<lb/>
tourist weeklies.</p>
<p>As I have discussed these projects in a general way with you (and indeed some<lb/>
of these were your own ideas or were transmitted to me by Doctor Recio, the<lb/>
head of the Patronates) so I have discussed them in a friendly way with Tina<lb/>
and Lydia, also with the American Ambassador on one occasion, and also with<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04816004"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira &nbsp;&nbsp; - 4 - &nbsp;&nbsp; 
September 2, 1955<lb/>
Mrs. Smith on one or two occasions. You will remember how interested Mr.<lb/>
William Caswell was at the time of the dedication. He and Mrs. Smith par-<lb/>
ticularly, got quite enthusiastic and before I left they called a hasty<lb/>
little meeting of perhaps eight or ten close friends, all Americans, I<lb/>
think. It was really a cocktail party for Mary and me but after the drinks,<lb/>
they asked me to expound on the future plans for Camp Lazear. I talked<lb/>
quite informally for possibly an hour and mentioned, in general, all of<lb/>
the above plans, throwing together without discrimination the ideas of<lb/>
Doctor Recio, of yourself and of me. They expressed strong approval and<lb/>
if I had not had to leave the next day, I think we might, right then, have<lb/>
made the first steps toward organizing the Havana Chapter of the American<lb/>
Friends of Camp Lazear. But it never went beyond the talking stage. This<lb/>
was about two years ago. I was supposed to correspond with them, write<lb/>
down the specific details of these projects and hopes and then form a group<lb/>
in this country which might be called the United States Chapter of the<lb/>
American Friends, to raise money along with the Havana chapter. The sug-<lb/>
gestion was made that the Havana Chapter might be expanded to include prominent<lb/>
and wealthy Cubans so that it would be the Cuban-American Friends of Camp<lb/>
Lazear, and it was to be mostly a matter of personal solicitation among a<lb/>
relatively few wealthy people. I can assure you that this was mostly just<lb/>
enthusiastic talk and that whatever plans we had, when the preliminaries<lb/>
materialized, were to be submitted to the patrons and that both of these<lb/>
groups were to be formed solely and entirely to accomplish not only the modest<lb/>
hopes of the patrons, but to accomplish perhaps their wildest hopes (that is,<lb/>
really the hopes of you and me). But again, I have been so terribly busy<lb/>
plus, very confidentially, a borderline nervous exhaustion state (from which<lb/>
I am fortunately recovering nicely), that I have done practically nothing and<lb/>
of course my American friends in Havana have done nothing.</p>
<p>Nothing was done except two things. Some time after my last visit with you,<lb/>
I did write down these various hopes and plans and included them in a report<lb/>
which I sent to the Walter Reed Memorial Association last November. I pre-<lb/>
sented the report in person and my main reason was to get the immediate sup-<lb/>
port of the Surgeon General of the U. S. Army with respect to a few items:<lb/>
to find for us the old Yldefonso Perez model of the Post Hospital which apparently<lb/>
is now at Carlisle Barracks and to save it for our museum at Camp Lazear; to<lb/>
enlist his support so that I might have the Finlay data microfilmed and to<lb/>
get from him not only some old Army cots of 1900 which might be in some old<lb/>
Army warehouse and also see if the Surgeon General's Library would finish<lb/>
translating every one of Finlay's papers.</p>
<p>The second thing I did was not done until a few months ago when Captain and<lb/>
Mrs. Gawne wrote that they hoped to visit Havana. I bestirred myself and<lb/>
worked hard several evenings, writing up in a different arrangement and<lb/>
describing briefly the various places in Havana and Quemados connected with<lb/>
the yellow fever episode. As it turned out, this revision might well be used,<lb/>
at least in part, for the little booklet you and I hope to prepare to be sold<lb/>
at the caseta. I think I sent you copies of these data. I had hoped then<lb/>
to follow through and send these to Mrs. Smith, Mr. Caswell and others but,<lb/>
again, I get too involved.</p>
<p>The last chapter of this story now follows. I think it was possibly two or<lb/>
three months ago that I had a letter either from Tina or from Mrs. Smith, a<lb/>
purely social letter (my brother and I ran into Tina and Lydia in Paris last<lb/>
fall). In any event, they reminded me that these American friends were still<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04816005"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira &nbsp;&nbsp; - 5 - &nbsp;&nbsp; September 2, 1955<lb/>
waiting to hear from me and would be glad to organize whenever I could help<lb/>
and give them the appropriate information. They expressed the hope that<lb/>
I might return this next December for Finlay Day and talk to them again, and<lb/>
that is where it stands.</p>
<p>Now actually, Pedro, as you see, everything up to now has been purely conversa-<lb/>
tion and, in summary, the embryonic plan is simply in line with what you and I<lb/>
have so often discussed - for me to form an American branch of the &ldquo;Friends of<lb/>
Camp Lazear&rdquo; (and the Reed family and others have promised to support this when<lb/>
I get around to it). Second, for you and me to form either a Havana section of<lb/>
&ldquo;American Friends of Camp Lazear&rdquo; or a &ldquo;Cuban-American Friends of Camp Lazear.&rdquo;<lb/>
Third, for these groups to know (from you, Doctor Recio, the Patrons and me)<lb/>
just what the Patrons can and cannot do and what they would like to have help<lb/>
on and then for these groups to go out and get the money and to work through<lb/>
the Patrons for the proper preservation of Camp Lazear plus a living memorial<lb/>
of some sort.</p>
<p>Now if anybody, unknown to me, has <del>more</del> ideas more expansive than this, for<lb/>
any other purpose than this or for any selfish purpose and for any purpose<lb/>
contrary to the wishes of the Patrons, I know absolutely nothing about it and<lb/>
would not support it if I did. I think you know me well enough, Pedro, to<lb/>
know that I have no capacity to deceive and certainly not the intention. I<lb/>
have no doubt that I have talked to many people and have not, perhaps, reported<lb/>
to you every talk or visit or conversation, but that is simply because I have<lb/>
continued to do what you and I have been doing together and independently for<lb/>
several years; namely, to try to find proper support from any and all appropriate<lb/>
sources in a diplomatic and non-conflicting way. Everything actually is held<lb/>
in abeyance because you and I, the prime movers, have not yet had the oppor-<lb/>
tunity to sit down together perhaps with Doctor Recio and decide, first of<lb/>
all, what the Cuban Government and Patrons can do themselves and what help<lb/>
they want for projects they would approve. This is the next step. Whether<lb/>
you and I can do it by mail or whether I can get to Havana in December remains<lb/>
to be seen but certainly we can discuss it three weeks from now in Philadelphia<lb/>
and may I suggest that you discuss my letter frankly with Doctor Recio if you<lb/>
think that wise now. Make your own list of your own ideas for Camp Lazear and<lb/>
we will match our lists in Philadelphia.</p>
<p>I don't plan to arrive in Philadelphia until noon on September 22 and plan to<lb/>
leave the afternoon of the 23rd. Why don't you and I disappear after the<lb/>
evening meeting of the 22nd. We could do a lot together in two hours, even<lb/>
if we have to stay up after midnight. Or, if absolutely necessary, I could<lb/>
get to Philadelphia, somehow, earlier in the morning of the 22nd and hide out<lb/>
with you that morning. My absence-time for the rest of this year is quite<lb/>
limited and every half day I am away is counted, but if you think we can dis-<lb/>
cuss this satisfactorily late Thursday evening, the 22nd, I will try to do<lb/>
whatever you propose.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH: alo<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f04816006"/>
Dr. Pedro Nogueira &nbsp;&nbsp; - 6 &nbsp;&nbsp; September 2, 1955<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I enclose a copy of this letter in case you wish to show it to Doctor<lb/>
Recio. I want it distinctly understood that if he did not know of any of this<lb/>
talk and informal thinking and planning, I assumed that you knew it and what-<lb/>
ever I had not told you was simply because it was still all in such a nebulous<lb/>
stage and under no circumstances were any plans of mine at least being made<lb/>
that would not have been brought, at the appropriate time, for the considera-<lb/>
tion of the Patrons. Whatever rumors or remarks otherwise you hear do not<lb/>
come from me, have no connection with me and do not have my approval. I<lb/>
imagine someone, not knowing how close you and I have been working and how<lb/>
greatly I feel indebted to Doctor Recio and his associates. Someone who has<lb/>
heard of the informal conversations mentioned above has simply &ldquo;talked big&rdquo;,<lb/>
a sort of wishful thinking, and that is all there is to the rumors you have<lb/>
heard.<lb/>
P.P.S: I am so frank about this that if you want an extra copy of this<lb/>
letter for anyone else, let me know and we will send it to you.<lb/>
Sincerely,<lb/>
P. S. Hench, M.D.<lb/>
PSH: alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
