<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04814001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Manuscript: Brief History of Yellow Fever up to 1905, by Pedro Noguiera, September 22, 1955</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Nogueira, Pedro</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04814001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1955-09-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Bennett, George</name>
<name type="person">Goodner, Kenneth</name>
<name type="person">Soper, Fred L.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Chaille, Stanford E.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Mitchell, S. Weir</name>
<name type="person">Matas, Rodolfo</name>
<name type="person">Ruiz, Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Wasdin, Eugene</name>
<name type="person">Geddings, Henry Downes</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Nott, Josiah C.</name>
<name type="person">Beauperthuy, Loius-Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>25 pp.</extent>
<date value="1955-09-22">September 22, 1955</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04814001</idno>
<title>Manuscript: Brief History of Yellow Fever up to 1905, by Pedro Noguiera, September 22, 1955</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Nogueira outlines the history of yellow fever and the many resultant casualties. He then describes the work of Finlay and the Yellow Fever Commission. He is critical of Sternberg's initial dismissal of the mosquito as the source of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1955-09-22">
<head>Manuscript: Brief History of Yellow Fever up to 1905, by Pedro Noguiera, September 22, 1955</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04814001"/>
<p><hi>BRIEF HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER UP TO 1905<lb/>
DR: PEDRO NOGUEIRA<lb/>
CENTENARY OF GRADUATION DR CARLOS J. FINLAY<lb/>
JEFFERSON MEDICAL COLLEGE<lb/>
PHILADELPHIA.-U.S.A.<lb/>
SEPTEMBER 22nd and 23rd.- 1955</hi><lb/>
<add>Given to me by Pedro<lb/>
9&sol;22&sol;55<lb/>
<hi>see p 17</hi></add></p>
<pb n="2" id="f04814002"/>
<p><hi>BRIEF HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER UP TO 1905</hi></p>
<p>Dr. Pedro Nogueira</p>
<p>Dr. George Bennett.<lb/>
Dr. Kenneth <add>G</add>oodner.<lb/>
<add>Dr. Fred. L. Soper.</add></p>
<p>Fortunate<add>ly</add> posterity which shall not experience such an<lb/>
abyss of pain; <del><unclear>is shall</unclear></del><add>that will</add> give to our testimony the appearance<lb/>
of a fable. Thus wrote the poet Petrarch <del>apropos</del><add>in relation to</add> the 1348<lb/>
plague in Florence. Likewise the gay adverturers who shared<lb/>
with Columbus the discovery of America had to look upon Yellow<lb/>
Fever in the same manner the Florentine<add>s</add> did. That wonderful<lb/>
expedition was accompanied by a mysterious affection which<lb/>
chopped off lives indiscriminatedly, and turned the few who<lb/>
survived into veritable human spectres. It appeared as if<lb/>
the grandeur and riches of the Great Khan were guarded and<lb/>
protected by a yellow monster, as a sort of divine punish-<lb/>
ment. <del>We</del> <del>t</del><add>T</add>hus <add>we</add> know Yellow Fever, which over four centuries<lb/>
was to unloosen its terrible fury.</p>
<p>?What can we say of its origin? Under the light of<lb/>
gathered data, the question of the pre-existence of the<lb/>
terrible endemia of America in past ages, perhaps hundreds<lb/>
of centuries before the Conquest, looms imperatively today.<lb/>
Nor can there be any doubt as to the fact that it was a per-<lb/>
manent focus, radiating epidemic outbreaks to Europe over<lb/>
four centuries.</p>
<p>It cannot be admitted that it originates in Europe, as<lb/>
there is nothing to that effect in the great works of Hippo-<lb/>
crates, who was a witness to the warring conflagrations of<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04814003"/>
-2<lb/>
his time, in which there possibly prevailed conditions sim-<lb/>
ilar to the contemporaneous ones.</p>
<p>The theory of doctors Audourd and Carter that it origi-<lb/>
nates in Africa, is countered by the fact that in the 15th and<lb/>
16th centuries the national<add>s</add> of several European countries fre-<lb/>
quented the Western coast<add>s</add> of Africa, which are areas that show<lb/>
today a high index of <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>endemia</add>, and there are no records of<lb/>
a mortality similar to that suffered by Ovando, Hojeda, etc.<lb/>
If such a state of affairs had developed, it would not have<lb/>
been overlooked by the writers of those ages, nor by the Por-<lb/>
tuguese navigators, such as Bartolom&eacute; Diaz, Alburquerque et<lb/>
al. In 1879 Dr. Joseph Jones, of the University of Louisiana,<lb/>
published a paper in the &ldquo;PROCEEDINGS OF THE LOUISIANA STATE<lb/>
ASSOCIATION&rdquo;, page 59, in which, after a critical examination<lb/>
of the works of Herodotus, Strabo, Cornelius, <add>Justin,</add> Virgil, Floro,<lb/>
Veleyo Paterculo, Caesar, Horace, Cicero, Xenophon and Taci-<lb/>
tus, states that he had not been able to identify the illness<lb/>
in any of them. <del><unclear>Further</unclear></del><add>Moreover</add>, he says that in the papers of the<lb/>
writers of the Middle Ages<add>,</add> Yellow Fever does not appear in any-<lb/>
thing until the discovery of America. Finally, the American<lb/>
origin of the disease is strengthened by the discovery of Jungle<lb/>
Yellow Fever in South America, and by the fact that there is no<lb/>
description of any important focus in Africa or in any other<lb/>
place.</p>
<p><hi>ANCIENT TIMES</hi></p>
<p>The study of the Mayan codices &ldquo;CHUMAYEL&rdquo; and &ldquo;TIZIMIN&rdquo;,<lb/>
made by the <unclear>Bishop</unclear> of Yucatan Creacencio Carrillo Ancora, proves<lb/>
beyond all doubt, - as pointed out by Finlay in his 1897 paper<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04814004"/>
-3<lb/>
&ldquo;CONFORMITY BETWEEN THE PHILOLOGY AND THE HISTORY OF YELLOW<lb/>
FEVER&rdquo;, - that before the discovery there were epidemics of<lb/>
Yellow Fever, or of &ldquo;Black Vomit&rdquo;, in the coasts of Central<lb/>
America. As described by Carrillo, in folios 16 and 17 of<lb/>
the Tizimin Codex, handed down to us by the Indians of Tizi-<lb/>
mincah, there is a note the translation of which reports the<lb/>
fourth epidemic of black vomit in Yucatan in 1648, which coin-<lb/>
cides with what is described in the Chumayel Codex. The said<lb/>
writer points out that as there is no other report of the di-<lb/>
sease until the said year, and that as the mentioned Peninsula<lb/>
was not discovered until 1517, it must be acknowledged that<lb/>
the other three epi<add>d</add>emics were suffered before the last date<lb/>
shown above.</p>
<p>The first accurate description of Yellow Fever seems to<lb/>
be the one made in the year 1495, after the battle known as<lb/>
Vega Real or Santo Cerro, faught by Columbus in Hispanicla<lb/>
against the Indians. After that the expeditions of Ovando,<lb/>
Nicueza, Hojeda et al, end in dreadful disasters. There can<lb/>
be no doubt that before the battle aforementioned<add>,</add> Yellow Fever<lb/>
exerted its lethal influence in the Antilles and in the Spanish<lb/>
Main under the names of MODORRA, MODORRA PESTILENCIAL and FIEBRE<lb/>
MALIGNA PUTRIDA; in Mexico under the names of PESTE and PESTI-<lb/>
LENCIAS, MATZLAHUATT and COCOLITZLE; in Yucatan under the name<lb/>
of XEKIK, and among the Caribs under the name of POULICANTINA.</p>
<p>Santo Domingo was scourged in 1495 and later in 1554, 1560,<lb/>
1567, 1580, 1583 and 1588, the last named date coinciding with<lb/>
pirate Drake's expedition which was totally annihilated. Ac-<lb/>
cording to the Spanish writers Hernandes Morej&oacute;n and Hurtado<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04814005"/>
-4<lb/>
de Mendoza, C&aacute;diz and Malaga were visited in 1507 and 1582.</p>
<p><hi>17TH AND 18TH CENTURIES</hi></p>
<p>In the year 1635 the Island of Guadeloupe was scourged<lb/>
and it caused the superb description of the epidemic made by<lb/>
Father Dutertr&eacute;. There was a second attack in 1648 when the<lb/>
epidemic reached Yucatan.</p>
<p>The Island of Cuba, a land favored by nature, was the<lb/>
most beautiful possession of the Spanish Crown, as in the same<lb/>
there are present all the necessary means which make for human<lb/>
happiness. Bathed by the Caribbean Sea, it sparkled in the<lb/>
distance as an emerald carved in a silver setting, and it served<lb/>
as a trading center to several world powers, thus being favored<lb/>
by great immigration currents. But<add>,</add> as if everywhere God wanted<lb/>
to remind man of his misfortunes, the cup of bitterness being<lb/>
behind apparent happiness, he placed among the delights of this<lb/>
paradise the exterminating disease of the Black Vomit. Accord-<lb/>
ing to Pezuela<add>,</add> in the year 1649 our country &ldquo;was pitilessly at-<lb/>
tacked by an unknown and horrible epidemic, imported from the<lb/>
American continent, one third of its population being devoured<lb/>
by a sort of a putrid fever.&rdquo; From that date on the bonfire<lb/>
with the <hi>yellow flame</hi> was kindled in the West-Indian Archipe- &check;<lb/>
lago, and the mass of new European visitors <del>shall make</del><add>made</add> the<lb/>
fire unextinguishable. In the years 1653, 1667 and 1668 Cuba<lb/>
is again attacked, and this condition will last<add>ed</add> <hi>until Gorgas<lb/>
applied the principles of Finlay early in 1901</hi>.</p>
<p>Barbados suffered an attack in 1647 for the first time,<lb/>
and in 1695 Admiral Wheeler's fleet <del>is</del><add>was</add> destroyed before the<lb/>
same could attack Martinique. In 1697 Admiral Neville suf-<lb/>
fered a similar damage.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f04814006"/>
<p>-5</p>
<p>Santa Lucia was visited in 1664 where 1,411 soldiers were<lb/>
killed out of a garrison of 1,500 men. In 1690 Martinique<lb/>
suffered one of the most fatal epidemics, known as Oriflamme,<lb/>
this being the name of the ship which brought it. As the men-<lb/>
tioned ship <add>came from Siam, making a</add> call in Brazil, the disease was named the &ldquo;Siam<lb/>
Illness.&rdquo;</p>
<p>According to Roche Lima, the first appearance of Yellow<lb/>
Fever in South America took place in 1658, in Pernambuco; it<lb/>
appeared in New York <add>in 1668, in Boston</add> in 1691, in Philadelphia in 1669 and in<lb/>
Charleston in 1699. It cannot be doubted that by the end of<lb/>
the century Yellow Fever is the owner of the American soil,<lb/>
and that the outbreaks reproduce<add>d</add> themselves each time a Euro-<lb/>
pean expedition trie<add>d</add> to penetrate into the West-Indian ring.<lb/>
Perhaps the Caribs play<add>ed</add> an important role in keeping this fire<lb/>
alive, by their numerous warring expeditions to the different<lb/>
islands.</p>
<p>But from the 18th century on, and due to the great military<lb/>
expeditions and to the facilities in the passenger routes, in-<lb/>
tensive Yellow Fever epidemics <del>break</del><add>broke</add> out. According to Grif-<lb/>
fith Hughes's &ldquo;HISTORY OF BARBADOS&rdquo;, the disease received its<lb/>
name because there it was called that <del><unclear>my</unclear></del>. The English<lb/>
speaking countries adopted that name for it, while the Spanish<lb/>
speaking ones called it &ldquo;Black Vomit&rdquo;, after the paper by the<lb/>
Spanish physician Juan Jos&eacute; Castelbondo, a resident in Cartagena<lb/>
de Indias, which was published in 1729.</p>
<p>In that century Havana was brutally <unclear><del>atcakked</del><add>attacked</add></unclear> several times,<lb/>
but we will only mention the 1762 epidemic, when the victorious<lb/>
army of the Earl of <add>Albemarle</add> saw his triumphant capture of<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04814007"/>
-6<lb/>
Havana blurred by the ha<add>vo</add>c played in his ranks by Yellow Fever.<lb/>
Out of his 15,000 men only 7,000 came out alive. The 7 Spanish<lb/>
regiments which arrived in Cuba in 1780, for the purpose of<lb/>
strengthening the forces of General Bernardo Galvez in Louisiana,<lb/>
were swept away and the same happened to the fleet of General<lb/>
Aristizabal when it returned from Santo Domingo.</p>
<p>Admiral Graydon in Guadeloupe, <add>in 1703,</add> and Admiral Vernon facing<lb/>
Cartagena in 1741, experienced the power of Yellow Fever. The<lb/>
latter, who had sailed from Southampton with 27,000 men to con-<lb/>
quer Mexico and Peru, lost 20,000 men in his ill-fated enter-<lb/>
prise. Gray's army in Martinique, and another one commanded<lb/>
by Abercrombie intended for the conquest of the other small<lb/>
islands, saw their <add>rank of</add> 13,000 men <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> disappear under the impact<lb/>
of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>Santo Domingo was a permanent focus during the whole cen-<lb/>
tury, and there are times when Yellow Fever is so intense in<lb/>
the Greater and Lesser Antilles, that it is hard to say who<lb/>
is the infected and who the infector.</p>
<p>If we move to the African Continent we find record of<lb/>
an invasion in Senegal in 1740, and in Sierra Leone in 1764.</p>
<p>Spain paid a high price for its trading monopoly because<lb/>
Malaga suffered 5 epidemics, causing the death of more than<lb/>
3,000 human beings in 1741. C&aacute;diz was scourged several times,<lb/>
and the Canary Islands suffered their first strong attack in<lb/>
1771.</p>
<p>First the cities of the British Colonies in North America,<lb/>
and later on those of the United States, were attacked on several<lb/>
occasions, making life practically impossible in some of the ports<lb/>
in the Atlantic coast and in the Gulf of Mexico. New York under<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04814008"/>
-7<lb/>
went no less than 7 important epidemics from 1702 to 1800.<lb/>
Philadelphia was scourged on 11 occasions and we all know<lb/>
about the 1793 epidemic, perfectly described by Mathew Carey<lb/>
in his excellent exposition of the horrors suffered by the in-<lb/>
habitants of that City. In this morning I want to say a few<lb/>
words of remembrance of the 4,041 persons who died from August<lb/>
to November of that year, and to do homage to our colleagues<lb/>
Hutchinson, Morris, Linn, Pennington, Dodds, Johnson, Glent-<lb/>
worth, Phile, Graham and Green, who were the victims of Yel-<lb/>
low Fever while fulfilling <del>to</del> their very last <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>moments</add> the<lb/>
sacred duties of our profession, - here in Philadelphia they<lb/>
wrote a page full of heroism and sacrifice.</p>
<p>Charleston was attacked 12 times and New Orleans suffered<lb/>
impacts on several occasions. The New York 1798 epidemic<lb/>
killed 2,300 persons; in New Orleans 4,044 human beings were<lb/>
lost, and Philadelphia was similarly shake<del>d</del><add>n</add> by the death of<lb/>
3,446 of its citizens. But this shroud reached other cities,<lb/>
such as Baltimore, Mobile, Norfolk, <del><unclear>stroving</unclear></del><add>leaving</add> death and desola-<lb/>
tion in its path.</p>
<p>In the 19th century we find the devastating epidemic which<lb/>
took hold among the men sent by Bonaparte to reconquer Santo<lb/>
Domingo. This expedition, 25,000 men strong, under the com-<lb/>
mand of General Leclerc, was totally swept away by Black Vomit.</p>
<p>Cuba suffered the sternness of <del>this</del><add>the</add> disease by more than<lb/>
25 outbreaks in the period extending from 1800 to 1887, and<lb/>
we may point out that the Spanish Government lost in the two<lb/>
Cuban wars more than 100,000 men. It may be stated that<add>,</add> un-<lb/>
questionably<add>,</add> Yellow Fever was the best ally of my country.</p>
<p>In this cent<add>u</add>ry the American cities along the Golf of Mexico<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f04814009"/>
-8<lb/>
were the ones mainly shaked. New Orleans had epidemic out-<lb/>
breaks from 1800 to 1878, and in one year alone, in 1853, it<lb/>
lost 8,101 of its inhabitants out of a total of 29,020 patients.<lb/>
Mobile, Houston, Galveston, Pensacola, Key West, etc., were<lb/>
attacked. We will not mention the total number of visits suf-<lb/>
fered by New York, New Jersey, Boston, Savannah, Norfolk, where<lb/>
in 1855 Yellow Fever killed 2,000 persons. Charleston had 5<lb/>
big outbreaks<add>,</add> <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> of which<add>,</add> the one in 1866 snatched 4,565 lives. In<lb/>
Memphis, Tennessee, scourged no less than 5 times, the epidemic<lb/>
killed 5,150 citizens in 1879 out of a total of 17,600 patients.</p>
<p>If we cast a rapid glance over the Old Continent, we find<lb/>
Madrid shake<del>d</del><add>n</add> in 1878, and the epidemics recorded in that cen-<lb/>
tury, in the cities of C&aacute;diz, Cartagena, J&eacute;res de la Frontera,<lb/>
M&aacute;laga and Barcelona, were really horrible, as in C&aacute;diz alone,<lb/>
a city which had 57,000 inhabitants at the time, 48,000 cases<lb/>
of Yellow Fever were recorded, with 7,307 deaths. J&eacute;rez de la<lb/>
Frontera had more than 14,000 deaths and its population was prac-<lb/>
tically desolated. In 1821 Barcelona lost 20,000 lives and Car-<lb/>
tagena, in 1804, some 12,000 of its citizens. Through the<lb/>
Canary Islands<add>,</add> it passed triunphantly on three occasions, leaving<lb/>
behind a wake of mourning and pain.</p>
<p>In 1856 Lisbon lost approximately 18,000 human beings, and<lb/>
thus <add>Livorno,</add> Brest, Marseille and Saint Nasaire were invaded.<lb/>
I<del>n</del><add>t</add> reached Gibraltar and Southampton and finally <add>Dr</add> Graves left<lb/>
for us a great description of the havoc it played in Dublin,<lb/>
in 1826.</p>
<p>In Africa the main epidemics took place in Senegal and<lb/>
Sierra Leone.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f04814010"/>
<p>-9</p>
<p>This rapid epidemiologic <add>and</add> historic outline of Yellow Fever<lb/>
brings us to the year 1878, when the disease invaded more than<lb/>
100 cities and villages in the United States, mainly in the<lb/>
States of Louisiana, Mississippi and Tennessee. The number<lb/>
of patients reached the figure of 120,000 out of which 20,000<lb/>
were lost. Besides taking a terrible toll in human life,<lb/>
it caused the country the economic loss of <add>$</add>100,000,000 dollars.</p>
<p>In view of this enormous destruction, the Congress of the<lb/>
United States passed a law in March 1879, setting up the National<lb/>
Board of Sanitation, appropriating the amount of $50,000.00<lb/>
for the same. The said amount was increased to $500,000.00 in<lb/>
July 2nd. The first resolution passed by the Board was to or-<lb/>
ganise a Commission to visit the West Indies, with the object<lb/>
of studying Black Vomit in the supposed sources of the disease,<lb/>
with a three month stay in Havana, then<del><unclear>es it would</unclear></del><add>to</add> carry on its<lb/>
work in Rio and other endemic areas. This Commission which I<lb/>
call the FIRST AMERICAN COMMISSION FOR THE STUDY OF YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
IN CUBA, was formed by Doctors Stanford, E. Chaill&eacute;, who presided<lb/>
over it, George Miller Stenberg, Secretary, Juan Guiteras, Engineer<lb/>
Mr. Thomas Hardee, and Messrs. Rudolph Matas and Henry Marcel. (We<lb/>
are fortunate to have in New Orleans that great figure Matas,<lb/>
who is the only survivor of that Commission.)</p>
<p>The report of this Commission was rendered on November 16th,<lb/>
1879, and among its conclusions the main one reads: &ldquo;Yellow<lb/>
Fever is an epidemic transmissible disease and the agent capable<lb/>
of transmitting the disease must be in the air.&rdquo; This conclu-<lb/>
sion, plus the microscopic preparations he had obtained, led<lb/>
Dr. Carlos J. Finlay, - who had participated in the works of the<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f04814011"/>
-10<lb/>
Commission, - to think of the possibility that the inoculating<lb/>
matter should be looked for in the blood vessels, and that from<lb/>
there it would pass by inoculation to the interior of a similar<lb/>
vessel<add>,</add> in the party receiving the infection. Thus Dr. Finlay<lb/>
moved along a new route, giving up his ideas in connection with<lb/>
atmospheric alkalinity, which he had studied<add>,</add> up to then. All<lb/>
the foregoing, the &ldquo;Nest Theory&rdquo; held at the time by Bemis,<lb/>
Stone et al, as well as the study of the evolutionary cycle of<lb/>
certain fungi, strengthened him in his new belief, and thus he<lb/>
<del>passed</del><add>expressed himself</add> in the International Sanitation Conference, held in Wash-<lb/>
ington on February 18th, 1861, the three conditions which are<lb/>
necessary for the propagation of Yellow Fever, namely:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1: The existence of a previous case of Yellow Fever.</item>
<item>2: The presence of a subject capable of catching the<lb/>
disease.</item>
<item>3: The presence of an agent, independent from the di-<lb/>
sease as well as from the patient, but necessary<lb/>
for the transmission of the same.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The eco is still alive of the revolutionary ideas con-<lb/>
tained in Dr. Finlay's paper titled &ldquo;The Mosquito <add>Hypothetically</add> Considered<lb/>
as the Agent in the Transmission of Yellow Fever,&rdquo; read by<lb/>
him in the Academy of Medico-Physical and Natural Sciences<lb/>
of Havana, in its session of August 14th, 1881. In this paper<lb/>
the third Washington conclusion carries name and surname, as he<lb/>
further points to the Culex mosquito, known today as the Aedes<lb/>
Egypti.</p>
<p>How was it to be believed what seemed a heresy? How<lb/>
could Finlay present a thesis bringing in the intervention of<lb/>
a new element, the insects, in the transmission of the disease<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f04814012"/>
-11<lb/>
to a healthy person? Being ahead of his time, it is logic-<lb/>
al that he was not understood and that he would <unclear>remain</unclear> thus<lb/>
over more than twenty years. Let us<add>,</add> review<add>,</add> what was the<lb/>
status of Yellow Fever at the time, in order to understand<lb/>
the greatness of his work.</p>
<p>What was it that explained this rapidly chang<add>ing</add> manner<lb/>
of attack? We are not going to make a stop before the di-<lb/>
versity of etiologic conceptions which were uttered, full of<lb/>
vagueness and lacking scientific basis, but which were the ob-<lb/>
ject of bitter disputes among its originators, although the<lb/>
said conceptions maintained everything concerning Yellow Fever<lb/>
in a deep mystery.</p>
<p>The work of Pasteur<add>,</add> opened a new field in the hypothesis<lb/>
of the etiology of Yellow Fever, and from that moment on numerous<lb/>
germs and bacteria were invoked, while the chimerical dreams<lb/>
of a number of researchers yielded to disciplined probationary<lb/>
work.</p>
<p>In view of the great diversity of bacteriologic opinions,<lb/>
the Honorable President of the United States, Mr. <del>Crover</del><add>Alexander Crover</add> Cleve-<lb/>
land <del>Alexander</del>, issued an order dated April 29th, 1887, appoint-<lb/>
ing Dr. George M. Stenberg, U. S. Army Surgeon, to go to Rio<lb/>
and Mexico to study matters connected with the said diverse<lb/>
opinions. The findings of his work were read by Stenberg be-<lb/>
fore the Medical Association of this hospitable City of Phila-<lb/>
delphia in April, 1888, and published in the Medical News of<lb/>
April 29th of the same year. He made evident that he had not<lb/>
found anything of interest in connection with his work on Yel-<lb/>
low Fever.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f04814013"/>
<p>-12</p>
<p>While all the above went on, Dr. Finlay continued his tenacious<lb/>
work to prove his genial hypothesis, effectively assisted by the<lb/>
only man in Cuba who believed him, his inseparable companion Dr.<lb/>
Claudio Delgado, encouraged in his irrevocable faith by his<lb/>
teacher Weir Mitchell, a pride of yours, and backed by Rudolph Matas<lb/>
in the beautiful city of New Orleans.</p>
<p>Upon his return to the United States<add>,</add> Dr. Stenberg, an un-<lb/>
tiring man, asked to be sent to Cuba to carry on his research.<lb/>
His request was granted by Special Order No. 93, of April 21st,<lb/>
1888, issued by the Secretary of War, Mr. William C. Endicott.<lb/>
This is what I call the SECOND AMERICAN COMMISSION FOR THE STUDY<lb/>
OF YELLOW FEVER SENT TO CUBA. Due to its limited means and<lb/>
having to render a report to the President before June 20th, he<lb/>
returned to the United States, but this made it possible for him<lb/>
to go to Decatur, Alabama, to study everything connected with<lb/>
Yellow Fever in the South of the United States.</p>
<p>Set on discovering the enigma of the disease, he ask<unclear><del>s</del><add>ed</add></unclear> to<lb/>
be sent to Havana again, and his request is granted by Order<lb/>
No. 30, issued by the War Department in Washington on February<lb/>
4th, 1889. By his tenacious and persevering work he was suc-<lb/>
cessful in eliminating many germs claimed to be the cause of<lb/>
Black Vomit.</p>
<p>There is no doubt that Stenberg was a real champion in this<lb/>
stage which he <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>completely</add> traversed. We saw him come to Cuba as<lb/>
the Secretary of the Chaille Commission, and in his eagerness to<lb/>
solve the riddle, he later on visited us on two occasions. But<lb/>
Stenberg was an experienced bacteriologist, as it is evident, and<lb/>
he followed the closed criterion of finding the solution in bac-<lb/>
teriology, unheedful of Finlay, not with standing the fact that on<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f04814014"/>
-13<lb/>
many occasions he had discussed with him (Finlay) man's impotency<lb/>
to defeat the terrible disease. Possibly no one had greater op-<lb/>
portunity of definitive<add>ly</add> solving the application of Finlay's prin-<lb/>
ples than Stenberg. Moreover, he had the occasion, when he<lb/>
visited Mexico, of making the acquaintance of Dr. Daniel Ruiz in<lb/>
Veracrus, who in 1885 had inoculated blood of a Yellow Fever pa-<lb/>
tient to a healthy person, to determine if thereby the infection<lb/>
could be transmitted. According to Stenberg's report: &ldquo;At the<lb/>
time of my visit to Veracruz he expressed his entire willingness<lb/>
to repeat these experiments in my presence. This was exactly<lb/>
what I desired, and accordingly Dr. Ruiz made three inoculation<lb/>
experiments upon three unacclimated persons in the hospital.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Further down he reports the failure of the said inoculations<lb/>
and adds: &ldquo;I was, therefore, anxious to make other experiments<lb/>
before leaving Vera Cruz but the time fixed by my orders expired<lb/>
without my having had an opportunity to do so.&rdquo; Thus we see<lb/>
on that occasion that the time factor possibly prevented Stenberg<lb/>
from achieving what Welch was to recommend later to the Reed Com-<lb/>
mission.</p>
<p>What we have quoted above is contained in page 109 of the book<lb/>
by Martha Stenberg titled &ldquo;GEORGE M. STENBERG. A BIOGRAPHY.&rdquo;<lb/>
A few lines before what I have transcribed there are the follow-<lb/>
ing words: &ldquo;Dr. Finlay, of Havana, believes that the disease is<lb/>
commonly transmitted by mosquitoes, which, after filling themselves<lb/>
from a yellow fever patient, transmit the germ by inoculation into<lb/>
susceptible persons.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>It is really unexplainable why Stenberg</hi>, a man of proved medical <unclear>Prejudiced</unclear><lb/>
culture, did not follow the ideas of Finlay, specially when he had<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f04814015"/>
-14<lb/>
failed to make any progress as a result of his untiring hours<lb/>
devoted to the study of Yellow Fever. Further down, when we<lb/>
direct our attention to several interesting points in regard<lb/>
to the Reed Commission, we will see that he had the honor of<lb/>
appointing the same.</p>
<p>Let us now mention that Dr. Guisseppe Sanarelli in 1887<lb/>
published in the Annals of the Pasteur Institute, a paper<lb/>
claiming that the cause of Yellow Fever was the icteroid bacil-<lb/>
lus, discovered by him. The publicity given to the same was<lb/>
such that the Surgeon General of the United States Army, General<lb/>
Wyman, at the end of 1898 sent a commission to Cuba, made up by<lb/>
doctors Wasding and Geddings, of the hospital service of the<lb/>
Navy, to verify the said claim. This is the commission which I<lb/>
call the THIRD AMERICAN COMMISSION FOR THE STUDY OF YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
IN CUBA. Wasding and Geddings published their conclusions in<lb/>
Washington, to the effect that they found the Sanarelli bacil-<lb/>
lus in thirteen patients out of the sixteen studied by them,<lb/>
thus maintaining in force the said chalatanry, prevalent at the<lb/>
time.</p>
<p>Stenberg, who had been promoted to the rank of Surgeon<lb/>
General, did not accept the ideas of Sanarelli, nor was he con-<lb/>
vinced by the conclusions of Wasding and Geddings, so he<lb/>
decided to send Dr. Aristides Agramonte to Cuba, whom he ins-<lb/>
tructed and authorized to do everything possible to clear up<lb/>
totally the said question. In his paper titled &ldquo;RELATION OF<lb/>
THE ICTERIOD BACILLUS TO YELLOW FEVER&rdquo; Dr. Agramonte proved<lb/>
that there was no connection between the two.</p>
<pb n="16" id="f04814016"/>
<p>-15</p>
<p>It will be noticed that at the end of the century the etio-<lb/>
logy of Yellow Fever is still an enigma except for Finlay, and<lb/>
we make an exception in his case because <add>after</add> he expounded in 1881<lb/>
his doctrine of the transmission of the disease by mosquitoes,<lb/>
he continued to work untiringly to prove to the world his scien-<lb/>
tific truth, studying in an exhaustive manner all the phases of<lb/>
it, namely, its etiology as well as bacteriology, epidemiology,<lb/>
clinical symptomatology, pathologic anatomy, prophilaxis, and<lb/>
describing minutely the anatomy of the Aedes Egypti, its habits<lb/>
and customs.</p>
<p>In the first period of Dr. Finlay's professional life con-<lb/>
nected with Yellow Fever, comprised between 1865 and 1881, he<lb/>
wrote ten papers on the subject, and from the last named date<lb/>
to his death, he published eighty works more related to the<lb/>
Black Vomit. His documents were written in several languages,-<lb/>
English, French, German and Spanish, but mostly in English, and<lb/>
in them he shows his deep knowledge. We cannot mention here<lb/>
his complete works, but we believe it would be well to single<lb/>
off, in addition to the paper read by him on August 14th, 1881,<lb/>
in the Academy of Sciences, the paper he made known in that same<lb/>
place in two of its sessions, namely, those of January 31st and<lb/>
February 29th, 1884, titled &ldquo;EXPERIMENTAL YELLOW FEVER COMPARED<lb/>
WITH THE NATURAL ONE IN ITS MORE BENIGN FORMS.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In the first part of this paper he starts by dealing with<lb/>
its incubational period, later on to discuss its diagnosis and<lb/>
benign cases in which albuminuria is present, and in those in<lb/>
which it is not. In the second part of his document he deals<lb/>
with Experimental Yellow Fever, inoculated by mosquito bites,<lb/>
setting down the manner in which to perform the inoculations.</p>
<pb n="17" id="f04814017"/>
<p>-16</p>
<p>In it he masterly describes the first ones carried out on<lb/>
Spanish soldiers stationed at the Caba&ntilde;a Fortress, as well as<lb/>
those performed on Jesuit Fathers in the &ldquo;San Jos&eacute;&rdquo; farm, in<lb/>
Marianao, (where in 1900 the Reed Commission was to establish<lb/>
the Lazear Camp), and in his conclusions Finlay says: &ldquo;From<lb/>
the fact that Yellow Fever is inoculable by mosquito bites,<lb/>
there follows the need of protecting the patients attacked by<lb/>
that affection from the mentioned stings, in order to prevent<lb/>
the propagation of the disease.&rdquo; We find here, specifically<lb/>
pointed out, the fundamental principle in force today in the<lb/>
prophilaxis of Yellow Fever. In the part devoted to its diag-<lb/>
nosis he deals with the called &ldquo;acclimation fever&rdquo;, pointing<lb/>
out the ephemeral attacks of the disease which render immune<lb/>
those suffering <add>the ailment, a Finlayan conception now identified</add> under the denomination of &ldquo;UNAPPARENT YELLOW<lb/>
FEVER.&rdquo; He also discusses the incomplete or abortive forms<lb/>
of Yellow Fever, in which the symptomatologic picture may be<lb/>
restricted to a feverish type characteristic of ordinary Yellow<lb/>
Fever, and its evolution within the limits pointed out, the<lb/>
other elements of the diagnosis being reduced to their slightest<lb/>
expression, or lacking completely.</p>
<p>In his paper read at the Convention of Hygiene and Demo-<lb/>
graphy, held in Budapest in September, 1894, he empahtically <lb/>
said the following: &ldquo;to prevent Yellow Fever the following<lb/>
should be done:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>&ldquo;1 - Prevent mosquitoes from biting patients of Yellow<lb/>
Fever.</item>
<item>&ldquo;2 - De<del>wtor</del><add>stro</add>y as many contaminated mosquitoes as possible.<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f04814018"/>
-17</item>
<item>&ldquo;3 - To consider a place free from Yellow Fever, it must<lb/>
be kept in mind that mosquitoes fed on Yellow Fever<lb/>
patients may live from thirty-five to forty days under<lb/>
favorable conditions, therefore, prevention must last<lb/>
until that period has past, as a contaminated mosquito<lb/>
is infectious during its life time.&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
<p>Please consider the value of these postulates under the<lb/>
light of our present knowledge, and to what an extent that mis-<lb/>
understood ma<add>n</add>, who found no respect for his scientific truth,<lb/>
was a <unclear><del>seer</del><add>Phrofet. purphet</add></unclear></p>
<p>In his memorable paper titled &ldquo;REVIEW OF THE PROGRESS<lb/>
ACHIEVED IN THE 19TH CENTURY IN THE STUDY OF THE PROPAGATION<lb/>
OF YELLOW FEVER&rdquo;, published in 1901, he gathers, with the help<lb/>
of his great companion, Dr. Claudio Delgado, the data on all<lb/>
experimental inoculations practiced thus far, which is a wonder-<lb/>
ful exposition of his tenacity and faith in his convictions.<lb/>
It may be argued that the said papers were not completely con-<lb/>
clusive, but there can be no doubt that he established the firm<lb/>
basis of a new doctrine, which would make possible the full con-<lb/>
firmation of his ideas later on. It is my opinion that if his<lb/>
guiding lines to put an end to Yellow Fever had been followed,<lb/>
the disease would have been conquered years before, thus saving<lb/>
thousands of human lives.</p>
<p>Before bringing to an end this part of our paper relating<lb/>
to Finlay, it must be mentioned that Yellow Fever was not his<lb/>
only concern, as he worked on cholera, filariasis, goiter,<lb/>
tetanus, ophthalmology, cancer, leprosy, tuberculosis, trichi-<lb/>
nosis, beriberi, glanders, etc., publishing more than fifty<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f04814019"/>
-18<lb/>
papers on subjects concerning public health other than Yellow<lb/>
Fever.</p>
<p>I do not want to tarry on the subject of the different<lb/>
opinions held in connection with insects prior to Finlay's<lb/>
relative to mosquitoes, nor on the ones which were formulated<lb/>
after that, as the majority of them deserves no special atten-<lb/>
tion. We will limit ourselves to a mention of Nott and Beau-<lb/>
phertuy using therefor the words expressed in Dr. H. R. Carter's<lb/>
book &ldquo;THE PRACTICE OF MEDICINE IN THE TROPICS&rdquo;, reading: &ldquo;Neither<lb/>
Beauphertuy nor Nott, in spite of the ingenuity of the theories<lb/>
expounded by them, may be considered as predecessors to Finlay<lb/>
regarding the theory of the transmission of Yellow Fever by mos-<lb/>
quitoes.&rdquo;<lb/>
<unclear><add>forkup</add></unclear></p>
<p>However, I may add that in the Convention on the History of<lb/>
Medicine, <add>recently</add> held in <del>Salerno</del><add>Rome</add>, Italy, this problem was definitely set-<lb/>
tled.</p>
<p>While Finlay was carrying out all that has been reviewed<lb/>
above, the drama of Cuba want on unfolding itself, was everlast-<lb/>
ingly present in its horizon, and yet no one paid any attention<lb/>
to him, - he was still the object of mockery. This gloomy<lb/>
panorama led General Stenberg to appoint the Reed Commission, or<lb/>
the FOURTH AMERICAN COMMISSION FOR THE STUDY OF YELLOW FEVER.<lb/>
Thus there arises Special Order No. 22, of the Headquarters of<lb/>
of the Navy in Washington, dated May 24th, 1900. In the new<lb/>
Order we find new proofs of Stenberg's nonacceptance of Finlay's<lb/>
<add>?</add> principles, as in the book &ldquo;<unclear><hi>MEMOIRS</hi></unclear> OF WALTER REED&rdquo;, by General<lb/>
Albert Truby, who lived the whole Cuban episode of 1900, the<lb/>
following is stated in pages 89 and 90: &ldquo;Having for years<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f04814020"/>
-19<lb/>
given thought to this subject, I became some time since im-<lb/>
pressed with the view that in Yellow Fever, as in Malarial<lb/>
Fevers, there is an &ldquo;INTERMEDIATE HOST&rdquo;. I therefore sug-<lb/>
gested to Dr. Reed, President of the Board, appointed upon<lb/>
my recommendation for the study of this disease to the Island<lb/>
of Cuba, that he should give special attention to the pos-<lb/>
sibility of transmission by some insects, although the expe-<lb/>
riments of Finlay seemed to show that the insect was not a<lb/>
mosquito of the genus Culex, such as he had used in his ino-<lb/>
culation experiments. I also urged that efforts should be<lb/>
made to ascertain definitely whether the disease can be com-<lb/>
municated from man to man by blood inoculations.&rdquo; This was<lb/>
<del>published</del><add>wrote</add> by Stenberg in his paper titled &ldquo;THE TRANSMISSION<lb/>
OF YELLOW FEVER BY MOSQUITOES&rdquo;, in &ldquo;Popular Science Monthly&rdquo;<lb/>
in July 1901. Ten years before, in &ldquo;The American Journal<lb/>
of Medical Science&rdquo;, No. 102, year 1891, Stenberg published<lb/>
a paper titled &ldquo;DR. FINLAY MOSQUITO INOCULATIONS&rdquo;, in which<lb/>
he stated that such works were unworthy of consideration, which<lb/>
brought above Dr. Finlay's rejoinder sent to the Editor of the<lb/>
Journal at the time, Dr. E. F. Davis, who was later to be the<lb/>
brilliant professor of obstetrics in the Jefferson Medical Col-<lb/>
lege.</p>
<p>The Reed Commission started its work by conclusively<lb/>
eliminating the importance of the Sanarelli Bacillus. The<lb/>
four members of the same, Reed, Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte<lb/>
promptly swept away that chalatanry. It is evident that in<lb/>
view of the negative results of this research, the Commission<lb/>
was going to engage itself in the bacteriologic study of the<lb/>
intestinal flora of patients of Yellow Fever and of healthy<lb/>
<add>An after - the fact &ldquo;recollection&rdquo; of Sternberg</add><lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f04814021"/>
-20<lb/>
<add>what evidence that Wood guided Reed et al re mosquito theory</add><lb/>
persons, but the <hi>guiding hand of General Wood</hi>, the findings<lb/>
of Dr. Roos in regard to malaria, and the observations of Carter<lb/>
on the incidence of Yellow Fever in connection with the extrin-<lb/>
sic period, perhaps all the above happily led the Commission<lb/>
to follow Finlay's path.</p>
<p>Thus<add>,</add> the Reed Commission start<del>s</del><add>ed</add> its studies receiving<lb/>
from Dr. Finlay all the data which, according to his opinion,<lb/>
was of interest. Reed was forced to abandon his work in<lb/>
Cuba called to the United States to report on an Army typhoid<lb/>
fever epidemic outbreak in the South, and left Cuba on August<lb/>
2nd, 1900. His departure brought about the following distri-<lb/>
bution of the remaining members of the Commission: Lazear was<lb/>
to work on the breeding and feeding of mosquitoes; Carroll on<lb/>
bacteriologic studies and Agramonte in Hospital No. 1. In the<lb/>
Board meeting of August 1st, held in Havana and presided by<lb/>
Reed just before his departure, it is evident that Lazear was<lb/>
the only member of the same who was enthusiastic over the mos-<lb/>
quito theory. To prove this last statement we quote part of<lb/>
a letter Lazear wrote to his wife, dated August 23rd, contained<lb/>
in Hench's &ldquo;DR. JESSE LAZEAR AND HIS CONTRIBUTION TO THE CON-<lb/>
QUEST OF YELLOW FEVER&rdquo;: &ldquo;Reed and Carroll have been at their<lb/>
bacteriologic work for a long time..... They are interested in<lb/>
the controversy with Sanaralli. I would rather try to find<lb/>
the germ without bothering about Sanarelli. The malarial<lb/>
work is my own.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Undoubted<add>ly</add> the plan of the Commission comprised expe-<lb/>
riments with human beings, so Lazear between August 11 and<lb/>
25 applied infected mosquitoes to nine American soldiers, in-<lb/>
cluding himself and Drs. Carroll and Pinto. These experiments<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="f04814022"/>
-21<lb/>
failed because the infected mosquitoes were not yet &ldquo;ripe&rdquo;<lb/>
<unclear>e<add>n</add>ough</unclear>. In August 27, Lazear inoculated Dr. Carroll who<lb/>
promptly developed yellow fever. On September 6 Private<lb/>
Dean developed the disease after inoculation also. Two<lb/>
days after Lazear wrote his wife (Sept. 8) the following: &ldquo;I<lb/>
rather think I am on the track to the real germ, but nothing<lb/>
must be said as yet.&rdquo; According to Agramonte's book &ldquo;THE IN-<lb/>
TERNAL HISTORY OF A GREAT MEDICAL DISCOVERY&rdquo;, when Dean took<lb/>
sick of Yellow Fever and the diagnosis was established by Dr.<lb/>
Roger <del>F</del><add>P</add>. Ames, a cablegram was sent to Dr. Reed reading as fol- <add>where could they be</add><lb/>
lows: &ldquo;The theory of the transmission of yellow fever by mos-<lb/>
quitoes, so much questioned from the beginning and the far- <add>where could they be</add><lb/>
reaching importance of which we hardly appreciate, has been <add>where could they be</add><lb/>
undubitably confirmed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Shortly thereafter a lamentable happening takes place:<lb/>
Lazear, infected by what appears to be an experimental sting,<lb/>
dies victim of the disease on September 25th, thus ending a<lb/>
life full of promise, the life of the man who, with masterly<lb/>
hands, guided the definit<unclear><del>ies</del><add>e</add></unclear> experiments to confirm what Finlay<lb/>
had said. From that moment another name, that of JESSE LAZEAR,<lb/>
was offered as a sacrifice to save thousands of lives, and under<lb/>
the blue sky of our country the light of his reasoning was clouded<lb/>
in his brain, and from our land there flew his last thoughts to<lb/>
his wife and <del>daughters</del><add>son</add>, and to his future <del>boy</del><add>girl</add> who was to bear <add>put</add><lb/>
the honor-giving name of Lazear.</p>
<p>Short<add>ly</add> after this loss, on October 3rd, Reed returned to<lb/>
Cuba and immediately thereafter, with the data tenaciously<lb/>
<unclear>wro<add>u</add>ght</unclear> by Lazear, he present<del>s</del><add>ly</add> at the meeting of the American<lb/>
Public Health Association, held in Indianapolis on October 23rd,<lb/>
<add>where?? could they be</add><lb/>
<pb n="23" id="f04814023"/>
-22<lb/>
the paper &ldquo;ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER. A PRELIMINARY NOTE&rdquo;, in<lb/>
which he calls <add>the</add> attention of the scientific world that what had<lb/>
been held by Finlay since the year 1881 was a great truth.</p>
<p>Walter Reed returns to Cuba in the first days of November<lb/>
and together with General Leonard Wood, plan<del>e</del><add>ed</add> the construction<lb/>
of a Camp in which to carry out the experiments which Lazear<lb/>
had already orientated, in order to conclusively prove the mos-<lb/>
quito theory. He select<del>e</del><add>ed</add> as its location the &ldquo;San Jose&rdquo; farm,<lb/>
in Marianao, where in 1883 Finlay had performed experimental<lb/>
inoculations upon Jesuit Fathers. We are of the opinion that<lb/>
Reed selected that place following <hi>Agramonte's suggestion</hi>, who<lb/>
knew that in spite of the Yellow Fever epidemics in Marianao,<lb/>
there were no cases of the disease in the said farm surely be-<lb/>
cause the Aedes Egypti were not present in it. The Camp was<lb/>
named after Lazear, in honor of the disappeared hero.</p>
<p>Two cabins of identical measurements were built, and in<lb/>
one of them, bearing <add>the</add> No. 2, experiments with infected mosqui-<lb/>
toes were made on volunteers, while in the other, bearing <add>the</add> No.<lb/>
l, it was proved that the FOMITES had nothing to do with the<lb/>
transmission of the disease.</p>
<p>This group of volunteers, - made up of Americans, Spaniards<lb/>
and Irishmen, - showed to the world its greatness and courage<lb/>
in experiments carried out in a disciplined manner, and with suf-<lb/>
ficient resources, which indorsed the greatest scientific truth,<lb/>
a truth our glorious Carlos J. Finlay had offered and the medical<lb/>
world had refused to accept.</p>
<p><del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>That spot</add> of Cuban land which Hench correctly identified<lb/>
as Cabin No. 1 with the help of Moran, one of the great volunteers,<lb/>
was still kept as a symbol of that great <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>event</add> in 1940 when it<lb/>
<add>so said Agramonte in 1915 but Reed didn't say so</add><lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f04814024"/>
-23<lb/>
was declared by the Cuban Government a National Monument. This<lb/>
was not possible in regard to Cabin No. 2 which was destroyed<lb/>
by the cyclone which attacked Havana in 1926. Cabin No. 1 was<lb/>
restored to its original status in 1900, and a park has been<lb/>
constructed around it in which bronze medallions of Finlay,<lb/>
Wood, Lazear, Reed, Agramonte, Carroll and Delgado were placed,<lb/>
with two bronze plates bearing the names of all those who vo-<lb/>
lunteered and of the persons who contributed to the definit<del>ive</del><add>e</add><lb/>
Conquest of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>Shortly after the holding in Havana in 1901 of the Third<lb/>
Pan-American Medical Congress, Reed presented the conclusions<lb/>
of the Commission, which permitted Gorgas (another unbeliever<lb/>
of the Finlay theory) to carry out the great work of making<lb/>
Havana wholesome which started on the 4th of February, 1901.<lb/>
We may call this the first work of <del>span</del><add>high point</add> in Public Health, irre-<lb/>
futably demonstrating its results. Thus, in February<add>,</add> 5 deaths<lb/>
were recorded in Havana, one in March, none in April, May and<lb/>
June, <add>one in July,</add> two in August and two in September. What had been the<lb/>
brutal and ferocious scourge of its inhabitants over four cen-<lb/>
turies, finally disappeared. Undubitaly the definitive con-<lb/>
quest of Yellow Fever by itself justifies the Spanish American<lb/>
War, in spite of the fact that in the period comprised between<lb/>
1898 and 1900 the United States suffered 231 deaths of Yellow<lb/>
Fever out of a total of 1,575 cases.</p>
<p>After his success in Havana Gorgas, supported by the Gover-<lb/>
nor of the Isthmus of Panama, General G. W. Davis, made possible<lb/>
the construction of the Canal which Lesseps was not able to build<lb/>
years before. To accomplish this he simply had to put into<lb/>
<unclear><add>Found in 1940 not in 1940 but much later</add></unclear><lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f04814025"/>
24<lb/>
practice a campaign against the Aedes Egypti, which was the key of his<lb/>
great success. - There can be no doubt that the disappearance of Yellow<lb/>
Fever in Panam&aacute;, and his victorious campaign against Malaria, are elocuer<lb/>
facts revealing Gorga's scientific, sanitarian, diplomatic and moral qua-<lb/>
lities, as well as his organising and executive abilities, which place<lb/>
him on the level of the first world's sanitarian.</p>
<p>Now, let my final words be to express, our joy and profound happiness<lb/>
to the Jefferson Medical College, for taking the iniciative in honoring<lb/>
Dr Carlos Finlay on the Centennial of his graduation.</p>
<p>Like a lovely mother, this honorable Institution molded the majestic<lb/>
figure of Dr Finlay and today, I feel and all of you, must sense his<lb/>
gigantic figure being projected all around us. - To you, Jefferson Medical<lb/>
College, the esteem of my country and our proffesion must be shown for<lb/>
honoring one, who loved and honored you during all his proffesional life<lb/>
and for mainteining after 100 years a faith and <hi>confidence in his <unclear>greatness</unclear><lb/>
as did his teacher Dr Weir Mitchell</hi> while Finlay struggled to prove to a<lb/>
doubting world his great scientific truth.</p>
<p>Thakns yours.</p>
<p><add>see Weir Mitchell's<lb/>
letter to Finlay explains<lb/>
his part in Finlay (verus Sternberg)<lb/>
Tocantins has copy</add></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
