<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04811005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Paul L. Tate to Vernon McKenzie, July 18, 1955</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Tate, Paul L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04811005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1955-07-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">McKenzie, Vernon</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Armstrong, George E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">O'Hara, Barratt</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1955-07-18">July 18, 1955</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04811005</idno>
<title>Letter from Paul L. Tate to Vernon McKenzie, July 18, 1955</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Tate testifies to the work done by Lambert as a nurse during the yellow fever experiments, and feels that Lambert should be recognized for his service. He also encloses a letter from Barratt O'Hara.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1955-07-18">
<head>Letter from Paul L. Tate to Vernon McKenzie, July 18, 1955</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04811005"/>
<opener>
Retained copy. Air-mailed to - Maj. McKenzie<lb/>
Hon O'Hara<lb/>
Gus. Lambert<lb/>
July 19 '55<lb/>
1530 Tyler Street<lb/>
Berkeley, 3, California<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1955-07-18">July 18, 1955</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Major Vernon McKenzie<lb/>
Office of The Surgeon General<lb/>
U. S. Army<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In compliance with the request of the Honorable Barrett<lb/>
O'Hara, contained in the enclosed <xref id="t04811009">letter</xref>, I take oath to<lb/>
the following statement regarding Gustaf E. Lambert:</p>
<p>I was the medical clerk at Columbia Barracks Army Hospi-<lb/>
tal, Quemados, Cuba, from September 9, 1900 to August<lb/>
11, 1901, covering the entire period of the yellow fever<lb/>
experiments conducted by the Major Walter Reed Board.</p>
<p>Private Gustaf E. Lambert was a member of that Hospital<lb/>
Detachment, and I knew him well.</p>
<p>I performed all the Army medical paper work for this<lb/>
hospital. As I made out all the Muster Rolls and other<lb/>
reports, and handled all Special Orders relating thereto,<lb/>
I was well acquainted with all changes and transfers of<lb/>
the men and their duties at all times.</p>
<p>In this respect I know that Gustav E. Lambert was on duty<lb/>
in the Yellow Fever Section before and all through the<lb/>
entire period of these yellow fever experiments as nurse<lb/>
for the yellow fever patients, and that he had entire charge<lb/>
of these buildings, under direction of Doctor Roger Ames,<lb/>
(Contract Doctor, later Major of Volunteers.)</p>
<p>In this capacity Lambert nursed many yellow fever cases,<lb/>
including ALL of the volunteers who had contracted the<lb/>
disease. Furthermore, he was the ONLY nurse there except<lb/>
for two female practical nurses, (immunes) who assisted on<lb/>
just one of latter cases.</p>
<p>Lambert faced greater risk of contraction yellow fever, as <add>he</add><lb/>
was not immune.</p>
<p>It has always been acknowledged that the fate of this great<lb/>
experiment depended on the experience and work of Doctor<lb/>
&check; Ames and Nurse Lambert, for if <hi>but one</hi> of the earlier cases<lb/>
had died, popular clamor in Cuba and the U. S. combined<lb/>
with the disinclination of Major Reed to risk human lives,<lb/>
would have ruined all chance of proving the Finlay theory.</p>
<p>I further know that Lambert did not have to work so long<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04811006"/>
(2)<lb/>
on such a dangerous and distasteful job. He volunteered to<lb/>
keep at it through his loyalty to Doctor Ames and Medical<lb/>
Science.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>Paul L Tate</signed>
Paul L. Tate<lb/>
Kindly read remarks on following pages.<lb/>
<seg>Notarized<lb/>
P.S.- I notice that Mr. O'<add>H</add>ara in quoting the unfavorable<lb/>
report of the Secretary of the Army did not complete the<lb/>
entire sentence.<lb/>
It occurs to me that this ommission may have had reference<lb/>
to the Army policy that there was to be no <del>more</del> reopening<lb/>
of this Act of 1929 which honored the members of the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Commission and those who offered their bodies for<lb/>
experiment. If it did I thoroly agree with it.--Too many<lb/>
have attempted to take undeserved honors in this event.<lb/>
Yet, there but TWO men, not honored, who were important to<lb/>
the success of the experiment: They were Doctor Ames and<lb/>
Nurse Lambert.--It is quite probable that without these two<lb/>
the experiment would have failed.<lb/>
If this is the cause, why cannot it be left to a Congress-<lb/>
ional Committee? Congress made the recognition. If a member<lb/>
of Congress desires to have that body recognize another in<lb/>
in this experiment which a former congress overlooked, why<lb/>
should the Army attempt to prevent recognition of one of its<lb/>
own former service man?<lb/>
I feel sure that Lambert, no matter how his Congressman's<lb/>
bill reads, expects no money, but perhaps a medal showing<lb/>
the Congressional recognition which he deserves.<lb/>
PLT<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04811007"/>
ADDENDUM:<lb/>
In connection with the foregoing it appears strange that the<lb/>
Army can find no record of Lambert's work with the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission. If the old Muster Rolls have been preserved, the<lb/>
record is there. I have read many articles about this experi-<lb/>
ment in which his name was mentioned.<lb/>
For instance, your The Surgeon General of the Army, Major Gen-<lb/>
eral George E. Armstrong, in 1950, having learned from the<lb/>
late Brigadier General Albert Truby that I desired a copy of<lb/>
the latter's book, &ldquo;Memoir of Walter Reed&rdquo;(then out of print)<lb/>
very kindly personally sent me a copy of that book with the<lb/>
compliments of the Army Medical Department, with one of the<lb/>
very nice letters that he knows so well how to write.<lb/>
In that story of the Yellow Fever Experiment, General Truby,<lb/>
who was Commanding Officer of Columbia Hospital for quite a<lb/>
while, refers to Lambert many times. Lambert's picture is there<lb/>
with the rest of the Detachment on page 154. He states he re-<lb/>
ceived much of his discription of the strictly quarantined<lb/>
yellow fever section from Lambert.<lb/>
On page 81 he says: &ldquo;A private of our Hospital Corps Detachment,<lb/>
G. E. Lambert, was dubbed by the men as &lsquo;Ames&rsquo; Man Friday.&rsquo; He<lb/>
was most loyal and faithful. Ames had this to say of him in a<lb/>
letter dated November 12, 1901:<lb/>
&ldquo;During the epidemic at Quemados, near Columbia Barracks, Cuba,<lb/>
he was always my important right hand man. Nearly all cases of<lb/>
yellow fever (over 67), either natural or experimental, at-<lb/>
tended by me in part or whole, were nursed by this competent<lb/>
soldier. The general supervision of the yellow fever wards and<lb/>
the running of the large disinfecting plant was entrusted to<lb/>
his care.&rdquo;<lb/>
I have a copy of a letter from Major Kean, Surgeon General of<lb/>
Western Cuba at that time, to Lambert, acknowledging Lambert's<lb/>
fine treatment of him when he had yellow fever.<lb/>
I have corresponded for a long time with Doctor Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
of Mayo Clinic, who has for many years been writing the only<lb/>
complete history of the yellow fever experiment, and who has met<lb/>
most of the volunteers, and he tells me that Lambert will have<lb/>
a prominent place in his book. He procured lots of his material<lb/>
from Army records. Why can't the Army find Lambert?<lb/>
So, it appears very strange that so many people, including<lb/>
officers of the Army, such as General Truby, Major Kean and<lb/>
others who were present at the experiment and knew of Lambert<lb/>
and his highly valuable services to the experiment, yet the<lb/>
present Army can find no record of him:<lb/>
If Lambert were permitted to appear before a Committee he has<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04811008"/>
(page 2, Addendum)<lb/>
plenty of convincing material relating to his work on the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Experiment, including letters from many of the<lb/>
volunteers, thanking him for his fine services and the probable<lb/>
saving of their life.<lb/>
I hope that in simple justice to a soldier who served the<lb/>
Medical Departmet of the Army and humanity so well and is now<lb/>
old and disabled, that he will be given at least the chance to<lb/>
present his case.--It is all he asks. Anything less would not<lb/>
carry out the &ldquo;Old Army&rdquo; watchword of HONOR.<lb/>
So, I ask you to use whatever influence you have to help do<lb/>
simple justice to this deserving man.<lb/>
Sincerely yours,<lb/>
Paul L. Tate<lb/>
Paul L. Tate<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
