<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04905004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Paul L. Tate to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Tate, Paul L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04905004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-03-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">O'Hara, Barratt</name>
<name type="person">Brumby, William M.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Armstrong, George E.</name>
<name type="person">McKenzie, Vernon</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-03-03">March 3, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04905004</idno>
<title>Letter from Paul L. Tate to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Tate defends Lambert's claim to recognition and acknowledges that Lambert believes Ames to be a great man.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-03-03">
<head>Letter from Paul L. Tate to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04905004"/>
<opener>
1530 Tyler Street<lb/>
Berkeley, California<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1956-03-03">March 3, 1956</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Philip S. Hench, M.D.<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Replying to your letter referring to the Lambert Case:</p>
<p>Doctor Ames is not included in the House Bill nor was he<lb/>
with intent excluded. Most of Lambert's previous attempts<lb/>
have included Ames as the first one named. A few years ago<lb/>
there was a congressional ruling that no congressman could<lb/>
present a Bill concerning an individual unless that person<lb/>
was a native or a citizen of the State from which the cong-<lb/>
ressman was elected.</p>
<p>Lambert resides in Illinois, so O'Hara could represent him;<lb/>
Ames was born in Louisiana, so his case would have to intro-<lb/>
duced by a congressman from that state, or from Texas, if<lb/>
he were once a native of that state.</p>
<p>Lambert's fight was originally for <hi rend="underline">Ames when he learned that<lb/>
Ames was buried in an unmarked grave</hi>. In his later campaigns<lb/>
he included himself. Then, When he could get no one to help<lb/>
for Ames, he was desperate. He told me of it. I replied that<lb/>
as he could not alter conditions, to &ldquo;Paddle His Own Cance,&rdquo;<lb/>
but added that it was doubtful he would succeed. I wanted<lb/>
him to leave that 1929 Act alone and try another method.</p>
<p>In lambert's life Doctor Ames was the greatest man in the<lb/>
world, and no bill he ever tried to get through Congress was<lb/>
&ldquo;ostensibly&rdquo; for Ames.--It was always mainly for Ames--and<lb/>
his nurse Lambert naturally wanted to ride along. The very<lb/>
association of their names in such a document would have been<lb/>
highly pleasing to him.</p>
<p>Why should he not want recognition? Ames <del>v</del><add>c</add>ould not possibly<lb/>
have performed all the manifold work of managing Cam<add>p</add> Lazear,<lb/>
inspecting the patients there and them attending them at the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Wards without having a man who was fully capable<lb/>
of doing everything for those yellow fever patients by himself<lb/>
as conditions arose and could be absolutely depended upon at<lb/>
all times.--Lambert was that man. Ames would never use another<lb/>
nurse and Lambert knew it. But he would never have stuck there<lb/>
for any other doctor. No man today realizes what a terrible<lb/>
job it was and its exacting conditions.</p>
<p>Lambert, lame and nearly blind, as he was made three hard bus<lb/>
trips to Houston and New Orleans, and spent many weeks helping<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04905005"/>
(Hench-Tate--2)<lb/>
Doctor Brumby assembly and publish that book, &ldquo;The Forgotten<lb/>
Man of the Yellow Fever Commission,&rdquo; besides contributing<lb/>
$650. toward the expense. The very title shows that this book<lb/>
was solely to publicise Ames, although of course others were<lb/>
mentioned in it. I think this whole book was a mistake, just<lb/>
clouding the picture through its predjudiced inaccuracies,<lb/>
but it shows Lambert was working for Ames, not himself.</p>
<p>Lambert has bee<del>t</del><add>n</add> trying desperately to get someone to intro-<lb/>
duce a bill for Ames. He has written many times to Brumby but<lb/>
can get no reply. I, too, wrote Brumby to try and locate him<lb/>
for him but my letter was returned unclaimed.</p>
<p>I saw a letter Mrs. Ames wrote Lambert when he tried again<lb/>
to get her to help her late husband. She very decidedly re-<lb/>
fused to do anything further. Said she had never wanted any-<lb/>
thing but recognition of her husband's work and had tried<lb/>
hard and long and knew she would never succeed and she hated<lb/>
every officer and politician in Washington and that no honest<lb/>
person could ever get past them! Lambert's comment to me on<lb/>
that was: &ldquo;There's no Swedish blood in her!&rdquo;</p>
<p>All the foregoing, (and there is much more) is just to show<lb/>
that Lambert tried hard to get help for the cause of Ames.</p>
<p>I also felt for a long time that the Act should not be re-<lb/>
opened, until, later, when I realized there were now no others<lb/>
to make legitimate claims except Lambert and friends of Ames.<lb/>
Then thought it unjust for the Army to hold a blocking policy<lb/>
on that Act of Congress. Why should one congress be blocked<lb/>
by an act of Congress of a previous age, and the Army prevent<lb/>
justice being done its own former servicemen through lack of<lb/>
knowledge of the events.</p>
<p>One thing they didn't think of--the possible influence of The<lb/>
Surgeon of the Army, if they gould get to him with the material.<lb/>
I knew from the three friendly letters I had received from<lb/>
him, and what Gen. Truby had told me about him that it might<lb/>
help to reach Major General George E. Armstrong indirectly.</p>
<p>So, knowing that Major McKenzie was sympathetic to the bill,<lb/>
I worded my letter to him in such a way that I believed he<lb/>
would show it to his superior for verification. I think he did<lb/>
just that and it was the little thing that helped for which<lb/>
Congressman O'Hara gave me credit.</p>
<p>You ask, what do I think about it. It is one more unhappy mix-<lb/>
up in this experiment of strange events. Just think!--The very<lb/>
idea of the Nurse being honored for his work, and the <hi>Doctor</hi><lb/>
who made the decisions and taught and trained the nurse, being<lb/>
forgotten! <hi>Of course</hi> if feel it is wrong, but you would have<lb/>
to have known Ames personally, as I did, to realize how badly<lb/>
I feel about it.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04905006"/>
<p>(Hench-Tate-3)</p>
<p>Lambert only feels worse. It is &ldquo;the fly in the ointment&rdquo;<lb/>
for him. If this passes the Senate he gets much of what he<lb/>
wished for himself, but it is small compensation for him<lb/>
unless Ames receives Congressional recognition.</p>
<p>Already he is writing: &ldquo;I feel like crying.&rdquo; &ldquo;If this goes<lb/>
through I'll feel ashamed of my honors. I was a good yellow<lb/>
fever nurse--I knew all about it, but who taught me? Ames.<lb/>
I would have known nothing but for him. Everyone remembered<lb/>
except Ames, the best of alll. Its terrible!&rdquo; etc.</p>
<p>Well, I think I have answered all your questions at length,<lb/>
perhaps too lengthy. But I wished you to know how this affair<lb/>
came about and have you not do an injustice in your mind to<lb/>
Lambert. I know him.--He'd give the whole thing up if it<lb/>
would help Ames.</p>
<p>Anyhow, all this may be for naught. The Senate Committee may<lb/>
shelve it. Being an old ex-reporter from the City of Washing-<lb/>
ton, I'm very pessimistic about predicting any happenings<lb/>
there.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially &amp; Sincerely</salute>
<signed>Tate</signed>
Paul L. Tate<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
