<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04907019">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, May 16, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04907019</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-05-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Ames, Jessie Daniel</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Richard B.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Love, Albert G.</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Mackenzie, Maj.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-05-16">May 16, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04907019</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, May 16, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Ames that he is trying to get her husband recognition for his medical care of the yellow fever volunteers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-05-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, May 16, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04907019"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1956-05-16">May 16, 1956</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Mrs. Jessie Daniel Ames<lb/>
Wrens Nest<lb/>
Tryon, North Carolina<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Ames:</salute>
</opener>
<p>We have not corresponded since our pleasant meeting in Cuba at the time of the dedica-<lb/>
tion of Camp Lazear, when you received the Cuban decoration. I was very happy about<lb/>
that affair.</p>
<p>I must not raise false hopes, but the incredible just might happen. I have known, of<lb/>
course, that Lambert has for years been appealing to Congress in behalf of a bill to<lb/>
honor Doctor Ames but of course Lambert would himself be included. I know that<lb/>
friends of yours in earlier years tried to do the same for Doctor Ames. Yet all of<lb/>
these efforts were in vain. I myself decided that they were without success because<lb/>
Lambert was trying to change the categories created in 1929 and was trying to erase<lb/>
an important distinction. Although Lambert very rightly claims to have exposed him-<lb/>
self to yellow fever in almost every possible way while he nursed the yellow fever<lb/>
victims, nevertheless he did not actually have injected into his body, by mosquito or<lb/>
needle, the live yellow fever virus and that is an important distinction. Through<lb/>
the years, I have made various inquiries through Generals Kean, Truby and Ireland,<lb/>
and also through the various Surgeons General, as to the possibility of honoring<lb/>
Doctor Ames and Mr. Lambert because I do think that both of them served in a real<lb/>
sense beyond the call of duty. I was always discouraged and again the reason was<lb/>
the very real distinction mentioned above.</p>
<p>Recently Lambert made another try through his Illinois Congressman and, presumably, he<lb/>
was again attempting to have the bill passed in favor of Doctor Ames. But by Congres-<lb/>
sional manipulation of some sort (I don't quite understand it), it turned out to be a<lb/>
bill to add Lambert's name to the Roll of Honor without mentioning Doctor Ames. The<lb/>
excuses given were that (1) an Illinois Congressman could not introduce a bill to<lb/>
honor a former citizen from another state; now the Congressmen from the respective<lb/>
states have the responsibility and privilege of initiating honors in favor of living<lb/>
or deceased citizens of their states and (2) after all, Lambert is living, is crippled,<lb/>
old and almost blind. He is the one that needs help; the pension is the important<lb/>
thing. An honor for someone no longer here is of less practical consequence.</p>
<p>After a bill in favor of Lambert had been worded and already passed by the appropriate<lb/>
committee of the House of Representatives, I was asked to support it. I wrestled<lb/>
with my conscience for two weeks. The question was whether, if this bill did not<lb/>
pass, Lambert might die before receiving an honor and should I therefore approve this<lb/>
bill and help it to be passed or should my very real objections to the exclusion of<lb/>
Doctor Ames make me object to the bill as now stated. Although I am most sympathetic<lb/>
to Lambert (and have been trying to honor him and Doctor Ames in my own ways for<lb/>
several years, via the memorialization and dedication of Camp Lazear, the bronze<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04907020"/>
Mrs. Ames &nbsp;&nbsp;- 2 - &nbsp;&nbsp;May 16, 1956<lb/>
plaque and the encouragement of the Cuban Government to honor Doctor Ames and<lb/>
Mr. Lambert and the others), I just could not accept the exclusion of Doctor Ames,<lb/>
which has been done apparently on the grounds of political expediency. Therefore<lb/>
I visited the Surgeon General's Office about two or three months ago and discussed<lb/>
matters with those concerned. They seemed to agree that Doctor Ames should be in-<lb/>
cluded. I was surprised, therefore, to find shortly thereafter that the so-called<lb/>
Lambert Bill (H.R. 5590) had been passed by the House and was now in the hands of<lb/>
the Senate Committee on Armed Services, Senator Richard B. Russell, Chairman.</p>
<p>I wrote to him and sent copies of my letters to the President of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association - General Love, living in Washington, and to the Surgeon General's<lb/>
Office and asked to be allowed to make a counter proposal and, if possible, testify<lb/>
at any hearing they might have before this bill would be passed by the Committee on<lb/>
Armed Services. Their replies were encouraging. General Love and Colonel Siler got<lb/>
in touch with Senator Russell's office and with the Surgeon General's Office and<lb/>
found them sympathetic to my proposition.</p>
<p>Last week, therefore, in Washington I visited Senator Russell's Executive Assistant<lb/>
and discussed matters with Major MacKenzie of the Surgeon General's Office, and<lb/>
with Colonel Siler and General Love of the Walter Reed Memorial Association. I<lb/>
also found them ostensibly quite sympathetic to my proposition. I returned home<lb/>
last night and have been advised to divide my proposition into various parts and to<lb/>
send it at once to the above mentioned parties. Senator Russell's assistant told me<lb/>
he thought he understood matters so well now that it would not be necessary for me<lb/>
to add much documentation to my proposition, that is documentation regarding the<lb/>
services of Doctor Ames and nurse Lambert. He said that there would probably be no<lb/>
public hearings or hearings of any sort but that the bill might be taken up quickly<lb/>
toward the end of the session and passed quickly. He thought there was considerable<lb/>
sentiment in favor of the bill as now constituted (the Lambert bill) and thought<lb/>
that we could simply use the same number on the bill and amend it by more or less<lb/>
changing the entire wording. He did warn me that the bill might not be taken up at<lb/>
all this year; on the other hand, he thought himself that it would be and that it<lb/>
had a good chance of passage. Major MacKenzie from the Surgeon General's Office<lb/>
seemed to think so also.</p>
<p>I asked Senator Russell's assistant as to whether the new bill (or the old bill re-<lb/>
worded) would have to have the support of Louisiana Congressmen and Senators to have<lb/>
Doctor Ames name included. He thought not but because of what I was told (mentioned<lb/>
above) I asked him if it wouldn't be much better if we could enlist the support of<lb/>
Louisiana Congressmen and Senators and he agreed that their support might be quite<lb/>
helpful. I am therefore asking you to get in touch at once with your Congressmen<lb/>
and your Senators to have them give whatever support to the new bill they can. How<lb/>
the Senate Committee will word the new bill, I haven't the faintest idea but they<lb/>
advised me to state my propositions (and divide the possibilities) as I have given<lb/>
them in the Addendum. Mr. William H. Darden, Senator Russell's Executive Assistant,<lb/>
told me that if the Committee found much sentiment, they might pass the whole<lb/>
Proposition No. 1. If they were less enthusiastic, they might pass Propositions 2 or<lb/>
3. If they were inclined to be in a hurry and act differently than they always have<lb/>
in the past, they might even act on Proposition No. 4, but I am not myself urging<lb/>
Proposition No. 4 because it is the very one that has been defeated so many times<lb/>
before and I personally feel there is more chance of passing one of the other three<lb/>
propositions than No. 4. I hope you agree with me. For your convenience, I enclose<lb/>
three copies of the addendum - my propositions, and one carbon of this letter.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f04907021"/>
<p>Mrs. Ames&nbsp;&nbsp; - 3 - &nbsp;&nbsp;May 16, 1956</p>
<p>In summary, the bill as it now stands, already passed by the House and under<lb/>
favorable consideration by the Senate Committee on Armed Services, is simply to<lb/>
add the name of Lambert (not that of Doctor Ames) to the 1929 Bill. But because<lb/>
both houses have on every previous occasion objected to adding any names to the<lb/>
1929 Bill, some of us believe that a rewording - to include Doctor Ames and to do<lb/>
what the Surgeon General's Office and Congress has always wanted to do before,<lb/>
that is maintain the distinction mentioned above - might have much more chance<lb/>
of passage and would probably satisfy all concerned.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I understand that Lambert, although pleased of course that an honor may<lb/>
come to him, is very distressed at the exclusion of Doctor Ames and I think he is<lb/>
quite sincere in this. I am writing in the hope that he will approve the new sug-<lb/>
gestions.<lb/>
P.P.S.: I shall at once look up the World Almanac to find the names of the Louisiana<lb/>
Congressmen that should be contacted and I too will write them. I am going on the<lb/>
assumption, of course, that Doctor Ames was a Louisiana citizen, a voter in that<lb/>
state, etc. Did he die there? At your very earliest convenience, could you get to<lb/>
me (possibly by next Monday) a paragraph telling me what Doctor Ames did after<lb/>
the yellow fever business, where and when he died, also the names of your Congress-<lb/>
man and Senator, to confirm my own opinion.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
