<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04908005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard B. Russell, June 13, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04908005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-06-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Russell, Richard B.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-06-13">June 13, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04908005</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard B. Russell, June 13, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench submits propositions to the Senate Committee on Armed Services regarding how to recognize the contributions of Lazear, Lambert, and Ames.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-06-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard B. Russell, June 13, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04908005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1956-06-13">June 13, 1956</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Senator Richard B. Russell, Chairman<lb/>
Committee on Armed Services<lb/>
United States Senate<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senator Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have written you previously expressing my great interest in the bill,<lb/>
H.R. 5590, to honor Mr. Gustaf E. Lambert. As I told you, Mr. Lambert<lb/>
deserves honors but I have suggested that if Congress is willing to do<lb/>
honor to Mr. Lambert after all these years, it would well for Congress<lb/>
to &ldquo;finish up the matter in fine and proper fashion&rdquo; by honoring two ad-<lb/>
ditional people: One who has never been honored before in this connec-<lb/>
tion - at least not publicly - namely, Dr. Roger Post Ames who was the<lb/>
physician who cared for all of the experimental cases of yellow fever of<lb/>
Walter Reed and his associates, and also the memory of Dr. Jessee Lazear,<lb/>
the young medical officer who, it might be said, was actually the first to<lb/>
discover the cause of yellow fever but, in doing so, lost his life, leaving<lb/>
his precious notes which were the basis for the subsequent successful re-<lb/>
sults of Walter Reed and Doctors Carroll and Agramonte.</p>
<p>I enclose four propositions. I am strongly in favor of proposition 1. In<lb/>
this way the full tribute would be given to those Americans who discovered<lb/>
the cause of yellow fever. For reasons of which I have written, I think<lb/>
proposition 1 is the most appropriate and it would maintain the distinction<lb/>
which Congress has maintained up to now, with respect to those who actually<lb/>
offered their bodies for the experiments, at the same time honoring Doctor<lb/>
Ames and Mr. Lambert for their extremely important contribution.</p>
<p>Proposition 2 would be the simple addition of the names of Doctor Ames and<lb/>
Mr. Lambert to the 1929 Bill and would be merely the addition of Doctor<lb/>
Ames' name to the present so-called Lambert Bill, H.R. 5590. I have no<lb/>
particular enthusiasm for propositions 3 and 4. They were suggested to<lb/>
me when I was in Washington as acts which Congress might pass if they were<lb/>
unwilling to honor Doctor Ames and Mr. Lambert (and Doctor Lazear) in the<lb/>
full and proper manner.</p>
<p>I personally would prefer to try another year for propositions 1 and 2, if<lb/>
either of these failed this year. While I favor proposition 1 over proposi-<lb/>
tion 2 for reasons which I have stated previously, I will certainly not<lb/>
interfere or object if Congress prefers to pass H.R. 5590, plus the addition<lb/>
of the name of Doctor Ames.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04908006"/>
<p>Senator Richard Russell &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Page 2 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;June 13, 1956</p>
<p>When I consulted with Mr. Darden in Washington a month ago, he assured me<lb/>
that the reasons for these honors were so well known by your committee<lb/>
that I would not have to support that part. I am quite prepared to support<lb/>
it with complete documentation which I have collected as a sort of intel-<lb/>
lectual hobby since 1939. I have visited practically all the survivors<lb/>
or families of survivors, and have been made the repository of extensive<lb/>
data from the families of Doctors Reed, Lazear, and Agramonte, and other<lb/>
survivors of the experiments.</p>
<p>I am prepared to appear before your committee at any time mutually agreeable<lb/>
and would be glad to come at my own expense. I am off for a quick medical<lb/>
trip to Europe but will return July 10 and have given Mr. Darden my addresses<lb/>
if you wish to give me any instructions. I am taking the liberty of sending<lb/>
this letter to the two senators from Louisiana and the representatives as I<lb/>
believe that Doctor Ames, having been born in New Orleans and having been<lb/>
buried there, would receive the major support from Louisiana Senators and<lb/>
Congressmen.</p>
<p>One line about Doctor Lazear. It is probable that you never heard of his<lb/>
name. Most civilians never have unfortunately, and indeed very few physicians<lb/>
have; yet actually it might be said without the slightest detraction from the<lb/>
wonderful work of Doctor Reed and his associates that Doctor Lazear was the<lb/>
first really to discover the cause of yellow fever, carry on in Doctor Reed's<lb/>
absence the three experiments, including the one on himself from which he died.<lb/>
It was his notebook which gave to Doctor Reed the final data. It was entirely<lb/>
necessary that Doctor Reed and the rest of the committee go ahead and, once<lb/>
and for all, prove the cause of yellow fever because the world did not and<lb/>
indeed could not have accepted Doctor Lazear's three experiments as conclusive<lb/>
evidence. Nevertheless this was the first real break in the wall and Walter<lb/>
Reed and his associates went on to finish the job in such magnificent fashion.<lb/>
In summary, the great Cuban physician, Dr. Carlos Finlay, discovered the theory,<lb/>
a remarkable contribution. He picked out of thousands of possibilities the right<lb/>
species of mosquito but could not prove the theory. Doctor Lazear actually<lb/>
proved the theory but died and Doctor Reed and his associates proved it to the<lb/>
world. Since Doctor Lazear has been so neglected I do urge that Congress honor<lb/>
him in this way. I would not involve Congress in controversy that would delay<lb/>
honor to Mr. Lambert unduly, but I see no reason for delay as Lazear's contribu-<lb/>
tion can be readily verified by the Surgeon General's Office by the reading of<lb/>
General Truby's monograph. Incidentally, General Truby's conviction that Doctor<lb/>
Lazear actually did inoculate himself as a secret experiment, is completely sup-<lb/>
ported by information given to me by Doctor Agramonte's daughter and by several<lb/>
of the volunteers, such as Moran and Kissinger. I have their actual interviews<lb/>
and statements on that point.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
