<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04906013">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard B. Russell, April 16, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04906013</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-04-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Russell, Richard B.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Tate, Paul L.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-04-16">April 16, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04906013</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard B. Russell, April 16, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench wants to testify before the Committee on Armed Services regarding Lambert's inclusion on the Roll of Honor. He asserts Lambert deserves honor, but it should be distinct from the Roll of Honor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-04-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard B. Russell, April 16, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04906013"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1956-04-16">April 16, 1956</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Senator Richard B. Russell<lb/>
Committee on Armed Services<lb/>
United States Senate<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senator Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you for your recent note in answer to my inquiry about H.R. 5590, the<lb/>
bill to add the name of Mr. Gustaf E. Lambert to the Roll of Honor in con-<lb/>
nection with the discovery of the cause and means of transmission of yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>I would like very much to be privileged to testify before your committee. I<lb/>
have known Mr. Lambert for a number of years as uncovering the unpublished<lb/>
facts of the conquest of yellow fever has been an intense hobby of mine, or<lb/>
an avocation, for the last fifteen years. I enclose two reprints. I have<lb/>
studied every phase of the work of Walter Reed and his colleagues and the<lb/>
work of Finlay. I have visited the homes of practically all the survivors and<lb/>
the families of the yellow fever participants who are no longer living have<lb/>
honored me by making me the repository of a very large amount of unpublished<lb/>
material.</p>
<p>I think I am therefore quite familiar with the contribution of Mr. Lambert. I<lb/>
have visited his home and he has been a guest in my home. I am very anxious to<lb/>
honor him and he deserves much. I would certainly go to the expense of going<lb/>
to Washington to testify before the Committee in his behalf; however I want to<lb/>
see that Mr. Lambert is honored appropriately.</p>
<p>Please consider this letter an informal one and I would prefer that it not be<lb/>
considered a part of your official data with respect to this bill. The reasons<lb/>
are these: Although Mr. Lambert deserves great honor and has been neglected,<lb/>
and although I am most anxious to help him get an appropriate honor from Congress,<lb/>
his honor should be distinct from that of the Roll of Honor. Actually, Mr.<lb/>
Lambert did not volunteer directly for the yellow fever experiments and his<lb/>
connection with the yellow fever patients began when, sometime before Walter<lb/>
Reed's commission began their work, Mr. Lambert volunteered to Doctor Ames to<lb/>
help care for yellow fever patients and other patients at another location in<lb/>
Havana.</p>
<p>Later, when it become necessary to care for patients with spontaneous yellow<lb/>
fever at the little hospital across the railroad track from the Post Hospital<lb/>
at Camp Columbia, Lambert and Doctor Ames merely transferred their activities<lb/>
there and then, of course, when the victims of experimental yellow fever needed<lb/>
care, these two men - the doctor and the nurse - took care of them too. Thus<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04906014"/>
Senator Richard B. Russell&nbsp;&nbsp; - 2 - &nbsp;&nbsp;April 16, 1956<lb/>
Mr. Lambert, up to that time, was merely doing his duty. He did wonderful<lb/>
work but it was done in line of duty; however he did it with such zeal that as far<lb/>
as he was concerned he might be said to have served beyond the reasonable limits<lb/>
of his duty. Nevertheless, the distinction should be maintained, I believe, in be-<lb/>
half of these who actually and &ldquo;officially&rdquo; volunteered. By that I mean the<lb/>
following: When General Wood gave Major Reed permission to call for volunteers,<lb/>
this information was spread among the soldiers at Camp Columbia Post Hospital<lb/>
by word of mouth. Presumably not only Doctor Ames but the other medical officers<lb/>
spoke to the soldiers who served them in the hospital and all of whom were poten-<lb/>
tial volunteers. We do not know to whom each man actually volunteered first<lb/>
but of course eventually they must have been interviewed by Reed himself. We<lb/>
know that Kissinger and Moran went to Reed and volunteered although each first<lb/>
heard of the proposition from Doctor Ames.</p>
<p>Now there is no place in the official record, that is the official papers or<lb/>
the later writings of any member of the Yellow Fever Board, where it states<lb/>
that Lambert volunteered, at least to Reed: nor have I found any written<lb/>
record that Lambert did actually volunteer to Doctor Ames for the specific<lb/>
experiments of Reed. I have many letters that he wrote to Generals Truby and<lb/>
Kean and to some of the enlisted men he knew, such as Tate, Andrus and so on,<lb/>
letters written long after the events of 1900. It is my distinct recollection<lb/>
that nowhere in the earlier of these letters did Mr. Lambert claim to have<lb/>
volunteered for Reed's experiments. I interviewed Mr. Lambert on two or three<lb/>
occasions and the same holds true for my interviews. It was only later that<lb/>
he mentioned, almost as an afterthought, that he had volunteered to Doctor<lb/>
Ames and he described the occasion of his volunteering.</p>
<p>Doctor Ames one day, very early in the days of Camp Lazear, told Lambert to hop<lb/>
into the Beherty wagon and they drove over to Camp Lazear on an errand of Ames'.<lb/>
Ames did not let Lambert leave the wagon. Then they went back to the yellow<lb/>
fever huts. During the ride Ames must have mentioned the volunteers and the<lb/>
money each was to get and Lambert made a remark that seems rather casual that<lb/>
he would just as soon volunteer for a little extra money, but Ames did not<lb/>
encourage him to do it, presumably because Ames needed Lambert to continue<lb/>
nursing at the yellow fever huts. Now if Lambert had been really serious<lb/>
about volunteering, even if only for the sake of the money, he could have<lb/>
taken the matter up again with Ames or he could have passed the word to Reed<lb/>
and asked that he be given this chance. There is no record anywhere, including<lb/>
the many statements by Lambert, that he did this. In other words, apparently<lb/>
this is the only time and these are the circumstances under which Lambert did<lb/>
&ldquo;volunteer&rdquo; and certainly it would not appear that even if he did make this<lb/>
remark to Ames that he did it with any idea of rendering service to medicine<lb/>
or the medical corps.</p>
<p>There is no question but that Mr. Lambert has a compulsive nature and that he<lb/>
carried out his duties with Doctor Ames at the yellow fever huts with unusual<lb/>
devotion, one might say extra-ordinary devotion. Apparently he was determined<lb/>
to do the job and to do it alone. He stayed there night and day and nursed<lb/>
practically all of the volunteers alone and for this he deserves great credit.</p>
<p>Now, actually in 1929, when Congress passed the bill honoring certain volunteers,<lb/>
it did not include the Spanish volunteers nor did it include even some of the<lb/>
American volunteers who did not get experimental yellow fever for one reason or<lb/>
another. As I understand it, Congress honored only three groups: (1) the four<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04906015"/>
Senator Richard B. Russell&nbsp;&nbsp; - 3 -&nbsp;&nbsp; April 16, 1956<lb/>
members of the Yellow Fever Commission, for obvious reasons; (2) the volunteers<lb/>
who exposed themselves to the filth of the fomites building and (3) the other<lb/>
volunteers at Camp Lazear who got experimental yellow fever, but not those who<lb/>
did not get it, even though they did everything that was asked of them, had the<lb/>
presumably infected mosquitos placed on their bodies and faced, psychologically,<lb/>
the same uncertainties as did the others. Another men who deserves great credit,<lb/>
perhaps more than any other man except those already honored, was Doctor Ames<lb/>
himself, the doctor who actually took care of the experimental cases. Would it<lb/>
not be ironic to have Congress now honor the male nurse and not honor the doctor<lb/>
who was in charge of all these experimental cases? Would it not be inappropriate<lb/>
to honor a man who, by the Army's viewpoint, merely served excellently (I would<lb/>
say magnificently) but only within the limits of his duty and not honor those<lb/>
who volunteered with full knowledge that they might not only get yellow fever,<lb/>
indeed probably would, but might actually die but who, for some reason not of<lb/>
their own doing (the mosquitos might not have been ripe) did not develop yellow<lb/>
fever? To honor Mr. Lambert now, largely because he is living, and to ignore<lb/>
his chief and the others who actually volunteered but whose results were nega-<lb/>
tive would be to put a premium on simple longevity and not to assess the contri-<lb/>
bution that these various man made. To honor Lambert now and not to honor<lb/>
Doctor Ames would be making the same distinction (merely that one is alive and<lb/>
the other not) that would have been made had Congress decided to honor Reed,<lb/>
Carroll and Agramonte and not to honor Lazear who died of the experiments.</p>
<p>I agree heartily that Congress should &ldquo;clean this thing up&rdquo; and correct any re-<lb/>
mote injustice but they should not accomplish another injustice in order to honor<lb/>
one man. Therefore I have a proposal which seems better to me. The service<lb/>
of Doctor Lazear was a very fundamental one. At the one point of time during<lb/>
which Major Reed was called to Washington for special duty, Lazear actually <lb/>
held the fate of the experiments in his hands and it was during Reed's un-<lb/>
fortunate absence that Lazear's first experiments became positive and then<lb/>
apparently the fatal experiment of Lazear on himself. Reed had to return and<lb/>
had to develop the later series of experiments because the first report, based<lb/>
largely on the experiments of Lazear, received no more acceptance from the<lb/>
American or general public than did the early reports of Finlay. Therefore<lb/>
although it might be said that Lazear was actually the first one to discover<lb/>
and <hi>prove</hi> the cause of yellow fever and passed on his discovery to Reed by<lb/>
way of the little pocket notebook, nevertheless Reed had to re-prove it in<lb/>
a way that the world would accept. Thus no one should try to, or can, de-<lb/>
prive Reed or the other men of one bit of their credit, but Lazear certainly<lb/>
deserves more than he over got and of course he didn't get any recognition<lb/>
because he died.</p>
<p>My proposition, therefore, is as follows: For Congress to pass a new bill, or<lb/>
on amendment to the old bill, and create perhaps a new medal, giving let us say<lb/>
the Lazear Medal to Mr. Lambert (alive) and to Doctor Ames posthumously, and to<lb/>
the volunteers who actually went through the experiments but did not get yellow<lb/>
fever. There would be no pensions involved and in that way Congress would re-<lb/>
tain the all-important distinction made on the occasion of its 1929 action.</p>
<p>I think you would agree that were this situation as of today and were it polio<lb/>
instead of yellow fever, one would have to make a distinction between our<lb/>
respect and regard for doctors or nurses who, thinking little or nothing of<lb/>
their own safety, took care of polio patients at some risk, and volunteers who<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04906016"/>
Senator Richard B. Russell&nbsp;&nbsp; - 4 - &nbsp;&nbsp;April 16, 1956<lb/>
actually submitted themselves, at the risk of life, to polio inoculations of<lb/>
live virus. In my opinion, Doctor Ames and Mr. Lambert stand at the head<lb/>
of the first group but with all due regard to their magnificent contribu-<lb/>
tions, they do not belong to the second group where Congress contemplates<lb/>
placing them.</p>
<p>My distress about all of this is that I do have great admiration for Mr.<lb/>
Lambert. I have tried to help him get recognition by writing to him and<lb/>
he is to have an appropriate and honored part in my book. He is old and<lb/>
feeble and crippled and almost blind, a rather pathetic but nevertheless<lb/>
proud and worthy figure. I hate terribly to do anything that might hold up an<lb/>
honor to him so that it would come too late, after he passed on. I would<lb/>
almost rather see Congress make a mistake and include him in the old bill,<lb/>
even though this is a real injustice to his chief, Doctor Ames, and to<lb/>
the other volunteers who were excluded. Fortunately, that is not my de-<lb/>
cision to make but if I thought that I could help Congress, specifically<lb/>
you and your committee colleagues, to write what I believe would be the<lb/>
proper bill and pass it quickly; if I thought that appearing before your<lb/>
committee and perhaps a committee of the House would accomplish this, this year,<lb/>
I would certainly be delighted to do whatever I can.</p>
<p>In view of the above, will you please, therefore, let me know whether you<lb/>
could hear me testify and present such documentary proof as I have (it is<lb/>
voluminous and would have to be summarized carefully, not a job that could<lb/>
be done over night), and when that might be. I have been invited to give<lb/>
two lectures at Johns Hopkins Medical School, May 9 and 10, and could arrange<lb/>
to visit Washington during that week. I am leaving now to attend the meetings<lb/>
of the American College of Physicians at Los Angeles, and will not be back until<lb/>
April 28.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
