<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04909006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul L. Tate, July 24, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04909006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-07-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Tate, Paul L.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">McKenzie, Vernon</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="place">Berkeley (Calif.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-07-24">July 24, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04909006</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul L. Tate, July 24, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is disappointed the Lambert bill passed before he could meet with the committee. He is sure the next Congress will pass a resolution regarding Ames' contribution. He states that Lambert has made indiscretions and distortions in presenting the yellow fever story.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-07-24">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Paul L. Tate, July 24, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04909006"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1956-07-24">July 24, 1956</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Mr. Paul L. Tate<lb/>
1530 Tyler Street<lb/>
Berkeley, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Tate:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just returned from Europe and find that a lot happened with respect<lb/>
to Lambert et al, while I was away. I note that the committee had the<lb/>
hearing even before they received my material. This disappointed me greatly<lb/>
because I dictated the material before the date given me by Mr. Darden, the<lb/>
Executive Assistant and, presumably, my material should have reached them<lb/>
before they acted. However I realize that congressional committees are<lb/>
sometimes erratic and bring up bills before expected dates; there is<lb/>
nothing that I could have done about it as apparently the matter happened<lb/>
while I was enroute to Europe.</p>
<p>On returning home, I find many letters from the congressmen and others to<lb/>
whom I wrote, all telling me that the Lambert bill was passed, all regretting<lb/>
that they had not known earlier of Doctor Ames, and all promising that they<lb/>
would help me get the same honor for Doctor Ames at the next session of<lb/>
Congress. I haven't the slightest doubt that this will go through and<lb/>
indeed I intend to see that it does go through. If necessary, I will visit<lb/>
Washington and, indeed, I will request permission to be heard by the ap-<lb/>
propriate committees of the House and Senate. It would be ridiculous to<lb/>
have the nurse honored and not the physician, Doctor Ames. I shall not<lb/>
stop until this matter is corrected.</p>
<p>My feelings about Mr. Lambert were quite mixed. Frankly, in many ways he<lb/>
has been a &ldquo;naughty boy,&rdquo; and I had to forgive him for saying many things,<lb/>
some of which were indiscretions, some distortions and some were misunder-<lb/>
standings or frank untruths. I am speaking from the record and have a<lb/>
record of these things and will send you one before the next session of<lb/>
Congress. The incongruity was that, having said some very nasty things<lb/>
about Walter Reed as well as about Kean and others, he nevertheless wanted<lb/>
to receive the &ldquo;Walter Reed Honor,&rdquo; as it were. Many of his accusations of<lb/>
General Kean were completely false and could be very easily proven so by<lb/>
the official records but when I called these to his attention, he refused<lb/>
to accept them. I have no desire to defend General Kean, if and when he<lb/>
made mistakes, even serious mistakes, but certainly the accusations which<lb/>
Lambert made were ridiculous because the official Army records, available<lb/>
to anyone, showed that Kean wasn't even in the position or in the station where <lb/>
Lambert said he was when he was supposed to have done certain things un-<lb/>
favorable to Doctor Ames.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04909007"/>
<p>Mr. Paul L. Tate - 2 - July 24, 1956</p>
<p>For example, Major Kean had nothing whatever to do with Doctor Ames'<lb/>
transfer from the station hospital. My reaction was that if the govern-<lb/>
ment could forgive Hanberry (who, as you know, deserted) and later honor<lb/>
him for a previous distinction, I would of course have to forgive Lambert<lb/>
for his intensities and indiscretions because he certainly deserved very<lb/>
real honor for what he did as of course does Doctor Ames, but more of this<lb/>
later.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
cc: Mrs. Ames<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
