<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04904020">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter fragment to [William M. Brumby], [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04904020</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient"></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-04-16">April 16, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04904020</idno>
<title>Letter fragment to [William M. Brumby], [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The author does not believe that Ames was ever officially transferred to the Board. However, he does think that no one could have done the work of caring for the yellow fever patients as well as Ames. 
</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-04-16">
<head>Letter fragment to [William M. Brumby], [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04904020"/>
<p>(2)</p>
<p><add>Part of letter to Dr. Brumby that<lb/>
Gen. Turby referred to <unclear>in included</unclear><lb/>
letter.</add><lb/>
<del>and I think it a marvelous production.</del></p>
<p>In regard to S. O. 83, I subscribe thoroly with the contents of the<lb/>
letters of both Mr. Anderson and Mr. Hirsch, as they put it. But<lb/>
neither of them subscribe to it in the phraseology you would desire.</p>
<p>They still leave one to decide if Ames was transferred to be a mem-<lb/>
ber of the Board. They don't say that this order was instigated in<lb/>
the Surgeon General's Office in Washingtom, where it would have to<lb/>
come from to make an appointment to thids Board.</p>
<p>Major Reed could have requested the Chief Surgeon in Havana to<lb/>
transfer Ames to him for duty, but no one in the Department of<lb/>
Western Cuba would have authority to originate an order appointing<lb/>
Ames to the Board.</p>
<p>I would think that such an order if it came through military chan-<lb/>
nel's from Washington at that time would have read something like<lb/>
this: &ldquo;Pursuant to instructions from the Surgeon General of the<lb/>
Army, (date) Washington, D.C., Acting Assisitant Surgeon Roger Post<lb/>
Ames, etc., etc. and then would have named him as a replacement or<lb/>
member of the Board. This would have come through the Adjutant<lb/>
General's office. (which existed at that time).</p>
<p>I think such an important order would have constituted a Special<lb/>
Order in its own right and not be mixed up with transfers of en-<lb/>
listed men to the same place and various orders to other persons.</p>
<p>Of course all of the above is just my dim remebbrance of Army<lb/>
paper work, Gen. and Spec. Orders, etc. I am just a layman and<lb/>
never held any official position there, so nothing I say is at<lb/>
all authoritive. But, I regret to say, that I do not believe<lb/>
that Doctor Ames was ever officially transferred to the Board,<lb/>
and I am quite certain that no such order will ever be found.<lb/>
And one cannot take a definite Army Order and translate it into<lb/>
something we would like to believe, worthy as that belief is.</p>
<p>I guess that Major Reed was not bothering much about a Board at<lb/>
that time, anyway. The Sanarelli dispute had been settled--Lazear<lb/>
had solved the mystery of transmission--The only use of of a<lb/>
Board was to sigh official papers. All Major Reed required then<lb/>
was an efficient, officer, doctor, yellow fever expert to put in<lb/>
charge of Camp Lazear and the Fever section. He got that in the<lb/>
person of Doctor Ames, and no one in all Cuba could have done the<lb/>
work so well. perhaps he was not a member of the Board, but he<lb/>
should have been. At that time Carrol and Agramonta might as well<lb/>
not have been there. The former slowly recovering from Y.F. and<lb/>
the latter away most of the time with his duties in Havana. Ames<lb/>
was practically the only man Reed had at that time.</p>
<p>I regret that I cannot be of more assistance to you in the more<lb/>
favorable way I know you desire, but the foregoing is the only<lb/>
way I can see it. S. O. 83 is just an order meaning only what it says<lb/>
on its face and nothing more.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>