<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04917004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Essay: On A Hillside, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, June 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04917004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-06-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Blue Ridge Summit (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-06-00">June, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04917004</idno>
<title>Essay: On A Hillside, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, June 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed pays tribute to her father, Walter Reed, in this essay. She describes her home in the Blue Ridge Mountains, their gardens, and her father's devotion to his family and to medicine.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1954-06-00">
<head>Essay: On A Hillside, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, June 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04917004"/>
<p>1</p>
<p>ON A HILLSIDE</p>
<p>There is a sort of little breeze that blows - a gentle breeze that<lb/>
stirs the leaves as it does one's memory. I find myself looking into space -<lb/>
daydreaming, as I sit by my garden. A robin is digging with great vengeance,<lb/>
uprooting a worm. Another robin and his devoted friend, a sparrow, are<lb/>
bathing in the bird bath. The sparrow sits a little back and lets the robin<lb/>
give him a shower bath. My cat is lazily stretched at my feet. He has forgotten<lb/>
the birds above him as he curls his head under his paw for a long nap.</p>
<p>As I sit and watch the butterflies, dipping here and there on the<lb/>
flowers, I go in my imagination to another garden on the side of a hill, and I<lb/>
see walking toward me a tall slender man. He has a tender expression of love<lb/>
on his face and as he looks down at me he says, &ldquo;Little daughter.&rdquo; He is my<lb/>
father - someone I love with all my heart. He is kind and affectionate with a<lb/>
great deal of humor. There is a tinge of gray in his hair and his blue eyes<lb/>
are always smiling. His busy desk in his office in Washington is closed. The<lb/>
laboratory windows are also closed. My father has come to spend a weekend with<lb/>
Mother and me. He has bought 12 acres of land and we are planning a home of our<lb/>
own - the first we have ever known, for my father is an army officer, a doctor<lb/>
in the Army Medical Corps. Our new home is on a hillside; we are in the Blue<lb/>
Ridge Mountains in Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>I drift into a little bit of heaven as I dream on. We are living in<lb/>
a small bungalow planned by my parents - their bedroom, my bedroom, a tiny bath,<lb/>
lots of windows, a door that opens on a wonderful view of the Cumberland Valley.<lb/>
The Tuscarora Mountains lie 40 miles across a fertile valley. The east door<lb/>
opens and as we sit at our dining room table we look through a grape arbor into<lb/>
a terraced garden.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04917005"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>Already the annual seeds have been sown and are blooming. On the<lb/>
first terrace are clumps of peonies; masses of gay colored petunias bloom along<lb/>
the edge; and below are beds of pansies and old-fashioned pinks close to the<lb/>
stone wall that starts the first terrace. There are clumps of phlox, larkspur,<lb/>
candytuft; beds of heliotrope and mignonette, rose geranium and lemon verbena.<lb/>
There are two rose arbors - one red and one pink - and at the end of the garden<lb/>
sickle pear trees are boasting small pears. On the sides are apple and pear,<lb/>
plum and peach trees. It's truly a fairy land! On one wall blooms a light and<lb/>
dark purple clematis from my grandmother's garden in North Carolina.</p>
<p>On each side of the flower beds that border the walk are vegetable<lb/>
gardens - my father's pride and joy. Here grow all the vegetables one's heart<lb/>
could desire - enough for an army! But a blessing to the less fortunate when<lb/>
fall comes. Many small boys in big farm hats and bare feet have helped build<lb/>
the stone fences for we have more than our share on our land. The stone fences<lb/>
will have blackberry and raspberry vines, roses and honeysuckle, and white<lb/>
clematis. A trumpet vine has grown high on the wood shed.</p>
<p>My parents are real lovers of the out-of-doors, of the birds and of<lb/>
nature. This has been handed down to me. Both of my parents have passed into<lb/>
the Land Beyond and I am living the life I have inherited from them - a home<lb/>
and a garden. My mother and father are a devoted couple. They sit on the<lb/>
porch, talking intently about the future of their home. The woodland at the<lb/>
end of the garden affords a walk for lovers. Here my parents have spent hours<lb/>
clearing the undergrowth, laughing at their aching muscles.</p>
<p>The sunlight filters through the trees. A busy squirrel is over head.<lb/>
A bird calls to his mate. My father holds my mother's hand and calls her<lb/>
<add>&ldquo;</add>Sweetheart.<add>&rdquo;</add> Her hair is a beautiful shade of auburn. Small curls on her head<lb/>
shine all red and gold as she comes into the sunlight. I watch them and wonder<lb/>
will I ever be so happy when I grow up. I have a brother; he is in the army<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04917006"/>
3<lb/>
and away from home. I am 17: my brother is 22.</p>
<p>Late that afternoon as my parents talk on the porch, a small boy with<lb/>
a telltale look of blackberries on his mouth and cheeks comes running to my<lb/>
father's side. Could Doctor Reed come quickly to their home, his sister who is<lb/>
sick in bed is very bad and needs a doctor right away. The small boy shows<lb/>
Father the short-cut through the woods and soon the tall slender figure and the<lb/>
little boy disappear through the heavy foliage. Later, Mother receives a note<lb/>
from Father: Could she send a bottle of sherry - he won't be back that night.<lb/>
The young woman who has two small babies dies. She slips into eternity just<lb/>
before sunrise, while a patient and loving physician sits by her bedside and<lb/>
does all that a doctor can do.</p>
<p>We have breakfast together, the three of us. Our colored maid is a<lb/>
good cook and my parents are Southern. We have oatmeal with heavy cream,<lb/>
chicken hash, hot biscuits, hominy grits, coffee with a delightful aroma, and<lb/>
strawberries from our garden. My father is a scientist, but when he retires<lb/>
from the army he is going to spend the best part of his life digging in his<lb/>
garden. Bertha's death has saddened us. We speak but little during breakfast.<lb/>
Mother goes to her flowers; Father to a heavy crop of weeds in his asparagus bed;<lb/>
and my attention is attracted to two small birds that have fallen from their<lb/>
nest in the grape arbor.</p>
<p>The day slips by and evening finds us on our front porch watching a<lb/>
glorious sunset. Father and Mother reminisce. They speak of other sunsets -<lb/>
of days long ago spent in Arizona where Mother went as a bride from North<lb/>
Carolina - days of the covered wagon. A son is born to them in Arizona. Did<lb/>
she remember on one of their trips when she spilled a jar of peaches down<lb/>
Father's back? The mule team had given an awful lurch forward and the wagon<lb/>
had gone on its side. Father had gotten out to help the driver. The conver-<lb/>
sation drifts back for plans of our real summer home. It is to be of native<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04917007"/>
4<lb/>
stone and brown shingles. There will be a huge fireplace with a motto above,<lb/>
&ldquo;Love ever by my fireside and peace within my door.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The weekend is over and we watch the train that carries Father down<lb/>
the mountain. He waves to us from the back platform. Already we are looking<lb/>
forward to his return. The following weeks bring him back to his hillside. He<lb/>
has an inviting box of Huyler's candy for Mother, and with a teasing look on<lb/>
his face he takes an envelope out of his pocket addressed to me. It is in a<lb/>
bold writing and inside the envelope on a white card is an autograph of<lb/>
Otis Skinner, a famous actor in the gay nineties. I had seen him at the old<lb/>
Columbia Theatre in Washington and had lost my heart to him. The next morning<lb/>
at my plate at the breakfast table was a tiny note addressed to me:<lb/>
&ldquo;Miss Blossom Reed - Breakfast&rdquo;; and in Father's writing on the inside of the<lb/>
little note was written:</p>
<p>&ldquo;My own little Dumpling,<lb/>
I have heard of your wild ravings over me and of<lb/>
my magnificence and I wish to say that I think quite as<lb/>
much of myself as you think of me, and I simply adore<lb/>
you because you have shown excellent taste in your<lb/>
admiration for me.<lb/>
Your Otis&rdquo;</p>
<p>I still have this little note.</p>
<p>Two summers pass and our home is completed. It is very exciting<lb/>
packing to go back again. We wonder if the two hound dogs, Prince and Trump,<lb/>
will remember us. The basket is ready for my tabby cat. Father carries it<lb/>
for me for he too is very devoted to my pet. We have our same colored maid.<lb/>
As we ride on the train and climb into the mountains our hearts are happy and<lb/>
gay. Father has been up several times alone to see the last touches, and a<lb/>
pump that went far into the copper rock but that now affords cool, clear water.<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04917008"/>
5<lb/>
A dear little pump house has been built with lattice work and painted white.<lb/>
The wisteria vines make an artistic setting as the blossoms tumble over roof<lb/>
and sides.</p>
<p>Due to Father's scientific work in Washington our army post days are<lb/>
over. We are at the beginning of a wonderful summer. It's June and the month<lb/>
of roses. But the sun goes behind a cloud for Mother and me. One morning<lb/>
while we are at the breakfast table the mail arrives. There is a letter from<lb/>
the Surgeon General's office to Major Walter Reed. Father takes off his glasses<lb/>
and looks at Mother, &ldquo;I must leave my darling girls. The Surgeon General<lb/>
wants me to go to Cuba to study the cause of yellow fever.&rdquo; Our hearts are<lb/>
heavy for we are now alone, but we have promised to be happy and above all to<lb/>
keep after the weeds. He will write often and so will we.</p>
<p>The summer passes. Somehow the days have been long. Mother has been<lb/>
made very nervous from Father's stay in Cuba. But he will return. Patiently<lb/>
we wait. We live in a boarding house in Washington. I have my cat. One fall<lb/>
night we wait on the front steps. Father is not sure of the arrival of his<lb/>
train in Washington. The house sits back in a yard. There is a walk to the<lb/>
gate. A cab drives up. Two men leave the cab and start coming up the walk.<lb/>
Mother rushes down the not too well lighted walk and throws her arms around the<lb/>
first man's neck, &ldquo;My darling! My darling!&rdquo; Father speaks from the rear,<lb/>
&ldquo;Emily, you are embarrassing the cab driver!&rdquo;</p>
<p>We are at Blue Ridge again. Proudly my father surveys his home.<lb/>
Mother goes from room to room. Soon she is in the terrace garden, gathering<lb/>
flowers for our dining table. We live a full and happy summer and I have<lb/>
friends whom Father would bring up to spend weekends. On one occasion when one<lb/>
of my friends was dressed in her best bib and tucker she sat on a sheet of<lb/>
fly paper and backed up to my father to see if he, being a doctor, could remove<lb/>
it. I never saw him more amused or politer.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f04917009"/>
<p>6</p>
<p>The last of September comes and it is time to pack again for Washington.<lb/>
The mountains and our hillside put on their cloaks of red and gold. The fruit<lb/>
lies under the trees in small piles, awaiting its owners. The fields are<lb/>
covered with goldenrod and wild asters - all purple and gold. A lazy bee drones<lb/>
by, and I sit on the slope of the lawn with my cat. The beauty of the out-of-<lb/>
doors makes my bedroom and suitcases look cold and drab.</p>
<p>Suddenly a voice speaks to me. It comes close and I am frightened.<lb/>
The voice says, &ldquo;Something dreadful is going to happen on the 17th of November.&rdquo;<lb/>
With pounding heart I rush to my father's side. I take his hand and hold it.<lb/>
I kiss his hand gently and put it down. I go to my room. What is this awful<lb/>
thing? I am so deeply depressed that I hear my father say, &ldquo;Little daughter<lb/>
is not well. I almost fear typhoid.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We return to Washington and go to an apartment. We bid farewell to<lb/>
our new home and our hillside. It's a lovely home. My father plans big days<lb/>
ahead. We will have horses, a cow, pigs and chickens, and Mother will be his<lb/>
farmer lady.</p>
<p>Now his prayer has been answered - one that he prayed ever since he<lb/>
was a very young man - that God would permit him during his sojourn on earth<lb/>
to do something to alleviate the suffering of mankind. He has made a brilliant<lb/>
discovery. He has conquered Yellow Jack! For his glorious achievement he is<lb/>
to be made the next Surgeon General. He is to receive the Nobel Prize.</p>
<p>I am to make my debut. Mother is busy planning our clothes. My debut<lb/>
dress is white organdy with yards and yards of tiny white satin ribbon edged<lb/>
with pearls that make a design on the wide and billowing skirt. My parents say<lb/>
that I look like an angel in it. But I am not interested. I am deeply depressed.<lb/>
The voice that spoke to me on our hillside rings in my ears and in my dreams.<lb/>
My nights are restless and I am afraid - for it is the month of November.</p>
<p>I come in from a walk and find my father in bed. He has had an<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04917010"/>
7<lb/>
attack of appendicitis. Some one brought him home from his office. He was too<lb/>
ill to come alone. It will pass and he is to go to New Orleans for work on<lb/>
an Army Typhoid Board. It is very important. He will be gone in a week.</p>
<p>I stare at him. This then is the answer to that voice. November!<lb/>
I feel numb. My darling father has a chill and he is taken to the Army Hospital<lb/>
at Washington Barracks. I kiss him as he lies on the stretcher. Two young<lb/>
soldiers look at me with kind eyes. &ldquo;Little daughter, my little joy,&rdquo; is all<lb/>
that he says. It is the 17th day of November. Was it that my father's soul<lb/>
and mine were so closely linked that this was told to me? The answer has never<lb/>
come. I have talked it over more than once with a good many doctors, but there<lb/>
has never been a solution. I cry my heart out and then go to comfort my<lb/>
mother.</p>
<p>We wait through the long hours of the days and nights. He is too ill<lb/>
for us to see. Six nights later I go to his bedside. I look down on a face<lb/>
wrought with pain. His hands are cold. I kneel at his bedside as he whispers,<lb/>
&ldquo;Little daughter,&rdquo; his last words on earth. A cutting wind blows outside the<lb/>
hospital doors. Two colonels in the Medical Corps hold my arm and take me home.<lb/>
Mother is ill in bed. I have kept my secret. The wind tugs at my skirts and<lb/>
chills me through. November 17 has passed. This is November 23, 1902. This<lb/>
tall slender doctor is dead.</p>
<p>What was there to say - only that God had bigger things on a higher<lb/>
plane for him to do. Silently we packed. We are dressed in the deepest<lb/>
mourning. The tramp, tramp, tramp of the soldiers' feet in Arlington, the<lb/>
clear sound of Taps that echoes through the hills rings in our ears. Lead<lb/>
Kindly Light - Peace Perfect Peace - comes from the choir loft - I am the<lb/>
Resurrection and the Life.</p>
<p>The perfume of lillies and violets and roses still cling to the<lb/>
walls. The glamour of my debut, of Father's being Surgeon General had faded<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04917011"/>
8<lb/>
like a dream. My brother is in the Phillipines and Mother and I are packing<lb/>
to go to her sister's home in North Carolina. My heart is completely broken.<lb/>
I am 19 now and I must be a brave woman and help take care of my mother. My<lb/>
father would have it so.</p>
<p>The dreams of my childhood days have gone. I stand at my closet door.<lb/>
The white organdy dress is hanging there - it is very beautiful; a pair of<lb/>
white satin slippers; an evening bag and gloves. I close my eyes and for a<lb/>
few moments I see my father in his full dress uniform - Mother by his side.<lb/>
She has on a light blue brocade satin with violets at her waist. How well I<lb/>
remember the day it came from the dressmaker's. Her waist is small; her skirts<lb/>
are very full. She wears long white gloves and a necklace Father brought her<lb/>
from Cuba. We stand there, the three of us. It is my debut. I am introduced<lb/>
to many officers. Their wives are young and gay. Softly an army band plays<lb/>
and I dance my first waltz with my father for he was my dancing master when I<lb/>
was a child. While I am dancing I hear my mother calling me. Some one has<lb/>
come for my white organdy dress - the slippers are too small. Gently the<lb/>
dress is folded. My gloves and evening bag are put into the same box. It will<lb/>
be for another debut, but not my own.</p>
<p>The months have gone and we leave the pine woods and the sandy roads<lb/>
of North Carolina and return to our summer home. Mother feels closest to<lb/>
Father here, more than any place on earth. The dogwood trees that border our<lb/>
lawn hold out their white arms to greet us. The soft new green is creeping<lb/>
up the mountains. I stoop to pick a violet. Can we go on alone? It does not<lb/>
seem possible that he has gone. Our home has a solemn look. How can we stay -<lb/>
we two who loved him so? We hear him call to us. We see those dear hands that<lb/>
have toiled so for our pleasure; the warmth of his smile.</p>
<p>I slip my arm through Mother's. The boy that worked for us stands<lb/>
on the porch. There are tears in all of our eyes. &ldquo;He was a grand man,&rdquo;<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f04917012"/>
9<lb/>
the boy says. &ldquo;I just can't think about him without crying. I've brought<lb/>
you some milk and eggs from home, some fresh asparagus that the doctor loved so.<lb/>
I can't get him out of my mind.&rdquo;</p>
<p>As we looked at our hills we thought of another hillside - the<lb/>
hillside that claimed him for all times. For on the slope of a hill in<lb/>
Arlington Cemetery is his grave. It's a beautiful spot. You can see the<lb/>
Potomac River winding lazily below. The slope is sunny.</p>
<p>Suddenly, I am awakened from my dreams. A heavy storm is coming up.<lb/>
I gather my cat in my arms and as I walk away from my garden I brush away a<lb/>
tear or two from my eyes. The little breeze that stirred my memory has turned<lb/>
into a heavy storm. The rain is pouring.</p>
<p>But I shall return to my garden, perhaps to dream again, to relive<lb/>
the days so dear to my girlhood heart. It is a simple tribute that I can pay<lb/>
to him whom I loved so dearly - a tribute of love and affection to my hero -<lb/>
and my beloved father - Walter Reed.</p>
<p>Blossom Reed<lb/>
daughter of<lb/>
Walter Reed-</p>
<p>June 1954-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
