<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04911015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Vernon McKenzie, September 22, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04911015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-09-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">McKenzie, Vernon</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-09-22">September 22, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04911015</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Vernon McKenzie, September 22, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench inquires if the army has any information about Hanberry's desertion from the army.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-09-22">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Vernon McKenzie, September 22, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04911015"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1956-09-22">September 22, 1956</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Major Vernon McKenzie<lb/>
Personnel Division<lb/>
Surgeon General's Office<lb/>
Department of the Army<lb/>
Washington 25, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Major McKenzie:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Next Friday noon I leave Rochester to visit Mr. James L. Hanberry in Orange-<lb/>
burg, South Carolina. I will spend next Saturday with him and then go to<lb/>
Chattanooga where I am to speak. As you may remember, Mr. Hanberry is the<lb/>
only surviving member of Walter Reed's group of human guinea pigs. I think<lb/>
you know that I have made the story of the conquest of yellow fever an in-<lb/>
tensive hobby for eighteen years and am writing a book on it. I have many<lb/>
questions to ask Mr. Hanberry, most of which are more important than the<lb/>
question about which I am writing you.</p>
<p>It is a matter of official record that Mr. Hanberry deserted from the Army<lb/>
about eight days after re-enlistment. This is recorded in many places.<lb/>
For example, on page 28 of Senate Document 822, 61st Congress, 3rd Session<lb/>
(1911); on page 6 of Report No. 1429, 70th Congress, 1st Session. H.R. (1928);<lb/>
on page 7 of Report No. 841, 71st Congress, 2nd Session (1930), H.R., etc.</p>
<p>In the Roll of Honor, published annually in the &ldquo;Army Register&rdquo; there is a<lb/>
very brief account of Hanberry's military career: &ldquo;Born South Carolina,<lb/>
12 December 1875. Private, Company L, 1st South Carolina Volunteer Infantry;<lb/>
service 21 August 1898 to 10 November 1898. Private, Hospital Corps, 13 Decem-<lb/>
ber, 1898 to 12 December 1901. Developed experimental yellow fever February 9,<lb/>
1901.&rdquo; Presumably his third term began on 28 March 1902, and eight days later,<lb/>
on April 4, 1902, he deserted &ldquo;At the General Hospital, Washington Barracks, D.C.&rdquo;<lb/>
There must have been some curious reason that made him desert from an Army hos-<lb/>
pital eight days after what was apparently his third enlistment, and one suspects<lb/>
that he may have rebelled against some incident at the hospital. The wording<lb/>
of Senate Document 822 gives one the impression that he deserted while a patient<lb/>
at the Washington Barracks General Hospital, but perhaps he was not a patient<lb/>
but a member of the hospital corps there. Presumably he disappeared for a<lb/>
number of years but because of his outstanding service during the experiments,<lb/>
the Army made no attempt to find him and after the 1928 awards (Congressional<lb/>
Medal, pension and so on), he reappeared and has been honored ever since.</p>
<p>Now Major McKenzie, if the Army records explain his desertion, I will not ask<lb/>
him about it. Could I get this information either from you (I believe you have<lb/>
the records of all these men), or from the AGO? If you do not have an adequate<lb/>
explanation, I think that he owes it to himself to give one before it is too<lb/>
late and next Saturday, after asking other more important questions, I will ask<lb/>
him very diplomatically and delicately if he cares to tell me the circumstances<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04911016"/>
Major Vernon McKenzie - 2 - September 22, 1956<lb/>
of his leaving the service. I am perfectly willing for him to put the best face<lb/>
on it. No one cares to embarrass him and in view of his great service, he<lb/>
deserves to have the incident forgotten, except that, whether he likes it or<lb/>
not (and he does) he has become a historical figure, a participant in a dramatic<lb/>
development which will be written about indefinitely; hence my contention that<lb/>
he should give us (you, me) whatever explanation he chooses to make.</p>
<p>Will you kindly wire me collect, to reach me at my home, 517 Fourth Street S.W.,<lb/>
Rochester, any time before Friday morning, September 28. If I get an ex-<lb/>
planation, and if he is willing for me to put it on his Army records, I will<lb/>
certainly send it to you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
