<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04917001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Note from Eileen R. Cunningham, [October 10, 1957]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Cunningham, Eileen R.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04917001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1957-10-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1957-10-10">October 10, 1957</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04917001</idno>
<title>Note from Eileen R. Cunningham, [October 10, 1957]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Cunningham comments on Reed's essay about her father and provides a few of her own memories about Walter Reed. She includes a transcription of a letter written to her by Emilie Lawrence Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1957-10-10">
<head>Note from Eileen R. Cunningham, [October 10, 1957]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04917001"/>
<p>Note from Eileen R. Cunningham.</p>
<p>When I was a little girl, I too, had the privilege of knowing Major Reed and the<lb/>
&ldquo;Hillside&rdquo; so vividly described by his daughter. Our summer home adjoined that of<lb/>
Major Reed and our wire fence separated the lawns and gardens crossed by an oldfashioned<lb/>
stile. How often I made use of it would probably have been embarrassing to my family<lb/>
had they known of each visit. Luckily for me, he loved children and being of unfailing<lb/>
courtesy and patience I was welcome to follow him about as he worked and to listen to<lb/>
his unfailing fund of stories about frontier life and Indians. How well I remember<lb/>
my father's <unclear><del>f</del><add>g</add>rief</unclear> that gloomy November afternoon in 1902 when he heard the sad news<lb/>
of his death for they were good friends and continually exchanging views on their plans<lb/>
as &ldquo;amateur farmers&rdquo;. I saw his daughter in June 1957 when visiting our old home<lb/>
at Blue Ridge Summit. Her little tribute to her father's memory gives an intimate<lb/>
portrait of him which only his daughter could draw. Families of great men sometimes<lb/>
pay a great price for the extra strain on nerves and health imposed by their achievements<lb/>
on front line battles for suffering humanity. Certainly his gay,19 year old daughter<lb/>
found her life irrevocably altered by his untimely passing and a little 8 year old<lb/>
neighbor joined in her sorrow. I can remember so well those lovely, sunny summer days<lb/>
of his last few vacations and the subsequent saddened lives of his family as they lived<lb/>
on each summer in the home he planned.</p>
<p>As part of the regular course in medical history I gave a lecture on the history<lb/>
of yellow fever, including of course, Walter Reeds work. I asked his widow for a<lb/>
picture of their summer home to show the students and she sent it with this letter:</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="letter" n="1935-03-06">
<head>Letter from Blossom Lawrence Reed to Eileen R. Cunningham, March 6, 1935</head>
<opener>
The Burlington Hotel Vermont Ave., Washington D.C.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1935-03-06">March 6, 1935.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Eileen:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It gave me much pleasure to receive your cordial letter. I am<lb/>
just back from Blue Ridge Summit where Blossom has built a lovely &ldquo;Inn&rdquo;<lb/>
and is having the most wonderful success in running. I live there with<lb/>
her now for the summer months. and I am sending you the only picture I<lb/>
have down here of the old home.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04917002"/>
<p>Note from Eileen R. Cunningham contd. 2</p>
<p>My hearty greetings to each and every one of the medical students and<lb/>
tell them there is a warm spot in my heart for all doctors. My wishes are that some<lb/>
of them may <unclear>grow</unclear> to have the fame that was and is Walter Reed's:</p>
<p>Tell them (the students) that Dr. Reed and I both loved that home and<lb/>
that it was there we knew you as a little neighbor. The <hi>last talk</hi> I ever had with my<lb/>
dear husband just before he was taken to the hospital for that fatal operation, was,<lb/>
what we would do early the next spring in our garden.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With my love to you dear Eileen,<lb/>
Affectionately,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Emilie L.(awrence) Reed.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
