<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04934001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Biographical sketch: Life and Letters of Walter Reed, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04934001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship">YES</term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>44 pp.</extent>
<date value="0000-00-00"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">04934001</idno>
<title>Biographical sketch: Life and Letters of Walter Reed, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Reed reminisces about her father and includes letters written by her father to her mother. [Hench] notes inconsistencies with her transcriptions and the originals in the margins.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="0000-00-00">
<head>Biographical sketch: Life and Letters of Walter Reed, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04934001"/>
<p>These are<lb/>
<unclear>variously edited</unclear> -- much <unclear>deleted</unclear></p>
<p>LIFE AND LETTERS<lb/>
OF<lb/>
DR. WALTER REED<lb/>
BY<lb/>
HIS DAUGHTER<lb/>
BLOSSOM REED</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04934002"/>
<p>My father, Walter Reed, has always held a memory dear to the<lb/>
heart of my childhood days. His gentle nature and fine character have left<lb/>
an indelible impression on those who knew him, especially I think, on his<lb/>
medical students who have alluded to him through my life time more than<lb/>
once as their guiding star.</p>
<p>Father was born in Gloucester County, Virginia on September 13,<lb/>
1851. My grandfather, the late Reverend Lemuel Sutton Reed, a Methodist<lb/>
minister, spent most of his life in the South, so father was raised in various<lb/>
parts of Virginia. A student always and having a love for medicine, he was<lb/>
anxious to attend the University of Virginia, as my grandfather was living<lb/>
at that time in Charlottesville where father had attended a private school<lb/>
owned and run by a Mr. Abbott, who was a graduate of the University of Vir-<lb/>
ginia. My father was one of five children, three brothers and one sister,<lb/>
and it was financially impossible for my grandfather to give him more than<lb/>
one year at the University. But he begged for that one year. On inquiring<lb/>
if he could take a degree of Doctor of Medicine if he passed his examinations,<lb/>
the faculty consented, thinking they were safe in their promise because at<lb/>
the youthful age of sixteen, it would be quite impossible.</p>
<p>In the summer of 1869, he graduated after nine months of untiring<lb/>
study, standing third in his class. The standard at the University was very<lb/>
high, and it was by only allowing himself three or four hours sleep, out of<lb/>
the twenty-four, that he so successfully graduated. Dr. Maupin, in present-<lb/>
ing him with his diploma, said he was the youngest student ever graduated<lb/>
from the Medical School in Charlottesville. He then went, as a medical<lb/>
&check; student, to New York to Bell<add>e</add>vue Hospital and received the degree of M. D.<lb/>
A year later, father then had hospital experience in several New York Hospi-<lb/>
tals, being an interne at Kings County Hospital, studying Children's diseases<lb/>
on Randall's Island, and later he was appointed district physician to one<lb/>
of the poorest districts in New York. I remember during my childhood of his<lb/>
telling of the misery and suffering of those patients, and of the very har-<lb/>
rowing experience which made a deep and sorrowful impression on him. At<lb/>
the age of twenty-two, he was one of the five Inspectors on the Brooklyn<lb/>
Board of Health. In 1874, he decided to give up his practice and enter the<lb/>
Medical Corps of the United States Army. This, I have been told was due to<lb/>
a visit to his father in North Carolina where my mother lived. The Army<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04934003"/>
#2<lb/>
seemed to hold a brighter future for this very youthful doctor whose thoughts<lb/>
and heart turned to dreams of matrimony. The examination for the Army was a<lb/>
difficult one, and it makes my heart ache after all these years have passed<lb/>
to know how he struggled and worked, making himself ill to accomplish this new<lb/>
end. In February 1875, he passed a brilliant examination, and received his<lb/>
commission as first Lieutenant in the Medical Corps of the Army. His first<lb/>
station was at Willet's Point, New York Harbour.</p>
<p>I have in my possession, letters which were written by my father<lb/>
to my mother. Mother was Miss Emilie Lawrence of Murfreesboro, North Caro-<lb/>
lina, and it was there while my grandfather was attending a conference in the<lb/>
Methodist Episcopal Church that they met, and might I add, &ldquo;love at first<lb/>
sight.&rdquo; In one of the earliest of these letters and written on pink note<lb/>
paper is as follows: &ldquo;Compliments of Walter Reed to Miss Emilie Lawrence and<lb/>
would be pleased to call this evening if agreeable.&rdquo; September 28th, 1874.</p>
<p>Mother and father became engaged in May 1875 and were married in<lb/>
April 1876, and left at once for a station in Arizona. My blessed father<lb/>
always wrote such sweet and tender letters to my mother asking for God's care<lb/>
always, and in one dated Brooklyn, March 4, 1875 he ends his letter: &ldquo;May the<lb/>
God who has watched over you and your happiness, thus far, still keep you<lb/>
closely under the shadows of his Almighty Wing.&rdquo;</p>
<p>On July 18th, 1874, when father was twenty-three and mother was<lb/>
eighteen, he wrote her from Brooklyn, as follows:</p>
<p>Miss Lawrence,</p>
<p>Another message has been gladly welcomed and again<lb/>
the happy privilege of replying, as best I may, is permitted me. I, too, have<lb/>
chosen the hour of night which you so beautifully alluded to in your letter;<lb/>
but though I acknowledge its bewitching influence, I feel that something more<lb/>
than its enchantment would be required to make to living expression, the slug-<lb/>
gish thoughts of my dull brain. If perchance a thought flashes dimly and fit-<lb/>
fully upon the horizon of my mind and I begin to trace it upon paper before<lb/>
<add>not so in the original</add> me, it is instantly blighted by the gingling <add>sic</add> bells and noisy rattle of some<lb/>
street car that goes tearing past my window and ere I can return to gather up<lb/>
the broken links and bind them together, the wished for idea has vanished for-<lb/>
ever. Nor am I blessed with the &ldquo;sighing zephyrs as they rustle amid the<lb/>
branches of the old oaks,&rdquo; to lull me with their plaintive moarnings <add>sic</add>. Oh! what <add>not so</add><lb/>
an indescribable difference there is between night in the city and night in<lb/>
the country; far greater than feeble words of mine can begin to tell. Here,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04934004"/>
#3<lb/>
the ever lasting day is crowded into busy night, nor can we draw the line of<lb/>
separation between the two. Both are equally characterized by the unceasing<lb/>
roar of humanity, struggling in the race of life, and many a poor aching<lb/>
heart, by day, &ldquo;bowed down with weight of woe,&rdquo; seeks at night, its humble<lb/>
home, but not to ease its aching, no never! till that last, long night that<lb/>
knows no earthly waking! But how different in the country! An evening of<lb/>
quiet repose succeeds a day of well spent, honest labor. &ldquo;The lowing herd<lb/>
winds slowly o'er its lea, and leaves the world to darkness and to me.&rdquo; Yes<lb/>
to nature and to me, and then how slight a step from nature up to nature's<lb/>
God! This is the hour of contemplation; of holy thoughts and sweet communion<lb/>
with self and friends undisturbed save by the &ldquo;Watch-dog's honest bark.&rdquo;<lb/>
Surely if happiness is ever decreed by mortals here below, it is at such<lb/>
moments that we experience it to the fullest extent. Blot them out and life<lb/>
to me would be an uninviting blank! I have been recently contemplating a<lb/>
<add>2 paragraphs omitted</add> departure from Brooklyn. My friends will consider me unwise in this, perhaps,<lb/>
but after due attention given to the matter, I believe I will be wise in so<lb/>
doing. I have about made up my mind to make a strenuous effort to enter the<lb/>
Medical Corps of the U. S. Army. The Examining Board which has not met before<lb/>
in six years assembles in New York City, August 4th, next. I should not desire<lb/>
to remain longer than three or four years at the outside. And now for my<lb/>
reasons. In the first place the Board of Health are requiring more work of<lb/>
the Inspector every day, and to such a degree that the idea of private practice<lb/>
cannot be thought of. In fact they desire the whole of an Inspector's time<lb/>
to be devoted to the interest of the Health Office District. This is doubtless<lb/>
<add>sic</add> right enough in that I for one fail to appreciate it. Secondly, these great<lb/>
cities have lost their fascination which formerly held me so fast. Four years<lb/>
ago I would have remained here, &ldquo;though the Heavens should fall.&rdquo; I gave my<lb/>
hopes and ambition a free rein and applied whip and spir <add>sic</add> unsparingly. To<lb/>
live in any other place than New York or Brooklyn, never entered my head, and<lb/>
if a person had advised me to go to some small town, I would have credited it<lb/>
to his insanity. To such an extent does our folly mislead us! But since then,<lb/>
a few more springs have come and gone, and though no gray hairs adorn my head,<lb/>
I have become a little wiser, I hope. I have carefully noted the success or<lb/>
failure of those around me and have watched them in their sorrows and joys.<lb/>
Yet during this time, I have been unable to discover the great advantage of<lb/>
living in Metropolitan cities, except to be in the &ldquo;wear and tear.&rdquo; It is<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04934005"/>
#4<lb/>
true I never worked harder, but I can't say it brought me any amount of comfort.<lb/>
I have still a third reason. Having entered my profession about four years<lb/>
earlier than is the custom, I have experienced all the troubles of a youthful<lb/>
aspirant for <hi>honors</hi>. As long as my success depends upon actual knowledge and<lb/>
experience, I managed to overcome all obstacles, but the moment that I entered<lb/>
upon the race of life, I found out at once, the disadvantages of a youthful<lb/>
appearance. It is a remarkable fact that a man's success during the first<lb/>
decade, depends more upon his beard than his brains, and inasmuch as I could<lb/>
boast of none of the former and but an infinitesimal quantity of the latter,<lb/>
I found &ldquo;Jordan to be a hard road to travel.&rdquo; Yet notwithstanding these<lb/>
many draw backs, my success has been greater than I could have expected and<lb/>
unless I can obtain the sanction of the homefolk, I will not leave. My stay<lb/>
in these cities has done me an incomparable good. By it I have obtained an<lb/>
extensive hospital and sanitary experience which is worth to me more than I<lb/>
can now estimate. It has always given me a truer insight into human nature than<lb/>
I could have acquired in an equal number of years elsewhere, while it has<lb/>
added to my respect for truth and morality, so that I count myself more than<lb/>
fortunate so far. On the other hand, I had thought that as I have no anxiety<lb/>
to plunge at once into the cares of life, a few years spent in traveling from<lb/>
one part of the country to another would be of profit to me. Of course all<lb/>
depends upon my ability to pass the examination which is a very rigid one.<lb/>
(I must confess that I dread it.) If at the end of that time (three or four<lb/>
years hence) I could find some fair damsel who was foolish enough to trust me,<lb/>
I think I would get married and settle down to sober work for the rest of my<lb/>
days in some small city where one could enjoy the advantages of a city and at<lb/>
the same time not feel as if lost. For in what does life consist? What is<lb/>
its true philosophy? Is it to win the applause of the rabble, or to sit in<lb/>
high places? Do we not arrive nearer to true happiness in striving to accept<lb/>
what Divine Wisdom allots to us; doing all we can to assist our fellow-men<lb/>
in being happy, and submitting uncomplainingly to the will of Him who gave us<lb/>
breath and life? Ever remembering that &ldquo;he that humbleth himself the same shall<lb/>
be exhalted.&rdquo; But really the hour has grown very late, and here am I philoso-<lb/>
phizing! My first impulse is to tear this up and spare you so many details,<lb/>
but on second thought I refrain from so doing, and beg that you will accept<lb/>
it in the same spirit in which it was written. I remain with much respect,</p>
<p>Walter Reed</p>
<p>A month later, from 115 Lee Avenue, Brooklyn, father answered<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f04934006"/>
#5<lb/>
mother's letter.</p>
<p>August 12, 1874<lb/>
Miss Lawrence,</p>

<p>Believe me, it is a genuine pleasure to lay aside the<lb/>
dusty book over whose uninteresting pages I have been bending all day long,<lb/>
and to take up my pen for a few moments. If I appear amazingly stupid, as I<lb/>
proceed, please remember that my mind has been racked during the past day or<lb/>
two with the &ldquo;atomic theory,&rdquo; and the &ldquo;law of equivalents,&rdquo; so that peradventure<lb/>
whatsoever I shall send, will not contain an atom of news or be equivalent to<lb/>
your loss of time in reading it. From early morning till far into the hours<lb/>
of night I must needs be plodding along through dry details and charging my<lb/>
memory with a thousand different matters which may possibly prove useful to me<lb/>
in the coming ordeal. The truth is I was not aware of how much I had forgotten<lb/>
and in how many places the rust had accumulated till I began a careful review.<lb/>
The more I read, the greater the task looms up before me, till I stand appalled<lb/>
at the work that must be done, and almost think that all I ever knew has for-<lb/>
saken me. But the one thing I will not permit to forsake me is my courage,<lb/>
and if effort will avail anything, it shall not fail me in this case. I went<lb/>
over to New York a few days ago and had a long talk with the Recorder of the<lb/>
Examining Board. To my utter astonishment, he informed me that candidates<lb/>
must stand an examination on Latin, Greek, Mathematics and History, in addition<lb/>
to medical subjects. Horror of horrors! Imagine me conjugating an irregular<lb/>
Greek verb, or telling what x &plus; y equals, or when Rome was founded, or the<lb/>
battle of Marathon fought. Why the thing is impossible! I shall utterly<lb/>
fail. Add to this that each applicant is examined five hours, each day during<lb/>
six successive days--thirty hours' questioning, and to cap the climax, there<lb/>
are more than five hundred applicants for thirty vacancies! The very thought<lb/>
of it makes me dizzy. Think of my condition and pity me, for I need all of the<lb/>
sympathy of my friends. Thus you see my time has been spent in quite a dif-<lb/>
ferent way from that you describe, no recreation, no jollity, no gliding<lb/>
&ldquo;softly o'er the rippling waters,&rdquo; no listening to &ldquo;wandering strains of<lb/>
melody.&rdquo; Your moonlight excursion down the Meherrin &check;River must have been<lb/>
quite romantic. It is enough for me to know that it was a &ldquo;feast of reason.&rdquo;<lb/>
I sometimes think that I am a peculiar mortal. Perhaps I am invited to be<lb/>
present at a party, composed of ladies and gentlemen assembled for the purpose<lb/>
of spending a pleasant social evening. I go with the determination to act<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04934007"/>
#6<lb/>
my part as well as I can with no malice in my heart toward any living soul.<lb/>
I arrive and am ushered into a brilliantly lighted parlor where are seated a<lb/>
dozen or more prettily dressed young ladies and as many starchy looking young<lb/>
gentlemen. The buds of modern society. Everyone seems in the best of humor,<lb/>
and I too, enter into the mirth of the occasion. As the conversation quickly<lb/>
flies from one topic to another, listen for a moment, yon fair one is going into<lb/>
ecstacy over the last Saratoga Boat race, and that flashily dressed young<lb/>
gentleman is expatiating with all his powers about the grandeur of a recent<lb/>
Ball. Perchance there is a lull in the conversation where forth with a damsel<lb/>
to the piano hies, and for the edification of all, drums away at an operatic<lb/>
air with all her might. Should anyone be so forgetful as to suggest a topic<lb/>
of interest, he soon finds himself without an audience. They say you are too<lb/>
serious, and thus the hours pass till finally the time of departure arrives,<lb/>
when expressing ourselves as being pleased beyond measure with the evening's<lb/>
entertainment and bidding many adieus, we depart. I loiter home slowly and<lb/>
muse by the wayside. I wonder how in the name of all that is sensible, can<lb/>
people be entertained with such silly frivolous conversation! Is there no<lb/>
germ of advancement implanted in the bosoms of such creatures? I cannot hide<lb/>
my utter disappointment in having thrown another evening away. I beg that you<lb/>
will excuse this hastily and miserably written letter, and believe me, as ever,<lb/>
with much respect,</p>
<p>Walter Reed</p>
<p>In the following letter father speaks of sympathy, the golden cord<lb/>
that binds humanity closer together. I am not surprised that he speaks of<lb/>
this at such an early age. His nature was one of tender sympathy always.<lb/>
His letter to mother is as follows:</p>
<p>Brooklyn<lb/>
September 17, 1874<lb/>
Miss Lawrence,</p>
<p>I owe you an apology for my long delay in answering<lb/>
your last letter. I would have written you promptly, had I not been deterred<lb/>
from so doing by severe sickness. During three long weeks, I have been confined<lb/>
to my room, and during the greater part of this time I was scarcely able to<lb/>
raise my head from the pillow. Hence I have, of necessity, been compelled to<lb/>
forego executing many plans which I had projected. No one of which gave me<lb/>
more reason for regret than my inability to write you. Doubtless, my own folly<lb/>
was the cause of my indisposition. I had been trying to do more than my<lb/>
strength could bear. It may be that I cannot do as much brain-work in the same<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04934008"/>
#7<lb/>
length of time, as I could do in my younger days; or perhaps a more correct<lb/>
statement would be that I have for so long a time, abandoned the habit of hard,<lb/>
continuous application, as to make it somewhat difficult, if not a matter at-<lb/>
tended with danger, to return into the &ldquo;traces&rdquo; quickly. I remember the time<lb/>
when I could study as much as twenty hours uninterruptedly, day after day, and<lb/>
not experience any bad effect from it, but I presume that time shall return<lb/>
no more. &ldquo;Man wants but little here below, nor wants that little long!&rdquo;<lb/>
Thus sang the sweetest bard that ever courted muse; and, for once, subscribing<lb/>
to that sentiment, I must content myself with the lighter task and leave to<lb/>
others the greater performance. But really there is a charm in studying that<lb/>
I fain must acknowledge. Let me become interested with what the author is<lb/>
saying and it is a difficult matter to &ldquo;break the spell;&rdquo; nor do I cease till<lb/>
my weary senses warn me that nature is well nigh exhausted. Oh! that we<lb/>
would always abide by nature's teachings! Then indeed would we be happy,<lb/>
healthy and wise. Perhaps I decide to dash aside the book, and for once,<lb/>
yield to refreshing sleep, but quicker than ever winged lightning cleaved<lb/>
heaven's vault, the thought flashes through my mind that there are a thousand<lb/>
things in the cast-aside volume of which I am ignorant, a thousand unanswerable<lb/>
questions that may rise up against me, in the day of my examinations, to humble<lb/>
and mortify me. Wracked by a thousand fears, I tear open the book and eagerly<lb/>
scan its pages, determined to exhaust every effort, and if need be, to suffer<lb/>
death rather than defeat! This is what I have done, and the result is sickness,<lb/>
<add>sic</add> mental paralysis, and is what I shall not dare repeat. Too happy in having<lb/>
partially regained my strength, I will see to it that I do not precipitate<lb/>
<add>sic</add> myself into former unhappy condition. This I can do the more easily, as I<lb/>
have an abundance of time in which to review my studies. A few days ago, I<lb/>
received a notice from the President of the Examination Board that I would not<lb/>
have to stand my examination till January 18, 1875. Of course, this suits me<lb/>
exactly, as it will give me an opportunity to visit home soon. I assure you<lb/>
that I highly appreciate the kind sympathy which you extended to me. I can<lb/>
study with a lighter heart knowing that I possess it. There are some things<lb/>
that I shall always remember. I know that sympathy is a golden cord that binds<lb/>
humanity closer together. To know that a heart beats in friendly sympathy with<lb/>
our own is one of life's sweetest comforts. To what noble aims have not men<lb/>
and women aspired, encouraged by this same knowledge! It is better than<lb/>
&ldquo;good news from a far country.&rdquo; It calms the bosom of the tempest<del>,</del> tossed<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f04934009"/>
#8<lb/>
mariner, though all be dark around; it cheers the warrior's heart; dispels<lb/>
his fears; it guides the scholar's pen, bids the down hearted look up, the<lb/>
faint be strong, and wraps the whole earth in a halo of glory! Before con-<lb/>
cluding, I will say a word or two on the &ldquo;novel&rdquo; question which you were dis-<lb/>
cussing in your last letter. There can be no doubt but that you have taken the<lb/>
right view on the question. Your legal friend, I think, is wrong for once.<lb/>
It is not to be supposed that a man should be right on every subject. I do<lb/>
not hesitate to say that ninety-eight per cent of all novels are second or<lb/>
third class -- the worst kind of trashy literature. We must not wonder at<lb/>
this when we think of the motives that lead to their production. It often<lb/>
happens that some young man or woman, college educated, living in luxury,<lb/>
finds it difficult to idle away the time which hangs so heavily on his or<lb/>
her hands. Woe be to the rest of mankind if the thoughts of writing a novel<lb/>
occurs to them, and how often is such a case. Again poverty presses some poor<lb/>
unfortunate and he flies to his pen for succor. The result naturally follows<lb/>
that the production must be worthless. To produce a good novel, there must<lb/>
be a sound thinking brain, the faculty of observing and interpreting a profound<lb/>
insight into human nature and a keen discrimination of character. Well, how<lb/>
often do we find such a one? Perhaps one in ten thousand instances. I cannot<lb/>
say more at present. I have managed to cover much paper with a very little<lb/>
that is worth the knowing. As this is only the second day that I have been<lb/>
able to sit up, it has been something of an effort to write.</p>
<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
Walter Reed</p>
<p>In father's letters during the following months, he often speaks<lb/>
of ill health due to over studying. He writes in November 1874:</p>
<p>Alas! I am so harassed. What to do surpasses the<lb/>
&ldquo;infinite of thought.&rdquo; At no time in my life did I ever appreciate more<lb/>
forcibly the statement that &ldquo;time and tide wait for no man.&rdquo; I must study --<lb/>
not a moment to lose, and it is the same studying that has delayed my conval-<lb/>
escence. Why I have not drawn an unsound breath for years. But now, when I<lb/>
need all my strength, lo! it fails me! It is like attempting to climb a<lb/>
hill with too great a burden. But what am I to do? Health or no health I<lb/>
must stand my examination in January. Language would fail to describe my<lb/>
chagrin and mortification were I to be prevented from so doing by reason of<lb/>
sickness. Still, I believe that when a person determines to accomplish an end<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f04934010"/>
#9<lb/>
that he should put forth all honest effort, nor turn aside unless for the best<lb/>
of reasons; and if he meets with defeat, let him accept it like a man, remember-<lb/>
ing that many better men have found themselves in a like situation. At all<lb/>
events, I shall pursue my course till every prop is knocked from under me.<lb/>
&ldquo;Sufficient unto the day is the evil thereof.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Father then alludes to one of mother's brothers, a doctor who<lb/>
was recently married.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the beginning of manhood when life is so full of<lb/>
hope, an honored member of the noblest professions on this round globe, and<lb/>
added to all these things, blessed with a sweet young wife!&rdquo; What more could<lb/>
mortal ask? When I look on so bright a picture and then turn my thoughts to<lb/>
the future and consider my bachelor days, I feel a little out of humor to say<lb/>
the least. How dark the horizon! Not a ray to cheer me on, no hand extended<lb/>
that I may grasp in mine and feel a new interest in life; no &ldquo;eye to mark my<lb/>
coming and look brighter when I come,&rdquo; no smile to greet me when the days work<lb/>
is done; no gentle voice to give encouragement amid life's sore trials! Such,<lb/>
such is mine! There is nothing like philosophically accepting the inevitable,<lb/>
others have trod the lonely road, and why not I as well. Others have sunk<lb/>
beneath the load. I'll fall where others fell! If I cannot obtain the prize<lb/>
I seek, this should not cause me to wish my friends the same misfortune. In<lb/>
fact it is the bachelor's peculiar duty and privelege <add>sic</add> to look with an approving<lb/>
eye on all his married friends and to wish them long life and happiness. A<lb/>
kind of general adviser, though not &ldquo;master of the situation.&rdquo; There were<lb/>
many other things I had intended speaking of, but want of space forbids.<lb/>
I remain,</p>
<p>Very truly, your friend,<lb/>
Walter Reed</p>
<p>No. 235 South 9th St.<lb/>
Brooklyn,January 9, 1875</p>
<p>Miss Emilie,</p>
<p>It may appear a little late in the day, but I will<lb/>
venture to wish you a &ldquo;happy, thrice happy New Year!&rdquo; May it bring you much<lb/>
happiness and many friends! The old year passed away so calmly and quickly<lb/>
and the New Year followed with footsteps so softly, that I was not aware of<lb/>
the change for several hours thereafter, in fact, balmly sleep had made me<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f04934011"/>
#10<lb/>
totally oblivious to all changes. I can remember the time when I would have<lb/>
been ashamed to make such an acknowledgement, for it was my custom to sit and<lb/>
watch the hands of the old clock as they slowly, but surely reached the hour<lb/>
of midnight, and when that important moment at last arrived, I would jump to<lb/>
my feet and give three hearty cheers for the New Year; or if influenced by a<lb/>
more sober mood, would remain on &ldquo;bended knee&rdquo; silently praying that my record<lb/>
for the New Year might be better and more acceptable than it had been during<lb/>
the old. But, of late, I have lost much interest in bidding farewell to the<lb/>
&ldquo;old&rdquo; or in welcoming the &ldquo;new.&rdquo; The night of the 31st of December, as far<lb/>
as I am concerned, has no more importance attached to it than any other night<lb/>
in the year. I have been absent from home and friends so many years that I<lb/>
even forget <add>sic</add> to celebrate Christmas, a day which in time gone by was to me the<lb/>
pleasantest of all. Very many times circumstances have been such as to prevent<lb/>
me from entering into the joys of the occasion, as happened during the<lb/>
Christmas just passed. I had to work and leave to others less arduous duties.<lb/>
Yet, this is not such as I would have it be. It is far, very far, from expres-<lb/>
sing my desires. I think there is no more fitting occasion than Christmas<lb/>
week for the reunion of the scattered members of a family, and for the renewal<lb/>
of those pledges of friendship and love which are so sweet to every heart.<lb/>
In this &ldquo;vale of tears,&rdquo; where there are so many burdens to bear, so many<lb/>
annoying trivialities to harass, it is but following our mutual impulses to<lb/>
long for some hour or day when we can cast aside all cares and exchange our<lb/>
frowns for smiles, our sighs for songs. I have much cause to fear that such<lb/>
an occasion will never present itself to my father's family. Like unto the<lb/>
chaff before the winds, we are scattered even unto &ldquo;the four corners of the<lb/>
earth!&rdquo; Still mingled with these feelings of regret, I can possess some con-<lb/>
solation, some comfort. I have a vivid consciousness of a love for my brothers<lb/>
and sisters as pure as the love of angels over which nor time nor distance has<lb/>
any power; of a veneration for my parents as noble as the noblest; of a memory<lb/>
of my sainted mother as pure as the crystals in Heaven's greatest dome; yes,<lb/>
thank God, so holy and bright is this memory that neither storm nor fire, nor<lb/>
flood, nor time, nor eternity, can ever dim its lustre! These things are left<lb/>
to me as &ldquo;my portion.&rdquo; These are my treasures that I hide in my heart of<lb/>
hearts and defy the power of worlds known and unknown to rob me of one &ldquo;jot<lb/>
or tittle&rdquo; of their preciousness! Possessed of such jewels as these, though<lb/>
lost in earth's dreariest desert, I could yet know some happiness. But to<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f04934012"/>
#11<lb/>
to retrace my steps a little, I was saying that the old year's departure was<lb/>
by me unobserved. Yet when I awoke on the morrow and found that such was the<lb/>
fact, many thoughts flooded my brain, thoughts similar to those expressed by<lb/>
yourself. Surely, if you have occasion for sadness, I should forever hide my<lb/>
head from the light of day. Truly, I cannot recall a year so full of sorrow,<lb/>
and yet in some respects, so happy as the past one. Paradoxical as this may<lb/>
sound, it is nevertheless true. Anguish! Remorse! feeble words to express<lb/>
what I have almost daily experienced. God Himself can only know what tortures<lb/>
I have borne; by what &ldquo;dark waters&rdquo; I have sat; and in this midnight of sorrow<lb/>
among the stars that shed a gladsome ray upon my path, there was one particu-<lb/>
larly bright and beautiful. Can you not imagine to what I refer? Even to<lb/>
your acquaintance, which I trust may yet grow into true friendship. This<lb/>
reminds me that one year has passed since I first met you. Yes, one year ago,<lb/>
I visited your little city. I only trust that before another year has elapsed,<lb/>
I may possess your esteem more than I do at present; that I may conduct myself<lb/>
so fairly and honestly that should anyone say in your presence that my words<lb/>
are flattering and my statements deceptive, you would be prepared to deny the<lb/>
assertion, or at least to know in your own heart, that it was false. Since<lb/>
then, the old year witnessed our acquaintance, I still cling fondly to its<lb/>
memory with all its griefs and burdens. Its dark days, I blot out from my<lb/>
rememberance tonight, and only recall its brightest moments. Thank heaven, I<lb/>
can and do forget the things of the past. My broken resolutions, my shattered<lb/>
hopes, all, all I bury and begin the new year as free from care as a bird!<lb/>
Did I say free from care? Oh! no! One thought bids me recall that expression,<lb/>
and that is my lack of religion. Though in my childhood it was my privilege<lb/>
to daily kneel and receive instructions at the feet of a christian mother now<lb/>
sainted, and though during my boyhood it was my good fortune to be surrounded<lb/>
by christian influences, and from boyhood to manhood to be guided by the wise<lb/>
counsel of a kind father, yet I find myself, tonight far from leading a pious<lb/>
life. Would to heaven that I could utter other words! But since I began the<lb/>
old year by making so many good resolutions, and ere it ended, had broken them<lb/>
all, I shall begin the present year with not so much as one. Perhaps it will<lb/>
be just as well. My only aim shall be to seek after truth and knowledge, to<lb/>
avoid the evil and cleave to the good, and in all things, as far as I am able,<lb/>
to conduct myself as a christian man and a Southern gentleman. To follow the<lb/>
words of the poet, &ldquo;Who misses or who wins the prize. Go lose or conquer as<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f04934013"/>
#12<lb/>
you can, but if you fall or if you rise, be each, pray God, a gentleman!&rdquo;<lb/>
I was glad to hear that Messers <add>sic</add> Longfellow and Bryant arrived safely and proved<lb/>
acceptable. I am not sufficiently well acquainted with the writings of either<lb/>
author to be able to refer to their best poems, but if my memory serves me<lb/>
correctly, there is a short poem by Bryant called the &ldquo;Rivulet&rdquo; which struck<lb/>
me as being very beautiful and expressive. You will perceive by noticing the<lb/>
number and street from which I write that I have changed my residence. This<lb/>
occurred somewhat suddenly, though not unexpectedly. There had been an under-<lb/>
current of dissatisfaction between myself and my most worthy land lady, dating<lb/>
from the time of my sickness. But I had hoped to avoid any open disturbance<lb/>
and bore with Job-like patience every unpleasant word or act. This course of<lb/>
proceedings conveyed no lessons of instruction to my land lady, but rather led<lb/>
her to think that I was a meek mortal upon whose neck she could place her foot<lb/>
with impunity. Poor deluded creature! She little dreamed that she was walking<lb/>
through a powder magazine with a lighted match in her hands; but she knows<lb/>
better today, for I opened my mouth at last, and she knows this morning what<lb/>
I think of Homeopathy, Unitarianism, Abbolitionism, Spiritualism, etc., for<lb/>
these are all included in the creed! But I leave her to an ignominious fate!<lb/>
I am pleasantly located. I should state that out of the consideration for the<lb/>
Board of Health, I have had my examinations postponed to the eighth day of<lb/>
February. You will please excuse all miserable scribbling, since I wrote with<lb/>
the paper on my lap. I remain,</p>
<p>Very truly, your friend,<lb/>
Walter Reed</p>
<p>
P. S. The paper on <del>c</del><add>w</add>hich I write is so transparent that in order to protect<lb/>
the contents of my letter from the gaze of the curious, (for there are such)<lb/>
I have thought it best to wrap about it an extra sheet.<lb/>
Sincerely,<lb/>
W. R.<lb/>
</p>
<p>Blacks &amp; Whites,<lb/>
Nottoway County, Va.<lb/>
March 24, 1875</p>
<p>Miss Emilie,</p>
<p>After a short and pleasant trip of about twenty-four<lb/>
hours, I arrived at this destination just one week ago. My sister and her<lb/>
little children were anxiously awaiting my arrival and accorded me a warm<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f04934014"/>
#13<lb/>
reception. I have talked myself almost out of breath narrating my wonderful<lb/>
adventures of the past few years and trying to amuse the children with remark-<lb/>
able tales of New York City life. Have also had the pleasure of grasping the<lb/>
hands of a few old acquaintances. The latter of these were children when I<lb/>
last saw them, but have now bloomed into womanhood and manhood. I never<lb/>
felt age weigh more heavily on my shoulders. The thought causes me to cry<lb/>
aloud with the poet. &ldquo;Oh! for one hour of youthful joy, give back my<lb/>
twentieth spring. I'd rather laugh a fair haired boy, than reign a grey<lb/>
haired king!&rdquo; This much of my letter by way of preface. You know that I<lb/>
will soon enter the medical corps of the United States Army. It is more than<lb/>
probable, nay it amounts to a certainty that I shall spend the next ten or<lb/>
fifteen years of my life in the service. Circumstances over which I have no<lb/>
control and concerning which I possess no knowledge, may, on the one hand<lb/>
cause me to resign my office in a few years, or on the other hand, lead me to<lb/>
remain in the Army all my life; the position being one which I can retain as<lb/>
long as <add>&ldquo;</add>I choose or resign whenever it shall seem fit. Heaven alone knows which<lb/>
&check; of these courses I shall pursue.<add>&rdquo;</add></p>
<p>The course that father did pursue at that time was to go to Mur-<lb/>
freesboro, North Carolina where he and mother became engaged. After visiting<lb/>
his family in Virginia and mother's sister in Norfolk, he entered the Army,<lb/>
June 1875.</p>
<p>From Churchland, Va., June 6, 1875, he writes:</p>
<p>&ldquo;On this beautiful, bright Sabbath morning, I gladly yield to the<lb/>
impulse which bids me write a short letter to you. There is no sermon to be<lb/>
preached in this Church--land, this morning. My brother has gone to his<lb/>
appointment some ten miles away; sister has concluded to beckon to the God<lb/>
of Sleep, and I left all alone, can find no more delightful employment than<lb/>
communing with you, who though across the borders of another state, has been<lb/>
so much present in my mind, all this bright morning. Yes! I have been sit-<lb/>
ting in an old, comfortable rocking chair (one of those honestly constructed<lb/>
chairs that our fathers and mothers loved to sit in when the day's work was<lb/>
done, and with my head thrown back and my hat drawn over my face so as to<lb/>
exclude the sun's brightness, I have been with you in imagination. In fancy,<lb/>
I saw you wending your way to the House of Worship, with an innocent smile on<lb/>
your sweet face. Seated in your accustomed pew, I saw your head bowed in the<lb/>
attitude of silent prayer and when that prayer had ceased, I beheld that calm<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f04934015"/>
#14<lb/>
look of devotion which should ever characterize the christian woman in the<lb/>
presence of her Maker. I looked into your eye, steadily fixed on the speaker,<lb/>
as he told of the trials of the christian in this world, and of the joys that<lb/>
await him in the world to come. I watched you as you left the Sanctuary, nor<lb/>
did my eyes leave you, until you disappeared across the threshold of your home.<lb/>
Perhaps at this very moment you had thought of me. Nor would I repress the<lb/>
prayer which sprung into my heart. Oh! Father! what is weak in me, strengthen,<lb/>
what is impure, purify; prepare me in heart and mind for the battles of life,<lb/>
and in all things make me worthy of my sweetheart's love! I made no effort to<lb/>
check my flowing tears, for as they coursed down my cheek, I felt that my<lb/>
prayer had been accepted in Heaven and that strength would be given me in every<lb/>
time of need, and to convince you beyond the shadow of a doubt, that nothing<lb/>
but Heaven's will (to which I always humbly bow) can long keep us separated!<lb/>
It would be a great source of much happiness to know that at some hour of each<lb/>
day you were thinking of me! A few evenings ago while gazing at the Heavens,<lb/>
my eyes fell upon the planet Jupiter, a beautiful and brilliant star, which<lb/>
every night may be seen in the southern part of the Heavens, accompanied by<lb/>
a smaller star just beneath it. While admiring its brilliancy, I thought to<lb/>
myself what a sweet satisfaction it would be to know that each night at some<lb/>
particular hour, you were watching from your window, this far off world, and<lb/>
thinking of me! I am expecting to go to Baltimore soon after I reach home and<lb/>
spend a few days with Dr. Torney. I shall hope for a letter from you at the<lb/>
Portsmouth Post Office. Believe me,</p>

<p>Devotedly yours,<lb/>
Walter</p>
<p>After visiting mother again in Murfreesboro, North Carolina, he <lb/>
writes from the Cosmopolitan Hotel, New York, July 25, 1876, this little<lb/>
incident:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Well, I must tell you about my trip from your classic little<lb/>
city to this giant metropolis. Nothing occurred to mar the pleasant journey<lb/>
from Murfreesboro to Boykins &check;. It was rather warm and dusty over the roads<lb/>
but the horses took it slowly. Nothing of interest occurred between Boykins<lb/>
and Portsmouth and in a very few minutes after reaching the last named place,<lb/>
I was aboard the steamer and on my way to the Monumental City. There were<lb/>
quite a number on board and among them several young looking couples, who, of<lb/>
course, attracted my attention, and here I must relate to you an incident,<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f04934016"/>
#15<lb/>
which, at the time of its occurrence, was painful to me. It was a few minutes<lb/>
after supper and we were nearing Fortress Monroe, I was on the forward part<lb/>
of the main deck and near me stood a young couple. The wind was blowing<lb/>
briskly and a sudden gust blew the lady's hat from the top of her head out<lb/>
into the waters of the broad Chesapeake! What a loss! What a calamity!<lb/>
As the hat floated away, I heard her husband upbraiding her quite severely for<lb/>
her carelessness in permitting the breeze to carry away her hat, and I heard<lb/>
her, poor creature, making the best excuses she could for the accident. What<lb/>
think you of this, does it not make your very soul sick? The loss of a bonnet<lb/>
sufficient cause for coarse words! I do not wonder that a woman regards<lb/>
matrimony as a perilous leap, since I find my sex such miserable fault finders.<lb/>
When this model couple had left the deck (the poor wife to hear still harsher<lb/>
words, perhaps) I sat and mused for quite a while. I was glad in one sense<lb/>
that I had been the silent witness of such a scene. I wanted it to sink deep<lb/>
into my memory and to make an impression which should forever remain. Not<lb/>
that I ever have any fear that I shall follow in such footsteps! Heaven forbid!<lb/>
But because these things are instructive and useful to any young man who con-<lb/>
<add>sic</add> templates matrimony since &ldquo;to be forewarned is to be forearmed!&rdquo; I saw them<lb/>
again on the following morning, he seemed quite affectionate and she happy,<lb/>
but oh! she had not forgotten those cruel words. I trust she had, but I do<lb/>
not believe it. The remainder of my journey was devoid of any particular<lb/>
interest. I looked at the centenial buildings now under construction, very<lb/>
closely, for you know you and I expect to visit them one of these days. What<lb/>
an occasion that will be. I reached my hotel at 5:30 last evening. I expect<lb/>
to go to Governor's Island this afternoon to find out how I can get to Willetts<lb/>
Point. I find that the U. S. Boat only runs on Wednesdays and Saturdays and<lb/>
hence I must find some other mode of conveyence. Will write you tomorrow.</p>
<p>Your fond and devoted,<lb/>
Walter</p>
<p>Willets Point<lb/>
New York Harbor<lb/>
July 27, 1875</p>

<p>I am once more upon my &ldquo;native heath&rdquo; and have taken<lb/>
the first opportunity of writing to you. Sunday afternoon, I visited Pier 1,<lb/>
East River, intending to embark for Governor's Island, in order to see our<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f04934017"/>
#16<lb/>
friend Dr. Hoff. On reaching the steamboat, however, I found that Dr. Hoff<lb/>
no longer resided on the Island, so that I had to trudge back to my hotel,<lb/>
friendless. In vain, I tried to find some way by which I could reach my Post.<lb/>
I went over in the afternoon to Brooklyn, and called on my old doctor friends<lb/>
at the city hospital. They received me cordially, in fact &ldquo;knew me from afar&rdquo;<lb/>
and ran to me but did not &ldquo;fall on my neck.&rdquo; Notwithstanding their friend-<lb/>
ship, they could not tell how I could reach Willets Point. After spending a<lb/>
few pleasant hours with them, swaying to and fro, under a green elm, in a hammock,<lb/>
I returned to my hotel. Early yesterday morning, I repaired to Army Head-<lb/>
quarters <add>sic</add> there learned that I could take the North Shore Railroad of Long<lb/>
Island, come to a town called Whitestone only two miles from the Post. I<lb/>
there heard that my good friend Dr. Torney had been stationed at Fort Wood,<lb/>
N. Y. Harbor, and was stopping at the Stephens Hotel. I hailed the first<lb/>
stage, reached the hotel to find he had just paid his bill and gone to his<lb/>
Post. After dinner I went out and had my baggage checked and took a hack to<lb/>
James' ship and then by boat to Hunter's Point, Long Island City and from<lb/>
there to Whitestone by rail. At the latter place I met the Senior Surgeon of<lb/>
the post, and rode out with him. He is very pleasant and I am especially glad<lb/>
of it, as I am quartered in the house with him. I met two Captains, two<lb/>
Second Lieutenants. They with the surgeon and myself form what is known as<lb/>
the &ldquo;bachelor-mess.&rdquo; We had a good dinner. After dinner, I went to the<lb/>
Commanding Officer's to report for duty. I put on my uniform to make a good<lb/>
appearance. I was soon in the presence of General Abbott. I found him to<lb/>
be one of the most pleasant gentlemen I ever met with. Leaving the General's<lb/>
house, Dr. Byrne took me to the hospital, being saluted on the way by about<lb/>
forty soldiers. You should have seen me returning the salute. I did it in<lb/>
grand style. After seeing a few patients, I returned to my quarters, and was<lb/>
soon asleep. This morning, I have been busy writing letters to the Surgeon<lb/>
General. I am more than pleased with my post. We have a most excellent band<lb/>
of music that plays three times a day. As soon as I heard it last night I<lb/>
thought of you. Address, Dr. W. Reed, U. S. A., Willet's Point, New York<lb/>
Harbor.</p>
<p>Devotedly yours,<lb/>
Walter</p>
<p>In a letter written August 20, 1875, father writes of going to<lb/>
Murfreesboro to visit mother: &ldquo;What if anything should occur to interrupt<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f04934018"/>
#17<lb/>
my going? Such for instance as being ordered to the West before that time<lb/>
arrives. Away with such a thought! I'll harbor none such. &ldquo;Uncle Sam&rdquo;<lb/>
couldn't be so hard hearted as to order a poor fellow away without giving him<lb/>
a chance to see his sweetheart. He is too good natured an old man to do such<lb/>
an act. At least we'll hope so.&rdquo; He speaks of studying French and German:<lb/>
&ldquo;With these and general literature, I can manage to spend my time quite pro-<lb/>
fitably. I want to study ten hours a day besides taking plenty of exercise.<lb/>
I am so much behind the times and make so poor an appearance compared with the<lb/>
majority of young gentlemen one meets in society! But I feel I should not<lb/>
spare one moment from my books.&rdquo; He alludes again so beautifully to his<lb/>
mother and says: &ldquo;Would it surprise you to be told I have been wearing crape<lb/>
for several days past? An order was issued on the occasion of the death of<lb/>
Ex-president Andrew Jackson, that all officers of the army should wear crape<lb/>
for a period of thirty days, as a mark of respect, which will account for my<lb/>
wearing it. It recalls vividly to mind the last and only time that I ever wore<lb/>
crape. Heaven grant that the time may be far distant when I shall again put<lb/>
it on. It was when my poor suffering mother died. Well might I wear an emblem<lb/>
of grief for such a mother! Sweet, gentle soul! Hadst thy summers not come <add>sic</add><lb/>
so soon, perhaps thy son would have been, today, a better boy! Dear sainted<lb/>
spirit! May thou ever hover near me so shall I be kept from all temptation!<lb/>
You were too young to remember her. Had you had known her &lsquo;twould have been<lb/>
to love her. Though you do not remember her, yet will you not mingle one tear<lb/>
with mine over her silent tomb? Oh! yes, I know you will. Thus remembered,<lb/>
dear mother sleep! And when at last thou shall stand before thy Maker's<lb/>
throne, oh! may I too be there, my hand in thine.&rdquo; <add><unclear>Missing</unclear></add></p>
<p>Willet's Point,<lb/>
September 15, 1875</p>
<p>Would you, could you believe that I would allow my<lb/>
twenty-fifth birthday to pass without so much as thinking of it during the<lb/>
whole day. The very day on which I wrote you last I was twenty-four years<lb/>
old (just think of it), and yet I was totally ignorant of it. Of course I<lb/>
felt the weight of years more than usual on that day, but I could not account<lb/>
for it. Suddenly on Tuesday the 14, it occurred to me that I was one year<lb/>
older and immediately the cause of my fatigue flashed across my mind. It<lb/>
is too late for me to grow eloquent over the subject (for I had intended to<lb/>
say something suitable to such an occasion), since the champagne has lost its<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f04934019"/>
#18<lb/>
effervescence, but still I cannot permit my birthday to pass without some<lb/>
remarks.</p>
<p>Alas, my twenty-fifth birthday has passed and what have I to show<lb/>
for it! What good deeds have I done that merit approbation! How negligent<lb/>
and wayward I have been! What golden moments of opportunity have come and<lb/>
gone, all unheeded! As I look back over my past life to-night, but few thoughts<lb/>
occur to me such as cause my bosom to swell with honest pride. Ah, how many<lb/>
heart pangs have I not suffered during these few years of my life? Are there<lb/>
as many more in store for me in the future? No! I'll not believe it. I<lb/>
know there will be griefs and disappointments, but will you not share them<lb/>
with me? .... Do not think that I fail to appreciate the many sacrifices that<lb/>
you make in confiding your future to my care. The remembrance of them is<lb/>
daily present with me and serves to increase my diligence.</p>
<p>Two months elapse and during that period his letters were too<lb/>
personal to publish. On December 13, 1875, he writes about mother's little<lb/>
nephew of eight who was ill.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I hasten to offer you my sincerest sympathy in this your time of<lb/>
distress, and I pray that the Good Being will watch over you and yours, and<lb/>
soon restore you to perfect health. How I long to be with you, if perchance<lb/>
I might be able to supply your slightest want, so that I could speak some<lb/>
cheering word to you. Oh! my darling, I am so uneasy about you. I am so<lb/>
afraid that ere you are strong enough you will exert yourself in assisting to<lb/>
nurse the poor suffering boy. Would that I were present to take some of the<lb/>
burden off your hands! Please extend to your sister, my most sincere and<lb/>
heartfelt sympathy for her in this affliction and tell her that I earnestly<lb/>
hope that her little boy is already out of danger. I will not forget to send<lb/>
up a prayer to Heaven for his recovery and restoration to her love. If you<lb/>
are nursing him, my darling, be sure to spend a part of your time in the open<lb/>
air, for as the disease (typhoid fever) is slightly contagious, you might<lb/>
contract it if you remained too constantly at his bed-side. Take every pre-<lb/>
caution with your health, and should you be prostrated with the same illness<lb/>
do not lose a moment in notifying me of the same and I will be at your side<lb/>
as soon as time will permit me.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Willet's Point<lb/>
December 20, 1875</p>
<p>Your letter of the 16th instant is just to hand. I<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f04934020"/>
#19<lb/>
had hoped and prayed that when your next letter came, it would bring me the<lb/>
glad news that your little nephew had been spared and restored to the love of<lb/>
his parents and friends. Alas! while I prayed that his life might be pro-<lb/>
longed to many years of usefulness, he had already departed for a better and<lb/>
brighter home. Ah! well may we exclaim, &ldquo;the bitter realities of life!&rdquo;<lb/>
A little tender bud cut off ere it bloomed! A little child removed from earth,<lb/>
but thank God, a little cherub added to Heaven! I am rejoiced to see, my darling<lb/>
that you accept his death in the spirit of a Christian. &lsquo;Tis hard to give him<lb/>
up. Oh! who can fathom the mother's grief for the loss of a darling boy!<lb/>
But after all, my sweet Emilie, we should not forget that, by his early de-<lb/>
parture from life, he has escaped so many trials, so many disappointments, so<lb/>
&check; many <del>y</del><add>h</add>ours of pain of body and mind. Ah! happy and blessed little angel to<lb/>
have reached home, ere the storm arose, and while yet the birds were car-<lb/>
olling sweetly! Little pilgrim of a few days, what sad, sad hours have you<lb/>
escaped! God removed you ere you had experienced the cruel buffetings of<lb/>
this world, and while yet thy heart knew not evil! And for this, ought we<lb/>
not rather to bless his Holy name, than yield to unavailing grief. Ah!<lb/>
my sweet E. when I see the little lambs hastening home, I would not call them<lb/>
back, for though I have scarcely begun life, yet I have known what<del>,</del> sorrow is,<lb/>
and felt the weight of care! Do not think, my sweet, that I shrink from<lb/>
meeting life's realities. No, No! that would display a want of courage and<lb/>
a want of faith. Nor that I would not wish to live many years yet! It<lb/>
may be that God, in his all-wise Providence, has some wise purpose for me,<lb/>
humble that I am to fulfill, and shall I shrink from it? We are but clay in<lb/>
the potter's hands, my precious, and our duty is to so conduct ourselves that<lb/>
we may become bright and shining lamps in this world and the next. In con-<lb/>
clusion, my own love, let me offer you the heart felt sympathy of your dearest<lb/>
and best friend; and to your sister, in her bereavement, what can I say?<lb/>
Naught, but that God will grant her the christian fortitude to bear the loss<lb/>
of her darling boy, and that, in His infinite wisdom, He will, at last, restore<lb/>
him to her embrace! God bless you my love. Ever your fond and devoted</p>
<p>Walter</p>
<p>Willet's Point<lb/>
N. Y. H., Dec. 22, 1875</p>
<p>My sweet, little E.,</p>
<p>After experiencing extremely cold weather for a period<lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f04934021"/>
#20<lb/>
of a week or more, we were, yesterday, blessed with a most charming day -<lb/>
a fair sky and air just cold enough to be invigorating. I could not resist<lb/>
the temptation of visiting New York and spending an hour or two in sight-<lb/>
seeing. You must know that Holiday week is the busiest and gayest of all the<lb/>
year in New York. The various store windows have put on their liveliest and<lb/>
brightest appearance and the streets are over-flowing with men, women and<lb/>
children, hurrying to and fro, and busy in making their Holiday purchases.<lb/>
I do not think that I ever saw Broadway so crowded, as on yesterday. It<lb/>
seemed as if the whole town had suddenly turned out. Enter whatever store you<lb/>
would and your progress was at once arrested. You could not move  <add>sic</add>, the ladies<lb/>
and children were on your right and your left, and your whole journey was a<lb/>
struggle. There were a hundred beautiful presents that I should have much liked<lb/>
to have purchased for you, my darling, but I knew that you would not accept<lb/>
them, but knowing that you would accept some little volume, I turned my steps<lb/>
toward Appleton's and there purchased an unassuming volume, which I beg that<lb/>
you will accept, my darling, as a holiday gift, and a token of my sincerest<lb/>
esteem and love. Were I able to make it a hundred fold more valuable, I<lb/>
would gladly do so, and yet I know that it would be just as acceptable were<lb/>
it even less humble. May you, my darling, spend some happy moments over its<lb/>
pure pages, and as oft as you shall turn its leaves, think of him who gave it.</p>
<p>In writing my last letter, I forgot to say anything concerning<lb/>
my solicitude in regard to your health. I am really afraid that you have<lb/>
been more indisposed than your letters would seem to intimate. Please tell<lb/>
me all. Do not keep me ignorant of the fact, if you are very sick. I re-<lb/>
ceived a letter from my sister a few days ago. She has concluded to wait<lb/>
till next October before sending her little girls to Murfreesboro, and I<lb/>
think she has done wisely. There are many questions that I would like to<lb/>
ask concerning Murfreesboro, but I will defer them till another time. I<lb/>
trust, my precious E., that you may spend as pleasant a Christmas, as is<lb/>
possible, under the circumstances, and that it may be many, many years before<lb/>
you shall spend another so clouded with grief. As ever, my love, your fond<lb/>
and devoted.</p>
<p>Walter</p>
<pb n="22" id="f04934022"/>
<p>
#21</p>
<p>&check; sic<lb/>
Willet's Point, N. Y. C.<lb/>
February 7, 1876</p>
<p>My sweet little E.,</p>
<p>With truth, I might exclaim &ldquo;snow, snow, nothing but<lb/>
snow!&rdquo; For we have had plent of it. Friday morning, I awoke to find the earth<lb/>
mantled in white, pure white, such as dazzles and blinds the eye. &lsquo;Twas the<lb/>
first heavy snow that we have had this winter, and hence we were proud of it.<lb/>
Of course, the only topic of our conversation was <hi rend="underline">sleighing</hi> to which we looked<lb/>
forward with much pleasant anticipation; and I am happy to say that we were<lb/>
not disappointed. The day was all that one could wish -- bright and beautiful,<lb/>
though very cold. I did not go sleighing during the day, but at 7:30 P. M. Lieu-<lb/>
tenant Young called by for me in his &ldquo;nobby&rdquo; little cutter, to which was<lb/>
hitched an animal that can make a mile in less than three minutes. Seating<lb/>
myself by his side and drawing the heavy robes closely about us, we were<lb/>
soon speeding with the wind. Oh! it was charming! The jingling music of the<lb/>
sleigh bells; the crisp, cold air; the flying snow; the silver moon over head,<lb/>
all combined to make a most beautiful winter scene and one that I shall long<lb/>
remember. But without my darling Emilie <add>sic</add>, it lacked the <hi rend="underline">charm</hi> of <hi rend="underline">your</hi> presence!<lb/>
Without which no scene of my life can be complete. I am not done telling<lb/>
you of the grand time we had sleighing. Saturday morning, Lieutenant Lymons<lb/>
and I procured a team and sleigh, (the latter large enough to seat nine) for<lb/>
the purpose of giving the ladies of the post the benefit of a trip over the<lb/>
snow. We left the post with six ladies and one gentleman, besides ourselves,<lb/>
and a merrier party never were brought together. There were Mrs. King, Mrs.<lb/>
Heger, Mrs. Tabor, Mrs. Abbott, Mrs. Oxholm, and Miss Abbott. Of course, it<lb/>
was impossible for such a jolly crowd to return without some accident. We<lb/>
had gone about six miles and were having &ldquo;no thought for the morrow,&rdquo; when<lb/>
suddenly one of the runners of our sleigh broke, and down we came, all in a<lb/>
bunch! We did not care for this, and instead of interrupting the jollity of<lb/>
our ride, it only served to increase it. We were in the town of Flushing when<lb/>
the accident occurred, so we were enabled to quickly procure other sleighs.<lb/>
Two others were soon found and dividing our party, Mrs. King, Mrs. Tabor, and<lb/>
myself in one sleigh, and the remainder in another, we were soon on our way<lb/>
home, as merry as ever, where we arrived safely. This, my darling, is an in-<lb/>
cident of Army life. I am happy to hear that you have such an addition to the<lb/>
intelligence of M'boro. Since his name is not Reed, I expect that you will<lb/>
greatly admire him. Excuse brevity. As ever, my darling, your fond and<lb/>
<pb n="23" id="f04934023"/>
#22<lb/>
devoted</p>
<p>Walter</p>
<p><add>Should this be<lb/>
&check; April 6, 1876<lb/>
&amp; follow that<lb/>
on p 24?</add></p>
<p>Willet's Point, N. Y. H.<lb/>
<add>April 6</add>March 6, 1876</p>
<p>In concluding my last letter, I was forced to do so<lb/>
somewhat abruptly, as the sound of the drum told me that the steamer, with its<lb/>
distinguished guests, was approaching. Buckling on my sword, with all celer-<lb/>
ity, I rushed down to the wharf, in company with General Abbott and his other<lb/>
staff officers. A moment after the Battallion, coming at a double quick, had<lb/>
<add>sic</add> reached the wharf and was drawn up in double file. By this time, the steamer<lb/>
handsomely decorated with flags, had approached the dock and soon she was<lb/>
made fast. So the Secretary of War and General Sherman stepped off the boat,<lb/>
the cannon which had been charged broke forth in one tremendous volley, and<lb/>
immediately the band began to pour forth &ldquo;Hail to the Chief.&rdquo; Being one of<lb/>
the Staff Officers, I was at once introduced to the Secretary and General<lb/>
Sherman and had the pleasure of grasping their hands. Besides these, there<lb/>
were many distinguished military officers in company with the Secretary,<lb/>
Major General Hancock, among the rest. We soon marched past the Battalion,<lb/>
which had come to &ldquo;present arms,&rdquo; and in the midst of descending floods, we<lb/>
marched to the Torpedo Building. General Sherman excused the Batallion from<lb/>
the Review, which was to have taken place, on account of the pouring rain<lb/>
which came down in torrents. As it was, we all got thoroughly wet, for we<lb/>
had to escort the party around through the Fort. After this, the Secretary<lb/>
witnessed the explosion of a torpedo out in the sound and then, embarking on<lb/>
board the steamer, took course for New York. I was very much pleased with<lb/>
General Sherman, chiefly because he seemed so modest and unassuming, for one<lb/>
occupying so high a position. General Hancock complimented me by telling me<lb/>
that I looked like a soldier, but added that I was a very young looking doctor!</p>
<p>Dr. Hege received a letter from the Surgeon General on Monday,<lb/>
stating that I would soon be relieved from duty, at this post, and I am, daily,<lb/>
expecting my orders to arrive. Don't stop your letters, as I will not leave<lb/>
for a week after my orders arrive. Ever, your fond and devoted</p>
<p>Walter</p>
<pb n="24" id="f04934024"/>
<p>#23</p>
<p>Willet's Point, N. Y. H.<lb/>
March 28, 1876</p>
<p>I never like to write a letter, my little angel,<lb/>
when I feel a little out of sorts; because I am apt to produce naught that<lb/>
will entertain and much that will appear dull and insipid, besides a tendency<lb/>
to reflect a shadow of gloom over all. Perhaps, you would inquire as to the<lb/>
cause of my ill-humor. Well it's all owing to the fact that I am a so-called<lb/>
&ldquo;doctor,&rdquo; and have under treatment a few obstreperous patients. You have said,<lb/>
my darling that a doctor's life is a horrid one, and you might add, in many<lb/>
respects, the most horrid life that can be possibly led. I know I permit my<lb/>
sensibility to become too acute, but really if I had my life to live over again,<lb/>
I'd never be a doctor. Not that I would have suited any other profession,<lb/>
for I am honest enough to confess that I have met with more success in my<lb/>
profession than I should ever have claimed in any other pursuit of life; but<lb/>
I would have escaped a few annoyances and displays of ingratitude. I was<lb/>
bound to say this much and now that I have delivered my opinion, I feel very<lb/>
much better and will proceed with my letter to my own sweet Emilie just as a<lb/>
clear headed man should do. You perceive that it takes but a very little time<lb/>
for the shower to pass over and leave the sky bright-kind <add>sic</add> of April weather;<lb/>
perhaps owing to the fact that the said month of sunshine and shadows (I<lb/>
meant to say showers) is almost here. Just to think that just one month ago,<lb/>
today, to the very hour and minute and second, I was in Murfreesboro, waiting<lb/>
for the arrival of three o'clock, when I should see my darling sweetheart!<lb/>
Doesn't the time pass almost like a dream? One month nearer, my darling Emilie!<lb/>
Oh! it makes my heart beat happily and quickly! And soon it will be two months<lb/>
and then three, but I can go no father, or I shall be unable to contain my<lb/>
joy! The main topic of conversation and interest, at the Post, just at present,<lb/>
is the near approach of a dramatic performance to be given by the officers<lb/>
and ladies of the Post. Our theatre is nearly completed and we expect to<lb/>
open it with a funny little comedy, called &ldquo;Helping Hands,&rdquo; written by some<lb/>
Englishman. The play is really a very good one, as several of the characters<lb/>
admit of a chance for excellent acting. Would you believe it, that I have been<lb/>
selected to take one of the most humorous parts. Never attempted anything of<lb/>
the kind in my life! I say &ldquo;selected,&rdquo; because I still have the matter under<lb/>
consideration. To think of my appearance on a stage, before an audience of<lb/>
two hundred or more, and in a funny character! Can you imagine anything more<lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f04934025"/>
#24<lb/>
ridiculous? Yet they all say that I am the very man for the part! What has<lb/>
your little boy done that he should have led people so astray? Adieu! my<lb/>
sweet love. Every your fond and devoted,</p>
<p>Walter</p>
<p><add>Should this be<lb/>
Mar 3, 1876<lb/>
&amp; precede the<lb/>
letter on p 22</add></p>
<p>Willet's Point, N. Y. H.<lb/>
April 3, 1876</p>
<p>The day is as uninviting as it could well be -- rain<lb/>
and hail fall fast and thick, and notwithstanding this, while I write, the<lb/>
whole Batallion holds itself in readiness to march at a moment's notice.<lb/>
Every minute, we expect to hear the drums beat off, and then there will be<lb/>
&ldquo;hurrying to and fro.&rdquo; Line <add>sic</add> will be formed in an instant, the music will<lb/>
strike up and we will be ready to receive the new Secretary of War and General<lb/>
W. T. Sherman, the Commander-in-Chief of the U. S. Army. I almost wish that<lb/>
we may be disappointed, for, although I would like to grasp the hands of so<lb/>
distinguished visitors, I have no particular desire to be exposed to a cold<lb/>
drenching rain such as is now descending. We are bound to get soaking wet,<lb/>
as there will be a grand Review, requiring at least three quarters of an hour<lb/>
for its performance. Oh! wouldn't you like to be a soldier, my little darling?<lb/>
No umbrellas! Nothing but overcoat and cap to protect one from the storm. If<lb/>
not a soldier, my love, you wouldn't object to being a soldier's wife, would<lb/>
you, precious? No! No! and that you will be! And oh! the sweetest, dearest<lb/>
little wife that ever lit up home with the sunshine of her beautiful, bright<lb/>
face! Oh! how I love to dwell on this vision! She, who is now my own, darling<lb/>
Emilie, will e're long, be transformed into my own, sweet little wife! And<lb/>
still she'll be the same dear little Emilie that she has ever been to my<lb/>
heart! Ah! I'll plod and work -- will meet every obstacle willingly and<lb/>
fearlessly -- will be content to wait, knowing the reward that awaits me in<lb/>
the near future; the love and trust of a pure, noble woman -- man's best and<lb/>
greatest comforter on earth! Pardon my brevity, darling, but as the drums<lb/>
are beating I must buckle on my sword and hurry to the parade-grounds.<lb/>
Fondly and devotedly your,</p>
<p>Walter</p>
<pb n="26" id="f04934026"/>
<p>#25</p>
<p>Willet's Point, N. Y. H.<lb/>
April 13, 1876</p>
<p>Well, the orders, which I have been so anxiously<lb/>
awaiting, have arrived. I am ordered to accompany a detachment of soldiers<lb/>
to San Francisco and then to report to the General commanding the Department<lb/>
of Arizona for assignment to duty. I will be placed on waiting orders for a<lb/>
period of four weeks, more or less, as the Detachment will not start till that<lb/>
time. I shall remain at home during the time. Will leave New York for Nor-<lb/>
folk, next Monday, and probably get to Murfreesboro on Wednesday or Thursday.<lb/>
Be prepared for a very startling request when I do arrive, for if I go to<lb/>
Arizona, I cannot return for three or four years, and to be separated from<lb/>
you, my sweet, for that length of time cannot be entertained. I write in<lb/>
great haste. Ever, your fond and devoted,</p>
<p>Walter</p>
<p>These orders culminated in an early and hurried wedding and on<lb/>
April 25, 1876 mother and father were married. He went alone to his station<lb/>
in Arizona in May 1876 to see what arrangements could be made in this then un-<lb/>
civilized country before my mother joined him. Mother did not join him until<lb/>
the following October. Father met her in San Francisco, and they started<lb/>
for their first station together to Fort Lowell, Arizona. This trip taken<lb/>
in an Army wagon took them twenty-two days. An interesting letter sent to<lb/>
my aunt, Mrs. J. N. Harrell, gives some idea of their difficult journey:</p>
<p>Dear Sister Ellen,</p>
<p>We left San Diego, November 15, 1876 at 2 P. M.<lb/>
My wagon, loaded with our baggage, had left at 1 P. M. I had been told, on<lb/>
careful inquiry, that the distance to the first station was 16 to 20 miles,<lb/>
which being the case, my wagon should have made it by 6 P. M. and my ambulance<lb/>
by 6 P. M. But &ldquo;the best laid schemes of mice,&rdquo; etc., etc. I soon found<lb/>
that the road was horribly rough and by 5 P. M. I had not made more than 10<lb/>
miles for I had to walk my team every step. By this time the sun was set<lb/>
and as there was no moon, it soon became so very dark that we could barely<lb/>
keep on the road. I had already overtaken and passed my wagon. By seven<lb/>
o'clock P. M. it had turned quite cold. I had Emilie put on her waterproof;<lb/>
I also had two overcoats, one of which I wrapped her feet snugly in and the<lb/>
other I had her put on, so that she was thoroughly prepared for the cold.<lb/>
I then told the driver to go very carefully, and to watch for any lights, so<lb/>
<pb n="27" id="f04934027"/>
#26<lb/>
that we would be certain not to pass the station in the dark, for I thought<lb/>
it must be near by. On we went, keeping a good watch on each side, till my<lb/>
watch marked 9 P. M., and still no station. Emilie began to ask &ldquo;How much<lb/>
further have we got to go?&rdquo; quite frequently, and I could only answer, &ldquo;It<lb/>
can't be far.&rdquo; A few minutes later and we espied a light ahead and to the<lb/>
right of our road. I now told Emilie to pluck up her courage as we should<lb/>
soon reach the station. However, when we had gone about half a mile, we found<lb/>
that the road left the light to our right, and hence I was much perplexed<lb/>
to know whether it was the station or not. I told the driver to go over and<lb/>
ascertain. He returned in about 20 minutes and stated that it was not the<lb/>
station! He said that the owner was very anxious that we should stay over<lb/>
night with him, although his accommodations were not the best in the world.<lb/>
He had neither hay nor grain for my animals; in fact, he could not furnish us<lb/>
even a bed to sleep in, inasmuch as he and his old lady had had a &ldquo;family<lb/>
jar&rdquo; on that very day, which had ended in the old lady walking off with the<lb/>
bed and bedding and leaving him the house. I could but feel extremely grate-<lb/>
ful to this gentleman for his kind proffer <add>sic</add>, but nevertheless concluded to<lb/>
decline his hospitality till some future day.</p>
<p>Our search thus fruitlessly terminated, we again began our weary<lb/>
march, Emilie, in the meantime, letting fall several very small tears. Bless<lb/>
her darling heart! I must give her credit for great bravery on this, her first<lb/>
night in an ambulance. I'm afraid, if there had been a stone wall near by<lb/>
I should have brought my head in violent contact with it. But there was<lb/>
nothing to be done but to go on. On, on, we plodded, so slow, so slow, for<lb/>
it was very dark and the road horribly rough. Several times it seemed as if<lb/>
the vehicle would certainly upset; several times the driver had to descend<lb/>
from his seat in order to find the road. Ten o'clock came, but no station or<lb/>
any sign of one! I had just examined my watch and found it 11 o'clock, when<lb/>
on making a short curve in the road, we saw a smouldering fire but a short<lb/>
distance ahead. On reaching it, we found that it was a small camp of two<lb/>
wagons. I got out and awoke one of the sleepers (there were two of them),<lb/>
who sat up in his bed, but was not very communicative. He told me that the<lb/>
station was about two miles further, but added, &ldquo;over the worst road in<lb/>
California.&rdquo; I thanked him for this cheering intelligence, and was about to<lb/>
go on, when he told me that the last mile was through a very bad canon, and<lb/>
then lying down and pulling the bed-clothing closely around him, he remarked<lb/>
<pb n="28" id="f04934028"/>
#27<lb/>
to his companion, &ldquo;He'll have a devil of a time getting through that canon to-<lb/>
night!&rdquo; which put me into such a good frame of mind that I gave the order at once,<lb/>
&ldquo;go ahead.&rdquo;</p>
<p>One mile and we had reached the mouth of this canon, and as we pro-<lb/>
ceeded, step by step, the hills arose on either side high and dark. If before it<lb/>
had been dark, it was now the very blackness of darkness. The trees overhead cut<lb/>
off every ray of light. The mules seemed disinclined to venture on, even under<lb/>
the lash, and it began to look as if further progress was impossible. I got out<lb/>
to take a look, but all I could find out was that we were in the midst of rocks<lb/>
and deep sand and no sign of a road! What was to be done? Fortunately the driver<lb/>
had a lantern and a part of a candle. This we lit, and taking with me a soldier<lb/>
who was riding with the driver, I started ahead to show the way. By keeping just<lb/>
in front of the team and holloaing <add>sic</add> &ldquo;Now to the right,&rdquo; &ldquo;Now to the left,&rdquo; and<lb/>
&ldquo;Now straight ahead,&rdquo; we managed to make some progress. Poor E. all this time<lb/>
was in the ambulance alone, and calling out continually, &ldquo;Where are you, Dr.<lb/>
Reed? Please come back and let the soldier carry the lantern,&rdquo; but I told her I<lb/>
could trust no man living to point the way out of this horrible canon; and on I<lb/>
went in sand nearly up to my knees, calling to the driver all the way what course<lb/>
he should take. Notwithstanding the very great advantage the lantern afforded<lb/>
and that I had an excellent driver, every fifty yards would find a wheel stopped<lb/>
by some great boulder. Oh! the terrible difficulties of that night! But every-<lb/>
thing must have an ending, and after we had been working like beavers for an hour,<lb/>
success at last crowned our efforts. We had passed the canon and reached the<lb/>
station (12:30 A. M.)! Ah! I should like to tell you what a sigh of relief es-<lb/>
caped my breast and how happy I felt when I saw the little house by the wayside ...<lb/>
I soon aroused the station-keeper, who was a very rough looking specimen of a<lb/>
frontierman, but under all this roughness he concealed a kind heart, as you will<lb/>
see.</p>
<p>But let me describe the station, called &ldquo;Jamul&rdquo; (pronounced &ldquo;Harmool&rdquo;).<lb/>
It consisted of a small house about 10 feet square, and a horse stable. The<lb/>
keeper's residence (the same house above mentioned) was constructed of plain<lb/>
boards, with spaces of half an inch between the boards, possibly for ventilation,<lb/>
as the window was very small. A dirt roof and dirt floor. A piece of canvas<lb/>
stretched on a frame, which he called his &ldquo;bed,&rdquo; a small stool, a broken chair,<lb/>
a pine table and a cooking stove completed the furniture. Now to show you the<lb/>
kind heart that this rough fellow had, he no sooner found that I had my wife with<lb/>
<pb n="29" id="f04934029"/>
#28<lb/>
me than he not only made a roaring fire, prepared us both a nice cup of hot tea<lb/>
(which with the lunch that we had, enabled us to make a good meal), but he also<lb/>
abandoned his &ldquo;bed&rdquo; for us, himself sleeping for the rest of the night in the<lb/>
stable! And for this kindness he not only did not charge a penny, but he would not<lb/>
take a cent although I insisted upon paying him! As soon as Emilie got within<lb/>
doors and saw the bright fire, her spirits rose accordingly, and when the tea was<lb/>
ready and we each had our cup, her humour was of the best. All her sprightliness<lb/>
returned and as she took a glance around the room and saw the various articles, she<lb/>
laughed heartily, and declared that she wouldn't take anything for this experience.<lb/>
We talked of homefolks and wished that they could see us just as we were. The<lb/>
&ldquo;bed&rdquo; was especially an object of much merriment to Emilie. She declared that she<lb/>
could never rest on such a contrivance; but when I had arranged things a little,<lb/>
had spread over the piece of canvas a blanket which I found in the room and had<lb/>
drawn my overcoat over us, we both soon fell asleep and did not wake till broad<lb/>
daylight. Thus passed Emilie's first day and night on her trip to Camp Lowell!<lb/>
Our love to you all. Your affectionate brother,</p>
<p>Walter</p>
<p>In August 1877, father was ordered to Fort Apache, Arizona. This <lb/>
Station was 700 miles from the railroad. He writes again to my aunt in North<lb/>
Carolina:</p>
<p>
Camp Apache, Arizona<lb/>
October 25, 1877</p>
<p>Dear Sister Ellen,</p>
<p>In this territory, as, in fact, in all others, officers<lb/>
of the army, especially those who are married, travel by ambulance whenever they<lb/>
can get one. Now I know the word ambulance will at once recall to your mind a<lb/>
long, black, funereal-looking vehicle, such as you probably saw during the war.<lb/>
These army ambulances, however, are constructed on the same pattern as the ordin-<lb/>
ary stage, only a little smaller, have two seats capable of seating four, and are<lb/>
drawn by four to six mules. They are painted white so as to absorb the terrible<lb/>
heat of the climate as little as possible. Such a vehicle you would have seen<lb/>
standing in front of our quarters at Camp Lowell at nine o'clock on the morning<lb/>
of August 11th, last. The wagon containing our baggage, to the extent of 1700<lb/>
lbs., had started for Apache on the morning of the 10th, so that we had but few<lb/>
things to put in the ambulance. I will enumerate its contents as it stood ready<lb/>
for the word to be given, &ldquo;go ahead.&rdquo; Inside of the vehicle there were the follow-<lb/>
<pb n="30" id="f04934030"/>
#29<lb/>
ing articles: On the back seat, Emilie, the dog, Undina, and myself; under the<lb/>
back seat, a box of medicines for emergencies, a lunch basket, a jar of preserved<lb/>
ginger, a pair of boots, a blacking brush, a bag containing a saucepan, frying pan,<lb/>
tin pan, and coffee pot. On the front seat, two folding chairs, my valise,<lb/>
Emilie's companion, a basket containing her work, a bundle of shawls, my overcoat,<lb/>
two double blankets, a feather pillow, a clothes brush, and four books of light<lb/>
literature; under the front seat, a mess-chest containing the necessary tableware<lb/>
for the journey, a box of provisions, and a large clothes basket containing every-<lb/>
thing from a hairpin to a pair of shoes. Suspended from various points of the<lb/>
roof were two hats, a sword, an umbrella, a pair of E.'s shoes, a carbine, a<lb/>
pistol, a belt full of cartridges, and two canteens filled with water. Now for the<lb/>
outside; underneath the driver's seat in front were my private case of instruments<lb/>
weighting 50 lbs., a sack of grain, and the driver's rations for ten days; on the<lb/>
seat behind, my trunk, and bedding consisting of a mattress, blankets, sheets,<lb/>
etc., done up in a canvas cover. There may have escaped my memory a few articles,<lb/>
but I believe I have mentioned all. If there was anything on top I did not see<lb/>
it. I have a lurking idea, however, that the driver concealed several chairs and<lb/>
boxes in odd places about the vehicle. I forgot to say that beside the driver<lb/>
there was a corporal on the seat with him, a very light man, weighing just two &check; <add>sic</add><lb/>
hundred lbs.</p>
<p>Thus equipped, after bidding good-bye to our Lowell friends, we started<lb/>
for Camp Apache, external temperature, 110 degrees. As Undina had never before<lb/>
ridden in a vehicle, she straightway set up a terrific barking, which she kept up<lb/>
till she was so hoarse that she couldn't hear herself, and then stopped. Our<lb/>
destination for the first day was &ldquo;Tres Alimos&rdquo; or &ldquo;The Three Cottonwoods,&rdquo; a<lb/>
small settlement 40 miles from Lowell. Aside from the heat, the day was not an<lb/>
unpleasant one for traveling. We passed our time in chatting and laughing at<lb/>
Undina's queer freaks (who, by the way, wasn't quiet in any one place for a minute<lb/>
at a time) till it was time for taking lunch. Perhaps you have never taken what<lb/>
is called a &ldquo;flying lunch.&rdquo; If not, let me tell you, you have missed a great<lb/>
deal of fun. Mind you, everything connected with the meal is done while the am-<lb/>
bulance is in full progress -- no stopping &ldquo;five minutes for refreshments,&rdquo; and<lb/>
as the road is most often very rough and rocky, and always so when you think it<lb/>
is about time to eat, and as the driver concludes to whip his horses up to their<lb/>
very best speed just at this time, whereas he had been persistently permitting<lb/>
them to walk for the past hour, why, the feat of getting anything into your mouth<lb/>
becomes a matter of considerable uncertainly . . . . It is needless for me to<lb/>
<pb n="31" id="f04934031"/>
#30<lb/>
narrate at length all the trials of this meal; I could not, however, forbear showing<lb/>
you what you have missed by never partaking of a &ldquo;flying lunch.&rdquo;</p>
<p>At sunset we reached our destination, &ldquo;Tres Alimos.&rdquo; When I had got<lb/>
Emilie into a very comfortable and well-furnished room, I proceeded to unpack all<lb/>
those articles enumerated in the beginning of my letter, and when you take into<lb/>
consideration the fact that I had to unpack all of them every night and put them<lb/>
back every morning, you will know that it was quite a task. I would have had one<lb/>
of the men do the packing for me, but it would have taken so long to teach him,<lb/>
for every article had to go in a certain place and nowhere else, that I thought<lb/>
it would be easier to do it myself. At 7 o'clock we had a very nice supper, con-<lb/>
sisting of fried spring chicken, good milk, butter, etc., and after I had seen<lb/>
about a lunch for the morrow, we retired, for we were to start the next morning at<lb/>
4 o'clock, so as to reach the next station, 30 miles distant, before noon and thus<lb/>
avoid the heat of the afternoon. . . .</p>
<p>At the aforesaid hour we were up and preparing for our journey. A cup<lb/>
of tea and everything stowed away safely in the ambulance, not forgetting the little<lb/>
dog, and we were ready for our day's trip. This day we had to pass what are called<lb/>
the &ldquo;Lime Kilns,&rdquo; a place where Indians (I mean hostile ones) have been often<lb/>
seen, and I must confess that I felt the least bit anxious. However, I said<lb/>
nothing to E. about it, but took good care to have all my weapons loaded and in<lb/>
good reach and kept my eyes well open. When I imagined that we were pretty near<lb/>
the &ldquo;Kilns&rdquo; I called to the driver and told him to let me know when he got there,<lb/>
whereupon, much to my satisfaction, he replied that we had already passed them.<lb/>
A ride of 15 miles further and we had reached our station, called &ldquo;The Point of<lb/>
the Mountain;&rdquo; so named from the fact of the station being situated just where a<lb/>
mountain range abruptly ends on the plain. Looking across a plain, 20 miles in<lb/>
width, we can see the &ldquo;Chiricahua Mountains &check;,&rdquo; well known in Arizona history as<lb/>
the home of the celebrated Indian Chief &ldquo;Cochise&rdquo; and his Chiricahua tribe, Indians<lb/>
that have killed more people in Arizona than all the other tribes put together.<lb/>
We can follow with the eye the plain, white stage road as it stretches across the<lb/>
intervening country and see it where it enters the mountains. Could the eye but<lb/>
follow it 4 miles further, we should see the spot where three mail-riders have<lb/>
recently fallen, pierced by the bullets of the savages. The last one was killed<lb/>
just a week before we commenced our journey. This night, as we had very good<lb/>
accommodations, we rested very well and awoke much refreshed. You would think it<lb/>
rather fatiguing, I guess, to have to ride 70 miles in two days. But there's<lb/>
<pb n="32" id="f04934032"/>
#31<lb/>
nothing like getting used to a thing, so that even frail little Emilie Lawrence<lb/>
Reed, although she had ridden and jolted over 70 miles of rough road in two days,<lb/>
stepped out of the station on the third morning as bright as a silver dollar and<lb/>
ready to ride 50 miles before sunset, if necessary. However, it was only 35<lb/>
miles we had to go on the third day. Our journey lay along a very pretty green<lb/>
valley, bordered on either side with a range of blue mountains. The road was<lb/>
level and as smooth as could be desired. On our right across the valley, distant<lb/>
about 10 miles, we could distinguish &ldquo;Camp Grant,&rdquo; a military post in this Ter-<lb/>
ritory. We had first thought of going by way of Grant, so as to rest a day or<lb/>
two, but concluded to abandon the idea, as we would really have to receive and<lb/>
return so many calls that our rest would be of little use to us. This day's ride<lb/>
was especially pleasant, as we saw plenty of green grass and live oak trees, obj-<lb/>
ects, especially the latter, that we had not seen for many a day. We passed<lb/>
through numerous herds of cattle, and saw many others scattered here and there<lb/>
over the valley, which added much to the beauty of the landscape. 
Toward after-<lb/>
noon the land became beautifully rolling and at 2 P. M. we alighted at &ldquo;Eureka<lb/>
Springs,&rdquo; the best atation in Arizona.</p>
<p>Here we found a large house, having 4 or 6 rooms and the windows provided<lb/>
with real window-blinds, and green ones too. A servant took our baggage and we<lb/>
were ushered into as nicely furnished a room as one could ask for. A good carpet,<lb/>
bedstead, bureau, centre table, etc., etc. By the time we had freed ourselves<lb/>
of the dust of travel, we were summoned to a nice dinner of fat mutton, vegetables,<lb/>
buttermilk, and all manner of good things. My! how we made the eatables fly!<lb/>
and such nice, cold, well water. Ah! this was a luxury which we could scarcely<lb/>
drink enough of. In a word, so charmed were we both with this station that we<lb/>
concluded, at once, to remain over a day, and rest and eat! We arrived on Monday<lb/>
and left on Wednesday. On the latter day we travelled 30 miles to reach Camp<lb/>
Thomas, a military post. We stopped at Lieutenant Powell's house, a bachelor<lb/>
acquaintance of mine. In fact there was only one married officer at the post and<lb/>
his wife was East. Emilie was the first lady ever at the post. She was such a<lb/>
curiosity that one little dog chancing to spy her, took to his heels for dear life,<lb/>
yelling at every jump. He soon returned reinforced by about 20 others and such a<lb/>
barking you never heard. None of them, though, had the courage to advance very<lb/>
close. At Thomas we were entertained just as hospitably as possible, as army<lb/>
officers always are when passing through a garrison. We remained over here a day<lb/>
also, in order to allow my wagon to precede me one day.</p>
<pb n="33" id="f04934033"/>
<p>#32</p>
<p>We left Camp Thomas on Friday and came 33 miles, part of the day over<lb/>
very rough roads. We passed through large orchards of &ldquo;prickly pears,&rdquo; a fruit<lb/>
which grows on the large leaved cactus. The fruit is the size of a large pear, of<lb/>
a beautiful purple colour, and an acid, agreeable taste. Emilie insisted upon<lb/>
eating several, whereof she much repented before next norning. Our destination<lb/>
for the day was &ldquo;Green's Camp,&rdquo; so called from the fact that Lieutenant Green, of<lb/>
the army, camped there many years ago. For the first time on our journey we had<lb/>
to camp out under the open heavens, as there is not a house between Camp Thomas<lb/>
and Camp Apache. We arrived in camp about 3 P. M. Soon afterwards I saw an Indian<lb/>
on a hill opposite camp. He came over, sat down by the side of me, and laying<lb/>
&check; down his gun, said &ldquo;El campo Apche,&rdquo; by which I knew that he <add>was</add> going to Apache.<lb/>
A minute later he said &ldquo;pan,&rdquo; at which I wasn't surprised, for they are always<lb/>
ready to eat. I gave him a loaf that was as dry as ashes and as hard as a rock,<lb/>
and the way he demolished it was astonishing. Having filled his stomach, he picked<lb/>
up his gun, said &ldquo;adios,&rdquo; and a moment later was lost to sight. When I got to<lb/>
Apache our recognition was mutual. The Indian turned out to be the celebrated<lb/>
&ldquo;Dead-shot,&rdquo; so named because he never misses his game, whether man or otherwise.<lb/>
We had our supper under the &ldquo;umbrageous foliage&rdquo; of a cedar tree and about 6:30<lb/>
P. M. prepared to retire. We had no tent but slept in the ambulance. The seats<lb/>
were so constructed that they could be slid together, forming a perfect floor.<lb/>
On this came our bedding and when we had made the curtains fast and tight we were<lb/>
ready for hail or rain. Little Undina each night found a warm bed at our feet.</p>
<p>We broke camp Saturday morning about 8 o'clock, as we only had 12 miles<lb/>
to go in order to reach water, for you must remember that in Arizona the length<lb/>
of a day's travel depends upon the distance between watering places. There are<lb/>
no streams every few miles, as in the East. Sometimes you go forty or even sixty<lb/>
miles without seeing a drop of water, and you rarely have to travel less than<lb/>
30 miles. &ldquo;Ash Creek,&rdquo; our camp this day was reached by noon. I made a heroic<lb/>
effort to catch some fish here, but after broiling in the sun an hour I only got<lb/>
one bite and that proved to be a plaguy turtle, to get which off my hook consumed<lb/>
another hour. I gave up fishing in disgust. &ldquo;Ash Creek&rdquo; is worth mentioning for<lb/>
this reason: about the time our dinner was well under way a terrific rainstorm<lb/>
came up, and as our bake-oven had no top our bread was soon afloat and the poor<lb/>
soldier, our cook, looked as if he had lost his best friend; but it was no use to<lb/>
try to make anything out of that bread, for it was so soaked that it weighed a<lb/>
pound to the square inch.</p>
<p>We left our camp next morning bright and early, as we were this day to<lb/>
<pb n="34" id="f04934034"/>
#33<lb/>
pass over the worst road in Arizona, yes, the worst road in the world. When we<lb/>
had gone about 4 miles we began to ascend very slowly and gradually the slope of<lb/>
the &ldquo;White Mountains.&rdquo; Soon we entered what is called &ldquo;Rocky Canon&rdquo; and no person<lb/>
who has been over this &ldquo;canon&rdquo; once will ever forget it. It is useless for me to<lb/>
attempt to describe this road to you. It is simply beyond language to describe its<lb/>
awful roughness. For a distance of about 3 miles the ambulance scarcely touches<lb/>
&ldquo;terra firma&rdquo;; the wheels jump from rock to rock with a perfect crash at times.<lb/>
But this is the good part of the road, I assure you. When we had gone over this,<lb/>
which required about 2 hours, we came to what is designated &ldquo;Nautaumes Hill.&rdquo;<lb/>
This is about three-quarters of a mile long to the summit. Standing at the foot<lb/>
of the hill and casting your eye upwards, you see nothing but solid stone, broken<lb/>
and tossed into all manner of shapes and positions. You would declare that no<lb/>
such thing as a wagon could ever go up or come down without being smashed into a<lb/>
thousand fragments. Imagine the steepest hill you ever saw, and then imagine its<lb/>
surface covered with stones the size of flour barrels, packed just as closely as<lb/>
possible, some on end, some on their sides, and some on their edges, and then you<lb/>
have not formed a conception of this hill.</p>
<p>The first thing to be done was to make everything perfectly snug inside<lb/>
the ambulance, and then to fasten two strong ropes, one to each side of the<lb/>
vehicle. To each rope two strong men held and then the ambulance was ready to<lb/>
start. The idea of the ropes was to keep it from upsetting, as very frequently<lb/>
only two wheels are on the ground, or stones, I should say. After the mules have<lb/>
plunged as if they would break their necks, we get a start, every man holding on<lb/>
to the ropes for dear life, the vehicle rising and falling, swaying and creaking,<lb/>
as if it would certainly go to pieces the next jump; fifty feet and we stop for<lb/>
breath; and it is a repetition of this from the foot to the top of the hill. It<lb/>
took just one hour and a half for my ambulance to make the three-quarters of a<lb/>
mile. As for my wagon, although I had only 1700 pounds in it, yet the twelve<lb/>
mules that I had harnessed to it, with the help of my four ambulance mules, could<lb/>
not budge it when it reached the foot of this hill. I worked from 10 A. M.<lb/>
till 5 P. M. and at that time we had made just thirty feet by actual measurement!<lb/>
I saw that it was useless to worry my animals any longer, so that I ordered the<lb/>
men to unhitch and camp there for the night. As for myself, I came on about three<lb/>
miles further to &ldquo;Camp Disappointment&rdquo; and spent the night under the lofty pines.<lb/>
I had with me only the corporal and driver. Emilie was very much afraid of<lb/>
bears and Indians until we got a rousing fire started, and then her spirits rose<lb/>
<pb n="35" id="f04934035"/>
#34<lb/>
and she ate quite a hea<add>r</add>ty supper, which I cooked as we had left our cook back<lb/>
with the wagon. I had left orders to unpack the wagon and carry part of the<lb/>
load up the hill on the mules. This they did, and thus managed to get up next<lb/>
day and reach &ldquo;Camp Disappointment.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I will describe briefly one more hill and then I am done with my<lb/>
letter. On this, the last day but one, we travel down &ldquo;Black River&rdquo; hill, the<lb/>
steepest hill I ever saw; so steep that it is necessary to lock the wheels and<lb/>
to drag behind the ambulance a large tree. Besides this, we fasten two ropes<lb/>
to the rear of the vehicle, to one of which the corporal swings and to the other<lb/>
my cook (who has overtaken us) and myself. The driver descends from his seat,<lb/>
for the danger is that the ambulance will go end over end. Having taken out<lb/>
the lead mules, we commence our downward progress slowly. We descend about<lb/>
sixty feet and then come to the &ldquo;jumping-off&rdquo; place, for it is a sheer descent<lb/>
of five feet, right over the face of a rock. Here we stop, examine every rope,<lb/>
every man braces himself for the struggle and the question is asked, &ldquo;Are<lb/>
you ready?&rdquo; The answer is &ldquo;All ready, sir,&rdquo; and the words given, &ldquo;Let her go!&rdquo;<lb/>
We pause a moment and then are jerked full twenty feet right over the rocks!<lb/>
So sudden was the leap and with such terrible force did I strike the ground<lb/>
that the very soles of my shoes were torn off! Suffice it to say that my<lb/>
ambulance landed safely and unbroken, and as the rest of our journey was smooth<lb/>
sailing, I will not inflict an account of the next day's trip upon you. For-<lb/>
give me, for I never wrote so disconnected a letter before in my life. If<lb/>
you will only promise to burn it as soon as read, all right; it is on this sole<lb/>
condition that I send it. Emilie joins me in love to all. Pardon my abrupt<lb/>
ending, write soon, and believe me very affectionately, your brother,</p>
<p>Walter Reed</p>
<p>In December 1877 at Fort Apache, my brother, General Walter Lawrence,<lb/>
Reed, was born. The following April, father writes an amusing letter about<lb/>
cooks, to my aunt:</p>
<p>Camp Apache, Arizona<lb/>
April 14, 1878</p>
<p>Dear Sister Ellen,</p>
<p>You know that in civilized life it is not allowable<lb/>
for an officer to have a soldier do his cooking, because he can easily get<lb/>
servants to do his work. But on the frontier, and especially in such a de-<lb/>
lectable country as &ldquo;Arizony&rdquo; where it is simply impossible to find hand-maidens,<lb/>
unless it be an occasional Chinaman, it is permitted to use soldiers as cooks,<lb/>
<pb n="36" id="f04934036"/>
#35<lb/>
provided they are willing to cook. Of course it is at the option of the soldier<lb/>
whether he will do duty with his company or cook. I will premise by saying<lb/>
that nearly all soldiers can cook after a fashion, and some of them very well,<lb/>
but most of them have a dislike to cooking for a married officer. The &ldquo;pig<lb/>
under the fence&rdquo; is the officer's wife. Soldiers will take any order and any<lb/>
amount of abuse from an officer without murmuring, but when it comes to re-<lb/>
ceiving orders or even suggestions from a lady, they rebel at once ....<lb/>
Another point to bear in mind is that soldiers, with but few exceptions, are<lb/>
very fond of their &ldquo;toddy&rdquo; and always get drunk after pay day, which comes<lb/>
every two months.</p>
<p>You will remember that up to December last we messed with Mrs.<lb/>
Colonel Andrews, and hence had no trouble about cooks. On the first of Decem-<lb/>
ber, however, we went to housekeeping, for reasons which it is not necessary<lb/>
to state, being no less than the expected advent of &ldquo;our baby,&rdquo; and so I had<lb/>
to look about for a soldier to do my cooking. After much search I lit upon<lb/>
one James Anmach, a high private in the rear rank. Now this same private<lb/>
Anmach is a considerable personage, having had no less than seven trades or<lb/>
professions, as follows: He is a natural born plasterer; in his early years<lb/>
he took up painting as a fine art; waxing stronger he devoted himself, his<lb/>
time and muscle to carpentering; finding that this occupation cramped his<lb/>
mental powers too much he turned his attention to brightening rusty knife<lb/>
blades and sharpening scissors, etc.; subsequently, circumstances over which<lb/>
he had no control forced him to become a plumber, for you know the greatest<lb/>
intellects must at times yield to the course of events; and finally, ruthless<lb/>
fortune converted him into a farmer. Now what he does not know about horses<lb/>
and cows is entirely superfluous knowledge. As an extractor of the &ldquo;albine<lb/>
fluid&rdquo; he has no equal. Indeed the cow herself is amazed at his dexterous<lb/>
performance. If the animal manifests any desire to run him through with her<lb/>
horns, he throws a lariat round the horns and fastens her head to a post;<lb/>
and then, if she makes too free with her posterior extremities, he simply ties<lb/>
them snugly together with a rope, and as he milks pays not the least attention<lb/>
to her frantic efforts to extricate herself.</p>
<p>Such an one was James Anmach, my new cook, on the first day of<lb/>
December, 1877. I should state that he knew nothing about cooking whatever,<lb/>
but as he expressed it &ldquo;he would not mind learning to cook, as it might be<lb/>
useful to him one of these days.&rdquo; I presume the real reason was because he<lb/>
<pb n="37" id="f04934037"/>
#36<lb/>
had so few trades. Upon his assumption of the culinary dignity I had a brief<lb/>
interview with Mr. Anmach, in which I expressed to him my earnest desire that<lb/>
he would abstain from all intoxicating liquors, for a time at least. After the<lb/>
birth of the future President I again told him that I hoped while Mrs. Reed<lb/>
was sick he would keep sober, for should he get on a spree and absent himself<lb/>
for a week or so, I would have no one to cook but myself and would be placed<lb/>
in a most deplorable position. He declared that should he think of getting<lb/>
drunk under the circumstances he would consider himself no better than a<lb/>
&ldquo;dog&rdquo; and that I might place full confidence in his sobriety.</p>
<p>Fortunately he turned out to be a very fair cook; a plain one, but<lb/>
he knew how to season food and could make pretty good bread and coffee, beside<lb/>
flannel cakes, etc. But he had the most curious ideas about crockery and its<lb/>
uses of any man I ever met. In the first place, he had a perfect mania for<lb/>
soup-plates. It made no difference what the dish was, whether beefsteak,<lb/>
chicken, tomatoes, corn, flannel cakes, or what not, he always brought it to<lb/>
the table in a soup-plate and insisted on my eating out of the same kind of<lb/>
plate. I really believe he would have served the coffee in the same, if he<lb/>
could have found another one. Luckily we have only six soup-plates, and when<lb/>
he got these full he had to resort to something else. I gently remonstrated<lb/>
with him and pointed out the uses of a few utensils, but whether my explanations<lb/>
confused him or were too stupendous to grasp, I know not; I do know that the<lb/>
following day at dinner he fairly knocked the breath out of me by serving the<lb/>
tomatoes in the slop-bowl, the potatoes in the soup-tureen, and the pickles<lb/>
in a gravy-boat. I ate my dinner in silence, and from that day I never made<lb/>
any suggestions to Mr. Anmach. He took a great deal of pains in preparing<lb/>
his dishes, but when once cooked his mission ended, and he served them regardless<lb/>
of all traditions.</p>
<p>I cannot remember all the ingenious freaks of this man Anmach.<lb/>
On one occasion he served the soup in the cream pitcher, on another day on<lb/>
lifting the lid of the soup-tureen what should I find but half-a-dozen peach<lb/>
dumplings reposing therein. I think he intended this as a surprise, but I<lb/>
betrayed no astonishment whatever. He could not have told from my face but<lb/>
that I had been used to eating peach dumplings out of soup- tureens all my life.<lb/>
A few days after that when I attempted to fill my glass with water and found<lb/>
instead boiled potatoes in the pitcher, I may have betrayed some momentary<lb/>
surprise, but I think not. You may think I am falsifying, but I assure you<lb/>
<pb n="38" id="f04934038"/>
#37<lb/>
that I am giving stern facts.</p>
<p>When I had lulled myself into the belief that private Anmach would<lb/>
cling to his early training and keep sober, it came to pass that that season<lb/>
of the year drew nigh which has been so beautifully described by Lord Macauley<lb/>
in the words &ldquo;Apple cider, cinnamon beer; Christmas comes but once a year.&rdquo;<lb/>
Perhaps the recollection of other days came back to him and led him astray,<lb/>
for at any rate Christmas night I heard a noise in Anmach's room about 11<lb/>
o'clock and going in found him quite drunk and made him go to bed. I locked<lb/>
the door and put the key in my pocket, but to my surprise when I went to his<lb/>
room next morning about 7 o'clock, I found the bird had flown. I then went<lb/>
into the kitchen and found everything in confusion. As I stood there and cast<lb/>
my eye over the various frying-pans and tea-kettles, and especially the cold,<lb/>
ashy face of the old stove, I realized for the first time the true beauty of<lb/>
soldier cooks.</p>
<p>I returned and told the mother of the future President that our<lb/>
festive cook was gone, and took council with her as to how the dilema was to<lb/>
be met. After a brief session of five minutes duration, it was decided that I<lb/>
should peel off my jacket and approach the pensive frying-pan. I cannot say<lb/>
that I essayed the task with songs of joy upon my lips, but still I was deter-<lb/>
mined that no one should cheat me out of my breakfast that morning. The bill<lb/>
of fare was as follows: Pan fresco, manteca cafe caliente y huevos asados. <add>see</add><lb/>
Now does not that sound like a city hotel? Reduced to plain English it is not<lb/>
quite so overpowering, but fresh bread, butter, hot coffee, and boiled eggs<lb/>
are at all times refreshing. For three days and nights I saw nothing of my<lb/>
truant cook, and during this time I got up various unspeakable and uneatable<lb/>
dishes. Emilie, however, lacked for nothing, for the ladies sent her meals<lb/>
regularly. On the morning of the fourth day a soft knock at the door announced<lb/>
the return of the wanderer. I had fully made up my mind to give him &ldquo;rats,&rdquo;<lb/>
but he ate such a quantity of humble pie that I could say nothing. He acknowledged<lb/>
his meanness in leaving me under the circumstances, calling himself a good-for-<lb/>
nothing &ldquo;dog&rdquo; and promising never to deceive me again.</p>
<p>Everything now went on lovely, and as Emilie was out of bed by Jan-<lb/>
uary 15 and able to direct affairs I had high hopes that we had passed the<lb/>
worst. Contrary to my advice, however, Emilie insisted that the vegetables<lb/>
should go into the vegetable dishes, the soup into the tureen, and a lot of<lb/>
other nonsensical ideas which I felt convinced our man Friday would never<lb/>
<pb n="39" id="f04934039"/>
#38<lb/>
submit to. And sure enough, just four days thereafter, January 19th, the man<lb/>
of many trades slid off again, this time on a drunk as before, and again I<lb/>
was elected cook. After waiting five days and finding that cooking was a<lb/>
trifle monotonous I employed another cook, private George Powers, the &ldquo;meek-<lb/>
eyed.&rdquo; He did very well, and as he was sober and learned willingly and<lb/>
quickly, Emilie was on the fair road to make him a first-class cook. But lo!<lb/>
there were breakers ahead! The Commanding Officer's cook got on a rampage and<lb/>
was sent back to his company. Hence the Commanding Officer (as private Powers<lb/>
belonged to his company) found himself under the &ldquo;painful necessity&rdquo; (which,<lb/>
by the way, was all painful fiddlesticks) of taking our cook to cook for his<lb/>
family. So on March 1st, we had to let him go and take as our bread-maker one<lb/>
private Bertrand Howard, the sullen, and, I may add, the lazy. He had the<lb/>
reputation of being an excellent cook, and thought he knew everything. He<lb/>
could make excellent cakes for breakfast and pretty good pumpkin pies, but<lb/>
beyond this his cooking was a mess. He could not bear for Emilie to give him<lb/>
&check; any suggestions, <del>as</del><add>and</add> as for her coming into the kitchen, it made him very angry<lb/>
for a week. He thought he knew so much that he wouldn't follow any receipt and<lb/>
in fact just cooked after his own style and liking. As we had had so much<lb/>
trouble I begged Emilie to put up with him, although she could hardly help<lb/>
throwing a frying-pan at his head. Mr. Howard was much inclined to laziness,<lb/>
so that when we began to move to our new house and he found he would have to<lb/>
do a little extra work in cleaning the kitchen, he came to me and said he would<lb/>
like to go back to his company. I was so disgusted with the gentleman's per-<lb/>
formance that I paid him and told him to report at once. Thus blooming April<lb/>
found us once more minus a cook, and that too while we were busy moving. I<lb/>
tried various soldiers, but could get no one to come. In fact there seemed<lb/>
to be a perfect dearth of cooks and I knew not what to do, when a happy<lb/>
thought occurred to us. What do you suppose it was? It was E.'s suggestion.<lb/>
To take back to our hearts our old friend the plasterer, alias the painter,<lb/>
alias the carpenter, alias the cutler, alias the tinner, alias the farmer,<lb/>
alias the cook, alias James Anmach of the Horse Marines.</p>
<p>And we did! We have the most beautiful contract drawn up imaginable,<lb/>
and it is as simple as it is beautiful. Private Anmach agrees to cook and do<lb/>
general work, such as milking, etc., to put the soup into its proper tureen,<lb/>
and not to put the potatoes in the water pitcher, provided he is permitted to<lb/>
have a week's drunk after each pay day, or once in two months. Once more the<lb/>
<add>sic</add> God of day has chased away the clouds and we are happy. I am glad to say that<lb/>
<pb n="40" id="f04934040"/>
#39<lb/>
under E.'s skilful generalship he is doing amazingly, even going so far as to<lb/>
make a citron pudding after your latest receipt, which was might<del>l</del>y good and<lb/>
gave us indigestion like all the world. <add>sic</add></p>
<p>And this is all I know about cooks in general and soldier cooks in<lb/>
particular. Best love to all, in which E. and baby join. Write soon.</p>
<p>Yours affectionate brother,<lb/>
Walter Reed.</p>
<p>
P. S. I am constrained to add a few lines which are so appropriate to the<lb/>
present occasion that you will not consider me verbose.<lb/>
&ldquo;We may live without poetry, music, or art;<lb/>
We may live without conscience and live without heart;<lb/>
We may live without friends and live without books;<lb/>
But civilized man cannot live without cooks.&rdquo;<lb/>
</p>
<p>In April 1879, mother and my brother left Camp Apache, for a visit to<lb/>
her home in North Carolina. Father felt it was unwise for them to remain longer<lb/>
in Arizona. In the winter he writes a letter on hunting:</p>
<p>Fort Apache, Arizona<lb/>
December 23, 1879</p>
<p>My darling wife,</p>
<p>My last letter was not a very long one for the reason<lb/>
that I was getting ready to go for a &ldquo;big hunt&rdquo; with Lieutenants Kingsbury and<lb/>
Cruse, although I did not mention it at the time. Well, we got away from the<lb/>
post about 8 o'clock on Wednesday morning, and away we hied to &ldquo;Bonito Fork,&rdquo;<lb/>
the scene of our former hunting expedition, on which occasion the deer we killed<lb/>
and the turkey we slew would not have furnished fresh meat for many days. On<lb/>
this occasion, however, beside four soldiers and four packers, we had twenty of<lb/>
the Indian Company, so that when we arrived at our camp that afternoon we found<lb/>
four turkeys and a fine big deer awaiting us. . . . Our little camp looked<lb/>
real pretty at night. We were on the extreme right, then came our soldiers'<lb/>
camp about 30 feet away, then the packers', and farther still the 20 Indians,<lb/>
divided into two camps of 10 each, so that there were five camp fires burning<lb/>
brightly and stretched along in a line about 30 feet apart. We had a good tent<lb/>
for ourselves and one for the soldiers. You should have seen our beds. Lieu-<lb/>
tenant Cruse and I dug a small hole on each side of the tent large enough to<lb/>
admit our backbones, and then filled both of them with long dry grass which we<lb/>
<pb n="41" id="f04934041"/>
#40<lb/>
cut from the mountain side, thus making a delightfully soft cushion for our<lb/>
bones -- a sort of hair mattress with springs, as it were, over which we spread<lb/>
our blankets. I slept with 4 blankets under me doubled over, and 8 over me<lb/>
with my night-cap and a good heavy comforter which Mrs. Harrison gave me<lb/>
around my neck, and I managed to exclude the cold pretty well. I forgot to<lb/>
say that I had Lieutenant Kingsbury's dog sleeping on my feet to keep them<lb/>
warm, and pretty cold it was too. Next morning (Thrusday) when we got up,<lb/>
bright and early, we found about half an inch of snow on the ground and the<lb/>
wind was singing merrily through the trees. The Indians had already skipped<lb/>
out for a day's hunt, and while we ate our broiled venison for breakfast we<lb/>
now and then heard a sharp crack of a rifle, which we knew meant either a<lb/>
turkey or a deer. After breakfast was over (I am sorry to say that I did not<lb/>
wash my face that morning, it was so cold) Lieutenant Cruse and I took our<lb/>
guns and climbed a high hill which took the breath clean out of us and then<lb/>
away we went, tramping over the roughest country you almost ever saw, and we<lb/>
kept our walk till 2 P. M. but we didn't get anything, as the Indians were<lb/>
ahead of us and frightened all the game away. We got back at 2 P. M. to camp,<lb/>
and such a dinner as we two ate would have supplied half a d<del>i</del><add>o</add>zen hungry men...<lb/>
By the time we had finished the Indians began to come in with their game, and<lb/>
before the sun had sunk beneath the western horizon we counted 13 deer and 10<lb/>
turkeys as the result of one day's shooting. I attended to &ldquo;drawing&rdquo; the<lb/>
turkeys, in fact, did it all myself, and Lieutenant Kingsbury superintended<lb/>
cleaning the deer. Before night we had them all hung up on a rope stretched<lb/>
between two tall pines and by the light glimmer of the camp fire the display<lb/>
of game was very fine. Next morning we were up before the stars ceased shining,<lb/>
busy taking down our tent and bundling up our baggage ready for a day's<lb/>
journey to another branch of Black River, about 7 miles farther away. We<lb/>
were there and in camp by 12 o'clock noon, and after camp was pitched we lay<lb/>
off on our backs, and snoozed and sang songs and had a jolly time generally.<lb/>
That afternoon the Indians brought in 5 turkeys and 6 deer and reported that<lb/>
they had left hanging out in the trees, from 5 to 15 miles away, 13 more big<lb/>
deer so large that they couldn't pack them on their backs. That night we had<lb/>
a glorious time broiling venison over the red hot coals. We ate and ate and<lb/>
yet did not seem to have enough. We held a council of war that night and<lb/>
decided to send in to the post next morning 16 deer and 17 turkeys as a gentle<lb/>
reminder to the folks at Apache that we were as good hunters as other people.<lb/>
<pb n="42" id="f04934042"/>
#41<lb/>
After getting the party off to Apache early next morning (Saturday) we started<lb/>
in various directions to get the deer that were hanging out. Sam Bowman and<lb/>
I went out with two pack mules, and after traveling about 5 miles over mountains<lb/>
and canons we brought in 4 beautiful deer, but such a tramp as we had. The<lb/>
Indian who went to show us where the deer were said that it was only &ldquo;poco<lb/>
logos&rdquo; that is &ldquo;a little far&rdquo; (Dandy-Bill, our old friend, by the way, was<lb/>
the caballiero <add>sic</add>, and I never knew what &ldquo;poco logos&rdquo; was before, but I know<lb/>
now. It means about 50 miles for a white man! I was so tired when I got back<lb/>
to camp that it took about 3 pounds of venison stew to refresh my drooping<lb/>
spirits! Saturday night it began to storm and rained all night, and continued<lb/>
so to do all day Sunday, so that no hunting could be done by the Indians. All<lb/>
day we lay in our tents with a roaring fire in front and did not have to go<lb/>
out, except for meals, which even the storm could not keep us from. . . . We<lb/>
concluded that night that our hunt was over, as the storm only increased in<lb/>
severity and we only waited for the return of the pack mules from Apache in<lb/>
order to pack up our duds and hie to the camp. They returned on Monday too<lb/>
late for a start back on the same day. On Tuesday morning (yesterday), however,<lb/>
we started back again to Apache and faced a terrible storm till 2 P. M. . . .<lb/>
In all we killed 41 deer and 50 turkeys! This morning we distributed the game<lb/>
and now everyone at the Post has enough fresh meat for their Christmas dinner.<lb/>
. . . . . A thousand Happy New Years for my sweet wife and son! God bless and<lb/>
preserve you both is ever the prayer of your fond and devoted husband,</p>
<p>Walter of Arizona</p>
<p>After four years of duty in Arizona, father was ordered East. He<lb/>
then received the rank of Captain and was stationed at Fort McHenry, Baltimore,<lb/>
in 1881, and while there, he studied at the Johns Hopkins University. In<lb/>
1882 to 1887, he was stationed in Nebraska, first at Fort Omaha, where I was<lb/>
born, and then to Fort Robinson. In 1887, we went to Mt. Vernon Barracks,<lb/>
Alabama, and back west again, this time to Minnesota and Dakota. In 1893,<lb/>
father was ordered to Washington, D. C., and made curator of the army Medical<lb/>
Museum, and professor of bacteriology and clinical microscopy in the Army<lb/>
Medical School.</p>
<p>My childhood memories are of a devoted father who was my idol and my<lb/>
playmate. My earliest recollections of him were <add>when we were</add> stationed at Mount Vernon<lb/>
Barracks, Alabama. In a reservation outside of the Post were the Apache<lb/>
Indians. After father had paid one or two professional calls on them, they formed<lb/>
<pb n="43" id="f04934043"/>
#42<lb/>
a strong friendship for him. Gero<add><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></add>mio was their chief, and father often laughed<lb/>
because I would never speak to them, unless he introduced me to them. Having<lb/>
a strong love for animals, father got for me, two young mocking birds, a little<lb/>
black pig and two kittens. The kittens grew into cats, and much to my delight,<lb/>
raised fine families. These kittens had a habit of eating lizards. Fits were<lb/>
sure to follow, but my dear father, always tender hearted over any living<lb/>
creature's distress, was soon on hand to offer his assistance. One Christmas<lb/>
morning, after breakfast, he and mother led me in my playroom to see a doll<lb/>
house, made by a soldier, under father's careful supervision, as a joyful<lb/>
surprise to me. As we entered the room, doll furniture was flying out of the<lb/>
door and windows. One of the kittens was inside having a fit! Taking me in<lb/>
his arms, he promised me that if I would stop crying, he would remove the kitten<lb/>
and put back the furniture. The reading of Uncle Remus was an evening pass<lb/>
time, before my brother and I went to bed. He read them to perfection. In<lb/>
the summer evenings, when my parents would sit on the porch and talk to friends,<lb/>
I was allowed to sleep in his arms until long after my bed time. Father loved<lb/>
Alabama. He so often spoke of the wonderful Magnolia trees for which he had<lb/>
great admiration. After two years in Alabama, we went for station to Fort<lb/>
Snelling, Minnesota. What fun it was to have him pull me over the snow on my<lb/>
sled, or to go to his chicken house, where he prided himself on having laying<lb/>
hens in such a cold climate. In the spring, hand and hand we would go into the<lb/>
prairie to pick for mother the most beautiful wild violets I think I have ever<lb/>
&check; seen. I adored to play by him, while he gave his spare moments to cultivatin<add>g</add><lb/>
flowers and vegetables. In a year's time we moved into St. Paul, where father<lb/>
was the attending physician. Besides helping me feed flies and bugs to a pet<lb/>
frog that an army officer had given me, and that I kept on the roof garden of<lb/>
the apartment house in which we lived, a good deal of his time was taken up<lb/>
by his blessed patience in paying professional calls on my doll babies, and<lb/>
there were a goodly number of them. If he was attending a child with scarlet<lb/>
fever, he would come home to find a doll put to bed with red spots painted<lb/>
from head to foot, nor would I rest easily until he had taken my patients pulse<lb/>
and told me what to do. As long as his little patient was confined to her bed,<lb/>
just so long did the sign, &ldquo;Scarlet Fever,&rdquo; stay on the door of my small bed<lb/>
room. One Christmas Eve just before I went to bed, I announced that every doll<lb/>
would hang up their stockings. Across the cover on the sitting room table, I<lb/>
pinned them in a row. It was much too cold for mother to accompany him, but<lb/>
out he flew to a near by toy shop, and the next morning, I found each little<lb/>
<pb n="44" id="f04934044"/>
#43<lb/>
stocking, stuffed with the tiniest of toys. How I loved him to tell me stories<lb/>
about Santa Claus<del>e</del>, and what amazing tales he could tell. All children loved<lb/>
him. But there followed one Chris-Eve <add>sic</add> that left a heart broken little girl. On<lb/>
that very day when I was fairly jumping with joy, a cruel War Department sent<lb/>
an adoring father to Dakota. I don't think there could ever be told how many<lb/>
tears were shed. In 1893, father was ordered to Washington. How many nice<lb/>
things were there for us to do together. The thrill of sitting by him at the<lb/>
circus and eating peanuts and pop corn that he enjoyed as much as I did; or<lb/>
standing hand in hand, watching a parade. We moved over to Georgetown in a<lb/>
lovely old home. There before an open fire, where a family of cats and a puppy<lb/>
adorned the hearth, father sat with his books, studyin.g I remember in the<lb/>
afternoons, watching for him to turn the corner. A horse car was his only<lb/>
means of transportation from the Army Medical Museum. How I would run to meet<lb/>
him, and what a warm welcome awaited me! On state occasions, I was allowed to<lb/>
go down to the Museum and pay a visit to his laboratory. There he would let<lb/>
me peep through his microscope and look at some of his different germs.<lb/>
Then he would take me in to see his monkeys. These were used for the purpose<lb/>
of vaccinating. When he would speak to them in German they would slide up and<lb/>
down on the bars of their cage and make faces at him. This was the occasion<lb/>
for much mirth from both of us. As I grew older, I can remember how many<lb/>
hours he would give in the evening to some of his medical students, helping<lb/>
and explaining to them parts of their studies that seemed difficult. This<lb/>
he deemed a privilege. <add>I was just nineteen when my blessed father .... etc.</add></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
