<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04934048">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, June 18, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04934048</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-06-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Clemons, Harry</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Atcheson Laughlin</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-06-18">June 18, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">04934048</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, June 18, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench gives suggestions of publishers for Reed's manuscript. He also lists errors in her manuscript.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-06-18">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, June 18, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04934048"/>
<opener>
To Mrs. Blossom Reed<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-06-18">June 18, 1941</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Reed:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Since I was unable to spend as much time on your father's letters as<lb/>
I had hoped, I had my secretary copy a number of the letters in full, but I can<lb/>
assure you I will not use these letters, except to give your background notes,<lb/>
without your special permission. Since returning, I read them over again and I<lb/>
agree with you that they are certainly most interesting and should by all means<lb/>
be published somewhere if possible. I imagine that some editors to whom you<lb/>
might send them might think much of the data was too personal, but it does certainly<lb/>
show his wonderful character. As I see it, the present day editor of magazines<lb/>
for laymen wants to jazz up most articles. You may have read the story of Moran<lb/>
published in the Saturday Evening Post two or three years ago. Someone interviewed<lb/>
Moran, took the main parts of his story and then jazzed it up considerably.</p>
<p>Andrus, one of the volunteers (as a matter of fact, the one who presumably<lb/>
volunteered to take the place of your father when he insisted on submitting to the<lb/>
mosquito bites) has written his story up briefly and has sent it to one or two<lb/>
magazines for publication but it was sent back with the usual regrets. I think<lb/>
there is probably no question that the letters would be published in some medical<lb/>
or some medical historical journal but these journals do not pay for manuscripts<lb/>
and your only reward would be the satisfaction of having your father's character<lb/>
adequately portrayed. Had you thought of enlisting the interest of the University<lb/>
of Virginia? Most large universities have a university press and of all institutions,<lb/>
the University of Virginia would be most interested. The librarian there, Mr. Harry<lb/>
Clemons, is most interested in the yellow fever story. They have a small Walter<lb/>
Reed collection of data already. Incidentally, my brother, Dr. A. L. Hench, is<lb/>
Professor of English Literature there and I would be very glad, should you wish me<lb/>
to do so, to send him your manuscript and have him discuss it with Mr. Clemons.<lb/>
Perhaps you would prefer to write Mr. Clemons directly. I understand from our<lb/>
editorial department that Little Brown of Boston, lay publishers, are interested<lb/>
in stories with a medical angle. I do not know anyone there but perhaps they would<lb/>
be interested in your manuscript. I am returning it to you today by insured express.</p>
<p>May I ask you a few questions regarding your manuscript?</p>
<p>1. In reading them, it seemed to me that the letters of March 6, 1876<lb/>
(your page 36) and that of April 3, 1876 (your page 39) were written in the opposite<lb/>
sequence. The one now marked April 3 was apparently written before the one marked<lb/>
March 6. I suspect that both of these letters were written either in April or in<lb/>
March.</p>
<p>2. Do you have the date of the first letter on your page 71? my p 1</p>
<p>my p 1 3. In the letter on page 71, should it be Major Petterson, with two &ldquo;t's&rdquo;<lb/>
or Peterson with one &ldquo;t&rdquo;?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f04934049"/>
<p>Mrs. Blossom Reed<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
June 18, 1941</p>
<p>my p 2 4. Your page 72, letter of &ldquo;Sunday, 1 P.M.&rdquo; Your letter suggests that<lb/>
your father's boat was running parallel to the shore at a distance of about two<lb/>
hundred miles. He then mentions the sights on the beach. Surely this must be a<lb/>
mistake. The boat must have been running parallel to the shore at two or at most<lb/>
twenty miles, and not two hundred miles. Could you check this with the original<lb/>
letter.</p>
<p>my p 7 5. Your page 78. The letter on this page mentions &ldquo;The Evening Star&rdquo;<lb/>
paper. Does your mother recall what city and what the date of this paper was?<lb/>
I suspect it may have been a Washington paper. I should very much like to trace<lb/>
this article.</p>
<p>my p 9 6. Your page 80. In the letter of July 19, a Dr. Durleam is mentioned.<lb/>
I am sure that this is Dr. Durham.</p>
<p>my p 10 7. Your page 81. You have the &ldquo;Transport Rawlines&rdquo;. I am sure it was<lb/>
the &ldquo;Rawlins.&rdquo;</p>
<p>my p 10 8. Your page 82. Do you have any idea of the date of the letter dated<lb/>
&ldquo;Monday afternoon, 5 P.M.&rdquo;? The mailing date might be on the envelope.</p>
<p>my p 11 9. Your page 84. The sentence given in your manuscript, &ldquo;His name will<lb/>
live in history of those who have benefited humanity.&rdquo; I wonder if this sentence<lb/>
is correctly quoted?</p>
<p>p 13-14 10. Page 86. For my own personal information I would appreciate greatly<lb/>
knowing who are the three &ldquo;Doctors__________&rdquo;. In the letter of December 11,<lb/>
pages 86 and 87. I will keep this in confidence but would very much like to know.</p>
<p>my p 18 11. Page 93. In the letter of December 23, your father mentions an<lb/>
article in the Washington Post. I assume this was sometime during the month of<lb/>
December. Do you or your mother happen to have this clipping or the date of this<lb/>
article?</p>
<p>my p 19 12. Page 94. Are you sure your father's letter was dated December 26 or<lb/>
should this have been on the 25th, Christmas Day? On the bottom of page 95, your<lb/>
father speaks of the young fellow &ldquo;who went in on the twenty-first and was suddenly<lb/>
stricken today at noon.&rdquo; This must refer to Moran and the official record shows that<lb/>
he became sick on Christmas afternoon.</p>
<p>my p 23 13. Your page 98. You quote &ldquo;and I must check for a while this letter.&rdquo;<lb/>
Is that an accurate quotation from the original letter?</p>
<p>my p 23 14. Page 99. You mention the number of letters which have been given away.<lb/>
Again I would be so happy to help to try to collect copies of these letters if your<lb/>
mother could give me some idea of those to whom these letters were sent. I should<lb/>
be glad to write around and collect for you and myself copies of these letters.<lb/>
This also applies to the distressing absence of letters between October 6 and December<lb/>
9, in addition to those missing letters of February, 1901.</p>
<p>Let me say again what a privilege it has been for me to read these letters<lb/>
and if I can help in any way further, I should be glad to do so. Should you finally<lb/>
decide that the only thing to do is to have them published without financial return<lb/>
to you, I will be glad to give you the names of three or four medical historical<lb/>
journals but I still believe that the University of Virginia might be the best bet.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh: ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
