<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t04934050">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Biographical sketch: Life and Letters of Dr. Walter Reed by His Daughter, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>04934050</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>25 pp.</extent>
<date value="0000-00-00"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">04934050</idno>
<title>Biographical sketch: Life and Letters of Dr. Walter Reed by His Daughter, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This manuscript discusses Walter Reed's yellow fever experiments in Cuba and provides letters written by Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="0000-00-00">
<head>Biographical sketch: Life and Letters of Dr. Walter Reed by His Daughter, by Blossom [Emilie M.] Reed, [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f04934050"/>
<p>LIFE &amp; LETTERS OF DR. WALTER REED BY HIS DAUGHTER, BLOSSOM REED</p>
<p><del>(The last</del> <add>(</add>copy of the last part from 1900 on loaned to me<lb/>
by Mr. Kellogg)</p>
<p>I was just nineteen when my blessed father passed away. Those were<lb/>
nineteen years of golden sunshine, and the memories I have carried in my<lb/>
heart daily since his death, have been the reward given me, for the loss of<lb/>
my idol and my hero.</p>
<p>During the latter part of his life, we owned a country home at<lb/>
Blue Ridge Summit, Pa. Father always had a vegetable garden, flower garden,<lb/>
and chickens.</p>
<p>In the summer of 1900, father went to Cuba to study the cause of<lb/>
yellow fever. Columbia Barracks, a military reservation about eight miles<lb/>
from the city of Havana was selected for the experimental station. The<lb/>
officers who formed the Yellow Fever Commission were Major Walter Reed, Dr.<lb/>
James Carroll, Dr. Aristides Agramonte, and Dr. Jesse W. Lazear. During<lb/>
these summer months of 1900, his letters to mother from Cuba were taken up<lb/>
with how we should take care of ourselves and many orders to the gardener<lb/>
about the gardens. He alluded very little to yellow fever in his letters, as<lb/>
it was a constant worry to my mother. His first letter written in June on a<lb/>
Transport is as follows:</p>
<p>At sea off the Jersey Coast<lb/>
Thursday, 9 P. M.</p>
<p>As I told you and little daughter that you might think of me as<lb/>
the sickest dog in the bunch: I now want to tell you how splendidly I have made<lb/>
out this far. We left New York at 10 A. M. I have not been sea sick a bit this<lb/>
time. The sea is quiet tho the vessel moves considerably. I had a good lunch<lb/>
and ate a very hearty dinner. Dr. Carroll and I have the best stateroom on the<lb/>
<add>PSHench<lb/>
pp 77-100 of Miss Reeds ms<lb/>
I think this should be June 21, 1900 P.S.H.</add><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f04934051"/>
-2-<lb/>
ship, because I happen to be the ranking officer aboard, and staterooms go by<lb/>
rank. There are several officers aborad--Major Petterson <unclear>&check;</unclear> of the Commissary<lb/>
Department, Major Dunn and wife of the Judge Advocate Department, and Lieutenant<lb/>
Wilcox. I expect to enjoy the trip very much as the bromide appears to be<lb/>
doing its work beautifully. The Sedgwick is of 5000 tons and was formerly the<lb/>
City of Chester. She is a fast boat and quite fast</p>
<p>A little North of Jupiter Inlet<lb/>
Florida Coast, Sunday 11 A. M.</p>
<p>My darling children can see that there is something of a gap between<lb/>
my first attempt at writing and this my second. Friday evening, I promenaded<lb/>
the deck with the Captain although the boat was pitching a good deal. When I<lb/>
retired at nine o'clock, I found that Dr. Carroll had given up the fight and<lb/>
I suppose that his example had some effect on me. When I awoke Saturday<lb/>
morning, there was a sensation of two or three tons of brick in the region of<lb/>
my stomach and an entire loss of appetite. The boat was rolling and the orange<lb/>
that I ate began to roll, too, until it rolled out: I stayed in my birth all<lb/>
day yesterday. Read some, slept more and &ldquo;fed the fishes&rdquo; as the occasion<lb/>
seemed to require: This morning I have had an orange, a cup of black coffee<lb/>
and dry toast. Now, I have come on deck to enjoy the delightful breeze. I<lb/>
think I can make out very well till tomorrow, when we reach Havana. At 8:30<lb/>
this morning I thought of my darling wife and daughter sitting down to break-<lb/>
fast in our little mountain home we love so dearly, and oh! how I did want<lb/>
some of those fresh strawberries, and oh! for just one cup of that good coffee!<lb/>
That would make me well immediately. Do write and tell me how the things<lb/>
grow. Both flowers and vegetables for I shall take such interest in them.<lb/>
Bless your darling hearts, how father looks forward to seeing you again,<lb/>
Sunday, 1 P. M.</p>
<p>We are now skirting along the Florida coast running parallel at a<lb/>
distance of about <hi>two hundred miles</hi>. How refreshing the sight of beach and<lb/>
<add>Peterson?<lb/>
should be June 24<lb/>
?<lb/>
20 miles?<lb/>
2 miles?<lb/>
<hi>2 miles</hi></add><lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f04934052"/>
-3-<lb/>
foliage is after 48 hours at sea. The strip of green seen over the water is<lb/>
so pleasant a prospect. Nestling here and there amongst the pines, I can see<lb/>
many pretty homes. Twice this morning we have seen a beautiful rain passing<lb/>
up the coast just parallel with the shore, and each time felt its refreshing<lb/>
coolness. The weather thus far has been delightful. The gong has sounded for<lb/>
lunch but I won't go down! I will have my lunch on deck, for I am afraid the<lb/>
sight of so much food would turn me up side down! How dear little daughter<lb/>
would enjoy seeing the schools of flying fish, as they suddenly rise out of<lb/>
the water and go hurrying along, apparently to get rid of the ship. Thursday<lb/>
afternoon a school of porpoise made sport for us for quite a while, as they went<lb/>
rolling and diving and chasing after each other. Tell daughter that as I write<lb/>
the Captain's little fox terrier stands and gazes wistfully at me as if she<lb/>
wanted to get in my lap. I'll write more before we reach Havana.</p>
<p>Not quite in sight of Cuba<lb/>
Monday morning, 7:30 o'clock</p>
<p>Well, sweetest children on earth, here is father up at this hour and<lb/>
on the saloon deck, after having sucked a lemon dry, swallowed a glass of<lb/>
cracked ice and shaved himself in the most approved style. What do you think<lb/>
of such an outburst of energy? Pretty good for a man who isn't much of a sailor:<lb/>
The day passed off beautifully yesterday. Delicious breezes, slightly clouded<lb/>
skies, and a fringe of green on the starboard side of Florida's coast. We did<lb/>
not leave it till late in the afternoon, and even after night came on we still<lb/>
saw its bright houses so that I did not feel so very far from our dear home<lb/>
and its precious inhabitants. We sat on deck till 10:30 P. M. Saw a steamer<lb/>
with all lights set, making for a Northern port, on one side and a U. S.<lb/>
Revenue Cutter, with her big search light, on the other, looking for smugglers<lb/>
along the Florida Keys. I then went below and by means of an electric fan<lb/>
and a wind scoop, in each of our two port-holes, managed to woo a good breeze<lb/>
which stayed with us the whole night, so that we slept well and both feel<lb/>
<add>should be June 25</add><lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f04934053"/>
-4-<lb/>
refreshed this morning! The sea is still very quiet so there is no motion<lb/>
to our ship. The weather is warmer than at our dear little mountain home,<lb/>
and I expect we will find it still warmer when we reach the shore. We expect<lb/>
to enter the Harbor about 10 A. M., and I am so anxious to get my letter in the<lb/>
12 o'clock mail, in which case my darling wife and daughter will get it by<lb/>
Thursday evening. How is every thing at our darling little home. I know<lb/>
the strawberries must be at their best and the pansies and asters are just<lb/>
blooming. I would give a dollar for a glass of that delicious water! 9:15 A. M.<lb/>
Moro Castle is just sighted, so that we will be at anchor about 11 A. M. The<lb/>
Cuban coast is looming up very prettily and I must bring my &ldquo;efforts&rdquo; to a<lb/>
close. We will report to General Leonard Wood this forenoon, and then go out<lb/>
to Quemados this afternoon. I am very well. Love and a thousand kisses to<lb/>
my precious girls.&rdquo;</p>
<p>An outline of the camp and raising of money needed for their experi-<lb/>
ments is well told in a paper written by General Jefferson Randolph Kean, one<lb/>
of my father's closest friends:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The yellow fever board, or commission as it is usually called,<lb/>
was created by War Department order, May 24, 1900, and was composed of Maj.<lb/>
Walter Reed and three acting assistant surgeons--James Carroll, Aristides<lb/>
Agramonte, and Jesse W. Lazear. The two latter were already on duty in Cuba<lb/>
when Reed arrived there on June 25.</p>
<p>A severe epidemic was in progress in Habana and at the neighboring<lb/>
town of Marianao, where Gen. Fitzhugh Lee has his headquarters. He was in<lb/>
command of the two Provinces of Habana and Pinar del Rio which include the<lb/>
western and of the island, but the city of Habana was excepted from his<lb/>
command and was under another general. Major Gorgas was the health officer<lb/>
of the city, and I was the chief surgeon of General Lee's Command, and had<lb/>
sanitary control of the outside country. I had been taken with yellow fever<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f04934054"/>
-5-<lb/>
on June 21 and was ill when Reed landed on the morning of June 25, and he<lb/>
hastened to visit me in the hospital at Camp Columbia. It pleases me to think<lb/>
that in my person he saw the first case of the dread disease with which his<lb/>
fame will be forever associated. The board was given quarters and laboratory<lb/>
space in a barrack-like wooden building belonging to the hospital and some<lb/>
half mile from General Lee's headquarters....</p>
<p>Reed was called back to the United States during the first week in<lb/>
August on account of the death of Doctor Shakespeare, to put in order the<lb/>
manuscripts of the typhoid fever board and the experiments began in his absence. . . .</p>
<p>I had at that time returned from a short sick leave in the States and<lb/>
was chief surgeon at Gen. Fitzhugh Lee's headquarters. When Reed mentioned to me<lb/>
on October 11 his intention to go to Habana next day to get General Wood's per-<lb/>
mission to go to the United States, I offered to get transportation and take<lb/>
him down. Accordingly, through the courtesy of the adjutant General, Major<lb/>
Michie, I got permission to use General Lee's find horses and carriage, and so<lb/>
we drove down in great style. When we were on the road I urged him to ask<lb/>
General Wood for a considerable sum of money to pay the expenses of a series of<lb/>
experiments and give liberal bonuses to Spanish immigrants who I was sure<lb/>
could be induced in that way to volunteer, especially as they came to Cuba with<lb/>
always the probability of having yellow fever. He did not commit himself as<lb/>
to what he would do, and I awaited the interview with keen interest.</p>
<p>General Wood received us graciously, as he knew us both well and had<lb/>
taken a course of study under Reed. They stood facing each other in the<lb/>
embrasure of a window of the palace looking out on the Plaza de las Armas and<lb/>
to me, a silent observer, it was a most dramatic scene with all the setting of<lb/>
a great historic moment. Looking out between them I could see Morro Castle<lb/>
and the blue waters of the harbor and on our left the ancient Fort la Fuerza,<lb/>
built by the gallant De Soto before he sailed northward to find his grave in<lb/>
the turbid current of the Mississippi. The two men offered a singular contrast<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f04934055"/>
-6-<lb/>
in their appearance. General Wood, massive, leonine, impassive; Reed, slender,<lb/>
alert, with mobile features and sparkling blue eyes as he told the story of the<lb/>
three cases and summed up the evidence. Then, after a moment's pause he said<lb/>
very earnestly, &ldquo;General Wood, will you give me $10,000 to continue and complete<lb/>
these experiments?&rdquo; General Wood's reply came almost without hesitation--&ldquo;I<lb/>
have this morning signed a warrant for that amount to aid the police in the<lb/>
capture of criminals, and surely this work is of more importance to Cuba than<lb/>
the catching of a few thieves. I will give you $10,000 and if that proves<lb/>
insufficient I will give you $10,000 more.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We said good day to the military governor and with joyous hearts<lb/>
betook ourselves to the Paris restaurant, were we celebrated this happy<lb/>
outcome with a good luncheon, and I pledged his success and future fame with<lb/>
a bottle of Rioja Clarete. . .</p>
<p>When Reed applied for the promised money, General Wood told him that<lb/>
he would place it for disbursement in Kean's hands, as he was an officer permanently<lb/>
on duty there and Reed would be saved the worry of it. So this was done, and I<lb/>
acquired in a subordinate and business way a connection with this famous board.</p>
<p>The building of his experimental station, Camp Lazear, where the<lb/>
tests should be made was at once begun, and Spanish immigrants were readily<lb/>
found who for a handsome sum were willing to be bitten by the &ldquo;little Flies,&rdquo;<lb/>
and if they were taken sick to be nursed by the senioritas Americanas, as they<lb/>
called the nurses. A most dramatic episode of this period was the volunteering<lb/>
of Moran and Kissinger to be the first victims of the experimentation.<lb/>
Kissinger was in fact the first case--a noble offer which has been often and<lb/>
fully told. These were followed by other American soldiers from the Hospital<lb/>
Corps, so that between the Americans and the Spaniards the supply of subjects<lb/>
for experiment was ample. The Spaniards furnished Reed much amusement,<lb/>
especially a jolly young Spaniard peasant named Antonio Benigno, but whom Reed<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f04934056"/>
-7-<lb/>
called Boniato, which means a sweet potato, on account of his fondness for<lb/>
that vegetable. His contract with Reed in Spanish, signed by both, hangs on<lb/>
the wall of my office. He was first to recover, and when I took his reward<lb/>
to him I got it in $10 and $20 gold pices. The poor Spaniard had never seen<lb/>
such great coins or so much money, and his joy was that of a child with a new<lb/>
toy.</p>
<p>On July 8, 1900, father writes the following letter to mother:</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba</p>
<p>I felt certain that when you read that paragraph about yellow fever<lb/>
at Quemados, in the Evening Star paper, you would cut it out and send it to me,<lb/>
and ask what in the world it meant! I have said nothing about yellow fever,<lb/>
because I didn't want to give you any worry, especially as I wasn't myself<lb/>
taking any risks whatever. There have been two or three cases in Quemados<lb/>
since our arrival. One a member of the Hospital Corps, and another a female<lb/>
nurse, both of whom were nursing Mrs. Edmonds, who was down with the disease<lb/>
in an infected house in Quemados. These cases are now convalescing. Dr. Kean<lb/>
is over his attack and should be in New Jersey by this time, as he left Havana<lb/>
several days ago. Dr. Carroll and I have been studying some cultures which<lb/>
were made from the blood of yellow fever, but there isn't a particle of danger<lb/>
in this. Please don't pay any attention to anything you see in the papers.<lb/>
I couldn't be in a safer place on the Island than in Camp Columbia. By<lb/>
General Lee's order, all Americans had already moved out of Quemados before we<lb/>
got here. No soldier is allowed to enter the town, and no case has occurred<lb/>
here for about two weeks. The last, I am told was that of a Spanish boy who<lb/>
lived about two miles from here. When I get the disease, I promise that a<lb/>
cablegram shall be promptly sent you. In the meanwhile, please don't worry one<lb/>
particle. We are not going into infected houses, nor to see patients with the<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f04934057"/>
-8-<lb/>
disease. We will confine our work to material that Dr. Argomonte brings us.<lb/>
At present there are about a dozen cases in Havana, but none of them at our<lb/>
disposal. So please rest easy as far as I am concerned. So you think, sweet-<lb/>
heart that I get up too early? Well, I go to bed so early and the mornings<lb/>
are so beautiful that I can't resist the temptation. You mustn't forget that<lb/>
we have breakfast at 7 A. M. ! I am trying to get my laboratories in as good<lb/>
shape as possible. When I return watch out or I'll be out cutting asparagus<lb/>
at five in the morning!</p>
<p>Camp Columbia<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba<lb/>
July 13, 1900</p>
<p>I wrote to little daughter, on yesterday, her birthday. I thought<lb/>
of you both a great deal and wondered how you were spending the day. I hope<lb/>
very pleasantly. You observe, dear Miss Wind-beaten Farmer Lady, that I am not<lb/>
writing at 5:30 A. M. but at 2:30 P. M. That very early rising did pretty<lb/>
well for a week or so, but I found that it didn't enable me to accomplish any<lb/>
more than by the old system of getting up at 6:45. I retire at 9:30. Break-<lb/>
fast at 7:30 and get to the laboratory, distance about 75 yards, say at 8:15<lb/>
A. M. Where I stay till 11:30 and then come home for lunch. Have I ever<lb/>
described my quarters to you? I really can't remember that I have done so. I<lb/>
have two rooms each 10 by 15 and a partition about 71&sol;2 feet high, so as to have<lb/>
good circulation of air. My front room looks north to the sea. A large door,<lb/>
and good size windows with glass sash and heavy wooden shutters. The rear<lb/>
rooms have only wodden shutters. In my front room, I have a long wooden table,<lb/>
stretching nearly across the room, which answers for my writing desk, and for<lb/>
official papers. Here also sits my lamp. On the other side is a long shelf<lb/>
on which I put my books. In the back I have a good hospital bed with mosquito<lb/>
bar and a small wooden table for my wash stand, good shelves for my under-<lb/>
clothes and a place for my clothes to hang. With a couple of comfortable<lb/>
folding chairs, you thus see, that I am living quite like a bachel<del>l</del>or, and that<lb/>
as my wants are few, I cannot complain of a lack of necessary comforts. Dr.<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f04934058"/>
-9-<lb/>
Carroll, Lazear, and I went in on the 7 P. M. train to Havana in order to pay<lb/>
our respects to General Wood and came out on the 9 P. M. getting home in time<lb/>
for my &ldquo;early to bed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Camp Columbia<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba<lb/>
July 19, 1900</p>
<p>Yesterday, we had the pleasure of entertaining Drs. Durleam and<lb/>
Myers, two English physicians, who have been sent out by the school of Tropical<lb/>
Medicine to study yellow fever. They are going to Brazil, and came down to<lb/>
Havana just to make our acquaintance, and to ascertain what, if anything we had<lb/>
discovered. I enjoyed meeting them very much, as they were two of the most<lb/>
typical Englishmen one could possibly meet. We have placed our laboratories<lb/>
at their disposal during the ten days they will be in Havana. I send my sweet<lb/>
Farmer lady a little sweetpea which grows in large numbers on the Parade. They<lb/>
look very pretty in the early morning. I hope ours are doing well and giving<lb/>
pretty bouquets for the center table. Now I wish that some of the nice rain<lb/>
that is falling this afternoon, could be sprinkling down on your garden and<lb/>
lawn. We have splendid showers nearly every afternoon and could spare lots of<lb/>
moisture for the drier parts of the earth. Some of the storms which pass out at<lb/>
sea, a few miles from the shore, are superbly grand: The play of lightning is<lb/>
something wonderful to see. Last evening just before dinner we took a drive<lb/>
over the new Military road to Vedado and were chased home by a storm coming<lb/>
from sea-ward. This morning we will drive out to Havana in order to return the<lb/>
call of our English conferers, who are stopping at La Florida Hotel. While there<lb/>
I must go to the Chief quartermaster's office and find out when the next trans-<lb/>
port will leave for New York. I have heard that one would leave on July 25th,<lb/>
which would bring it here July 30th. If so I would probably sail the next day<lb/>
and reach New York about August 4th. Wouldn't that be jolly? I hope it is so,<lb/>
as I want to see my precious children so soon again.</p>
<p><add>Durham? yes - but<lb/>
(apparently Reed's recall was NOT a hurried affair PSH)<lb/>
This is my impression too - apparently he asked for it <unclear>lw</unclear></add></p>
<pb n="10" id="f04934059"/>
<p>-10-</p>
<p>Camp Columbia<lb/>
July 30, 1900</p>
<p>I packed my trunk this afternoon and took it to Havana in order to<lb/>
have it and its contents thoroughly disinfected preparatory to boarding the<lb/>
Transport Rawlines, on Wednesday. You never say anything like the care with<lb/>
which every piece of wearing apparel is subjected to steam or Formalin, for<lb/>
fear that yellow jack may be conveyed to the United States. Of course, it was<lb/>
absurd to disinfect my baggage, but no exceptions are made. Wednesday morning<lb/>
the contents of my valise will also be put in the big sterilizer. We will reach<lb/>
New York, Monday 6th, and be held over in quarantine till Tuesday afternoon.<lb/>
After visions of fried chicken and waffles, I simply had to turn into bed so as<lb/>
to hurry Tuesday along as much as possible. Those pansies that my darling wife<lb/>
sent me were very sweet and pretty, and I appreciate them so much. But I am<lb/>
more anxious to see them with my own eyes as they grow at our dear country home.<lb/>
Tomorrow or next day I will begin my homeward sea voyage, and I hope without<lb/>
being very sea sick this time. Adios: He returned to Cuba early in October.<lb/>
He writes from the Transport:</p>
<p>Havana Harbor<lb/>
Monday Afternoon,<lb/>
5 P. M.</p>
<p>We have just passed the El Morro, Cabanas and several other Spanish<lb/>
fortifications and are now at anchor near the floating dry dock. The city of<lb/>
Havana from the shore is certainly very beautiful, but as I write I see the<lb/>
wreck of the Maine not more than 400 yards away, and it makes my very blood<lb/>
boil. The whole Island wasn't worth the loss of those brave men and that<lb/>
gallant ship. Our journey down was very pleasant, but your old husband couldn't<lb/>
stand the motion of the ship. I ate quite a hearty dinner, but half an hour<lb/>
later, that dinner was lost forever! Friday I passed a miserable day but better<lb/>
Saturday and Sunday. Everybody aboard the ship was as kind as possible, but that<lb/>
<add>? Rawlins<lb/>
Insert see over<lb/>
Should be Oct 3, 1900 PSH</add></p>
<pb n="11" id="f04934060"/>
<p><unclear>C<hi rend="subscript">1</hi><lb/>
B<hi rend="subscript">3</hi></unclear></p>
<p>Don't forget the fried chicken character &amp; hot waffles!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Father returned the early part of August to<lb/>
<unclear>Washington</unclear> so that he might complete a report with<lb/>
Drs Vaughan &amp; Shakespeare <unclear>upon</unclear> &ldquo;Typhoid<lb/>
fever in the Army&rdquo;. He returned to Cuba early in<lb/>
October ---- etc</p>
<pb n="12" id="f04934061"/>
<p>-11-<lb/>
couldn't remove that everlasting <hi rend="underline">goneness</hi>! I have made up my mind that I am<lb/>
not a good sailor! The Harbor here is very pretty with the ships of the various<lb/>
nations, at anchor, and the little Cuban sailboats gliding here and there. The<lb/>
surrounding hills are very graceful and pretty. Coming in from the sea, the<lb/>
shore line and interior was very striking with its fringe of green and blue<lb/>
mountains; but again I see the wreck of the Maine. Certainly every American ship<lb/>
that enters this Harbor, should sail around the wreck, dip its colors and fire<lb/>
a salute! I never saw anything that so touched my inner nature, as the sight of<lb/>
those bare ribs of iron and her foremast sticking out of the water. What a<lb/>
monument our countrymen should place there! Well, we will go ashore <hi rend="underline">tomorrow</hi><lb/>
and I will expect to see our dear boy. I am so anxious to see him again. The<lb/>
boat that takes the mail is along side and I must close my letter.</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba<lb/>
October 6, 1900</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now you mustn't have any fear about my being here <hi rend="underline">now</hi> any more than<lb/>
you did in <hi rend="underline">June</hi>, for there is much less danger <hi rend="underline">now</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Then</hi> we had an epidemic<lb/>
next door to us, <hi rend="underline">now</hi> it's no nearer than Havana, 6 miles away. Honestly,<lb/>
lovie dear, could you ever have respected and loved me if I had proved myself to<lb/>
be a moral coward? I don't believe when you come to consider the matter care-<lb/>
fully, but that you will yet say that I did the right and proper thing.<lb/>
Certainly my conscience would have never rested easily. Dr. Lazear contracted<lb/>
the disease at the yellow fever hospital in Havana by letting an infected<lb/>
mosquito bite him. He saw the insect on his hand and deliberately let it get its<lb/>
fill of blood in order to test our theory. Five days later he had his chill,<lb/>
followed by high fever. His case was a very severe one from the beginning, his<lb/>
death occurring on the sixth day thereafter. He was a splendid brave fellow and<lb/>
I lament his loss more than words can tell, but his death was not in vain. His<lb/>
name will live in history of those who have benefited humanity. The dangerous<lb/>
part of the work is now over and there is no need for you, my sweetheart, to<lb/>
continue to worry about me.&rdquo;<lb/>
<add>&rarr; this was Oct 4 1900<lb/>
25 July 6&sol;19<unclear><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></unclear></add></p>
<pb n="13" id="f04934062"/>
<p>-12-</p>
<p>In December, he writes of his first case of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks, Quemados, Cuba<lb/>
December 9, 1900</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is with a great deal of pleasure that I hasten to tell you that we<lb/>
have succeeded in producing a case of unmistakable yellow fever by the bite of the<lb/>
mosquito. Our first case in the experiment camp developed at 11:30 last night,<lb/>
commencing with a sudden chill followed by fever. He had been bitten at 11:30<lb/>
December 5th, and hence his attack followed just three and a half days after<lb/>
the bite. As he had been in our camp 15 days before being inoculated and had<lb/>
had no other possible exposure, the case is as clear as the sun at noon-day and<lb/>
sustains brilliantly and conclusively our conclusions. Thus, just 18 days from<lb/>
the time we began our experimental work, we have succeeded in demonstrating this<lb/>
mode of propagation of the disease, so that the most doubtful and sceptical must<lb/>
yield. Rejoice with me, sweetheart, as, aside from the antitoxin of diphtheria<lb/>
and Koch's discovery of the tubercle bacillus, it will be regarded as the most<lb/>
important piece of work, scientifically, during the 19th century. I do not<lb/>
exaggerate, and I could shout for very joy that heaven has permitted me to<lb/>
establish this wonderful way of propagating yellow fever. It was Finlay's theory,<lb/>
and he deserves great credit for having suggested it, but as he did nothing to<lb/>
prove it, it was rejected by all, including General Sternberg. Now we have put<lb/>
it beyond cavil, and its importance to Cuba and the United States cannot be<lb/>
estimated. Major Kean says that the discovery is worth more than the cost of<lb/>
the Spanish War, including l<del>o</del><add>i</add>ves lost and money expended. He is almost beside<lb/>
himself with joy and will tell General Wood when he goes to town in the morning.<lb/>
Tomorrow afternoon we will have the Havana Board of Experts, Drs. Guiteras,<lb/>
Albertini, and Finlay, come out and diagnose the case. I shan't tell them how<lb/>
the infection was acquired until after they have satisfied themselves concerning<lb/>
the character of the case, then I will let them know. I suppose that old Dr.<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f04934063"/>
-13-<lb/>
Finlay will be delighted beyond bounds, as he will see his theory at last fully<lb/>
vindicated. 9:30 P. M. Since writing the above our patient has been doing well.<lb/>
His temperature, which was 102.5 degrees at noon, has fallen to 101 degrees, and<lb/>
his severe headache and backache have subsided considerably. Everything points,<lb/>
as far as it can at this stage, to a favourable termination, for which I feel so<lb/>
happy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Two days later he writes:</p>
<p>December 11, 1900</p>
<p>&ldquo;Our patient, concerning whom I wrote you in my last, is doing very<lb/>
well. We had Dr. John Guiteras, Dr. Finlay, and Dr. Albertini out here to see<lb/>
him yesterday afternoon. They were all immensely interested and Dr. Albertini<lb/>
did not hesitate to say &ldquo;yellow fever.&rdquo; The others too regarded the case as one<lb/>
of probable yellow fever, but desired to see how his temperature and pulse would<lb/>
run during the next few dyas. Dr. Amador, an<del>d</del> expert in yellow fever, says the<lb/>
disease is undoubtedly yellow fever. Of course, I can't blame anyone from with-<lb/>
holding a diagnosis until they are satisfied, but from my standpoint it is very<lb/>
amusing. The case is as plain as the nose on a man's face, but as Dr. -----<lb/>
has pronounced in an interview our theory as being very &ldquo;wild and improbable,&rdquo;<lb/>
of course he wants to be &ldquo;let down easy,&rdquo; for he must surrender. He will come<lb/>
round in a few days. Dr. Gorgas also saw the patient and pronounced the case as<lb/>
so suspicious that had it occurred in Havana he would not have hesitated to send<lb/>
him to the yellow fever hospital. Ah! wonderful is nature, and I thank God<lb/>
that he has allowed poor unworthy me to look a little way into this secret.<lb/>
Six months ago, when we landed on this island, absolutely nothing was known<lb/>
concerning the propagation and spread of yellow fever--it was all an unfathomable<lb/>
mystery--but today the curtain has been drawn--its mode of propagation is<lb/>
established and we know that a case minus mosquitoes is no more dangerous than<lb/>
one of chills and fever! Hurrah! I will write to Dr.----- is a few days about<lb/>
<add>who?<lb/>
who</add><lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f04934064"/>
-14-<lb/>
the case. Of course he will at once write an article to say that for 20 years<lb/>
he has considered the mosquito as the most probable cause of yellow fever. That<lb/>
would be just in order for him to do. Dr. ----- of the Marine Service has written<lb/>
a very discourteous reply to our Preliminary Note in the same Journal that our<lb/>
article appeared in. . . . Dr. Cobb, of the same service, has also written a<lb/>
very courteous and interesting answer to our paper, in which he proves to his own<lb/>
satisfaction that the mosquito can't possibly propagate the disease, and says<lb/>
that it would be dreadful after all the years of disinfection that his service<lb/>
has done if this theory should be what we have claimed for it. And so the ball<lb/>
rolls on!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba<lb/>
December 14, 1900</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was kept so busy yesterday, I could not get an opportunity to write<lb/>
to my precious invalid. In the first place the occurrence of a second case of<lb/>
yellow fever in our camp within three and a half days of the bite of a mosquito,<lb/>
made me of course very happy. This time one of the Spaniards was its victim.<lb/>
This is his second day and I am glad to say that he is doing very well. Our<lb/>
first case, the brave young soldier, we consider out of danger. Drs. Guiteras,<lb/>
Finlay, and Albertini have pronounced both cases to be unmistakable yellow fever.<lb/>
Of course they could not do otherwise, as the symptoms and cause of the disease<lb/>
are absolutely characteristic. Tonight a third case promises to develop, as<lb/>
his temperature is 104 4&sol;5 degrees already. He began to complain on yesterday,<lb/>
his fifth day, just as X. Y. did, and I feel certain that his symptoms will be<lb/>
better developed tomorrow. As we have only bitten five individuals so far and<lb/>
it is too early to speak of one of them yet, me thinks we are doing pretty well<lb/>
for this season of the year. So far our men in the infected clothing building<lb/>
are well and hearty, and as they have spent fourteen nights, therein, we feel<lb/>
encouraged accordingly. To say that Dr. Guiteras and other physicians are<lb/>
profoundly impressed is to express the situation very mildly. You can imagine,<lb/>
<add>who? <unclear>Wasdin</unclear>, probably</add>
<pb n="16" id="f04934065"/>
-15-<lb/>
my sweetheart, how happy I feel over this absolute demonstration of our con-<lb/>
clusions. Nothing could be more satisfactory and the results have been obtained<lb/>
sooner than we had hoped for. I shall now write to General Sternberg, and tell<lb/>
him of the good news as I know, he too, will be greatly delighted. You might<lb/>
just mention to anyone that we feel very much encouraged! Today has been 83 degrees<lb/>
in the shade, can you beat that for December.</p>
<p>Camp Columbia, Cuba<lb/>
December 16, 1900</p>
<p>Here I sit writing with the thermometer at 75 degrees at 9 P. M. I<lb/>
couldn't possibly find time to write yesterday. The day was so busily occupied<lb/>
with the affairs of our experimental station that I was kept on the jump all day long.<lb/>
I had to smile at the advice that my darling wife was giving me about not trying<lb/>
to experiment now, but to postpone until next summer, &ldquo;when the mosquitoes have<lb/>
more vigor.&rdquo; When I read that, our fourth man's eyes were getting redder and his<lb/>
temperature higher, and as far as I was able to judge, the insect appeared to be<lb/>
getting in his work very well! What do you think of that for winter experimentation?<lb/>
Four out of five inoculated coming down promptly? Oh! my! but the last week has<lb/>
been an eventful one for your old husband! And what is perfectly delightful, the<lb/>
first three may be considered out of danger, while the fourth only sick 24 hours<lb/>
is doing as well as could be expected at this stage of the disease. This morning,<lb/>
we again had the experts out from Havana, and it was very amusing to see our three<lb/>
Spaniards all in a row as it were, occupying their three beds, and looking (at<lb/>
least two of them) quite contented over the near prospect of $200.00 in good<lb/>
American gold. Our experiments have opened the eyes of all around. I sent a cable<lb/>
to General Sternburg, yesterday, and another today. I should not be surprised if<lb/>
he fell out of his chair! I wonder if the good news has made my precious wife<lb/>
better! I am so anxious to hear. My that last letter was as blue as indigo! How<lb/>
could I talk or arrange about coming home, my darling, when I had my hands so<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f04934066"/>
-16-<lb/>
very full of most important work? Indeed, I don't want to come here next summer,<lb/>
if I can possibly get out of it. I had much rather finish now and have done with<lb/>
it. As the matter stands now, I don't see how I can possibly finish my present<lb/>
work till the last of next month, and then comes the Pan American Medical Congress<lb/>
which meets February 5th. We should certainly present a short report to the<lb/>
Congress, as it would be of the highest importance to do so. Several hundred<lb/>
physicians from South American, Mexico, and many prominent men from the United<lb/>
States will be here, and I am sure that we should not lose the opportunity of<lb/>
bringing to their prompt attention these most important observations on yellow<lb/>
fever. The paper will attract more attention than any other that will be presented.<lb/>
I say this in all modesty. It's even more important to have ascertained how this<lb/>
disease is propogated than to find the parasite that causes it. Our observations<lb/>
completely revolutionize the opinions heretofore held on the subject, and must<lb/>
be of the greatest benefit to the United States and to this Island. Americans<lb/>
will no longer dread to come here, now that they will know how to avoid the<lb/>
infection. It makes me very unhappy to know that my sweet wife is so wretched mentally<lb/>
and physically. If I could leave tomorrow, I would gladly do so, but common sense<lb/>
and my judgment tell me not to do so. Monday morning--17th. Dr. Ames has just<lb/>
reported that our fourth case is doing splendidly, temperature has fallen to 99 3&sol;5<lb/>
degrees. Isn't that glorious? Four cases and no deaths, but my sweet wife said<lb/>
that they would all die, and that the country would turn against me and that I<lb/>
would be everlastingly disgraced! &ldquo;Go long,&rdquo; my darling, and stop trying to make<lb/>
your old husband come home! I am going to see General Wood this morning with<lb/>
Major Kean, in order to tell him concerning our success. Some how, or other, I<lb/>
feel very happy this morning and wish that you and little daughter were here.&rdquo;</p>
<p>After father's very affectionate endings to all of his letters, he never<lb/>
failed in one of them to send a kiss to my much adored cat.</p>
<pb n="18" id="f04934067"/>
<p>-17-</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba<lb/>
December 18, 1900</p>
<p>&ldquo;I got two long and very sweet letters from my darling &ldquo;Miss Invalid,&rdquo;<lb/>
yesterday, and read them as I rode out to the experimental station, and how I laughed<lb/>
over them! Not exactly over the one of the twelfth of December--for that letter<lb/>
was a sort of doleful contribution to epistolary composition, but over the second<lb/>
one of the 13th, which was written after you had read of our success with &ldquo;los<lb/>
mosquitos,&rdquo; and which was a very, very sweet letter indeed. If my sweet wife and<lb/>
my precious daughter are proud of me, then I don't care much what the rest of the<lb/>
world thinks. You would have been delighted, indeed, had you been here, this<lb/>
afternoon when we had sixteen of Havana's chief physicians out to see and examine<lb/>
our yellow fever cases. It was to me extremely interesting to see how cauticus they<lb/>
were, at first, for some of them came, evidently already much prejudiced; but as<lb/>
the examination went on, they were compelled to admit, and did after awhile admit<lb/>
that the cases were none other than genuine yellow fever. Just one of the sixteen<lb/>
thought that perhaps our mildest case was doubtful, but the other fifteen<lb/>
acknowledged that the four cases were cases of yellow fever. Our last case, which<lb/>
was taken sick December 15th was just entering his fourth day, and was so plain that<lb/>
it could not be disputed. It was indeed a great victory for us. As they left the<lb/>
ward and indeed while there, you never heard such talking! La <unclear>lingua</unclear> es-panola<lb/>
had free vent for once! Our last case is quite sick, but I think he will pull<lb/>
through alright. Now that the mental strain of the past few weeks, is over, I<lb/>
feel splendidly and &ldquo;sleep like a top!&rdquo; I am now taking it very slowly and<lb/>
enjoying every day. The recovery of my purposely made sick patients has naturally<lb/>
made me feel happy and more thankful than I can express. Just to think that<lb/>
Christmas is almost here. How the time fairly flies! December will be gone<lb/>
before we know it. From the bottom of my heart father wishes his darling wife<lb/>
and daughter a merry, merry Christmas and a happy, happy New Year.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="19" id="f04934068"/>
<p>-18-</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks<lb/>
December 23, 1900</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yesterday I received your darling letter and was so delighted to hear<lb/>
that you are &ldquo;feeling well again.&rdquo; Last evening I attended quite a swell banquet<lb/>
in Havana given to Dr. Finlay by some seventy or eighty physicians of Havana.<lb/>
It was a very recherche affair and extremely enjoyable. Everything was in Spanish.<lb/>
The Governor General was there. The toasts were all in Spanish and the speeches,<lb/>
while flattering to Dr. Finlay, for his conception of the theory, gave us full<lb/>
credit for the discovery. It is to me surprising and extremely satisfactory<lb/>
to see how very quickly the profession of Havana have accepted our results. I<lb/>
have seen in the Washington Post, General Sternberg's statement about the cablegram<lb/>
from me. I suppose that the Post will now have another silly editorial on the<lb/>
subject. I have allowed the men who have spent twenty nights in our infected<lb/>
clothing house to come out, and they are now in quarantine. Two other soldiers<lb/>
are now occupying the house and sleeping not only in the same beds and between the<lb/>
same sheets on which our yellow fever patients have rested during their attacks, but<lb/>
they sleep in the <hi rend="underline">very shirts</hi> that our patients wore throughout their entire sickeness!<lb/>
If anything should give them the disease, this should succeed! Don't you think so?<lb/>
Infected clothing and bedding has been a horrible nightmare during these past three<lb/>
hundred years, but me thinks it will die out very early in the next century!<lb/>
Yellow fever can no more be transmitted in that way than can Intermittent fever! How<lb/>
General Sternberg and hosts of others could have believed in the contagiousness of<lb/>
clothing, I cannot possibly see. They are simply accepting the statements of others<lb/>
who had nothing on which to base such statements. A little careful testing of this<lb/>
theory has served to knock it completely into smithereens. I thank God that I did<lb/>
not accept anybody's opinion on this subject, but determined to put it to a<lb/>
thorough test with human beings in order to see what would happen. My own observations<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f04934069"/>
-19-<lb/>
at Pinar del Rio convinced me that infected bedding was indeed a myth. Actual<lb/>
trial has proven that I was right and that what the medical profession believed<lb/>
was wrong! So you have dared to send me a fruit cake, how sweet of my dearest<lb/>
wife to think of her Mr. Mosquito! I shall be glad when Christmas has come and<lb/>
gone and New Year has come, for then only a few weeks will elapse before I can turn<lb/>
my face homeward to my precious girls, whom I want to see more than words can<lb/>
tell.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks, Cuba<lb/>
December 26,</p>
<p>&ldquo;And now I must tell you something about my latest experiment and how<lb/>
it is turning out. You already know that I have constructed two houses. Each 14<lb/>
by 20 feet. Both tightly sealed inside, and so screened both as to windows and by<lb/>
double doors that no flying insect can get either in, if he comes from the outside;<lb/>
or out, if he or she is once put within. Building number one has only one large<lb/>
room. In this my nonimmune individuals sleep every evening and by day rest in a<lb/>
tent nearby and take things calmly. Dr. Cooke and two hospital Corps men have just<lb/>
come out of quarantine. After spending twenty nights in Building number one in the<lb/>
midst of very much soiled yellow fever bedding. Two other young Americans are<lb/>
now sleeping there in beds and clothing that our yellow fever cases have just<lb/>
vacated. So much for building number one. Building number two stands across a<lb/>
little valley or depression about eighty yards from number one. The room 14 by<lb/>
20 feet is not only sealed but is lined throughout with cheese cloth, so as to be<lb/>
very tight. It has two fixed fine wire screen windows and is protected by double<lb/>
wire screen doors so that when one enters, he first opens a solid door, and then<lb/>
finds himself in a small vestibule. Next he opens a wire screen door swung on spring<lb/>
hinges and finds himself in a second vestibule. Having closed this door behind him,<lb/>
he now opens a second screendoor and finds himself in the room proper. This room<lb/>
is divided entirely across from floor to ceiling and from wall to wall by a wire screen,<lb/>
<add>Should n't this be Dec 25-</add><lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f04934070"/>
-20-<lb/>
so that there is a larger room 15 by 14 the &ldquo;mosquito&rdquo; or &ldquo;infected&rdquo; room, as<lb/>
I call it and a smaller room 10 by 14 the non-infected room. This latter is entered<lb/>
by an entirely separate door, whereas the &ldquo;infected&rdquo; room can only be entered through<lb/>
the screen doors before mentioned. On the 21st at 11:35 A. M., we liberated 15<lb/>
infected mosquitoes in the large room, and at 11:55 A. M., a young American entered<lb/>
the room and lay on the bed marked &ldquo;A&rdquo; for thirty minutes during which time several<lb/>
mosquitoes bit him. I stood with Dr. Carroll and Dr. Ames on the other side of<lb/>
the screen at the place marked &ldquo;B&rdquo; and saw the insect light and begin work within<lb/>
five minutes from the time he entered. The same afternoon at 4:15 o'clock, he again<lb/>
went in and was again bitten, remained twenty minutes. Bed marked &ldquo;B&rdquo; is being<lb/>
occupied by a non-immune who sleeps within one foot of the screen, breathing the<lb/>
same air as in room with bed &ldquo;A&rdquo; (infected room). This young non-immune is quite<lb/>
well, but the young fellow who went in on the 21st was suddenly <hi>stricken today</hi> at<lb/>
noon, (just <hi>four days</hi> after he entered and was bitten) with a sharp attack of what<lb/>
promises to be yellow fever! The board of experts will see him tomorrow and make<lb/>
their diagnosis. His temperature, this evening, is 104 degrees and all his<lb/>
symptoms point plainly to yellow fever. Could any experiment be more striking?<lb/>
A common room, divided by a wire screen, and having the same air, infected on one<lb/>
side and not infected on the other side of the screen <unclear>!!</unclear> This, my darling, is what<lb/>
I call the &ldquo;argumentum ad hominem.&rdquo; Don't worry about the mosquitoes getting out<lb/>
for they are tightly locked and the key is in my pocket. About three days from<lb/>
now, I shall let a young Spaniard go in, and then no more. Non-immunes will<lb/>
continue to sleep on the other side every night! Don't tell this to anyone. I<lb/>
have not told anybody but your darling self. It won't be long before the year<lb/>
1900 will have passed. I can't say that I will be real sorry to have it go, since<lb/>
it has kept me away from my precious girls. I do hope I can be with you more in<lb/>
1901. I went to the Starke's to see the Christmas tree which Mrs. Stark<del>e</del> and Mrs.<lb/>
Kean had prepared for the children. In addition to presents for the children, there<lb/>
was a present for Dr. Kean, Dr. Stark<del>e</del>, Captain Slocum, Major Dunn, Dr. Allen, and<lb/>
myself. What do you suppose mine was? A big mosquito with these lines attached:<lb/>
<add>25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>?<lb/>
or 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>
25 according<lb/>
to Moran</add></p>
<pb n="22" id="f04934071"/>
<p>-21-</p>
<p>&ldquo;Over the plains of Cuba,<lb/>
Roams the mosquito wild<lb/>
No one can catch or tame her,<lb/>
For she is nature's child.<lb/>
With yellow jack she fills herself,<lb/>
And none her pleasure mar,<lb/>
Till Major Reed does capture her,<lb/>
And puts her in a jar!<lb/>
And now alas! for Culex<lb/>
She has our sympathy,<lb/>
For since the Major spotted her,<lb/>
She longs to be a flea!&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="23" id="f04934072"/>
<p>-22-</p>
<p>The reading of these lines by Mrs. Slocum &ldquo;brought down the house,&rdquo; and<lb/>
I had to accept Miss Culex with many blushes.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
December 28, 1900</p>
<p>&ldquo;If these holiday gayeties don't come to a cessation pretty soon, I for<lb/>
one will be completely used up! Last night we all went down to attend the Governor<lb/>
General's ball and didn't get home until one o'clock this morning. I wish that you<lb/>
could have been at the palace last night to have seen the style and dress of the<lb/>
Cuban ladies. They really looked very pretty and were dressed quite ele<del>v</del><add>g</add>antly.<lb/>
There must have been a thousand people there, making altogether a very brilliant<lb/>
scene. Music for dancing was furnished by a military band stationed in the park<lb/>
outside. I enjoyed watching the people as they passed in and out and especially the<lb/>
dancing of the Cubans. I met a good many people that I knew. Today, the morning<lb/>
was taken up with a visit from half a dozen doctors who wished to see our last<lb/>
case of yellow fever and to visit our camp. Am glad to say our patient is doing<lb/>
very well and promises to make a good recovery. I shall now begin on our paper for<lb/>
the Pan American Congress as I want plenty of time in which to write it. I don't<lb/>
know how I shall feel when I stand before an audience of several hundred foreigners,<lb/>
but guess that I can manage to hold my own. About one thousand are expected, but<lb/>
I don't think that so many will come. The days will soon pass by. Now that will<lb/>
bring me to you and little daughter.</p>
<p>December 31, 1900</p>
<p>&ldquo;There goes the nine o'clock gun, fired from Morro Castle. We hear<lb/>
it here very plainly on a quiet night as this is not only a quiet night, but it is<lb/>
a most beautiful moon-lit night, just such a one as we might have at our dear little<lb/>
mountain home in June, with the thermometer standing in my room at 77 degrees! It<lb/>
is impossible to think of such a balmy warm night as being the 31st of December!<lb/>
What a country for a heavenly climate this is! But I, also, hear the buglers<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f04934073"/>
-23-<lb/>
blowing tattoo, and I must check for a while this letter. Heaven be with you my<lb/>
precious girls, and with my dear boy, while the moon creeps on through the night!<lb/>
God keep them all well and give them happiness through the New Year! 11:50 P.M.,<lb/>
December 31, 1900. Only ten minutes of the old century remains, lovie dear. Here<lb/>
I have been sitting reading that most wonderful book, La Roche on yellow fever,<lb/>
written in 1853. Forty seven years later it has been permitted to me and my<lb/>
assistants to lift the impenetrable veil that has surrounded the causation of this<lb/>
most dreadful pest of humanity, and to put it on a rational and scientific basis.<lb/>
I thank God that this has been accomplished during the latter days of the old<lb/>
century! The prayer that has been mine for twenty or more years, that I might be<lb/>
permitted in some way or sometime to do something to alleviate human suffering<lb/>
has been answered. 12 o'clock, Midnight: A thousand happy New Years to my<lb/>
&check; precious, <hi rend="underline">thrice precious</hi> wife and daughter. Hark: there go the twenty four buglers<lb/>
all in concert. Sounding &ldquo;Taps&rdquo; for the old year! How beautifully it floats through<lb/>
the midnight air, and how appropriate. Good night my sweet joys, a thousand sweet<lb/>
dreams of father and dear brother! Kisses and love and love and kisses for my<lb/>
&check; precious, <hi rend="underline">thrice precious</hi> girls in these first minutes of the 20th century!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I regret that a number of letters written during January 1901 have been<lb/>
given away and father's last letter from Cuba is dated February 5, 1901:</p>
<p>Columbia Barracks<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba<lb/>
February 5, 1901</p>
<p>&ldquo;So you have really marked January off of your list! Well, so did I,<lb/>
sweetheart, and it makes me very happy to think that if all goes well and the ship<lb/>
isn't delayed by storms, I ought to be drawing very near to Washington by this<lb/>
time next week. My state room is all engaged and I have nothing to do but pack<lb/>
my trunk and say goodby to a few kind people and I am off for wife and baby bunting.<lb/>
<add>sic</add><lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f04934074"/>
-24-<lb/>
Today the paper was read and met with a most favorable reception. The attention<lb/>
during the reading was all I could have asked for and applause at its conclusion,<lb/>
long and hearty. A resolution expressive of the high appreciation in which our<lb/>
work was held, together with the thanks, was unanimously adopted. I received<lb/>
dozens of the warmest kind of hand shakes from Cuban, Spanish, Mexican, South<lb/>
American and North American Physicians, men whom I had not even met. The hall was<lb/>
crowded and even the doors packed with listeners. It was indeed a signal triumph<lb/>
for our work. But, sweetheart, I don't care for that, and I'm not going to forget<lb/>
&ldquo;when the boat sails,&rdquo; for I care more for what my sweet wife and daughter think<lb/>
and say, than for the applause of all the rest of the world! This will probably<lb/>
be the last letter before I leave this sunny island, and I'll get home almost as<lb/>
soon as this does. Take care of your darling selves, and meet me with a smile.&rdquo;</p>
<p>After his return to Washington, he devoted the greater part of his time<lb/>
in teaching as professor of bacteriology and clinical microscopy at the Army<lb/>
Medical School and professor of bacteriology and pathology at the Columbian Univer-<lb/>
sity. In the summer of 1902, Harvard University bestowed on him the honorary degree<lb/>
of <add>A. M.</add> M.A., and from the University of Michigan the degree of L.L.D. After an acute<lb/>
attack of appendicitis, he died on November 23, 1902. In Arlington, overlooking<lb/>
the Potomao River is his grave. On his tomb is a bronze tablet bearing the in-<lb/>
scription that was selected by the Surgeon General and his staff!</p>
<p>Walter Reed, M. D. of the University of Virginia.</p>
<p>A. M. of Harvard University,<lb/>
LL. D. of the University of Michigan,<lb/>
Professor of Bacteriology, Army Medical School<lb/>
and<lb/>
Columbian University, Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He gave to man control over that dreadful scourge, Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
