<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05808063">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, October 26, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05808063</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-10-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carroll, Mrs.George</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-10-26">October 26, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05808063</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, October 26, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench wants to meet Mrs. Carroll and show her photographs of the dedication of Camp Lazear. He also would like to make copies of some of James Carroll's manuscripts.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-10-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, October 26, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05808063"/>
<p><date value="1954-10-26">October 26, 1954</date>
Mrs. George S. H. Carroll<lb/>
2814 Rhode Island Avenue, N.E.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
My dear Mrs. Carroll:</p>
<p>I must attend medical meetings in Philadelphia on Saturday and Sunday,<lb/>
November 13 and 14 and must attend a committee meeting in Washington on<lb/>
November 12, probably in the morning, which would take about two hours.</p>
<p>I do hope that you will be home on November 12. I should like very much<lb/>
to do two things. First of all, I would like to bring my kodachromes of<lb/>
Camp Lazear and spend a half hour showing you these lovely colored pictures<lb/>
of the dedication of Camp Lazear and the honors to Doctor Carroll with<lb/>
photographs of his bronze plaque and so on. Secondly, I would like in<lb/>
particular to do this time what you very graciously said you would let me<lb/>
do the next time I came to Washington. Namely, that you and I would take<lb/>
just a few of the manuscripts that we laid aside in that small special<lb/>
package down to a photostat company and have them quickly copied. You and<lb/>
I can go together, perhaps Friday afternoon by taxi, to the company, stay<lb/>
with them for the half hour or so that it would require and then take the<lb/>
manuscripts right back to your house. I was so pleased when you told me<lb/>
last time that you had no objection to my doing this and I was so glad<lb/>
that your lawyer of the firm of Leckie and Sherier agreed that it was<lb/>
appropriate for you to let me do this.</p>
<p>I hope you received the letter I send you some time ago about your arthritis<lb/>
and I should be glad to talk to you about this further. Indeed, if you<lb/>
want me to do so, I can talk to Doctor Gibson. He very kindly wrote me in<lb/>
answer to my letter about you. He is very anxious to help you in any way<lb/>
possible and to cooperate with me or anyone else who might help you.</p>
<p>As you of course suggested, I have not written to your sisters-in-law<lb/>
yet or discussed with them in any way the material in your possession.<lb/>
For your convenience, I enclose a stamped envelope and a little memoran-<lb/>
dum which you can just check. I do hope this date is agreeable to you<lb/>
as it will be impossible for me to get to Washington again this year and<lb/>
of course I shall bring back to you the two or three photographs which you<lb/>
kindly loaned to me and which I have hesitated in consigning to the regular<lb/>
mail.</p>
<p>Sincerely yours,<lb/>
P. S. Hench, M.D.<lb/>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
P.S.: I have again written Doctor Gibson to see if there is any way in<lb/>
which we can assist you in getting full information about possible surgery.<lb/>
I have <hi>not</hi> contacted your lawyer, the one to whom I talked on the phone<lb/>
with your permission. I am sure that you will be gracious enough to let me<lb/>
copy the yellow fever data as you and your lawyer promised I could without<lb/>
any further prodding from him. As you say, if I wrote to him he might contact<lb/>
you and use that as an excuse to send you another bill.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05808064"/>
<p>Doctor Hench:</p>
<p>1. I can meet you Friday, November 12, presumably in the afternoon and<lb/>
go with you to a downtown photostat company.<lb/>
2. I understand that you are picking the name of a downtown photostat<lb/>
company to do this photostating and will go there with you.<lb/>
3. (Alternate to No. 2): If you have not made final arrangements with<lb/>
any photostat company, I suggest the ______________________ Company which<lb/>
I know about <unclear>and</unclear> which is recommended to me by my lawyer.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
