<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804042">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, July 24, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Ames, Jessie Daniel</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804042</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-07-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-07-24">July 24, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804042</idno>
<title>Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, July 24, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Jessie Ames writes that Hench may keep the fever charts as soon as she gets them back and can send them to him. She thinks the War Department does not have a complete dossier on her husband, and attributes this to carelessness.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-07-24">
<head>Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, July 24, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804042"/>
<opener>
WILL W. ALEXANDER<lb/>
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR<lb/>
C. H. TOBIAS<lb/>
ASSOCIATE DIRECTOR<lb/>
M. <unclear>ASHBY</unclear> JONES, HONORARY PRESIDENT<lb/>
HOWARD W. ODUM, PRESIDENT<lb/>
CHARLES S. JOHNSON, FIRST VICE PRESIDENT<lb/>
MRS. W. A. NEWELL, SECOND VICE PRESIDENT<lb/>
RUFUS E. CLEMENT, THIRD VICE PRESIDENT<lb/>
EMILY H. CLAY<lb/>
SECRETARY-ASST. TREASURER<lb/>
KENDALL WEISIGER<lb/>
TREASURER<lb/>
<dateline>
Commission on Interracial Cooperation<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
710 STANDARD BUILDING<lb/>
Atlanta, Georgia<lb/>
<date value="1942-07-24">July 24, 1942</date>
</dateline>
R. B. ELEAZER<lb/>
EDUCATIONAL DIRECTOR<lb/>
MRS. JESSIE DANIEL AMES<lb/>
DIRECTOR OF FIELD WORK<lb/>
R. P. NEBLETT, JR.<lb/>
FIELD SECRETARY<lb/>
JACKSON, MISSISSIPPI<lb/>
Dr. Phillip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You did not have to put up an argument to convince me that I would<lb/>
want to contribute the Yellow Fever charts to you. As soon as I<lb/>
get them back I will return them to you, keeping them only long<lb/>
enough to insert Case #1 - Kissinger. You may have them all or you<lb/>
my select the ones you want and send the rest back here. I would<lb/>
like some of the phostats to put in the portfolio just to keep that<lb/>
record complete. On the other hand if you do not want all these<lb/>
originals, the ones you return can serve that purpose.</p>
<p>It seems to me from the general tone of your questions and some of<lb/>
your observations that the record of the only really important result<lb/>
of the Spanish American War is largely dependent upon memories of<lb/>
those living but not present when the experiment was conducted; and<lb/>
the observations and deductions of the dead who did not support their<lb/>
statements with factual evidence. At least I am sure that the failure<lb/>
of the War Department to have a complete dossier on my husband was<lb/>
not premeditated. It was carelessness. Also I can understand some-<lb/>
thing of Dr. Kean's stubborn insistence on his stand as to those who<lb/>
helped and were deserving recognition. He had spoken with authority and<lb/>
without much evidence. When evidence was adduced that indicated he was<lb/>
not after all omniscient, he just could not re-open the case. He would<lb/>
be admitting that maybe he had made other mistakes.</p>
<p>I had no idea that those charts were the original ones. I knew that<lb/>
they were so marked but I thought that was a slip. It would never have<lb/>
entered my head that any such carelessness could characterize the<lb/>
handling of the War Department or any other establishment of the<lb/>
Government, except some of those established by this administration.</p>
<p>I promise you that if my sister-in-law does not give you satisfaction,<lb/>
I will see her myself. I have a pursuasive tongue and I have been<lb/>
known to be convincingly humble.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05804043"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>If when you get settled in the Army hospital you have the time and the<lb/>
inclination I should like for you to write me and tell me just how you<lb/>
got started on this project. It is not exactly in line with your<lb/>
special interests as far as I am able to judge.</p>
<p>If you recall anything else in my files that you would like to add to<lb/>
your collection, I am glad it is to be kept in the Mayo Clinic until<lb/>
you realize your plan of the Museum, I will gladly send it to you. I<lb/>
am enclosing the Laredo report about which you asked. That is, you<lb/>
asked whether or not I had a copy of it. I think you would not have<lb/>
done this had you not wanted it to study or to add to your records.</p>
<p>With the sincerest wishes for your happiness in serving in the Army,<lb/>
I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially yours,</salute>
<signed>Jessie Daniel Ames</signed>
<seg>
P.S. The Times-Picayune photostat has not come. I am going to be in New<lb/>
Orleans this fall and if it has not been sent you by them, I will see to<lb/>
it in person.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
