<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05806071">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, January 22, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05806071</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-01-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Schwieger, John D.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="place">Guanajay Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-01-22">January 22, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05806071</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, January 22, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus suggests corrections to Truby's manuscript.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-01-22">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, January 22, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05806071"/>
<opener>
From J. H. Andrus - 805 Cooper Street - Camden, New Jersey.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-01-22">Jan. 22, 1942.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Received your manuscript on the fifteenth, read most of the<lb/>
night and expected to send it on within a day or two; unfor-<lb/>
tunately there have been more visitors and other interrupt-<lb/>
ions than usual so it will not go to Mrs. LaGarde until to-<lb/>
morrow - Friday.</p>
<p>This is a grand bit of writing and - even in the cockeyed<lb/>
days through which we are living - I do not think you should<lb/>
have any trouble finding a publisher.</p>
<p>The<add>re</add> is little that I can offer. Knowing your desire for<lb/>
absolute accuracy, however, I offer the following:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Preceding p 40 &ldquo;Key to buildings shown on map&rdquo;.</item>
<item>&ldquo;91 Wards, including office&rdquo;. No wards. S. end of bldg.<lb/>
was Post Surgeon's office. Remainder of S. half was gen'l.<lb/>
office. In N. half of 91 pharmacy was next to office and<lb/>
storeroom and quarters for one or two non coms in remainder.</item>
<item>&ldquo;92 Pharmacy, etc.&rdquo; Wrong. At S. end of S. half were<lb/>
one or two small, private rooms. Remainder of S. half was<lb/>
medical and receiving ward. At N. end of 92 was partition<lb/>
of bars to form lock ward to hold 4 to 6 beds. Remainder<lb/>
of N. half of 92 was venerial ward.</item>
<item><p>&ldquo;93&rdquo; This was surgical and convalescent ward.</p>
<p>Between 91 and 92 there was a building housing toilets and<lb/>
bath which is not shown. Only entrance to this building<lb/>
was from center passage - across walk from boiler house.</p>
<p>There was a hall or passage between the N. and S. halves of 92<lb/>
so patients from 93 could enter toilet building without having<lb/>
to go around 92 as would have been the case if map was correct.</p></item>
<item>104 - 110 - 122 I recall but one building in this general loca-<lb/>
tion in 1901 and 1902 and that was occupied by female nurses.<lb/>
As I recall, there were from 6 to 8 nurses which would make 110<lb/>
seem too small for quarters, mess and bath. 104 or 122<lb/>
seems more probable.</item>
<item>p 67 &ldquo;H&rdquo; on diagram should read, &ldquo;small addition in which guinea<lb/>
pigs were housed&rdquo;.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f05806072"/>
<item>General Truby</item>
<item>Page 2.</item>
<item>p 73 - 74 - 75 having to do with the yellow fever epidemic at Guan-<lb/>
ajay Barracks.</item>
</list></p>
<p>My recollections of some phases of this episode are very dis-<lb/>
tinct and amazingly vague on others. In my one-volume book,<lb/>
&ldquo;Big Moments In A Little Life&rdquo;, I have recorded what I remember<lb/>
under the title, &ldquo;My First Meeting With Yellow Fever&rdquo; A copy<lb/>
is enclosed.</p>
<p>Please bear in mind that, while you are recording a historical<lb/>
event for publication, I only explain a purely personal &ldquo;big<lb/>
moment&rdquo; to a limited audience of relatives and friends who know<lb/>
none of those involved except myself.</p>
<p>You will note that I have refrained from naming any of the doc-<lb/>
tors. That is due to uncertainties. When Schwieger and<lb/>
I reached Guanajay Captain Quinton was the Post Surgeon.<lb/>
He had an assistant but I am unable to recall his name.</p>
<p>From a day or two after I reached the Post until I was on duty<lb/>
at the yellow fever hospital I was on night duty. As there<lb/>
was seldom occasion for the doctors to visit the wards at<lb/>
night, I had absolutely no contact with them.</p>
<p>That you replaced Captain Quinton as Post Surgeon registered<lb/>
as I had known you at Columbia Barracks.</p>
<p>It is strongly in my mind that you were absent from the Post<lb/>
for a few days prior to the death of the case which started<lb/>
our epidemic. And it seems to me that you returned just<lb/>
a few hours before his death. The fact that these are<lb/>
impressions - rather than certainties - is why they were omit-<lb/>
ted from my manuscript.</p>
<p>At the (tent) yellow fever hospital, the<lb/>
first doctor I recall is Dr. Robert P.<lb/>
Cooke. He was on duty but a few days<lb/>
when replaced by Dr. John F. Dunshie.<lb/>
Of these facts I am certain but I do not<lb/>
know whether either of them had been on<lb/>
duty at Guanajay before the epidemic.<lb/>
My guess is that Dr. Cooke may have re-<lb/>
placed your (and Capt. Quinton's) former<lb/>
assistant and that Dr. Dunshie, (an im-<lb/>
mune and probably a yellow fever special-<lb/>
ist), was sent to handle the yellow fever<lb/>
situation.</p>
<p>If any of this is helpful I shall be very glad. You and I<lb/>
both know that it is not too easy to grope back through the<lb/>
mists of more than 40 eventful years and always come up with<lb/>
all the details of an involved situation.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
