<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05803011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, November 10, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05803011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-11-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Andreu, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, W.A.</name>
<name type="person">Beauperthuy, Louis-Daniel</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana State University Lafayette La.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia (Charlottesville, Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-11-10">November 10, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05803011</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, November 10, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench mentions the lack of cooperation by Cuban doctors in memorializing Camp Lazear. He notes that he has been able to obtain research materials from the Reed and Lazear families, but little from the Carroll family, and he is pleased that Rodriguez Leon has assembled her father's papers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-11-10">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, November 10, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05803011"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-11-10">November 10, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon<lb/>
Avenida K 254 entre 15 Y 17<lb/>
Vedado, Habana<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora Rodriguez Leon:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I must offer you my sincere apologies for not having answered<lb/>
long ago your kind letter of April 8. At <add>that</add> time, and for five months there-<lb/>
after, I was completely immersed in one of the most difficult jobs I ever<lb/>
took on; namely, the publication of a review of all the English-speaking<lb/>
literature on rheumatic diseases for the last five years. I gave up every-<lb/>
thing. I practically saw nothing of my family, gave up a vacation trip,<lb/>
neglected to answer my correspondence and at times even forgot to pay my<lb/>
bills. I have just finished the job and am now &ldquo;back in circulation&rdquo; again.</p>
<p>You will be interested to know that we are making slow progress<lb/>
in the matter of our mutual interest; namely, the real story of the conquest<lb/>
of yellow fever. This spring I had some correspondence with two Cuban physi-<lb/>
cians, Doctor Nogueira and Doctor Andreu, who wrote to me telling me about<lb/>
their plans to join with me in memorializing Camp Lazear. However, I have<lb/>
been rather discouraged about the cooperation I have received from them.<lb/>
One of these letters was actually in answer to a letter I had written 18<lb/>
months before. To their letters I sent a long detailed reply. Although<lb/>
this was weeks ago. I have had no answer. I have just written them again and have<lb/>
asked Johnny Moran to try to find out what is wrong. I am even more anxious<lb/>
to cooperate with them than they think I am but they don't seem to respond to<lb/>
my efforts. I have heard that at l<del>e</del>ast the government named Camp Lazear a<lb/>
national monument. But giving the place simply a name without raising funds<lb/>
and making plans to preserve it seems to be inappropriate. The Mayo Clinic<lb/>
is still willing to make a generous donation to our proposal and I am hoping<lb/>
to see an associate of the Rockefeller family in New York in a week or so<lb/>
to interest him also, so that from this side of the water we still have our<lb/>
hopes and plans.</p>
<p>I have been asked to speak on November 17, at the Medical<lb/>
School of the University of Virginia on the conquest of yellow fever. You<lb/>
will remember that Walter Reed, Moran, and General Kean were all students<lb/>
at the University of Virginia. In the lecture which I plan to give, I have<lb/>
two or three nice lantern slides with photographs of your father. These I<lb/>
certainly plan to show. I have received an even nicer invitation to speak<lb/>
on the &ldquo;Walter Reed Memorial Day&rdquo;, May 12, before the International Congress<lb/>
on Tropical Medicine, held in Washington. On that day a statue of Walter<lb/>
Reed will be unveiled and presented to the Hall of Fame.</p>
<p>I have continued to assemble as much material as possible<lb/>
concerning all the members of the Yellow Fever Commission and I have been<lb/>
most fortunate in getting great help from the Reed family and the Lazear<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05803012"/>
Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
November 10, 1947<lb/>
family, who have given me or loaned me practically everything they have.<lb/>
What they chose not to add to this collection they allowed me to copy. They<lb/>
realize that this collection must not belong to any one individual but must<lb/>
be assembled for proper safeguard and displayed in some large medical insti-<lb/>
tution. Unfortunately, I have not gotten much from the Carroll Family. Sad<lb/>
to relate, the son, George Carroll, believes his father was not given due<lb/>
credit. You know all about that old sad story, but as the result of these<lb/>
feelings, he has been frankly hostile and I have not been able to make him<lb/>
understand that I want to give his father full credit if only he would put<lb/>
in my hands, such documents and papers as he has, which will show more clearly<lb/>
his father's contribution.</p>
<p>I am indeed delighted to hear that after these many years you<lb/>
have been able to collect all of your father's papers and bring them to your<lb/>
present home. I am already preparing the preliminary manuscript for the book<lb/>
that I hope to publish. I must confess that I do not have nearly enough on<lb/>
your father. I do need your help badly and I am delighted to know that you<lb/>
have been able to collect the old material. Because of its extreme importance<lb/>
to all concerned, I should like to come to Havana and spend a few days there<lb/>
reviewing your material. Would it be possible for me to do this, perhaps in<lb/>
March? I can arrange to come over to Cuba from Florida where Mrs. Hench and<lb/>
I had hoped to take a winter vacation. This is very important to me and I<lb/>
will promise that I will not be any more of a bother than I can help. I have<lb/>
made a thorough search of the National Archives, the old War Department records,<lb/>
the Army Medical Museum and other sources and have found not nearly enough to<lb/>
satisfy me as to your father's contribution. Of course, I know the general<lb/>
story, but that isn't what I am after. I'm after details, such as one could<lb/>
only find in personal letters, diaries, memoranda and notes. As you say, &ldquo;the<lb/>
Finlay fever&rdquo; is raging in Cuba. I shall be delighted indeed to have you<lb/>
translate my book into Spanish.</p>
<p>Please allow me to send the congratulations of Mrs. Hench and<lb/>
me on the birth of a little baby girl. Aren't they wonderful? Our four<lb/>
children are getting quite grown up. The oldest girl, age 18, is a freshman<lb/>
at a college in Vermont. The oldest boy, 17 years old, is in a prep school<lb/>
in Pennsylvania. The 14-year old girl is home but will go to a girls' school<lb/>
in Ohio next year and our little 4 1/2 year old boy is a great joy but he cer-<lb/>
tainly is active.</p>
<p>If I were able to come to visit you in March, I would try to<lb/>
disturb you as little as possible. I could review the material in your home<lb/>
at hours convenient to you, making notes and perhaps making arrangements to<lb/>
photostat or photograph the more important items. If necessary I can obtain<lb/>
the services of a stenographer. In the hope that I might be able to make this<lb/>
visit, I shall write to the Hotel Nacional to see if they can make reservations<lb/>
for me. It would indeed be a distinct pleasure to come.</p>
<p>I wonder if I have sent you a photograph of the mural honoring<lb/>
your father on the wall of the Agramonte Memorial Library at the Medical Center,<lb/>
Louisiana State University. It is a bronze mural and I believe I had sent you<lb/>
one but if not, let me know and I will send you one with much pleasure. I do<lb/>
hope that a review of your data will give me an even clearer picture of your<lb/>
father's distinguished contribution.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f05803013"/>
<p>Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>November 10, 1947</p>
<p>It will be most appropriate for me to have this material<lb/>
at the time of the International Congress in May and Doctor Sawyer, the<lb/>
chairman of the program committee, has asked me to see to it that although<lb/>
my talk (it has been called the &ldquo;principal oration&rdquo;) is to be given on the<lb/>
Walter Reed Memorial Day, I am to give full credit to all concerned, in-<lb/>
cluding Finlay, of course. By the way, I would certainly like to see the<lb/>
items you mentioned, the papers of the Noguchi controversy and also the<lb/>
original print of Beaperthuy's article. I have never been able to get a<lb/>
copy of the latter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
