<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804030">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, July 3, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804030</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-07-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ames, Jessie Daniel</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-07-03">July 3, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804030</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, July 3, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Ames that he has been called-up for active duty. He poses numerous questions about the material she has sent to him. He expresses his desire to paint an accurate portrayal of Ames' contribution to the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-07-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, July 3, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804030"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-07-03">July 3, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. Jessie Daniels Ames<lb/>
710 Standard Bldg.<lb/>
Atlanta, Georgia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Ames:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am about to enter the Medical Corps of the army, presumably with<lb/>
the rank of Lieutenant Colonel, as chief of the medical service of a large<lb/>
station hospital. I have been so busy getting together a group of men for this<lb/>
hospital that I have been until now unable to write to you. I have finally had<lb/>
the photostatic copies made of many of the items in your portfolio and I am so<lb/>
grateful to you for sending them. I do not expect to enter active service for<lb/>
about three more weeks and would be very grateful if you could<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Send me the twenty-two or twenty-three original fever charts<lb/>
which you have of Dean, Lazear, etc. I am anxious to study them and make photo-<lb/>
static copies of them.</item>
<item>2. Regarding the letter of February 27 from T.D. Berry to Dr. Ames,<lb/>
do you have a copy of the reply from the editor of the Journal of the A.M.A.?<lb/>
I should appreciate your further comments about Berry's contention that Dr. Ames'<lb/>
case of yellow fever was an experimental one. Who was Berry? I can't place him.</item>
<item>3. Do you have any copies, carbon copies or otherwise, of Dr. Ames'<lb/>
answers to Dr. Berry's letter? Is Dr. Berry living or if not do you know the<lb/>
address of his survivors?</item>
<item>4. In Berry's letter of March 20, Dr. Ames is quoted at the bottom<lb/>
of the first page as follows: &ldquo;The fact that I was one of the unreported ex-<lb/>
perimental cases is established only by the press reports of which I have no<lb/>
acquaintance.&rdquo; I don't know quite how to interpret this. Was Dr. Ames inferring<lb/>
that his case was really experimental or not?</item>
<item>5. In the second part of your inclosure XVIII in Dr. Ames' letter<lb/>
to the Surgeon General dated December 30, 1901, requesting all the data on all<lb/>
the charts and clinical records of various yellow fever cases, I would appreciate<lb/>
it greatly if you would send me as much of this as you have by registered mail<lb/>
or insured express. I will study it promptly, with your permission copy some of<lb/>
it promptly and return it to you definitely before I leave for service.</item>
<item>6. The letter and enclosure VI from O'Reilly to Dr. Ames indicates<lb/>
that Dr. Ames had the original charts and that O'Reilly had copies made and re-<lb/>
turned the originals to Dr. Ames. Does this refer to the fever charts which<lb/>
you still have?</item>
<item>7. Your label on enclosure XXX suggests that there were several<lb/>
reprints present and the reprints were not present in the portfolio when I re-<lb/>
ceived it.</item>
<item>8. In your letter to me of April 2, under your answer to my second<lb/>
question, you state that Dr. Ames' chart shows that he was sick for nine, not<lb/>
three or four days. I am especially anxious to have a copy of his chart. Would<lb/>
you lend it to me with the others?</item>
<item>9. Were you able to find Dr. Ames' map of the infected district<lb/>
near Camp Columbia among his sister's possessions? You were kind enough to say<lb/>
that you would write to her. I shall appreciate greatly if you would send me<lb/>
her name and address. I should like to send her one of my reprints on the<lb/>
yellow fever story.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f05804031"/>
<item>Mrs. Jessie D. Ames</item>
<item>- 2-</item>
<item>July 3, 1942</item>
<item>10. I showed the group photographs (your enclosure VIII) to Dr.<lb/>
Cook, Mr. Lambert, General Truby and one or two others but they were unable<lb/>
to recognize any of the men except Dr. Ames. Obviously it was not taken at<lb/>
Camp Columbia or Camp Lazear. Do you know about the approximate date when Dr.<lb/>
Ames started to wear a moustache? This would help to identify the time when<lb/>
certain photographs were taken.</item>
<item>11. You mentioned that a cousin of yours in New Orleans might have<lb/>
some Havana newspapers or a copy of the &ldquo;New Orleans Picayune&rdquo; for July 30, 1905.<lb/>
I would appreciate it greatly if I could have a photostatic copy of that article<lb/>
if you are able to do so.</item>
<item>12. Do you have another copy of your enclosure No. XX. I gather<lb/>
that you do not from the heading on this enclosure.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Let me express my deep appreciation for your lending me this in-<lb/>
valuable material. I only hope that I can do justice to all the men concerned<lb/>
and give an accurate portrayal of Dr. Ames' real contribution. You have helped<lb/>
me tremendously and any further help you can give me will be greatly appreciated.<lb/>
Perhaps when I reach my military station I can still carry on this study as a<lb/>
hobby and I would appreciate the privilege of writing you further.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
