<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05806118">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John H. Andrus, February 17, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05806118</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-02-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Andrus, John H.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Zunzunegui, Mr.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-02-17">February 17, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05806118</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John H. Andrus, February 17, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thinks that the original records and fever charts still exist, but does not know where they are. He encourages Andrus to rewrite his story to emphasize his own role in the experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-02-17">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to John H. Andrus, February 17, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05806118"/>
<opener>
Y F<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-02-17">February 17, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Mr. J. H. Andrus<lb/>
805 Cooper Street<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Andrus:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your last letter interested me greatly. You say you were given a <hi>copy</hi> of<lb/>
your yellow fever chart and suggest that Reed kept the original which was probably<lb/>
later used by the engraver to make plates for reproduction and that the originals<lb/>
might well have been destroyed thereafter. May I ask a few questions. How long<lb/>
after your illness were you given your copy of your fever chart--right away or weeks<lb/>
later? Who do you think made the copies--the nurse who took care of you (i.e. Lam-<lb/>
bert) or someone else? Seeing in Washington how carefully kept are all records of<lb/>
illness, etc. of all soldiers, I still believe that somewhere the original records<lb/>
must be kept but if so they are well hidden. Did your <hi>copy</hi> resemble the original<lb/>
correctly? In the Senate Document (which I have) it shows on page 79 that Moran had<lb/>
a little fever a day or so before Christmas. He insists he did <hi>not</hi>, and that someone<lb/>
copied his fever chart wrong.</p>
<p>In view of your perfectly understandable desire to publish your story in a<lb/>
general (not a medical) journal I believe the only thing you can do is to keep send-<lb/>
ing it around to various publications. I believe some of the more high brow magazines<lb/>
might take it when some of the more popular and larger ones might not. If you are<lb/>
discouraged remember that many a good story has a <unclear>hard</unclear> time getting published. I<lb/>
hope it won't happen but if you get <hi>too</hi> discouraged remember that I'm sure it could<lb/>
be published in a medical historical magazine and you could get reprints although<lb/>
you would receive no money for it unless Hygeia published it. In that case you might<lb/>
get $25.00 or $50.00 which isn't much. But Hygeia has a wide circulation (150,000,<lb/>
I believe) and is read by many laymen. Unfortunately I can't help you with lay pub-<lb/>
lishers as I know none of them.</p>
<p>I have carefully read your second version and compared it paragraph by para-<lb/>
graph with the first one and I note that many of the suggestions I had planned to<lb/>
make have been taken care of--either suggested to you by Generals Kean and Truby<lb/>
or corrected by yourself. The main suggestion I had in mind was to have you make<lb/>
your quotations from Reed's papers and others less conspicuous by handling them a<lb/>
little differently. The way you had them first they interrupted the continuity some-<lb/>
what and made it appear that you were copying considerable from what laymen might<lb/>
consider relatively uninteresting professional reports. I was going to suggest that<lb/>
you omit mention of the references and just quote what you wanted, putting it in<lb/>
more or less as conversation with the simple statement &ldquo;as Reed later wrote&rdquo;. But<lb/>
I see you've already done that in part.</p>
<p>Very properly and cleverly you have attracted the reader's attention at once<lb/>
(on your page 1) by starting out with a bit of the personal and dramatic part of<lb/>
your story before going back (on page 2) to explain the (less interesting) background.<lb/>
But even so I think you might amplify the personal part on page 1 by adding to it<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05806119"/>
Mr. J. H. Andrus<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
February 17, 1942<lb/>
material now on pages 11 and 12 before going on to the statistics and background<lb/>
now on page 2. In other words, I don't think you've got enough of the human interest<lb/>
part on page 1 to hold the reader's interest when he suddenly hits page 2. What you<lb/>
have on page 1 catches but isn't enough to clinch his interest, I'm afraid, and you<lb/>
may lose him on page 2. If necessary, you can later repeat yourself and say again in<lb/>
somewhat different words what you say on pages 11 and 12.</p>
<p>By the way on page 5 you say that Building #1 was &ldquo;poorly ventilated by intent<lb/>
and solid wood shutters excluded sunlight&rdquo;. As we found it Building #1 has heavy<lb/>
solid wooden shutters and heavy sliding <hi>solid wooden</hi> sashes (in lieu of windows).<lb/>
Reed described the wooden shutters but spoke of sliding <hi>glass</hi> sashes. The man<lb/>
(Zunzunegui) who lived there all these years insists that the sliding wood panels are<lb/>
original and not put in since he went to live in the shack in 1906. Do you think Reed<lb/>
was wrong when he spoke of the glass? Did you ever see those windows to recall them?<lb/>
I will write Dr. Cooke about this but would like your opinion also.</p>
<p>I would omit the third and fourth lines on page <unclear>5</unclear> (in parenthesis). It breaks<lb/>
the flow of thought and you will add the list anyhow. In three or four places you<lb/>
have a sentence in parenthesis: in general I would suggest either omitting the sen-<lb/>
tence or removing the parentheses. If it's pertinent, it should be left in without<lb/>
the interruption of parentheses. If it's not quite pertinent I'd omit it as you aren't<lb/>
under the necessity of explaining fully a scientific thesis. In other words I believe<lb/>
your story could be definitely improved and made more saleable by <hi>stressing the human</hi><lb/>
interest side of it and making it less &ldquo;scientific&rdquo;. Its value is a good <hi>personal</hi><lb/>
human interest story. You should add to that part of your story. I would think over<lb/>
the events again--and add lots of little details you don't mention. For example, on<lb/>
page 1 paragraph 1--who was &ldquo;the doctor&rdquo;, was he serious and sober as he scrubbed your<lb/>
arm, or did he joke with you? What was Forbes doing? Was he very sick or watching<lb/>
with amused curiosity? What kind of a room or tent were you in? What thoughts passed<lb/>
through your mind as the needle went in? Describe the ambulance waiting ominously<lb/>
outside--the picturesque old &ldquo;jalopy&rdquo; of a Dougherty wagon, etc. Describe how Reed<lb/>
looked--uniform, etc. In summary, <hi>add color</hi>, all the color you can legitimately and<lb/>
honestly put in. Make the story just as <hi>personal</hi> as you can. The trouble is that you<lb/>
hate to do this--you draw back in modesty. But once you've decided to tell <hi>your story</hi><lb/>
(not the story of the Board's work) you've got to plunge in and <hi>do it</hi>. The Board's<lb/>
story has been told and retold. Now the only value to your story is that it's <hi>your<lb/>
story</hi>--your personal slant. My main criticism is that to some extent your story as<lb/>
now written is neither fish nor fowl. It's a little part <unclear>you,</unclear> but a lot quotation<lb/>
and explanation. It's half way between a story and a scientific paper. I'd be<lb/>
strongly tempted to have you minimize the latter much more. Of course you've got to<lb/>
put some of it in <unclear>so</unclear> that the reader will know a little of what it was all about.<lb/>
But my <unclear>impression</unclear> of it is that it isn't personal enough to make it original enough for<lb/>
a publisher to say &ldquo;Here's some dope <hi>never told before.</hi>&rdquo; Perhaps by amplifying your<lb/>
personal part you can get away with the (second-hand) scientific part as you now have it.<lb/>
As I estimate it, of the 16 pages you write only 6 are personal (page 1, first half,<lb/>
page 7 last third, page 8, first two-thirds, pages 9 - 12 and half of page 13). Can't<lb/>
you <hi>amplify</hi> this?</p>
<p>It's a grand story but I don't think you do <hi>your</hi> story justice. It's lost--<lb/>
swallowed up by the <hi>Board's</hi> story.</p>
<p>It's so hard to make myself clear by letter. I wish I could talk it over in<lb/>
detail with you. I do hope you know that it's because I think you <hi>do</hi> have a story<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05806120"/>
Mr. J. H. Andrus<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
February 17, 1942<lb/>
and <hi>must</hi> tell it that I am making these comments. If you react like I usually do<lb/>
when somebody criticizes my manuscripts (and I've published almost one hundred<lb/>
scientific articles; I say this merely in defense) you will probably first think<lb/>
that my comments are not quite true and that anyhow you're sick of trying to re-<lb/>
write it. But I hope your second reaction will be like mine usually is--I get to<lb/>
seeing the other viewpoint and after a while I see what my critic meant and then<lb/>
I try to accept not all of his suggestions but as much of them as I see fit. It<lb/>
is in that friendly spirit that I write you what I hope you will regard as con-<lb/>
structive, not destructive, criticism. <hi>Please</hi>, <hi>please</hi> keep at it--<hi>your</hi> story must<lb/>
be told. I'm not suggesting you over-dramatize it or tell it falsely, lividly or<lb/>
glamorously but just personalize it more and amplify the personal details you haven't<lb/>
even seen fit to put in. Take the reader with <hi>you</hi> (not with Reed) into the tents,<lb/>
the lab, the camp, etc.</p>
<p>By the way (again) who was the &ldquo;man (on page 7) brought from the Major's<lb/>
lab. in Washington&rdquo; whom you replaced? Was it <unclear>Neate</unclear>? On page 9 you speak of the<lb/>
Major's &ldquo;recent illness&rdquo;. What was it and when?</p>
<p><hi>Please</hi> let me help further in any way I can.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
