<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804058">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, August 23, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804058</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-08-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ames, Jessie Daniel</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">National Archives, Washington, D. C.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-08-23">August 23, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804058</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, August 23, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes the difficulties he has encountered in memorializing Camp Lazear. He discusses where he believes his collection should eventually be stored, citing the Mayo Foundation, the University of Virginia's Alderman Library, and the National Archives. He does not want the items to be in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-08-23">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, August 23, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804058"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1950-08-23">August 23, 1950</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. Jessie Daniel Ames<lb/>
The Wren's Nest<lb/>
Tryon, North Carolina<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Ames:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am glad to have your letter of August 12 and I have been interested<lb/>
to read of your reaction toward your possession of the yellow fever charts.<lb/>
Actually, that was my own feeling, that these charts do not belong to anyone<lb/>
individual and I was surprised that the Surgeon General's Office did not re-<lb/>
quest the return of those years ago from your husband.</p>
<p>I agree with you that they belong to the nation and should be made<lb/>
available to historians and students of the conquest of yellow fever and the<lb/>
lives of those concerned. That is why I have not accepted any of the hundreds<lb/>
of items that have been given to me as personal gifts. I am merely the tem-<lb/>
porary custodian until such time as more proper and permanent disposition can<lb/>
be made.</p>
<p>I have had all sorts of set-backs with regard to the little memorial<lb/>
museum which we had hoped to build in Cuba on the site of Camp Lazear. As<lb/>
you know, I made several trips there. My plans were interrupted by the war<lb/>
but about two years ago I went to Cuba again and spent a couple of weeks there.<lb/>
During this time, I interviewed various public health officers, the secretary of defense<lb/>
and the members of the Engineering and Building Department and the Vice President.<lb/>
They all received me most cordially and accepted plans which I had drawn up. As<lb/>
a result of previous visits of mine they had finally designated Building No. 1<lb/>
a national monument but I found that they had done nothing to protect it.<lb/>
I offered the Vice President a sum of money and asked if he would allow me<lb/>
to at least put a protecting covering around the building. With typical<lb/>
Latin-American vehemence he protested that the Cuban Government could not possibly<lb/>
let me spend my own money but that they would protect the little building. I saw<lb/>
the owners of the land around the building and they said that they were as help-<lb/>
less as I since the building itself is a national monument. However after my<lb/>
visit the Cuban government did allot $50,000 and pass a bill to initiate pro-<lb/>
tection of Building No. 1 and carry out my preliminary plans but most regret-<lb/>
fully I must tell you that within a few months that administration went out,<lb/>
a new one came in and what happened to the $50,000 is anyone's guess. Nothing<lb/>
has been done. However I have been corresponding with Johnny Moran and there are<lb/>
a few other Americans who are interested in the project and we have tried some<lb/>
how or other to proceed but probably we will have to raise all the money in this<lb/>
country.</p>
<p>In view of the constant delay by the Cubans, I do not believe that<lb/>
they deserve to have the enormous amount of material I have collected not only<lb/>
from you but the families of all the survivors, including the Reed family.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05804059"/>
Mrs. Jessie Daniel Ames<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
August 23, 1950<lb/>
Three institutions are very anxious to have the material. The Mayo Foundation<lb/>
is willing to set aside a special room for its display in the new library of<lb/>
the new Mayo Clinic which has just been started. The advantage of having it<lb/>
preserved by the Mayo Foundation would be that many thousands of doctors would<lb/>
see the material each year whereas if it were put elsewhere a very small number<lb/>
would see it. The University of Virginia Library (where Reed graduated) also<lb/>
wants the collection and last year when I visited the National Archives in<lb/>
Washington, the curator who knew of this collection asked whether I would con-<lb/>
sider sending it there. I have sought and received much advice on this point<lb/>
from many, including the Reed and Lazear families, General Kean and others and<lb/>
it now seems best to have the material preserved in one place but allow the<lb/>
other institutions who wish the material to have microfilmed copies of all the<lb/>
data. In this way all will be satisfied, and from the standpoint of safety,<lb/>
the records or copies of the records, will be not in one place but in several<lb/>
places. It is my plan therefore not to give the little Cuban museum (if it<lb/>
ever materializes) the originals but merely copies which will suffice. I hesitate<lb/>
greatly to trust the originals to the Cubans. There is no purpose in<lb/>
returning the fever charts to the Surgeon General as long since their old records<lb/>
have been sent to the National Archives. I regret to say that here they are<lb/>
scattered in hundreds of places and it is extremely difficult for anyone to<lb/>
find them. I have spent as long as two weeks at a time in Washington, getting<lb/>
each day pitiably small collections as we traced down one file after another.<lb/>
Ordinarily the National Archives would be the place for all of this material<lb/>
but in view of what I have just said, I and some of my advisors have serious<lb/>
doubts.</p>
<p>Rest assured that the material which I hold merely as a trustee is<lb/>
being taken care of. Much of it is in safe deposit boxes, including your<lb/>
fever charts and it will be preserved in toto, the choice not being made by<lb/>
me alone but with the advice of the Walter Reed Association and the families<lb/>
of those most concerned.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: Did you know that Mrs. Walter Reed died a month ago?<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
