<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05808017">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Mrs. George Carroll to Philip Showalter Hench, November 4, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carroll, Mrs. George</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05808017</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-11-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-11-04">November 4, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05808017</idno>
<title>Letter from Mrs. George Carroll to Philip Showalter Hench, November 4, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Mrs. Carroll discusses the death of her husband, George Carroll.  She regrets that her late husband was uncooperative in furnishing any data to Hench concerning his work and mentions tensions among the surviving Carroll siblings.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-11-04">
<head>Letter from Mrs. George Carroll to Philip Showalter Hench, November 4, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05808017"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-11-04">November 4, 1953.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench,<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Words cannot express my appreciation of your thoughtfulness in sending<lb/>
me your telegram of sympathy and your subsequent letter of October 29, 1953.</p>
<p>I am going to try to write you a coherent letter but I am like a ship<lb/>
without a rudder. I am bewildered, cannot eat nor sleep and do not seem to<lb/>
think clearly.</p>
<p>While my husband had been ill several times, I just could not accept the<lb/>
fact that he could not get well. I read of so many miracle operations being<lb/>
performed on the heart that I thought one could be done for my husband but<lb/>
the physicians said his trouble was not the type that could be helped in that<lb/>
manner. The death certificate states that death was due to congestive heart<lb/>
failure and arterioslerotic and hypertensive cardiovascular heart disease.<lb/>
Whatever the cause, I am left alone and I do not want to live. If I were<lb/>
not a Christian, I would take an easy way out but I know if I want to meet<lb/>
him, I must go on living until my time comes. As a physician, you meet death<lb/>
every day and sympathize with the bereaved but you will never know the real<lb/>
agony of losing a loved one until you experience it. I lost my father and<lb/>
a brother and felt very badly but nothing like I feel now, it is almost<lb/>
like losing my right arm.</p>
<p>I too regret that my husband was not more cooperative in furnishing you<lb/>
any data he may have had regarding his father. He always intended to have<lb/>
a book written stating the true facts as he said the family was never satisfied<lb/>
with Dr. Reed's actions but time went on and nothing was ever done. I have<lb/>
two locked trunks in my possession but I do not know if there is anything<lb/>
in the one trunk that would help you as I understand that when mother Carroll<lb/>
died, my husband and the two surviving sisters each took some of the papers<lb/>
so they <add>are</add> probably somewhat scattered. The other trunk is supposed to contain<lb/>
the father's uniforms and these together with the Congressional Medal were to<lb/>
be placed in the Army Museum when the three would get together to make the<lb/>
presentation but this was never done. Already the two sisters are <unclear>feuding</unclear><lb/>
over the medal. The one sister and my husband had it in a safe deposit box<lb/>
for many years and the day before the funeral, the sister went to the bank<lb/>
and got the medal and asked me for my husband's key. I told her I could<lb/>
not go through his things now so she wants me to mail her the key later. The<lb/>
other sister has written me for advice as she wants the medal to go to the<lb/>
Museum. I am advising her to consult her lawyer as I certainly would do if<lb/>
I had any claim to it.</p>
<p>Later on, when I get back to normal (if I ever do) I shall be glad to<lb/>
let you go through the records in my posession if I can legally do so. I<lb/>
would like to help you in any way I can to obtain the information you desire.<lb/>
In the meantime I will endeavor to find out if the sisters have any data<lb/>
in their <unclear>possession</unclear>.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05808018"/>
<p>It is very kind of you to offer your suggestions through my attending<lb/>
physician for the treatment of arthritis. I have read of the wonderful<lb/>
results you have achieved with cortisone. I took three bottles (40 tablets<lb/>
each) and it seemed to help me while taking it but when I ceased I had<lb/>
quite a reaction. I am discouraged as my hands are very much deformed and<lb/>
my activities are limited, in other words I have adjusted my life to my<lb/>
&ldquo;joints&rdquo;. I have had arthritis for twenty years and was forced to give<lb/>
up a nice position sixteen years ago as then I had so much pain that I<lb/>
could not walk very well nor use my hands. After many years of various<lb/>
kinds of treatments and plenty of rest, the pain subsided except at<lb/>
intervals but the deformity continues. I cannot close either hand now.<lb/>
(I am typing this myself as I can write slowly whereas writing by hand<lb/>
causes cramps). I am very depressed and have been for years. I am<lb/>
5' 2" tall and weigh 107. Before my husband's death I weighed 114 but<lb/>
I do not eat nor sleep except when I use sleeping pills prescribed by<lb/>
my doctor. It is the only way I get any rest.</p>
<p>My husband and I often talked about my going to the Mayo Clinic to<lb/>
have a thorough examination and avail myself of your services in this<lb/>
dreadful <unclear>disease</unclear> but we just kept putting it off and now he is gone.<lb/>
Perhaps within the next year, I can visit the Clinic.</p>
<p>Dr. Hench, would it be asking too much for your opinion on the merits<lb/>
of a foot operation? I have been having so much trouble with my feet and<lb/>
last week consulted an orthopedic surgeon who by the way was with the Mayo<lb/>
Clinic for about five years. He is Dr. Marvin Gibson and he told me he<lb/>
admired you so much. I was referred to the office of Dr. Tobin by the<lb/>
widow of Dr. Custis Lee Hall, my former physician who died two years ago.<lb/>
Dr. Tobin was busy so I talked with Dr. Gibson and he had X-rays made and<lb/>
most of the bones are out of place. He says he thinks an operation would<lb/>
help but that it is up to me to make the decision. I consulted my regular<lb/>
physician yesterday and he said that while he is not an orthopedic surgeon,<lb/>
he would not advise me to have it done at my age. Then I talked with my<lb/>
sister (who is ten years younger than I) as she had the same type of<lb/>
operation over a year ago and she thinks it is worth while. She says it<lb/>
is very painful and that she was laid up for two months but now her feet<lb/>
are so much better that she does not regret going through the operation.<lb/>
If I thought I would get relief, I would have the work done this month<lb/>
and get it over with before warm weather comes again. Dr. Gibson says<lb/>
he does not see how I walk as well as I do.</p>
<p>I hope you will forgive this lenghthy letter as I know you are very<lb/>
busy. I will appreciate any advice you care to give me and in the meantime,<lb/>
I will endeavor to find out how much data the relatives have which may aid<lb/>
you in your work.</p>
<p>With kindest regards to you and your most gracious wife whom I met several<lb/>
years ago, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Mrs. George S. M. Carroll</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
