<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05808019">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, December 3, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05808019</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-12-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carroll, Mrs.George</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-12-03">December 3, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05808019</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, December 3, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests permission to examine the material concerning her late father-in-law, James Carroll. He hopes to meet with her during his next trip to Washington, D.C.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-12-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, December 3, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05808019"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-12-03">December 3, 1953</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. George S. H. Carroll<lb/>
2814 Rhode Island Avenue N.E.<lb/>
Washington 18, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Carroll:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I certainly appreciate your letter of November 4. I am distressed to<lb/>
know of your confusion and lonesomeness but of course this is quite<lb/>
understandable. Fortunately, time tends to heal all things and I do<lb/>
hope and pray that as time passes you will become more and more interested<lb/>
in the life of your relatives and friends and in that way the sorrow<lb/>
will be lessened.</p>
<p>Since writing you, I have been invited to speak at the Walter Reed Hos-<lb/>
pital February 18. If you expect to be in Washington at that time, I<lb/>
should like to visit you to pay my respects and perhaps to discuss some<lb/>
of the matters mentioned in your letter. I agree that the Army Museum<lb/>
has a right to receive whatever you, as the widow choose to let them<lb/>
have and it would seem to me that would be the place for the medal since<lb/>
Doctor Carroll worked there. Perhaps the Army Museum would make either<lb/>
a nice photographic copy of the medal for the various relatives, or they<lb/>
might even consider making a plaster model of the medal, if you and Mr.<lb/>
Carroll's sisters would give the original to the Army Museum. This is<lb/>
merely a thought on my part. I know some men at the Army Museum, indeed<lb/>
I know General DeCoursey, the Director, and if you wish me to do so I<lb/>
will be glad to sound him out on the matter, but I will not do it without<lb/>
your permission.</p>
<p>As for the other things, certainly you, as the widow, have the right to<lb/>
do with them as you wish. As I have told you, I do so very much hope that<lb/>
you will permit me just to examine the material. I only have one pur-<lb/>
pose and that is to be as accurate as I possibly can in describing in<lb/>
my book exactly what Doctor Carroll and each of the other men did. I<lb/>
am hoping very much that you will find with your husband's souvenirs<lb/>
of his father an important notebook which was kept by one of the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Board and which apparently later was borrowed by Doctor Carroll<lb/>
to use for his notes. There are in this notebook some unused notes<lb/>
which I am anxious to study.</p>
<p>Do you expect to be in Washington throughout February? If so, I shall<lb/>
arrange to stay over in Washington an extra day so as to visit with you<lb/>
and perhaps give whatever helpful suggestions I can with regard to the<lb/>
very valuable souvenirs of Doctor Carroll's work.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05808020"/>
<p><unclear>Mrs.</unclear> George S. H. Carroll</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>December 3, 1953</p>
<p>Since you are under the care of a physician I should not presume to<lb/>
give you advice regarding your own arthritis unless your physician<lb/>
should wish me to act in the double capacity of a friend and a con-<lb/>
sultant as well.</p>
<p>Cortisone when taken properly can be very helpful indeed but like all<lb/>
hormones, it must be taken indefinitely. Nevertheless by certain tricks<lb/>
we have learned the last year or so, we have been able to lower the dose<lb/>
notably in many patients and some have been able to discontinue it, at<lb/>
least for certain lengths of time.</p>
<p>I wish I could advise you regarding the foot operation but I cannot do<lb/>
this without seeing you as a patient. You seem to have excellent ad-<lb/>
vice but I can understand that you hesitate to have any operation un-<lb/>
less it is necessary. So often the feet of arthritic patients are<lb/>
badly deformed and do need surgery if the proper supports are inade-<lb/>
quate.</p>
<p>I shall await a reply from you with interest and do hope that I can<lb/>
see you in February.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
