<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05806012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">&ldquo;The Tale of a Guinea Pig&rdquo;, by John H. Andrus [1941]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05806012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-00-00">[1941]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05806012</idno>
<title>&ldquo;The Tale of a Guinea Pig&rdquo;, by John H. Andrus [1941]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus describes his role as a volunteer in the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-00-00">
<head>&ldquo;The Tale of a Guinea Pig&rdquo;, by John H. Andrus [1941]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05806012"/>
<p>1</p>
<p><hi>T h e  T a l e  O f  A  G u i n e a  P i g</hi><lb/>
By John H. Andrus.</p>
<p>With Dr. Carroll I entered the quarantined grounds of the<lb/>
yellow fever hospital and stopped in front of one of the small<lb/>
wards. Dr. Ames emerged with a hypodermic syringe in his hand.<lb/>
Maybe my voice was not quite steady when I asked, &ldquo;How is <del><unclear>Dr</unclear></del><lb/>
Forbes, Doctor?&rdquo; Dr. Ames grinned, &ldquo;You are not worrying<lb/>
about Forbes, you're worried about Andrus.&rdquo; He was probably<lb/>
right. Entirely aside from my friendly interest in Forbes,<lb/>
it would have bucked up my waning courage to have been told<lb/>
that he was out of danger.</p>
<p>Forbes was at the height of a pronounced case of yellow<lb/>
fever. He had been inoculated with the disease by the injec-<lb/>
tion of one-half cubic centimeter of blood taken from a case,<lb/>
acquired naturally, that had proven fatal. The hypodermic <unclear><del>a</del></unclear><lb/>
syringe in Dr. Ames' hand contained one cubic centimeter of<lb/>
Forbes' blood taken but a moment before.</p>
<p>Dr. Ames scrubbed a place on my arm <add>with antiseptic</add> and I watched with fas-<lb/>
cination as he inserted the needle and slowly pressed the plun-<lb/>
ger. I knew that, from that instant, nothing could prevent<lb/>
my having yellow fever. I knew that my inoculation would<lb/>
cause me more pain and place my life in far greater jeopardy<lb/>
than the bite of a rattlesnake. I glanced at Dr. Carroll.<lb/>
His had been the first experimental infection - five months<lb/>
before - and he was still far from recovered. As a Hospital<lb/>
Corps man I had nursed yellow fever patients; I had seen men<lb/>
writhing in pain and heard them babbling in delerium and I had<lb/>
seen yellow fever deaths. With that needle buried in my arm<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05806013"/>
2<lb/>
it was too late for heavy thinking. The shrug that accompan-<lb/>
ied this conclusion brought a sharp twinge in my arm and an<lb/>
even sharper admonition from Dr. Ames.</p>
<p><hi>Apprehensions Justified</hi></p>
<p>I was inoculated at 12:15 p.m. Jan 25, 1901. Six days<lb/>
later Major Walter Reed, in a letter to the Surgeon-General of<lb/>
the Army, George M. Sternberg, wrote of my case:</p>
<p>&ldquo;... I am very uneasy about the non-immune soldier<lb/>
who got the same amount of blood at the same time&rdquo;<lb/>
(as four mosquito-made immunes). &ldquo;He seems to have<lb/>
acquired a very serious infection, his temperature<lb/>
running along the 104&deg; line now for three days ...<lb/>
Should he die I shall regret that I ever undertook<lb/>
this work. The responsibility for the life of a<lb/>
human being weighs upon me very heavily just at<lb/>
present and I am dreadfully melancholic. Every-<lb/>
thing is being done for him that we know how to do.&rdquo; *</p>
<p>To go back to Dr. Ames - as he withdrew the needle and gave<lb/>
my arm a final rub with antiseptic he said, &ldquo;Too bad it's<lb/>
Forbes' blood you are getting.&rdquo; Visions of some <unclear>other<del>b</del>hor-<lb/>
rible</unclear> disease flashed in my mind as I asked, &ldquo;Why, Doctor?&rdquo;<lb/>
&ldquo;Well&rdquo;, he replied, &ldquo;you know how Forbes talks - don't be sur-<lb/>
prised if you start talking the same way&rdquo;. In the larger<lb/>
affairs of the moment I laughed, promised Drs. Ames and Car-<lb/>
roll that I would be back and stepped into the waiting ambu-<lb/>
lance to be driven to Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>* Extract from page 227, Biography of General Sternberg.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f05806014"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>Camp Lazear, a little more than a mile from Columbia Bar-<lb/>
racks, was in an isolated open field. It consisted of two<lb/>
small buildings, a large mess tent and seven small tents for<lb/>
use as quarters. There was a permanent staff of three or<lb/>
four immunes who served as cook, ambulance driver, etc. The<lb/>
main purpose of the camp was to isolate volunteers for inoc-<lb/>
ulation from any possibility of contact with yellow fever<lb/>
except experimental. I <add>was</add> <del>am</del> the only volunteer for inoculation,<lb/>
after the camp was established who was not quarantined there<lb/>
for approximately two weeks before infection.</p>
<p>There, too, most of the inoculations were performed and -<lb/>
as in my case - infected volunteers were held there, under<lb/>
observation, until they became sick. Upon my arrival I was<lb/>
assigned to a tent and was at liberty to go where I pleased,<lb/>
within the camp, while the &ldquo;bugs&rdquo; with which I had been infec-<lb/>
ted set up housekeeping and raised families in my blood stream.</p>
<p>One of the first things I did was to write home. I told<lb/>
my mother that I had been detailed to accompany a troop of the<lb/>
Seventh Cavalry on a practice march into the interior of the<lb/>
Island. and would not be able to write again for two or three<lb/>
weeks. I didn't feel too good about this. I wanted to leave<lb/>
things so that the folks at home would not worry when they did<lb/>
not hear from me for a while and that was the most reasonable<lb/>
explanation that occurred to me. I did not like the idea of<lb/>
lieing in my letter for I realized that it might be the last<lb/>
letter I would ever write home.</p>
<p>And now, with time on my hands, I thought of what Dr. Ames<lb/>
had told me about my talking the way Forbes did. He stammered<lb/>
so badly that he was utterly unable to express himself until<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f05806015"/>
4<lb/>
he was able to invoke, &ldquo;S-s-s-say, n-n-n-now l-l-l-lad&rdquo;, and<lb/>
then he was able to speak a few words almost normally. Was<lb/>
it true that, by having some of his blood injected into me, I<lb/>
might acquire the same impediment? That shows how young I<lb/>
was. I was almost certain that Dr. Ames had been &ldquo;kidding&rdquo;<lb/>
me but there was enough uncertainty so that, with little ef-<lb/>
fort, I could worry about my predicament. If yellow fever<lb/>
did not kill me I might have to go through life &ldquo;Say, now<lb/>
lading&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Time passed slowly. I knew, from what I had heard of prev-<lb/>
ious experimental cases, that there was a wide variation in<lb/>
the time between inoculation and the chill that heralds the<lb/>
disease. Perhaps I have over-emphasized worry. The food<lb/>
at Camp Lazear was very much better than we were accustomed<lb/>
to at the barracks and I did not worry enough to impair my<lb/>
appetite. I had a bad quarter-hour, however, when I learned<lb/>
that Dr. Ames was sick and, himself, in the hospital. He had<lb/>
doctored all the experimental cases and had lost but one -<lb/>
Dr. Lazear - in whose honor this camp was named.</p>
<p>At 1:15 p.m. Jan 28 - just three days and one hour after my<lb/>
inoculation - the chill I had been waiting for arrived. At<lb/>
first I thought my imagination was playing tricks on me for,<lb/>
at noon, my temperature and pulse had been normal and I had<lb/>
enjoyed my dinner. At three o'clock I decided that my imag-<lb/>
ination had never been quite that vivid and suggested that my<lb/>
temperature be taken. I was ordered to lie down on my bed<lb/>
and the waiting ambulance was called. I am not at all clear<lb/>
about the happenings of the next few days. I remember being<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f05806016"/>
5<lb/>
enraged because they insisted on carrying me to the ambulance<lb/>
on a litter. They wouldn't even allow me to sit up. But I<lb/>
soon lost interest in all such affairs. My legs, back and<lb/>
arms seemed of immense size and bursting with pain. My back<lb/>
arched, my legs and neck drew back - back - back and I dazedly<lb/>
wondered whether all the pain was because of the abnormal<lb/>
position or whether - if I could bend still farther - it would<lb/>
ease the pain.</p>
<p>And no mile was ever so far. It seemed that those fast-<lb/>
trotting Army mules had been on the way for weeks. I don't<lb/>
remember reaching the hospital.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
