<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804017">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, March 24, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804017</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-03-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ames, Jessie Daniel</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">James, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-03-24">March 24, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804017</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, March 24, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench appreciates the list of documents Jessie Ames sent to him. He poses specific questions about her husband's role in the yellow fever experiments and inquires about old fever charts and carbon copies of various letters.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-03-24">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, March 24, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804017"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-03-24">March 24, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. Jessie D. Ames<lb/>
700 Standard Building<lb/>
Atlanta, Georgia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Ames:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I certainly do appreciate your sending me the most interesting collection<lb/>
of letters and records about your husband. I am studying them with great interest<lb/>
and am making copies of some of the items, assuming that you are willing for me to<lb/>
have them so that I may know as much as I can about your husband's medical work in<lb/>
Cuba and later. Will you permit me to ask you a few specific questions?</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. In the Senate Document 61 (compilation of papers on yellow fever by<lb/>
Reed et al) it says that your husband was in charge of Camp Lazear. When I was in<lb/>
Havana I asked Mr. Moran about this and he said he could not recall having seen your<lb/>
husband at Camp Lazear at any time during the days he (Moran) was there. It was<lb/>
Moran's impression that Dr. Ames stayed at Camp Columbia and of course Moran's memory<lb/>
may have played him false and certainly Moran was <hi>not</hi> trying to minimize Dr. Ames'<lb/>
service. He spoke most highly of them and indicated the great importance of Dr. Ames'<lb/>
successful services to all the soldiers with experimental yellow fever. When in<lb/>
Chicago recently I asked Mr. Lambert about this. He readily recalled Dr. Ames' presence<lb/>
at Camp Lazear. Can you give me any details to amplify the above? Do you recall any<lb/>
incidents, etc. which Dr. Ames told you about his visits to Camp Lazear? Did he sleep<lb/>
at Camp Lazear or at Columbia Barracks while Camp Lazear was open, etc.? I am so<lb/>
anxious to get a complete and accurate picture of his services. I note that Dr. Reed<lb/>
(in his letter of Mar. 11, 1901) mentions Dr. Ames' &ldquo;administrative work of the camp.&rdquo;</item>
<item>2. Some of my correspondents have asked me whether Dr. Ames truly had yellow<lb/>
fever in Cuba. I am delighted to have proof thereof in the form of his &ldquo;yellow fever<lb/>
immunity card&rdquo; which I shall photostat.</item>
<item>3. In Dr. Reed's letter (March 11, 1901) and somewhere else I can't at the<lb/>
moment recall, I have noted that Dr. Ames made a map of the Quemados epidemic of yellow<lb/>
fever--apparently he indicated on a map of the town which houses or blocks were infected<lb/>
with yellow fever. Do you have any idea where that map is? I have hunted for it in<lb/>
the National Archives (Washington) among the mass of data pretaining to yellow fever<lb/>
in Cuba, Reed, etc. etc. Do you happen to have a copy of it in your possession? I am<lb/>
most anxious to trace it. The Reed family do not have it. In Dr. Reed's letter of<lb/>
March 26, 1901 he acknowledges receipt of the map and &ldquo;the accompanying histories of<lb/>
the cases of early and late yellow fever.&rdquo; Do you have any idea where these case<lb/>
histories are? I can't locate them in Washington.</item>
<item>4. Who is the Dr. James referred to in Reed's letter of Mar. 26, 1901? Is<lb/>
it perchance Dr. James Carroll? I suspect not.</item>
<item>5. In Reed's letter of Dec. 21, 1901 he says, &ldquo;Concerning the charts for<lb/>
<hi>your book</hi> ----etc. I hope you will put your experiences in permanent form ----.&rdquo; Did<lb/>
Dr. Ames ever write a book or articles about his yellow fever work?</item>
<pb n="2" id="f05804018"/>
<item>Mrs. Jessie D. Ames</item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>March 24, 1942</item>
<item>6. Do you have any copies of Dr. Ames' photograph either of 1899-1901<lb/>
or of 1902? I can of course have those in your book copied but they aren't any too<lb/>
clear--the one is somewhat soiled, the other somewhat faded. If you have one I'd like<lb/>
very much to have it not only that I may reproduce it in my book but that I may place one<lb/>
permanently in the little medical museum I hope to see erected some day at Camp Lazear.</item>
<item>7. I will copy the group photo with Dr. Ames in the center and show it to<lb/>
Lambert, Moran, Truby, Kean and others to see if they can identify the place and the<lb/>
men therein. I do not recognize any of the men as being those in the yellow fever<lb/>
experiments although I have seen several photos of those men. I assume there is no<lb/>
notation on the back of the photo.</item>
<item>8. In Dr. Ames' letter to the Surgeon-General dated Dec. 30, 1901 he requests<lb/>
charts and clinical records of yellow fever cases treated by him in Cuba. Did he ever<lb/>
receive these charts? I wonder where they are? We could find practically none of<lb/>
them in Washington.</item>
<item>9. In Dr. Ames' letter October 10, 1905 to the Surgeon General he mentions<lb/>
"a book published by the Medical Dept.--&ldquo;History of Yellow Fever at Military Posts.&rdquo;<lb/>
I have not run across such a book. Do you know it? Did Dr. Ames obtain a copy?</item>
<item>10. Could you send me a copy of your &ldquo;Record--Roger Post Ames, M.D., in Yellow<lb/>
Fever Experimentation, etc.&rdquo;? It is important for me to have such a copy and if you<lb/>
have one for me it would save considerable time and expense copying it. Also do you<lb/>
have a copy of the &ldquo;copy&rdquo; placed in your book behind this &ldquo;Record&rdquo; in the same trans-<lb/>
parent envelope?</item>
<item><p>11. I don't suppose you have any more carbon copies of the various letters<lb/>
in enclosures XXXI and XXXII--letters from the War Dept., from Senator Sheppard and<lb/>
General Smith; your interview with General Ireland, letters from Agramonte, Andrus and<lb/>
Lambert. I feel very presumptuous in asking if you do have spare copies but our photo-<lb/>
graphic department is swamped with work as is also my own secretary (due to spring<lb/>
medical meetings) and if I were to ask for copies to be made here it might take some<lb/>
time to get it done and I hate to keep your invaluable book very long.</p>
<p>Incidentally, were you aware that the lower ring of the book seems to have<lb/>
been &ldquo;sprung&rdquo; so that it fails to shut closely and it is difficult to keep the pages in<lb/>
proper place; furthermore there is danger of tearing the lower holes of the transparent<lb/>
sheets. I am trying to be as careful of the book as I can.</p>
<p>In late April I hope to visit Dr. Pinto in Omaha, General Truby and Mrs.<lb/>
Lazear in California. I shall ask each to tell me of Dr. Ames' services.</p></item>
<item>12. In your letter to me (March 5, 1942 - page 2) you say that Dr. Ames<lb/>
&ldquo;was not only in charge of the (experimental) cases but he assisted in selection of the<lb/>
men who submitted to the experimentation and he inoculated them.&rdquo; I have never seen<lb/>
that statement elsewhere. Can you prove it? Surely Drs. Reed or Carroll inoculated<lb/>
the men at Camp Lazear.</item>
<pb n="3" id="f05804019"/>
<item>Mrs. Jessie D. Ames</item>
<item>- 3 -</item>
<item>March 24, 1942</item>
<item>13. You will be interested to know that Agramonte's &ldquo;Inside History<lb/>
of a Great Medical Discovery&rdquo; was first published December, 1915 in &ldquo;Scientific<lb/>
American&rdquo; and later privately reprinted by Agramonte himself in Havana. You can<lb/>
look up the &ldquo;Scientific American&rdquo; in your local public library.</item>
<item>14. In addition to the material in your book do you have any snapshots<lb/>
or photographs of Dr. Ames or his colleagues in Cuba in 1900-1901 at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
Columbia Barracks or Military Hospital %1 or any Havana newspaper clippings about<lb/>
the epidemic or experiments?</item>
</list></p>
<p>Whatever help you can give me I will greatly appreciate. I wish I had<lb/>
known your address last year because I was invited to speak at a medical convention<lb/>
in Atlanta and spent two very pleasant days there. I should indeed have liked to<lb/>
meet you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
