<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05803026">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, February 12, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05803026</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-02-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Frances F.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-02-12">February 12, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05803026</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, February 12, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes that he is looking forward to examining Agramonte's papers. Hench wants the original records in order to reveal the true story behind the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-02-12">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, February 12, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05803026"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-02-12">February 12, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Senora Estella Agramonte de Rodriguez Leon<lb/>
Calle K No. 254<lb/>
Vedado, Havana<lb/>
Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora:</salute>
</opener>
<p>At long last Mrs. Hench and I are returning to Cuba. We will be at<lb/>
the Villa Atlantique, Palm Beach, Florida, from Friday, February 20, to Sunday,<lb/>
February 29, and plan to come by boat, arriving at the Hotel Nacional, Monday<lb/>
March 1, to stay for about a week. I have much to do and many people to see,<lb/>
most important and most pleasant of all will be the opportunity to see you again.<lb/>
I note from your Christmas letter how busy you are and I will try not to bother<lb/>
you more than once. Perhaps we might have a little preliminary conversation at<lb/>
your convenience and then if it would serve your convenience, I could hire a<lb/>
stenographer. I could ask you certain questions and the stenographer could trans-<lb/>
cribe our interview, allowing you to see the transcription and alter it later in<lb/>
any way you saw fit. I am most anxious to learn something of the material that<lb/>
you found in the old trunks. I am also anxious to know whether your mother's<lb/>
diary may have helpful information in it. A long time ago, I believe we dis-<lb/>
cussed the possibility that you might be able to find some extra reprints of<lb/>
your father's, that I haven't been able to get. I am wondering if the correspon-<lb/>
dence between your father and the editor of the Scientific Monthly might have<lb/>
been preserved; this is in connection with the article which your father wrote<lb/>
for the Scientific Monthly, December 1915.</p>
<p>A letter from your father to Mrs. Lazear, years ago, stated that your<lb/>
father had given the address at the unveiling of Lazear's statue in the Finlay<lb/>
Park, across from the main building of the Department of Sanitation (I think<lb/>
that is the building). I have not been able to find your father's address.<lb/>
Perhaps it was not published and the manuscript might be available somewhere.<lb/>
After Reed read in English the paper of the Board at the Pan-American Congress<lb/>
in Havana, February 1901, your father read a Spanish translation of the paper.<lb/>
A copy would be of great interest.</p>
<p>Most important of all, would be the discovery of your father's records<lb/>
of his experiments with mosquitoes, interspersed with notes by Reed, which<lb/>
records of your father he mentioned in a letter to General Kean dated July 3,<lb/>
1908.</p>
<p>I hate very much to bother you like this, however, there is no question<lb/>
but that there are still certain people in the United States who are inclined to<lb/>
discount, somewhat at least, your father's contribution. Certain articles, letters<lb/>
and records available to this country have given them support for their attitude<lb/>
and it is this attitude that I am so anxious to counteract. About the only way<lb/>
I can do it effectively is to find the pertinent and concrete records of what<lb/>
your father did from time to time. Unfortunately, your father did not escape<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05803027"/>
<unclear>Ac</unclear><lb/>
Ag to Am<lb/>
Senora Rodriguez Leon<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
February 12, 1948<lb/>
what happened to every one connected with the affair (and to all of us for that<lb/>
matter). As the years passed by and as he wrote or spoke from time to time of<lb/>
the affairs of 1900, his memory evidently played tricks and he contradicted<lb/>
himself here and there, sometimes rather importantly. This is quite under-<lb/>
standable. Everyone else connected with the affair contradicted himself,<lb/>
many remembered things that never happened, etc., and I have been able to<lb/>
weave my way fairly successfully through the contradictions but it is important<lb/>
for anyone who wishes to give the true story of your father's contribution<lb/>
to get the support of further records if they might be available. You have<lb/>
been such a wonderful help in the past I will try so hard not to impose upon<lb/>
you unduly and I am sure you know of my great desire to present the story<lb/>
truthfully with fairness to all concerned.</p>
<p>Should you wish to give me any instructions, I enclosed a stamped<lb/>
envelope (I found the Cuban stamps left over from my 1941 trip).</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PAH:alc<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
