<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804038">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Josephine Ames Morris, July 21, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804038</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-07-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Morris, Josephine Ames</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-07-21">July 21, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804038</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Josephine Ames Morris, July 21, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes his research on the conquest of yellow fever. He is anxious to learn as much as possible about Ames' contribution.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-07-21">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Josephine Ames Morris, July 21, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804038"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-07-21">July 21, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. Will Morris<lb/>
515 Adams Street<lb/>
New Orleans, La.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Morris:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I understand that you are the sister of Dr. Roger Post Ames. For<lb/>
several years now I have been making quite a study of the conquest of yellow<lb/>
fever particularly the work of the army yellow fever commission in Havana in<lb/>
1900. As a result of these investigations I have uncovered much new informa-<lb/>
tion which I expect to publish in a few articles in medical historical journals<lb/>
and probably in a book. I have received much information from the relatives of<lb/>
Dr. Walter Reed, Dr. Lazear, Dr. Agramonte and others. Permit me to send you<lb/>
three reprints of an article, published in a recent issue of a medical journal.<lb/>
I thought you might like to have one for yourself and perhaps a couple for others<lb/>
of Dr. Ames' close relatives. Should you wish more, I should be delighted to<lb/>
send them to you.</p>
<p>I am anxious to learn as much as I can about Dr. Ames' contribution to<lb/>
the yellow fever problem. According to one view, Dr. Ames actually lived at<lb/>
Camp Lazear and was Executive Officer there and also took care of all of the<lb/>
cases of experimental yellow fever. Mr. Moran, one of the first cases of experi-<lb/>
mental yellow fever, whom I personally visited, does not remember that Dr. Ames<lb/>
actually lived at the camp. However, Mr. Gust Lambert of Chicago, who nursed his<lb/>
cases for Dr. Ames, insists that he was. I am inclined to feel that Mr. Moran's<lb/>
memory is at fault on this point.</p>
<p>Do you have any of Dr. Ames' records, any photographs or clippings or<lb/>
other data of Dr. Ames in connection with the yellow fever experiments? I should<lb/>
be so grateful if you would let me know what you have and if you would lend these<lb/>
to me, sending them to me either by insured express or by insured registered mail.<lb/>
I should be delighted to pay all shipping expenses and will assure you that they<lb/>
will be returned promptly and safely. I have already thus borrowed considerable<lb/>
material from other relatives of the yellow fever investigators and with their<lb/>
permission have had the material photostated, photographed and copied here. It<lb/>
is my hope not only to use these data to complete the full picture of Dr. Ames'<lb/>
contribution but also to exhibit the copies of your data in a little historical<lb/>
medical museum which I am planning to erect on the rediscovered site of Camp<lb/>
Lazear in Havana, Cuba.</p>
<p>Fairly soon I expect to enter military service. I would appreciate it<lb/>
greatly if you would therefore let me know at your earliest convenience if you<lb/>
have anything so that I can arrange to study it and have it copied here before<lb/>
I leave for army service.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
