<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05803028">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, April 15, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05803028</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-04-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter L.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Beauperthuy, Louis-Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-04-15">April 15, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05803028</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, April 15, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench writes about returning Agramonte's papers to her and informing Kean, Truby and Lawrence Reed about important points which the papers clarify. He informs her about his success in lobbying the Cuban government for funds to preserve Building No. 1.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-04-15">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon, April 15, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05803028"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-04-15">April 15, 1948</date>
</dateline>
Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon<lb/>
Calle K No. 254<lb/>
Havana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senora:</salute>
</opener>
<p>On my return home I found a small mountain of work to dispose of and<lb/>
was delayed in having copied the most interesting material concerning your<lb/>
father which you most kindly loaned me. Now it is all copied and according<lb/>
to our conversation, I am <hi>first</hi> sending (air mail, registered mail) by separate<lb/>
post the photostatic copies of all the material.</p>
<p>After you have informed me of their safe arrival, I will return to<lb/>
you the original data in any way you wish, either by (1) air mail registered<lb/>
or insured postage or (2) through the Cuban Embasy from Washington; I will be<lb/>
in Washington May 11 - 12; or (3) through Dr. Pedro Nogueira of Havana (of<lb/>
whom you may have heard as he is much interested in the whole yellow fever<lb/>
story). He will attend the International Congress on Tropical Medicine in<lb/>
Washington May 9 - 18 but will be in the the States about four weeks so he<lb/>
would not be able to get it to you until mid-June. (I realize you do not<lb/>
want any Cuban to examine the data but I could wrap it and <hi>seal</hi> it. I'm sure<lb/>
he'd be glad to deliver it to you in person. However you may wish it returned<lb/>
by one of the first two routes.</p>
<p>I am most grateful to you for your real courtesy in going to so much<lb/>
trouble to find the material and then in lending it to me. It has cleared up<lb/>
several important points on which I (and the published record) were much con-<lb/>
fused. As I promised, I will now call some of it to the attention of certain<lb/>
men in this country (e.g. Generals Kean and Truby and General Reed, Walter<lb/>
Reed's son) who will be most interested to see it. Also I am writing both<lb/>
the Curator of the National Archives and the Adjutant Genera., U. S. Army and<lb/>
will straighten out the record regarding your father's absence from Havana in<lb/>
September - October 1900 (when Lazear died) so that the record of his trip to New<lb/>
York on <unclear>military</unclear> duty will be recorded. I have had extra photostats made and<lb/>
I will deposit them in the appropriate permanent files pertaining to your father.</p>
<p>By separate post I am sending you <hi>photostats</hi> of the following:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Autograph record of yellow (fever) mosquito bites - 8 pages<lb/>
(Also a photograph of pages 1 and 8).</item>
<item>2. Carroll article - 5 pages and envelope with Guiteras note.</item>
<item>3. <unclear>Discuss</unclear> del Agramonte, pronunciado en la ceremonia del des<lb/>
cubrimiento del busto del Finlay - 8 pages.</item>
<item>4. Beauperthuz, Finlay y la comision Americana - 7 pages.</item>
<item>5. Agramonte speech planned for the inauguration of Lazear's<lb/>
tablet in Columbia University - 2 pages.</item>
<item>6. Two letters of October 5, 1900, written in New York (2+1=3)</item>
<pb n="2" id="f05803029"/>
<item>Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon</item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>April 15, 1948</item>
<item>7. Reed to Agramonte, May 25, 1900 - 2 pages.</item>
<item>8. " " November 14, 1899 - 3 pages.</item>
<item>9. " " August 25, 1899 - 2 pages.</item>
<item>10. Agramonte to Adjutant General - February 12, 1903 - 2 pages.</item>
<item>11. Wood to Agramonte, September 22, 1900 - 1 page.</item>
<item>12. Steinhart to Agramonte - October 18, 1900 - 1 page.</item>
<item>13. Scott to Agramonte, September 20, 1900 - 1 page (front and back<lb/>
= 2 pages).</item>
<item>14. Paymaster General to Agramonte, January 13, 1903 - 3 pages<lb/>
(2 pages, one both sides).</item>
<item>15. Ten letters, Sternberg to Agramonte - April 19, 1898 to January 26,<lb/>
1900 - 12 pages.</item>
<item>16. Reed to Agramonte, May 2, 1901; envelope and 2 folders - 7 pages.</item>
<item>17. Statement signed by Spanish volunteers, November 22, 1900 - 3 pages.</item>
<item>18. Agramonte to Sternberg, December 24, 1899 (page and endorsements -<lb/>
2 pages).</item>
<item>19. Hemmeter to Agramonte - 3 letters and small note - 5 pages and note.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Apropos this last item, you may recall that a copy of one (two?) letters<lb/>
from your father to Hemmeter was attached. Several times you offered me your<lb/>
father's letters to Hemmeter but I didn't take it with me as I insisted you'd<lb/>
already given me a copy. On my return I was chagrined to find that your father's<lb/>
letter to Hemmeter of which I <hi>have</hi> a copy is dated February 2, 1913. I do <hi>not</hi><lb/>
have your father's letter of <hi>November 30, 1912</hi> to Hemmeter mentioned in Hemmeter's<lb/>
letter January 18, 1913 (first sentence) and also February 1, 1913. I wish indeed<lb/>
that I could borrow your copy of your father's letter (to Hemmeter) dated November<lb/>
30, 1913. I was so certain your father had only written him one letter, I didn't<lb/>
examine closely enough what you handed me. Would it be possible for you either to<lb/>
lend me the missing letter of November 30, 1912 (without which I cannot fully<lb/>
understand Hemmeter's replies or your father's objections), either sending it<lb/>
to me airmail registered so that I can copy it here (making extras for you) or<lb/>
having it copied (photostated) in Havana at the Alabama Photo Studio (Obispo<lb/>
Street, I think). I would greatly appreciate this.</p>
<p>You may have heard or noted in a recent Havana paper that I was ap-<lb/>
parently successful in my request to the Cuban Government to take steps to pre-<lb/>
serve the caseta (Building One) at Camp Lazear (Finca San Jose). I saw various<lb/>
officials, the Vice-President, officials in the Ministerio Obras Publicas, and<lb/>
others. They telegraphed me that $50,000 had been ordered to be set aside as a<lb/>
start to preserve the caseta. I am very glad of this.</p>
<p>I wish you could be here between May 12 and 20. I have been asked to<lb/>
give the &ldquo;principal oration&rdquo; at the evening session of the International Congress<lb/>
on Tropical Medicine, at the memorial on the Conquest of Yellow Fever (Washington).<lb/>
Then on May 20 in New York City will be unveiled in the Hall of Fame the bust of<lb/>
Reed. I have sent those in charge a photograph of your father and also recommended<lb/>
that they reproduce the Cornwell painting which also includes your father, because<lb/>
even though the ceremony unveils a bust of Reed, his colleagues must be recognized.<lb/>
I'll send you a program of each of these events if I can.</p>
<p>If you can possibly do it, without interfering too much with your very<lb/>
busy life, I do hope you can continue to look for data concerning your father's<lb/>
connection with the yellow fever work. It is so important to bring out <hi>all</hi> the<lb/>
facts. Especially, do I hope you can run across correspondence between your<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05803030"/>
Senora Estela Agramonte Rodriguez Leon<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
April 15, 1948<lb/>
father and the editor of the Scientific Monthly because I am sure it would<lb/>
account for the strange contradictions put into your father's mouth in that<lb/>
article, which I suspect were put in by a re-write man to &ldquo;pep-up&rdquo; or dramatize<lb/>
the article for the laymen. To find such an explanation would be very important.</p>
<p>Again thank you so much and please give the kind regards of Mrs. Hench<lb/>
and me to your husband and son.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
