<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804036">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, July 17, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804036</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-07-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Ames, Jessie Daniel</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Carson (Colo.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-07-17">July 17, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804036</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, July 17, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench appreciates Jessie Ames' answers to his numerous questions about Roger Ames. He requests that she donate some of the original fever charts for an planned exhibition at a Cuban museum.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-07-17">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jessie Daniel Ames, July 17, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804036"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-07-17">July 17, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Miss Jessie Daniel Ames<lb/>
Box 485<lb/>
Emory University<del>, Georgia</del><lb/>
Atlanta, Georgia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Ames:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I appreciate very greatly your last letter with the numerous<lb/>
answers. I have had the fever charts photostated and I am returning them<lb/>
by separate post. Did you know that these have been officially missing for<lb/>
<unclear>1o</unclear>, these many years? I have searched high and low through the Archives<lb/>
Building, Adjutant General's old record division, and the Surgeon General's<lb/>
office, etc. with nary a trace of these fever records. You can imagine my<lb/>
delight when I noticed in your portfolio your husband's letter to the Surgeon<lb/>
General's office asking that the original charts, etc. be loaned to him.<lb/>
Apparently they were either loaned to him by the Surgeon General's office<lb/>
without making a note there as to where they were, or perhaps they were given<lb/>
to him.</p>
<p>I wonder if I can make a very real request of you. I have amassed<lb/>
quite a lot of material on the yellow fever story. Mrs. Lazear has given me<lb/>
many of her husband's items, Generals Kean and Truby have contributed, the<lb/>
Lazear relatives in Baltimore gave me a lot of stuff as did Walter Reed's<lb/>
family; also Dr. Kelly who wrote up the life of Walter Reed handed over to me<lb/>
all of the data which he had collected. They are to go into a permanent<lb/>
yellow fever collection to be kept here in a special collection at the Mayo<lb/>
Clinic, and if my plans materialize, to become the nucleus for a memorial<lb/>
museum to be erected either at Camp Columbia or at Camp Lazear in Havana.<lb/>
I think I told you I acquired title to the little Building No. 1 at Camp<lb/>
Lazear and I am trying to raise the funds to buy the camp site and to have a<lb/>
memorial building erected around the little building. On the walls of this<lb/>
memorial building I plan to have various photographs, fever charts, maps and<lb/>
other data connected with the yellow fever experiments. That was one of the<lb/>
reasons I wanted a photograph of your husband--so that it could be placed there.<lb/>
Would you be willing to present to this collection at least some of your fever<lb/>
charts? Of course, the ones of greatest historical interest are those which<lb/>
concern the first three cases--Carroll, Dean (XY) and Lazear. I wonder if your<lb/>
present use of these fever charts has ended. While I realize that they would<lb/>
have considerable sentimental value to your children, especially the fever chart<lb/>
of your husband, I wonder if you agree with me that they ought to be placed in<lb/>
a proper historical setting. If you feel this way about it, I would be only<lb/>
too grateful for whatever documentary contribution you can make. In the mean-<lb/>
time, however, as I have said, I am returning them all to you with very sincere<lb/>
thanks. Were they to be contributed to the collection they would be shown in<lb/>
the museum with the appropriate identification, as having been presented by you,<lb/>
if you wish with an additional statement &ldquo;In memory of Dr. Ames&rdquo; or something to<lb/>
that effect.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05804037"/>
<p>Mrs. Jessie Daniel Ames</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>July 17, 1942</p>
<p>I am delighted to have the address of Dr. Ames' sister. I<lb/>
shall write to her tactfully, in the manner you suggested.</p>
<p>I hope to be able to continue my investigations and study by<lb/>
correspondence from my military station. We are always so busy here at the<lb/>
Mayo Clinic that it is quite possible, despite the busy life in camp, I<lb/>
will find that I have more time than I have had for some years.</p>
<p>I will be so grateful for the photostat of the Picayune article.<lb/>
Rest assured that I am so impressed by the contribution you have made that<lb/>
any information I can get about him from any source will be most welcome.</p>
<p>Presumably I leave here for about six weeks' training at Fort<lb/>
Custer, Michigan next week, and then I expect to be sent to a station<lb/>
hospital at Camp Carson, Colorado Springs. May I suggest, however, that<lb/>
you write to me here for the time being until you hear from me from camp.<lb/>
If plans materialize, I am to have the rank of lieutenant colonel and will<lb/>
be chief of the medical service of the Camp Carson or some other large<lb/>
station hospital. Somehow or other, my being a medical officer in the<lb/>
army draws me closer to you and your husband and the rest of the men so<lb/>
concerned with the yellow fever project.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
