<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05806115">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, February 7, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05806115</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-02-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">West, Fred G.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">MacArthur, Douglas</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="person">Colby, John</name>
<name type="person">Kneisley, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Schwieger, John D.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Guanajay (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1 (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-02-07">February 7, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05806115</idno>

<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, February 7, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus informs Truby that he is altering some details in his manuscript so that it better accords with Truby's account. Andrus identifies people in photographs, makes references to World War II, and writes about Ames and Agramonte.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-02-07">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to Albert E. Truby, February 7, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05806115"/>
<opener>
J. H. Andrus<lb/>
<dateline>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1942-02-07">2-7-42</date>
</dateline>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<salute>Dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you for your letters of Jan. 26th and Feb. 1st. Of<lb/>
course I am glad that your memoir is finished and I hope you<lb/>
find a publisher very quickly, and I have little doubt but<lb/>
that you will.</p>
<p>My only fear is that, now that it is completed, there will be<lb/>
no more letters from you. I have thoroughly enjoyed our<lb/>
excursions into the past as well as all other phases of our<lb/>
correspondence...</p>
<p>As regards the Guanajay episode, I made a copy of that port-<lb/>
ion of your manuscript which touched upon the same details<lb/>
covered in my &ldquo;Big Moment&rdquo; chapter, and shall re-write mine<lb/>
so they agree.</p>
<p>I realize, of course, that what I write is not of the least<lb/>
importance as my story is not intended for publication.<lb/>
Perhaps some day my son or grandchildren may compare my type-<lb/>
script with your book. They will agree...</p>
<p>As a matter of fact, I am more than willing to agree that you<lb/>
are far more likely to be right, on the minor points at var-<lb/>
iance, than I. The entire incident was the most harrowing<lb/>
that I have ever experienced so there may be some justifica-<lb/>
tion for getting some details distorted after 40 years...</p>
<p>Thank you for the information about cellophane. So far I<lb/>
have been unable to locate any except the thin...</p>
<p>See West<lb/>
folder</p>
<p><hi>The West picture</hi> puts me on the spot. I told you that I<lb/>
was certain that No. 27 in the group photograph was Fred G.<lb/>
West, the detachment barber, and not Clyde L. West. If<lb/>
you find that I was in error in this you will question the<lb/>
accuracy of many other assertions I have made.</p>
<p>In spite of the fact that you have a letter from Clyde say-<lb/>
ing that he is No. 27, I stick to my guns. (There must<lb/>
be some explanation of this - are you sure that he refers<lb/>
to the same group photograph we refer to?)</p>
<p>This involves my reliability or I would not persist. If<lb/>
anyone were to tell me that No. 1, in the group, was Dr.<lb/>
Pinto instead of Lieut. Truby, you would not blame me for<lb/>
dissenting. I knew Fred G. and Clyde L. very much better<lb/>
than either of the officers referred to.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05806116"/>
<p>General Truby</p>
<p>Page 2.</p>
<p>If there was no way of settling this issue I would have drop-<lb/>
ped it but there is a way. Under date of Dec. 18th I had<lb/>
a letter from another guinea pig, James L. Hanberry, in which<lb/>
he asked if I had Clyde West's address.<lb/>
(I haven't. He visited me several times<lb/>
when I was at Walter Reed Hospital and gave<lb/>
me a Maryland address. A Christmas card<lb/>
mailed there this year was returned as unde-<lb/>
liverable.)</p>
<p>If you will send a print of the group photograph to<lb/>
James L. Hanberry,<lb/>
61 Summers Ave.,<lb/>
Orangeburg, S. C. he should be able to<lb/>
clear up the matter of identification of West and to check<lb/>
all others in the group...</p>
<p>Had a letter from Lambert, today, saying that Dr. Hench had<lb/>
visited him on his return from Washington two or three weeks<lb/>
ago and planned to return at a later date. He says that<lb/>
Dr. Hench also visited Forbes' mother.</p>
<p>Forbes has been something of a mystery - to me at least.<lb/>
I don't remember the source but from somewhere I have gather-<lb/>
ed the impression that the Vererans' Bureau have had no<lb/>
address for Forbes and have been unable to pay him any of the<lb/>
annuity to which he is entitled...</p>
<p>Your comments relative the Batan Peninsula arrived yesterday<lb/>
with the current &ldquo;Life&rdquo; containing a map of the area.<lb/>
Your letter and the map, in combination, give me a far better<lb/>
understanding of Gen. MacArthur's situation.</p>
<p>One vital element does not seem to be clearly understood by<lb/>
our military analysts and commentators. Some seem to<lb/>
think that Gen. MacArthur is being supplied to replenish<lb/>
disbursements of food and munitions. Others, that he can<lb/>
not be supplied and that he and his men face inevitable<lb/>
death or capture. Which is right?</p>
<p>I am terribly disappointed at the way the war - all of it ex-<lb/>
cept on the Russian front - is going.</p>
<p>With best wishes and kindest regards,</p>
<p>Sincerely,<lb/>
J H Andrus</p>
<pb n="3" id="f05806117"/>
<p>General Truby</p>
<p>Page 3.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>p 79 &ldquo;The Governor-General had, of course, approved the Board's<lb/>
plan of testing Finlay's theory on volunteers&rdquo;...</p>
<p>Are you sure General Wood's approval hadbbeen secured at this<lb/>
time? Dean, you will remember, had been designated as XY<lb/>
because authorization for his inoculation had not been obtained.</p></item>
<item>Yes</item>
<item>p 92 On the sixth line you refer to the Post Commander's consent<lb/>
not having been given. Was the Post Commander's consent<lb/>
necessary in addition to authorization by General Wood? Yes as he<lb/>
did not then know of Reed's conference with Gen Wood-</item>
<item>p 115 Folk (not Faulk) Writing of Folk and Jernegan you say,<lb/>
&ldquo;Both of these men <add>then</add> took the mosquito test and both developed<lb/>
yellow fever. Jernegan's mosquito inoculation was nega-<lb/>
tive. He was finally given yellow fever by blood inocula-<lb/>
tion. You cover this beautifully on p 113.</item>
<item>p 116 No. 14 in the group photograph is not Jernegan but Private<lb/>
Kneisley. Jernegan's likeness in the painting, &ldquo;Conquerors<lb/>
of Yellow Fever&rdquo; was copied from a print I furnished Mr. Kel-<lb/>
log. I knew both men and am certain.</item>
<item>p 177 No. 40 is not Weatherwalks but Private John Colby.</item>
<item>p 118 Add to &ldquo;Volunteers Not Shown&rdquo; Warren G. Jernegan and Edward<lb/>
Weatherwalks.</item>
<item><p>p 118 - foot &ldquo;During the entire period of the Board's work, he<lb/>
(Agramonte) was in charge of the large department laboratory,<lb/>
located at Military Hospital No. 1, on Principe Hill.&rdquo;<lb/>
The <unclear>Lab.</unclear><lb/>
was <unclear>contained</unclear>-</p>
<p>Military Hospital No. 1 was closed April 29, 1900. I have<lb/>
record of this in a sketchy diary kept during my military ser-<lb/>
vice. I recall that all patients had been removed and the<lb/>
large detachment of Corps Men assigned to different posts.<lb/>
Finally, on April 29, there were not more than 10 or 12 of us<lb/>
left. All of us departed on that date, Schwieger and I<lb/>
going to Guanajay and the others to other posts.</p>
<p>On page 53 you speak of Dr. Ames reporting to Columbia Barracks<lb/>
on April 10, 1900, coming from Military Hospital No. 1.<lb/>
His reassignment was probably due to closing No. 1.</p>
<p>I have no doubt about Dr. Agramonte having a laboratory in<lb/>
Havana that occupied most of his time. He MUST have had<lb/>
duties elsewhere or he would have died of boredom for he was<lb/>
rarely at Major Reed's laboratory and there was little he<lb/>
COULD have done at Camp Lazear. I was not at the latter<lb/>
point and do not know whether he ever did anything there<lb/>
or not.</p></item>
<item>Note</item>
<item>p 152 Am not sure about experimental cases being taken to the yel-<lb/>
low fever hospital on their beds. I was not. I was,<lb/>
however, taken on a litter.</item></list></p>
<p>With kindest regards and every good wish,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>J H Andrus</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
