<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05808077">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Mrs. George Carroll to Philip Showalter Hench, May 2, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Carroll, Mrs. George</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05808077</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-05-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-05-02">May 2, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05808077</idno>
<title>Letter from Mrs. George Carroll to Philip Showalter Hench, May 2, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Mrs. Carroll claims that Hench never returned the papers she loaned to him two years ago. She has lost all interest in the Carroll affair and does not wish to have further contact with Hench regarding the matter. She comments on the credit given to Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-05-02">
<head>Letter from Mrs. George Carroll to Philip Showalter Hench, May 2, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05808077"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1956-05-02">May 2, 1956.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Just a few lines in reply to your letter of April 16th (unsigned) re-<lb/>
questing permission to photostat certain papers in the Carroll collection<lb/>
when you are in Washington in the near future.</p>
<p>The papers are not in my possession as I stored them for safe keeping<lb/>
just before I entered the hospital last November as I did not know what might<lb/>
happen. In looking over my correspondence with you, I find that you have<lb/>
never returned the papers I loaned you when you were here February 19, 1954.<lb/>
A later letter shows that you were having the photostatic work done and that<lb/>
you would send the papers by registered mail. I trusted you with these papers<lb/>
as I thought you would keep your word.</p>
<p>I do not want to be rude but I have lost all interest in the Carroll<lb/>
affair because it is much too late to remedy the situation for all those most<lb/>
interested have passed on. It is regrettable that Mother Carroll who knew<lb/>
all the facts did not have some one write a book during her life-time. My<lb/>
husband was ill for so long that he was not able to do so either. The two<lb/>
remaining children were so young when their father died that they do not<lb/>
remember many things. It has been Walter Reed's show all the way through,<lb/>
partly because he was the commanding officer in charge at the time (who<lb/>
always gets the credit) and partly because the Reed family promoted the<lb/>
affair from every angle. I attended the affair at the Cuban Embassy in April<lb/>
1954 and no sixteen year old girl ever acted so silly as Blossom Reed did<lb/>
when the Cuban Ambassador presented the medal to her. I was thoroughly<lb/>
disgusted.</p>
<p>Please return the papers I loaned you on February 19, 1954 as I loaned<lb/>
them to you in good faith, then we can consider the matter closed. It is<lb/>
immaterial to me whether Dr. Carroll gets credit due him at this late date<lb/>
for what does it matter when all who would appreciate it are gone. After<lb/>
all &ldquo;the paths of glory lead but to the grave&rdquo; and who cares about you or me or<lb/>
any one after the last call is sounded.</p>
<p>I had the operation last November 16th and it was an ordeal. I got an<lb/>
infection in left foot and suffered terribly. I was lame before the operation<lb/>
and I am still lame. The only difference I can see is that I exchanged sharp<lb/>
agonizing pains for <unclear>weak</unclear> tender feet. The metatarsal heads were removed<lb/>
and as I said it was an ordeal. The operation lasted four hours and I was in<lb/>
the hospital three weeks. When the main <unclear>piors</unclear> of a bridge are removed, you<lb/>
have a weak structure which eventually collapses. That will probably be the<lb/>
way with my feet but I was so miserable before that I decided to take a chance.<lb/>
One cannot foresee the outcome but I refuse to worry for in the words of<lb/>
Somerset Maugham &ldquo;I have my suitcase packed and am waiting for the last train.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Sorry I will not be able to help you and awaiting return of the papers I<lb/>
loaned you, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Mrs. George S. H. Carroll</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
