<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804069">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: Supporting evidence for the role of Roger Post Ames in the Yellow Fever Campaign, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804069</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Parker, Charles</name>
<name type="person">Angles, Eduardo</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Bridges, C. H.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Jackson Barracks, New Orleans (La.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804069</idno>
<title>Report: Supporting evidence for the role of Roger Post Ames in the Yellow Fever Campaign, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This report supports Ames' inclusion in the Act, approved February 28, 1929, to recognize the public service rendered and disabilities incurred as voluntary subjects for inoculation during the yellow fever investigations in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report: Supporting evidence for the role of Roger Post Ames in the Yellow Fever Campaign, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804069"/>
<p>FROM MRS. ROGER P. AMES</p>
<p><hi>R E C O R D</hi></p>
<p>ROGER POST AMES, M.D.<lb/>
in<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER EXPERIMENTATION<lb/>
at<lb/>
CAMP LAZEAR, CUBA<lb/>
1900 - 1901<lb/>
WITH SUPPORTING EVIDENCE</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05804070"/>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>Record and Supporting Evidence<lb/>
In Re:- Yellow Fever Campaign in Cuba<lb/>
of<lb/>
Roger Post Ames</hi></head>
<item><p>I. <hi>History of Act</hi> - sought to be amended.</p>
<p>The Act sought to be amended reads as follows:<lb/>
&ldquo;An Act to recognize the high public service rendered by Major<lb/>
Walter Reed and those associated with him in the discovery of<lb/>
the cause of and the means of transportation of Yellow Fever&rdquo;-<lb/>
Approved February 28, 1929.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. <hi>Who Are Included in This Act</hi>.<lb/>
&ldquo;That in special recognition of the high public service rendered<lb/>
and disabilities contracted in the interest of humanity and<lb/>
science as voluntary subjects for the experimentations during<lb/>
the Yellow Fever investigations in Cuba.&rdquo; - twenty-three persons<lb/>
wore chosen.</item>
<item>2. <hi>How They Were Chosen.</hi><lb/>
In a <unclear>hearing</unclear> before the Military Affairs Committee, the Surgeon<lb/>
General, then General Ireland, assisted by Colonel J. R. Kean,<lb/>
retired when asked to define and limit the classes and persons<lb/>
to whom such recognition was due, arbitrarily set three classes<lb/>
and named the persons.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>a. The four composing the Board on the basis of their<lb/>
scientific contributions, one of whom died before<lb/>
the experimental work in which the others were in-<lb/>
volved was begun.</item>
<item>b. Those who were infected voluntarily by the Yellow<lb/>
Fever mosquito.</item>
<item>c. Those who were infected voluntarily by blood infusions.<lb/>
This classification was agreed upon but not written into the Act.</item>
</list></item></list></p></item>
<item>II. <hi>Roger Post Ames Should Be Included in the Act under Class a</hi>.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>A. <hi>He Was Directly in Charge of the Experimental Camp</hi>.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. &ldquo;Regarding his (Dr. Ames) connection with the work of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board, at the head of which was Major Walter<lb/>
Reed, the records show that he (Dr. Ames) <hi>was on duty at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, the experimental camp established by the Board<lb/>
from the date of its establishment, November 20, 1900, until<lb/>
February 28, 1901, on which date the camp was discontinued</hi>.&rdquo;<lb/>
Letter from G. H. Bridges (S) Major General, to Mrs. Roger<lb/>
Post Ames, November 19, 1929.</item>
<item>2. &ldquo;<hi>Dr. Ames was Surgeon in immediate command of Camp Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear</hi>, United States Sanitary Experimental Station near<lb/>
Quemados. And he was Attending Surgeon of the United States<lb/>
Army Yellow Fever Commission. A telephone connected Major<lb/>
Reed's room at Columbia Barracks with Dr. Ames' tent at<lb/>
Camp Lazear.&rdquo; Daily Picayuno, New Orleans, July 30, 1905,<lb/>
in re Yellow Fever Epidemic in that city to which Dr. Ames<lb/>
had been sent by the Surgeon General to take charge of Jack-<lb/>
son Barracks.</item>
</list></item>
<pb n="3" id="f05804071"/>
<item>-2-</item>
<item>B. <hi>Command of Camp Lazear Was Not in Regular Line of Duty</hi>.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. &ldquo;This the second series of experiments began November 20, at<lb/>
an <hi>experimental camp near Quemados</hi>, called Camp Lazear, and<lb/>
embraced 14 cases.&rdquo; Document No. 10, 59th Congress, 2nd ses-<lb/>
sion, page 2.</item>
<item>2. &ldquo;<hi>A camp was especially constructed for the experiments</hi> about<lb/>
four miles from Habana, christened Camp Lazear.&rdquo; Idem page 13.</item>
<item>3. &ldquo;The necessity for <hi>an experimental camp became more imperative</hi><lb/>
as time passed. --- We immediately set about choosing a loca-<lb/>
tion for our camp----on the twentieth of November we <hi>inaugurated<lb/>
our camp which we called Camp Lazear</hi> in honor to the memory of<lb/>
our dead colleague, <hi>consisting then of seven army tents guarded<lb/>
by a military garrison</hi>.&rdquo; Pages 24-25 &ldquo;Inside History of a Great<lb/>
Medical Discovery.&rdquo; by Dr. Aristide Agramonte.</item>
<item>4. &ldquo;Dr. Ames was Surgeon in immediate command of Camp Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear ---<hi>A telephone connected Major Reed's room at Columbia<lb/>
Barracks with Dr. Ames' tent at Camp Lazear</hi>.&rdquo; New Orleans<lb/>
Picayune, July 30, 1905.</item>
<item>I have<lb/>
copy <unclear>the<lb/>
Lazear</unclear></item>
<item>5. &ldquo;Dr. Ames had no connection with the yellow fever Board <hi>before<lb/>
the establishment of Camp Lazear</hi>; he attended the cases of<lb/>
Drs. Carroll and Lazear when they came down with the fever <hi>in<lb/>
the regular course of duty at Columbia Barracks</hi>.&rdquo; Dr. Agramonte<lb/>
to Mrs. Ames, May 27, 1930.</item>
</list></item>
<item>C. <hi>Charged With Some Responsibility In Securing Volunteers and Subjects<lb/>
for the Experiment</hi>.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. &ldquo;I noticed that in Major Kean's notes recently prepared for the<lb/>
Secretary to the Surgeon General, I am credited with being<lb/>
offered the sum of $200 for my part in the experiments at Que-<lb/>
mados. As you are the only person with whom I discussed this<lb/>
matter prior to submitting to the experiments, I wish you would<lb/>
kindly correct this mistake.---you told me that Major Reed was<lb/>
ready to pay up to $500. You advised me to accept.---You had<lb/>
made a similar offer to Mr. Parker----. Since I never discussed<lb/>
the matter with Dr. Carroll and the money end was never brought<lb/>
up afterwards, you are probably the only one of the entire Medi-<lb/>
cal Board now living who can testify to the actual amount of-<lb/>
fered me.&rdquo; Letter to Dr. Ames from John J. Moran (Named in the<lb/>
Act) March 14, 1907.</item>
</list></item>
<item>D. <hi>Rendered Scientific Services of Greatest Value</hi><lb/>
Roger Post Ames was a trained, scientific expert in the diag-<lb/>
nosis and treatment of Yellow Fever:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. <hi>Classed with Dr. Lazear</hi><lb/>
&ldquo;The cases studied during the Quemados epidemic had been diag-<lb/>
nosed by a board of physicians <hi>selected largely by reason of<lb/>
their familiarity with yellow fever</hi>. This Board consisted of<lb/>
Drs. Nicola Silverio, Manuel Herera, Eduardo Angles and act-<lb/>
ing <hi>Assistant Surgeon Roger Post Ames and Jesse W. Lazear</hi>.&rdquo;<lb/>
Major Reed, U.S. Army Etiology of Yellow Fever, page 4.</item>
<item>2. Special Order No. 83 attached him to the Board investigating<lb/>
contagious diseases in Cuba.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f05804072"/>
<item>-3-</item>
<item>3. &ldquo;--he was detailed---to take care of the experimental cases. He<lb/>
certainly had excellent judgment and although <hi>the cases were of-<lb/>
ficially confirmed</hi> by a special board, <hi>he was the first who came<lb/>
in contact with them and made the earliest diagnosis</hi>.&rdquo; Dr. Aristide<lb/>
Agramonte to Mrs. Ames, May 27, 1930.</item>
<item>4. The famous case carried as XY on the records for so long was<lb/>
diagnosed by Dr. Roger Post Ames upon request of Major Reed: &ldquo;and<lb/>
his attending physician, Dr. Roger Post Ames, U.S.A., an expert<lb/>
in the diagnosis and treatment of this disease did not hesitate<lb/>
to diagnose XY's attack as one of well pronounced yellow fever.<lb/>
The diagnosis, therefore, not being in doubt----&rdquo; Major Walter<lb/>
Reed, &ldquo;Etiology of Yellow Fever&rdquo; page 15.</item>
<item>5. &ldquo;His (Dr. Ames) scientific services began when a case developed;<lb/>
as soon as high temperature or the least symptom appeared, the<lb/>
case---was placed under Dr. Ames' charge until his final recovery.<lb/>
<hi>They all recovered</hi>, a fact which we all thought was a &ldquo;feather in<lb/>
his cap.&rdquo; Dr. Agramonte in a letter to Mrs. Ames, May 27, 1930.</item>
<item>6. In charge of Camp Lazear, the success of the experiment depended<lb/>
upon Dr. Ames' scientific knowledge of diagnosis and treatment of<lb/>
yellow fever.<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>&ldquo;The highly dangerous character of these experiments and the<lb/>
good fortune of the Board in its second and third series of<lb/>
cases is shown by the fact that <hi>Dr. Guiteras, of Haban, in a<lb/>
series of seven cases</hi>, innoculated in Habana, <hi>lost three bring-<lb/>
ing his experiments abruptly to an end</hi>.&rdquo; Senate Document #10<lb/>
59th Congress, 2nd session, page 3.</item>
<item>"This terminated our experiments with mosquitoes which the<lb/>
necessarily performed on human beings, <hi>fortunately did not<lb/>
cause a single death</hi>. &ldquo;Inside History of a Great Medical<lb/>
Discovery&rdquo; page 30. Aristide Agramonte.</item>
<item>See also Number 5 above.</item>
</list></item></list></item></list></item>
<item>III. <hi>Major Walter Reed Personally Depended Upon Dr. Ames' Scientific<lb/>
Training</hi>.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. &ldquo;Carroll (James of the Act) has arrived and of course has given<lb/>
me some of the latest news. Hanberry's chart is simply <hi>beautiful</hi>,<lb/>
indeed this is an invaluable case.&rdquo; Letter from Major Reed to Dr.<lb/>
Ames, March 11, 1901.</item>
<item>2. &ldquo;Now, my dear doctor, pray tell me when I may expect that map of<lb/>
Quemados with your notes thereon? I am so anxious to get it, as<lb/>
I need it very much in preparing a paper that I am now writing.<lb/>
Please, therefore, send it right along by mail under government<lb/>
stamp without waiting for Mrs. O'Reilly's case. I will appreciate<lb/>
it so much if you will.&rdquo; Major Walter Reed to Dr. Ames, March 11,<lb/>
1901.</item>
<item>3. &ldquo;Please accept my sincere thanks for the map of the infected Dis-<lb/>
trict in Quemados together with the accompanying histories of<lb/>
early and late Yellow Fever. The labor you have given to this<lb/>
work is fully appreciated by me.&rdquo; Major Walter Reed to Dr. Ames,<lb/>
March 26, 1901.</item>
</list></item>
<pb n="5" id="f05804073"/>
<item>-4-</item>
<item>IV. <hi>In Performing This Special Duty for the Advancement of Science, Dr.<lb/>
Ames Exposed Himself to the Disease</hi>.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. On January 26, 1901, while in line of special duty, Dr. Ames de-<lb/>
veloped symptoms of Yellow Fever but he was not committed as a<lb/>
patient to the hospital until January 28. He returned to duty<lb/>
on February 5. Major Alec Stark attended him and signed the neces-<lb/>
sary papers which are on file in the War Department.</item>
<item>2. &ldquo;Because he was considered immune to Yellow Fever, himself claiming<lb/>
to have had the disease or much contact with cases in New Orleans.<lb/>
I do not know upon what basis his immunity was founded.&rdquo; Dr. Agra-<lb/>
monte to Mrs. Ames, May 27, 1930.</item>
<item>3. &ldquo;I sincerely hope you have quite recovered from your recent &lsquo;attack&rsquo;<lb/>
and that you are now immune to all &lsquo;bugs&rsquo; that fly or <unclear>creep</unclear>.&rdquo;<lb/>
Major Reed to Dr. Ames, March 11, 1901.</item>
<item>4. In a conversation with his wife just before he was placed in charge<lb/>
of Jackson Barracks in the epidemic of 1905, by the Surgeon General,<lb/>
Dr. Ames spoke of his case of <unclear>Fever</unclear> and of his fear of death since<lb/>
he had knowingly exposed himself to the disease when he took charge<lb/>
of the cases in Cuba.</item>
</list></item></list></p>
<p>- - - -</p>
<p>Roger Post Ames is entitled to inclusion in the above named Act:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>II.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>A- He was directly in charge of the Experimental Camp. Lazear.</item>
<item>B- This command was special and not regular duty.</item>
<item>C- Assisted in securing volunteers for the experimentations.</item>
<item>D- Rendered scientific services of great value upon the success<lb/>
of which depended the success of the entire experiment.</item>
</list></item>
<item>III.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>A- Major Reed depended upon Dr. Ames' scientific knowledge of<lb/>
diagnosis and treatment of Yellow Fever.</item>
</list></item>
<item>IV.<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>A- A non-<unclear>immune</unclear>, Dr. Ames exposed himself and contracted the<lb/>
fever in carrying out special duties in the advancement of<lb/>
science.</item>
</list></item></list></p>
<pb n="6" id="f05804074"/>
<p>CALENDAR NO. 1560</p>
<p>SENATE</p>
<p>71st Congress<lb/>
3d Session<lb/>
Report<lb/>
No. 1503</p>
<p>Mr. Steck, from the Committee on Military Affairs, submitted<lb/>
the following</p>
<p><hi>R E P O R T</hi></p>
<p>The purpose of this bill is to include the <unclear>name</unclear><lb/>
of Roger P. Ames among those honored by the act of February 28,<lb/>
1929. Although Doctor Ames's name does not appear among those<lb/>
recommended by the Surgeon General of the Army to be included<lb/>
in the above-mentioned act, there is no doubt that he was pres-<lb/>
ent and was one of those in immediate charge of the yellow fever<lb/>
experimental camp, known as Camp Lazier, near Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
Cuba, the latter part of 1900 and fore part of 1901, and actually<lb/>
contracted yellow fever while at the camp.</p>
<p>Although the report of the Adjutant General of the<lb/>
Army claims that Roger P. Ames took part in or submitted him-<lb/>
self in any manner to the experiments conducted by the yellow<lb/>
fever board, it is plain that he was on duty at the camp, in<lb/>
immediate charge, and did contract yellow fever. In view of<lb/>
this fact, your committee feels that he is entitled to the honor<lb/>
bestowed on others connected with these experiments.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
