<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, March 5, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Ames, Jessie Daniel</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-03-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Laredo (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">Jackson Barracks (La.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-03-05">March 5, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804009</idno>
<title>Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, March 5, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Jessie Ames will send Hench some of her husband's papers. She thinks the success of the yellow fever experiments depended on her husband and that he was not immune while he was nursing the volunteers. She was hurt by Kean and Ireland's lack of support for her husband being honored.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-03-05">
<head>Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, March 5, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804009"/>
<opener>
WILL W. ALEXANDER<lb/>
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR<lb/>
C. H. TOBIAS<lb/>
ASSOCIATE DIRECTOR<lb/>
M. ASHBY JONES, HONORARY PRESIDENT<lb/>
HOWARD W. ODUM, PRESIDENT<lb/>
CHARLES S. JOHNSON, FIRST VICE PRESIDENT<lb/>
MRS. W. A. NEWELL, SECOND VICE PRESIDENT<lb/>
RUFUS <unclear>E</unclear>. CLEMENT, THIRD VICE PRESIDENT<lb/>
EMILY H. CLAY<lb/>
<unclear>SECRETARY &middot; ASST. TREASURER</unclear><lb/>
J. SHERRARD KENNEDY<lb/>
TREASURER<lb/>
<dateline>
Commission on Interracial Cooperation<lb/>
INCORPORATED<lb/>
710 STANDARD BUILDING<lb/>
Atlanta, Georgia<lb/>
<date value="1942-03-05">March 5, 1942</date>
</dateline>
R. B. ELEAZER<lb/>
EDUCATIONAL DIRECTOR<lb/>
MRS. JESSIE DANIEL AMES<lb/>
GENERAL FIELD SECRETARY<lb/>
TELEPHONE<lb/>
WALNUT 7962<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Early next week, on Monday to be exact, I shall send you by express<lb/>
a portfolio containing the data I have gathered and organized on<lb/>
the record of my husband, Dr. Roger Post Ames, in the Army's fight<lb/>
to demonstrate to the satisfaction of the Congress and the public<lb/>
that Yellow Fever was carried by mosquitoes.</p>
<p>I shall send a covering letter giving an index to the contents<lb/>
with designations as to original records which you cannot find else-<lb/>
where. These are, as you know, of great value to me and to my<lb/>
family.</p>
<p>You have asked my opinion of the treatment accorded my husband.<lb/>
Without this invitation from you, I should refrain from saying more<lb/>
than is contained in the portfolio. Now, I shall express my opinion<lb/>
anew.</p>
<p>I want to say first, however, that my husband did not talk about the<lb/>
Cuba situation nor did he say anything explicit on the treatment<lb/>
given him both by the Army and the Yellow Fever Board. He did speak<lb/>
of Major Reed in terms of admiration and even affection. His remarks<lb/>
on Dr. Carroll and Dr. Lazear were not as commendatory though I<lb/>
cannot recall that there was anything personal in their tone. He<lb/>
was not a man given to griping.</p>
<p>When Dr. Lazear died, the Board was left with no member who knew any<lb/>
thing about Yellow Fever. That from the records. This was a bad<lb/>
blow I think because the members had to turn to the only other person<lb/>
who had experience and who could be depended upon to give an early<lb/>
and correct diagnosis. The difficulty in this was that this other<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05804010"/>
<unclear>meaning</unclear> Ames<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
person was a young doctor, just turned thirty-<add>one</add> and a civilian to boot.<lb/>
The Board wanted the credit for themselves and the Army. The members<lb/>
looked with more than antagonism on the Public Health and Marine Hos-<lb/>
pital Service, an antagonism which developed into downright jealousy<lb/>
and bickering in the last epidemic in this country, New Orleans, in 1905.</p>
<p>Not a member of the Board had had Yellow Fever at that time nor did<lb/>
Major Reed ever have it. Yet the success of the experiment depended<lb/>
upon one expert who was not of them. He was not an immune as was later<lb/>
proven by his contracting Yellow Fever while the experiment was going<lb/>
on. It has always seemed to me that these two conditions colored<lb/>
the attitude of the Board from the beginning. That is a young civilian<lb/>
doctor and a non-immune upon whom they had to lean.</p>
<p>My husband was not appointed to fill the vacancy created by Dr. Lazear's<lb/>
death. I think the conditions outlined above were the causes. Roger<lb/>
was put in charge of the experimental cases; according to correspondence<lb/>
included in the portfolio, he not only was in charge of the cases but he<lb/>
<hi>assisted in selection of the men</hi> who submitted to the experimentation<lb/>
and he innoculated them; checked the progress of the infection and<lb/>
reported to Major Reed's headquarters when symptoms developed. His<lb/>
success is shown in the records in the portfolio.</p>
<p>what proof?</p>
<p>As a reward for Roger's services he was commissioned a Captain and later<lb/>
a Major of Volunteers, commission which were revoked when he was discharged<lb/>
from the service after a term of service in the Philippines.</p>
<p>That the Army still depended upon him is evidenced by the fact that he was<lb/>
ordered to Laredo, Texas when Yellow Fever broke there but this time<lb/>
as a Contract Surgeon, a position viewed by the Army as neither fish -<lb/>
flesh or good red herring. At Laredo he made his first contacts of<lb/>
any importance with the Public Health and Marine Hospital Service.<lb/>
After a successful career there during which he and I were married, he<lb/>
was ordered to report for duty at Jackson Barracks to take over during<lb/>
the Yellow Fever epidemic of 1905. It was there that there was real<lb/>
trouble with both the officers at the Barracks and with the Army. This<lb/>
was his trouble. The Army and the Marine Hospital Service mixed it also.</p>
<p>Of my own knowledge, I can state the following facts; Major Baily and<lb/>
Dr. Little of Jackson Barracks wanted the troops moved. They did not<lb/>
believe in the Yellow Fever mosquito theory. Upon my husband's advice,<lb/>
they were kept at the Barracks. Colonel Maus was compelled to come over<lb/>
in order to give authority to the advice of my husband. A contract<lb/>
Surgeon has none, not even a reputation. As a result of the decision to<lb/>
follow my husband's advice and because the Surgeon General and Colonel Kean<lb/>
had complete confidence in my husband's ability to handle the situation,<lb/>
a confidence born of the experiments in Cuba, the troops did stay. Both<lb/>
Major Baily and Dr. Little placed every obstruction in the path of my<lb/>
husband's work.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f05804011"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>During the height of the epidemic, my husband took the soldiers on<lb/>
excursions out to Lake Ponchetrain for recreation and possibly for their<lb/>
morale. They returned always before dark, of course. This along with<lb/>
other of his acts, kept the situation in the Barracks tense.</p>
<p>My opinion of the Yellow Fever Board and my conclusions on the reasons<lb/>
why my husband was treated as he was were more than confirmed by two<lb/>
interviews I had in Washington and by letters from Senator Sheppard of<lb/>
Texas giving the results of interviews which he had.</p>
<p>Senator Sheppard found that there was no record of my husband's service<lb/>
of any value in the War Department. He wrote me that he had his record<lb/>
inserted. I don't know whether this was done or not. I know Senator<lb/>
Sheppard thought it was. I wrote out an account of the interview with<lb/>
Surgeon General Ireland immediately after I had it - a copy is in the<lb/>
portfolio so I will not go into that.</p>
<p>I did not write out an account of the interview I had with Colonel Kean.<lb/>
It was too painful. Though General Ireland's was no less brutal than<lb/>
Colonel Kean's remarks they were not as painful, for Roger had not known<lb/>
General Ireland nor had he counted him a friend. From Colonel Kean's<lb/>
correspondence with my husband, some of the letters of which are included<lb/>
in the portfolio, I had expected something different from him. However,<lb/>
he belittled the service of my husband; he reproved me for seeking some<lb/>
recognition of his services to the Yellow Fever Board when he told me<lb/>
that my husband was a modest man who would be the last to approve of my<lb/>
actions in trying to get such recognition; he said that there were others<lb/>
who were left out of this field of recognition and that if they reopened<lb/>
the list, it would be flooded with such people. Upon being pressed to<lb/>
name more than two others, my husband and Mr. Lambert, he failed to give<lb/>
a single name. He was somewhat peppery because I continued to insist at<lb/>
this point. He said that when the lists were made up they had decided<lb/>
the classes and that my husband did not fall into either class. He also<lb/>
said, and this amazed me, that he had no idea that Roger had a family.<lb/>
This amazed me because of correspondence from him in which he spoke of<lb/>
&ldquo;the bride.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I think nothing quite so bowled me over as what I call Colonel Kean's<lb/>
attitude toward my husband and his general belittling of him as well as<lb/>
of his professional service. I have not spoken of this interview except<lb/>
to one man whose friendship for Roger has lasted through all these years.<lb/>
He told me, this friend, to go back and write out both interviews while<lb/>
they were still fresh. I could not do that in the case of Major Kean.<lb/>
I think that the only real hurt that was given me in this whole affair<lb/>
came by way of Colonel Kean.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f05804012"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>The slur on my husband's honesty, integrity, and honor given by both<lb/>
Colonel Kean and General Ireland in their manner of speaking of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever which my husband contracted did hurt. &ldquo;The less said about<lb/>
that the better&rdquo; both told me, as though they had gotten to-gether on<lb/>
their words.</p>
<p>I can understand now just why they said that. The one disquieting ele-<lb/>
ment or rather the most disquieting element in the whole story was that<lb/>
a non-immune civilian doctor took such enormous risks, risks that not<lb/>
one of the Board would take. They chose to assume that being an immune<lb/>
my husband was doing nothing specially dangerous. I am equally sure,<lb/>
though this is not susceptible proof, that my husband did nothing to dis-<lb/>
abuse their minds if he knew they were making such an assumption. If<lb/>
he did not, it was not because he wanted to be a hero but because he<lb/>
believed profoundly in the mosquito theory; he believed that he could<lb/>
guard himself and escape infection; that he feared he might not be sent<lb/>
to take over if it was known he had never had Yellow Fever. He had spent<lb/>
all his professional life up to then in working with Yellow Fever. That<lb/>
was in fact his specialty and he wanted to continue experimenting with<lb/>
it until the theory was proven. These statements are made without any<lb/>
other support than my knowledge of my husband.</p>
<p>There was doubt as to the way my husband contracted Yellow Fever. He<lb/>
never told for his own reasons. Again I deduce he was conscious of having<lb/>
been careless in the handling of infected mosquitoes. I do know that he<lb/>
kept a &ldquo;coop&rdquo; of mosquitoes - Dr. Guiter<del>ries</del><add>as</add> refers to the receipt of<lb/>
such a coop in his letter to Roger. When he was at Fort McIntosh and<lb/>
Fort St. Philip, I know that he fed those mosquitoes regularly by in-<lb/>
serting his arm into the coop and letting them feed on his blood. I<lb/>
know this because at the time, I was not only quite young in years but<lb/>
I had been quite successfully protected from everything calculated as<lb/>
crude or seamy by my father, <del>and</del> the very idea of his feeding mosquitoes<lb/>
on his blood appalled and repelled me. I think that in the process of<lb/>
keeping alive the mosquitoes needed for the experiment in Cuba he in-<lb/>
advertently allowed himself to be bitten by an infected one. He would<lb/>
not have admitted to this under any circumstances.</p>
<p>I tried to get both General Ireland and Colonel Kean to enlarge on their<lb/>
remarks on his case of Fever but they would not. Incidentally both of<lb/>
them did protest too much for the effect they hoped to attain. You see<lb/>
though I was not acquainted with Roger during this period, I did <del>not</del><lb/>
know him and I did know his very unusual code of personal ethics. He<lb/>
never claimed for himself anything to which he was not entitled and not<lb/>
all of this and he did not lie. He could keep silent under the most<lb/>
extraordinary pressure to make him talk.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f05804013"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>It is my profound conviction that my husband has been done a grave injustice<lb/>
and that he has been deprived of the recognition to which his service en-<lb/>
titled him. I think that this would not have been done had he been alive<lb/>
at the time official recognition was given the men in this work. I think<lb/>
that this was done and is being done now because of the determination of<lb/>
a certain group of men connected with the work to hold within the Army all<lb/>
the credit and honor. In the case of Colonel Kean, this I conclude from<lb/>
my interview with him, I think that he would have included Roger - for<lb/>
Colonel Kean had the final decision on the personnel of those included -<lb/>
had he been able to include his own name. He did say that he would like<lb/>
to be one of them but he spent his time in Washington and could not<lb/>
honestly say that he had anything to do with it. This does not read in<lb/>
the way in which he spoke the words. His manner and his inflection cannot<lb/>
be transcribed to paper.</p>
<p>I shall be glad to supplement the record I am sending you if you find<lb/>
it incomplete and I have the lacking material.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Jessie Daniel Ames<lb/>
(Mrs. Roger Post Ames)</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
