<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05808073">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, April 16, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05808073</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-04-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carroll, Mrs.George</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-04-16">April 16, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05808073</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, April 16, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests permission to meet with Mrs. Carroll and to have some manuscripts of her late father-in-law copied. Hench explains that he wants to give James Carroll due credit in his planned book.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-04-16">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, April 16, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05808073"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1956-04-16">April 16, 1956</date>
</dateline>
Mrs. George S. H. Carroll<lb/>
2814 Rhode Island Avenue N.E.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Carroll:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was so very sorry to have missed you the last two times I was in Washington.<lb/>
I think you were not feeling well at one time and had perhaps gone to be with<lb/>
your sister. Unfortunately I was so busy that I could not spend the time<lb/>
locating your sister. I phoned your home but got no answer.</p>
<p>Mrs. Carroll, the time has come for me to close my books, so to speak, and<lb/>
start writing the book on the conquest of yellow fever and about the only<lb/>
unexplored sources of information are those which you so kindly let me look<lb/>
over briefly. You were very kind in suggesting that the next time I came to<lb/>
Washington I could have the important material photostated and that is what<lb/>
I would now like to make arrangements to do.</p>
<p>I must give two lectures at Johns Hopkins Medical School at Baltimore on<lb/>
May 9 and 10 and I am most hopeful that you will permit me to stop in Washing-<lb/>
ton either the weekend of May 5 to 7 or the weekend of May 11 to 13. You and<lb/>
I can pick out the material to be photostated. As a matter of fact, I think<lb/>
we laid that aside in a special little bundle. Then, depending on which<lb/>
you would like to have done, I can either take it, with you (if you care to<lb/>
go), to the Armed Forces Department of Pathology where they have a photostat<lb/>
machine and where they said they would cooperate with me; or, if you prefer,<lb/>
I will arrange ahead of time to take it to a professional photostat man. It<lb/>
does not take long to photostat material - perhaps less than one minute per sheet.</p>
<p>If you are willing to let the Armed Services Department of Pathology do it for<lb/>
us, they will do it for nothing and it will be quite a saving but if, for some<lb/>
reason or other, you prefer to have it done otherwise, I will make that ar-<lb/>
rangement. I am so glad that you will let me do this and if you wish, we<lb/>
can make an extra copy so that no matter who gets the originals, you can have<lb/>
an extra set. If you want more than one set, I will see that you get it at<lb/>
no cost to you and of course you keep all the originals.</p>
<p>Now the reason I am writing in advance is that unless we do so, the photostat<lb/>
man might want us to wait or he might be so busy he would have to do it later<lb/>
and I am sure that you would like to have it done on the spot, quickly, and<lb/>
then be able to take the material home with you. Of course if you are willing<lb/>
to trust me, I could bring it home here and have it photostated at the Mayo<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05808074"/>
Mrs. George S. H. Carroll<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
April 16, 1956<lb/>
Clinic, have a couple of sets made for you and mail you the whole thing by<lb/>
registered mail. I did this once before with another person and returned<lb/>
the material in a locked tin box and sent the key in a separate registered<lb/>
envelope. In that way everything is completely safe.</p>
<p>I will appreciate very much your cooperation in this matter and then you<lb/>
will not have me troubling you any more and I will be able to do what I<lb/>
have wanted to do - to show how much Doctor Carroll did in the yellow<lb/>
fever experiments and some of the material that you have will be so very<lb/>
helpful in doing that.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
<seg>
P.S.: I heard that you decided not to have the operation. I do hope your<lb/>
arthritis has not become more active. There are one or two new cortisone<lb/>
preparations that appear to be very useful. Remember, if I can help you<lb/>
through your doctor, I shall be glad to do so.<lb/>
</seg>
(Dictated by Doctor Hench but signed by secretary in his absence.)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
