<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05806121">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John H. Andrus to Philip Showalter Hench, February 22, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Andrus, John H.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05806121</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-02-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Gillan, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">McConnell, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-02-22">February 22, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05806121</idno>
<title>Letter from John H. Andrus to Philip Showalter Hench, February 22, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus speculates on the location of the original yellow fever charts. He recalls that Reed was quite sick before arriving at Columbia Barracks, in November 1900.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-02-22">
<head>Letter from John H. Andrus to Philip Showalter Hench, February 22, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05806121"/>
<opener>
J. H. Andrus<lb/>
<dateline>
805 Cooper St.<lb/>
Camden, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1942-02-22">2-22-42</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I shall attempt to answer some of the questions raised in your<lb/>
letter of the seventeenth and write another letter about your<lb/>
kind criticism of my literary efforts.</p>
<p>The copy of my chart was made by Miss Gillen, immune, practical<lb/>
nurse who was supposed to look after me. That she had to<lb/>
call Lambert for anything more complicated than a drink of<lb/>
water was not her fault. She just didn't know.</p>
<p>I took my copy with me when leaving the y. f. hospital. While<lb/>
I never compared it with the original I believe they were iden-<lb/>
tical - they were in general appearance. The original, and<lb/>
my copy, were on standard Army forms. The columns, separat-<lb/>
ing DAYS, did not meet Major Reed's requirements. If you<lb/>
refer to the charts appearing in Senate Vol. 61, you will find<lb/>
that the frequency of taking temperature varied from three<lb/>
times a day to hourly. This necessitated special (hand)<lb/>
columnar ruling and hand lettered headings superimposed on the<lb/>
printed headings.</p>
<p>General Sternberg's biography contains copy of letter from<lb/>
Major Reed to the General, of Dec. 22, 1900: &ldquo;I wish to re-<lb/>
quest that Dr. McConnell, of the Museum, may be sent down to<lb/>
join us on the next transport leaving New York. I would<lb/>
like to have him make drawings of the mosquito and larvae from<lb/>
live specimens. There is some other work here which he<lb/>
could also do. He should bring camera lucida and suitable<lb/>
paper for this work&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In a letter of Jan. 27, 1901: &ldquo;As McConnell has completed his<lb/>
drawings here .. He carries with him a copy of our additional<lb/>
<hi>note with charts</hi>. I hope that Dr. Gould this time will<lb/>
have proofs to you in time so that corrections can be made<lb/>
before publication&rdquo;..</p>
<p>In a letter of Jan. 31, 1901: &ldquo;..I will ask that McConnell<lb/>
change the period of incubation on chart number eleven to<lb/>
five days, seventeen hours&rdquo;..</p>
<p>All this seems to point to the probability that the copy from<lb/>
which the chart <add>printing</add> plates were made was prepared by Dr. McConnell.<lb/>
If his drawings can be located, the original charts may be<lb/>
found pasted to the back. This is common advertising prac-<lb/>
tice.</p>
<p>Am afraid I can be of no help as regards the windows of the<lb/>
infected bedding building. I was never in it. During<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05806122"/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Page 2.<lb/>
the day the solid wood shutters were always closed and in the<lb/>
evening only the screened aperture showed from the outside.</p>
<p>The man I replaced was a private of the Hospital Corps who,<lb/>
with Hospital Steward John Neate, had been on duty at the Army<lb/>
Medical Museum. Both accompanied the Board to Cuba.<lb/>
I &ldquo;met&rdquo; this man and that is just about all. He left the<lb/>
laboratory within ten to twenty minutes of the time I reported<lb/>
for duty. I had never seen him before and never saw him<lb/>
afterward. Efforts to get his name from the War Department,<lb/>
two or three years ago, were unsuccessful.</p>
<p>In regard to illness of Major Reed, referred to in my story:<lb/>
It is my understanding that the Major had been quite sick,<lb/>
while in the United States, shortly before. (He arrived<lb/>
at Columbia Barracks, this time, on Nov. 13, 1900.)<lb/>
The Major was not very robust. You may recall that General<lb/>
Truby, in his memoir, refers to the care with which the Major<lb/>
watched his diet. He died following an appendectomy and,<lb/>
it seems to me, General Truby speculates on the probability<lb/>
that the condition was chronic.</p>
<p>Please do not hesitate to call on me for anything you think<lb/>
I can help on. You have placed me under heavy obligation<lb/>
and I like to pay my debts.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>J H Andrus</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
