<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804025">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, April 2, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Ames, Jessie Daniel</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804025</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-04-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-04-02">April 2, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804025</idno>
<title>Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, April 2, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Ames answers Hench's questions concerning her husband's role at Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-04-02">
<head>Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, April 2, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804025"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
The Southern Frontier<lb/>
ISSUED BY<lb/>
COMMISSION ON INTERRACIAL COOPERATION, INCORPORATED<lb/>
710 STANDARD BUILDING<lb/>
ATLANTA, GEORGIA<lb/>
<date value="1942-04-02">April 2, 1942</date>
</dateline>
MRS. JESSIE DANIEL AMES<lb/>
MANAGING EDITOR<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In preparing the report of my husband's record I did not, as<lb/>
you may have noticed, put in anything for which I had only my<lb/>
husband's words. He did tell me some things about Camp<lb/>
Lazear, but you see that had I used his stories as the basis<lb/>
of my report, it would have resolved itself into my recollections<lb/>
of his spoken words against the word of a living man, Dr. Kean,<lb/>
who was in a position of authority.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>1- Dr. Ames was in charge of Camp Lazear. The supporting evidence<lb/>
is found in the record where I quoted the New Orleans Picayune<lb/>
of July 30, 1905. Part of the news story is not included for<lb/>
I did not think it applicable to the point I was making. The<lb/>
story further stated that there was great excitement the night<lb/>
my husband phoned to Dr. Reed at Columbia Barracks that the<lb/>
first experimental case, Kissinger, mosquito infected, had de-<lb/>
veloped fever. To Dr. Reed's question as to whether or not<lb/>
Dr. Ames was sure it was <hi>the</hi> fever, he was assured that it was.<lb/>
I haven't a copy of the Picayune of this date but if you would<lb/>
like to have the exact words I can get a cousin of Roger's in<lb/>
New Orleans to go down and copy the whole story. I felt reason-<lb/>
ably sure that the story was true, and still do, for at that<lb/>
time Dr. Kean was in the Surgeon General's office in Washington<lb/>
and had Roger made a misstatement of fact, he would have been<lb/>
rebuked either by Dr. Kean or Colonel Maus from San Antonio.<lb/>
The story bears out Roger's own account of sleeping at Camp<lb/>
Lazear. In addition to this story I have a letter from Dr. Kean<lb/>
dated December 9, 1929, a copy of which I am sending you, in<lb/>
which he states that because they thought Roger was an immune,<lb/>
he was &ldquo;selected to be in charge of the personnel of Camp Lazear.&rdquo;</p>
<p><unclear><del>2-</del></unclear> It seems to me, and this aside from the things my husband told<lb/>
me, that with no member of the Board in attendance at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
my husband, a surgeon in the employ of the Army and admittedly<lb/>
an expert in diagnosis and treatment of a disease which was being<lb/>
experimented on, would <add><unclear>not</unclear></add> have been made &ldquo;administrator&rdquo; of personnel<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05804026"/>
-2-<lb/>
with no other duties. Roger never said that he was alone with the men at<lb/>
Camp Lazear but he never spoke of another doctor. It was this ommission<lb/>
which made me press Dr. Kean and General Ireland for the names of some<lb/>
other doctors there. To support my statement that none of the Board was<lb/>
at Camp Lazear I refer you to page 20 of Dr. Agramonte's pamphlet beginning<lb/>
with sentence &ldquo;After the case of Dean.....&rdquo;</p>
<p>One part of the story of this &ldquo;Great Medical Discovery&rdquo; which I have not<lb/>
mentioned for it has no bearing on my husband's work is that dealing with<lb/>
the attitude of the three groups of experimental cases. Since my husband<lb/>
did not doubt that yellow fever was carried by mosquitoes and could be<lb/>
contracted in no other method, he spoke frequently of the fears of the men<lb/>
who submitted to the bed linen tests. He considered them the real heroes of<lb/>
the <del><unclear></unclear></del> times because they believed that they would contract the disease<lb/>
while the mosquito infected cases, at least in the beginning, took it all as<lb/>
something of a lark. Later they were a bit more fearful but as no patients<lb/>
died of the fever their fears were not so great as those who slept in the beds<lb/>
with the supposedly infected bed linen. My husband had something of a grim<lb/>
sense of humor which he displayed in talking about this part of the experiment.</p>
<p>The occasion for speaking of this part of the story came up more frequently<lb/>
than any other as the move for individual pensions began long before my<lb/>
husband's death. It was his opinion that no permanent disability followed<lb/>
yellow fever. He may have been mistaken. He did think it highly amusing<lb/>
that the cases should consider themselves heroes after the fact when at the<lb/>
time they were not impressed by their own fortitude.</p>
<p>There is much more that I could tell of our conversation on Cuba but there<lb/>
is no point in doing so as they did not relate to the professional side of<lb/>
his work.</p></item>
<item>2- This question of my husband's case of fever has been one that has annoyed<lb/>
the Department and Dr. Kean more than any other. I am sending you a copy<lb/>
of Dr. Kean's letter to me in which he speaks of the <hi>alleged</hi> case of fever<lb/>
and his not knowing anything about it. I am also sending you copies of<lb/>
correspondence between General Ireland and Senator Sheppard showing that<lb/>
this was not included in Roger's record and that it was finally put in only<lb/>
upon Senator Sheppard's insistence. In fact, as I think I have written you,<lb/>
the fact that Roger was not an immune but did take over the Camp seems to have<lb/>
created a most unfavorable reaction to Roger personally. His chart incidentally<lb/>
shows that he was <hi>sick somewhere or other for nine days</hi> instead of the three<lb/>
or four days of which Dr. Kean spoke. Viewed in the light of the attitude<lb/>
of the Board members in the document of Dr. Agramonte his act of devotion shows<lb/>
up rather well. I think that his case of fever was deliberately suppressed<lb/>
for this reason.</item>
<item>3- I have looked for the map referred to by Dr. Reed. I concluded at length that<lb/>
it was later turned over to the War Department as part of the records. Now<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05804027"/>
-3-<lb/>
that you write you could not find it there, I shall explore the only place<lb/>
left. I will let you know, as soon as I do, whether or not it turns up.<lb/>
I know that the making of such a map was Roger's idea. He was a man of<lb/>
some few fixed ideas in his profession. One of these was this thing of<lb/>
having a map made of an infected community and the taking of copious<lb/>
daily notes on the location of every reported case, proven or suspected.<lb/>
He either insisted on a hospital orderly who could draw or on the<lb/>
employment of a civilian who could do the work. He did not always have<lb/>
the cooperation of his superiors in this. <hi>I do not have the case histories</hi><lb/>
of the patients. However, recently I have found out that my husband's<lb/>
sister has a great many of his papers and I shall try to get hold of them.<lb/>
If by chance there are any of these or the map among the papers I will<lb/>
let you know at once.</item>
<item>4-You know, I never noticed the &ldquo;Dr. James&rdquo; reference until you called my<lb/>
attention to it. Raising three children from scratch appears to have dulled<lb/>
my perception for details. I never heard Roger speak of a Dr. James. I<lb/>
can't clear this up for you.</item>
<item>5-My husband did not write articles or a book on his experiences in Cuba. I<lb/>
should only be guessing if I gave any reasons for this omission. It is a<lb/>
pity now that he did not, isn't it?</item>
<item>6-I am sending you another picture of Roger which you may keep. It was taken<lb/>
around about the late fall or early winter of 1900 I am sure. It was before<lb/>
he was made a captain for his collar does not carry the &ldquo;V&rdquo; and his shoulder<lb/>
shows, I think, one bar though there may not be any.</item>
<item>7-There was no notation on the back of the group picture. I have a mounted<lb/>
copy which carried nothing on it. It was taken at the time of the picture<lb/>
I am sending you. Mr. Lambert wrote me that he either showed or gave you<lb/>
a picture taken at the time of the experiments. I do not know which one<lb/>
that would be. If it were one without a moustache that would not indicate<lb/>
that it was not taken at the same time.</item>
<item>8-I am sending you the clinical chart of Private Kissinger. I have all those<lb/>
on the list attached to the additional data I am sending you. If you want<lb/>
them, too, let me know and I will send them on. I am leaving for Texas the<lb/>
10th and will be gone until the first Monday in May. If you want them<lb/>
before I get back, let me know.</item>
<item>9-I have no copy of the book to which you refer. It strikes me that the<lb/>
Medical Department of the Army is or was somewhat casual in the handling of<lb/>
its documents.</item>
<item>10-The copies of the record and other data are included herewith.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f05804028"/>
<item>-4-</item>
<item>11-Copies of the correspondence are also included together with other letters.<lb/>
When your letter came I decided to dig into my own files - I had used only<lb/>
Roger's for the most part - and see whether or not something else might<lb/>
be found which would help you. This accounts for the correspondence between<lb/>
me and Dr. Kean and the rest. Also, I found the account of my interview with<lb/>
Dr. Kean. I was sure I had refused to write it out even though Dr. White<lb/>
insisted that I do so. In reading it over, however, I do see that I softened<lb/>
it considerably. His, Dr. Kean's, flattery of me with which he <unclear>interlarded</unclear><lb/>
his discourse, is omitted entirely for obvious reasons. Besides it sickened<lb/>
me.</item>
<item>12-I am not surprised that the lower ring on the book has sprung. It is an old<lb/>
one, originally a zippered portfolio, and has seen quite heavy use. I have<lb/>
plenty transparent envelopes so don't pay this any mind. I have no doubt<lb/>
you are careful of the contents. Most doctors are careful.</item>
<item>12-I used the word &ldquo;innoculation&rdquo; by mistake. I was referring to mosquito<lb/>
infection which my husband did carry out. I do not recall his speaking of<lb/>
innoculating any case so someone else undoubtedly performed that service.</item>
<item>13-Dr. Agramonte sent me a copy of his privately printed pamphlet. I have all<lb/>
the pamphlets which I listed.</item>
<item><p>14-I have nothing you speak of in this item. I may be able to get some Havana<lb/>
newspapers of that period from a cousin there. His father, my uncle, was one<lb/>
of the few civilian cases my husband treated.</p>
<p>I have had to use my judgment in selecting the material I have sent you. Had<lb/>
I sent you everything without selection, you would have been overwhelmed by<lb/>
the quantity. What I have omitted seemed to me trivial or not applicable to<lb/>
an extent sufficient to justify inclusion. But if there should be something<lb/>
else upon which you need a little light thrown I will help if I can.</p>
<p>I am interested in having the work of Dr. Roger Port Ames objectively evaluated<lb/>
for the sake of his three children who never knew their father. I think that<lb/>
your judgment will be accepted by them as fair and just. They are completely<lb/>
free of any psychological twist in reference to him, a condition achieved by<lb/>
the exertion of much self-control on my part.</p>
<p>I am surprised that you stumbled on Roger and his record at all though I, too,<lb/>
wish it had been before your visit to Atlanta last year.</p></item>
</list></p>
<closer>
<salute>Very cordially yours,</salute>
<signed>Jessie Daniel Ames</signed>
<unclear>X</unclear> I find I have left the copies of the Andrus'<lb/>
letters and the others at home- I will mail them<lb/>
to you tomorrow <unclear>J D A.</unclear><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
