<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05801001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Timeline of Aristides Agramonte's service with the Army Medical Corps, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05801001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05801001</idno>
<title>Timeline of Aristides Agramonte's service with the Army Medical Corps, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This document details Agramonte's career; from April 18, 1898 to June 15, 1903.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Timeline of Aristides Agramonte's service with the Army Medical Corps, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05801001"/>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head><hi>DATA REGARDING DR. AGRAMONTE</hi></head>
<item>A = Agramonte</item>
<item><hi>1898</hi> April 18 A. to Sternberg offering services to Army Medical Corps.</item>
<item>April 19 Sternberg to A asking whether A had had any experience with<lb/>
yellow fever or had had the disease. (I cannot locate A's<lb/>
answer.)</item>
<item>May 3 Acting Assistant Surgeon Agramonte assigned to temporary duty<lb/>
under Reed in Path Lab., S.G.O., Wash. D.C.</item>
<item>July 15 A. ordered to proceed from Washington to New York and via<lb/>
U.S.S. Resolute to report to General Shafter for duty<lb/>
in yellow fever hospital at Santiago de Cuba.</item>
<item>July 25 Arrived in Santiago de Cuba; went to Siboney, then back to<lb/>
Santiago (Letter of A to Sternberg, July 29, 1898).</item>
<item>Nov. ___ Returned to Washington (See A's letter to Kelly, March 22, 1905).</item>
<item>November 24 A. ordered by Sternberg to proceed from Wash. to Havana to study<lb/>
yellow fever under direction of the Chief Surgeon at Havana.</item>
<item><hi>1899</hi> April 17 A. submitted to Sternberg (Wash)<del><unclear>o</unclear></del>report<del><unclear>0</unclear></del>from<del><unclear>s</unclear></del>yellow fever<lb/>
Hospital No. 3 at Havana.</item>
<item>June 17 A. submitted another report to Sternberg.</item>
<item>July 9 Missing letter of A. to Sternberg (This letter mentioned in<lb/>
another letter that I cannot find).</item>
<item>July 21 A. in yellow fever hospital Santiago; letter from Sternberg to A.</item>
<item>August 9 A. left Santiago, returned to Havana</item>
<item>August 15 A. at Las Animas Hospital, Havana; sent report to Sternberg.</item>
<item>November 14 A. was apparently at U. S. Military Hosp. No. 1, Havana;<lb/>
letter from Reed in Wash. addressed thus to A.</item>
<item>December 13 Sternberg to A. re A.'s report to be sent to Medical News<lb/>
(published February 1900).</item>
<item>December 24 Letter from A. at U. S. Military Hosp. No. 1 to Sternberg (Wash)<lb/>
stating he wished to solicit the new chair of Bacteriology<lb/>
at the U. of Havana.</item>
<item>December 29 Sternberg to A. stating A's contract will be annulled as of<lb/>
January 15, 1900.</item>
<item><hi>1900</hi> January 8 A.'s contract not to be annulled yet: Sternberg cable to DeWitt,<lb/>
Chief Surgeon, Havana.</item>
<item>January 26 A. still working at U. S. Military Hospital No. 1, Havana<lb/>
(Sternberg to A.).</item>
<item>March 2 Sternberg to DeWitt suggesting annulment of A's contract unless<lb/>
his services needed elsewhere as pathologist and bacteriologist.</item>
<item>March 29 A. transferred from Military Hospital #1, to report to Chief<lb/>
Surgeon, Dept. of Havana.</item>
<item>April 25 A. assigned for duty in charge of the Department Laboratory,<lb/>
Dept. of Havana.</item>
<item>May 11 Sternberg to A., making research suggestions.</item>
<item>May 23 A. transferred from Dept. of Havana and Pinar del Rio to<lb/>
report to the Chief Surgeon of the Division for duty in<lb/>
charge of the Division Laboratory (Division of Cuba).</item>
<item>May 24 A. appointed to Yellow Fever Board (Par. 24, S.O., 122, A.G.O., Wash.).</item>
<item>June 27 A. ordered to visit Santa Clara and return to Havana.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f05801002"/>
<item>Page 2</item>
<item>July 17 A. ordered to visit Pinar del Rio to study epidemic of<lb/>
&ldquo;pernicious fever.&rdquo;</item>
<item>August ___ Passed exams for M.D. degree, U. of Havana (see 1905 letter to Kelly).</item>
<item>September___ Obtained by competitive exam the chair of Bacterioloty and<lb/>
Experimental Pathology in the U. of Havana (Still held<lb/>
this in 1905; see letter to Kelly).</item>
<item>September 1 A. renewed contract at $150.00 a month.</item>
<item>September 20 A. wrote letter to General Wood requesting permission to go<lb/>
to New York to purchase laboratory apparatus for U. of<lb/>
Havana.</item>
<item>September 20. Scott to A.; telling A. to apply for leave of absence for 15 days.</item>
<item>September 21 Fifteen day &ldquo;leave&rdquo; granted (S.O. 164, Hdqts. Division of Cuba)<lb/>
(This &ldquo;leave&rdquo; was not counted against A.).</item>
<item>September 22 Wood to A.: authority to go to New York to buy $3,000 worth<lb/>
of laboratory equipment for U. of Havana.</item>
<item>September 24 A. left Havana presumably on the transport Sedgewick<lb/>
(Carroll, on Sept. 23, 1900, wrote his wife: &ldquo;Agramonte<lb/>
left for New York <hi>yesterday</hi> with his wife.&rdquo;)</item>
<item>October 5 A. in New York; left orders with Bausch and Lomb Optical Co.,<lb/>
and with Leitz Co.</item>
<item>October 12 A. arrived back in Havana, returning from New York apparently<lb/>
on the transport Sedgewick.</item>
<item>October 12 - 31 On duty in charge of Division Laboratory and also as member of<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board.<lb/>
(See A's own Personal Reports dated Sept. 1, October 1,<lb/>
November 1, 1900 and sent to the S.G.).</item>
<item>October 16 A's 15 day leave of absence was extended 3 days (S.O., 182,<lb/>
Hdqts., Div. of Cuba) as he had been away 18 instead of 15 days.</item>
<item>October 23 A. authorized to go to and fro between Quemados and Havana.</item>
<item><hi>1901</hi> May 16 Major Havard to S.G., Wash., inquiring whether A. has been<lb/>
relieved from the (yellow fever) Board.</item>
<item>May 21 Sternberg to A.G., Wash., recommending that A. be relieved from<lb/>
duty on the Yellow Fever Board. and to report to the Commanding<lb/>
General, Dept. of Cuba, for assignment to duty.</item>
<item>May 21 Cable of Corbin (Adj. General) to Wood (Havana) relieving A.<lb/>
from duty with Yellow Fever Board (S.O. 118, A.G.O., Wash, D.C.)</item>
<item>May 28 A. assigned to duty in charge of the Dept. Laboratory at <del><unclear>Municipal</unclear></del><lb/>
Municipal Hospital No. 1 and of the microscopical and bacterio-<lb/>
logical work at Las Animas Hospital (S.O. 117, Hdqts. Dept.<lb/>
Cuba, Havana, May 28, 1901).</item>
<item>June 20 A. ordered to visit Post Hospital, Columbia Barracks 4 days a<lb/>
week (in addition to present duties) (S.O. 134, Hdqts. Dept.<lb/>
of Cuba).</item>
<item>July 16 A. relieved from Las Animas Hospital duties.</item>
<item>July 26 Leave of absence for one month granted (July 28 - Aug. 21).</item>
<item><hi>1902</hi> March 26 Sternberg to A. notifying him his contract will be annulled on<lb/>
April 30, 1902.</item>
<item>May 8 Gorgas to Sternberg: A's contract to be ended May 15, 1902 (But<lb/>
was it annulled then? Apparently not.).</item>
<item>August 13 A. to Sternberg sending his contract for annulment on August 15.</item>
<item>May 16-Aug. 15 On leave of absence (See letter to A. from Paymaster General,<lb/>
January 13, 1903).</item>
<pb n="3" id="f05801003"/>
<item>Page 3</item>
<item><hi>1903</hi> February 10 S.G. authorized to employ A. as contract-surgeon for temporary<lb/>
service at Cabana Barracks, Cuba at $100.00 a month.</item>
<item>June 15 Contract annulled.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
