<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804075">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Biography of Roger Post Ames, by [Jessie Daniel Ames?], [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804075</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Angles, Eduardo</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Bridges, C. H.</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Mobile (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Tampa (Flo.)</name>
<name type="place">Santiago (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Montauk (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Huntsville (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">Fort Barrancas (Flo.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort McIntosh (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">Jackson Barracks, New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1 (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804075</idno>
<title>Biography of Roger Post Ames, by [Jessie Daniel Ames?], [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This biography focuses on the reasons why Ames should be included with the Yellow Fever Board and the volunteer soldiers in the Roll of Honor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Biography of Roger Post Ames, by [Jessie Daniel Ames?], [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804075"/>
<p>From Mrs Ames</p>
<p><hi>COPY</hi></p>
<p>Roger P. Ames was born in New Orleans. <add>1870</add> Graduated Medical<lb/>
Department, Tulane University, in 1890. Resident physician U. S.<lb/>
Engineer department, 4th Engineer district, Mississippi River Commis-<lb/>
sion in 1891. Quarantine Officer of State Board of Health of Louisi-<lb/>
ana in 1892 and 1893. Was in private practice in New Orleans from<lb/>
1894 to 1898, and during this time was physician to the Incurable<lb/>
Home, New Orleans, and visiting physician to Turo Infirmary. Was<lb/>
resident physician at this Infirmary during yellow fever epidemic at<lb/>
New Orleans in August, September, October, and part of November, 1897.</p>
<p>Became Contract Surgeon U. S. Army, May 12, 1898, during<lb/>
Spanish-American war at Mobile, Ala. Assigned to 19th Regiment U. S.<lb/>
Infantry as Senior Surgeon (being the only surgeon in command) from<lb/>
May 14 to July 12, 1898, was in camp at Mobile, Alabama, and Tampa,<lb/>
Fla.</p>
<p>Ordered in July 1898 to Santiago, Cuba. On arrival assign-<lb/>
ed to duty with 10th regiment, U. S. Infantry, relieving Major S. I.<lb/>
Robinson, Senior Surgeon with command from July 19 to November, 1898.<lb/>
In camp at Santiago, Cuba, Montauk, N. Y., and Huntsville, Ala. Con-<lb/>
tract annulled at his request.</p>
<p>Re-entered the service April 15, 1899 and was ordered to<lb/>
Havana, Cuba. There he was assigned to Military Hospital No. 1, and<lb/>
was given special duty connected with the sanitary work at the Palace,<lb/>
Havana. On various occasions was ordered to special work connected<lb/>
with the diagnosis of yellow fever cases, inspections, etc. On dis-<lb/>
continuance of Military Hospital No. 1 was ordered, April 11, 1900<lb/>
to Columbia Barracks. While at Columbia Barracks he was in charge<lb/>
of the yellow fever wards at the Post Hospital during the yellow<lb/>
fever epidemic at Quenados, near the post. It was here that he took<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05804076"/>
Page #2.<lb/>
part in the notable experiments as to the source and cause of yellow<lb/>
fever under Major Walter Reed. On account of his previous experience<lb/>
with yellow fever he was made the resident physician of the yellow<lb/>
fever hospital and the yellow fever experimental camp. Regarding<lb/>
this he says in a memorandum of his own: &ldquo;While at this station it<lb/>
was my peculiar good fortune to study yellow fever in its very earli-<lb/>
est stages, and to see the mosquito theory, under the wise adminis-<lb/>
tration of the Medical Department, U. S. Army, fully demonstrated;<lb/>
and at the same time having the honor of treating the experimental<lb/>
cases, two of which cases were members of the Medical Department Com-<lb/>
mission.</p>
<p>When the experimental station, Camp Lazear, was opened,<lb/>
I was placed in immediate charge, under the direction of Major Reed,<lb/>
President of the Commission. The work of this Commission and the<lb/>
wisdom of the one ordering same, is of national record, and the<lb/>
result only second to the discovery of anesthesia. The clinical<lb/>
and other bedside record work for this distinguished Commission was<lb/>
performed by me. On many occasions, both verbally and in writing,<lb/>
the President of this Commission has expressed himself fully appre-<lb/>
ciating the high character of my work and assistance rendered him<lb/>
in the investigations.&rdquo;</p>
<p>While treating these cases Dr. Ames was stricken with<lb/>
yellow fever in the latter part of January 28, 1901.</p>
<p>On January 24, 1902 was made Assistant Surgeon of Volun-<lb/>
teers U. S. Army with rank of Captain, and on January 28, 1902 was<lb/>
given rank of Major.</p>
<p>Was assigned to service in the Philippines with the Sixth<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05804077"/>
Page #3.<lb/>
Separate Brigade, arriving in the Philippines early in 1902. Was<lb/>
assigned to Oras, Samor, P. I., where he was made chief quarantine<lb/>
officer in August, 1902.</p>
<p>Honorably discharged in February, 1903 and on his return<lb/>
to the United States again became a Contract Surgeon, U. S. Army.<lb/>
Was at Fort Barrancas, Fla., April 22, 1903. On September 29, 1903<lb/>
was ordered to report for duty pertaining to yellow fever in vicinity<lb/>
of Fort McIntosh, Texas. Referring to his work at Fort McIntosh the<lb/>
Inspector General, Major J.D.C. Hoskins, made the following report in<lb/>
June, 1904. &ldquo;Contract Surgeon R. P. Ames, U.S.A. is the Post Surgeon.<lb/>
Surgeon Ames seems to be very efficient in his administration of this<lb/>
hospital. He is very active in his investigations about yellow fever<lb/>
in the vicinity of the post. No deaths occurred at Fort McIntosh<lb/>
from the yellow fever outbreak.</p>
<p>He was married to Miss Jessie Daniel of Texas in 1905 while<lb/>
still serving in that state as Contract Surgeon. Was sent to Jackson<lb/>
Barracks, New Orleans, La., when yellow fever broke out in that city<lb/>
in 1905. Although the post was in the heart of the city his super-<lb/>
visory work was so efficient that the epidemic did not reach the<lb/>
troops, although the post was in a highly infected area.</p>
<p>Regarding the work of Dr. Ames at Fort McIntosh Passed<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon Dr. T. D. Bevry said: &ldquo;several cases occurred at<lb/>
Fort McIntosh but all recovered.&rdquo; From these cases Dr. Ames infected<lb/>
mosquitoes and kept these infected mosquitoes alive on his own blood<lb/>
until he could turn them over to Dr. Carroll who in his laboratory was<lb/>
able to combat claims that had been made about the discovery of a para-<lb/>
site. He joined the U. S. Public Health Service in 1906 or 1907 and<lb/>
remained with it until his death in 1914. In that year he died while<lb/>
fighting yellow fever in Central America.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f05804078"/>
<p>From Mrs Ames</p>
<p>FROM MRS. ROGER P. AMES</p>
<p>Roger Post Ames, Surgeon in immediate command of Camp Lazear, was<lb/>
on continuous service from November 20, 1900, when the Camp was opened<lb/>
until February 28, 1901, when the Camp was closed. Not a single one<lb/>
of the experimental cases died which remarkable record was attributed<lb/>
to the unselfish devotion and scientific skill and knowledge of Dr.<lb/>
Ames. Had there been the average mortality, twenty-five per cent<lb/>
being the average, public condemnation would have been so severe that<lb/>
the experiment would have had to be abandoned. There is no reported<lb/>
record of another Surgeon in the Army who rendered the same service in<lb/>
the same field. As the one surgeon upon whom Major Walter Reed looked<lb/>
for this highly trained services, the name of Roger Post Ames should<lb/>
be placed upon the Roll of Honor with the names of the Board and the<lb/>
volunteer soldiers who committed their lives into the hands of Roger<lb/>
Post Ames.</p>
<p>----------------</p>
<p>The Surgeon General of the Army in a report to Senator Steck,<lb/>
Chairman of a sub-committee of the Committee on Military Affairs,<lb/>
asserts that the services of Roger Post Ames in the yellow fever<lb/>
experimental work in Cuba were only those required of him in &ldquo;regular<lb/>
line of duty&rdquo; and that these services were merely routine and of no<lb/>
greater value to the success of the experiment than those of orderlies<lb/>
nurses, and hospital stewards; that therefore his name does not deserv<lb/>
a place on the Roll of Honor created by Act of Congress, February 28,<lb/>
1929.</p>
<p>Regular duty of Army Surgeons in times of peach consists of<lb/>
attending &ldquo;Sick calls&rdquo; to which soldiers with ordinary ailments re-<lb/>
port; visiting patients in hospital; and inspecting hospital;<lb/>
giving orders for the day. Barracks hospitals have regularly est-<lb/>
ablished quarters, not tents, under a military garrison.</p>
<p>Evidence which shows that services performed by Roger Post Ames<lb/>
in Cuba were not regular and routine, but extraordinary, unusual and<lb/>
of such importance as to merit placing his name on the Roll of Honor.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>A. Camp Lazear, itself, was not a barracks hospital to which<lb/>
soldiers, regardless of their complaints, reported. It was a<lb/>
specialty camp of tents created for one highly scientific and<lb/>
dangerous experiment and the surgeons in charge of the camp had<lb/>
to be scientifically trained, experienced, and equipped to carry out<lb/>
the purposes of the experiment.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This the second series of experiments began November 20, at<lb/>
an experimental camp near Quemados, called Camp Lazear, and embraced<lb/>
14 cases&rdquo; - Senate Document #10, 59th Congress, 2nd Session, page_____</p>
<p>&ldquo;A camp was especially constructed for the experiments about<lb/>
four miles from Habana, christened Camp Lazear.&rdquo; Senate Document<lb/>
#10, 59th Congress, 2nd Session, Page 13.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The necessity for an experimental camp became more imperative<lb/>
as time passed. - - - We immediately set about choosing a location<lb/>
for our camp. - - -on the twentieth of November we inaugurated our<lb/>
camp which <unclear>we</unclear> named Camp Lazear in honor to the memory of our dead<lb/>
colleague, consisting then of seven army tents guarded by a military<lb/>
garrison.&rdquo; Page 24 and 25 &ldquo;Inside History of a Great Medical Dis-<lb/>
covery&rdquo; by Dr. Aristides Agramonte.</p></item>
<item><p>B Roger Post Ames was Surgeon in immediate command of Camp<lb/>
Lazear because of his scientific fitness.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f05804079"/>
<p>FROM MRS. ROGER P. AMES</p>
<p>#2-</p>
<p>&ldquo;Regarding his connection with the work of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board, at the head of which was Major Walter Reed, the records show<lb/>
that he (Dr. Ames) <hi>was on duty at Camp Lazear, the experimental camp<lb/>
established by the Board, from the date of its establishment November<lb/>
20, 1900, until February 28, 1901, on which <unclear>date</unclear> the Camp was dis-<lb/>
continued</hi>.&rdquo; Letter from G. H. Bridges (S) Major General, to Mrs.<lb/>
Roger Post Ames, November 19, 1929.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dr. Ames had no connection with the yellow fever Board <hi>before<lb/>
the establishment of Camp Lazear</hi>; he attended the cases of Drs. Car-<lb/>
roll and Lazear when they came down with the fever <hi>in the regular<lb/>
course of duty at Columbia Barracks</hi>.&rdquo; Letter from Dr. Agramonte to<lb/>
Mrs. Ames, May 27, 1930.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dr. Ames was Surgeon in immediate command of Camp Jesse W.<lb/>
Lazear, United States Sanitary Experimental Station near Quemados.<lb/>
And he was Attending Surgeon of the United States Army Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission. - - - A telephone connected Major Reed's room at Columbia<lb/>
Barracks with Dr. Ames' tent at Camp Lazear.&rdquo; Daily Picayune. New<lb/>
Orleans, July 30, 1905. In re Yellow Fever Epidemic in that City to<lb/>
which Dr. Ames had been sent to take charge of Jackson Barracks.</p>
<p>A scientific expert was grouped with Dr. Lazear by Major Reed.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The cases studied during the Quemados epidemic had been diag-<lb/>
nosed by a board of physicians selected largely by reason of their<lb/>
familiarity with yellow fever. This Board consisted of Drs. Nicola<lb/>
Silverio, Manuel Herera, Eduardo Angles, and acting Assistant Sur-<lb/>
geon, <hi>Roger Post Ames and Jesse W. Lazear</hi>, U. S. Army Etiology of<lb/>
Yellow Fever, page 4 - by Major Walter Reed.</p></item>
<item><p>C. Roger Post Ames was specially equipped to take charge of Camp<lb/>
Lazear, and upon his scientific knowledge in carrying out the purposes<lb/>
of Camp Lazear depended the success of the experiment and the demon-<lb/>
stration of the theory on the Causation of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>&ldquo;His (Dr. Ames) scientific services began when a case developed;<lb/>
as soon as high temperature or the least symptom appeared, the case -<lb/>
- - - was placed under Dr. Ames' charge until his final recovery.<lb/>
<hi>They all recovered</hi>, a fact that we all thought was a &ldquo;feather in<lb/>
his cap.&rdquo; Italics Dr. Agramonte's in a letter to Mrs. Ames, May 27,<lb/>
1930.</p>
<p>&ldquo;This terminated our experiments with mosquitoes which the neces-<lb/>
sarily performed on human beings, <hi>fortunately did not cause a single<lb/>
death</hi>.&rdquo; From Inside History of a Great Medical Discovery.&rdquo; by Aris-<lb/>
tides Agramonte.</p>
<p>&ldquo;The highly dangerous character of these experiments and the good<lb/>
fortune of the Board in its second and third series of cases is shown<lb/>
by the fact that Dr. Guiteras, of Habana, in a series of seven cases,<lb/>
innoculated in Habana lost three, bringing his experiments abruptly to<lb/>
an end.&rdquo; Page 3, Senate Document #10, 59th Congress, 2nd Session.</p></item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
