<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05804033">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, July 12, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Ames, Jessie Daniel</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05804033</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-07-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-07-12">July 12, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05804033</idno>
<title>Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, July 12, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Jessie Ames answers Hench's questions concerning her husband's role in the yellow fever experiments. She suggests that Hench contact her sister-in-law for further information on Ames. She states that it is difficult for her to examine the past, but feels that she should as a duty to her children.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-07-12">
<head>Letter from Jessie Daniel Ames to Philip Showalter Hench, July 12, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05804033"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-07-12">July 12, 1942</date>
1288 Durand Drive NE<lb/>
Atlanta<lb/>
Georgia<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>This is written by me and before I continue, I want you to under-<lb/>
stand that all errors are typographical. I am off to Virgina on busi-<lb/>
ness this week and unless I inflict you with my own stenography it<lb/>
will be some time before you can hear from me. And I judge your time<lb/>
is short before you close your office up there.</p>
<p>1- You doubtless have the faver charts by now. I sent them<lb/>
from Emory several days ago.</p>
<p>2-3-4- I have no copy of the reply from the editor of the<lb/>
Journal of the A.M.A.- I have no carbons of any answers to<lb/>
Dr. Berry's letters to my husband. I think Dr. Berry is dead.<lb/>
He was a doctor in the Marine <unclear>Hospital</unclear> and Public Health<lb/>
Service. I will write to-morrow to Washington and check on<lb/>
him and his relatives. You may find something you want from<lb/>
him or them and in the light of your short time, the least I<lb/>
can do is to run down this line.</p>
<p>4- This question deserves a whole paragraph. I can explain and<lb/>
I think interpret that sentence in the Berry letter. <unclear>Dr.r</unclear><lb/>
Dr. Berry was younger than my husband. He was Irish. He was<lb/>
devoted to my husband and his devotion was quite personal.<lb/>
He had Yellow Fever when he was stationed at Laredo with his<lb/>
service and my husband in charge of Ft. McIntosh took care<lb/>
of him. Dr. Berry thought that he owed his life to my husband.</p>
<p>He made a rash statement in his letter to the Editor of the<lb/>
Journal and then called for <unclear>corobberation</unclear>. My husband was<lb/>
temperamentally unable to tell Dr. Berry that he had gone<lb/>
too far. So he merely stated that the fact was established<lb/>
only in the newspapers and he knew nothing about even these<lb/>
reports.</p>
<p>As far as my own knowledge goes, my husband never claimed that<lb/>
he was an experimental case. At least he never did either to<lb/>
me privately or in my presence to anyone else. I think it<lb/>
unreal to assume that he was one. According to the pamphlets<lb/>
written by other people, my husband, after Dr. <unclear>Lazear's</unclear> death,<lb/>
was the only doctor connected with the service who knew Yellow<lb/>
Fever from the first symptoms. It also was established in the<lb/>
same pamphlets that the chances of recoverery depended entire-<lb/>
ly on early diagnosis and promt first treatment. It would have<lb/>
been foolishness of the first order to allow this authority<lb/>
to be one of the experimental cases. Especially since there<lb/>
was no lack of material among private soldiers and natives.</p>
<p>Why my husband's case of fever was deliberately suppressed<lb/>
I have already written to you my opinion. I think I have also<lb/>
written you that he must have been careless in handling the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes of which carelessness he was profession-<lb/>
ally ashamed. You may recall that Mr. Lambert tells the story<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05804034"/>
of carrying my husband on a cot while he was sick with the<lb/>
fever so that he could order the proper treatment of one of<lb/>
the experimental cases. This is <unclear>akwardly</unclear> expressed but you know<lb/>
what I am saying. This has never been interpret<del>t</del>ed by me as an<lb/>
act of heroism on my husband's part so much as an act of expiation<lb/>
for his carelessness which might have been the cause of another's<lb/>
death.</p>
<p>I think you may safely mark off the claim by some one that my hus-<lb/>
band was one of the experimental cases. It reflects on his pro-<lb/>
fessional judgement and the good sense of Dr. Reed.</p>
<p>5- I have sent you ever single solitary map, chart and other data that<lb/>
I have. Read my answer to question 9.</p>
<p>6 I think it must refer to the fever charts which you now have.</p>
<p>7 The reprints were not enclosed. I felt sure you had copies of every-<lb/>
thing that has been printed on the Cuba story. I listed them to indicate<lb/>
the sources from which I gathered the data for the record.</p>
<p>8 I have done so.</p>
<p>9 My husband's sister's name and Address are<lb/>
Mrs. Will Morris, 515 Adams Street, New Orleans.</p>
<p>I will not appear indifferent and careless in helping you to gather<lb/>
the material on my husband. In order to avoid this I must tell you<lb/>
a little family history. My hsuband's sister, he had two but this one<lb/>
was his favorite to whom he wrote regularly and sent everthing, was<lb/>
never partial to me. I was years younger than my husband and not a few<lb/>
years younger than this sister. I tried to get her to send on to my<lb/>
daughter the papers which she had written that she had. It would be<lb/>
more than useless for me to write to my sister-in-law for them. I<lb/>
told my daughter to make her letter casual which she did and got the<lb/>
reply that when my sister-in-law found the time she would send them.</p>
<p>She mentioned in the letter she wrote to my daughter that she had<lb/>
papers &ldquo;of your father written before he ever knew your mother&rdquo;. For<lb/>
all I know they may be nothing but cancelled checks but when you asked<lb/>
for exact data on this period of my husband's life which I did not<lb/>
have it occurred to me that may be there might be something in these<lb/>
papers.</p>
<p>I suggest that you write to her yourself; that you send the reprint<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever story; that you tell her what you are doing; that<lb/>
you ask her for pictures, group and of my husband alone taken at this<lb/>
time; that you ask about maps, of the infected district or any other<lb/>
tho I think you would better ask just for maps made at that time in-<lb/>
stead of designating what maps; that you do not mention me or that you<lb/>
have secured any data of a personal or private nature, tho you probably<lb/>
have already gathered that you would not do so if you really want re-<lb/>
sults.</p>
<p>10 Wearing a mustachce, off and on and this is not meant to be funny, be-<lb/>
gan when my husband was about sixteen years old. During our too brief<lb/>
married life he shaved and grew another one exactly three times. It<lb/>
was one of his small vanities, this proving that he could grow one <unclear>faste</unclear><lb/>
than nature ordinarily allowed.</p>
<p>11-I have sent to my cousin for the photostat of the Picayune of the s<lb/>
story for which you ask. There is nothing to be had from Havana<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05804035"/>
I'll send the Picayune story as soon as it comes.</p>
<p>12- I do not have another copy. If you are not in a huryy for it, I can<lb/>
slip it in during some leisure moments of my secretary. If you want<lb/>
it right now I can have it sent out.</p>
<p>At first it was not specially easy for me to dig into the past<lb/>
but it was a duty to my children to do so. Besides it was mighty lit-<lb/>
tle for me to be doing in the light of your undertaking. Later it has<lb/>
given me pleasure. Your method of asking for what you want in the one,<lb/>
two, three manner has made the <add><unclear>easy</unclear></add> work of getting to you what you want<lb/>
to know in the order you want it even tho some of your questions<lb/>
reminded me of final examinations in which the professor asked a quest-<lb/>
ion of ten words which took a thousand to answer. But I thought if<lb/>
you wanted all I had to say I should not ration w<del>a</del>ords. I still have<lb/>
plenty left.</p>
<p>One of the keenest pleasures in this whole job has been the revival<lb/>
of the memories of my husband's genius for arousing undying loyalty<lb/>
among his associates, with a few exceptions, and his amazing capaci-<lb/>
ty for democratic behavior.</p>
<p>My son, or did I tell you, is a Lieutenant in the Medical Corps, USNR.<lb/>
He is in Little Rock now but expects to be transferred soon. I hope<lb/>
for his happiness he will be sent to sea soon. My older daughter be<lb/>
gan her third and last year of interning on July 1st in Detroit. It<lb/>
is her first experience so far north and she is not greatly impressed<lb/>
so far. All three of my offspring are satisfactory persons.</p>
<p>I hope you will keep me informed of the progress you make in this<lb/>
work and that you will let me know where your hospital will be. I<lb/>
shall be eager to know whether or not my sister-in-law has anything<lb/>
you need.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Jessie Daniel Ames</signed>
Box 485<lb/>
Emory University<lb/>
Georgia<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
