<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05808080">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, May 10, 1956</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05808080</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1956-05-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Carroll, Mrs.George</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Tate, Paul L.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1956-05-10">May 10, 1956</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05808080</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, May 10, 1956</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes his continuous attempts to contact her husband, George Carroll, and his lack of success.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1956-05-10">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Mrs. George Carroll, May 10, 1956</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05808080"/>
<opener>
Written from Hotel <unclear>Sheraton - Schcdere</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
Baltimore<lb/>
<date value="1956-05-10">May 10, 1956</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mrs. Carroll</salute>
</opener>
<p>Telegrams are so short and when read they can seem so cold and impersonal.<lb/>
Therefore, I want to write you this note (through the help of a typist here in<lb/>
Baltimore) to supplement the night letter I sent you last night. I was still<lb/>
in California after the meeting of the American College of Physicians when<lb/>
your letter of May 2nd reached Rochester, and I did not get to my office to<lb/>
read it until just before I had to leave to come here, where I am giving two<lb/>
lectures (yesterday and today) at the Johns Hopkins Hospital.</p>
<p>I wanted to write, instead of wiring you yesterday but I had no one to type<lb/>
for me. Nevertheless, I did want you to have an answer from me as soon as pos-<lb/>
sible--hence, my telegram. I think I can, in a letter, add some words that will<lb/>
make my wire clearer.</p>
<p>Mrs. Carroll, in your recent letter you wrote me very frankly. You said you<lb/>
didn't want to be rude but you were disturbed about something and you were simply<lb/>
taking the opportunity to write me frankly. Now that is what I want between you<lb/>
and me, frankness and friendliness and when I read your letter just before leav-<lb/>
ing (I took it home to bring along with me) I was <hi>not</hi> disturbed. I knew there<lb/>
was a misunderstanding. I thought you must have written it without reading care-<lb/>
fully my earlier letters to you--those of February 26th and April 26th, 1954.<lb/>
After all you would hardly have those two-year-old letters handy. I remembered<lb/>
very clearly that all I had asked of you during our long chat of February 19, 1954<lb/>
was permission to <hi>borrow</hi> the photographs and that I would have them copied (re-<lb/>
photographed) carefully and would then return to you not only the originals but<lb/>
extra copies for you to send to your husband's sisters if <hi>you</hi> wished to. I knew<lb/>
what I personally had done since then to bring these back to you personally, and<lb/>
knew that I had tried honorably to fulfill my promise.</p>
<p>Knowing this, when I read your letter the first time I said to myself: &ldquo;That's<lb/>
too bad; she doesn't recall how I've missed finding her at least twice. But I'm<lb/>
on my way there now. I will find her at home and then give her the photos, and<lb/>
show her again how well I appreciate her friendliness and cooperation; <add>we</add> will have<lb/>
a cheerful laugh together over the misunderstanding and all will be well.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Then on the plane coming here, I read your letter again, this time more lei-<lb/>
surely and carefully. I noted what I had not fully appreciated before--the sen-<lb/>
tence in your second paragraph where you write: &ldquo;In looking over my correspon-<lb/>
dence with <hi>you</hi> - - - &rdquo;. The first time I read it I assumed you meant that you<lb/>
had looked over <hi>my</hi> correspondence with <hi>you</hi>. But reading it several times now I<lb/>
realize that you probably meant just what you said and that you meant you had re-<lb/>
read <hi>your</hi> correspondence to <hi>me</hi>. This could mean, or seems to me to mean only one<lb/>
thing,--that <hi>you</hi> have written to <hi>me</hi> since my visit of February, 1954, and that<lb/>
I had never gotten it; furthermore that you, not hearing from me in reply, thought<lb/>
I was ignoring you and trying to postpone the return of your photographs.</p>
<p>Since re-reading your letter and gathering this idea from it, I have been quite<lb/>
upset because, my dear Mrs. Carroll, I can assure you I would never do that!<lb/>
Furthermore, I hasten to tell you that there has been absolutely no correspondence<lb/>
from you to me that I ever got! If you wrote me once--or more, perhaps, since my<lb/>
visit, I never got the letter or letters. Indeed I have been somewhat upset<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05808081"/>
-2-<lb/>
because I never did hear <hi>from you</hi> in answer to my letters of February 26, 1954<lb/>
or April 26, 1954. And now it would appear that <hi>you</hi> must not have received my<lb/>
letters either!! What an unfortunate situation!</p>
<p>In my letter of February 26, 1954, I reported to you the progress I was<lb/>
making with respect to the copying of your photos, I told you of the special<lb/>
care--the extra special care--I and the Chief of the Mayo Clinic Photographic<lb/>
Department were taking to see that <hi>nothing</hi> would happen to harm them. I told<lb/>
you I would not only return them to you but would send you copies of the origi-<lb/>
nals so that you could have them in case anything ever happened to the originals.</p>
<p>In that letter I offered to send extra copies of these photos to <hi>you</hi> in case<lb/>
<hi>you</hi> wished to send them to Dr. Carroll; sisters. Furthermore, I said I was<lb/>
making (as soon as possible) a copy of the rough list I had made of the material<lb/>
in the trunk--a copy for <hi>you</hi>, and that if <hi>you</hi> wanted them I would send <hi>you</hi> extra<lb/>
copies for <hi>you</hi> to give to your husband's sisters and one for your lawyer, but<lb/>
only if you wished. I said <hi>I</hi> would not correspond with your sisters-in-law or<lb/>
with your lawyer. I did this because you had honored me with your trust and<lb/>
friendship and confidence and had told me frankly that you preferred that they<lb/>
would not learn of my visit with you; that they might misunderstand and start<lb/>
troublesome inquiry which would be quite unnecessary because you were merely<lb/>
<hi>lending</hi> me these photos.</p>
<p>In that letter I also told you I was sending you by separate post a copy of<lb/>
Dr. Kelly's book. I had found out that you had no copy and would like one. I<lb/>
had an extra one, wanted you to have it (who would have a better right to such<lb/>
a copy), and sent it. (I do hope it arrived. Perhaps it did not, for I have<lb/>
never heard. That would be too bad indeed for copies of that book are rare.<lb/>
That extra copy I was actually saving for my medical-school son, but when I heard<lb/>
you didn't have one I just decided to give my extra one to you at once and hope<lb/>
that sometime I could find another for him). Please do tell me if you <hi>never</hi> re-<lb/>
ceived it!</p>
<p>In that same letter I suggested ways in which the yellow fever data could be<lb/>
copied in the most convenient way possible for you.</p>
<p>When I did not hear from you I assumed you might be away as you had told me<lb/>
you were so very lonesome in your home. So I waited two months and wrote again<lb/>
on April 26, 1954 for two reasons: to tell you to be sure to accept the invita-<lb/>
tion to the Cuban embassy affair and to report again about the photos. I told<lb/>
you I had sent copies of your photos to some &ldquo;survivors&rdquo; or interested people<lb/>
(Lambert, Tate, etc.) to see if they could identify the people in the one photo,<lb/>
as you did not know them nor did I. Not having heard from you I didn't know<lb/>
whether to trust your photos to the mail so I decided to abide by <hi>your</hi> decision.<lb/>
If you wanted me to mail them I would; if you hated to trust them to the mail even<lb/>
though registered, (and I hated to mail them,) I would <hi>bring them myself</hi> to you on<lb/>
my next visit.</p>
<p>Again I had no answer and I can now only believe that you were away and never<lb/>
got that one letter. I could only do one thing, put the photos away for safe<lb/>
keeping until I could contact you or hear from you. I have a large safe deposit<lb/>
box in the bank and also a safe just to see that such sentimentally and histor-<lb/>
ically important material is not lost.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f05808082"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>And so I did that until I could try to find you personally. I came to<lb/>
Washington at least twice, actually I think it has been three times that I have<lb/>
carried your photos back and forth. On each visit I either phoned your Rhode<lb/>
Island Avenue house or, if I had no answer, drove out in a taxi, but never once<lb/>
could I locate you. Once I phoned your old address downtown where I had first<lb/>
called in 1941, but of course you were not there. As I recall, once I called<lb/>
your lawyer, but I hesitated to do this because you told me you didn't want him<lb/>
to &ldquo;Bother about your business&rdquo; too much, and so I only asked where you might<lb/>
be located but the office did not know.</p>
<p>Now, my dear friend, what more could I possibly have done? I could only<lb/>
think of two things--either you had lost interest in them and had no concern in<lb/>
telling me how and when and where to return them, or that you were sick or away<lb/>
and that in due time I <hi>would</hi> hear. If the first supposition were true (and I<lb/>
couldn't believe it) I determined even so to look you up and return them. If<lb/>
the second were true I would certainly not send the photos by mail, have perhaps<lb/>
some tenant or relative receive them in your home and possibly misplace or lose<lb/>
them before you returned.</p>
<p>And so now that you know how carefully I have tried to carry out what I<lb/>
thought were your wishes, now that you know that I have kept full faith with<lb/>
you, I hope you will forgive me for what you must have wondered about if you<lb/>
never did hear from me. And knowing how that I have never heard from you after<lb/>
either letter or the book <unclear>I'm More</unclear> you will forgive and understand why you never<lb/>
heard from <hi>me</hi> in specific reply.</p>
<p>But let me comment on just one thing more. From reading your letter I sense<lb/>
a continuation of the grief and lonesomeness which you were still suffering when<lb/>
I visited you. This does distress me for I had so much hoped that with time<lb/>
your most understandable sorrow would lessen. I had heard indirectly (was it<lb/>
from your doctor? I can't recall) that you had decided against an operation.<lb/>
Now I'm so sorry to hear that you had it and were disappointed.</p>
<p>I wish indeed I could help somehow. Is there any way you think I could<lb/>
help you through your physician? You told me once that you had thought of coming<lb/>
to the Mayo Clinic and I told you I would do everything I could to see that, if<lb/>
you did come, you would get the very best advice our whole institution could<lb/>
provide. Indeed I made inquiries at the clinic about the possible cost of this<lb/>
and that, but you did tell me you hated to go away so far and that your own family<lb/>
physician wasn't sure you needed an operation at that time.</p>
<p>But if now, or soon you think you would like a thorough medical check-up, I<lb/>
will be more than glad to help you and your physicians in Washington arrange it<lb/>
so that what useful data they have need not be repeated in Rochester.</p>
<p>Just one last word. Everyone of us in medical or spiritual trouble needs<lb/>
friends. In view of the sympathetic and skillful services of your own physicians<lb/>
you do not need my help in that way. But I rather thought--indeed I flattered<lb/>
myself--that my friendship meant something to you and that I was somehow helping<lb/>
you just a little wee bit during our long day's visit, because you and I could--<lb/>
and did--talk for hours about things and people that interested us both--and we<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f05808083"/>
-4-<lb/>
talked very little about yellow fever.</p>
<p>I hope and believe that our friendship may continue and I hope you have<lb/>
accepted my friendship without particular regard to my very sincere interest in<lb/>
your father-in-law's memorable contributions. You know how determined I am to<lb/>
honor him and his memory, and indeed it is not too late, for that story will<lb/>
never die and the <hi>truth</hi> of the story just makes it all the more thrilling. But<lb/>
as I have had the wonderful pleasure of making <hi>real</hi> friends with so many of the<lb/>
fine men who were in Cuba in 1900--Moran, Kissinger, Lambert, the Lazears and<lb/>
others, so I have valued our relationship, yours and mine, something that de-<lb/>
pended on much more than whether or not I had copies of this or that, something<lb/>
that, as far as I am concerned, will continue long after you might have let<lb/>
everything be copied! Friends mean a lot more than that to me, and I have be-<lb/>
lieved--and hope-- that my friendship means more than that to you. If I haven't<lb/>
made that clear, then somehow I have failed in showing you my sincerity.</p>
<p>In your lovely letter of November 4, 1953, you ended by sending &ldquo;Kindest<lb/>
regards to you and your most gracious wife whom I met several years ago.&rdquo; Your<lb/>
words pleased me very much because my dear wife <hi>is</hi> very gracious and very lovely.<lb/>
She was very sorry that you did not feel able to join us a few years ago when we<lb/>
had a little dinner party at our hotel. But we hope that on another visit she<lb/>
will come with me and that we can have another chance for a pleasant, quiet<lb/>
evening. Our younger daughter (she's very lovely too!) who was married Christ-<lb/>
mas, 1954 and now lives in Bethesda is going to have her first baby in late June.<lb/>
Mrs. Hench hopes to be with her for three weeks to help out. Unfortunately I<lb/>
cannot be with them then as two years ago I promised an old friend I would speak<lb/>
at a medical congress in France which he was arranging. So I must keep my<lb/>
promise (I always try to!) and go to France for a quick trip in June.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely your friend,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench</signed>
<seg>
P.S. After all this, I almost forgot to say that I will do my best to get in<lb/>
touch with you Friday if at all possible or certainly Saturday and we will both<lb/>
feel easier when your wonderful old photos are back safe in your keeping. If my<lb/>
daughter, Susie weren't eight months pregnant I'd like to bring her along, but<lb/>
she's not up to it this time.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
