<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05811032">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Robert P. Cooke, December 11, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05811032</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-12-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Cooke, Robert P.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Haskins, Arthur</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Casade Salud Hospital, Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-12-11">December 11, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05811032</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Robert P. Cooke, December 11, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench requests Cooke's help in identifying photographs taken at Pinar del Rio. Hench is interested because Haskins, a prisoner at Pinar del Rio, died of yellow fever, but his cell-mates escaped the disease. This impressed Reed with the possibilities of the mosquito theory.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-12-11">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Robert P. Cooke, December 11, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05811032"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-12-11">December 11, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Robert P. Cooke<lb/>
Lexington - Rockbridge Health Department<lb/>
Lexington, Virginia<lb/>
<salute>My dear Doctor Cooke:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It has been a long time since we have corresponded. About a week<lb/>
ago I gave my illustrated lecture on the &ldquo;Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo; at the<lb/>
University of Virginia Medical School, on invitation of Alpha Omega Alpha<lb/>
Medical Fraternity. As I always do in that lecture, I included a slide with<lb/>
your photograph and I called attention to the fact that actually four Univer-<lb/>
sity of Virginia men were among those concerned with my story: Major Reed,<lb/>
General Kean, Johnny Moran (who later went to the University) and yourself.</p>
<p>I now write to you again for some information and I am most hope-<lb/>
ful that you can help me out because you are probably the only one alive who<lb/>
can.</p>
<p>You of course remember the epidemic of yellow fever at Pinar del Rio<lb/>
in the spring of 1900. You remember that first Agramonte, then Reed and a<lb/>
few days later Lazear, went from Havana to Pinar del Rio to investigate the<lb/>
epidemic. A post mortem was made on a soldier, Arthur Haskins (or Harkins)<lb/>
who had been a prisoner in a cell at Pinar del Rio, had gotten yellow fever<lb/>
and died just about the time Agramonte arrived at Pinar. His cell-mates (who<lb/>
had slept in the same cell, eaten the same food, etc.) escaped the disease and<lb/>
this fact impressed Reed with the possibilities of the mosquito theory. This<lb/>
story has often been mentioned by Reed and others. Therefore the case of<lb/>
Prisoner Arthur Harkins has a certain historical importance.</p>
<p>In reconstructing the entire story for my book I had hoped to find<lb/>
old photographs of the barracks, perhaps the prison cell, etc. On my trips<lb/>
to Cuba I have not yet had time to go to Pinar to see whether or not the<lb/>
buildings still remain. In my examinations of old Army records, maps, etc.,<lb/>
I did not run across anything thereon until recently.</p>
<p>Several years ago (about 1941) while rambling through some old Army<lb/>
photographic files in Washington, I did find six photographs of Pinar del Rio,<lb/>
copies of which I enclose, identified as follows: (see numbers on the photos)<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. (113459; MID - 225) (<unclear>SC-113459</unclear>) - Cuban Pacification about 1908<lb/>
Spanish Cuartel, interior view of quadrangle, Pinar del Rio, Cuba,<lb/>
M.I.D.</item>
<item>2. (113460; MID - 223) (SC 113460) - &ldquo;Cuban Pacification about 1908,<lb/>
Spanish Cuartel, front View, Pinar del Rio, Cuba.&rdquo;</item>
<item>3. (113461) (SC 113461) Cuban Pacification about 1908. Pinar del<lb/>
Rio, Cuba.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f05811033"/>
<item>Dr. Robert P. Cooke</item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>December 11, 1947</item>
<item>4. (113463; MID - 219) (SC 113463) - "Cuban Pacification about<lb/>
1908, general view of the south west from roof of Cuartel: 1 - House<lb/>
<unclear>used</unclear> by regimental commissary and quartermaster. 2 - City reservoir.<lb/>
3 - Regimental and Q. M. stables. 4 and 6 - Wooden barrack buildings,<lb/>
built for United States Troups in intervention now occupied by rural<lb/>
guards. 5 - Cas<del>c</del>ade Salud Hospital, Pinar del Rio, Cuba, January <unclear>1989</unclear>.<lb/>
(These numbers are not marked on my copy of this photo.)</item>
<item>5. (R B 4094) Pinar del Rio Barracks.</item>
<item>6. (No file number) Hospital camp, Pinar del Rio, Cuba, 1898.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Although most of these photos were taken in 1908, I assumed that these<lb/>
same buildings were used by the American troups in 1898 - 1900, but couldn't be<lb/>
absolutely sure. I also wondered whether the prison in which Arther Haskins was<lb/>
kept was shown in any of these views but of this also I could not be sure.</p>
<p>A few months ago General Truby (you surely have read his fine book on<lb/>
the yellow fever episode) made me the repository of data he used for his book.<lb/>
I have been slowly studying and digesting this material and recently found in<lb/>
General Truby's copy of &ldquo;Annual Report of Brigadier General Fitzhugh Lee, A.G.O.<lb/>
Quemados, Cuba, August 23, 1900&rdquo; the following statement in report 5, pages six and<lb/>
seven (statement signed by Major J. R. Kean, dated August 20, 1900). "Acting<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon Agramonte was then sent to inspect, and arrived on the 19th,<lb/>
in time to hold an autopsy in the case of general prisoner Arthur Harkins (God-<lb/>
frey's report named him Haskins) who died on the 18th. The typical lesions of<lb/>
yellow fever were found. He reported three well marked cases in hospital,<lb/>
seven suspects and 2 convalescents.</p>
<p>"The command was put into camp on the 22nd instant, there having been<lb/>
meanwhile three more deaths making a total of 12.....</p>
<p>&ldquo;The origin of the fever is now difficult to determine. The infantry<lb/>
battalion with their band were quartered in the Cuartel, a fine old Spanish<lb/>
barrack, which has been most carefully renovated and disinfected prior to its<lb/>
occupation by American troops. <hi>The guard house was also in this building</hi>. Just<lb/>
off the reservation and not more than 100 yards from the Cuartel is a collection<lb/>
of squalid eating houses, saloons, etc. The rest of the command were quartered<lb/>
in new barracks constructed a year ago.... The fact that 65 per cent of the cases<lb/>
come <hi>from the Cuartel</hi> and that among them were <hi>three general prisoners</hi> would in-<lb/>
dicate that the Cuartel was infected.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When I recently found these statements I came to the belief that the<lb/>
photographs Nos. 1 and 2 (Spanish Cuartel) which I had gotten about 1941 were<lb/>
in all probability photographs of the very same Cuartel used in your day by the<lb/>
American troups and that in this <hi>same Cuartel was the guard house and prison<lb/>
in which Prisoner Haskins had taken ill</hi>.</p>
<p>Now, Doctor Cooke, I am most anxious for you to examine these old<lb/>
photographs and see if you can help identify the buildings therein. Can you<lb/>
specifically answer these questions?</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Is the Spanish Cuartel (photos 1 and 2) the same one used in<lb/>
1900 by the American troops with which you served?</item>
<pb n="3" id="f05811034"/>
<item>Dr. Robert P. Cooke</item>
<item>- 3 -</item>
<item>December 11, 1947</item>
<item>2. Please note photo 2: Where was the prison (guard house) in<lb/>
this view? Note that all the windows on the first floor are<lb/>
barred which leads me to believe that not only the prison windows<lb/>
were barred but others also on the first floor.</item>
<item>3. Note in photo 2 the horse-drawn ambulance outside the entrance<lb/>
just to the right of the central passage-way. Was the hospital<lb/>
also in this Cuartel or was the ambulance at the Cuartel perhaps<lb/>
to remove someone from the Cuartel to the hospital situated elsewhere?</item>
<item>4. See photo 1. Does the interior photo show the prison? What<lb/>
were the small ground shacks at right angles to the main building<lb/>
used for?</item>
<item>5. Photo 3 was obviously taken from the roof of the Cuartel. Can<lb/>
you help me identify the various buildings in this photo? Am I<lb/>
correct in assuming that the two long one-story buildings in the<lb/>
left background were &ldquo;the new barracks constructed a year ago&rdquo; (in<lb/>
1899)? What is the 2 story building in the center background? Is<lb/>
your hospital shown in this photo?</item>
<item>6. Please see photo 4 and its title. Can you place for me the sub-<lb/>
numbers mentioned in the title (but not marked in on the face of my<lb/>
photo)? It mentions the Casade Salud Hospital (1909). Was this your<lb/>
hospital? If not, does your hospital show in this photo? If so,<lb/>
please mark in ink on the photo and return to me.</item>
<item>7. Please see photo RB 4094 (photo 5). Can you identify it further?</item>
<item>8. Please se photo 6, labelled &ldquo;Hospital camp, Pinar del Rio 1898&rdquo;.<lb/>
Can you identify it? Do you recognize it? Was this the same hos-<lb/>
pital camp used by you in 1900?</item>
<item>9. Where was your hospital in 1900 - in tents, in the Cuartel or<lb/>
in some other building? Is it shown in any of these photos?</item>
<item>10. What does the designation M.I.D. (on the photos) mean?</item>
</list></p>
<p>I do hope you can help me locate in these pictures: (a) your hospital<lb/>
where you took care of the first cases of &ldquo;pernicious malaria&rdquo;, (b) the prison<lb/>
where &ldquo;<unclear>cabine took sick</unclear>. As I stated earlier, I believe you are the only one<lb/>
who can help me in this matter, at least among those I know. Generals Kean and<lb/>
Truby and Mr. Moran were never there as far as I know. If you can't help me,<lb/>
is there some other person still alive who was there in 1900 who could help me?</p>
<p>Thank you very much for your help. Please remember me to Mrs. Cooke.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
