<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05813001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Obituary for Thomas M. England, September 4, 1943</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05813001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1943-09-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1943-09-04">September 4, 1943</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05813001</idno>
<title>Obituary for Thomas M. England, September 4, 1943</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This obituary, which appeared in the "Journal of the American Medical Association," discusses the career of England - an original yellow fever experiment volunteer.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1943-09-04">
<head>Obituary for Thomas M. England, September 4, 1943</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05813001"/>
<opener>
46<lb/>
MEDICAL NEWS<lb/>
<dateline>
Jour. A. M. A.<lb/>
<date value="1943-09-04">SEPT. 4, 1943</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>
<table rows="1" cols="2">
<row>
<cell>of syphilis and gonorrhea, giving ten lectures on the subject<lb/>
each year. In the new appointment Dr. Clarke, in addition to<lb/>
teaching, will supervise the field training of the students of<lb/>
public health specializing in venereal disease control. He will<lb/>
continue as executive director of the social hygiene association.<lb/>
<lb/>MICHIGAN<lb/>
<lb/>State Medical Meeting.--The Michigan State Medical<lb/>
Society will hold its seventy-eighth annual session in Detroit<lb/>
at the Statler Hotel, September 22-24, under the presidency of<lb/>
Dr. Howard H. Cummings, Ann Arbor. Out of state speakers<lb/>
will include<unclear>:</unclear><lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. James E. Paullin, Atlanta, Ga., The Responsibility of the Medical<lb/>
Profession in Postwar Planning.</item>
<item>Dr. Frank H. Labey, Boston, Biliary Tract Disease.</item>
<item>Dr. Oliver S. <unclear>Ormshy</unclear>, Chicago, <unclear>Avitaminosia</unclear> in Dermatology and the<lb/>
Value and Limitations of the Sulfa Group in Skin Diseases.</item>
<item>Dr. Edward <unclear>L. Jenkinson,</unclear> Chicago<unclear>,</unclear> Deformities of the Pyloric <unclear>Antrum</unclear><lb/>
Due to Perigastric Adhesions and Bands Simulating Intrinsic Gastric<lb/>
<unclear>Lesions</unclear>.</item>
<item>Dr. Paul R. <unclear>Cannon</unclear>, Chicago, <unclear>Protein</unclear> Metabolism and Resistance to<lb/>
Infection.</item>
<item>Dr. Edward A. <unclear>Schumann</unclear>, Philadelphia, Postpartum Sterilization an<lb/>
Indefensible <unclear>Procolure</unclear>.</item>
<item>Dr. Irvine McQuarrie, <unclear>Minneapolis</unclear>, Causes and Treatment of Edema<lb/>
in Childhood.</item>
<item>Dr. Kellogg <unclear>Speed</unclear>, Chicago, Treatment of Open Fractures.</item>
<item>Dr. Harold I. Lillie, Rochester, Minn., Certain Observations on Head-<lb/>
aches of <unclear>Intranasal</unclear> Origin<unclear>.</unclear></item>
<item>Dr. Everett D. Plass, Iowa City, Wartime <unclear>Obstetrics</unclear>.</item>
<item>Col. Leonard G. <unclear>Rowntree</unclear>, M. C., A. U. S., Washington, D. C., sub-<lb/>
ject to be announced.</item>
<item>Dr. A. Ashley <unclear>Weech</unclear>, Cincinnati, The Challenge of Postwar Pediatrics.</item>
<item>Dr. John C. <unclear>Whiteborn</unclear>, Baltimore, Methods of Personality <unclear>Study</unclear> in<lb/>
Relation to Medical Problems.</item>
<item>Dr. <unclear>Hobart</unclear> A. Reimann, Philadelphia, The Viral Pneumonias.</item>
<item>Dr. William S. Sadler, Chicago, Psychiatric Aspects of the Warring<lb/>
Nations.</item>
<item>Dr. Peter C. <unclear>Kronfeld</unclear>, Chicago, Preventable Blindness.</item>
<item>Dr. Harry R. Foerster, Milwaukee, <unclear>Dermatitis</unclear> of War Industries in<lb/>
General Practice.</item>
<item>Dr. Walter C. Alvarez, Rochester, Minn., Small Unrecognized Strokes,<lb/>
a Common Cause of Illness in Older Persons.</item>
<item>Drs. Robert D. <unclear>Mussey</unclear>, Rochester, and Thomas R. Wilson, co-author,<lb/>
Abnormal <unclear>Uterine</unclear> Bleeding Past Middle Age and Its Management.</item></list><lb/>
<lb/>Wednesday, September 22, designated President's Night, will<lb/>
be a public meeting at which Dr. Schumann, Philadelphia, will<lb/>
present the Andrew P. Biddle Oration on &ldquo;Medical Education<lb/>
and Present Day Philosophies of Government.&rdquo; On September<lb/>
24 a special meeting will be held for the public at which Sister<lb/>
Elizabeth Kenny, Minneapolis, will speak. In the afternoon<lb/>
Sister Kenny will discuss &ldquo;Poliomyelitis: Contrast Between the<lb/>
Kenny and Orthodox Concepts, with Results of Treatment.&rdquo;<lb/>
The program will also include sixteen discussion conferences<lb/>
on the specialties. The woman's auxiliary will meet Septem-<lb/>
ber 20-22.<lb/>
<lb/>MINNESOTA<lb/>
<lb/>Grants to the University.--The University of Minnesota<lb/>
Medical School, Minneapolis, announces a new annual appro-<lb/>
priation by the state legislature of $15,000 to the medical school<lb/>
for special research in the field of cancer. Announcement is<lb/>
also made of the continuation of the grant of $10,000 a year<lb/>
by the Citizens Aid Society to the medical school in support of<lb/>
cancer research and the program of cancer education and a<lb/>
continuation of the annual gift of $5,500 by the society to<lb/>
support the George Chase Christian professorship in cancer<lb/>
research. A grant of $5,000 from the Jane Coffin Childs<lb/>
Memorial Fund for medical research has been made for the<lb/>
support of the work of John J. Bittner, Ph.D., and Dr. Robert<lb/>
G. Green and his associates in the departments of physiology<lb/>
and bacteriology on the nature and mode of action of the milk<lb/>
influence in mammary cancer. A grant of $3,500 a year for<lb/>
a two year period has been made by the Commonwealth Fund<lb/>
of New York toward the support of the Psychiatric Clinic for<lb/>
Children. Toward the support of this clinic the Stevens<lb/>
Avenue Home of Minneapolis will continue its grant of $10,000<lb/>
for the year beginning July 1, 1943. The medical school has<lb/>
accepted a grant of $3,000 from Parke, Davis &amp; Company to<lb/>
establish a fellowship in clinical hematology in the department<lb/>
of anatomy under the supervision of Hal Downey, Ph.D.<lb/>
<lb/>NEW YORK<lb/>
<lb/>Lecture on Traumatic Surgery.--&ldquo;Traumatic Surgery<lb/>
with Emphasis on the Treatment of Wounds and Shock&rdquo; was<lb/>
the title of a lecture by Dr. Walter D. Ludlum Jr., New York,<lb/>
given before the Medical Society of the County of Greene in<lb/>
Catskill, August 27. The lecture was sponsored by the state<lb/>
medical society and the state department of health.<lb/>
<lb/>Salary Changes for Mental Hygiene Employees.--On<lb/>
October 1 a plan will be made effective in salaries of all mental<lb/>
hygiene employees under provisions of the salary standardiza-<lb/>
tion law. Classification of positions for 21,000 employees of<lb/>
</cell>
<cell>
the state department of mental hygiene providing salary increases<lb/>
for many will go far toward providing administration of mental<lb/>
hospitals, the New York Times reported, August 19. In a<lb/>
statement to the press Dr. Frederick MacCurdy, state commis-<lb/>
sioner of mental hygiene, said that &ldquo;careful attention was given<lb/>
to gradation of positions so as to augment the possibility of<lb/>
promotion from grade to grade and to make as many career<lb/>
positions as possible in hospitals.&rdquo;<lb/>
<lb/>New York City<lb/>
<lb/>Changes at New York College of Medicine.--Dr. James<lb/>
Leroy Wilson, formerly of Detroit, has been appointed pro-<lb/>
fessor of pediatrics and chairman of the department at New<lb/>
York University College of Medicine. New appointments<lb/>
include the following: departments of anatomy and psychiatry,<lb/>
Dr. Margaret A. Kennard, New Haven, Conn., assistant pro-<lb/>
fessor of anatomy and assistant professor of neuropsychiatry:<lb/>
department of dermatology and syphilology, Drs. Arthur Edward<lb/>
Goldfarb and John Cooper Graham, Brooklyn, assistant clinical<lb/>
professor; department of ophthalmology, Drs. Richard Townley<lb/>
Paton and David Henry Webster, clinical professors; depart-<lb/>
ment of psychiatry, Dr. David J. Impastato, assistant clinical<lb/>
professor. Dr. Bernhard Dattner has been promoted to asso-<lb/>
ciate clinical professor of neurology: Dr. Frank C. Keil, clinical<lb/>
professor of ophthalmology: Dr. Walter Guernsey Frey Jr.,<lb/>
clinical professor of ophthalmology, and Dr. Ervin A. Tusak,<lb/>
clinical professor of ophthalmology.<lb/>
<lb/>Physicians Barred in Compensation Cases.--Two physi-<lb/>
cians whose workmen compensation practices were said to be<lb/>
among the largest in the city lost their licenses to do that<lb/>
work on August 11 by order of the state labor department<lb/>
because of fee splitting and other misconduct, the New York<lb/>
Times reports. They are Drs. Emanuel A. Schiffmann and<lb/>
Leo S. Sacharoff. Two other physicians, guilty of similar<lb/>
charges but in lesser degree, had their licenses suspended for<lb/>
six months and three months respectively: Robert H. Feldman<lb/>
and William Philip Smale. The Times stated that 1,200 physi-<lb/>
cians are under or scheduled for investigation as a result of<lb/>
disclosures concerning &ldquo;kickbacks&rdquo; by the recent Moreland Act<lb/>
inquiry into workmen's compensation abuses. The recent 4<lb/>
cases are the first decisions to be made after departmental trials.<lb/>
Previously Dr. Theodore R. Freedman, Brooklyn, lost his<lb/>
license without formal hearing when he sent a resignation<lb/>
instead of appearing when summoned (THE JOURNAL, July 10,<lb/>
p. 757).<lb/>
<lb/>Illegal Practitioner Sentenced to Workhouse.--The<lb/>
state education department announces that Frederick Charles<lb/>
Quitzreau pleaded guilty, June 2, to holding himself out unlaw-<lb/>
fully as a practitioner of medicine and was sentenced on <unclear>June</unclear><lb/>
16 in the City Court of Special Sessions to serve six <unclear>month</unclear><lb/>
in the workhouse. Quitzreau is said to have a long <unclear>record</unclear><lb/>
illegal representation. Although he claimed graduation at <unclear>the</unclear><lb/>
Friedrich-Wilhelms-<unclear>Universitat</unclear> Medizinische <unclear>Fakultat, Berlin.</unclear><lb/>
Prussia, in 1908, a letter from the school states that a Mr.<lb/>
Charles Quitzreau &ldquo;neither studied at this university nor did<lb/>
he receive a degree.&rdquo; Before his credentials in Germany were<lb/>
investigated, he was admitted to the medical examinations in<lb/>
<unclear>Saskatchewan</unclear>, Canada, Illinois and Maine but failed in all of<lb/>
them, but he is reported to have practiced medicine in these<lb/>
places. In 1922 it was stated that he had been convicted while<lb/>
a member of the Anna (<unclear>Ill</unclear>.) State Hospital on a charge of<lb/>
practicing medicine without a license and was fined $100 and<lb/>
costs. Quitzreau is reported to have been a resident physician<lb/>
in Philadelphia and in Verona, N. J. He was said to represent<lb/>
himself as a physician in Potsdam, N. Y., although one report<lb/>
stated that &ldquo;he is doing nothing in the way of work.&rdquo; He<lb/>
has applied for staff positions at hospitals and sanatoriums in<lb/>
different sections of the country.<lb/>
<lb/>NORTH DAKOTA<lb/>
<lb/>Observes Ninety-Third Birthday.--Dr. James Grassick,<lb/>
Grand Forks, observed his ninety-third birthday on June 30,<lb/>
Dr. Grassick, who received degrees at Rush Medical College<lb/>
in 1885 and at the University of Michigan Department of<lb/>
Medicine and Surgery, Ann Arbor, in 1888, started practice in<lb/>
Buxton in 1885.<lb/>
<lb/>OHIO<lb/>
<lb/>Yellow Fever Volunteer Dies.--Lieut. Col. Thomas M.<lb/>
England, for twenty-four years executive officer of the Fifth<lb/>
Service Command Medical Branch, Fort Hayes, Columbus,<lb/>
died on July 23, aged 67. Colonel England was exposed to<lb/>
fomites during the famous Yellow Fever Experiments con-<lb/>
ducted in Cuba in 1901 by the U. S. Army Commission of<lb/>
which Major Walter Reed was chairman.</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
