<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05907008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, June 14, 1943</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05907008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1943-06-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>


<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Roper, Laura Wood</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1943-06-14">June 14, 1943</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05907008</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, June 14, 1943</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench congratulates Kellogg on his award from the National Art Director's Club. He expresses regret that Cornwell's remarks at the unveiling of the yellow fever painting were never recorded. He mentions the books of Laura Wood, Hume and Truby.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1943-06-14">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, June 14, 1943</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05907008"/>
<p>STATION HOSPITAL<lb/>
Camp Carson, Colorado<lb/>
<date value="1943-06-14">June 14, 1943</date>
Mr. George Kellogg<lb/>
Johnson and Johnson<lb/>
New Brunswick, N. J.<lb/>
My dear George:</p>
<p>I am much relieved and delighted to know that you are continuing<lb/>
the Pioneer of American Medicine series. That is really a wonderful<lb/>
thing, and incidentally it may be your greatest contribution to medicine.<lb/>
I am delighted to know that you received the award. You and Cornwell<lb/>
certainly deserved it.</p>
<p>I have just returned from a trip to Hot Springs Arkansas, visit-<lb/>
ing the Army-Navy Hospital there. I was asked to give my yellow fever<lb/>
talk there. It was very well received. You will be interested to know<lb/>
that I am giving it this week before a civilian group in town and next<lb/>
week before the nurses here in the hospital--all by invitation. Colonel<lb/>
Goldthwait, Commanding Officer at Hot Springs,<del>is</del><add><unclear>was</unclear></add> very interested in <unclear>hearing</unclear><lb/>
<del>using</del><add>the</add> sidelights that I could not mention in the formal talk. One thing<lb/>
I have always regretted is that no one took down Cornwell's remarks when<lb/>
the yellow fever painting was unveiled. Would he be willing to write<lb/>
them down as he now remembers them? If not, couldn't he give an &ldquo;explana-<lb/>
tion&rdquo; of the painting and have your secretary copy his remarks? Someday<lb/>
I do think his artistic analysis of the painting, how it came about, and<lb/>
why he had certain objects and subjects in it would be most useful. In-<lb/>
deed, if it were not published elsewhere, I think it might be valuable<lb/>
as an appendix to my book. (I cannot of course promise the latter. Hea-<lb/>
ven knows what my publishers will want to put in it. It is just a thought<lb/>
of mine.)</p>
<p>I am delighted that you are enjoying the new job, and know that<lb/>
you will bring to it all the feeling that you did in your other work. I<lb/>
am also glad to know that you are still living in New York. What is your<lb/>
address? In case Mary and I ever land there I know of no more jovial<lb/>
partner for an evening's debauch.</p>
<p>I don't think you have to worry about General Kean. I had a letter<lb/>
two weeks ago, since the dedication, but on that occasion he received so<lb/>
many letters from old friends that he told me that he expected to be snowed<lb/>
under with correspondence for some time.</p>
<p>Have you seen Laura <unclear>Woods</unclear> book on the life of Walter Reed? She sent<lb/>
me a copy and it is really very nice. I thought the inclusion of the yellow<lb/>
fever painting in Hume's book added much to the book. It is no secret that<lb/>
by the simple repetition of a fine painting, the painting becomes more and<lb/>
more famous. I am everlastingly grateful that I had something to do with<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05907009"/>
-2-<lb/>
including General Kean, General Truby, and certain others in it. The page<lb/>
proof of General Truby's book looks fine and it ought to be out in June.</p>
<p>My family arrive the 25th of June. Will I be happy!</p>
<p>Always sincerely,<lb/>
P. S. HENCH<lb/>
Lieut Colonel, M. C.<lb/>
PSH:rw</p>
<pb n="3" id="f05907010"/>
<p>The presence in Havana of the remarkable American Painter Mr. Dean Cornwell, who<lb/>
was commissioned by the firm of John Wyeth &amp; Bros, of Philadelphia to paint one of<lb/>
the most crucial events in medical history: the discovery of mechanism of the trans-<lb/>
mission of the yellow fever. The arrival of this great artist has raised again the<lb/>
often discussed question of the necessity of completely vindicating the underesti-<lb/>
mated Cuban scientist, Dr. Charles J. Finlay, whom it was unjustly tried to strip of<lb/>
the priority of this scientific conquest. The moment has arrived to draw away with-<lb/>
out hesitations the veil which on many ocassions covers the exact value of Dr. Finlay's<lb/>
experiments. If it is true that this discovery has a happy culmination thanks to<lb/>
the valuable help given by the Technical Commission designated by the United States<lb/>
Government, it is not less true, that this great Cuban, 20 years before this coopera-<lb/>
tion came about, in the year 1881, already told the Academy of Medical Sciences of<lb/>
Havana his conclusions after many years of work and careful studies. He told them<lb/>
that the horrible sickness which makes so many lands uninhabitable was due to the<lb/>
mosquitoe &ldquo;Stegomeya Fasciata&rdquo;.</p>
<p>This discovery, product of patient investigations which lasted almost all his life<lb/>
will be immortalized thanks to Mr. Cornwell who is in Havana with the intention of<lb/>
compiling the greatest possible number of data and become familiar with the atmosphere<lb/>
and types of the Cubans of that time, to be able to make a real reproduction of the<lb/>
meetings between Dr. Finlay and the doctors of the American Commission.</p>
<p>But reading the explicative pamphlet of John Wyeth &amp; Brother which we received<lb/>
from Mr. Cornwell a doubt arises when we see that the name of Mayor Walter Reed,<lb/>
doctor of the United States Army who was at the front of the above mentioned Commi-<lb/>
ssion, appears as the &ldquo;conqueror of yellow fever&rdquo;.</p>
<p>When a telegram arrived at our editorial offices announcing the arrival of the<lb/>
artist, signed by Mr. A. Greene, its contents about Dr. Finlay were not the same as<lb/>
that of the above mentioned pamphlet, because it only referred to Dr. Finlay in<lb/>
connection with the picture.</p>
<p>But in our interview with the American artist part of our doubts was dissipated<lb/>
because he assured us that Dr. Finlay will be the central figure in the picture.<lb/>
That does not prevent us from being prepared to do what we can to see to it that<lb/>
the foremost accomplishment of our countryman will not be disreputed, which does not<lb/>
mean in any respect that we try to minimize the great cooperation of the Commi-<lb/>
ssion from our neighboring country.</p>
<p>WHO IS DEAN CORNWELL</p>
<p>In the large lobby of the National Hotel we meet Mr. Dean Cornwell. We were intro-<lb/>
duced to him by the newspaperman Louis Posada. The artist who is considered one of<lb/>
the greatest American Muralist willingly gave us full details of the purpose of<lb/>
John Wyeth Brother. In the meantime, when the artist left our company for a little<lb/>
while to go to his rooms in the hotel looking for some copies of the pictures which<lb/>
he already painted in connection with the series of Pioneers of American Medicine<lb/>
we talked with Mr. Conrado Massaguer who gave us the biografic data of Mr. Cornwell.</p>
<p>Dean Cornwell was born in Lousville, Kentucky, in the year 1892, his first years<lb/>
were dedicated to music. Later he studied painting in the Chicago Art Institute<lb/>
working for some years on the artistic staff of the Chicago Tribune. After many<lb/>
years perfecting his work in the most important art centers in Europe, he was named<lb/>
Member of the Academy of National Art of the United States.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f05907011"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Actually Cornwell is considered one of the foremost American muralists and the most<lb/>
prominent illustrator. During the years 1915-1927 he painted more than 1000 illus-<lb/>
trations in all and he is probably the only artist whose works have been published<lb/>
in magazines and newspapers and at the same time exhibited in the Royal Academy of<lb/>
Art in England.</p>
<p>Among his principal works of arts are the murals in the Memphis Court in the Supreme<lb/>
Court of the State of Tennessee, in the Los Angeles Public Library, and lately in<lb/>
the salons of the General Motors Bldg. in the New York World Fair and in the Astoria<lb/>
Hotel in New York City. As an illustrator he colaborated on magazines like the<lb/>
Cosmopolitan, Saturday Evening Post, etc.</p>
<p>When Mr. Cornwell came back to us he started to explain the plan of John Wyeth<lb/>
Brother. This institution, very close to the American Medical class had made a deal<lb/>
with the artist to paint a series of pictures under the name of Pioneers of American<lb/>
Medicine and in this series, the artist will reproduce the most remarkable happenings<lb/>
with which American doctors have been connected. When this series of pictures will<lb/>
be finished, the same will be at the disposal of all Medical Societies, and the<lb/>
transportation expenses etc., of these pieces of art will be for account of John<lb/>
Wyeth Brother Incorporated. Besides, they will have lithographic copies made to be<lb/>
given to all the doctors interested in having one.</p>
<p>This series of pictures has the purpose to show to the American people all that<lb/>
humanity has to be grateful for to the New Hemisphere's men of science, trying to<lb/>
erase the predominant belief that geniuses like Pasteur, Kock, Ehrlich and others,<lb/>
are an exclusive privilege of Europe.</p>
<p>Finlay's picture will be the 3rd of the series of the Pioneers of American Medi-<lb/>
cine, the first one was of Dr. William Belmont who was famous for his experiments<lb/>
and observations in connection with the gastric substance and the psycology of<lb/>
digestion; and the second picture was of Dr. William Osler eminent American physi-<lb/>
cian who died in 1919.</p>
<p>Those canvases are two beautiful pieces of art in colors and expressions. The<lb/>
artist was extremely careful in the exact reproduction of the faces of all persons<lb/>
who appear on those pictures, and they have the most insignificant details of the<lb/>
places where the events took place. On this new picture of the yellow fever the<lb/>
persons of the Drs. Finlay, Read, Lazear, Carroll and Agramonte will appear with<lb/>
the same careful study. Since Cornwell's arrival at Havana he is busy looking for<lb/>
data in connection with Dr. Finlay's strong personality. He is also paying atten-<lb/>
tion to the typical atmosphere, visiting many places of old Havana and looking at<lb/>
documents connected with the second half of the last century and the life in the City<lb/>
during that time. He was already in many places talking always with the best in-<lb/>
formed persons. His first visit was made to Dr. Finlay's son, from whom he obtained<lb/>
pictures, personal things and references in connection with the taste and customs<lb/>
of the late Cuban Sage.</p>
<p>On his visit to the National Museum he examined the personal desk, microscope and<lb/>
other things of the late Dr. Finlay. Also he had had an interview with the<lb/>
Havana Historian Emilio Roig de Leuchseuring in whose companionship he visited the<lb/>
Academy of Medical Sciences and the National Archaic.</p>
<p>With all this data as intellectual background, Cornwell will go back to the<lb/>
United States to start work on Finlay's canvas. Following the system of all the work<lb/>
he will dedicate one full year to the creation of this new picture. We ask Mr.<lb/>
Cornwell for an explanation of what the picture of the yellow fever will be<lb/>
like. Mr. Cornwell, pleasing always, took a piece of paper and started with his<lb/>
left hand (he is lefthanded) to draw a sketch of what he intends to paint.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
