<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906097">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, May 27, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906097</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-05-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Law, Frank F.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Atcheson Laughlin</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mrs. J.B.</name>
<name type="place">Cleveland (Oh.)</name>
<name type="place">Panama Canal (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-05-27">May 27, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906097</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, May 27, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses his speech for the upcoming unveiling of the Cornwell portrait and requests more details on the event and on the painting.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-05-27">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, May 27, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906097"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-05-27">May 27, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
257 Cornelison Avenue<lb/>
Jersey City, N. J.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I imagine your mind is so full of the details of the Cleveland affair that<lb/>
you have assumed that I knew more about it than I really did. You have sent me very<lb/>
meagre details and as I have wired you today, I don't have in mind the exact set-up<lb/>
except that you have now told me three or four of the invited guests and that I am<lb/>
to be the only speaker, which I didn't really know until yesterday. I had assumed<lb/>
that somebody else would possibly discuss Wyeth's purpose in presenting the painting<lb/>
to the medical profession, with some running comments on the difficulties encountered<lb/>
in making it accurate. I thought perhaps you might be doing that, or Mr. Law. However,<lb/>
I now assume that you will not be doing this so that I will do it, as you will see in<lb/>
the enclosed partial first draft. I wish indeed I had known about this a couple of<lb/>
weeks earlier. We have been dreadfully busy. Since seeing you I have attended two<lb/>
more medical meetings and my associated is now attending a third, which has given<lb/>
me much extra work.</p>
<p>I haven't had much time to freshen up the story in new language and<lb/>
unless you have serious objections, I am afraid I will have to borrow generously<lb/>
words and paragraphs from the Lazear dedication talk which I sent you before, but<lb/>
which, for fear you can't find it, I am sending you again. (Please bring this copy<lb/>
with you to Cleveland as I need it.) I am especially inclined to be allowed the priv-<lb/>
ilege of repeating myself because my Lazear talk had only a very restricted publication<lb/>
and of course this talk probably will not be published except in brief newspaper accounts.</p>
<p>Since you are giving me more or less the whole job, I am a little worried that<lb/>
fifteen minutes will pass only too quickly for me, if not for the audience. The part<lb/>
that I am sending you <unclear>takes</unclear> six minutes speaking time. I will certainly have to skip<lb/>
over the story of the conquest rather briefly and can only give a couple of sentences<lb/>
to the current significance of the conquest, its relation to the building of the Panama<lb/>
Canal, which is now such a vital link in our defense and the relation of such American<lb/>
public health activities to our friendly relations with South America. But if you think<lb/>
that twenty minutes would be definitely too long, I shall slash the talk unmercifully<lb/>
and make it just fifteen minutes. I should like to know whether the painting is to be<lb/>
unveiled before or after the talk as the wording of the talk might be a little different<lb/>
here and there. I might turn to the painting and point to the various figures, particu-<lb/>
larly when I give the next to the last paragraph of the talk, but it is quite all right<lb/>
and if you want to have the painting unveiled just after my talk and follow it up by<lb/>
an introduction of Kissinger and Mrs. Reed, that is quite all right with me, but let<lb/>
me know.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906098"/>
<p>Mr. George A. Kellogg</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>May 27, 1941</p>
<p>Also before I hand the talk to the newspapers I would like to know what<lb/>
sibsidiary figures you finally portrayed in the painting.</p>
<p>I am surprised that you want fifty rather than twelve multigraphed copies<lb/>
but we will do our best. I will arrive at the Hotel Cleveland Sunday morning and<lb/>
would like very much to get in touch with you at your earliest convenience, as I<lb/>
will be busy at an Executive Committee meeting in the afternoon. If I can possibly<lb/>
airmail a few copies, to get to New York Saturday, I assume that I am to send them<lb/>
to your office. <del>Or</del><add>Where</add> shall I send them so that if they arrive Saturday afternoon they<lb/>
can still be of use to you?</p>
<p>I am a little concerned as to the news value of my talk. Obviously it will<lb/>
have to be rewritten by the newspaper men. The head of our editorial department<lb/>
thought that it would have sufficient news value as it is now outlined, but I was<lb/>
hoping to hear from you if you had any special suggestions or requests for me to<lb/>
put certain date in the paper.</p>
<p>One more final thing. There are two more friends of mine who are going to<lb/>
be in Cleveland that day--Dr. and Mrs. Walter Simpson, 247 Blossom Heath Road,<lb/>
Dayton, Ohio. He is a nationally known physician who has been much interested in the<lb/>
Walter Reed affair and if there is still room for you to invite him I would be very<lb/>
grateful if you would. If your quota is filled, could <unclear>l</unclear> invite him as my guest at<lb/>
my own expense, <unclear>as</unclear> I would be only too glad to have him there.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
<seg>
P. S. Just this minute I received your engraved invitation which looks<lb/>
very nice (although my name is spelled &ldquo;Philip&rdquo; not &ldquo;Phillip&rdquo;), and your letter.<lb/>
I will call you at the Allerton Hotel as soon as I arrive early Sunday morning at<lb/>
the Cleveland Hotel. As the invitation looks so nice, please send one to my brother,<lb/>
Dr. and Mrs. A. L. Hench, East Jefferson Street, Charlottesville, Virginia, and also<lb/>
one to my mother, Mrs. J. B. Hench, 5524 Kentucky Avenue, Pittsburgh, Pa. They won't<lb/>
come but I would like them to see what big company their little boy keeps!<lb/>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
