<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906188">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Suggested Arrangement of Key to Painting, by Philip Showalter Hench, [1941]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906188</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Fernandez, Nicanor</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Presedo, Vincente</name>
<name type="person">Martinez, Jose</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Olson, Wiliam</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-00-00">[1941]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906188</idno>
<title>Suggested Arrangement of Key to Painting, by Philip Showalter Hench, [1941]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In a numbered list, Hench names and identifies the figures in the Cornwell yellow fever painting.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-00-00">
<head>Suggested Arrangement of Key to Painting, by Philip Showalter Hench, [1941]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906188"/>
<p>SUGGESTED ARRANGEMENT OF <hi>KEY TO PAINTING</hi> (P.S. HENCH)</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head>SUGGESTED ARRANGEMENT OF <hi>KEY TO PAINTING</hi> (P.S. HENCH)</head>
<item>1. Dr. Carlos Finlay, the Cuban physician who originated and developed the theory<lb/>
of the transmission of yellow fever by the mosquito but whose work was<lb/>
ignored for 19 years.</item>
<item>2. Dr. (Major) Walter Reed, President of the United States Army Yellow Fever Board<lb/>
which proved conclusively the cause of yellow fever.</item>
<item>3. Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, member of the Army Board, inoculating Dr. Carroll with an<lb/>
infected mosquito. (Dr. Lazear died a month later as a result of self-<lb/>
experimentation, a martyr to science.)</item>
<item>4. Dr. James Carroll, member of the Army Board, who developed the Board's first<lb/>
case of experimental yellow fever as a result of the inoculation portrayed.</item>
<item>5. Dr. Aristides Agramonte, Cuban physician and member of the U. S. Army Board.</item>
<item>6. Gen. Leonard Wood, Governor-General of Cuba, who threw the weight of his authority<lb/>
behind the Board.</item>
<item>7. Major Jefferson R. Kean, Chief Surgeon of the Department of Western Cuba, friend<lb/>
and advisor of Reed and his colleagues.</item>
<item><p>8. Lieutenant Albert E. Truby, commanding officer of the Columbia Barracks Post<lb/>
Hospital, Quemados (near Havana) Cuba, where the early experiments were<lb/>
performed.</p>
<p>(Alternate description: Truby who succeeded Captain A. N. Stark as commanding<lb/>
officer......etc.) I think the first description is preferable although the<lb/>
the latter is a little more fair to Stark but I can mention Stark in passing<lb/>
in my paper.</p></item>
<item>9. Dr. Roger P. Ames, U. S. Army Medical Corps, Yellow fever expert who successfully<lb/>
cared for the patients with experimental yellow fever.</item>
<item>10. Dr. Robert P. Cooke, contract surgeon U. S. Army Medical Corp who volunteered<lb/>
to be shut up in a house (Bldg. No. 1) with infected bedding for 20 days to<lb/>
prove the non-infectiousness of &ldquo;fomites&rdquo; (personal belongings).</item>
<item>11. John R. Kissinger, Private, U. S. Army Hospital Corp.</item>
<item>12. John J. Moran, acting steward, Army Hospital Corp. He and Kissinger were the<lb/>
first two who volunteered to submit to inoculations after the mosquito theory<lb/>
was accepted by the Yellow Fever Board.</item>
<item>13. Warren G. Jernegan, Private, Hospital Corp who submitted to experiments with<lb/>
infected clothing and later to inoculation.</item>
<item>14. An American private representative of the eleven additional volunteers:<lb/>
William H. Dean (case &ldquo;X-Y&rdquo;), William Olson, Levi E. Folk, Wallace Forbes,<lb/>
John H. Andrus, Clyde L. West, James L. Hanberry and Charles G. Sonntag<lb/>
who accepted inoculations; Edward Weatherwalk, James Hildebrand and Thomas<lb/>
M. England who were exposed to &ldquo;fomites.&rdquo;</item>
<item>15. A Spanish immigrant, representative of the four who volunteered for inoculations:<lb/>
Antonio Benigno, Nicanor Fernandex, Fincente Presedo and Jose Martinez.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
