<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906123">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, June 23, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906123</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-06-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, Ida E.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-06-23">June 23, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906123</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, June 23, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg discusses the publication of Hench's remarks on the Cornwell painting in medical journals. The Wyeth Company will provide color inserts of the painting for publication.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-06-23">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, June 23, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906123"/>
<opener>
GEORGE A. KELLOGG<lb/>
<dateline>
257 CORNELISON AVENUE<lb/>
JERSEY CITY, N.J.<lb/>
<date value="1941-06-23">June 23, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench,</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your two letters and the manuscript were received last week;<lb/>
also the expense sheet which I thought rather amusing as well as<lb/>
very complete. Just between ourselves, I think that it exuded an<lb/>
atmosphere of honesty and candor which is strangely lacking in<lb/>
many expense sheets with which I have previously had intimate per-<lb/>
sonal contact. You will receive a check direct from John Wyeth &amp;<lb/>
Brother within a few days.</p>
<p>As to the publication of your speech, our choice, of course,<lb/>
would be <hi>Hygeia</hi> as it has the largest circulation. For <hi>Hygeia</hi> do<lb/>
you suppose it would be possible to take out the preliminary remarks<lb/>
concerning the painting and use them as an explanatory footnote?<lb/>
Perhaps this sketch would have to be revised just slightly for that<lb/>
purpose.</p>
<p>The magazine of second choice would be &ldquo;Minnesota Medicine&rdquo; in<lb/>
which the same method of handling the introductory remarks might be<lb/>
used. In any event we will be glad to provide either of the maga-<lb/>
zines with a black and white halftone reproduction of the painting<lb/>
as well as black and white reproductions of some of the sketches and<lb/>
photographs of persons included in the painting. It might be that<lb/>
the editor of one or the other of the magazines would prefer to have<lb/>
small black and white halftones and have us provide a full color<lb/>
printed reproduction of the painting which could be used as an in-<lb/>
sert or frontispiece facing the article. It would take us almost two<lb/>
months to get this insert printed and delivered to them but I doubt<lb/>
if they would be using the article before that time anyway. If you<lb/>
care to bring up the subject of a full color insert which we would<lb/>
print and pay for you might suggest it to the editor in this manner:<lb/>
For example, &ldquo;I, (Dr. Hench,) believe that I can persuade John Wyeth<lb/>
and Brother to <unclear>supply</unclear> a full colored insert if you would care to use it.&rdquo;<lb/>
I am sure that neither of the magazines would be willing to print<lb/>
anything in full color themselves.</p>
<p>As to the &ldquo;Annals of Medical History&rdquo;, if the article were to go<lb/>
to them I feel quite confident they would be willing to do quite an<lb/>
elaborate job. In their July issue of this year (which I have not<lb/>
seen at the moment) is scheduled a reproduction of the speeches made<lb/>
at the dedication of the Osler Memorial at Philadelphia on which oc-<lb/>
casion our Osler painting was unveiled, a short article on the series,<lb/>
&ldquo;Pioneers of American Medicine&rdquo;, an article by Dean Cornwell on how<lb/>
he painted the picture (incidentally I wrote this for him after pick-<lb/>
ing up some of the painter's jargon) and in addition fourteen or six-<lb/>
teen pages of halftones.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906124"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>We are buying a considerable number of reprints <add>from this July <unclear>number</unclear>.</add> <del>as it is</del> From<lb/>
the standpoint of getting reprints <del>that</del> the &ldquo;Annals of Medical His-<lb/>
tory&rdquo; would be entirely satisfactory. It is only the wider circula-<lb/>
tion of &ldquo;Hygeia&rdquo; and &ldquo;Minnesota&rdquo; Medicine" that makes those two pub-<lb/>
lications appear more attractive.</p>
<p>As you see from the foregoing, we will be much pleased to have<lb/>
you take action with any of these publications, even including the<lb/>
&ldquo;Bulletin of Medical Librarians Association&rdquo; if indeed we come to<lb/>
that. With any of these publications we will be glad to supply both<lb/>
full color inserts and as many halftones of other pictures as they<lb/>
wish to use. Your suggestion that Fishbein might use the photograph<lb/>
of the painting with Van Etten and Lahey I think is sound. He might<lb/>
use this along with a full color insert for &ldquo;Hygiea&rdquo; which in that<lb/>
publication is something of a project as the circulation is about one<lb/>
hundred thousand.</p>
<p>I want you to feel free to commit us to an &ldquo;all-out&rdquo; cooperation<lb/>
with any of these journals, for the better the manner in which the job<lb/>
is done the more benefit will redound to the publication and ourselves.<lb/>
In all cases where the painting is reproduced we would, of course, like<lb/>
a credit line in small type, &ldquo;courtesy of John Wyeth and Brother&rdquo;</p>
<p>I just received a copy of your letter to Mr. Cornwell concerning<lb/>
the new photograph of Moran. I have talked with him on the 'phone and<lb/>
he is going to hold the painting until the photograph arrives and make<lb/>
whatever changes he thinks adviseable before the painting is delivered<lb/>
to our engravers.</p>
<p>As to your postscript concerning our printing the speech, we will<lb/>
certainly do this if none of these magazines accept it. I have a feel-<lb/>
ing, however, that this will not be necessary.</p>
<p>I am enclosing with this letter the photographs you requested along<lb/>
with a few <unclear>other</unclear> pictures which might be of interest to the editors of<lb/>
these publications. If the material enclosed is not sufficient do not<lb/>
hesitate to let me know.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>George A. Kellogg</signed>
<seg>
P.S. I have not heard further from Mrs. Kissinger. I agree with you<lb/>
if he is to be paralyzed as you described it would be much better for<lb/>
the end to come as soon as possible. This has proved to be an unhappy<lb/>
ending to our contact with him but he unquestionably enjoyed the occasion.<lb/>
</seg>
Dr. <unclear>Philip</unclear> S. Hench,<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota.<lb/>
GAK:L<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
