<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906160">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, August 13, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906160</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-08-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-08-13">August 13, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906160</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, August 13, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses changes to Cornwell's "Conquerors of Yellow Fever" painting that would improve its historical accuracy.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-08-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, August 13, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906160"/>
<opener>
<del>leave on desk.</del><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-08-13">August 13, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
257 Cornelison Avenue<lb/>
Jersey City, N. J.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I never did quite understand how it came to pass that Cornwell included<lb/>
as many figures as he did in the yellow fever painting. You recall my original<lb/>
suggestion was to confine the figures to the five hot-shots--the four Americans<lb/>
and Finlay. Then Truby suggested many figures, more or less all those connected<lb/>
in any way with the experiments and mentioned various names. The upshot of it<lb/>
was a compromise whereby Cornwell included fourteen figures, of which only seven<lb/>
were really identified. I gather from you that you were willing to let the<lb/>
other men stand for anyone who wanted to think he or his relative was in the<lb/>
painting, but I think that is a bad thing from the standpoint of history. You may<lb/>
be pleasing some people who are momentarily alive but history will demand a better<lb/>
accounting than that. At my suggestion, Cornwell did include the fifteenth figure--<lb/>
the Cuban volunteer placed between Moran and Kissinger. Undoubtedly with the en-<lb/>
couragement of others but on my suggestion also, it was decided to consider the<lb/>
seated figure on the left General Kean, the seated figure in the center, General<lb/>
Wood, the standing figure between Finlay and Agramonte was to become General Truby<lb/>
and Dr. Cook was to be one of the two figures on the porch railing. From the very<lb/>
start I understood that the mustached figure on Moran's right was to be Jernegan.<lb/>
That still leaves two figures &ldquo;anonymous&rdquo; as the newspaper article expressed it.<lb/>
I shall be glad indeed to go into a huddle with myself and with Generals Kean<lb/>
and Truby, and at my very earliest convenience will nominate names for these two<lb/>
or three other men. I suspect that the figure whose face is not very clear and<lb/>
who is placed in the background behind Moran was more or less planned to be Andrus.<lb/>
Since he was one of the very last who volunteered, the only claim that he has to get<lb/>
in the painting is that he, according to his own story, took Reed's place as volun-<lb/>
teer and secondly, he has been personally helpful to you all. I do think that the<lb/>
painting must be purposeful in every detail and that each person should be identi-<lb/>
fied. In the description of the painting there is plenty of space for you to state<lb/>
definitely that these men were chosen to represent their colleagues whose names<lb/>
were actually mentioned in my paper.</p>
<p>I have not yet received the early proof but will be anxious indeed to see<lb/>
it. Your preliminary plans for the McDowell painting sound most interesting. I<lb/>
have had a great deal of fun out of the yellow fever painting and wish indeed that<lb/>
I were enough of an authority to help you with the next one.</p>
<p>Incidentally, I came across a catalog from a concern that sells autographed<lb/>
letters. They have two or three letters of Dorothy Dix. Would you like to have them?</p>
<p>I was very much interested in the New York Sunday Mirror article and sent<lb/>
them a check last week to send me twenty-five copies. The check has been returned<lb/>
with the statement that they have no copies available. I don't want to rob you of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05906179"/>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
August 13, 1941<lb/>
your own copies but if I could buy a dozen without disturbing you, I should be<lb/>
very happy to do so. I enclose a carbon copy of a letter that I am sending to<lb/>
Fred Rankin. I happened to play the organ at Fred's marriage to Edith Mayo.<lb/>
I have known Freddy for years although I was always more friendly to Edith than<lb/>
to Fred.</p>
<p>I will be attending the <unclear>Wisconsin</unclear> State Medical Meeting as I am chairman<lb/>
of a luncheon round table discussion and I am also invited to read a paper before<lb/>
the general session and so I will be glad to see the painting at that time. Will<lb/>
you be along with the painting?</p>
<p>Can you send me a couple more photographs of the painting or a couple of<lb/>
extra colored reproductions of the painting upon the margins of which I can make<lb/>
notes to send to Truby and Kean?</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
