<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906118">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard M. Hewitt and the Committee on Medical Education and Research, June 20, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906118</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-06-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hewitt, Richard M.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="person">Law, Frank F.</name>
<name type="place">Cleveland (Oh.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-06-20">June 20, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906118</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard M. Hewitt and the Committee on Medical Education and Research, June 20, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses the ethics of having his yellow fever talk reprinted and distributed by the Wyeth Company. A note by Hewitt on the second page states that he sees no ethical problems with publication.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-06-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Richard M. Hewitt and the Committee on Medical Education and Research, June 20, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906118"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-06-20">6/20/41</date>
</dateline>
<salute>To Dr. Hewitt and the Committee on Medical Education and Research:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You will remember that in connection with my researches on the<lb/>
history of the conquest of yellow fever, I was called upon to advise Mr.<lb/>
Dean Cornwell, the New York painter, regarding the details of the conquest.<lb/>
As a result, I was invited to give the dedicatory address at the unveiling<lb/>
of this painting in Cleveland during the A.M.A. week. The affair was a very<lb/>
nice one and entirely ethical. The invited group was small but very select.<lb/>
It included the mayor of Cleveland, Dr. Van Etten, the President of the A.M.A.,<lb/>
Dr. Lahey, the President-elect of the A.M.A. (see enclosed photograph), Miss<lb/>
Blossom Reed, Walter Reed's daughter, Mr. Kissinger, one of the survivors of<lb/>
the experiment, representatives from a few medical schools, among them the<lb/>
University of Virginia, and Dean Eben Carey, of Milwaukee (who, by the way,<lb/>
has invited me to give the same talk in Milwaukee this Fall), and representatives<lb/>
from a few art museums, also former Surgeon. General Ireland &amp; wife, Col, Siler etc.</p>
<p>The Wyeth Company which sponsors these paintings, pays about $10,000<lb/>
<unclear>a piece</unclear> for them. In addition, I know they have spent several thousand dollars<lb/>
having Mr. Cornwell and their representatives visit Cuba and other places to get<lb/>
the proper background for the painting. When these paintings are finished, they<lb/>
are sent to various medical exhibits (commercial) and are also sent to various<lb/>
medical schools and medical societies which request them. Thereafter they are<lb/>
deposited on permanent loan in some appropriate place. For example, the Osler<lb/>
painting is now in the old Blockley Hospital, Philadelphia. The Walter Reed<lb/>
painting may be deposited either at the University of Virginia or the Walter Reed<lb/>
Hospital.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, colored plates are made of the painting and as a type of<lb/>
ethical advertisement, the Wyeth Co. send out about 15,000 of these, already framed<lb/>
and autographed by the artist; one of mine doesn't even have the name of John Wyeth<lb/>
Co. on it--the other one does. In addition, as many as 100,000 copies are sent<lb/>
to various physicians throughout the country, these being unframed and not signed<lb/>
by the artist. With each of the previous paintings, they have sent a small brochure<lb/>
giving a brief synopsis of the subject painted. A well known Chicago physiologist<lb/>
(not Carlson, and at the moment I can't remember his name but he has been here fre-<lb/>
quently) was the chief advisor on the Beaumont painting. The Wyeth people were<lb/>
already preparing this brochure but when they heard my talk, Mr. Law, the President,<lb/>
and Mr. Kellogg, the head of their promotion department, said that they would very<lb/>
much like to discard their own write-up and send with each copy of the picture a<lb/>
copy of my talk. In order to avoid any possible criticism, they suggested that I<lb/>
have my talk published somewhere, if possible in a medical journal and they would buy<lb/>
the appropriate large number of reprints. The other alternative would be to obtain<lb/>
permission to print my talk illustrated with a copy of their painting.</p>
<p>Walter Simpson of Dayton, Ohio, was in the audience. Unbeknown to me,<lb/>
he showed a copy of my talk to Paul Hoeber, who said he would like to publish it<lb/>
in the Annals of Medical History. That evening he discussed it with Fishbein who<lb/>
said he would like to have a shortened version of it for Hygeia. From the standpoint<lb/>
of the company, they would of course like to have included the first two pages where<lb/>
I call attention to the painstaking accuracy of the artist. I suspect that neither<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05906119"/>
Fishbein nor Hoeber would include the first two pages but would probably start<lb/>
on the bottom of page 2. The Wyeth folks suggested that Minnesota Medicine<lb/>
might publish it and they would be glad to give this journal the color plates<lb/>
or colored reproduction already for insertion at no cost to them, and the only<lb/>
mention of the Wyeth people would be the small name &ldquo;Wyeth&rdquo; printed at the lower<lb/>
right hand corner of the reproduction. Time Magazine has already reproduced<lb/>
their Beaumont painting and a colored reproduction of the Beaumont painting has<lb/>
been used as a frontispiece of the <unclear>Mosby</unclear> reprint of the Life of Beaumont.</p>
<p>What would you advise me to do? Since my talk has nothing to do with<lb/>
pills or medicine but is merely a few words of well-merited praise for the artist<lb/>
and then a short version of the yellow fever story, it seems to me it is entirely<lb/>
ethical for me to let them use it some way or other. It seems to me that this<lb/>
is analgous to the use of certain articles by Banting, Sir Henry Dale <add><unclear>Minister</unclear></add> and others<lb/>
in the Eli Lilly Souvenir Volume which I am sending for your attention. The<lb/>
only ulterior motive I have in letting them use it is that I have included one<lb/>
brief paragraph on Camp Lazear, as we have found it recently. I am careful not<lb/>
to ask for help in my attempts to raise some money to memorialize this camp site<lb/>
properly but I can well imagine that if a copy of my talk went out to many thousand<lb/>
physicians, at least a few might spontaneously be stimulated to join in with me<lb/>
in my campaign to preserve the camp site and the little historical building which<lb/>
still remains and which I purchased this Spring in Cuba.</p>
<p>The easiest solution would be of course just to let the Wyeth folks<lb/>
print my talk as is with the introduction unchanged or slightly changed. But I<lb/>
will abide by the decision of yourself and the Committee on Medical Education<lb/>
and Research.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench</signed>
6-20-41<lb/>
Recommendation 1: Whether Dr. Hench desires to send this to a<lb/>
journal or to let Wyeth be the original publisher, it seems to me an ethical<lb/>
project. It puffs no remedy and Dr. Hench, with his present position among<lb/>
those interested in the history of yellow fever was the obvious one to give<lb/>
the address.<lb/>
Richard M. Hewitt<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
