<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906011">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 18, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906011</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-02-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-02-18">February 18, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906011</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 18, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg discusses his conversation with Cornwell and the changes that are planned for the yellow fever painting. Hench may take the preliminary sketches to Cuba with him if he likes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-02-18">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 18, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906011"/>
<opener>
John Wyeth V Brother<lb/>
Incorporated<lb/>
Manufacturing Chemists,<lb/>
Philadelphia<lb/>
<dateline>
1600 Arch Street<lb/>
<date value="1941-02-18">February 18, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
The Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>As I wrote you yesterday, I had dinner with<lb/>
Mr. Cornwell last evening, and explained in detail the reason for<lb/>
the suggested change on the Yellow Fever picture. Mr. Cornwell was<lb/>
somewhat upset to begin with but after he thoroughly understood<lb/>
what we were driving at, he became enthusiastic about the oppor-<lb/>
tunity to paint a more dramatic situation.</p>
<p>As I told you when Mr. Withington and I were<lb/>
at your home, I was afraid that the down light which he expected to<lb/>
use in the patio could not be had honestly if the men were on the<lb/>
porch of the officers' quarters; however, Cornwell made the suggest-<lb/>
ion that we use the porch of the officers' quarters as a background,<lb/>
putting Kissenger and Moran on the porch, or sitting on the porch<lb/>
rail, and place the balance of the group in front of the porch,<lb/>
where the down light of the late afternoon would be perfect. By<lb/>
doing this he feels he can work in a little more landscape and a<lb/>
little more tropical shrubbery. In all other details, he will be<lb/>
very glad to paint the picture as you described it.</p>
<p>He says he may not be able to get as good a like-<lb/>
ness of Lazear with his head bent down over the arm of Carroll; how-<lb/>
ever, he says that any man who wears whiskers is much easier to paint<lb/>
than one who does not, and inasmuch as Lazear was the only man of the<lb/>
group who had them, he will be instantly identified. As to Reed and<lb/>
Finley, he can use them in exactly the poses of which he now has<lb/>
photographs and drawings.</p>
<p>I promised Mr. Cornwell that if you came through<lb/>
New York on your way to Havana some time in March, I would bring you<lb/>
up to the studio. The painting should be pretty well along by that<lb/>
time but not so far along but that further suggestions will still be<lb/>
possible, providing they don't involve any radical change. I myself<lb/>
am very anxious to have you see the picture in progress.</p>
<p>As to the sketches, Mr. Cornwell has agreed to<lb/>
work over the features on both sketches which you saw, and if you wish<lb/>
to do so, you can have them both when you go to Havana. If you find<lb/>
they are interested in them and would like to have one, or perhaps<lb/>
even both of them, you can bring them back with you and we will be<lb/>
glad to cooperate in holding out on the Cubans, so that when they do<lb/>
get them they will appreciate them. In the meantime, perhaps you can<lb/>
get something out of them that you want.</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906012"/>
<p>Dr. Philip S. Hench</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>February 18, 1941</p>
<p>As to Kissenger and Moran, would it be possible<lb/>
for you to get me photographic copies of any pictures which you have<lb/>
of both these men, which were taken at or about the time of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever study? Undoubtedly there is a photographer in Rochester<lb/>
who would be good at making a copy of any or several of these. Nat-<lb/>
urally we will be glad to pay all expense involved. Cornwell is<lb/>
going ahead with the new sketch or sketches and will hold off paint-<lb/>
ing any features on these two men until after we have gotten fairly<lb/>
good likenesses. If you believe it will be necessary for me to write<lb/>
to Mr. Kissenger or Mr. Moran to get this material, I will do so, but<lb/>
will wait until I hear from you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>JOHN WYETH &amp; BROTHER, INC.<lb/>
George G. Kellogg<lb/>
Advertising Director</signed>.
GEX:HR<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
