<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906006">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 7, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906006</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-02-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-02-07">February 7, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906006</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 7, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg thanks Hench for providing so much information for Cornwell's painting. He will discuss changes in the painting with Cornwell.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-02-07">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 7, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906006"/>
<p>257 CORNELISON AVENUE<lb/>
JERSEY CITY, N.J.<lb/>
<date value="1941-02-07">February 7th, 1941</date>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
Dear Dr. Hench:</p>
<p>Mr. Douglas J. Withington of John Wyeth &amp; Brother, Philadelphia<lb/>
gave me your recent letter concerning the new painting on &ldquo;The<lb/>
Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. I also have your article on Lazear<lb/>
which I found most interesting.</p>
<p>When Mr. Cornwell visited Cuba last October I accompanied him,<lb/>
at which time we got what we thought was adequate background on<lb/>
Finlay, as well as the work that the U.S. Army Commission had<lb/>
done.</p>
<p>We are to be in Washington, D.C. Monday and Tuesday of this week<lb/>
with Mr. Cornwell, who has now completed two preliminary sketches<lb/>
in oil.</p>
<p>Since reading your letter and your article we feel it is quite<lb/>
essential to show you these sketches before he starts doing the<lb/>
work on canvas. Would it be possible for Mr. Withington and<lb/>
myself to see you a week from this coming Monday, or Tuesday;<lb/>
that is February 17th or 18th? We could arrange this easily<lb/>
as we have to go to Chicago about that time. If some other date<lb/>
a little later would be more convenient, I believe that it could<lb/>
be arranged. We will, of course, bring Mr. Cornwell's sketches<lb/>
with us.</p>
<p>If you can wire me at the above address, collect, it will facilitate<lb/>
making the arrangements for this trip.</p>
<p>With our many thanks for your cooperation, I am</p>
<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
George Kellogg<lb/>
George A. Kellogg:ef<lb/>
CC - Mr. D. J. Withington</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906007"/>
<p>Dr. P. S. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>February 17, 1941</p>
<p>At the time I wrote the copy I had never heard of Finlay, as far as<lb/>
I can recall, so when we got down to paragraph 4, in preparing the<lb/>
telegram from New York, the writer says, - &ldquo;Its contents about Dr.<lb/>
Finlay were not the same as that of the above-mentioned pamphlet&rdquo;. In<lb/>
other words, they already began to suspect us of duplicity. We were<lb/>
perfectly innocent in the matter, however, for two years ago I thought<lb/>
of no one but Walter Reed and his Commission, and two weeks before we<lb/>
went to Cuba I had been sold the bill of goods on the Finlay idea, and<lb/>
really began to place Walter Reed pretty far down the scale in im-<lb/>
portance, feeling that Reed and his doctors had stolen all the glory<lb/>
from Finlay. It now becomes the privilege and duty of John Wyeth &amp;<lb/>
Brother to attempt to do in a picture painted by Cornwell what you are<lb/>
doing in your writings; in other words, to give a fair and well-balanced<lb/>
credit to all. The more I read about Moran and Kissenger, the more I<lb/>
feel that they should be in the picture. I will talk to Cornwell about<lb/>
this tonight.</p>
<p>To get down to paragraph 5 in the translation, in the light of our<lb/>
recent conversation, I think this is very funny. I was present at only<lb/>
part of that interview and did not realize that Cornwell was committing<lb/>
himself to the extent of assuring them that Dr. Finlay would be the<lb/>
central figure in the picture. As you have said, it certainly turned<lb/>
out that way in the sketches which you have seen.</p>
<p>On page 3 of the translation it is perfectly obvious that, as someone<lb/>
has said, the Cubans are making a God of Finlay. They are prejudiced<lb/>
in his favor. One reason, I suppose, is that they really don't under-<lb/>
stand anything about the technical requirements of proving such a<lb/>
theory as Finlay <del>did have.</del><add>had.</add></p>
<p>I won't take any more of your time for the present, but it seems to me<lb/>
that there will be a little hell raised in Cuba when we show the finished<lb/>
picture, <del>but</del><add>perhaps</add> we'd better show them nothing but the preliminary sketches.<lb/>
We will discuss this later.</p>
<p>With kindest regards to Mrs. Hench and our thanks for your splendid co-<lb/>
operation and hospitality, I am</p>
<p>Very truly yours,<lb/>
George A. Kellogg<lb/>
George A. Kellogg<lb/>
RO<lb/>
Encl.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
