<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906038">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 26, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906038</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-02-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-02-26">February 26, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906038</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 26, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench comments on Truby's suggestions regarding the Cornwell yellow fever painting.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-02-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 26, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906038"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-02-26">February 26, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George Kellogg<lb/>
257 Cornelison Avenue<lb/>
Jersey City, N. J.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was very glad to receive the photographs of the people you met in<lb/>
Cuba and they are interesting to have. While I am not in a hurry for some of the<lb/>
material that I loaned you, I am most anxious to have you return at your very<lb/>
earliest convenience the Agramonte article in the Scientific Monthly for December,<lb/>
1915. I must have parts of this photostated right away to send in my report to Dr.<lb/>
Ramos, which must go out if possible in the next week. Unfortunately, the other copy<lb/>
of this article which I have is so marked up that I do not wish to photostat it.</p>
<p>I have just received a carbon copy of General Truby's letter to you. I<lb/>
am sure you will find it most interesting and helpful. I am a little disturbed<lb/>
about his suggestion to make such a large, formal grouping, and I think his painting<lb/>
would have little action in it. Furthermore, I think it would emphasize General<lb/>
Wood too much. If you wish, by all means put General Wood into your scene but I<lb/>
still think that a painting portraying the actual inoculation of Carroll by Lazear<lb/>
would be the best. It seems to me that General Truby contradicts himself a bit.<lb/>
In the first part of his letter he says he hates to see a painting depict the scene<lb/>
with persons therein (meaning Reed) who were actually not there. But then he goes<lb/>
on to describe a scene which never took place, with General Wood and various enlisted<lb/>
volunteers also present. However, he undoubtedly wrote you a hasty reply before<lb/>
having a chance to think over the subject completely. At the moment I still think<lb/>
my suggestion is a little better because it permits more action in the picture, but<lb/>
I am a little concerned about the idea of having the scene laid out on the lawn in<lb/>
front of the officer's quarters. I can well imagine Lazear walking over from Reed's<lb/>
laboratory across the grass to Carroll, who might have been on the porch, and there<lb/>
inoculating Carroll (although we know this was undoubtedly done in the laboratory)<lb/>
but I can't imagine them stepping down from the veranda of the officers' porch to do<lb/>
this experiment out on the lawn.</p>
<p>General Truby's letter, however, shows such keen interest in your venture<lb/>
and such a willingness to go along and accept certain artistic license that I believe<lb/>
in the long run he will be satisfied with whatever the group of us think best. I<lb/>
shall await with great interest your comments telling me of Mr. Cornwell's reactions.<lb/>
I shall also be interested to hear of General Kean's reaction to the project. I have<lb/>
not yet heard from him.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. Please return the Agramonte article as soon as possible.<lb/>
</seg>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
