<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906236">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, October 27, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906236</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-10-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Marruz, Garcia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-10-27">October 27, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906236</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, October 27, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg discusses the favorable reaction to the Cornwell yellow fever painting. He has sent a proof and copies to Agramonte's daughter.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-10-27">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, October 27, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906236"/>
<opener>
GEORGE A. KELLOGG<lb/>
<dateline>
257 CORNELISON AVENUE<lb/>
JERSEY CITY, N.J.<lb/>
<date value="1941-10-27">October 27, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sorry that we were not able to send you more copies of &ldquo;Del<lb/>
Diario de Marina&rdquo;. We did not have it translated. I only had<lb/>
the article searched to see if there was anything in it about<lb/>
the painting itself. Our translator said there was nothing be-<lb/>
yond that they spoke of the painting very highly and at one point<lb/>
called it &ldquo;magnificent&rdquo;, or something to that effect. In other<lb/>
words, the story was favorable.</p>
<p>I have been away from this office for a full week and have seen a<lb/>
copy of the reprint from HYGEIA. Aside from some typographical<lb/>
errors I like the appearance of the reprint very much indeed and<lb/>
hope you will find it useful. You may look for the insert of<lb/>
&ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo; in the November 1st issue of the JOUR-<lb/>
NAL OF THE AMERICAN MEDICAL ASSOCIATION. Our distributor from<lb/>
Cuba was here a couple of weeks ago and saw a proof and told me<lb/>
that he thought it would produce good feeling among physicians in<lb/>
Havana. Dr. Marruz has been made director of Public Health since<lb/>
I, was there and we know definitely that he approves the picture.<lb/>
In fact, I have a short note from him today. He has not seen the<lb/>
large print as yet--only the clipping from the New York Sunday<lb/>
Mirror but a large print is on the way to him.</p>
<p>We shipped the autographed engravers proof which you returned<lb/>
along with a dozen other framed prints to our distributor in<lb/>
Havana and they are going to delivery it to Miss Agramonte in<lb/>
person. I found that to ship one framed print alone was very<lb/>
expensive and involved a lot of customs difficulties.</p>
<p>Thank you very much for the Dorothy Lynde Dix letter. I did not<lb/>
want you to go out and purchase this for me but inasmuch as you have<lb/>
done so I can assure you that it is highly valued.</p>
<p>Our representatives inform us that the doctors here in the United<lb/>
States are delighted with the &ldquo;Yellow Fever&rdquo; painting. The publicity<lb/>
which the picture had received in newspapers and journals had ar-<lb/>
roused their interest previous to the time when our prints were pre-<lb/>
sented by our men and as far as we can tell now this painting is the<lb/>
most popular produced to date. I was in Boston this past Friday and<lb/>
our man up there told us he was almost mobbed by doctors in the <unclear>Leahy</unclear><lb/>
Clinic when he brought up one for one doctor, and that he had had a<lb/>
similar experience in a large medical building. I think I told you<lb/>
that we planned to give away 12,000 framed copies but I think the<lb/>
pressure on us from physicians who will want them will increase that<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05906237"/>
-2-<lb/>
number to around 15,000 or even 18,000. Wyeth has the bear by the<lb/>
tail in this picture venture and won't dare to let go. Fortunately<lb/>
business is good and the budget is a little more flexible than it<lb/>
has been in the past.</p>
<p>I hope that you will let me know when you are coming down this way<lb/>
again as I feel that we should have a self-congratulation party on<lb/>
this venture.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>George A. Kellogg</signed>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
The Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester<lb/>
Minnesota<lb/>
GAK:L<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
