<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906092">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, May 20, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906092</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-05-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Cumming, Hugh S.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Jordan, Harvey E.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William Houston</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, Elizabeth</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-05-20">May 20, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906092</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, May 20, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses his speech for the upcoming unveiling of the Cornwell portrait and suggests guests to be invited by Kellogg.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-05-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, May 20, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906092"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-05-20">May 20, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
257 Cornelison Avenue<lb/>
Jersey City, N. J.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I still think you are making a mistake in not having Ireland or some<lb/>
similarly prominent man give the main talk, but inasmuch as I am chosen, I will<lb/>
accept with pleasure and will do my best. I am anxious to know at your earliest<lb/>
convenience the general setup of the program, the approximate number of guests,<lb/>
etc., so that I can &ldquo;feel out&rdquo; my expected audience and arrange the type of talk<lb/>
that will be suitable.</p>
<p>How many other speakers will there be? Is Miss Reed responding with a<lb/>
few words? Is Kissinger to talk? Kissinger is a nice old fellow, but has very<lb/>
little schooling and from the standpoint of grammatical construction, etc. speaks<lb/>
poorly. I would suggest, therefore, that you notify him that he will merely be asked<lb/>
to respond briefly to an introduction, expressing his pleasure at being there and, as<lb/>
he usually does, telling how glad be is to have had a modest part in the experiments<lb/>
done by the physicians, etc. I warn you not to have him talk extensively because he<lb/>
never uses notes and is inclined to ramble. Is someone going to say anything about<lb/>
your researches to make the painting accurate? Do you wish me to touch on that briefly<lb/>
in passing? Did you have in mind that I would use a certain amount of the talk that<lb/>
I used at Washington and Jefferson, a copy of which I believe I sent you? Of course,<lb/>
it will have to be re-arranged and the emphasis will not be as much on Lazear, but on<lb/>
the whole group. Is anyone else going to tell the general story of the yellow fever<lb/>
investigation?</p>
<p>My present tentative plan for the talk (which is subject to change) is to<lb/>
start out with a few words expressing my appreciation, as one physician, for the<lb/>
stimulus that I as a medical man have gotten from your series of paintings. I<lb/>
thought that I would touch upon the zeal with which you have undertaken this job and<lb/>
mention the care and thought that you and Cornwell have put into making it accurate.<lb/>
I would then suggest that perhaps many of the audience did not know or might have<lb/>
forgotten the details of the story and for their sake I would briefly review it. I<lb/>
would then give a short running account of what happened, including my recent discov-<lb/>
eries of Lazear's deliberate rather than accidental infection, mentioning (only to<lb/>
pass over it almost immediately) our discovery of the present whereabouts and condition<lb/>
of Camp Lazear. Then I would evaluate this in terms of public health and present<lb/>
defense, all of this very briefly, and then end on an inspirational note. I must<lb/>
know at once, however, whether this overlaps any speaking assignments to any other<lb/>
invited guest. It would seem nice to have Miss Reed and Mr. Kissinger introduced<lb/>
after my talk, that the audience will have been freshly told of the significance<lb/>
of their contribution. Are Van Etten, Cummings or Ireland to be there for it?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906093"/>
<p>Mr. George A. Kellogg</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>May 20, 1941</p>
<p>You were kind enough to suggest that you would invite some of my friends.<lb/>
I am sorry that my wife won't be <unclear>alon</unclear>, but I have four friends in Akron, Ohio who<lb/>
might like to come--Dr. and Mrs. Theodore Bliss, 236 N. Highland Avenue, and Mr. and<lb/>
Mrs. L. M. <unclear>Seiberling</unclear>, 97 Mayfield Avenue. Dr. Bliss was formerly here at the Clinic<lb/>
for some years. Mrs. <unclear>Seiberling</unclear> was my wife's maid of honor at our wedding and Lu<lb/>
is the son of the <unclear>Seiberling</unclear> Tire folks. He is, of course, not a professional and<lb/>
perhaps doesn't rate admission to this affair.</p>
<p>Are you going to invite Dr. Robert P. Cooke, Lexington-Rockbridge Health<lb/>
Department, Lexington, Virginia? You remember he participated in the experiments as<lb/>
did Captain Thomas M. England, 1715 East Long Street, Columbia, Ohio. Mrs. James O.<lb/>
<unclear>Cawne</unclear>, 2540 Massachusetts Ave., Washington, D. C. is Lazear's cousin. Dr. H. E.<lb/>
Jordan, Dean of the Department of Medicine, University of Virginia, has been much<lb/>
interested in the yellow fever story. You will of course send an invitation to Mrs.<lb/>
Lazear. Another cousin is Mr. John Lazear, 922 South Negley Avenue, Pittsburgh, Pa.<lb/>
A son is Mr. William Huston Lazear, 1325 Fifteenth Street, Sacramento, California.<lb/>
A cousin of Lazear's is Mrs. Charles P. Orr, 6101 Howe Street, Pittsburgh, Pa.<lb/>
Some of these relatives might well run up from Pittsburgh. Dr. James E. Peabody,<lb/>
281 Lowell Avenue, Newtonville, Massachusetts, and his daughter, Miss Elizabeth<lb/>
Peabody, Department of Biology, Wilson College, Chambersburg, Pa. have been long<lb/>
interested in this story and did much to get the pension and Congressional Medal for<lb/>
the participants. I think you have Mrs. Walter Reed's address and the address of<lb/>
Reed's son. Dr. Wilbur A. Sawyer, Director of The Rockefeller Foundation, New York<lb/>
City, is of course the greatest authority on yellow fever today, and he is quite<lb/>
familiar with the yellow fever story. He was my co-speaker at the Washington and<lb/>
Jefferson affair. Miss Frances B. Seth, 4511 Windsor Mill Road, Woodlawn, Baltimore,<lb/>
Maryland, is another cousin of Lazear. Don't consider any of these guests mine. If<lb/>
you invite them they should be your guests.</p>
<p>Three or four of my other friends, if you need them, would be Dr. John<lb/>
Garvin, Jenkins Arcade, Pittsburgh, and Dr. and Mrs. Frank Edmundson, 5317 Fifth<lb/>
Avenue, Pittsburgh. Dr. J. D. Heard, my former Professor of Medicine, 121 University<lb/>
Place, Pittsburgh, is much interested in medical history, and Dr. W. W. G. Maclachlan,<lb/>
527 Medical Arts Building, Pittsburgh, was also a former teacher of mine.</p>
<p>Please do not consider it necessary to invite these friends of mine, but<lb/>
some of them might come up from Pittsburgh since they may be attending the A.M.A.<lb/>
anyhow. I shall be grateful if you will rush the requested information at your<lb/>
earliest convenience.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
