<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906073">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to George A. Kellogg, March 27, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906073</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-03-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Schuler, Hans</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-03-27">March 27, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906073</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to George A. Kellogg, March 27, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean criticizes the sketches for the Cornwell painting and discusses the anti-Reed sentiment in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-03-27">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to George A. Kellogg, March 27, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906073"/>
<opener>
Dr. Hench<lb/>
C<lb/>
O<lb/>
P<lb/>
Y<lb/>
<dateline>
2804 N. Street N.W.<lb/>
Georgetown<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have had your letter of March 4th stuck up on my<lb/>
desk conspicuously ever since it came and have received two letters<lb/>
from Dr. Hench and a carbon copy of Gen. Truby's letter about the<lb/>
grouping of the actors in the Yellow Fever painting, but I have<lb/>
hesitated to write to you because I cannot get up any enthusiasm<lb/>
for such an artificial grouping as Dr. Hench proposes -- the<lb/>
biting of Carroll by Lazear's mosquito was done in secret. There<lb/>
were, I suspect no witnesses, although Sergeant Neate may have been<lb/>
there. Reed was in the United States, and certainly Dr. Finlay was<lb/>
not there.</p>
<p>Now, this sketch has just come from you, and it<lb/>
looks as if they were all collected and posed for a photograph --<lb/>
posing for photographs was a thing that Reed had such an aversion<lb/>
to, that after his death the only picture that he had ever sat for<lb/>
is that terrible one as a young man in the full dress uniform<lb/>
which has been so much reproduced and has done his fine, noble<lb/>
face so much injustice - Schuler's bust is a good likeness and it<lb/>
should have been used for the 5&cent; stamp and other representations of<lb/>
him -- I hope that Mr. Cornwell will use it -- I really think that<lb/>
Mr. Cornwell's first conception of Finlay giving Reed the mosquito<lb/>
eggs in a dish in a Cuban patio is much more artistic and much<lb/>
nearer to the historic varities. In my mind's eye comes up<lb/>
always as the truly dramatic moment in a wonderful setting, the<lb/>
interview between Major Reed and General Wood in the Palace in<lb/>
Havana -- I described it 13 yrs. ago in an address at Reed's birth-<lb/>
place, and it will save me from writing a long description of I<lb/>
send you the address where you will find it - on page 300-301 -<lb/>
of the excerpt.</p>
<p>But, of course, the artist could not bring in<lb/>
Dr. Finlay or Reed's assistants, so this is not a suggestion for<lb/>
Mr. Cornwell, unless he should want sometime a picture with just<lb/>
those <hi>two</hi> in it. The importance of the occasion was that without<lb/>
General Wood's approval, Reed could not have had any Camp Lazear,<lb/>
nor could have continued these secret experiments or those with<lb/>
infected bedding - for to prove the harmlessness of other sources<lb/>
of infection, was of vast importance.</p>
<p>It was the demonstration that stopped all fumigations<lb/>
and disinfections of inanimate objects - bedding, clothing, baggage, etc.<lb/>
and taught us that contact with the yellow fever patient himself<lb/>
was of no more danger than with a man with a broken leg.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906074"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Now, my dear Mr. Kellogg, I do not wish to oppose any plans<lb/>
of my friends or to make converts, but just to tell you how I feell<lb/>
about it, I have been for many years a proponent of Reed's fame<lb/>
and I do not fear that it can now be harmed by giving to Dr. Finlay<lb/>
the credit which is his due. Finlay made the discovery and<lb/>
identified the variety of mosquito as far back as 1881 and<lb/>
published it far and wide in the United States, as well as Cuba.<lb/>
But, he could not convince anyone (except his assistant Dr. Delgado)<lb/>
in 19 yrs. Then came Reed and in the words of Dr. Goldberger<lb/>
of the Public Health Service, <hi>Reed converted a discredited theory<lb/>
into an established doctrine.</hi></p>
<p>The trouble with the Cubans is that they have been made<lb/>
indignant by the failure of Americans to give proper credit to<lb/>
Finlay as the discoverer and they go to the other extreme of claiming<lb/>
everything for Finlay. I think that it is a squabble unworthy of<lb/>
scientific men.</p>
<p>Dr. Hench is now in Cuba and I hope will win from the<lb/>
Cuban authorities, the support and cooperation that is due his<lb/>
energy and devotion to the investigation he has undertaken.<lb/>
That so busy a <unclear>man</unclear> could have diverted so much time and labor<lb/>
from his professional work, is extraordinary. I wish to help<lb/>
him in every way in his study of the Cuban episode of 1900 - 1901<lb/>
and to have not injected myself into the discussion of the<lb/>
picture. But, I have no objection to having my feeling in the<lb/>
matter known.</p>
<p>Please return my address when you have read it -- as it is<lb/>
my only copy.</p>
<p>We were <unclear>as</unclear> pleased to get Robin's picture and your note.<lb/>
She is a dear little girl and we were much struck by her pise and<lb/>
ease of manner and her maturity of mind. She has real personality.</p>
<p>I hope you will excuse my long delay in writing. I have<lb/>
no clerical help, as you see, and have had much to do, what with<lb/>
income tax returns and other matters.</p>
<p>Mrs. Kean sends her regards to you and to Robin, and I<lb/>
am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>(SIGNED) J. R. KEAN</signed>
er<lb/>
3/27/41<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
