<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05909084">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to John R. Kissinger, May 7, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05909084</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-05-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kissinger, John R.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-05-07">May 7, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05909084</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to John R. Kissinger, May 7, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran notifies Kissinger that they are going to receive the Finlay Medal from the Cuban Government in Washington, D.C. He provides further detailed information concerning the upcoming event and hopes that Kissinger will be able to attend. This letter was forwarded to Hench.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-05-07">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to John R. Kissinger, May 7, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05909084"/>
<opener>
<hi>COPY FOR OUR GOOD FRIEND, Dr. PHILIP S. HENCH</hi>.<lb/>
Please deposit, for collection, the check I sent<lb/>
to you for the Cuban money you left with me.<lb/>
J. J. M.<lb/>
<hi>VIA AIR MAIL</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-05-07">May 7, 1940.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. John R. Kissinger,<lb/>
R. F. D. No. 8,<lb/>
HUNTINGTON, Indiana.<lb/>
<salute>Dear John:</salute>
</opener>
<p>A lot of water has gone over the dam since you and I said<lb/>
&ldquo;Good Bye&rdquo; in &ldquo;Little Old New York&rdquo;, 'way back in February, 1901, you<lb/>
to enter on furlough and I to take a position with Frank Luerssen in<lb/>
his drug store, in Salem, N. J., until September of that year when I<lb/>
was to enter the University of Virginia, to study medicine.</p>
<p>Well, John, the principal object of this letter is to notify<lb/>
you, in the name of Dr. Moya, Secretary of Sanitation of the Cuban<lb/>
Republic, that you have been elected, in company with your &ldquo;human-<lb/>
guinea-pig&rdquo; companion, to receive the &ldquo;FINLAY MEDAL&rdquo; or &ldquo;ORDEN DE<lb/>
FINLAY&rdquo;. The presentation will be made in Washington on May 15th.<lb/>
You will be in distinguished company, so Dr. Moya informs me, for<lb/>
among those to be honored with the &ldquo;FINLAY ORDER&rdquo; will be Dr. Parran,<lb/>
Surgeon General of the U. S. Public Health Service, the Cuban Ambassa-<lb/>
dor to Washington, and others, including Miss Clara Maass, posthumous-<lb/>
ly, the nurse who died from experimental yellow fever, at Las Animas<lb/>
Hospital, on August 24, 1901. For your personal information, BUT<lb/>
NOT FOR PUBLICATION, I am authorized to inform you that we are to<lb/>
have conferred upon us the MAXIMUM classification or grade of the<lb/>
&ldquo;FINLAY ORDER&rdquo;, that is to say &ldquo;THE GRAND CROSS&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I suggested to the Cuban authorities that, so far as I knew,<lb/>
you had no other income than your annuity of $1,500.00 per year and<lb/>
that, while I had no doubt you would make every possible sacrifice to<lb/>
come to Washington, it might be in order to contribute to, if not<lb/>
entirely cover, your travel expenses to Washington and return to your<lb/>
home. I am, therefore, enclosing my personal check on The First National<lb/>
Bank of Boston, in amount of $50.00, in behalf of Dr. Domingo Ramos, Cuban<lb/>
Secretary of National Defense, who will reimburse me for a similar amount.<lb/>
I am doing so in order to get this letter and the check off to you so<lb/>
that it may reach you in time, by air mail, so you will be able to get<lb/>
away in time and reach Washington, NOT LATER THAN TUESDAY NIGHT, MAY 14TH.<lb/>
If you so desire, you can return to your home, after the ceremony of<lb/>
presentation is over. I hope, however, that we can have an hour or two<lb/>
to ourselves to talk over the old days at Columbia Barracks Post Hospital.<lb/>
Upon your arrival in Washington, please get in phone communication with<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05909085"/>
<hi>Mr. John R. Kissinger</hi>.<lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>May 7, 1940.</hi><lb/>
General Jefferson R. Kean (you will find his name and telephone number in<lb/>
the Telephone Directory) and he will inform you as to my hotel and room<lb/>
address, since I do not know as yet the name of the hotel at which I will<lb/>
stop. Give me a telephone call at any hour, after your arrival in the<lb/>
Capitol City, and if I should not be in the hotel at the time you call,<lb/>
leave a message for me so I may get in touch with you without delay. In<lb/>
case of any mishap which might prevent me from getting in touch with you,<lb/>
call up the Cuban Embassy. They will know at the Embassy who you are<lb/>
and will be able to give you all necessary information as to time and<lb/>
place of presentation of the medals.</p>
<p>Would suggest that you keep away from newspaper reporters until<lb/>
after the ceremony of presentation of the medals is over. THIS IS MERELY<lb/>
A SUGGESTION, HOWEVER. The Cubans will see to it that you get all the<lb/>
publicity you wish, perhaps more than you will want, but please do not get<lb/>
the idea that I want to muzzle you.</p>
<p>If you do not want to make use of the $50.00, please return the<lb/>
check to me and I will, in turn, refund the amount to Dr. Ramos. That is<lb/>
a matter for you alone to decide. I am paying my own expenses to<lb/>
Washington and return, not because I am so financially well heeled as the<lb/>
Cubans or you may think, but as a matter of principle. I do not mind<lb/>
telling you, however, that if an offer to pay my expenses had beenn spont-<lb/>
aneously made, I would have accepted the offer. This is for your con-<lb/>
fidential information.</p>
<p>In conclusion, and also STRICTLY CONFIDENTIAL, this latest honor<lb/>
to be conferred on us is indirectly due to the recent visit to Cuba of<lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench, whom you well know. I hope you will write a letter<lb/>
of thanks to Dr. Hench and tell him that you see &ldquo;his fine Italian hand&rdquo;<lb/>
in all this. I am writing Dr. Hench about the matter so he will know<lb/>
all about it.</p>
<p>Until the 15th of May, then, and trusting that this long letter<lb/>
will not tire you out, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>.
My address:<lb/>
John J. Moran,<lb/>
c/o Cia. Sunoco de Cuba, S. A.,<lb/>
Avenida Menocal Nos. 455-457,<lb/>
HAVANA, Cuba.<lb/>
oooOooo<lb/>
Dear Dr. Hench<unclear><del>:</del></unclear><lb/>
I just learned, through the Rojas family, that your boy had to<lb/>
undergo an operation for appendicitis. That will account, in part ONLY for<lb/>
your silence since you left Havana. Elida joins me in affectionate regards<lb/>
to Mrs. Hench and your good self. Will get the maps off to you within the<lb/>
next few days. Sorry to inform you that I will have to fold them, since they<lb/>
are too long for a mailing tube.<lb/>
Sincerely,<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
