<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906044">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, March 4, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906044</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-03-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-03-04">March 4, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906044</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, March 4, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg discusses the Cornwell painting in progress, proposed changes to the painting, and the possibility of producing a second painting to appease critics in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-03-04">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, March 4, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906044"/>
<opener>
<unclear>answered long hand<lb/>
comment paint on bldg<lb/>
Table &amp; chairs on lawn<lb/>
K &amp; Moran Standing<lb/>
sent come ts</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
257 CORNELISON AVENUE<lb/>
JERSEY CITY, N.J.<lb/>
<date value="1941-03-04">March 4th, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Phillip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minn.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have gone over both your letters and the one from<lb/>
General Truby, with Mr. Cornwell.</p>
<p>I agree with you that I think there is a certain<lb/>
amount of inconsistency in General Truby's suggestions. I question if<lb/>
we will get General Wood in the painting. I am afraid that our<lb/>
artist's patience will not last long enough to include another principal<lb/>
figure in which a good portrait will be necessary. He is quite agree-<lb/>
able to placing Moran and Kissinger in the background.</p>
<p>As you say, I think General Truby's suggestion for<lb/>
the placing and arrangement of the picture would be rather static.<lb/>
Mr. Cornwell has made a sketch in which he shows figures standing at<lb/>
various levels on the steps of the Officer's quarters. Carroll and<lb/>
Lazear are seated at a table on the ground at the edge of the steps.<lb/>
It is quite true that this probably did not happen, but as we have<lb/>
said before, neither was Major Reed there when it happened. It gives<lb/>
the artist a chance to place heads at several levels; an arrangement<lb/>
he is desirous of having.</p>
<p>At the risk of sounding pedantic, I'm going to<lb/>
write a little on the art side of our problem:</p>
<p>First, we must have a fine painting. If we wished<lb/>
to get what was merely a photographic reproduction of a particular<lb/>
incident that took place in 1900 with all details accurately portrayed,<lb/>
we would have to get a cheaper artist, and then we would have a mere<lb/>
pictoral record of historical data. However, such pictures have<lb/>
little or no value in the fine arts world. One of the reasons we are<lb/>
using Cornwell is that the pictures must have a permanent fine arts<lb/>
value.</p>
<p>Mr. Cornwell must look upon the material in this<lb/>
story as a symphony composer looks upon melodic and rhythmic ideas.<lb/>
The composer takes from his available material what he finds useful<lb/>
in creating a piece of music. The painter has to take from our<lb/>
story what he can use to create a symphony in color and design.<lb/>
Thus, in order to get a fine painting we cannot tie his hands too<lb/>
closely.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906045"/>
<p>Dr. Phillip S. Hench</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>3/4/41</p>
<p>To go back to the subject of placing the figures<lb/>
on the porch: He tells me that to paint likenesses from the avail-<lb/>
able photographs that he has, to place the figures on the porch, would<lb/>
be an artistic lie which he would be ashamed to exhibit. These heads<lb/>
are all photographed with a light that comes down almost vertically -<lb/>
as the light did come down in the old fashioned photographic studios.<lb/>
The light which would strike the faces on the porch would be light<lb/>
reflected from the ground and would entirely change the contour of the<lb/>
faces. This he could do only if he had the actual people posing for<lb/>
him under light from this latter source.</p>
<p>I think that you agree with us that what we want<lb/>
from this painting is a representation of the spirit of the truth.<lb/>
If we had had a photographer in 1900 going about taking photographs<lb/>
of everything taking place, they would all be correct representations<lb/>
of what was happening at any one time, but I question if any of them<lb/>
would give posterity a comprehensive picture of what the study of<lb/>
yellow fever meant -- Our painting must be a synthesis.</p>
<p>As to satisfying the Cubans -- it is quite possible<lb/>
that we will complete a second painting using the version which you<lb/>
saw in Rochester; but it cannot be done until next year. I say, it<lb/>
is possible, because Mr. Cornwell's fee for doing the job is not in<lb/>
our budget this year, and next year is always anybody's guess. I am<lb/>
afraid we will have to worry about the Cubans later. Frankly, our<lb/>
total business down there today wouldn't pay for the cost of a canvas<lb/>
by Cornwell in five years.</p>
<p>We are having the two sketches which you saw,<lb/>
tastefully framed so that should you wish to take them to Havana, you<lb/>
will be welcome to do so. I am hoping that you will be coming through<lb/>
New York and spending an hour or two with Mr. Cornwell in his studio.<lb/>
Will this be possible?</p>
<p>As to General Truby's letter: it contains<lb/>
much information which is of great value to Mr. Cornwell, and I am<lb/>
going to write him a letter of appreciation tomorrow.</p>
<p>I am inclosing a copy of a feature story which<lb/>
has run in a number of newspapers around the country. I am afraid<lb/>
the reporter did not quote Mr. Cornwell very accurately. In the first<lb/>
place, Cornwell cannot drink more than three Daiquiris under any cir-<lb/>
cumstances -- and to read the story you would think he was tight all<lb/>
the time he was in Havana! This publicity story is good only<lb/>
in that along with disseminating a considerable amount of misinformation,<lb/>
it does serve to interest the public to a degree in the painting of<lb/>
the yellow fever investigation!!</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>George Kellogg</signed>
G.A. Kellogg/fr<lb/>
Att.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
