<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05903035">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lucy T. Howard, January 17, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05903035</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-01-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Howard, Lucy T.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Siler, Joseph F.</name>
<name type="person">Love, Albert G.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-01-17">January 17, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05903035</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lucy T. Howard, January 17, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Howard that he has a large file of letters between her father and Reed and Carroll but is still searching for more, especially between Howard and Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-01-17">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lucy T. Howard, January 17, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05903035"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-01-17">January 17, 1947</date>
</dateline>
Miss Lucy Howard<lb/>
45 Pondfield Road, West<lb/>
Bronxville, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Howard:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wish often that I didn't have to spend time on my routine medical<lb/>
work; it interferes so much with my hobby! I do apologize for my long delay in<lb/>
returning to you the most interesting and useful data from and about your father.<lb/>
I have at last had them all copied and herewith return the originals. Should<lb/>
the latter ever be mislaid I will have a set on hand which would be available<lb/>
for you.</p>
<p>On November 21, 1946, having been elected a new member of the Board,<lb/>
I went to the Washington meeting of the Board of Managers of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association of which your father has so long been an active member.<lb/>
The following were present, mostly old friends of your father: General Ireland,<lb/>
General Kean, Colonel Siler, General Love, Admiral Stitt, Mr. Gilbert Grosvenor<lb/>
(national geographic) and Mr. Hans Ireland. They wished to be remembered to<lb/>
your father most cordially and regretted his absence. I took a few snapshots.<lb/>
Let me send you a set.</p>
<p>I now have quite a file of letters between your father and Doctor<lb/>
Reed or Doctor Carroll: I have about 40 such letters. There are still a few<lb/>
missing, letters referred to in ones I have but still missing. They include<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) a letter from Major Reed to Doctor Howard, dated November 11, 1900,<lb/>
mentioned in one from Doctor Howard (Nov. 16, 1900) to Reed.</item>
<item>(2) a letter from Reed to Doctor Howard (Mar. 5, 1902), mentioned in your<lb/>
father's letter of Mar. 7, 1902 to Reed.</item>
<item>(3) a letter from Carroll to Doctor Howard (Nov. 1, 1905), mentioned in<lb/>
your father's letter of Nov. 13, 1905 to Carroll.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Mr. Herman Kahn, acting chief, Division of Agriculture Department of<lb/>
the National Archives, has made a search for these missing letters and could<lb/>
not find them; nor could he find any letters between Doctor Lazear and your<lb/>
father.</p>
<p>So, if you are in an adventurous mood, Miss Howard, and see any more<lb/>
letters sticking out of book-edges or used as book marks, I do hope your womanly<lb/>
curiosity will wonder whether they include the missing items! I do hope they<lb/>
turn up sometime and I have no doubt they will because your father admired<lb/>
Reed so much I am sure he has saved them somewhere. Meanwhile I am very grateful<lb/>
for your most courteous help.</p>
<p>You recall I discussed with your father what I believed to be a little<lb/>
misstatement on page 48, of his 1930 book, &ldquo;<hi>A History of Applied Entomology</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
where he wrote: &ldquo;They (Reed, Carroll, and Lazear) came to the entomological<lb/>
offices in the Department of Agriculture to study mosquitoes before they went<lb/>
to Cuba----&rdquo;. I'm sure that is correct as far as Reed and Carroll are concerned<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05903036"/>
-2-<lb/>
but I'm equally sure Lazear did <hi>not</hi> come with Reed. Lazear suddenly decided<lb/>
in January, 1900 to enter the army, was promptly accepted and went to Cuba<lb/>
February 2, 1900, not having met Reed or Carroll. He first met Reed in Cuba<lb/>
in March, 1900 and Lazear never returned from Cuba. To be doubly certain of<lb/>
my facts I showed this excerpt of your father's book to Generals Kean and Truby<lb/>
and both agree with my conclusion. But this is just a little error, important<lb/>
only to a perfectionist like myself who is trying to piece together every bit<lb/>
of the story.</p>
<p>It is quite possible that Lazear did come alone or with Doctor Thayer<lb/>
from Hopkins to visit your father in 1899, or early in 1900, when he was inter-<lb/>
ested in mosquitoes at Johns Hopkins. This version appears on page 4 of his<lb/>
&ldquo;memorandum&rdquo; (yellow paper) and is more correct than the statement in the 1930<lb/>
book. After all the 1930 book was written 30 years after the events and it is<lb/>
no wonder your father's timing of the various visits had become a little hazy<lb/>
and mixed.</p>
<p>As to your father's comments on pages 469-470 to the effect that<lb/>
Sternberg's instructions to Reed were of the most general nature and not<lb/>
detailed, I have uncovered ample corroborating evidence and Generals Kean and<lb/>
Truby likewise agree that your father was absolutely correct, the contrary<lb/>
writings of General, and later Mrs. Sternberg notwithstanding.</p>
<p>In your recent letter you said you might be moving to Washington.<lb/>
I do hope so; you have many friends there who ask of you. Have you any idea<lb/>
when you may move?</p>
<p>Miss Howard, when I last visited you I said I would <hi>very much</hi> like to<lb/>
have a photograph of your father as of about 1900 or thereabouts. I want to<lb/>
publish it in my book. In your father's book he modestly reproduces the<lb/>
photographs of scores of scientific colleagues, many less eminent than he,<lb/>
but none of himself. You said you thought you could lay your hands on one and<lb/>
would lend it to me. I do <hi>not</hi> need to keep it. I can have it copied (photo-<lb/>
graphed) in the Photographic Department of the Mayo Clinic and return to you<lb/>
the original safe and sound (registered mail). Indeed I would be glad to send<lb/>
back extra copies as &ldquo;interest&rdquo; on the loan.</p>
<p>I would also like very much to consider reproducing in my book Reed's<lb/>
letter about &ldquo;Howard and Kerosene.&rdquo; You were so kind to send me a photostat.<lb/>
I'm delighted to have it but I fear it would not reproduce to the satisfaction<lb/>
of publishers. I photostated some important letters of Reed and of Lazear<lb/>
and finally had to photograph them. Sometime if you could have a local photographer<lb/>
copy that letter and let me buy not only a print but the film I'd appreciate<lb/>
it very much. Or if your father's trust in registered mail reaches the point<lb/>
that he'd be willing to lend it to me I could have it photographed here (an<lb/>
extra film for you if you wish).</p>
<p>I was especially interested in your father's &ldquo;memorandum&rdquo; (undated,<lb/>
typed on yellow paper) modestly disclaiming certain credit given him. Does<lb/>
your father, or do you, have any recollection of when it was written. I <hi>would</hi><lb/>
like to know.</p>
<p>Your father, when I visited him in May, stated he had a collection<lb/>
of snapshots, et cetera, at Onteora. If in your house-cleaning or treasure-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05903037"/>
-3-<lb/>
hunting activities you come across them and find any of your father and<lb/>
Doctors Reed, Lazear, or Carroll it would be most interesting to see them.</p>
<p>One more thing: in your father's letter of October 31, 1906 to<lb/>
Doctor Kelly he speaks of a talk about Reed's work he gave at a dinner at<lb/>
Graham Bell's which may have initiated the Reed Memorial. I have a letter<lb/>
your father wrote Doctor Kelly on January 19, 1924 in which he again mentioned<lb/>
&ldquo;the speech I made at the Graham Bell dinner.&rdquo; Does your father now recall<lb/>
whether this was an extemporaneous speech or one written down and whether a<lb/>
copy was ever published or might be found in his personal files?</p>
<p>I fear I have asked you again to do several more favors for me. I<lb/>
can only say again how much I am indebted to you and restate my earnest desire<lb/>
to set forth clearly your father's important advisory role in the Conquest of<lb/>
Yellow Fever.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alp<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
