<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 20, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-02-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Amador, R. A.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Cumming, Hugh S.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">California</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-02-20">February 20, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906016</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 20, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench sends Kellogg photographs to be used by Cornwell for changes to the yellow fever painting. He discusses Clara Maass, the Cubans' representation of Finlay's work, and a need for two versions of the painting to please both Americans and Cubans.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-02-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, February 20, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906016"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-02-20">February 20, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
257 Cornelison Ave.<lb/>
Jersey City, N. J.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Please pardon me for not writing you Monday. You recall I had to give a<lb/>
talk at the University of Minnesota Friday. I found that it was to be published so I<lb/>
had to spend the past two or three days writing it up. Hence my delay. Let me tell<lb/>
you how interested I was in the visit of yourself and Mr. Withington. I must confess<lb/>
I was a bit concerned when you wrote you were coming out. I was fearful lest your trip<lb/>
here might be a waste of time and money, and your reassurances that you found my informa-<lb/>
tion helpful make me hope that it was worth your while coming.</p>
<p>Now for the data you asked for. I am enclosing some photos that may help<lb/>
Cornwell. I want him to keep them as long as necessary but I would <hi>appreciate their</hi><lb/>
return when he is through with them. I am sending:</p>
<p>Most important: a group photo of the hospital corps at Camp Columbia,<lb/>
Havana Cuba. This photo was taken Sept. 1900, the month that Lazear died. It shows<lb/>
Lieut. Truby (now General Truby) who was <hi>acting commanding officer</hi> of the hospital. As<lb/>
you can well imagine he will be of invaluable help in settling disputed points as <hi>he was<lb/>
there and saw what went on</hi> and has a keen memory fortified by a diary. This photo was<lb/>
taken on the shops of one of the hospital wards. If you will consult the two photos I<lb/>
gave you (one of the officers' quarters and one of the &ldquo;wards and operating room,&rdquo; Post<lb/>
Hospital, Columbia Barracks) you will recognize this building and stairs at once. Re-<lb/>
member this photo is <hi>NOT</hi> the porch of the officers' quarters but the porch of one of the<lb/>
wards. But I have no doubt the general architecture was about the same as the two photos<lb/>
I gave you will show, and this photo gives a close up view not only of the type of<lb/>
boarding, etc., but more important, of the uniforms worn by the men.</p>
<p>Lieutenant (no<del>t</del><add>w</add> General) Truby was an officer in the <hi>regular medical corps.</hi><lb/>
You will therefore note the difference between his uniform (he is #1 in the photo) and<lb/>
that of Drs. Pinto (#2), Amador (#3) and Cooke (#4) who were all merely &ldquo;Contract Surgeons&rdquo;,<lb/>
i.e. lay physicians hired from civil practice to act as army physicians in a temporary<lb/>
capacity. Just why the uniforms of Drs. Pinto (white), Amador (khaki? with <hi>khaki</hi>?<lb/>
shoulder straps) and Cooke (khaki with <hi>dark</hi> shoulder straps) should have differed I do<lb/>
not know. Doubtless you can get the answer from Gen. Truby or Gen. Kean or find copies<lb/>
of these uniforms in the War Dept. (Possibly from the Chief of the Signal Corps in<lb/>
Washington as apparently the Signal Corps included the army photographers).</p>
<p>Note the varying uniforms of the noncommissioned officers in the second row.<lb/>
But especially note figure #10 - Private Kissinger. You wanted a photo of him in 1900.<lb/>
Here it is. John J. Moran, the other original volunteer is not in the photo because his<lb/>
term of enlistment had expired and he was acting as a civilian clerk in Gen. Lee's head-<lb/>
quarters. (Moran had been a noncommissioned officer, (acting hospital steward with rank of<lb/>
sergeant) but was no longer in service when he volunteered to Major Reed. Hence, being<lb/>
a civilian now, he was not in this photo. Remember that if Mr. Cornwell decides to<lb/>
use him and Kissinger I suspect it would be justifiable artistic licence to put Moran back<lb/>
in uniform if you wanted to; but to be historically accurate Moran was then in civilian<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05906017"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
February 20, 1941<lb/>
clothes. There is another rather similar photo of Kissinger taken also in 1900 which<lb/>
appears in a booklet &ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo; by James E. Peabody. Kissinger's<lb/>
photo appears on page 9 and shows his uniform <hi>but</hi> he is here an acting hospital<lb/>
steward (sergeant) not a private. (It is the same photo as in the Dodge Auto News<lb/>
article which I enclose.) When he volunteered he was a private; as a result of his<lb/>
bravery he was promoted to be a sergeant and this photo therefore was taken later than<lb/>
the scene Mr. Cornwell will be painting. This same booklet contains another photo of<lb/>
Dr. Carroll, a later one of Agramonte and the conventional ones of Reed, Lazear and<lb/>
Finlay. Moran tells me he has no photos of himself taken in or near 1900 but I am<lb/>
sending you 3 recent ones and you can compare them to one of him taken in the World<lb/>
War when he was a captain. I think with a little imagination you can figure out<lb/>
what he looked like in 1900 and I'm sure he'd be glad to criticize a pencil sketch<lb/>
of himself which Mr. Cornwell might airmail to him. He is a fine man and most help-<lb/>
ful. I suggest that if you decide to have either one in the painting (more or less<lb/>
as incidental background figures) for heaven's sake have <hi>both</hi> in. I also suggest you<lb/>
write each one your plan and they may be able to help you with other photos (though<lb/>
I doubt it), also with data on the uniforms, etc. But remember, Kissinger's memory<lb/>
isn't too good and he's not well educated; Moran is better. I really think it would<lb/>
be nice to have them in the painting, representing as it were, all the privates who<lb/>
offered their bodies for the experiments. And since a half dozen others of them are<lb/>
still living (though all but Moran and Kissinger volunteered at least in part for the<lb/>
money) in your descriptive folder re the painting you might say that &ldquo;Kissinger and<lb/>
Moran were inserted to represent <hi>all</hi> of the brave soldiers who volunteered,&rdquo; etc.</p>
<p>This booklet by Peabody was published by the Dept. of Public Education.<lb/>
American Museum of Natural History, New York City. I wrote them for a copy. They<lb/>
only had their own but I finally got a copy from Dr. Peabody (present address, Dr.<lb/>
James E. Peabody, 281 Lowell Ave., Newtonville, Mass.) He may have one for you if<lb/>
you sent for it. If not, borrow one from the museum. But remember that there are<lb/>
a number of minor errors in Dr. Peabody's version (as there seems to be in everybody's!)<lb/>
For example, Peabody's versions of Lazear's illness, and of Kissinger on page 10,<lb/>
are very dubious:</p>
<p>I also enclose a small copy of a photo of Dr. Agramonte taken around<lb/>
1900-1901 (?). It is autographed by him in 1902. Note his uniform. It seems to be<lb/>
identical with that of Dr. Pinto (#2) with a cross on the collar and some sort of<lb/>
insignia on the shoulder straps. Whether they were the insignia of any rank I do<lb/>
not know. Gen. Truby will know, also Gen. Kean. This photo of Agramonte is the<lb/>
one in Kelly's book, 1906 edition, page. 272.</p>
<p>In summary then I am lending you the following photos (1) hospital corps,<lb/>
(2) names of corps, (3) Moran - formal photo taken in recent years, (4) snapshot of<lb/>
Moran in 1940, (5) Moran and Kissinger with Dr. Hutchison in 1940, (6) formal photo<lb/>
of Kissinger taken in recent years, (7) 3 snapshots of Kissinger taken by me in 1938,<lb/>
(8) small photo of Agramonte in uniform. <hi>Please return them at your leisure</hi>.</p>
<p>9)<unclear>Dodge auto news re Kissinger</unclear><lb/>
10) <unclear>Sat Eve Post re Moran</unclear></p>
<p>I am writing today to (1) Mrs. Lazear, (2) Gen. Truby, (3) Gen. Kean,<lb/>
(4) Dr. Cummings. I think it likely that Mrs. Lazear might even have one of Dr.<lb/>
Lazear's actual uniforms. At least I will ask her and if so she might be sufficiently<lb/>
anxious to have him accurately portrayed as to be willing to have the uniform photo-<lb/>
graphed in Santa Barbara and a copy sent you. I'm sure she'd never lend it to you.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05906018"/>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
February 20, 1941<lb/>
But perhaps a California representative of yours might do her the honor of actually<lb/>
calling on her and presenting your request discretely. The same might be said of<lb/>
Major Reed. His son, General Walter <del>Russell</del><add>Lawrence</add> Reed, lives in Washington, D. C. Perhaps<lb/>
he or his mother (still living) has his uniform. I can ask Miss Agramonte about her<lb/>
father's uniform when I see her next month.</p>
<p>As to Miss Clara Maass (so spelled by Dr. Albertini) she was a native of<lb/>
Orange, New Jersey, aged 25, a nurse employed at Las Animas Hospital. Remember that<lb/>
she had no part in the experiments of Reed et al (i.e. the army commission) but<lb/>
volunteered for the later experiments of Guiteras et al who in Aug. <hi>1901</hi> (not 1900)<lb/>
were trying to verify the commission's work. I have no doubt that by writing the<lb/>
reference librarian of the Public Library in Orange, you would get much data on her,<lb/>
also perhaps a photograph of her. I believe, but am not sure, that she had been an<lb/>
army nurse. Gens. Kean and Truby will know. On page 29 of Chapter 4, U. S. Senate<lb/>
Document 822 (61st Congress, vol. 61 - 3rd session) the official document regarding all<lb/>
the yellow fever experiments (it is in the New York Public Library) it says that Miss<lb/>
Clara <hi>Maass</hi> served as a trained nurse in the Medical Dept. of the Army during the<lb/>
Spanish War, later served as a trained nurse in Las Animas Hospital, volunteered and<lb/>
was bitten by infected mosquitos Aug. 14 and died Aug. 18, 1901. (This also is partly<lb/>
incorrect; she took sick Aug. 18 and died Aug. 24, 1901 - See American Medicine<lb/>
Nov. 23, 1901, page 809).</p>
<p>Albertini and the U. S. Senate Document spell her name Maass but in the<lb/>
New York Times for Sunday, Aug. 25, 1901 (page 1, I think - I have a photostatic copy)<lb/>
under the heading &ldquo;The Third Mosquito Victim&rdquo; is a description of her death. Her<lb/>
name is there spelled Maas (one s). It states that she was a daughter of Mrs. H. A.<lb/>
Maas of 344 Main St. <hi>East</hi> Orange was 25 years old and had been a nurse for 5 years.<lb/>
During the Spanish War she was in camp at Jacksonville and Savannah and later went<lb/>
to Cuba and the Phillipines, again to Cuba and her death. Her sister, Miss Sophie<lb/>
Maas, tried to get to her death-bed. Perhaps in East Orange they have a memorial to<lb/>
her and perhaps her sister still lives and has her uniform! Doubtless the librarian<lb/>
can give you the dope.</p>
<p>I have at hand a copy of a speech given by Albertini, Sept. 28, 1936 when<lb/>
the cardboard plaques were unveiled in Las Animas. In this speech Albertini says,<lb/>
&ldquo;I witnessed in Dr. Finlay's house, No. 110 Aguacate Street, the presentation of the<lb/>
Commission to the great Cuban sage who delivered to Dr. Reed a small soap-dish with<lb/>
eggs, etc.&rdquo; I hadn't noticed that sentence before. I must find out if he recalls the<lb/>
exact date in August when this occurred and how many of the commission actually<lb/>
visited Finlay. Did he tell you? Albertini was <hi>not</hi> helpful to me.</p>
<p>I am returning your films. Thank you very much for letting me have copies.<lb/>
However I wonder if you couldn't have your company photographer take a real good<lb/>
5 x 7 or 8 x 10 of each preliminary sketch. I'd very much like to send one not only<lb/>
to Mrs. Lazear but also to Gen. Truby, to Kissinger and Moran and Miss Agramonte. I<lb/>
think the small snapshots are <hi>hardly impressive</hi> enough to stimulate the interest of<lb/>
those you hope to get valuable data from! What do you think? After you left I kicked<lb/>
myself in the pants for not having run them up to our photo dept. We could have had<lb/>
them really photoed in 10 minutes. I suspect Mr. Cornwell may seriously object to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f05906019"/>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
February 20, 1941<lb/>
letting any photos of preliminary sketches out but if he knows to whom they are to<lb/>
go he may realize that it would be useful.</p>
<p>Also please send me a few of the small reproductions (black and white)<lb/>
of the Osler and Beaumont paintings. I think I can insert them in some of the above<lb/>
letters to show the folks how fine and artistic your project is. I fear me that some<lb/>
interested parties may not cooperate without a little persuasion, fearing the<lb/>
commercial aspect of the affair. I suggest you in due time send Truby, Kissinger,<lb/>
Moran, Kean and Mrs. Lazear, also Dr. Peabody, colored reproductions (unframed)<lb/>
so that they can see the quality of the work.</p>
<p>Now to answer your letters. I am returning a few of the snapshots you<lb/>
sent but could I keep the 4 of the old patio? I'd love to keep the copies of the<lb/>
Cuban articles re your visit. May I? I think they are <hi>marvelous</hi> and so amusing in<lb/>
the light of what we all know. But boy, oh boy, have you all gotten yourself<lb/>
(unwittingly) into a mess! Either you promised too much (too many pleasant Cuban<lb/>
drinks?) or they wangled you into seeming to promise more than you can ever (honestly)<lb/>
come across with! I am sure you will know that I believe that Finlay's claims have<lb/>
been too much ignored and I plan to emphasize his contribution. <hi>But</hi> in giving Finlay<lb/>
his just desserts we mustn't do to Walter Reed et al what Finlay believed they did to<lb/>
him:</p>
<p>Please don't let all the controversial data confuse you. This is the<lb/>
dope in very simple terms. Finley had a swell idea; it was correct in the <hi>main</hi><lb/>
points that a certain mosquito was the cause. But he couldn't even prove it to the<lb/>
very Cuban colleagues who ever since have been bowing down to him as a god. And why<lb/>
couldn't he prove it in 19 years of work? He inoculated 102 patients; he claimed to<lb/>
have produced 16 positive cases of experimental yellow fever. None of them were<lb/>
severe or <hi>classical.</hi> Assuming they were all 16 cases of yellow fever (which they<lb/>
probably weren't!) <hi>none of these patients were quarantined</hi>. All were living and<lb/>
moving about Havana and environs and all (if they had yellow fever) might just as well<lb/>
have gotten it <hi>naturally</hi> like everybody else was getting it (through some other mos-<lb/>
quitos than Dr. Finley's). That is why nobody, not even the <hi>Cubans</hi> (who later<lb/>
swallowed Finlay hook, line and sinker!) accepted his data. For the <hi>same reason</hi><lb/>
Reed wasn't at all satisfied with Lazear's first 3 cases; Carroll and Lazear got<lb/>
the disease but <hi>neither</hi> was quarantined; only Dean was quarantined and it was that<lb/>
one case - Dean's - and not really Carroll's or Lazear's that convinced Reed that<lb/>
Lazear had been on the right track. The Preliminary Note by Reed et al, without the<lb/>
follow up work done at Camp Lazear, would have been laughed at just as much as<lb/>
Finley was laughed at for 19 years. That's the dope in a nut shell and don't let<lb/>
Mr. Cornwell or anybody else persuade you otherwise. If you want to read the cold<lb/>
(too cold) argument look up the following in your own medical library:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) J.A.M.A., May 23, 1903, p. 1429 - &ldquo;The Transmission of Yellow Fever&rdquo;<lb/>
by Carroll. Herein Carroll takes Finlay's experiments apart and shows he could <hi>not<lb/>
have produced a single case of yellow fever.</hi></item>
<item><p>(2) J.A.M.A. June 13, 1903, page 1659 - Finlay's letter to the editor<lb/>
of the A.M.A. objecting violently to Carroll's article.</p>
<p>Also same pages - Agramonte's letter to the editor agreeing partly<lb/>
with Carroll but suggesting that Carroll had been too critical and that Finlay was<lb/>
a swell guy, after all. (This letter got Agramonte in dutch with <hi>both</hi> sides!)</p></item>
<pb n="5" id="f05906020"/>
<item>Mr. George A. Kellogg</item>
<item>- 5 -</item>
<item>February 20, 1941</item>
<item>(3) Medical Record, Aug. 31, 1901, page 343. Another letter by Finlay<lb/>
who was by now claiming more and more and getting madder and madder!</item>
</list></p>
<p>You must read the above. It won't take 30 minutes. Also you and Mr.<lb/>
Cornwell <hi>should</hi> read the following for background notes; they are very interesting<lb/>
<hi>popular</hi> articles:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Agramonte - Annals Int. Med. Aug. <unclear>1923.</unclear></item>
<item>Ireland - The Conquest of Y. F. The Military Surgeon, Feb. 1929.</item>
<item>Kean - Walter Reed (some real dope) Military Surgeon, Mar. 1928.</item>
<item>Agramonte - Military Surgeon, Nov. 1930.</item>
<item>Agramonte - Scientific Monthly, Dec. 1930 (not the Dec. 1915 one I<lb/>
loaned you) These are all vital for you to see, most interesting<lb/>
and entertaining, written in a popular vein and describe dramatically<lb/>
the places, scenes and reactions of the men involved. If you read<lb/>
them, you <hi>can't possibly</hi> be satisfied to give to the <hi>American audience</hi><lb/>
the type of painting originally planned.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Now as to the Cubans. You sure are in the soup there! How can you<lb/>
possibly get out of it unless you paint two versions? If you want to avoid the<lb/>
condemnation of all concerned that's all you can do and I suggest you gracefully<lb/>
label the Finlay Scene &ldquo;Conquest of Yellow Fever I - Dr. Finlay meets the U.S.<lb/>
Army Commission, Aug. 1900&rdquo;.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Conquest of Yellow Fever II - The U.S. Army Yellow Fever Board dis-<lb/>
covers the cause of yellow fever: Dr. Lazear inoculating Dr. Carroll.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I think that plan would be swell and if you present the Cubans with the<lb/>
first version (preferably via my little museum, says I) you can get out of part of<lb/>
your trouble. It beats all how, with every honorable intent, a man can get into a<lb/>
pickle without knowing why. I did the same thing when I went to Cuba, had no idea<lb/>
they were mad, but because I stuck up for Reed et al they were <hi>not</hi> overjoyed to<lb/>
help me. I <hi>got no dinner parties</hi>, I can assure you!! But I have since heard that<lb/>
they learned to respect my knowledge because they <hi>didn't</hi> fool me.</p>
<p>Before you finally decide on having the scene <hi>in front of the officers'<lb/>
porch</hi> be sure to get Kean's and Truby's opinion. If you're not going to have it<lb/>
<hi>on the porch</hi> why not have it <hi>in front of &ldquo;Reed's</hi> little laboratory&rdquo;; as a matter of<lb/>
fact Carroll's inoculation by Lazear was doubtless done <hi>in the lab</hi>; if you depict<lb/>
it in front of &ldquo;Reed's lab&rdquo; it will be just that much more nearly correct. But I<lb/>
leave this to your conscience as modified or fortified by Kean and Truby. If they<lb/>
don't squawk, the comments of Reed's son, Mrs. Lazear, Gen. Ireland, Moran and<lb/>
Kissinger and others closely interested parties will be relatively less important.<lb/>
Kean and Truby are the <hi>watchdogs</hi> for <hi>truth</hi> whom you should get on your side. They<lb/>
are reasonable men and will doubtless agree to a certain amount of artistic license.<lb/>
One more point - would Kissinger and Moran have been <hi>sitting</hi> on the porch in the<lb/>
presence of superior officers? Perhaps they would have been &ldquo;at ease.&rdquo; Doubtless<lb/>
they would have been looking on with <hi>great</hi> interest and <hi>not</hi> casually. It will be<lb/>
easy to find out from Kissinger and Moran but I <hi>won't</hi> write either of them till you<lb/>
decide whether to put them in it or not. Then I'll be glad to write to them.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f05906021"/>
<p>Mr. George A. Kellogg</p>
<p>- 6 -</p>
<p>February 20, 1941</p>
<p>One more comment: In the Cuban version can't you depict Reed otherwise<lb/>
than <hi>with hat in hand</hi>, as it were coming to Finlay &ldquo;with hat in hand,&rdquo; swallowing<lb/>
Finlay's oracular words with never an idea of his own! Why not more <hi>action,</hi> Reed<lb/>
looking at the mosquito dish or shaking hands with Finlay or some such. Make Reed<lb/>
less the suppliant and more the equal (he was much the scientific <hi>superior</hi>) of<lb/>
Finlay, and give <hi>Lazear</hi> more place!</p>
<p>I enclose an article in the Sat. Eve Post, Aug. 5, 1939, re Kissinger.<lb/>
Popular articles on Moran appeared in the Literay Digest for Jan. 14, 1928 and in<lb/>
the World's Work for Dec. 1927.</p>
<p>Yours for some more rows with the genial Cubans!</p>
<closer>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. Dr. Bulbulian and his associates are more than busy full time<lb/>
with the Mayo Clinic m<add>o</add>ulage work. He suggests Miss Nellie Starkson, Field Museum,<lb/>
Chicago, who was formerly here. He thinks that she might be able to do the work<lb/>
for you.<lb/>
</seg>
Addresses:<lb/>
Dr. Robert P. Cooke, State Dept. of Health, Lexington-Rockbridge Health Dept.,<lb/>
Lexington, Va.<lb/>
Mr. John R. Kissinger, Route #8, Huntington, Indiana.<lb/>
Mr. John J. Moran, Sunoco Oil Co., Avenida Menocal 455-457, Havana.<lb/>
Mrs. Jesse W. Lazear, 116 East Padre St., Santa Barbara, California.<lb/>
General Walter L. Reed, 2810 Thirty-Sixth Place, N.W., Washington, D. C.<lb/>
(Miss Agramonte) Mrs. Estella Agramonte Rodriguez-Leon, 15 St. No. 311, Vedado, Havana.<lb/>
Mr. J. H. Andrus, 805 Cooper St., Camden, N. J.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
