<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906215">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, September 23, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906215</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-09-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-09-23">September 23, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906215</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, September 23, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg discusses the painting of McDowell, which is being planned by Wyeth, and describes Rankin's criticism of the Cornwell yellow fever painting.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-09-23">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, September 23, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906215"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
257 CORNELISON AVENUE<lb/>
JERSEY CITY, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1941-09-23">September 23, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I hope you will pardon me for not answering your letter of September<lb/>
15th at an earlier date. Mr. Withington and I met in Louisville on<lb/>
the night of the 12th and drove to Lexington, Kentucky the next day.<lb/>
Dr. Rankin was unable to see us Saturday but we employed our time<lb/>
pleasurably and profitably by spending half a day in Danville at the<lb/>
reconstructed home of Dr. McDowell and talking to a few people who<lb/>
were interested.</p>
<p>We saw Dr. Rankin on Monday noon and then saw Dr. Arthur McCormack<lb/>
and his wife on Tuesday in Louisville. Dr. Rankin would be happy to<lb/>
see the popular version of the McDowell story painted, that is the<lb/>
one in which the discontented local citizens sit around a tree with<lb/>
a hang rope suspended over a branch while the operation proceeded.<lb/>
However, for more exact information he referred us to Dr. McCormack.<lb/>
Dr. Rankin proceeded to give us quite a lecture on the propriety of<lb/>
having a non-regulation sun helmet on General Wood in the Yellow<lb/>
Fever painting. He further pointed out that the General would have<lb/>
had his congressional medal on, something he considered a very<lb/>
important point. It is possible that we may have the original paint-<lb/>
ing changed but it is too late to do anything about the plates, that<lb/>
is the printing plates. Rankin seemed very anxious to have the sun<lb/>
helmets taken off all three men who are wearing them as he said they<lb/>
were not regulation and having been in the army for many years he felt<lb/>
that the soldiers would not like them as they give the picture a<lb/>
British complexion. We can see his point. On the other hand, we have<lb/>
had no objection from General Kean or General Trubie both of whom were<lb/>
there at the time.</p>
<p>In our interviews with Dr. McCormack and his wife we found that while<lb/>
they were both much interested in the story and Dr. McCormack had done<lb/>
a great deal toward raising the money to make the reconstruction of the<lb/>
McDowell home possible, it was Mrs. McCormack that had really read<lb/>
carefully on the subject. She, however, has done most of her work on<lb/>
the story of Mrs. Jane Todd Crawford. Furthermore, Mrs. McCormack who<lb/>
in a general way represents the women's auxiliary of the State of<lb/>
Kentucky, being rather prominent in their affairs is violently opposed<lb/>
to the lynching story which she says is a popular concept based on a<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05906216"/>
-2-<lb/>
newspaper item which ran in Louisville many years ago, said newspaper item<lb/>
having been written by a reporter who only wanted to fix up a good story<lb/>
(Incidentally, she said she had ascertained through long research that this<lb/>
reporter was a drinking man). Anyway, we surmised after two hours' conver-<lb/>
sation that if we were to paint the popular version we would have a rather<lb/>
well organized small group in Kentucky who have made a serious study of the<lb/>
McDowell story right on our necks. Of course, we knew in advance that both<lb/>
William Allen Pusey and Dr. Schachner who wrote the authoritative book<del>s</del> on<lb/>
McDowell both laughed at the story.</p>
<p>The upshot of the matter is that we will have Mr. Cornwell submit sketches<lb/>
to several of these parties in which the dramatic moment<del>s</del> picked out by<lb/>
Dr. Pusey are represented, namely, the time at which Dr. McDowell visited<lb/>
Mrs. Crawford in her home and obtained her consent to perform the<lb/>
operation. Frankly, we don't believe there are any <unclear>Henchs</unclear> in Kentucky.<lb/>
We would like to win Dr. Rankin's support to this editorial angle and<lb/>
because he is something of a hero to Kentuckians and of course is<lb/>
nationally known, it would be very nice if we could interest him in making<lb/>
a little speech on the subject when the occasion arises, that is when the<lb/>
picture is unveiled. So much for our contacts in Kentucky.</p>
<p>I was much interested in your report on the exhibition of paintings in<lb/>
Madison, Wisconsin. Mr. Withington's report was essentially the same. He<lb/>
attempted to get the store to take the fur coats out of the windows in<lb/>
which the paintings were shown but with no success whatsoever. The point<lb/>
that upset me most was the fact that the Medical Society did not have any<lb/>
cards in the window to tie the exhibition up with the Society. The store<lb/>
got all the credit for having the paintings and of course the purpose of<lb/>
the exhibition is to give the local medical society who arranges for their<lb/>
exhibition a bit of nice publicity.</p>
<p>Your story about the spectator who admired the window dresser was very<lb/>
amusing.</p>
<p>I called Dr. Bauer as soon as I returned and asked him for a quotation on<lb/>
25,000 reprints of the Hygeia article. I have not heard from him yet as<lb/>
he said it would take some time to get the figures. I have asked to have<lb/>
the reprints bound in blue paper so that they will make a nice looking<lb/>
pamphlet and of course the same insert which is being used in Hygeia will<lb/>
be <unclear>tipped</unclear> in. I anticipate that they will not charge us more than about<lb/>
$15.00 or $16.00 per thousand for the bound reprints. Incidentally, we<lb/>
are setting aside 5,000 for you which we consider a wise investment.</p>
<p>I have not had the opportunity to write Dr. Kahn as my secretary has been<lb/>
sick now for almost ten days. I am glad to know that we were not wrong on<lb/>
the method of using the test tubes and I shall send him this information.</p>
<p>The large reproductions are now off the press and are being framed. In-<lb/>
cidentally I received a very nice letter from Miss Agramonte, a copy of<lb/>
which I am enclosing.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>George Kellogg</signed>
George A. Kellogg/ecs--Encl.<lb/>
(P.S. follows)<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05906217"/>
-3-<lb/>
<seg>
P.S. Withington and I are making arrangements to have one of our men stay<lb/>
with the paintings continously. That will be his only job - to travel with<lb/>
them and arrange for their display. We think we have just the man for the<lb/>
work. The troubles in Wisconsin came as a result of our not having anyone<lb/>
there who knew what to do. Confidentially, we expect to just take one of<lb/>
our smart, young detailmen who is unmarried and doesn't mind traveling<lb/>
continuously and train him to be a traveling showman to cooperate with<lb/>
local medical societies and institutions that are exhibiting the paintings<lb/>
and see that the local society gets good publicity in the local papers and<lb/>
actually gets real value from having the exhibition. Wyeth can only get<lb/>
their money's worth out of the project if the pictures accomplish something<lb/>
for the local doctors. When any exhibition is over we want the officers<lb/>
of the medical society to be able to say that the exhibition of the Wyeth<lb/>
pictures did a fine job for them. John Wyeth &amp; Brother, Inc., in that<lb/>
way will get dividends on dollars invested.<lb/>
G.A.K.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
