<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906221">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, September 25, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906221</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-09-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Rankin, Fred W.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Mayo Clinic, Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-09-25">September 25, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906221</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, September 25, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thanks Kellogg for the acknowledgement included in the journal article on the Cornwell painting. However, he suggests a few changes to the acknowledgement.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-09-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, September 25, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906221"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-09-26">September 26, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
257 Cornelison Avenue<lb/>
Jersey City, N. J.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am returning the two pages of proof, which are as I understand<lb/>
it, to go with the reproduction of the yellow fever painting in the November 1<lb/>
issue of the Journal of the A.M.A. I think it was mighty generous of you to<lb/>
print such a nice and comprehensive acknowledgement. It is also a diplomatic<lb/>
thing to do, and I hope that the Cubans won't backfire by suggesting that they<lb/>
approve some other editorial idea than the one finally portrayed and that they<lb/>
wash their hands of the present painting. The Mayo Clinic is of course sensi-<lb/>
tive about the way its name is used in advertising matters but I see absolutely<lb/>
no objection and indeed think it most kind of you to mention me so generously.<lb/>
I asked the head of our editorial department and three or four of my close<lb/>
friends if they thought anyone could criticize me or the Clinic for allowing my<lb/>
name to be so used and they all said, &ldquo;Absolutely not.&rdquo; I do believe that you<lb/>
exaggerated the value of my services to you in relation to the services of your<lb/>
other official advisors, particularly Generals Kean and Truby, but of course<lb/>
that matter is out of my hands.</p>
<p>Permit me to make two or three changes which I think are important.<lb/>
First of all, in the list of acknowledgements, I believe it would be very dip-<lb/>
lomatic to include Mrs. Estela Agramonte del Rodriguez <unclear>Leon</unclear>, Dr. Agramonte's<lb/>
daughter. It is true that her comments and criticisms on the original and sub-<lb/>
sequent versions were sent to you largely through me but I believe even before<lb/>
the last letter that you just had from her that you had already had at least<lb/>
one letter from her, and now, especially since her letter of September 11 to<lb/>
you, I think it would be gracious to include her name. Perhaps her name could<lb/>
be inserted as I have done on the proof, in the list of the Havana people.<lb/>
However, if you think the expression &ldquo;all of whom were personally consulted&rdquo;<lb/>
does not apply to her, I suggest that you include her in the next paragraph<lb/>
after the names of the Mrs. Reed, and I would suggest that you identify her<lb/>
as the daughter of Dr. Agramonte.</p>
<p>I am delighted to hear her comments about the final painting and in order<lb/>
that you may send her one of the original engraver's proofs I am returning to you<lb/>
for her one of the two you sent me. I think she will be most happy to have it<lb/>
and I believe you will feel better about having sent her one. Later, you can send<lb/>
me another of the large framed reproductions and I would appreciate it greatly<lb/>
if Mr. Cornwell will autograph it. You can then send Miss Agramonte a few other<lb/>
reproductions as she requests.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906222"/>
<p>Mr. George A. Kellogg</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>September 26, 1941</p>
<p>In the second paragraph of the printed key, the name Olson is spelled<lb/>
with two &ldquo;s's&rdquo;. Please delete one &ldquo;s&rdquo;. No. 14 represents eleven additional<lb/>
volunteers. Only ten are mentioned, the name Hildebrand having been left out.<lb/>
Please insert this as marked.</p>
<p>One more point. Let me comment on the spelling of the names Olson<lb/>
and Weatherwalks. The first is variously spelled Olson and Olsen. It is spelled<lb/>
Olson on page 23 of the official Senate Document 822. It is also so spelled<lb/>
in the following Congressional Bills: HR 13060 (1928), HR 11686 (1928) and<lb/>
S 3364 (1928); it is also spelled <hi>Olson</hi> on page 10 of the Hearing before the<lb/>
committee on military affairs of the House of Representatives April 11, 1928.<lb/>
I assume, therefore, that that is the correct way to spell it despite the fact<lb/>
that it is spelled <hi>Olsen</hi> on pages 28 and 104 of the Senate Document and also in<lb/>
a letter dated April 16, <unclear>192</unclear> written by Colonel Kean and sent to Honorable John<lb/>
Morin of the Committee on Military Affairs.</p>
<p>The other name is variously spelled Weatherwalk and Weatherwalks. It<lb/>
is spelled <hi>Weatherwalks</hi> in Colonel Kean's letter just mentioned, also on page 23<lb/>
of the official Senate Document 822, also in the three Congressional bills mentioned<lb/>
above, but it is spelled Weatherwalk without the final &ldquo;s&rdquo; on pages 29 and 104 of<lb/>
the Senate Document. By virtue of preponderance I suspect that the spellings<lb/>
<hi>Olson</hi> and <hi>Weatherwalks</hi> are correct. It would be nice to have these names correct<lb/>
in the Journal of the A.M.A. and elsewhere. I spelled them <hi>Olson</hi> and <hi>Weatherwalks</hi><lb/>
in the Hygeia article. Do you have time to check on this by writing to the War<lb/>
Department? I believe the Chief of the Pension Bureau who sends out the Congressional<lb/>
monthly awards to these men or their widows could give you the official spelling.<lb/>
If you find it, will you please send me the correct spelling?</p>
<p>I am sending a carbon copy of this last page to Generals Kean and Truby<lb/>
but I don't know whether they know which is correct or whether they could get me<lb/>
the correct spelling in time to send it to you.</p>
<p>I was much interested in your conversations with Drs. Rankin and McCormack.<lb/>
I was amused at Dr. Rankin's criticism about the helmets. I suppose criticism of<lb/>
one sort or another will be popping up from time to time from various sources and it<lb/>
will be interesting to see how many are justified and how many are not. It is<lb/>
curious that Generals Kean and Truby did not criticize the sun helmets on the three<lb/>
officers. Apparently you are finding almost as many conflicting stories <unclear>about the</unclear><lb/>
McDowell episode as you did about the yellow fever story but if you are as vigorous<lb/>
in tracking down the truth as you were in the yellow fever story I am sure you will<lb/>
have very few valid or serious criticisms of your vital work.</p>
<p>It is extremely generous of you to be willing to send me so many reprints.<lb/>
I will await them with pleasant anticipation and assume that when you write Dr. Bauer<lb/>
after hearing about the price of the whole 25,000 you will tell him that your order<lb/>
includes mine and that he can ignore the letter that I sent him, a copy of which I<lb/>
sent you. It might be just as convenient for him and much more convenient for you<lb/>
and me if you would ask Dr. Bauer to ship me the 5,000 reprints directly rather than<lb/>
having them shipped to you and then having you ship them here.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
