<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906182">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, August 23, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906182</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-08-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Matas, Rudolph</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Fernandez, Nicanor</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Presedo, Vincente</name>
<name type="person">Martinez, Jose</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-08-23">August 23, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906182</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, August 23, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses identification of the figures in Cornwell's painting for an upcoming "Hygeia" article that will feature a copy of the painting. He presents a strong argument for including Ames.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-08-23">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, August 23, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906182"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-08-23">August 23, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>First let me thank you and Mr. Cornwell most sincerely for the beautifully<lb/>
framed autographed sketch of Walter Reed. I am very proud to have this and it will<lb/>
hang in my office in the Mayo Clinic beside one of the colored reproductions of<lb/>
the painting which I hope soon to have. In this, as in all your dealings with me,<lb/>
you and your associates have been extremely kind.</p>
<p>Now let me transmit to you the suggestions of Generals Kean and Truby and<lb/>
of myself regarding the identification of the as yet anonymous figures in the paint-<lb/>
ing. I can understand your amused pleasure to find that Matas and others have so<lb/>
promptly and so self-satisfyingly nominated names for the anonymous figures. Look-<lb/>
ing at it in a narrower light, you are of course glad to have this painting mean<lb/>
&ldquo;all things to all men&rdquo; and for them to see in it <unclear>whomever</unclear> they wish to see in it.<lb/>
I do not criticize you for this view and there is much to be said in favor of it.<lb/>
In the last analysis it is for you and your associates to decide whether you wish<lb/>
to &ldquo;leave the door open.&rdquo;</p>
<p>But I have thought much about this and have taken the liberty to suggest<lb/>
more specificity in identification. Let's take a long range view. I believe as<lb/>
time passes this portrait will assume more and more historical significance and I<lb/>
believe that posterity will demand considerable specificity; history will demand<lb/>
as much accuracy in naming the figures as Cornwell's conscience demanded in hav-<lb/>
ing correct uniforms. Posterity will say (at least I think so): &ldquo;Who is that and<lb/>
that and what right has he to be in the portrait?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Because I feel this way I was delighted that you designated the two seated<lb/>
figures Major Kean and Gen. Wood and that Mr. Cornwell changed the original insignia<lb/>
(as shown in the earlier sketches) to those appropriate to the rank of the Major<lb/>
and General. Indeed even the poses of these men are appropriate--Kean leaning for-<lb/>
ward with intense interest, Wood looking on more aloofly, with hand to mouth as if<lb/>
pondering the tremendous significance of the work in hand and also remembering the<lb/>
risks he and the others were assuming if things went wrong.</p>
<p>I like the symbolism of the group of soldier volunteers, waiting and ready<lb/>
to be the next to be experimented upon. I like the eager interest of those officers<lb/>
who, though subordinate in scientific rank to the principles and therefore placed<lb/>
somewhat in the background, nevertheless played an important and vital part one way<lb/>
or another. I am so glad Dr. Cooke and Gen. Truby are specifically named.</p>
<p>Now for the figures un-named or tentatively named. It has been my under-<lb/>
standing (and I believe Mr. Cornwell told me in his studio) that the mustached<lb/>
red-headed private on Moran's right (to our left of Moran) was more or less drawn<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05906183"/>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
August 23, 1941<lb/>
after Jernegan so chosen because he was one of the most-used volunteers (he under-<lb/>
went every test offered) and especially because his mustache made him picturesque<lb/>
and different. (He is #14 in the enclosed old photo of the hospital detachment.)<lb/>
Both Generals Truby and Kean agree that Jernegan has an excellent right to be<lb/>
specifically included.</p>
<p>The Spanish immigrant (and if I used the words &ldquo;Cuban volunteer&rdquo; in any<lb/>
previous correspondence it was a slip of the tongue because Cubans were supposedly<lb/>
immune, and hence newly arrived Spanish <unclear>immigrants</unclear> were used)--this immigrant might<lb/>
well remain unnamed but specifically designated &ldquo;a figure representing the four<lb/>
Spanish immigrants who volunteered for the experiments, (namely <add>Antonio Benigno,</add> Nicanor Fernandez,<lb/>
Vincente Presedo, Jose Martinez)&rdquo;. (I have given the names in the<lb/>
order of their getting yellow fever.)</p>
<p>The rather obscured American volunteer in the background between Moran and<lb/>
the Spanish immigrant also might well be specifically designated "a figure repre-<lb/>
senting one of the <hi>additional</hi> eleven American soldiers who volunteered, namely<lb/>
William H. Dean, William Olson, Levi Folk, <del><unclear>W</unclear></del>,<add>Wallace<lb/>
Folk,<lb/>
John<lb/>
Andrus</add>, Clyde West, James Hanberry,<lb/>
Charles Sonntag, Edward Weatherwalk, James Hildebrand, Thomas England. (The first<lb/>
eight are named in the order they developed yellow fever; the last three lived in<lb/>
the infected clothing building and never got the disease.)</p>
<p>This leaves only the two officers on the porch railing. You say that Dr.<lb/>
Cooke is the figure in white. That's alright with me. Dr. Cooke certainly should<lb/>
be in it. But if you see his picture (#4 in the hospital corps group) you will see<lb/>
that neither of the officers on the porch rail resembles Cooke too closely. Indeed<lb/>
I believe the officer in the brown coat perhaps looks a bit more like Dr. Cooke<lb/>

than the figure in white. However, I leave that up to you and Cornwell.</p>
<p>Who shall the other one be? Were he a private he might well go un-named<lb/>
and merely be another &ldquo;representative&rdquo; but since he is an officer and fairly<lb/>
prominant I think he should be named. One of your earlier correspondents suggested<lb/>
including Dr. Carter (whose paper, next to that of Finlay, was Reed's most important<lb/>
stimulus) but as Gen. Kean points out in the enclosed (excerpted) letter Carter<lb/>
was only tangentially related to the experiments and may or may not have been in<lb/>
Cuba. Capt. Stark was commanding officer of the Post Hospital except for the short<lb/>
time when Lieut. Truby hold that position, but he had probably less actual connection<lb/>
with the mosquito work than Truby, and since the latter is included I don't believe<lb/>
Stark need be in it also. Dr. Pinto might be mentioned--he was one of the earliest<lb/>
persons experimented upon, but the early volunteers accepted the experiments most<lb/>
casually; they expected nothing and nothing happened. Pinto (who is still living<lb/>
in Omaha) did <hi>not</hi> get yellow fever, did <hi>not</hi> volunteer later, and hence doesn't seem<lb/>
to rate.</p>
<p>About the only other person I can suggest is Dr. Roger Post Ames (now dead,<lb/>
widow living) who was the hospital's chief yellow fever expert, who was the head man<lb/>
who took care of the <hi>spontaneous</hi> yellow fever cases at the post prior to the experi-<lb/>
ments and who faithfully and most successfully cared for all the <hi>experimental</hi> cases<lb/>
brought back from Camp Lazear to be cared for at the post. Probably largely because<lb/>
of his skill and care not one volunteer died of experimental yellow fever (except<lb/>
Lazear, of course). It seems to me and to Gen. Truby that Dr. Ames thus deserves<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05906184"/>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
August 23, 1941<lb/>
first consideration for the un-named figure.</p>
<p>In the official Senate Document (page 71) Reed's paper states: &ldquo;The<lb/>
personnel of this camp (Camp Lazear) consisted of two medical officers, Dr.<lb/>
Roger P. Ames, acting assistant surgeon, United States Army; an immune,<lb/>
<hi>in immediate charge:</hi> Dr. R. P. Cooke, acting assistant surgeon, United States<lb/>
army, nonimmune....&rdquo; (Moran disputes this and says he never saw Ames while he,<lb/>
Moran, was at Camp Lazear, that Ames stayed at Columbia Barracks. But I believe<lb/>
it was either Gen. Truby or Gen. Kean who told me that they accepted the record<lb/>
and Reed's statement and that though Ames probably only went to the camp when<lb/>
someone got sick, he nevertheless was &ldquo;officially&rdquo; in charge). Despite this<lb/>
contention Ames would seem the most worthy because of his care of the volunteers.<lb/>
Note what Gen. Truby says in the enclosed letter. You will note that Gen. Kean<lb/>
is not so definite in approving his name but I have sent him a copy of Truby's<lb/>
letter today and he (Gen. Kean) will presumably write you directly to reach you<lb/>
air mail Monday morning. If Gen. Kean nominates somebody else, <hi>by all means</hi><lb/>
take his suggestion as he ranks as the greatest living authority on these experi-<lb/>
ments.</p>
<p>It is doubtless too late to take Gen. Truby's suggestion to do the face<lb/>
over from a photo to be obtained from Mrs. Ames. Ames is <hi>not</hi> in the group photo<lb/>
enclosed. But the Ames family will probably not worry too much over the dubious<lb/>
likeness if Dr. Ames is honored by inclusion. As to the appropriateness of the<lb/>
uniform and insignia I cannot venture to speak, but both the white coated and the<lb/>
brown coated officers appear to be lieutenants; their shoulder insignia resemble<lb/>
those worn by Dr. Cooke (#4 in the group photo) and both were contract surgeons<lb/>
with the rank of &ldquo;acting assistant surgeon&rdquo; (same as Lazear). So the uniform<lb/>
insignia would not seem to be inappropriate for Dr. Ames if you decide to include<lb/>
him.</p>
<p>All of the foregoing I send you simply in a spirit of helpfulness. You can<lb/>
do <hi>whatever you want about it.</hi> I assure you, and we who are interested by-standers<lb/>
will abide by your decision and respect your final judgment. I will send a copy<lb/>
of this letter airmail special to Generals Kean and Truby. I imagine Gen. Truby<lb/>
has made his final comment but there is still time for Gen. Kean to let you hear<lb/>
from him Monday before your deadline.</p>
<p>By the way, please refer to General Kean as <hi>Chief Surgeon, Department of<lb/>
Western Cuba</hi> (and <hi>not</hi> as &ldquo;head of the U. S. Military Hospital in Havana&rdquo; as noted<lb/>
erroneously in the New York Mirror). If you want to add a further citation, he was<lb/>
friend and advisor to Reed and his associates (and did more for Reed than any other<lb/>
outsider with the possible exception of Gen. Wood).</p>
<p>May I suggest that when you make up your description for Hygeia and the A.M.A.<lb/>
you send a carbon copy airmail to Generals Kean and Truby and to me. If there is<lb/>
any last minute correction or slip I'm sure they will advise you in time to correct<lb/>
proof.</p>
<p>Best wishes as always.</p>
<closer>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
<seg>
P. S. What final inspiration was responsible for the cigarette on the<lb/>
table? Was Cornwell smoking one when he gave the painting its finishing touches, and<lb/>
did he figuratively lay it down &ldquo;in the painting&rdquo; with a sigh of relief? Or did<lb/>
Carroll smoke? I've chuckled ever that final touch.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
