<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906101">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, May 28, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906101</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-05-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Law, Frank F.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Jordan, Harvey E.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Atcheson Laughlin</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mrs. J.B.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="place">Cleveland (Oh.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-05-28">May 28, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906101</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, May 28, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg supplies Hench with details on the upcoming unveiling of the Cornwell painting. He discusses Law's introduction of Hench, the guest list, Hench's speech, the planned order of proceedings, and the painting.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-05-28">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, May 28, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906101"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
257 CORNELISON AVENUE<lb/>
JERSEY CITY, N. J.<lb/>
<date value="1941-05-28">May 28, 1941.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench,</salute>
</opener>
<p>You are quite right about my neglecting to tell you many essential<lb/>
details concerning this luncheon. I hope that I cleared up most of<lb/>
your questions this morning on the 'phone. After talking with you I<lb/>
talked with Mr. Law at Philadelphia and he told me that all he expected<lb/>
to say about the series of paintings, &ldquo;Pioneers of American Medicine&rdquo;<lb/>
would be as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Some years ago John Wyeth and Brother felt that they would like to<lb/>
make some contribution to the general knowledge of medicine outside<lb/>
the ordinary field in which pharmaceutical houses function. It had<lb/>
been noted that every school child and the man in the street is<lb/>
quite conscious of the contribution made by European scientiests<lb/>
like Lister, Pasteur and the Curies. However, very few Americans<lb/>
had ever heard of Dr. William Beaumont, McDowell, and Trudeau.</p>
<p>We felt that we could make a contribution in the form of a pictorial<lb/>
study of the contributions of American medicine.</p>
<p>Today I have asked you to join me in inveiling what is really a pre-<lb/>
view of the third painting in the series, &ldquo;Pioneers of American Medi-<lb/>
cine&rdquo; We have with us a gentleman who is a physician who has contri-<lb/>
buted much to the success which we hope this painting will enjoy.<lb/>
This doctor who stands high in his profession cannot rest in the<lb/>
manner of ordinary men. Some four years ago when he went to Cuba on<lb/>
a vacation of two or three weeks he decided that he might improve his<lb/>
time in some manner and his first thought was to see the locale of<lb/>
the yellow fever investigation which took place near Havana in 1900.</p>
<p>His interest and some of the historical facts which he discovered he<lb/>
will tell you himself. It is sufficient for me to say that his in-<lb/>
terest in the yellow fever investigation has grown into an absorbing<lb/>
hobby. He may write a book on what he has learned. He could write<lb/>
two of them.</p>
<p>Not long after Mr Cornwell began work on the present painting this<lb/>
outstanding physician-historian kindly consented to aid Mr. Cornwell<lb/>
in developing the editorial theme of the painting. Since that time<lb/>
he has contributed invaluable information and advice. He was not<lb/>
satisfied merely to give us his <add>own</add> opinion and referred us to more than<lb/>
a dozen of the people previously unknown to Mr. Cornwell who had actu-<lb/>
ally been in contact with the yellow fever board during the time this<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05906102"/>
Dr. Hench<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
May 28, 1941<lb/>
this work was being done. I wish to introduce to you our speaker<lb/>
for this occasion, Dr. Philip S. Hench, of the Mayo Clinic.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This is not exactly what Mr. Law will say, of course, but it is the<lb/>
impression which I gathered from his telephone conversation of this morn-<lb/>
ing, and I told him I would send it to you so that you may know what to<lb/>
expect.</p>
<p>I wish to review for you the names of certain persons who have ac-<lb/>
cepted Mr Law's invitation:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Mrs. Reed</item>
<item>Mr. Kissinger</item>
<item>Dr. Eben J. Carey, Dean<lb/>
Marquette University Medical School</item>
<item>Dr. Vincent W. Archer,<lb/>
University of Virginia</item>
<item>Dr. Harvey E. Jordan, Dean<lb/>
University of Virginia Medical School</item>
<item>Major-General Ireland</item>
<item>Mr. Cornwell</item>
<item>Mr. Wm. S. Milliken, Director<lb/>
Cleveland Art Museum</item>
<item>Dr. Nathan Van Etten, President,<lb/>
American Medical Ass'sn.</item>
<item>Dr. Parkinson, Dean<lb/>
Temple University Medical School</item>
</list></p>
<p>There is a numerous list of physicians whose names would probably mean<lb/>
nothing to you at the moment. Others who have been invited and from whom<lb/>
we have not had time to receive acceptances include the editors of three<lb/>
Cleveland newspapers, four of the better known science writers from New<lb/>
York and Washington, the Cleveland representatives of the Associated and<lb/>
United Press Services and a miscellaneous group of newspaper men numbering<lb/>
about a dozen; the Mayor of the City of Cleveland; the Superintendent of<lb/>
Schools, the President of Western Reserve University; the directors and<lb/>
presidents of half a dozen art associations and galleries. My prediction<lb/>
is that there will be about seventy-five present but we will have to wait<lb/>
until tomorrow to make an accurate estimate.</p>
<p>In confirmation of our conversation of this morning I think you are<lb/>
quite right in borrowing from your Lazear dedication talk, your copy of<lb/>
which I am returning herewith. I don't think that twenty minutes is too<lb/>
long for your address as I believe the people who will be at this meeting<lb/>
are for the most part there because they are interested in the story you<lb/>
have to tell.</p>
<p>In talking with Mr. Law we decided to arrange the order of procedure<lb/>
as follows:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Introduction by Mr. Law</item>
<item>2. Address by Dr. Hench</item>
<item>3. Introduction of Major General Ireland by Mr. Law (It is presumed<lb/>
that you will have mentioned to the audience that <unclear>Gen</unclear> Ireland<lb/>
is present.)</item>
<item>4. An impromptu speech by Gen. Ireland, which may include the read-<lb/>
ing of one of the letters supplied by Mrs. Reed if you think<lb/>
there is one which is appropriate. (After looking them over I<lb/>
don't feel very optimistic on this.)</item>
<pb n="3" id="f05906103"/>
<item>Dr. Hench</item>
<item>-3-</item>
<item>May 28, 1941</item>
<item>5. Introduction of Mr. Kissinger by Mr. Law (I will have coached<lb/>
Mr. Kissinger that all he is expected to say is that he is<lb/>
pleased to be there in honor of Major Reed.)</item>
<item><p>6. Introduction of Mrs. Reed by Mr Law which will include the<lb/>
request that Mrs. Reed unveil the painting. Mrs. Reed does<lb/>
not wish to speak, so she says. (In a private party she is<lb/>
an inveterate talker and admits it. In fact, she boasts<lb/>
about it, all in fun.)</p>
<p>The painting will be covered by a silk cloth to which ribbons are<lb/>
attached and will require a slight jerk to have the cloth fall to the<lb/>
floor and reveal the picture.</p>
<p>(Space for applause.)</p></item>
<item>7. Mr. Law will introduce Mr. Cornwell, asking him to say a few<lb/>
words regarding the technical problems of painting such a<lb/>
picture.</item>
</list></p>
<p>This I believe, as done in Mr. Cornwell's customary manner, will<lb/>
add much to the interest of the occasion and help cover his embarrass-<lb/>
ment in that the painting is not complete in all details. Incidentally,<lb/>
a lesser artist would have slapped the picture togeher so that it would<lb/>
have been complete for the occasion on Monday, but Mr. Cornwell's em-<lb/>
barking on a project of this nature leaves time without meaning. In the<lb/>
long run, while it may inconvenience us somewhat that the work is not<lb/>
done on schedule, John Wyeth and Brother are certainly better off. We<lb/>
will get much more of the artist's time and attention for our money than<lb/>
we originally planned.</p>
<p>The foregoing events will end the unveiling.</p>
<p>In answer to additional auestions, the Reed, Lazear, Finlay, Moran,<lb/>
and Kissinger portraits are complete. The faces and figures of Trudy,<lb/>
Wood, Cook and Kean are sketched in. He did a nice head of a Cuban in<lb/>
the group composed of private soldiers. Cornwell would prefer to have<lb/>
the two men on the porch and the four figures in various private uni-<lb/>
forms be<del>ing</del> thought of as merely representative of the soldiers in the<lb/>
investigation rather than striving to get 100% likenesses. I told him<lb/>
this morning that a good likeness in profile would be impossible as<lb/>
Kissinger probably has no memory of what he looked like at the time, nor<lb/>
has anyone else (that is, from profile).</p>
<p>I am looking forward to receiving tomorrow a preliminary copy of<lb/>
your speech which can be handed to press representatives in advance here<lb/>
in New York City; also that you will bring fifty mimeographed copies with<lb/>
you to Cleveland where I will meet you at the Hotel Cleveland on Sunday<lb/>
morning.</p>
<p>As agreed on the 'phone, you will use the story about the old Wyeth<lb/>
representative who spent his Sundays with your father as an impromptu in-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f05906104"/>
Dr Hench<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
May 28, 1941.<lb/>
troductory story but not include it in the typed copy of your speech.<lb/>
The newspapers will pick out the defense significance from your story<lb/>
and possibly use it in the headline. Most of the copies of your speech<lb/>
will be handed to newspaper representatives present by our Mr. Arthur L.<lb/>
Greene, who is handling our newspaper contacts. He can explain the de-<lb/>
fence angle to them.</p>
<p>I am sending invitations to Dr. and Mrs. Simpson and Dr. and Mrs.<lb/>
Hench in Charlottesville, and also to your mother in Pittsburgh.</p>
<p>I am sorry that this whole affair has come on so rapidly and have<lb/>
been such a drain on your time. It is just one of those things which<lb/>
was conceived of rather late and has rapidly been built up to quite an<lb/>
occasion. You may be sure that we appreciate your efforts and that they<lb/>
will be appreciated by all those present. A preliminary story went out<lb/>
last week and Mr. Greene tells me that the &ldquo;New York Sunday Times&rdquo; ran<lb/>
it. How many other papers took it we don't know. I have not yet seen<lb/>
a clipping. We have two clipping services, however, that work<del>ed</del> on the<lb/>
papers all over the United States, and they pick up practically every<lb/>
line that appears.</p>
<p>I enclose a photograph showing the unfinished painting with Mr.<lb/>
Cornwell and Col. C M. Walson, Second Corps Area Chief Medical Officer,<lb/>
looking at the painting which was released with a second story to 150<lb/>
newspapers for publication in Saturday and Sunday papers. I am sending<lb/>
you a copy of this release as it will give you somewhat of an idea of<lb/>
how far the painting had progressed last Friday when the photograph was<lb/>
made. From this photograph it would appear to me that Cornwell had really<lb/>
done a good likeness of Trudy, who is standing between Finlay and Agramonte.<lb/>
The hands on the Reed figure have since been completed and the Lazear <add>hand</add> and<lb/>
<del>Finlay</del><add>Carroll</add> arm will be done in careful detail before the painting is shipped.<lb/>
Cornwell remarked to me this morning that he could spend two weeks work-<lb/>
ing on the shrubbery alone. This is a good story of which I think you<lb/>
might make impromptu use. You note the whitewashed rocks along the path?<lb/>
Last week when Cornwell was driving with some wealthy friends on Long<lb/>
Island and there they passed a wall which had exactly the same type of<lb/>
rocks which he needed in his painting He asked the chauffer to stop<lb/>
and he hopped out and filched one of the rocks and brought it back into<lb/>
the car. He remarked that his host and hostess were not overly pleased<lb/>
but when I was in the studio yesterday I saw the 25-lb boulder on his<lb/>
studio table.</p>
<p>I just talked with Mr. Cornwell's secretary a few minutes ago and<lb/>
he is going to have the picture shipped to Cleveland tomorrow, Thursday<lb/>
afternoon. He said he hoped to keep it until at least Saturday night<lb/>
but the long holliday and union trucking regulations make that impossible.<lb/>
If he did we might have to be an unveiling without any new picture and<lb/>
we couldn't have that happen.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f05906105"/>
<p>Dr. Hench</p>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>May 28, 1941</p>
<p>The photograph shows the painting at a considerable angle and does<lb/>
not do it justice in the state that I saw it yesterday.</p>
<p>Please tell Mrs. Hench that I wrote her a postcard from Williams-<lb/>
burg as I wanted to prove to her that I could write a postcard and re-<lb/>
member to whom I sent it and what I had said.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>George A Kellogg</signed>
GAK:L<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
