<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05903016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lucy T. Howard, August 17, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05903016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-08-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Howard, Lucy T.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-08-17">August 17, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05903016</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lucy T. Howard, August 17, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is trying to locate correspondence between L.O. Howard and the yellow fever investigators at various U.S. government agencies. He inquires if Lucy Howard has any of her father's papers at the family home.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1946-08-17">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Lucy T. Howard, August 17, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05903016"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1946-08-17">August 17, 1946</date>
</dateline>
Miss Lucy Howard<lb/>
Onteora Club<lb/>
Tannersville, New York<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Howard:</salute>
</opener>
<p>After visiting you and your father in May, I was in Washington<lb/>
and did as you suggested. I got in touch with Miss Mabel Colcord, who<lb/>
told me that she had sorted out all of your father's personal correspondence<lb/>
and had <unclear>sent</unclear> it to him. The rest had been sent from the Bureau of<lb/>
Entomology to the National Archives. To make certain about this, I talked<lb/>
to Mrs. Maud Miller, the chief mail and file room clerk at the Bureau of<lb/>
Entomology. She spent a day trying to locate any further correspondence<lb/>
between your father and the yellow fever personalities, chiefly Doctors<lb/>
Reed, Carroll, and Lazear. She was unable to find anything and assured<lb/>
me that all of the material not given to Doctor Howard had been sent<lb/>
to the National Archives. I then visited the National Archives, showed<lb/>
them what correspondence I had copies of and asked Mr. Herman Kahn, the<lb/>
Chief of the Division of the Interior Department of the Archives, for<lb/>
his assistance. They apparently spent sometime hunting for further<lb/>
correspondence on your father. They finally uncovered about twelve more<lb/>
letters, copies of which I did not have--letters between your father<lb/>
and Carroll, between your father and Doctor Reed. They found no letters<lb/>
between your father and Doctor Lazear.</p>
<p>You will remember that some of the correspondence of your<lb/>
father mentioned additional letters between himself and the above<lb/>
mentioned party. In particular your father published one of those letters<lb/>
from Walter Reed and it would appear that somewhere in his personal<lb/>
effects there must be the remains of this correspondence.</p>
<p>I hate, indeed, to bother you, but you were kind enough to<lb/>
suggest that you might be able to find time to locate a box or a trunk<lb/>
of your fathers which might have in it the missing data, and I believe<lb/>
this material you thought might be in Tannersville. I do hope that<lb/>
this material will eventually turn up. It is of considerable importance<lb/>
to show not only the relationship of your father to the conquest of<lb/>
yellow fever, but also to show the early interest of Doctors Reed and<lb/>
Lazear in learning about mosquitoes. Being the daughter of a famous<lb/>
father, unfortunately, carries certain responsibilities and obligations,<lb/>
doesn't it?</p>
<p>You and your father were very kind, indeed, to me. I<lb/>
thoroughly enjoyed my visit. I only wish that I could have the opportunity<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05903017"/>
Miss Lucy Howard<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
August 17, 1946<lb/>
of examining your father's data without bothering you unduly. I<lb/>
apologize sincerely for bothering you further, but I don't know to<lb/>
whom else to turn. Were you planning on bringing this material back<lb/>
to New York? I expect to visit Washington this fall, and if you think<lb/>
it necessary or helpful, I would be delighted to run over to New York<lb/>
to help go through this material so as to give you as little trouble<lb/>
as possible.</p>
<p>In July, I attended the meeting of the American Medical<lb/>
Association in San Francisco and thereafter visited Doctor Lazear's<lb/>
son in Santa Barbara. He knew very little about his father's work.<lb/>
Because of a tragic misunderstanding on the part of Mrs. Lazear, the<lb/>
children had been raised in almost complete ignorance of their father's<lb/>
work. It was a real pleasure to tell him the true story. I don't<lb/>
believe I ever sent you or your father a copy of an article that I<lb/>
wrote sometime ago on the yellow fever story. Permit <add>me</add> to send it to<lb/>
you by separate post. Please give my very kindest regards to your<lb/>
father.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alp<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
