<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906066">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, March 21, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906066</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-03-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Dominguez, Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cumming, Hugh S.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Manson, Patrick</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-03-21">March 21, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906066</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, March 21, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thinks Kellogg handled the Cuban situation well. He comments on the Finlay supporters in Cuba. Hench discusses the Cornwell painting in progress and the suggestions Kellogg has received from various men concerning the painting.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-03-21">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, March 21, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906066"/>
<opener>
Yellow<lb/>
Fever<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-03-21">March 21, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Mr. George A. Kellogg<lb/>
257 Cornelison Avenue<lb/>
Jersey City, New Jersey<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was most interested in the various letters, copies of which you<lb/>
sent me. They were illuminating and helpful. I think you handled very well the<lb/>
delicate situation proposed by your Cuban representative. I have Dr. Dominguez's<lb/>
book - he is the most rabid of the pro-Finlay Cubans. I met him and he gave me<lb/>
his book. He is <unclear>so</unclear> rabidly pro-Finlay that he has become not a scientist but<lb/>
merely a propagandist. He is, by the same token, rabidly anti-Reed and so forth.<lb/>
General Kean has corresponded with me about it and tells me it is filled with<lb/>
mistakes, although of course it has much truthful and interesting data in it. I<lb/>
read French only so so, enough to get the drift but not with sufficient case that<lb/>
I could trust my own translation and use it as a basis for criticizing a man's<lb/>
statements. Therefore, I repeatedly asked Domingues for the English translation<lb/>
which he told me about, told him I wanted to do full justic to Finlay (which I<lb/>
most certainly do) and therefore, wanted the Finlay version. But he stalled me<lb/>
off without adequate explanation. And you now give me the answer--apparently<lb/>
he considers it in poor shape for current publication.</p>
<p>Personally, I would very much like to see a copy and see it published<lb/>
<hi>but</hi> I quite agree that you shouldn't get mixed up in it. It might <del>keep</del><add><unclear>help</unclear></add> you in Cuba<lb/>
but not in the United States. I can't understand why he and his colleagues seem<lb/>
to need outside help to push its publication. Last year I understood the government<lb/>
was about to publish it and hand it out free. I asked Ramos for a copy but he said<lb/>
it &ldquo;wasn't ready.&rdquo; But they are all filled with such fanatical zeal in behalf of<lb/>
Finlay that I wouldn't think Dominguez needed outside help. Perhaps Ramos and other<lb/>
higher up see a fight ahead and don't feel sure enough to start shooting. It's<lb/>
all so silly and so sad. For Finlay <hi>Was</hi> a great man and they do him an injustice<lb/>
to inflat him beyond recognition.</p>
<p>I will be very pleased to receive the photos of the Cuban version<lb/>
and <del>c</del><add>w</add>ill certainly try to get some constructive criticism and get their reaction.<lb/>
I do not think the Cuban sketches are wasted. I still hope you can fix them up for<lb/>
Cuban exhibition unless a majority of Cubans were to <unclear>criticize</unclear> the details of the<lb/>
get-up as seriously as did Miss Agramonte. Let me repeat, if you really want me<lb/>
to show the colored ones to the Cubans, I'll do it and you can ship them to your<lb/>
Cuban representative or addressed to me at the Hotel Nacional.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906067"/>
<p>Mr. George A. Kellogg</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>March 21, 1941</p>
<p>I will drop you a line from Havana, or perhaps from Palm Beach before<lb/>
and after I go to Havana March 27 or 28 for one week. My Palm Beach address will<lb/>
be Villa Atlantique Hotel - March 23 to April 16 or 17. I shall let you know more<lb/>
about our New York stopover later. I certainly would like to see the sketches of<lb/>
the American version and meet Mr. Cornwell. By the way, who were the two sitting<lb/>
figures in the Cuban version - <unclear>Delgado</unclear> and who?</p>
<p>I still think my suggestion about the American version is better<lb/>
than to have, as you call it, a &ldquo;mob-scene.&rdquo; I agree that it would be nice to have<lb/>
a formal group portrait of all concerned but there would be no life - no advertising<lb/>
value - no action in it. Also, General Kean has confessed that he likes the idea<lb/>
of General Truby but likes his own idea better - a portrait of Reed getting General<lb/>
Wood's permission. It was apparently a dramatic moment and General Kean was the<lb/>
only other one present. Naturally he recalls it with <unclear>gusto</unclear> but as he admitted,<lb/>
Lazear <unclear>et al</unclear> were not there and hence that scene is inappropriate. I am still a<lb/>
little worried about having the experiment on the lawn: That aren't scientific:<lb/>
But with the others, I agree that the artist must have some license. I'm sure that<lb/>
99 per cent will be pleased with the result especially if you stick to the &ldquo;big<lb/>
five&rdquo; (Finlay, Reed, Carroll, Lazear, Agramonte). When you start adding others you<lb/>
will get into trouble. I quite agree hearily that it would be a fine thing to<lb/>
have Moran and Kissinger in it, but only as &ldquo;representative&rdquo; of the band of soldier-<lb/>
volunteers and on the little descriptive folder you should say definitely that they<lb/>
are in it as &ldquo;representatives&rdquo; and then give the names (I can supply them). Beyond<lb/>
that I would not go unless you want an unidentified female figure for relief. I'll<lb/>
ask Moran and Albertini if Miss <unclear>Maas</unclear> was around (or any other female nurses) when<lb/>
Lazear and Carroll were doing their phase of the work.</p>
<p>I thought your letters from Moran and Truby very nice. I was amused<lb/>
at Doctor Cumming's expression that you were &ldquo;smoking a cigarette around a keg of<lb/>
gunpowder.&rdquo; Last year I too rushed in, not knowing anyt<add>h</add>ing about the depths of the<lb/>
controversy. But I still say if you in your medium and I in mine, portray <hi>the truth</hi>,<lb/>
our work will live and stand and the hell with anything else. Don't let anything<lb/>
or anybody discourage you or stop you. It will be a grand, perhaps a great,<lb/>
picture and if it is true it will live as the representation of the truth about<lb/>
those who conquered yellow fever. Cummings, I see, has his favorites and wants<lb/>
Carter and Manson and perhaps <unclear>Roas</unclear> in it. Yo gods, who not include the whole<lb/>
American army of intervention and have a scene like one of those French battle scenes<lb/>
by <unclear>Detaille or Meissonier:</unclear>.</p>
<p>I was distressed to see poor old John Kissinger's letter. He must<lb/>
be failing. It still breathes some <unclear>pep</unclear> and meal, still the same (proper) adoration<lb/>
of Reed but I thought I had closed the breech between him and Moran. Apparently<lb/>
he doesn' understand why I've spent so much time in Cuba. He must think I'm just<lb/>
getting Moran's version that he and Kissinger volunteered together with Moran as<lb/>
spokesman rather than believing Kissinger's version that Kissinger volunteered a<lb/>
day or so ahead of Moran. I don't know which is correct but intend to find out<lb/>
from official sources not dependant on memory. So don't worry about Kissinger's<lb/>
letter, I'll make the old fellow <unclear>happy yet:</unclear></p>
<pb n="3" id="f05906068"/>
<p>Mr. George A. Kellogg</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>March 21, 1941</p>
<p>I will appreciate it if you will continue to send me such<lb/>
carbons and photostats as will be interesting and helpful. I am certainly glad to<lb/>
know about the Dominguez affair for I might have gotten mixed up in it myself.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:FP<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
