<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906003">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 7, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906003</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-02-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-02-07">February 7, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906003</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 7, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg feels it is essential that Hench see the preliminary sketches before Cornwell begins the work on canvas.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-02-07">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Philip Showalter Hench, February 7, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>Dr. Finlay will appear standing in his laboratory near his working table, on which<lb/>
can be seen his microscope, testing tubes, etc. He will have in his hands a recipient<lb/>
containing mosquitoe <unclear>larvae</unclear>, showing the same to the members of the American Commi-<lb/>
ssion who is grouped at the right side of the canvas. This group will be formed by<lb/>
doctors Walter Read, Agramonte, Lazear and Carroll. The original size of the can-<lb/>
vas will be two and one half meters high by 3 meters long.</p>
<p>Having sufficient information, we left our interviewer because Massaguer and Poseda<lb/>
were waiting for him to go to a banquet at the Country Club.</p>
<p>Going to our office we were remembering the most remarkable details of Dr. Finlay's<lb/>
work. In the year 1881 when for the first time the Cuban doctor proclaimed his<lb/>
phathogenetic theory saying that the Stegomya Mosquitoe was the carrier of the yellow<lb/>
fever, thus called because its main symptom is the jaundice.</p>
<p>At that time the epidemic had its root in the zone of the Mexican Gulf, propagating<lb/>
later to the U.S. and Canada following the course of the San Lorenzo and Mississippi<lb/>
rivers. The epidemy also spread to the South and to some countries of Occidental<lb/>
Europe.</p>
<p>When Dr. Finlay offered his experiences to the Academy of Medical Sciences in<lb/>
Havana, the scientific world was indifferent to his postulates. Insensible to this<lb/>
indifference he continued his studies until the opportunity arrived when the civili-<lb/>
zation gave him credit. When after innumerable sacrifices the independence of our<lb/>
country was possible in 1900, the government of the United States, interested in<lb/>
the extermination of this horrible evil, named a Commission for the substantiation<lb/>
of Dr. Finlay's experiments. This Commission was integrated by another Cuban<lb/>
doctor, Mr. Agramonte, and the Americans: Major Walter Reed, Lazear and James<lb/>
Carroll.</p>
<p>With the cooperation of the modest Cuban sage and following faithfully his direc-<lb/>
tions the Commission started to experiment with the Stegomya Fasciata a very black<lb/>
type of mosquitoe with silver spots in the thorax, a very common mosquitoe in the<lb/>
endemic area and above all in the poor sections and in stagnant waters.</p>
<p>Some of this <unclear>especimen</unclear> were taken and permitted to absorb the blood of patients<lb/>
having yellow fever. Several days after those mosquitoes had bitten a number of<lb/>
voluntary persons who heroically let themselves be innoculated with its virus, they<lb/>
were hospitalized together with other persons who were not bitten by the mosquitoes<lb/>
and being in perfect health. In those who were bitten the yellow fever developed,<lb/>
but not in the others.</p>
<p>Thus Dr. Finlay's theory culminated in an all around success, making possible the<lb/>
adoption of many prophylactic measures in order to end the yellow fever. Our country-<lb/>
man gave all he had, he gave advices and materials of his own, and in spite of his<lb/>
generosity, it was tried to take from him the primacy of his discovery.</p>
<p>Many publications giving news of this discovery tried to obscure Dr. Finlay's<lb/>
achievement to the benefit of the Commission, and many times they gave to the latter<lb/>
all the glory and credit, particularly the English Medical Biography and almost all<lb/>
they encyclopedias.</p>
<p>The question of the vindication of Dr. Finlay's glory was discussed at the X Inter-<lb/>
national Congress of Medical History held in Spain at the request of Drs. Rafael<lb/>
Menocal and Sergio Garcia Marruz, representatives of the Havana University and the<lb/>
Cuban government. The Congress recognized the right of the Cuban doctors and in one<lb/>
of their conclusions accepted unanimously the declaration recognizing the priority<lb/>
of Dr. Finlay to the discovery.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
