<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05906204">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, September 1, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05906204</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-09-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kellogg, George A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Recio, Alberto</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-09-01">September 1, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05906204</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, September 1, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses Cuban attitudes towards Finlay and the identification of figures in the Cornwell painting.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-09-01">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to George A. Kellogg, September 1, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05906204"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-09-01">September 1, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Mr. Kellogg:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am glad to hear that Finlay wrote you a second and more gracious<lb/>
reply. His first letter was certainly inconsiderate. Regardless of his feelings<lb/>
about his father's share in the glory he might have expressed some appreciation<lb/>
that you gave him an obviously prominent place. As Recio and Albertini told me<lb/>
more or less in confidence, they know the situation, appreciate the American<lb/>
viewpoint and conclude &ldquo;You <hi>never</hi> can satisfy some folks here,&rdquo; meaning Finlay,<lb/>
Dominguez and their school of thought. I appreciate your mentioning to <unclear>Finley</unclear><lb/>
my desire to see the &ldquo;Cuban version&rdquo; finished. It will help me in my unfinished<lb/>
business in Cuba, and I do think it would be a fine thing, at least to finish up<lb/>
the &ldquo;preliminary oils.&rdquo; For heaven's sake, preserve them. I may kidnap one<lb/>
some day for my Cuban museum (if I ever get it).</p>
<p>You doubtless have by now Truby's last letter in which he strongly urged<lb/>
that the figures for Cooke and Ames be switched. As I wrote you Mr. Cornwell<lb/>
obviously made no real attempt to paint Cooke's likeness even though he had a<lb/>
photo of him. Since Truby says the officer in white with the dark hair (my key--<lb/>
figure #9, named by you as Cooke) could readily pass as Ames and the one in brown<lb/>
(my key--figure #10) &ldquo;looks more like Cooke&rdquo; than figure "9, I would urge that you<lb/>
simply tell Miss Vernon to switch the printed names for figures 9 and 10. No<lb/>
need to change the numbers on your black and white photo unless you want to honor<lb/>
Cooke by being mentioned ahead of Ames (which honor Cooke deserves).</p>
<p>Truby reminded me that Moran was actually a civilian clerk, not a soldier,<lb/>
when he was inoculated. I, of course, knew that and am sure you did too. Moran<lb/>
was an acting hospital steward (with the rank of sergeant) at the time of his<lb/>
honorable discharge, July 2, 1900. He then became a civilian clerk in the office<lb/>
of Gen. Fitzhugh Lee and was in that capacity when he volunteered to Reed. He re-<lb/>
mained technically a civilian clerk till Feb. <unclear>1901</unclear>, all through his experiences at<lb/>
Camp Lazear and his recovery. But history has so universally spoken of him and<lb/>
Kissinger as the first two <hi>soldiers</hi> to volunteer that it seemed more of an honor<lb/>
<hi>to the army</hi> and more in keeping with Moran's social status (a &ldquo;soldier&rdquo; rather than<lb/>
a civilian) among his comrades to represent him in your painting as a soldier, not<lb/>
a clerk. Certainly Moran, when I showed him the original sketches, made no request<lb/>
for absolute &ldquo;calendar accuracy&rdquo; in the matter and seemed to prefer tacitly to be<lb/>
represented as a soldier.</p>
<p>Truby also tells me only the privates, and not the officers, wore the silver<lb/>
crosses on their hats. Here again the &ldquo;error&rdquo; seems insignificant. Who the hell<lb/>
cares! But it would probably only take a few cents worth of paint and a half hour<lb/>
for Cornwell to paint out the crosses <hi>on the officers' hats</hi> sometime.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05906205"/>
<p>Mr. George A. Kellogg</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>September 1, 1941</p>
<p>I assume the titles I gave the figures in my suggested key were accurate;<lb/>
neither Kean nor Truby corrected them to me.</p>
<p>I hope you get to see Rankin enroute to Madison. I'll probably see you<lb/>
in Madison; my reservation is The Loraine Hotel, Sept. 11-12.</p>
<p>I am trying to locate the Dix letters for you.</p>
<p>I note that you did not happen to include Agramonte's daughter to<lb/>
receive an engraver's proof. I feel guilty to have two and for her not to<lb/>
have any. Though I would like to keep both of mine why not let me return one<lb/>
to you to send to Mrs. Rodriguez-Leon. You can later send me a framed autographed<lb/>
regular reproduction. Although you have only had her criticism of the Cuban<lb/>
version I'm sure she'd like the new one and she ought to have one. Let me<lb/>
know. I've saved the packing they <unclear>came</unclear> in and can readily return it to you.<lb/>
It should come <hi>from you</hi>, not from me.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
