<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05911001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum: Experiences with the Yellow Fever Commission in Cuba 1900, by John R. Kissinger, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05911001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>15 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05911001</idno>
<title>Memorandum: Experiences with the Yellow Fever Commission in Cuba 1900, by John R. Kissinger, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kissinger describes the yellow fever experiments and comments on the men involved. He also describes the experience of suffering from yellow fever and the treatment for the disease. Kissinger remarks on inaccuracies in the play "Yellow Jack." He maintains that he volunteered before Moran.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Memorandum: Experiences with the Yellow Fever Commission in Cuba 1900, by John R. Kissinger, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05911001"/>
<p>EXPERIENCES WITH THE YELLOW FEVER COMMISSION IN CUBA 1900<lb/>
Mr. John R. Kissinger</p>
<p>I wish that Doctor Hench could give this story for he could give it<lb/>
much better than I could. When I attended college, I left after the seventh<lb/>
grade. I got my schooling in the factory and on the farm and those places where<lb/>
I could learn and therefore, you have to take my talk from just a common man<lb/>
and not an educated physician.</p>
<p>In regard to this yellow fever experiment, I can say that I am the only man<lb/>
who has been through the whole thing from beginning to end with Major Reed and his<lb/>
co-workers who is alive today. John J. Moran is alive but he was in the second<lb/>
phase of the experiment. These doctors were sent there in June 1900, and they<lb/>
went down there with no <add>exact</add> idea of just what they intended to do. Major Reed had<lb/>
just returned from Texas where he had experimented with typhoid fever and, through<lb/>
talking with General <unclear>Sternberg</unclear>, who was a Surgeon General in the Army at that time,<lb/>
they took up the subject that Doctor <del>Carroll</del><add>Finlay</add> had brought forth, that yellow fever<lb/>
was not contagious but had to be carried by the mosquito or injected into the<lb/>
blood in some other way than by germ. In talking it over the general said that<lb/>
if Congress and the Senate would provide the money, he would be glad to send some<lb/>
doctors down there and experiment and find out if Doctor Finlay's statement was<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f05911002"/>
-2-<lb/>
right that he had just written a short time ago in the medical magazine. He had<lb/>
been bringing this subject up for nineteen years but the doctors had given him<lb/>
the laugh.</p>
<p>Doctor Agramonte and Doctor Lazear arrived in the Columbia<del>n</del> Barracks and went<lb/>
on to <del>Pan Delorio</del><add>Pina del Rio</add>. The soldiers stationed there were dying one and two a day.<lb/>
The diagnosis in their case was malarial fever. As soon as Doctor Agramonte made<lb/>
an autopsy on the first case he pronounced it yellow fever. In that was the first<lb/>
point of their experiments. The patients were placed under mosquito netting so<lb/>
that the mosquitos could not come in contact with them and the soldiers around<lb/>
the camp. After a time a decrease was noted in sickness and death in the camp.<lb/>
Doctor Agramonte and Doctor Lazear returned to the barracks and joined Doctor Reed<lb/>
and Doctor Carroll as they had reached a point where they did not know just what<lb/>
to do. They tried guinea pigs but had no luck or results with them. One day <add>in July or<lb/>
Aug</add> Doctor <del>Reed</del><add>Pinto</add> and myself went into <del>the experiment room</del><add>Dr Carroll's lab at Columbia Barracks<unclear>.</unclear></add> and they had just put<lb/>
mosquitos on some of the other fellows that were in there, and of course we<lb/>
allowed them to place mosquitoes upon us. The doctors said they did not know<lb/>
whether this species of mosquito would carry the germs, or how long they had to<lb/>
bite a yellow fever patient before the condition would be transferred to a non-immune.<lb/>
The experiments were negative.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f05911003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>One day I was in the experiment room, but I will just tell a little before<lb/>
that. I was in charge of the operating room at that time and practically all the<lb/>
(Dr Carroll, Lazear, Agramonte &amp; Reed)<lb/>
time I could spare from my duties was spent watching their experiments to see how<lb/>
they were trying this way and that to find the germ but were at a loss. One day,<lb/>
Doctor Lazear came in the room. He had a glass tube in his hand and in this tube<lb/>
Dr Carroll &amp; myself<lb/>
three mosquitoes. He said, &ldquo;Gentlemen, I have a mosquito in here that will produce<lb/>
I know they were discouraged &amp; <unclear>unculfar</unclear> of the mosquito theory &amp; this may have<lb/>
been an offhand remark, spoken lightly.<lb/>
yellow fever.&rdquo; Doctor Carroll said, &ldquo;Alright, place it upon my arm and see if<lb/>
you are right or not.&rdquo; Lazear placed the tube upon <unclear>Caroll's</unclear> arm and the mosquito<lb/>
(check time)<lb/>
lit immediately and began to feed. Three days and a few hours later, Doctor Carroll<lb/>
went down with a severe case of yellow fever. The first case that they produced<lb/>
that was carried by the mosquito.</p>
<p>The next case that was produced was private Dean. The case was known at that<lb/>
time and afterwards as XY. I may be criticized for bringing this up but I think<lb/>
I am justified. This young man came over to the experiment camp one day and made<lb/>
to <unclear>their</unclear> face. It was most unusual for a private to speak so <unclear>boldly</unclear><lb/>
to <unclear>officers</unclear>.<lb/>
light of their experiments. They challenged him to let them put a mosquito upon<lb/>
him but he laughed and went away. He was a convalescent <add>from some illness</add> and in the habit of taking<lb/>
a nap <add>after lunch</add> so they <add>Dr Lazear or Agramonte (probably Lazear)</add> placed a mosquito upon him while he was asleep. In the history they<lb/>
say he had the permission of his superior officer. I know that he didn't. When<lb/>
he got yellow fever, he did not know where it had come from. My recollection is that<lb/>
when he later learned the facts he was at first angry, later gets proud of the fact<lb/>
that he had shared in the experiments.</p>
<p><unclear>It</unclear> wasn't<lb/>
there <unclear>when this</unclear><lb/>
was done <unclear>but<lb/>
he</unclear> had the<lb/>
private <unclear>discussions</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>about it. It</unclear><lb/>
was kept<lb/>
secret. This<lb/>
was <unclear>ofered<lb/>
rejections</unclear></p>
<pb n="4" id="f05911004"/>
<p>-4-</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear was the third case. While in the wards, surrounded by yellow<lb/>
fever patients, a mosquito landed on his hand and instead of brushing it off he<lb/>
<unclear>thought</unclear><lb/>
said, &ldquo;I am here with yellow fever around me. We will see if this will produce<lb/>
yellow fever.&rdquo; He reported to Doctor Carroll and they watched very closely. In<lb/>
less than four days Doctor Lazear was taken with yellow fever. I went in to his<lb/>
office one night and his face was flushed, he was nervous and his eyes were red.<lb/>
I said, &ldquo;Doctor, you are sick.&rdquo; He replied, &ldquo;Yes, Kissinger, I do feel sick.&rdquo;<lb/>
I said, &ldquo;Have you reported to Doctor <del>Agramonte</del><add>Ames</add>&rdquo;? (This was the doctor appointed<lb/>
to take care of these patients. He had been through a great many epidemics and<lb/>
had become a specialist in yellow fever.) Lazear said, &ldquo;No Kissinger.&rdquo; Major Reed<lb/>
had been called back to the United States and was giving a report of the typhoid<lb/>
fever experiment. Doctor Lazear was making out his reports and <unclear>when</unclear> I told him<lb/>
he should report to Doctor <del>Agramonte</del><add>Ames</add> he would not do it as he wanted to make out<lb/>
these reports so that when Major Reed returned if anything happened he would not<lb/>
have lost anything by being negligent about the reports. That was courageous.<lb/>
He did not fly across the ocean in the wind and rain or fly to the south pole, but<lb/>
he gave his life for something that he was trying to find out to help humanity.<lb/>
That man had a future. Why should I hesitate to volunteer. Not that I wanted to<lb/>
die but if a man like that could give his life why should I hesitate to take a chance.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f05911005"/>
<p>-5-</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear died in less than four days. Now these doctors had produced<lb/>
three cases of yellow fever. They were satisfied with their knowledge but the<lb/>
medical society found flaws with their experiments. Doctor <unclear>Carroll</unclear> had been run-<lb/>
ning around to different quarters and buildings all over the camp and they said<lb/>
that he could have picked it up in any other way than by a mosquito. Private Dean<lb/>
and Doctor Lazear the same way, they could have got germs from the clothing.</p>
<p>In order to prove that it was carried by a mosquito, they went into the<lb/>
second phase of the experiment. They went a mile from <del>Commodos</del><add><unclear>Quemados</unclear></add> to a plantation<lb/>
about 1,000 acres in size and there established a camp called Camp Lazear.<lb/>
Everything was to taken into consideration so that there would be no doubt that<lb/>
the fever was produced the way they believed and not the way some people thought.</p>
<p>Owing to the fact that I had promised the doctors that I would stay in the<lb/>
barracks and around my quarters for thirty days they thought it safe to place the<lb/>
mosquito upon my arm and make the test at once. Doctor Agramonte brought five<lb/>
mosquitoes into my tent and placed them upon my arm. He waited three days and<lb/>
then placed five more mosquitoes on my arm, three of which were the original<lb/>
mosquitoes. On the fifth day, the doctor brought the same mosquitoes back into<lb/>
the room and placed them upon my arm. The reason these mosquitoes did not produce<lb/>
yellow fever in the first trial was that the mosquitoes had bitten patients three<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f05911006"/>
-6-<lb/>
up <unclear>to twelve</unclear> days before and the others had bitten only four to twelve days<lb/>
before. The third time they had mosquitoes that had bitten yellow fever patients<lb/>
from twelve to twenty-one days. They found that that was what they should rely<lb/>
upon. It would take twelve to twenty-one days but seventeen to nineteen days<lb/>
was considered best for placing the mosquitoes upon the arm. They had also found<lb/>
out that they had to find what time the mosquitoes should feed upon the patient,<lb/>
whether it should be the first, second, third or fourth day. They found that both<lb/>
the second and third day could produce yellow fever in the mosquitoes but they<lb/>
were at a loss to find out what type of mosquito.</p>
<p>Doctor Finlay had given his theory that there was just one type but he had<lb/>
the disease with<lb/>
not produced that mosquito. They found that the Stegomyia mosquito, a little female<lb/>
mosquito was the one that would carry the yellow fever, and they began to get some<lb/>
place with the experiment. On the 8th, after being experimented on the 5th, about<lb/>
<unclear>9 pm</unclear><lb/>
I had been out that evening chasing a dog off the grounds with John <add>Moran</add>,<lb/>
I felt warm 11 o'clock, and I <del>left the</del><add><unclear>rose</unclear> to</add> open tent flap. About 11.30 I woke up and felt chilly.<lb/>
I started to rise from my bunk to close the tent flap and was stricken with a<lb/>
severe chill. I lay back on my bunk. The hospital steward, who was supposed to<lb/>
sound asleep (drunk)<lb/>
watch me and take my temperature every two hours was not around so it was up to<lb/>
me to look after myself. When I began to get warm I lit the candle and began to<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f05911007"/>
-7-<lb/>
take my temperature when the guard asked me what the matter was. I sent him to<lb/>
report to Doctor <del>Reed</del><add>Ames</add> that I had a severe chill and now my temperature was 101.<lb/>
You know how much time it would take to walk twenty-five feet and call the doctor.<lb/>
By the time the doctor got there I felt as though six Ford cars had run over my<lb/>
body. Every bone in my body ached. My spine felt twisted and my head swollen<lb/>
and my eyes felt as if they would pop out of my head, even the ends of my fingers<lb/>
<unclear>sore aching</unclear><lb/>
felt as though they would snap off. Since then I have thought how much courage<lb/>
it must have taken Doctor Lazear if he felt the way I did and to sit there and<lb/>
<unclear>at</unclear> 4 <hi>AM</hi><lb/>
write those reports. They took me down to the yellow fever hospital <add><unclear>at</unclear> Columbia Barracks</add> about half<lb/>
a mile from the camp. At six o'clock <add>AM</add> that morning, I told Doctor <del>Agramonte</del><add>Ames</add>, &ldquo;I<lb/>
think this is all a false alarm. I feel just as well as I ever did.&rdquo; Doctor <del>Carroll</del><add>Ames</add><lb/>
said that if I was feeling alright at six o'clock at night I could go back to<lb/>
camp but at six o'clock I was not feeling quite as good as I had in the morning.<lb/>
Yellow fever is different from typhoid fever--it is short and sweet. The temper-<lb/>
ature does not run as high as in typhoid. The main trouble is with the albumin<lb/>
that forms. Two-fifths albumin formed in my case which showed in the second day<lb/>
and I was practically clear of it eight days later. In treating yellow fever as<lb/>
far as medicine is concerned, I received two grains of calomel when I first went<lb/>
there, after that I received little chunks of ice which I put in my mouth and<lb/>
dissolved. My mouth was washed out regularly. The treatment was ice and salt<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f05911008"/>
-8-<lb/>
<unclear>by rection</unclear><lb/>
solution injected. That was Doctor <del>Agramonte's</del><add>Ames</add> treatment for yellow fever which<lb/>
pulled every man through that he got from the start. He said he did not lose a<lb/>
man that he got right from the start but after twelve hours there was something<lb/>
about it that he could not control. The chart of yellow fever runs differently<lb/>
from that of typhoid fever. If the chart goes up and down, then the doctors are<lb/>
not worried, but if it takes a practically straight line, that is when they become<lb/>
alarmed. Just before a yellow fever patient dies he usually becomes a raving<lb/>
<unclear>The last day of his life leading.</unclear><lb/>
maniac. Doctor Lazear destroyed almost everything in the ward. in his <unclear>delerium</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>2 lady nurses &amp; hospital corp man had difficulty in keeping a bed</unclear></p>
<p>Now I will tell you about the other experiments. They would take a non-<lb/>
immune and take the blood from a yellow fever patient and inject it into the non-<lb/>
immune. They produced three or four cases that way. They had proven in my case<lb/>
and in three or four Spaniards who followed me that fever was carried by the<lb/>
mosquito. Now they had to prove to the medical society that they were wrong<lb/>
about it being contagious. They constructed a building 14 by 20 feet. At each<lb/>
end of the building there was a very small window double screened so that the<lb/>
mosquitoes could not get in and the building received just as much air as was<lb/>
necessary to keep the men from suffocating. They took bedding from yellow fever<lb/>
patients who had died and they did not shake it out but put it in an air-tight<lb/>
box. They carried it to the camp. I went back in charge there as hospital<lb/>
<unclear>Weatherwalk<lb/>
1 or three more Dr Cooke, <del>Froste</del> &amp;<lb/>
Jernegan</unclear><lb/>
steward and it became my duty to take this bedding when the three men came and<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f05911009"/>
-9-<lb/>
strew it around the walls and in the aisles. The men had clean beds to lie on.<lb/>
They occupied the room for twenty days although they were allowed ten feet from<lb/>
the building to exercise during the day. We did not allow a man to come within<lb/>
twenty <add>5</add> feet of these men and I carried food to them and did not allow the food or<lb/>
utensils or dishes to come in contact with the men in any way. In this way the<lb/>
medical society could not say that the germs were carried to them. They were there<lb/>
for twenty-<del>one</del> days and they came out feeling better and weighing more than when<lb/>
they went in. These three men were Doctor Cook, Jenniger and Weather<del>man</del><add>walk</add>. Doctor<lb/>
Cook was the volunteer but he did not allow the mosquito to bite him so that he<lb/>
did not get yellow fever.</p>
<p>I have often been asked if Major Reed was experimented upon. He was not as<lb/>
he was getting old and his health was poor. It would have been practically murder<lb/>
to have the mosquito placed on his arm and suicide to place it upon himself.<lb/>
He talked to Doctor Agramonte and he said, &ldquo;I could not ask other men to do a thing<lb/>
that I hesitate to do myself.&rdquo; But the other doctors would not place the mosquitoes<lb/>
upon him. Doctor Reed gave his health for this experiment. He was so interested<lb/>
in it that he did not take care of his own health. He returned to the United States<lb/>
in 1902 and was operated upon and died.</p>
<p>The doctors now decided to try and produce yellow fever in the same atmosphere<lb/>
where the men worked. They build a room about the same size as the other experiment<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f05911010"/>
-10-<lb/>
room (14 by 20 feet). In the center they put a partition of double screen. Two<lb/>
large windows at each end and the doors were also double screened. Two men stayed<lb/>
in this one part while the other room was the yellow fever room. John Moran was<lb/>
in the first. Moran had been experimented on twice before and was negative.<lb/>
He entered on the 20th of December. He removed his clothes and lay down on the<lb/>
bunk. Seven mosquitoes were turned loose in the room and they fed on Moran. He<lb/>
left the room then and stayed around until two o'clock in the afternoon. He<lb/>
returned to the room and five mosquitoes fed on him. On the 25th of December<lb/>
Christmas day, John Moran was handed a Christmas present. He went down with<lb/>
a mild case of yellow fever, This was one time when they found out definitely<lb/>
just what species of mosquito for they knew what species had been placed in the<lb/>
room, seven female stegomyia mosquitoes.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f05911011"/>
<p>-11-</p>
<p><hi>Slides</hi>--</p>
<p>Remarks--After Doctor Carroll died, Doctor Lazear took over the duties.<lb/>
The mosquitoes were kept in boxes that had bitten yellow fever patients. The<lb/>
doctors marked down days and even birthdays from the time they were hatched until<lb/>
the time when they were ready to be put upon the yellow fever patients.</p>
<p>Temperature Chart--After the mosquitoes had bitten me on December 5, my<lb/>
temperature dropped back and forth and about 11.30 at night was about 100&deg; then<lb/>
it dropped about 3 degrees in the <del>afternoon</del><add><unclear>morning</unclear></add>. At night it was 102.6&deg;. The next<lb/>
day it dropped to normal. The following day it rose very rapidly to 103.6&deg; and<lb/>
then dropped back and continued almost in a straight line. On the fifteenth day<lb/>
I was practically normal.</p>
<p>I want to tell you how it reacted on me. I was weighed two weeks before<lb/>
I did the experiment and weighed 148 pounds. A week after the experiment I weighed<lb/>
118 pounds. Yellow fever is very hard on the patient. Six years after I returned<lb/>
from the service, I came down with myelitis of the spine. The doctors were doubtful<lb/>
if this was caused by the yellow fever experiment, but some doctors think it was.<lb/>
I had been working very hard in the operating room and had a nervous breakdown and<lb/>
was in bed for three weeks. My nerves were shattered probably from the experiment<lb/>
as the doctors had invited doctors from Havana and at that time there were several<lb/>
war vessels in port from other countries and these doctors and Army doctors were<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f05911012"/>
-12-<lb/>
there to watch them put the mosquitoes upon me and to see how I would react.</p>
<p>Comment--Doctor Reed did not say, &ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you!&rdquo; to Mr. Kissinger<lb/>
or Mr. Moran.</p>
<p>Comments on Doctors Lazear, Finlay, Agramonte, Carroll and Mr. John J. Moran.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f05911013"/>
<p>Notes taken down <unclear>by stenographer</unclear> on <unclear>occasion</unclear><lb/>
Mr Kissinger back before EX- <del>June 1</del><add>May 31</add>, 1938</p>
<p>Major Reed was a West Point man and a typical red tape man. The man on<lb/>
the stage does not just seem to strike me as the right kind to show the people.<lb/>
He was a man who was a human being, a very modest unassuming man. He received<lb/>
achievement bravely and very modestly. I had the pleasure, although he was<lb/>
a West Pointer, of associating with him. He talked privately with me. Not<lb/>
many men have that privilege of talking with an officer. He was a man with a<lb/>
future.</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear had a great deal of courage and was an outstanding figure<lb/>
of the yellow fever experiment. His whole life was ahead of him and he spent<lb/>
it in research of yellow fever. It was a great honor to have associated with<lb/>
such a man.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll was the same type of man as Doctor Lazear in moral make-up.<lb/>
It was a great honor to associate with him. I saw these men reproduced on the<lb/>
stage in the play &ldquo;Yellow Jack.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Doctor Agramonte worked just as hard and gave just as much to the experiment<lb/>
as these other doctors, but owing to the fact that he was a Cuban, and is still<lb/>
alive, or was at that time and for some time afterwards, the Government practically<lb/>
did not recognize him and history does not recognize him. He was the same type<lb/>
of man as the others.</p>
<pb n="14" id="f05911014"/>
<p>Doctor Finlay came into my ward and I came in contact with him several times.<lb/>
He was the most enthusiastic man I ever say. His theory was proven after nineteen<lb/>
years of fighting to bring the theory before the public. He had very little<lb/>
encouragement in his work and very little chance with the Spaniards in Cuba.<lb/>
He almost had to give up the idea of the experiment being right when the other<lb/>
doctors came to his rescue in Cuba.</p>
<p>John J. Moran is a very high type of man. How much better really if he could<lb/>
have given these talks that I am giving. He came from a high type of people, the<lb/>
Moran's in Iowa. Moran and myself volunteered for humanity and medical science<lb/>
and he is just as much entitled to glory as I am.</p>
<p>Remarks on the slides of the camp--Here is the building where the clothing was.<lb/>
There was no stove in the building. They would have suffocated with a stove.<lb/>
There were windows at each end and in front. The men were in there twenty-one<lb/>
days and received no bad effects from the experiment.</p>
<p>Camp Columbian. Here is the operating room which I was in charge of. This<lb/>
building was the office and surgical ward. This little building was the bath and<lb/>
lavatory. The center building was the convalescent ward.</p>
<p>Camp Lazear, Doctor Ames' tent and tents of the Spanish emigrants. Behind<lb/>
the tree to the right is the building with the room for the clothing. Behind that<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f05911015"/>
is the building where Moran and the mosquitoes were and where he got the disease<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<p>On the stage Doctor Finlay, who never smoked a cigar or cigarette, is a<lb/>
typical Scotchman smoking a pipe. They called Major Reed &ldquo;Chief&rdquo; in the play.<lb/>
I would have liked to have seen anyone call him that.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
