<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t05911016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on John R. Kissinger, [by Philip Showalter Hench], June 2, 1938</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>05911016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1938-06-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Sidney</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1938-06-02">June 2, 1938</date>
<idno rend="suppress">05911016</idno>
<title>Notes on John R. Kissinger, [by Philip Showalter Hench], June 2, 1938</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kissinger responds to questions regarding the yellow fever experiments. He asserts that he volunteered before Moran.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1938-06-02">
<head>Notes on John R. Kissinger, [by Philip Showalter Hench], June 2, 1938</head>
<pb n="1" id="f05911016"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1938-06-02">June 2, 1938</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>NOTES FROM MR. JOHN J. KISSINGER</p>
<p>Moran was in the Quartermaster's department down in Quenados. I<lb/>
had been discharged from the service and had taken his place in the operating<lb/>
room. Moran after being discharged, got a position as in this<lb/>
quartermaster's department. Moran and I were great friends, so he would come<lb/>
back and forth to the camp. He lived in Quenados. I had my room in the<lb/>
operating department. He would come over to visit me quite often.<lb/>
When the doctors first come down <del>to</del><add>from</add> Quenados to Columbia Barracks, when they<lb/>
first began to collect mosquitoes for their first experiment, there were nine<lb/>
men who offered themselves to be bitten by mosquitos: Dr. Pinto, now of Omaha,<lb/>
Dr. Carroll, Dr. Lazear, I think Lieutenant Triby, myself and 4 others around the<lb/>
camp whose names I do not remember.</p>
<p>Q. You were not quarantined--you merely walked in, let mosquitoes bite<lb/>
you and went about your business? Dr. Pinto and I were there when they let the<lb/>
mosquitoes in and we allowed them to bite us. It must have been in July or August.</p>
<p>Q. You were not quarantined, etc.? No. There were about 9 of us bitten<lb/>
within a few days or a week.</p>
<p>Q. Nothing happened? A. No.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f05911017"/>
<p>2.</p>
<p>Q. Was Moran bitten then? No, Moran did not come in until after Dr.<lb/>
Lazear had died and they were talking about Camp Lazear, which was to be<lb/>
created. Moran was over to my quarters and we were talking about it. I<lb/>
told him that I had already spoken to Reed <del><unclear></unclear></del> about volunteering.<lb/>
Moran and I never went together to Dr. Reed. Before this time I had casually<lb/>
volunteered. I told Dr. Reed when they were creating Camp Lazear, and I<lb/>
heard the conversation all the time. No call was given out.</p>
<p>Q. How did they spread the word around that they wanted volunteers?<lb/>
&ldquo;They practically told it out.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Q. You had already casually volunteered to Reed? Yes. I said to the<lb/>
doctors that they could try them on me any time.</p>
<p>Q. When was it that you and Moran started talking this over? It must<lb/>
have been along in the latter part of October. After Lazear died and when<lb/>
Dr. Reed was talking about creating the experimental camp, Moran came over<lb/>
to my quarters. We were talking about the experimenting and I told him that<lb/>
I had volunteered. Moran said &ldquo;Kissinger, I am going in it myself. I am<lb/>
going to volunteer. I think it is the right thing for us to do. Why shouldn't<lb/>
we take chances as well as when we come into the service? I have made up my<lb/>
mind to study to be a physician and <del>it will</del> if we are fortunate enough to<lb/>
get out of it alive, it will give me a start in that direction.&rdquo; The next<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f05911018"/>
3.<lb/>
day he went up to Reed alone and volunteered, and when we were taken out to<lb/>
the quarters, Moran joined us. He dropped his work there as young quartermaster<lb/>
and joined us. Mr. Moran was not in on the preliminary work.</p>
<p>I was not in the room when he saw Reed. I was on duty when he went up.<lb/>
Reed told both of us: &ldquo;There is money enough for you fellows that will take<lb/>
this here task.&rdquo; Moran said practically the same thing that I did, that we<lb/>
would not consider going in it for money, but for humanity and science.</p>
<p>Q. Did you at any time <del>have a</del> formally have a talk with the doctors?<lb/>
Yes. When I overheard them talk in the experiment room about creating Camp Lazear.<lb/>
I went to see Major Reed at his officer's quarters. He was on the porch. That<lb/>
is when I went up and told him. It was along in the latter part of October I<lb/>
decided to remind Dr. Reed of my promise and told him that I was ready to go<lb/>
with him, to go out to Camp Lazear and volunteer. He said, &ldquo;Kissinger, you know<lb/>
there has money been provided to pay you fellows a compensation for the experiments.<lb/>
I think it will be quite a sum of money.&rdquo; I told him, &ldquo;Doctor, you couldn't<lb/>
buy my little finger. I am not here to sell my health or my life but if you<lb/>
can use it for humanity and medical science I am willing to volunteer under<lb/>
those conditions.&rdquo; He told me, &ldquo;Kissinger, I consider that very much of a<lb/>
courageous act. I surely appreciate that.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="4" id="f05911019"/>
<p>4.</p>
<p>&ldquo;As far as saluting and saying, &ldquo;I salute you, gentlemen,&rdquo; that is all a<lb/>
mistake. That was before Moran volunteered. I think it was a day or so before<lb/>
Moran came to me and told me he was also going to volunteer.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Q. What was the mortality among the soldiers? A. &ldquo;Well, you can't hardly<lb/>
just give that definite. 25%, 30%, 40% were dying. It varied with the difference<lb/>
in handling the patients. With the small epidemic we had in our camp, there were<lb/>
about 35% who died from that.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Q. What was the treatment? &ldquo;Injections by rectum of ice water (saline) were<lb/>
given.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Q. When you first knew that you were sick, what were your sensations?<lb/>
&ldquo;The fact that I had already stayed in Columbia Barracks 30 days under voluntary<lb/>
quarantine more or less indicates the time of my first volunteering (November 20).<lb/>
We arrived at Camp Lazear on November 20. Owing to the fact that I had been<lb/>
30 days under observation they thought it was safe to place the five mosquitoes<lb/>
upon my arm. Dr. Agramonte came in about 2 in the afternoon and placed the five<lb/>
mosquitoes upon my arm. Three days later, November 23, they placed the same<lb/>
mosquitoes upon my arm. About twelve days later, on December 5, they placed three<lb/>
old mosquitoes and two new ones on my arm at 5 P.M. On December 8, at 11:30 P.M.<lb/>
I first noticed a chill. In the evening Moran and I had chased a dog out of the<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f05911020"/>
5.<lb/>
camp and then retired about 9:30 P.M. Steward Colby was an uncommissioned officer<lb/>
in charge of Camp Lazear. He was across the tent, and he was dead to the world.<lb/>
I woke up about 11:30 to close the tent flaps. I felt a chill, so I lay back, pulled<lb/>
the blankets up over me, and I don't know just how many minutes I was in that chill.<lb/>
I had my bedside table <unclear>beside</unclear> me so I lit a candle and took my temperature. Just<lb/>
as I lit the candle the guard asked about the lights. As soon as I removed the<lb/>
thermometer I said to him, &lsquo;You report to Dr. Ames that I had a severe chill and that<lb/>
my temperature is 100.&rsquo; He <del><unclear>waslke</unclear></del> walked over to Dr. Ames' tent and he came in his<lb/>
pajamas. Until he got there it seemed as if every bone in my body had been crushed.<lb/>
It seemed as if my head were going to burst open. I became sick to my stomach, and<lb/>
they removed me at 4 A.M. to the Yellow Fever quarters, down below Quenados, that is,<lb/>
they took me away from Camp Lazear to Columbia Barracks the yellow fever quarters about<lb/>
1/2 mile from the main hospital grounds.</p>
<p>Q. Did you think you were going to die? No, the only time that I really gave<lb/>
it very much of a thought was when I was passing a tent, just a night or so before I<lb/>
went down, and overheard Dr. Ames tell some of the men that he wouldn't be in my shoes<lb/>
for a good many dollars. I went back in the tent and it run through my mind that when<lb/>
my attending doctor would repeat those words, what chance did I have? But I threw it<lb/>
off. I didn't worry about myself during my illness. My main worry after I began to<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f05911021"/>
6.<lb/>
get over it was more of something to eat.</p>
<p>Discussing Moran's letter with me, Mr. Kissinger says this part of the letter<lb/>
is incorrect: &ldquo;We did not go in together. I had already volunteered. We did<lb/>
talk it over, and Moran told me that Dr. Ames had talked to him, and that he was<lb/>
going to volunteer also. To my best recollection, he went alone. But as far as<lb/>
publishing anything I am quite willing to allow Moran's incorrect version to stand.<lb/>
However, I take issue on the point that he was the spokesman for us both. I had<lb/>
already spoken for myself as I had been there and known Dr. Reed already for a<lb/>
considerable period of time. Moran has just as much credit coming to him as I do,<lb/>
but I don't like to have him saying that he was the leading spokesman, as I was<lb/>
acquainted with <del>Dr.</del><add>Major</add> Reed. After Sidney Howard went down there and talked to him,<lb/>
Howard changed the whole atmosphere of the book. He was practically the leader<lb/>
of it. As far as that is concerned, no credit was given to any of us.&rdquo;</p>
<p>If you are trying to reach the truth, if John J. Moran or any of the others<lb/>
can prove to me that I am wrong, I am willing to give in.<lb/>
<del>Dr.</del><add>Major</add> Reed and Lieutenant Trilby was sitting on the porch of the officers' quarters<lb/>
and I went over, saluted him and told him. That is what I have in my memory.<lb/>
This was one or two days before Moran had volunteered. That night when Moran came<lb/>
over I spoke to him about this.</p>
<p>I think that Moran felt that owing to the fact that I was getting so many<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f05911022"/>
7.<lb/>
writeups in the paper I was trying to throw the glory upon myself.</p>
<p>Commenting on Major Reed's &ldquo;office tent&rdquo;, Mr. Kissinger doesn't remember<lb/>
that Reed had any office tent, nor can he remember that Moran acted as secretary<lb/>
to Major Reed at Camp Lazear. &ldquo;He did help me with making up my reports at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks and in helping me make out my payroll. Major Reed did not stay<lb/>
at Camp Lazear but visited the camp every so often. The ones who stayed at the<lb/>
camp were Dr. Ames, the attending doctor, who was immune, Dr. Carroll and Dr.<lb/>
Agramonte, who slept there. They didn't stay there continuously. Major Reed<lb/>
never stayed in that camp over night.</p>
<p>Mr. Kissinger stated that in Mr. Moran's recent radio talk, he mentioned<lb/>
betting with Suntag, not Jernegan.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
