<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06001041">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Philip Showalter Hench, [January 9, 1947?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lambert, Gustaf E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06001041</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-01-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Sheppard, Morris</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Amador, R. A.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Colby, Newell, R. Ryan, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lewis, Nellie</name>
<name type="person">Gillan, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Martinez, Jose</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Schwieger, John D.</name>
<name type="person">Moore, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Lewis, Senator</name>
<name type="person">Sullivan, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1 (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-01-09">[January 9, 1947?]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06001041</idno>
<title>Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Philip Showalter Hench, [January 9, 1947?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lambert corrects a draft of an interview of Lambert by Hench - conducted on June 21, 1946. He also tries to advance his case for being included in the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-01-09">
<head>Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Philip Showalter Hench, [January 9, 1947?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06001041"/>
<p>Received<lb/>
<date value="1947-01-09">Jan 9, 1947</date>
To Doctor Hench</p>
<p>Lamberts corrections of our<lb/>
Interview of June 21, 1946</p>
<p>Dear Doctor</p>
<p>I have received the papers many thank<lb/>
but two copies of letters that Andrus<lb/>
sent to senators Sheppard and Lewis<lb/>
were missing</p>
<p>I have read over printed interview! I know my<lb/>
english is poor, and pronouncing faulty. but<lb/>
even so, the young lady could had made a litle<lb/>
less garbling I have <unclear>to</unclear> point out page by page</p>
<p>Page 1</p>
<p>Board consisted of officers only, Kissinger and Forbes I<lb/>
couldn't have said were members of Board or<lb/>
commission, they were men who took part in<lb/>
the experiment! <del>wast</del><add>wasn't</add> there mentioned that Ames told<lb/>
me I might soon be out if Grayham happened to be<lb/>
the only patient when I told Ames I did not care to<lb/>
go in quarantine as I had 7 1/2 months of it at Nos. 1.<add>Military Hosp</add></p>
<p>Page 2</p>
<p>Maj. Kean came in the morning <unclear>Hepburn</unclear> at night<lb/>
I so stated</p>
<p>page 3</p>
<p>I did not say may you <hi>go</hi> and tell the Doctor, that<lb/>
would have been insolent or disrespectful I had<lb/>
no Idea of being so, but to follow the Doctors orders<lb/>
I know Doctor Hench that if you had the<lb/>
president for a patient you would insist the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06001042"/>
nurse took orders from you not from the patient.<lb/>
I said I was going to put it back in the glass, I did<lb/>
not have time to put it back before the storm <unclear>brook</unclear>.<lb/>
I did not say that Ames shut the door knowing<lb/>
it would have been absolutely dark, there was<lb/>
no window</p>
<p>page 4</p>
<p>I did not say, never had time to wash floor, I<lb/>
had pleanty of time with only two patient<lb/>
I did say I couldn't wash the floor (meaning the<lb/>
way it should be washed) just throw water and<lb/>
let dirty water run down, boards being so far<lb/>
apart I could put my hand between them<lb/>
I couldn't have said <hi>a man</hi> but <hi>the man</hi> (meaning<lb/>
the <unclear>one</unclear> in charge of Depot (Steward Pike)</p>
<p><hi>page 5</hi></p>
<p>Surely I couldn't have been foolish enough<lb/>
to mention Dr Stark as one who could have<lb/>
been transefered in place of Dr Ames Stark<lb/>
was post Surgeon I did mention Amador<lb/>
or Cook</p>
<p>page 6</p>
<p><unclear>Transeferred</unclear> I think Aug 7<hi rend="superscript"><unclear>th</unclear></hi><lb/>
Prisoners sent from Pinar Del Rio to Columbia<lb/>
Barracks when claiming sickness sent to receiving<lb/>
ward at hospital I was not gaurding them,<lb/>
there was no guard sent with them, or posted<lb/>
with them.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06001043"/>
<p>page 7</p>
<p>I remember I couldn't tell directions I'll draw<lb/>
the buildings as used</p>
<p>Railroad cut</p>
<p>Camp<lb/>
<unclear>Table</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>terrible</unclear><lb/>
for see</p>
<p><unclear>Grayham</unclear> 1<lb/>
Maj Kean 2</p>
<p>Mrs <unclear>Grayham</unclear> 1<lb/>
<unclear>Hepbarn</unclear> 2<lb/>
Kissinger 3</p>
<p># 2<lb/>
(113?)</p>
<p>Mrs <unclear>Hunt</unclear> 1<lb/>
Dr Ames 2</p>
<p>Lamberts # 1<lb/>
(114?)</p>
<p>a tree</p>
<p>about 50 ft</p>
<p>40 ft</p>
<p>all of the patients <unclear>taken</unclear> care of in this<lb/>
bldg except 8 marked in other bldg</p>
<p>50 ft</p>
<p>table chair</p>
<p>My bed.</p>
<p># 3<lb/>
(115?)</p>
<p># 4 (116?)</p>
<p>Andrus</p>
<p>30 ft</p>
<p>little toilet erected about<lb/>
Nov 1900</p>
<p>no door</p>
<p>If messured with tape I think it would check</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06001044"/>
<p>page 8</p>
<p>Dr Ames did not put the women to work because<lb/>
we had no female patients, after Mrs Hunt left<lb/>
they were sent down for the purpose of caring<lb/>
for femal patients... Here the young lady got her<lb/>
notes mixed I certainly did not say that we put<lb/>
the Doctor who took Dr Ames place in 116 as a<lb/>
patient. I put Ames in 13 (Folk and Forbes was<lb/>
in 115) and when Andrus came in the day<lb/>
after Ames took sick the new Doctor put Andrus<lb/>
in 116 and made the women move in to 114:<lb/>
They were all sick that were down there, but only<lb/>
one had black vomit I did not say some of them<lb/>
the black vomit case I told you about at 4718 Wood-<lb/>
lawn ave. Maj Gorgas told the man (Old Sullivan)<lb/>
he was the only man he ever seen who at his age<lb/>
have had black vomit 3 times and recovered</p>
<p>page 9</p>
<p>The lady have a habbit of using plural where singu-<lb/>
lar should be used, where an inciden happened<lb/>
once and so stated she has made it appear as being<lb/>
common practise, Colby was on his 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> class, and<lb/>
over the hump as one might say Sergt Ryan was<lb/>
on his 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> day and very nervous, it's hard to<lb/>
sleep with one eye open when real tired and<lb/>
I tied a string to Colby's bed and to my tumb<lb/>
before laying back in chair and asking him to<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06001045"/>
give it a yank in case Ryan called and I didn't<lb/>
hear, there was only one realy sick soldier</p>
<p>page 10</p>
<p>I did not say that Amador, Albertino and<lb/>
Findlay came to see the <hi>patients</hi> or Maj Kean<lb/>
while he was sick Albertino and Amador<lb/>
came to see Kissinger the first day only, and I<lb/>
said it was Amador who put his head<lb/>
under Kissingers blanket. Autopsy was held<lb/>
in an old Messhall, not old hospital. When I<lb/>
wrote Agramonte and asked him if in<lb/>
his opinion Maj Reed considered autopsy's more<lb/>
dangerous then soiled clothing, in view of the<lb/>
fact that he stood so far away, that letter<lb/>
would never have been writen except for<lb/>
the question mentioned I showed you the<lb/>
reply I had from Agramonte wherin he said,<lb/>
Maj Reed did not consider autopsy table<lb/>
dangerous but that <hi>it is on record</hi> that yellow<lb/>
fever epidemics have started from contact<lb/>
with soiled clothing. The battery <del>to</del><add>of</add> which the<lb/>
man had been a member, and 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Cav. band<lb/>
<hi>about 200</hi> lbs</p>
<p>page 12</p>
<p>Dr Carroll was in Officers quarters <hi>not ward</hi>! <hi>stable</hi><lb/>
lantern, I couldn't have said doorman as there<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06001046"/>
were none I said I woke first Maj Reed and then<lb/>
Carroll. they, Maj Reed and Carroll took some<lb/>
slides along not <hi>we</hi> and they, not <hi>we</hi> punched<lb/>
ear and finger I only rubbed off with alcohol<lb/>
and cotton</p>
<p>page 13</p>
<p>Mrs. <hi>Gillen said</hi> when she came after me in<lb/>
big ward (Bldg 115) he was acting awful Forbes<lb/>
and Folk were in 115 Miss Lewis was taking care<lb/>
of Dr Ames up in the Officers ward <add>page 14.</add> Dr Ames.<lb/>
order was, that water taken and urin passed should<lb/>
average the same every four hours, or hold back<lb/>
on water. No I did not catherize any dead men<lb/>
I said I had one that I used on the man who died<lb/>
I suppose I mentioned that because he was the<lb/>
only one I needed to use it on up to that time.<lb/>
Andrus was on his <add>knees</add> with head dug in pillow<lb/>
I said to Dr Ames &ldquo;I wish you could come down&rdquo;<lb/>
Dr Ames then said, can't you see I am sick in bed<lb/>
myself! we haven't had a death yet amongst experimental<lb/>
cases! with his permission I got a man</p>
<p>page 15</p>
<p>to the question who took care of Dr Ames I can't<lb/>
remember my answer but I know after he<lb/>
was cleaned out he got no more medicine and<lb/>
Maj Reed looked in to see him whenever he came<lb/>
down I really don't know if Dr who took Ames place<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06001047"/>
looked in to see him. After arriving at<lb/>
officers ward he was a patient of Dr Stark</p>
<p>page 16</p>
<p>Dr Stark signed Ames' release not relief<lb/>
Dr Ames told me Dr Carroll was awfully<lb/>
sick you go up there and help them (I was sent<lb/>
as we had no patient in pest house at that time)<lb/>
What I actually said was that Dr Carroll laying<lb/>
on his elbow, <add>with</add> left foot on floor right foot on<lb/>
bed intending to get up</p>
<p>page 17</p>
<p>Nurse standing on right side of bed<lb/>
Dr Lazear <hi>worked</hi> his head off, not looking his<lb/>
head off.</p>
<p>page 19</p>
<p>I can't remember that case history records were<lb/>
mentioned, I would have been entirely in the<lb/>
wrong if giving opinion who wrote them as<lb/>
I had no way of knowing, the charts I saw<lb/>
Lottie working, copying some of them</p>
<p>page 22</p>
<p>I was born 1874 not 1884, tried to enlist in<lb/>
Navy but an account of what Doctors both in<lb/>
Scotland, Germany, Sweden, Philadelphia and<lb/>
examining Doctor in Navy said rupture (he<lb/>
saw mark of <unclear>truss</unclear>) I later joined Hosp Corps for<lb/>
what was promissed as philipine service Doctor<lb/>
Stark took one look and said undescended<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06001048"/>
testicle (I did not like to mention this<lb/>
with a young lady present) I was the last man<lb/>
Dr Stark operated an in Cuba Dr Stark<lb/>
sent me to ask Maj Keans permission as he had<lb/>
taken over temporarily the past after Dr Stark<lb/>
I voluntered when Maj Carter asked if there was<lb/>
any immunes or any one who wasn't afraid of<lb/>
yellow fever no one was detailed or ordered to<lb/>
work were there was fear of yellow fever volunteers<lb/>
plants<lb/>
was asked for. In one of disi<add>n</add>fection is wrong<lb/>
there was only one</p>
<p>page 25</p>
<p>I realize the officers named contributed a lot to<lb/>
the success of the experiment but they did so in a<lb/>
material way both Gen Wood and Maj Kean was<lb/>
at that time immunes and would have been in<lb/>
no danger if entering the pest house Bill 13060 was<lb/>
passed to compensate those who exposed themselfs<lb/>
to loss of health or life Officers of the Board for<lb/>
their scientific work, men for serving beyond<lb/>
the line of duty. If work in pest house was not<lb/>
outside the line of duty then why couldn't a man<lb/>
have been detailed there, when I asked Dr Ames<lb/>
what will I do with the disinfection plant (that<lb/>
was considered so necessary at this time) he<lb/>
said I need a man down there at once close<lb/>
the plant which was doen. The only difference<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06001049"/>
I can see is that I voluntered for work<lb/>
beyond the line of duty before any one els and<lb/>
I did so without promise of extra pay. I<lb/>
know the men who took fomites test felt they were<lb/>
there trying to get yellow fever, but none of them<lb/>
had black vomit spewed right on their heads<lb/>
like old Sullivan did to me Maj Gorgas stood at<lb/>
head of bed and grabbed a towel and threw<lb/>
over my head so I could wipe my face and<lb/>
asked if I had any disinfectant I realize the<lb/>
man wasn't an experimental case but some<lb/>
of his black vomit was sent up for the use of the<lb/>
Board Senator Thomas in his report to the<lb/>
Senate (He being chairman of committee) wrote<lb/>
this man should have quit when first case of experi-<lb/>
mental yellow fever came in. I would then<lb/>
have been asked to <unclear>Volunteer</unclear> to take care of them<lb/>
It has been pointed out that Dr Ames was only the<lb/>
physician for the commission if such was the case<lb/>
he certainly laid himself open to criminal<lb/>
prosecution when he injected contaminated<lb/>
blood into a healthy person I don't know but<lb/>
what I could have been held. as an asessory to the<lb/>
crime At the time Dr Ames drew blood from<lb/>
Martinez to be injected into jernegan he<lb/>
had a wadd of cotton and himself rubbed<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06001050"/>
the arm of Martinez, but told me to clean<lb/>
of a spot under left shoulder on jernegan,<lb/>
at this particular time Dr Ames spoke the only<lb/>
harsh words he ever used toward me in the<lb/>
two years I worked under him, he said &ldquo;I did not<lb/>
tell you to take his hide off I only asked you<lb/>
to clean a part&rdquo; it wasn't the words he used it<lb/>
was the way he said it, I suppose he was nervous,<lb/>
I know several persons have tried to get on the<lb/>
band wagon through Bill 13060 Moore was <unclear>one</unclear> he<lb/>
worked in Camp Lazear, <hi>handled dirty clothing</hi><lb/>
he claimes when helping me in disinfection<lb/>
plant experiment was then ended Apr 1901, another<lb/>
was Schwieger he had yellow fever 7 months before<lb/>
experiment started, his claim is that he helped to<lb/>
take care of Lazear, he helped only one day, and was<lb/>
an immune <unclear>Neet</unclear> who worked in laboratory I<lb/>
believe is one (or was one) the most deadly poison<lb/>
is handled in both laboratories and chemical<lb/>
plants but its harmless when handled properly,<lb/>
it would have been the mans own fault if<lb/>
he had been bitten by infected mosquitose<lb/>
I have read photostatic copy of letter from Maj<lb/>
Reed to Dr Ames after Maj Reed had induced<lb/>
Surg Gen to give Ames the rank of Major<lb/>
Andrus wrote me it was <unclear>easyer</unclear> for war dept to throw out all bills<lb/>
then to investigate<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06001051"/>
From what I've learned from Mrs Ames<lb/>
Dr Ames commanded the hospital detachment<lb/>
at Army Post near New Orleans, just <unclear>as</unclear> Dr Stark<lb/>
commanded hospital at Columbia barrack,<lb/>
Lt. <unclear>Litte</unclear> commanded Post as did Col Baldwin<lb/>
at Columbia Barrack. That is information I<lb/>
received from Mrs Ames</p>
<p>I have made every thing as clear as I know how, I have<lb/>
tried to show my version of things, if I have showed<lb/>
eagerness in proving my point I'm glad to say I <add>have</add> never<lb/>
wanted to make my point so much that I were<lb/>
willing to lie <add>to</add> make it. Neither have I ever wanted<lb/>
anything so bad that I wanted to steal it.</p>
<p>Sorry it has taken me so long in sending back<lb/>
the papers, but when reading glass have to be used<lb/>
most of the time work goes slowly I'm afraid my<lb/>
reading will soon end</p>
<p>Very Respectfully</p>
<p>Gust. E. Lambert<lb/>
8009 Avalon ave.<lb/>
Chicago 19 Ill</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
